Dart.
Okay, so as I said, this is going to be.
So Sean McGrath who is a programmer, who did, like I said, a bunch of
the programming on N plus plus, and who's now working on new game and
he also did it before.
M plus plus, that was his most recent product.
You did a game called dyad which you could check out,
He is interested in doing a potentially a game that's free to play
that was he's, you know, he's thinking of doing his next game free to
play and for whatever reason he felt, you know, he was maybe a little
uneasy about this or he wanted to kind of get it a little bit, I'm not
sure exactly why.
I'm sure he will explain that to us in the opening here, but he wanted
to essentially have a mock debate about it, where he would get
somebody who wasn't necessarily super invested meaning, I don't, it
doesn't matter.
Me right whether he does his game free to play or not.
Like I'm not personally affected by, this doesn't affect me
necessarily, but I do care about the game industry in general.
I do have opinions about stuff and I am an argumentative person.
So he basically wanted someone who fit that criteria to argue with him
about this a little bit kind of probably to make sure that Keys
thought it through all the way and also, so he can kind of feel out
exactly.
You know how other people would might react to this or all sorts of
stuff like that, right?
So that's what we're going to be doing now.
And of course, that involves us having to do some Skype set up here.
So please bear with us for a few moments.
While we try to get this stuff set up, I'm sure it will be a little
bit of an adventure, but hopefully we will be able to make it work.
So I'm going to go ahead and start that process here and hopefully we
can, like I said, make this happen without too much pain, but you know
again anything that involves
To play is, it's a thing, right?
All right, so let's go here.
Let me get this set up so we can talk to Sean.
We will not have much of a debate, if I cannot talk to Sean that much
is clear.
Let's see here.
Do do do and this up.
Okay.
So I will come to online status online and then we will see some ads
here, wonderful ads for whatever.
Let's see if we can call Sean.
Call.
Hello.
Sean.
Howdy.
How's it going?
It was very interesting because I was watching handmade hero and
there's stream delay.
You were setting it up.
Well, calling me, it was very confusing for a moment, it's freaky.
That's just, that's just how it goes.
Yeah, it's very, very terrifying.
So I guess the first question here is, we have no webcam for you.
Is that as well?
Oh shit.
Oh crap.
Can I swear?
Yes, you can.
If you would like to, I suppose, but I mean I'll try not to but yeah,
it happens.
Is the audience for the streams going to be for, you know, all right.
I'll do my best.
Sorry.
Yeah.
Oh wait, do we have a webcam now?
We should.
Perfect.
Is it okay?
Cool.
I guess I'm going to set up my stream but I can just go, it's fine.
Okay, well you can't really go yet because now we have to check with
the chat that any of this stuff works.
Oh, it doesn't of course.
Alright.
So those of you who are on the handmade hero chat, who I am looking at
now.
Can somebody tell me what?
Like can you tell me what you see like, do you see Sean?
Can you hear?
Sean right, you know what?
What's going on I guess is what I would say.
The other thing I'll do is I'll maybe make myself a little bit bigger
here as well.
Let's see here.
How do I, how do I make my, how do I make myself?
Holy shit, look how big I am.
Oh my God, this is faster.
It just got to be there.
It is edit scene.
All right.
I don't even know what I'm looking at here.
All right, webcam.
I should Zoom an emotional mess in my room.
I don't even know.
This is just a disaster.
All right, it's where I, it's working like short of and I duplicate
this
Add.
Oh my God.
All right.
I just want to add I want to like add our duplicate, one of these
things so I can have, I guess I can add Arrow.
So let me see if I can add a global source of air.
Oh no, I can't.
There's monitor, add Global Source webcam.
Oh, are you won't be able to?
There we go.
What I did it.
Huh, I didn't work for me.
Yeah, perfect, right.
Okay, people on the stream.
What how are we at?
Can we start this or not?
Can we, can we here?
Sean.
Can we hear me?
Can you see?
Both of us?
People who are watching on handmade Heroes.
I think this is working.
I think that actually
Eric John.
It's a miracle.
It is a bit of a miracle.
It is I just assume nothing ever Works.
Alright so are we almost ready start?
This I'm going to go check one more thing and then we'll get started.
All right.
Sean is much louder.
Sean is way louder and I am quiet like a mouse.
They say like well I just I just moved my microphone away from my
mouth so maybe that'll help.
No, I think that's just I'm just going to adjust my volume here.
I think that's all.
You're probably fine.
Alright then alright let's try this.
I turned down Shawna Tad.
How do we feel now guys is this is this better?
And people are asking.
I don't know if you're seeing the handmade hero chat, but people want
to know if you have a cat.
No.
Sean says, he does not have a cat.
I have a lot of pets, but no cat.
A lot of pets, but no cat.
Yes, I have a zoo.
The sound is, ok.
All right, so I think we're ready to go here.
I think.
Cool.
Alright.
Sean, you ready?
Sure.
Let's do this.
Now I should tell you up front.
Before we start that I do have a treat for you.
Yes.
I heard I prepared a treat for you.
All right but I want first before I so I'm going to I'm going to give
you essentially a present first but before I do that I just wanted you
to take some time to tell people who may not be familiar because you
talk to me about this already and email, you said here's what I'd like
to.
Do why don't you explain in sort of your own words, right?
What it is that you actually want to get out of this or like what, you
know, what you're thinking, what the point is so that they're on the
same page as you.
And I are, because I sort of understand, but, you know, they might not
sure.
So, basically, I've been a vocal opponent of free to play for, at
least, you know, at least a decade.
I've given talks about how awful it is and persuaded as
many people as possible to not do free-to-play because it is
universally
Worse for the game, it's worse for the game, it's worth for the people
playing it.
It's worse for everybody except developers can make a whole bunch of
money or whatever.
So it's always worth, it's always bad for you plays always bad.
I've always hated it.
However, I'm looking at a game that I want to do and I'm pretty
serious about it.
And I think the only way I can get made as if it's free to play, and
that's not reason enough to do for you to play in my opinion.
If the only way this game could be made is free-to-play, I just
wouldn't do it.
It.
Unless I thought that free-to-play was actually the best model for the
game.
And I believe that I have convinced myself that free-to-play is
actually what's best for the game.
But I'm concerned that I've convinced myself of something that's not
actually true and I think it would be pretty hypocritical of me to go
ahead and make the game unless I've thoroughly vetted.
My free-to-play is okay.
Point of view in my current situation.
So I you seem like a person who hates free to play as much as me and
likes arguing, probably not as much as me, but maybe and have my
previous opinion that free-to-play is just straight-up awful all the
time and there's absolutely no Redemption for it.
So I if I can convince you or at least throw ideas off of you and if I
don't convince you, if you're just like, if you still think it's bad
but I can like get new ideas about why
Bad or makes my position makes me feel stronger, but my position or
makes or killed my position, whatever I want to test my position.
Against somebody, you know, who could actually perhaps prove me wrong
if that makes any sense, it makes perfect sense.
First of all, I would say, you're never going to make it as a single
executive right now.
That's just the stuff.
You just said, they're your debit.
They're going ever going to promote you, man.
It's not going to happen.
I'll survive.
Okay, fair enough.
So
All right, that all makes good sense.
I I think that's exactly what I have served for the email.
So hopefully everyone at homes on the same page as well.
But before, so before we start I felt like it was important for us to
kind of like set the tone, right?
So that is why I developed this particular treat for you.
Oh boy.
So what I'd like you to do if you could because I mean you have to
understand, right?
Like I don't get really paid for this, right?
This is outside of handmade Heroes.
Time.
So especially thank you by the way.
Essentially, this is like this is free, right?
Like it's basically a service for you that I'm providing, which I'm
happy to do, right?
Okay.
But and you know I said I would do the argument and the argument is
going to be free, but the catch is that the rest of the stuff that
might happen on this stream besides me, arguing with you is not going
to be free.
So if you go ahead and go to handmade here a.org /, donate Tut HTML,
I'm sorry debate.
Debate dot.
Oh God, you can see that I've created a bunch of add-ons for you.
And those add-ons are ones, you can purchase at any time during the
debate, and I'll honor them.
But in general, without purchasing any of them, all you get is
actually just just the argument, just in audio form.
So it's up to you again nut, you know, the argument.
I'll argue
Exactly a strenuously in his hard.
They are going to be exactly the same.
There's no Integrity difference here.
It's just cosmetic changes.
I've only put cosmetic changes on there.
All right, so let's continue.
Well, okay, hold on.
I got I do have to, I can't actually purchase any of these items
because I don't own a credit card, but I would love to buy
The EF F hat.
If you have any, if F hat, I would like to buy that you want to buy.
Don't have that hat?
Yeah, but don't have to bother.
I don't have a credit card.
So, yeah.
All right.
Well, that's really difficult for me because I feel like in general,
if you want it in.
So in your game, what will you do for people who don't have credit
cards, they just don't have to, they don't have to pay anything.
Okay?
So they would basically they wouldn't get the EF F hat.
They wouldn't get the FFA.
Okay.
So probably
We're going to have to continue the debate without the FF hat, right?
Because I mean at the end of the day if you can't pay for the
free-to-play stuff you can't pay for the free-to-play stuff now I
guess you could try to convince someone else on the stream to pay for
it I mean anyone could buy it and that's okay with me but someone's
gonna have to pay the two dollars for the EF F hat.
Now of course we don't even have the video add on yet.
So at this point you wouldn't really be able to see the EF F hat.
I guess.
So is the video ad on you have to pay for that too.
There's a lot of stuff there that would have.
To happen, but let's continue the argument, you know, just with that.
With that, in mind, my God, it dollar for you for the video.
I don, I really want to pay for this.
So here's the thing, basically, like with free to play, the first
thing I guess I would ask is what you sort of laid out there when you
were talking, sort of suggests to me that their stuff about the game,
but maybe I need to know in order to effectively argue this because
you said something.
Like the most effective thing here, right?
Like the most the best business model for it.
You said was going to be free to play.
So could you maybe start by telling me?
Why is it that you think that the that that business model is somehow
special for your game?
Or that like, give me a little bit of background there.
So I know why you're coming to that conclusion.
Sure.
Well, this is going to be unfortunate because you said in the Q&A of
handmade hero that you don't care about Esports at all.
Well, that's just my me playing them, right?
I know.
I'm totally fine taking the position.
I understand millions of people love them.
So so let's take it.
A given that people will like that.
So don't worry about that.
Okay?
So yeah, like I want to make
Take DOTA.
Okay.
Just say don't know.
Let's just start there.
I want to make again this like donor.
Right.
Okay.
So what is required to make it a good competitive esport, right?
There's a couple of things, wait a minute, people have purchased
Video ad on Sean.
This, this dude, I'm telling you, man free to play makes mad money.
And two people have purchased the EF F hat.
If we're to hats now and the ad free credit, the ad, there were going
to be advertisements.
And they've already Pete, Dunn, 15 minutes worth of ad free on the
street.
This is going to be hard for me to even keep track of.
Hold on.
Did you argue against this, though?
The, the money is rolling in.
Did your mic?
Oh, all right.
All right.
Hello.
Hi.
My still there?
I had to put on the hat.
Can you see the f?
F hat.
People paid good money for this.
I've got the stream delay thing so I don't know what's going on.
Look at that.
Do you have one of those stickers that say, I do not consent to the
search of this device?
I don't uff local.
You should get one.
I don't.
And I also guess at this point, you know, if people want me to turn on
the light, there's also the global illumination add-on that they can
buy, just want to remind them of that.
So anyway, I just want to say that on my end.
I'm offering all of this for free.
This is all the basics is all the basic package.
Wow man, you're not going to last long in this, okay?
But so continue.
Okay, so basically
Okay, so there's two sort of main factors with trying to make a game
that's competitively viable, that has the depth and the breadth of
DOTA right to.
The first one is obviously a lot of people need to play it, right?
Like the people who you know you can go back and you can look at.
I've been any sport fan for a very very long time and it goes
stretches back to brood War when it was only in Korea and you can look
at brood war in Korea and how the strategies developed over time.
They blizzard didn't do patches.
For six years, I think.
And none of the none of the units that blizzard had designed were used
in the way in which they had designed that.
Right.
What happened is the game was played by, you know, hundreds of
thousands millions of people in Korea primarily and strategies
developed and things like that.
So the only way that the game actually got competitively viable and
competitively deep which through a lot of people playing it, okay?
So you need a lot of people play it, right?
So therefore the more people playing it,
It the better the game is going to get because you have more data to
analyze and you can balance things better, right?
Okay.
So free to play gets a lot of people playing it, okay?
So that's one thing.
The second thing is, in order to now this goes against brood War, but
I think times are different now.
In order to sort of foster an online community, and remain
competitive, and host tournaments, and and get people together to have
stats to have a hosted dedicated server, you know, all that fun stuff
that Everyone likes,
Matchmaking and all that crap.
You have ongoing expenses, right?
You have you don't you don't have your expenses up front at time of
purchase of the game.
If your expenses carried on for indefinitely, right?
The free-to-play model lines up, your Revenue with your expenses,
better than anything else, subscription does it too.
But subscription doesn't work for the first problem, which is getting
a lot of people play it, right?
So you have to the two problems.
Are you need money constantly?
Because the game is expensive constantly and you need a lot of people
playing it and ad-supported, you know, maybe that's an option but like
realistically and I wouldn't ever do ad supported but
But free-to-play seems to be the thing that fits both of those two
requirements better than anything else.
And I think it's downsides can be mitigated against, but can be
lessened by by a benevolent dictator, basically.
So, just to be clear when you say that subscription model doesn't get
a lot of people playing the game, what you're talking about sustained.
Because I mean I'm assuming like
Most games nowadays that I think of, for subscription model, their
Games like World of Warcraft or something like this, in the earlier
before they went, I think they're somewhat half-free now or something
like that.
But in the early days, you know, you would get a month free or
something like that.
So, you did start out, you know, you could have arbitrarily many
people playing for a month, right?
But then presumably after that, they would win 0 away or something
like this, right?
Yeah.
And I don't even know like because there's not a lot of
Turn based games that are coming out now.
So I have absolutely no idea if that's even viable at all now, right?
Like there's no data in the last couple of years of subscription-based
games coming out and doing okay, everything's been moving to free to
play.
Okay.
So I guess let's take a look at that.
That specific aspect, then because like you said, you were somebody
who previously, didn't agree with free to play as a model, right?
I still think that every free.
Play as is is awful and unacceptably, an unacceptable.
I don't think anyone is doing it, there are, you know, there are
there's a gradient of people doing it really, really poorly and people
doing it slightly less evilly, but I don't think anyone doing it now
is doing it like to meet my what I would call my minimal ethical
standards for, but that doesn't mean that that doesn't exist.
Okay?
So I guess maybe before I go any further on that topic then and also I
should say that people have purchased
All of the Hat add-ons for me now, so I kind of feel like I should
probably switch hats.
Periodically.
So don't be alarmed when I do that before them all at once.
Yeah.
Well I feel like people want to see individual hats, so someone
purchased the pig hat and also the luxurious Deluxe top hat so that
will be coming out later as well.
Okay, so I guess if we're going to talk about that one part, then
again, that's information that I don't quite have yet which is what is
it that you are saying is, is
This ethical like, what are you going to be doing that?
You feel makes this more ethical than say what valve is doing with
Dota or something like this.
Okay.
So valve is probably the closest, okay?
So they're there you would call them as far down on the ethics like as
far down as far up on the ethical.
However you want to call it as close to good on the ethical scale as
as exists at the moment that I'm aware of.
But you are aware of.
Yes, I was and I actually have done quite a bit of research into this.
Okay.
What valve does wrong is they spend all of their development Budget
on.
Cosmetics.
The, I don't know.
I think there's 27 people working on DOTA last.
I heard and I don't know how those people's time are allocated but
based on what they won't have, I'm sorry, it's really distracting
seeing you with the pig hat on with stream delay.
So I have to minimize that.
Sorry.
So what valve valve, I think they've 27 people were going to do this.
Last I heard I don't know if that's true or not anymore but the
majority of their money seems to go into
Cosmetics.
Right, producing Cosmetics, based on what they actually release most
of their work seems to be cosmetics.
And another interesting thing is player content tools.
So there, you know, you can go make a cosmetic for DOTA and then sell
it on the valve store right there on Steam, Workshop stuff and all
that, right, right?
But they have like, they release like their 3D editing, like their
animation editing tools, they release their part,
Call system tools their whole pipeline for importing and creating
Cosmetics.
They've released all of that, right?
And they put a lot of effort into it because they're not like I've
tried them, they're not like developer tools, like they're actually.
Their you eyes are actions which are focused.
Yeah, exactly.
So they put they seem to be putting effort into that and cosmetic
items.
They're putting very little effort into
Very little resources relative to the rest of the development budget
or relative to their income is more like it.
Right to actually improving the game for everybody.
And that's where I think valves, that's where I have an issue with
valves ethics.
I mean, clearly they're doing like they're not bad because all their
stuff is free.
Like you can play the entirety of the game for free.
It's only Cosmetics, blah blah blah, all that's good but their
development resources.
I don't think our, I don't think they're putting in
Human Resources into making the game better, like there's still two
heroes from DOTA 1.
That have not been ported to Dota 2 for like three or four like six
years now or TI 55 years.
Now how is that possible?
Like, it's not that hard and they're making I don't know how much
built literally, billions of dollars off of it.
Like they should have been able to devote more resources to the game
and they're not and that's where I have an issue with what valves
doing but I think, otherwise, I'm okay with what I was doing.
so yeah, that would be my sort of ethical thing is basically what
valves
Aang, I don't know about the workshop in the user tools.
I'm not, I don't know how I feel about that and then actually, taking
the money that we make are free to play, and putting it all into the
game, not like 10% of it, and then going, and driving Ferraris off
cliffs or whatever they do with their money.
I'm pretty sure that driving for ours off.
Cliffs is a pretty big line item, but it probably doesn't account for
all of it.
Well, I don't know.
So, I guess the, the thing that I would point out which I mean,
hopefully, like, this is kind of obvious.
Right.
That what you just described is kind of what the primary fear is with
the whole concept of free to play, which is that, the product isn't
the game, the product is the part that you sell, that's what your
action making money off.
So isn't it kind of just a very natural consequence of trying to run a
business?
Whose product is the Cosmetics that most of the money would be spent
on the Cosmetics?
Like, isn't that kind of a consequence?
Of if a business adopts, this business model.
Well that's the case if it's like a publicly held Corporation because
they have to make the have to maximize profit, right?
But that's not the case revolved are not public and even if they said
the majority of their development, budget was spent on Cosmetics.
That's fine.
You can do that if they're spending an adequate amount on everything
else which they're not which is the problem, right?
So like if they're making I don't know how much what do they make.
Like a billion dollars off.
Do do last year Revenue.
I don't know what their expenses are but it can't be their server
expenses.
Can't be that high, right?
So they don't really have that high of a per user cost but they're
making I think to 70 per user per month or something like that.
If they were to take, you know, their let's say, they make half the
say, 250 million dollars profit, right somehow.
There aren't there.
They have 750 million dollars of server expenses.
I don't know how but that's what their that's what their server
expenses are.
If they're making only 250 billion dollars of profit off of the game,
they're not putting anywhere near that back into the game, right?
So when you're putting, you know, with 27 people, right?
Riot has 1000 right valve?
Could easily grow the DOTA team.
I know valves motto is we never hire people or whatever, and we hate
hiring, which is fine.
But when you take in that much money you have, I believe you have a
responsibility to put majority of it back into the game.
And if you want to spend, you know, if they're making six hundred
million dollars or whatever it is, and they
I put 200 million dollars back into the development over the course of
a year.
If they put 100 million of that into Cosmetics that's fine because
they're still putting 100 million into development which they're not.
I don't know how many people like I said, I don't have anymore
actually working on live development but
I feel like two people could be doing as much as they're as they're
getting done.
Not that's outside of their like content creation tools and things
like that.
But just actual content that's added to the game.
It's like two or three people's of work, two or three people's worth
of work.
So that's my problem with it is that they there
Enough into the into the actual development of the game.
They could like I said that they could put a lot into Cosmetics.
I don't think that's a problem.
As long as they put more back into it, but like you said, it's if
you're trying to run it as a business, if you're trying to run it as a
business to maximize profit, then know it can never ever be ethical
but you don't have to run a business to maximize profit.
Well, so I guess the next question that I would ask then is what is
that balance?
So
Normally in, you know, a traditional Marketplace.
If the question is, okay?
I am trying to provide this thing, whatever it is.
And in this case, it's a game.
Normally, what we do is we say, well, you know, I want to know how
much money I should put towards the development of the game.
So I set a price for the game, like a subscription fee, or whatever it
is.
And then, I know everyone who pays a subscription fee is trying to pay
me to develop more of this game.
That's really obvious like what that means.
But in the model that you're sort of advocating, it's sort of a like
developer honor System.
I guess you might call it.
You're basically saying, well, we're going to have the product not be
that thing.
Meaning, nobody pays for the development, the game development, the
game is just supposed to happen, right?
What you pay for is a bunch of cosmetic items, but we don't expect you
to spend all your time developing the Cosmetic items.
We expect you to in order to be an ethical developer to set some
percentage.
Of that diversion.
So how is that?
How are you seeing that as a model who set that percentage?
Do you set that percentage?
As the developer.
Are you making that percentage up?
Like how is that economic system working?
Well, it doesn't work because I don't think anyone does this in your
game that right?
Well, the kidding it's going to work.
Well, I mean it,
If a certain amount of money gets made that, yes, of course it will
work because there's enough money to throw at the problem.
And then, the problem goes away.
But will know, even that I'm not even talking about, the problem goes
away.
I'm like, saying, we have a decision.
We could hire another artist to make cosmetic items, or we can hire
another programmer to work on gameplay code or something, right?
Right.
Which one of those two people do?
We hire?
How is that decision getting made?
Yeah, like that's, you know, that's actually the root of the problem,
right?
I don't know how.
Actually, make that decision.
I think you'd have to make that decision.
I think you'd be able to so much transparent about it and just be
like, look, this is how much, you know, if we're open about it, we
say, look, this is how much money we're spending on development of the
game?
This is how much money we're spending on development of Cosmetics at
this, is how much money we're making.
I don't think we would talk about that, but maybe we could be public
with.
Here's the percentage that goes into development of cosmetics.
And here's the percentage that goes into development of the game, and
if we're transparent about that, does that alleviate that concern?
Well, I guess, I don't know if it'll
Alleviates the concern or not.
It's simply a more something to think about in terms of, if you
believe
You've that you know, this sort of a model was something that you're
saying is okay in general to adopt because presumably you're not I
mean maybe you are making the sergeant about no but presumably you're
not making the argument that you are.
The one company that has ever allowed to ethically adopt this model.
Presumably I sort of em.
Okay.
Okay, so so what you're saying is that if I wanted to make a game
using, you're allowed to all your eye, okay?
So there are two people.
There are two people allowed to do it.
Basically okay in all seriousness it you really saying that?
No well no but I there are very few people whom I would even trust
with what I'm asking.
People to trust me with if that makes any sense and I didn't and the
trust thing is an issue and I do hope that it can like we can't come
up with a way to
Be transparent enough that the trust isn't isn't there as an issue.
But yeah no I do think that it puts too much power into the developer
to make arbitrary decisions about where to spend people's money to
make the game better, right?
Like if the decision is entirely up to the developer and it's in a
black box and closed room and no one knows about it, right?
Like, that's a problem period, no matter who's in charge.
And I don't know how you sort of solve that other than with trusting
the developer.
Like you, like you were asking, is am I advocating that I'm the only
one who can do it?
I don't know who else I would trust with it to be completely honest.
So perhaps in like some weird way, I am saying that but yeah, I don't
know.
I don't know what to do about this other than hope that transparency
sort of salt it.
Well I think that there's a real problem there, right?
Because I mean essentially what you're saying if that is is what it
all boils down.
To essentially what you're saying is this is not a good idea, but
don't worry because I'm a
Good person.
So the fact that it's not a good idea is not going to affect me,
meaning?
No, I'm not saying that sentence that are there that are to drive
development in different directions than they should be driven.
I'm not going to fall prey to them because I'm me.
Uh-huh.
Well, I know I'd be like, that's like the funny way of phrasing it but
like no matter what you do, there's downsides right?
Like no matter what business model, you choose to run, there are
positives and negatives to it, right?
Let's say we this game cost 3 million dollars to make.
And let's say I have 3 million dollars and I spent three million
dollars and I make this game, right?
And I charge $40 for it, and it doesn't make that money, right, I'm
screwed.
Right, and that's not good for the game and the game will be a failure
and no one will play it in blah blah blah, right?
No matter what you do.
There's positives and negatives to your your business model choice,
right?
Doesn't matter what it is in this situation, the - of who controls
development resources and all and the question you brought
Yep.
I think, is far, far, far less of a negative than
Not having enough people to gather enough data to make intelligent
balance decisions or not.
Be able to run the community that we need to run and not be able to
run the matchmaking servers and and the game servers and all that fun
stuff that we need to run in order to make the game competitively
viable.
Not being able to run, those is much more of a negative than the
development resource.
Issue.
And in my opinion, do you disagree with that?
Yes, I mean I don't know that I disagree with with the specifics of
that analysis.
What I disagree with is the framing of it.
So what it suggests is that there's a pros and cons column of
different funding models.
And that what we're talking about is what are the pros of one and what
are the cons of the other?
But I don't think that's really a very fair way to
Look at what these business models actually mean.
Because actually what's more important about the business models is
not pros and cons but rather where the incentives are, right?
Meaning, it's sort of more, it's less like saying, you know what?
What, you know there's a risk here and there's a benefit there, it's
more saying okay, normally if you sell a game, your incentive is to
make the game good as a whole, right?
Okay?
There's no other
Other incentives there, right?
The only incentive is to convince people that this is a good game and
that they should buy it.
There are no, there's no smaller D.
You know, there's no more fine-grained incentive than that, that's
your goal.
The game is the product.
If you make it good, then it is a good product that people might want,
right?
If you don't, it isn't, there is it?
That's and that's very straightforward.
Right?
In the case that you're sort of advocating with the free-to-play, then
it's about what the incentives are for the developer.
You are not in
Devised as a developer economically, speaking, to make the game better
your incentivised to make a game where people will purchase add-ons,
that's what your incentivize to do.
Just straight up because you could make the best game that anyone's
ever had.
But if it doesn't run in a way that encourages add-ons, you will never
make the money you need to do any of the things you're talking about.
So it's less about what the pros and cons are and more about what you
as a developer must think about day to day in order.
Her to survive.
The first thing in your head has to be.
How do I monetize this game?
Rather than how do I make this game?
Great, how do I make this game?
Great is only a tangential step to the process of getting someone to
click on the, I want to buy a hat.
Does that make sense?
If that makes sense.
There's two things here.
And where's this, while you're answering that, I'm going to switch
hats from the pig to the Top Hat because someone thought that as well.
All right, then.
I want to know how much money you make off this, by the way.
Going to do something with it at handmade con all of the money that
comes from a doll, like I was, I was wanted to force you to have to
buy these things.
So the stream has I shouldn't have announced the URL that was my
mistake but okay I would have bought them.
Sorry.
All right that's how like anti everything I am.
I don't even have a credit card.
That's a problem or a cell phone.
Okay.
Press.
So anyways, okay so there's there's yes.
What you just said is completely true, it, right?
The first the first,
Why do you think we're looking at granny?
Because we have to do attachment points and skinning around attachment
points and things like that.
And that's just going to be like the hats on, man.
That's a, that's like a master program, right?
Like that's going to be like, you know, two months of work or
something, right?
Just to get all that right and get like a pipeline for exporting and
then attachment points and skinning meshes on attached.
Fuck that shit shit.
Sorry, I can't swear, that's that I didn't want to that's why we're
looking at granting, right?
Because because of free-to-play, right?
So
Yes, you're absolutely right.
That's something that we have to consider at all times.
If I may interject, this one pro tip and I learned this from many
years of working on that product try to watch your phrasing because
you end up saying things like, that's why we're looking at granny and
it just sounds bad out of context.
I've done a lot of things like, oh, man.
I've been doing granny 25 years or all these, like, you just want to
make sure that you just kind of say, like, you know, it was a mistake.
I admit that we should have named the product, something that doesn't
have those accidents in it.
Anyway, continue, did you choose the name?
We chose the name together I guess.
All right.
Well I like it.
Okay.
So the other issue I think is kind of naive from your point of view,
right?
Like it's not true that when you make a game that all you care about
is making a really good game to sell it like this just flat-out.
Just demonstratively.
Not true, right?
Like look at development.
Budgets versus marketing budgets of games, right?
Marketing budget of Halo is more than the development.
You my marketing budget of Madden or whatever is more in the
Development budget, right?
So that's not true.
And what's not true.
That the only thing you're concerned about with the create a product
and sell it model is that all you consider all you're concerned about
is quality, you're not going to do anything else, but no, but I'm
talking about the developer, the marketing budgets, the same in any
case, like you're going to have this.
All those same things are true about marketing on your end, meaning
right after market the game.
So, we're talking about the person developing the actual game, right?
But the, the freedom
Part of it could just be considered you know I'm a marketing thing,
right?
Like it could be like we're this is we're making the game,
irrespective irrespective, we're making the game completely in
isolation of the free-to-play and marketing stuff and the free-to-play
marketing stuff is done on its own with a separate budget and that's
like a marketing side, right?
That's different from the actual game.
Now, there's crossover of course, but if I know that again, I would
also disagree with that categorization, right?
Because they are fundamentally different in
In case you were talking about trying.
Raise the awareness of or convince people that they want to purchase
this game that you have made, right?
Yes.
In the other case you actually have to have the game itself.
Be something that has these things in it and that encourages you to
purchase them because otherwise you won't right.
No.
Yeah, okay.
But they're fundamentally different things.
One is about marketing.
A thing that you made the other is making a thing that has this
separate commercial product.
Inside of it.
And they're not, I don't think you can analogize them in a
straightforward fashion as you did, okay?
That's fair.
That's true.
On the flip side though, even the products themselves are different,
right?
Because this isn't like a product that you could put in a box and ship
and then the, then me as the developer would walk away from right,
like with diet or whatever, right?
I shift the game, and I'm done, right?
Save a bug patch, which I never actually had to do one for diet was
bug-free.
So,
I was just done, right?
So I shouldn't be getting any more money for that and I shouldn't be
worrying about it because I'm done with this game.
It's not done right when it comes out, even if it came out after three
million dollars or whatever amount of development budget to get like I
finished product out the game still not done ever.
It's potentially never done, right?
Because there's always if I'm always balances, there's always new
things to add, there's always new game modes, there's tons of crap,
like I have a, I've been thinking about this game for 6 years, right?
I have like, binders, full of notes about things that I want to try.
And this is an ongoing thing.
So having a payment model that matches the ongoingness of the design
and development of the game.
I don't think I think that actually is more ethical because now, I'm
encouraged to or incentivized house doesn't match the model the game,
because the things that people are paying for, aren't in the binders.
Okay, but if it incentivizes, no, I'm not.
Implementing the binders because they can't buy the stuff that's in
the binders, that's in the binders is the game that you guys do for
free.
Well it's not well yes that's that is a that is a very black and white
I think way of looking at it right?
You say all you're doing is developing all you care about is are all
that matters for making money is the Cosmetics, right?
And that's just not true.
Like if the game isn't good.
Although
This statement I can say there's evidence that it's not true.
But in the except for the case of League of Legends games that the
game has to be good, it has to continuously improve it has to get
better.
It has to actually be a good game.
Money needs to be spent on the development of the game.
Otherwise, people notice that you're only doing cosmetics and people
lose interest, right?
And it's not and these are old, like, literally only Cosmetics.
There's no play to win or anything like that.
So there's no
Sensitive to we can't make the game not better.
We have to continuously make the game better.
So that's I don't think that I don't think that separating them in
such a black-and-white way.
Is fair.
I think it's actually I wouldn't even call it just fair.
I would almost say that what you just said is exactly the point that
I'm trying to make the way you described.
It was perfect was exactly encapsulated what I feel is so detrimental
about the business model, right?
The way you talked about it is like we can't we have to make the game
good.
So far no one will play it.
Dot dot dot so we won't so no one will buy the hats right?
And it's like that is exactly the correct the correct statement for
the position, the developers in the game and making it good enough.
The only requirement is as good enough that people will play it, so
they'll buy the hats.
There is no not right.
That's well, I only said it for demonstrating your point.
Here, that is true.
That is the minimum goodness, that the game has to be right.
But like, yeah, that's the problem.
Okay.
But there's a minimum goodness that the next Assassin's Creed game has
to be, has to be to write, like there's a minimum goodness at the next
Call of Duty game has to be too, right?
And whatever the companies that make those are will push to that
minimum and that's it.
How is that any different?
Well, that I don't think that's actually true at those games, right?
If they make a much better game or at least the theory is, if you make
a much better game, especially as an independent developer, you know,
with when you're talking about Triple, AAA with extra as, on the end
of it or whatever, then again, kind of who
Always because maybe it's goes into the realm of like pop culture and
marketing and at that point or whatever.
But for an indie Studio.
At least if you make a much better game, presumably a lot more people
are talking about it.
A lot more people are playing at that sort of thing.
It's the kind of a thing where the game itself is in general.
The better.
It is the more of a product.
It becomes, whereas instead, if you just talked about a situation
where it's like, well we make money on this separate part of the
A game that isn't the game because nobody paid for the game.
Then really, we have a different curve that we're shooting for, it
doesn't even necessarily matter how many people play the game, what
matters is.
If the people who spend a lot of money on add-ons, play the game, we
don't even care.
If good players play this game, it could all be bad players that play
this game.
We don't even care if it's balanced because balance won't necessarily
affect it, right?
We don't even know and it doesn't matter all of those things.
They are only relevant to our survival in so far as they
Might prevent people from participating in the secondary economy,
whereas none of those things would generally be true for a different
type of game for different type of game, you know, it's just the
product you don't, you're not, there's no way Little Miss to it.
There's no concept that certain players are more valuable for us to
have that others.
None of, that is true, right?
So I don't see, I don't see how you're getting there.
I don't see her getting there with that.
Well, okay, so all of what you just said describes Riot to a tee.
Right.
That's, that's right.
Right there.
Right?
All they care about is getting their maximum like they don't care
about the competitiveness of it like there's just years of
demonstrating that they don't care about the quality of the game.
They only care about catering to their most valuable players or
whatever, right?
And and yes, that's, you know, that happens.
That's why free-to-play sucks, right?
But that doesn't need to happen, it doesn't have to be that way,
right?
Like that's just because it's easy to make money.
When you do that, that's what people do but that doesn't, it doesn't
have to be that way, right?
Like valve does a pretty reasonable job of not doing that.
They do some stuff with, you know, rewards at the end of the game and
randomized boxes and all that fun stuff that they do that stuff is
questionable.
But for the most part the way in which they
The way in which they balance the game, at least, the way in which the
game design ideas are applied to slowly in my opinion.
But the way in, which the game ideas, are applied, like ice frogs
balances and you know, whenever they remodel a hero, they do a really
good job with it.
Like everything is the voice acting is incredible and that's all free
or whatever.
They're putting the money into actually making the game better.
And I think that if you look at relative player, rates relative
player, base increases or decreases and you look at DOTA vs League of
Legends.
The graphs are like in the complete opposite direction, right?
DOTA is gaining players at the relative rate that league is losing
players.
So I think that
The the quality of the game is what is actually does matter.
You're saying it has absolutely no bearing on anything.
The only thing that matters is the quality of the things that you sell
or the way in which you construct, your Skinner box to get people to
buy things, right?
And I don't think that's true.
It doesn't have to be true.
It might be true in most examples, but I don't think it has to be
true.
I think you can make the game and continue to make it better with the
money that you're making off.
The free-to-play, things spend a good chunk of your money on.
Actually improving the game versus spending it on hats.
I don't see why you can't do that.
Well, it's not really that you can't do something, right?
Because most things that are a bad idea or most things that are
generally unethical.
Like if you're talking about a process, a virtuous, and divine being
who comes down and wants to do them in a way that isn't evil could
write like, you know, you can be
Be a stockbroker who isn't evil.
It's just the system is not set up to reward that.
So as a result, that is not who stays in business, right?
The people who participate in business models, which are inherently
rewarding of devious Behavior, or manipulative Behavior.
The people who tend to survive are the ones who engage in that
behavior, right?
That's just that's just the nature of incentives.
They are creating a feedback function, which makes it more likely that
bad behavior is reinforced, right?
That's it.
That's, that's true.
That is certainly true.
So that again, that's why I think it gets back to what we started this
with which is it sounds like what you're saying is, yes, the business
model has all of the problems that we're talking about, but the reason
you don't have to worry about it is because I Sean McGrath
I am a good enough person, that that's not going to happen to me,
right?
Okay.
So there's there's, there's two things here.
We talk about incentives.
I want to get back to incentives in a second, but the Mishima graph of
being benevolent dictator or whatever.
Now, I would like Plato.
It's a Play-Doh sort of, you know, the classic Plato thing dictators
are great.
If you have the exact right one?
Yes exactly.
So I'm willing to hear any ideas.
Minimize my power in this relationship that I would be bringing on
with people who might buy a hat and my game, right?
I'm I want to not be a benevolent dictator.
I would much rather be in a situation where
I'm like, legally enforced or legally required or something to not be
a dick.
Like if if there's a law that that like requires it, I would feel
totally comfortable with that and I don't actually have an answer to
that.
I don't know what I can do to like alleviate that concern.
But what I, what I am getting at though, is that in this situation
because of my goals for the game which are to make it a highly
competitive,
High quality, you know, do level quality, much more competitively
viable than even DOTA game free to play.
Fits that better than anything else.
And yes, it has downsides.
And yes, those downsides can potentially be crazy evil.
But you know, what can you do?
But you were talking about, by the way and what can you do?
Isn't rhetorical what can you do?
If you can give me ideas and suggestions or anybody has any ideas or
suggestions to what I can do to sort of shift the balance of power
away?
From, you know, a benevolent dictator two people.
I would love to hear it because I'm certainly would like to do that,
right?
Like, I don't this isn't a scam to make a whole bunch of money.
This is like, I literally think free-to-play is the best possible
option for this game because you were talking about incentives before,
right?
And I was saying that the development cost is an ongoing thing, right?
I'm incentivised to continue to work on the game and continue to make
it better.
Now, whether or not you think that the incentive
Is more towards making hats or more towards making a better game.
It can't be argued that there is at least something to making a better
game.
Where after a game that's been released, that's been sold with the
sticker price.
There's no more incentive to work on the game ever, right?
We can shut the server's down next week, you know release.
Game shut the server's down, right?
That would actually be the most economically viable thing to do.
That's what I would be incentivized to do, right?
Make the game sell as much as possible.
Shut the server's down as soon as possible.
That's how that would be the best way to make money off of a game
where you just buy it at the start.
So, well, not really if you assume that people buy it over time but
either way, like shut it down as soon as possible.
Right.
Well yeah, after you, I guess when your tail when you perceive there
to be no more you you aren't really gaining any more users I guess
than you would say, okay.
Well
We'll finish.
But yeah, so I guess what I would say though, there is what you're
saying when you're saying like, you know, if there's some law or if
there's something, I guess, what I was trying to say at the beginning
was that that's what traditional purchasing models are traditional
purchasing models are the best thing that we found for ensuring that
what you sell is the thing, you are incentivized to make.
That's what that is.
It's because we don't know how to create a law that says, if we're
paying generally money for this thing,
Is do a good job, separating it.
We don't know of a better way to do that.
Right?
If we did, we should replace capitalism in general with that concept.
Because man, that would be better, right?
Yeah.
So capitalism is just the only way we've actually found that like
concept that there's a product with some profit margin built-in and
you look to see what you might want.
To spend your money on and you buy that thing.
That is what we figured out that is that law.
And so when you replace that with free-to-play, what you're doing is
saying, you're saying, you don't want to play by that law anymore,
you're saying you don't actually
We want the law where people have to buy a particular thing.
That is the thing that they actually are getting instead, you're
trying to sort of bifurcate that and say, well, I don't feel like I
can figure out a way to sell you this product as a product.
So instead, I'm going to give it to you and then try to get you to do
other things that will Generate random revenue for me.
And that, like I said, despite anything that we said on the stream so
far, really just sounds to me like a trust me, right?
It's like, trust me.
I won't make it Sleazy.
And at the end of the day,
Okay, you might not right, you might not do that, but that doesn't
really change any arguments fundamentally about the business model,
the business model itself still has none of that protection for the
consumer built into it.
Whereas say even a model that was more like every four months we sell
the update to this thing which is the new game set that people buy or
something or a subscription model where you pay a small amount a
dollar a month or something.
Like this would have that built-in because now you're just
incentivised to
Give people a good overall experience and there is no need to create
things where they're incentivized to shop to buy hats to do whatever
which you know if you're fantastically lucky and maybe it's just you
and Five Guys or whatever, hey you hit some, it's it hits big and you
never have to worry.
So you're not incentivised to make bad decisions all that much and
you're a good guy.
So it goes great or whatever.
But think about the other case, where you're just, it's on the line.
You don't know if you're going to make payroll next month and you can
do this giant hat, promotion, or
It's like, it's just not set up to incentivize good, behavior know.
And like you said, okay, so that example, you just head right where
you do the giant, you do the giant hat sailrite, okay?
So you do the giant hat sale.
Okay, so you have to do that, right?
But the other
The other you do that, giant has sold as temporary thing, by the way,
don't mean.
Like that's the whole game, but then it's a lot of money and then it's
like, well, every quarter, we have, the giant hat sale.
Okay let's just let's let's hypothetically say that happened.
Yeah, a little slippery slope.
I'm just I'm just giving you a stuffy whole, it's a slippery slope.
Yeah, but like your example of we do a giant hat sale once every four
months or three months, right?
That's not so bad like that's not that's not the end of the world,
right?
Like if you change the game and you sacrifice, you know, development
resources to do the hats or you, you know what, by hats everywhere,
while you're playing the game or whatever, then you have a problem,
how are you going to do a giant hat sale without doing the things?
You just said, I mean, you have to put a ton of
Art Resources by making the hundred hats of the Hat sale and the, and
the hat Days of Christmas, right?
The 12 days of hat, mess or whatever, right?
I mean, we're right, isn't that exactly what we're talking about that?
No.
Okay, I don't think so.
I think like to a degree.
Yes.
Right.
But I think, when you, you have to take the other side of it to,
right, which is you're getting ongoing revenue and you can use your
ongoing Revenue to support ongoing development, right?
And I think that's, that's really important.
That's a
It's a very important distinction between making your money up front.
If you make your money up front, you can't do that.
Now, you're talking about subscription and I think I think
subscription is just just dead.
I don't think you could do subscription.
Like I don't think it's financially viable to do subscription.
If you can prove me wrong.
I'd like to hear examples, but from what I can tell, sorry, not
Snapchat, sorry, WhatsApp, I mean for a game and what's app is free
and dollar-a-month pressure?
I'm sorry dollar year, it was dollar a year.
It was, but I'm pretty sure it's free now.
Well, you have to Facebook
Autumn.
Okay, so it's been dead for three.
Four, five years.
Well, but they got, I mean, millions of people they had.
I mean, how do you know how many users they had it with some
ridiculously huge number, right?
Yeah, blizzard had how many tens of millions or 10 million or whatever
playing playing paying for while monthly they don't anymore?
I don't know.
Like that was that game is also I mean how old is that game?
I don't even want to know how old I bet you they're making more money
now with free to play to be honest than they ever were.
Oh
Yeah, and again, I will never argue with you that you will make more
money if you want to go like the free-to-play route, right?
It's a big money maker because it's a way of kind of sucker in people
into something, right?
And then charging them different ways that you figure out to, to
charge them, right?
But I could play.
As you're like, I don't know, are you sure?
This is scription can't work, right?
I mean like pretty pretty, pretty sure.
How like WhatsApp was was pretty late in the game, like Zynga had.
It was already had come and gone by the time WhatsApp.
I was charging a dollar a year for.
Okay.
Okay, so let's use it.
Let's, I'd like to hear a game example, right?
Because from what I could tell, every game is getting off of
subscription and going to free to play.
Now that could be just to maximize Revenue, I don't know, but the
counter, the other argue, the other side of like, my two points about
why I thought freedom play was best.
The other side is
Sorry what was said, I've already lost my train of thought, sorry, the
other side was we did as many people as possible in order to get
balance data to get data to balance the game right now because she's
supremely important like the number one.
Most important thing is if we get 100 million people playing the game
or whatever ridiculous number, we can get like 10 million, people
100,000 people playing the game would be fantastic.
That gives us enough data to actually make it tells you balance
positions, right?
I don't think we can, we can get that.
With without it being free, I just don't think that the end.
I don't think people are willing to spend a dollar a month, even?
I just don't like if you can if there's a game that you can point me
to where they've actually successfully recently in the last two years,
successfully run a subscription model, I would like to hear it because
I haven't heard, I don't know of any.
What does Eve online do?
By the way, Eve online is weird.
There are subscription but you can you can buy in game, you can buy
your subscription cards with in-game
Currency.
So people make money off of like creating in-game currency by blowing
up ships, and salvaging them, and stuff, and then buying time cards
and then selling those.
So very interesting concept, okay?
Eve is one of the most interesting games, okay, out there.
If you're ever interested in reading about fiction in games, you
should read about Eve protection because like the Russian mafia lost
two hundred fifty thousand dollars in like one day and there was a
huge drama but it it's really great.
It's great.
Anyways.
So no I do are they like is their revenue, then coming from a
subscriptions that was a couple years ago when I learned about that.
I don't know about it now but maybe but I bet you it's purely
historical.
Okay.
I mean games that are like new games that have come up because Eve has
been around for 10 years or whatever.
Well, here's another question for you.
So, how much money are you expecting people to spend on this game
every month in general with your FTP model?
Okay.
That's a that's a pretty complex question.
Do you mean just median dollar spent per user playing or do?
You mean, like they're okay, two bucks.
Two bucks bucks.
Two bucks a month on average per person.
So basically we're talking 20 for dollars a year.
Yeah, so basically it's like them buying a game buying your game at
retail or whatever, you know, on on steam or something once every year
once every two years, something like that.
Well I don't know what your price point is, could be $25, right?
It would be.
This is going to be like a pretty like DOTA level quality so tissue.
So it might not be every two years.
It would be every year then because
Have to pay twenty four dollars a year for a DOTA level games.
Going to be 25 bucks, not not 12.
If you played it and see the quality of the voice acting and all that
fun stuff, I'm just saying it's yeah what I'm saying.
It should be 25 and you're going to be 12 every two years would.
Oh sorry I'm saying I'm saying it should be like 60 bucks.
Okay.
So it's more like it's about twice a year.
You have to buy it at the beginning of the year and in the middle of
the year or something like that.
Am I getting my math wrong?
If I'm spending $25 every year.
That's $50 every two years.
Ears, which would be buying the game once every two years.
Never mind.
Yes.
I guess that's true.
Okay, you're doing your math, right?
Okay.
You're doing your math rock.
That is correct.
All right, at least one of us was all right.
So they have to buy the game once every two years and how long is this
game going to be running for?
This is the this is where I think that I'm being super non benevolent
dictator e here.
Once the game is like once we shut down production and shut down
servers or whatever the game is either public domain or GPL with all
Assets available as well.
So the game will run until we don't run it anymore at which point
everything is released for free.
But what is your goal for house?
10 years, 10 years.
So basically what you're talking about is people, if they were going
to buy this game in general,
Over 10 years time you want them to spend something on the order of
250 dollars on your game?
Yes.
$250 per player over 10 years sure which would translate into
something like buying the 50 dollar game five times.
Yeah, okay, and so, in your opinion, there's no way you could do that
in that actual way, meaning you could not do something where you sold
the game up front and they bought an expansion pack, every couple
years or something like this.
That's not on the table.
No, that's that's that doesn't work.
That that makes the game worse and it makes the game worse because
there's a whole bunch of reasons why making it more.
So let's say you and I play together to Team game, right?
So we're friends, we play against it, we play with each other, right?
I'm financially able
Purchase the game and you're not right now.
The game is segregated where you can't play with your friend.
Because one person could purchase the game of one person.
Can't write if the game is just completely free for everybody with no.
Like you all non cosmetic items are unlocked for everybody at all
times.
It means that everybody plays the exact same game all the time and
there's no segregation which you would get with the.
You have to buy the game every six months or every year or whatever.
Okay.
But so that's Switching gears a little bit that's not really talking
about the financial side of things that's talking about more of the
accessibility of
Of this game.
Yes, no, I'm not stalking with making the best game possible for the
people who are playing it point of
Like if you're, if we're talking about, I'm my argument is that in
this particular situation, doing free-to-play is the best option for
the people who are playing.
And I don't, maybe that's, that's what, that's what, that's what I'm
that's where I'm coming from, right?
Okay.
I just think put that part of it aside.
For one second, I was trying to just finish off our discussion on the
actual payment model.
Is there a problem with selling the game?
That way?
If you factored out the the social aspect that you were starting to
bring into it there where you want everyone to be able to access the
game.
I was trying to figure out there any other business models that you
consider potential possible, or if you think that literally FTP is the
only one that
Actually works because that's sort of more where I thought you were
saying before you were like subscriptions dead.
We can't sell this game.
I was like, okay, why can't you sell the game again?
Just remind me of why you can't just sell this game.
Okay.
So that's why we can't just sell the game is because there's ongoing
things and we have to run the server and the game is going to be
constantly changing.
And if we sold the game, the way you just said it, segregates, the
game for different people in your accessibility thing comes up, but if
you don't care about the accessibility, then you could sell the game
that way.
You don't think so you could like you're saying, is it financially
viable.
Yeah.
In other words, do you feel?
Like there are reasons you couldn't just sell the game as a product
that are separate from what you who you want to be able to access it?
Well, I don't know, but I don't think you can just separate who you
want to be able to access it because those are like, like, let's say
you buy the game and two years later, your buddy wants to play it,
John Blow or
He likes it, he finds out about it, he's like, I want to play this
game, he buys it.
And now you have to pay like, $200 to catch up to him or whatever or
pay fifty dollars, or whatever.
After you've already bought it once, like that's just that's weird,
right?
Like that, like that demanding, that people pay money in order to
continue playing it or like, separating it.
So that these are the people who have spent money this, this quarter
or, is this half year or whatever it is.
And these are the people who haven't that's just weird.
And probably makes the
Game worse and like that just doesn't sound.
That sounds like it makes the game worse for players, and I don't
think that you can separate that from well.
Hold on anything.
I mean, keep in mind though that it's, it's all the same amount of
money, right?
That we're talking about here.
So somebody had to still pay $250 worth of cosmetic hats or something,
to make it up in the in your other case, right?
In the words that you can't just say, like, oh okay, well it's weird
to charge people for the game that they're actually playing.
Because somehow now it's considered
Weird, I guess for people to pay for the game that they're playing.
But it's not considered weird that we're expecting the average player
to spend $250.
Buying hats.
Mmm, that's what you just said.
If I may.
Okay, let's go ahead and say that.
That's what I said.
Well, tell me how that's not what you said.
I guess it's more of the interesting part.
You're thinking not okay to expect someone to buy this game.
Every time I would love to do know.
It's you totally could expect somebody to.
I just don't think people are willing to spend it.
So you said it was weird to say.
I think it's about here, is that?
Yes, I think I think.
I think it's we, I do think it's and then it makes the game worse.
Those are the two things you said, yes.
And I do think it's true.
Look at take a look at Starcraft 2, for example, right?
Not my favorite game.
Quite awful.
Game actually, but
Every couple of years that come out with a new expansion set, right?
And if you don't buy that expansion set you just you can't play the
game anymore, right?
So you've bought a game you've spent your $60 or whatever and you
wanted to keep playing it now, you can't put anymore because no one is
playing that version.
They're only playing the upgraded version, right?
So in order for you to continue playing, you have to pay right, right?
Okay.
So that that is how that model works, right?
Right.
That's a worse.
That's worse for the player, I think.
Okay.
That is that worse.
the player that basically means that if you don't want to play this
game anymore,
you don't pay the Developers for the work that they did over the past
two years, right?
Mmm, why is that weird?
What's so weird about that to you?
Because there's there's a social pressure of because it's a team game
and it's a multiplayer game, there's a social pressure of playing with
your friends right?
And if your friends are all paying $100 or whatever they're forcing
your almost that's almost forced upon you to continue playing the game
where if it's free to play you just don't write like you just don't
pay and you can still play, right?
Like when we
Who says that right?
Somebody has to buy another $250 worth of hats to cover their not Hat
by.
Yes, that's absolutely true.
And you don't think that's weird.
I do think that's weird.
Do you think it's less weird?
Yes.
I think it's.
I think it's less.
I think it's equally weird.
Maybe more weird but whoa okay but its overall
Impact.
T' on the quality of the game for the average player.
If we're concerned about the quality of the game, experience for the
average player playing, I think the free-to-play model delivers a
better quality because you're just going to get more people playing.
And the more people playing means, the more competitively viable.
The game is means the more the the less wait time there is when
finding a match all of these things, right?
The more people that are playing the better, the game is, right?
So if you say you have to pay your alienating people, right?
So that's just flat-out, true?
And you're there for the game quality is going to be suffering.
Now, if you are
Alienate people every six months or whatever.
You're never going to get, like, your player count is never going to
go up.
It's only going to continuously, go down and as your player count goes
down the quality of your game goes down.
And that would mean that.
The method that you're saying of paid fifty dollars every two years or
whatever, you're getting a worst game, the longer the game goes on.
Okay.
But is that actually true meaning that like do so from what you're
sort of suggesting right?
If what if everything that you're saying was actually true, we should
have expected League of Legends to be fantastic right now.
Right?
Because well right, so what y if this model is encouraging this and
Starcraft should be much a much worse game than League of Legends,
right?
It probably is about the about, they're both equally bad.
Okay?
They're both equally bad.
I haven't played either them so I have no idea.
I played the original Starcraft but I haven't played one since then.
Okay.
I think you're actually talking about Starcraft 2, not sorry.
I'm sorry about your Starcraft to start off.
One is a fantastic game, okay?
Yes.
Okay, so Starcraft 2, I don't know, I don't think there is a
significant quality difference between Starcraft 2.
I mean, there's a quality difference between Starcraft, 2 and League
of Legends, Starcraft 2 is clearly a much higher.
It's made by blizzard, they know
Doing right, we're Riot.
I don't necessarily think they do, so I don't think they're that there
is any correlation between either of these models and quality in the
real world, okay?
So you think that's actually unrelated
I don't know if I don't know, I don't know.
I'm gonna say yes.
And if you come back with something where I'm clearly wrong, I'm fully
willing to change my mind on this.
But yes, for the moment I'm going to say they're more or less
unrelated.
Okay, I'm saying, but I'm saying both models produced for the most
part crap, bad situations, or higher in everything produces a bad
situation for the most part.
Okay.
Well I mean, I guess like I said it's a certain extent.
I think most of this is continuously keeps coming back to the fact
that I don't
Holistic Lee know how much argument there is to be had here?
Because even that statement right kind of just says you're almost
saying the model is really it's not even really an argument it's
because it's just like trust me.
I'm going to do something different than everyone else does.
Anyway so again we're kind of back to the like why is this an okay
decision?
It's an okay decision because I'm not going to mess it up basically,
right?
No I stay I get well yes but not just that like I actually think and I
think
Ink that it's from what I've said.
It's pretty truthful.
I think that free-to-play actually has the potential to produce, at
least the way I want to do.
It has the potential to produce a better gaming experience for the
average player playing.
And I don't think that's true of this early any existing free-to-play
models but or any existing free-to-play implementations, but I
certainly think that that's true for this case.
Like I actually think it will produce a better game, which is why I
think,
it's a totally viable business model well, and you do realize that it
does sound a little bit suspicious when you say something like
No, existing free-to-play game.
Ever actually satisfied.
The criteria that I'm talking about, but I think this new one that I'm
going to do won't have the problem.
Whereas, on the other hand, we do have plenty of examples of people
who sell their games who don't have this problem, right?
Yes.
You're plenty of examples of people some games that have is similar,
not obviously the same issue, but similar at the whole issue is right.
But one thing we have positive examples in one case where as the case
Talking about, we have no positive examples face, okay.
Okay.
But that's not a reason to totally throw something away.
It's not, but you have to understand, that's what you're basically
saying.
So you're saying, we have no evidence that this model works but I'm
still saying, trust me, I'm going to make it work.
Do I think?
I think Dota 2 is better off being free to play.
Okay, I think if Dota 2 charged money for the game.
It would be a less good game.
Okay, I'm not saying that they're doing it ethically.
I'm like 100% ethically.
I'm saying that that business model makes that game better.
Okay.
So you think that but I can just get back to the FTP thing.
So you're actually saying that you think Dota 2 is an example of a
positive f2p game.
Yes, yes, I'm saying that but I'm not saying that it is that it meets
what I would consider my minimum moral or minimum ethical standards or
whatever.
Okay, so you have minimum ethical standards and you don't know of a
free-to-play game that meets them.
I don't over free to play game that made some that's true.
And I do think that Dota 2 kind of comes close and I think that Dota 2
is better off being free to play the not being free to play.
Do you know, any of examples of games that you just?
People just sell like a traditional game, where you buy it that meet
your minimum ethical standards.
Nowadays.
Yeah, there's plenty of small.
There's plenty of indie games to do.
Okay.
From a big Corporation, though.
I don't think so, but so just to get back to the just just so we can
solidify that one point.
So, we are, at least in agreement that there are no examples of
free-to-play games that meet your ethical standards at all.
But there are examples of games that just people buy that, do meet
your minimum ethical standards.
Yes.
Does that trouble you at all?
Know why not
Is none of the games that meet my minimal, ethical standards are
multiplayer.
Esport type games that require maintenance constant maintenance
overtime to keep the game.
Good and constant work on back-end infrastructure and server and all
that fun stuff, right?
So, none of the games have the expenses or the long, the long-term
expenses and development costs of one of these games that you do by.
And that,
I consider ethical.
So there's a difference there between what the product actually is,
right?
No game.
That does what I'm saying with this long-term server stuff and
long-term development stuff, no game that does that?
That's
Old in a store is ethical, in my opinion.
Well I guess what I just to clarify though, that is an example or
that's an explanation of why you believe, you must try the
free-to-play model.
That is not an explanation of why.
It doesn't worry you that you are that you have no positive examples
of something meeting your minimum ethical bar.
Oh, but I'm saying that I have no positive examples of a game that had
that
has its long-term.
I'm saying that I have no positive examples of a game that has the
long-term requirements that we have, that's sold in a store either.
There's just no positive examples, period, free to play or not free to
play of games that have this sort of ongoing thing that I are.
You feeling hungry thing like literally in the store right now,
though.
I mean, I'm assuming if you look in history, you'd find lots, right?
Like wouldn't Ultima Online or EverQuest those those
Meet that criteria.
I I think Ultima Online.
What?
I don't know all too well.
How about Guild Wars?
Guild Wars?
Doesn't meet that criteria.
They're free to play know the I'm talking about in history.
So the original Guild Wars was $40 every every year or something like
that.
That was their model.
You bought.
You bought the latest Guild Wars.
Yeah, that would do fine.
I would, I would prefer, you know, how much more I would prefer to do
that, but I don't think it.
I don't think that's, I don't think it'll work.
I just I flat out, don't I don't think it'll work and I don't think
it's actually as good for the game.
Okay.
So, but again, just to get back to the original question.
Yep.
No, there are no examples in anything.
There are no free to play examples that I consider ethically sound and
that does not worry.
You, that was my question.
Why doesn't it worry you
That's what I think it does worry.
I like we're having this discussion, right?
So clearly clearly it does worry me.
Okay.
All right.
So you like, or at least what you do at least worry about this?
Well yes.
Otherwise I wouldn't be having this conversation right.
Okay, okay.
Alright so that's good.
Okay, so let's let's move on.
I think we've kind of got that under control at least.
All right I think I feel like or at least if you have some additional
things that you feel like you haven't explored about your thoughts on
that part of it, we can go there but I do know I've got most of that
out.
Yeah, I think that's good.
I was sorry.
I was confused with with, okay, what were you trying to get there?
But yes, okay, so let me ask a question about the thing that you
brought up before, which was sort of, you sort of started to say, and
it sounded like a lot of what you were sort of talking about in terms
of why you don't want to sell the game.
You kept saying, you think it would make it worse game and what it
sounded like you kept coming back to was the concept that you would
like there to be a symmetric payments on the part of the users,
meaning,
You want it to be the case that some people don't pay for the game.
And some people pay a lot of money for the game.
That is what you were sort of saying, right?
Is that a correct statement of what you were saying before about?
That's a good thing in your mind you have to quantify a lot, right?
Like I'm, I'm not, okay.
With, you know, the people spend ten thousand dollars or whatever on a
free to play game, like I'm not okay with that.
We have some ideas about how to alleviate that such as once.
You hit a certain amount of expenses for the month, like, one idea
that we have is like, let's say, fifty dollars, which is a $50.
If you spend $50 for a month, you just get everything unlocked for the
rest of the month or whatever and whatever you paid for like, Whatever
item you bought.
You still get to keep those for future months, but that way Wales
won't spend more than $50 a month.
Like there's a hard cap on it, right?
If you do spend more,
Or.
You're not getting anything, right?
So there are things that I want to do to make sure that that doesn't
happen.
Right?
Where people are spending ten thousand dollars or you know five
hundred dollars a month or I don't want to Star Citizen situation but
the asymmetric payment within bounds I think is okay.
Yeah, okay.
So basically what you're saying there is you want a sort of a
non-explicit self-balancing market where some people
Get a service for free because somebody else paid too much for it,
right?
If you want to say too much.
That's I don't know if too much is fair, but because the median price,
right?
This is the cost to the everyone.
To play this game was going to be two dollars and fifty cents a month
or something.
You said I but whatever you say, it was hypothetical number right?
But sure.
Yeah.
So the median cost me 250 and so we're basically saying is some people
will get to fifty two dollars and fifty cents worth of game
development and of course we're still
Still not sure about that part.
So maybe let's say they're getting a dollar or two dollars of game
development and 50 cents.
They're not getting because that's into the Cosmetics, right?
Because you're saying basically you're allocating These funds in some
percentage way, so I don't know.
But let's just say it's some reason percentage of that.
So you're doing this on the graphing, you are virtuous person.
So out of every two dollars and fifty cents, you're actually spending
$2 on developing the game not cosmetic items or something like this.
Let's just check.
Sure.
Sure, sure.
We are good.
A good portion of, yes.
Pharaoh something, something that's pretty high, right?
You're only putting 50 Cent's towards the actual money, making part.
You're spending $2 on something everyone gets right?
Well this part there's there's company profit involved to so would
actually be less than that.
But yes, but yes but it's relatively magnanimous compared to what you
could be doing which is spending, say 50 cents on the game and two
dollars on the monetization, right?
You mean you could be right, you could back percentage could change
wildly but yeah, whatever it is sure.
So, what I'm saying is for every person who doesn't pay 250 a month,
Right?
Someone else has to pay five dollars a month, right?
So someone else is getting in terms of gameplay, they're getting
still, you know, they're shorted a certain amount on the actual game.
But someone else is getting that that for free basically, right.
Yes, but I don't like your usage of the word too much.
It's all like what to say above.
The median is fine, but I think too much carries too much negative
connotation.
Okay, they're paying for I guess.
I don't know how
It, let's call it a subsidy.
They are subsidizing, perhaps we should say players who are not
playing for the game, because without them, we all the people who are
paying more for the game.
None of the other people would be able to play the game who aren't
paying for it right now.
Absolute.
Right.
So that's that's kind of the idea, right?
Absolutely.
And so this to you, you think that's a good idea, meaning you think
it's good to have a market where basically some people pay more money
for something so that other people don't
Have to pay for that thing but that is not actually structured in any
reason away.
So meaning the person who doesn't pay, 250 might have the 250.
They just decide not to pay it and the person who pays the five
dollars, that may actually be their last five dollars.
That doesn't actually matter.
It's just you like that system in general irrespective.
Well, I mean, if somebody spends their last five dollars, there might
be, you know, no, I don't like that.
But yeah, in general, I mean, I think,
It's too black and white in the way in which your framing it.
I think, because you're just you're flat out your enticing, the
somebody's going to have to spend a hundred thousand dollars on this
so that you know, 25,000 people are 20,000 people or whatever can get
it for free, right?
Like that's where you're going with this and I don't think that's
really fair necessarily.
I wasn't going there, I was actually trying.
I'm actually trying to get you to describe to me what you are thinking
of, in terms of who pays for what and is that fair?
Yeah, I think I think it's totally fair that some
People who are willing to and able to subsidize for people who aren't
willing are our table.
Yeah, I think that's totally fair.
I mean I think that if you look at I mean, this is this is a grandiose
claim or whatever.
But I think if you look at any sorry, I keep shitting on your country.
But if you look at any water and why it might not be as much as you
did probably, all right.
Well, if you look at any more like a modern reasonable, industrialized
Nation, they have things like subsidized health, care and subsidy, all
sorts of subsidies subsidized.
Childcare subsidized, everything, where there is
Payment people who are able to pay pay more and you know I'm not a
government.
I don't have the ability to enforce people who are able versus people
who are unwilling, right?
So they're the same thing as far as I'm concerned.
So I mean they're not the same thing as far as the government is
concerned but there's same thing as far as me as a game developer are
concerned, right?
So yes people who are able to pay more
Do and people who are less able.
Don't I don't think there's anything wrong with that now.
Okay?
So yeah, if I could expand on that, because that is exactly, that's
what I'm assuming was the answer.
Okay.
So I do have a number of problems with that.
So the first problem I have with that is I don't think it constructs
much of an analogy to socialism, because in socialism, you have a
system where you actually are at least trying to be nominally
needs-based.
Meaning it really actually is trying to assess whether somebody can
pay for a thing or not and the
idea behind you.
No more of a socialist run system is that we try to make sure that
everyone gets this service and the people who can pay
It pays to pay more for it, than the people who can't write okay, in
your model, that's not true at.
All right?
Somebody may have lots of money and they just decide not to pay for
this game and then other users who want to see that, you know, let's
say, we're in hard times, right?
It's a question about whether your games going to stay up and running
a bunch of users, who really don't potentially have the money to be
spending on this and possibly should be doing something else like
saving for retirement with that money or doing whatever else, right
start buying more items because they want to keep
the game afloat, right?
There's nothing in the system that you're talking about.
That actually has a needs component.
The only thing that's there is basically a hard cap, which says that
literally, if this person doesn't physically have any money,
obviously, they couldn't spend it.
But other than that, I don't see anything in your system, which
actually does ensure that the people who are more, who are getting the
service and can pay for it actually do.
Yeah, there's not obviously, right, but there but I think with the
Monthly limit.
You're not getting the sort of ridiculous, whales that you hear about,
right?
You're not getting the Star Citizen 88,000 dollars for spaceship
thing, right?
Like that's you can't do it.
You can't spend more than whatever we decide the monthly cap is let's
say it's 50 bucks.
That's high.
But let's say let's just say it's 50 dollars because that's probably a
reasonable number.
So we say if you spend more than $50 this month, you get every item
for the rest of the month, completely for free.
So you
You we've actually implemented a hard cap.
I want you could spend.
So if we do that, then the concern about like if you are spending
money that you don't have on a video game and you're talking about
less than $50 per month, you know like okay maybe that's bad like
clearly that's bad but I don't think that that's my responsibility at
that point if it's capped at such like a, you know, reasonable
Brr.
Well, let's talk about the cap then because that actually brings up
another interesting point, right?
Okay.
So the game will go out of business.
If you keep the cap in place but it's clear from the data that the
game would stay in business.
If you raise the cap from fifty to a hundred dollars, do you raise the
cap?
From 50 to 100?
No no I don't think so.
So you're going to commit upfront to saying that we're going to State
a cap and we're never going to change that cap that cat is fixed.
Yep.
Right.
And that'll by being fixed with inflation, you know?
You know, okay.
Something crazy might happen, right?
Oh noes.
So basically like you're going to be the first f2p game that needs
like treasury backed Securities that you check every to see what you
can spend on it that month in order to get the the items lat.
That's precisely, it'll be adjusted on a day-to-day basis with the
CPI, okay.
All right.
I'm just saying, like, like in five years, we might be like, okay, the
cap $75,
That because inflation is right, right whatever.
But yes that that cap will be stated up front.
Okay, well, wait a minute, it would be seated up front but could be
raised, I'm saying only with only like with I'm saying that the cap
will never be raised but I'm also saying that like if something crazy
happens where the u.s.
and Canadian dollar just go fucking whack, right?
And a dollar now is worth 25 cents, right than the cap, has to be
raised in order to account for that.
But that would be the only
Type time that the cap will be raised, I wouldn't raise the cap to
keep the company in business, right?
I want to do that.
I would raise the cap if the dollar is suddenly worth nothing.
Okay, so it's basically like a fifty dollars in gold cap.
If that makes like a like a, like a fifty dollars in gold today.
Today's $50, however, much that buys, that gold, that is the cap or
something like that.
So that if later, you know, if later it turns out that that's too,
it's too far off from that, we reserve the right to change the cap to
whatever fifth whatever that
Of gold is worth today.
Something like I don't think that's exactly how I would phrase it but
yes up.
So that one Coastline, at least it.
Put the merchant system back into the somewhere.
Well, gold is completely stupid though because it's not it's just as
arbitrary as currency.
So yeah, number of chairs made or something by a particular country
for a year, might be a better better better index.
So I'm trying to think if there's other avenues that I'd like to
explore their.
So I mean, I think so, I think I've gotten most of the things like
I've gotten most of sort of the
The I guess the Avenues of it which is it sounds like there's there's
some things like for example with the cap, there are some things which
I feel like you could stay up front and actually codify right.
In other words, we were talking a little bit before you were saying
like if there was some law I could subscribe to that was like don't be
a dick.
Right?
I do that.
So it sounds like maybe there are a few of those things that you could
actually do such as stating that there's a cap that cannot be raised
other the in
Inflation goes up by a certain amount or something like this.
There are some things, right?
You could do if you wanted to, so that wait, no, that's that's one
that I, that is one that I'm absolutely going to do.
I don't know what the cap is going to be.
I'm playing with 50, I don't know what it's actually going to be
right, and another right, and the other one, and it'll be something
reasonable.
And I mean 50s, kind of unreasonable, but I do have free to play
works.
You can't be that low and, you know, that's a downside.
But what you going to do?
And then the other one, I don't know what you're going to do is sell
the game.
Look at Norm.
A person.
So I'm that's why we're having this discussion is like, and again, it
doesn't bother you that like the cap is $50.
So somehow like 12 months, someone pays $50, 06 06 hundred dollars a
year for this game and you're like, no, that's fine.
I mean, yes, it's fine.
Okay, that's, you know, like that will make the game better for more
people.
So yes, it's fine.
But the other thing was all assets.
Code everything goes into either.
GPL or public domain.
Once the server's go off and development stops.
That's another thing that's like all this is something that can be
codified.
Yeah, it's a Sunday in a contract as opposed to just like trust me.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And like anything that we can do to be like this is you know, we're
trying to be as ethical as possible here.
And I'm only doing this and I seriously like legitimately am only
reason I'm doing this because I actually think it is the best for the
game.
And if we were five years ago, when people were spending money or ten
years ago, when people were spending money on,
Subscription games.
I wouldn't, I wouldn't want to do free to play, even if it made even
if the, even if it made like astronomically more money, right?
Like, I don't care.
That's not why I'm doing this, right?
I'm doing it because I'm trying to make the best game possible.
And I think in this case free-to-play is actually going to deliver
that.
And so if that's actually true that in the past you would have been
okay with a subscription model, right?
Hmm.
Is there going to be a subscription model that people can elect to
use?
Yeah, the $50 a month thing.
So six hundred dollars a year is the subscription.
Okay, that's kind of unreasonable.
Wouldn't you say no?
I mean, unreasonable from what point of view from the point of view,
that whatever the game is that you're developing with the 30 people
that you have or whatever that you would have sold for $60 a year or
whatever.
It's not the same game.
That's the difference though.
It is sold for the actually the same.
It is absolutely not the same game.
If it's sold for $60, we have fewer people playing it.
If we have fewer people playing it, we don't have the data.
To make the game as good we have, don't have the data to make the game
as good.
You're not getting as good of a game.
It won't be as competitively viable.
It won't be as good.
We don't have the money to run the servers to constantly improve
everything we just that money doesn't exist.
So write your thing.
But okay, so what you're saying is it's the game is worth ten times
more money.
As a result.
Yeah, yeah, easily.
Easily, 10 times, more money.
It's worth zero.
It's worth infinitely more because without it without a left, people
playing it to gather data to make the game competitively viable, the
game is worth zero.
How many people is that 100,000 100,000 people?
Yeah, so you don't think you could sell a game to 100,000 people.
No.
Okay.
You know what?
I probably could.
I don't think I'm comfortable enough.
I don't have the
The okay, personally I just don't have the money to make to pay for a
game that has to be developed in that way.
Well, how we're going to develop the game to begin with?
Then, I mean, how are you going to get this free to pray Revenue to
start coming in without the money, to do The Upfront development, to
make the game with art and stuff, complicated, involves government
grants and government grants, like, free to play and, or either away.
Yeah.
And freedom.
Play.
Allows us to release the game immediately crappy versions like, you
know, beta Alpha.
Pre-alpha, like whatever Greek letter you want to associate with it,
some really awful version of the game.
Like, have you seen my stream?
Like what I've been working on when I get a triangle flying around?
Like we could just release that right?
The triangle flying around?
Yeah, well there you go, we can release the triangle flying around
right I think it wasn't flying around yet when I saw it but it was
there.
Oh well if flies now okay.
Yeah, it's great.
So like we can release that now or as soon as we have our dedicated
server up which should be in the next couple of weeks.
So like we can release that game and
And it's available and like, people can start talking about and people
can start playing it now, right?
And we can slowly bring in free to play stuff.
Once the game is pretty good, like, I'm not even worried about like
actually producing Cosmetics or any of that stuff.
So there's actually like a good game there, right?
But if we get people playing it now for completely for free under the
assumption, like we're not hiding.
The fact that we're doing free to play, we're not hiding what we're
going to do.
We're being pretty transparent about it.
That's why I'm having this discussion to, right?
So we're not operating people aren't getting the game.
The assumption that is going to be free forever for everybody.
People are if they're going to play the game.
Now there are operating under the assumption.
It's going to be free to play at some point so
You know, we couldn't release this game for free and then have people
like pay $60 for it at some arbitrary time, right?
Where we can roll in free-to-play stuff earlier than we could sell it
for $60, for example, and use that to fund the development of the
game.
I see, well, I mean, there are plenty of examples of that sort of
thing, though, for like I mean, Prison Architect would be a classic
example of that, right?
I don't know how much money I made in Early Access or whatever it was
1.4 like million units or something.
Now, if you look at it, it's insane.
How many?
There was some ridiculously huge number.
Yeah, Nuclear Throne did 110,000 or something.
Yeah, that it
Good for them.
I mean, I don't know.
I don't know how, I don't know how to do it well, but again, so I'm
just asking the question little rhetorically.
It seems like we do have lots of examples of ways that you actually
can do that well.
So I don't know that.
I necessarily believe that somehow the f2p part is that, you know,
you're saying government grants.
But like, okay, I mean, if magically, you can get government grants
then I mean all bets are off.
It's like if the government comes in and says, everyone has to do
free-to-play, then, obviously, they win their the government.
You can't fight the government.
So I'm not going against that, but that's exactly how it works, but
take that out.
The equation for a second and assuming that you have to come up with
this as a viable, business model in general free-to-play doesn't get
an advantage there.
You still have to find the money somewhere the game.
Yeah, I don't know.
I think it's, I think it's, I think it being free to play makes
finding the money easier and I think it makes
I think it makes finding the money easier and then it sort of
transitions nicely from the hey, we're finding the money to, hey, we
actually have a game that's, you know, like a production level, you
know, finished polish game or whatever.
Like it, there's a transition examples of that because I can point out
lots of examples of people who did like early,
Access or kick starters and had various other products.
Do you have an example of some smelling developer that started in f2p
game with a triangle or whatever else and somehow was able to fund
themselves the whole time till they got a game with some art in it or
whatever?
No, no, I don't know if any of that, I don't know of any of that
either.
So why are you saying that?
You think that would be effective?
Why are you saying?
You think that would be?
What makes you think?
That's bad is going to work at all.
The government grants.
What are the what are these?
Grants say regarding food?
If I'm very curious about it, nothing not part of the argument, but
I'm just curious now nothing specifically about like it has to be free
to play.
But it's like, what's your business model?
These are the business models that have been accepted in the last
couple of years, right?
Like dyad was funded by the by the Ontario government as well.
But at that time, I don't think I mean free to play against the single
was around but like it wasn't valued that high.
But now it's like,
Free to place pretty big.
Okay?
And these government programs would not accept.
We are doing some other thing like what prison architect did or
whatever?
Well, they could they would accept them.
But it's a question of how much like each site basically.
It's a long one quarter page application.
Each section of the application gets weighted differently gets about
applied like a score to it and then those scores are weighted and the
score for business model or the wait for business models quite high
and free-to-play scores very high on that.
That's pretty terrifying.
Shawn.
Separate from this discussion.
Amen.
Canada terrifying.
Welcome.
Welcome to Canada.
It's my turn to rag on your country.
That is a really stupid.
Just did you see our new prime minister?
No, it's pretty good-looking.
Oh, really?
Oh yeah, he's a hottie.
Okay good.
We elect actors here.
So there's no reason you can't go for cosmetics and there you go.
If we can elect Ronald Reagan, you can Arete like to ever you want.
I feel like, yeah.
All right.
Well I think I don't feel like I have any other specific things that I
want to ask about.
I mean, I feel like again, I haven't.
I certainly haven't heard anything that would make me less nervous
about it as a business model.
Because as far as I could tell, most of the things I was concerned
about wasn't that you weren't concerned about them is that you're just
like, I'm not going to do them right that kept being kind of the
answer was like, I'm not going to do.
I'm not going to spend my time, trying to figure out how to get people
to buy Cosmetics.
I'm just I'm just not
And so the fact that, you know, you may be worried that all the
incentives are for me to spend my time figuring how to make this game
be a game where people want to buy Cosmetics.
I'm just not good, do it, right?
Well, that's not true.
I'm going to do some of that like I said like I'm not gonna do it to
its detriment.
Oh no, I'm no.
No, of course or whatever right.
So that so I guess I was thinking for is like I don't feel like I've
been a suede very much because it sounded like the entirety of the
argument that the FTP is not going to be a problem here.
All, boiled down to, I'm not going to do the bad stuff, right?
Right, well no, I don't think so.
I don't think that's true.
Because my other one of the arguments and I was making is that free to
play.
Is actually the best solution and I was talking about getting the
large number of people to play it and lining up payment with
development, right?
But again, that's about why you think it's going to be a good model
for this game?
What I'm saying is that the concerns I have about free-to-play?
We're not assuaged in any way?
Other than trust me.
I won't do the things you're worried about.
Okay.
Well, what about this though?
Okay, you could say.
That the business model choice for particular game is, how do I phrase
this?
The business model choice for particular game, it can be a wide
variety of things and all of them have a direct impact on the quality
of the game, or a different way of putting it, as they have a direct
impact on the quality of the experience that the average game player
will have right, you buy a game up front.
We get this experience, right?
You you're going to get this experience, it has some quality value
associated with it.
You you pay a subscription model and you're going to have this
experience and it has a quality value associated with the same with
free-to-play, right?
I think in this situation A my situation free to play
Delivers the best quality experience to the average player, and not
just like the median player, but like 22 like across the whole
Spectrum.
It's the best for everybody, except for, I guess the people are
spending $600 a year or whatever, but for the vast majority of players
free-to-play is going to produce a better experience for them.
So in that regard, I think that's pretty unique.
Amongst free to play games.
I don't
I think that's necessarily the case anywhere except for perhaps DOTA.
Well, hold on a second, though.
Again, that is really has nothing to do with if someone comes to this
and goes, I find when I play all this f2p stuff, it's really annoying.
It's always trying to trick me into buy something.
It's giving me the Christmas crate that I have to pay a dollar to
unlock.
Its they've got economists who are trying to figure out how to sell me
the most number of goods that look like they're coming to it with all
of the concerns because they've played all these
You to play games and legitimately.
They have seen a lot of stuff about these games if they don't like
right?
Yeah, they're coming to you and they're saying those are my concerns.
And your answer is not that don't worry about it because, you know, we
have these ways in which we know it won't happen, you're just saying
we won't do those things to you.
Well, I've given you two things that are the cap, right?
At $50 a month is six hundred dollars a year which is like not that
much of a cat.
But okay, well, we have it.
I said it's 50 but but you even said the phrase to that you can't go
very low because quote unquote you know, how free to play games work
and it can't go.
That low.
I can't
Right, so you raised fish, probably 50 bucks.
You're already saying it looks like a nasty distribution where a bunch
of people carry all the weight in a bunch of people don't or whatever
and that's okay.
Whatever.
But point being, we've established that part.
Uh-huh.
And there really wasn't anything else.
There was the fact that you won't shut down the servers without
releasing the source code, but that doesn't affect what happens, while
the games actually commercial.
Right?
So, what was, what were the other things that were supposed to make me
believe?
Well, no, it was Christopher with all over the place and everything
else.
The fact that I
I mean the fact that I did say that I would like to codify something,
we're either percentages of development or things like that but
you're, you know, you're absolutely right.
And that I think what it comes down to what you're saying is, is it
creates a massive power imbalance between the consumer and the
developer, right?
Like, the person who's paying the money has very little power in what
happens with the thing that they're paying for.
Right?
So, you're paying $10 a month or whatever.
Well, it's also adversarial, I guess is the other
Meeting you in order for you to survive you must convince me to spend
money on the game.
That's just a basic tenet of how this is going to go.
So you know what, you see when you look at these other companies is
that they do exactly that.
Like, that's what zynga's all about.
They're like trying to figure out every possible way to manipulate me
into paying this money.
Right?
And, you know, when I come to your game it's like why how do I know
that you're not going to go down that route?
And I guess what I'm saying is I haven't heard anything other than,
trust me.
I'm a nice.
Guy which means right?
Ooh, but it doesn't really help.
Actually, anyone who doesn't necessarily know who you are, or doesn't
necessarily know who your business partners are, or what will happen,
right?
No, you're absolutely right.
And and I don't know what the solution to that is.
If you know if you want to help me come up with one or if you can come
up with one, I'd fucking love to hear it, right?
But that isn't something that I think.
I can tackle right like, I can't tackle the hey we're going to fix
free-to-play across the board and make it an ethical business model.
Right?
That I don't know.
I don't have a solution to but what I do have a solution to I think is
that free-to-play can be applied pragmatically to a situation that
benefits everybody and it actually becomes the best option.
Not
The option that were using because we're trying to exploit people and
make a lot of money.
I think actually can be the best option for making a particular type
of game.
This, this probably is the only type word ongoing competitive blah,
blah, blah.
So, my only argument my argument isn't that free-to-play is great.
Everybody should do it.
That's not what I'm saying.
What I'm saying is that free-to-play is awful.
However,
In this one isolated situation or maybe there's others that I haven't
thought of but in this particular isolated situation free-to-play
serves the game.
The players and the developers better than any other business model.
Right.
And so again, that's true of most of the Esports free-to-play things,
correct, meaning, that is the same statement you would make about
them.
It's just that they didn't choose to optionally be ethical when they
applied it, but all the things you're saying right?
You know, words League of Legends.
What you just said, applies that if what you're saying is correct,
that free to play as the best model for these types of games.
Then they chose the best model, right?
No that's not.
I'm not saying that if your places
For these type of games I'm saying the free-to-play is the best model
for my particular goals which is to make a competitively viable high
quality game that has lots of people playing it in order to get
competitive viability.
That's what I'm saying.
That's not Riot School.
Okay, so for the goal, it's not about the type of game, it's just a
goal, it's the goal, but the type of like the goal implies a certain
type of gamer like has to have an online has a server as matchmaking,
yellow blah, blah blah, right?
It has to have all of those features and has to have ongoing
development with, you know, Gathering tons of statistics about item
combinations and hero combinations and blah blah blah.
In order to figure out what is balanced and what is in balance and how
to balance it and all that sort of stuff, all of that stuff is
required to make.
The best most competitive possible Team game, which is what my goal
is.
So for that goal, I think free-to-play serves at best and that's not
right, it's cool.
Okay, so what's the difference between you and Riot, Carlos?
Right?
Which gets me exactly back to what I'm saying.
So, that's a pretty significant difference.
No, it's all just about what your motivation is, right?
And whether or not you're going to be ethical as a person, it has
nothing to do with the game.
Self is the same kind of game, right?
It's the same kind of game, same kind of business model.
Everything else is the same.
All you're saying is, I won't do what right does trust me, right?
No, I'm saying I won't do it right, it does.
Because that's not even, like, that's not a, that's not a goal, like,
that's not apply its doing this.
That's what ethics are golden ethics?
There's no difference.
What you're trying to do is your ethics, that's the definition of what
it is, right?
It's like okay, right?
Okay, you know, I mean there's no just because you're calling it a
goal, it doesn't.
Make it any different.
It's still a thing in your head that you're telling us to trust you
about, right?
Oh, I do think that there's definitely the element of.
Hey, I know everything is evil, but trust me.
I'm not evil.
There is definitely that and I don't know what I can do to get around
that.
But what I'm saying is that, I'm not starting from the position where
Riot or Zynga or whoever else is starting from, right?
Like those, making a whole bunch of money is 0.
I have zero interest in that, right?
Like that's not even like 10 gently a goal.
That's like, I don't even care.
Yeah, so that's not why I'm doing it.
I'm doing it.
You know, if it's altruistic reasons or whatever it's not, it's
Nicole reasons, right?
I want to do free to play for practical reasons.
I think it's I think it is the actual best model in this situation and
if you think that that if you just say well because your goal is
different.
And what you want to do is different that's irrelevant and it still
boils down to trust me, which I guess is what your argument is.
Is that true?
Well, my argument is a little more specific than that, right?
Because in general, you know, since we're trying to talk about a
business model as
As the core, you know, gravamen of the argument, right?
It's like the thing we're talking about is the business model, not
Sean.
McGrath like if the argument was, is Sean McGrath a good person or
not, then I agree that all of these things are relevant because that's
what we're actually talking about.
But in this case, we're talking about specifically, the business model
and what the hazards of that business model are to a developer, right?
Okay, and won the argument that I again, keep coming back to that.
I think you seem to be consistently
Getting is that you're saying that those hazards aren't a problem
because you won't fall prey to them, right?
And I guess what?
I keep trying to just make sure that we have solidified is the fact
that that is actually where we're Landing meaning.
We're not trying to say that these hazards aren't still all there for
your game because they all are, it's okay.
You don't think you will fall prey to them.
Yeah, I think that they're all there.
Yes, that no, that makes perfect sense.
And I think that that's a fair assessment, and I'm not saying that I'm
not going to fall prey to them.
I'm going to say that.
I'm gonna try really hard not to
To write but like anything that can be done up front to be like this
the these this is the framework in which I'm operating and I can't
overstep.
Like if there's like a legal thing that I could be like this is what
I'm willing to do and anything outside of this is off the table
completely.
I'd be I'm totally willing to do that.
I totally would like to do that and if I can come up with a way of
doing that, so that other developers could also do it.
That would be good because I don't think free to play.
Is bad inherently.
I think every implementation of it is bad in the fact that there's the
power imbalance or whatever.
All that shit is bad but the actual idea that the game is free and
some people have the option to pay for it that like just that little
fundamental nugget there, I think is fine.
It's just everything that's surrounding it.
Everything that's like bread branched off of that little tiny idea has
been awful and entirely driven by entirely by Financial motivations,
right?
And I
Don't think that it has to be but I don't have a concrete solution to
that problem.
Like I'm not saying this is how we're not going to do that, right?
Like I don't have that because there's so many ways in which you could
be enticed to just be evil, right?
And I don't have a solution for all of them and part of it is.
Yeah, just trust me but anything that I can do to be like, hey you
don't have to just trust me, there is like a thing that I'm signing
here or whatever.
It says, I will only operate Within These parameters.
L, I think that would be really positive thing and I'd be totally
totally.
Why I totally want to do that, right?
Because I do want to do this for you to play in order to best serve,
the people playing the game and that's sort of my point of view.
Well, let me throw out some options for you then George what you think
of them that's here.
So, if you really want to do this altruistic Ali, right?
One could imagine that you have some budget for this game.
That is what you think the development costs are from year to year,
right?
Where you're basically saying that like you know, we need to run the
Servers and that's going to cost X dollars per user or something.
You know?
Probably it's more difficult calculation than that but we have some
appears like to support this many users in this many countries.
We know it's going to cost this much money.
We want this many artists working on the game, you know, optimally for
the stuff that we want to roll out, you know, blah, blah blah separate
from free-to-play.
So, meaning, assuming that the game was just going to be purchased
flat or the Canadian government was going to come in with some crazy
grant called the Sean McGrath support Grant which just pays for you
too.
The game right?
Call him up and tell him.
We want that.
Yeah, I Would.
By the way also like the case Amira Tori.
I'm not Canadian but I'd be willing to be for this grant grant, right?
That would you could you could probably get it but so
What about a system that worked a little bit more like say Wikipedia,
right?
Where it's like, okay, the game will be free to play in a year where
we did not raise the target amount, the previous year.
So you're saying if your players give you enough money through women's
went through just like whatever you want, it could either be if it's
if it's free to play that year where they're buying stuff, if they buy
enough stuff to pay the next year's budget, it just completely the
next year, you know, it completely unlocks for everybody or something
this or it's just, there's a donation drive.
And if the donation Drive hits the development cost, they don't do
free to play Penny Arcade District did this, for example, for ad, free
for their site.
In fact, valve does something like this sort of, with the compendium,
except they still just try to make as much money on everything else is
that can too.
But, no, they make so much money off that compendium.
It's ridiculous.
So, in other words, imagine something like the compendium where every
year, you have a compendium.
And if enough people buy it to pay for whatever is the set Development
Goal.
So your company profit that you feel is ethical amount to make plus
your development costs.
Then the next year doesn't have the freedom, everyone just gets the
whole game.
Well, that's intriguing.
Okay?
So let's see.
Why is that, why is that good?
Why is that bad?
I mean I'd have to think about it for a while that seems like good on
the surface, right?
Like it doesn't seem like there's anything wrong with that.
One problem with it is it only covers one year, right?
And you have to think a little bit more long term for things like
this, so, you know, we could have some contingency built into that
where we have to go 30% over or something like that.
So that
And we can get something like that would probably have to be done.
Let's see.
OK, another problem is
Let's say let's just I'm just throwing this out as an idea as why it
might not be good.
Let's say we have 12 artists on staff we actually need seven to do the
game content.
Right?
What do we do with each other five?
Do we do?
We do we fire them because with they're not their only needed for
free-to-play stuff and then do we have to bring them back a year a
year later?
If we don't make it for the next year, right?
Like there's there's kind of a staffing Logistics issue, don't think
that you'd be paying for all of those.
In other words, you have the team that you have and you're going to
know.
We don't we don't need them.
All.
No, it's not need there in the budget.
Meaning, if you do, the, if the compendium thing succeeds in a given
year, then that next year, that whole team is still doing all the
other stuff.
They're still making the free-to-play items, just everyone gets them.
Oh I see.
So we do it.
It's there's no difference to you.
You're running exactly the same way.
It's just a total cap on the on the the sort of the that it's time to
cap really because people can keep giving you money, they can keep
buying the company and they just want to give you money, right?
Yeah, but it's basically like, it's a bar, that's like, if you go
above this, we won't try to do anymore selling you stuff for the
period of time that that compendium covers shit.
Why not just take a little further, why not?
Just say it's free to play up until we beat some amount of money.
Maybe that happens in February or second month of the year or
whatever.
And then after that, everything's just free for everybody.
Yeah.
Why not just do that.
I don't know why not.
I don't know, that's a good idea.
We should just do that because lack and I mean, I don't know, I'd have
to I realized I'd have to think about it, right?
Like I'm sure there's some downsides to it but like that sounds like a
fantastic idea because it seems like that also helps mitigate some of
these problems because then it's like you're not in a position where
you're
talking about how to always grow and how to always make more money.
You're just like, we know what we want to do with the game this year,
we'd like to focus on development.
If our fans, let us do that we do.
And we won't be thinking about, you know, how do we do all these other
things if they don't then all right.
Like, you know, we're back in the kind of f2p nastiness that's just
where we.
So why I really like this idea is because it actually does all the
good things the free-to-play does with all the things that I talked
about and makes it even better, right?
It's even better because now it's
Okay, and now you don't even have to buy anything now.
It's like you don't have to do anything.
Like you just have absolutely everything for free.
Nothing is segregated at all and there's no pops anywhere, but buying
shit like it's just completely.
Like, I like it.
I like this idea a lot.
Yeah.
Okay, I'll probably do this.
Okay, well honestly, that we can still free to play though.
Yeah, that probably would go a long way towards my sort of comfort
level with the game because then to me,
me that puts in sort of like I said,
Little more codification of the of the trust me.
I actually want to develop the game, not the free-to-play because now
you're telling me up front.
That if as fans we pay you the money.
You actually wanted.
You'll just work on the game and you won't care about this other
stuff.
And that gives me the option as a customer to potentially get what I
actually want, which is, you just working on the game and not, oh,
yeah, I would totally prefer that too so that gives them that option.
And so, that's that to me, is a, is a pretty big.
That's a
Pretty big positive to me if you come out and you do something like
that.
Yeah I would totally do that now there's it would have to be a little
bit more involved in what you're saying right like because like I said
there's the contingency of run devils in the details and there but
there's also like we want to expand to do another game or whatever and
you know part of the money has to
Whatever, right?
There's going to be some details to it but like having that Kapoor,
it's like hey if we go over 10 million or 20 million or whatever
development budget is, whatever number we set and I mean, it could be
arbitrary and it can be stupidly high for.
We could still be evil in that regard to, right?
But let's say we're not thanks.
Now we have one point of not being evil, right, where we have like a
clear like, hey, you know, difference between 10 million and 100
million dollars is pretty obvious to people, right?
So we've been like, okay, whatever our cap is it's 10 million dollars
or whatever.
We say, if you hit this cap, everything is just free for the rest of
the year.
Yeah, I have the absolute no problem doing that.
Well, that's a fantastic idea that seems like a pretty positive thing
to me because again, that that's sort of, I guess what, I'm look at
the two problems that I see with what you're talking about from a.
I'm now thinking as a selfish perspective instead of me thinking about
is like, I'm arguing fup for people in general trying to bring up
points that maybe they would make which is what I was doing before.
Think of it, the self-expression, let's say, I actually want to play
this game so for some reason I get into Esports so
I said before, I don't care about Esports.
I just wake up one day and I'm like, I need Esports of my life and
would be these ports in your life by the way.
And I want to play a game, right?
Or your game is one of the games I considering, right?
Sure.
When I look at that, there's two things that bother me one.
Is that thing was like, I want the game like I want to play.
I want to know that somebody made a game and I'm getting the game.
I don't want to get, you know, this weird shape of the game which is
like, it didn't have the hats and I don't have the weird, you know.
I just want the game.
Yeah, I want you to make a man, what have a game, right?
Want to get a store with a game inside of I just want the game, right?
And so that's that alleviates that going to like, okay, if we're
paying this developer enough money they'll just give us the game.
I like that.
Right.
That's good.
Sure.
I liked that too.
The thing I don't like is there is no way really for me to pay a fair
price for the whole game because like you said that's going to end up
being six hundred dollars a year which is pretty darn high.
So if me if our if as fans we don't hit your cap and individual can't
really Rectify their situation
At a fair price, which I don't see much of a way around that.
Because like you said, the whole point of this model is that, it's
lopsided, so it kind of falls apart, if you say oh, I'll just charge
you what the fair market value would have been at that thing.
It doesn't weigh.
You can't.
Do that, right?
But like, but my point is that you're getting its you're getting a
different game, right?
Like if you do that, you have fewer people playing it, you have less
data, you have less.
It's a different game, right?
You're not the to you're not getting the same game so don't think it's
fair to compare them.
Well I'm not saying it's fair to compare them or not.
It's just saying as a person I can't pay what anyone would ever
consider a fair price for a game because the game is like 60 70 bucks
or something like this and actually get the game that was made for the
same development budget.
By the way, that would have gone into say Call of Duty.
Which I
I can buy for $60, right?
So it's I'm just saying that, like, from that perspective, it doesn't,
there's no way to turn it on an individual basis into the, I just
bought the game version, but no, I don't think there is.
And so around the park, we do that.
We don't The Upfront development.
Yeah, there's no way to do it at least.
If I least, I can't think of it, the other had a hundred million
dollars.
Like try Eric, what's the company that makes?
Yeah, Treyarch.
Well, there's actually, do they have multiple Studios?
I think they alternate for Call of Duty, right?
I think they stopped because it was Infinity Ward and Treyarch.
And then
I think it's just Treyarch.
And I don't know, whatever.
Either way, I don't have their development.
No, nobody does, right?
So we can't, that's not even an option, right?
Well, okay, I think I might, I think I might be done.
I think, I think that's it.
I think I said everything I had to say, I feel like what you would
play this game under, the, under that condition.
So, I think what I would say is, I don't know how to alleviate one
problematic piece, which is that
That cap could be set unreasonably high.
So, as to ensure that it basically never happened, right?
And I don't know how you fix that, really right?
Because I mean, you could try to put something up front, that sort of
like your peg to the price of gold thing.
We were talking about before, where you're like, oh the cap is $50 in
this Peg to inflation.
Something one could imagine that like, oh, the cap.
Every year for the global cap is set to 10 million dollars to
inflation or you know, you had something I could maybe see that but
even so it's
Still very hard.
I don't, I don't know that one.
So there is kind of a little nasty loophole where it's like, well the
developer could always still decide in any given year to just
basically screw me as a customer if they wanted to, and I don't know
the way around that but in general, assuming that, that price was set
fairly and was set to a reasonable development budget plus profit.
Yeah, I think I could be okay with that.
And, you know, if that if that were the model, I think I would
certainly, I could at very least say I'd be much more, okay.
With that than FTP.
Yeah, I would totally right.
I think it's a great idea like it wasn't because it doesn't
It doesn't hurt any of the things that I want to do, right?
Like it.
I still get to do everything that I want to do.
I don't get to make a stupid ridiculous amount of money but I'd wanted
that anyway, right.
So it's like this seems to be at least, you know for the 10 minutes
that I've heard of this idea.
This seems to this the seems to be reasonably you know as soon as her
it seems reasonable seems like a good place to start at least.
And I don't see a problem with that.
Like I think that's probably a good idea.
Well yeah, then that's pretty cool.
Because again, like I said, from a selfish perspective, one of the
things that I mostly am concerned about is I want to be able to just
buy the game and I also want a way to free the developer from having
to think about this aspect of it and I'd love to not have to think
about it yet.
And so I feel like that is the part where the progress can be made.
If you can move away from a free-to-play, is the fallback for the
business.
Model.
There's a big difference between that and free-to-play is the business
model?
Well, what do you think?
But do you think it's a fallback, like compendium type thing or do you
think it's?
Hey, it's just free to play until we hit as much money as we need at
that point.
Everything is free.
What?
Like we don't, we don't have a special event, like, compendium or
whatever.
It's just January, 1st rolls around.
It's free to play until we make 10 million dollars or whatever it is.
So, here's what I would probably say and I'd have to think about this
a little more because I came up with us, this idea.
Literally just, as we were talking, it wasn't like I had time to think
about it either, but what I would probably say is again as a player, I
want to buy what I want from you is I want not free to play.
I want to pay you $60 and get my game.
That's what I wanted, right?
So what I would suggest is, how do you make this system into something
that looks a lot like that.
Meaning at the beginning of the year, if all of us can go and just
say, okay, you said something, you said like twenty four dollars a
year was what you wanted.
Wanted to make from us or something, right?
Yeah.
If everyone paid, whatever the amount is to get up to that number,
right?
Then the game is free.
So maybe there's something like, okay, there's just like a
contribution thing or you at the beginning of the year, there's the
thing you can buy which is like I'm trying to get us towards this goal
or maybe you get a little badge, if you spend over the amount that
you're supposed to something that's like designed to allow everyone to
come together.
Our and try to make the game free.
And if they fail, then they fail like another example would be you pay
this much money into the game and you just get that many credits for
free-to-play items throughout the year if the thing fails.
So we can all pile on and try to like by the thing, right?
And if we don't make it then I just get that many items or something
but you know I don't know.
Is that actually like functionally better than just flat it's free to
play until we hit a certain revenue and then it's free for
Buddy, because that actually better, I don't know.
Well, I want some way to do this before, it turns free to play.
So if, as players we want to do it, we don't have to actually ever
have the free-to-play version.
Okay, so I just so yes, I mean, it's I like what you're saying.
It's just, I want a way to make it so that if players want to keep
this game an actual game and not a piece male game so that they never
have to have a day where, that's not true.
Oh, I'm sorry, I want a piecemeal game.
Yeah, in other words, like what your, what basically would happen,
right?
Is that I'm playing the game.
Have the whole game and then on January 1st.
My gang goes back to like, only the pieces of the game.
Right.
You know I'm saying like I don't get all my hat.
My hats are all gone.
Your hats are gone but it has like the the functional parts of the
game are still there, right?
But the hats are all gone.
Okay Cham.
So what I'm saying is that if as players we just want our hats to
always be there, I want a way in December to get to that goal for you.
So that in January, it doesn't have to happen.
Whereas if it has to go back to free to play and then we have to earn
our way back up to it starting.
Then it's kind of like there's no way for the players to ensure that
that never happens and furthermore, there's no way for them to single
too early.
They can't tell you in June that they want the game free next year.
And so you as a developer have to be thinking, oh, it's getting close
to December, I don't know what's going to happen.
If we better have a bunch of f2p stuff already, we got it.
You know, like you're constantly inside.
So I want to wait, I want the players.
If they take initiative to be able to move it backward.
In time to a place where it's keeping you totally out of the FTP thing
if they do it.
That's also I don't know how to achieve that but that's what I'm
saying.
Yeah, no, that's understandable.
I think that's, I don't think it's a bad idea, I don't know if it's
yeah.
I don't know what the right, I don't know what the right answer.
Is that guy I heard this I heard of this like a 30 seconds after you
heard of it.
So but no, I think this is a good direction.
Like I think that this totally beats, you know, this meets what my
goals are, right and you know if it's free to play as a back as a
packing that's fine too, but it's still like free-to-play.
Like even if this, even if this happened, still free to play.
Yes.
By the actual definitions of those three words.
and I mean, like I said, you know, free-to-play one of the things that
it is like
I guess from the perspective of somebody who doesn't like free to
play, it's like, why don't I like free to play, right?
The answer is because all the free-to-play stuff has all of these bad
manipulative properties to it.
And so, someone saying trust me that won't happen is not particularly
compelling, right?
But that doesn't mean that, I don't believe that you couldn't figure
out a thing that is slightly different from free-to-play that actually
creates a business model where that doesn't happen, right?
And so that's why I'm saying,
This that's kind of interesting because like, okay, maybe it won't
work, but at least now there's a reason you're trying something
different where I'm like, okay, maybe now I can have some confidence
in you because you're not doing exactly the same business model.
There's a difference here and maybe that'll work, maybe that will
start to produce developers who aren't being manipulative, right?
And yeah, I would like to do this.
Just for that experiment alone just to see if other people would be.
Yeah.
I mean who knows?
Right now I think it's a good idea.
I'm gonna do this.
This is what I'm going to do.
This is a really good idea.
I think I'm just gonna do that.
Well thanks.
But yeah no I mean it's still free to play right?
Like it's still like at its core free to play and
The it meets all the goals that I have and why I wanted to do free to
play in the first place.
Well, so, I guess Sean.
So do you have any other stuff that you want to talk about me?
Do we cover everything you wanted to cover?
I ask the questions I had.
I pressed on the places that seemed pressey.
Yeah, I think somebody feel about it.
So I think it's good.
Like I think it did more or less it covered all the points I did.
I at least convince you.
in any way, separate from the thing that we just sort of that you just
stumbled upon yes, that
Because it's always been my assumption and perhaps, I'm projecting my
assumption upon you as well, that free-to-play is never good ever for
the game or for the players, right?
Like there's no example except for perhaps DOTA we're free to place
actually better for the game and for the players playing and it's
always been my assumption that that's just flat-out.
True free-to-play is always worse but I don't know I've now come come
to the point where I don't think that's true at
I don't think free-to-play is necessarily worse.
Have you?
Do you still feel?
Or if you do ever feel that it's always without a doubt?
Absolutely worse in all situations.
Well, I guess what I would say is I think that even the premise of
that question mean it's sort of presupposes that I don't like free to
play for reasons which are actually not the reasons.
I don't like free-to-play, right?
I don't dislike free to play because of some inherent fundamental
aspect of the
business model of it.
The reason I fundamentally don't like free to play is because the
incentives do not align as I explained before.
And my assumption is that, since all of the evidence of free-to-play,
we have show that those incentives actually are totally followed
exactly the way you would think they were.
I just assumed that is what happens when you are talking about a large
game.
You know, something like you're talking about where it's, you know,
millions of dollars on the line that those incentives.
That's what they produce, right?
It was, that's the evidence I see.
I can look at the business model and go, that's what the incentives
are.
So it's not surprising that this is what happened, so it's not that I
don't like free-to-play because there's something that I see in like
the aspect of paying for a hat.
That's bad, right?
It's not like, oh, why is paying for a bad in some holistic sense?
It's like, know what I don't like is as far as I can tell, all the
incentives are going in directions that I feel are deleterious to
making a particular.
You know, an art a piece of art
Art, a thing that you're passionate about whatever you call it when
you're developing something and you care about it, right?
They don't go in that direction.
And so that's why free-to-play bothers me.
If there were a bunch of examples of people doing free to play games
that were really genuine and sincere treated their players with
respect and all of these sorts of things that aren't really true.
From what I see.
And like you said, even the best example are people who ship the
Christmas,
Right?
Hey the Christmas crates.
Good, no.
Don't you know what they do?
Do you know what they'd do, if you, if you buy it, you know about the
gifting well.
So the Christmas crate I'm talking about, is one year and I don't
know, which way this was, they came out with a crate, right?
And the crate was that.
I think this was for Team Fortress 2, if I remember correctly.
Okay, the Christmas crate was, you get a Christmas crate in your
inventory and you, you have, you don't know what's in it, but there's
It's like different but they have some like probabilities that they'll
tell you, right?
Yeah, yeah, and you have this, that have this at all their game, it
just shows up and you have to, then pay, you know, whatever it is five
dollars to unlock your Christmas crate.
If you don't unlock it by December 25th, it goes away.
Yeah, they do this all the time.
Right?
I think, I think that that might be like Vera fracas is idea to, which
is odd.
So, it's like, it's a classic example of like, the best people you can
point to are using the dirtiest worst.
Most manipulative things you can possibly do in a in a car.
To take money from their players.
Now, again like I said, that's not a criticism of free-to-play, it's
just, it looks to the outside Observer like the incentives and
free-to-play, which point in that direction are 100% follow.
It's like, yep, you get exactly what you think, you would get you get
So again, you know, feel free to be the very first person to
demonstrate that there actually is an FTP seeing that doesn't produce
this but yeah, I think you're right though.
Think like inherently from illegal?
Like from just a legal Corporation standpoint you're absolutely right.
Like of course that's what you're gonna get, right?
But I don't think that that that's I don't think you have to get that,
right?
And I don't think that your motivation of choosing free-to-play has to
be that either.
Oh sir, right?
And again, this is why I say it comes down to that.
Trust me thing, and that's true, right?
It's like, if you have someone who will literally, always make the
best decisions for the players of this game.
Then why does it even matter?
What the business model is, right?
The business model could be anything.
The business model is we take children and throw them into a grinder
and we Stir It Up and we produce game goo, which produces a great game
and the like super benevolent killed.
Awesome person would make sure that those were only children who were
evil at heart.
So, we were doing a favor by
In them up or whatever, right?
So it's good but point being normally that's just not what humans do.
That's why we are very careful about our selection of business models
is because incentives are followed, that's what humans do.
And once in a while you do get, you know, Gandhi and Jesus, walk hand
in hand and they decide to eschew all these things and it's fine.
But again, like I said, so when you're asking the question of do I
feel like maybe it's an okay decision?
That was never really my question.
My question.
Is not.
Could you use this business model to do something good?
Of course, you couldn't.
You can use almost any business model, do something good.
My thing is more like as a business model.
It is fundamentally aligning incentives in a bad Direction and I don't
see really anything other than maybe that idea that I had at the end
that we're talking about here, that changes my mind about that.
Okay, yeah, I sort of I agree.
I agree with with the thing at the end, being something that
definitely changes your mind or has that potential.
Yeah, yeah.
But I don't, I still don't agree that.
Like, it's, it's hard though because it is like, it's true, right?
You're spending money on like you're spending development, resources
on a story, you're not spending the development resources on a game,
right?
Like that is just that's just completely true.
However, there's also the things that I brought up with, you know, the
number of players and and having to ongoing support cost server costs
and things like that which free-to-play pays for blah blah blah so I
don't know I still I haven't I'm not
I haven't changed my opinion.
That
It's all like what you were saying.
Like it doesn't like your, your interests are not your interests are
to the system produces profit.
That's all it is, right?
And I don't necessarily think that that is true.
I'm not phrasing this.
Well let me give you one more sort of example just to see if maybe
this puts it in a perspective that you can either more strenuously
disagree with or agree with, okay?
So incentives, matter, most or rather, what incentives do is, they
determine what you will do, when you are at your particular line,
right?
Everyone has a different line.
If you are a purely profit greed, motivated individual right, then
those incentives are all you would follow, right?
So, hopefully we agree that like, if an unscrupulous person is going
to do an FTP game, then they are just going to look at literally, what
is the things we can do?
That will make people buy?
The most stuff that is what an unscrupulous person will do because
that is what the business model encourages them to do right there,
okay, how can we sell the most hats?
It doesn't matter.
The only thing the game has to do is make them buy the Hat.
That's it.
It doesn't have to be a good game by any other metric is that to make
them buy the hat.
And so to the extent where we will make a good game, it is only
because we know that we need to make a game good enough for someone to
buy a hat, right?
That's what an unscrupulous.
That's what someone who's literally motivated.
Only by the money, right guys?
Think.
All right there.
That's a thing, right?
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, but other people's lines are a different places.
So let's say you have the most altruistic person ever, who just wants
to do the best thing for the game, right?
Okay.
Well, fundamentally speaking in order to the best thing for the game.
They need to keep their team picked right?
And finally this week if they're a nice person they also are trying to
not fire people or lay people off, right?
So they have real responsibilities that they are trying to meet that
our financial right?
Yes.
When it comes down to the wire the FTP.
Business model means just fundamentally.
That, if I have a choice between like, upgrading my game server, this
this month or fixing the store, which broke and isn't working right
now to buy new items, I am going to fix this sort of buy new items
because I know that unless I have a an excess of cash or I'm just like
Awash in money and it doesn't matter.
I need to be fixing the stuff as my prior, my priority.
One programming problem is not
To make the game better is to make sure that we can still sell items,
right?
Absolutely.
And so that's what I'm talking about incentives.
I mean, no matter where your line is, if your line is all the way down
to like, okay.
My line is at the point where I got to make payroll or if you're
lying, is all the way in the other direction where it's like, I'm just
trying to make the most money possible.
No matter what it is, the incentives are what tell you, which decision
you make their right.
And what I'm saying about free-to-play is they never point in the
direction of the game ever?
Not even once the only time the
Of the game comes into play is the if you are worried that people will
not play the game, long enough to buy the item, right?
And so it's all you.
You are the only person who is bringing other incentives into it.
It's Sean McGrath.
That is trying to encourage the game to get better.
Not the business model.
Sure.
Yeah.
Okay.
I think that's I think that's fair but you could also say that I mean
this isn't true so much now, but this was true before twitch.
YouTube is that even in commercial games, all that mattered was the
screenshot, right?
And and the and the review that you got in PC Gamer or whatever, you
know, 10 years back.
That's all that matters.
Yes.
And that games would only strive for that and nothing else, right?
Yeah.
Like how many polygons going to be rendering?
The screenshot?
Who cares about anything else, right?
And if I may just point something out there.
That is why we have fantastic Graphics now.
Full stop.
Maybe.
But that's also why we have shitty games now?
Yes.
No.
And that's exactly right.
That is exactly true.
So, this is exactly I'm saying the incentives of your business, model
matter.
The fact that we have a screenshot Centric trailer Centric way of
selling games, right now, is why our games are universally gorgeous.
It worked.
Now it didn't work for the thing that maybe we wanted it to work for
most but it works but has actually had massive detriment to quality of
games certainly.
But
Massive like huge giant like you can't make a game anymore.
It's impossible because you know you've got to make it look this good
or whatever and developing tools to whatever the whole bunch of
reasons.
We all know the reasons why so I don't know.
Like so f2p, that Vector, the one you were just worried about with
graphics and screenshots that Vector is pointing towards store.
The thing that they need to do is have the best possible purchasing
motivator, whatever, that is the gate, what we will have
Have in the future if f.
P.
What is the predominant business model like screenshot purchasing is
for the past 10 years or whatever?
20 years is, we will have games that are fantastic at selling you
stuff.
Just like you said, we didn't get great games out of the graphics,
boom, because the incentives aren't pointing that direction.
No.
Yeah, you're right.
No, you're absolutely right.
No, that's completely true.
But you know we did get things.
You know, having good graphics is a good thing, right?
And like having super powerful Hardware does allow like, I couldn't
have made, you know, ten years ago or whatever.
I couldn't have made like a high production game on 10 on Hardware at
the time because it was way too hard.
Now, it's super, super easy, right?
So, like, you know, there has been advantages that could be applied to
making games better and, you know, maybe they are being applied by
people who aren't going for that.
Super high-end screenshot or whatever.
Yeah, that's good point.
I like that.
Yeah, it's good.
Well, I think we do is there anything else you wanted to add to this?
Now, I think I mean I said basically I say now I mean granted.
Like I said, one of the problems with picking me for this is I
literally don't think I've ever actually personally played a free to
play game in any real capacity, right?
Like I've never actually I've never played DOTA for example.
So there may be other aspects of it that I am the wrong person to
argue because I just don't know enough about them, right.
But I think I covered everything that I think about from a financial
standpoint business model standpoint, ethical standpoint.
I think I got basically everything I think about in there.
Yeah I think it's a counterproductive to I mean it seems like we got
some more interesting with it.
Yeah.
I think you covered most of the I have more or less of the same
issues with freedom play.
As you do right?
Like I hate everything about her that you hate for the exact same
reasons, right?
And my only perspective was hey, I'm not coming at coming at it from
that point of view, I'm coming at it from.
Hey, this is actually the best option for this game.
And, you know, your point is completely valid that like because of the
way that the business is setup in the model is set up.
It is literally entirely up to, you know, a benevolent dictator to
And sure that evil stuff doesn't happen.
So yeah, I think you know and then you came up with that fantastic
idea of the, the drive to make it, not free to play.
For the next year, I sort of like that, you know, a penny arcade
continue to do that after their first year of doing it.
I feel like they've done it at least twice but the thing that I assume
and I guess I don't know if this is true or not.
But the thing that I assume about that is that I don't know like Penny
Arcade
Aid in general.
I don't really know much about their business model and how much that
add part is part of it.
Like I don't really know enough about that.
All I know is that they did, I think do it at least two years where
they did.
If you paid a certain amount by by this date, it was ad-free.
It was a Kickstarter.
Right?
Is it at?
Yeah.
Is it at free now?
No, it's not.
I just went to their website.
They have ads.
Yeah.
So it didn't work clearly.
I mean they did it.
They definitely did it for one year.
But again, like if you looked at the prices to on it, it didn't look
like they had enough people who were willing to pay for this to me.
Yeah, it was like a million dollars or something they wanted, right?
Yeah, I don't really remember but it was, it was like, it didn't look
like they had people who cared enough about having ads off the front
page to actually want to do it.
Oh, I see.
Okay.
Yeah.
And that and again, the other part about that, too, is like in the
case of this game, right?
The reason that I was trying to come up with that idea as well as like
if you literally don't think you can if you literally think FTP is
your only option for making the game which kind of is what it's keeps
sounding like you're saying, right.
I just I can't think of another way to do it, right?
If you can't think another way to do it and you give players the
option of funding it in an alternative way then at least if they don't
you're like well I did the best I could.
Done.
Right?
Which is a better thing to say than just.
I made it FTP and then I took all the money.
Right?
Yeah.
I know.
It's at least four.
That's right movement to on this on the standpoint of like at least
you maybe you know, you sleep a little better at night making an FTP
game.
If you know that you gave people the option of having it not be at FTP
game, right?
Yeah.
I think that that's been like a plus.
I think that's totally fair like to do and I think it's a good idea to
do that because like I don't if I don't have to worry about a store
and selling shit to people, my life is way better to write.
So
Yeah, I think it's a good idea.
I'm going to do that.
Thank you.
Good thinking, I like it.
Well, well yeah, it's been a pleasure chatting with you.
It was a thank you for doing this.
I really, I really appreciate it.
Oh, good.
I'm glad and I don't know how much money we made.
Do you want me to Chatham?
Yeah, find out how much, how?
I don't have an easy way to sum it up.
I guess.
I think we made.
So we made, okay, we made to one, so we made it.
Dollars plus, so that's be twelve dollars and twenty dollars.
So we, we made like $32 $32.
You'll free to play is amazing.
I don't know what to say.
So I ran that as a bit of a joke, but in reality, it does argue a
little bit for the effectiveness of your business model because yeah,
I don't know what to say point.
I don't think we need to
argue about whether or not free to play him a country, that's a good
point.
Yeah, that's good.
I think that's pretty clear that it.
So anyway, you know what will we do with that money?
I don't know.
I will try to figure out something to buy for thirty dollars as part
of handmade con that we can give away $30 worth of candy or something.
I don't know what, okay?
Well, whatever it was, whatever that number is, if you're giving it
away at
Make on.
I will contribute that a total amount.
So if it was throat $30 or whatever whole double.
All right, well I will actually go do the math, exactly.
Okay.
You're gonna have to wait until handmade Conte, get the money because
I don't have a credit card.
So I confront the $30, all right, whatever it is.
I'll make sure you very much whatever.
All right, man.
All right.
Well, thank you very much.
I really appreciate it.
I feel good about the conversation.
It was a lot of fun.
And so, hopefully, that was useful and also does this game have
A name like for people who are watching.
No, no no name.
Yeah, we got nothing yet.
All right.
What's your what's your Twitch Channel if they want to check it out.
SSS, McGrath I haven't done, I haven't streamed in a while.
It's going to be another two or three weeks before I stream again,
anyway.
All right.
Well, if you want to check out if you want to subscribe to stream to
see the game when it comes out.
SSS McGrath on Twitch, blame blame Casey's former company for not
allowing me to stream the API until I've actually paid for a license.
They won't let me stream the try.
They were like, you can't show your game unless you can't share your
game with Granny in it, unless you've actually paid for a license
Marius.
Yeah.
Hey man.
So tell tell Jeff, it's a bunch of bullshit.
You want, you want to be able to stream, just the trial.
I want to just be able to stream implementing it.
You'd think that actually streaming the trial, they would like,
because then they could watch you and make sure that you're actually
doing it.
I don't know, man.
Relax.
Oh, that's weird.
All right, yeah, I'll ask them about that.
Oh well, thanks not that.
I have any sway there at all, but I'll still ask because I'm curious
to know why they would even care.
But, yeah, I think what the trials over in two weeks anyway, so much
fun.
Yeah, all right, man.
All right, well, thank you very much.
I really appreciate it.
No problem.
Take it easy.
Okay.
See you.
All right.
Well there you have it.
So hopefully I ask the questions that other people would want to have
asked.
We don't actually know exactly how this will turn out and I guess like
I was saying before, you know, I'm certainly skeptical of free to play
but not necessarily because, you know, like all business models,
there's a dirty aspect to it.
But that's true of almost everything.
So it's not so much that, I'm, you know, anti free to play.
Because I think that there's
Very specific about the actual Act of free to play notes.
That makes the game bad.
It's more because as far as I can tell, all of the incentives in the
business model are aimed in the wrong direction and don't encourage
that, right?
And so that was mostly the the angle that I wanted to sort of explore
there was just a figure out what was going on in that from that
standpoint.
And I feel like Sean, you know I mean it did seem very clear that like
you know, obviously he doesn't feel like you will do those things
because he's him and you know feels like he's not going to do those
who knows right.
Right.
And, you know, I don't know, was that the case with zingo when they
started or where they purely people who were just out to be
unscrupulous?
Right from the outset, right?
I have no idea.
I don't know how, you know, people admit get corrupted in these
things.
I don't know what happens.
I can tell you that I have seen some people who have, you know,
traditionally were not particularly corrupted vigils have gone on to
do some fairly Shady things and convince themselves.
Despite, you know, possibly other evidence that what they were doing
was somehow not unscrupulous, right?
So I do worry about that a little bit because, you know, it's not like
everyone who's evil wears, an evil mustache, or goes like this with
their pinky.
So you can
necessarily know, ahead of time if you're someone who's going to make
an unscrupulous decision in the future, I think it's a little more
subtle than a little more creepy, but
Again, you know, the fact that Sean was debating this in the first
place.
Does sort of suggests to me that at least he's taking a little bit
seriously.
And I think if you are going to do an FTP game, that's at least a good
start.
Also, it's kind of felt like we came up with sort of some interesting
ideas there about how to maybe make it.
So that players can encourage you not to be unscrupulous and so maybe
some of those could be prevented and they could help create, you know,
a free-to-play business model that wasn't potentially so deleterious.
Again, that's purely speculative.
I have no idea if that can actually work and until we
See some examples of that working.
We will really, not know because it's anyone's.
Guess think that's about it.
I guess on the chat.
I don't know how you guys how you guys felt about that.
So I guess maybe I'll go to the chat I guess it's oh my God, it's
11:00 here.
That was very long but we'll go to the chat and see anyone who's still
watching, which I guess is actually a lot of people.
It looks like you can let me know.
You know.
Did that seem relatively good?
I feel like we do.
We cover the things that
You wanted to cover, or are we going to have to do a redo at some
point where people send in questions or something like this?
Let's see.
Gary.
Johansson, why do you hate the selling of hats?
I don't actually hate the selling of hats in any particular way more
than any other aspect of free-to-play.
I think it was just that for some reason that was, like, one of the
first things that, you know, valve was doing with selling hats or
something like this.
I don't remember like, in the tf2's, for some reason, it stuck as like
the iconic sort of f2p transaction is, I sold this hat like they put a
new hat on my character.
Ever.
So it's actually not so much that.
That that's something I particularly hate.
It's more that that's my go-to turn of phrase for free-to-play
transaction.
D Perry, did you manage to discuss any issues surrounding being locked
into a certain game due to the amount of money?
You've spent on it, not particularly.
But the idea that I sort of proposed at the end, would have alleviated
that problem because the
If the cap was hit, would allow somebody to access everything.
Right?
And I think, Sean's monthly cap also means that the high spending
players which are kind of guess the people you're talking about, also
can always cap out a month and get everything in the game.
He was saying that basically, like if you spend $50 on the game in a
month, you just get everything for that month.
So you can always opt to just unlock everything for yourself at any
time and kind of go back.
Maybe that's a little bit mitigation, but in general.
No, I don't think we talked about
What you're saying there that and I'm not very familiar that myself.
Unfortunately, I said I'm one of the reasons that I'm not necessarily
the best person for the debate.
I try to do a good job but I don't play f2p games.
I've never spent a hundred fifty dollars buying hats or something like
that, right?
So I don't have any personal perspective on that really
A pigeon games with our Icarus says, would you play in f2p MOBA of
Master spy?
Well, I'm the master spy.
So I don't know what that would mean, right?
Because everyone would just I'd Master spy all over them and they
would just get Masters fide right out there like Apprentice spies and
I'm the master spy.
So how do you even have a MOBA, right?
Maybe can be asymmetric like, I'm the master spy and everyone knows
I'm a master's by and everyone else is like an apprentice by and it's
like ten on one or something.
BTN games.
I think it was ideal as a thought process to consider the impact of
the model.
You choose, Thank you out of Interest.
How do you feel about a game where you start with a certain amount of
game tracks?
And then you can buy expansion pack with more tracks in the future?
Should you make them so personally I feel like that's actually a good
business model.
The problem is it has a few problems with it.
That again I feel like if I were taking the devil's out of position, I
would Point them out and they're very similar to free-to-play.
Basically, what they are is if you
Talking about a model where every few months we come out with an
expansion pack that you can buy and it's a legitimate well-considered
thing.
That's good that we, you know, we worked hard on and we're selling you
this, this additional part of the game that seems totally fine to me,
right?
That's like people bought this game.
They really liked it.
The dev team worked hard to make it bigger and better, and other
selling them to you.
That seems totally fine to me.
Unfortunately, like I said, it kind of has a little bit of the problem
of FTP, which is that there are some incentives.
To then starting to like, drag out updates into lots of little
purchasable pieces, and you saw that happen with things, once DLC,
like cheap DLC became a thing.
So, in the old days, when you had to go to the store, you had to buy
an expansion pack off the rack.
That was a much had a lot more Integrity because it meant that you had
to sell them a high-priced single infrequently shipped thing that I
feel like maybe didn't have so many bad incentives associated with.
Now that you can sell a little things for 99 cents.
Three dollars, whatever.
Mansion pack could mean anything and it's a little more nebulous and
so I think it kind of does get back into the territory where it's like
as a business model.
I don't necessarily like it as much so you know, like, for example,
this something we
About at my rocket about how we're doing things and we would like to
do games that have potential expansion packs with them.
And so we, you know, it from my mind, that's definitely something that
I feel like has to be very clear what it is.
You have to limit the number you do and you have to put in a lot of
checks and balances to make sure that that remains an ethical way to
sell things.
And unfortunately a lot like what Sean was saying where it's like kind
of like you know, how does a good person codify these things.
It is very hard to.
Codify and so you know so like I said I don't know and I have some
concerns about it.
I guess basically what I would prefer is if the marketplace itself had
the concept of expansion pack that was something different from DLC so
that it was clear what it was.
And you could be a developer who consciously specifically said, we do
expansion packs.
Not DLC because I do think there's a difference between those two
things, right?
And it's just that doesn't exist.
And so as a developer it's about again, entirely honor System and
Honor System stuff just isn't necessarily that good.
How do you know you can trust me case.
Samira Tori to make those decisions about this game, right?
And, and so again, like I think there's some of those things where I
don't think there's nearly as many as f2p, but they're there.
How about p2f Locklear's with small room until they finish the game?
Love, it would love to see it question.
A fifty dollar monthly limit with Benefits instead of his players to
play a lot to pay a lot of money.
Each month for items.
They probably don't need at least there's a risk there.
I think that's possibly true.
I mean, like I said, I like you saw.
I wasn't that
I wasn't that interested in the 50 dollar cap.
I didn't think that was that big of a fan Improvement, but, you know,
I don't know, it's probably better than nothing, right.
It's probably better than letting people spend $2000 a month.
The only flaw in your discussion is that you look at games from the
perspective of two highly intelligent people and forgot that.
Not even if both players are retarded idiots, who will gladly eat, my
star star star and ask for more with a proper advertisement involved.
Yeah.
I mean what can you say right?
Like I think first of all there that's that's not necessarily entirely
the case, right?
Like there are certainly markets of players who are intelligent right
and especially when you're talking about Indie gaming, those are
people who are seeking out specific less advertised experiences and
you know they might be being a little more thoughtful about their game
buying, right?
And so it's not necessarily the case that 95% of players for all games
are going to be some kind of
Abstract consumer like you're making them out to be right?
So I don't know.
Is it true that the public at large does not seem to show a lot of
discretion in terms of what they purchase?
Yes, I won't argue with that and unfortunately,
I don't know that there's really anything to do about that.
What I love to have some way.
We could wave a wand and make a magic educated populace know, but at
the same time it's like well that's true of all business models,
right?
All business models definitely have the case that the fact that people
are not educated consumers, as much as we might like them to be, it
means it leads to worse products.
And that's true of all of its models that we currently have.
Unfortunately,
Gaston 5, the problem through suggested method is that everyone that
wanted to FTP turned off in the beginning of the year, we'll have to
buy the standard price in unison or have the high inequality charging
that Sean complained about.
So one thing that maybe you could do about to fix that problem, right?
Would be.
Maybe you could you could imagine doing something where, instead of
you actually paying the free-to-play stuff, it's more of a pledge
drive and it's a pledge Drive isn't successful.
That money is never charged.
So it's more like a
Starter, right?
And then that way, everyone puts their money in and if it's
successful, it's gets charged.
If it's not isn't and it's just regular FTP from there.
So, the kick starter model, I think if you follow that more closely
would be a better solution, right?
And that's why I was trying to push on.
I wasn't so coherent about it.
Because like I said, I only just thought of it.
That's why I was trying to push on away from the constant of, it's
just, it's f2p until it's a cap.
I don't know if that's necessarily the best model.
I think there should be ways of people pledging the money and then if
it doesn't happen, they don't necessary have to spend that.
Money on FTP.
Byblos says, I slept through the whole discussion.
I apologize.
Will you be uploading it to YouTube?
Yes, with Sean's permission.
Obviously I will check with him but I did record it.
It should be recorded here and so I can do that.
But at the very least of streamed on Twitch so it's already on Twitch
on demand and will be for a few days.
Anyway, regardless
Mr.
Fourth dimension just wish there was some way to make the lopsided
payment distribution better, or at least make the lopsided
needs-based.
I couldn't agree more.
That again, that was a big point that I brought up.
I don't know how you fix that problem.
I wish that was the case as well.
Godfather expansion packs of the old days.
Had enough cons justify a three dollar price tag that gave you 10
hours, more gameplay, or even more depending on the type of game.
Yes.
And that's exactly what I was trying to say when I was talking about
that and that's like what we were talking about at Molly, we were
talking about how we want to do the game.
That was definitely something that we were sort of saying is like, you
know, we feel like that we would want that, right?
You know as we sell the game and then it's you know it's a fifteen
dollar expansion pack, that's actually supposed to be a legitimate
like buying a game for $15 and the only difference between it and
buying game for $15.
Is that that game adds on to another game?
Not that, you know, it's just something we concocted to get you paid
15 more dollars, right?
But the problem again, is that the business model doesn't really
support that because, because digital distribution is so easy.
And because there's so much, you know, sort of uncertainty around and
all
Stuff.
It is kind of easy to gain that system, right?
It's easy to not ship something that's worth it to the player.
The heat pirate.
It's time to bring back shareware, right?
I Feel It In My Bones.
Well, I don't know about that.
I mean, people seem to think that demos don't really work very well
anymore.
A lot of the data shows that demos lead to much lower sales and maybe
that's because people are playing the games and then just not buying
them because they weren't good.
But maybe it's because they only want to play a little bit and then
they move on.
And that's not really fair to the developer because they should be
paid for that time.
If they actually were enjoying it, I don't know.
And I don't pretend to know
Icarus rare, we're sorry easy Sy would micropayments work.
That is I still don't understand why you think subscription model with
low monthly prices wouldn't work.
People who want to play the game will play the game.
Well, what he kept saying, and I again, I don't know if this is true,
this is just what he believes.
And I mean, you know, I'm in no position to argue about this aspect of
the market.
So, I certainly can't say one way or the other, whether he's likely to
be correct.
But what he was saying is, you need the non-paying players, because
you need that many
People in the service.
Now I don't know, I probably would never go that route, but if that
really was true.
So if you're taking what he, if you're taking that belief of his at
face value which, you know, at some level could be true, it's not
definitely not true, right?
Then you have to concede that he does need a way of offering his game
at zero dollars to some segments of the market, right?
And so the question is, how do you do that?
So it's a legitimate question, you know.
And you know, I would my answer would be, I don't want to make a game
if that game requires me to use that business model right.
But that's my feeling about it.
And so he doesn't feel that way about it.
And so that's, you know, I guess where the argument comes in.
Sean McGrath says YouTube away.
Don't care.
I put everything I said in the public domain.
Okay?
So basically, he's saying we can upload this and also shown, by the
way, I will put it on the handmade hero BitTorrent.
I'll put the raw file on there, so if you would like to grab it and
upload it to your YouTube channel or archive it or do whatever you
want, you can grab it from that BitTorrent, the raw file.
So you can just have your own copy of the recording
and sea games is needs-based really the fairest bar, how about how
much you
The game based.
Like I said, I don't really know about that part or either way.
All.
I was trying to point out with that particular part was that the
people who pay don't necessarily fit any metric other than just they
were the people who paid.
And so it's not true that that somehow aligns better with the like the
people who like the game, the most paid the most, or the people who
could afford the most paid, the most none of that is necessarily true.
At all right.
There's nothing in the system that guarantees that it's simply that
the people who were compelled to pay paid in the people who didn't
didn't
And that's all we know about it, right?
We don't have any data or evidence that suggests any other
correlation,
Character Hansen, can I be the guy that sells you unscrupulous items
in the game?
You are making like the gun salesman in Resident Evil 4.
In?
What game are you talking about?
Are you talking about in Sean's game?
I you'll have to ask him.
Okay.
Now how did you come up with that explanation of player?
Consumer Behavior?
The one involving incentives, responses.
Those incentives being used, wrongly and FTP
Well I guess I'm not sure exactly the question is in general that is
the way I think of Economics models.
And that's typically the way that economists think of it economic
models is what our people incentivized to do and what our people, what
aren't people incentivized to do.
And in general there's some places that I agree with Economist and
place.
I don't agree with Economist the places that I don't agree with
economists are on consumer Behavior.
So in terms of consumer Behavior, I don't agree with sort of the
classical.
Thinking that people always do what is best for them in terms of their
monetary incentives.
I believe people are much more behavioral much more skinnerian and can
be reinforced to do things that are very much.
Not good incentives for them, but where I do agree with the comments
is that business follow businesses tend to follow incentives, quite
well?
And the reason for that I think is because they are the ones who are
actively weeded out.
Meaning there is a natural selection process in business that
enforces, the people who do not follow the incentives are weeded out
the people who do become
I'm stronger and that ensures that you only end up with businesses who
are good at following the incentives or go.
The incentives of your economics model tend to be followed and I think
LD evidence that we see reinforces that basically what you see like in
the United States, you see primarily corporations who are very
effective at maximizing, the incentives of the systems that we set up.
And so, the way I think a free-to-play is exactly the same.
I say, once you have a Marketplace that works in this particular way
in custody or start engaging in it, I think you will see that whatever
the incentives are for purchasing, their that is, what will get
followed on the business side and the businesses who don't follow that
will simply go away.
Now, one of the things that Sean can do potentially is if he keeps his
cost down, he can come out of that.
Tier of competition, right?
If you're not trying to compete with League of Legends and DOTA and
you're trying to compete for a lesser slot games that took cost a
million dollars to produce a year, instead of a hundred million
dollars for this year, whatever.
Then maybe you don't have, you won't get weeded out because you're not
actually competing in the same incentive space.
There's room in the slop potentially, for ethical people to find a way
to operate ethically, despite the incentives that may happen, right?
So I don't deny that.
That that's possible.
It's just that, that is not what the system is, designed to produce.
Let's see.
Is there a release date yet?
For what?
For what are we talking about?
Is release date for what?
Carrie.
Johansson know, the Molly Rock game.
Nobody sells you items in the Molly Rocket game.
So to speak, at least, not in the way that you were suggesting, so
sorry, there is there's not a position for that NC games.
What's your personal idea of the best model to incentivize a great
game.
You talked about the graphics focused issues with the standard 6, is
our model, you know, I don't know that there is much beyond the model
that we have.
Now, we're basically saying, like, Okay, an indie market place with
reasonable, press $15, $25, price points and educated consumers is the
best thing we've found so far.
And, you know, I really don't know how we make something better than
that.
At the end of the day, purchasing decisions are still going to be made
by individuals and enough.
People need to decide to buy a particular game.
In order for that game to be successful.
And so at the end of the day, I think it really comes back to the fact
that
No matter what business models we choose?
If you want to get past the sort of standard, I pay you for a game,
and I have the game and I play it.
If you want to get any better than that, it's going to start attacking
the problem at the, at the market at the, I'm sorry, at the audience.
How do we get players, who engage more accurate, the games, how do we
get players, who demand more from their games?
How do we get players?
Who know are more aware about which games are available, and which
ones they might like, right?
And and again that's that's a media issue.
That's an education issue and and those are just really hard problems.
So you know, I think that currently the most ethical thing we have is
just the standard one of you go to steam, you buy a game for 15 bucks
and you play it.
That's the most ethical thing we have right now and getting beyond
that.
I think starts to get into issues that maybe go beyond just the
economic model.
This is adequate.
If you do this sort of shut, again, I recommend trying to have Sean
Plott as a guest.
I do not know who that is but I will, I can try searching for them.
Girl and the coded game.
You're making.
Okay?
So you're talking about what's its release date?
No there.
Release date for it yet now.
Pagan heart.
We haven't even announced that yet.
It's pretty early to announce a release date.
Are if you're talking about the one at Molly rocket.
Anyway, Pagan heart, definitely, like the system of raising the cost
and extra needed to, for growth Etc.
But then having a supporter perk for those who donate a certain amount
for the extra oomph benefits and if that fails Freedom after becomes a
fallback one thing, Delta divided people into buying that might be if
they had committed to that donation, but it fails as a whole, they
still get that benefit regardless, or they just don't have to pay it
so it could be strictly
Right?
So it's like, all those donations pileup, either.
They get all charged and it's free, or it just does free to play in.
Those are they aren't charge.
That would also work time to switch hats.
That's a good point.
I think we go back to no hat.
Will just end the hats people bought all three hats.
So you know we ended up in a situation where
we're, that was necessary, but
All right folks, it's pretty far past my bedtime.
So I have to go.
Thank you very much for joining us for this discussion.
I enjoyed it.
Hopefully, Sean also got sort of what he needed to get out of it in
terms of his own consideration and what he thinks is maybe the right
course for the game.
And also I would thank him sort of in the abstract as well for taking
the time to consider it because at the end of the day it's very
Obvious that players except free to play.
And there's nothing stopping Sean from just going ahead and being as
unscrupulous as he wants to be and making a free-to-play game.
So at the end of the day even though it's not really a business model
that I liked and I it's one that I have, obviously, lots of
reservations about that.
I voiced at the end of the day I do, you know, appreciate the fact
that he's taking the time to think it through and maybe to try to not
be unscrupulous about it.
That's more than a lot of people are doing so in so much.
Much as I can say that I think it's a really sort of dangerous idea.
At the same time it's like well since you are doing the dangerous
idea, thank you for trying to do it in a more ethical way than you
have to, because certainly nothing again.
The whole point of the business model is, there's nothing in there
that requires you to be scrupulous in any way really.
So so that's that.
We will be back tomorrow for the final episode of handmade hero this
week, that will be at the standard handmade hero time.
Now, 5 p.m.
Pacific daylight time.
Love to see you back here for that.
Thanks for joining us for this discussion and we will talk to you
guys.
Well we'll see you guys on the internet.
Also don't forget Sean McGrath just if you don't if you didn't already
know who he was, there's SSS McGrath I believe on Twitch is his is his
twitch channel so you can go here and watch that.
And also if you would rather follow him on Twitter, he also has a
Twitter feed.
You can
subscribe to and that is in the
Exact same place word wise SSS McGrath.
So yeah.
If you're interested if you liked what you had to say, you're
interested to see how his game development goes, then definitely go
here and maybe subscribe to his Twitter feed so you can keep in touch.
All right, that's it.
Take it easy.
Everyone hope to see you guys back here tomorrow.
Until then have fun programming, and I'll see you guys on the
internet.