Recording cycled.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show recoded complete game live on Twitch.
No engine, no, libraries.
It's time for us to kind of get down to it here yet.
Last, the last week we ended on Friday with some perspective
projection which means that our Z code is basically working.
Now as far as the render is concerned, which leaves us with one
remaining thing left to do which is to start digging into how we are
representing Z levels in the world.
Kind of this
A sticking point.
We've been dancing around it for a while.
It's been the bane of our existence for quite some time because again
in a 3D game it's easy to conceptualize Z, it's just another thing.
That's treated the same as everything else but in a 2-D game, we have
to do all these kind of gyrations to think about exactly how we want
to handle Z.
If you want to do it in an interesting robust way, and most Tony gate,
2D games don't.
But again, since this is a programming series, we want to kind of
tackle this head-on and show how to confront an interesting technical
problem like this.
Where there are
Really right answers only trade-offs and show how we make trade-offs
that lead us to a good place in terms of code.
So what I like to do is get right back into that, but before I do, let
me just mention briefly.
It is day 109 here on handmade hero, which means that if you have
pre-ordered, the game on handmade hero dot-org and you want to follow
along with a code that I am doing, you will want to unpack day 108
source code, because that is what I am working with today, and that is
what we will be using as a basis for
The code that we do right now.
So here's where we were at.
We left off on Friday, we had fixed our perspective transform and you
can see that we're not drawing a ground right now so that we can see
actually the tree rings that go increasingly back into the distance so
we can see three levels of the world.
Now, it actually goes much further than that the world does?
I think it goes, I don't even know how far it goes down, but very,
very far.
I think I want to say may go 2,000 rooms deep right now.
I'm not sure if
I'm right about that but I think we may generate two thousand rooms
straight down and what we do right now is we actually have some little
simple yellow rectangles here that we could walk down right now.
We walk down them, the top-level Fades out and the a new level fades
in at the bottom.
So we're totally set with how that works.
And the perspective is looking pretty correct here.
Our render is completely on optimized right now.
So it's still a bit slow but that's totally fine because that's
something that we'll be getting to sometime soon.
Anyway.
So, what we need to do now is we need to have a little bit of a more
coherent idea about how we're handling these you levels.
We wanted to quickly check the perspective mat.
Just to make sure we didn't have anything weird in there.
I was a little nervous about the actual values we plugged in, for our,
for our monitor distance and stuff into our math.
So you want to take a little bit of a look at that.
But what we would like to do after that is, just get back to the issue
at hand, which is figuring out how to represent these Z values in
terms of storage and in terms of other stuff.
So that we can kind of get, you know, just a better feel for them.
So, I guess one thing that I would like to do now is just say,
alright, let's take a look at that perspective, projection.
And let's think about what we're actually representing in the world
here, and how we want it to appear, how it should appear in terms of
how big it actually was.
And we'll see if things.
Make some sense.
Now, I agree that the way that I've tuned it here as probably not
super realistic.
If these are actually stories of a building, you have to figure that
probably they'd be a little bit more separated than they are now,
right?
And so probably I tuned it a little conservatively and so really it's
not maybe as bad as I made it out to be, but I think it still is a
little wonky.
So maybe we'll take a look at that.
But let's go in here.
Let's say we switched it to something.
A little bit more like that, that looks a little bit more correct to
me in terms of maybe if it actually was sort of more like the story of
a building like a supposed to be, we set it to 3 meters which is
around one storey height for a building certainly not cathedral
ceilings but you know something that's a regular height that should
actually be right.
And that probably is a little bit better than than it than it was than
I had it tuned, right?
But looking at that as a looking at that as a
Set of parameters, right?
If that looks particularly reasonable backing out, what's in here,
right?
What we're essentially saying is is kind of weird, like, what this is
saying is that the camera distance above the target, which is the
place that we're looking at the camera doesn't about the target.
We're setting it to the same thing as the focal length, right?
And I guess, I mean, that could be a reason.
That's, that's the thing that was weirding me out.
Basically, that could be totally reasonable, but I want to kind of
explain what that is and why I was a little nervous about it just
because it doesn't really line up with what I was expecting to see.
And when things don't line up with what you're expecting to see, it's
usually worth taking another.
Look at them.
Now granted, what I'm expecting to see as a person who programs 3D
graphics for a living, may not be what you should see in a 2-D game
and this may just be a learning experience for me where I'm going.
Oh, oh.
Okay, in a 2-D game because of the way the art it works.
And the two dienes, it actually does make some sense but you know,
just in case there's some additional drama in here.
I want to make sure that we understand it, right?
So let's talk about this for a second.
So, fundamentally speaking.
We've got a world down here, right?
And we've got some trees that were talking about here on these plates
and then we've got another plate below it.
Here's another, you know, with some more trees that go around in a
ring, right?
Blah blah, blah, blah, right.
The tree is
Go all the way around.
And and in the middle of this, there is an imaginary Target and we're
imagining that the camera, right?
Z comes up boots, Z comes up like this, this is the z-axis and there's
an imaginary point that we're basically calling the camera.
Right.
That is looking down on this stuff, right?
The cameras kind of looking down to see these things.
And what I was expecting is I was expecting to have, you know, a
basically a parameter here.
That was the monitor, right?
Sort of the monitor is here, basically and that distance here was our
focal length, right?
And then I was expecting to have some other distance here, which is
how far the camera is from from the Target, right?
This is the camera distance to the Target, and that's what we base,
the perspective equation on.
Because, basically, we're taking these things and we're projecting
them onto this imaginary monitor here.
And we're using these two parameters to do so, now, what I realized
after we did that, that I thought might be part of the confusion, is
what we did not do.
We're implicitly, is we never actually said, how big the monitor is,
right?
So we have M to pixels and M, 2 pixels is just a value that we
specified, randomly back in the day, and M 2 pixels is entirely
implicitly.
Defining the size of the actual monitor.
Now, we didn't Define the size of the monitor based on its actual
size, in any way, right?
So the fact that the monitor itself its size is being represented in m
2 pixels.
Could be one of the reasons why these values don't make a lot of
sense.
It could be that m.
2 pixels is actually a very, very wrong value because we set m 2
pixels based on an arbitrary thing when we had an orthographic
projection that wasn't doing any of this.
And so, what I want to do today is just go, how big is the actual
monitor?
How would this work out if we actually Define its
Eyes and how big we expected pixels to be in World units in that sort
of thing, right?
so,
what I want to do is go take a look at m 2 pixels, right?
Because that's gets set back in here somewhere.
M 2 pixels right.
And basically what we said here is that a pixel, right?
He's 42.
I'm sorry.
A meter is 42 pixels, right?
That's how big?
That's how big a meter is, right?
And so I think the problem, the reason that there's a 10 in here and
in fact, the now that I'm even looking at this, I think my suspicion
from
After the stream on Friday was very much correct.
M, 2 pixels as 42.
Well, where are the pixels in this diagram?
We were talking about them as if they were here back in the day when
we were doing M pixels because it was an orthographic projection.
But now, where are the pixels were the pixels are on this plane.
So if we are saying that basically one meter equals 42 pixels,
Then now we have to ask ourselves, how big is our monitor.
Right?
It's a legitimate question.
Let's go ahead and see what our Dimension is right when we actually
create our display service.
So somewhere in here, right, we've got a, you know, a client with the
height kind of a thing going on here.
See create window.
Where do we do this?
I don't actually want to create window.
I want to create a where we create our back buffer.
We have 960 by 540, right?
So we have a 9 960 by 540 Monitor and we're saying that for every
forty two pixels we have a meter, right?
So if I were to back out the math, right?
If I do 960 / 42, right?
Nine, sixty divided by 4, T 2, that gives me a monitor size of twenty,
two point, eight, five meters, right?
22.8 5 meters across, right?
So this is the size of our monitor across and then 540 loops around
that properly 857 should be 86 M.
There we go.
And then 540 divided by 4 T.
2 is 12 meters down, right?
Twelve point eight, six point.
Eight.
Six meters down.
Right?
So that means our monitor, right?
Is the size of a room.
Basically, this is like the size of an apartment, right?
That that is a very, very, very large monitor.
In fact, you might say that, it's about ten times the size.
Is of a monitor and hey, guess what?
That is exactly.
The number that you have to plug in here to get these values to feel
more correct.
So I suspect what is actually happening here is that our M to pixel
value is completely erroneous and actually does not in any way
represent what should be going on with our world coordinate system?
So I feel like we've got to fix that, right?
I feel like that's something we're going to want to to repair, right?
and so,
Maybe maybe we shouldn't tackle any more Z's up today, maybe we should
just go through and make sure that our m 2 pixels is actually going to
be something that works correctly.
So let's take a look at this here.
Let's think about this for a second.
So basically, m 2 pixels is used in only really two places.
Now if I, if I remember correctly.
Right?
I believe that m 2 pixels is essentially used only to compute our
actual projection, which is where we want to use it.
But also in one place where it's kind of annoying to have to use it
but it's basically where we compute our bitmap offsets, right?
And the reason that we need it, there is because we are bitmap offsets
are in pixels because
That is how we know what, that's how we measure them, right?
So there's a couple ways that we could try and mitigate that fact.
In fact, there's a couple ways I can think of right now to mitigate
that fact.
So, maybe what we should do is try to get M to pixels out of the
pipeline entirely by converting the values that we currently need it
for into something else.
If that makes sense, right?
And if we do that, then we can set our perspective.
It's warm up.
So that it's the only place that thinks about how pixels and World
units, interact and the rest of the game.
Never thinks about it at all.
I think that's a pretty important thing to want to do, because that
way, it makes it easier for us, when we go to start supporting
multiple resolutions at the same time it makes it.
So that that's not some big ordeal, right?
We want to be able to just say okay if we want to change the
resolution to 1920 by 1080 from our you know, from our current
resolution it's just a simple thing to do and it's
Not this big sort of ordeal where we have to.
Think about everyone who's thinking about pixels, right?
We want basically as few people as possible ever thinking about pixels
so that we can be resolution independent up to as far of a point as we
want to be right.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead and suggest that
perhaps we just encode our hotspots as being proportional to the size
of the bitmaps.
The
Cells, right?
So instead of having them proportional to this m, 2 pixel stuff.
Instead we can just have our bitmaps, not have any of that
information, not have any of that sort of concept at.
All right?
So if we take a look at handmade render group, right?
You can see how we've got this V2 a line right now.
And right now that's in pixels, right?
But what we could do here is, we could sort of say that.
Well, what if that was a line percentage, right?
So the loaded,
it map was actually saying what its alignment point was as a
percentage of its width and height, that way, it can be passed through
without ever being multiplied out, right?
It can always be in some, you know, independent thing that will be the
same, whether the units are meters or pixels or anything else, right?
Because the percentage of a distance is the same, whether you're
measuring in pixels or measuring it, anything else, right?
So if I was to change this to a line percentage, let's see what that
would do to the code, right?
So when I am doing this sort of operation here, where we're like, OK,
m 2 pixels offset, and then we have a line whatever.
When we do, our push bitmap call,
In this case, I believe that we don't we never actually at this point
specify how big we want that thing to be.
So, okay, this and this is going to be I think this might actually be
even more interesting.
So this is all good.
I think, I think this is, I feeling good about this.
I think this is probably what we should do.
So I'm going to go ahead and go down this road.
There's two steps we need to take and I'm going to see about taking
both of them.
So the first step is to extract out that alignment but is still going
to introduce.
One thing that has to do with M to pick
And you'll see that in one second, right?
So what I want to do is introduce the alignment here.
So what happens if I was going to do that, if I want to pull this
alignment out as a lineman percentage, I need something to multiply it
by, right.
So I need to make this alignment like so and my bitmap aligned
percentage here, I need to multiply it by something that is a
reasonable percentage right now, since we're still in pixels
everywhere.
I actually know what that percentage is supposed to be.
It's supposed to be
In pixels because this is accepting pixels right here.
So what I need to do is say, alright I just need the bitmap width and
height, right?
And then if I multiply the percentage, the aligned percentage by that
bitmap width and height that will give me where that alignment point
is.
Right?
So, let's go ahead and
And take a look here.
What did I do there?
Bitmap a line percent.
Oh right.
This is a hadamard product, right?
It's a vector product.
Let's go ahead and do that.
So when we do this top, when we do this, this alignment stuff here.
Now we got a little more work to do, you can kind of see that we've
got a few places just they're not very, there's not very many but
there's a few places that set this alignment.
So now these things, but they have to do, is they have to basically be
smart about the way they encode things.
So right now we've got this alignment, it's gets passed in, but
Not a proportion of the width and height.
So, in order to do that, what we want to do, I believe we have a safe
ratio function.
Do we not have a safe ratio function?
I'm going to take a look and see if we do here, safe, ratio, we do.
So, I'll do safe ratio one.
Let's say, well actually, we say F ratio 0, so safe ratio, 0 and
produce.
A ratio of these, where we include code the X and the Y based on that
bitmap width and height, right?
So it's the same line of value.
It's just in
Instead now we're changing it to mean the percentage, right?
Of the width and height, okay?
Hopefully, that makes sense.
Let's take a look, here, we've got okay.
These guys have to be up, converted to float, switch is fine.
We've got a line percentage here instead of a line and then these guys
as well are all going to be aligned percentages like that.
And then we just have to see.
Oops, didn't mean to do that.
Then we just have to see whether or not any of that works.
I don't know if it will looks totally fine to me, right?
So basically we've got essentially
Li the exact same thing as we had before.
Let's just make sure that our offsets are working.
As we expect they are they do look like they are.
Everything's kind of works as I expect if there are so that's all
good.
Nothing, nothing, nothing particularly weird happening there, so
that's good.
All right.
So that totally eliminated one of our m, 2 pixels things, right, which
is now restoring these as a percentage but unfortunately we're still
using the width and the height of the bitmap.
Actually when we go to store our actual to me, our actual
Data there, right?
When we do that push, we're still using the width and the height of
the bitmap which means that this is still m 2, pixels is still getting
directly used in the actual encode call.
And what we'd like to do is we'd like to get rid of that, basically.
So, what I want to do is I want to introduce the concept that the
bitmap itself.
Right also has sort of a native scale value.
That says, what the
Is based on the bitmap what its native scale is X2 I right.
In other words what I want to do is say okay, you know, we've got a
thing which is like y x like this, right?
And what I want to do is say okay, from now on, we need to actually
say how big things are going to be on the screen.
We're going to give those in actual meters from now on.
So when we say how tall the guy is, we're going to give that it m,
right?
We're going to say how tall the guy should be in meters.
Yes.
So when we do that, what I'd like to do is say how tall he is in
meters in one dimension, right?
Like why I'll give the Y value and then it'll solve for the x value,
right?
It will not solve it, will compute the x value based on a
multiplication.
Knowing what essentially, the aspect ratio of the Sprite is meaning,
I'll say whatever the X pixel width is right.
Well, I guess we'll do it this way pixel width.
Over pixel height will be something that we store with a bitmap.
And when we do this, right?
The fact that this is in pixels, right?
It's like 32 pixels over 60 pixels or whatever pixels cancels out and
we end up with just a dimensionless ratio.
Write it no longer.
Is that it's in pixels.
And so again, that will help me to eliminate pixels entirely from the
pipeline here, by just specifying that and getting back to sort of a
sort of a pixel neutral way of specifying things.
So, let's take that, let's go ahead and take that step, right?
And let's say width to height right?
Or I guess we'll say with over height, right?
Something like that.
It's just a scale value.
That says, if I have a height value, I can multiply by this to get the
width out of
It no matter what it is.
Okay, so what I need to do now is every time we actually load a bit
map, I need to go ahead and compute that value, but that is not very
hard to compute, right?
It's just a simple ratio.
So every time we do a debug load bitmap, it's pretty trivial for us
to.
Just go ahead and store that value, right?
With over height is just going to be a simple ratio.
Well, if at all you say, for sure, one for now, I guess.
Well, 0 is probably better.
If the, if the well it doesn't really matter that there should never
be a bitmap that doesn't have both values being greater than 0, right?
So what I want to do is take the ratio here there.
I'm sorry, the result with a result height do take the ratio between
the tube and produce that value and so then that will give me a
permanent way of doing that computation, right?
And again, I guess I got to up convert those to float since there by
default integer.
Once I have that, now, when we go to, do our push bitmap calls, right?
Instead of the old days, where we had m, 2 pixels, governing
everything.
But I'd like to do is just say okay from now on what we're going to do
is were actually going to say how big we expect things to be right,
how big and M we expect them to be and we can still, we can actually
when we load things, if we want to keep our current way of doing
things, right?
If we don't want to disrupt the way we're doing it now, and we
essentially want to base the size of everything off of how big it's
bitmap was, which we probably don't really want to do.
But you know, we could do that.
We could say it's like native height value or whatever is based on
that m 2 pixels value, right?
So we can still keep the old m 2 pixels in here.
If we want to write, which would just be the native height of the
bitmap and
that's just going to be whatever the height was divided by m 2 pixels,
right?
Or more explicitly pixels to M times that, right?
And that would mean that this when we do that read, write, whenever we
read a bitmap, we would have to say what we want, our pixels to M to
be, but what I think we can do now.
If we do it this way, is we could make it so that literally the bitmap
loading routine is the only thing now that ever cares about pixels to
meters.
He's at all.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go grab M to pixels right
here.
And I'm going to go ahead and go back up to this function and just
paste that in here.
So I'm going to say pixels to M right here and I'm going to say that
that's, you know, right there.
It's so for every forty two pixels.
There's a meter, right.
Which I think is probably not how big.
I don't know if that's how big we want it to be.
Maybe that is how big things should have been.
I'm not sure.
I don't remember.
We'll have to think about that.
It seems a little odd but well, doesn't matter, never mind, ignore
that for now.
We'll think about that for a second, a little bit later, but let's say
we go ahead and do that.
We now have everything that we need in order to basically do this
completely, without any values in the pipeline at all.
So, let's go ahead and take a look at m 2 pixels and where that is
used.
Right.
You can see that essentially, it's really something that's basically
only used in the render group, right?
It's not
Used anywhere else.
So I'm going to go ahead and try to get rid of that.
I'm going to go ahead and get rid of that.
I'll take a look at the game State value.
We'll see if we can get rid of it, m, 2, pixels, and pixels to M,
right?
I'm just going to go ahead and try to to exercise that, right?
So this is going to be a little bit, the world, the world chunk Tim
and M stuff, this this stuff right here.
We need to start thinking about a little bit differently.
Anyway, when we do those
Old chunks.
We don't actually care what the pixel values are of these weak.
This is going to be something.
We're going to do a little differently.
But for now we will do, we will leave this guy just in here but only
just there, so let's do this.
This.
All right.
Let's just use that this way because I don't want to actually deal
with the ground.
Buffer is just yet since they're not even turned on at the moment,
let's see here.
And get rid of that guy.
Now we go over to the render group m, 2 pixels goes away, and the
allocate render group call allocate render group takes that out of the
equation.
So and now we just have to go in and actually clean up anywhere that
was doing this.
So what does the screen width in M have to do with anything?
Here.
Okay, so this is another good example like this, right here is a good
example of also, why we don't want to do it because this basically
this is essentially a culling value, right?
This camera bounds and M.
And what we want to do is we eventually want to set this based on what
the renderer thinks you can see.
So this is actually another good example of some place where we really
want to start cleaning up this, because this should be the renderer
that tells us
How big we actually want those camera bounds to be?
I should think if that makes sense.
That's just my guess anyway.
But yeah, at the moment it's unclear what we want to do with that.
So I'm going to leave that just for now, so we can get all of the
renderer working with no pixels to meters.
And then we will see if we can remove pixels to M entirely, or if we
don't remove it, entirely have it in a place where we know that
there's some, a couple coherent values that are computed with it and
then we throw it away, right?
So, let's take a look here, essentially.
Now when we get the
Tootie basis P stuff.
This will be something that we that will be the routine that we
actually do the work in.
But now everybody else I believe can get rid of the pixels to M stuff.
So I'm going to go ahead and see if we can if we can just exercise
that entirely draw a rectangle, slowly is still taking that pixels to
meters.
Yeah, so this is our reflection thing here.
Yeah, and that's just using it to figure out how much it wants to move
how much it wants to move by.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and Nerf this guy for a second
here.
Again I'm just trying to Pare down the amount of code that we have to
use to get rid of this see here and technically I suppose, I don't
actually have to do this, in fact now that I think about it.
I don't actually have to get rid of this from the renderer.
I'm trying to get rid of this from everyone external to the renderer
and from all the storage.
So I suppose technically this routine having it isn't necessarily a
bad thing, I could be okay with that.
I'm not sure.
Yet, I'll have to think about that.
I'll have to think about that a little.
All right, I'm gonna let that sit for a second.
So I'm going to leave that in here and we'll leave that there.
And then I'm going to remove basically that from the rest of these
guys here.
Okay so draw a rectangle slowly.
So here's our push bitmap.
Call.
What I want to do now is just say OK when we do a push bitmap, call
the size of this thing.
We are going to know now because the actual size of the bitmap is
going to be, whatever that bitmap, whatever that bitmap native height
is right is going to be one parameter and the bitmap native height
times, the bitmap width over height is going to be the width, right?
And now it may seem weird that I'm doing that instead of just having
the native height and the native within here.
But the reason I want to do that is because soon
We'll do is we'll just start passing in what we want the height to be,
and then, that way everything has its own height specified, right?
And those people who have constantly saying, when do we shrink and
shrink the hero down, we can finally shrink the hero down today.
I know that there are many people who had bothers them that the heroes
Too Tall right now.
This would be the time you could do that if you wanted to.
All right, so okay, so we go do our alignment here.
The alignment now is going to be an alignment percentage times the
size right times that size Vector, which is how big the thing is going
to be drawn.
And what I'd like to do is well is now inside the push bitmap call
because we weren't doing this before eventually what I'd like to do is
also in fact I guess I will just do it here.
I'm going to record the size right in here when we do that.
Push, because I'd like to keep that sighs because I'm going to use it
in the drawing Loop, right?
That's how big I want this thing to be in meters on the screen right?
In m in the world.
Okay, so let's go back up.
Well, actually, I guess let me remove it from these other ones here.
Let's remove m 2 pixels from this stuff.
So there we go.
M, 2 pixels used, anywhere else, not really.
It's only used in here and
Here.
So if I do pixels to meters here,
That was 42 for now.
Casey move this.
Or remote this as the case may be and so now when we do our get render
entity basis P, right?
Essentially, we now have a thing where we can start to think about
this perspective, transform
As actually operating in M, right?
I can get rid of the m, 2 pixels entirely here.
Right?
I can get rid of it here, I can get rid of it here.
I can get rid of all of this stuff, so that now it's no longer
happening.
There's no no longer any m, 2 pixels happening at all.
It's just entirely happening in meters, right?
And once this all happens in meters, then I can go ahead and at the
very end
convert it out to pixels by just multiplying by whatever that factor
should be right.
And that factor is going to differ the m.
2 pixels factor is going to differ based on the resolution of the
screen, right?
Because I want it to be the same effect, regardless of whether the
screen has 940 or 1980 or however many pixels it has, right?
So really what I want to do here is when I do this result p and I do
screen center plus projected X Y, right?
See what I want to do is I want to do something more, like a
traditional projection.
And really there's two sort of ways that we could do this one way
rolls of them both into one multiplication.
Other way does a transform to a unit cube in and out and I don't know
that we really want to talk about that too much because it's not super
relevant but I'll mention it briefly just so those of you who have 3D
aspirations will kind of know what I
So when you're dealing with 2D art, you have a lot of advantages which
is that clipping is not a particularly difficult thing for you.
Clipping is actually relatively trivial and it's essentially something
that is very hard to go wrong.
You can actually do something called guard band, clipping for mostly
everything in the culling is very straightforward.
You don't have angled things, just a lot of things go your way.
In 3D, you don't actually have that luxury.
And so what they typically do is they use a thing called the unit cube
and they clip to a 4D unit homogeneous Cube, okay?
What this thing is is, it's basically, you can imagine it just the 3D
part of the cube.
Actually, it's all good, right.
Let's go to in here, you can sort of Imagine going to a unit cube,
right?
If you wanted to do clipping so that you could figure out.
Like, all right here is the shape of the monitor, let's say the
monitors always going to be this front face here, right?
This face right here, this is the Monitor and the entire world fits in
this unit cube, okay?
So everything in the world has been shrunk down aligned and squashed
into this unit cube.
What typically happens in 3D projection is that you do actually do
exactly that, right?
You have some notion of the camera, right?
You have the world out here.
You take the frustum that you can actually see of the world.
Okay.
This is the near clipping plane and this is the far clipping plane,
okay.
You take this frustum and you literally warp it so that it fits into
this thing, right?
This part right comes out to like there, whatever, right over here,
you know, this this part right here comes out to
They're whatever.
It's, you know can I get some apps in here and the clipping happens.
Now in this uniform Cube space, so this part gets, you know, thrown
out and this part gets kept, right?
And the clipping happens that to produce actual the correct fragments,
that should happen, sorry that the triangles as they need to be
clipped or actually clipped in that unit cube space.
Okay?
So all of the coordinates that you have when you do your projection
when you actually do the Matrix, the projection Matrix
we actually do essentially this step right here,
Bowl of your coordinates are actually between negative 1 and 1, right?
So x, y and z are all between negative 1 and 1, or if you're in
direct3d there's actually it might be between 0 and 1 the Z value.
They did some stupid stuff but anyway
Assuming you're an opengl, it's all between negative 1 and 1.
So, first you do this smoosh, then they do the clipping again, this is
done on the GPU.
You are typically not doing the clipping, you just provide the
Actually Matrix that does this smush.
So you do the smush, the GPU does the clipping and then the GPU blows
out these - 121 coordinates into actual screen coordinates, right?
So it multiplies by the pixel width and height, right?
And adjust for the fact that the center was here, and now the center
is going to be down here.
So it actually applies an offset as well to actually figure out what
the pic where the pixels are right.
And so basically there's like this concept of
First you do the smoosh, right?
And then you do the blowout, right?
That's not what they're called.
This is typically called like view to window transform or something
like that, right?
Or you know like clip space to window space might be another term for
it, right?
This however is called the projection.
Certainly this is the projection Matrix that does this etc, etc.
So that's basically the capsule overview.
Now we don't have to do this step there's really no reason for us to
care about this at all.
It's really just not something we're going to have to worry about.
So what that means is we don't actually have to do the smoosh.
We can just have one value because if you think about what this moose
does, essentially there's a m
You know, World units, there's a world to unit cube transform and then
there's a unit cube 2 pixels transform, right?
And so there's two scale factors that one that transforms the world
into the unit cube.
One that transfers a unit cube into the pixels.
What we can do instead is just do world to pixels directly.
And that's why we could if we want to and I think we probably should
just to keep things simpler.
Just have essentially a m, 2 pixel value like we did.
Right.
We should just be able to use one value.
Instead of splitting it into two values, even though that's mirrors
more, what happens in 3D pipeline because we really don't care, right?
We don't care about that in the 3D pipeline.
It's okay, so let's say we want to do that right now, maybe that's a
bad decision because maybe when we go to the opengl path will want to,
you know, will want it to be done, more symmetrically on both sides.
And, you know, we'll cross that bridge when we come to it for now.
I don't think we really have to care.
And so, basically, what happens is, when we do this projected X Y,
this is doing the projection in meters in World units, right?
And off it goes.
And I'm going to leave that to do for now because we're actually doing
right now.
And so then right here what we need to
Is this is the place where we actually need to do that projection,
right?
So here is the place where we actually need to do.
M, 2 pixels.
The only place that we actually need M to pixels at least for the time
being right.
All right.
And so if we back that out and we do m 2 pixels here, right?
And that was, that was this way, I believe.
Oops, sorry.
That was a this way, right?
That gives us the only place
That we actually needed to use that.
Okay, so we got M to pixels here.
Why is bitmap still doing this?
Don't want it to be doing that.
That's not what it should be doing at all allocate render group.
What is it doing?
I'll get renters group has m 2 pixels.
It had it set to one doesn't
make a hole.
Well, alright doesn't matter.
We'll cross that bridge when we come to it.
So yeah, so as you can see, now we've got our dudes.
They still there still exactly the same size as they were because they
are passing that - height in and so everything works just fine with
them.
Or actually, you know, what are we actually using that new?
We're not using that right through.
They may be busted now that I think about it.
We got to go in and let me fix that there.
I don't think they're busted though, I think.
Sign.
So right here, where we do this base of scale bitmap with and bitmap
height.
This, I really just want to now use the scale value that we had in
their original.
I probably should have said, scale, maybe we'll change that name in a
second when we start to clean these things up and tree size, .y down.
So, let's take a look here, draw a rectangle slowly.
Oh, right, sorry.
Did that a little bit stupid lie.
What I actually wanted to do, was put it here.
All right.
Size that EX
Entry.
Sighs.
That why?
Now I don't actually know No Object file generated, right?
This is not a b2i anymore, it's just a V2.
Don't actually know if that's all good now.
Okay, so our guy, I love when they get tiny, they end up moving so
quickly.
Okay, so now we have to go in and actually debug what I just did
there, but we're getting a little closer.
We're getting a little closer to having m 2 axles out of the equation.
Which is what I want.
Okay, so when we do this, we've got our sizes in here.
Our base is scale, I believe is right.
The basic scale is just allowing us to is.
What does that perspective?
Transform their, so get render entity basis P, like here.
That is still all working as I would expect, right?
We've got M to pixels operating here, just on the final output
projected, X Y, which is what I want.
This scale.
However, so I guess we also need the scale value because we only
compute that Z.
We actually need our scale value.
That's probably what our problem was there.
We need to scale up that report back for for actually producing the
pixel base size.
There we go.
All right.
Okay, so now we're almost there.
We've gotten down to a fairly.
We've gotten down quite a bit.
So let's go ahead and take one more step here.
What I'd like to do now is to have to have push push bitmap, right?
I'd like to push bitmap, to start specifying the size that it thinks
things should be right.
So input bitmap, whereas my push bitmap call right here.
What I want Push bitmap to do is I want Push bitmap to start taking a
Gail.
So in addition to an offset, I want to basically take, you know, a
height in the world.
So that, you know, when it comes in here, we're not going to be using
native height anymore.
We're just going to be using height.
That's what I'd like to do.
So what I'm going to do is say would do it this way height and height
like that.
And then all of these push bitmap calls are going to have to have
height value.
That's like how big they want things to be.
Now, I don't actually know what a lot of these should be will have to
play with this when we do our ground Splats.
Again, we'll, we'll have to go in and sort of
A redo that but that's fine.
That's sort of a stuff, that's a pending piece of code.
Anyway.
So all right, what did I do?
I put that in the wrong place, kind of not what you want.
So let's fix that.
There we go.
What's so push bitmap here.
So now we've got a bunch of these things, like the Shadow, the Torso,
The Head, and the cape.
Now we know that all of these things are actually the full height of
the guy.
So I forget how big we decided we want our dude, to be, let me go take
a look at how big we wanted our guy to be.
We had a thing in here for that actually, right?
We had, when we add a hero,
Or whatever.
Let's see where's add player.
We had a thing that said, how big we thought they were supposed to be,
right?
Because we added Collision for them.
So player Collision.
Looks like it's about 1.2 meters tall, right?
Is that
How big is that?
1.2 meters in feet.
About 4 foot tall that seems fine.
So, what I want to do here is say alright, the dudes about 1.2 meters
tall right now.
It's a little weird because we're specifying that, but, you know, is
he a little oblique?
I don't know.
But whatever, that's what we're going to say.
So that's where that is how big the shadow should be.
I don't actually know, I don't know, maybe the Shadows about 025 tall
something like that.
What is this?
What cannot convert?
Why do I always want to put it before the position?
And I feel like that indicates to me that it should just go.
Before the position.
So you know what?
There it is.
He is now before the position, usually you should just design a PR
i--'s around what people actually do rather than what you would like
them to do.
So if that's what I'm doing, that is what I should that is what I will
make make happen.
So now how tall is the tree?
I don't know, maybe the trees 3 meters tall, I'm not sure, although if
the tree is 3 meters tall, it's taller.
How tall is?
That's a full story.
Hi.
So maybe we want our trees to eat be, you know, very short.
Stumpy trees, I guess it's how that but, you know, works out.
I don't know how big a sword should be.
Maybe let's say half a meter, I'm not sure.
Again, these are values that will tune and let's see ahead.
We'll just leave those at half a meter as well.
This is I'm not doing anything intelligent here because we don't care
what these values work out to be at all.
Alright so if I go ahead and run this now let's see.
I'm not sure that doesn't look quite right for how high.
The guy is relative to the tree, does it?
I think so.
I may have a bug there.
I want to take a look at this because
Let's take a look.
So if I'm standing here, right?
And my guy is 1.2 meters, well maybe that's not a bug, let's see.
So, how big is the tree?
The tree is 2.5 meters and my guy is what?
My guy.
Is.
Oh, but you know what?
There is one thing that I have to to sort of count on here, but I'm
not counting on which is how much space is actually in the hero
bitmap, that's not being used.
So hold on one second.
I want to take a look at that because we're saying with the height of
the bit map is, and the bitmap doesn't necessarily end right at his
head, right?
So let's take a look here, actually, it's in test one.
Let me take a look at the test hero.
Let's see.
Let me take a look at the front head there.
Edit that gimp.
Hello gimp.
No rush on the loading, their gimp.
Take your time.
So yeah.
So there's a big old empty space at the top of his head to and at the
bottom to probably actually.
So if we take a look at where the Torso ends, right?
There's a there's a big old empty space there to actually so really
this guy is unfortunately not at all the correct size in the bitmap.
So I don't know how we want to handle that at the
Moment.
But basically what that means is that he needs to be synthetically,
scaled up a bit from what is actual size is, right?
Because it looks like he's about an extra like third or something like
this, right?
In addition to wear
He should actually be so that's more like it and that actually does
look relatively reasonable, right?
That looks like he's now more or less the right size relative to the
tree if that makes sense, right?
That looks like that.
Looks like how big you should look near to a tree.
Now, I don't super love that, right?
If that's a biggie, actually should be right.
I don't super love how big he is relative.
The
Three.
So I think we want to cheat that a little bit.
I feel like we want that vout him to be closer to the size of an
actual tree, because that's just the vest the aesthetic of a 2-D game.
So I feel like we actually want, like, Euro size coefficient to be,
you know, some kind of a erroneous value here.
Let's go ahead and put that in there, alright?
So now the hero is, you know, is about that size and that seems that
seems pretty good relative to the tree.
Now, I would also like to be a little closer at this point.
So let's go ahead and fix that as well.
I don't actually know why I just closed the game.
There was no reason to do that but let's go ahead and go up here too.
Render entity basis.
And what I'd like to do here is first of all see okay the this is
what's the deal with the focal length?
Now I feel like this focal length should actually be much smaller than
it was but in order to look at a whole room maybe we do need a fairly
long focal length.
I'm not sure, but it does seem weird.
So I'm going to I'm going to play with these values now but they're a
little bit different.
I'm just going to see if some more reasonable values to put in here.
Make sense now at all, or if they don't, if they still don't.
They still don't quite make any sense in terms of what we've got going
on here.
So I'll leave them as they were.
For a moment.
Let's go ahead tweak that till we get something a little more usable.
Let's see.
Hear feel like that's a little still want to be a little closer than
that.
See here.
So maybe we go to do something like that.
And that's
That's getting closer to what I would expect the game to look like.
So something like this.
Yeah.
That's getting that's getting closer to good.
Certainly it's getting closer.
It's not, not sure exactly.
We'll have to see once we actually get some stuff in there.
Exactly what the size should be.
But that feels a little more reasonable to me on the
I think that's pretty good.
Might want to make the hero just a little bit bigger.
Let's go ahead and do that as well.
I like having the hero, be roughly, the size of a tree even though he
should not be just feels feels right to me so that feels a little bit
better.
Again, we have a bunch of bitmap issues to work out there.
So let's go ahead through now.
Now that we're a little closer to what we want and yeah and start
cleaning the stuff up, okay?
So, now that we've got this sort of stuff Happening Here, we have a
couple other issues.
One, is that our Collision sizes?
We want those to line up with the size of the hero probably which at
this point, they won't necessarily.
So I feel like that's something we're probably going to have to take a
look at relatively soon but I want to focus at the moment on just the
that M stuff just so we can kind of finish that out.
So now I think we can get rid of the
Have height stuff.
The native height stuff can just go away if that makes sense.
Because I don't think we actually need it for any particular purpose.
So let's go ahead and nuke that we go and get rid of it there.
Right?
So, that gets rid of most of that stuff, and that means that, now
we've only got this.
We've got our pixels to M getting used in just a couple places here,
right?
Just in basic Computing, that that screen area.
Right.
And then in the renderer, okay, so let's go ahead and get rid of it in
the renderer.
Let's, let's do a little bit more there.
So I think unless otherwise specified all inputs to the renderer are
in World coordinates, m is not pixels anything besides we
so I guess we pretty much don't want m, i mean pixels ever.
So I think we want to do here is something like it is mandatory that
all inputs the render are in World coordinates, not pixels.
If, for some reason, something absolutely has to be specified in
pixels.
That will be explicitly marked in the API.
But this should occur exceedingly sparingly.
Okay.
So, Loops m.
Let's take a look.
So we have two places that use it.
Now, we've got it in, in the render entity basis P stuff, right?
We've got it in here, and then we've also got it in.
We're we're passing it to the draw rectangle, slowly call.
And so I just want to take a look at what the draw, a rectangle slowly
call is doing.
I believe all the draw rectangle slowly call is doing, is using it to
do its own, projection into the map, when it moves.
So I'm going to say to that's okay for now but I don't know that we
actually want that to stay forever.
But anyway what we will do is I will leave it going so that it
actually
passes through here.
So let's take a look at pixels to meters as it comes in here.
So we've got we've got that's not the one I wanted.
Where does that render get render entity basis?
So we've got this working up to the point where then it finally, at
the end, has to put stuff out into into pixel space, right?
And in order to make this work properly, what I want to do is I want
to have this be based on how big the screen actually is.
So when it calls get render entity basis P, I want it to actually pass
in how big this this output Target is, right?
So basically there's something like a screen dimension, you know?
And the screen dimension is screen.
Dimension is is this
And then at screen center is just going to be 0.5 times that.
And so I actually think is screen center only ever used when it
passes.
Yeah, so what I'd like to do there is is get rid of that potentially
take a look at the screen center thing when it's when it's happening
here and instead, past the screen dimension, right?
Because that's something that can just be back in.
Just be computed from that, right?
So the screen center is just half of the screen dimension, right?
So I'm going to pass that screen dimension in here.
There we go.
All right, so if we compute it that way, what I want to now do is say
all right.
M, 2 pixels.
I don't actually want to use a fixed value for that.
Because it'll be different depending on the monitor, right?
The number of pixels on the display is going to determine how many
pixels a meter maps to.
So what I'd rather do is say how big a meter is on the screen, right?
So what I want to say here is actually different value.
I want to say something like monitor width in M, write something like
that.
And I want to say in what
Modern within World units.
Might be the better way to say it.
So how big do I want the monitor?
To be right?
If it was measured in,
Base of the world and so how many world units across is that monitor
going to be right?
And I think what I want to say is that like, okay, if there was
something
That was, you know, taking up a certain amount of space on the screen
on the near clip playing like right up against the monitor, you know,
how big, how many meters across should that be and maybe I want to say
it.
Maybe I even want to say it.
How many meters something tick up on the screen?
At a particular distance?
Might be the other thing but it's kind of hard.
I'm just not sure how I want to specify this value.
Exactly.
Right.
But I want to do it in some percentage of the screen size.
I guess we can just do it as a
You and kind of tweak it to what we want but maybe then we'll sort of
back it out and try to figure out if it makes sense of the value,
right?
So what I want to do is say something.
Yeah.
Like
Monitor with or I want to derive the m 2 pixels value by basically
going.
Oops.
Oh no, I'm out of time.
You're kidding me.
Well, let me just finish what I was doing and then we can kind of go
go from there.
So what I want to do is I want to say the screen dimension.
Whatever that screen dimension X is m.
2 pixels is basically to be
Based on that screen.
Dimension X, right?
And so if the, if the number is, you know, if the if the screen should
be 3 meters width wide or something like that, right?
Then however, many meters to pixels is it's going to be whatever that
screen dimension is /, you know?
However, whatever that, whatever, that number is.
That's how many pixels are going to be in one of those chunks.
Right?
And so at that point, it's no, it's
It's now, you know, supposed to be more resolution independent.
So, in theory, I can get something that will be the same, no matter
which resolution, I use, right.
And I'll just take a little bit of time, just a baby.
A bit of time from the Q&A to show, what I mean by that, right?
So assuming that I have it work like this, right?
So now that it's based on that value, but I'm kind of saying here is,
let's suppose that we were to change the dimension.
Like it looks like this, right?
This is what it looks like, okay.
Suppose that I went to go and change the dimension now, to some other
dimension, right?
So, you know, let's say, let's say, I am.
In fact, let me do it the old way.
So I'll just set it to 42 here.
And here's my guy right at 42, okay.
And you can kind of see like, you know, we're playing the game, and we
got how many trees across.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven trees across, right?
So then I go into win32, handmade, right?
And I say, okay, instead of that, I want to change the background.
Effort to 1920 by 1080.
We're going to do a high-res here, whatever?
Right.
It's just going to be high res.
So we start the game with a different back buffer.
Right.
And now you can see it's like it's a different game, right?
I can fit all the trees.
I can fit all the trees across and instead of only seven across, I can
fit eight across and then probably nine ten or whatever, right?
So what I wanted to do instead of that because I wanted to say, all
right, let's make this based on the actual size of the screen so that
no matter what the resolution is actually set to, you know, it will it
will work, right?
So, if we go in here and we say all right, that's how big it is now,
right?
If that makes sense, if that's how big it is, you can see we can get
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight of these on, and we
don't quite get to that to that night there, what?
I'm sorry seven on and we don't quite get to the eighth, eighth just
kind of comes on as as this one comes off, right?
If that's the value, that's at 1920 by 1080, if I, then go ahead and
change the resolution to be back to a different value, right?
The old value, that was the lower res, right?
I want this.
To basically be the same value.
And so, where are those trees?
Let's see here.
Can we get them to the right thing here?
One, two, three, four, five, six.
And there is a seventh, oh, but it should have been eight, right?
So are we still a little bit off?
I feel like that's still not quite right, you make sure 12.
This is the topmost trees.
1 2 3 4 5 6 and there's the 7th tree, right?
Go ahead and put this back.
What is the last second?
1920 / 2.
Oops, that's not right.
19 20 divided by 2 is 960 1080 / two of these are correct.
Right.
So I make sure I have the aspect ratio correct as well.
Okay.
Let's go back up to the high-res version.
There's there's the actual trees.
So yeah, it's still not quite correct that.
Oh, yes, it is.
We just can't see the end of the bitmap.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
And then there's that, that extra tree there's just the barely the
beginning of it because we can only this is the, this is a full 1920
by 1080.
So, there we go.
And then, if I go ahead and switch it back down again,
We should have that exact same thing, right?
And we do
So that's good.
So we're getting there.
We're getting there slowly, but surely okay.
That's our m, 2 pixels is computed that way.
Right?
Are m, 2.
Pixels is computed there.
Then, the only problem we really have here is that, you know, we
probably want we've got pixels to M being computed here as well.
So we want to do is make it so that it's at least uniform there.
So we'll go ahead and pull that out.
Will say that that's happening right here.
So we have M to pixels and then we have, you know,
Pixels to meters.
So
And then this this will just take that value m 2 pixels Solis.
Then we're unified in there.
And now we're going to have to do.
We'll have to leave it to tomorrow because I don't want to eat up any
more Q&A time.
Is what we'll have to do tomorrow is just make sure that we then have
anyone external to the renderer who needs to know this stuff, will get
it from the renderer so that it's not something that they just kind of
do ad hoc outside.
Made of what, you know, what they're supposed to be doing, right?
so, let's put that in there, so
Oops, just pixels.
Thank you compiler, for catching that, for me, and there we go.
So now we're back to okay.
There think we're in good shape and I will go ahead and go to the Q
and the, a as well.
Both the Q and the a work handmade see.
Okay.
So if you have any questions about what we just did, please go ahead
and put them into the chat.
And if you could please make sure that they start with Q: so that I
will see them.
I'm just testing out and make sure all this is working here and it
looks like we are in good shape.
There we go.
That's starting to feel pretty nice.
Starting to feel pretty solid, pretty happy with it.
Got a bunch of work to do, obviously, to kind of solidify that Z
handling even further.
But we're getting to a nice place.
Where now, everything is specified in sort of a more comical fashion
which means that also if Yankton draws the bitmaps at different sizes,
it doesn't matter now because we can tweak them exactly the way we
want them to be the right height and stuff in the engine.
So we're not like using the bitmaps as the height of things.
Either.
We're scaling them so we got a lot.
Good stuff happening here.
That makes sense.
So yeah.
Let's take a look here.
Should the he wrote resizes.
Not be dictated by the resolution of the art, IE to maintain constant
pixel.
Density says, grumpy giant 256.
So I am not really of the opinion that a high-res game, like 1920 by
1080, should be pixel accurate and the reason for that is I think you
give up too much if you go pixel accurate.
So what I
Want to do is I will want to have the size of the hero beep
potentially Dynamic based on you know whether it's certain to unlock
or whatever.
I'll want every tree to be slightly different sized, right?
So I will actually want to play with the scale as a way of adding
interest to the art and so I don't care at all about maintaining pixel
of perfectness.
I think that's something that's a little bit more appropriate for a
lower res game.
If you're doing real pixel art, you may be wants that to be aligned or
something like that.
But once you get up to a certain degree of resolution, I don't feel
like it's really that worth it.
So I would rather throw everything at the bilinear blend, let it be a
little bit blurry, but allow me to have that flexibility to scale.
I feel like that just adds more visual interest and it loses but that
is certainly your decision.
If somebody wanted to go the other way with that, I would not be at
all upset with them, but I would point out the fact
That since we're using sub-pixel placement, you're never getting a
crisp if value.
Anyway, you're always blending between two pixel values.
So I think you kind of have to think about, whether you really care
too much about pixel accuracy at that point, right?
Once you're moving things smoothly, I think pixel accuracy is not such
a good idea, it's actually detrimental to the look.
And so even if you were in a situation where you were trying to be
pixel accurate, I would question whether that was like necessary, the
right decision, I'd have to see the game and you have to make, you
have to convince me.
Basically.
If you want your game to be full screen, how would you want to handle
screens with different aspect ratios?
So I don't know.
And we'll have to do some work at that will have to make that
decision.
I don't really want to deal with it right now because it's not that
relevant to what we're doing.
But it's a good question, right?
If we were to play on a 4x3 display, as opposed to 69, I'm to say,
what do you want to do, do we want the player to see less of the
screen and have to just deal with it and be like, hey, man, if you
wanted to, but you know, more field of view, you should have gotten a
bigger screen or do we want to put like bars on the screen so that
they get a letter box for
I don't know and that's just a decision that will have to make but it
won't really affect our renderer.
That's, that's the aspect ratio is something we're able to play with a
little more freely so that won't really be a problem for us.
We can choose to do different things, the future girly and oh, Bloom,
baby familiars.
It probably has to happen.
Yes, I'll add it to the, to do file, but I mean, I think we all know
it's the right thing.
Let me take a look here.
Okay, so in reminders, let's go ahead and say little baby versions of
yourself that follow you around and help.
There we go.
Okay, noted
Tiny Shadows, look funny you are correct.
I never did go fix that sighs we should probably do that.
But you know what?
I don't know.
I don't know how much we care about dealing with this right now but
I'll tweak those values a little bit so let's see.
Underscore hero.
and,
The shadow.
She needs to be bigger.
You're a size.
See, I don't know what it actually.
The value should actually be.
That looks about right.
X-rays on the good.
And then I guess we also have the problem here.
We've kind of got like, other stuff in here.
We don't really know what we're doing, like the familiar is, and
whatever those guys are totally scaled wrong.
So, I don't know what those should be.
But, you know, I guess that's not horrible, right?
That seems pretty reasonable.
And what about this guy here?
That's the Torso monstar.
Let's kill him up as well.
All right, we can make the Torso monster really big.
Now, if we wanted to, we could have menacing
Yes, it's super menacing.
Now that he's a tourist.
So monster, right?
All right.
Coronal Dragon.
It could be interesting to have larger trees that span multiple Z
levels.
It's true.
Of course I'm not sure what that would actually mean because that
would imply that you were climbing up and down something with a tree
that you could see.
I guess you'd have to be like climb up a little Hill or something, I'm
not totally sure.
Will the game support scaling to arbitrary resolutions now?
Yeah, it mean it does already, right?
So if you like you saw me says switch it in there and it worked.
So now you can set it to higher res and it just works.
But until we optimize the renderer, you definitely don't want to do
that.
And even once we optimized the renderer, you probably don't want to
ever run in higher than this resolution.
I'm thinking on most machines, I mean, unless you machines just a
monster, because in order to run in the high resolutions, you'll
probably want to run the GPU path, which we have
Done yet.
Because basically in order to run it like 1920 by 1080 or above,
you're going to want the GPU because the GPU is the only thing that's
got the horsepower for that.
So in our CPU renderer, we're going to want to stay low res, that's
going to be a trade-off.
We'll have to make, but that's fine.
Like I said, the CPU render isn't something we expect players to use.
It's just something we're doing to prove that we know how to do
everything in there and that we understand everything that happens
before we go ahead and use the GPU.
But, you know, once once we have the GPU in there then is it.
That's the time.
When you can get a good.
Frame rate on those higher resolutions, but the CPU render will
supports killing the higher resolutions.
It just won't be performing at those High Roasters, I would suspect
and the key word, I'm using right now is a Das Keyboard 3 for anyone
who wants to know,
Could you explain what the if and if stuff is and when how you use it?
Sure.
If sin, if zeros and end dates are basically ways of me conditionally
turning code on and off, right?
And so typically, when I don't want to deal with something right away
like there's there's a couple of different ways.
I'll do it right if I'm trying to work on porting some code to some
changes, like I make some changes and I want to do something.
I want to go through and make sure stuff works.
Sometimes I want to isolate
What I'm actually going to get working first, so I can bring it up,
test it, and then go and then work on a separate section later.
So, what will happen typically?
Like let's say a good example here, we did it today multiple times,
right?
Is like I changed some variable, right?
Like I'm gonna go from a line to a line percentage or back right, and
you can see there's a bunch of code that's affected and maybe I only
want some of that code.
I only want to work on some of that code.
So what I'll do is, I'll first comment out right effectively with it,
if it's just
like, if I had done this right,
I'm effectively just commenting that code out with any of zero and
then I'll put the rest of the code and then I'll come back to it,
remove the if 0 and poured it right.
So basically allows me to sort of do a tiered approach to getting code
working when I do some kind of a major change that's one way I use it.
The other way that I use it is to have stuff that I can just flick on
and off depending on what's going on.
So an example of that would be.
We wrote some test code down here.
For when we were doing normal mapping.
And so, you can see what right now in the game, we're not running any
of that, normal mapping test code, but if I go in here and turn it on,
you can see that.
Now we're running the normal mapping test code, right?
And so that's another thing that I use it for is just to be able to
quickly switch on and off pieces of code in a really easy way.
That doesn't you know basically cost me anything to do, right.
Will it's serious?
Have different artwork for the top and bottom and if so, how would you
make them seamless per step, artwork?
Each at their own height?
No, actually I suspect that the stairwells will just be
This is there will just be a bitmap.
They're just going to be one bitmap because remember, at the level
where you are, the stairwell, he's always in the correct place, if
that makes sense.
So I feel like it'll just work to just have the stairwells
Basically, be sort of transitioned between the two.
I have to think about whether there's anything else we need to do
there.
We may have to do something where we silently move them sort of
essentially between Z levels.
Like
Adjust their Z height or fade between them.
But I think we might be able to get away with not doing that.
I'm not sure we'll have to see, but yeah, it's a good question and I
don't know the answer to it yet.
We'll have to, we'll have to figure out how we want to do it.
The problem we have basically, as we're, the only game, I know of that
handles being able to continuously move between Z like this.
I've actually never seen one.
Do it before a really that has perspective, and so we're given a shot.
What we can do is in the end if we
I find that it's too hard.
We can just change back to orthographic which is actually trivial for
us to do.
We just stopped doing the divided, right?
So we can change back to orthographic of any time if we want to and
still keep the rest of the Z working the way it is.
Can we at least get some crappy Ms.
Paint program, our art stairs in there instead of yellow blocks.
No, what happened to the cool?
Velocity Boost from stairwells velocity boost.
I don't know what velocity boost are we talking about?
I'm not sure.
I know about the velocity boost.
Towards the end when packaging.
Will you show us compression methods and ways to package all the art
Assets in one file, packaging?
All the art Assets in one file?
Yes, compression methods.
Probably not will probably do just a basic, like Zealand style
compression.
We probably won't really go into in depth on.
Like, okay, if you really want to do compression, here's how to
understand like all compression stuff and because I'm not a
compression guy.
So I'll probably do some pretty basic compression.
Basically just an LZ compressor and that'll be all that will do.
And as for whether it's going to be 2D 3D or isometric, it's basically
like 2D art but it's fully 3D in terms of like how we're allowing the
world to work and we're just doing that to basically show how you can
robustly program, the three dienes.
So that we don't, so that people kind of can get a little bit of that
learning.
Is the hero supposed to shrink on the stairs.
So the reason that the hero shrinks on the stairs, I don't know.
If you remember this, you should know why that is but you may have
forgotten the reason is because of this, if you remember, we're one
frame behind lagging, right now, on setting the Z location of the guy,
right?
If I remember correctly, right?
Because camera relative ground P, this stuff here,
Here.
I think we set the basis wrong.
Now I could be wrong, I could be incorrect about that but I think we
are basically out of phase if that makes sense with where things are
and Z.
I'm not sure.
that, that maybe we're not, maybe that's okay, but I have to think
about whether
Whether the camera and the guy are moved together.
Not you know what, I take back what I said.
I'm not actually sure if that's true.
We haven't actually gone through and verified that yet.
So I'm not actually sure for the thing dating, it's definitely one
frame of lag but for the position it might be okay.
So maybe not so that may only be because of the way the movement
routines are working that he shrinks because it's whether or not the
cameras, getting updated properly with the ground value.
So let's take a look at that.
I can go in there and actually answer that question.
That wasn't what I thought it was but I'm not sure.
I necessarily know exactly what is the one frame lag behind.
So let's take a look at how this works here.
Okay, so we do all the movement here and then when we set when we do
an end Sim, okay?
Yeah, so that's that's what it is, all right?
So let me let me explain what it is.
It is what I thought it was.
Yeah, it is why I thought I was.
So here's how this works, right?
We open up a Sim region and we begin sin that maps.
All the guys, in the same region, we do a simulation on them by
iterating over them.
And while we are iterating over them, we've pushed their bitmaps on at
the end right.
After we move them, we figure out where they are and we say that is
where the entity is in Z, right?
Now, the problem is by the time we are doing this, we have not yet
updated where the camera is for this Frame because where the camera is
for.
This Frame, actually gets updated in here and Sim after rendering has
already occurred, right?
Because that happens.
That essentially means that the camera is always one frame behind
where the guy is.
So he the guy moves down.
Well, a little one frame before the camera goes to follow him.
Ansem.
Because remember n Sim, right?
Is where the camera motion happens.
The camera motion happens right here in ensign
So in order to fix that what we have to do and we probably do want to
do this at some point is make sure that we stratify or updates
properly so that we know we have the renderer be informed of the
cameras location at a time that is after the Sim has closed out which
we can totally do.
In fact I'll put it to do it.
Okay.
Double semicolon.
Are you upset about a double ice devil?
Semicolon, do double silicones.
Bother you.
Brother you for some reason?
What do you have against the devil semicolon?
Why do you just like the double semicolon if you don't like it, double
semicolon that I think the only answer is to make it three semicolons.
Am I wrong?
I feel like that's the right way to go.
If we ran out of questions, thank you for streaming.
It's always a privilege.
Pre-screen was painful though.
Well I'm sorry.
You guys had to deal with it once again I don't say it enough, but
thank you very much to the moderators for trying to keep the twitch
chat in line.
I know it is not easy.
It's always a bit of a struggle.
I don't know who is here today?
I guess.
Garland.
Oh, Bloom Abner, cam breaker.
Oh no, dragon and drive 137 the whole gang I think was here today.
Thank you guys for doing that.
No everyone appreciates it.
I know I certainly do more than anyone and like I said before, we
talked about this privately a little bit, but I definitely going to do
this.
I want to set aside part of the patreon money that comes in as part of
this touch the stream to do something nice for the moderators.
At some point.
One of the things we talked about is if we have a handmade hero con
will pay their travel expenses, that kind of stuff.
So I want to do something good because I feel like it's important to
basically, you know, I want to try
to distribute that patreon money as equitably as possible.
And you know, I'm not the only person who contributes to making
handmade hero.
Good.
And so, you know, we definitely want to
We definitely want to do something cool like that.
But we just haven't actually had any sort of coherent idea of what
that should be.
So if you have ideas, feel free to post them on the board, but we
would like to thank the moderators of some point for doing that work
every day.
It's a lot of work and it's pretty thankless.
I wouldn't want to be someone who has to deal with the influx of
crazy.
Crazy twitch FrontPage or switch happens sometimes.
Unfortunately, so anyway,
With that in mind, thank you moderators.
We will definitely be doing some nice things for you with the patreon
money as as we have the opportunity to do.
So, like I said, I'm sure everyone appreciates it.
I know I do and we will find ways to say thank you as this project
continues for.
Now let me simply say thank you.
Everyone for joining me for handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you as always.
It feels really good to be cleaning up the code.
I'm really happy with how the prospectus stuff is turning out.
I'm happy with how the Z stuff starting to clean up.
So I feel like we're really making good progress here toward
solidifying, everything.
And once we get all that done, we can do some render optimization
which I think it's going to be a blast.
So I'm looking forward to it.
I'm having a good time.
I hope you're having a good time and if you are having a good time,
please come back and see us again.
Tomorrow, 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time.
Right here on Twitch if you want to participate in the pre stream and
ask me queasy
Crazy questions.
We take off topic questions during the pre stream, you can come back
tomorrow around 4:45 instead because we do about 15 minutes of
questions and at the beginning.
So I hope to see everyone back here again, tomorrow.
And as always, if you'd like to play around with the source at home,
you can do so by heading over to handmade here a.org and pre-ordering
the game.
It comes with full source code and I uploaded every night after I'm
done coding here.
There's also a patreon page which I just mentioned, which basically
supports the video series and we hope to do some nice things.
So Community with that to going forwards, like I said as we figure out
what the right things to do are there so if you want to support it,
that would be great.
You can go there and you can subscribe and we also have a forum site
that you can go to which has a place to ask questions and it's got an
aunt, an episode guide and the Scott ports to Mac and Linux good stuff
like that.
So check that out if you're interested.
And finally, we've got a tweet bot tweetbot that basically tells you
what the schedule is.
And so that's a great place to go if you're just trying to catch the
stream live because sometimes we're off on various days or we need to
move the stream and that's a good place to make sure you always know
when the stream is for that day.
So if you want to catch it, you can catch it.
That's it for today.
Thanks everyone for joining me.
And I'll, hopefully see you again here, tomorrow.
Take it easy.
Everyone and have a fabulous Tuesday, until I see you next.