Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream on Twitch, no engines
and no libraries.
It's just us here programming, and today we are going to do a little
font work.
Now, we already did work to extract fonts in our asset processing
utility.
And we actually showed how to use a library there as well.
So we actually have two paths in our asset.
Packer one that doesn't use any libraries in case you want to go full,
no library and then another one that shows how to use Shawn Barrett's.
Excellent, font library in case you would like to use that instead, we
did that in honor of his birthday and also because a lot of people ask
me if there was a library to use, what would it be?
And Shawn's libraries are always the answer to that question.
So we did all that and
You got that in there, but all that does for us, whether you use a
library or not, is it only gets out the information about the glyphs,
what we haven't written yet being either path, is any way to get out
the actual metrics for the text, such as how to space letters between
each other called kerning, which we discussed on the introduction of
fonts or where the Baseline is.
For example, like how the font should sit on a horizontal line, that
sort of thing.
So we
We haven't done any of that work in, either the path that I showed,
how to use a Champs library, or in the path that uses, no libraries
where we call into Windows to extract that information.
And so, what we need to do today is we need to start working on that
so that we can augment our asset pack file to include this
information.
So that when we process a font for use in the game, it will have the
metrics necessary for the engine to then align the font in a sensible
way.
So that it looks like what the font designer intended when they
created the font,
And you know, it will have a relatively attractive appearance on the
screen as a result.
That's the goal anyway.
So if you haven't already watched the introduction video to fonts you
probably want to do so because I'll be referring to things like
kerning and I'm going to expect that, you know what they mean?
I'll try to give a brief refresher where appropriate, but you really
probably want to know some stuff about fonts, not too much.
You don't have to be a typographer, but you just want to know some
basic terms as we go.
So we're going to be doing coding today for sure.
So,
Is one day 168.
If you would please, if you're one of the people who pre-ordered the
source code on handmade here at up org, please unpack day 167 source
code into a directory.
That is the source code that I will be starting with today.
So if you would like to follow along at home, that's the way to do it.
So, here we go.
What I'm going to do, which is a little bit odd.
Potentially is, I'm not even going to open up the asset processor just
yet.
And the reason that I'm not going to open up the asset processor just
yet, is because again, like I say, many times always write the usage
code for something.
First.
If you can, that is a classic thing.
That we're going to see right now.
Basically, I mean, I kind of do know what I need for fonts, because
I've written them so many times before but on handmade hero, even when
I know what I'd already, right?
I try to still show you the way to go about it properly so that when
you're doing it yourself and maybe you haven't done this before,
you're tackling a new problem, which I still do every day.
I often times.
Tackle any problems, I want to make sure you see the correct way to
approach a programming problem in and don't just see me sort of typing
out stuff.
I already know how to do right, which is
A particularly useful.
So, in this case, I know that I need information about these fonts to
line them up, right?
And yes, because I've done font program before I could probably guess
exactly what those things might be and how I might need them.
And I could go into the asset processor and just do it.
But if this was your first van system you wouldn't know that.
And so you'd be left in a situation where you're like I don't even
really know what data I should store with the fonts to do this
alignment.
And so when you find yourself in that situation that's when I
Say, make sure you write the usage code first because the usage code
will guide you.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go in and write the actual
routines that display text on the screen as if we have the information
necessary to line them up.
And by looking at how that code comes out, I will then be able to
essentially reverse.
I will be able to look back solve, right?
For the information will actually need in the asset file and how I
want that information structured.
Right.
So that's pretty
Handy.
And I say that a lot, that's what I mean.
When I say it was right, the user code first, when you find yourself
in a situation where there's one side of the code that you do know how
to write.
And really, I guess I should say it's kind of a more general statement
even than always write the usage code for us.
What I really mean, is always write the code, you know how to write
first, right?
It sounds kind of obvious when you say it, but most people actually
don't do it, it's weird.
They tend to like if they know how, you know, if they have something
that they're going to go implement.
They tend to like start writing the interface for it first or
something, without reading the implementation code, and that leads to
problems.
If they have something where they know what the interface is that they
actually want.
But they, but they, you know, haven't written anything to it.
Yet they'll go do the implementation for its.
We're it like you getting these weird situations where it's like, you
write the wrong side of the code and someday I should probably try to
figure out a good way to like formally explain exactly the process
that you want to go through but the long and short of it is when
you're about to start.
Ting something.
If there's a mystery, if there's a piece with a question mark over it
right, don't start their start at the place you actually know and
crawl into like push into the question mark that will allow you to
make sure that you're on firm footing as you go in there rather than
starting in the question mark and working your way out because that is
really what causes a lot of problems because then you find that you've
done something that doesn't really fit the
Of the system that you had because you had all these known things that
you know, that it had to work with, right?
So that's what we're going to do here.
We know that we have to write this stuff.
I don't know what data store, so I'm just going to go write the
functions.
I know that I want for like display, some text on the screen.
I'm going to write them in the way that I want them to work and then
I'm going to see what falls out of that in terms of the data and the
functions that the asset system should provide for getting that back
to me.
So let's start with a pretty simple task, something that should be
very easy for us to do, right?
Right now if you look at win32 handmade you'll note that we have some
stuff in here.
In fact I don't even remember where it is.
We did it a long time ago, but we had these little debug timers,
right?
You can see them here.
And the way that those debug timers worked is, you know, if you had
handmade internal defined then these debug
Hers would like, do a bunch of stuff that's that's not actually the
one that I'm thinking of there.
That is a debug timer.
That's not the one I meant.
I meant those little debug timers.
Let's see here.
Where are they?
You know, the ones.
I mean, they were like cycle counters.
These right here, right?
You see these guys, so we have some debug cycle counters.
It was a really, very basic system.
I was just showing some really, really rudimentary ways.
You could time some code, right?
And we didn't have
have any way to display this at all.
So we just had the win32 platform layer, dump it out to the debug
Port, right?
So, what I would like to do is I'd like to make a way for us to
display.
Those debug counters on the screen.
Write something very simple.
So that when we open the game, we can see those debug counters
updating on top of the frame.
As we go write something that would be a very straightforward part of
what we want to do in terms of debug display.
That's very simple.
So if I take a look at how these are being displayed right now, we can
kind of see debug cycle.
Here is how Beckett's you know dumped out right at the moment.
And so what I want to do is kind of start down that path and I want to
imagine that we had a way to print this out.
Now, there's two parts of printing this out that we have to write one
of them we care about right now in one of them.
We don't sew the two parts of it are first of all, we need a way to
actually put fonts on the screen.
That's the part we care about and then there's the part about how to
actually convert numbers like numerical values.
In the text and that part, we don't care about quite yet, we will care
about it once.
We actually want the, debug counters to actually start printing.
But for the moment, we don't care about that because we're working on
the font part of things first.
So what I want to do is I want to take this routine, right at that,
you can see right here.
And what I want to do is I want to go into our game and I want to
start printing.
I want to start imagining, I guess it's, I can't quite put it yet.
I want to start imagining that.
I was able to print this out to the screen.
And so what I'm going to do
do is I'm going to make a little function here.
In handmade dot CPP.
And again, handmade dot CPP is kind of just are dumping ground for
things that don't have a home yet.
Things kind of grow in handmade CPP and then we move them out into
their own files, sort of, as we determine what forms a coherent system
and what stuff we want to think about together, right?
So if I have this here, I'm going to just call this overlay cycle
counts or something, or cycle counters.
And so the overlay cycle counters function.
Obviously it needs to take the game memory so that it can Loop over
these things.
And when it Loops over these things, we don't have the ability of
doing output debug string.
Because now we're, you know, we're not in the platform layer.
And so, what we want to do is replace those calls to Output debug
string, right?
With our own way of, you know, our own font overlay system.
So, in order to do that, obviously we need a renderer like we need to
be able to Target a bitmap and all these
They're sorts of things.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead and assume that we're
going to be passed a renderer here, right?
One of our, one of our render groups, something that can do that
rendering, right?
So in here I'm just going to assume temporarily, okay?
We're going to get a render group and the render group, right?
Is the thing that will do the output for us.
And so when we come through here, we're going to want to do basically
this the same stuff.
So what I, you know what, I'll probably say is well for now let's just
assume that we have something that's like you know render string for
something like this, right?
And you can pass a string to be rendered.
So I want to do a render string.
I think we were doing push basically, right?
So maybe push text is a better one, something like that.
And so here's my render group and when I do these debug cycle counts
thing, right?
I'm just kind of going to push that that text on there and thing that
it doesn't really say.
It doesn't really specify is where the text should actually show up,
right?
So that's kind of a little thing that we kind of going to need to
address, right?
So we'll talk about that.
In a second.
But for now let's just assume that we're going to have some way of
dumping that text.
We Loop over the counters that we have and just like before we just
check, you know, if this counter ever got hit, then what we're going
to do is we're going to print it out.
We don't have any way to do this yet.
We don't have a way to do this as printf because that's again, a
Windows platform thing.
That's happening there, a CRT Windows sort of thing and we're not,
we're trying not to lose any libraries in handmade hero.
So, we
Want to call that.
So what I'd rather do is I'd rather temporarily say, okay until we
have a replacement for that, what I'm going to do is assume that that
text buffer thing, right?
I'm going to assume that that text buffer part of it is actually just
going to be
Whatever the debug counter part of it was, oh wait.
But these don't even have any names do they.
That's kind of weird.
I guess we never gave these names.
We just never we just never bothered with that.
I guess because we were just doing other things at the time.
That's kind of weird.
Well, that's something that we want to do.
So, you know, we'll just say to do Casey give these things names soon,
right?
But we can actually just sort of cheese the names in here pretty
trivially, right?
All we would have to do is just do something like name table and say,
all right.
Well you know we know that these counters all have specific values so
we're just
Going to go ahead and tell you what the names are right here.
Again, not what we would like to do long-term because we don't want to
have to be involved in the like sort of fussy management of these
things.
So, we'll look for a better solution to that later.
There's a lot of things we could do to fix that, but again, not really
important right now.
So for the moment we'll just do the super cheesy and not particularly
good thing of saying that will take the name table and we'll use the
counter index that we're talking about and that will allow us to go
ahead and push that string on there.
And then what we want to do again besides just the nanny part is we
would like to eventually tackle the part where we print it out so that
we can actually see the values of those performance counters.
That's the end goal.
Okay.
Now there's the matter of resetting.
Our stuff here, which is not something I want to do in here because
this is just the overlay.
So we'll still let that reset happen in the platform layer.
But eventually again, that to a lot of this stuff, we're going to
start hoisting out because the only reason those debug cycle Counters
work, sort of getting dealt with it all in the platform layer was
because that's the only place that we can output them.
So as we're sort of like those of you who've been watching, no in our
sort of to-do list situation as we going through things.
Oh, hey, look at that.
We sort of finish that one, we're in the, the debug code section.
So what we want to do here is we're sort of going through all this
stuff that we need.
And so the first thing that we're doing is the fonts but the idea is
stuff like this debug cycle, counters will be adding lots of stuff
like this over the course of the next few weeks and we want them all
to sort of be nicely contained in the, the handmade hero code proper
and not in like a
Formally or anything like that.
So anyway,
While we're in here we're going to do these push texts and then
eventually we'll sort of tackle this guy but for now this will just do
that kind of simple print out thing.
Now like I said what we don't quite know here is we don't actually
know where those those texts.
Things go is the thing right?
We don't actually know where those are being sort of pushed and right
because normally there'd be like some coordinates here, or something
like that.
Now what we could do obviously is we could introduce something here.
Where I have to start specifying coordinates and all that stuff, but
that's not particularly good because you know, if we're talking about
debug code, I don't want to have to spend a lot of mental energy or
pass a bunch of things.
Through my code in order to do debug print outs.
So what I'd rather do is make it so that the thing that draws fonts in
the engine for debug stuff is actually like pretty clearly labeled as
such.
So instead of a push text, I'm going to go ahead and say that we have
something else, which is kind of like a way of
saying that I'm
saying that I'm doing like a line of debug text, right?
And then I'm just going to expect at the moment.
I'm just going to expect that the render group has these debug
Services built into it, so it just knows that every time I open a
debug text line I kind of just want them to like feed down the screen
and later we'll kind of maybe augment that with some better ways of
saying what gets categorized in different ways.
So when we have too much of this stuff, it doesn't just kind of
overflow things.
But at the moment like I just
Start basically with that.
Whereas, if we were doing something more for graphics work, which we
will do a little bit with our fonts, because we're probably going to
display strings once in a while in the actual game, right?
That would be something that we'd want to do with with coordinates
like put the text here.
So what do I want this?
Debug text line to look like, right?
So if I go into handmade render group,
And kind of see here that you know, we've got this render transform
and the render transform is clearly something, right?
That's going to be used to do you know the actual rendering for the
game at that time.
So what I want to kind of introduce separately is maybe like a render
transform that is used for debugging that separate, right?
So it's not using the same one as for the game, it's using like a
separate render transform that it, you know, does in a completely
different way.
Something like that, right?
And furthermore, I'm thinking that probably what we would like to do.
I mean essentially what we'd like to do is have a whole another render
group that's just for debug stuff, right?
And I wonder too now that I think about it, I wonder too.
If we want to just make that render group be implicit, it's some kind
of global variable.
That's always available for debugging.
You don't have to pass it around anywhere.
It's just, it's just, there's a way to get it because since it's only
for debugging and we will be trying,
compile it out, you know, at the end of the of the
How the development cycle?
I do wonder if maybe that's not an easier way to go.
Because we want everyone to be able to access the debug Services, no
matter where they are in their code, whether or not they've been
handed a render group, right?
So I'm thinking, maybe what we really want, is something more like
this, where you can kind of do the debug text line thing, and that
just kind of has a magical Global that it always knows.
It can get at that's going to allow it to get its debug information
properly, you know, properly.
Displayed
so, I think I'll
Make that a little bit better.
So I think I like it so that we can just kind of pass the sort of
debug text line stuff we can sort of just past those directly.
And so, let's try that.
Let's at least try that.
So if I'm going to have that, then what I would like to do here, right
is.
I'd like to have something that was like Global variable which is like
a render Group which is like the debug render group.
Something like this.
And in fact I guess, you know, if you think about it it doesn't even
necessarily have to be a render group.
It could be its own like sort of debug Gathering thing.
But for now I'm going to make it a renderer because I'm not sure.
So we may change that to be something slightly different instead of a
render group.
You know what, I think just thinking about it in my head I feel like
we're going to want it to be separate because like here's what I'm
thinking and I'm not sure.
This is a tough one, this is really a tough one.
So what I'm thinking is suppose we have like lots of code and all the
code has debug output in it.
Obviously you're going to want to be able to pick what debug your
viewing and what debug you're not viewing.
So you know what I'm going to do that is it just gets buffered up in
this in this debug SIS thing and then you can like pick which one
you're viewing or whatever, but you probably could do that when in a
forward feeding fashion as well, where it's just like it just throws
out all the calls.
That that are, you know, would be filtered out by the current
selection of what you want to view.
So we could still do it, something that immediately kind of renders to
a render group.
So I don't know.
It's a pretty tough.
It's a pretty tough thing.
I guess, I'll stick with render group for the moment and we'll see
what happens.
I guess as we go, and who knows?
All right.
So if we have our debug render group here, then we're just going to
assume that when we come in to game update and render that we, you
know, we'll sort of initialize that guy before anything significant
happens, right?
So that there is a place where the debug stuff can actually go to.
Yeah.
And so, if we assume that that's the case, then we can take our debug
text line, we can say.
Okay, we've got our debug text line here, and it's going to take a
strip.
And that's supposed to output and what we would like to do now is we
would like to go through and convert that to actually drawing stuff.
Now we know how to draw strings, right?
Because we kind of have our nothing's Fountain happening here.
So we kind of know that we can draw a text this way.
Already just using the rudimentary stuff that we kind of
Pulled out before.
It's not particularly pretty, but it works, right?
So let's start by doing that will start by using that exact same
thing.
And what we can do here is say okay,
You know, whatever the value in the string is that's the Unicode code
point that we would want will still make these that match vectors
here.
So we did initialize those match vectors and we would say that we want
to Loop over the string sort of getting the best math best match
bitmap from each, right?
So yeah, so we set the tag Unicode code Point.
Wait to something we would then Loop
Over the string.
And as we Loop over the string, we look for the bitmap that
corresponds to each individual setting.
So to do that again.
Also, we would need the Assets in order to sort of grab those those
asset bitmaps which would also, you know, now that I think about it.
I feel like the render group is always supposed to have that in it as
well, but the assets are actually right in there, right?
So really, this should just be this could just be debug render group
assets, right?
Like, so,
So that's how that works.
That would get the bitmap that we actually need.
And similarly, we should be able to actually push that bitmap.
Now using the push bitmap call, right?
So push bitmap, here we go, and that's pretty basic it's just like how
big we want the bitmap to be and then like you know where we want the
bitmap to be right?
And that's that's really
About it.
So there we go and guess we also technically have the ability to
colorize it, so we might as well.
Okay, so when we do this push bitmap right again, this is just really
pretty basic.
We're not really, we're not getting very far here or anything like
that.
We're just kind of doing the really, really simple stuff.
I'm just trying to get some minimal thing working.
Let me go ahead and compile this, see where we're at?
Let's see.
Is it not Global?
Is that not the name of our thing?
let's see, internal
Global variable.
So let's see.
Render group does not have an overloaded member function.
That's true.
You are correct.
I guess what I could do though is is actually just make one here
render group equals debug render group.
And then do that.
Okay, so that would actually output all of the bitmaps not in any
particular place and not at any particular size of use to anyone, but
it's getting us started.
Okay.
So let's see what we can do here if anything.
So in here, what I'd like to do is at the very end of everything when
we get all the way down to the bottom.
Right.
What I'd like to do is I guess perhaps even outside the time block I'm
not sure that's kind of a good question but you know I want to Overlay
those cycle counters on here and and see if we can't get them to sort
of do.
Do something overlaying our system, right?
So if I call that, what should happen now is, we should, we should
either we should crash or assert right away, right?
Because we have initialized that debug render group, right?
So if I read it, now, as soon as anyone tries to do anything, right in
here, this is just we haven't set it up, right?
So in order to get this to start working at all, the first thing that
we're going to have to do is we're going to have to set up that.
Debug render group.
So, if we wanted to set up a debug render group,
What we need to do is we need to have some memory for it, right?
Because we don't have anything like that at all.
And so, if we take a look at at the render group itself, when we
initialize a render group, right?
This stuff can all just live in the global, right?
Look, all this stuff lives in the Global's, but it's this push buffer
that actually needs space, right?
The push buffer has to exist somewhere for the debug render group.
So when we do our allocate render group,
You can see that what we do is we have to pass it in Arena and then
the arena it will actually allocate its face from right like that.
So you can kind of see how that goes.
And in fact, the render group in this case is actually a like it
returns a pointer because it will allocate into that Arena.
It'll actually allocate itself as well.
So yeah,
So I guess that means really, we could just do it like this.
You could do something like this.
If we've got the debug render group, then use it kind of a thing,
right?
And that would certainly prevent us from crashing, but it's not going
to help us overlay anything.
So right, so that's fine.
So what we'd like to do now is we'd like to actually initialize that
render group and so we want to do is when we first start up I guess if
you want to just steal a little bit of space from say the
And Arena where we can initialize that debugger Arena and have it
actually work, right?
So what we'll do is we'll say debug render group, equals allocate
render group will throw it some memory from the transient Arena and
then we can can go from there.
So handmade render group.
It needs an asset system to.
I guess we probably want to do it like this where we know that will
actually have some assets.
We don't really know what the push, buffer size should be.
We're kind of just making stuff up.
And we'll go ahead and say that this doesn't render in the background
because well, well it's not gonna render in the background.
So anyway,
If we actually get that, now, our debug render group should actually
do something.
Of course.
The interesting thing about the debug render group, right?
Is this not actually going to do anything until we actually call
render group to Output, right?
And so, if we want to at the end of this, after we, after we do our
overlay cycle counter stuff, we can come in here and do render to
grouped output with our debug render group.
So we can even do something like this where we say, you know,
If there is one, we would like that to happen.
The output Target should still be valid.
Oddly enough.
Don't actually know draw buffer and presumably we can just slap our
stuff right on top of the game surface right by just saying, hey,
render on top of the thing that was already there.
Presumably, now we have a problem, which is that when we do render
group to Output, you will notice that when we call that, we don't
actually have
Jimmy and I guess we could even do it tiled.
If we wanted to write we could we could do this threaded I'm not sure
which one we want to do but either one would work, right?
I don't know where, where is, where is the render queue?
I guess it's the high priority queue.
So, there we go.
So yeah, we can do this tile if we want to and all that.
But basically, what's going to happen at the end of this, this finish
render group thing will be call.
Which does that sort of the end generation bit?
What's interesting about?
This is the render group itself would need to get recreated at this
point and to some degree.
We don't actually want that to happen, right?
We would rather have it so that we can have a render group that we can
kind of reuse.
I feel like and so what I'd kind of rather do is have like, you know,
something like begin render pass or something, or begin render, you
know, an end render something like this, where, when you call begin
render, that's when it actually does a generation ID, you know,
something like this.
And then you know, maybe the certs even oops assets that's good.
Maybe the search that it's not doing that so it doesn't assert this
equals zero and then when you end render it asserts is not equal to 0
and we could make it so that the asset system doesn't generally
return.
0, I don't know.
Probably can't always do that.
So we won't actually say that that's true, but we can certainly assert
this one, right?
so anyway,
so if we do it, beginning to renan, begin render and render, then that
will all work nicely.
And the only thing that we would have to do to make this reset itself.
Because remember, if you take a look at this, the only thing that
actually tracks where we are in the render group is just the push
buffer size, right?
So if we wanted to, we could just reset the push.
Buffer size 20 and now, we've cleared the render group and can just
use it again, right?
So we can just do an end render here.
On the debug render group.
And everything is magical and fine, right?
And as long as we do a, corresponding begin render before we start
everything again, just just peachy, you know, it's kind of like it's
peachy and so we would have to do that again immediately after
initializing the transient Arena.
So that's, you know, we'd want to start the rendering like so,
but off you go, and we could also make a Boolean here, even for
debugging, which, you know, I mean, we could do something like this
inside, render that and say, you know, assert group inside render
and,
Inside render.
So we can just do something like this, right, where we say.
Okay, assert that you're not inside a render.
And then now, you are
Right.
And similarly here, assert that you are inside a render.
And now, you aren't
Something like that, you know I'm saying and if furthermore the other
thing we could do is anytime anyone tried to push to something, right?
So you know, if we took a look in here at like push render elements,
we could just make sure that anyone who ever tries to do this.
We just assert that we're inside.
So that no one can do it outside of one of these these passes.
And, you know, just giving myself a little security buffer, right?
Just just trying to give myself a little bit.
Of a safety net in case I make a mistake somewhere.
Okay, same would be true for all of this stuff, right?
Just making sure we always have, you know, a render group that's been
properly set up.
So okay.
So suppose we do that, right?
Then we do begin and render for the render group, we could just keep
rendering to it and reusing it over and over again, which is kind of
nice and, and that's all good, right?
So, let's see inside render here.
Off the wrong pointer.
There we go.
Same with this guy and now for these dudes, right?
When we do our
Render group.
We now need to do a beginner Ender on the render group, right?
Like so.
And now this turns into an end render on the render group.
Yeah, finish render group same thing.
This is going to be an end render and then up where we did the
allocate, we're just going to do a begin render.
And now we have the option of saving this as well, rather than
allocating it every time, which we might want to do to kind of up to
us.
Okay let's start.
Oh say so is that that's may not be initialized as well as the other
thing, right?
We didn't actually initialize that in our allocate, which I should do
Here we go.
So in here, we want results in render equals false so that we know,
We are not starting inside render.
Certainly
Okay, so that's all fine.
Now, what we need to do is we need to actually start setting up our
render group, so that the render group will, you know,
Be able to display the bitmaps be able to say the debug bitmaps.
So, what I want to do first is create an orthographic display and I
remember there are two types of ways of transforming that we talked
about on handmade hero perspective, where things that are further
away, get smaller and orthographic where they don't, right?
And so for our debug output, we just want things to be orthographic
because we're just trying to make like a flat overlay on the screen.
So when we initialize our debug render, we want to set an
orthographic.
Render group here so that we're just flat drawing to the screen with
nothing weird happening, right?
So if I set an orthographic display for the render group,
We know that our screen has a particular size, right?
I guess, I don't know at this point, whether the the screen has
actually been set like the draw, buffer itself has been set, it
probably hasn't.
So I think I want to use buffer directly there.
Like so right.
So we've got buffer width height.
So and then we've got our m, 2 pixels, m.
2 pixels, of course, is a little bit weird.
For these purposes because now we're not really thinking about any
kind of real world units.
But if we have a meter, how many pixels should it be?
You know, we can pretty much pick an arbitrary thing.
I don't know, let's say 100 depends on how we want.
How scaled we want our author orthographic text display to
Be right, but that's about it.
So, let's see what happens.
Now, you can actually see right here, that's actually drawing to the
00, location a bunch of the font stuff of, right?
So, we're already seeing the results of that debug render.
You can see that happens even before I launch a hero, right?
So those are just the, you know, the sort of the letters that were
talking about.
Okay, so the next thing that we want to do is actually get those
displaying in a way that looks more like an actual usable thought the
other thing that we don't really know about here is in terms of like
what we all want these actual sizes to be.
I don't know what to think about that a little bit more, but let's
press on a little bit first, just so we can get more stuff happening
before we try to make any of those decisions, right?
So if I want to display this, debug text line here, then what I want
to do is I need some way like this is just drawing them all at 0-0.
I need some way of actually sort of drawing them across on the screen,
right?
I need them to line up as as letters, so, I'm just going to introduce
like a variable here at X, and that's just going to, I'm going to move
it like, you know, from left to right as I draw a letters pretty
straightforward, right?
So if I put that
In here and I just you know and I was to add something to the value
here.
Then what I could do is say okay you know, how big are these guys
right there some kind of scale value?
I don't know.
They looked like way too big before so I've got some kind of scale
value here right?
And I'm just going to add whatever the scale value is and you know if
you figured that that scale value was somehow related to the bitmap,
we'll figure out how much we should Advance by in a second.
So, there we go.
Hey look, we're starting to get some debug text in there, so that's
pretty good, right?
But, you know, it's in the center of the screen and, and it being in
the center of the screen is not really what we want, right?
That doesn't help us super much.
So what we would probably rather have is some way of like having it
start to display itself like up in the corner and furthermore every
time we get a new one, we want to move down to the next line, right?
So what I'd like to do is say
Okay, I've got an at y variable as well the at y variable.
I'll Advance every time, you know, we get to a new to a new line of
debug text.
Now, what you can tell though is that since this is this is just a
function that renders a single line he by text, I don't actually know
when that happens, right?
So at that point we need some additional piece of information here and
hopefully you can kind of see where this is going.
In a second we need another variable right?
We need an at y variable here to store whatever the Y Line is and we
would need that to actually reset itself.
Time, we restart every time we moved to a new frame, right?
Because otherwise it'll just move up right off the screen and that
would be the end of it.
But at the end of this, right?
We would know.
Okay, we just gotta move down a line, right?
I'll actually get since y goes up.
We would move, you know, we'd subtract to go downward, right?
And so what we would need here is we need something like internal
void, oops.
Reset or like debug reset, or something like that, right?
And that would have to reset this at y equal to 0 because if we don't
do that, right?
Just so you can understand what I'm talking about here.
If we don't do that, then it just runs off the bottom of the screen
will never see it again.
Like it's already gone before we even start for the even assets are
loaded.
It's gone right?
So we need something that's going too deep to do that reset for us and
so we know right?
We know when that would be we know that at the end you know sort of
when we're all done with everything.
We do this and render that we could do our research here and it would
clear thing out.
Now, we could also do it at the beginning.
It turns how we want to structure it.
There we go.
Right now we're getting closer, we got to move it up here and also you
may notice that we get a bunch of Z's in here.
The reason for that is we haven't put.
This is kind of the fun part of our router asset matcher.
It's like we don't have any lowercase letters.
So it just thinks like oh I should just get the closest ASCII to that.
It doesn't understand lowercase in capital letters.
Maybe we should make it do so and knows to just get the, the uppercase
version of something.
If it can't find a lowercase, right.
But we're getting closer, right?
We're getting closer to a font.
So okay, so probably right that scale value.
It looks like it would need a little more spacing.
You know, it looks like maybe it needs something more like that.
In order for the line Heights to be correct there.
You can kind of see they're a little bit better.
Maybe just even a little bit more something like this, right?
And so there, that's a, that's a better-looking, debug display there.
And so you know what, what the heck?
We're having a little party here.
Why don't we just go and have it?
Weird.
The lowercase letters to write because right now we don't actually do
the uppercase letters.
So when we do the glyph extraction, I don't actually remember how we
even did this.
It's in here somewhere.
Let's see.
There it is right and so if you were doing this here, what I'd like to
do is make it so that we have more stuff than just those.
And so I'm going to go ahead and say we've got something like
you know, you 32 care.
Range to like something like this.
And then we do you know you know you know what I'm talking about this
sort of thing.
Right?
Just making a little thing so I can output a bunch of ranges of
characters.
So we don't have any punctuation in there, but, you know, we could
look at the ASCII table and see ASCII table.
And if we look in here, right, the ASCII table is of course the we've
talked about it multiple times in the Stream.
It's basically a numeric table that says, what the numbers are that,
correspond to the letters, right?
Um, that we care about.
And so, if you take a look in here, you can see that like, we'd really
don't care about most of this stuff.
We don't need Carriage returns or cancels, or file separators, or
whatever these things are, who knows?
All we really need is this stuff over here.
And so if you take a look at what these are like 33 so you know
exclamation point if you look from exclamation point honestly we
probably just want everything that's in there all the way up to
2 tilde.
So what I probably could do is I probably could just not even bother
and just do that, right?
And that's probably fine.
So let's give it a shot and see how that works.
Hopefully it works.
Okay.
And so if I run test asset Builder on this, presumably now we'll get a
little more lettering.
There we go.
You can see it all nice there.
And yeah that's exactly what we wanted.
Debug cycle count.
So for space we don't have space now I don't know that we want to
actually store a glyph for space because we know that it's not there.
So I think probably what we want to do is actually just special case
space because we don't need to ever actually draw it, right?
So that seems like what we would want to do is something more like
this.
You know, and that way we, you know, actually get spaces in there
properly.
So there we go.
We've we've got
Some funds.
So next thing is next.
Let's move that guy up to the corner, which is something we wanted.
And then I think we'll be ready to start talking about font metrics
because there's a bunch of things as you've already seen that, we
would want to fix if we were trying to make this font output actually
look nice.
So what do we want to do here?
First of all, like I said, got to move it up to the corner so in order
to move it up to the corner I need
Of initializing at X and at y, to actually be something up in the
corner and that sort of that to me suggests that, the debug reset
wants to go up at the top, right, because that's sort of where it
would, it get where it would actually set that up, right?
So, somewhere in here, it would do that and maybe we include sort of,
with, that debug reset.
We sort of include
Orthographic in there, right?
And so what that would do is it would take maybe that buffer width and
height, right?
So we'd have with it the the width.
And the height like so.
And
That would give us probably buffer with buffer height.
What the information is that we actually need to move things to the
corner as well, right?
Because if we do that orthographic, we now know that this is the width
and height of the thing.
And we know that this is the m 2 pixels, right?
So what we could do is we can set at, why, right?
If we do m 2 pixels,
In fact, when you think about it, m, 2 pixels.
If we just set that to 1 m is really not M, it's World units, right?
It's just the units were passing in our stuff as which happens to be M
everywhere.
So that's why we call it m 2 pixels.
But we could say that we just wanted pixels to pixels, right?
So we could just set this to 1.
Then we know that the screen is with wide and we start at the center.
So if we wanted to go up to the top, right, it'd be pretty trivial.
Just do like - half the height, right?
Seems pretty simple.
And we could also do a thing here, where we said like left Edge,
right?
And left Edge, we could set as well.
I don't know why I'm bothering set these 20.
There's no point in that, but you can imagine doing left edge here and
and left Edge is what x would get initialized to.
So we can that would allow us to move it as well.
So let's let's take a look at this.
Let's get this working first.
Where is my text?
Where's my text of course the scale is totally going to be wrong now,
right?
Because if m 2 pixels is 1, then it's the like a single letter is
going to be like huge right?
Is that correct?
Meters to pixels.
So,
Assuming we actually wrote the code right in the renderer.
right, so if we have M to pixels,
Right.
Then this m is what we're inputting things.
As
So if we said that we wanted something to be 1.0 high, right then what
that means is it would be one pixel High.
So I'm assuming that what that means is that our scale would now be
drastically.
Small.
So we would actually need our scale to be much, much bigger than it
was before, right?
In order to make it the right size.
First, we didn't actually see anything, so that's not a good sign.
I also make it so that we're not actually initializing at wide take
first things first, right?
Yeah.
So, there is everything and I want to also see, I'm going to lean on
the loop live coding, a little bit here.
I just want to see what happens when we change this scale, right?
So if I change the scale, does that do anything?
It does.
So that's good.
However, oddly it.
It doesn't seem.
Like, how is it possible that it goes away and then comes back?
That's a bit weird, right?
Wouldn't you say?
Although, I suppose the loop live coding because it's a global.
We can't actually use the loop live coding for stuff in a global.
So that's mmm-hmm.
But there we go.
So it does Scout properly.
So, I wonder if we can.
it wouldn't be too hard to just kind of
To move that around, right?
It would actually it would be relatively straightforward for us to fix
that.
And I feel like we should.
And the other thing that I was going to say here.
So I was kind of leading up to wrapping these guys.
So, fix this for looped Live code editing, because I'd like to do that
as well, and it's pretty simple for us to do.
So, I think we want to do that as well, but I won't do that quite yet,
because that's kind of leading up to some things there that I want to
do.
And so I don't want to
Disrupt that train point being scale works fine now, so that's good.
We're going to leave it at 20, which I believe would be about 20
pixels right tall and that looks sort of, right?
So what I want to do now is I want to figure out a way to move at why
up properly.
So, when it gets reset, it would actually use again, half the height
and move that up to the top.
And that way when it comes, it would move down.
Now, I guess we're actually moving up that far so something like this.
And there we go up there.
Now, of course it's a little bit off the screen because we're moving,
half the height and there were drawing at the
Detroit of that thing.
So really it's going to be that you know, plus the font scale or
something like that, right?
So if I have a thing up here where I was like, Global variable font
scale,
like so and I say, you know, font scale equals 20
Something like this.
Then I would want to kind of move down by half the font scale as well,
right?
And that would line me up with where I wanted to be.
Okay, so there we go.
Now we're at the top of the screen like we wanted to be and similarly
I kind of want to fix that left Edge nonsense, but this is going to be
the exact same thing, right?
It's just going to be subtracting a way the width to get us to the
edge and then adding back in like one characters Worth or whatever to
get us to the left Edge and so then, you know, we should be in the
right place or not.
Oh, what's that?
Why I met left Edge.
There we go.
Okay, so now we've got roughly what I wanted happening, right?
We've got it lined up where we want it and we've got it printing out
where we wanted, but there's a ton of things that we haven't, but we
don't have that we want, right?
So even before we talk about how to get like the numbers and stuff in
here, we're ready to start talking about.
The font part is a number of things that you can see.
I think I might leave them until tomorrow.
To point out.
Because since tomorrow is the day when we'll be addressing all of
them, it seems a little weird for me to point them all out.
Now, but point being, you can see like lowercase letters are as tall
as capital letters, It's mono spaced.
So things that are like small, you know, at the same amount of spacing
in between them, all sorts of stuff is not what we would want here.
So even though we're, you know, we're getting a little bit further,
there's a bunch of stuff that we want to do, and so tomorrow, we'll
start tackling those those metrics a little more specific.
We but hopefully now you've seen it's pretty straightforward how the
debug Tech stuff would actually work and off we go.
Now there's another thing here which is this is too slow for text at
the moment.
So we also want to think a little bit about the fact that calling this
get Matt best match bitmap from every time is not perhaps the best
idea.
And so that's something we want to think about as well, but that's
about it for today.
I think we're just about out of time.
So I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A because we're at a good
stopping point and tomorrow, we can tackle all of the stuff we
actually want to do to turn this stuff.
Which as you can see, is just me writing the the simplest possible
thing and getting it to the point where it's working.
Turn this stuff into a more useful system, first of all, addressing
some of that.
But also, all of these things in here, there's
These hard-coded constants, how do we start moving those into the font
system so that we can get that information from the fonts, right?
That's what we doing tomorrow.
As the next step in our font metrics exploration, but I'll go to ahead
and go to the Q&A now.
So, if you have questions now would be a great time to ask me them,
put a q: in front of it, and I will be able to see it if you don't put
a coup in front of it.
Well,
It will be lost to the sands of time.
Colombian will you be addressing the subscript superscript?
N space m space at other types of space tomorrow as well.
Probably not.
So it's handmade here.
Will not really have any took typography in it.
It is not a typography kind of thing.
So we will not be doing any advanced typography like we won't be
caring about like whether the left and right double quotes lineup or
any of that sort of stuff that's happening that physically hard to do.
But it's not relevant because pretty much almost all the handmade
here.
Text is going to probably be debug text.
There's not going to be a lot of text in the game.
So if this game were about text,
well, you would want to spend a lot of time on your typography but
since we are not doing that we won't be I won't be writing any of
that.
However hopefully you can see just from what I've done so far.
There's no mystery to it if you want something that's going to be
subscript, well you just need to move it down, right?
And if you want it to be subscript in smaller, you move it down and
you change the scale, right?
So, there isn't like, there isn't like anything magical about fonts.
They're just bitmaps like everything else.
Put your drawing to the screen and you can manipulate them exactly the
same way.
And so, if you want different space sizes, different Dash sizes, that
sort of stuff, there's no mystery to it, that it's just putting
bitmaps next to each other.
And so really, the only thing that differentiates fonts from
everything else is the lookups that you have to do because you're
trying to translate some kind of encoding of like streams of them.
So there's like the Unicode to glyph thing.
Like there's that, right?
And then the meta information that you need about how you want to do
that lining up.
Like where should a
Per strip character Go versus absurd character, you know how much
current and should there be between two letters.
But otherwise, there's no mystery to it.
You can just get in there and any font effect you want.
It's just like writing anything else.
We've written on him in here.
There's nothing magic about fonts.
Spring Cruiser.
Will you add edges to the font?
You mean like it like an outline?
I wasn't planning on it, since I don't know that we would want that
for anything in particular, but
Is that what you mean by edges?
I'm not sure what you mean by edges actually.
What's the difference between making a game and C++ and making a game
in Java?
Well C++ is a language for writing code.
That gets compiled into actual x64 Assembly Language or machine code I
should say and so you know you're running a game directly on the
hardware when you write in C plus plus Java.
Is a language that compiles to a virtual machine, a virtual byte code,
so it never actually does that.
And it's about
Telling the virtual machine what to do.
And then typically because that's, you know, obviously very slow.
Typically, what happens in Java is, you then have a thing called a
jit, which is a thing that takes that that code and turns it into like
x64 assembly, you know, when you're actually trying to run the game
and that sort of stuff.
And I mean you probably could do pre compiled Java as well, right?
If you wanted to, that's not typically how to use, but you could do it
that way.
Of course, Java doesn't actually allow
Memory access and stuff as much.
It's more about, you know, it's more about having references to things
and this sort of stuff and it doesn't, it's not really about sort of
manipulating bits at the low level.
That's not what they wanted you to do with it.
Although again, like everything else, there's always some way
eventually to make it happen if you really wanted to.
So, making a game in Java is mostly, it's usually something reserved
more for people who are trying to do, sort of less low-level
programming.
Even though, you know, honestly, I don't know.
I don't want to disparage Java too much because I don't program in
Java and so you know, I probably shouldn't do something that I don't
use.
But on the whole honestly I don't really know what the point is of is
it's not a good high level language.
It's higher level than you know, see but it's not a good higher level,
it's just arbitrary.
It's like it.
Introduces, this annoying VM that doesn't do anything good for you and
it doesn't have very powerful language constructs.
So
you know, I don't super understand people's decision.
When they decide to program in Java doesn't make a whole lot of sense
to me.
I would say if you're going to go with a high-level language, I pick
something else.
You know, there are better higher level languages out there, I would
think.
But for me, I like the low the lower level, the better usually.
So I prefer C and C++ because they give me a lot more control over
what's going on.
And I don't have to worry about what the, you know, how the pipeline
goes from like my Java code to a VM to the jit to the execution, like
none of that.
I'm in control.
I don't have to worry about all these sort of other things that I
don't have control about.
Bryan crews are yes outlines I wasn't expecting to add outlines to the
fonts?
Is there?
I mean if you want to add outlines to the fonts then your it's just a
bit would be a bitmap operation.
You'd probably do there or you'd have to go do your own truetype like
line rasterization which you could hack into like sdb truetype if
that's what you really wanted.
Robbie.
Hi Casey question on the array.
You typed and pulled out again.
You 32 care.
Brackets.
Brackets to is this an array with pairs of you 32s?
Yes, it is.
I would have expected, you 32 brackets, brackets 0.
So in see,
You were talking about this part right here, then I realized I didn't
have to do it, but in see the way that you do an array or a 2d array,
right?
Is you keep stacking brackets on.
In fact, you can do as many as you want.
Right?
And the way that they work, is it starts with the furthest one out.
So for example, if I have this many and I did something like this,
Right?
Although you wouldn't have an array of one but you get the idea.
So if I had something like this, what that means is the first array in
the, the rightmost array Index.
Right.
This one right here is the one that increments in memory by the
smallest amount.
So, effectively, if you were to look at these you 32s, well, heck I
can just show you
So in here, I'm going to make this array.
Right?
And I'm going to do some stuff to it.
So here, let's clear it and then I'm going to do some addressing into
it.
Right.
Okay, so I'm going to look at in each case.
I'm just going to go one unit along each of these guys.
Right?
Does that seem reasonable?
And and there we go.
So in fact, I guess I could just do it this way.
A
B, c, d, e f, right?
So, the way this works in see, is this is the the ones are closest
together, is that the rightmost edge?
And this is the ones that are farthest.
Apart that index will move you the furthest apart.
So, this is like saying I have an array of seven arrays of six arrays
of five arrays of for arrays of three, arrays of to you went 32s all
the way back to the other end, right?
And so, if I compile that guy down and I set a breakpoint there,
R at the debug text line.
We can see the array in memory.
Happens.
Like so, oops that didn't work.
Come on.
Why, why will you not copy copy my value?
Copy it.
I do not know why you will not copy my value.
Fine.
Oh, X31 5980.
There you go.
Happy now fantastic.
All right, so if you look at me writing into this guy, this will write
in an a to that location.
Know why?
That did not show up.
You did actually go there.
Did you not find a zero?
There's my a right right there.
So these are you 32s?
You know what?
I should probably do them as, uh, just so it's a little easier to see.
There we go.
All right.
All right, one more time.
How come I wasn't?
How come I'm not like what's going on there?
Does anyone know why it's doing that?
But I can't drag that value down.
It's weird, right?
So there's my a and you can see that I have a 1 here, so if this was a
0 it would have put it right here.
But because I moved, I said move one, you know on the lowest index it
moved it.
One bite over.
So these are basically sequential right the lowest index.
Is sequential the next up.
The next highest in.
Next up is going to be by however many this this one was, right?
So this is 2, bytes each.
So moving one on this guy will move two bytes each time, right?
So now we would expect it to move to B forward, which would be like
over here, right next sense.
Now, this one's going to move three times to B for it, because it's
moving three arrays of to forward.
So that's going to move.
Six forward, just buy an index of one here.
Right?
1 2 3 4 5 6, right?
And there you go.
And then, let's see.
Where is this guy?
This is one.
So, this is going to be five arrays of for arrays of three, arrays of
to.
So that's 5 times.
4 is 20, right?
That is the one we're doing, right?
Yeah.
So 5 arrays of 4 is 20.
Times 3 is 60 times 2 is 120.
I don't even want to count that's going to be down here somewhere,
right?
In theory.
See, 5 times 4 times, 3 times 2 is 120.
So where is the array at its at a zero that seems 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10, 11 12.
That doesn't seem right.
Oh, I'm off by one.
Because of this thing I was Catholic.
I'm off by one, it's only the fourth one up.
Okay, good.
I was like, what's going on?
So it's 4 times 3 times 2 is all, it was, so that's it.
6 times 4 is 24, so that's totally fine right now.
It's the 120 that one should be down here.
There we go.
That could reasonably 120.
I could buy that.
And then this one's going to be 6 times, 5 times, 4 times, 3, times 2.
So who are you?
Who knows what that is?
Something way down there, right?
So, that's how those
Are red in general.
The way that you read a see declaration is pretty bizarre.
It's always go as far right as you can first until you hit a
parentheses or the end.
Go as far left as you can till you hit a parentheses or the end,
repeat this process, right?
I know what I said, sounds weird, but that's what it is.
It's go as far right as you can until you hit that.
Go as far.
Left as you can until you hit that, right?
That's how you read them.
So if I say array this, then I have well and we'll get things a little
simpler here.
If I say a ray that I've got an array of three arrays of to, and now,
I've hit the end, there's nothing left.
So imagine there's an imaginary parentheses at the end.
So an array of three arrays of to, then I start over going to the to
the left.
You eights.
So this is an array of three arrays of to uh right.
Start at the name.
Go, right, right, can't go right anymore.
Back to where I was.
Go to the left done, this can get very complicated and you can make
all kinds of ridiculous stuff.
For example, what is this?
Anybody know.
Well, it's an array of three arrays of to got the end pointers to you
eights, right?
So this
is an array of three array of to raise of two pointers to you ate,
right?
But what,
Is that anybody know?
Just do what I said, start in the name.
It's, you know, her a or I should say something like Foo.
Foo is.
So Foo is, is it an array?
Not yet.
Foo is I hit a parentheses?
So now I go backwards.
Foo is a pointer
Right now, I hit another parentheses.
So now I go to the right again, to an array of three.
Keep going to the right array of two.
And I hit the end, go back to beginning you Eights.
Right?
You want to make it more complicated?
Go ahead and make it more complicated.
Let's print the size this.
Right?
In fact we can make it even more.
Ridiculous, how about that?
How about this?
Right now, we've got Foo is hit the right, paren?
Go to the left, got the pointer.
Oops, come back.
What just happened?
Okay, there we go.
Mmm foo is go to the right.
Hit the prin.
Go to the left who is a pointer.
Hit this paren.
Go to the right to an array of three.
Hit the paren, go to the left, hit the print again.
I guess we have a redundant set of parentheses there that pair.
I guess doesn't really need to be there.
You get rid of that right?
Ture of three, hit the right paren.
Go back to the you 83 you ate.
And this whole thing is an array of too.
Right?
There's two of that whole thing.
So,
Is an array of two.
Pointers to arrays of 3.
U 8.
Who knows?
Why would you have that?
I don't know, but you can have it if you want it, right?
So that's, you know, that's what that is.
Happy birthday.
Foo Undeclared identifier.
Are you talking about?
Why are you grumpy about that?
Pointer to an array of three.
Array of 2.
Why don't you like that?
Feel like I should be able to do that.
Maybe I can't.
I feel like I should be able to do that.
Maybe I actually can't.
This is not a variable declaration style, I would ever use, but Foo is
a pointer to an array of three you ate.
I guess you're not actually now that I think about it.
That's actually not legal.
You can read it.
But you can't actually write it.
because that completes the definition already and you can't really add
the array of
In there.
So if you wanted to do the thing that I said, you'd actually have to
put the two there, if that makes sense.
I think so that it would be like Foo is an array of two pointers to
arrays of three.
You ate right like that?
That's the only way you could actually do that declaration because
once you actually wrap it up you're not really allowed to then make
that ba3 thing again.
Not sure why.
I guess that's just because the way the see parser is written.
It doesn't have the ability to take that.
For whatever reason, right?
It's like it it it can't handle you wrapping the type up in there
because array subscripts in the parser have to be parsed before the
final type of the thing.
So when you actually do that, I assume you kind of would need another
type, their write, something like that and of course you can't that
doesn't actually work.
So they pretty much only allow you to actually put the array subscript
in there.
I don't know how I got off on this tangent but point being that's how
to read see decorations.
If that makes any sense.
Will you implement colored text Will colored?
Text is just you can just tint it using the renderer that we already
wrote.
Right?
So if you wanted the text to be colored, you know if this is what's
happening currently where it's white, if you want to color it you can
just say oh you know you wanted red you just change the tint the color
that you pass the renderer to be read write and then it's red.
So because that we've already gotten color modulation built into the
renderer so you can just pass it.
If you're passing it, a wipe.
It map.
It's free to just color change it.
Kubrick Caleb do programmers, actually use that crazy race Mannix that
you also know, as, as evidence, by the fact that I accidentally
constructed something that you can't even actually type in C, I never
type anything, even remotely that complicated.
It's just I happened to remember how to generally read those because
sometimes you have to, but, I mean, to say the very least, your goal
should be to never have to know that stuff.
I just said because if you actually, it's more for reading other
people's code, when they've done something crazy,
I wouldn't I never you know hopefully you never do that.
Use some type deaths or something.
If you have to
Insofar as you didn't answer the bit about how if the color info would
be embedded in the text as control codes, know that doesn't sound like
fun to me at all.
You're talking about basically like just putting I mean I guess if you
were trying to write like a text editor or something but I don't know
why.
I mean you can always just
If you want to you can certainly have a thing where in here you parse
and see if you get something right?
Like if you wanted to be mr.
Does ridiculous stuff all the time?
You could do something like, oh, you know, if you know, I do this.
That I'm going to change the color or something like that.
I mean, it's really, really straightforward.
If you want this, you can do it.
It's not my jam at all.
So you know, I wouldn't be something I would be doing but you
certainly can, you know, you certainly can do it if that's what you
want, right?
That what you're looking for, you know, if that's your jam, go nuts.
You know, do do, whatever you got to do to make yourself, you know, a
happy puppy.
If you want to, I suppose you could do, you know, some kind of
ridiculous thing.
We're like okay you know I saw a backslash in the text or something
and so when I see a backslash in the text I'm going to like read out
some kind of a like code at this point.
So it's like okay you know if if the if the thing
Is.
You know, looks like that.
Then what I'm going to do is I'm going to assume that the at three is
going to be like the these are going to be like color values or
something.
So you know, maybe I'll double check also that you know at to is is
not zero just to make sure that I'm not the end of the string.
Or something, right?
So it's like, okay, just make sure that there's a backslash followed
by the pound followed by.
Three characters of some kind, right?
And so then we just say like okay you know, assuming that that happens
then I'm just going to take those three.
Doctors write whatever they are.
I'm going to assume that they were like you know numbers from 0 to 29
or something.
I don't know, right?
I'll just assume that their numbers from 0 to 9 because why not?
And that'll just be my color value.
Right.
That's going to produce a number, right?
Because the ASCII character is 0.
1 2 3, 4 5 6 9, they go sequentially.
So if I subtract the character value from zero, I'll get a number
between 0 and 9 and actually integer, right?
And so, then I just want to scale that I want to turn that to an R32
and I just want to scale that into a 0 to 1 range, right?
And so, thus, the color scale there, right?
Is just going to be 1 over 9, because I wanted to convert a number
between 0 and 9 to add a few 0 & 1.
So if that's like I said, if that's your jam.
I got you covered.
You're looking at something like that.
Probably.
I'm guessing that's like off the top of my head.
So then, you know, if you wanted I don't know what you're what you're
thinking here.
But if you want something like that, then you're just like, okay.
You know, I want I want red.
For that.
and,
You know, get some green.
In there.
Yellow.
I don't know.
That we're talking about.
So yeah, pretty straightforward.
Obviously, we don't want to print the control codes.
So after we eat them, just skip them,
Except I forgot that it would skip this one.
If you're going to do it that way you'd probably I'd probably I'd
probably go ahead and do that, but yeah.
In some object oriented languages thing is, can become that
complicated after what that means, what?
Printing text to a separate background, be easier than putting it
straight on top of the game background, I don't know.
That would be any easier.
Maybe there's some other reason you might want to do it.
But yeah, insofar as nice that was very quick to implement.
Yes it is.
I mean there's nothing to it, right?
It's really basic.
How about a 2d array of function pointers might have been why a few of
those variants didn't compile because it thought you were, declaring a
function pointer array star Foo.
Maybe around how many more episodes until you the switch from
suffering to Hardware rendering.
I don't know that we'll ever switch to Hardware rendering until like
the end.
I mean I would I would rather always do software rendering so it's
only for Speed purposes that we would do the other one.
Right.
Can you rotate and transform the text?
Well, sure.
I mean it's just going through the bitmap just like everything else
is, right?
So if you wanted to, you could rotate and transform the text, I think
our Bush bitmap call, doesn't take one of those.
Additionally, so you'd have to change the transform, right?
You'd have to look at the spin it.
But obviously you could do that, right?
So you know, if your
you're in here in the render transform and, you know, you've got
sort of the, the
Awesome scales of narrow.
So I guess in our render transform, we don't actually use interesting.
We don't actually use the we can actually put axes in there.
So basically like right now we yeah right now we don't actually expose
any pushes for that.
So we would need to First actually have a push for that, right?
Because right now, when we push bitmap, we don't actually push an axis
system on there, right?
So we need to add that if that makes sense.
Because right now, we support it, but if you look in here, when we do,
when we actually draw the bitmap right here, you can see that.
We actually just always specify the like the axis right here.
So we need to just grab those axes out of out of the actual push
buffer.
That would be the only thing that have to happen there.
Obviously, you can change the scale if you want to, to write.
If you want to be mister mister and code stuff in their code, which
seemed like what people wanted to do, you know, you can
Go nuts have a party.
Right.
Something like this.
Probably.
Discussing.
So you know if you want to change the scale we could change the
rotation to but we didn't.
We don't actually have in the renderer.
We don't have the pushover stuff.
All of our rotation code was just in.
Code should probably add some rotating stuff soon.
Just we can make sure we never break it but yeah I mean if you want to
like we could make counts be tiny now, right?
Probably.
Oops, got to actually pass it.
There we go.
Right now counts as a little tiny baby counts.
That might be a little too small.
Let's be honest.
Go half size.
Right.
All right, stream is ended.
And if the stream is ended, its ended folks, you know, nothing about
that.
Let's go ahead and close down.
Close it down.
Okay, everyone, thank you for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, we got our fonts going today, but like I said, we kind of
just put in some hacked in values right now, which was the goal of
today's episode.
In fact, so what we want to do tomorrow is we want to now go and look
at what those hack values.
All were and then go into our asset processor to sort of start
providing those actual values from the Faust themselves, so that our
fonts will look nicer and
Be lined up, appropriately.
That's what we want to do tomorrow.
Hopefully you'll join me for that.
We'll be right back here at the same time, same place, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time right here on Twitch.
So hope to see you for that until then.
If you want to play around with the source code yourself at home, it's
pretty easy to do.
If you pre-order the game at handmade, he wrote up or you can download
it every night.
I upload the latest changes for the day and you can grab them.
So if you want to do that, check it out.
And we also have a patreon page if you want to support our video
series.
These if you like watching the show, please check it out.
And we also have a forum site.
You can go to ask questions on the forums or if you want to get
Community Resources like porous to Mac and Linux people have been
working on or anti depe sewed guide that people have been working on.
Those are up there and we also have a tweetbot the tweets the
schedule.
So if you're trying to catch the stream live you like watching it live
you like asking the questions that is the place to go, subscribe to
that or just check it.
Periodically it tells you what the schedule B every day.
That's about it.
Thanks so much.
Much for joining me.
We will be back here tomorrow.
Hope to see you all here, until then have fun coding.
And I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy.