Okay.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code entire game live on Twitch know libraries.
No engine, just our own little typing fingers typing away.
We are in the process right now of figuring out how we want our engine
to work.
And we've done a bunch of work on that already.
And we have a little bit more that we want to do right now.
We're trying to do essentially, decide how we want our entity system
to work, how we want to process entities, how
Want to give them attributes and that sort of thing.
And we only just started on that yesterday.
So we're not very far into it.
We're sort of just at the point where we're writing some simple code
that you know, shows how an entity might behave things like a familiar
that follows you around, or a monster that attacks you.
So we can write some of those very simplistically and see the sorts of
things that the engine is going to have to provide for us when it's
actually in place in order for us to make good, you know, good
gameplay, good entities, that respond to the player, the way that we
want them to without it, causing a lot of extra complexity or
problems.
So that's what we're doing right now.
And so let's get back to it.
For those of you who have pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
dot-org, using the pre order button.
If you want to follow along with today, today is day 60.
And so, I don't know what data, I don't how that Maps do that maps to
like.
So we're on our second week of programming, right?
40 hours a week each day here is about an hour.
So 40, so we're 20 hours into our second week.
So we're halfway through our second week of programming here on the
Basically if that makes sense, our second are.
So if this were a job, if you were going to work every day and doing
this.
All right, so if you want to go ahead and grabbed a 59 Source out of
the source download that is what we're starting with today.
And that is how you will line up with me if you want to follow along
with what I do at home.
So, let's go ahead and take a look here.
Boot up dead em and see where we're at.
Okay, so basically what we had
We had our little familiar that follows us around.
We haven't done Sprite sorting yet.
Like I said, which is kind of annoying because it means that things
don't sort in front of or behind each other properly yet, but it's
really just an annoyance.
It doesn't really affect anything.
That'll be for when we write our full renderer later.
So I'm just kind of ignoring it for now.
So we have our little familiar Here and Now what I'd like to maybe do
I think probably the easiest thing to do would be to add just a little
bit.
Of gameplay, here in the sense that I've kind of got.
I've got my arrow keys.
I don't know why we got to fix our shadow as well.
Our jumping Shadow is totally wrong right now.
I'd like to, I guess make this this little torso monster here.
That's just my torso that's standing there.
I'd like to make our little test torso thing there, you know, attack
me in some way.
Like like, I'd like to make it.
Be moved to a distance some distance nearby me and also we can make
the familiar do that to wear it.
You know, it only moves within a certain distance of me and then you
know, maybe launch a projectile at me or something like that.
Just a basic.
A really simple thing that a game might do nothing particularly fancy,
but something that would let me then add, you know, hit points to my
guy hit points to it.
And then, you know when, when it gets, when it gets down to zero
though, and it
He's become effectively dead.
Right?
So let's go ahead.
And do that.
sorry, I'm still eating my
I guess it's called it's a Sumo.
It's called a Sumo Mandarin or something like that.
It's a they're really good.
They're like some kind of a, they're called Sumo mandarins because
they have like a little top not like a Sumo does and now they're
pretty tasty citrus fruit.
Tastes kind of like a tangerine.
I guess.
All right.
so,
We already had our ad monstar to add a monstar.
And what we need to do here is start to think about what the monster
is actually going to do.
We had an update familiar call, right?
And now we also want to have an update monstar call which I believe.
Are.
We actually calling it?
Yes, we are.
So we're already calling the update monstar.
Oh, you know what I should do first, though.
Let's fix our jump Shadow because that was kind of a mistake.
Let's go ahead and make that work properly.
So entity visible piece records.
How we want to draw a piece of something.
We kind of had our push.
Peace.
Call that did that?
In part of the problem with that is that the the offset Z I guess of
the guy.
So I'm trying to think of why we have this this happen.
Exactly.
Let's go ahead and see.
So this was the problem right here.
So really high entities Z?
It should have been not should not have been merged in there because
the Shadows need to stay on the ground there.
So entities Z should not actually be added here that that was a
mistake.
So really, I guess what we want to do is is add some kind of a I don't
know exactly how we want to do it, but we want to be able to add like
a coefficient in here.
Maybe that that says it whether it would be at the Z or not.
It's kind of cheesy.
I'm not sure again.
This is not particularly good, what we're doing here.
I haven't thought through exactly how we want to handle it.
But so if we have the entity Z as like coefficient, I guess so that
basically you've got the ground point and then you've got that height
above the ground point.
I could just
Reduce an entity Z, coefficient here, which basically multiplies it
right.
Which allows me to keep the Shadows on the floor.
Again, not particularly great, but you know, what?
Can you do?
So if we go ahead and add that into our push piece call here.
So normally piece push piece, The Entity CZ would be 1.0, right?
So that we are at wherever the entity actually is in Z, but then we
could also have.
I suppose, I could also
So do it this way for now where we just take it as a default parameter
like so and then so when we do a push piece on a shadow we can just
set that to zero.
So every time we do Shadow Alpha we just set that to zero like so we
could also have a separate call for doing Shadows again.
Don't love it.
It's kind of experiment.
I don't love the way it's working out.
So we may decide that that's just not how that's going to work in the
end.
What did I do here?
Oh, it's zc.
Whoops-a-daisy.
See.
And so, that should keep our shadow back on the ground.
I believe when we jump, yes, it does.
So that's all good.
And similarly, one.
One thing about that is, the shadow Alpha I suppose, on, on our, on
our floating head, should have probably be a little bit less.
Right?
So if I go in here because the head is floating above the ground.
Someone asked me in, during the stream to
Make the Bob Hite be.
So he's so kind of, I don't know if you can see that.
It kind of Bob's up and down the head.
Does the shadow should probably be responding to that Bob as well.
So we might want to do something like do Bob sign so that we grab
whatever that Bob amount is that we were using, right?
We would do that here and then use that Bob to modulate the shadow as
well.
Modulation just a fancy word for multiply.
Basically, this Bob sign is going between 0 and 1, right?
I'm sorry - 1 + 1 which is the sign and then we've got our shadow
Alpha.
So, what I'd like to do is I'd like to essentially blend between two
Shadow Alpha values as you bob up and down, right?
So what I want to do is sort of say, alright, Shadow Alpha.
Which comes in here.
I would like to stay that the shadow Alpha itself.
We're going to start at about, let's say, half of what, because we're
just, that's that's how far we float.
Right?
We're going to start at about, about half the shadow Alpha.
And then what I want to do is I want to go like down and up in that
range.
So I basically want to take my sine which is going between negative 1
and 1 and multiply it by some number that will look kind of move that
range a bit.
Like let's say, it moves.
Up and down by like to write either direction.
So the shadow will get very light when it when it goes.
And I think we also because we're moving it up is positive and down is
negative.
But that's the opposite of what we want to do to our shadow value.
So we actually want to flip the sense of it.
When you get slower, you want to get brighter.
So the alpha should go up if that makes sense.
Brighter is probably the wrong term there, but you know what?
I mean, we want to get more intent more of it Blended in.
So now he's like, oh no, I was wrong.
Why did I why did it?
What did I do wrong there?
Because it's going the wrong way.
Way you can see it's getting lighter when it goes down.
So when the sign gets - he should be going down.
Yes, so if I have my shadow Alpha,
And he gets lower.
The science should be - at that point and so I should want to add to
the shadow Alpha.
Should I not?
What am I missing about that?
I'm not sure did.
I not recompile it weird.
Let's think that through.
So we take the sign and the sign comes back between negative 1 and 1.
We are
Pushing the P.
Oh wait, no, we're pushing the piece on here.
We push, you know, whatever.
The 1010 m 2 pixels is right to move it up and down up and down, like
so.
And is there anything special that I should know about push piece?
So push piece uses the offset directly.
Like so.
Oh, you know, what is push piece?
This is a little bit janky.
Push pieces, probably in pixel space, isn't it?
Yeah, that's really ugly.
So I guess I don't care too much about this right now because since
we're not really doing rendering but that's really ugly.
So really that it's not, it's in pixels, which of course, are going
down on our in our screen Direction.
So that's why this becomes a positive.
That's, that's really kind of ugly and definitely not something we
want to keep.
But like I said, we don't, this code is not is just for testing
purposes.
And when we do the full renderer will be going through that which will
be very different.
So yeah, but I just wanted to kind of throw that in there just so are
our head kind of had its shadow respond properly, just to get to see.
All right, so everyone's working properly with that now and that's all
good.
So,
I guess while I'm out of here.
Let's go ahead and make the familiar stop a little further away from
us because right now he tries to get as close as possible, which
doesn't seem very good.
So, maybe I'll say, I don't know the closest hero distance squared.
Maybe we'll try to stop, you know, about a metre away or something,
right?
That seems reasonable.
I'll put a square around that just so people can see that supposed to
be square root, even though 1 squared is still just one.
So I'm not sure if weight is that right?
Click this here too.
High and closes hero squared is greater than 1.0., Right?
That should stop him.
I feel like that should have stopped him further away.
Of course, he still has momentum I suppose but even so that should
have stopped him a little further away, which I'm not sure why I did
not.
Let's let's increase it to something higher just to see because it
should stop and I'm not sure if we've got a bug there.
So that seems is that really three meters in our world length?
It's a little odd, right?
Doesn't that seem a little bit far for 3 meters?
I'm sorry.
A little bit close for three meters.
I would have expected three meters to be a little bit less than that.
I guess.
Well, you know what?
Our guy still is huge.
We never scaled our guy back down.
So it is true that that maybe is three meters in the case in, you
know, in the case that we're actually talking about.
So that's fine.
So there are there are there are familiar won't get too close to us,
which is nice because it was getting a little cramped in here to be
honest with you.
So that seems a little bit better.
And, and that way we can just kind of, have it be a little more
reasonable than what it was.
All right.
There we go.
So, let's talk about, let's go ahead.
Add hit points, maybe to our guy, that seems pretty reasonable.
So, if I go over here to handmade H, and I look at the entity struct.
So again, the way we've been doing things so far and this is again
designed to sort of get us into the position where we can do something
a little more sensible.
Is we just dump everything into low entities.
So anytime we want to do something.
We just put it directly into low entity.
And then what I hope will happen is a nice pattern of usage will
emerge in the code where we can see how we want to start breaking that
up into.
Do something else right into into something?
That's not all just every single variable is in one giant struck
because that won't be very efficient for storage, right?
It works just fine, but
it's really overly verbose because most enemies won't use most things.
If there's lots of different variables in there that are specific to
specific entities.
So inside low entity.
I'm going to go ahead and say that we have some kind of Health
parameters here, right?
Let's say that we've got something like, you know, hit point Max and
hit point.
Count.
So that we well, I guess I could say hit points.
So I could basically say, all right, we've got, you know, hit points
here and, and they are trying to get how I want to do this.
I don't know if I actually want an actual struct for hit points.
I think I might, you know what, I might want.
I light want something more, like,
Abyss.
Right.
We reach hit point.
Actually has an actual, you know, has some State associated with it.
Potentially, if that makes sense.
So, we'd have a hit point Max and then we'd have some kind of a hit
point.
Storage array.
And the hit point storage array would kind of be, you know, would be
attached to that.
Now, one interesting thing about that is I wonder if hit points
themselves should be entities.
That's kind of a different, I'll put it to do there so we can think
about that should hit points themselves, the entities.
So that basically you just have a set of hit points that sort of
attached to you and then I go down.
I don't know if I like that idea or not might be a little too General,
but let's say we do this.
And so we have hit points.
And then you've got some hip points here and however many hit points
you can actually have let's say it's something like 80 know maybe 16
is better and then our hit points.
We actually have like whether or not it is is filled.
And maybe how much it is filled.
So maybe it just got something like filled amount, you know, and flags
or something like this.
So that way, the reason I'm making a little struck for hit point is
because I might, you know, I want to start thinking about stuff like,
oh what if you know, you get a poisoned one?
Or there's a special that's on it.
Where like, oh, it's fragile.
So if it ever gets taken away, it's something magical happens.
I don't know.
Like there's things that could happen here with hit points, which is
why I was also saying, maybe they should be entities because
that way they can have like crazy amount of
comet Oriel structure going on with them.
This low any structures getting pretty large at this point, which is
kind of dangerous.
Like I said, but what do you do?
So what I'd like to do is say, let's draw those hit points then and
when you do add player assume when we did it, add low entity.
I can't remember.
But I assume we always clear everything we do so that I'll start out
to 0.
So when you add a player will say that it has an entity hip Point.
Max of something.
Let's say you start off with the canonical three hearts worth of
damage.
Because you know,
That everyone always starts with three hearts.
Obviously what else could possibly be?
And then I guess I want to do those hit points that you actually have
will set them too.
You all the way full.
If we did the standard for possible segments in a heart or you know, I
don't know whether half or four is good.
But let's say that we go with with four segments for now, then what we
could do is say the hip point zero equals hip Point 1 equals hit .260
and then I'll just say in too low.
Hit point groups, hit point to, and we'll set that filled amount to
for which, for now we'll say is the maximum, which is kind of
unfortunate.
I guess.
What we really could do is we could even make that down.
You could bake this down into one variable, but we don't really want
to do that yet because again, that's kind of premature spatial
optimization.
We don't even know if we storing it this way.
So just leave it as easily accessible things for now.
Then I'll just make a pound to find here for lack of anything better.
But hit point sub or hit point.
Phil Max count count macksville.
I don't know, hit point.
I want and I want a pound to find for this for basically, so, I guess
sub.
Shit Point sub count.
We'll just call it.
Thats not a good name.
I can't think of a very good name off the bat.
So that'll basically initialize those three hit points for us.
And then what I could do is start to draw them, right?
So we've got that compiling.
So if I go down here and we do, we look for where we test for the hero
where we've got any type hero.
When I do this drawing, right?
I could now sort of draw some little rectangles.
Some kind of a health meter.
in there, so,
I suppose with our entity visible piece.
I could also do that, where if loaded bitmap is 0, right?
We could have color value in here, right?
RGB.
And that color value.
In fact, I could change the alpha as well to basically be in here.
So we do it like that.
So if I have the RGB and a and then I have the offset, I could then
just have sort of like a width height to it as well.
And that would allow me to do, I guess, we'll, I could call this half
Dimension, right?
Or just to mention.
This is how big you want to be, and then we divide it by 2, and we use
it for Red rig.
So combined, with the offset, that would give
Me everything that I need to just draw a rectangle there, right?
So let me go ahead and recompile that and change these Alphas two A's.
in the places where they're supposed to be 60, and
What I can do is just do an if piece bitmap check here and then that
would allow me to draw rectangles with that same system where we're
just kind of pushing it on there.
So if I do this, go ahead and get that rectangle, they're assuming
that I'm going to use the exact same.
All this exact same stuff.
Pull this out into an X and A Y like so.
So this is our x coordinate for the rectangle.
This is our y coordinate for the rectangle.
X y.
Here we go.
And when I draw the rectangle, then I can just go ahead and do that.
In fact, I could do is be a little even more aggressive and call the
center that there we go.
Okay.
And so that way, when I draw the bitmap, I'm just grabbing out the
center X and the center why?
But when I draw the rectangle, I can place do the, the center, minus 5
times that that dim.
So, I'm half the
Could get me to that one corner of the rectangle and then I can add
half the dim to get me to the other corner of the rectangle.
Right?
And that seems pretty reasonable.
Now, of course, I need to do m, 2 pixels transform on that.
In fact, I should probably do that here.
So I do m 2 pixels on the dimensions and then we'll go ahead and use
it there.
I could also roll the 0.5 in their half Jim like so.
And then that's just.
Nice and simple.
So that a draw the rectangle for us.
We should then also pass the RGB and a I don't know if our rectangle
call even supports Alpha, it might not not.
I think about it.
So we may not really actually able to use that Alpha parameter, but
we'll just leave it like that for now because I think we never
implemented anything that could support Alpha yet.
Doesn't just use RGB.
That's all it can do.
So assuming that we've got that set.
Let's go ahead and compile that and now I should be able to draw.
Some little rectangle markers that would just basically show us what
the health status is of the hero at any given time.
And so let's go ahead and put in something like that because that
seems like a good thing.
We're going to we know we're going to have to have health M.
That's a pretty obvious thing to need to have.
So maybe I'll just have a thing here.
And probably will pull this out into a function once we see how it
works because I feel like the monstar will also want a health meter.
Right?
So what we'll do is we'll say, all right.
There is a Max Health on the sky.
There's a hit point Max.
And so, what I want to do here is I want to figure out how to sort of
Center this around the guy, right?
So I've got a guy, he's standing here.
And maybe I just want to put something like this in place, right?
So what I want to do.
Is I want to figure out.
A good way to parameterize.
How to place these things offset from the from the dude, okay, and
what I think about how to do that, right?
I kind of have to look at this is of kind of discrete placement
problem.
I have a center line here, right?
The Y is easy, right?
The offset of them from this as easy as just a fixed amount below.
So, we just know, we would just, you know, we'd subtract some number,
or in this case, add some number because we have things are going the
wrong way in this court system as we just looked at.
But anyway, so we'd move them down here, but
When we want to align them, it's going to depend on the max hit points
because we have two cases, right?
In the even case.
We have a center line and we have an equal number of things on either
side of the center line, right?
And the spacing it runs, right?
That Center Line.
It runs right down the middle.
So it would be one and a half to get to here and one and a half to get
to hear, right?
But in the odd case, we will have a separate thing, right?
We will have that Center Line running right down the middle.
And so the distance to get from the center line to here, will actually
just be one, right?
So, it'll be that spacing will be will be different.
So if you think about like what this implies, right, like again, one
of the, if you're working on some like this, and you don't immediately
know the answer, one thing that's kind of nice to do is to sort of
draw out the first few and usually, if it's something simple like
This that will just immediately tell you what the answer is just by
inspection.
You don't have to be overly clever.
And so just to show how that would work.
So there's some things that we would know about this, right?
Again, we know how far we want the offset to be this way.
We know how big we want these guys to be.
But more importantly, what we actually care about is their centers for
placement.
All we really need to know to figure out the placement right should be
how wide this space is, right.
So we basically have a spacing parameter.
Let's call that s.
Okay.
So we want to do is given a number of these.
So we'll say that s is the space between them, right?
And in x,
And we'll say that n is the count of them.
So, that's how many of these there actually are.
So we have our spacing and then we have our count.
And so that should tell us.
If we just assume that the center line is 0 for now that should, this
is all, we should really need right to figure out where to place the
stuff because it's all it's dependent on it.
Just that, you know, this tells us how far they're separated.
This tells us how many there are, that should be all we actually need
and this will actually, this is actually the max.
Count not the current count, obviously, because we're going to fill
them in based on whether they're set, or not.
So really, this is the max out, but for purposes of this alignment,
all the carrots, how many of the things we want and the space between
them, right?
So let's go ahead and and do out the cases, right?
So, here's our
Centerline.
And here's our n, right.
So for n equals 0, we have nothing, so it doesn't matter.
For n equals 1.
It should be right on the center line.
For n equals two.
There should be two on, either side of the center line, right?
Separated by S.
Right.
So the the the amount will separate will move, it will, will talk
about the results in terms of two things, where the first one is.
So we're the first one goes, I guess we don't even two things and then
we
Where the next ones are because we just add s to it, right?
So all we need to do is figure out where that first one is and then we
would just add the spacing to get to each individual extra one.
So we only need just that one offset is all we need.
So the first one, this is a non case, we don't even have to handle it
because zero should never.
You could just not do anything, doesn't matter what your turn because
they'll never draw anything.
So, if you have one, the first should be at zero, if you have to the
first should be at negative point, five times s, right.
It should be at half an s.
Right, if we have three then we should have like, so there we go.
We should have the first one be at negative s, right?
So it should be.
It should be start there and go forwards.
If we have a fourth one, right?
We should have it like so.
Should now be - 1 .5 s, right?
So you can kind of see what the pattern is building.
Here are ready for every additional one.
We have passed one, right?
So, so we start at two at two, we have -.5 at three we have another
point five, right?
So it's negative s.
It's 1.0 s right there.
1 .5 s.
So really we just have however money and is minus 1.
Right times that point five right times.
S, that is all we really need to produce this step because it goes up
by .5 each time.
So we just need to say how many do we have that are above to or I
should say above one, right?
So, starting at 2:00.
I'm ever made.
There are above 1 and minus 1, and then we do that that count, right?
So, n, minus 1, x .5.
S looks like our winner there.
That's all.
We should really need to do.
Due to space these out properly, and then again when we get the first
one, we can just add s to each individual.
One to move it forwards.
So that's how I'm going to go ahead and write that.
If we go ahead here, let's go ahead and solve for that that first X.
And so, that first X is going to be however, many hit points.
This entity has, so that's in our low entity, that's in our hip Point
Max, because the hit point.
Max tells us how many could be filled.
That's how many we want to draw.
That's like his his max HP at the moment.
So I have that hit point Max.
I want to subtract one for it.
And first I probably want to check to make sure the low-energy hit
point Max.
Least one because otherwise we're not going to do anything.
So we'll go ahead and say, if the hit point, Max minus 1, there we go.
We've got it.
That's our n minus one.
That's this term right here, right?
Then we have our point five.
And then we have our spacing, our spacing Annex.
So, our spacing and X.
I don't know exactly what that number should be, will have to tune it.
I would guess I would say that whatever the size of each one of these
is.
So if we basically say the the dimension of of our health being so our
health, Tim, whatever that actually is.
Let's say it's point to in the in the pixels per meter space, right?
Whatever that spacing is, you know, what?
And this is, this is I guess something that we should address as well.
Kind of going forward is since we don't have any offsets for anything
else yet.
I think we didn't actually do the code for push piece here that would
change that to meters.
So this should actually be in meters per pixel, right, so I should
probably go ahead here and get that game state in maybe that just gets
stored in the piece group to, so you don't have to pass it.
Every time.
That makes sense.
In other words in this piece group.
Maybe piece, group, Dot Game state.
Both game state.
Like so and so that way the piece group game said you can just access
things like the world and stuff.
So when we go ahead and set those offsets, let's say that those
offsets for now are all.
Let's make all of those in m 2 pixels so that they're in meters
because I'd rather have them be in meters.
So, peace game state.
M 2 pixels.
Oops.
Where is our m 2 pixels?
Where do we actually store that?
So, we don't actually have that stored anywhere.
We actually need that.
We want that to actually be something that you can access reliably.
So let's go ahead and get that into the game State.
Let's, let's put that in there.
M 2 pixel.
Like so.
Okay, and that way we can do m, 2 pixels and just anyone can grab it
from anywhere what you want because it's not really, a very varying
variable.
So I don't really want people calculating it all over the place.
Alright, so we got our m 2 pixels in there and that'll be fine.
This could technically be set somewhere else.
In fact, what is this lower left?
This is old stuff, isn't it?
We don't actually use this anymore so we can clean that up.
That's just that's just gone now.
Alright, so inside here where we
We actually do our in.
It is actually a reasonable place to do this too.
Because if you take a look at it, as soon as the world is initialized,
it's got that it's got that towel side and M in it, really, those
should probably be pulled out of the world as well at some level,
because I don't know that they need to live this early in the world.
We could also put m 2 pixels in the world, but I don't know.
These are the sorts of things that really just don't matter.
It doesn't matter where those stories as long as people can get at
them.
They're fine.
It's probably not worth over thinking.
When we start to go clean up engine components.
We may decide that there's an obvious right place for stuff like
metrics and then we would coalesce them that point when it's, when
it's important to do.
So.
So anyway, if I go ahead and do this here, I got it actually add that
to my group there.
So game State game State like so.
So this
Actually, allow me to to put everything in the meter to pixel format.
So let's go ahead and compile that and make sure they haven't broken
anything.
Obviously.
This has to go after game.
State is defined.
So that's fine.
Oops.
And this is in, this is off the group.
Not the piece, we go.
Let's see.
So our spacing X, as we were doing this.
I'll finish up typing.
This in our spacing X is going to be + m, 2 pixels.
The something like twice the dimension of the health or maybe just the
dimension of the health.
So let's just say that, it's the health is, are separated by one whole
health bar, in between each one.
Will, we can adjust it later to see how we would like it to look.
And then we have the dimension of it, which is how big will draw it.
So now we actually know where that first one is going to be right?
And I suppose we could also move these in here.
This is all part of that Health drawing.
So then, all we have to do is actually go through and draw hovering.
However, many pieces you have.
Again, this this might require us to think that this this is might be
a bit bigger at this point.
We could we could be drawing a lots of drawing.
I'd like I think this push piece thing is pretty dumb.
I think it was a stupid idea, really.
This should just be part of the renderer that allows us to push things
on there in spaces.
So well, I'm actually going to put that in here because this is just
dumb.
This is dumb.
This should just be part.
Of the renderer push buffer, add correction of coordinates in there
and be done with it.
So we'll we'll basically deal with that a little bit later.
All right.
So if we take a look at this, now, what we need to do is we need to
push a piece, we need to do like a push wrecked call or something like
this.
That is going to do, that's going to take that Dimension.
Right?
So instead of a bitmap here, it's going to take a health dim.
It's going to take like a coordinate and a health dim at the end and
no alignment, right?
Because it's just a rectangle.
And so then in addition to those it also has to take the r g and B,
and so
Do is we'll have our r g and B here.
And again, you can kind of see.
Maybe this would also be since we're kind of just doing miscellany
today at this point and we got 20 minutes left.
I don't know that.
I want to start on the monastery.
I'd rather just finished the hit point stuff.
Maybe what we'll do is we'll throw in a 3D Vector so we can finally
3D and 4D, Vector.
So we can finally just do these are G and peace properly, right?
So anyway, so let's go ahead and do this like so.
There we go, and our r g and B, and I'll pass an a as well, even
though we don't actually support it just because I would like to
support it eventually obviously for our rectangles.
So in here what I want to do is say alright, let's go ahead and and
loop over.
However many of these you've got right?
So we have a health index equals zero.
The health index is less than that.
That hip Point Max that we have.
And for each one of those, we're going to grab out, whatever.
The hit point actually was so we've got this guy here.
So we got to hit point.
And that's going to be equal to the low entity hit point.
Plus which ever one we're on, right?
And so we go through there.
And now what we need to do is we can set the r g and B to like we'll
just set it to bright red.
Right?
If it's filled.
But if the hit point let's say filled amount is we'll just we'll just
say if it equals 0 for now, we will represent it quite properly yet.
We'll look at that in a second.
If the hit point filled amount is zero, then it'll change.
You just a dark gray or something like this, right?
And then what we need is, we need to be able to, on our push piece.
We actually need to be able to do the, the push wrecked call.
We need to be able to do something that actually does the rectangle.
Push.
Obviously this right now, I don't know if I want to support and easy,
but well, we'll do it anyway, so when we push this on here, we've got
all the same stuff that we had before only alignment goes away and we
end up with Dimension.
So we'll put in dimension there.
Then we've got our piece, has an actual dim, and that dim goes on
there.
We then also have an r g and B, RG and B.
And those get assigned right here.
Peace.
Our peace.
She right.
Peace be.
There we go.
You could slap that in there as well.
Equals Alpha A is for Alpha.
It's like some kind of children's book and that.
It would allow us to push, rectangles, in addition to bitmaps course.
We don't have a lime anymore.
So we get rid of that and poops.
That's no good.
Health count or what would I call it?
Hit point.
Count, get Point Max.
That's what it is.
Your point, Max.
So that should allow us to draw those.
Now.
I don't know if I broke other things.
I went in there.
Oh, dear.
That's pretty funny.
So yeah, in case anyone was wondering when you change to m 2 pixels
anything that was not previously in m 2 pixels.
Yeah, so we're this is way too much obviously.
Even.
So because that was in pixels before and like I said, I wanted
everything to be in World units.
I don't want things in pixels.
So there's our head Bob back again.
Still probably a little bit too high.
Look at that.
That's that's more like what it was.
And so now I got to finish up my health meter.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So what we need to do now is place it at the position that it actually
should be in.
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to create something that's
like first first or or
Substitute P.
We'll just start with P, right?
Or hit p.
And that is going to be an offset from the player.
It's going to be a fixed, why, but it's going to be based on this
first X.
So, we've got first X.
And in fact, I could just bake for a sex, right in there, like so.
And and then I could have however, far off the bottom.
We want it to be in y, right?
It's going to be down a bit from where the guy should be like, so and
I don't know if we do we properly reverse the why either that's the
other thing.
So we haven't properly.
First a while yet.
So that will actually be above them.
So maybe we can go do that now to just to get that cleaned up as well
because we want all of our.
Why going up.
We don't want to have this crazy stuff in here, even when we're just
playing around with it, be nice to get rid of it.
So maybe we'll do that.
So there's our hit p and here's our D, hit p is how much to move for
each one.
We already said with that was, it's the spacing amount.
And so then we just go in and put that in.
So we've got our hit p and every time we draw one, we just move it, by
whatever that distance is that supposed to move between health bars,
right?
And so, in theory that
That should give us it.
Although it doesn't look like it did properly which is not good.
We've got our spacing x0, not that's good.
I meant plus equals.
There we go.
All right, so that doesn't look right to me.
That's because this is supposed to be -.
All right, we're supposed to start at negative.
The amount that we computed.
There we go.
And now we want to make the spacing.
So the spacing actually has to
Now that I think about it, that was a dumb thing that's going to but
them directly together, right?
Because if you think about what happens there in terms of how we need
them spaced.
So this is the dimension, right?
So this would be half the dimension.
So if I move exactly one of the dimension over, they will a but
exactly.
So if I want some space in between them, I need to do the dimension
plus some amount of space, right?
So the distance between them in terms of,
Spacing should actually be something more than that, like, maybe 1.5
times it is.
If that's a reasonable amount, just to give it some space in between
them.
So there's our health, our health meter there.
And now let's go ahead and reverse that y-coordinate which will mean
that we'll have to sort of fix the way we were doing some of these
other things here.
But okay.
So for push peace, let's see how we're doing there.
So offset Z and players.
Those were already being negated.
So really all of this stuff looks
About right.
The thing is that what we want to do is say that whatever the why
channel was the why channel is going to get negated in here.
So whatever people pass in we negate it in here.
So basically this this is actually going to be offset x negative
offset y like.
So I think that's what we want.
So that everyone who passes in something here.
It'll go the opposite direction, right?
Which I think is what we
So in theory, what that would mean is if that's actually working
properly then when I pass in those offsets to the hip points, I should
be able to make them lower like by doing that.
Right?
Why is that not working?
Oh, right.
We should probably unify these two as well.
So I changed it in here, but I did not change it in here.
So what I should probably do again, this is kind of stupid because
I want to get rid of this anyway, but you know, while it's there, it's
there, right?
So let's change this call to be pushed bitmap.
Right?
And this is push wrecked.
And both of these will just call in to one function that does the
whole shebang basically like so.
So this will be pushed piece and push piece will have all the
parameters, right?
So it basically has has every every last little thing.
Like so, oops.
And this way is just me trying to make it so that I ensure that I'm
not going to have bugs like that one where I just accidentally change
something in one place and don't change it in the other, right?
So that's that's really all that's happening there.
Be Alpha and entities that zc.
So that just takes everything and does all the computations that we
actually want done.
And then what these guys will do is push bitmap and push piece just
call into it.
With whatever they have.
So we have the group, the bitmap offset offset.
See the alignment, the alpha, right?
The are the G and the B are all.
Just one in this case and the entities EC that goes away and then
we'll do the exact same thing here.
Only this time we don't have a bitmap.
So the bitmaps gone.
We've got the offset Z.
We've got the line this time.
We've got the we don't have the line.
Sorry.
That's 00.
No, change in the alignment.
Then we've got the G.
The Beebe.
A and we're done, so.
Oh no, we're not.
We've got one more parameter, which is the dimension.
So let's go ahead and get that in there as well.
So this guy passes the alignment and then no Dimension.
Like so this guy passes that and then the dimension, which
Where is that?
There?
It is.
Okay, never mind.
I was like where it's not on there, but it is on there.
And so then we just change Pete, push piece to be pushed bitmap.
And I think we're good.
That should solve that problem for us, and it did.
So there's our little Health meter little bit too low now, so, maybe
that's a little bit aggressive.
So let's go ahead and change it to that.
So there we go.
So there's our health meter and that's all fine.
No particular.
A particular big deal there and we've got about 10 minutes left.
So like I said, maybe let's start to add our 3D vector and r4d Vector
in there to our Mass so that we can stop having sort of all this
annoyance.
Oh, you know what to I suppose The Entity zc should probably be in
there, right?
Because that probably shouldn't move when he jumps.
Right.
That's probably stay down there at the bottom so that seems that seems
pretty reasonable.
So yeah, so what I was thinking is just, you know, maybe we should
have something where we can represent.
Like as we want at least be able to represent color values like rgba
in vectors as well and like not have to be passing them, piecemeal
like this and being able to access them all at.
Once would be kind of handy.
So what I'm what I'd like to do is go ahead and go into handmade math
and
Just just blow out these into two more types, right?
So basically we'd have, you know, three of these.
We'd have one for a V3, one for a V4.
And in addition, to the ones that we had already,
Like this.
And it might also be nice to do it so that you could access these by
other names, right?
Something like this so that you have, you know, an alternate way of
thinking about any given one of them if you want it to be some other
naming scheme than what you've got.
Right?
So that might be handy and this would allow us again and I'll just
I'll multiply these guys out here just so I have an additional way of
constructing them like so
And there you go.
Oops.
So that'll give me you know, more of these guys, right?
And now I've got each individual type that I wanted and off you go.
So that would allow me to pass those color values in there.
And
Let's go ahead and compile that.
Let's see, gotta change their turn type.
There we go.
And that way, I could start to talk about these three dimensional
vectors in in more interesting ways.
And so we probably won't get to too much of that because we only got
about eight minutes left, but I'll start with the very, very basic
stuff.
So right here, if I wanted to obviously, I could make this a V4 that
was just the color, right?
And then that becomes a lot more compelling because I can kind of do
stuff like this.
Right.
That basically just allows me to to be a little more convenient with
what I'm doing.
So I could just go ahead and
Do something like this, right?
And then, when I pass this along, I just pass it in as a color value,
right?
And that just just, again, start simplifying, things simplifying life
a little bit.
So there we go before color.
And then this is just colored at our color .g colored up, be coded a
right and no literally no change to the code.
Like what it's actually doing is just it's just
Making it a little more semantically easier for me to deal with.
And so up here.
I can do the same thing.
I can I can pass that through the pipe.
Down to push piece just to clean up, get some of those out of there,
make it a little more coherent.
And then that's just going to be colored G color B, color a, and then
this guy who takes them in a different way.
He only takes an alpha.
No big deal, right.
He just packs them up and it's the same thing for him.
No big deal.
And then this guy can just pass this color straight through which is
kind of nice.
It's okay.
No big deal there.
Everything is relatively obvious.
What's happening?
And then
Let's take a look and see I can start to maybe clean up some other
stuff that we were doing there.
Let's see here.
Let's see.
So well, no, I guess I won't do anything.
I won't do anything there yet.
So we could take obviously colors and their I'm trying to think of
where else, there was one place.
I definitely want to do, I'm not sure if I want to do it right now,
but we could do it in there which is which is those diffs, those discs
that come back.
I don't know if you remember but basically we had these discs that
come back as a d XY and DZ the world.
Difference could now just be a vector3.
It's just a straight-up vector3 that says, what your differences in
the world.
So maybe we'll just start with that.
I only got five minutes left, but I don't know how hard that would be.
Let's find out.
So, if I go to world difference, if I go to basically everywhere that
was using that and just change that to be a V3, right?
Very simply now I could just
Make that result equal to exactly what I'm Computing here.
Right.
Pack that
a vector 3, like so,
and I guess, then the
Chunk side and M times, dv/dt tile, X Y.
So, that would literally just be after we compute this, we could just
multiply it by the chunk side and M and then add that those offset
differences.
Think about what you want to do in Z, so it basically would just be a
full three-dimensional.
You know, what?
The now that I look at it.
I feel like we don't have enough time left because we actually want to
think that through its I'll I don't know if I want to say think that
through I'd like to explain what we're doing there a little bit more.
So while I'm not back that out and we'll
Let It Be oops, that's not good.
Well, let that be a thing that will start on Monday because we could
we could pretty easily do this but I just want to be able to explain
that a little more clearly because we're going to want to go write a
multiply there and so that we can collapse all this down into one
thing, which will be pretty easy.
So all this go and for the last couple seconds here, I'll mention one
thing about way we're doing this.
So sometimes people like to template eyes these, right?
They like to go ahead and say
Say, they'll do something like, you know, a template here where
they'll have, you know, templatized on the number of these things.
So then you would do stuff more, like, V2 like that.
Like, you'd pass an integer.
It become both eyes on the integer 2 and then it would give you that
many of them, right?
I don't find that to be useful at all because it introduces templates
into the code base, which are almost always bad.
They are worse for error messages.
They're worse for compile time.
They're worse for Pediatric, be output size, which slows down compile
time as well.
They're worse for debugging, they're worse for viewing in most of
buggers because the buggers don't handle them as well.
So it's basically just bad to have templates.
Templates are just bad on a number of fronts.
And so you want to make sure you if you're going to use them that you
actually get
Back in enough from them, commensurate with what your you know, what
all of that huge hit you're taking a lot of programmers, don't think
about that.
A lot of programmers, just like to do stuff and they don't actually
try to compute the total cost to their project in doing so but I think
that's a mistake.
And so if I'm ever going to introduce Templeton to codebase, I always
think very hard about whether they're actually necessary and how much
time I'm actually going to say by having them for vectors.
I'm not really going to say very much time.
Because basically we can do a really simple cut and paste job.
And basically, just blow out the operators that the temp, the template
would have blown out for us anyway, and how long is that really going
to take?
I mean, look at this file.
There's not much in here.
There's only a very small number of vector operations will just copy
those, do them once and then everything is correct, and we don't have
to worry about like, weird like template specialization to get the
fact that we can access these by RGB Zan days and all this stuff.
So it just, it just works out a lot better.
So for vectors, I, unless you have some really
Weird stuff where you have.
Like hundreds of different lengths of vectors like, you know 3 S 4, S
5 6, 7 8 9 10, 11, 12 13, you know, whatever like that where maybe it
does.
It is something where you really need to be able to template eyes or
something.
I would highly recommend not template eyes in your math classes.
It's just works a lot better if you don't.
And yeah, you might have a few cut and paste bugs, but you'll debug
them right away.
And then, you'll be done.
And you'll never have to think about it again, and you won't have
introduced templates in your code base, which causes a lot of
problems, and their problems that people refuse to acknowledge often
times, but then,
Then you know invariably I show up on some projects.
I'm like, why does it take 30 minutes to compile?
And it's like well, it's because we use standard string and we have a
giant Temple ties math class and we have all this in this like, okay.
This was a really bad idea, right?
So you want to be judicious with that stuff.
Would it kill you to use templates here know, having one or two sets
of simple templates in your code is not going to hurt you.
You totally could template eyes this.
If you really wanted to, it would not ruin the world.
But in general, I find this a good product to not introduce templates
where they're not really needed because you pay a lot of costs that
people don't want to acknowledge, but that are very much there.
All right.
So having said that we have come to the Q and A right on time.
Look at that.
If you could when we are doing Q&A, please prefix your questions with
q:.
So I can see them and please keep them in stuff that we've done on the
stream or that we're going to do our sorry.
Could we turn on the stream or that we have done not on stuff that
we're going to do because that's what we're going to do.
We will get to and we do it right?
So off topic or future looking stuff.
Let's keep that to the priest rememory when we do off-topic stuff, but
for right now, let's stick to stuff.
We've actually done.
That makes sense.
Let's take a look.
Is it making a struct for HP is pre-programming?
A little?
Well, not really because, again, what I'm doing here is trying to
figure out the stuff that I want the engine to handle.
So, in some sense I have to pre program.
In that sense, I have to add things that I need, right?
That I think I'm going to need because that's the whole point of this.
I think I don't know if you remember, but I said
When we first started, what we were doing?
What we're in the process of doing right now.
Back several hours ago, I guess it would have been 20 hours ago or
something like that.
20, even 30 hours ago.
I said you always write their usage codes first, but the problem when
you're starting off when you have no engine,
No game is that you don't actually know what any of the usage cases
are.
And so that's where you do the experimental code stuff.
And so that is exactly what we're doing now.
And so we are our pre-programming everything we've done in the past 48
hours is pre-programming, right?
This is not the actual game code.
This is not the actual game, but you don't have a choice.
You have to do something first so you can see how it shakes out, you
iterate on it.
A bunch of times, you try to keep all of them quick and then you can
sort of see roughly what you
need.
So that's kind of the way that you have to do things when you're first
bootstrapping because you don't have the luxury of writing the use of
first.
If you don't know what the uses code looks like, right, so this is the
next best thing.
Why not?
Just use hit point Max equals 12, instead of dividing it into three
hearts and four segments, because this I feel like there's a concept
of segmented.
Heart that wants to be represented here.
Like when something gets poisoned you'd get poisoned, the whole heart
versus the individual pieces or something like that.
I don't know.
Like I said, it was just a Whimsical thing.
I was like, let's try it this way.
So you could do it the other way, as well.
If you intended to have each individual, segments of a heart be have
its own set of properties.
I noticed the floating head was always behind the player.
Are you going to do?
Go for a depth of her approach or Draw back to front to handle this,
back to front.
And the reason that there's a very good reason for that.
It's not arbitrary.
The reason to do back to front in this case is for two reasons.
One, is it increases the effective fill rate on graphics cards and
possibly also for us, depending on exactly how we implement the
renderer.
And so I'll explain why that is true.
And then there's another reason, which is better.
So quality, and I'll explain why that's true as well.
So if you imagine how a graphics card works, right?
A graphics card is drawing to the screen and you tell it to draw some
triangle, right?
And in the case of a Sprite, you're telling it to draw two triangles.
Usually what?
And, you know, the Sprite occupies, those two triangles like so and so
what it has to do now is it has to go ahead and put that into put that
basically
It needs to rasterize the triangles grab the texture, right?
Because this texture is out here somewhere.
It needs to go grab that it needs to copied in here and it needs to
apply it to the frame buffer, right?
It needs to write the pixels in just like what we're doing, but it
doesn't in slightly different way, obviously.
So, if we are to turn on z-buffering right?
Or as you said depth buffering, right?
If returning on a z-buffer, then there's two choices we can have for
when we turn on the z-buffer, one reason to turn on Z.
Buffer is what you said, which is to have it sort the objects for us.
So
Do is we say, some, we assign Z coordinates even though we're not in
3D.
We assign Z coordinates to this, this texture here, right?
And when we assign those z-coordinates, what we do is we say, okay,
when things are lower down on the screen, they get like a higher or
lower Z value, depending on whether we decide to make it go less than
or greater than in terms of the see comparison.
We assign it a z value to them.
Em and then we let the depth buffer figure out whether like this
bright and this bright would include each other based on their Z
values, right?
So when it draws the pixels each time on each pixel, it's checking the
Z value and seeing whether it should be in front of or behind now that
is one use of the Z buffer and that's using the z-buffer sort of as it
was intended, right?
For sorting.
But there's another way you can use the Z buffer and I shouldn't say
use it.
This is happening all the time whether you like it or not, but it's it
choose.
Its whether you choose to leverage it which is early out.
Right?
So basically the z-buffer, when the graphics card goes to rasterize, a
little chunk of pixels it goes and looks to see whether the Z values
that you're about to test.
Because you know, it's got some idea of the Min and Max for any you.
Let's say, I've got a right, you know.
Little square of pixels on to this other square of pixels.
Let's say it's a 4x4, right?
It's going to rasterize some stuff in here.
What it'll do is it'll grab the frame, buffers 4x4, and it knows what
the Min and Max of that are because it's store at the Min.
And Max is e, right?
And it knows what the Min and Max possible z's are for you as well
because it knows what triangle is producing this fragment and it knows
what the minimum maximum Z can be.
For at that point.
It can compare these two before ever touching any pixels.
And go.
Could I ever produce a z value in this thing that I'm writing?
That would actually be in front of this thing that's already in the
depth buffer.
If the answer is no it just skips the whole for by Forbes right off
the bat and it saves you a bunch of Texel grabbing and it saves you, a
bunch of fill rate there, right?
So that cuts down your memory bandwidth.
What that means is that if you can optimize the order in which you
draw to always draw from front to back anyway, right?
If we were always to draw from front to back, we could maximize the
chances that things would just, you know, if you have a giant Sprite
here, that included everything.
And then when we start drawing, things behind it, it'll never actually
even have to fetch the texture memory for the Sprites that were behind
there.
So it becomes much more efficient if you can do this, so we so since
we have just a bunch of Sprites on the screen, there aren't that many
of them, you know, maybe there's a thousand of them, we could sort a
thousand, things pretty quickly.
It's not like we have hundreds of thousands of or millions of
Angles like 3D game has were each.
There's lots of little facets.
So if we can do that sorting that would
Get much faster because then we know we're always fully maximizing the
potential for the card to early out.
Right?
So we turn on the z-buffer but we just won't use it for sorting will
use it for optimization.
Okay.
So the other reason to do this is for Alpha compositing, right?
So let's say that we basically have a we have two things, right?
And again, we want to draw them on top of each other.
So you have to imagine these two things are on top of each other,
right?
We're drawing these
On top of each other.
Here's the top one.
And here's the bottom one.
Right?
So, if I want to draw these two things on top of each other, what
happens if one of them is translucent, so it's got like a part that's
like, only 50% opaque and so it should be able to see this other guy
underneath it.
Right?
Well, if you use the, the depth buffer for sorting, then you have no
idea which, which order these guys come in.
So when you do your raster operations,
Are actually rendering the pixels.
It may be that like, you know, let's say this was red and this was
green.
So it should be a green filter dread that comes in here, right?
So maybe this is let's say this is our Angie.
What's a good?
What's a good way to say this?
Okay, here's a good way to say this.
So this is white.
Right under here.
And this is this is a green filter basically, so it's going to it's
going to take out the blue and the red channels, right?
So let's say we render these, right?
And we don't know which order they come in.
So it may be that when we get to rasterize this this top guy who's
translucent, right?
It may be case one.
Is that we have white pixels underneath us and case 2, is that we have
black pixels underneath us.
Okay?
We need to write one piece of rendering code, that no matter which of,
these happens, right?
In case one it produces the green filtered white.
So it produces a green, right?
And in case two, it also produces a green eventually.
So that when you go and draw this bottom guy later, right?
Because in this case, the bottom guy already got drawn in this case,
it didn't, when you go and draw the bottom guy, you now know that your
depth tests failed, right?
So you were behind it, but you're still going to draw because of
something and you need to be able to go say, oh, okay, what would this
guy have done filter wise?
Right, but now you're in trouble because you don't actually know that
this guy was a filter.
You're just looking at pixels.
And so you're like, oh they were black with a black if someone filled
them.
So you'd have to use the destination Alpha Channel.
Which is okay because obviously there is a destination Alpha channel
to make that determination for you and then you have to worry, okay.
We've got three things stacked.
On top of each other.
What do you put in the destination Alpha Channel?
Because maybe you got three of them stacked and this guy came first,
then this guy, then this guy how do you make those Blends work out?
It just gets to be a nightmare.
And in fact, I think it's an unsolvable problem.
Like you can't actually ever compute the right result.
If you always draw in the same order, no matter which way it is, you
can either do it with no extra storage.
So you don't even need us now, stationed off at all.
If you draw back to front, right?
Because if you always know that you're drawing
In the back things first and the front things.
Last, you're going in that order.
You can always just draw the pixels down and then when you do your
blend you just grab the pixels, little their blend them and write them
back.
And that just always works.
If you want to go front to back.
It's a little bit harder.
You need to use that destination, Alpha to store.
How much Alpha still available as you blend down, but it's still a
totally wrote operation.
You just grab, look at the destination Alpha, use that to do the blend
and then put it back.
So if we do our front-to-back sort we can do perfect Alpha
compositing,
And perfect early out and we'd be crazy not to, right.
So we never have to deal with any of this nonsense.
3D games, have it real hard.
They have to, they basically have to separate their things into
translucent and non translucent and sort the translucent ones and draw
them to separate pass.
It's really bad.
There are some methods for order independent transparency, but none of
them are perfect yet.
They all have down signs.
Would it be entirely possible to completely reconstruct the current
code by following every episode of the series without pre-ordering the
game?
Yes, we don't do anything off stream.
So every last line of code.
There's a video of me typing it in.
Keep in mind that the art assets obviously are you can't recreate.
I mean you could try to repaint them, I guess.
Do you think that I as a totally new person of program, you'll be able
to follow along with the pace you are working at doing rapid changes
to the code without sometimes telling us why I think I almost always
try to say why I just don't explain it in detail.
If it's something we've already kind of talked about.
So, yes, I think you can.
If you start at day one, if you jump in right now, no, absolutely not.
You have to start at day one, because it's impossible for me to
explain everything every time.
We would never get anything done.
So I have to say once I've explained, for example, how vector addition
works.
I'm never going to mention that again.
I just expect that, you know, and if you didn't know, you should go
back to the video where we talk about it and make sure you understand
it.
Right?
So that's definitely true.
But if you actually started day one, I try to make sure that explain
everything at least once.
And if I haven't explained at least once, that's a good thing to ask
him to Q&A.
You never explained how this thing works and I'll explain it.
So we always plan everything at least once.
Is there ever going to be a moment of reflection at some point in the
future where you provide a somewhat high level overview of the engine
components we've encountered so far?
What they will provide and why we need them.
Yes, so that's exactly what we're doing right now is trying to get to
that moment of reflection meaning.
We don't know what the engine components are or what we need from
them.
Until we've actually tried making, something that does all the things
we might want to do.
So that's exactly what we're doing right now.
So at the end of this, which again, I think we'll still be another
couple weeks because we only do an hour a day, so
People.
You like, we haven't even spent a full week on prototyping, this code.
So, you know, you have to imagine that that's almost no time.
Right?
Like only a week's worth of programming because we did about, we did
about a half a week or two thirds of a week, was building a win32
platform layer.
And then the rest of the time which is sort of, you know, almost a
week.
Now, I guess not quite, I don't know how much it's been is just doing
this prototyping so we can see what our Engineers to do.
That's just not that much time.
So we need to give
A little more time.
So we can get all the pieces in place.
And once we see what they all are, then we will definitely do that.
Where we'll go.
Okay.
Let's see what we got.
And let's think about how we want to design the engine to do all these
things.
I think it would be really cool.
If you can't find a smooth scrolling room based camera combination.
Yeah, so, I've been kind of thinking that the screw is going, is kind
of nice.
I don't know.
So, what we may do is something like Outdoors, it's smooth scrolling.
But indoors, it's room, based.
I want really want to have rooms because I like rooms.
I really want to have screen locked rooms because I really like that
about Zelda.
And so maybe what we'll do is like the Overworld Scrolls, but the
dungeons are rooms that you fight through.
I don't know.
We'll see.
That's
You can play around with.
It's like I said, I want to make sure the engine handles both.
Just watched people can see how you do them.
And so so we're supporting them either way, but I'm not sure what the
game will actually use in the end.
Is the translucent things you were talking about hard to do on to DUI.
Do you write the UI in the same Z buffer?
Or is it separate?
So usually you I is easier to sort because again, you kind of know
exactly the order it should be drawn in already because it's already
structured.
So typically UI elements you just know like okay.
Here's the UI elements constructed with this goes on top of this goes
on top of that.
So typically you don't really need the z-buffer at all when you're
doing UI.
You would only use it.
Like I was saying, same thing for here, where you would use it for
acceleration, only you wouldn't probably need it for sorting.
Let's see.
I don't see any other questions related to stuff.
We've done.
so, I think
Well, we may be done early this morning.
Everyone can go get breakfast.
It would seem
And by the way, looking at the chat there.
Yes, I agree with Garland.
Oh, Bloom, I think scrolling rooms are a bad idea.
I liked, I liked locked rooms.
Personally.
I shouldn't say bad idea.
I just don't like them, but I do like scrolling occasionally.
So maybe like I said, we'll have like the Overworld map scroll or
something.
I don't know.
We'll figure something out.
Will you be implementing more memory handling code?
And if yes, what kind of things, honestly, probably not.
You've seen almost all the memory management.
We really need to do for the for the entire shippable game.
The free list thing that I did.
The other day that took 10 seconds is mostly all I almost ever need.
So yeah, memory management is like a non-issue.
It's why I always get so confused when people talk about garbage
collection.
I'm like, what problem are you even solving in your code?
I have no idea.
Looks like stacks and free list.
Is it?
Everything in the game can be written with a sack and a free list and
they're trivial to implement and they're very robust and easy to use.
And so maybe like I guess one thing is the stack stuff.
I haven't really done in Earnest.
So you'll see me write a stack thing, especially when we do the
renderer, but but yeah, memory management is Trivial.
It's just not something you think about in a game ever and
Yeah, I I really just don't know why people program that way, it's
something and it's not like it's like only novice programmers for in
that way.
Like I see, you know, like you'll get, you know, the Unreal Engine or
something does, you know, like 100,000 string allocations a frame or
these sorts of things, right?
I have no idea why they program that I literally have none and those
are like, professional high-end programmers.
They obviously know what they're doing and just they just that's the
way they program.
It's really weird to me.
It's like so foreign.
So obviously, it's okay.
I mean you can be someone who has crazy memory management stuff going
on every frame.
I just, it's causes so many headaches.
I just don't know why you do it and it has impacts on your performance
and it's all this problematic stuff.
So, and it makes it harder to find your lie, you know, you can have
leaks a lot more.
There's a lot more potential for leaks or weird things.
And yeah, all I can say is, I don't understand it.
Because what you see me doing this dream, so far is like 50% of all,
the memory management.
I'll ever do.
And like I said, Stacks are the only other thing that we'll put in
there probably.
If you do a bounding.
Ox, which is an inset x amount of M.
Tiles from the room Edge, you could use the Collision of the player
with the bounding box to start smooth scrolling to the Next Room, Etc.
Yeah.
I mean, the thing is, I don't want the player to be able to see what's
in the Next Room before he enters.
It is why I don't want a smooth scroll rooms.
I want you to just snap on to the next room and be locked in like a
traditional Zelda Style game.
I want that happening.
So I don't want smooth scrolling in the dungeons.
That makes sense.
How will we be handling resolution variance?
Well, in a 2d game there's not a lot.
We can do.
I mean will run fine on 4K monitors, but our art is only at a certain
going to be at a certain resolution when the game ships.
And so I think the art maybe use me.
I tried to make sure that the Arts Peck.
Was roughly 4K safe.
Meaning if you're on a very beefy machine with a ton of fill rate,
because obviously for a Sprite game, it's all about fill rate.
There won't be very many polygons, you know, vertex throughput is is
irrelevant.
So it's all about memory bandwidth.
If you got a high memory bandwidth card and you want to play it for K.
I think the Arts should hold up relatively well there.
But again, when you do a 2-D game, you kind of just have to
pick some resolution, you're drawing the art at and you're not going
to get you can't really do anything to get better than that.
You know, that's just where you're at.
What kind of error handling logging?
Do you have in place now?
And how will that possibly change?
So we don't have any, we don't have that yet.
That will be something that we do.
As part of the renderer pass.
We have no error handling or logging.
If there was a little there was a like you could output debug string
in the win32 layer.
I think we did.
For some things, but it's not good.
It's not, it's just, we've just just a trivial, like, debug output
thing.
So, we will be actually doing a fair bit of that.
We will be implementing our own like tray system, but that's going to
come a little bit later down the line right now.
We don't really need much in the way of debugging because we're just
doing simple code.
And we're not trying to, we're not trying to make the code right now,
very bulletproof or anything like that either.
This is just sort of the test code.
And so
We really just don't need those features yet.
Why are strings such a problem for so many engines?
I have no idea, no idea.
How hard is it to Port a 32-bit game engine to compile a 64-bit output
client?
If the original game splits executables to support to surpass the for
Gig cap?
Splits executables to suppress the forged cap.
Who does that?
Is that a thing that people do?
What games split executables to.
So that they can have more than four gigs total allocated?
I'm interested to know.
I've never heard of that.
Zelda had scrolling when you transition between rooms are going to
have something similar.
No, I wanted it.
Like I said, Binding of Isaac style, where you come into a room, you
just see that room instantly and it's like, you're locked in it.
Would you mind giving a brief walkthrough of the memory management
going on right now in the code from the from the game boots and
forward?
Yeah, it's really very simple.
We allocate one block of memory.
So if you look inside,
well, I just draw a diagram.
So what happens on boot is we basically allocate a giant block of
memory, right?
And right now we haven't really given any thought to how big we want
to be like, basically, this is the the, the memory requirement for the
game.
So if we say that the game requires 2 GB to play, let's say, then this
is going to be a 2 gigabyte block and that's what the game will run
in, right?
It's really gonna be a little less than that.
So if we say that the game is, you know, two gigs to play, then it
would be a 1.5 GB block.
We'd leave some room for you.
Obviously, so everybody that is that's what happens.
And then what happens is the game itself basically uses that memory in
this going to partition it right now.
We have it split.
There's a transient section and a
Action.
And I haven't really talked about what those are going to be for yet.
So I'll leave out that discussion for now because that's coming later
for right now.
We're dealing with this section, only the permanent section for the
game.
Basically, all it does is it sticks.
All the stuff that needs into the permanent section.
So, you know the entities go in here or whatever and the tile chunks,
right?
And basically, there's just an arena which just pushes things on here
and right now, nothing ever gets Freed at the
Except for tile chunk occupancy.
So basically, like tile chunks can have an entity like can store like
entities that are in them and those can grow or Shrink.
And so sometimes you don't need as much space for a child trunk.
So we have one free list, which is like a free list for for entity,
occupancy, child shock.
Which just points into wherever the first free one is and those are
daisy-chained together.
So whenever you want to get a new one, you just grab it off of this
free list.
That's all we do.
As we go forward, it will not get much more complicated than this.
The transient section will basically be about storing Stacks that we
use for computation.
And for storing assets like sound that can be reloaded in anytime and
so don't have to persist and that's it.
Like I said, memory management is a non-issue.
Especially if you're making a game that's 2D, but even if you're
making a game the 3D really it's just it's just a non-issue.
It is not something you should think about.
It is something that should be really obvious exactly how it works and
basically free list and stocks should get you everything you need.
And that basically gets you essentially allocation list.
Meaning there's no work done per allocation.
There's like one if there's like an F on a pointer to see if there's
something in the free list.
That's all you should need like if an increment
That's your entire memory allocator.
And if you're doing something more complicated than that, I would love
to see the reason because I don't know what it would be.
I've rarely come across the thing that you can't Implement in this
way.
Why is it impossible to resize a raster image?
And why does everything have to be rasterized for drawing?
Why can't textures be vector-based?
Well, textures can't be Vector.
B Vector based by definition because they are.
You know, a texture by definition is a storage set of pixels.
But if you're asking why you can't have vector-based stuff, you can if
you want to the problem is its lower, right?
I mean that's that's the problem.
If you want an equal amount of fidelity.
The number of vector elements in, there is very, very high, but you
can rasterize those on the graphics card if you want to using stencil
buffer.
And so on the real problem, a lot of the
With rasterization is the fill region definition.
So typically, if you have artists want to actually do vector-based
stuff, they create bezier curves, right?
That are defining the boundary of something and those curves are
typically concave.
So you have to first probably processing to be convex if you want it
to be fast and then you need to triangulate these.
If you want it to be fast and to some certain level of tessellation
and then you need to add.
Add fins for anti-aliasing on the edges unless you want to use multi
sample, blah, blah blah.
Whereas textures are just you have the image and all you have to do is
sample from it and draw.
So you can draw a lot more textures, a lot more quickly than you can
Vector images, because they're just a lot more processing for the same
amount of fidelity that has to happen.
So anything that uses
Actors will be way slower than something that uses textures for the
same resolution.
And so you have to really get something back from it.
You have to really want that resizing and most of the time, you don't
really want that resizing.
It's not really that relevant because normally monitor resolution
doesn't increase that much overtime.
You know, how long has it been since and we you know to get from 1920
by 1080 to the 4K.
It's not even here yet.
Like most people don't have that.
It's been its many, many, many, many years.
So it's unclear why you really would want to ship the game that looked
worse, because it was in Vector.
Just so you could rescale it later because it will look worse because
you'll just have you'll be able to do less with these right?
You just have you just have less horsepower.
Couldn't rebuild handmade CPP and win32 handmade CPP in separate
threads.
Is there a way to pipe the error messages in a sane way using the
build bat approach.
Oh, so you just want to Billow?
Okay, you want to like build and not wait for one build and then build
the other thing because, yeah, you could totally do that.
I just don't know why we would.
Our build time is our turnaround time.
We don't care how long it takes to build the win32 one.
Most of the time, we only cuz we don't ever touch it.
So we only really care how long it takes to build the first one.
So, I don't know that building a multiple threads actually it would if
anything would hurt us because it would increase the disk bandwidth at
the same time that we're trying to do the compiled of the thing we
actually care about.
So I think we don't want to do that would be my answer.
But yeah, you probably could
SWTOR.
Does it talking about the 32-bit splits into two separate processes?
SWTOR Star Wars the Old Republic?
Okay.
So it splits up into two separate processes.
Got that's really odd.
I've never heard of that technique.
I mean it make when you say it, I'm like, okay, I see how you would do
that.
You, you know, you're trying to basically have more memory.
So you're sort of your sort of implementing your own address,
windowing extensions, at that point.
Doesn't sound like a very good idea to me.
I think you just want to stream more intelligently, but maybe I don't
know.
Maybe they had a good reason.
It doesn't sound.
Like a good idea to me, but, you know, I don't know.
I've never tried that.
Let's see, Binding of Isaac, does have scrolling between rooms albeit
a very quick transition.
Early.
True.
I didn't know that.
Let's find out.
So, if I go to northernlion?
Pretty much, sure.
I will get paid Channel visitors.
I'm northernlion, and I wanted to go Binding of Isaac.
But, of course, we have to watch ads because it's YouTube heaven
forfend.
All right.
Well, we'll let that go ahead and catch up while I look at other
questions.
What is the drawing app or using?
We are trying Mischief.
I have not purchased it yet.
I'm using the free 15 day trial or whatever, but it seems to be
working pretty well except for this one bug.
So I was going to buy it.
I think I like it a lot because you can do this.
Like, I wish we had done it from day one because we have the whole
diagram here which is pretty darn cool.
Right?
But so I don't know like maybe I'll try saving it and we'll just see
if we can have all the diagrams go together.
I don't know.
That'd be kind of fun.
But so I'll probably buy it.
It's been working out pretty well and I'll just ask them if they can
maybe fix that bug with the alt-tab.
All right.
So you're saying this that these Scrolls between rooms.
I didn't know that.
Wow.
You're right.
I never even noticed that.
All right, so maybe I do want scrolling, then I wanted it to feel like
that.
So is, I guess a quick scroll is not a problem.
That is, it is crazy how fast that is?
It's so fast.
I didn't even remember it was there.
So yeah, I'd be okay with that because I never noticed it being
annoying in Binding of Isaac.
And so, I think that as long as we kept it to that, I'd be fine with
it.
I'm totally fine with that.
I just don't want the player to have time to think about what's in the
Next Room before.
Were they actually have to deal with it potentially and maybe
sometimes I do.
I mean, I could, I could believe that.
Maybe once you go that route, maybe you get power-ups.
That allow you some time to look first.
That could actually be a thing.
But yeah.
All right.
Thanks for pointing that out.
I'll somehow, I mean, I played a lot of Binding of Isaac.
I didn't even never really notice that it never occurred to me, that
they were actually scrolling.
I wonder was that only in rebirth or was that in the original one as
well?
Because because I didn't really play rebirth, very much.
I was not a rebirth fan.
I like the original.
I don't know if I can get a video of the original Binding of Isaac,
not rebirth.
Maybe this is that.
Oh, the ads.
It's just like ad tastic in here.
I really want to feature.
I can just pay for YouTube and not have to.
Yes.
It was in both of them, which is crazy.
I never, I literally never way.
If you asked me, I would have said it didn't have that.
All right, so I think we're done.
We have we have finished up on the stream.
So I'm going to go ahead and wrap it up for today.
I wonder if we should go ahead and save our giant drawing to the
desktop here.
And we'll just say handmade diagram will save that.
Let's see how big that is, too, because I assume it's saving it
vector-based because I'm pretty sure that's how that program works.
So, let's see here.
Did I not say this to the desk?
There?
It is.
Okay properties.
So it's pretty small.
So we might be able to just do all the rest of the diagrams.
On here, maybe I should start being more careful about how I label
them and then we'll just tap it.
Like post this file somewhere for people to download because people
had asked about that before.
Yeah, I don't know.
Now, it seems like that's actually plausible, right?
All right.
So thank you, everyone for joining me.
For this morning edition of handmade hero.
Thank you for getting up early.
I know I had trouble getting up early.
I wasn't, I went to bed pretty late.
Last night.
It was a bit rough.
It's true, but I'm glad you showed up because I had fun programming
with you.
As always.
I'm glad we started.
I'm glad we added V3 and V4 s today.
So on Monday, I think a p.m.
Pacific Standard time again on Monday, for those of you who'd, like to
come back for next.
We will go ahead and finish out our V3 and V4 structs there so that we
can stop having to pass things around when as like a V, 2 plus Z and
stuff like that.
So I'm looking forward to cleaning that up.
It was bugging me and I just finally decided today.
We got to fix it.
So I did.
And I think that'll be good.
So we will continue down.
We've got hit points on our guy.
Now, we can probably add hit points to our monstar as well.
And then we could add some way for them to fight which I think would
be good.
And that's the sort of stuff that we need to do next week and you
know, maybe add a power up those sorts of things.
We got to start adding those things.
We can see how they go make that entity class really large basically.
Well, it's not even a it's just a bag of bits of this point.
Calling it a class is very high.
Falutin.
I would say RNA
Our entity bundle of datas and we want to start thinking about how
we're going to deal with that as well.
And so that's that's really the point that we're trying to get to
having a bunch of behaviors, having a bunch of data that's in there.
And then how are we going to start breaking that apart?
So we don't have to store all of the data that could possibly be for
every entity on every entity because that would be intractable very
quickly.
I would think so.
We'll see, that's the kind of stuff.
We need to figure out and will be figuring out next week.
I hope you'll come back and join us.
Monday p.m.
Pacific Standard Time.
Same place here on Twitch.
Yeah, and I hope to see you all there.
If you would like to follow along at home.
You can do so by pre-ordering the game on handmade hero dot or kit
comes with all the source code.
So every night you can go download the source code that I did that day
and play around with it yourself, which is kind of a handy way to
learn just having something you can kind of play around with and see
what happens is really pretty good for if your
Learn the concepts that we teach on the Stream.
So if you want to check that out, please do if you want to support the
video series.
We also have a patreon.
You can do that's up there.
We have a tweet bot that tweets the schedule.
So if you want to be always know what the schedule is, you can go grab
out there and then we also have a news and Forum site, which you can
check out which has good stuff.
You want to go view the old episode, that's got a great place to do
that episode guide.
It's got a coding resources page that Sports to Linux and Mac that
people have done that.
I highly recommend.
Checking out if you're trying to follow
Long, I different platform already, before we get to those ports,
people have already done.
So you can just grab that part of the platform layer and then follow
along, just like as if you were on Windows.
And and then finally there's a form up there.
So you can post questions and talk about serious, which is a great
place to get help from people and I answer questions there as well.
So yeah, definitely check it out and have a great weekend and I hope
to see you back here on Monday.
Take it easy, everyone.