Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on stream.
Today is day 282.
Yesterday, we implemented room based movement, scrolling for our
camera and I'm not sure exactly what we're going to do today because
we're basically working on, you know, sort of how game code is going
to happen inside our game.
Like the stuff that actually is the logic that is makes up the design
of the game.
If you will as opposed to most of the stuff we don't have it here
which is trying to
Like core engine Concepts, what we were doing.
So we're kind of into that other Zone and so what I'd like to do today
is continue down that path.
And right now we I think probably what we should do is take a brief
step back and just go through.
Now that we have everything sort of working.
The way that I envisioned it would sort of skeletally, maybe this
clean up that code, and make sure that it's all happening in the
places that we want it to happen.
And in the way that we want it to happen so that we can move forward
on that.
And
Like I said, the way that we're going to have to approach this is we
probably have to get a little further down the road of actual game
before we could really do much more in terms of making decisions about
how we're going to do stuff.
Like for example, right now I'm not even actually doing any entity
packing.
I'm just copying entities in two places as if they were being packed
and so on a lot of that stuff, I think will persist because we just
want, we just don't want to start over, engineering a sec.
And if I'm not certain about what exactly it's going to entail.
So right now, we're still a little bit early, as far as game code is
concerned to make any hard decisions about stuff, but we're getting a
little further.
Anyway, I'm going to jump in there and just see what suits my fancy
and that's case.
And I think my suspicion is I think I mentioned this at the end of the
last dream, clean a little things up, and then start to work on sort
of the structural aspects.
Let's actually make real rooms some rooms stacked on top of each
other.
Some rooms next to each other, the way that we actually want them to
be and and get that encoding correct with the 3D in the physicality of
it because there's like I think a lot of that code was just for me
initially made our first attempts at making stuff work.
We just have some stuff that's kind of residual in there.
Like how we move entities how their Collision is structured that sort
of stuff, you know, needs to kind of be upgraded.
And so if that's like what I kind of think we probably need to focus
on before moving any further.
Alright.
Today like I said is day to 82.
So if you want to follow along at home packed day 281 source code
that's what I'm starting with here and what I will do briefly as just
run the game and show you where we are at the moment.
Here we go.
So yeah, like I said, you know, right now we've got our ability to
kind of go through rooms now and surprise.
Feels kind of nice to do that.
My only sort of concern with it is, it's very quick, right?
It's very Speedy that transition from room to room and I feel like for
a Snappy action game like this, though, I don't know.
I feel like that's sort of warranted.
So I'm not really sure that we want to slow it down.
Obviously, we could slow it down if we wanted to, and so, I don't
know, we'll have to see over time whether we want a tune that to
something slower or not, but it feels
He's pretty good as you go from room to room.
Now, I'm actually enjoying that that sense of motion quite a bit and
you know, your character doesn't pause your character Still In Motion
while you're doing it, which is also kind of nice.
So it doesn't feel like a stall feels like actual progression through
the world, right?
So that's nice too.
So anyway what I was trying to get across before though is that you
know, we don't really have a solid model for how we want to do
Collision stuff now.
Because like I said, we're sort of into the stuff that's actually the
way the game will really work and the way that I want to have the
Collision stuff work is it is kind of integrating important and
there's a couple things that we also want to support.
Basically there's going downstairs and going
there's are two operations that are, you know,
How should I put this?
So, going downstairs and going upstairs, are things that I do want to
have happen in the game.
Like it's things like Binding of Isaac, going downstairs is kind of
nice.
The way that it works you just kind of hop down a whole but there's no
going back upstairs.
And in Zelda, this was never really a thing.
Zelda.
Really doesn't super distinguish between going downstairs and just
moving, right?
So like if I'm in a, if I'm in like a room or something, you know,
typically what will happen is, I'll just jump like this and like, you
know, this part of the room will be drawn as if it was higher.
This part is drawn as if it's lower and that is the act of going down
just that, you know motion, right?
Whereas I kind of want the
Fucking I actually want, you know, to have this concept of stacking
where I jumped down and I actually have the world come out at me and
that layer peels away, which we had working in the game before but as
a smooth ramp kind of a thing.
Well the heroes now kind of a Hopi dude.
So what I want to do is I want to also make sure that we get that sort
of concept in there.
Now, 54 in its final form, which is how do you hop between two
different heights, if that makes sense?
And those are very discreet.
Meaning there isn't going to be like, there can be variability in the
heights of things on this play field.
Meaning we can you know sort of Jitter what those Heights are.
In fact, I guess now I think about it we could Jitter those just at
the moment.
If we wanted to, I think, right?
So in here, when I do an ad wall command, for example, we pass like
ABS, add wall ABS XYZ, you know, I could give it something here.
That was a random, random number
I don't know what our random series is at the moment.
Let's take a look.
It's just at series.
Series.
Sounds like you're going to start interacting with an Apple product.
So if I wanted to, you know, I could give some displacement here.
I think we might even have a random between.
I don't know if we do if we don't, but let's say you could do up to a
quarter meter in either direction, right?
So what I think we could do is we can actually stagger the locations
of these things as well.
I just want to double check that but you can see in here when I do
sort of this chunk position, begin grenadine.
That sort of stuff.
When we actually have this entity, we can give that entity and offset,
since when it gets packed into the world, that offset would be obeyed
or rather.
I guess it would be right here.
That offset can actually include a z offset, right?
So let's take a quick look at that.
I just want to see if that works because we didn't really talk about
that.
So, those look like they did get the Z offset, but they don't seem to
really draw as if they did, they are sorting as if they did, but not
actually being displaced as if they did, which is a little bit weird
to say the least.
I'm not sure why that is.
that may be a bug in our code for the Hop for the
Points.
But I'm not sure.
So we'll have to look at that.
Let's see, are these actually displaced?
I guess I could tell by making them be displaced much more severely.
So let's just double check.
So let's say, I just place them up to a meter, which is absurd.
Oh, whoops, I made a slight error there, admit that, that was an
error.
I didn't mean to do that to the wall.
I meant to do it to the floor, my bad, you know, just you gotta
sometimes make some, you make an error, you know, sometimes make an
error, I made an error.
I apologize for that upfront.
That was, that was a
A bad.
I did a bad thing and I apologize.
So, I'm going to pass random series here.
Yeah, rough day.
Let's put it that way.
It was a rough day so I'm going to go ahead and now try this.
See if I can do it actually correctly.
By displacing the item, we really wanted to displace.
There's an idea for you.
So when we do add standard room, I will now pass along the, the
serious that we are using and then I will remove that code from add
wall since that was not in any way my intention.
But hey, at least it looks like it was working.
I just was looking at the wrong values.
All right, so now these things actually are displaced, which is good,
that's what I wanted.
And so they can be displaced, right?
And that's good.
So as you can see, we can still Hopalong them just fine.
And that's all good.
Right?
And what's interesting is, you can because the floor actually has
Collision.
I can't hop into some of those, I have to hop around them a little and
then onto them because they actually have Collision volumes, which is
exactly the point.
I was trying,
Only get two.
So what we want to do here, right?
Is we want to start thinking of these a little bit more specifically
and starting to treat those diseases.
Correct.
And also we have these sort of sorting problems.
Like, before you can see, when this thing gets high.
Remember we hacked the Sorting for the for the dude.
So we want to start to coalesce all that stuff and have a very, very
specific way in which we handle all of these, the Z, displacements and
going between levels.
So that it's not as ad hoc, and we don't have like tons of problems
with it throughout the whole development, right?
We just don't want
Want to.
the point here is mostly that you're going to build a lot of code once
you start making the game, proper
You will build a lot of code on these systems as they stand and so if
you make some sloppy decisions there, you're going to live with those
sloppy decisions throughout, right?
And so, we want to limit the number of those we have, by saying if
there's ones, we can see the obvious right solution to here.
We should do that first, right?
We should actually fix those beforehand.
So that looks works.
Great there.
You can see our hopping code is pretty awesome, right?
It always Nails it.
One of the nice things about procedural animation to is that it's
never wrong.
Like regular animation, is it always hits?
Its Mark said oh he's like reacts properly and all that sort of stuff,
right?
You do have to worry about foot slide or anything like that.
So anyway that's all looking great.
And so I'm glad that that all worked.
Oh wow, I got high enough to go up.
One camera level.
Did you see that?
That was awesome.
All right, I should I'm sorry this is not productive.
Playing around with this.
But you know, sometimes you just you play around with stuff.
I kind of want to see what if we always bias it upwards.
So that it's eminently possible to get to the next floor.
I just want to see what happens.
None of these look that high though.
I guess that one, that one's low.
Wait, why would?
I should be looking for a point that's really fat, you know, saying
Bear with me for a moment here.
So, in Sim region,
Let's let's zoom on down.
Zoom on down, don't ask me what that was.
Don't know what happens with the Cameron Z.
We don't even check.
so, this is what
What, how are we doing?
Z motion of the camera.
Do we set the Z motion of the camera to the guy directly during
movement or something?
I mean, we do so we just hard set to the chunk Z, so forget that
that's over.
That's done.
We actually want to have code like this, right?
We want to have code where we can sort of go by go by height
differences there and we want to be able to smoothly interpolate
between those certainly, right?
So let's take a look at how this is actually working because I'm not
actually sure I want to also go into the world code and see what our
tile like, what's our tile.
Sort of Dimension here when we do chunk Tim.
So we have chunk Tim's, we allow fully rectangular, right?
Rectangular prisms, that looks like for our space.
So I think what I'd want to do is just take a look here with the but
the chunk.
Damn actually was I like we still have ground chunk control in here,
goodbye.
So when I create the world which I guess would be in World mode when I
create the world initially I pass it.
What we want those Dimensions to be and so it looks like we say tile
side and M tiled twice the tile side and M oh wait that's the
greatest.
Sorry we do ground buffer with grammar for height.
So this is now irrelevant as well because
Care about the ground buffers lining up with it.
So our world chunk Dimension is going to have to be modified as well
and typical floor height.
The typical floor, height is 3 meters, right?
And that's important because that's how much we would want our camera
to move, right?
So I guess how do I want to treat that?
I want to treat it basically the same way that we're treating, the
other Delta's here.
So presumably there.
Vroom, Delta code here would be, like, whatever the typical floor
height would be, is how much we move, right?
We could just keep these where we say, whatever the world mode is its
typical floor height.
I could just say that, that's how much that Delta is and then, the
apron, I guess would be pretty similar.
I guess.
I don't even need to really change much about how that's working at
all.
I could just say that that's the same here.
And so what I wanted to do is say, well, let's go ahead and treat
these the same and I guess we could even treat it.
Roughly the same in terms of pull in pull out, I think.
So, I'm going to go ahead and do that.
Let's take a look here.
So, if I do this code out and like I said, you can see that this code
has a fantastic amount of similarity to it, which is why I say, I
think I said in the last dream, we should probably take a minute to
condense it down because it can be made much less redundant but I
still I'm just wanting to play around with it, the moment.
So here, if I was to do the room, Delta stuff,
This would allow me to do.
Okay.
So, you know, we're going up a room or here.
We're going down a room.
And then we do the map trunk space.
Right?
So if you look at this this is very, very regular.
So I feel like this could be done with a for I Loop pretty trivially,
right?
And all we would do if we wanted to do that would be to Loop over the
elements.
So for each element we would do one of these right.
Instead of doing like that X is 2 Y is and Dot you know dot whatever
is we would just say like okay instead of dot X we just use ee right.
Whatever the element is that we're on
and then the same thing here, right?
We just say
Is this why does does anyone know why for a coder sometimes inserts?
Like a space when I'm doing stuff?
I don't know why.
I haven't been able to figure that out.
I'm not sure what I'm doing something and it insert a space after I
hit left bracket, but only left bracket.
I wonder if it's something in my custom file that I forgot about,
which seems likely, but I just don't, I haven't had time to go.
Look at it.
Like, it does it but I don't know.
Like, I can't always reproduce it.
Like it just did it but I don't know.
So I feel like maybe it's not just my bug.
Maybe there's two.
I don't know.
Alan, if you're out there.
You got any ideas?
I don't know what that's from.
Okay.
So let's see, new camera P map into chunks space new camera P applied
Delta.
So that does Cascade properly.
So, I think,
That's a complete solution for that part of the equation, right for
this part.
I'm not sure about it yet.
I'm going to put in the Z here and because the Z we need to do some
slightly different things, which is to say that.
Now, the bounce obviously can't be there because the balance is going
in the direction that we would want to go.
So, there shouldn't be any Z happening at all for, very obvious
reasons, but we should still be able to condense this.
Down.
So that's not a huge deal either way, but just something to just
something to note.
All right, so I'm just going to go ahead and recompile this here.
We condense that down and now we've also got Z Motion in there.
Unfortunately, in order to actually try hopping up.
I'm gonna need a little bit more of a, of a ramp kind of thing.
Probably to see what happens if I do that.
So, what I'm going to do is I'm just going to go ahead and create
A ramp in that standard room just because why not, right?
So here's World mode.
And when I do add standard room, I'm gonna do a thing where instead of
doing this random, right?
I'm not going to do it random.
I'm going to say that if offset X is greater than zero, then I'm going
to apply an offset Z.
So that basically the whole world is kind of a ramp that goes up.
Maybe we'll also do.
You know if offset Y is greater than 0?
So, like the bottom, I'm so the top upper like this
Corner upper right?
We'll have that sort of look to it and so what I'll do there is I'll
just say like okay yeah that ramp will just be oh dear it'll be like
the offset X plus the offset.
Why
And and we'll make that be real.
Let's get real here.
Gotta love that, not very good, set of code analysis.
It's like, hey, it's between negative four, four and negative, eight
and eight.
But for some reason, the expression evaluator couldn't tell that you
couldn't cast at maximum positive or negative 12 to a real.
Go figure pretty sure it can handle it.
Anyway, let's go ahead and run this.
So here we are coming upwards.
Of course, can I actually get there?
Oh, but you know what?
We don't allow ourselves to hop up.
Do we right now?
At least not very large.
We look for things that are below the head.
So if you're higher than the head you can't really hop to it.
Can you, is that true?
So we may have to give ourselves.
I don't know what our rules should be.
Obviously you can't have two things that are you know too high.
But what's the rule going to be for that?
I don't know.
Yeah, I don't know.
Do we prevent that?
Closest distance squared.
well, maybe not
Doesn't look like we're actively preventing that right now though.
So why can't I hop in here?
It looks like I did, it looks like it will never pick those higher
ones, no matter what I try.
Right.
You can see it's only going to the lower ones.
So, I'm not sure why that is.
Why is that?
Hm.
I must have forgotten something about this code or there's just a bug
in it.
Let's see.
Get closest traversable
so, when we do the closest reversible thing here,
That's not going to cause the hopping that's just the head bit.
So here's
here's how this works.
So we are calling get closest reversible, and if it is found, we just
do what we do.
We never reject a move here, right?
I mean, there's no rejection.
So it would be, it would be inside, get closest, reversible.
That would be what the problem would be, right?
And I guess part of the problem might be that since we're taking Z
into account.
I mean it's possible that it never is the closest thing.
I mean it could be right and so I guess I don't know.
But what I would say is we can certainly we can certainly, you know,
test that hypothesis.
If I just assumed that the delta
From the head to the point, which I've computed, which is a full
three-dimensional Delta, if I just 0 at Z value, then I will only be
testing what is the closest point in 2D, right?
And so then I should be able to hop to other things.
And now you can see that I actually do, right?
So I guess the problem is they were just further away.
Now what's interesting about that is that suggests to me that these
things are much higher than I thought they were going to be, did I
mess up that code?
I guess that would already be two meters high.
So, there is that.
Max entity velocity is higher than it should be.
What is the entity velocity Dare?
I ask
So those are much higher.
I guess that's true though.
Those are really, really high to be fair.
So I should probably just tone those down for now because that's
actually a pretty reasonable.
Yeah, I don't think we want anything jumping up quite that much in a
single shot.
All right, so I guess that wasn't really weird.
I guess that was actually what we would have expected, but
Hold, please, because we've got more work to do in that regard.
So first of all, I want to take that ad standard room and I would like
this to not be so much.
So what I'd like to do here is say okay, you know, maybe add like a
tenth of that or I guess like a quarter of that, let's say so that it
doesn't climb up quite so much because if it's going to be 8 plus 4
2012 so like 1.2 meters would be a little too little but you know five
me.
There's maybe isn't too much because we're supposed to be making a
ramp, so let's just let's just see if that's a little calmer.
Yeah.
So that's more reasonable certainly right?
And that works really well.
Okay, so that's fine.
That's all good.
And so I think we can move on to the other stuff that I wanted to work
on there.
For now.
Yeah.
So
Since we have this in here.
Oops, and made that CPP.
Get closest.
There we go.
When we do the get closest reversible, the thing about that is I
probably want to make sure that we don't leave this in here because
obviously
It would be bad if you imagine having a bunch of very like different
heights that you could jump to close to you, it would not
differentiate between like the one that's way, way down there and you
wouldn't want to ever jump to and one that's right next to you.
They would only be looking at their to D Delta.
So first, what I'm going to do is I'm going to say, well let's get rid
of that temporarily and see what happens with the with the more calm
situation.
Okay?
So if the height difference is
Aren't too much.
Then closest point is still pretty good.
It looks like right, that still works pretty well if it would seem
Right.
All right, it's interesting that it ever goes down.
I'm not sure why it goes down like that.
I guess we get just a little bit below zero.
Which again is probably some stuff we want to work on with the camera
code.
But anyway so point being that's actually kind of nice because then we
can still just use total distance and it's probably fine.
Although I don't know like if we want there to be fairly big hops that
that the, the fellow does that wouldn't work as well.
So my see, my my thinking on this anyway,
Is that we probably want to do something a little bit more.
Like whatever the point is that's closest in 2D is greatly preferred,
you know.
So maybe we don't 0 it right but we probably do get rid of a lot of
it, you know, and there's two ways we can do this one is we can take
the head Point Z.
And multiply it by some coefficient.
So that things are effectively squashed in the Z Direction in terms of
picking.
What the closest point is and that seems like a reasonable thing to
do.
The other thing we could do is not if we don't actually want to
compress the entire space, what we can do instead is just compress
just the space right, nearby?
So we could say is like up to one floor away in either direction.
However much.
We want you to hop that we just remove right.
And that would just
Really absolute value - that amount clamp 20, right?
That would be another way of handling it.
I don't know which one of those makes the most sense but I suspect
that the one where we just remove a certain amount of the space is
probably the best so I'm thinking that probably what we would want to
do is say that the head to point Vector is going to be equal to you
know whatever its absolute value.
I'm sorry.
They had to point Z value is going to be whatever its absolute value
was
So you know, now we know okay we know this is positive from zero to
something.
Positive, we'd subtract away whatever we wanted that, you know, and
what should this value B?
We don't really know.
But we subtract away some amount that we're staying like everything
within here is fair game for hopping.
Or something.
And maybe that's a little bit too much.
So let's say it's to or something like this, whatever 1.5 I don't
know, half the floor height, whatever we think you should be able to
hop in one go.
And I don't know what that is so we take whatever that is we subtract
that away and then we clamp that clamp above zero I guess it's how we
would say it right?
And that way we know that it's only going to be values that are above
one that we actually start discriminating based on the Z, right?
So I don't know.
That seems like one way to do it.
I don't know.
Like I said if that's the best way to do it or not, it's hard for me
to determine really but you can kind of you can see roughly how this
goes.
And what's interesting about this too is you can see that we're going
to have some problems.
If we allow hopping between relatively high things, the head of the
character, right?
The head needs to interpolate on the Z just like everything else.
Right?
So there's that as well.
There's also the sort of ancillary question, which is do, we actually
want the spatial warping in X here or do we only wanted and why?
Because you can see how this is a full perspective transform here.
And we probably don't want that for gameplay purposes.
We probably want those to be sort of more in line.
So, again, we've got some work to do there in terms of how we're
handling our
Displacements more specifically, right?
Yeah.
Go little hero.
Go.
I should be able to hop over this wall.
There we go.
Oh man, but it inside the tree now.
All right, anyway.
Yeah, I'm playing around with that a little bit too much instead of
programming.
This is the problem.
Whenever you make something that you enjoy moving around yourself, as
you end up sitting there moving it around and not actually working.
All right?
So,
Let's see here.
Hmm again we have a number of things that we need to be working on
Sosa question of choosing, which ones we want to.
So I think what we want to do is try to tackle like the Z thing and
get that nailed down for good.
Right.
I think that's probably what we want to do.
And the problem that we have here is that we have to
Different kinds of Z values.
And so, what I'd like to propose is that we actually just have this is
this is what I think is what I want to go with.
And it's going to be a bit of a struggle to like move everything over
to it, but I think it's worth doing and like I said, I want to do it
one time and not have to worry about it again.
So this is the plan.
For finals, e.
Okay, so I think what I want to do for the plan, for final Z based on
all the trade-offs and sort of the experimentation we did with ramps,
and all these sorts of things.
What I'd like to do is I would like to say, look, I don't think actual
z-transforms work very well in a 2-D game like this.
I played around with them.
A little, we had going up and down the ramp, it was cool, but there
are just too many problems with it and it creates a sort of like
difficult thing for the
Person to understand who's looking at the game as well, because it's
unclear like what the perspective means.
And it's, it's just confusing.
But at the same time, I really liked that feel of going up and down in
the world, right?
So, I like that idea of coming up and you like you you know you kind
of move up a level.
I like the idea of having that nice scaling transition that happens
there.
So what I think I want to do is make a very delineate, it split that
there is basically a floor Z.
And a, you know, actual Z.
Okay.
And so, what these would be
Is this is something that actually creates perspective.
And this is something that is entirely orthographic.
Okay?
This will be the actual Z in the world, so your actual Z coordinate is
always treated as orthographic.
Z your floor's e.
On the other hand is going to be based on the world chunk, probably,
right?
So what we'll do is we'll just as we already have will say that world
chunks are just slices through the world that you go up and down
between discreetly.
And so, whichever one of these your on, that will
As you two have a transform.
So when we actually set up your end of the transform, we will split it
into two Z's, the actual Z and the floor Z and the actual Z will be in
both places, meaning, right?
Right now we have this thing where like your offset when you pass that
And your transform.
We had this in the renderer, this was effectively
A and this was effectively Ortho Z but that will go away.
Okay?
And what we will actually do is just have actual Z in both places.
So, everywhere is going to use the same Z and then the only thing that
we do
Is we will sift entities based on their floors e and put them into
buckets for the renderer where there's a certain perspective plane
each you know in each bucket, right?
And those buckets will also correspond to our Alpha fade and the
reason also that we need to do that in case you don't remember can
spin a while.
Since we talked about this I do like the alpha fate and I do think I
want to ship it.
So, I don't know if you remember, but as you get higher here,
eventually things are supposed to fade out.
I guess they don't quite fade out very soon because you can see things
below you.
So it's more like things above you.
You know what I can do.
What I could do is say okay, let's actually not do this.
So this way the ramp goes in both directions.
Right.
So things get lower, in addition to getting higher.
So now we should see that Alpha fade happen.
Except we don't.
That's weird.
Hmm.
Well I guess we've got two jobs to do then restore our Alpha fade
first of all.
Because it's, where's the alpha fade?
I must have accidentally nuked it
Cuz there's this Global Alpha value, right?
It's probably that we just haven't updated this code fade, top start
fade.
Bottom start, where do we set those?
Babe top.
So we start at a fifth of the typical floor height, and we end at one
at three-quarters of the typical floor height.
We set the global Alpha based on that.
Well.
I'm also interested to know what if I just set the global a fall to
0.1.
okay, so we know the global
Is working.
So our fade values are just wrong.
We must have updated it and not really paid attention to that when we
were playing around with something else.
So in here, where we do our fade topsy,
what are we looking at?
What value?
We're looking at.
We're looking at the camera relative G position of what an entity.
yeah, so we're saying, hey whatever this entity is ground point is
let's
Let's subtract the cameras location.
And see.
That seems reasonable though.
If the camera relative ground p z is greater than get any ground
point.
I don't really know to be honest, what that even does.
I'm gonna not use that for a second just so I can see what happens if
we use the entities P for a moment.
Come back.
There we go.
So when we compute this and we do a clamp map to range, this is z
value, must not be the Z value that, I think it would be I guess I
don't know specifically what the cameras location is.
So I guess let's step in there and take a look.
There we go.
so, if I take a look at this,
And I say, what is the camera relative round pee?
So the camera relative ground P for this entity.
Is well, is well below.
It's well below where the camera is.
Where is the camera?
cameras 2000, which is what I guess I would expect and What entity is
this
It's a floor.
Which makes sense.
This is probably that first entity.
That's the corner entity anyway, it would it would
I'm up, right?
These are all at zero.
Which is what we would expect.
It is a little odd that I'm not seeing anyone who's like higher.
Right?
Because we should be.
There we go.
so yeah, those people should be fading out right fade top-end Z is 2
point 2 5
And fade top start Z.
Is 1.5.
I think I see what's going on here.
so basically, what's happening, is that the way that we've got it set
up currently
When we move the camera down.
Well, that's still wouldn't explain it.
So I'm going to go ahead because I'm interested to know here.
I want to do standard room.
Well,
I'm trying to think I want to place an entity specifically so that it
would be high enough up that we would see that change and I'm just
trying to think of the best way to do that one is I could place one
specifically that high.
The other thing I should probably do is let me get rid of a bunch of
the entities so when we create, so we don't have as much to think
about when we create the world.
I'll only create one room.
And so we won't have like many, many rooms screen index less than 1.
and so if I was to go set the camera down,
Right between these two.
It's clear that at some point.
I know what a problem is.
So that camera pee.
yeah, duh that camera p is the location that the camera starts at
Right.
So when we apply the offset to the world, we're applying the negative
of the camera to where we're going to place things, right?
If that makes sense.
Although no.
Well, okay, never mind.
That should give us the exact same result.
I don't get it.
I don't
I feel like I must be missing something relatively obvious, but I
don't actually know what that something is, unfortunately.
Because the first I thought that I had it was like, oh well the camera
P.
Probably isn't taking into account the awesome, but it actually,
totally is.
So this value is taking in account that smooth offset that we're
applying.
So, it should be consistent.
It shouldn't be, you know, creating any kind of a weird error there.
I suppose, I could also take a look and
and just look at,
if I was to add a debug value here,
And maybe I'll do this only when it's the hero head.
So that, when we're running.
I can see what that is.
So, here we see the camera relative Grampy for the head, right?
And when we come down like that, you can see that it actually.
It actually chases us down once where a certain distance and that
makes sense, right?
Because when we first hop down, we haven't gone far enough down for it
to start thinking it needs to follow us, right?
It hasn't he reached the apron but once it does reach that apron then
it starts to try and pull us back in, right?
So that looks like a relatively sane value.
And then when I hit the floor, again, on the other side, that all
looks pretty saying,
Okay, so now let's talk about like this right here.
Let's take a look at that guy because we only have one of those.
So we could also be very
That?
Which one that was.
That's the monstar I believe right?
Oops monstar
So now will show whatever the debug is the debug monstar value.
So there's the debug monstar value, right?
So okay.
All right.
Well, that makes it easy.
So I guess really there is no bug.
Our problem is simply that we we don't actually load in the world, one
thing above us, so, it looks like the monstar just disappears.
It gets unloaded, right?
You can see it's not there anymore.
It's just gone.
At that point.
So somehow that entity must be getting evicted.
Because otherwise it would still be printing out.
Something
And instead of spreading out nothing.
So, what happened to our enemies?
And that's what we have to figure out.
All right, so let me take a look.
What's going on in terms of gather in the Z Direction.
How big do we actually want to expand here?
Do we want to do an upper floors?
Hey, look, and I would say, yeah, we probably do for now, so let's go
ahead and do that temporarily and see if that has to do with anything
to do with it.
So hey, now everything's fine again.
Enter Alpha feed is working.
So I guess that was just because we just were purging, we didn't ever
keep those floors in which is kind of I guess I don't know why we
weren't doing that but we just first whatever reason had not been.
All right?
So now I can I want to talk about the part that I actually wanted to
talk about the.
There is a question of should that Alpha fade be happening sooner?
Which I suspect is probably yes, right.
But the part that I wanted to talk about more specifically is what
happens when you have trees that overlap week, you can kind of see
what I'm talking about.
And I mentioned this back when we first were doing this.
So let's go ahead and and create in our standard room, something that
will allow you to see a little more clearly, what's going on?
So when we do add standard room,
Oh, I guess I should say when we do the ad wall stuff.
So this stuff here.
what I'd like to do is say, let's add
Some more walls in here.
I'm going to add some in, I don't know why we're still doing it this
way, but I'm going to add walls and say if tile x equals
I don't know - 2 or I guess - negative 2 would be 3 in this case.
And I guess now.
I think about it, though.
I probably want those on the other side.
Something like that or maybe a little closer.
Just something that we can see as it fades out.
Okay.
So hopefully you can kind of see what's going on here, right?
When I when these fade in and out and this will only get worse as we
have more stuff in the world, right?
Like right now, we just have some placeholder, he kind of things like
some trees or whatever.
But as we get more stuff, this it'll get worse, you can see what
happens.
The alpha value for these things is such
That.
Let me see if I can.
Get an even worse scenario here.
There we go.
The alpha is such that when you draw multiple things on top of each
other, right?
If I was drawing two things on top of each other, I get more coverage
in that area because it's drawing the two trees independently.
And each tree has a certain amount of fade right associated with it.
So as a result, I end up in a scenario where that fade, that amount of
fade right is inconsistent.
And it depends on the amount of overlap, but that's probably not what
we want, right?
It's just kind of looks amateur, right?
It looks like oh I'm just setting all the alpha values down lower but
that's not what we would want.
Our final thing to look like, right.
What we want it to do is we want it to that whole layer to kind of
fade out.
If not all at the same Alpha, then at some artistically decided Alpha,
certainly not just whatever the overdraw happens to be in that area,
right?
That's not a particularly
That's not particularly compelling.
I guess is what I would say as an artistic choice.
So, what I would want to do is, I want to have it so that we Alpha
Fade Out the entire thing as as one group.
And in order to do that, the renderer needs to be able to render those
in passes.
It needs to be able to render all the entities that are in one slice
into into one pass.
And then all the entities that are in another slice into another fast
because there's no way to do it in.
You're going to do something crazy like building fragment list or
something like this.
There's no way to do it.
Other than to basically draw the top layer into one bitmap, draw the
bottom layer into another, and then composite the two with a single
pass that does.
Do the correct Alpha uniformly.
If that makes sense, there's really no other way to do it, especially
not if we want to have multiple layers of this that they're
potentially doing it.
Meaning, you know, a situation where you can have a bottom layer
that's Alpha fading out as it gets further away and a top layer that's
got it.
That's fading in as it's coming down and they're sort of on top of
each other like that.
You know the more things you stack up, the more it would get
intractable to try and figure out tricks that would make this not
happen, okay?
So that's that's that's what we're talking about.
Yeah, so yeah, that's what we need to do.
And that's going to require some some fiddling, right obviously.
So if we take a look at the handmade render group stuff,
we're going to start thinking about how this might go.
Now we probably don't really have to be very specific about this.
What we probably have to do is just expand our notion of sorting to
actually have these two tranches because when we do our list sort and
we already do our stuff where we play with how the sort key gets
generated, right?
We can probably just make it so that our sort stuff with like, sort
bias and that's where stuff we can probably just make it so that this
all comes out in the wash, and all we have to do is insert something.
Into the render list that's like, hey, the alpha value when you get
here, it changes right?
Like the alpha value for all for this plate changes.
We probably don't actually need to make an entirely separate path for
saying, hey draw, all these things to this target draw, all these
things to another Target.
I think
Now why might we not want to do that?
Well, the reason we might not want to that is if we wanted to start
using the multiple Alpha pass for other things, then you could imagine
wanting to have those other things potentially be rendered.
Such that their depths stuff was not related.
Like their depth sort was not related to how they were having that
happen.
And so in that point you would want the ability to say hey this goes
into a certain bin, this goes into a different bin, whatever right?
Who, if you're like, I did not get much sleep last night.
Thanks to mail jet.
Anyway, I am not sure.
So I'm not sure what I want to do about that.
So I I mean I could see an argument either way for having them go.
for having actual targets and, and having something different since we
have
I guess it does occur to me that we do have
as part of the Sorting process clip rectangles.
So we already kind of have this idea that everything that goes into
the entry header has a clipped rectangle index.
What we could do is expand that clipped rectangle index to also
include a Target, right?
So when we have render entry cliprect what we could say is, oh yeah,
in addition to cliprect you also get a something here is like, you
know,
Render Target or something like this and then, you know, we can stack
up and render targets and say, okay, there's red a target for the
floor.
There's a render Target for this floor around her for this 40, and for
this floor, and at the end, we do Blitz each render Target on top of
each other kind of a thing, right?
So we could do that because we already support that sort of indexing
per entry where we say, what's the state of this thing, as it kind of
goes out the door.
So, I don't know, I guess I will say, that's a good place to call it.
It's a lot to think about, but that's what we want to do tomorrow,
because we'd really like to get the Z situation completely sorted.
I think, at least, in my opinion.
So I'm gonna go ahead and go to the Q&A.
And that's what we should.
We're gonna have to come in tomorrow with a good idea of how we want
to start tackling that.
They blow that up down camera movement, looks so cool.
I do hope the train height of the rooms makes good use of this.
Well I don't know.
Yeah I guess we could we could sort of leave it in so that as you go
up it actually sort of moves up a little bit to follow you.
Even if you're not leaving the room I definitely want it to
transition.
Like when you jump it's like a big transition to go to.
The next room is like I jump in a hole and we go down.
But yeah, I don't know, like we could use it for other sorts of things
as well.
Insofar, as could you do something with glm injeel?
Max blend equation for the alpha.
I mean not that I can think of.
Do you have a suggestion?
I mean, the fundamental problem is it's the same as the order
independent transparency problem.
The fundamental problem is that you have a surface being seen through
another surface.
Right?
And so the equations for that typically are going to involve going,
all right?
I'm looking through this color, so it should tint.
Whatever the color is below it or something like that, right?
and if I've got another one in between,
then I need to know that these two, even though I could draw them in
any order, I need to know that these two are going to be
are going to be combined in terms of their amount that they're going
to fade out.
So, whatever I would have seen, they need to fade out.
Now since we sort everything, we do have the advantage of knowing that
we're always going to draw them either this, this this or this this,
this depending on whether we choose to always draw front to back or
back to front.
So the question is well, alright, if I was always going to draw front
to back, is there some way that I could put something like in the
destination Alpha channel that lets me know?
When this guy is getting drawn that he should not add to the amount
that this guy got drawn to or something.
But I just don't know how, you know, what part of the color
contribution when you draw that final guy like, you know, say I'm
drawing back to front.
I draw, you know, the background, which is full-color.
I draw the next thing, which is the out, the faded out tree.
I modify that color.
And yeah, I can store something in the alpha Channel and the
destination.
I'll Channel I could.
And then I'm coming in and doing another Tree on top of it.
How do I know that the results should be as if I took, because the
correct result is that trees color right there?
Alpha blended with the thing underneath without the interceding tree?
Because remember, it would have
You included that other tree?
How do I know what to what value to take out of the RGB channel in
order to get it back to, what it used to be before the other tree was
there, right?
And it seems to me like it's just an impossible problem.
Like you can't because you have no idea what the out, what the RGB
value used to be.
And that's the problem.
To the person who said can you create the word of Warcraft game?
Like I would just like to say right now that blizzard totally needs to
create a game called word of Warcraft and it's basically like it's a
one of those games like Bookworm or letter Linker or whatever.
And you would just have to use all words that come from the warcraft
Universe to like beat enemies in spelling or something, right?
That would be so funny.
If the Contour of your entities wasn't anti-aliased, you could have
used the depth buffer and reverse, the render order of the entities
being faded front to back.
But alas is hard to do properly with the alpha blending around the
Contours.
well, a couple things, first of all, we don't really want to use the
depth buffer for that probably
Although I guess if we're, if the only solution is to do another pass
and it, you know, because you don't want to add a depth of her in a
reason because you're doubling your bandwidth, right?
Your readwrite bandwidth.
Is it for no reason?
But yeah, I guess if we have to produce a separate color buffer.
Anyway, maybe that's the better idea but as far as we're talking
about, you're saying reverse the render order for the entities being
faded so that their front to back then I guess I don't see how that
helps I guess.
Well, okay.
I guess I do see that helps.
So basically you'd use the depth buffer and you just go.
And then you clear the depth buffer when you
Or you started drawing.
The next floor is that basically the idea because that that would work
everywhere you mentioned rendering to an Austrian buffer then
compositing is one means of getting this are Dolph effect but you also
mention something along the lines of using a fragment
Could you please elaborate a bit more on that approach?
Yeah, it's it's really actually quite simple.
It's just something that you wouldn't think of.
If you didn't realize that modern gpus are basically just CPUs that
you have really poor ways of programming.
Okay, so
For lack of a better term.
I'll call these per-fragment Atomic lists but I don't even know what
you would call them.
That you don't even really need a name for them because they're just
the standard thing which you'll see in a second.
So the idea here is let's say that I wanted to solve order independent
transparency and the kind of problems were talking about are basically
anything that you want to do regarding the fact that there's multiple
things that cover a pixel and they can see some of them are like
translucent transparent, whatever.
okay, so, traditionally the problem is, you know, I've got a, you
know, a little pixel here right here in the thing,
This is my pixel and so typically, what's going to happen is
everything is like a forward rendering process, right?
So everything is like all these triangles come by and they all kind of
overlap this pixel partially, or completely, or whatever else, right?
And so my job is as a renderer designer, right is, I've got triangle,
zero and triangle 1 and triangle to and whatever, they're overlapping.
This pixel.
I'm supposed to design something so that when I see triangle, 01.
And
To come in and cover this pixel, right?
And each one has whatever its colors and you know lighting and
everything should be.
My job is seeing them in order make it so that basically something
happens with t 0, right?
That produces the new state of the pixel, okay?
That state then gets fed into T1, right?
Whatever happens here and that produces the new state, right?
Then that state gets fed into T2 and that
produces the final state, right?
So, it's always, you know, I have to think about making my renderer
work by saying every time, a triangle touches this pixel,
Right.
Then I have to compute a new state for the pixel, right?
And the reason that you get into trouble is if at some point what you
really wanted to do was know that if T2 was going to be here, don't do
something with t0 or something like that, right?
Meaning, if I have to start having magical foresight, right, to sort
of say, oh, I need to know what I might put in here before.
I know what I should do here.
And you see that example it's exactly what.
With our trees, right?
We have our two trees.
This.
And what I wanted to do was say oh in these pixels here, don't ever
render this tree with its Alpha because when this one comes in, it's
going to want to render its tree at the right Alpha there.
We don't want to see this tree behind it, right?
So it's exactly that thing.
If I just magically knew that the tree was coming it wouldn't be a
problem.
And so for example, D Seven, Samurai was suggesting, for example, a a
way of using the depth buffer.
So there's all these tricks that you then end up building where you're
like oh well I could sort.
The things first or I'll have a depth of 4 so I can reject certain
ones.
So I'll do a depth free pass and then the depth prepass will know that
t2s depth value is the closest Value so teeth 0 can check it and then
it knows and we'll put a flag in there and you know, and you just go
through all of these different things and you're like, ah, okay so
what for Pac-Man Atomic lists are as like, say forget it just let's
just assume we're going to burn a bunch of computational resources on
this problem and stop having
Do all of this.
Just forget about it.
And instead what we're going to do is every time a triangle covers,
this pixel what we're actually going to say is that the pixel itself
is not really storing a state, it's storing a list.
So the frame buffer is now a pointer buffer.
Effectively, right?
And you can imagine this if we went and implement it in our software,
renderer, it's pretty easy, right?
We just actually, for every pixel we make a little pointer to some
list of things, some list of triangles that covered it, right?
And that's exactly what you would do in the situation.
So, what you do is you write your pixel Shader to have some notion of
what it is trying to remember, right about these things that come
through.
And instead of making this have a color as it state, it just has a
pointer to the first fragment if it's 0.
Then there is no fragment there yet, right?
When it sees one, it just makes this thing point to that, fragment
whatever it is.
It sees the next one, it just does the standard push down thing like
we do, right?
It pushes it down one and puts it in its place and it creates a little
singly linked list that just stores.
All of the fragments that touched this thing, right?
And there's other ways you could do it, too.
You can also do more of a fixed array one where you just store, like,
for fragments per pixel or something, all the same Concepts.
You can either do it as a list or it erase all the same, trade-offs,
apply as you would be thinking in C or whatever saying,
Same stuff, right?
then at the end you now have this buffer, that's basically like, you
know, a linked list buffer,
And you write one final pixel Shader.
Right?
And that pixel Shader.
All it does is it reads this buffer.
pixel by pixel and outputs the
Color by looping, looping through the list, looks that all the things
in the list and making those decisions that it couldn't make before
because it couldn't see everything.
Well, now it can see everything at once decide what the final color
will be and outputs that.
Right.
So this goes from the linked list buffer to a color buffer and now you
actually have your image and like you said, one of things you could do
you could sort you could actually just run a sort in there, right?
And then retire, the fragments in order you could look to see whether
you have a fragment in there.
That says, I'm, you know, this is, this is on, you know, maybe these
things are keyed and these say, I'm on one level, I'm on another.
And you could blend them both separately, and then Alpha composite
them with a different Alpha value, right?
So you can do anything.
You could imagine
Make listen here, and it's just, it just gets very expensive to do all
this, but you could do it, right.
So, why did I call it?
A perfect monatomic list?
Well, the / fragment Parts pretty obvious?
It's because we're storing them for fragment in the frame buffer,
right?
But the atomic part, the reason for that is in a GPU architecture,
it's totally possible that the architects who created the hardware may
have had it such that multiple people could write to the frame buffer
at the same time, right?
So for example, let's say that I have a person who's working on a
piece of the frame buffer, and another person who's working on another
piece of paper.
So these are two different threads.
Here's three thread, a and thread be, right?
Or rather let's say they're both working on the same part of the frame
buffer.
So these both map to this part of the frame buffer.
Right.
The GPU could have done something where it bifurcated, the work to
Fred's threads A and B because it knows it can merge their work after
they're done, right?
Because in the standard way, that things work right in this way where
we just come in and do things one after the other.
If I know, for example, that I could enter leaves these in some clever
way after the fact or resolve their differences in some way or who
knows what I, you know, I could make that.
Or maybe I've got some situation where I'm literally loading the
pixels and like looping them through or whatever and I just, I don't
know.
I mean, I don't know but point being
How should I put this point being there's different ways that this
could involve threads actually do the same time, more likely.
And similarly, I have somewhere that I need to store the memory for
these linked lists, right?
So let's say that this is not really realistic because hey, the GPU
can't really do this or maybe it wouldn't or who knows whatever.
What I also know is, I need to store this linked List information
somewhere.
So maybe I have some
Buffer that I'm writing these.
Thanks to that kind of, you know, chain in, you know, like we do and
he made here, like we've got memory and we're all can these links
well, somehow, when I get the next link, when I get the next place to
slot in my chain of length values, if both A and B are both trying to
that the same time, you get all the classic multi-threading problems.
So certain gpus have the ability to do these Atomic operations that
allow you to do things like
Eight new links atomically so that multiple threads that are both
shading at the same time, don't hit that same the same multi-threading
problems.
We hit in handmade Hero on CPUs.
So you will see things like, you know, interlocked ad
Right or something is now something the Jeep you can do.
It can say, I need to do a locked increment and even if there's 12
shaders that are all trying to, like, grab these links out of the
pool.
Well, I'm going to make sure that they are serialized properly, so
they don't stomp on each other.
This is very modern.
This is not something you could have done, probably five six years
ago, it AMD added atomics.
I think added them first.
I can't remember.
But now basically all gpus that you would buy like if you went out to
buy GPU today, I don't know about mobile gpus but like in a in a PC it
would be very unusual to have one that didn't support operations.
That are actually this complicated.
That's the sort of things they can do now.
So as far as I know, like, you know, if you wanted to do an algorithm
that worked like this for handmade hero, you could and you really
would be mostly at worrying about older stuff like the Raspberry Pi or
Android phones or you know, whatever is where you would start to run
into problems.
But you know any any AMD Nvidia probably even Intel GPU purchased in
the last 2 years.
Would be able to do these
So so they're they're you know, they're around, they've been around
for a while they're just, you know, they're unusual because we're used
to thinking of Graphics in this like non General way but gpus keep
getting more and more General.
And so they do you can make a linked list for Pixel if you want.
And you just have to pay the cost of all that extra computation.
But if you're willing to pay it it can do it.
Kb3, sounds insane, or are there any modern games that use this?
you know, I'll be honest with you I guess I don't know but I assume so
I mean I guess I just I guess I don't know.
That's a good question.
I would assume that they do.
You know, I would ask, like the battlefield guys were tied, ask dice
or something?
And they probably like, oh, yeah, or maybe crytek, you know, they
seemed like the kind of thing they would do.
Quickly games.
Could you just pre-render normally to an Austrian buffer?
And then composite it with the primary frame buffer with the Fade Out
Alpha that will, that's what I'm suggesting we do.
That was my, that was what I was saying.
At the end of the stream is what we will probably do.
So yes, you definitely can do that.
And that's what I think we should do, but obviously, you know, there
are other options.
Do you Seven Samurai?
The anti asking didn't throw a wrench, you could have used the depth
buffer front to back running all the way and compensate for some of
the extra bandwidth unless overdraw.
I mean, so here's the thing.
we could if we wanted to use the depth buffer week, we could do
something like Alpha to coverage for
for the edges.
Right.
it just seems like again, I feel like that's probably more bandwidth
again than we should, then we need
Kb3.
I mean, that sounds like it has a huge performance implications
talking about the fragment list.
I mean, here's the way to think of it, right?
It all depends on what you are trying to do to put something good
looking on the screen.
Using the CPU and GPU power that you have, right?
And so let's say for example, that handmade hero was targeting like
super high end hardware.
For some reason like like we were like handmade hero is going to
require like a G-Force, 900 series.
So, you know, it's going to require a 980 at least, right?
So just
Don't even think of running ham this disc 2-D game, right?
Don't even think of running it on like an old like, you know, peace
are because forget it.
Let's say we're going to say that which is sort of what you know, like
someone like Battlefield says because they're looking to be like super
great and they'll do maybe they'll do like an old version.
So that people who don't have those can run on it or whatever.
But, you know, they're sort of saying, hey, you know, in order to get
play the game that this game was ment to be played.
You're supposed to be installing crazy Hardware in your machine.
So let's say we said that for handmade hero.
Well then it's like it's not like you're going to look and go.
Well, yeah, this per frame.
Atomic stuff is a really huge performance implications.
It will take us 10 20 times.
It'll be 10 or 20 times slower to render these Sprites using this
method then if we didn't use it, right.
But the question is, what were you going to do with that 10 or 20 x
overdraw?
Anyway, look, could you have done anything with it?
And maybe the answer is, no, look, maybe the answer is there so much
horsepower there, you couldn't have done anything useful with it, but
if you go ahead and say, well, we're going to spend it on making
atomics, and do you know a render resolve pass or whatever.
All of a sudden, maybe now, we can do all these super cool effects
like, you know, smoke with multiple depth ranges that comes in.
And like a the light goes through
Written like accumulates from different directions because we know
exactly what is going on at each depth level and we can do like we
have multiple depth levels of things through so we can do, you know,
bokeh properly going around edges and I mean who knows.
Right.
So all of these things are just tools and the idea is that gpus
nowadays if you decide to Target a higher end GPU you have a
ridiculous amount of horsepower.
And the question is, what are you going to do with that horsepower and
so things like Atomic list may sound ridiculous because you're like
well there's there's so much extra work involved here and like yeah it
may be 10 times more work or something, but
What were you going to do with that?
Where you just going to overdraw the screen like a thousand more times
or something you know or not that but you're going to overdraw the
screen 10 times more.
Well if you can figure out something useful to do with it, okay?
But if you can't write then, you know, this this becomes a very
attractive thing because now you can do algorithms, you couldn't have
done before and that's what a lot of these features are about.
speaking of,
Mooc example.
Do you see what David Rosen posted today?
I did not.
It just kind of looks like some fairly I guess to not be rude.
Fairly basic Blobby smoke.
It just looks like some particle systems.
If you want to see the smoke that I was like, whoa, that looks
awesome.
Did you see in the trailer for Battlefield one, the green mustard, gas
or whatever?
It was that stuff?
Looked amazing.
I'm there was like an in-game thing looked like, with that in it.
That looked so cool.
I'm very interested to see what that is.
Cosmic sword.
I thought most games were only designed to max out.
Console Hardware.
Well, you have to remember that atomics are in console Hardware.
Like a PlayStation 4 has a Tom has has fragment atomics.
I mean, I'll be honest with you, I don't program the PlayStation 4, so
I guess, I don't know, but it's a bulldozer courtship or whatever.
Right?
It was it I mean I'm pretty certain that.
All right, I'm going to wrap it up.
All right, thank you for joining me for this episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along, with series at home, you
can always pre-order the game on handmade here at our org and it comes
with the source code.
So you can follow along.
We also have a forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions a patreon page, you can pledge to if you
want for the video series and a schedule about the tells you when
we're going to be live, speaking of what we're going to be live, will
be back here tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
And we also have a past episodes can annotate episode.
Guys can go to if you want to catch up on old episodes while you wait.
That's about it.
I hope to see you guys back here tomorrow till then have fun
programming.
I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.