Hello everyone and welcome to handmade.
Here are the show that where we code a complete game live on stream
and I was kind of enjoying making the cut scene yesterday.
And so I kind of want to make the rest of the cutscenes and so I'm
just going to do that today is day 2 22.
So if you're trying to follow along at home, you want to unpack day,
221 source code and you want to make sure you have the our pack
because when we're doing stuff like cutscenes, you got to have the our
packs and make sure you download it that I showed how to download it
or rather to unpack it yesterday.
But if you remember yesterday, we started a kind of explain the basics
of making a multi-layer cutscene, and we went ahead and made this one.
Right here and you can kind of see it's looking pretty cool, actually,
I think there's some things we might want to adjust about it.
Certainly it's, you know, there's a little if you just want to make,
but it's looking really nice and it's got that kind of nice depth to
it.
I really like, the way it's starting to come out.
So what I'd like to do is just go through the rest of the cutscenes
and get all of the cut scenes working essentially, the same way that
they're working right here, so that we sort of have each piece and
then we can assemble them into the
All cutscene, once we have each one kind of tune and there's stuff
that I, we can do after that, that, you know, to kind of to kind of
pull things together in a more coherent way more usable way.
So, we might even want to do a little bit of that today.
But so if you take a look at what we've got here, you can kind of see
this.
This stuff is really pretty generic, right?
Like we haven't really done anything.
That's all.
That's if the cutscene all we really need to do is just make this sort
of information here where it says, kind of like how many layers there
are and how they're supposed to.
To work, we could even do something like this, where we just say, like
layer count, right?
And the layer count is eight.
And then in here, we could say, oh, layer count.
You know?
And, and that's now pretty generic.
We're basically just taking this layer placement thing and the shot
index write this.
In fact, this right here is essentially the entire data for, you know,
for the cutscene right.
That's all we need.
So if we wanted to, we could easily make this a separate thing.
In fact, I guess now that I think about it really there's not much
reason not to
you can imagine us doing something like this where we just have, you
know, a thing called a cutscene or just, you know, am maybe a layered
scenes like that, that
And we could just have this stuff in here, going to say, all right,
how many layers are there?
You know, what's the shot index?
We could even have something in here, where you know, if we take a
look at the file formats, the assets, we've got this asset type ID, we
could even say what the asset type ID was, right?
So we could just say the asset type, what the shot index was what the
layer count is, and then we just need a pointer to a layer placement
array.
That's got all that information in it, right?
Like so.
And that's the basis for our cutscenes.
And we may have to expand this a little bit certainly and, but
For the most part that's really all we need.
And we could also say how long the duration of this thing was supposed
to be would be another thing that we could do pretty easily.
So, for example, we could say in here.
You know what?
We wanted.
That duration to be for now I'm going to leave it, so it's just zero
to five.
They'll all be normalized, but we could kind of play around that a
little later.
So now if we want to convert this thing so that we could actually do,
you know that particular thing we could say that we wanted to do like,
you know, render layered scene or something like that.
We could take whichever layered scene.
We were talking about
And then we could take whatever the T, normal was like, whatever the
you know, this value was because that's really all we need.
Oh and there's some things, there are some other things that we could
prioritize right that camera start and end that was another thing as
well.
So I'm going to go ahead and grab this stuff here.
I'm going to go ahead and pull that out like so and now we've got a
thing that renders that layered scene, right?
And so if I want to I can make this guy do that right here I can just
say, Okay render layered scene
And all I need to do here is make sure that I passed the stuff that we
might need, right?
So it's going to be the assets, couldn't either render group.
It's going to need.
I fact I think it probably pretty much just needs everything that we
originally had but instead of the tea cutscene is now going to be
giving us some kind of a normalized, some kind of a normalized thing.
All right, so that's just this right, like that.
And so, all we need now is to actually Define that layered scene.
And so this stuff here is what we would have been defining the layered
scene.
Right?
And so I can go ahead and grab that out and I can put it here right?
And I can then I wish I fix that Emax indentation thing but what do
you do anyway so I've got a layered see now.
That I can to find here's the scene we're going to render so I can
pass that along.
Like so and into that I'm just going to put all the information that
we had, right.
We know the layer count actually just do it like this we know the
layer count is eight.
We know the shot index is 1, we know the asset type right, the asset
type is just this guy here opening cutscene.
So we can we can fill that in a second, right?
That's this guy here.
And so that's pretty much everything then we just need the layer
placement, right?
Equals layer placement.
Like so and that's pretty much it for defining a scene.
So then I'll need to do is up here.
Every time we were going to look for stuff.
We start to use that.
Now, these two guys like I said, we hadn't defined yet.
So let's go ahead and put them in there, will do camera, start camera.
And that way, these guys can be in there as well and so we can just do
something like this camera, start.
I put that down here.
Let's see.
Seem camera start.
Will slow on the typing today.
Some reason and seen camera, and I'll grab that guy.
And again this is just you know I've said it a million times this is
just exactly the way that I normally program things when I know the
the fundamental thing I'm trying to do.
I just write it which was what we did yesterday and then I just look
at the stuff that's going to get you know, that I want to use again
and I just pull it out, right?
And it's the easiest way to do it.
It prevents all of that, sort of design, paralysis up front and the
whole like going back and forth on things that really don't matter and
that don't match the problem.
Well, you just solve the problem and then you generalize from that
rather than the other way around, always the best way to go.
If you know how to do one solution, right?
If you know how to do one cut scene, you could just get in there and
code, it just code that one cutscene.
And then all of the things that you then needed, for the overall
design will just come out.
If you don't know how to do one cut scene, obviously, that's not going
to work.
But when you have a situation where, you know, that that one part of
it, you pull out from there and that's always the easiest way to
design from that, from that point.
Okay, so anyway, we come through here, we've got our
are all this stuff is going to be exactly the same, right?
Nothing weird is going on there.
We pass in the teen normal so that's all good.
All of this stuff is going to be the same only.
Now we're getting that shot index for getting that out of the scene,
same with the layer cap getting that out of seen, same with the asset
ID, right?
So this is the asset type.
That's really it.
And so now I just gotta clean up couple things are m, 2 pixels.
Yeah, this stuff.
This is some stuff again that really needs to get.
I think cleaned up a little bit but it's you know, it's fine for now,
but I feel like we want 20 more coherent idea of what's going on
there.
But anyway, so let's see here, we've got signed unsigned problem.
You're right.
These should be you 32 certainly, here we go.
Layer placement is going to be off of a scene now and
That looks like that's just about it now distance above ground.
So this is a little bit tricky, right?
So this is kind of a problem because we need to know for this guy.
We don't really have any way of specifying, what's going on with his,
the fact that he's kind of special that he doesn't move at all, right?
And we could just move him way back, but it's kind of a special thing
that we want to remember about these.
And so what I want to do is I want to just go ahead because there
might be other things like that.
Like if we if there's other things especially
All things about a layer.
We may want to start, you know, we might want to start
Having more extra cipa, deeper layer, right?
So instead of just packing into a V for let's actually say, here is
the P of the layer, right?
Here's the height of the layer, right?
So now that's explicit instead of that sort of, you know, implicit
Vector for thing, we were doing there.
And then, we can also think that we can do here which is like add
infinity or something like that, right?
So we can just say where we expect that thing to be right and we can
say, you know, move that Tiffany.
I think I want to do something more like this actually, so we can make
it flag.
So you can layer flags and I'll show you why that is seen layer flag.
At Infinity again.
I said very slow.
I'm typing today.
For some reason you never know.
Some of you have a slow typing day so this is actually going to be
Flags.
Like so.
And so, what I want to do there is I want to now expand this notion
just a little bit, right?
So now we're going to do is going to say, okay, this is a scene layer
and here is our layers, right?
Then.
This becomes instead of layer placement, this is just layers.
It's not really placement of the layers anymore, it's more than just
just it's more than that, right?
And so now we got that all good.
We'll go say it's seen layer layer equals seen layers 60.
In fact, I guess I could just grab it out, like so.
Okay, so we grabbed out that layer.
Now, the layer itself, we can say, it's got the layer P, right?
And that's good.
Now, we can sort of grab those out, more explicitly, you can see what
thereat.
We don't have to do like placement dot w, which is kind of confusing
with what's going on there.
Right now, this is a little clearer what's happening.
And so now what we want to do is say well okay the P which we're going
to do it is going to be the layer P, but now we're going to check
those flags, right?
So if those flags indicate to us that it's supposed to be at Infinity,
we might do something else, right?
So basically
We come up here.
We say, if somebody said this is this is at Infinity.
Meaning it's infinitely, I like an affinity.
But what is that?
What is in Affinity?
Don't ask me, I just made it up.
So anyway, if it's at Infinity, we're going to take that pz and we're
going to add distance above ground to it.
So that it's always relative to distance above ground so that way we
can just make that be - 200, right?
But we can add distance above ground to it.
Dynamically.
So we can say, oh, okay, this guy.
He's actually going to be ad Infiniti, right?
Seen their flag at infinity and so now all I have to do is just re
bracket these guys.
You know what, just because we can, we might even use a little bit of
a macro for that, right?
Because I don't know.
It's just why not use a macro for that?
Kind of ridiculous, totally unnecessary.
Did it anyway?
Just did it anyway.
All right.
And so these are going to be seen layers now.
And hopefully that will give us.
Well we really try to do here is get our seen back, right?
So there it is.
And everything looks the same as it did, which is exactly what we
want.
And so now we can just start working on other scenes.
Now we can just say, all right let's go ahead and change with
sinesses, you know, you render, you know, use it.
Use the exact code that we have to just render another cutscene.
And that way, we know that we can just reuse, you know, all that code
that we did, we don't have to write it another time.
Alright, so let's go ahead and start.
We're going to do it.
Back to the same way as we did.
Last time, I'm going to go ahead and make this guy.
Down here.
So let's go ahead and and switch to handmade cutscene do.
There's a dot h, I guess there is a dot h.
Well, if there's a handmade cutscene .h, might as well put this stuff
in it.
I didn't know, I don't remember making one of those but I guess we
did.
So there it is.
Happy birthday.
We now have handmade cutscene dot h and made cutscene .h.
Wonderful.
Wonderful, who knew who knew indeed, okay?
So now we can just go ahead and make that full screen.
We can see our cutscene and now we can edit our cutscenes, just like
we were doing before and and off we go.
So inside render cutscene all I'm going to do here is just make a
different cut scene like I said before.
Really pretty.
Pretty basic.
Nothing.
Strange gone.
You're so, I'm just going to take this part of it.
And I'm going to grab this and make a new one, right?
So now we basically have okay, note Casey, this is shots one.
Then we come down here, this is going to be shot too.
Okay.
And then if I just do if I just run this again in theory, I guess you
know what should probably do is this
Stand up, racket those up.
So don't conflict with each other.
Now we're technically rendering the second one.
We just haven't changed it at all yet, right?
Oh, and of course emacs decides to helpfully indent that wrong.
So that's always good.
Just want a little you know, always want intends to be wrong certainly
when want them to correct.
So in here we've got shot too.
So now I'm going to switch to shop to and we're going to do exactly
the thing that we did before.
We're just going to look at those layers individually so I can see
what they are.
So here is
Our first layer and I don't really know what our camera motion is
necessarily going to be on this one, right?
I'm going to remove that an Infinity Flex.
Don't think there are any layers that Infinity on this one.
They're all going to move through.
But I'm going to stop the camera.
I'm going to take the camera motion and make that not happen yet,
right?
You know what I should do to now I'm thinking about it.
I might if zero this guy out for one second because I feel like the Z
is also something we would want to do.
So we kind of baked the Z in here, right?
I'm going to, I'm going to switch this back to full screen for just
one second so you can see what I'm talking about.
So if you take a look at what happened here, we had distance above
ground, equals 10, minus t normal, 5.0 or whatever, right?
That seems like, potentially a bad idea because this is now hard
coded.
And what we really want is we want
Want that to be sort of, part of the whole camera move.
So I think what we'd rather do is this right?
Which create a stops it from moving at all in the Z direction, right?
And then we'd want to encode that in the camera, start end, right?
So we want the camera to move from 0 to negative 5 or whatever, right?
And furthermore we probably want this distance.
Ground thing we want distance above ground to not have anything else
encoded with it.
So we'd probably want to do it more like okay.
It goes from 10:00 to 5:00, right?
So we're just we're just putting in exactly what that motion used to
be then distance above ground, can now be encoded as the Z part of
this, right?
In fact, we wouldn't even really need to do just change this above
ground at all.
This is about ground, can presumably just be 0.
I think and it wouldn't matter at all, right.
So distance above ground when we put that there.
Now, pz is just going to be whatever the cameras e was.
So it's cameras, the offset, like so, and I think that should return
us to what we were at before, right?
So now everything's just baked into the camera movement.
The distance above ground is just a meaningful meaningless value.
We don't even ever look at it's because that's just an offset that
gets implied in the inside the renderer for us.
We don't need it because we're offsetting are older layers.
And so now we're back to where we were now that it gives us full
freedom to control, each individual, cutscenes camera.
Using those two variables, which is more what we want, right?
So here we go.
We're back to see sha-2.
Now here's our first layer and it's not moving at all.
Obviously it's not moving because we're not actually moving the
camera.
And so for this scene I think this is going to be another slow Zoom.
So this one we could we could go ahead and say like went from zero to
negative 5, right?
So it could be another slow.
Zoom.
Kind of like that.
Maybe it's zooms a little bit more.
I don't know.
We'll see.
But that's going to depend on how close all the layers are certainly
Okay, so I don't think we need to offset this layer if I remember
correctly, and I don't know that.
We want it to be that far away either, so I'm not sure where we want
to put that layer again, maybe that layer is it - 20 feet or something
like that?
It's probably going to be a lot smaller that layer.
You can kind of see.
This is quite a big movement when you're that close in, but that is
sort of what this scene, this scene doesn't have very many layers, so
it's a very close in shot.
So let's go ahead and reduce that movement.
Maybe we only move about
And M, write something like that.
Maybe even less, maybe even only a half meter for Words during that
will see like what we want that to be.
We could also extend the amount of time that it would go over, right?
The other thing that we're not really doing right now is we're yeah,
we're not really doing time.
And so that's again, another tuning thing that we're probably do a
little bit later.
After we make all this stuff, be what we want.
So if we assume that it was 20 meters away that that even still seems
like probably a long distance but I don't know, maybe it's not too
bad.
Dad.
So if we just go ahead and adjust this up to the point where it's
going to be sort of what we wanted.
That looks a little bit more correct and we'll see what happens when
we when we drop into the lair.
So let's drop it.
Another layer here that layer again is going to have to be in front of
the of the little kid.
Right?
Like so something like that.
And yeah, probably have to off the set though slightly and then I
don't.
Member what we've got four, other layers here.
I think not that much.
Let's see what we have.
I don't know if there's another layer or not.
I don't remember.
I think there's an icicle Slayer.
Yeah.
There's some icicles there.
So those are, let's see what those look like.
You kind of see those up at the top.
So those are probably supposed to be like much closer to us, you know,
that sort of thing.
So you kind of get a little more depth on them.
Let's move them, even closer.
Just so you get a lot.
I want to get a lot of motion on those.
Right?
So there maybe eight.
Yeah, something like that and so that's going to need to be moved up a
little bit.
I also to kind of put them in the right position.
Yeah, that's starting to be a little more like it.
I don't think there's a fourth layer, pretty sure there isn't.
Yeah, so there's no fourth layer.
So that's really all we're looking at for this particular scene.
So now, let's try to work out that Parallax a little bit better and
get sort of where everything is supposed to be lining up a little bit
better.
I want to see.
Let me just see where we're at with this guy.
All right.
Yeah, so I think we want a little more of a parallax effect on that
window.
So I kind of want the window to be like closer, you know, just closer
than it is.
So I'm going to, I'm going to really drop that down quite a bit.
Let's see here to maybe something like this.
That's looking definitely better but I think maybe we want to drop the
kid back a bit as well.
Right.
And so now we could just kind of aligned him a little bit differently,
I think in that might be okay, right?
Some just want a little more centered in the window.
Yeah.
Yeah, and then a little lower too.
I think something more like that.
That's starting to be starting to be a little bit closer.
He might still be a little too far away, just thinking.
It's hard to say hard to say.
That may be about, right?
So with that, I think that's roughly correct.
And so, what I want to do now is make sure that the camera again just
like we did before, is zooming in on him.
And so that we get, you know, a clear sense of motion towards where
the kid actually, is, that makes sense.
So, a little bit down.
Thinking maybe that sort of thing.
That's feeling pretty good.
We think of that.
I like that.
Now, I feel like there were also supposed to be some snowflakes.
I may have forgotten to include the snowflakes in the art pack my
mistake.
That was my mistake.
So, we may have to, I may have to ship snowflakes at some other point
in time because we were going to maybe add some snowflakes slowing
down here.
But again, that's sort of separate from the way we're doing these
cutscenes.
So, we'll get all these done and then I'll see if I may have forgotten
snowflakes.
Admit that does my mistake, missing snowflakes, you know how it is?
Is so on and so forth.
Anyway so there's that cutscene I'm relatively happy with that and so
that's just again only three layers.
So that's all we need here.
So that is the kid and three, I guess we could call him the hero
because he is a hero as you know and then we have the wall the window
and then we have the icicles
Okay, so that's a fun cutscene, that's all good.
So now let's make another one.
Cut scene 3.
Sean index and start all over again.
That is the outside when I should probably also do this.
And this cutscene, if I remember correctly, it's kind of a fun one.
This is going to be tricky.
I didn't know if this would work when I kind of suspect it out, I
wasn't sure if this perspective would work, I don't know.
And so it's basically, it's a shot that actually is meant to move like
laterally, like, I'm sorry vertically, which is kind of weird that I
included one vertical, run, and one horizontal run shot, which are
kind of like unusual.
They're not as common with this kind of a technique and so I don't
really know.
They're going to work or not, but you know, if they don't work,
there's always, you know, you typically go through a lot of revisions
in art stuff anyway.
So, you know, if we have to do some, some revisions we did than we do
and that's totally fine.
So let's take a look at how this is going to look here.
So, I'm going to go ahead and hold off on that one too much, because I
don't actually know how big that needs to be, so I'm going to move on
to
To, you know, these closer field ones first and then we'll see.
So this is basically the like sky.
In fact, the sky probably shouldn't move because that really is the
sky for reals so well.
Okay, but since it since the weird shot, we'll see,
Because since we're it since it's sort of emulating an over-the-top
camera move that might actually make the Sky Move, depending on how we
do it.
So I don't want to say that quite yet.
Alright, so here's the second one, there's the outdoors, the, the
woods there, right?
That's happening.
So let's see what happens there and this might be tricky to, I don't
know if this is a thing where we might have to we might need a way to
counter rotate to counter move people because of the fact that we're
supposed to be simulating a rotation.
And so we're going to have to have a probably in this.
I'm kind of glad I did the flags thing.
We're probably going to have to do another flag.
That's like this guy is counter.
Moving with the cutscene.
You'll see what I mean in a second or at least, I hope that that you
will
So I'm going to keep adding layers there because I can't quite tell
exactly how I want this to move just yet.
Okay, so there's our next layer
Here we go.
Yeah.
So these are not basically this is not supposed to be, this is
supposed to be moving up.
I think and the boys head is supposed to be moving down so you can see
there's a fourth layer which is like the good put that in there which
is the kid.
There he is.
And so, what I want to do is I'm trying to make it, I want to make it
so that it's like, it's like kind of coming over the top of the head,
right?
It's like, it's like kind of an overshot.
And so, what I want to do is say, okay, the camera is kind of moving
upward.
So those back layers are actually, I want them to look like your comic
coming over the top.
So the kid's head will move correctly with the camera but the other
ones won't if that makes sense.
So, I'm going to go ahead and just add in here and I'll pop back to
the
The the regular view here.
I'm going to add in here another flag.
That's like counter why or something like this, right?
Like that does a counter camera motion and and maybe maybe I'll
actually say like counter camera just entirely.
I don't know if that's the right thing to do.
But we'll do counter camera XY or just counter camera would never do
captors Z but well maybe so we'll just do will do them all counter
camera, why look?
So we'll do it that way.
All right.
And so when we do this, this stuff in here, it's the same exact thing.
You can kind of see that we're doing this TV Camera offset thing.
So instead of doing it that way, what I'll do is I'll do them
individually, right?
So I'll do PX equals PX, minus camera offset X.
X and I'll do p y equals right?
Like that sort of thing.
And so that way, what I can do is just switch on it, I can do it the
same way, right?
I can say,
This.
Right.
And that way I can control whether it does counter or not.
And so this would be counter actually said that should be the plus
case and this should be the - case.
And then again we do the same thing for why
So again, nothing should change.
Now, if I recompile this right, if I if we build with this, nothing
should change or everything should change apparently what did I do
wrong there P?
Plus it's kind of camera.
I don't know what I did.
There shouldn't had a problem.
What what happened there their flags and so it should do it in either
case right camera offset X camera.
Offset y goes off at py that should have worked, oh but Z I'm not
actually doing Z and so, right, I forgot to do the Z case cameras @p Z
equals peasy.
Nice camera.
There we go.
Got to doozy.
Okay.
So let's go back to what we were doing.
So now in here, if I want to write, I should be able to say that those
background scenes are actually going to counter move counter, right to
the camera.
And as I said, I don't really know if this is going to work.
I couldn't tell you, but I'm going to try, right?
So, it's going to do this sort of a thing, right?
Can you kind of see what I'm talking about there?
So it's a again, like it's really tricky.
It's kind of a
Shot.
But we'll try to figure it out.
We'll see if it works and if it doesn't work then it doesn't work.
No big deal.
All right, so first of all, we're going to have the kids start
probably a lot lower than he starting right now.
He's going to be probably you know down maybe down there.
He's got to get all the way out of the out of the frame.
Really if that makes sense.
So he's got a kind of yeah, he's got to kind of do something more like
that and we probably need maybe the camera to move.
Move a little bit further than it does because maybe the shot is like
a bit longer.
Let's say, yeah, but that's that's actually that's already starting to
look roughly like what?
I wanted.
So I think we're going to be okay, I think we're probably going to be
okay.
Now that that background there is got to be a lot bigger obviously so
you know that things got to be I don't know probably like way bigger
than it is right now.
It's got to be like this sort of a thing, right?
Probably well, maybe not quite that much.
Let's try to try to get that back down to, oops, something reasonable.
What did I do wrong?
That's 22.
That's 25.
All right, so that looks like roughly what we would need and I want it
to be able to pan all the way down so that you kind of see it.
So again that the distance of panning there, it's going to have to be
pretty, you know, if that's only going a meter up than I guess, it's
just means that the scene does that mean that this was actually just a
lot closer.
I guess it means it's a lot closer.
So these guys are definitely in you know a lot more than they would
have been otherwise, right.
So it's like a four and a the you know in a
Let's say, five.
Write something like that.
Because one meter is, you know, is 1 meter, the end of the day.
So this is going to be kind of a tough shot.
I guess if it goes for a long time, maybe it would work, but it's
going to be a little bit of a tough shot just with how much ground has
to be covered in the pan.
That makes sense, right?
Yeah.
It's weird how your mind kind of reads these different sorts of scenes
and how it interprets the motion of static 2D plates, right?
Okay,
Yes.
So I'm going to say that it needs to move quite a bit more in.
And I guess the five meters four meters thing we could just say that
it's closer in would also be, you know, the probably the right thing
to do.
Because I'm just trying to reconcile those, those distances for m is
actually pretty darn far.
So, you know, that's a little weird but, you know, I guess one meter
it probably is a total of 2 m camera move.
Maybe I'm not sure.
Depending on how you want to look at it, right.
But that's yeah.
So that's getting a little bit more.
I'm going to move him in just even a little bit more than that, right?
Yeah.
So that's again, that's getting there.
But it's going to need.
Yeah.
Even so it's still needs, probably a lot more, a lot more than that.
I'm going to go ahead and do it this way.
Let's get that.
See how that works.
And this will be a lot smaller as well.
So that's a little more what I wanted but even so.
And again the speed of this is just too much.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to maybe go ahead and assume that
these are longer than five seconds, right?
Cut scene.
Let's assume they're more like 10 seconds or 20 seconds since that's
probably more what they actually will be in the real game.
I'm guessing although it's hard to say until we have the voice acting
in there exactly how long we would want each to be, but it's probably
more like that, right?
So that's probably it's going to be more like that speed in actuality,
right?
So yeah.
That's a little bit more like it.
Okay, so let's continue with that.
Let's try to get that more nailed down.
So yeah I can't quite tell how that should be, but it probably is
going to have to start like a bit further up, right?
It's probably going to have to start further up and pan further down.
So again we're probably going to have to increase this movement and
and move this up a bit, something like that.
Oops, wrong direction.
Because we want to start looking out the window, you know what I mean?
We want to start with this looking out the window and I'm not sure
exactly where we would want that.
But yeah, let me just see what that ends up looking like in terms of,
in terms of stuff.
Yeah, it's a tough shot.
It's a tough shot to be sure.
But, all right, let me also fix that background while we're there.
And you know what, I'm going to fix the, I'm going to, I'm going to
make tea, normal equal zero for a second, just so I can focus on this
one way.
The shot is lined up, right?
Which is pretty free for me to do.
I could also sort of make the, the handmade hero guy be maybe a little
bit.
Place a little bit differently.
Something like that, maybe.
I'm not sure.
I guess that's rightfully, right?
Like I said, this is a difficult shot, I'm not sure if it's going to
work.
It's a little bit hard, but that's okay.
And so, this guy is probably, this is more like, probably further away
as well.
And it's, you know, so let's make that big enough.
That we it covers the whole window as well, like, so, and then we also
need our, our guy here to be, you know, this guy's going to be at
Infinity, so, that's fine.
So, how big does he need to be needs to be?
Probably about 45 wide.
I need to be even bigger than that.
You need to be more like you know, 80 or something.
Ninety.
There we go.
So let's see.
So he is a scene layer flag.
He's actually at Infinity.
Okay, so now I'm going to unlock the movement just to see where we're
at.
Right.
And it's sort of.
Works.
I mean it, I think maybe if the Boy comes out of the picture slower
than that, it would work.
Potentially, it's not as maybe as good as I would have hoped.
We also got to make some of those background layers, a little, just a
little bigger, right?
You can kind of see the edges there, right?
As it comes through, and if you can see that kind of over there in
the, in the left corner.
So I'm going to go ahead and beef that up a little bit there.
Oops, wrong one.
My bad.
Same with this guy.
So yeah.
Yeah.
Alright, let's take a look.
Let's see what happens if I make this guy kind of more at the same
speed as the background, if that makes sense.
And then we make him a bit bigger.
I'm not sure if that will work or not, but, again, something something
to try.
So the other thing we could do is we could give a little bit of
forward motion to it, right?
And I'm kind of interested to know how that would work.
Like if I did this
That's a little too much but just a little bit of forward motion to it
to see if that helps with the effect at all.
Yeah.
That that seems like a little better to me.
I kind of like having a little bit of that in there, so I'm going to
go ahead and and see how that, how that plays out.
And that case, then this guy does need to be much closer.
Take a look at what the funeral is at zero.
So I guess the problem here is maybe the camera starts a little bit
too far up to like if I just were to drop it down, just a hair.
Right.
Then the kid could be higher up and that might help.
I don't know if it will or not or if it won't but it just I feel like
maybe that would be a little bit helpful.
So like something like
Something like that, maybe.
Oops.
Something like that and then if we let it go.
So then it halfway it's like here,
See where it's at here.
Bobby comes out of the picture, just really quickly.
Yeah, it's tough.
Let's see how it is.
So I just don't get much feeling emotion from him.
For some reason, I feel like with the Z going forwards, he should, he
should be moving quite a bit.
And so I don't know if that's just because we're not close enough to
him or what.
But I want to get more of a feeling of motion of the, the boy's head
getting bigger, and maybe we just need to move the other part back or
something, but I'm not, I'm just not getting that feel if that makes
sense.
That's, that's a little weird.
And I'm not sure what that, I'm not sure what that's about.
All right, so let's see.
Let me just see what happens here.
Why can't we see anything?
There's the dude.
At Point 2.
We completely lose them but I don't know why.
Why isn't he there doesn't really make sense to me?
Because the camera supposed to be 800.
So he should still be in front of Congress.
We have a near clipping plane, I guess not.
Exactly sure.
But at three, we do see them.
So there is right.
So that's pretty close camera.
All right.
That's pretty close.
Yeah.
All right, so what happens at one?
It's already past him.
I don't know why I'm not getting enough enough zoom on him.
So here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to move the other layer back just to see if that gives me
more some kind of more success.
I don't know if it will or it won't but I just I don't know what else
to do.
So as what I'm going to do, I'm going to make that one be a little bit
more since this is a fake camera move shot.
It's kind of hard.
It basically means that we can't just use the net.
Look on the other shots, we just lean on the fact that we're doing an
actual perspective, transform to make it so that we don't have to
worry.
And it all just works, right?
But in this one work since it's kind of a hack we don't really have
any way of, you know, leaning on that aspect of it, right.
So yeah, it's a bit hard to say the least.
all right, so he should be
Now.
There we go.
So let's see if this is any better with that sort of moved.
If we could, if we quote see what we can do, not sure.
Yeah.
Alright, so now we just got to make this be a little bit more.
Ocean.
Starting to get it, starting to get it.
Let's make it a little more forward motion.
That's Court of more the, okay.
So that's more what I wanted.
I guess I just wasn't.
I didn't, I should have set up the motion over the boy's head first,
that's more what I wanted to feel like, was that.
So, that's, that's much better.
Okay.
So that should make things a little bit easier on us.
Now, we're going to have to dive down deep, you know, further down to
end on on the, the toys, obviously.
But other than that, I think now, we're in much better shape.
Right.
And will probably want to move the toys back a bit as well, if that
makes sense.
Yeah, so that's that's getting better, right?
That's getting better.
Yeah, yeah.
See what happens at T normal equals one.
So this is the end of the cutscene can just look at what's that?
Last shot.
That's correct.
We've got this shot.
And that's correct.
So now let's hope that that's roughly good in terms of the of how the
shop looks.
Yeah.
So again, not the best but it worked.
I guess as well as could be expected.
So, let's take oops.
I don't know why I stopped it running, I guess I just did for no
reason.
So let's take a look now at the next scene.
I think I think I like this next scene that's coming up here.
I remember which one it is properly.
Let's see how we're doing.
All right, so I'm going to clear out these flags.
You get us back to something a little more reasonable here.
So cures, oops,
See what we've got.
Move this 2 - 10.
There we go.
All right.
And this one is probably going to be.
I think another slow zoom in.
I don't think there's this one's doesn't have any weird.
This is not a weird camera one.
Yeah.
So there we go.
That's looking pretty good.
So really all we need is a slow zoom on this one and that's probably
fine.
I don't know, maybe it needs to be a little bit.
Sir.
Oops.
Then that in terms of motion motion speed,
Motion speed.
Here we go.
Let's put that out a bit.
Just a teens.
All right.
So, let's go ahead and add that next layer in.
And it's going to be a little bit closer.
Oh, you know what?
No, it's not.
It's going to be exactly the same.
There's Santa Claus, he's just doing a Santa Claus kind of thing,
right?
Just hanging out.
I think that's all good and I believe this one is actually animated,
so this is going to be.
This is going to be added.
This is going to kind of add a new feature.
That makes sense.
You can see that there's an animation, a slight animation to this one,
right?
Like so that, that makes sense.
So I think
We will have to add a feature to our system, shouldn't be too hard to
do, but let's go ahead and finish up by making layer for.
So that's just a little I guess.
That's one of the people who's in the foreground, is there is there a
fifth as well?
Yeah, so there's a fifth as well.
Okay, so let's see.
I feel like this, I feel like something's a little weird here.
I'm going to make these all those smaller so I can see them better.
I thought there were more children in the shot.
Normally, I don't know where they are.
They're like, missing.
I thought they were off to the left.
I wonder if I exported it raw or something.
That's kind of weird.
I don't know.
What's going on there.
I'm a little confused.
But I guess that's just me.
So I may have to update the our pack at some point.
If I figure out that that's actually not what's supposed to be
happening, but yeah, all right, so there's little girl who supposed to
be in the foreground and then we've also got some tinsel there.
Let's make that tinsel happen.
There's some tensile as well.
So that's it for that shot though.
That's really all there.
That's really all there is.
So we'd have that there's a little bit of Animation to it was the only
thing.
So that's something that we're going to have to do.
All right.
So let's see.
I guess, yeah, I'll just assume for now that it's actually correct.
Although, I think I must have explored wrong because I feel like there
were supposed to be more children, it and I have no idea where they
went, they're just gone, apparently, sorry kids.
So, all of that is, is
About right?
I think and all we really need to do is fix these other ones here.
Alright, so for the tinsel, let's get the tinsel up to the correct
size.
The tinsel is going to be pretty close, I think probably, right.
It's going to be more like that sort of thing, probably even closer
than that, maybe not sure.
Yeah, probably something like that.
And then I just want the tinsel to be kind of up.
I don't, I don't want to be so in the way that makes sense.
So it should be something more like this.
You know I'm saying?
Maybe like that.
Oops.
Yeah, something like that.
That seems more correct.
Yeah.
And then, I believe the kid in the Santa are supposed to be a little
bit further down, so I believe they're supposed to be maybe, you know,
something more like this.
That sort of thing.
Yeah, if I remember correctly.
So, yeah, I'm almost certain.
There are some kids missing.
So I'm gonna have to react sport one of those.
I'm not to, I'll have to rebuild the AJ at some future date because
there's supposed to be some kids kind of over in the corner.
And I don't know what happened to them when I was saving the files.
I must have like, misplaced, I misplaced a bunch of children, it was
not my intention, right?
That was a mistake.
I don't didn't mean to misplace children, you know, I try to always
keep track.
Well, the children as much as possible unless they're just being
annoying in which case you may, you may decide to misplace them on
purpose, just so that you just straight-up don't have to deal with
them, you know, and that's also fine.
That's we totally we are totally fine with that on.
He made here, we encourage that just a good way to get rid of
children, that are kind of being you know, really just just
Just really getting in the way.
All right, so let's let's move for over just a little bit there.
She kind of occludes a little bit of the scene though.
She includes the other girl.
They're a little bit too much so maybe, maybe she shouldn't be quite
that large.
Let's go ahead and make her kind of a little more tiny there, maybe
just a bit lower.
Yeah, that seems that seems okay.
It seems fine.
And maybe we'll move Santa Claus over because I think he's not over
where Shadow is on the ground there.
So I'm going to move him and the kid over a bit too.
Yeah, that's a bit better.
That's a bit better.
Yeah, maybe just a lips, just a, just a touch, slightest touch.
I mean, I don't even want to tell you how slight I'm talking about
when I say slight touch.
I mean like the slightest dissed, okay?
So if we wanted to make this cutscene, do the animation that it's
supposed to do, right?
Then what we need to do again, is we
We need some way of saying that these two things don't play at the
same time, right?
And so we can do a pretty simple version of that.
If we want to again you know we can just sort of have Knockouts in it.
Can just say all right this scene layer we have a like mint.
I'm right in a Max time or something.
Something that says where the thing, you know, exists, if that makes
sense and we're, you know, where it doesn't.
And so, all we would do with that is allow ourselves to have a
knockout range and so we could have something like this like knockout
or or wood, called transient layer, something like that.
A layer that's only going to up here during these times.
And so if we want to set like one of these transient Flags, what we
could do then is say like oh okay you know these two guys are both
transient layers and so the timing at which they're going to happen,
this one's going to happen you know for the first half of the shot.
For something.
And this was going to happen for the second half of the shot, right?
Really pretty straightforward.
And we can we can even make this just a parameter like, you know, Shot
Change time.
And that's 10, right?
And then this would just be shot change time.
Shot Change sign.
So that's, that's really it.
Then what we do is inside red related scene is as we go through the
layer, indices, what we would do is say, you know, all right.
We'd have a, an active flag or something like that.
And then we'd say, if active, and we'd only push the bitmap Evans
active.
And then we just say, okay, it's true by default.
If the layer Flags indicate that this scene layer flag is trans that,
this is a Transit layer, then we just say, okay, if the T normal
For the thing.
Oh, and I guess that's true.
That's this is normalized time.
Here we go.
If that t normal is greater than or equal to whatever the Min time is,
Then it's past the point where the layer should start being active and
then we just want to check to see if the Tina Rose less than the layer
Max time.
And you notice, I intentionally use the greater than equal to and less
than here.
That's because I want to be able to have the layers change precisely
on an instant.
So that that way if it's a time is exactly 0.5 we would switch up to
the next one.
So I'm just making sure that the intervals don't overlap on one
particular specific T.
So that's very that's intentional, right?
So there's
There's, you know, the sort of the animated version, right?
And you can see them kind of doing their little thing there where you
put the hat on and, you know, we could think of doing something like a
fade.
There, we like transition between them with a fade and I don't know if
that's a good idea or not, but but, you know, we could also consider
it if you want to do something like that.
Then what we do is we kind of do a ramp between the two.
I'm not sure if that's good for the style that we have here, but point
being.
That's that's what that looks like.
Alright?
Okay.
So let's let's try to do one more in the five minutes we have left
because we're getting there.
We've done quite a few of these shots and that's good.
We've done about half of them.
Here we go.
Here's shot five.
Don't know why I did two layer counts there.
So here's shot five and I'm shot five.
Let's go ahead and see what we've got.
Okay, so again, it looks like we got a backdrop coming in here.
Let's see what that looks like.
Yeah, that's just a standard backdrop shot.
I think we could probably actually keep it back a little bit further
though.
Let's see what our next layer is.
Like I said, okay, so here is our like, this is like our big entrance,
really, you know, this is like this is, this is this is the money shot
right here, people, this is where it all starts to happen.
So I'm going to make that the, the background shot.
I'm going to actually make that be quite a bit further away.
So it's slower moving, right?
And and make it bigger.
So I'm going to make it more.
Like this, right?
So it's only subtly moving and I might make this be more of a dramatic
camera move.
So it's got a little more motion to it.
I think that's what we might do here.
Okay, so now I'm going to go back up.
Get those doors in there and will maybe make the doors.
So we need those doors to fill the frame, right?
These, this is going to again leverage that transient flag for us
because we're going to have this is going
Something that disappears halfway through and gets replaced by the
rest of the layers, right?
So these are all going to be shot, change time to 1.0 the next one's
and although actually I guess technically, maybe not all of them have
to be.
Maybe the other ones could be not.
I think this is where the doors burst open.
I don't actually remember.
Let's see.
Yeah, so that's where the doors burst open.
Yeah, so that looks pretty good.
All right.
And so then we need
Then same thing for the next one.
This is going to be maybe just a touch closer than the other ones, and
it's going to use that same Shot Change time.
And then, we're going to go ahead and get that next one up there and
there he is.
Finally, finally coming into our story.
Krampus the demon, everyone's favorite holiday figure bursting through
the doors.
He's a little too big.
That's true.
So
Go ahead and back him up a bit there.
And this needs to be a little white larger.
It looks like okay,
see how that works.
Nice.
So, you just kind of comes in, you know, you can't stop Krampus.
He comes in whenever he wants to come in, you know, I'm saying?
I mean, if he's going to come into your orphanage, he's going to come
into your orphanage.
What can I say?
And I think we should all just Embrace that.
All right, so he's going to be a little bit closer.
I think I wanted to have a little bit more motion on them like, yeah,
relative to the rest of it.
And then I'd like to also there's a snow layer I believe in here, so
I'd like to get that in there.
That also should be.
Yeah, there we go.
There we go.
That is just an idea.
I'm liking this shot.
This is this is just great.
I'm liking this shot a lot.
That's that's really satisfying.
Yeah, that's good stuff.
That's good stuff that
Is video games, ladies and gentlemen, video games.
And so we got that all in there and that's nice.
I probably want to change the pan up a little bit to just give a bit
of motion to it.
A bit of upward motion to it because it's like kind of go.
So it's kind of going up towards Krampus like that.
I feel like that's better or Krampus.
As the case may be, if you're pronouncing it more, the sort of the
Continental Style,
So that's good.
I like that.
That's making me.
That's making me happy.
So the Q&A technically begins now but yesterday, I don't remember
there being many questions about this sort of thing.
So I might do one more because I really like doing these scenes.
It's fun to see them getting into the game, you know?
So I'm just going to go ahead and say, let's do shots six while we're
at it.
Let's see here.
So let's do shot, index 6, knock back the layer count again.
And this one is, of course, now the Krampus is in, of course, as you
know,
Krampus is going to go after the kids.
That's just how he rolls.
What can you do?
He's there for the children who are naughty, that's just that's just
what he does.
You know, that's how he does, that's how he rolls.
All right.
So this is probably going to be.
He's probably about you know let's say 8 m 8 meters back.
So let's go ahead and get that sort of placed a little bit more
appropriately.
Like so looking pretty good there.
Like in that Krampus.
It always gets great when Krampus comes into the picture in my
opinion.
I feel like that's when things start to go well for any video game as
soon as Krampus is in it.
All right.
And so there's no transients in this one.
This one's I pretty sure I remember.
It's just
it's just
Regular regular layers.
No, no weirdness there.
So, here we go with the layer count there.
Let's up that, there's that snow.
Again, kind of just giving a little bit perspective, perspective, to
things.
I try to export the snow on separate layer.
So you kind of got this feel of like they're being more spatialization
to each individual image if that makes sense.
So, okay, let's go back up to, let's get another one.
There, there's the the poor little child but he's chasing, you know,
it's hard to get away from Krampus.
Obviously, Krampus is very difficult to run from.
I'm sure.
Are all aware of this.
If you've ever been chased by Krampus that, you know, that that's
true.
And I think we've all been chased by Krampus at least once or twice.
Okay.
So let's move him over a little bit.
Let's move him.
Oops, that was wrong direction.
Let's move him over a bit and down a bit as well.
He should be a little bit lower.
Yeah.
So it's something like that and I think we want to be kind of going,
maybe a little bit up towards Krampus again.
So I feel like we
The shop to sort of pan, a little bit to the side, right?
We want to be panning.
Oops, not that side.
You want to be panting.
I think to the side so it kind of so the kids kind of running away,
ish ish, you know.
Not exactly but dish.
So I'm going to make that a little bit more subtle, just going to make
it like that.
Just so the centering is that kind of thing.
So that that roughly looks right to me, I think that's good.
Okay, we've got one more layer, which I think is the tears.
There might actually be two more layers, but there's a
layer of Tears if I remember correctly on the kid.
Yeah.
So that we're going to have to make a little bit smaller though.
There it is.
All right.
How small should that be?
There are the tears I'm going to set the, I'm gonna lock that t in
place for us.
So I can line up those tears.
So, they should not be coming out of his nose because it's not snot,
it steers to.
So let's go ahead and sort of move that over a little bit.
and just see something like,
This is where if we were going to do a lot of these cutscenes, it'd be
nice to make a little positioning, something, we can position them
with the mouse, if that makes sense.
So, I think that just needs to be up a little bit, like, something
like that.
Maybe.
There we go.
So I think that's about right, that's where we would want it, but I
don't know if we want that to move separately from the kid probably
not because it's sort of tied into his tear duct there.
So maybe not.
And let's go ahead and add our fifth layer as well, right?
There's a fifth layer, some other little kids.
That I think there's only fifth there, I don't think there's a six
layers there.
Pretty sure.
Oh there is my Lord, lot of layers to this one.
All right, so there's six layer two.
All right, so for this layer we just need this to be a little bit more
sane.
So this would be, I don't know how big should be, she'd be well, she'd
have to be about as big as he was if she's a little bit front of him,
right?
So maybe like almost on the same layer.
Almost, I don't know.
Not sure.
Something like that.
Oops.
Yeah, something like that and then with the garland that's got to be a
little bigger.
And that's also going to be I guess a little bit further up, probably
guessing, not sure.
Yeah, something like that and maybe a little bit more out of the way.
Not sure.
Where that should be exactly.
So that seems like it wants to be smaller than that in higher up.
I'm guessing, I don't know.
I'm not really sure what's meant to happen with those.
I feel like that's a kind of tricky one to place.
All right, let's unlock that and see how this is looking.
It Feels Alright to me.
I feel like the snow should be a little more mid-ground.
So I guess one thing I would do is say let's make that snow more like
in five, something like that.
So that it's a little more mid-ground that feels a little bit better
to me.
We could even make it so that it's a little smaller Maybe.
No.
All right.
I'm pretty happy with that.
I'm going to go ahead and see where we're at on q&a's.
Let's find out.
If anyone has any questions, if nobody has any questions, I'll just
keep doing the cutscenes because we're you know, coming down.
Few Khan.
Why not pass?
How long each cutscene is instead of it being the same for all
cutscenes?
Well, we will, we will do.
That it's just at the moment, we don't really have to do anything with
that.
We're not sinking them to music.
So yeah, we I guess what I'd say if you con we will be doing exactly
that it's just right now we only have to lay them out.
We don't have to do much but
G 7 for the weird camera movement seen, what do you think about
interpreting against a curve?
Instead of linearly?
I like that because if it was rotation, you would do a curve.
But I don't know.
Looking at the scene, I don't have high hopes for it ever looking
quite, right?
So I don't know what to say about that, exactly.
But yeah.
And you know, for those of you asking Yang Shanley does all the
artwork for handmade hero.
She is a an illustrator
So, yeah, any of the artwork for the game looks great.
I love it.
It and like I said, I don't really are tracked, it too much.
I just let yangshin do it.
Or like I'm just like, okay, you know, there's going to be Krampus
going to come through the door and I'll like do little sketches of,
like, here's like how maybe the scene is laid out.
Like you know, there's a Krampus here, there's this there, right?
And then she just kind of comes up with everything so she you know she
made up what all of these people look like?
And what Krampus would look.
I can and so on.
So if that makes sense.
All right, so if everyone seems to want more
More cutscenes.
Let's just do them.
Let's just do that.
Make sense?
You can always ask questions Tomorrow.
There's always there's tons of is the handmade hero, every weekday.
You can always ask questions or let's just let's just be these are so
much darn fun to do.
I could do them all day.
All right, so let's see where we're at with shot index 7, let's see
here, start with one layer.
So here is our Intrepid Hero.
This is another counter motion.
Seen by think this is going to use the neck.
This one's so easy.
We should be able to do this one in no time.
There's only two layers that are thing is
Krampus in the kid.
That's it.
And so, these are going to be counter motion.
Layers are going to be two layers, counter motion the kid slides to
the right.
The Krampus slides to the left.
That's really all there is to it.
So the cameras is moving, right word, right?
So it's moving.
It's moving this way.
It's not zooming.
So it's basically this kind of a shot.
And so this one's going to have seen flag, whatever seem layer flag
transient.
It's going to have seen flour counter
X, right?
So it's basically going to oh, what did?
What did sap?
Oh, that's great.
I don't know why.
I thought that was going to happen.
There we go.
So it's basically like this kind of a shot, right?
It's a kind of a shot where you sort of have the two things moving in
opposite to reveal, right?
Each other to review know the Krampus reveals what's behind the
Krampus
quote unquote.
Yeah, I think that's right.
That's roughly what supposed to happen.
So I think all we need to do is move the Krampus over slightly, right?
We just need to move the Krampus over slightly.
We maybe need to move the camera more, right?
So, it moves out of the way, a little bit more of what maybe we don't.
I'm not sure.
And then we kind of need the the kid to be a little bit more hidden at
the outset, right?
So we need the kid to be just a little, just a tear to the side.
So that's about it and you can kind of see, you know, obviously very
heroic little limbless child is stopping the advance of Krampus here.
I don't want to, you know, spoiler alert, spoiler alert but that's
what's happening, right?
That's what's happening.
So, okay, so that's fine.
So we can keep going again with shot eight.
Let's get shot 8 in there.
Let's go ahead and do this.
We don't need shot change time on these.
I guess I don't think shut change.
Time was necessary in any of these, actually.
It's just just the ones that have the transient layers, all right.
So on shot Seven.
Let's open that up.
So I'm shot Seven, we've got another Krampus.
You can kind of see I don't know what happened here.
Why are we why are we still sliding to the side?
What's going on?
Okay.
Oops, I headed the wrong one.
My bad.
Shot 7 shot, eight.
Okay.
All right, so if I take Rick care, if I get rid of this one, we're
still still got our shot Seven.
The Perils of using such a tiny window.
I can't see what I'm editing.
All right, there we go.
All good.
All better.
Now, let's go ahead.
And do this.
Okay.
Now we've got our Krampus as we should and we can do our zoom in like
we were doing before, right?
I don't remember how many layers it has for what they are.
There's the glove magic glove and I think there might be there might
be some other layers.
I don't really know.
I guess there's some kids.
Let's see here.
Let's try and get all the stuff tiny or so I can actually see what's
in there.
There's three layers and what's the fourth layer already fourth layer.
More of the sort of Garland that hangs down from the ceiling.
That's it.
So it's just those four layers, so that should be relatively
straightforward.
Okay, let's start with layer 1.
As we generally, do a minute, that should be centered, right?
And it should be encompassing, the whole screen.
So, something like that.
I'm going to check it to T normal zero.
That looks good.
Let's go ahead and get the layer count up to 2.
There's my glove.
The glove is a present.
Obviously, as you can see, I'm going to go ahead and float that down a
little bit so that it's it's sort of like a being presented to them.
What just happened?
Why did I get smaller?
I know why that happened and I don't know why.
That should be about, right?
I think so.
I'm going to take a look at the motion of that might unlock to normal.
See what happens there, the hand should be moving a little bit
differently and so yeah, I guess that's not quite enough.
So let's maybe do that.
Like that would be better.
All that's still.
It's a bit too small.
I think maybe it should still be that big
because it's supposed to be about the size of his head.
It's a big glove.
That's pretty good.
All right, so let's now just put in those other two layers as you can
see, Krampus is kind of a very positive.
You know, very positive figure in the story.
Yes, he was coming to chase down the children.
Once he saw that the little little hero child is actually good and is,
you know, is trying to do good things.
He decided to
Going in and chasing the chasing the other child down.
And he decided to maybe spend some time, helping out this little kid.
Unlike Santa Claus who basically just ruins everything all the time,
just like in real life.
So yeah, so there's that.
Okay so you can kind of see we got those kids in the corner there and
then we'll get that Garland in and then we'll be done with this one.
So, there we go.
Oops.
Might need to get a little further back.
All right.
And that looks like it wants to maybe go down a little bit, you know.
Correct me if I'm wrong but I feel like the camera kind of wants to
dive a little bit more towards the glove.
Right.
Like that.
I feel like that's a much nicer pan.
So, you know, I don't want to, I don't want to be mr.
Indulges himself all the time for all this stuff, but let's just, why
not?
Just go ahead and do something like this too.
if we just did senior interval and we just said, or we could even just
do
Interval R32.
Bob, or something like that or Min value max value.
I don't know.
This is getting ridiculous.
I'm just going to say that's parameter.
This is a bit of a hack but I don't really care because again this is
not, you know, going to be very heavily traffic code or anything.
I'm going to say / Amex Bram, why like that?
I'm going to pass a generic Vector there and and then when we actually
have these guys here I'm going to bundle those up.
So I'm going to do I'm going to do like this sort of thing.
Right.
Don't know why they didn't give me an error.
I should have given me a partially bracketed initializer list there.
I feel like that's a little odd, you know, I don't mind telling you
it's a bit odd, a bod if you will.
But let's see what happens there.
Go ahead and loop around there.
I think we made sure our tinsel.
There is a little little off the loft.
All right, that's better.
Okay.
So, what I want to do here is I want to make that glove.
I just want the glove to like move up and down a little bit.
So I want to be able to do something here where I can say oh seen
layer flag you know like floaty or something like that.
And if I say floaties, I want it to kind of just bob up and down.
And so, what I'm going to do is say, okay, it's floaty and then the
first thing will be like how much it pops up and down.
So maybe like half meter up and down.
That's probably too much, but we'll start with that.
And then the period which will just be, a regular period.
Let's say,
And we'll, and then we can just tune those two values to get whatever
it is that we want, right?
And so in here, we can say, the the peasy, right?
We can precept that so you can say, Okay, layer flags and seen layer
flag floaty.
We can say the p y plus Z equals.
I don't know.
The sign will just use a sine wave, so like it Bob's up and down just
kind of gradually.
So we can just say, okay, whatever the / a
Whatever that / Amex is, that's how much it Bob's and whatever the
params why is, that's how fast it Bob's and we just plug T normal into
it, right?
Not know layer there.
So that's all we're talking about, right?
And so that's that's not nearly fast enough.
Obviously the site the period needs to be more.
Honestly a sign weight signs, going to take 2 pi to go through and we
are only going from 0 to 1.
So we need that period to be much higher.
Don't know why I ever would have thought that was a good value and
probably need this to be less than a meter but let's see.
Yeah, so there is it's bobbing kind of slowly, right?
So, I don't know if I like that effect or not, but that's the, that's
the idea.
What do you think?
We'll leave it in for now?
I don't know if it's a good idea or a bad idea but there you go.
So that's good.
That's how much time you got.
We got another nine minutes.
Let's do one more shot.
Let's just do one more shot.
So let's do shot nine.
There it is.
I think this one's just a straight Zoom.
No, it'll probably assume up to the to the corner actually.
So let's see here.
all right, so
there is our little, our little kid going back to his room so it's
probably going to be a zoom down towards him, right?
So it's probably going to go you know, that way and this way right?
That sort of thing, maybe a little less, a little less this way.
There we go.
That's looking pretty good, right?
I think.
And yeah.
So so that's about all we need for that layer, really, I think.
So.
We would just need another layer at this point, right?
Which I think it's literally just to like ceiling layers is all it is.
Yeah, that's it.
I don't know if there's forth.
Yes, there's just it's just like some stuff that's up close to us on
the ceiling.
That's always there.
So these are going to be like much smaller and we're probably going to
do like one, two, three like that sort of thing, right?
Because they're going to move past this pretty quickly.
I think so.
Yeah.
So let's go ahead and get those placed.
I'm going to T normal 0 this so I can place them at zero and and
adjust them that way.
So let's start with this.
This guy here, he's going to be like this, this garland that kind of
goes over in the corner, right?
He's he's like,
I don't know, he's like this sort of thing.
You know I'm saying?
Something like that.
I don't know if that should probably be bigger.
Maybe, that should be a little bigger actually, not sure.
Probably possibly.
How do we feel about that?
We feel pretty good about that.
Oops.
So I guess one really is the right number for that, okay?
So that seems about right for him.
Let's go ahead and make the lamp a bit bigger as well, because the
lamp should probably be bigger maybe even bigger than that, might even
be like that kind of a thing.
I feel like and probably over at least a little bit.
You know I'm saying?
Cuz it's got like a hard Edge there, so that it should be.
It should be like, off on against the edge,
Like that.
And so then all we need to do is get this this other Garland in there
and the other Garland's going to be have to be quite a bit bigger
actually.
There we go and that'll be just up against the ceiling, I think.
So that's just needs to be raised just a smidge.
All right.
So now I'm going to unlock it from T normal zero and just take a look
at what happens when we zoom into there.
That feels nice.
All right, so I think that's it.
I think that's it for now.
I think we've got everything there again, we got some good work in
here.
We got all our cutscenes laid out.
There's only two more to go.
So, we're almost done.
We just got to do two more tomorrow.
And then tomorrow, after we do those two will make it so that they all
play back in sequence.
And then we've got an opening cutscene - the sound which since we
don't have the voice acting yet.
You know, that's how that's going to go, all right?
Do you enjoy the screaming of the Linker lamenting an driving and
sisyphean Agony that he can't write to the exe?
Yes, kind of because Microsoft's Linker is kind of a piece of junk and
so anything that causes it pain and suffering is totally acceptable to
me.
Icarus.
Do you have someone lined up for voice acting?
No, and that's why.
In fact, the voice acting isn't included in this pack is because I
haven't found the right person to do the the narration for the opening
sequence.
So when I do get a good narrated opening, I will include it in a pack.
The first thing with a glove, it was a left-hand glove, and the next
it's a right-hand glove.
Well, that's that's, you know, if that's the case.
That's, that's yangshin.
She may have to fix it because I don't know, it's not really supposed
to be different handedness.
Let's find out which one we're doing here.
So that would be this seam.
It's a right-handed glove in the second one.
Yeah, you're right.
Although actually, I guess what I could do is I could flip it.
If I wanted to, that would be pretty easy, actually, right?
I could flip the glove from from
from left to right, which would make it a right-handed glove, which
maybe is a good idea because there's no reason that it has to be going
in any particular orientation.
Especially since it's glowing, that makes sense.
Let's see here.
The door was open in the first scene, but closed before Krampus
enters.
Yeah, that's true.
That should probably, I should probably make some notes of, like,
stuff that needs to get fixed for, like, art notes.
Basically, just revision, art notes.
There.
Maybe I think there was one with the door closed.
I don't know.
I'll have to ask.
I'll ask you a question about it.
I don't know where that one went.
Backhand shot to.
I noticed a gap at the top of the window.
Is that still there?
It might be
Let's take a look.
Are you talking about shot to or shot three?
Actually.
Which one do you mean?
Do you mean this one?
This is this is shot to oh yeah, it does look like the like it's too
far down for it up in the corner.
So I think that might I think I don't know if that's what you're
talking about, but that does look like there is one, so maybe
That better.
Yeah, it's not enough Parallax in this one.
but anyway,
keeper Caleb.
Can I adopt one of the children?
I don't really know what the policies are of this particular
orphanage.
That's a good question.
Try the community for voice acting quite a few of us would be willing
to would be willing and Happy Bikes I guess.
But it would have to be someone with a very specific like with who's
very good at voice acting, right?
Like I want to the voice acting to be high quality.
Will this game have support for left-handed people?
I don't know.
I don't suspect it would be really all that different to play
left-handed or right-handed since it's like four directions on the
left hand for directions on the right hand, regardless of which
handedness you are.
So
Could you explain the fading for animation?
Which fading what fading are we talking about anything special planned
for the 256 day?
No, I do not have anything special planned.
What's the best way to get my repo blessed on GitHub.
It's kind of random but the current blessed Restrepo hasn't been
updated in 3 months.
Email me is the best thing to do
You should add a little bit of snow on that one to add depth.
Yeah, I should add, I have to update with snow.
I think I need to write these down.
I think on the just so I can remember them here.
Of course, I don't have a pen because there's a couple different
things like glove handedness and so on.
But I don't know what they all are.
You know what I could do is I'll just put them in here.
Okay.
We will need our own trig function, so we can stop signing by using
the C standard Library.
Yeah, I mean, again, the C standard Library still supplies, a couple
things for us right now.
It's supplies sprintf, IT Supplies, sign it supplies floor, and seal
it supplies.
Round f.
Basically, the things in here.
So and squared F, some of these are really trivial.
So some of these won't take any time to implement like, like
literally, no time to implement other of these such a like, like
Florence seal, might be a little, take a little way to work cosine.
Sine will take an 8 and 2 will take a lot of work.
Those those will be much harder to replace where some of these other
ones are way easier like truncate.
We already saw, we already know how to implement.
It actually I'm sorry round.
We already know how to implement that with using sse2, so,
Her Domina you mentioned earlier that we could make the animation to
go smoother by fading.
For example once we have to put a hat on the hero I was wondering what
that would look like.
Yeah that just would basically be taking the time range and picking
apart of the time range to just change the opacity on those two layers
so that one ramps from 1 to 0 and the other Ranch from 0 to 1.
That's it.
That makes sense.
I noticed the cutscene dip Maps, don't scale with the window size.
Why is that?
That is because that we are not asking, that is not how our window
works.
Right now.
Our game is rendering at 1080p always.
So it doesn't ask the game for a smaller window ever.
It never does that if it
Week, it would work just fine because we can already change the
resolution.
So for example, if we wanted to we can go to and made through to
handmade dot CPP.
We can already go to like this thing where we are doing a full, we're
asking for the full back buffer.
If we want to, we can change it to a tinier back, buffer, right?
So our engine totally supports
You know, we're doing things resolution Independence.
You can ask the engine to produce a smaller image if you would like
and it will and it will keep everything correct.
But right now, for our testing, we don't try to.
We don't have Windows past the window size in as what the resolution
that we want.
Is that makes sense because we I want to test at the actual resolution
the game is going to run at which is 1920 by 1080.
We're never going to let you resize the window of the game.
That's like there won't be a window for the game.
The game will be full screen so you know it's intentional that that is
cropping
Mr.
Harris mentioned.
You have Florence seal are kind of difficult.
I mean, they're not nearly as difficult as sign or a tan, but they're
just a little bit difficult because in order to properly handle all
cases, you actually have to use some magic constants and do some
craziness Martin's Mosaic.
Oh, posted about this.
Actually, he posted some code on GitHub for it even and it's not, it's
non-trivial like you have to actually stop.
Now if you choose to use sse4 or whatever, then it's super trivial
because there's actually just a straight up.
Lauren seal function, but if you're, if you're assuming that you're
using sse2, then you have some work to do.
And again, it's not the most hardest work, but it's definitely like to
do it, right?
You can do a crappy job, but if you're trying to it, right?
It's a bit of work.
If to think it through, it's like, you know, four or five instructions
or something that you have to do.
Why do we want to reduce sign?
We want to reduce sign because well it's really all just for
educational purposes.
Like there are maybe some reasons why you would want to actually
reduce sign for real which are performance-oriented reasons, but the
reason we would want to redo sign is simply because this the point of
the stream is to teach low-level programming and if we call life
Functions to do things will never learn how they're done.
And so sign is actually relatively complicated function, and if you
just call it and never know how it works, then you don't really
understand how you do like power series, approximation Zoar, Taylor
series approximation, or things like this.
And so learning how to do that, very important.
Because if you ever want to simulate a function, that isn't in the C
runtime Library, you would not know how to approach it.
Right?
And so, so part of, you know, the whole idea of him here is to not use
any libraries so that we learn
Learn how to do everything.
Rather than relying on other people to have done it for us.
And so, you know, right now because by default, everything linked to
the C runtime Library.
If you program in C, we still call some function, see the runtime
library.
But before we ship I would just like to go through and take you know
the handful that we do use and replace them with our own versions so
that we can literally be completely library free.
And everyone can see how to implement all of all the things that are
in the C runtime library and again there's no
Overwhelming reason why you have to do that to ship a game.
You could certainly ship a game with the c runtime Library.
It's just for educational purposes, I don't want to have there be a
bunch of mysterious stuff that no one knows how it works, right?
So, alright, that's it for now.
I'm going to call it a night.
So let's go ahead and close on down.
Thanks everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, and I'm pretty happy
to see those cut scenes in the game.
There are a lot of fun and yeah, just nice to have some some cool art
in there.
So thanks for joining me.
If you would like to follow along, with series at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
If
Reorder the game.
It comes with source code so you can play around with it and follow
it.
We do on the stream, you can also get the art assets early.
Like, if you want those cutscene assets to play with as your
programming, along with the series that comes with it as well.
So go ahead and check that out.
If you're interested, we also have a forum site, you can go to.
If you'd like to ask questions about the series, we have a patreon
page, you can go to if you want to support the series, the video
series.
And we also have a tweet bot.
You can go to which tweets the schedule at you.
Speaking of the schedule.
Cool tomorrow, 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time.
I will see you guys back here.
This will finish up our cutscenes, and that will be a pretty fun
thing.
All right.
Thanks everyone for joining me until tomorrow have fun programming.
I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.