Hello everyone and welcome to handmade Heroes.
Sure, we could a complete game live on stream.
We our I think we finished pretty much all of our bug stuff in here.
I don't think there's anything else left that we wanted to pay
attention to budweis.
So we reorganized our to-do list yesterday and today I think we should
just take one more look at it because we kind of stopped in the middle
of it.
But I think we pretty much did most of what I
To do there.
Here is our to-do list and you can kind of see what's going on there.
So it looked to me like the most sensible thing probably to do, was to
go ahead and just take care of that sorting stuff.
So that we have a way to disable sorting when we're in the debug
system because we don't really need it.
We don't really need it there and it slows things down tremendously
because there's so many little rectangles for the for the fonts and
stuff and there's really a couple different ways we could do that.
There's two ways we could approach that problem one.
Way to approach that problem is to be could just say, look, we're not
going to sort it all in the debug system.
The other way we could do, it is try to package those elements up into
something that is sorted as a unit.
So, you know,
We could do rectangle lists and stuff like that that we kind of build
this this whole thing and they don't need to have individual entries,
right?
Because in the game it kind of makes more sense to have individual
entries for every Sprite because they tend to do get sorted around or
that sort of stuff, but if you think about the use case for the debug
system, you can sort of see that.
It's much more like well.
Okay, this this whole line of text is pretty much known that it
doesn't need to get sorted other than as a big block, right?
If you were going to sort it because it's not, like, I'm going to let
the, you know, the first letter B in front of something and the second
letter B behind it, they're all going to be sorted as a unit.
And so, you can understand how another approach to it would be if we
did want to enable sorting in the debug system, which maybe we do,
then what we would want to do is just say, hey, there's got to be some
way to do something.
A little more elaborate here, right?
Where we can cut a bunch of these things up and have them go through
the sorting system in a more sensible fashion, right?
And so, I don't know which one of those I want to do, I guess.
One thing I could look at just kind of briefly and maybe we'll, you
know, we'll just do that today.
One thing I kind of wanted to look at is, you know, when we actually
print these things out.
So we have I believe in the debug UI stuff.
I think we've got some stuff in here like text.
Yeah, I think techstop is where all this this action happens.
And so you cut a scene here, one of the things about tech stop, when
we get past it is we do you know, we do get the string here and you
can kind of see that when
When we have the string, we do know ahead of time, probably the
maximum number of bitmaps that we would push on there, right?
So if we wanted to, we could probably do something where we do a more
elaborate piece of work here.
So, for example, you know, let's, let's just take a look real quick
over here, just to kind of underscore what I'm talking about.
Give you a little idea of what I mean.
So if we run the game here, right?
We can go in here.
And we can turn on that show sort groups thing.
And you can see that like all of these things are are sorted.
And you know, when I open one of these you can just see there's just
crazy.
Just absolutely crazy numbers of these sort groups here because every
last little one of these rectangles is thrown into the sorting system.
So every last little character is thrown into the sorting system and
and again, there's really no reason for that.
Now, another thing that I point out here is not only is there really
no reason for that, but if you think about it, there's
Really no reason for the renderer to have to think about all of those
things as being separate anyway, either.
Because as far as its concerned, it would like, to know something
probably like, oh, I just got a hole like group of things, I can just
render here.
I don't have to, like, step through them and think about different
clipping rectangles for them and stuff like that, right?
So let's take a look at this, just real quickly.
If we look at builds Sprite graph here, you can see that it's taking.
You know what?
36 percent of the time, they're right in debug mode.
And and obviously, if we compile and release mode, you know, we'd get
a lot more out of that we can sort of see, just do a quick test to see
what that would be.
Like, because I would like to know I care about its performance in
debug mode as well, unlike other pieces of code, potentially because
in this case, I want to go to use the debug system and not have it
slow things down, but I do kind of also just want to know about
roughly speaking.
What am I going to get there?
So if I, if I go over here and look at the profile, let's take a look.
So we can see builds.
Graph here.
It, what is it at 10:00 there?
10% and I don't know if it ever gets particularly slow.
It's still not too bad but it's, you know, it's like it's quite a bit
slower, but you can kind of see.
And that looks like all rectangles that looks like all these
rectangles are problematic.
I'm
And I'm guessing you can kind of see how the sort stuff goes there.
You can see it go.
So so we could try, right?
We could try to eliminate some of this sorting by just having all
these things grouped together.
And like I said, I don't know how how plausible that is.
But I just want a quick take a look.
So let's say, for example, that we wanted to make that be something
that, that, that would, that would, that would aggravate.
Let's just, let's just see quickly, what that would be.
So I think that's what's that of the frame view.
There's a profile bars.
Is that what it is?
Now, it's not profile bars.
Its frame bars, right?
So
I believe it's this guy right here and in the frame bars thing, it
looks like what we do is we go through the stored events here and then
we, yeah, we do the rectangles.
And what are we doing here?
We're just going the region wrecked is.
Yeah.
The the Min Y and the max.
Why?
Like that?
So the problem here
To a certain extent.
Is that we don't necessarily know how many rectangles we need a
priority, right?
We don't really necessarily know how many of those rectangles we're
going to have.
We know that we're going to have frame count numbers of rectangle
slots but we don't know how many stored events there are per per slot
but we could certainly do something a little bit more intelligent
here.
If we wanted to something that was more of
Like hey do these rectangles in blocks, you know you can imagine doing
them in blocks of 256 at a time or something like that where we just
kind of slot them in two like a series.
And and so just to give you a little bit idea of what I'm talking
about.
So let's say we go over to and would render group
You can see on here.
Whereas our entry, there it is.
You can see when we have something like render render entry rectangle,
you can see what we've got.
We've got the pre multiply color at the p and the dim what we could do
instead is we could do something like this.
And I guess I could even do it this way.
Right?
Where when we push one of these render entry rectangle patches on, we
could set a count field.
That was like, how many of these are there going to be?
And then instead of just sending down a single render entry rectangle
as part of this process?
We would send down a whole group of them, write a whole cluster.
And since the batches gets sorted as a group that would take pressure
off the sorting system as well as pressure off the rendering iteration
Loop because it doesn't have to do things like look up the clip
rectangle for every single rectangle.
If it knows that all of the rectangles in the batch are the same,
right?
So that's pretty straightforward.
You can see how that would work right?
And what I did here was I just kind of left ourselves an array of one.
But really, we would make this video
An array of however, many we wanted.
Like, when we actually push this on the render stack, when we set the
count, we would just make it so that it's, you know, however, big
however, many we feel like storing in that batch.
Right.
And the
Same thing would be true in the case of the render engine pit map.
You can see here how we've got it.
Like, okay, we've got these pieces of information.
We could do the exact same thing with the render into bitmap, right?
We could do something like, say okay, there's a render entry bitmap
batch, and that is just some number of these
Right.
So that hopefully is pretty clear how we would do that.
And since those things in theory should just flow through the system,
we wouldn't have to do anything special to support them.
The only thing we have to do is make sure that our to renderer back
ends understand when they encounter them that they just need to
iterate over.
However many of them.
The count field says that there are right and that would be all there
was to it.
Furthermore we could if we wanted to then just get rid of the concept
that you can ever put a
Under entry rectangle on at all and just make it so that you're always
putting on a batch, right?
And it's just a question of if you only wanted one, then there's a
batch of one
So that seems pretty straightforward.
Yeah, and I don't know that there's anything
Yeah, I don't know that there's anything particularly weird about
that.
Think that would just work.
So you know, if we want to do something like that I'm just thinking
how we would probably do it when we go to do something like draw frame
bars here we would have to do something like that where we would open
a batch so we'd probably do something like
You know, rectangle batch begin batch.
and we would pass, I guess the render what would be past their we
would pass the
Probably we would pass.
I'm guessing the render group.
And probably, that's it.
Maybe we would need the you, I transform.
I'm not sure that we would though because the transform can actually
vary per rectangle.
So I think it's actually just that, right?
although, since the clipping rectangle point,
I guess you have to pass.
At least which cliprect you're going to be using but again, I don't
know that that was stored in there anyway.
Where is the clip?
Rect stored.
Is that in the render group.
It is in the render group so I guess we don't really even need that.
Just pass.
Something like, hey, we want to send down rectangles 256 at a time.
Most, and we want to do it on this render group.
We'd have this wrecked batch thing here and then we would just have a
thing where it was like, oh yeah.
You know, when we call Push wrecked or whatever instead of passing the
render group, we would pass like the wrecked batch, right?
So we'd say, like out here is a wrecked patch, you know,
here's a wrecked batch like so and that would be it.
I think that would basically be it and then we'll all we would have to
do is when we were done at the end of this.
We would again just close out.
We'd close out that batch right.
Oops.
Um,
When outside there?
so, I think
We just be something like that.
We probably have to say that this is a rectangle batch.
So I think we just have something like that and then all we have to do
is actually put something on the other end of it that allows that to
work, right?
And so if we were to, let's see here, if we were to go to the render
group itself,
And in here, I would actually implement.
This would look something like
and batch in here.
I don't really know that there's all that much that I would need to do
here.
It's mostly just bookkeeping.
So this is here it's going to be minimum or I should say Max
rectangles per batch.
So, pretty much.
What we would do is this rectangle batch thing, would just store the
current like basically I need to do is create sort of, you know,
almost a bin.
That's going to hold these rectangles as they come in.
And all I'm going to do after, you know, I after they come in is issue
them as the batch.
If I get to the max number, that can be held in that bin, I will
simply make a new bin and start putting more in it, right?
And that's it.
That's all I'm going to do.
Now there is a little bit of a catch here and in fact, so in order to
support this, I think, you know, I'm not there's there's two ways I
could do this and I'm going to do it the way that makes things kind.
Easier on the using Code as opposed to being space minimal because I
think that's probably the right decision here, you know, we're
probably not going to be super memory, constrained, a lot and handmade
hero.
When we go to ship, I think we want something here, like total count
and used count.
Right.
Because what's going to happen is we're going to have to reserve space
on the render stack for however many the total number we might push is
but then we're only going to use some subset of those, right?
We're probably not going to use them all.
And so we need to know when we encounter this guy.
How many of them we need to render but you also need to know how many
of them there were to begin with these so that we can skip over them,
right?
That's all.
Oops.
Okay.
And I think this actually wants to be a pointer.
I don't know why I didn't do it as a pointer probably because I don't
know what I'm doing.
That's okay.
Okay, so yeah.
All of these guys, I think they really want to be pointers.
The reason is because they're going to update state in that guy.
So that's probably needs to happen.
So then we've got these wrecked patches.
They are whatever they are.
And I think that all would be fine.
Okay, so what do we store inside this rectangle, batch?
Well, let's just see what we actually find that we need in here.
So, when we begin one of these, right?
We're going to do is we're going to push one of these render entry
rectangle batches.
We're going to push that on there.
So we need to
Have the entry for it.
And furthermore, the entry itself is going to have these guys.
So I don't know that we need, we probably really don't need anything
else like we can probably almost just return the pointer sort of.
The only reason that we can't is because we need to potentially
sometimes update the pointer, but I think we may be able to get away
with only ever using the pointer that might actually just work.
So, yeah, I'm going to switch over to this window.
So I don't
Run the risk of.
Running behind my head.
okay, so if we have this rectangle batch,
I'm going to go ahead and say that the entry equals with the entry
that we're going to push, right?
And then the entry will have the total count set to Max, rectangles
per batch and
The used count will be equal to 0.
Then when we end the
Ouch, I guess there's really nothing that we have to do when we end
the batch.
So really, you know,
Really, we could consider getting rid of the end of H entirely because
I guess there really isn't anything to do and in fact I guess until I
know that I need it for something.
I suppose I just shouldn't have it there right?
Because that's just wasteful at that point and you know we wouldn't
really know if it was working.
Anyway like if I messed it up and there was a bug we would never know.
And then we'd think that we'd done it right or whatever so might as
well just leave it out of there.
And just say okay new rectangle batch and we'll change it to begin in
pair of later we find out.
We need that.
But the moment, I don't know what I would do with that.
So really all we have to do now is sort of re rejigger these routines
a little bit so that they work properly with the batch concept when I
push one of these guys on here, right?
I'm going to be calling one of these push render element things and so
in order to do that, I've got to sort of look at what's going on with
say, push wreck that I want to kind of
I want to kind of copy.
What's going on here, right?
So I am going to need a sort key for the for this stuff.
So when we do the new rectangle batch, I think that kind of educates
me a little bit as to what I'd have to pass her because we essentially
need to do this same stuff, right?
Because we need the sort key to come through correctly.
So we essentially need some kind of Exemplar.
Like, we need to pass, we need to receive some kind of a point that we
could use.
In order to get the render entity basis, right?
We need that.
So that is really the important part of that process.
Yeah, I'm not sure, we don't care about any of this though.
I don't think.
But yeah.
So we're going to do.
We do that?
We're going to have to say, like sort P, okay?
So we come in in the batch, what we want to do is say, and I guess if
the sort if the sort is called we don't need to really record any of
these guys, which is kind of, interesting, I guess if it's behind us.
Right.
So it's even a little weirder than that.
I guess we could just do.
Yeah.
And I guess we can just literally do that.
So you could say, if the basis is valid,
You know then we'll do it otherwise we won't which is kind of
interesting.
Okay.
Yeah, that's all right.
Well anyway,
So what's going to happen here?
is, we're going to
I guess we can.
If this little more explicit is we're going to say, alright, let's say
there's no pointer will make it so that if the pointer is null, then
it doesn't record anything.
And we'll just say when we do this.
We're going to pass, whatever that sort p is.
And we're going to need an object transform for it.
So we need to pass.
So I was correct in thinking before that, we need the object
transform, we need whatever the transform is that you want for
sorting.
So you say this batch, you know, it's using this transform and we can
take a look at what we're going to use Four Points here.
But you can kind of see that it's really not all that big of a deal
because for sorting there actually isn't any Z component here.
So we can actually if we
To just pass, you know?
Essentially nothing that makes sense.
And that should be fine, right?
Yeah, I think that's fine now.
I guess I do have one question here.
Which I guess now I think about it.
This is starting to look a little bit more complicated, right?
And the reason for that is if we actually wanted to have it still sort
correctly, in addition to just the Z we would need sort of the
boundary that we would need the shape that it ends up taking the
maximum area and we kind of already wrote the code for that.
But when we did sort of that other style sorting that other style
thing where we did, what was it called?
We had like this way of grouping things together.
Begin aggregate sort key.
Right?
We had that Aggregates or key thing.
So, what happens when we did the aggregate sort key as we would sort
of, you know, we would accrue those bounds.
And I guess I don't really remember what we did with that piece of
information.
I don't really remember how the aggregation actually worked in terms
of buffering these things up.
You know I'm saying.
Like, I know we did the sort of
I know we did the sort of stuff with
First aggregate.
So we would put our aggregate bands in here and then we would say
But they still have their own entries.
That's the weird part, right?
It's still pushing a sword entry on for these guys,
Which is weird.
So, I don't really remember.
Why that would work, right?
I don't really remember what ends up happening.
I guess it's just they all get assort key that's equal.
They all get sort keys that are equal to each other and I guess we
just sort of made it so that that would just work somehow
Right?
You can see us doing that.
Here we go through them and we said all their bounds equal to the same
value, you know?
And I guess that works.
I'm not sure how we handle that in the backend.
I honestly just don't remember, it's been too long.
But that's all we were doing.
So that doesn't really help us, but you can kind of see what was going
on here, right?
When we push, those guys on we were sort of taking all of the, the Min
and Max and stuff like that.
And we would sort of switch those together for a sort.
And we, if we wanted to do this correctly, we would actually have to
do is essentially the same thing and so we wouldn't really be able to
do a sort P.
It's some sense, we have to do a sort Z here, right?
We'd have to do something like this and where we just passed, whatever
the sort Z was.
And we would have to use the X & Y, would have to kind of be grown
organically from the things that were pushed down the batch.
Right?
So as things get pushed down, the batch we would expand with each
individual one what the rectangle was that enclose them, if that makes
sense.
So yeah, but if we did want to do that, I guess at the end of the day
it's actually not really that hard to do that.
It just means we would have to to modify the third key after the fact
which actually doesn't seem particularly hard so maybe we just do it,
maybe we just do that.
But yeah it here we just basically have a sort Z.
So we say we have the batch, we want this batch, sort of the sea,
we're going to feed you a bunch of stuff and so you can just take
whatever.
bounds are I suppose we could also say that
I suppose, we could also use the for lack of better term.
We could use the
Aggregate Z the like when when the things come down we could use what
their Z averaged out to be as the Sorting Z would be another way to do
it because you're assuming that says he's always going to be the same
for everybody and so I suppose you could do that.
I don't really know how I feel about that one way or the other, but it
seems plausible.
Well let's let's see.
So if I took a look here I'm just going to push this a little further
because I like I said I don't really know, but in here if I just said
okay you know, here's push wrecked.
Here's how push wrecked is working if I wanted, push rekt here 2 to
begin to push onto one of those one of those batches then
What would that look like, right.
It's still going to do pretty much everything else the same.
But here it's going to have its going to get one of those rectangle
batches.
And when we do all of this extra stuff, instead of pushing your render
element, we're just going to, I guess you could say, we're just going
to add it on to that list and we need
Check.
First to see whether that list has space for it.
And if it doesn't have space, we need to sort of extend it, right?
So, there's a couple things we could do here.
First, of all, we could say, well, you know, if the batch
entry is valid because it was not, we don't want to bother, we would
also want to say, if the batch entry
used count is less than batch entry total count.
Right?
And I guess actually I think about it, we probably need to do
This is capture.
Too many if statements.
So if the use count is greater than or equal to the total count, then
we just need to do a new rectangle batch.
and,
That's about it.
Right.
Yeah.
Here we go.
So I need some way of getting the render group.
I'll just store that in the batch I think.
But you can kind of see what's going on here.
So, all I need to do is say, okay, if there is no room, then just
start another batch.
I don't know what to pass as the sort see here, but that's okay
because I could store that in the batch.
If I wanted to, if I want to just call it directly with the Z.
I guess.
I'm just like, I said, I'm still not quite sure about that.
How I want that to work.
But anyway, then we say if we can do one of them we can you know, go
ahead and do push render element.
So really I just need to do a check here.
say if we were able to get one and it can fit
Then we just say the batch entry used count.
Is where we are going to put this guy.
And that is a render entry rectangle.
So we've got our place to put it now.
We know that the wrecked is valid because we're just accessing off of
that guy.
Can't be no anymore because we checked up here to see if it would have
food fit or not.
And so, everything else is just exactly the way that it was before,
right?
So when we do a push truck, this is this is what it would look like
now.
And I don't love how much duplicated code there is there really, you
know,
Compared to the non batch case.
So I don't know how I feel about that but, you know, I guess we'll
just see.
We could try to condense it a little bit more.
In the future.
So yeah, looking at this code, I think that's all pretty reasonable
right there.
Isn't anything particularly unusual going on there?
So the question is just for these rectangle patches what are we going
to do about how to get that Z in there, right?
Because we do have stuff like this.
The spray pattern of the screen area so we can do whatever we want to
do in terms of creating the sort bound from that as we go, right?
That's not particularly difficult.
I do.
So yeah.
Hmm.
So I guess what we would want to do here is say we have the screen
area.
So what actually has to be stored in the actual sort key itself.
Okay, let's take a look.
So we've got the type, we've got the clip brecht and we have to push
the sort key to this guy separately, but we're going to have him.
We could recall we could presumably record where it was and then we
end up with, what's it?
Whoops.
Is it sorts right bound?
I guess yet?
What are we actually pass through here?
So we have sorts right bound, so we need to have the sort key, which
is this stuff here.
And then we need to have the offset, the flags and whatever the debug
tag is, right.
And the flags, the offset, we know what it is.
It's well, the office.
All that stuff is going to be set for us directly.
So really all we have to do is that the sort key in the screen area,
those are the two things that need to kind of be.
You know, more specified.
Now, I suppose.
Since we kind of know.
Roughly that these guys have to be.
These are always kind of these flat aggregate.
Guys, we don't have to worry too much about like we know we're not
going to have a manual sort key in there or any of that other kind of
stuff.
So I don't really know that we need anything, particularly fancy
there.
If we wanted to aggregate out the size,
So I think we could just basically do what we were doing for the
Aggregates in here, where we essentially just do one of them.
Now I would just say we could just do it as if it's a z Sprite and
that seems reasonable
In this case, we just actually disease.
In this case, we agree that those two bounds and the screen bound.
I don't know what we do, it doesn't look like we really touch, the
screen bound here, which doesn't make a whole lot of sense to me.
It seems like when you aggregate these guys together, it would seem
like you would want to aggravate the screen bound as well and it's
weird a little bit that that's not happening, right?
Like, that's really weird and I do wonder if that's a bug.
It kind of feels like a bug here.
It feels to me like there would presumably be
Right in here.
You would want to Union the screen areas together, right?
Oh I guess the reason that we're not doing that is just because the
screen areas are actually used separately when it comes down, I guess
that does make some sense.
Okay.
I could see that.
But yeah, so what we would need here is we would need to have this
who need to get this and we would need to expand the screen area as
the guys get pushed down.
So it does seem.
I mean just looking at this you can see how much sort of stuff there
is here and so I'm wondering just kind of like how much complexity
there is if it's just like it starts to seem like, maybe it's just a
better idea to just turn off the Sorting, right?
Because this is kind of what I wanted to see like, how much stuff
would it take.
It's like, okay, to actually feed it to the sorting system in a
reasonable way, it seemed like it starts to get to be a lot of stuff.
Would it not be better to just have a thing that just like turns off
the Sorting, right?
And that kind of just seems like a better idea, I don't know.
So I think I may just go ahead and call that and say that that was
enough for me to go.
Yeah.
I don't know about this, right?
Like it just it's starting to seem like just that's too much stuff.
I don't want to have to up to continue with those code path.
And yeah, so just like forget it, you know, not going to happen.
Oops.
How do I get the render group here?
Okay.
so,
If that's the case, then what's the easiest way for me to turn off?
You know, just turn off the Sorting, if I remember correctly, we
already had the concept of multiple passes through the sort, right?
And so if I remember correctly, how this worked is, when we did the
sort entries, we would kind of go through things and we would hit
individual like sort points where we would stop, right?
And you can kind of see I guess that happening here where we do build
Sprite graph, it passes back like a sub count.
Right, so when's Bill's Freight crew, wouldn't build Sprite graph goes
through?
You can see it sort of doing its thing here where it keeps going.
But sometimes if it hits a stopper, which is Sprite barrier, offset
value, then it knows that that's going to be the end of it, right?
And so, what I'm wondering is, could we also do, you know, I don't
know what exactly gets pushed on there.
I'm going to take a look at how we were pushing that on.
See what I've also got to work with Sprite.
Barrier offset value.
So when we push the start bar on there, we've got the sword entry
offset, spread barrier, offset value.
I'm assuming we could also push other stuff on there because that guy
presumably gets ignored, right.
Yeah, so that guy doesn't actually ever get used when the indices come
through.
And so what I'm assuming here is if we wanted to we could also have a
way of specifying in addition to that sort barrier.
We could we could have something where it also, there is also a way to
indicate that everything after that sort barrier until the next sort,
like everything in between those two sort barriers should not be
sorted, right?
So you'd get sub count here, right, like this, and you would do
recursive front to back or whatever.
In the case, where you got one,
Actually cared.
But what we could do instead is when you do build Sprite graph here
and you would get back some kind of information that that you know
after you did this sort.
The next set would not actually be sorted, right?
It would not.
It would just get output directly.
So I think the easiest way to do that if we look at recursive front to
back you can see what it's kind of doing it does.
It's a little out index plus plus sort of thing right here and all we
would have to do is just output.
Those offsets for everyone in the list without ever actually.
Doing any sorting.
So the problem is build Sprite graph as it goes through.
These guys kind of needs to
Give us a little bit more information back so it's going to need like
something like Sprite graph results or something like this.
And we would need the count, which is how many nodes are in it and
then we would also need like what we were supposed to do with those
guys.
Now, note, we build the graph as we go here.
So what that means is that we need sort of the initial barrier to be
the thing.
That tells us what's supposed to happen.
So we need like sort, you know, sort next or something to come back as
the thing.
That tells us what we need to know, right now, it's possible that we
don't actually have to return that because it's possible.
We could check it on the outside as well.
And I have to think about that.
So, when we do that, we do SUB entries, and then we do first sub,
count plus 1.
There's the skip right there.
So if we wanted to, we could actually, I guess
We could actually just just pull it out ourselves so the way we would
do that.
Oops.
I believe is just by saying like, Okay, so
We would grab out sub entries.
And we would take whatever the sub count, the came back, would go that
far into it.
We now know that this is like the Terminator, right?
Whatever that Terminator was.
And the only thing is we don't actually know whether the whether the
Terminator actually existed or not.
So we do have to probably check here something like, if you know,
first index is less than count.
We know we're going to do more of them.
Right.
And so assuming that, that was the case, then we could do something
with the Terminator here to let us know whether we should sort.
So we, you know, we have should sort.
We assume that that is true and then we sort of when we come through
here, we know what we want to do is if something like, if we should
sort.
We do the standard pass like so.
And otherwise that we do the other one.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
So really we would just say
The exact same thing.
Only in this case, we wouldn't probably need any of this stuff.
I don't know that we need the width and the height, even
so, I think we're really just talking about
About that.
So when we do that, we're going to need for.
When we do that, that output, their we're going to need the the walk.
Because it's got to do its output.
So it's going to have to take this as well.
And I think
Think that should do it.
So I think we just need something like that.
It's like, hey, go through this mini and we'll go through starting
here, you know, keep going till you hit the end or a terminator and
when you go through them, just do the output directly.
So then it would be essentially this
It'd be this routine, drastically simplified.
So it would be, you know, don't need any of this stuff.
We don't need any of that.
None of this stuff at all.
Pretty much any of it.
Yeah, so we need literally none of that.
All you would do is just output.
Exactly what the offset is of everyone in this list until we hit the
next barrier.
And that'd be it.
Right.
So again, we still need to return however many we processed because
that's important since it needs to know.
we've got the,
Total number that we want to do here, right?
The input node count and then we've got the input nodes.
These are just the exact same things that are here.
And I think that's it.
You know, I don't really know.
I don't really know what we're going to find out.
So the only thing I think that we need there is we just need a way of
figuring out whether a Terminator indicates that we should turn
sorting off for the next group that comes through.
I think that's really all we need.
So if the sort entries have an offset that specifies this piece of
information that it's a Terminator, then I would suspect and I don't
really know, but I would suspect that we could then say well anything
that we have in here like these flags, for example, we could use for
that, right?
So we could say because I don't really know.
I guess that that stores the index in there so we fly to want to use
that but, you know, really any of these things, they're not getting
used.
So any of these things we could use to indicate what was supposed to
happen there, or we could even have like a different value for the
Sprite barrier offset, right?
If we wanted to
so I'm not sure what I want to do for that since these will not be set
by anybody, I think I'm just going to use the flags fields and I think
so I'm intercepting like Sprite
Barrier.
Turns off, sorting something like that.
And, you know, maybe that's just some weird value like this, it
doesn't matter.
It can be any can be anything at all.
It's not really a flag.
So what I could say is like okay, you know, if the Terminator flags
have this in it.
Then it's going to Peach return true there.
I guess that's a pool, so it doesn't matter.
So you just say hey, if the barrier turns off sorting then you
shouldn't sort anymore, right?
And is that the there's the build
And so, I don't know.
But I'm assuming that that will not do anything yet because we have
not, you know, unless we messed something up and you can see how slow
we are here.
When all of these things are doing their little sort, right?
So now let's go ahead and see if we can actually insert that
Terminator in there insert an actual Terminator that does.
Turn off the Sorting for the debug group.
And we're still going to have some problems with that.
If it's not we're not home free because we are still sort of using
The Sorting in the debug group.
So this is still not going to quite solve the problem, but at least we
have a waitress sorting, that's a start.
So we'll do a push sort barrier in here and we'll have a be 32 that
you can pass, which is like, let me go over here, so I'm not behind my
head which is like turn off sorting
And when I can do, is say, well, you know, the sword entry Flags will
equal.
If turn off sorting, then they will equal that crazy value that I
suggested there.
Where is that?
At,
He'll be this guy.
Otherwise, we'll be nothing.
So on these guys, we don't want to turn off sorting so you know these
guys want to keep it on.
And so then what we need to do is go into the debug group and when
we're about to do the debug rendering, then we can push start barrier
that does turn it off.
And that seems fair.
So in here, when we actually do our, I guess when we do our debug end,
and actually know where we
here it is.
I think this is probably where we would do it.
So I think we would just say right here push this Arc barrier the
turns off the Sorting right and see how it goes.
That does not look particularly good to me.
To say the least.
Let's go ahead and verify that that's actually working, but that is
not helpful that did not change at all.
Wait, what?
What just happened?
What am I missing here?
People
Did I flip the sense of it?
Somehow I did.
I flip the sense of it because I'm not thinking straight, okay?
So what I did because that's just how it is.
I guess is when we actually, where is our sort?
Here we go.
So in our actual sort I said should sort is equal to whether it should
turn off sweaty, but really, I want to say if it's not going to turn
off sorting, right?
So that was just dumb.
So that's, that's better now, okay?
So in theory,
oops, in theory, we are now
Able to get our sorting turned off, I think, right?
Don't quote me on that.
So, there we go.
Yeah.
Yeah, so now we're all good and even in debug mode, we're not too
slow, right?
We're not fast, but we're not too slow.
But now, of course, like I said, we have the problem that if we don't
use any sorting here, we're going to have to be more careful about
when we draw things, because if we don't use any sorting then like all
the UI transform stuff and things like that isn't going to help us.
We're going to have to just draw in the correct order but that's not
really particularly difficult.
I don't really think that's a big deal.
So we can just
These things I think and it's not really the end of the world, right?
Like for example, if we wanted to, we could just in our Tech Stop for
example.
I think we just oops.
Where is techstop sudden you?
I
yeah.
So in these, we could just revert to kind of the way we're doing it
before, where we have the shadow one, and the text one, we just flip
the order in which these happen.
And then I think we restore our text formatting, right?
And similarly, like if we take a look at that, when we draw the button
code, whereas basic text element,
So here we would just say, okay, just, you know, reverse the order of
those guys.
And then we're good, right?
So I think most of the things that we do would not be a problem in
that respect.
The tooltip, we will have to fix.
I think the tooltip is the only thing that really requires it, but as
you can kind of see that's all all well and good, right?
So, yeah, so that's all fine and dandy.
We take a look at this.
Now in most circumstances, it's not a big deal.
You can even see here.
Build Sprite graph has dropped dramatically.
It's almost negligible now, right?
And in that in, even then, you know, it was way up at the top.
And so, just looking at what's going on here, that's that's, you know,
I think that solves the problem because this is all we really needed
for.
We don't really need this to be a solid feature of any particular
kind, right?
So it's all good.
So yeah.
So our tooltips are a little bit broken.
I think that's the only thing that we have to fix.
But that's not, I don't think that's super difficult.
Because they're just going to sort wrong.
So, all we have to do is just fix our tooltips there and I think we're
good.
All right, so that seems fine.
Looks like we're just about out of time.
Let me just quickly.
Take a look at those two.
Chips.
And then assuming that, that's okay.
I think that's a reasonable solution to the problem.
Like I said, I didn't like the batch stuff because I feel like that's
adding a lot of complexity and it's only for the debug stuff.
So it didn't really seem like a particularly productive use of time
complexity in the renderer.
So I think that's going to get rid of it.
So yeah, the tooltips.
If we do add tooltip, those just get called kind of out-of-band there.
So what I want to do is I want to say when we had tooltip
We'd have to sort of defer this until later, and so you can kind of
see how it's working.
Here, we would need some sort of a delay, where we wouldn't render it
until after the fact.
Now, if we are not going to render it till after the fact, we would
need some place to put it.
And so we would kind of need like a little buffer or something.
Just just that
That holds the text, right?
That we wanted to print.
And so there's the caressed that there's the actual text.
So we just need somewhere to put that text and, you know, we could
just make a little buffer here.
I don't.
really remember how we did stuff in here because it's been so long
so I think probably and also, all of these things can go away now if
we want to
So yeah, I don't know exactly how I want to do this but I feel like
probably the easiest way is to just have it be a static thing down
here, right?
I mean, we can just do
That right.
I think that would be it.
Yeah, I think that's it because if we just do something like this,
then we can sort of say we can turn to do two things.
We could just say, like first of all we'd have internal void, draw
tool tips and that would just take the debug State and it would just
Loop through all the tooltips that there were right.
So it just say like, you know, for tooltip index,
Is there a index is less than your dog State?
Tort account depend X.
and then we would just say, like, this whole thing here, I don't know
that we need
Any of that to happen more than once, I think that's sufficient.
I think it's just this
Right.
Something like this.
So we essentially say like okay let's Loop through these tooltips and
then we just need to get the text out.
So you know the text is whatever the tooltip text was.
At that point and then all the rest of this stuff, you know, would
just do its thing.
When we do add tooltip, what we would do there is to say like okay
when you actually do have tooltip you get back, the caressed are that
you're going to fill out the result.
There is just the debug State tooltip text.
It's just whichever one of those you're on.
Right?
And then we would just say, like, well, okay?
We sort of got two cases.
I think I want to do this.
So I guess what I want to do is say okay, got the result if the debug
state
Tooltip count is less than the array count of how many we could fit.
Then we're in good shape because then we just say like okay increment
it and do it.
Right?
However, if we can't, then I think we just want to keep filling the
old one, right?
We just want to overwrite the old one, whatever that was, so because
we've run out of space and that's fine.
Or maybe we don't wanna do anything but I don't know.
That seems fine to me.
So I think that's roughly what we want.
And then when we do this situation,
When we do add tooltip really what we want to do is say that the text
buffer that were passing here, in this case is going to be the tooltip
buffer itself.
Now, since we have actually gone ahead and tried to prevent buffer
overruns here, why?
I don't know because it's just some random game code.
But you know, whatever what we probably want to do is when we do add
tooltip, we would need something like tooltip text or something like
this or tooltip.
Buffer.
We just need two things.
We need the size and we need the, you know, the data.
And so, when we do this, we actually want tooltip buffer results.
We want to say that the result size equals like the size of the debug
State Should I guess.
I'll just say size of Debo State, tooltip text zero.
And then here we'll set the result Theta.
So now when people go to print these out and they get back a tool tip
buffer
Then what they can do is just say like okay text buffer, got size and
then text before data is all we need to do and that I'll just print it
directly out into there and everyone's happy in theory.
I don't actually know if everyone is actually happy but let's say that
they were going to be happy.
And I suppose, I should also say that I'm actually going to put that
up.
So I think that's it.
We just have to actually make this do its thing.
Same here.
and,
Password.
Now recall that we're not actually ever printing this out, right?
So, now, what should happen is in theory, will still have the tooltips
getting generated but we're never going to see them, right?
So we just move around here because they're just getting buffered up
in that array and we never actually do it.
But what we can do now that we have them buffered and we have our
routine to draw them.
Is all we have to do is actually just called raw tooltips at the time
when they would be on top of everything else, and then they should
appear.
On top of everything else in theory.
So right before the end render group, I'll just say, Okay, draw the
tooltips then
and now if we didn't mess it up, which who knows?
If we did will get them.
Oh and of course we have to reset them as well.
So once we draw tool tips when we do
Draw tool tips.
I guess we could do that, right?
When we draw them, we can reset them.
I don't know.
That doesn't make much sense to me.
I think I'll probably do it in here like something more like this.
Like, you know, tooltip count 10, you know, when we sort of
Initialize everything that seems a little bit better to me.
Anyway, so here's the profile.
There's the tooltip and it is correctly.
Sort of hovering over it.
I like that cumulative to point thing.
That's a nice feature and there's our frame, indices.
I don't really know where those are getting printed out, but you know,
they are here is another example of that, let's go to the thread view,
there's an example of them getting stuck.
Act on top of each other.
So that's pretty nice and all that and great.
So wonderful fabulous.
So nice whatever doesn't matter close the program.
Okay, so that is that
And it's time for the Q&A.
We don't have very much time left but I kind of ate into it.
But what you gonna do
also, if you wanted to see it running with the without all the debug
Miss in it,
Looks like we're 60 frames a second.
Now, and we're 60 frames a second everywhere now, so that's nice.
I don't know what we're like in.
Software still pretty good.
We're almost 30.
We're not quite holding 30, but we're
pretty good.
So, that's cool.
Got to go put some art in here and get and like get the actual
z-transform stuff happening because we're almost there and it's going
to be fun to start having world to move around.
And I think
Is internal app out.
If I said, I can turn all other way around, but yes, it's pound to
find internal static.
Could you talk a bit more about the meta programming stuff use at
work?
I'm kind of annoyed at the limitations of C C++.
It looks like the ji compiler won't be released any time soon.
Do actually parse the code and construct an AST or is it simpler than
that?
Yes, I actually parse the coding construct, an AST
Are you a fan of templates or do you use void star instead?
I use metaprogramming.
I don't like templates because I just don't feel they were designed
very well.
So it's always just kind of frustrating to program with them.
Why was the grouping approach for speeding up the debug sorting the
first one you tried?
Would it have been better in some way?
Yeah, so
the reason that I sort of want to do that was because I was like,
well,
it might be nice to have some sorting to have the ability to still run
sorting in the debug system, right?
And now we don't have that.
Now it turns out that we really just didn't need it anywhere and so,
we probably just won't ever needed anywhere, but if we had done the
aggregation system, it means that we can choose to still use sorting
values in the debug system, right?
And that would have been nice.
Would have been potentially nice, but since we don't really have a use
case for it, I'm not sad about it at the moment.
Would you recommend using a DOT bat file or bash script over a cmake
file for instance?
Yes,
That is all I use nowadays.
I find that make files are just a waste of everyone's time.
You end up with slower builds and another whole thing to maintain.
So I just
I don't see anything really good.
Any good reason to ever use and make file in?
You have, you know?
Let's say 500 files, Maybe.
Maybe.
I don't know like at work, I think I can regularly compiled about 150
thousand lines of code with a bat file.
So you can go to a pretty large product size, but, you know, if you've
got 10 million lines of code, well you probably not gonna be able to
write.
And your work are there any people the programming Loop or are they?
Shunned and thrown out.
Obviously I wouldn't hire anyone for my team who programmed in
object-oriented programming, just because I don't want to deal with
it.
But, you know, that doesn't mean that there aren't plenty of
programmers out there who programming training program, writing, who
aren't good, right?
so, you know,
I don't like object-oriented programming, so I don't want to work with
anyone.
Who's going to make me use object-oriented programming to interface
with their code.
Like that's just not something I would be okay with because I don't
want to do that.
So part of being in control of your own programming,
Environment is deciding what you are and are okay with, right?
But it doesn't really make a that doesn't mean that they're that
object-oriented programming is something that, you know, no good
programmer has ever done or something.
So
Doctor sat related to yesterday's, same region issue.
Would it be feasible to merge overlapping regions and then make a pass
to slice it back up into non-overlapping regions?
Unfortunately, no, the reason for that is because some reasons require
an apron and I don't really know what to do.
That is the, that is the problem.
If some regions didn't need an apron, there was a lot of things that
we could probably do, but they do.
And so I don't know about that.
Can you imagine a scenarios where batch rendering might be useful in
handmade hero?
Yes.
So we're definitely going to have one place that we're going to add a
batch type command and that's for particle systems.
I think because in order to get enough particles in there, you can't
be pushing A render element per particle.
That's ridiculous.
We did that for our simple particle system when we were just playing
around with it.
But that's not really a sustainable way to make a part of a system.
So we will probably have a sort of batchi thing for that.
But
Only thing we probably would need it for.
I've only recently started to think about metaprogramming, not
expecting you to go in death, but could you briefly list some of the
features you implanted know?
All the Molly rocket stuff is not stuff.
I really want to go into
We've been composing the music sfx for handmade hero.
If any or do you have some else when that we licensed music for
handmade hero.
So we already have that sound effects wise.
I don't really know what we're going to do.
We'll probably deal with that way.
Further down the line though because, you know, I'll just be using
placeholder side effects that I probably record myself or something up
until the point where the game is like mostly done.
And then we'll probably like because, you know,
We're so slow because we only get to program an hour a night that you
know by the time the game is mostly done.
They're still probably several months of programming to do to like
finalize everything.
And during that time a sound designer would have plenty of time to
replace.
You know are 50 or 100 sound effects with something reasonable, right?
So it's not like a normal product, we're like, well we can't really
wait till the last week of development when the games all done, you
know, but but here like the last week would stretch out into 40 days,
right?
So we can have someone come on relatively late in the project to just
do some sound effects for us, which is probably what we'll do.
But I want to wait till then because that way, we'll know what side
effects we actually need.
Whereas right now, I don't know all the sound effects that actually
need because until the game is, you know, pretty playable.
And you know, you've kind of built most of what you think you're going
to want.
You don't really know what your sound effects list is.
And if you want it, if you try to build it, you're going to do one of
these like design document kind of weird things, we try to plan
everything out in advance and that, you know, that goes about as well
as
Trying to plan out all the code in advance, right?
It helps to have a bunch of ideas about where you're going, but at the
end of the day, if you want to make a meticulous list, like here's all
the Sprites we will need or here's all the sound effects will need.
It's really not super possible.
I think to do that upfront entirely, unless you're doing a very
antiseptic and non-creative development process, you know,
All right.
Looks like a bat, it.
Thank you, everyone for joining me.
For the estate of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game.
My handmade hero dot-org.
It comes with source code so you can follow along with it.
An experiment.
Yeah.
We've got a form so that you can go to if you want to ask questions
about the series.
We've got a patreon page and go to if you want to support the video
series.
We also have a schedule about the tells you when we're going to be
live, if you want to catch an episode live and we have an episode
guide, you can go to.
If I catch up on old stuff, that is about it for today.
I will be back next week, check the schedule, but for the schedule.
But I think it's going to be 8 p.m.
Just like it was this week.
That'll probably be the time from now on.
Just like it says in the trailer just like it says right there until
then have fun programming this weekend.
Maybe play some games, have some fun and I will see you guys on the
internet.
Take it easy everybody.