When ice cream and upload to Youtube.
Okay.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game from scratch.
No libraries.
No engine.
So that we can see absolutely everything that happens from start to
finish when a game is running our computer.
This series is designed to teach you about every last thing that goes
on and we have done a pretty good job.
Getting ourselves up and running.
We basically have a little kind of like stand in tile map that we
created yesterday.
And so we're kind of in the thick of it right now trying to basically
get some notion of what our game engine will have to do so that we can
start building it.
And one of the things that I talked about over the past couple of days
was that you don't want to start building things like a game engine
before, you know, what they have to do and know how you want them to
do.
It only is right.
The usage code.
First is my Mantra.
I say it all the time and I mean it and basically what I mean is we
don't want to write a game engine until we have a game.
I know that sounds a little paradoxical because you're like how can a
game about the game engine?
And the answer is just use whatever the dumbest stand-in thing is that
you can and get the structure worked out properly.
So what we're basically doing is we're just drawing rectangles on the
screen and we're just pretending that those rectangles are going to be
something beautiful later on.
And the goal, there is to basically make it so that we can spend some
time up front without having to invest any time in developing, the
engine essentially making something that that works the way we want
our game to work.
So that we
A look at it and go here is exactly how we want our engine to
function.
So that when we build the engine components that we actually need,
we're not wasting a lot of time designing the wrong then we build the
game only to find out that their clunky and hard to use in the context
of the game that we wanted.
So that's what we're in the middle of doing right now.
We're going to continue that today.
If you are following along at home and you have pre-ordered the source
code on handmade hero dot-org, using the handy dandy pre-order button,
then you should have gotten a link in your email and that link has a
download page.
You can download the zip file which has everydays Source included in
it.
And if you look, we are currently on day, 29, so you will want to
unzip day, 28 source code the previous day.
That is what I am starting with now.
And so if you unzip that and start with that source code, you will be
exactly where I am right now.
So let's go ahead and get ourselves.
Oops.
It's a bad typing day.
I can already tell Gotta Move That.
Keyword out a little bit.
Let's go ahead and take a look at where we were, just so we can
refresh our
Memory a little bit.
We at the end of last stream had just gotten a little rectangle moving
around.
And here is our sort of fanciful little tile map that we had created.
You know, what might be interesting to.
I think just for the for the sake of what we've been doing.
It might be nice to clear, the gutter area to Black.
I don't know if you guys remember basically, we're only filling in
sort of a region that were pretending as our screen.
We don't actually do anything.
With the rest.
So it might be interesting to hear that to Black.
It's just so we don't have confusion about where the screen ends.
That's just something that I think might be interesting.
In the other thing that might be interesting too is to Center this a
little, so we can kind of see the gutter areas.
Well, I don't know, just something to think about I was I think maybe
before I talk about it's just I kind of want to do so we can jump into
the again the win32 code that displays us makes that actually pretty
easy for us to do so, it'd be pretty easy for us to
To make that happen.
Basically, we've got a, we've got a function that sort of displays our
bitmap to the screen.
It's this win32 display buffer in windhoek.
All right, and when we do that, if we wanted to, we could make a
Windows call, but cleared the screen first.
It's called padlet, you know, so we could just we could just go ahead
and call that.
I'll show you the call that I'm talking about papal.
It.
So basically all it does is it says, all right, I want you to do, I
want you to take this rectangle that I'm going to pass in the left.
Basically the left and top.
That's just a misnomer there.
It should be why top.
But I guess anyway you passing the left, and the top, and the width
and the height, it goes ahead and does whatever this operation is that
you tell it to do and Blackness is what we want their we're just going
to tell it to do Blackness and then windows will just do that clear.
So that way the rest of the Wind part of the window that we're not
Drawing to basically is going to be.
Where is that window with window?
Height?
Got here.
The rest of the window that we're not drawing to will just be clear,
but Blackness, so we're not confused.
And the other thing is we'll just set an offset here.
We'll just set a little offset bits basically offset X set X and
offset.
Y will basically set those to be like 10 pixels in or something, just
to leave a little gutter there.
So stretch TI B is the function that we were calling stretch GI B.
That we
Calling to copy our bitmap to the screen.
You can see that it's got an X and Y, dest in there.
So, if I want to, I can go ahead and just set that offset X and offset
Y in here.
And then when I go ahead and compile that we should get a nice.
Yeah, there we go.
So you can see, I just wanted to clean that up.
So we can just kind of see what the actual display is.
Seems like a good idea to me, and then we can go ahead and go from
there.
Okay.
So what we did yesterday is we sort of made
Little, our little yellow.
Whatever you want to call this.
Here are a little yellow rectangle and he kind of walks around.
We were trying to verify as well.
And I guess I'll double verify that just because we were mentioning it
before verify.
That we are getting 30 frames a second.
So that we know that nothing weird is going on, pretty soon.
Hopefully, we'll get a chance to write some debug code that.
Makes it easier for us to always keep an eye on all this stuff right
now.
We have these kind of crazy printf that are going on here at that.
We use to verify some things and I'd like to get out of the business.
I love that but we're not quite there yet.
What, you know, baby steps one thing at a time.
But basically we verified that we're running at 30 frames a second and
we verified that we could do some simple stuff like movie.
Around.
And so now what I want to do is I want to just take a little bit, a
little go a little bit further and just say, let's get the basic thing
working of let's have this this little yellow, our little yellow
rectangle here.
Let's have him actually bump into stuff so that when he hits the the
edge of the tile map, right, let's have him stop.
Right?
So that he doesn't sort of collide with things and then let's also go
ahead and make something so that when he exits out through one of
these doors.
He actually goes to the next tile map.
That's a, that's a pretty basic set of things that we should do.
And let's just, let's just go ahead and do that because I don't think
that'll be too difficult to do so because those are sorts of things
again, that we have to kind of, we have to kind of see how they work
so that we can start to build an engine around these things.
All right.
So let's take a look at what we've got here in our code.
Again, for the tile map, we just slammed in and I think I said this
yesterday.
Very clearly.
We're just doing exploratory code here.
So you want to just do the simplest possible thing.
Don't overcomplicate anything.
Don't think about code cleanliness or any of these other things.
You just want to get the simplest thing working and then build up from
there.
Okay.
So, what I want to do here is, I want to figure out some way when I
move this guy, right?
Because I've got a call here, this call right here.
I essentially have something where I'm moving the player around, and I
want to know whether when I do this move, I want to be able to say if
the move is invalid, right?
If I would have moved into an area of the town map, that was occupied.
I want to disallow that move from happening, right?
I do not want the, the player 2.
Able to go somewhere that they shouldn't be able to go.
And so in order to do that, I need to look at the tile map, obviously.
So I'm gonna go ahead.
Put that time up there.
But really what I need to do is I need to know for a player X and a
player.
Why I need to know whether the player is, you know, where that x + y,
is relative the tile map.
Because if you think about what we've got, right, we've got this tile
map on the screen where the tiles themselves.
Occupy several pixels, right?
So the
The tiles in the pixels are not the same and so we have is we have a
pixel location of the guy and we want to map that pixel location.
Like let's say the pixel location is here and this is the tile map
coordinates, right?
Are something like this.
You know, we need a way of saying for a particular pixel location of
the guy or a player location of the guy, we need to map him into where
he is in the tile map, right?
So I want to be able to pick that and go.
Oh, that's 33 in the tile map so that I can see if that location is
occupied in the town map or not.
And stop the guy from going there.
Right?
So let's go ahead and see if that's true by.
Basically, let's go ahead and write something that will sort of do
that.
At check.
Basically will say, okay.
You know, let's see.
I need to basically compute player tile X and I need to compute player
tile line.
And those are going to be computed off of these values.
Now.
I know and I got to move these up here to, I know that our tiles are
this wide and this High, I know that they start here in here.
So the first thing that I need to do, right?
And I guess I should do this on the diagram, so it's clear.
We know that right here, that
Upper corner is given by upper left X and upper left y, right.
So what I want to do is I want to turn whatever the players position
is into something that's relative to that first.
Right?
I want to make it relative to the upper the minimum, the minimum X and
Y of the actual map.
So what I want to do is, I want to subtract whatever their position is
from this position because that will give me the distance along X that
I would have to go to get to where they are.
Right, which is just like that.
And then the
Distance along y as well, that I have to go to get the word.
They are so that that is what I want to do first.
And again, those of you at home who know, all sorts of things like
vector math and that sort of stuff.
Don't worry.
We are getting to all that stuff in coordinate systems, but I'm just
trying to go through this from first principles so that everyone can
see how we get to the final stuff that we want to do.
So, so what I want to do is I want to make it relative to that.
Right now.
It's relative to the screen, right?
We're talking about drawing the player at player X and player, why?
You remember, we computed where we were going to draw them, we compute
it off this.
So these are basically pixels but we can't use pixels.
We need to use map coordinates.
And so the first thing is to make it relative to the to the origin of
the map, right?
Okay.
So we do that we say let's go ahead and subtract those upper that
position appear again upper left X upper left y right.
So I'm going to go ahead and subtract upper left X upper left Y and
that will give me something relative to the
The corner of the tile map.
Then what I want to do is know which of these buckets.
It falls into tits, fall into the first bucket.
Second bucket, third bucket, right?
And that is just a simple divided, right?
If you imagine that this, this right here, right is the tile with each
one of these is one tile with.
If I want to know how many tiles over I am.
I just have to Tech take his x-coordinate and divide it by that tile
with and it'll tell me one, two, three, four, right?
If he's there.
But it's going to give me a fractional value.
Right?
So, basically, if I, if I divided this, if I divide to, where he is
here, by the tile with, I would get some value less than 1, right?
Because it doesn't hit one till it gets to here.
Right?
So if I were to truncate that value, remember, we talked about
truncation.
We're on the number line, right?
You've got wherever you are on the number line, you go back to the to
the next lowest number, right?
If I were to
Kate that number, that would give me the correct tile slot 0.
If I go over here, right, then if I were to truncate that it would
drop me down to one.
As soon as I go over this boundary.
I'll start dropping back to to as soon as I go over this boundary
also, driving back to 3 and as soon as I go over this boundary, I'll
go to for, right.
So all I really need to do is divide by the tile with and then
truncate and I get Which slot I go into and I can do that for x and I
can do that for y and figure out where my time at.
I am, right?
so if I divide by the tile with,
And I divide by the tile height here, right?
Which happened to be the same, but I'm going to do the math as if they
weren't just so we can always decide to change the rectangular Tiles
at some point if they really wanted to write oopsie Max little
overzealous there and then I go ahead and do that truncation.
So I'm going to go ahead and do the truncation here.
So we'll we'll go ahead and truncate now, you notice I'm not rounding
right?
I am not doing a round.
I'm doing a truncation and one thing that we might do to, you know,
this might be nice.
Let's go ahead and do this.
Let's call truncate real 32, right?
And that truncation, just does this exact thing without the rounding,
right?
Makes sense.
So I'm going to go ahead and and and actually and do it that way.
These should all be in line.
By the way.
There's no real reason not to be Such trivial functions.
So I'm going to make a truncate which just basically does that and
that way we can see in our code.
It's so instead of looking like a cast, it'll it'll give a little more
information to the person who's reading it.
So they know that we were trying to do something very specific.
We're trying to truncate, we're trying to
Location here right now.
We've got just a bunch of things to discuss here again, but I have to
kind of meet her them out over time.
So let's just focus on this for now.
So maybe this divide this will actually give me the title X.
Tau y that I was looking for and from there.
I can now look up into this tile map thing and see.
Now there's a problem obviously, which is that I don't actually know
whether it's going to be valid or not.
Right?
I don't actually know whether I'm inside because I could have had any
values.
I might be outside.
The tile map.
So, one thing that I probably should do is I should start off by
saying, okay is and you know, what, we also are trying to do a check
here.
So let's let's I want to do this.
There we go.
Okay.
What I want to do is basically compute a speculative value.
So, whatever, the new player Y, and the new player X would be right.
I want to do those, and then check those before.
I actually
Really?
Commit them to be the new player location, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and compute those.
I'm going to go ahead and check them.
And so I'm going to be doing is valid.
I'm going to assume it's false and then I'm going to say if the player
tile X is greater than or equal to whatever so 0 and less than or
equal to whatever the array size is here.
So our tile Map size was currently.
And, you know, I could go ahead and go ahead and do this right here
tile map count.
X is 17 and tilemap count Y is 9, right.
I can go ahead and make costumes for those.
So here's the town that count X Loops X and here is the tile map.
Count.
Why there we go.
And so I'm going to go ahead and check to make sure that I'm within
those boundaries, right?
So I'm going to say if we're greater than 0.
So we're not off the left side basically and the player tile X is less
than the time.
I'll map count X and so I've got UPS.
What's going on there?
What did I do?
Why are we not matching emacs?
Never ceases to disappoint these days.
Okay.
That was just an e Max.
It's got bugs and how it thinks that you Opitz things are opening a
template and then it's just it's it's awful.
Anyway, okay.
So there we go player Tau y less than tilemap count.
Y, and there we go.
So we're just going to see if these are within bounds, right?
And if they're within the bounds that we're trying to that of our tile
map, we can now look up in the tile map and see whether the tile map
is occupied, right?
We can see whether there's
One or a zero in there, right?
So is valid right?
If that well we can just do it explicitly to first, we can say,
tilemap value is going to be equal to our tile map right here and
using the lookup that we actually just computed.
So player, Tau y comes first because again, these are in sort of
inverse order.
You look up the way that sees irate syntax is is this is the the least
significant part and this is the most significant part of the sort of
the indexing into the race.
So we want to look this way for X.
That's this.
This is X here.
And this is why right?
Okay, so when we actually get that, tilemap value out, whether or not,
we can move, there is essentially equal to whether or not that tilemap
value equals 0.
Because 0 means is an occupied and that we can move there right now.
We've got other things that's not going to be great because well,
there's reasons.
We'll see exactly.
So we're going to probably want to do a little more than that, but for
the moment
If that's if that works, as long as it's valid, we can go ahead and
accept those positions like this.
Right?
So let's go ahead and do that.
Alright, and so we do have one problem right now, which is that our
guy is not himself actually in the map, right?
He starts way out there.
So we kind of need to move him over here somewhere, right?
So during initialization, you know, basically,
In here, right?
Nice reply, move.
This all the way up to the top.
So during initialization, when we actually go and say, the game is
starting.
What I want to do is I want to go into the game State and set this
player ex-player.
Why here?
Me first, create it to be something that's going to be at least
somewhat useful, that's going to be a value.
That's not already standing in some place invalid.
I'm just picking this number out of a hat.
I don't know if it's actually going to be right.
No, it's not.
So let's try a little bit further.
Since this is initialization.
I can't use the restart trick here.
Unfortunately.
Okay.
So there we go.
So now the guy moves around and basically, you can kind of see that I
can't get into, right.
I can't, I can't get into things that are blocked but
But like I said, there's some some weirdness is there such as the fact
that?
Well.
Okay.
So some of them are by Design like we said before, on the previous
frame, we want to be able to Eclipse things when we're standing on
them because we imagine that the guy will be a little sprite here and
connect an eclipse kind of what's in front of it.
So that's actually not too bad.
But what we do want to do as well as we want to stop the guy from
going into things like like that.
We want to take into account his with because right now we're only
checking the point.
That's actually the player location.
We're only
Checking to see if that is moving into a tile.
Invalid, that that's, that would be invalid.
So he can go all the way like halfway in to something without getting
stopped.
So we want to do is actually check that Outer Edge, right?
We want to check to make sure that the outer edge is is not going to
hit something, right.
So there's a couple ways that we could, whoa.
Oh the flashing.
Yeah, so that's pretty interesting.
So we're going to have that.
Yeah, ma'am, wonderful have to deal with that a little bit.
So basically, I don't know if you can see that.
We're kind of getting some flashing there because of the Pat, but
Blackness thing that I put in there this this this Pat but Blackness
this thing because that happens before the stretch GI B windows will.
Sometimes if the page flood happened in between here, you'll just see
the Blackness before the stretch divots.
So we kind of want to only actually clear.
The parts of the window that we're not drawing to instead of instead
of doing this.
So we could set the clip region or we could clear the different pieces
of it, you know, stuff that I really don't want to have to do right
now because it's so irrelevant but let's go ahead and do it anyway.
So if I wanted to clear the four rectangles that would clear out the
the region that we're at.
You could imagine just saying, you know, I don't know if you know what
I'm saying here, but if we just cleared these
Has basically instead of actually clearing the whole thing.
That's a pretty quick way to just get around that problem.
So if we did 002 window height to offset y, basically that would clear
that Top.
This would clear that top piece and then the bottom piece, of course,
would be would be offset y, plus buffer height and it would be the
window width and
Whatever this is- the window height, although we could actually just
past the window height because windows will clip it for us.
They're so that's fine.
And then here, we have to clear, the gutter, on the left side.
Again.
We don't care if we overwrite anything, so b00 to window height and
offset X and then this will be offset X Plus buffer width and that
would clear all the way to their.
Okay.
So so this is just complete nonsense that I've made here.
Is that right?
Yeah.
I think that's
Correct.
I don't actually know window with is not a member, right?
It's just right.
So, yeah, so all I was trying to do there and I think I did it right
again.
I don't even want to go into detail because that was just Randomness.
So, yeah, that looks right.
So, all I try to do is just basically clear this rectangle here, this
rectangle here, this rectangle here, and this rectangle here, right
in.
So that we'd never overwrite this and get that annoying flashing that
was literally all I just did, because it was going.
I mean, so I decided to rid of it.
All right.
So anyway, we're in we're colliding with the tile map now and we just
want to do a little bit better job.
Again.
We're going to have to work.
We're going to have to do stuff, way better than what we're doing
right now eventually, but again, just to sort of try and build up from
first principles.
I'm just showing you the stupidest possible thing that you could do,
right?
All right.
So let's try and at least make it so that when we hit the edges that
we stop.
So what's the easiest way to do that?
And and this is I'm hoping this leads kind of conveniently into what I
wanted to talk about and I think
Think it will as far as this issue is concerned.
So if we start to look at this, right, what's a real easy way?
If you think just think for a second?
What's a real easy way?
We could fix the problem that I was just talking about in.
Let me go, I'll go ahead and bring this back up again.
So, I'm talking about this problem.
I've got this guy and he runs into the wall, right?
And I want to stop him here, but he runs in that far, right?
And the same happens on the other side, right?
So, what's an easy way that I could make it so that that stopped
happening.
Right?
What could I do to prevent that?
Well, one really simple thing we could do is to just check because we
already wrote the code to check up one point against the tile map.
I could just check the two other points, right?
So, that'd be real easy to do except for the fact that I got a cut and
paste all this code, right?
I got a cut and paste this whole thing.
So it would be nice right to pull this out into a thing that just
checks the point in the tile map, right?
That would be
Be handy.
So that seems like a pretty good compression to make here, just to
start with.
It seems pretty obvious, if I want to check multiple points.
Let's just make a function, that returns.
This is valid for the point.
Right?
So let's go ahead and do that.
And let's see where that leads us.
Right?
So, I'm going to go ahead and make a function here.
That just says, is point.
Let's say occupied or something like that, right?
I don't know.
Something like this.
So for maybe is, is, is
I'll map Point empty, right?
so,
I want to do is I want to say, all right.
I'm going to take in now.
Whatever this X and Y is, so it's a test X and a test.
Why, right?
I'm going to take those in test decks and a test wide.
And I want to return whether or not it was it was empty or not, right?
So is it empty?
If it's empty, I'm going to say that it's not empty and then we'll see
if the tile map value equals 0, then we'll say that it is empty.
Right?
And I'm going to return whether or not it's empty.
Does that make sense?
Pretty pretty.
Eight forward there so you can see if I compile.
This.
We've got problems, though.
Obvious rather to the relatively obvious problems.
And that is that there's a bunch of data about the tile map.
And that data isn't really easy to pass.
You're like, let's say I come, I'm going to need the upper left, upper
the upper left X, the upper-left why I'm going to need the width and
the height, the tilemap.
I mean, the time app itself.
So you can start a you can sort of start to see this is an indication
to you.
Again.
We're talking about archives is an indication to you of what things
go.
Together, in terms of what you will want to pass around, right?
And although in this case, maybe you could have guessed these things.
It is always easier and always more accurate to let them come about in
exactly the way that they just did.
Right?
Okay, no longer.
We don't have to do any guesswork.
We basically know that functions like this are going to either going
to do math on the tile map, right are going to need these exact things
because they won't be able to do any math without it.
They're going to need a well.
You know what?
I've got them to find right here, right?
They're going to need all that stuff, the upper left.
Upper left.
Why the tile with the tilite, right?
They're going to need that.
So let's just go ahead and say that that's part of some structure that
we call a tile map.
Let's say we don't know what we're going to call it yet.
But let's call it that for now.
So if we pass the tile map, that just makes it convenient for this
thing to get access to all of the aspects of atomic that it's going to
need to do its job, right?
And so again, this is just an organic way to figure that out.
So we don't pre-plan.
We don't guess we know and knowing is always better than guessing.
So we go ahead and we do that and let's go ahead and compile that you
can see we need some more data here.
We need the count, right?
We need so we need something in here.
That'll tell us basically the pal map tile map.
Count.
Let's call it Dimension Dimension X.
Tilemap.
Well now it's count, taxes better.
So we know.
Yeah, tilemap count why?
Let's just have those two in there.
Right?
And so then we'll change these tile map like that.
I'll nap count X and this will be tilemap.
Well, and you know what?
We could probably get rid of the word tile map because it's already in
there, right?
So we can just do count X count.
Why?
There we go.
And now we have a kind of nicely functioning thing.
We just don't know where to get the actual tile map data from
Well, we can totally do that.
We can totally put the tile map in here, but we have a problem, which
is that technically, if we want this thing to be relatively flexible
and not care.
What size, the town map is we want to probably make it so that it
doesn't hard-code in see what the width and height are, so we kind of
need to turn this into the same accessor like we were doing up here
with our pixels, right?
Where we do a bite for Pixel where we do this kind of thing where we
do math to unpack the X&Y basically, to figure out where in the town
map.
We are with an X and A Y.
Now,
It's the same exact math.
We use before, right?
If we have that tilemap, and this is, I guess is what we want to call
these the tiles.
I suppose, if we go in the tile map, when we access the tiles, we want
to do the same axis.
We were doing before.
We know that the X just works the way that it that it always does it
steps one through.
So we can just add the X and because every, for every X tile you go,
you're going to go over one entry in the tile map table, but since we
are now basically turning a 2d thing into a 1D thing.
That?
Why, every time you go up one and why you're going to have to advance
by the entire tilemap count in X, right?
And I'm going to diagram this out for you in a second, but I want to
make sure that compiles first.
So there you go.
Okay.
And so, what I'm talking about here is what we did in the
excuse me.
Let's see here.
Let me go ahead and delete this guy.
There we go.
So what we did right is originally, we said we wanted tilemap, and we
had sort of a height and a width count.
Right?
And we had see basically do the addressing for us.
So we would fill in a why when we want to access it, and we'd fill in
an X, and we would just get out an entry in the tile map, right?
And so, we just
Lives.
This as a 2d thing right where we would plug in an x value that goes
this way and we plug in a y value.
That goes this way and that was our conceptualization of it and see
did it for us but we need to do is we needed to say?
All right.
We're no longer going to declare what the size of it is.
We're just going to have a pointer so it could be any size we want
later on.
In order to do that.
We need to basically have a way to do our own Dynamic array accessing
that will will essentially map this array to some
Arbitrary chunk of memory such as we can still access it in X and Y.
And so what we want to do to do that, right?
Is we want to use that same Z pattern that I've been talking about a
lot lately, right?
Basically, we stick the Row, the first row of things into the first
second, third, fourth, fifth sixth, seventh entries or whatever,
right?
Then we get to the end of a row.
We start the next row.
So we just packed the rose in.
So basically this row, right?
This row Maps into the first part of the buffer.
Right, then this row Maps into the next part of the buffer, right?
And so on and so forth till we've had all the rows so that leads us.
You the computation that we need to get.
We want to access something in here when we want to change an HW right
into something.
That's just one access or, right.
So we had an x y and we want to change this into a single thing like
an N.
We just want to have one value that we enter.
How do we do that?
Well, it is always going to, to unwind in the same way when we unpack
those rows X is the smallest accessor.
It moves by one.
So, basically, our X remember because our X was, this is our
And so, if we were accessing into the first row of X, we would always
just use whatever the index actually is.
So we just use x, right.
So we're going to add X to our accessor when we have to compute what
our accessor is.
Oops, should do that yet.
So if you have tile map.
We know that we add X and that moves us through it.
But for why we now know that for everyone in why we move we would move
a whole set of x's we move a whole row.
So we need to take that width.
Right?
And we need to multiply the Y times, the width to know how far to go
and that leads us to the canonical form of how to access a 1D thing.
In a 2d way.
It's always the, the least.
Again, accessor, right?
Plus the next least significant accessor times.
However, large this thing was.
However, large the, however, large the, the maximum value, you know,
the sorry, the number of elements in whatever this thing was
accessing.
So, the number of elements in a row, right?
Which is the width in our case and we could keep going, we could have
a three-dimensional thing, right?
We could have a thing that was packed three dimensionally and we just
have it again.
We just have Z
X width x height, right plus y times width plus X, right.
So you just keep multiplying dimensions on because remember, if we
were going in Z, we have to account for an entire two dimensional
piece.
That was packed in.
So we have to do the width times.
The height is how far you'd move in Z to get to the next one.
Right?
And so this just chains out forever to however many dimensions.
You want packing n Dimensions into one D is just
This relationship that happens and you'll see it everywhere in code.
So that's all we're doing here.
Right?
And you can see that, this is the way where is it?
But this is the way that I've written it out, right?
You can see that I wrote out, whatever that count, X is every time you
move some one in, why you're going to move that many in X.
However, many X's there are total in one line and then the x, of
course, is just its own incrementer.
So that's that, that sort of that, how to pack 2D things into a
one-day thing or ND things.
Really?
That is what's going on there.
So hopefully that makes some sense to you.
All right.
So when we do that, we now have a function that we can pass a tile map
to and then we can do our testing, right?
And so let's just do the basic version First.
I have my tile map here.
I'm going to declare one of these tile Maps, right?
I need to go ahead and Define all of these values, right?
So let's go ahead and do that.
Just real quickly here.
Let's say, tilemap count, X count, why upper left?
This see, blah, blah, blah, right?
No, big deal.
Everything's fine.
And then I'm just going to go ahead and move all this stuff into
their.
So we basically have you know what I can and I can move these directly
into their for now.
So we basically have this is 60 60, the upper left X and upper left
wise are there we go, and the tiles.
These are our tiles.
Now, our tiles equals tiles and of course, we'll have to cast that.
It's now it's, it's 1D.
All right, because this is a 2d array and C would complain if we cast
it.
Well, you know what, I'll show you.
I'll show you the are just you can see it.
And then we've got our counts in here.
Let's go ahead and do that.
Count and count.
And that is really all we have to do that.
Is that is it?
So if we go down here and now we want to do our tile map work we
should.
And you know what, let's go ahead and just change all these.
Guys, town, map tile map.
Anything else tile map tile map, map.
It's good at math me.
See what else we got to do here.
Let the compiler guide you.
Well, we're gonna talk about that second to do.
There we go.
That wit height and tiles.
Okay, so I think we're good there.
There we go.
So this is the cast that I want to talk about.
Right?
Basically what I'm saying, is that a 2d array, something to the fair
declared, as a 2d array in C cannot be cast as something that's a 1D
array.
And so we have to tell it that, it's okay.
We're going to treat that as a 1D array like it's fine.
Don't worry about it.
Okay, and so we haven't actually done anything yet.
So our code is still running.
Exactly the way it was before, but now we've packed the thing in
there.
So let's go ahead and say, all right.
Let's replace.
The check we were doing right with the new check.
So we've got this function here.
We've got is tilemap point empty.
So we want to do is replace.
Our is valid that we're doing for is valid.
We want to replace that by just calling the tilemap query that we
wrote with the new one.
So, there we go.
Oops.
We're going to delete all this stuff because this is the same.
This is we don't need it anymore because we just wrote a function to
do it.
And in fact, we can even just going to wrap this in there with just
say, is Tom at Point empty.
And then, if it is then we'll go ahead and use it.
So there we go, and you can see that it works now that we've factored
it out, and it works exactly the way that it.
So, if we want to, now we can call this on multiple points.
We can just start adding points to test.
Like, if we want to write, we can just say, all right, let's test a
bunch of different points.
Let's test the new player, x, minus the player with write the half the
player with.
So that would be, you know, that would be this, this part this corner
of the player and let's let's go ahead and do the other Corner as
well, right?
It's going to be here.
Of course.
I got to move him out of there for us.
We don't get stuck.
That's good idea.
And so will test all of those.
And if we're going to say they all have to be in an empty space in
order for this to work.
Right?
And so, we just need to move the player with up here.
Again.
This is sort of you should feel those tingles.
You can see, the code start to move into into sort of it sort of
aggregate, which is what we're trying to do here.
So, there we go.
And now, when I move in theory, you see how I stop there.
I couldn't get in there.
Stop again, right?
And so, now,
Of a budding against the tile and we can't we can't go into it.
Right.
So we're starting to get somewhere.
We're starting to get somewhere.
We've got some information about, what, how we should make things
work.
We're sort of getting a little closer, right?
You would never want this game to play like this.
It feels awful.
You get stuck on the sides and all that stuff.
So we're a real far from a good game.
But you know, hopefully you can see how we're making sort of slow and
steady progress towards the design that we want right baby steps, but
the steps are easy to do and really easy to understand and that's
It's what you want to do.
When you're coding baby, steps that are concrete and where you have
good information about whether your design is going in a good way.
A good direction or a bad direction, right?
All right.
So now that we've got this, the other thing that I said that I want to
do, right?
Is if the player moves off of the tile map.
I want them to move into a new tile map, right?
So let's think about what has to happen in order for that to occur.
So in order for that to occur, we know one thing right off the bat,
which is this tile map here is not going to be able to be static.
We're going to need multiple of them.
Right?
And so in order to do that, we've already set ourselves up for that a
little bit because we've got this tile map here.
So I'm going to go ahead and promote that tile map out to the H file
so that I can see it and understand it.
So, there we go.
We've got the tile map, and that's all good.
But we're going to need more tile Maps, right?
We're going to need, let's say at least four tile map so that you can
walk around between a couple.
All of these tile Maps.
So in order to do that, what I'm going to do is I'm going to Define
more than one of them, right?
I'm going to Define more than one of these tile Maps.
Exactly how you might think.
You know what?
Let's just do two, because two will be easier for us.
All right.
So I'm going to have two things here.
I'm going to have tile 0, right?
And there's of course Emax messing up the indentation.
Thank you e Max, there we go.
And tiles one.
So now I have to tile maps and I'm going to go ahead and make these
semi coherent.
So I'm going to basically say, all right, there's no doors on these
except for the doors that would actually lead to a valid.
Tilemap on the other side.
So they're going to be like above and below each other so you can go
out the top of this one because it's zero.
There you'll come in on the bottom.
Right make sense.
Yeah, so should be good.
So basically I'm just going to Define to tile Maps here.
And I'm going to find this tilemap here, right?
And I'm going to Define this town map here.
And I'm going to do the shorthand of just cloning this time out
because it's got the stuff in it that we want.
And yeah, and then I'll just go ahead and change the tile Splinter
here, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and say, all right, we've got the tile map to
tiles pointer is going to point to, you know, what.
And you know what?
Let's also do this.
Let's say that we've got two of them.
Let's just make him an array.
So, we've got tile map to write brackets to.
So this is tile map 0.
It's going to do these
Things like that.
I'm going to say that.
Tilemap 1 equals tiles one.
So there we go.
Do we go 0 Talbot?
There.
You are 32.
Okay, and I need to clone the other values that are in the town map
here.
And that should also tell you something, the fact that I have to clone
them is suspicious.
Right?
So keep that in mind again, always always just kind of look at things
and be aware of what is happening and where things are going and how,
they're how they're doing it.
Let's go ahead and compile that.
Let's see here.
What is right down map.
So, alright.
So we've already got so I should call this tile Maps.
So what we want to do now is we kind of storing our tile Maps.
We got to talking.
Maps.
One on top of the other.
I should probably make them look a bit different.
So I'm going to make one of them, completely empty and leave other
one.
The other one basically as it was, right.
So this one's going to be completely empty and the other one is going
to be exactly as it was.
So there we go, get rid of all those.
Look at this.
There's all of our ones are gone, okay.
So, what I want to do now is say that I've got these tile maps, and
then I'm just going to say that there's a current tile map, that is
the tile map that we're on.
Right?
And we'll say that that style.
It's got a point tile map 0 for now.
And so everyone who was using tilemap dot below me is now going to use
tilemap Arrow, right?
It's going to reference some pointer to a tile map but it's not really
necessarily going to know which tile map it is.
And so these are going to work like that, right?
And if I recompile this in theory, what is the problem here?
Here, there we go.
If I were if I were compiled this in theory, I should be able to what
are you?
You bet.
Oh, right.
So this guy also needs to access the tile.
So this is another thing that we might want to think of.
So, we already have the code for accessing a tile, right?
We wrote it up here.
It's this thing, right?
So we may want to also pull that out which is basically get tile
value, right?
So we can pass in a tile map and the the sort of entity to tile X in
through to tile.
Why.
Right?
What we may want to do is just say, all right, let's go.
Ahead and and pass it in there and let's call that direct so or
unchecked.
So that we know that we're not, we're assuming that we've already done
a check on it to see that it was valid before we actually did it.
So, we're going to do something that does.
This right there is our tile why there's our tile X, and this could be
an inline function, because it's nice and Tiny.
We're just going to return that tilemap value.
So, now we have a way to query in and we don't have to know about this
code anymore.
We can just pass in a thing where we actually ask for our player tile
X and our player will tell why in a convenient way and we can get it
out.
So we just pulled that out there, right?
Let's see here.
So now this guy can use the same thing, get tilemap value unchecked,
and it can go ahead and ask for the column and the row and it will do
that access right there.
So we still are running exactly as we would expect to run its all
good.
Except now, you'll notice our doors are gone except for the bottom
door, which is good.
So all we need to do now is make it so that when we come out here,
when we walk out of here, we will be able to leave and move on to the
next screen.
So what we need to think about?
Is the fact that these tile maps are sort of?
We kind of want to think about the tile Maps as having, you know,
continuity so that almost as if it's one big tile map, but we probably
don't want to make it just one big tile map.
And the reason for that is we would waste a ton of space in the cases
where the tile maps are not dense.
And let me go ahead and show you what I mean by that.
So one way to do this, oops, that would be pretty easy, right?
He used to say.
All right, essentially, what we have when we have all of these tile
Maps, right?
Is we know like we've got these two tile Maps.
They're stacked on top of each other like this, right?
And I don't know.
I've got some, I've got it.
Looking kind of like this.
I've got this is put in there.
There's a barrier here, but there's a door there that you can go
through.
Right?
Looks like that.
So, one way to do this, right, would be to make the whole thing.
This whole thing could be one tile map, right?
And we're just viewing a subsection of the tile map.
That we could do that.
The problem with that is what happens when things get absolutely
massive.
Like, let's say that we end up with a fully 3D, sort of structure for
these tile Maps where we've basically got you.
Imagine each of these is a tile map and then there's tile maps on top
of tile Maps, right?
There's like you go up a level and there's Tom apps here.
And this time is there this thing goes on extremely far.
There's like 400 tile maps in this direction, right?
And then there's a 300 tile maps in this direction, but they're very
sparse.
Like we don't fill them all in, like there's no tile maps in here.
Most of the levels are not, you know, maybe maybe this.
There's 20 tile maps that go up.
There's like ladders that go up and up and up on one spot of the map.
But you know, we don't actually have that anywhere else.
So they're going to be very sparse and they and it could be very
sprawling and sparse.
And so what you don't want to do is you don't want to store everything
as a giant 3D voxel.
Basically kind of a thing where it where the entire map for the whole
world is is stored in some giant array because
As we've seen how much space does it take to store something.
Well, a linear thing, right?
Something that's just things along a line, right?
Is just however, long, the line is right, if the line is n long, then
it's going to be n space to fill it.
So if we have to store, you know, I don't know.
Let's say we store a thousand tiles in a line then we basically have a
thousand times, the size of a tile.
However, big however, much we need to store in a tile.
That's how big it would be.
Right.
And you can pretty much see that when you have something like this.
Even if this was like, you know, 10,000 or something.
I mean, how many are really going to go across?
This never is going to get to a particularly Big Value even if tiles
were you know, a megabyte or something?
Well MB a little bit large, let's say they were what KB 1 K per tile.
Right?
Then really all we have here is we've got we've got a 10 megabyte set
to store that whole thing.
Right?
So it's just not it's just not that
that big right?
It's not a big deal.
But as soon as you start adding more dimensions in there, as soon as
you add another dimension, where you're going to do two Dimensions
here, right?
If you have another 10,000, it becomes 10,000 squared, right?
It's 10,000 times, 10,000 to store it because for every 10,000 of
these you have, you've got 10,000 rows now, so you've got like a
10,000 rows of 10,000 entries.
And these numbers get big really fast right in.
So much as you cannot make a line that big you can make a square get
big really quickly in terms of how many interior tells it has.
And if we go one further and go to cubed, right?
So now we've got essentially, we're storing a 3D World, right?
Where we've got, you know, you can go up ladders and down ladders,
right?
So you can move up tile maps and downtown Maps storing.
That is now cubed in, however, large, you want the world to be in any
given direction, right?
So again, since
We just want we only want to be able to store stuff where where stuff
actually exist in the world.
If there's a tower in the world.
You can go up, 20 flights in it.
We want to only have to store the 20 flights.
We don't want have to start 20, flights virtually for every Square on
the map for every tile map on the, for every section of the town map
on the on the world because there might be nothing there.
So you're just throwing empty are so essentially, what we want to do
is we want to be able to say we only have tile Maps.
We only have a 2d tile map section where one actually exists in the
world so that we can have feel free to have a long winding thing.
Things I'm tall things in places where we want them without paying the
cost of that everywhere making it prohibitive, right?
And so, you know, that's just, that's just prevents you from having to
pack your world so that everything is densely packed in one area.
You can make like on a large following things and still take up the
same amount of memory.
And that's again, that's called sparse storage, sparse is the word we
use for that because you can say that something is dense, which means
that like all the entries are there.
Are you can say that something is sparse, which is that, you have a
storage scheme that doesn't cost much to store nothingness.
Right?
So what we're looking for is something Sparks that, lets us store
tilemap sections, only where the player can actually walk to and not
waste a bunch of memory.
Storing them, where they're not,
And so again, that's why I can't just make a giant 2D tile map of the
entire over world because I may want to have long thin things
extending out through parts of the world.
And if we were to actually try to store tiles for the entire world as
if it was a giant filled in 2D grid, we would blow out memory too
quickly or something like that, right?
Okay, so we want some kind of sparse storage for this thing.
So what I want to do is basically say, okay, I would like my tilemap
queries.
I'd like to be able to still do a query as if I was querying stuff.
Sort of uniformly, but I would also I would like to basically say is
it okay for the player to move outside of this door, right?
Can you move down?
What's down here?
Right.
I want to be able to know the answer to that question.
And so in order to know the answer that question, what that means is
that going off the edge of one tile.
App should bring me on to the next tile map.
And we only have 10 minutes here, which is a little tight.
So I'm wondering if I should, I would like to start this.
I would like to start this.
But I don't know if I have time.
We'll see what we can do.
So, what I want to do here, right, you can sort of see what happens.
What I want to say here is.
Okay, so you can see this is tile map Point empty thing.
It's only got one tile map, right?
And so, it wouldn't be able to look at a different tile map.
So what I kind of need to do is I need to be able to do that in a way
that asks about more than one tile map.
Right?
I need to be able to ask about this in a way.
That's more than one tile map, so you can already see.
Already have a hint which is I know I want to be able to do these
Point queries easily.
So I basically want a function that works exactly like oops.
It's not move that that works exactly like this, but I don't actually
want it to only access one tile map at a time.
I wanted to access the whole world's worth of Tau Maps, right?
So if you imagine what this would look like in a thing that says, you
know, if I clone this function basically and I say something like
Is World Point empty?
Right?
And I want to be able to pass this sort of a test X and a test.
Why?
And I want to be able to know, you know, essentially what's going to
happen to the point, considering the whole universe of Tom apps that
we may have defined.
Right?
What I need to do is figure out a way to sort of get it so that the
coordinates of this thing, you can we can we can even, you know, we
can look at it directly.
Here.
Right.
Just imagine clothing this function when we come in here.
And we use the test X and the test wide.
They are relative to some tile map right there relative to some tile
map in the world of tile Maps.
But if I go off that tilemap, I would be relative to some other tile
map.
So what I want to do is instead of only considering the case, so, you
know, empty was set to false instead of just assuming that a tile is
not empty, if it that a tile is
Like filled which is what we're doing.
If it does not exist inside this town map.
What I want to do is use these cases more intelligently to figure out
what tilemap I would be in, right?
And ask that tile map.
Does that make sense?
So, what we need to do is introduce a higher level of coordinate,
here.
We need to introduce sort of where we are in tile map space, right?
And so, what you can see is I was started to do that here.
I said, we've got to tile Maps.
We've got Tom ab0 and Tom app one.
So you can imagine saying we have some index that's where in tilemap
space.
We actually were right.
So instead of passing this in a tile map, what we need to do is pass
in like, you know, basically the world map.
Let's say world map or just were
God's world.
We're going to pass in the world here and we're going to pass in some
kind of notion of which tilemap X X and Y.
We are on now at the minute.
We at the end, you know, what, I probably should just to show the the
full thing here.
I probably should go ahead and say that we actually have four tile
Maps, right?
Because that way I can show an X and A Y happening, okay.
So, well, you know, you know what I'm saying, this kind of thing.
Right?
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
Okay.
So let's say I go ahead and blow that out and these are all empty
again.
So I've got Tom apps, two and three.
Okay, and so, let's pretend that we've got this guy here and this
Is tiles.
This is tell 0, 0, and this is going to be, so that's like I'm going
to say that's x and y, basically.
So basically we've got tiles X and Y.
So this would be right below this guy.
And so, then, both of these guys will be able to exit off the side
like this.
And these guys will be coming in on the side that.
So now we've got tiles 10.
And 11.
And so that again, 10 would be on the top.
So it be that way.
And the other one be on the bottom.
So it looks like that.
No.
No, that's a mistake wired by do that should be.
Oops, should be there.
Shouldn't it?
Yes.
Oh, no.
I'm right.
Remind getting confused, confused by my own scheme.
So, I'm just kind of making this by hand here.
There you go.
And so, you know, these guys will be in that pattern.
And so now, I've got my tile Maps here, and I'm going to go ahead and
lay them out manually again, just because we're not at the point yet,
where I really know what I want from everything.
So we can go ahead and do this for all of these, right?
We have our tiles, we've got our tubing, our mother tile essentially
which so we're going to go ahead and clone that Tom app.
So that everyone has their values initialized, right?
And we haven't quite finished pulling all the stuff out that we want
to, but we're going to go ahead and just do the basics here.
So this is 0 0, 1 0 1, 1 like that and we're just going to initialize
them exactly to what we just label them has in the other thing so you
can see.
There we go.
UPS got to finish the world stuff first.
Let's go.
Up over that skip over that I don't care about any of this.
Okay, there we go.
And there we go.
All right.
So we've got a bunch of work to do here.
Right?
And this is why I said, I don't know if I want to start this yet
because we may leave things in a broken state today, which would be
unfortunate.
But sometimes you got to do that.
Basically, what we need to do now is we need to sort of have something
that contains all of our tile Maps, right?
And so I'm just going to say that we've got that world struct, right?
We've got that world struck that.
We don't really know what.
Contains yet, but we know at the very least, it's got to contain these
tile Maps, right?
It's got to contain all these tile Maps.
So, basically, we've got the tile Maps here.
And we we have to sort of have that pointer and the only thing we know
so far is that we're going to have to store all these tile maps and
we're going to have to have them in at something like this world
struct so that I can pass them around to things that need to be able
to work with them.
So we've got Tom apps and the tile maps are going to equal a pointer
to our Tom obstruct, right?
So, there we go.
So inside the world here now, we sort of have something where we're
going to go.
All right.
We have a tile Map X in the tile map.
Why that we're going to use is coordinates to look up into this thing.
So we're going to have to use the exact same math.
But we just did this kind of a strided look up in sort of this, get
Tau, value unchecked, right?
And that is something that we're going to want to do again.
We're just going to clone that function for getting the tile map out
of the world.
Right?
So we have a world structure and we're going to have a tile Map X and
a tile map.
Why?
That we are?
Owing to use to pull out the, the world coordinate.
So again, we know exactly what this looks like, right?
We're going to have a thing where we essentially have account X and
account Y.
And we're going to look up a tile map in here.
Now, what we said, we've got a problem.
You know, like I said, this is still going to be dense so far, but
we'll kind of.
Yeah, I'm running out of time on the stream is basically what it boils
down to.
I want I won't be able to get to the sparseness.
So we'll just drop a thing in here to do.
Beginners sparseness basically how much we have to do?
Okay.
So basically what I want to do here is I want to be able to say, all
right, get me the tile map that goes with some coordinates for the
town map.
And all that's going to do is exactly the same math we did before.
It's going to look up into the tile Maps.
Using the the tile map Y and the tile Map X.
And it's going to use essentially counts that we've put in there that
says, how many across each one is, right.
So we've basically got a tile map count X and a town map count.
Why?
And that'll go ahead and look.
Up an actual tile map like this, right?
And we will return that tilemap with that.
And now what we probably want to do is make sure that is guarded
itself.
So we'll look to see whether the tile Map X.
And tilemap, why are in bounds again using the exact same math that we
were using before?
Nothing out of the ordinary going on here like that world and we go
Sceptile map.
Oops, like that.
And
Same thing for wise.
So there's our wise, right?
There we go.
So we've got our get Tom a function and what that can do is that will
now give us a tile map, right?
There's our groups World point.
There we go.
That'll give us a tile map by saying, whatever the, whatever the title
X and Y, that we have there.
Go get Tom app.
Whatever that towel X and Y that we get passed in, we're going to look
up what the map is that corresponds to that tilemap X and Y, right?
We're going to say if that tile map is valid, if there was actually
tilemap at that location.
Then we're going to do this thing in that tile map.
Right now.
There's a bunch of stuff that we're like I said, we're out of time.
Let's dream.
There's a bunch of
We still have to fix which is unfortunate.
I was going to get this back to compiling and then we will start the
Q&A.
And tomorrow.
We will finish talking about all of the stuff that we need to do to
make this actually work properly.
Okay.
So, what did I forget to do Tom up.
Count, textile map count, why tilemap count X time account?
Why what?
What is it?
What is it complaining about?
Not a member.
Oh, oh.
Oh, yes.
This is actually the world pointer there.
Cannot convert to between.
Oh, yeah.
This is this is totally just that's just copy pasta as people say,
it's just hard for me to deal with when I'm talking on the stream.
It's hard for me to concentrate on making sure that I do.
My basic substitutions correctly, which is unfortunate.
All right, so we returned the tile map and this thing needs to return
a town map pointer, right?
There we go.
Okay.
So where are we at here?
We're still running properly.
Okay, so I want to start the Q&A, but I'm just going to briefly.
We say where we ended up and then tomorrow I'll recap it.
So basically all we're trying to do here is extend our notion of tile
Maps out to having multiple tile Maps, right?
And so right now, we're still doing everything as if we're just on
this one time at, but we want to do is be able to move between Tom
app.
So we introduced a second layer of coordinates.
That's our tile Map X and Y.
And that's going to tell us where in the tile Maps.
We are so we can pull out the right.
Tilemap.
Now, you'll notice there's some odd things here.
Right?
Look, we've still got upper left and up.
This is like a rendering coordinate, really.
And some stuff that we don't that doesn't really make sense for the
circumstance.
And so we definitely want to kind of start looking at these and seeing
if these really should be here in here or if they should be in the
world and stuff like that.
And we also have some stuff to think about in terms of what those mean
versus pixels.
So we've got a lot of stuff to work out here.
So I'm going to I'm not going to try and explain any more of that
because we need all day.
I think tomorrow to explain all what's going on there and move on.
But for now, let's end with that because we're like, I said, we're
still in a good working State, I think.
Even if we restore
Right from the beginning.
We're in a good working State.
And so that's a fine way to leave it.
And then tomorrow, we will concentrate on being able to move between
our town Maps which will be our which would be a great place to end
the week actually because then we got a guy moving around a little
world and that crowd of clears the way for starting to get into more
bigger and badder stuff.
All right, let's start the Q&A.
Basically.
I think it's now would be a good time to start the Q&A.
So let me go ahead and go in and
Put the filter on.
So please put Q: in front of your questions and keep the questions of
stuff.
We did on the stream today.
If you have questions, like how do I get into the game industry or
what language are you programming in and stuff like that?
Please come to a pre stream because before the stream starts, I answer
all kinds of questions like questions about anything.
And so yeah, so basically anything, please keep the questions in the
post stream to being stuff that's on the code.
We did today or code that we've done in a previous day.
Okay.
And Jean blow mentions.
That we have initialized any of the world stuff and he is correct.
We haven't yet.
I probably should do that in case we forget tomorrow and wonder what's
going on.
We should probably initialize these to actually be what they actually
are so far.
So there.
Yeah.
Thank you, John.
Let's see.
Why does player sometimes?
Stop a pixel away from the wall?
That's an excellent question and something that we'll be getting into
a lot more later.
When we do, like, a proper movement model for the player.
The reason is because if you look at what's happening here, well, you
know what, let's let's go ahead and step into the code actually and I
can show you exactly why it's it's happening.
So if I open, where is handmade, where is he?
Me dot CPP.
It's not in here.
All right, so let me just break a little break aside game update and
render game update and render.
So, the breakpoint.
Let's see.
Oh, yes.
Sorry, gotta gotta rebuild that guy.
All right.
So let's go ahead and break in here, and I could show you essentially
what's going on there.
So if you take a look.
Let's let some should I do this?
Let me grab the controller.
We don't have control.
I'm trying to figure out how I can stop this in a way that makes
sense, because I want to stop it.
Did move.
Oh, right.
I forgot.
We plan for this.
I already am at the point where I can do this.
I'm going to have this guy moving forwards, I'ma set the loop point,
right?
And then, I'm going to reset them.
So, there we go.
Perfect example of how we can use our Loop point.
So, our guy is moving this way, right?
I'm gonna go ahead and set a breakpoint in here.
We're going to look at the values, right?
So I come in here, and we look at what our deep layer X, and our deep
layer Y is right.
So our deep layer X and D player, why are going to be 64 when the
player, you know, if the players maybe Direction like, it's going to
be like 64 x, right.
So, you're going to move 64 pixels a second, right?
We're going to take the input.
Or the frame and put DT for a frame, right?
We're going to we're going to multiply that by this by the Deep layer
acts.
Right?
So we're going to multiply this value times D player X and that's how
far we're going to try to move them.
It's to pixels right to pixels.
So, the new player X in the new player, why?
Are two pixels away from where they were on the previous frame on any
given frame, okay.
So, what will happen is in the case, where we cannot move the player,
because the new point is inside the wall.
He could stop one pixel away from the wall because he's trying to move
to pixels forward.
It could be that he could have moved one more pixel and not been
inside.
The wall makes sense.
So when he goes forwards, you will note.
He.
He's always moving to pixels.
He could he could having literally that happens.
I'm going to stop the, I'm gonna stop the
The looping playback.
So when we get into the situation in that case, he happened to end
right on a pixel.
The, the moving too big for the time happen to end them in.
Right through it.
But but in other circumstances, he might not.
So trying to think if there's a good way to do that.
I think this is even it will only.
Yeah, there we go.
Right.
And so the way we would fix that simply like we're not going to use
this as the actual player movement code.
We're trying to build it, you know, build up to it.
But if you wanted to fix that, right?
You could imagine how you might want to do it.
You would want to figure out.
If you could still move the player some shorter distance and and not
hit the wall, right?
We could do something trivial and weird if we wanted to write.
We could go in here and do something crazy.
Like,
And this is not, I would not recommend doing this.
But if we wanted to write, we could do something like this Buhl.
32 moved player, right?
Move player equals false while not moved player or maybe something
more like four inch fry equals zero.
Try is less than 4 + + try and we'll leave not move.
Player in there, something like this and what we could do here.
And again, this is not at all what you want to do, but I'm just kind
of illustrate to you further.
What's actually happening in the code.
We could try to move the player if we can't move the player, you know,
if you can, we say moved players was true and we break out of the
loop.
If we can't, then we try making a smaller.
We try going a little bit less.
So we Sadie player X, you know, x equals, you know point.
Eight or something.
So, we move it a little, we just reduce the amount that we try to
move.
Right?
Does that make sense?
And so now when we move you can see, I but I but right back up to the
every time, right?
I don't I don't stop that one pixel way because what it does is it
gets there.
It gets to the point where it where it has the problem and it's a one
away righto.
Well, or maybe not that's not
Should work.
Let's see.
What happened there.
What did I do?
What did I do wrong?
This should have worked.
Let's, let's take it.
Let's take a look in there.
I want to see what's going on.
So, let me set a breakpoint in here.
What?
What happened?
Why can I not set a breakpoint?
Is this msv.
See not loading.
Our pdb?
What is the problem?
Is this just me being stupid.
It, maybe me being stupid.
I want to see what happens.
If I rebuild this.
That would suck.
If M SV, C can't handle us bus rebuilding, our pdb.
That's awful.
That's really unfortunate.
That that's true.
Well, anyway, I guess I can see what's going on here now anyways, so
I'll double check that.
The bug is still there.
So, I wonder if it just didn't yes, the bug still there.
So, that's fine.
So, I can still find the book.
So it reloads are code, but it won't reload.
Our pdb is it won't we load our debug info?
So it can't set a breakpoint properly or what's the deal?
Is this just further msv.
See, being lousy at its job.
That's unfortunate.
Well anyway, so I can see, you can see there.
I'm not going all the way up.
I'm stopping one pixel away on that one.
So let me take a look and see what happens during that.
So when I hit here, right?
Where
My player X.
So here's my game state.
I'm going to take a look at it player ex-player.
Why, right?
And, and I now have a deep layer X and a deep layer y of
Zero and negative 64 and I want to go ahead and see what those are.
I want to see what that y value is.
So it's - -2.1 so we were unable to do the move on to pixels.
So now I'm going to go ahead and make it less.
So it's going to be one point seven pixels.
That's going to try to move now.
So now tries to do that and then it reduces it again.
So it just never reduces it quite low in enough, I guess is the
problem or know, it does does it.
Oh, no.
It doesn't quite do it justice.
Get a couple more tries see if that that solves the problem there.
I'm kind of disturbed that MSP see won't we load our pdb though?
That's kind of, that's really annoying.
That's really, really annoying.
Okay, so I think we were we are now at the point where we're stopping.
Yeah sort of at the right places.
I believe I should probably add some kind of key to make us move a
little faster.
Through.
Yeah, so you can kind of see what I'm talking about here, right?
Yeah, so basically that's just a really cheesy way of saying if you
can't do the move that you were trying to do, try moving a little
less.
And basically this all comes from the fact that we're not doing the
movement continuously, right?
Essentially, what we would want to do and this is the sort of stuff
that we'll be getting into later is if we have an obstacle of some
kind and we have a player and the player is trying to move between
two, you know, this is over the time step, the player should
From here to here.
What we want to do is we don't want to test this and say is this valid
or not and then use that.
Right?
And there's two reasons.
We don't want to do it.
Right?
And let's say this is our obstacle, right?
There's two reasons.
We don't want to do it.
One is the one that you already asked about which is that if the move
can't happen and we just deny it flat out, then he standing here.
But really he should be standing right here.
We wanted him to move as far as he could in that direction, right?
So that's a problem.
Right?
That's problem one, but we've got another problem and that
That is the thin wall problem.
So let's say we've got a thing.
That's basically looks like this.
The player is here and the time, step would move him here.
Well, if all we do is check the destination that he goes to Hill
Tunnel right on through that wall and that's a gameplay problem.
He's not supposed to be able to Tunnel through that wall.
Furthermore.
It creates a time-dependent.
Tunneling problem at 30 frames a second.
Maybe that's how far he moves, but at 60 frames a second.
He only moves fast that far.
That means four people playing at 60 frames a second.
They can't go through the
And for people who are playing at 30 frames a second, they can't.
So that's total you.
No, no, no, no, no, no, like all bad.
Right.
So I want to underscore just in case it wasn't clear that like, this
is not, we don't want to do be doing any of this stuff in the final
game.
This is just doing the simplest possible thing so that we can sort of
see how to start structuring like the storage of the game structures,
and that sort of stuff and just to get things working in a reasonable.
Sort of fashion.
And so we're just going to leave that bug in there for now because
we'll be doing different things for the player movement system, when
we go to actually tune it, if that makes sense.
It almost sounds like you could get the wrong tile map when trying to
move between Tom apps with the function.
You just did.
I'm not sure exactly what that mean.
Sorry.
Let's see.
Are your variables for Tom apps too similar to each other or am I just
easily confused?
I wouldn't say that you're too easily confused because one of the next
things that we'll be doing obviously is like having all these x's and
y's and widths and Heights and stuff can get confusing.
And so one of the things we'll be doing probably.
We probably not tomorrow but next week is introducing structures that
help manage those things like will be interesting vectors and things
like that to try and simplify these sorts of things.
So yeah, I mean, I would say yes, they are confusing and that is a
good thing to notice because that is something that we will be
addressing as we go forward, but I can only address one thing at a
time on the stream and I didn't want to just type this out.
The correct way to do it or anything because I wanted to show how we
sort of Loft up into the correct into the correct structure.
Let's see.
A lot of people are asking questions that are more like pre stream
questions.
If you want to ask questions, like some of these which are is C or C++
best, if you want to code games and have you thought about teaching at
universities?
What are on your hands?
Those sorts of things, any of any questions that are just not related
to the code that we're working on today, are in a previous day, come
to the priest Fame, come 15 minutes before the stream starts.
I'm usually, you know, before the the scheduled time and I'm usually
on and answering questions like that.
Is there an advantage using Blue 32 instead of Boule 8-bit?
Yes.
I mean, basically you don't want to be using values that aren't the
most convenient value for the processor.
And so 8-bit is typically not the most convenient value.
It's not aligned to a 32-bit boundary and there's a bunch of things.
I mean, we'll cover this a little bit more later.
But basically what you want to do is you want your Boolean values when
you're just throwing them around.
You want them to be, basically, whatever the type is that the
processor is most comfortable dealing with if that makes
That's so when you store them, you might want to pack them into bit
fields, which will probably do in the future for things and when
you're just Computing with them, you typically want them to be just
whatever.
The easiest value is for the processor to deal with, which is usually
32 bit.
Can you go over briefly how to encode the tiled data?
In a single Unit 32 I couldn't get it the first time.
Well, we haven't really encoded any tile day to get, I just used a un
32 because I needed some number that would say, occupied or not.
So, I just used a 32-bit value and we all were doing is storing a zero
and a one in there at the moment.
So this will get more complicated.
Our tile structure will not be a un 32 in the future.
It'll be some kind of struck that has information in it.
Like what, what the tiles you know, what kind of talent is that Earth
is at War.
Otter, is it, you know, whatever and like what its properties are, is
it magical?
It doesn't have health on it.
Those sorts of things.
why does left and right side Collision work, but not the top and
So the reason is because I don't know if you've ever seen.
So so here's you know, if you've ever seen like oops.
If you've ever seen something like a standard, tilemap game, not sure
how to show this.
Well, okay.
So if you've ever seen a game, a standard tilemap game, right?
They tend to look like they've got like a wall or something like this
and then maybe there's like a rock here or something.
So, you know, this sort of thing.
And the hero right?
Is like this little dude, you know who's hanging around and he's got
like a sword, right?
And all that kind of stuff when he walks around.
He you know, he can't walk into an obstacle.
That's like that's like left or right.
He can't interpenetrate them.
But when he walks up to something like this rock, he can actually
Eclipse it quite a bit, right?
You can kind of stand right in front of the rock with his sword or
whatever, right?
And that's because of the sort of fake purse.
Div that games have we're like, they're sort of they're not really top
down.
A lot of times are sort of like fake.
Three quarters were even though like the tiles are square.
The guy is drawn as if you're kind of looking at him from the side.
So we don't we want to let the Collision allow the guy to walk all the
way up there and maybe you know, maybe we want them to stop a little
bit away from it, but just a little bit not all the way and when when
it comes down,
Onto something.
Then we do want to stop in their potentially or maybe we want to let
them go a little bit behind it.
I'm not sure.
But either way, you can kind of see what I'm getting at there.
There's like this kind of weird perspective rules.
So we don't know exactly how we want to model that in the game.
But that's why I'm allowing him to do that.
The reason in the code that it works that way, like the re the reason
how the code accomplices that is.
We're checking three points for collision.
And those three points are there there.
And there we're not checking any points appear.
So it stops when this point hits the edge and it stops when this point
hits the edge, right?
But it doesn't stop when these points in anything.
Those points can anything they want, so it will only stop.
Once one of these points gets up and hits the tile, right?
Which is right there.
Why are you using number 32?
I'm not sure what that means.
Why save tile width height in each time that if these values never
change, so we probably won't, I guess this is what I was saying
before.
We just we had to stop the stream before we lofted stuff out of the
Tom app and into the world struct.
So yeah, sorry that we just didn't get there.
What are the differences between structs and classes?
There is no difference between a struct in a class.
Basically, C++ just uses a different Access Control depending on which
you put pick.
So, basically struct essentially has no restrictions on who can access
its members.
So if I have struct Foo into X, and I want to access that somewhere.
So I'm inside Main and I have one of these foo foo foo X.
That's allowed I can access X.
If it was a class.
I would not be able to this would give an error, right?
It would say that, you know, only it's a private member.
And so really, the only difference between them is you can think of if
there was some master thing, if there was some Uber guy called like,
You know, storage or something, then storage Foo would be or I, you
know, I don't even introduced that.
So, struct Foo right is just class Foo with a public on it.
So struct Foo equals class Foo with public at the top.
That's that's what, that's what struck through is.
And the opposite is true, as well class.
Foo is the same as struct Foo with a private at the top.
So that's that's that's it.
No other real difference between them.
I mean the same is true of inheritance.
Like if I inherit from something, if I say public Bar here, that would
be the same as me.
Not saying that, right?
I could I could and and and vice versa like I could inherit the sky
privately here and I would be equivalent to what would happen.
I think I'm pretty sure that's I don't use in her.
I'd last time I use inheritance was like 2001 or something.
So I don't remember.
But I believe inheritance does the same thing where it's like the
public and private is inverted.
Let's see.
Not many questions about the code.
Do you always put in through to can you use only enter?
Okay, so I see what I see what the question is about now.
So basically what we've done here is so in t, in C is has
traditionally been ambiguous.
There is no telling how big it is.
It could be eight bits on old old computers.
It could be 16 bits on more modern ones.
It could be 32 bits on today's computers or in the future.
It might even be 64 bits.
Sometimes right?
Who knows?
Where it could go from there.
So, when you say into, you have no idea how big of a number you can
store in.
See, I don't think I, maybe there's something the spec that says it
has to be at least eight bits or at least 16 or something, but in
general, I don't think has
To be any particular size that makes sense.
So, what we want to do when we're programming, most of the time is
specify, what at least, we think the minimum size, we need is for
things on the platform.
Right?
So I'm using in 32 2, B II defined in 32 to basically be something
that is a 32-bit integer because that's usually what I want.
And when I want a 64-bit, integer, L, stay in 64, etc.
Etc.
So you can see these types I made up here.
So there's nothing wrong with using it.
It's just that it's harder to control because
You don't have any idea what size that actually is.
So so that's basically it.
Wait, so in 32 is because you want to make the game for 32-bit
computers and later.
You will optimize it for 64-bit computers.
No, it is simply because I want to make sure that the values that I'm
talking about are 32 bits wide.
It doesn't have anything to do with optimization.
It has to do with the fact that 16 bits would be too few, if that
makes sense.
And also the fact that the that x86 and x64 tend to be very happy
working with 32-bit value.
So you tend to want to use those most of the time.
Because they work.
Good on aligned 32-bit boundaries and and so on and so forth.
So this is this code that were running right now is actually being
compiled a 64-bit code, but we don't use 64-bit integers because a lot
of times they take up more space and we don't actually need the extra
32 bits that they provide.
And so, and they also are more expensive to compute with because when
you're using like Cindy and stuff, a 32-bit integer, you can do for
wha
I adore 8 wide or 16 y depending on the width of the CMD unit.
Where a 64 bit.
You get half that so yeah, so so no, we're already compiling 64-bit
and optimizing for 64-bit basically when we actually start doing
optimizations, but we're saying that we want to store 32-bit values in
places.
The player moves faster diagonally than it is supposed to.
Are you planning on fixing that?
Well, did you look at the code before asking that question?
I don't think that you did.
Because if you notice, it says right here to do Casey, diagonal will
be faster fixed.
Once we have vectors.
Did you notice that?
Why did you not look at that?
Hmm?
Hmm.
Maybe you were just going by the video.
You don't have access to source code and that's fine.
But we have a comment for that.
How do you plan on handling code duplication in enemies or other game
entities without inheritance?
Well, we'll have to see when we get there.
Looks like there are no more questions about today's.
Code or previous code.
So, I think
I think we're basically done.
I'm not familiar with pound Define.
What is it used for?
Well, pound if I is just a macro.
So all pound Define does is pound to find, says anywhere that you see
this string, replace it with this string.
It's just a straight substitution in text form.
So instead of like a constant that actually has a type.
Like, for example, if you say, you know, in team concert Foo equals 4
or whatever that means that this is actually an integer type that gets
inserted in your code and you couldn't use it for something else.
Right?
Whereas
Just pounded.
Finding is literally text.
So you could even, you know, use it to do something where that, that
had nothing to do with whatever its actual value was and that just had
to do it, the text of the thing, right?
And so sometimes you use them to to, you know, just replace.
I don't like typing, the word static for example.
So I type I like to define the word static, which has multiple
meanings in C++.
I don't like the fact that they had multiple meetings.
So I make three different.
Keywords, basically using defined their textual substitution.
So I can use the one that I want for the surface situation that I
want.
I think it's clear to read that way.
When you use in 32, does it have a different influence on the code
than normal ENT?
No, not on this platform because it is into 32 an inch are the same on
this platform on other platforms.
It might because if it was defined to be 64 bits on some platform than
interview to and have a different effect because it would be 32 bits
instead of 64 bits.
All right, so I think that's it for today.
what I would like to do is, I'm going to go a few minutes extra on the
stream here because we on the
In the forum's, someone was requesting an edit to the H file that I am
totally fine with making and so I want to go ahead and make it but I
didn't want to take Upstream time for it.
So I'm going to go ahead and do it.
Basically, what they were wondering is could we make the header file
clean for being basically see, you know, could they could we make it
clean so that in C++, it would just compiled.
And I'm sorry that it would compile.
Clean in C.
So even if you didn't have C++, and you were trying to write a
platform layer with something that couldn't compile C++ code that you
could use it.
And I think that should be pretty easy, actually.
You, so I'm going to go ahead and and try that.
Basically, what I want to do is split out handmade this.
This this thing here, split it out into essentially, a handmade dot h,
and a handmade platform.sh.
So handmade platform.sh will have just the bare minimum.
That would be necessary.
And so I'm going to go ahead and see if I can if I can do that, so,
Why do this?
Let's see here.
I need, I want these guys.
I don't need pie though.
I need these there.
Well, do I even need those?
Let me see what we pass.
Trying to figure out what we need for the platform layer to talk to
us.
Yeah, we do need those.
So we need those, we don't need any of this stuff.
So we're just going to pound include handmade platform right here.
So we got a pound.
Include those.
What else we got then?
Do you a that we need these.
We need this stuff.
We don't need get controller, that can stay outside.
So we need game input, right?
We need these guys, we need
See, all of this.
Yeah, we need all of this stuff.
Needs to come up.
So let's put that in there and we need.
I think that's it.
That's all we need.
Pretty sure.
Yeah, so basically what I've done is I pulled out the bare minimum
that you would need to call us from a platform layer.
And now I'm going to do is I'm going to make this compiled in C,
right?
And so, what I want to do is eliminate anything that is C plus plus in
it, so first of all, I need to make sure that we always typedef.
So, in C++, it always will Define.
If you have like struck thread context, you can then use the word
thread context, right?
As a type named in.
See, that wasn't true.
You had to actually, also typedef these like that you had to type def
them so that you'd to actually get the name to be used as a type.
So we need to do that everywhere that we have one of these.
One of these sort of structs that the platform layer talks do, right?
If that makes sense.
So that's pretty straightforward to do typedef.
Like this type death.
That, there we go.
To type death.
State that.
So, really just going through and doing some basic stuff here.
I
Know how see will fare with this thing.
I'm a little worried about it.
We could at this point go ahead and pull it but we'll see.
We'll see what happens on the on the C compiler here.
I'm going to go ahead and finish typing all these guys.
And I think that may just be all we really need to do.
Not sure.
There's really anything else to do.
Yeah, looks pretty sane.
To me we can also extern, see this.
So there's an if C plus plus extra and see thing that we can do.
I don't know if that will help people.
Let me go ahead and close this down so we can compile.
So there's a way you can do basically an if deaf for C++, if deaf C++
extern.
See.
I forget what the, what the thing is for it.
It's yes, this thing.
It's this thing right here.
This is what we want.
So essentially all we're trying to do here is say alright, basically
everything in this file, if we're compiling with a C++ compiler.
Let's treat everything in this file as if it was, as if it was C code,
so, see, here, is that out?
So only if we're on the C, compiler will do that.
And that all, that just makes it.
So these names don't get mangled.
I
If you remember we did some stuff with this inside ham, a DOT CPP.
We did this extra and see thing.
Right?
And so that basically says, apply that to everything that we've got,
you know, make sure all of these names don't get mangled.
I think this will be a slightly better.
You know, like I said, I did the minimal stuff, but I think this will
be all you would need now to be able to, to build a platform layer
link.
To handmade hero.
And then now, we've got all our sort of other stuff that was kind of
in the, in the platform file that doesn't have anything to do with
calling us from the platform layer.
We've sort of put that in here now, I suspect math.h is probably not
necessary.
Am I correct about that?
Let's see here.
In fact, I don't even know if we use math.h anymore.
Do we?
Yeah, we don't.
So that was only for our sine wave.
So maybe we'll get rid of that and we'll go when we want to do our
sine wave.
Again will Implement sign ourselves like it said, standard into is
there.
We could decide to get rid of standard in Tazewell and just to find
these to be something right now because we know what they are and
later put our own sort of crackers in here.
So for example, what that would look like is we would go ahead and
say, all right, there's no standard anymore.
We're going to say the intake is a care in.
16 is a short entity to is a tent and then
You know, this is well.
You know what, I guess I can't even do that now.
I think about it because I don't know if it's a standard platform type
for, in 64, because on it's like, it's like, you know, long long or
it's underscoring Sprint.
64.
I don't know if there's differences there.
So maybe we'll leave that in for now.
But one thing we could do is go look to see if there was a.
I don't know if there's a standard way, we can write 64 here now, and
if there was, we could go ahead and do that.
We could go and do that as well, and that would get rid of this.
Include, which might be helpful.
And now, I don't know.
Do we actually use any of the pound of finds in here either?
We might not.
So, one thing, another thing we could do, we could get rid of these
guys, right?
So we can get rid of our pound defines, move them in there.
Yeah, so that's another thing we can get rid of.
So we're just going again for the minimal stuff that we need in here.
That gets passed between the two layers.
Looks like that is probably as minimal as we're going to get for.
Now.
That's good.
Now again, we could get rid of that thing.
Let's see.
Is there a platform?
Is there a c standard for 64-bit integer?
Oops, that was a good smelling, their integer.
And so, let's see.
Do we have anything?
No, we don't want to.
We don't want to include that, though.
That's the thing is they're just a standard without having to include
standard end because I don't think, yeah, there's nothing you can do.
We don't want that.
So, I don't know if there's a way to do that the way that you used to
do.
This sort of thing is the way I would do it.
Is I do like a pound if and then in the pound, if you would put,
whatever the compiler name was or the platform name was that you were
working with and if so, you would use their particular way of defining
that in 64.
So,
I know we could we could look at doing that in the future.
But for now, I think that's it because I want to wrap up the stream.
Not go too long.
But there's a good start for people who wanted those things separated.
And so you could take a look at that.
So like for the person who requested for them, was the person who is
doing the Swift Port, take a look at that.
See if there's anything else that you need to be done there, but that
should give you a better start.
Sort of out.
And you know what?
I'll move this.
I'll move this guy out here as well.
All right, so, so that should do it.
I think that should do it and then we'll wrap that for a day.
So everyone, thank you very much for joining me.
I hope to see you back here again at 10 a.m.
Tomorrow.
We'll be doing this again and we will go ahead and see if we can get
our guy walking around to multiple Tom apps tomorrow, which will put
us in good shape for actually starting to construct our world, which I
am interested in doing.
So I think that should be
Be fun.
Thank you very much for joining me.
If you would like to purchase a copy of handmade hero with the Full
Source, you can do.
So the pre-order button here will give you a download link.
So you can download the source code to the game if you'd like to play
around with it and follow along.
Every day when we do coding, you will be able to download the source
every night.
As soon as I update it.
If you want to support the video series.
We have a patreon, you can subscribe to.
And, of course, we also have a news and Forum site, you can go to,
which has tons of useful.
Informations got the schedule here.
It's got an episode guide where you can catch up on old episodes.
It's got a coding resources page where people have ports Abacus X
Linux and so on.
We've got a code discussion forum.
You can post your questions.
So we basically have everything up there that you would need to follow
along with handmade hero.
So, I encourage you to check that out.
Thank you so much for joining me here.
I hope you have a very merry Christmas.
If you are celebrating Christmas today, and I will hope to see you
tomorrow at 10:00 a.m.
Sharp Pacific Standard time.
Thanks, everyone.
And we will see you tomorrow.