Up recording, start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero show.
Rico to complete game live on stream.
We are sort of, well, we just finished a little bit of a diversion
that I had promised to show people some metaprogramming.
So, I showed some meta program the stream for two days.
And I went pretty well.
We've got a little parser, it's kind of just a toy, but it shows kind
of how to do that little cycle where you can parse some code output,
some code, compile it into your game and have it do stuff for you.
That could be potentially useful.
So that's in there.
Now, we didn't really have specifically any particular like
overbearing need for it.
It's not a crucial part of the project, but it was a reasonable place
to do it where you can kind of see how it was going to work and
understand the relatively confined context like what it
You and why?
So, I thought it was a pretty useful thing.
But today, I'd like to get back to finishing up sort of our debug
output stuff because we still have several things we need to do there.
And I'd like to kind of finish that up and get that into a situation
where we can start using it more effectively for actually doing debug
work.
And right now we have some nice features in there but but a lot of
stuff we just have not implemented, right.
There's a lot of things that that need to kind of just actually make
up, make a push for being complete and so what I'd like to do today is
start contacting that.
Now today is Day 2008, so if you want to follow along at home day,
2007 is a source code that you're going to start with.
So please make sure that you unpack that into a directory and that's
what you're going to be working with.
Now, if you want to follow along with me, okay?
So here we go.
Let's go back to where we were.
Before we did our little metaprogramming Excursion so you can see like
when we did them in a previous version we did some stuff where we were
like doing some automated debug print out stuff.
So there's all this kind of nonsense here.
All of that stuff was just in a little like piece of test code that we
did that.
I can easily remove here, right?
It's this thing here where we did like test entity, write this stuff
and so I'm just going to get rid of that.
And when I get rid of that, then when I compile
All of that should go away, right?
So now we're back to the standard thing that we were looking at before
but now we can also start to use.
We had finished this thing.
We could pick entities with the mouse cursor as well.
So we can also use that
Alright, so basically we have the ability to sort of print things out
here.
We have the ability to pick things at the mouse and what we're going
to try and do today is sort of consolidate things and work out exactly
how we would do something where the printout comes from the app, not a
standing structure.
In the debug code, right?
So what I want to do is I want to take sort of the the stuff
Doing at the metaprogramming where we kind of just hack at least sort
of printed it out there.
What I'd like to do is integrate that into this tree view stuff in
some way that we could sort of, you know, pick an entity here.
Have that entity show up so that I can come in and you know, do sort
of the standard like expand and collapse thing as well.
Like all that stuff.
I would like to be able to inspect things that way as we go, right?
So let's figure out how we're going to do that, because that's a
pretty big problem.
It's a pretty difficult problem to solve actually, as you'll sort of
see as we work through it.
There's a lot of subtlety there and there's a lot of different
decisions about how you want to
To make that work.
So if I go over to hand me dot CPP we sort of had the beginnings of it
here, right?
You as you can see we've got this like debug to get element thing.
So I sort of said You know here is roughly what I would want to have
happen, right.
I'd want to have something like this happen and now that we have meta
code
we could even do something where this was generated for us
automatically, and like I said, now that we have a medic, medic coding
front end there, we could decide to do that but
That part is not really is not really the part that's, that's, that's
super relevant.
Really more, the part that's relevant is the conduit between this
piece of the code and the debug piece of the code, right?
What I need to do here, is figure out how I'm supposed to ever
actually get any of these entities.
And, and so that's what we're trying to do here.
So, let's say,
That I was looking at this here now, what we do know is I could if we
were to look at this thing here, I could sort of look at this and say,
well there's this debug entity thing and there's all the stuff that
you might want to look at on it, right?
You can kind of see all of this stuff here and, you know, one way that
we could deal with it, if all of these things were always in memory.
All the time is I could just say something like, okay,
Here is an entity.
Here's a thing that I might want to view put it into the debug stream
because, you know, we've got the ability right, like, in our
In our profile sorts of stuff, you know, we've got this ability.
Down on the here, we've got this ability to like, add these debug
records, right?
And whatever, the debug records are, we could, you know, we could
augment that debug record structure to store stuff, like here is an
entity that I wanted to display, right?
And so the problem with just doing something like simply sticking
maybe like a pointer in there.
That's just a little piece of information like here is the, you know,
here's here's the end of the base pointer is that something like for
example, even this entity the same entity it all
The exists transiently.
Like right now, we unpack the similarity.
We do the simulation, and then it goes away, right?
And so, really anything that the that the user could inspect in the
debug view, like like the programmer could inspect in the debug view,
after the fact, anything that's going to fall into that category has
to get captured at the time that we pass through this code, it can't
be inspected later in the debug system as sort of a walk in memory,
because the memory is actually gone.
Or more specifically, the memory still there, but it, it ain't filled
with this information.
It's filled with something else or just garbage or who knows what.
And so the question is, how are we going to actually deal with that
problem?
And I think, you know, as you can see, if we jump back to sort of our
minds space, when we, when we wrote this code, what I think probably
we were going to do here is say like okay instead of capturing all of
the data that we could possibly ever want to inspect
Which would be way too much data and very unwieldy and not probably a
very good idea.
Instead what we could do here is say, oh well maybe what we could do
is just capture like one selected thing, whatever like a selected and
the is like a hot entity or whatever, select one of those.
And then capture all the information about it into the stream that
would work.
So that's one way we could do it and that appears to be sort of the
way, like I said that we were going to we were kind of going down
before it has some drawbacks, right?
One of the drawbacks is that you know, if you were to pause a frame
you know like capture just just a frame by itself without the
knowledge of What entity you wanted to know about on that frame or
entities.
You cannot go back and change your
After the fact, right?
You cannot go back and recapture other entity data because it is
already happened.
The best that you could possibly do in that circumstance, is something
like jump back to that, the memory State at the beginning of that
frame, which, you know, we could save or something like this using the
looped Live code editing, sort of system and change What entity were
asking for at that time to get them different entity out, right?
So, that's something we could do.
But something we can't do is just crawl all the data as part of the
debug system it's simply not possible.
You have to continue to run sort of the game Loop in order to have
that happen.
So like I said, not sure what the best solution is to this problem in
general, in terms of the inspection.
It's you know it's six of one half-dozen of the other and certainly,
you know, one thing we could do is say okay, let's you know, let's
just go ahead and actually just dump them.
All other thing we could say, is
In debug mode, you know?
When we do a Sim region thing, we use this memory and what we could do
instead of having that be Transit,
We could actually have that be permanent memory.
Meaning when we use, when we do the same region and we put we unpack
all of our entities into the same region that we're simulating,
instead of going and throwing that away.
We could instead save it to inspect it later.
okay, but even on top of that,
Again, getting back to some motivation of why we might want to keep.
Doing it this way though, is that even on top of that we have a
problem which is that there would only be one state of the entity.
So for example if we wanted to know what the state of an entity was
before it got stimulated and then after I got stimulated so we could
see like how its position changed or what, you know, type it was
changed or you know things like that that may have occurred that were
changes in the entity from one point.
In time to another again, we can't do that with a system where all
it's doing is taking the memory and inspecting it after the fact.
So, I think even though it has some drawbacks.
I think, at least for our current system and, you know, with the
understanding that, you know, on handmade hero, we're not building the
absolute best debug system the universe.
Because the thing, we're shipping here, is a game that a debug system.
We have to be willing to accept a certain, you know, Line in the Sand
of.
Let's not try to solve every problem, right?
Given that fact, I think the most reasonable thing to do is sort of
stay with this kind of a system where what we're doing essentially is
saying okay.
We're going to decide a few things to look at beforehand.
We're going to capture the information about those things that we
think is going to be relevant as part of the code and in the event
that that turns out to not be the data that we needed.
Oh well we have to go change the code and rerun the test or whatever
it is.
We're trying to do that's just the reality of the situation.
It's still a lot better than debugging blind.
It would still be a very useful system.
Does it allow us to curl the data arbitrarily?
No, but then again, neither does anything else really until we
finally,
Get some real debuggers and I would not hold your breath for that.
So that said, let's go ahead and push forward with this.
And what I'd like to do is go ahead and say that, you know, maybe this
thing right here is going to essentially just go through this system,
right?
We've got this concept of debug records here, debug records.
I'm sorry debug events, rather and these debug events have actually, a
type associated with them, right?
And then they've got
Information.
So what we can probably do presumably is we should be able to sort of,
you know, piggyback on top of that basically, in order to dump data
that we think we might need.
Okay, so I'm going to do that in sort of the simplest way possible at
the moment and you know hopefully it will be something relatively you
know, it won't be too problematic for us basically.
Okay, so here we go.
I have
Have a debug event and I've got a type for the debug event.
I can go in here and say that the debug event.
Is now going to be able to Output some values, right?
And if we take a look at the values that this is outputting, right?
Maybe we've got some things like we've got a real 32s, right?
Or you 32 science 32s, that sort of thing.
And, yeah, you know, that's, that's really mostly the sorts of stuff
that we would want to start with.
We probably don't need to do anything else quite yet.
Because, you know, I'm trying to think.
We want to store anything.
We don't really want to blow the debug instruct up too much, because a
lot of people are using it, but there are a lot of ways that we could
get around that.
So you could imagine, for example, us writing a sort of system for
this sort of thing where we actually did something, you know, more
like this.
So as we sort of do the we got a 64 and a 32 pack together there and
then here in the union we could actually have longer things and we
could start encoding.
I'm these with variable sizes, so we could have the type.
For example, has, you know, sort of an understanding of a size that
goes with it, and then we could have things in here, that we're going
to be different sizes.
I kind of feel like that might be a good idea to some degree but I
don't know, right?
I'm not sure.
Seems like it probably would be though and in that case, we would have
things like this, you know?
Right.
So a bunch of our fundamental types would probably exists in here so
that they could get captured as a whole.
Right.
And again that's not that's really mostly about efficiency.
That's not really about any sort of ability to capture because we
always could just pretend that everything is like R32 you through to a
sturdy to that sort of thing, right.
And then in here you know what we would do is we'd say OK.
Well there's V2s and v3s
What can't actually use be 3 because that's actually a function, we
already have.
So I got to have to kind of make up something for it there.
But yeah, you can imagine something that looked like this.
If we want to do something like this, right now, as you can see, when
I create this Union, it's going to take up more space.
It's going to take up as much space as a rectangle three, which is
like six floats, right?
Which means that it would massively bloat, the space required to store
the basic debug events, which is just like only 128 bit wide, right?
Normally like if you if you ignore this stuff here, normally it would
just be 64 bits, 16, bits, 8, 8, and 32, right?
So, that is not good.
Given the amount of debug information that we're currently pushing
through the system, we definitely wouldn't want to do that.
And so, the way that I would handle that in the
The event is instead of advancing by a whole debug event at a time, I
would always Advanced by whatever the actual size is of the thing that
we're talking about.
And then I would go like from there.
I would then you know, they're both a reader and the writer would go,
which type am I?
Am I actually working with your and whichever type that is I Advance
by however, much.
You know, I need to as a result.
So that's up again.
Pretty straightforward thing to do.
We could totally do that.
We don't have to do it quite yet because we could just let this thing
get bigger, you know, I could do this and if I go ahead and do that,
I guess that's not defined yet.
I guess I could just do it like this.
so we could just say, okay, you know, there's up to some large number
of these
Right?
Since I was all take the same to a space.
I think I said six so we could do something like that, right?
And in theory,
That's the works, right?
So, our debug stuff is very bloated.
Now, it's much larger than it needs to be, but it would still work
just fine.
And so, it's really just a memory compression thing is, all that I
would be doing there is to make sure that we weren't using a bunch of
memory bandwidth unnecessarily to sort of write these things out and
work with them.
Right?
So that I could do as well.
And I'm, you know, I don't really know if that's sort of a good idea
or bad idea.
I don't have a particularly
Strong opinion about either way but let's just say that for the time
being we just kind of leave it like that and we see how it goes.
So let's see here, something like this.
Maybe.
Yeah, it seems reasonable.
So if I've got something like this now, you know these things should
be.
It should be fairly obvious that this is not particularly difficult to
do at this point.
If I want to record some stuff to the debug stream, it's actually
pretty easy.
All I need to do is Define these debug value things to actually write
to that debug stream, right?
And so, in order to do that, I could come in here, I think I might
want to do this explicitly for the moment.
I've got some reasons why, I think I would like to do it that way.
And since especially since we haven't met a generator.
Now I think that might be a good idea to do.
I'm not 100% certain of it necessarily but it just does it seems like
maybe that's probably a good thing to do potentially, maybe.
So let's say, I go here to the to the actual code that we were looking
at before and I'm going to write it out manually for the time being if
I come here and I look at
We were writing out, you know, we've got a storage index.
I'm going to go ahead and abbreviate these guys since this is the
variable format that I want to kind of use going forwards.
You know I kind of was experimenting with it a little bit.
See what I liked the best and this one was the one I like the best.
So if I take that,
And I imagine just sort of like like sort of post pending the thing on
there, right?
Like whichever one we're going to actually do here.
I don't know that we really need to do that because we could use type
Discovery to kind of make that happen for us.
But at the time you know, I don't know that we really want that to
happen.
I'm not sure we could do something like that, right?
I don't know if we need it or not, I guess I can try without it first.
If we were going to try without it first, the thing that we would have
to
You is inside our sort of our debug system where the stuff actually
starts to happen if I wanted to do it inside handmade platform, right?
Then, you know, we've got this extra and see sort of situation here.
And that was something that we added for the benefit of people who are
trying to call this code from other languages.
And it would create a problem for us, basically, in terms of being
able to use these debug value things in that way, because we could not
use function overloading in order to determine what kind of variable
was being dumped.
Whereas if we did force you to sort of specify what it was, you were
trying to dump like this then it would still work from C and again I
don't know that I have a super strong opinion about that.
I'm going to go ahead and say that I don't really care about see
linkage, very much.
I don't think it's a particularly valuable thing and I was only
because I don't care if we link to see, you're not right at all.
We're never going to compile in straight.
See because we have operator overloading and stuff like that.
So I would say I would pretty much ignore this and I might just say
like okay that's a very end of all of this.
We could even say if the C plus plus here.
And basically say that like okay, inside our debug system, all of
these things only get defined to be something else in the case where
we actually are able to, you know, to do so.
So I'm trying to think of the best way to do that.
It might be something like this, it might be something like, okay, if
C++ is defined, you know.
It's fine, C++ and defined.
What are we looking at here?
Are if in our debug system is on, so it's like it's a I think it's
handmade internal right?
You know, I never did like
The way they do, preprocessor stuff and see so bad that we have a week
Professor.
Anyway.
So can meet internal assuming that we're in C++ and handmade internal.
Find then you can get a bunch of these things, but if either of those
is not true, then they just kind of disappear, right?
But if they are true, then something like debug value becomes like,
you know, push debug value, or something like this, you know, we're
debug push value or debug, you know, record value.
I don't know, whatever you want to call it.
And essentially what we're going to do is exactly this stuff up here
like exactly the same stuff that we were doing.
Doing the only differences this stuff that's happening.
Here is actually going to be super like we're going to store different
data so you can see here like
Inside this Frame marker stuff.
For example, we could do exactly what the frame marker does.
So if I come in here, and I say, like, all right, we're going to do
the debug value call.
There's the debug value call.
It's going to look exactly like that for a marker stuff.
Looks so we create a synthetic counter to say this is where it's
coming from, we record a debug event here and we say that the debug
event is going to be whatever the whatever the type was of that.
Killer you know whatever this particular thing is in order to do that
unfortunately we need some kind of like a cracking function like we
need some way.
This is why I was sort of saying, it's kind of annoying.
We need some way to translate a type into a debug event, right?
So we need something like this like where we'd say debug event from
and then we would pass it the debug value.
So it would be something like this.
There's the value and I would say, get me the debug event from that
value, we then have this stuff for like, okay, event seconds, elapsed
seconds, elapsed in it.
That is the thing that was being stored previously.
We are not storing that in this case, right?
We are actually storing one of those other members and we're storing
the members based on sort of what we're actually getting past.
And in fact, I guess now that I think about it.
Record debug event common.
Where do we actually?
Okay, so actually that's not even true.
What I said, record, debug event, common, just need to do a romantic
encounter.
It doesn't even need to do any macro stuff at all.
Actually, that's kind of nice.
So actually, what happens there is that can actually be sort of a
function call sort of thing.
It's got the translation unit index problem here.
I guess is one sort of nasty thing about it but but really this this
is actually
Really reasonable.
I think so.
I think what we would do,
Is there something like this?
We want to record a debug event and that debug event is, you know,
let's just say that we lie and say that it's well, we could even just
say that it's an R32 or something like this, right?
So we tell it to do record, debug event common, you pass something
like that and then in here where we're actually going to set the thing
like set event data, you know, or something like this set like diva.
value set event data or something like that, we would just pass,
whatever the value is and whatever this record debug event common ends
up giving us back
In fact, how do we actually, I guess it just spontaneously defines
that right on the stock for us.
Yes, that's what it does.
Whatever event we have, we just passed that in there along with the
value.
And now this thing, debug value set event data.
That's the thing that will do all of that cracking for us, right?
So what we would then say is like, okay, we just have, you know, an
Infinity of these where Infinity is actually some very small number
like 10, you know, it's not a particularly big Infinity.
You know, not every Infinity has to be huge.
We just have one of these guys where we've got
one for every type of value that we're sort of putting out there,
right?
So, for oops, for every one of the, of the debug event types that
we've got write all these sorts of things.
That's what we would do now.
I don't actually know, that's not what I'm talking about.
I actually walked platform.sh, I want this one, right?
So, I just want these guys.
So, yeah, I need to fill out this event for each of these different
types, right?
So there's the R32, right?
It would take an R32 and it would say that the event, you know, Wecker
32 0 equals value.
You know, and I feel like the rest of this is really pretty wrote, you
know, I'm saying.
So there's like the V2 and that would just be something like this.
Right.
And that just kind of goes on advaitha infinitum.
So that would record you know, all the different types of X we have
and then similarly you know we could do something like all right.
There's the here's the you and the S-Type and that's like s32 and you
You know, I'm saying and then, you know, if we want to rectangles,
those are again, same same deal.
I got some rectangle value here that I want to store, and it looks
exactly the same only we do the Min and the max
Right.
And so that's that's really all I was talking about.
We're now saving, you know, all of those values.
Oops one.
That would save all of those values to the debug stream.
So that we would be able to, you know, sort of memento them, like
capture them and be able to show them later.
So that that's really all I'm talking about second see linkage.
Oh, are we still we're still in the extra and see block, of course.
So let me grab it.
Grab this little guy here, there we go.
So we need to put that out here.
I don't remember what we've called these guys in the platform thing.
I don't know, it was Veeck s32 and Becky 32.
My bad.
So it was that sort of a thing, right?
Okay.
So yeah, okay.
So we also have a little bit of a problem there, whereas, if we want
these sort of automatic cracking values to happen.
Well, you know, now that I think about it, if we want these Auto ones
to happen, we don't really have to have these in here, right?
We don't we can just do it for the types that we actually do have
defined in here if we want to and and then you know, we can sort of
take those up now, there is a reason why we might want in the
Form file to define those, right?
Because they are kind of things that you could imagine the platform
layers, wanting to use.
So I don't know, you know, if that's the best thing to do or if that's
not the best thing to do.
It's really kind of touchy what goes in the platform layer and what
doesn't go in the platform layer.
So I'm not I'm not certain what the right answer is there.
But you can imagine, for example, just taking these guys, the ones
that rely on other types.
Like that, they can be moved.
So, if I were to take these out and go to handmade math.h, you could
imagine us just sort of putting in here, like, okay, the debug
cracking functions for these guys.
Actually, could go, you know, right in the, you know, right with the
code that defines them.
So in the file that you define v 2 is V 3 S, you get the debug
crackers for those as well.
You know, me and that would work pretty well.
So yeah, of course are handmaiden.
Anna stuff again.
Doesn't really have all the definitions that are probably wants week.
Sort of have this thing where we're stable still using some of these
older versions of stuff.
I can go ahead and fix those just for fun.
Yes, please read from disk, real 32 should be R32.
So distance limit.
There we go.
That's what we're looking for.
And where was our interests backed.
What else do we have?
There's one get rid of that guy, get rid of these guys, I should
probably just do a day where we just get rid of all of those at some
point, it should happen.
And we also have one in handed world, right?
We introspected that.
So these are those, as well.
Okay, so someone still using a Unit 32 here.
I don't really remember her.
There it is.
There we go.
Okay, so now we just got to actually get this stuff working, but
that's basically.
That's basically what I want to start with.
Is that that concept right there, the way that we played it out.
Okay, so now we got to make sure this stuff makes sense.
We call record debug event, common, we do whatever this stuff is going
to happen.
There we called ebook set value data and that nonsense we have.
So there's our missing semicolon I can fix that none of the seven
overload.
Can do the hip Point.
That's correct.
I'm going to start.
This off, by not having a raise in there yet, so we could do with a
little bit later, same with that, and let's see.
Okay, so now, we just have to fix these little printout routines that
were kind of old, print out routines were playing with, guess they
might as well leave them in working order.
Okay, so now in theory anyway, we are actually recording these, and it
does look like that's true because you can see we hit an assertion in
here.
When we're doing our debug collation, you can actually see that we get
to the point where
We have collated the frame and we're like, oh, hey wait.
you know, we actually got to a
sort of a situation here, right?
We got to a we got to a
Type of event.
We didn't recognize, we don't know what it is.
So you know, looking at this, I feel like what we could do is much
exactly like the way we collated are other debug records.
We can now collate, these ones that are coming from the
Like these debug records that are coming from the game.
We could reassemble them back into a structured piece of data that
could be walked by by the engine right?
At least it seems like that would be a reasonable thing to do.
So yeah again if we want to we should be able to build you know some
kind of like a an introspective of
Basically just build the actual struct set that we were doing before
we should be able to build that from the Coalition data.
So the way that we have these sort of debug variables and stuff the
way that we were building them in here where we sort of have
like, yeah, like if you just look at this sort of variables,
the way that we were doing this stuff, we should be able to
essentially build one of these.
I would think up from the, you know, from from the sort of parse that
we get.
So as we're kind of coming through here
When I see these various values, I'm going to go ahead and try just
building one of these variable groups and seeing what happens.
Now, there is a sort of caveat there, which is again, there's really
not a lot of with one of the things that, that we sort of set
ourselves up for success for our.
But we haven't actually dealt with yet is, if you remember debug
values and debug things, they have this concept of an ID, right?
So we've got these like, debug variable
Thanks and the debug variable links were things that had, like, sort
of these, these IDs, you could build from them, right?
So when you were iterating over something, there is this notion of
like an ID there.
And the ID was something you could use to tell like which one you were
looking at and stuff like this, right?
And this is sort of the part that like I said, is like kind of really
subtle and going to be difficult.
Because if we are taking data every frame from the app and sort of
reprocessing it, right?
Like it's getting captured as part of the run of the
App.
So it has no permanent address ability in that sense.
We're going to need a way to know how to talk about that piece of
information in order for it to work with the rest of our debug UI,
because our debug UI needs a way to know that something exists from
frame to frame, right?
And since this is the thing that's going to tie early ethereal, we
need to make up ways to have that happen.
And, like I said, we sort of set ourselves up for success by starting
down the road of having this debug ID concept.
So, it will, I think be very plausible for us to figure out a good way
that we can use that to enforce exactly.
Something like that.
Exactly.
A sort of stationary ID system that will allow us to sort of fetch
those things back, but it's going to again, be a little bit
complicated.
so anyway,
let me see, where was I?
So, what I want to do here is I want to start to build up a thing that
can actually be output as necessary from these things, when we get,
you know, basically that assertion that we got.
So, when we hit the assertion, when we're inside collate, debug
records, I want to be able to start collating data records.
In addition to these other
Lots of records that we have, right?
You can see we've got like, collation frame, and collation and block
and those sorts of things are happening.
I would like to, I would like to have something that was going to
capture the other kinds so we've got begin.
Where do we have event?
Type equals event frame marker, then we've got Collision frame
assuming that we're on a frame we've got begin block and end block.
And so I think what I'll probably do is sort of move that out into
sort of
A more complete concept and maybe, you know, I could leave even these
the same as they are at the moment and then assume that like, this is
the thing that handles, maybe all of the all of the other ones here,
although like, you know, I could just do this.
I could just do this right here.
There really isn't much reason not to, I suppose, if I switch on the
event type,
I could just say that here is begin.
Block.
Like so.
Here's end block.
and that is,
All we would need to do for that.
Then we would have our default case here.
And I think that should just do exactly the same thing of it as it
did.
Right.
That should just immediately say, hey I got an event.
We don't want don't understand.
And so then from there, we can sort of put in all of those other cases
where we were trying to Output some things like these guys, right?
And so in here, I'm going to go ahead and say, all right, we've got,
you know, all these different cases that we want to handle where we're
going to.
Basically just shuttle data back and forth, like so,
And so now if I just go ahead and let this not do anything, then we
should just consume the debug events Pharmacy, nothing will actually
happen with them.
But you know, everything still works.
Okay?
And presumably, we are still able to view like the the function
profiles and things like this.
So we know that all the rest of the debug events are still getting
collated exactly as we would expect them to.
So, that's all good news as well.
But now, once we get to these, we can start to actually use them for
something and of course, in our collation,
Know that we, you know, as we were sort of doing that, that collation
process as we sweep through it.
We have this sort of notion of like open block and close block and
that sort of stuff, right?
We can kind of Leverage that because we have, like, all of these
Notions of, like, what the threat is, and all that stuff, right?
So when we're in here, we already know which thread we're talking
about.
So inside that debug thread that
Debug thread information.
We can have sort of this notion of things that are being built up,
right?
We can have a notion of data that is being captured.
And so if we look at this, debug variable stuff, as that we have here,
really what we could imagine, is saying that per thread, we could just
have something like this, where all the stuff we were doing before to
build up debug variables will actually could just do that exact
process over time using our debug collation, right?
And again, this because this would be sort of a rolling buffer sort of
thing,
Would mean also that in theory, you know, things could even cross a
frame boundary and presumably they would they would still actually
work, right?
In theory.
Okay, so if we take that and sort of move a little bit forward with
it, so, Okay, so we've got one of these things and we want to start
making like, you know, sort of a stack sort of a situation.
In fact, you can almost imagine the open block thing is almost.
We're almost doing exactly the same thing here, right?
We're doing a thing.
Where we kind of, we open something up.
We put data into it, we close it, right.
And that may open in a nested fashion, if we want to have like
hierarchical data, that happens in there.
That wouldn't Theory just kind of work, right?
At least we hope it would, who knows?
Okay.
So if we want to do something like that,
We're probably going to need at least a couple of the things here.
We're going to need something like debug event.
You know, open data block or something like this, right?
And debug event, blows data block.
Right, so we can Factor the same way that we've got these like begin
block, end block things here.
We would also have the ability to like open and close data blocks,
which are not the same thing, right?
They have nothing to do with performance or timing things.
They're just like, sort of opening up data region, writing stuff to it
and then, you know, closing it out again, right?
And I'm trying to think.
I guess this seems like the most reasonable way to do it.
Yeah, so when we're doing this stuff when we have open data block and
close data block,
It's pretty much going to be something like, you know, open, debug
data block is going to be the sort of thing.
I don't know why we care about starting frame index necessarily, or if
we care about sorting framing next, we probably don't because it
doesn't really have anything to do with timing, but we may need that
for other reasons.
I guess it does come from a debug record.
That's true.
It does have an opening event, and presumably it would be change
exactly as these
So it would look probably exactly like one of these things.
The only difference is that in addition to this, this stuff, it would
have some kind of another pointer kind of on it, right?
And so it makes me think that probably we would just want to reuse
that code as necessary.
So we would have something like, okay, we've got, you know, first
open, you know, code block and first open data block or something like
that.
So you can imagine saying, like this sort of a thing perhaps, and then
forcing this stuff to kind of understand both of them.
So, if we have first open block here, I got first open code block.
And first open data, block this stuff.
Would all be first open code block.
Keep on going.
First Oak, been towed block?
Yeah,
See what else we got here.
Where is my cursor?
There it is.
This would also be first at the code block.
Let's see.
First open code block.
First urban code block, first open code, block first, open coat.
That's actually it.
So these just need to get put on there.
So if I, if I take a look at him a platform that H, right?
We just need these two different events.
But we have now and we can also even write this in there because I
believe we actually have.
Yeah.
So, you know, inside handmade debug I'm sorry inside.
Handmade dot CPP where we're doing this.
I'm going to change this just for a moment.
I'm going to actually make it so it's more like this where it's like,
handmade
You know, it's like it's like debug data block or begin datablock,
something like that.
And then this will be like, debug and data block.
And that's just sort of, you know, that's, that's something that we
could rap in one of those like, little, like, utility classes
eventually as well.
And
Yeah, so I think I think that should probably do it so if we did it,
that way, if I go ahead and put these guys in there, if we do begin
data, block this way again this would be just sort of a very
straightforward thing.
I'm going to eat the parameter for now, but it would do exactly the
same thing as say this, this function does is as the values do.
But instead of this stuff you know please don't really have any useful
names I suppose.
I guess we could give that a name of whatever the
For amateur was here.
Yeah, we could you know, we could say something like like
Valley.
I don't even know, but we could, for example, string eyes, whatever
they point.
So, you know, if this is entity then it's entity.
We could also do something where we pass two things here.
So you know we get a pointer that we might use for something but we
also have a name which is like you know hot entity or something like
that.
So we actually have a name and a value to go with it and we store the
name here and we do something with the value.
A little later on.
So instead of having to do a function to crack this, obviously we
would not have to because we know exactly that it's always adjust a
data block opener.
And that's pretty straightforward thing that we would do.
And so in here, when we're taking a look at this stuff, like with
event type, we know that this is going to just be open data block.
in fact, I guess I don't even have to set the type because I can now
use that function properly, like so,
And when were recording the value here, you know, probably what we
would do is record like pointer, you know, rptr, 0 equals, whatever
the that that is.
So you know, it's a way of kind of getting that that piece of
information there and maybe we would do something like porno 0.01 and
those would be stored so that you kind of get like basically a debug
ID out of it potentially, right.
So you can imagine saying like oh yeah so what this thing is
You know, we want some kind of a stable addressing thing for it that
we could use a little more reliably and so you know maybe we we've got
if we take a look inside handmade at H.
I feel like we have ways of accessing a low entity, right?
Low entities have an actual index, so we could pass something like,
whatever that low entity index actually is, which we should be able to
get from in here.
Let's take a look.
So here we are.
Looping over RC amenities, right?
And if we look inside the same region thing, we've got same entity.
And I assuming the storage index, there is the guy that we actually
need to know, right?
If we take a look at what storage and X actually does in Dubai storage
index.
Due to do get Hashem storage index, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Yes, yes, whatever.
They're there we go.
Right.
So no still not.
There yet adding to be storage at a new raw.
There it is, right?
So you can kind of see that storage index is something that's going to
be stable over time, right?
It's an
That I learned these array.
So, in theory, right?
We could do something like that where when we in handmade STP when we
do begin data block, we could say that that we know is a stable thing
for it.
And so, then all we really need to do is stay say, and in fact, I
guess we could even do go one further and say that's the stable index
of this thing, right?
That's, that's like a stable pointer.
That will be the same over time.
And then the other question is, well, there could be multiple things
that are going to have that piece of information associated with them.
And so we might want to say like this is the hot entity or something.
This is a specific thing.
So we could give a second guy here, that is something like the hot
entity pointer, you know, like we could introduce some kind of setec.
Synthetic, stable thing that sort of differentiates between these two,
So you know something like hot.
This would just be like hot entity nub or something.
It's a funny phrase but something like this.
Oops.
And all I'm doing here right is.
I'm just making a little trick which is to say that if I wanted to
give the data since the debug system, something to like stabili
identify the thing that I'm talking about across frames, then I know
that I have a stable way of referring to, which entity it is because
every entity has a low entity that index that stable over time, that's
where it's like stored persistently, and whatever.
So I could use that, but that doesn't necessarily tell me what part of
data I'm using about the entity.
so,
What I'm doing here is, I'm just passing some value that says, hey,
here's an arbitrary pointer that stable but just differentiates this
from potentially some other call right now.
We don't really need to do that because we have that whole counter
system and stuff and then named Hot entity is probably sufficient as
well.
You know.
So in theory, do you know, do we really need to do this?
No but you know since we got two pointers maybe we use two pointers.
I don't know.
But yeah, so now so we could alternatively just do that because that
you know is based saying we don't need the second pointer even though
our debug system allows like two pointers for an ID or something like
that, right?
So anyway,
Here's our debug begin data block.
That is really all there is to it, nothing particularly fancy,
obviously it just does its little thing here and then when we do debug
and data block,
I'm going to go ahead and essentially make the exact same thing.
Here, debug and data block is going to be the exact same thing.
Only this time you're not going to rest the pointers because you know
that they the debug have to end in order.
That's just the thing will say about our data blocks.
It's fine.
And so it doesn't actually have to have any data.
It's just sort of saying the block is closed, right?
And then I think we should be mostly set there, shouldn't really be
anything else to to bizarre about that.
So inside.
So this is like a vector of pointers inside here in our handmade
platform.sh.
We would have to add that to this, right?
So back pointer and maybe there's just two of those I guess
technically there could be three of those.
That's how many
there is space for currently but anyway,
Debugging data block.
That is correct, right?
Yeah, so inside you like, we don't really need a block name for the
end, because again, that just kind of pairs up automatically.
So I think that's totally fine without actually having one of those
and off we go.
So, we also have to deal with these guys here.
Debug begin data, block and debug ended a block.
Those are the ones that are just kind of when we compile out, I still
want to be able to compile everything out if necessary.
Okay.
So I think we're in good shape.
Now, these guys should be ready to go and so really all we need to do
is inside our open data,
Closer to block collation system.
We need to have a way to actually start recording some of that data,
but we're just about out of time, so I'll probably stop soon and go to
Q and A.
I don't know that we will have time to kind of get this stuff in here.
But what I can do since we're going to be reusing this open data block
concept, what I can do is just sort of pull out this code that I'm
going to need to do that with.
So I'd have a thing like this, which is like, debug open block or
whatever it is.
Let me just let me just grab it right here.
This thing.
So if I have an open debug block,
This is the thing that would like get me the the next one.
So like, you know, allocate open debug block, something like this.
And what this would do is it would just say, okay, from the debug
state
If you need to go ahead and get a new debug block, you just pass the
debug state in it.
Will look for the first three block.
It'll see if it can get it, if it can, it will use it.
If it can't, then it will just go ahead and make a new one out of that
collation space, right?
So that's really it.
Oops, that's debug State result.
We go so something like that, right?
And if I then go in here, and just replace that where we were doing
that previously, like this stuff right here, I can just have this with
allocate debug block.
Rocket open Diva block.
That get ripped gets rid of all of that code that will would have been
duplicated.
Because I'm about to have to do that.
Exact same thing for my, you know, my other open and open and close
block.
So, in here, when we do the first first open code block debug State
forestry block thing.
So this right here, you can see the first free Block.
First open code block, this is also that same for thing.
This puts the thing back on the free list, right?
so, this is essentially like a
This part right here is essentially the deallocate one, right?
So I could have the exact same thing deallocate open debug block,
here's the debug state.
And if you take a look at how this code works again really, really
simple.
We're just saying, whatever the the block is, that we're trying to
free, it's going to be whatever.
The first three block was.
And then the first few block itself is going to become the pointer to
that block right?
It's open.
Right?
So if I go ahead and do the deallocation here, I replace that piece of
code.
With a known thing.
And again, that's really just me being proactive because I know I need
to do it.
So I'm just going to do it.
I would have had to write the exact same code for these guys so I
don't want to write the same code twice.
There you go.
So all I would do is say, hey thread first open code block is the
block that needs to get freed and we're done, right?
That's a pointer.
There we go.
And off again.
So again, no change here.
Now, it should be exactly the same as it was previously, let's just
make sure of that, and there it is.
So that's all good.
So yeah.
So I think we're all fancy now.
Okay, so I'll go ahead and go to the Q&A here, case, anyone has any
questions about what we did again?
We're kind of just like getting prepared to capture all that data,
which will try to do tomorrow again from the debug log and then we'll
kind of go from there.
I'm going to take off the old wrist guards.
All right, let's see.
Could you explain how this code works?
It's fast inverse square, root.
I still have no clue how it works.
Let's see.
Float Q.
Reciprocal square root.
3/2 x 2.
Number equals 0.05, y equals number.
I EcoStar along evil floating-point bit level hacking Books.
Five, seven, three, seven.
Five nine TF minus.
I Square Root Down /.
That's okay.
Okay, I guess what I would say about that is no, I probably can't at
least not right off the top of my head.
I can sort of give you a clue as to what it's doing.
You know, there's some pretty standard techniques for this sort of
thing, and it looks like it's using at least two of them in here.
So, basically, when you compute things, and we'll see a little bit of
this later on handmade hero when you compute things, in a compute, in
a computer that are complicated, such as square, root, sine, cosine,
tangent, whatever, you know, transcendental functions, and things of
this nature.
Are typically what you do is the way you compute them is, you use,
like series expansions in one case, right?
So you have like things like Taylor series or you know, series
expansions that are series that will converge to the answer.
So you'd make like a series, you know, like the old-school kind that
you did in high school or whatever you'll do like a series expansion
where the series creates the mathematical function that you were
interested in to a certain level.
Level of precision based on how many terms of the series you some.
And then you actually just do some number of those in the series and
compute it, right?
Another thing you do is you do what's called route-finding by say
newton-raphson or things like this, which are techniques where if you
have a function and it's derivative or multiple derivatives depending
on the circumstance, you can start out with a guess that you think is
close to the answer you want.
And then you can run this to refine the answer to get it much closer
to what you wanted, right?
And so what I see happening at the end there and I have to go, like I
said, I'd have to work it all out myself to really know what it's
doing but what you see at the end there is just some kind of
refinement like a newton-raphson iteration.
InStep or something like this.
It's an iterative refinement.
Where you're taking a guess and you're moving it closer to the actual
solution, right?
And that's very, very common.
In floating Point function.
Computations if I've given, if you really care about this sort of
thing, I've said this many times on earlier parts of the stream, what
you want to do is read this guy's books.
They're extremely, extremely good and I don't know if maybe there's
like a good
Oh man.
I don't like being reminded that form enactment is dead from an actin
is dead.
All right?
Anyway,
We do it for now.
If you look up his books they are all about how to construct routines
that are doing these sorts of things using series is and refinements
and stuff and he kind of walks you through it.
In fact it's it's I don't want to call it the handmade hero of real
math Computing because I feel like his stuff is a lot stronger than
than mine certainly so that might be a bit of an insult to Foreman but
point being his mental state is very similar to ours.
Sense that people do all this kind of crazy math formalism and stuff
and it's a disaster and he goes and looks at the actual practical way
that the math works like really underneath and goes, this is how we
would actually compute this thing.
And so if you like handmade hero and you like math, you will love
these books.
They are very good and they talk about those sorts of things.
So if you really want to know more about that, kind of, that part,
that's what he would talk about in here.
Now, this the first part of this function is not really something.
Thing that firm and acting probably would talk about very much the
first part of this function where they're can wear their casting the
flute to a long and then using a magic value to deal with stuff,
right?
What's happening there?
Is floating Point numbers like any other number.
He's just a collection of bits and the bits are in a known layout,
right?
There's a sign bit at the top, there's a exponent, and there's a then,
there's a mantissa, right?
And the sign bit says, whether it's positive or negative, the exponent
says that the scale is in the mantissa, says, what the actual value
is.
You know, it can imagine like scientific notation, right?
It's the part where you've got like something, you know, 1.2 39,
whatever, blah, e.e.
something, you know, 20 is some scientific notation number just like
you learn to school.
Well the E, something that part is the exponent, the one point blah
blah blah, that's the mantissa.
The one is implicit in floating Point, Unit actually story,
But point being, that's the mantissa.
And then the positive or negative like if it's files were - that's the
sign bit, right?
And that's how floating-point numbers are stored.
And so what use typically will see?
When someone sits down to really over optimize a floating-point
routine?
Often times there are certain operations that they need to do which
can actually be done much more efficiently by actually just
manipulating the B directly.
And so the I shifted down by one, right, is what, whatever, they
figured out, shifting down the, I shifting down by one, which shifts,
like one bit of the exponent, like, into the, it's just one bit of the
exponent down into the mantissa, right?
It's just the exponent down by one it shifts a 0 into the sign bit.
But that's okay, because, you know, that the signed it was positive
because you can't take the square root of a negative number, right?
That's already off the
Bubble, so that operation.
Then using this magic constant, which they carefully constructed to
do, exactly a specific thing when you did the subtraction will put,
like the number into a state.
That would have taken them many floating Point operations to arrive at
potentially.
So it's just a way of going like, oh, okay, I figured out that the set
of operations I want to do like I want to like divide this number by,
you know, 12 or something.
And I figured out that I could do that by like actually like using a
magic constant and subtracting it and whatever, right?
So that's like the how the first part Works in like usually it's a lot
easier if the person who actually wrote the routine notated, how they
arrived at that constant.
But in the case, if you're trying to really reverse engineer,
something that you've literally never seen before and you're not
familiar with where that concept comes from, you're at you're going to
have to do some wackiness by watching.
What happens to a floating Point number.
When its
I could from that and that actually shouldn't be too hard for you to
do.
You should be able to plug some known floating Point numbers in there,
easy, 11.5, 1.25 things like this.
Look at what happens to them.
And you'll be able to see the operation that they're simulating by
cheating like that, if that makes sense.
So that's all, you know, hopefully that's enough of an explanation to
get you started on that.
Like I said, I'm not going to spend time trying to reverse engineer it
because that sounds like a lot of work.
And we're probably not going to build yellow stream, it's not the kind
of code that I work with very frequently.
It's possible that if you ask someone who often does floating-point
optimization stuff on this with bit twiddling, they would recognize
that constant.
It may be a common trick constant.
Some things are common to constant some things are uncommon, right?
Some things are trick.
Ants that are used in many places.
Some things are constant that you made up.
Just for this one algorithm that you want and you're unlikely to
appear anywhere else.
And so that's just again, something to be aware of, you know, you
could also search for it.
But I doubt, you know, that's probably
not the most useful thing to do, but just
Just for fun.
It does not look useful 5f 3759 tips.
I've 9df.
So there you go.
In fact, you can see right here.
Oh, did you actually get this from here?
We'll wait a minute.
They are explaining it right here.
Why are you asking me to do this when the explanation is right here?
Yeah, so you know, I guess this is good though, it's exactly what I
just said it was right.
So they're just trying to do a fast computation that they sort of
worked out that they could do that.
Really, you know, really quickly.
So they're producing 1, over the square root of x.
The log 2.
Right.
And they're doing that you because using this magic constant as a way
to do that much more efficiently right in their terms.
Now, of course it's
When I say much more efficiently, this is from the old old old days,
right?
Because as they're even telling you right here, you know, nowadays,
you can get the square root, the processor can do it basically for
you.
They've got square roots, kind of built-in.
So it'd be kind of stupid to actually ever be using this thing.
But, you know, it's a useful exercise.
So it's fun to still, you know, I would encourage you if you actually
are interested in for some reason to go through and actually watch it
work that way.
So you get some idea, right?
What would be a good project for a beginner game programmer?
Just a really simple game I would recommend asteroids or Space
Invaders.
Probably asteroids, is the very easiest, I would say that everyone
should probably make an Asteroids game.
I made an Asteroids game.
When I was little it's a very simple thing.
There's no contact, there's no support services, there's no obstacles.
It's like one of the purest games you can make, in terms of, you know,
the Simplicity and the directness of it.
So, you know, I would say, asteroids, make a good version of asteroids
get that going.
I understand it all.
That's a really solid place to start, right?
La 238.
I just read that natural selection 2 for which unknown Worlds made
their own game engine.
Say they no longer support Windows XP does handmade hero run on XP and
why wouldn't it so handmade hero?
I don't know whether we'll run on XP.
I don't know whether we'll bother running on XP when we ship or not,
we would run on XP, just fine, regardless, except for one, very
specific thing and that is whether we support 64-bit only or whether
we support 32-bit and 64-bit.
If we decide that handmade here or a 64-bit only that it will not
support Windows XP.
If we decide that we will be supporting 32-bit as well, then it will
And you can see that we already made sure that we do run on Windows
XP, way back, when, right?
So if you go to our whoops, that's not what we wanted and made org.
That is Hamid.
Khan handmade Heroes.
Dot org.
If you go to the the tweetbot, like, no, I'm totally confused right
now the Forum site.
If you go to the episode guide, you should be able to see in sort of
this, the platform stuff.
There's a thing where I actually test running on Windows and p x p.
I don't remember exactly where we did it.
Let's see here.
I don't actually know.
I'm not sure where we did it, but it was somewhere in here.
I suspect here it is.
So time is three Windows.
The custody
You can see as testing it on Windows XP and we go through and I
demonstrated like one of the main reasons that you might not run on
Windows XP.
I showed like what you would do with it, which is how to like set the
linking Flags correctly and stuff and then I showed us running on
Windows XP right now.
We would not run on Windows XP and the reason for that is we allocate
a big block of memory to store all our debug stuff and all this other
things.
So right now we are not 32-bit compatible.
So,
Right now, we would not want to say it but that's the only real
reason.
Everything else we do.
We could run on Windows XP, just fine.
Now as for the reason why natural selection 2 doesn't run on Windows
XP, I have no idea.
Could because they require DirectX 12 or 11, it could be your, you
know, because they require some audio system, that's not there.
It could because they require 64-bit, I really don't know.
I really don't know.
Set it for cues, like I missed any.
I think I got them all.
Have you used the new steam controller?
What do you think about it?
I have not used the new steam controller.
No.
I have played with the old steam controllers, meaning the ones that
were, you know, maybe maybe a year ago or so and they have changed it.
Since then, I did not super see the point of it, to be honest with
you.
I didn't really think
it was all that usable for playing.
Keyboard and mouse games.
So I wasn't really sure what the point was.
Like I was like, I can't see anyone actually using this for that.
So it just seemed like a really bad Gamepad, you know?
It was like this is going to be really bad for anything that you want
to use the GamePad for and it doesn't actually work for playing
anything else.
So I don't know why it exists but
You know, I haven't used the latest one, maybe it's like way better.
I don't know.
Let's see.
A piece of the tool chain, set of tools used for CMS to like Microsoft
Visual Studio have made it.
Effectively impossible to keep running in a stew on Windows XP.
A choice must be made between stopping the Love of the Game so that it
may run on Windows XP in perpetuity or maintained element in the game
because we don't speak compatibility with fail.
Interesting.
so yeah, I mean it sounds like again in typical Microsoft fashion you
know, they just
They just for some reason.
Keep doing all this ridiculous stuff that makes life harder for
everyone.
You know, you know you didn't get anything for that right.
You know they just broke it to break it because they, you know, do
that sort of thing.
Soy sauce, the kid numerical methods that work.
This is the book.
You're recommending, right?
Well actually, I recommend anything by from acting, I guess I haven't
read them all.
But I read real Computing Made Real and
Numerical methods that really work or that that usually work, American
Heroes is no hierarchical methods, that usually work and they were
both really great.
I could stand to read them again these days actually because a lot of
that information is gone out of my head because it's not the HIPAA
code that I write very often and there's probably a lot of things that
I do that.
Honestly would be better if I kind of knew what we were doing there.
But yeah, so either book, I think you would would be good to read.
Pseudonym 73, that is a great statement.
Everything that runs on Windows PE runs on Windows NP.
That is so true.
It's also true that you could probably verify that the you could
probably verify the output of any windows and P program on Windows
pee.
You just don't know whether you could produce the output or not.
Nobody does.
Elven, any tips on reading books, I find it really hard to read them.
I do enjoy their table of contents, gets me excited, but when I read
on, it gets quite boring.
I do not know how to answer that question.
I like Colonel dragons.
Answer actually.
so, my recommendation for reading books is that if you're talking
about reading programming or like, well, more importantly, math books,
I guess what I would say is,
Math books are often written by people who do not know how to
communicate anything to anyone.
Foreman Acton's books are unusual.
Actually in the fact that they are very well written, like he's
actually a decent writer but a lot of math books are written in a way
that it's pretty clear that nobody who actually doesn't already know,
math extremely.
Well will ever understand them and it's not necessarily there's no
reason for it.
It's just because math.
People just don't know how to communicate ideas very well.
I think it's because they're so used to thinking in terms of math they
think that just by listing a bunch of equations is like the most
efficient way to get a point across.
But it rarely actually is and I feel like a lot of times there's
people who know a lot of math but don't actually
Know how to use any of it because of that like it kind of exists in
this like vacuum.
And so, you know, usually the best thing to do when you're trying to
succeed at reading and math book is actually to go, try to find
someone who crosses that Barrett Bridge a little bit.
Because every so often
There are people who are both good at like math and good at
communicating and those people write books that are much easier to
like actually get into.
Now it's still a very active process reading.
Those books is still active.
You have to do the actual exercise in the book you have to like when
they show a derivation of something work, it out yourself on the side
because otherwise it'll just go like right through you.
You won't actually get any of the information, right?
But
it's really just like 99% of the success is finding the right book
first, because a lot of people
A lot of people write these books that are just waste of paper, like
they're just like big reams of like the math behind something and it's
like no debts.
No there's you don't need to write that like that's complete waste of
time, right?
You don't need to have a book that's like all of the math.
The important part about writing the book is like structuring that
math in with explanations that allow it to like Echo here, you know?
so, you got to seek those out and they're hard to find and so I guess
I would say
You know, it's not easy, but look for recommendations and a specific
about that part of it.
Like is this actually is this actually explained?
Well and does it sound like the person actually knows sort of the like
intuition behind this or do they are they just regurgitating a bunch
of math that they learn to do in college or whatever.
Right.
And
That's really all I can say.
And no, I actually have not read linear algebra Done Right by Sheldon
axler.
I think.
Let's find out.
So, when is the first edition?
You Gotta Wear its first edition.
Corrected printing, 97.
So ironically, it was published the year after I learn linear algebra.
So that would explain why I have not read it.
It was too late.
But you know, my linear algebra, so Rusty these days.
I could go read it and I would probably like relearn a lot of stuff
that I have forgotten so maybe someday I will read it.
How do you deal with some of the generally poor social skills in
programming math Fields, noticing this more and more lately,
unfortunately.
I don't know, I guess, I don't.
I mean I don't have to
I mean I program more or less by myself I work mostly with artists and
while it's true that some artists you know artists are also probably
not necessarily always the strongest class of people for social skills
necessarily but I mean like everything else, it's usually more about
About whether, you know, I get along with them or whether I work well
with them and less about whether they have some kind of, abstractly
good social skills, right?
And so you know, most the time I don't think of it as like does the
person I'm working with have good social skills or do I have good
social skills?
It's usually more like do we get along?
Okay.
And do we, are we able to like resolve conflict, productively?
And are we able to like be on good terms with each other all the time,
and not be resentful, or angry, or whatever, right?
And so,
At least in my experience, I typically have not had much trouble
getting along with.
With the people I need to get along with in order to do work at like
Molly.
But you know, your mileage may vary and I think I said it varies quite
a bit from person to person.
I have like there was one person that we worked with at one point I
was a contractor that I did not like working with and we just don't
work with them anymore for a number of reasons but by and large, like
almost everyone, I've worked with you Noah,
R.
You know, either I adapt well enough to how they need me to work with
them or they adapt to me and it's been okay.
And, and so, yeah, I don't know.
Programming wise, we I haven't had to cross that bridge.
We might at some point, if Molly is, you know, more successful in the
future in terms of what we end up doing in terms of, you know, if our
products do well enough for us to hire a programmer or two at some
Then I'll have to obviously, you know, take some of that more
seriously in terms of what I would need to do for hiring a programmer.
But at the moment we only really ever hire artists
so,
so yeah.
All right, folks, I think we can safely call it a day, I suspect.
So I'm going to go ahead and close down here.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me, for another episode of
handmade here.
It's my pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game.
I hammer here at org and it comes to the source code.
If you want to play around with it, you could also support us on
patreon.
You can go to our Forum site, ask questions.
Look at the anti-deficit guide, you can go use the Tweet pot, which
lets you do when we're going to be live.
And I would also remind you that our time.
For tomorrow is little bit different than what I initially announced
due to.
I had to make some arrangements for something tomorrow evening.
So I had to move the screen back.
It was going to be the same time as it was today.
It's going to be 8 p.m.
instead.
It's going to be at I believe, 6 p.m.
tomorrow.
So you know, always check this guy if you want or the Tweet.
But actually I think the tweetbot has it as well.
Yeah.
So there it is.
The tweetbot says it.
So beware that also Thursday.
So two days from now I will be doing a live stream with Sean McGrath
or ssss ssss McGrath on the chat regarding free to play games.
I'm not really sure what it's going to be about exactly but he is
working on a free-to-play game and he I think he wants to have a
little bit of an
Devil on the shoulder conversation about it.
So so we will have that conversation so that will be immediately
following handmade here on Thursday.
So handmade here, all started seven, it'll go from 7 to 8:30 and then
at 8:30, Sean will I guess Skype in or however, he wants to get
himself into the stream and we'll go from there.
I also would say that finally was kept having to do just make sure
that everyone was nailed down for handmade con there is a few things
like last-minute things that weren't 100% settled.
So I couldn't announce the speaker list with 100% certainty on Monday
but we actually got it 100% certain today.
And so, next Monday, I will actually post the the entire handmade con
schedule with the times, that everything will be happening at handmade
concert.
For those of you who already have tickets, you'll know exactly what
you're doing.
If you would like a sort of teaser way to figure that out if you go to
handmade hero.
Oops, and made sure that work before Monday.
If you actually go to the tweetbot,
You should see there's a little Puzzler on here.
And what I did is I sort of picked intentionally fairly obscure.
I mean as obscure as you can really do with screenshots.
I tried to pick like from potentially less notable, or less easy to
recognize games from people potentially.
But you know, sometimes that's hard to do.
Basically what I did is I picked two screenshots from each of the five
speakers who will be participating in
In handmade Con 2015.
And so if you want to figure out who the speakers are beforehand, you
should be able to do it by scrutinizing.
This lovely little block.
I won't say anything else about it, but on Monday, you can see if
you're right.
It's some of, it's a little difficult, some of them are easier, but
there you go.
So there you have it.
That's all the news from, handmade he roll, and I'll be back here
tomorrow.
Again, it will be at 6 p.m.
not 8 p.m.
due to a schedule change, but I will be back here doing a little more
work on the debug system.
Until then, I hope you guys have fun programming on your own and I
will see you on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.