Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream.
I it's going to be a slightly shorter stream today than it.
Normally is maybe about 20 minutes shorter or so only because I just
didn't want to push it too long.
I only wanted to stay on stream for about two hours or so, rather than
two-and-a-half or three, which sometimes I do just because I was
pretty sick over the past two days and I'm only now, just just now
feeling better, I was still feeling pretty lousy last night actually,
but
Feeling okay today but I don't want to push it.
So I am going to do it, a little shorter than normal, but other than
that, we should have a normal programming day before I get started, I
did want to re mention I mentioned it last week, but just figured two
weeks just to be sure.
I want to mention that the folks over at handmade Network who as you
know, build the site that we use to post the handmade hero for him.
No, you do not need to show me an ad right now.
They have just finished, adding their open project submission.
And if you are somebody who's working on a project, that you feel like
is appropriate for hosting over here at handmade Network.
So if it's a project that you feel like is about to the kitten
programming and, you know, caring about programming in that sort of
thing, and wanting to spread the sort of that sort of, for better, for
lack of a better term.
The ethics of like, you know, being serious about programming and
trying to do really high quality software that they have got a submit
a project button now.
And
So all you have to do is just register on the site, if you haven't
already, which you may have.
If you've ever used a handmade hero forums, then your username and
password from there, we'll work and they'll be a submit button here.
So you can submit a project for consideration.
And then they, you know, if the project gets picked up it'll get
hosted on here with along with all of these other projects that are on
here, a lot of pretty cool projects already on here, tweet with see is
pretty cool.
It shows how to write a Twitter client, too.
We from C using just using the curl dll, which you can download pretty
easily SUV.
Libraries, of course, Sean Barrett's collection of libraries for doing
all sorts of great stuff that are really easy to integrate for coder.
The editor we use on stream, it was also got Milton on here which is
the drawing package.
We use on stream and we're just here it is.
And so, there's just a lot of stuff on there.
That's pretty cool.
Including a bunch of projects.
I have not checked out yet because a lot of them are still, you know,
there that might be pretty early in, in their development, right.
There is some ones on here that I'm particularly excited about.
Just there's there's a couple of debugging projects and I don't know
how much they'll come to fruition or not, write any time you start a
piece of software, you never know what how it will come out.
But if any of these debugger projects come out.
Well, that's going to be pretty exciting to, I think, because I would
love
of to have more options.
For debugging and windows than I have right now because it's kind of a
little bit constrictive the way it is right now.
Anyway, I just wanted to make everyone aware of that if they weren't
already.
So if you're someone who's working on a project that you think would
be a good fit for the site, you can now just go ahead and submit it.
And that's really all you have to do.
So, that's it for that.
And now we can move on to the handmade heroing.
Today is day 358, we have one minor issue, it was
Just an oversight on my part.
We did all the work for this, but I forgot I even said it that we
needed to cast a particular, we need to cast function from a const to
a non cons care in order to pass it so that we could be clang safe and
we just missed that one issue.
So we're going to take care of that and then we will be on to 3D.
That's again, it'll just take a quick second to oops.
That's not what we want.
It all.
Don't even know why that's still there.
That's a good.
And let's just get rid of that.
There we go.
All right, so let's go ahead and jump in here.
I'm going to go ahead and open up for a coder, and I'm going to grab
that project file.
And again, I'm just going to go in really quickly and change that one.
That's not what I wanted.
That's what I wanted.
I'm going to change that one piece right there.
You can see where we use function because you can sort of see that is
if my head was not in the way you can sort of see, there's almost
nowhere where it gets you.
Used.
Right.
It's only this one location.
And so what I'm going to do is I'm just going to pass the care stars
as necessary in here.
Now the debug name where we pass the care star, this doesn't actually
get used, I believe.
So if you look at what do you bug named, does we stopped using that
thing that gets passed down and we left it in as a vestigial remain
only because we would we would have loved to have been able to put it
there and our whole system was working with it being put there but of
course GCC and clang.
Ruined our fun by making
Can it not be an actual predefined strength?
It's actually a variable, it's actually a like as if it was a static
constant string inside the function that you're in which is kind of a
bummer.
So anyway we had to undo that but here is the only thing that I think
we have to change, and that's it.
So let's just go ahead and get that going.
I'm going to say all right, this should be fixed as a day 358.
Please let me know if it
Doesn't resolve all outstanding playing issues.
Thanks again, Casey Kim has been amazing at telling us the stuff we
need to do.
So, is Martin's up here.
Martin's posted a, I don't remember where it was, but Martin's posted
here.
No, I don't know.
Martin's posted something somewhere else.
I guess, a
The things to fix and it was great because I think now we just
compiled on clang out of the box because we fixed all the things that
were not clang compliant.
And I wanted to do that for the folks who like to compile the code
base on clang because there's no reason for us not to support that the
compilers aren't that different at the end of the day so it's not
really if you're careful it's not in you know if you're careful and
don't use a ton of C++ like advanced stuff.
One of the things that's generally true.
In the past is like Microsoft C.
Compiler tends to not be as compliant with the C++ standards as it
gets updated as does clanging, clangs tends to be really up-to-date on
those sorts of things so you can definitely get into situations.
Usually the other way around where if you know you're super super C++
person in like to use all the latest features on clang, you pretty
much always can on Visual Studio.
You may lag a bit and so when you're you know, if you're on claying
doing
You're crazy C++ stuff and then you bring that code base over to
visual studio.
You may find that a whole bunch of features you were using just aren't
in yet and you can either cross your fingers and hope that they'll
issue an update sometime soon, the fixes them or you just have to stop
using those features, right?
So that does pose a problem, sometimes going the other way is usually
not a problem going, the other way, it's usually just small things
like this.
Like using a couple things that maybe not quite standard and they work
on visual studio and they don't work on.
On on clang, for whatever reason, and you got to kind of sort that out
or there's warnings like clang doesn't like the way you cast something
and visual Studios, okay with it.
So it's usually just more like minutiae like that going the other way.
So usually there's no real reason.
If you're already compiling on Visual Studio, it should be relatively
straightforward for you to make sure that you can compile on clang as
well, because the chances that the compliance on clang are is not as
good as visual Studios low, right?
If you're sticking to just standard stuff.
Okay, so let's talk about where we're at today because I think at this
point, I would like to get started on 3D stuff and just talking about
sort of what our goal is for the next couple weeks.
And this is pretty much the last time I think that I'm going to really
do any work.
That's not gameplay related.
So after this, I think I'm going to go ahead and move on to just
Implement in-game stuff as much as I am loath to do.
So, as I've said many times, I would much prefer to just write engine
code forever and have
Somebody else, right?
The game, but that's not really an option for obvious reasons, since
I'm the only person here.
So, you know, will program the game as well and we'll just, you know,
muddle through it.
I'm sure we'll do a fine job at the programming since I know how to
program.
But you know our game design is not going to be the best game design
in the world.
That's just the way that it goes when you are not a game designer but
I'm okay with that.
The goal for this is to have all the programming documented and to
give good programming resources and hey all the source code will be
So those of you that are Saucy game / designers will always be able to
improve it after it is done as well or make your own games on top of
it.
As I said, many times the source code to the entire game will be
released into the public domain.
No, later than two years after it's released.
So the entire code base can be used for other things at that point as
well, at least at that point.
If not sooner, I could leave myself open to link to releasing it
sooner than that.
Just not later.
So, let's just talk about what I wanted to do here so that it's clear.
So, we implemented a tire Pipeline and that pipeline is partially 3D
partially, too deep.
So what do we what do we essentially do?
So the way that we created things at the present time is we sort of
have an idea of a 3D World and that 3D world is really.
In fact 3D, we actually support like 3D bounding boxes and stuff like
that and 3D Collision.
And a particular person or entity in the game of any kind tree human,
whatever can be at any location in the 3D worlds and they can move in
3D.
So somebody can can literally like hop up in 3D and do sorts of all
sorts of crazy stuff.
Who knows?
What
And then at some point we kind of switched over to 2D and where we
switch over to 2D is a little bit hazy.
Not what I don't mean to say that, we don't understand it because we
wrote it.
So obviously we you know, we know what the transition is but it's hazy
in the sense that it doesn't kind of there isn't like a hard line
where it comes over to from 3D to 2D.
It's sort of just like at the entity boundary where entities get
output and then what happens after that, there's definitely a place
where everything
In 2D.
But there's also kind of a middle crafty area where things are sort of
in 3D sort of in 2D.
Okay, and then we have an entire 2D sort of pipeline where we've got
things like Sprites that that get sorted.
So, you know, we're now looking at the screen and these Sprites get
sorted based on like, where they overlap, and we actually build graphs
to determine, you know, like what the sort order should be, when
multiple things overlap and all this sort of stuff.
And essentially what I found when doing this
And you have to remember, I'm not a 2-D game programmer, I'm really a
3D game programmer.
I've almost never, I've never really worked much on a serious 2D
system and so, you know, I didn't have any idea ahead of time about
how this would go or whether I would like it, right?
Because it was a new thing for me.
I'm used to rendering things in 3D for the most part.
And I'm not used to having a switch to 2D at any point, really.
And so this the to dienes of it ended up being kind of distasteful to
me for a number of reasons.
One is, I did not like the sort.
I thought the sort the the concept that I had to build graphs that
things and sort them is really bad.
And the reason that I think that it's really bad is because I think it
really puts some hard constraints
On the number of Sprites you can have on the screen at once.
And while this doesn't pose a problem presently for us because we're
not really pushing it.
I don't see a lot of options for doing some things that I probably
will want to do in the future, like you no more aggressive use of the
particle systems and things like that.
And right now we don't have a problem because the particle systems
don't spawn, you know, hundreds of particles that are all overlapping.
But if we were to do that, if we were to spawn,
Rules of particles that are all overlapping those would form connected
graphs that have to get sorted and that's just it's just pushing a lot
of logistical sort of work on to the CPU that I'm really nervous about
and I feel like it will just constrain what we can do graphically in
the game.
And so I really didn't like that.
And I also didn't like the fact that we didn't have the ability to use
perspective properly.
I, you know, I've
Kind of gone back and forth on this.
I still don't really know how I feel about it, but I do kind of feel
like I would like at least the option of experimenting more with
allowing, the perspective to actually be more natural than it is.
And for example, having it so that we could do, you know, our dungeon
wall sort of stuff looking more like this sort of thing.
And when you move left to right having it actually shift, I don't
know.
I don't like the fact that we've sort of ham
Ourselves into only being able to do sort of much more rigid upright
stuff because I don't know, just having looked at it and play with a
little bit.
I don't know that that's really the best answer there.
And so I also felt like that was a little constricting.
So what I wanted to do is I want to say all right, look, I'm just
going to call that an experiment that failed.
It's not that there's anything in particular wrong with it because
plenty of games ship this
Sway, you know, all the old arcade games didn't have a z-buffer or
anything like this, so you can trivially continue down this path, and,
and do it this way, and you could ship handmade hero as it is right
now, Graphics wise and still have a fine game, right?
You know, if you take a look at what we've already got here, I'll run
it if you take a look at what this looks like.
You know, if you replace this art with final art,
You know.
This is fine, right?
It's moving.
Totally fine.
And smooth wise.
We're some bugs.
We might clean up or something on there, but that's a totally playable
sort of a thing, right?
So I'm not suggesting that there's anything wrong with the approach,
but in terms of wanting to push some of the other stuff in there, I
just feel like I'm going to want to do stuff like aggressive particle
systems and stuff because we have the capability of doing that now.
And I don't see any reason not to use it, but I just don't see any way
to get there.
With this kind of a back end, I just don't like it and part of that
may just be my naivete in the 2D world.
You know, one of the things that's true about programming is when you
built up a certain amount of experience with a certain type of
pipeline.
In my case, I'm very used to 3D pipelines, then it can be.
It can be that.
Your brain just isn't used to thinking about how to solve the problems
cleverly in the 2D world or something like that.
So it could just be my sort of
Having had a lot more experience with 3D pipelines, but in general,
that's just the perspective that I come to it with.
I don't see a lot of ways of making the 2D system perform as well as I
think the 3D system would if we embraced sort of similar of that Tech
like Z buffers and stuff like that, I was going to avoid them if we
could.
But just when I kind of got down into there and sort of saw what was
necessary if I wanted to have a purely 2D pipeline, it just doesn't
seem like
it can get as far as the 3D pipeline could.
So what I'd like to do is basically back up to this part here.
And there's nothing in particular that I care that I'm upset about
with our 3D the way that we're doing it.
There may be some things we want to improve here over time, but
they're not essential because we do know the 3D position of everyone
in the game right now and that's all we really needed.
So we'll just clean up anywhere in there that we were accidentally not
caring about the 3D position of things we can certainly fix that.
But then also,
I really want to do is sort of start at this point where we were
taking our world in our salmon, all the stuff that we'd already done.
I'm going to leave that pretty much intact and all I'm going to do is
start a little bit of minor surgery on this part here.
I mean, I guess you could call it major surgery but really like the
architecture isn't going to change much.
It's mostly about pulling out things like getting rid of the sort and
turning on a z-buffer.
So really, it's I don't even know how major the surgery is going to
be.
But either way let's just
it's a surgery will leave major and minor to the history books will
see whether it turns out to be major or minor.
And take sort of the stuff that we were doing before and look at how
we can just put everything to the screen in a 3D way, instead of
putting it to the screen in a 2d way.
And that's really all I wanted to do.
All right.
Now even though I think architecture Ali just because of the way that
we've done things, this isn't probably going to be that big of a deal
in terms of changes to the structure of the code base because it's
still going to fundamentally be roughly the same thing happening.
We're still going to have just a push buffer that we put stuff into
and then that's just going to get retired to the rendering API.
It's going to look exactly the same as it does right now.
We may find nonetheless that what we're doing there will require a lot
of work because we're going to have to engage much more dramatically
now with the 3D API because we're not just bleeding Sprites to the
screen.
I mean, that's all we're doing right now.
Like the only thing is we're doing right now.
I mean, we do a little bit of a tiny, little bit of work with the 3D
APA right now because we allow multiple frame buffers for doing that
fade-in fade-out stuff that we're doing.
So we do a little bit of work right now with that, but we're going to
have to engage a little bit more with the 3D API because now we are
going to be in full 3d.
We're going to have to turn on a z-buffer.
We're probably going to want shaders.
We're probably going to want a lot of stuff in there and so we're
going to have to engage a little more with a 3D API.
I don't think there's anything wrong with that because that's what
people have asked for many times.
Anyway, I think people on the stream want to know that stuff because
it's reality of it.
I don't love covering that stuff because it's just so underbaked.
All the time, you'll see when we get into it, just how janky some of
this stuff is it's ill-thought-out.
It doesn't form a cohesive whole, it's plagued with lots of Legacy
stuff.
It's you can see that it doesn't really understand where it's
eventually going and it's not coming together in terms of a unified
architecture for a Computing device.
It's got all these problems that compared to looking at how a CPU
works.
It's just real bad.
And so my
Hope is always that.
Someday that industry kind of consolidates and gets their act together
with defining a real programming model for themselves.
But until that day comes, we are stuck with what we're stuck with.
And so, I kind of hope that I didn't have to dive into some of the
minutiae there because it's really, I hope the kind of thing that in
five years, perhaps no one will have to think, about maybe, 10 years.
I don't know how many will be, but, you know, you know, maybe I
I should just say, well, it's worth teaching anyway, because that's
being really optimistic to think that the industry will come together
before then.
So who knows?
But anyway, so that's unfortunate but that's just probably what we'll
have to do because we're going to want some more control over how
things are being put to the screen at this point.
If for no other reason than the fact that we are still a 2-D game and
so straightforward, 3D polygon rendering is not going to be 100%.
Correct for what we need to do.
We're going to have to play with some Sprite card, sort of stuff.
And so we may need some Shader stuff to do things for us that we would
normally not need.
So even if we don't push the graphics quality too far, so we wouldn't
necessarily need shaders to that.
Just doing things like basic lighting will probably require shaders
because of the nature of our to.
2D world and how we're probably going to have to use it, right?
Okay, so that's fundamentally what we need to do.
Now, let's talk about the difference between Z buffer and sorting, and
I've got about three minutes before the hour break here.
So, let's just talk about this real quick.
And then, we'll maybe try to just go in and turn it on, right?
Because that's the simplest thing we can do to get started.
All right, so let's talk about sorting versus Z buffer.
And this is, this goes back.
Really in gaming to the Quake days.
That's how old this sort of situation is.
And the reason it goes back to their is because Z buffer wasn't a
particularly viable scheme on CPUs, be back in those days.
The 326 CPU wasn't really fast enough for a z-buffer scheme.
So you were always kind of talking more about sorting.
Find it kind of stuff.
Maybe I should say at 286 wasn't, I don't know.
I don't remember what the hardware was at the time.
Yeah, sorry I can't remember but basically like pre quake.
Most things were in this category, there was probably some game
somewhere that used a z-buffer for something.
And folks, who are very Ardent students of 3D rendering and games
history, may be able to point to some places where it was used prior
to Quake.
But Quake is the big one.
So I'll talk about that for a second anyway.
So most of gaming history up until the Quake time period was in the
Sorting camp.
And what this basically meant was, you know, when we were drawing
things to
Bringing, if two things were overlapping, what we tried to do is just
figure out which one of them was in front.
So, you know, if this is a and this is B and it turns out that b is in
front of a, right?
So a is like, back behind it.
Then what we try to do is draw a first, right?
And be S.
So we would draw a in and then we would draw be in to overlap it,
right?
And the reason we did this is because we simply didn't have any time
inside the inner Loops that were drawing these
Things.
Remember, this is all on the CPU to do any sort of anything really.
We just had the kind of make sure that we had the fastest possible
memory copying that we could to get stuff onto the screen.
And then, on top of this, you know, the free storting doesn't really
quite cover.
How advanced people were trying to be with a lot of these things.
There is also entire systems, based around nothing.
I mean, whose entire purpose was to eliminate overdraw.
Right?
Because when you have this kind of sorting, what you can notice very
quickly, is that, if you take a look at what happens, right in here,
you wasted a bunch of time, copying a into this region because B is
just going to overwrite it.
So, unless be happens to be transparent or translucent,
You spent a bunch of time writing things from a that you didn't need
to.
And so, furthermore, you would because again it was so expensive to do
anything on a per pixel basis.
In these days, you would even get things that would try to do much
more advanced stuff, like figure out that a is actually that.
And B is that, right?
And so it could break it up into two, rectangles, for example, sample.
So, here is a 1.
Here is a 2, and then here's B and do it that way, right?
And these took all sorts of forms and even Quake, which is what I was
about to talk about in terms of the transition to having a see buffer
has tremendous amount of work spent the whole system of the bsp and
and how that was divided in portals and all this stuff was designed to
eliminate as much over draws possible as well.
And so again I just want to emphasize the fact that in these days per
pixel cost was incredibly important.
And it you had to really really be careful about that sort of thing.
So this is how things work.
They try to figure out what was that each point in a region on the
screen and then do something that would copy it to that part of the
screen and off you go.
All right?
Now there's a lot of problems with this, right?
And it only, it really, only makes sense.
when that per-pixel cost,
Is so high.
And so dominant that it makes sense for you to start actually doing
the work to split things up.
And as you might imagine, it only really works for things that are
relatively large because if you imagine you have lots of tiny things,
right?
in a case where you've got lots of particles, let's say
she's me in a case where you've got lots of particles or something.
That's fairly tiny.
There really is no way to save the time anymore because as you know as
as the individual objects are dealing with or I should say let me
submit use the word Primitives, right?
Because I don't want to I don't want you to think of objects in the
gameplay sense.
So individual Primitives like particles or triangles or Sprites or
whatever?
They are as Primitives approach the size of pixels.
So when a primitive becomes, you know,
three by three pixels in this in the
Then the cost of filling them.
Ends up being roughly the same as the cost perhaps even less than the
cost of doing complex testing of the intersections of them were trying
to sort them or doing anything else, right?
So it only really make sense doing, you know, / primitive looking in
between Primitives and trying to figure out how to like reduce over on
stuff.
Only makes sense when that work is cheaper than the cost of doing the
actual filling, right?
Once that's no longer true.
Now you put yourself in a situation where all of this work is actually
harming you, right?
And this is what I was afraid of in the handmade here a pipeline.
I saw that happening and I just was like, mmmm, I think this is I
really don't want to be back in this period.
I know we're kind of looking at the game is sort of a bit of a retro
thing, but I don't really want to go that retro because it's just old
Tech and it just doesn't make sense on Modern Hardware.
So what happened during the Quake era was the thing started shifting
over to a z-buffer, even in software, so quick actually uses a
software, a z-buffer, excuse me.
Like I said,
Kind of recovering from illness today, kind of gross.
Okay?
Anyway.
So quick actually uses a software, a z-buffer.
If I remember correctly, it's a right.
Only z-buffer for one of the passes.
So what it's drawing, the world, it writes to the Z buffer, but never
reads from it because it can do a perfect draw of the world.
It knows exactly what it means to draw in what order to make that
work.
But then when it draws characters that uses the z-buffer,
That's what I recall, anyway.
And the reason for that was because since characters it's very much
like a handmade hero since characters could kind of be integrated into
the world in ways that are kind of complex to determine their
relationship between Primitives in the world.
It becomes very difficult to figure out, you know, a character's arm
that passes through a doorway.
Right may need to draw part of the arm on one side of a bunch of world
Primitives, but the rest of the character on the other side of the
world premiere, it just becomes very difficult to get all of those
sorting cases, right?
And you end up writing incredibly expensive code for the polygons of
the character, right?
And what that means is it now puts really difficult constraints on how
many polygons you can have in the character.
Right?
Because again, these sorts of things don't scale.
Once the Primitive start getting smaller, you just sorting time in the
figuring out how to process them becomes very dominant and you end up
in a bad situation.
And so what is z buffer is for those of you who don't already know
what it is.
It is.
It's actually called a z-buffer, z buffer.
If you're Canadian or British, I believes they use the term said 4z,
it's also probably more correctly called a depth buffer.
And because really, it has nothing to do with the Z coordinate.
Just to give you a little bit of perspective here, right?
You know, in our world, we've got stuff that's like, you know, oh,
where's this?
This is the x axis is the y axis, this is the Z axis, and it just so
happens that we tend to go.
Okay?
When we do our transform into screen space, we tend to decide to a
Line-X this way, why this way and Z goes into the screen.
I'm sorry that's not true.
Comes out of the screen depending on whether you're a left-handed or
right-handed, but we tend to think of things this way and we tend to
think of things this way.
So when we're talking about looking at the screen and talking about
how far away, something is at a particular pixel, it happens to be the
Z axis that goes into and out of the screen, right?
Because this is the Y on the screen, this is the X on the screen and
so Z is coming in or out directly.
Of the screen.
But, you know, it's kind of a crude term, what we're really talking
about again is, is the depth, right?
So it doesn't matter XYZ.
Those are just things we use for nominal eicher.
It's happens to be how we use it.
We're just talking about the depth, how deep into the screen?
Something is and so these sorts of things just you could call it a
depth buffer or more properly is really the the term that probably
should be used.
Z buffer is kind of old and old way of saying it.
especially, because
There was something called a w buffer as well, which was using a
different format.
That wasn't really the Z coordinate and all these other sorts of
things.
So again like you know, these are just kind of shorthand names for
this thing that are maybe at first Oracle will talk about them a
little bit more later.
But really the real sort of tangible idea that this thing is is that
it is a buffer that restores that stores the depth of things on the
screen.
And so let's talk about that.
All right, so what we know when we do rendering is that, obviously,
and we've already done this because we already wrote a renderer that
does, this is we have a thing that stores RGB and a at every pixel,
right?
So, typically what we're doing is a reading from some Sprites or
whatever, we're reading from, that's like the source information.
And like we do in handmade hero, we may have some fairly Advanced code
that does, like, bilinear filtering on these things and all sorts of
other nonsense.
Sort of scale and rotate them or do whatever else is going to do.
But eventually we figure out a single rgba color that we're going to
write to a particular pixel location.
And so, then on the screen,
Here's our screen, right?
We typically have some kind of a frame buffer.
And we write this rgba pixel that we figured out what the color should
be.
We write that into a particular location, right?
So our notion of what the screen is, is a buffer that holds at every
pixel value, some RGB and a value right now.
The a value is not super useful to us most of the time in handmade
hero because we don't use its called destination Alpha.
Right.
And, you know, we use the RGB a, we use that Alpha channel on the
input on the source bitmaps, right, on the Sprites, we use that all
the time to determine where they are transparent, and where they are
solid.
So obviously a is very important in our Sprites, but is a important in
our frame buffer.
Not really?
But that's only because we haven't written any algorithms that really
use it.
Now, we could write, we could write rendering algorithms that use
Alpha value to tell us something about how much coverage there's been
at this pixel so far, you can use the destination Alpha for example,
to do things like when you are compositing, if you want a composite in
other orders, besides back to front in order to get transparency to
work properly and stuff like that.
So it's, you know, you can think about this Alpha Channel that's there
in that, you know, this, it's just an extra eight bits.
You can already think about that Alpha channel that we have.
In addition, to our red green and blue color as sort of already
Extending the notion of the frame, buffer to include extra data, we
can use, right?
And that's the core concept that we're looking at here with the depth
buffer, we don't happen to use it on handmade here.
I don't believe in any real Seto.
Wait, no, we do when we make multiple frame buffers, right?
Remember we did that.
That stuff where we wanted to make it so that there was multiple
floors
In the game.
So there was like a floor and you can see through the floor to floor
underneath it through like a hole in the floor and we implanted that
that's an example of where destination Alpha sort of made sense,
right?
We rendered this the sort of this Frame buffer here for the top floor,
and it left an alpha hole in it.
So that when we then blended it on to the final frame buffer, right?
It acted like a sprayed again.
So, we did kind of use destination Alpha.
We just didn't use it in the final frame buffer, right?
Which again, there are rendering.
Seems that even in the, the frame buffer, where your compositing, all
the stuff that you're doing for the final composite even there, you
might use it.
We just didn't have to but okay.
So you did even see you even saw us use destination Alpha again just
to emphasize.
What why I'm sort of driving that point home.
What is that?
Well, that is an extension of of the thing that we're targeting for
our render, our render Target.
Our frame buffer.
That's an extension of the thing.
We're rendering to that in addition to just storing the colors, we
want to store there.
It's also storing additional information that we can use with later
operations to produce an effect that we need that we require for our
final results.
That's what that a is, right?
So it's an augmentation, right?
Alright.
So a depth buffer is nothing more than that.
A depth buffer is just saying, hey we've got an r, a g, a b, and an A
in here.
What if we then just said let's add more.
Let's add more stuff, right?
So maybe these are all eight bits, right?
So we've got 8888.
What if we then said, let's add some more stuff in here.
What if we added?
Some 24-bit value, right?
That was a depth component and often times there's an 8-bit value for
something called a stencil.
This is a way that this is this is kind of old school to be honest.
I don't know that this is really how you would necessarily
conceptualize it as much today, but I'm sort of going to take you back
to the Quake days when 3D Hardware.
First came online to start supporting stuff like Quake, It looked like
this.
So instead of having this is 32 bits, let's augment it with another 32
bits.
So now, we've got essentially 64 bits per pixel, let's say right.
Let's talk about that.
All right, so let's suppose we augment the 64 bits per pixel and now,
whenever we're rendering, what we're going to write to every pixel is.
Yes, the are the G.
The b, in the, a just like we were doing before.
We can store all four of those components.
However, we want to whatever we're doing there for blending or Alpha
blending all those sort of things, whatever it that's working the same
way as it was.
But now, every time we write a pixel, we're also going to write in a
depth value and a stencil value.
We're just going to write those in there.
And what are those?
Well for now, let's just say they're whatever.
We want them to be, we don't need to really talk too much about how
their computer, but we're just going to augment it with that piece of
information.
So that part the writing part will be exactly the same.
When we go to actually store a pixel.
We are doing nothing more than just writing to 32-bit values or one
64-bit value.
If you want to think of this as one big thing,
And we're breaking it up into rgba depth and stencil, okay so it's no
different, it's just running 64-bit pixels at a time.
Instead of 32-bit pixels at a time but there's no other difference.
It's exactly the same.
But now we are going to say let's augment the top part of that right
now you remember how we used to do stuff, right?
So I'm going to talk about sort of our old pixel
Phil first, so our old pixel film.
How did we do that?
Well, we sampled textures right.
And we like, bilinear.
Filtered them, right?
So we would have something like the hero.
And this was in a texture.
You know, or a Sprite is what we call it in the 2D parlance often
times but you know it's a texture and when we implemented the 3D path
for handmade here, right?
We allocated a texture on the card for the Sprite so at the top of our
pixel fill Loop, right?
We would go grab wherever we thought we were in the texture somewhere.
We would grab four pixels, right?
You know, ABCD, we would blend those together with a by linear filter
and we would come up with a source color.
That's how we would do that.
I guess I should draw it like this, we sample the texture, we by
linear filter, it, we come up with a source color, right?
We would then look in fact, I should probably draw this even better.
Let me in fact let me just do this.
Let me do this really much better.
Here we go.
So, we would sample.
From the texture.
Right?
That would produce for us.
This A B C D.
We would then pass that through the bi linear filter.
And the by linear filter again was looking at we're inside that for
Pixel box.
We were and it was blending proportional to that so it would produce a
source color.
So now we just have one color value.
We would then sample the destination.
Right.
So here's the screen, right?
This was the screen.
Whatever it was.
You'd say, where is that going?
And that would produce a desk color.
So we had the place on the screen, we were drawing too, we had the
place in the texture, we was Gruber grabbing from and we would add let
me call that Source we would add the source to the destination using a
blend, right?
And that blend was proportional to the alpha value.
Right, specifically, The Source alphabet value.
So, whatever was in here, right?
Because this Source had an alpha value, whatever was in here, would
guide us to how we would blend together if the alpha value was 255.
Then the source completely replace.
The destination itself value was 0 we did nothing.
The Source got thrown out and it was somewhere in between we would add
the source proportional to that versus the destination for channel.
1 - that right?
So we inversely blend it, right?
And furthermore in here, these are pre multiplied, right?
Not that that matters for this discussion.
But these are pre multiplied.
So we had some other things in here like gamma and pre multiplication,
but that was really only to deal with the color and Alpha channels.
It has nothing to do with the structure of this Loop, right?
So that's the old way we were doing things.
Now, the new way of doing things is almost exactly the same, it just
has an an additional step, right?
So we have a sample texture.
We have a sample texture step and it does produce four of these guys,
right.
And it does going to it is going to do the same stuff.
So it is going to do the bilinear, same exact thing, right?
But in addition to the sample of the texture that comes in, right?
We're also going to get somewhere.
And I, and I guess I should say there was an additional step.
I think, actually, in here that I didn't talk about right, there was a
color interpolation
Right, that came in here.
Right?
Because if you remember correctly, when we would specify our bitmap,
right?
We would specify a color for that bitmap and I don't really know if we
actually interpolated it to be honest.
Maybe we didn't interpolate it but there was a color that came in here
that was we could set when we were drawing the Sprite that would tint
it, right?
It would shade the color.
So we actually had an input.
That was constant, it doesn't come from the texture, it came from
outside, right?
Anyway, this is the part right here that gets replaced with something
more complicated.
So now in here, right, when we have our source color, right?
So we have our source after our texture sample in our by linear, we
have a new thing that comes in from the side.
Yes, we have color.
We would still have that coming in here but we also have Z stencil.
Alright, let's say depth stencil.
Okay.
And what are these two things?
Well, the depth value is wherever we drew this Sprite.
So let's say we were drawing the Sprite somewhere in the world, we've
got handmade hero and, you know, here's the trees or whatever and
we're drawing the Sprite here.
Well, when we specified, where the Sprite was, we specified a z value,
and that Z value might have been different at all of the pixels.
So if this thing is standing up straight in the world, it may be
higher as its top than its bottom.
So maybe the Z value is, you know,
Is, you know, 1.3 here or something.
And the Z value here is like 2.6 or something, right?
And so as you go up the Sprite depending on which row of the Sprite
you were on, it might get to be more, right?
So the middle of this thing here is going to be higher than 1.3 less
than 2.6.
The top is going to be two parts.
Exactly.
And so
Right?
So it will interpolate the Z across the surface of this Sprite and
that's important to remember we'll get back to why that's important is
second
Okay.
And then the stencil value is just going to be a constant thing that
we set, right?
So our stencil value is just something that in addition to setting the
Z, we're going to set the stencil and we're just going to set the
stencil once for the entire thing.
It's not going to be interpolated and we'll talk about what it even is
in a second, right?
Okay, so then when these pieces of information come here, color depth
and stencil we are essentially augmenting this by linear filtered
results.
So it's s Source, color Alpha value.
We now have a depth value.
I guess that's a bad thing to write it.
As I'll write it as Z for now we now have a depth value, right?
And I don't know what I'll write, stencil as let's write it as L.
Let's say.
Right.
We now have an augmented pixel that has in addition to what we sampled
from the texture.
We have now a z value that was wherever we are on the actual Sprite,
its actual Z value, right?
And a stencil value, that's something that was input from the exterior
routine, right?
And so that's very similar to the color in this sense that we just set
it.
It's just an arbitrary thing we set.
Now Z is an arbitrary thing, we said as well to be clear, but it's got
a real, it means something specific.
So even though we could set,
Something arbitrary.
We're not setting up something arbitrary.
We're setting it to something very specific about where it's located
in the world.
Whereas the stencil in the color value are very arbitrary and they
have to do with what we're trying to like, how are we trying to color
this particular Sprite or whatever, right.
And you'll see more about what the stencil value means a second.
Alright, so now that we have an augmented pixel, something that's got
additional information in it.
We now pass it through the real meat of the situation and let me just
say like this is this is the addition part here.
I'm not going to leave that in there cuz I write in what actually, is
this part of then comes exactly the same as well, right?
So at the end, we're going to do exactly the same thing, but it's this
part in here, the changes, okay, so once we have this, we are then
going to sample, the destination.
Just like we did before, right?
And the destination comes in.
Now, remember the destination has the z-buffer, right?
It has the depth buffer information and the stencil buffer information
because it is 64 bits big, right?
Our Sprites are not 64 bits big.
Our Sprites are getting augmented by that input value.
Those additional values that were input when we told it to draw the
Sprite where we told the to draw this, right?
Right.
So our source textures are still 30
B, big.
But our frame buffer remember is 64 bits.
So when we sample the destination, we get a desk color, right?
We get the dust Alpha that we don't care about.
We're not using it right now, but now we get a desk Z in a desk tell.
Right?
So now we have both a source, managed to put an S of of these, we have
a source Z and a source, stencil, and we have a desk Z and a desk
tensile as well.
Okay.
So here is where the big change happens.
Now, before doing this blend operation, what we do is a step and it's
often called kill for some reason.
Because basically it's saying terminate the pipeline early, I guess is
why it's called kill, but it's often called, like, Tech skill or stuff
like this.
Yeah.
It's, I have no idea why these things are called this, but the, the
more correct term for it, I think.
And the one that's used more in the open jails, but spec is pass.
Which sounds a little less threatening as well.
So what we do now is we do comparisons
Okay, we compare the source Z and the desk Z, we can pair the source,
stencil and the desk stencil.
And we produce an idea about whether this pixel operation that we're
about to do passes our criteria for actually occurring, right?
So we do a source Z versus desk Z comparison, right?
and we see whether it passes, we do a store Source, stencil versus
just sensible comparison and we see if it passes
And we can also, even if we would like to, we can do other pass
operations when we start together things, like, based on the alpha
values of things that there's, there's a lot with programmable
shaders, there's all sorts of things you can do here.
So, I'm just kind of talking about the more traditional ones now, but
programmable shaders.
Get into lala land really quickly and you can do all sorts of things
of them.
So, by no means don't take this as the complete set of things that you
can do.
I'm more talking about, just the basic pipeline, what a basic pipeline
does.
Okay.
And what's critical about this is these are actually user settable
Right?
So we can actually choose to say whatever operator we want in here
like greater than, you know, equal to not equal to less than or equal
to any comparison.
We want we can stick in here.
Okay.
So pretty obviously you can see if you just look at the Z part of
this.
Here is where we can get our per pixel sorting, right?
Because if we go back to the example, we originally started with where
I had an A, and A B and I want B to be in front of a right.
In this region, I want B to come first.
I want to see be, I don't want to see a right, well, the Z value for
all of a right wherever I'm drawing that, you know, maybe that's 1.3
or whatever, right?
And let's say Z is 2.6 or whatever something like this.
So in my world z comes close to the further towards the screen.
Let's say, so I want B to be in front.
Well at all of the pixels in here.
What's going to happen is a will have been drawn, right?
Because I'll
Come in here and I'll draw a, there's nothing in the z-buffer yet
because it's just a so whenever we load in whatever, we've cleared our
Z value know, maybe our Z value, when we cleared it with zero.
So everything in the frame buffer is 0.
We come in to draw a and we're drawing 1.3 everywhere, right?
So we just write one point.
Three is in because we're constantly comparing one point three and
zero and saying, oh you know, and in this world what I said, Z Z gets
bigger as we come closer to the screen.
So what I'd want to do is to say
If I want these things to pass, I want the source see to be bigger
than the destination Z, right?
So I'd use a greater than here.
It's what I'd set that to, right?
I want Source Z greater than Desta Z.
Let's say so it would come in here and say oh one point three is
bigger than 0.
Write it write it, write it, write it, write it, write it, write it.
And so our whole frame buffer at that point would have 1.3 s all
throughout here zeros everywhere else.
Then we come to draw B and in all these areas well it just loads a 0.
It says, well, 2.6 is bigger than zero in this area, right?
It loads of 1.3, but 2.6 is still bigger than 1.3.
So it will draw be first right.
Now, what's crucial about this is it doesn't matter what order we
render these 2, right?
Because if we were to draw be first, it would write 2.6 has all
through here and then when a rendered it would load the 2.6 has out of
here and go is 2.6 is 1.3, great enjoy sex know.
So don't draw the pixel, right?
So it's testing every pixel and now we don't care.
This is order independent.
Right.
So we get this really nice solution of just being able to dump
everything down to the GPU.
If we don't care and it will just do the test per pixel to figure out
whether or not something should be in front of something else and
you're done now, this provides a lot of additional power.
It means that we can not only do we not have to sort because we can
just throw things down order independently but we can also do stuff
like have two things that intersect.
So for example, if we were to look at two objects that
Lost through each other.
Like this, right?
Well, if we were to look at this from here, right?
We would expect to see something like this.
If this is a, this is B, right?
We would expect to see be all through here and a right in here, right?
Even though a might have existed back here because it's passing
through it, we want to not see it, and that'll work, just fine because
since the Z values are interpolated anywhere that a passes in front of
be a will draw first.
And everywhere that it passes behind B, it will draw a second.
Doesn't matter whether they pass directly through each other, so it's
Freights can just intersect and do everything else and you're still
fine, right?
So that's pretty nice.
Now.
I'm going to talk about the stencil value next.
But then I'm going to talk about some caveats here because it's not
all Rosy.
There are some issues that you have to be aware of and so I'll give
kind of a little bit of a just a brief explanation of those but here
is a additional part of the pipe, right?
We said there's a stencil value.
What does that do?
Well if you think about what happens here this is z value gives you a
nice way of having a single
Floating point value that you can use to determine how to sort things.
But back when SG, I was doing things because way back in the Silicon
Graphics are I believe that's where the stencil buffer came in.
I don't know if they invented it but they definitely had them on their
machines.
This was an additional thing that allowed you to do.
Sort of more, I guess, traditional blocking of things if you wanted
to.
So what a stencil is is a stencil is an 8-bit value.
Well, I mean, you know,
To be really anything.
But traditionally it was an 8-bit value.
This just looked at more as binary right?
And what you could do with it is you could say well okay maybe I want
to set a thing that says like if the stencil value is equal to some
value that I want it to be equal to then I'm going to draw and
otherwise I'm not going to draw, right?
And so what you could do is you could do essential, effectively raster
operations on to the frame buffer where you could do stuff like say,
oh okay, I'm going to
You know into here A Primitive that just sets the stencil value to
everywhere in there and then I'm going to set do a rather raster
operation that sets this value to 1 right now.
When I render I'm going to do something that well that's actually not
that useful because those are rectangles so you'd probably do it with
clipping.
Let me do that a little bit more crazily.
Maybe I set this value to 1.
And this value to 2, right?
And that's something you can't really do with a straightforward
viewport clip, right?
You could do it with a clipping plane, you know, what, I'll go even
crazier, just to make it unlikely to be
You're the cutting plane.
You do this?
It's a circle a narc.
So, there's the one.
There's the two.
So I can't really set up.
Any clipping planes or anything like that to do it.
It's an arc.
It's harder to do, right?
Nowadays, hilariously and shaders.
You could still do that by using.
Serene space evaluation of a circle to figure it out but it's don't
just forget it.
Don't even go there let's not go.
There point being in the Primitive days back in an STI, you could not
have done that.
So you know, stencil buffers are less likely to use these days because
there's so many other options.
But in those days I'm just trying to give you the perspective back
from when these things first sort of happened so you could you could
do operations on the stencil buffer to set on the part of the buffer
that stores, the stencil value to set things like this.
And then you could
Up basically binary equivalent say hey you know what, what I'm drawing
here, I only want to draw two places where the sense of I equals 1 and
then I'm going to do another pass where I draw two things that are
essentially equals two to sort of create blocks of my scene, right?
So I can create like, you, I places or picture-in-picture sorts of
things that can be have fancy outlines.
They don't have to be like rigidly clip to a rectangle, right?
And so typically in the old days this road on the same, 32 bits as the
Z buffer and the hardware to do it was kind of enabled by default if
z-buffering was on.
So typically, when you talked about a z-buffer pipeline, you typically
got stencil sort of for free and it was just this extra little
technique.
You had that.
In addition to a z value, which was this 1624 bit value.
Depending on the case, you may be also got this 8-bit, stencil value
to play with as an additional bonus right now.
Isn't always the case.
You might have had only a 16-bit z buffer and no stencil it depended
on again, the hardware in the situation.
But if you some perspective there that this was this extra thing,
right, and you can see why those two went together because they're
basically the same sort of thing.
They're just this little comparison of the source and the destination
that just produces a bit.
Basically, this says, do I want to actually draw here or do I want to
fail and just stop drawing this pixel all together, right?
And so that's all that was.
So that's how a z-buffer pipeline works and you can see how it gets
rid of the whole problem of having to do sorting, like we did in the
old pipeline because now the Sorting is done per pixel and so it just
works, it's nice.
You can shove as many things you want into it and they'll always get
sorted correctly because every pixel gets sorted on its own.
Okay, let's talk about the caveat.
You know how people say caveat emptor?
I don't know what that means.
I've never looked it up.
I'm going to say like caveat Emperor because that sounds cooler.
Like maybe the emperor.
Needs to be aware of this situation because he wasn't thinking about
it anyway.
So there is one nasty problem that comes along with this.
And for handmade hero.
I don't think it'll be that nasty because of our situation, but
if you are the sort of Saucy, gentleman that that writes these sort of
Really Advanced 3D pipelines, like, you know, the crytek engine, the
Doom engine, these sorts of things that are, you know, super, super
Advanced kinds of stuff you have to care about this sort of thing and
it can be a big concern and you've got your ways that you work around
it, right?
And so I just want to kind of talk about those a little bit on
handmade hero.
I think we'll probably have a lot easier time because we don't have
the kind of scene complexity, that's something like Doom has, right?
So anyway, there's a problem that happens here.
And that problem is with the blending,
And basically, the problem is that blending is not order independent,
okay?
So what I was just saying about the z-buffer, what's really, really
nice about the Z buffer, is it basically allows your 3D pipeline to
not care about sorting.
So now you can render your Primitives in any order that you want,
right?
So I can just stack things all over the place, render them in any
order.
And if I've got things that are looking like this, right?
It doesn't matter what.
I send these things down.
If this is a, you know, B, C, D, or whatever, it doesn't matter if I
draw it be CDA or ABCD, your CD a b or B DCA, none of those matter
because it will always sort correctly because it's using the actual Z
coordinate of the actual thing relative to the camera to figure out
how to sort this stuff, right.
And when we get further, I should also just sort of preface this by
saying I'm not talking right now, very much about what that Z value
actually is.
In this buffer, what that depth value is it actually is a little more
complicated because you can choose what it actually is.
There's a lot of different ways you can choose to have it be evaluated
and so we'll get to that more when we get down to the actual
nitty-gritty but just there's some depth value in there that we can
count on and the Sorting just works, right?
So this allows us to be completely order independent.
The problem is that blending right?
That operation we had always been doing where we did one.
Sorry where we did Source Alpha times Source plus 1 minus source.
Alpha.
Times dest, right?
You remember this?
This is the linear blend.
It's the thing.
That's the backbone of like all game everything, right?
And this is how we were blending our colors into the display, right?
Well, what you can see about this is it's not order independent,
right?
It's talking about these Alpha values.
This destination is some previous set of Blends that have happened and
Sa 1 minus sa right?
It's in fact.
This one - sa right here.
The number of times that something gets multiplied by that 1 minus sa
changes based on the order, right?
So if I do things, in one order versus another,
I may end up with a very different result than if I do them in in a
different way, right?
This gets exacerbated, once the Z, buffer is involved for another
reason, which is that values may actually get killed entirely.
So let me give you a just, a very simple example of how this becomes a
problem and you can sort of hopefully see what I mean.
When I say there's there's a nasty issue here, right?
So, let's say I've got something.
In the world that's supposed to be translucent or transparent.
Right.
Let's say it's a bubble.
So here is handmade hero, right?
And here is a little bubble that handmade hero blue, right?
So if he's blowing bubbles, here it is.
In our current handmade hero, this is really just not a problem.
These things will sort if this is a and this is B, these things will
sort to the be gets drawn first and egg gets drawn after, that's
exactly what we want.
Because the hero is drawn here, right?
And then this transparent bubble, gets drawn on top.
What that means is that all of those values for the hero are already
in the frame buffer, so that when the bubble is drawn, it can pick
them up blend with them and write them back.
So it will nicely.
Shade the hero with the bubbles color which is exactly what we want.
What will happen in a z-buffer situation.
Well, first of all, we can no longer just throw everything into the
same batch and expect
Work.
Why can't we do that?
Well, the reason that we can't do that is because this bubble, if it
happened to get drawn first would completely erase the hero because
when the bubble gets drawn, it will draw into the z-buffer.
Its its values.
And when it draws its values into the z-buffer, right?
Nothing else will be able to draw there.
Now, if the bubble happens to get drawn second, then it's okay because
when the bubble is getting drawn, it will pick up the Z values of the
hero.
And that it will say I'm closer than
Zero and so I should draw on top and then it'll work but you can see
that that order dependence.
Now comes back, right?
We had gotten rid of it for opaque things but now it comes back for
transparent things.
So the only real solution that we have here in the trivial sense of
the word, if all we have is a z-buffer is we still we get back to sort
of course sorting
Which is that all of our transparent objects.
Have to go into one bin and all of our non transparent objects can go
into the other bin.
And then we draw all the non transparent objects.
First, we draw the transparent object s, right?
You can see how that would then fix this problem of the bubble
erasing, the hero entirely, right?
But even that isn't a complete solution.
What if we have two bubbles that overlap Each Other?
Well, if one bubble is closer than the other bubble, it will produce a
different result than if it was further away because again, the
shading is not order independent, this is not an order independent
equation.
If I apply this,
Equation, you know, hero bubble one, bubble to.
I will get a, you know, a different result than if I do hero bubble to
bubble one.
So, again, the Sorting actually has to occur again.
If we want order independent transparency to actually work, it has to
be sorted, right?
And I should say, are definite.
Transparency.
Always is order dependent.
So we have to sort it in order to make it work.
And this is just a real bummer.
Now, there are ways around this that are non intuitive and there are
also ways around it that are completely psychotic and you will never
believe that they actually work, but there are ways of doing them.
So let me talk about those.
So one way around this, that's kind of counterintuitive is to change
this equation to be order independent.
Right.
And there actually are proposals for doing this.
And you can look and see.
There are papers that talk about.
Hey, this is a question that depends on the order that I apply it.
What if I picked an equation that didn't depend on the order in, which
I apply it?
Could I then have this work and one way that you can you can imagine
doing that.
That is not nuts, is to just talk about additive blending, right?
One way to do this is get rid of this term.
If I just do sasc.
Oops.
If that's all I do.
Then I have no problem.
That's just those are just things that make the screen brighter when I
operate on it, right?
And so, one of the things that used to be very common is particles
that always made things brighter like brightening particles, right?
And, you know, these kind of Blobby explosion e sorts of particles.
I just make things brighter that just works because then it doesn't
matter what order you do this.
If you think about what happens here, it just becomes a big long, some
of these values, right?
It just, you just keep summing them up and it doesn't matter.
So your result for a pixel is just sasc + sa SC + sasc.
From from different Sprites, right?
So it's just that, that darkening, that dimming of, or that lessening
of the contribution of the underneath color, is the only thing that
makes it order dependent in the first place.
So you can choose to use some kind of equation that doesn't have that
property.
But the problem is that limits, the kind of composition you can do,
because you no longer have the option of doing something like that.
Now, that is not the only one, there was another one.
I remember there is a paper that proposed ways of doing
And see that doesn't have the brightening effect all the time.
That is also order independent.
I don't remember what it was though, but there was a paper that talked
about that.
So there again, there are options there of saying, well, okay, if we
want to go back to just doing the transparent versus non transparent
objects, all we do is sort those and then we run it and we let them do
their thing.
We could pick a different way of retiring that equation.
Right?
But there is another option and this is the pure lunacy option.
And oddly enough, you can actually do this on gpus.
That's how far gpus have gotten.
It's kind of crazy when you think about it.
All right.
So what's gpus have introduced?
Believe it or not is atomics?
so,
and maybe I'll call this, you know.
Frame buffer, atomics.
And I'll try to give you some perspective on what these are.
It's completely nuts that you can do this, but it's one of those
things where it's like gpus have gotten so powerful.
This point, they're just adding really all kinds of things that you
wouldn't expect, you know, someone in my position who, you know, saw
the first 3D effects card and was like, wow, that's really amazing to
think about the fact that these have atomics frame, buffer operations
is completely nuts, but it's awesome.
And so here's where we go down the rabbit hole of like the kinds of
crazy stuff you can do on
Is nowadays.
So if you imagine what happens, what I was talking about there.
Well,
Really, the reason that we have that problem again is because we're
not sorting, right?
I mean the problem is that we're not sorting anymore.
Why didn't we want to sort?
Well, there was a lot of overhead to sorting, and also we kind of need
to sort things based on the pixel value.
Because, you know, if we want again, that case to work, where two
things intersect, right?
Or we have those kind of nasty problems, like the painters algorithm
nightmare problem, where you've got, you know, triangles that do this
sort of thing.
I'm not going to draw this right, am I?
That's, that's a terrible drawing.
Don't know if I can.
How do I do a racer?
There we go.
I did it.
All right, so if you have one of these situations where you've got
three, triangles that actually aren't intersecting, but they all
overlap each other.
You end up with a cycle that can only be broken by actually splitting
the triangles, right?
And again, a z-buffer, totally solves this problem because since its
operates for Pixel it has, it doesn't even care.
It just it just works, right?
You'll get exactly the right result.
So, we want all of these things, but now we want the ability also, for
all of our transparent stuff to work, right?
And it's just like, how we going to do that.
Well, what they end up doing is they do per pixel sorting.
And I'm not even making this up, this is actually a real thing.
So what they will do is they'll say all right.
What do we need to do to do per pixel sorting?
Well, what if I was just to record a fragment color or a pixel color,
I won't use the word fragment.
Yeah, we'll talk a lot more.
What fragments are later?
But what if I was at each pixel location, right?
Here's a pixel location.
Instead of, you know, right now I'm doing rgba Z, and maybe stencil or
something, right?
What if I said?
Nah, forget that instead of just storing one of those per pixel, I'm
actually going to store a linked list.
So in this pixel, I'm going to store a pointer to one of these rgba
Z's and then a pointer to the next one.
And I'm not even making this up.
It's a linked list.
Of this stuff.
Where every time I write to the pixel, I add a new link to the chain,
right?
So if I overdraw this thing eight times, if there's eight things
overlapping, this pixel.
I'll actually have eight links in the chain.
Right?
Then I write a Shader that does a resolution of that buffer, right?
That resolves.
That buffer.
That all it does is after all the rendering is done and every pixel is
a linked list of values, it then goes through, and sorts the linked
list at every pixel and then retires, the fragments those pixel values
in order.
So that you still get correct order dependent.
I'm doing even though you've rendered things potentially completely
out of order.
I'm not kidding, this actually works.
You can actually do it.
Now obviously there's a huge cost to it because you're taking up a lot
more memory because you have to store, you know.
However your much overdraw you have on average, you have to store that
much more data in there, right?
That's very expensive.
So it's by no means some kind of Panacea.
That's just free to do, is still, very expensive, but you can do it.
So, if you actually want that, you can get it.
And obviously there's optimizations around.
This one thing that you'll often see if you were going to approach
scheme.
Like this is, well, you really only need the link list for the for
transparent things.
The opaque things can also, you can still do that bifurcation, where
you draw like all the opaque things first so that you just have
One value in a buffer that's like, here's my screen.
If there were no transparent objects then you just draw the
transparent objects into one of these things with the linked list.
Then you can just at the end know that you never, you never created
extra links for opaque things because you never need to know opaque
things past a certain point, right?
Because you only some explaining, this very well.
If I have some stack of stuff.
Let's, let's look at this.
A single Pixel, let's stack it up.
Like, it was like we were looking at it from, you know, this
direction, right?
And there's just a fantastic amount of things stacked on this pixel,
right?
So this is just one pixel we're looking at and we're looking at it
this way.
So these are all stacked on top of each other, right?
ABCDEFG, all stacked on top of each other, right?
Well if you imagine, let's say that A and B are
Right, let's say that c and e.
Are opaque.
In fact, let me figure out a better way to label these.
So let's say it's transparent transparent opaque transparent opaque
opaque transparent.
Right?
If I just did the naive thing, I would end up with a linked list that
was one, two, three, four, five.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
I would have seven links in my linked list, right?
And that's a huge not have to do all that updating and all that work,
right?
But if I were to instead do something a little bit more clever and say
let's draw all the opaque stuff first, right?
So that means I draw a c e and f.
I draw them first.
So what I would end up with in that buffer is just F it's all I would
have right.
Then I go to draw my transparent objects, I can use the Z buffer and
say only add to the linked list if
My z-buffer passes.
That means only the stuff in front of f, will pass, which is only one
thing.
It's just G, it's just this one thing.
So I end up with only a linked list of f and g that has to be sorted
and further more like I was saying, I really don't have to sort this
part so really I can just have a buffer of things that are the opaque
backdrop of the scene, that's everything up to the point where the
opaque objects stopped.
It and then linked list of transparent things in front of them.
And again that's free for me to produce Beyond just one level of
partitioning.
It's not even really sorting, it's just a partition of transparent
objects and opaque objects and the opaque objects First Responders.
It's just a property of their material so I don't even really have to
look at anything.
They don't have to form graphs or anything.
I can just purely partition it.
Every time I go to render an object, it is this an object that has
transparency
You're not based on its material settings, or whatever, and it just
goes into one buffer, the other, right?
So you can see how this could be made Fairly efficient, as long as you
know, you don't have too many transparent things in the scene.
Now again, particles, make this harder because particles are often
times want to be transparent.
And there's lots of them so you typically have to think harder about
how you're doing stuff like that and there's lots of ways you can work
with these things when you go down the rabbit hole of modern 3D
rendering, it's like all these crazy hacks and ways of doing stuff to
get what you want to have happen.
It's not clean like Ray tracing where the rendering is very
straightforward but the spatial partitioning is where the hacking
comes in and the sampling and all that stuff, right?
So you know it's different rasterization has a different set of facts,
right?
So anyway so that's how that works.
We're almost out of time but I think I've covered almost everything.
The only thing I wanted to mention is that overdraw still matters
And so this is the one other caveat, which is that just because you
have a z-buffer, it's like yes.
The Z buffer does solve your sorting problems for you in a lot of ways
now transparency and translucency, it does not.
So you still have to come up with other solutions to fix that.
You're not out of the Sorting woods.
Yet when you have a lot when you have to a lot of that in the game,
however, you're dealing with it.
Right?
So that's the matter is, it's important to understand but it does
solve all the other sorting problems for you and it
Allows things to nest in 3D, really cleanly.
Because since it's interpolated per pixel, not per object, it ends up
with a lot of sorting things that would have caused problems when you
have to do them logistically by bounding boxes are no longer problems
because now instead of primitive it's per pixel and it can resolve
things very cleanly like those painter.
Algorithm Cycles are not a problem anymore.
Even intersection not a problem anymore.
You can still handle that cleanly per pixel, right?
But overdraw still does matter.
And let's just say what that actually means.
So what overdraw means is obviously like gpus are fast.
But not.
You know, infinitely.
Fast.
And so, yes, a GPU does allow you to overdraw the screen many times
and, and certainly much more powerful than the CPU in terms of filling
pixels because it's all a GPU is designed to do.
It's just a giant pixel filling machine.
So obviously it's really good at that, and you can take advantage of
that and be a bit sloppy in order to get better rendering stuff out of
it.
So that you don't have to think about all the sorting and that sort of
thing.
And sloppy is the wrong term.
Because you're still, you're going towards the strength of what you
have, which is not really sloppy, but I just mean you be more loose,
you don't have to do all the sorting and
That but it still matters how much you overdraw because the GPU can't
overdraw the screen, an infinite number of times.
So the speed with which you can draw to the screen is still important
and one of the things that's really affects, this is not just how many
times a pixel is filled, but it's how much work you have to do every
time that you fill one.
And what that means is let's say this is very important when you get
into shaders.
Now, a Shader as you probably know.
Is basically a piece of code that can be executed on the GPU, for
example, per pixel.
So on every pixel you could execute this Shader, that can be a
relatively expensive complicated set of mathematical operations that
can do calculations for what that pixel should look like.
And these can Encompass, a lot of very complicated things.
This can Encompass things, such as like, complicated, lighting
equations, that sample, multiple light sources that you shadowing
information that do transforms to
You're out.
What kind of reflectance is happening at this pixel.
There's lots and lots of things that can happen and you can end up
with shaders.
That can be very expensive.
They're doing lots of operational, GPU using lots of floating-point,
computations, that can be very, very slow.
What that means is the more complicated you make these shaders.
The more expensive, it can be to overdraw the screen because, you
know, yes, if all you're doing is taking a constant rgba value, from a
texture, like all your sampling one texture, right?
And
Get to the screen, you may be able to overdraw the screen.
Just put Splat Sprite, some type of Sprites on top of Sprites.
Facebook ad infinitum and maybe it is basically infinitely fast
because oh my God, gpus are so powerful per pixel, it doesn't matter,
you're fine, right.
But if all of a sudden, instead of sampling from one texture, your
sampling from 16, textures at a time, you're doing like, you know,
thousands of math, Ops or something to compute.
All kinds of complicated shading and combining the results from all
these textures and surface lighting.
And
tons of Shadow maps from tons of lights, and all this sort of thing,
right?
Now this cheaters very expensive.
And if you're trying to overdraw a pixel with that kind of expensive
Shader, 20 30, 50, 100 times.
All of a sudden your games performance, consider a crawl because even
though the GPU has tons of flops at his disposal, it's not infinite.
It can't just do an infinite number of math operations.
So even though you have a z-buffer and overdraw as a graphical,
artifact is no longer a problem and the Sorting doesn't matter, you
can just draw as many things as you want.
And they will sort properly.
You still have to understand that, filling in actual pixel is costly
what that means is that there are still ways in which you must
structure your pipeline, if you are going for high performance,
complicated shaders and stuff like that.
You may have to make certain concessions in your pipeline designed to
mitigate this problem.
And so one example of a way that this often works is what's called a z
prepass
and what this is, is, hey,
I know that I'm going to be using some really complicated shaders that
are very expensive so I really don't want to worry about that
situation that I just described where I've got like all these things
stacked up.
Like here's all these pixels stocked up on top of each other.
There's six pixels worth of overdraw there, right?
6 / shouldn't say 6 pixels.
Let's just say 6X overdraw.
I'm going to overdraw this pixel six times, but I've only got enough
GPU horsepower to execute my Shader like two times, right?
It's like so, what am I going to do?
You know, do I start to try and calm?
I seen more aggressively the, you know, what do I do?
And the answer is well for opaque stuff.
Actually, you have another option at your disposal.
What you can do is draw the scene at six x overdraw, just like you
were doing, but with no Shader brush,
Sickly, right?
Get rid of the Shader, turn it off.
Instead of filling the color values of the buffer at all, just right
to the z-buffer, right?
And this is called a z prepass.
So what it does is it fills the that Z value buffer with whatever the
latest buffer value actually was right.
So even though there are six different things that all overlapped,
this pixel, I only end up with the Z value of the final one and it was
pretty cheap for me to do.
Because no complicated Shader was getting run.
There were, you know, 10 math Ops in my simple z-pass Shader, not
1,000 math Ops in my super complicated, Mega lighting Ridiculousness
Trader.
Right now, once I have done my zp past and I have that final z-value,
I do the actual color pass, right?
Where I do execute the Thousand math op Shader.
But what I
Do is I predicate that on Z of being equal.
To Z right on my source C being equal to my desk Z.
So I say remember back here at our where we can I get the come?
How where are we?
Where I drew it up here somewhere.
Okay, here it is.
Right.
Remember because we've got this this sort of theoretical pipeline
happening.
I've got these past comparisons and I'm going to say the source Z has
to be equal to the destination see of this buffer in order for this
pixel to pass.
Right?
What that means is, I will never draw a pixel.
If it's not the final one that we would have seen.
So all those other pixels don't have to be drawn and what's really
great about modern gpus is they're smart enough to early out.
So even though this comparison conceptually happens at the end of the
pipeline, right, in some sense they actually do it up here.
So what they will do is at the earliest possible
possible time and of course, depending on how you write your Shader
shaders can modify the Z value and stuff like this.
So the earliest possible time may not be right at the beginning, but
either way at the earliest possible time they can
They will determine whether or not this pixel will be drawn and if it
cannot be drawn, they will not bother doing all of these operations.
Right.
So that's really, really cool because it means that you can save a lot
of computation.
Now it's not quite as rosy as I make it sound.
And the reason for that is because these things are wide as we've
talked about before gpus work, the same way as our CPU renderer.
Worked.
And if you remember, we fill multiple pixels at a time.
We filled.
I think for pixels across, at a time we filled this at a time gpus
typically will do more.
Like, you know, this at a time.
Right.
So gpus will kind of fill more like a 4 by 4 block or something like
that at the time.
Depending on the architecture.
I don't keep up with this sort of thing so I don't really know how
many pixels they feel at a time at the moment but they fill a bigger
swath of pixels at a time to the CPU but basically it's the same thing
and if you remember how that works is what happens is the entire
pipeline gets run for all 16 pixels at a time and you can only early
out if all 16 pixels are not going to pass that Z.
So what that means is you do end up with some ways.
it's there because if you did have some of these pixels pass you're
going to but a bunch of them wouldn't
Have you're still going to blow all of those thousand math apps
Computing, the entire four by four even though you only needed a
little bit of it.
So to a certain extent it's not as perfect as it would be.
If every pixel only ran in terms of flops, you're actually talking
about it on a slightly coarser level, but hopefully things are not
going in and out quite so closely for Pixel anyway.
Like presumably your triangles or at least as big
big as a few of these.
So, you know, typically a triangle is going to at least take up some
of that space, let's say, especially when you start getting to higher
resolutions.
So you know, a z, prepass is definitely really great and it can
eliminate certainly all of this crazy far back stuff, but when you
start to get to the edges of things, it's not quite as, you know, as
perfect as you would expect if you were thinking of it as a per pixel
basis, so overdressed still matters.
And when you're looking at higher end, graphics performance,
Need to think about it and have a pipeline that acknowledges the fact
that it is not free to compute pixels.
So if the pixel color values, your Computing are never shown on the
screen, you want to take steps to mitigate that.
Even if you are still requiring, the z-buffer to do, most of that
coloring for you, you still sort of need to be aware of that.
So I'll go ahead and take questions.
We'll probably obviously, we don't have any time for
To do any code today because we had just a lot of stuff to cover.
Their didn't know how long I would take to fill that, but there's a
lot of stuff in there.
So we'll take a look at actually doing some coding tomorrow.
Ask if anyone has any questions let me let me just go ahead and
take a look.
Disused asks, is it possible to use differing and possibly post
processing and super resolution for order independent transparency.
Yes, it is one.
You know, one way that you used to do transparency in the old days
order, an event transparency to a certain extent was to do screen
door.
What's called the screen door effect?
And what that is is again you just you basically say well okay you
know one way to do it is to think of a pixel as the
Circular color value.
And I'm just going to try to write to the pixel and do the alpha
blending per pixel.
Another way to look at it is let's look at more than one pixel at a
time.
So maybe I'm looking at more of a grid of pixels and what I'll do is
if a thing is transparent, I'll fill in just maybe like every other
pixel or something like this, you know, in some kind of pattern and
then I'll hope that when I have other transparent things, they don't
quite line up.
Exactly.
And so I'll fill them in a different order and then those things.
If I downsample that buffer would blend together and produce sort of a
transparent effect, right?
And that is certainly one way of
Going to approach it and that actually becomes also, again more
feasible because modern gpus have something called multi sample
buffers, which are buffers that have per pixel more than one sample
and their jittered, and you can do some things with that.
If you want to try to, I don't know that high-end people do that.
I think they try to do more, the linked list and chunked rendering
sorts of approaches, but that's not really my area of expertise.
So I don't feel comfortable saying one way or the other, whether
that's a technique that people use nowadays in,
Actual high-end work or not.
You would have to ask more dedicated rendering sort of person.
How prevalent a technique like that tends to be these days?
But it definitely, it's definitely.
I guess all I'm trying to say is, it's definitely plausible.
It was used in the past, I just don't know if it's really relevant
today.
That's, that's all I'm trying to say was enabled per pixel sorting on
the graphics card.
What if any software control is available via shaders?
Or is it just a hardware optimization?
That some graphics cards do behind the scenes to handle the opacity
issue without pre-filter z-buffer?
Actually it's entirely in shaders, so it's entirely up to you that
implementation.
Shouldn't of the linked list thing is actually entirely up to you.
The
I guess I was kind of going kind of fast and I sort of skipped this
part.
I didn't say why this was important.
I just said that it was there the point of the atomics.
Now, you know what atomics are?
If you've been watching handmade here, atomics our way of multiple
CPU, cores or multiple CPUs to synchronize their access to memory in a
way that they don't accidentally overwrite each other.
And this is very important for multi-threaded programming because at
the place where those threads have to communicate, you need a way of
synchronizing them and atomics.
The only way to do that because otherwise, the two cores would just
write on each other's memory and have no idea.
They would not be able to sync up in any real waste.
You need some way at least one way of being able to cleanly Signal a
right to a memory that you know, will not get overwritten by somebody
else, sort of in-flight, right?
And so, for a long time, GPU is never had anything like that.
That was accessible to you if they obviously had to deal with this
internal themselves because they are heavily multi-threaded
internally.
But then they started exposing these.
The shaders I believe amd's, the people are first introduced it
several years ago, Atomic rights, the frame buffer.
And what these are is they're just like the things you can do on the
CPU, like Atomic increment or something like this for Atomic Swap.
And what they allow you to do.
I started on Exchange, I should say.
And what they allow you to do is when you are doing a right to a frame
buffer, you can actually do that right atomically.
So you can have two people looking at the frame buffer going.
I want to put a I shouldn't say frame buffer either.
Just the destination.
Whatever the thing is that you're writing to, I want to people to be
able to access the same time.
I want them to be able to
We swap a linked list value in and know that nobody else did that same
swap the same time, right?
And so that allows you to in the Shader build the linked list and then
later you can write a Shader that synchronous.
So it's not multi-threaded because hey, it's doing it for every pixel.
So I mean it is multi-threaded, the sense that every thread could be
operating different pixels but there aren't multiple threads trying to
talk to the same.
Talk about the same pixel.
That one can just be a Shader.
That literally walks a linked list and these are you write these and
shaders?
That's how advanced shade.
Those are these days.
Shaders are incredibly incredibly.
Complicated and Powerful.
They can do almost everything that you can do in regular C code.
Really you can do that in the Shader, they're very general purpose.
They have different performance characteristics but they're very
general purpose.
That's why you have.
I mean you know their stuff that will compile C code to run in and
shaders, right?
Compute shaders and so if you're if you're talking about not shaders
that are in the actual Graphics pipeline you literally can write just
C code and have it work.
That's what these opencl and Cuda and stuff.
Basically, our is their ways of writing, just general purpose code,
with atomics and everything.
That just run on the GPU.
So they're very, very flexible nowadays.
It's just the like
it's just the difference.
There is just that the performance characteristics are different
between the two, so you have to be aware of that when you're writing
the code.
Anonymous.
519 what do you think of frame buffering like Vulcans Mill box?
Present mode to decouple the game update rate from the Display
Devices.
Refresh rate, you can render as many frames as you want, but only the
most recently rendered frame is swapped in on vertical, retrace.
I mean, I guess what I would say about that is
I mean first of all I would say my opinion is is skewed, something
like that and I think it's because I have very specific priorities for
how I.
What I feel like is important that do not necessarily aligned with
high-end rendering people's priorities or Gamers priorities
necessarily right for end and how I would describe my Outlook it is I
think
In rate is critical.
I think it drastically affects the way again, feels.
And I do not find variable frame rate as an acceptable way of
displaying graphics.
That is my opinion and it is not necessarily relevant to a certain
segment of the gaming population or the developer population.
Perhaps not even the majority of it, right.
They may much prefer variable frame rates.
So in my mind, I would much rather that a game ran at a fixed frame
rate.
Whatever the appropriate fixed frame rate was with less graphical
quality.
Then one that pushed the graphical quality limit right to the edge.
And didn't quite always make 30 frames a second.
So it's swapped it like, you know, sometimes 40 frames per second,
sometimes, 27 frames a second, you know, that sort of thing.
So I feel like a 100% consistent frame rate is absolutely critical and
the most important thing that you can do.
And so I don't care about things like mailbox mode because that is
totally not, if your, or if you're in a situation where you can't be
synced to the refresh rate, so, that you always have a frame ready
when, when the next predicted frame refresh happens.
I've already lost the battle and I consider it a failure, right?
So because of that, that's not a kind of mode that I'm interested in,
but you can understand why, that mode might be very important to some
people who have different priorities.
If your priority is very high graphics quality and you don't want to
make concessions to maintain a fixed frame rate, right?
Then you can understand why something like, mailbox mode would be very
important.
Right?
Because it allows you to get that trade-off much more narrowly, right?
It allows you to really Target 100 percent of the GPU power every
frame.
You don't have to leave any slap there, because if you're a little bit
over a little bit under any time, it doesn't matter because the frame
rates for swapping will be much closer to accurate.
So, you can understand the value of something like that.
It's just not a value.
I want.
And the in.
So yeah.
And so it's up to every developer.
To have their own opinion about that.
And for devs, that are about that maximization.
Those are the kinds of modes that that really make a lot of sense,
right?
And by the way, I should add that, that attitude that I'm talking
about, that's my preference pervades, like, everything in the
pipeline.
So that means, like, for example, I would never make a pipeline that
was designed to accelerate something like, oh, I'm inside a room.
So I'm going to call the stuff on the other side of this wall because
I know that I can't see through it because I know that as soon as I
step away and look at a mirror at a window where I can see outside
that.
Frame rate would just tank if I was relying on that culling to
eliminate the stuff on the other side, right?
So I always tend to think about pipelines as I want them to always do
and exactly predictable amount of work all the time which is a very
different way of looking at a pipeline van.
I want to maximize the graphical quality of any given scene that I'm
in those are really different attitudes and they they they pervade.
Everything that you do.
And I don't think that either one is right or wrong, you know, it's
just about what you value.
And I really value that consistency.
Like, I want to work towards the most consistent graphical
presentation that I can get.
but that is not going to be the right decision for everyone and so
other people will want to push the most amount of GPU power every
frame and we'll make different trade-offs potentially
Is it valid to render to sub buffers and then render those sub buffers
to the back buffer.
So as to be able to render more than one sub buffer at a time,
I don't necessarily know what you mean by the question, but I guess I
would just say if I understand it correctly, then not only is the
answer.
Yes, but that is exactly what we're doing in handmade here right now
and so and in the 3D path as well.
So obviously there's no reason that you can't also do that in 3D if
you wanted to, if you need multiple passes.
Which a lot of times you might want to do for a number of reasons.
it's an eminently, valid technique and I guess I, yeah, I would just
say definitely yes, but but we're already doing that in handmade hero
even in the 2D path, that's how we do the floor, the alpha fade of
the, of the
Level floor is done in that exact fashion and so if you, if you go
look at how that's working, that would work exactly the same as if
everything was rendered.
3D z-buffer, a, you just have to Z in addition to two color buffers
you would have to Z buffers as well.
And that's
Yeah.
So yes.
And so the risk.
Oh, do not be afraid to ask questions.
Handmade here is a complex project at this point and so it's easy to
not really know what's happening in some parts of it.
but yes, if again, if that was the question, just wanted to make sure
Then yes we were.
We're already doing that and moving the 3D does not change that
calculus at all.
It's just that we may not have.
We may not have to do as much of that right now.
I think we render every floor potentially into a different buffer.
I can't remember whether we bother doing that or not we might not in
fact.
Yeah, we probably don't because the only thing we really need is one
extra buffer for the
Faded floor on top.
So we probably don't really make much use of it now I think about it
so probably yeah we would probably have a similar situation in 3D
where we might have two different buffers and one of the buffers is is
for exactly that purpose, right?
It's still exactly the same purpose, but we might not have to do it
because we could use a z-buffer for this in the future potentially in
a to pass scenario and other sorts of things.
So it may be possible for us to do it without a sub buffer.
Now that we've got a z-buffer
But we may still want to do it to to a subwoofer for other reasons.
That we don't know yet.
So I would expect that we would you know, I would expect to to have
To have at least one extra buffer in the 3D pass as well for even if
it's just for, like, lighting or who knows what it may not be for the
alpha, but but we'll probably have still.
We will still use the multiple render Target stuff, if that makes
sense.
All right, I'm going to wrap up here.
See here.
There we go.
Let me click double check.
Let's see, do you feel you're still on the path to finishing the game
in six hundred episodes?
I have no idea.
But again, six hundred episodes is just
Purely arbitrary ballpark to State the obvious.
I this is the first time I've ever done a programming where I've tried
to do the teaching.
At the same time on the stream is the programming.
So I have absolutely no idea even when I started how long it would
take because you know a lot of what we do.
Like today's episode, there's no coding.
We just me explaining stuff so that people would understand what we're
going to do.
And so I have no idea how to gauge that sort of thing.
So 600 was just a
Ballpark of like a this is how long it may be would take.
I would say it hasn't actually been that unlikely like it looks like
that may be roughly true.
It's really hard to say.
It's a little different now because we just recently switched to, to
our streams, on the weekends, twice a weekend and so previously, 350
of those were an hour apiece and now the next 250 up to
It will be two hours apiece, that's more time to write.
So I don't know we've done most of the engine work.
We're still refining.
Some things we want to do a little bit of 3D work here before we move
forward, but we're still going to have about 400 hours of gameplay,
programming, we can do and that's a lot.
I'm not a game designer.
So you know the amount of gameplay program we're going to do.
I don't know how much we really need to do.
I don't have that much to say there.
I'm just going to show how
Do like architectural stuff and how to program game code cleanly.
And, you know, try to get that points at those points across, but I'm
not a game designer.
So I don't have, I don't have to spend a lot of time, explaining game
design because I don't know it.
I'm not going, I don't have anything to say about game design.
If you want to learn game designer, you have to go talk to somebody
else, right?
I'm just talking about how to program the game, assuming that you have
a design that, you know, that you like and that you think you can
design again competently and, you know, so you gotta go listen to
John, Blow or somebody who knows how to design.
in a game, you know, if you want to design a game,
And so I think that's the important part to say there and so I yeah,
six hundred episodes maybe about, right.
It's only time will tell, you know, like I said, I have no way of
predicting it at all because it's a totally new experience for me.
It's not how I normally program.
I'm not usually talking the whole time, honestly, so I have nothing to
go by.
So yeah.
Do you find the weekends?
Go by faster with streaming on them and you have you do you have more
time for 935?
Yes.
I find that it was very good to move them to the weekends.
It's better for work on I-235 for sure and it keeps my schedule a
little cleaner.
So it's been it's been a big plus
Let's see an obvious.
What if I don't my game to be deterministic or what if my game does
physics calculations?
I need to update at a fixed rate for stability, different people, have
different
Monitors are different, refresh rates.
Most people seem to the to then interpolate, but this adds latency
isn't male boxing.
The better approach in this situation.
Well, again, like I was trying to say before I believe that I always
make concessions for fixed frame rate because I feel like it's very
important likewise saying everyone makes their own concessions.
So if we're what you want is a term in ISM, which I never care at all
about it.
All right, I've never cared about determinism.
Then if what you want is determinism, then you have to make other
concessions, right?
And you've got a whole bunch of work to do that, you might have to
make their what the best approach is for determinism.
I don't know that mailbox necessary the right approach because for
determinism male boxing is doesn't really give you anything on fixed
frame rate display is very much, right.
It's pretty hard to you.
Not really getting very much out of it.
All it's doing for you is kind of helping a little bit.
Once in a while, right?
It's more useful on displays with, with variable sink and and it
variable sink is not available in most Gamers machines.
So so I don't really know.
But all I can say about that is as a developer who determinism is not
a primary goal for me at all.
I don't tend to think about things that way I always just say fixed
frame rate is, is the the big thing?
So this can skip this, if you'd like explained it
Already.
Could you explain z-fighting and solving it as a problem?
Not yet.
I that's a very good question and it is something that we're going to
talk about.
But because I haven't gotten to the point where we're actually talking
about what stored in the z-buffer, it's a little premature because we
need to talk about what's in the Z buffer before we can talk about why
z-fighting even exists, but we will get there and it is important.
I don't know that we'll have too much problem with it on handmade hero
specifically because I don't know if we'll run into
Relations where it matters.
But we we might and depending on how we're doing, what certain
layering sorts of stuff and so we will definitely address that.
All right, I'm going to wrap it up now.
We're over time.
Thank you everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org.
It comes with a source code so you can play around with the same sort
of stuff that we're playing around with on stream and learn from the
series.
We also have a forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions a patreon page, you want to support the
video series a schedule, but you can use to figure out when we're
going to be live generally.
We're on weekends at 11 or 10 depending
On the the time and we also have an episode guide that you can use to
catch up on old episodes.
If you want to see how we've built all the stuff that already exists
in this area, seems just coming to it.
Now, that's it for today.
I'll be back here tomorrow to talk a little bit more about Z and we
might
Programming the depth depth, buffer version of the game tomorrow,
since I think we've covered most of stuff, we need to cover up set the
talk, a little about how we're going to do 3D transforms and stuff
like that.
So that may take a little time as well.
Depends on where we're at, we may go a different route and turn the
z-buffer on first and then go to the 3D transform part of it.
So, it depends on how you want to approach.
That can't tell.
Exactly, we'll find out tomorrow when we start to take a look at
what's the most sensible way to approach it.
So hope to see everyone back here.
Tomorrow tomorrow will be 10 a.m.
again.
So, same time, same.
A place until then have fun programming this weekend and I will see
y'all on the internet.
Take it easy everybody.