Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we could complete game from scratch live on Twitch
using nothing.
But our own.
Our very own handwritten code.
No engine.
No libraries for us.
It is.
It is our code or nothing here on handmade hero.
And we are right in the middle of doing sort of our structure,
structuring our sort of code, to into the, I guess I want to say one
of the most important parts for
later on in development, which is kind of how we process think about
in-store entities in the world where they are spatially, how they get
updated.
That sort of thing, how they are tracked, how they interact with each
other.
That's what we're working on right now and we're partway through it.
I want to get right back to it because we do have a lot of work to do.
So, I'll briefly just say that if you are following along, if you
preorder the game and you're following along with the source code at
home, you should have received a link in your email that link allows
you to download a zip file inside.
That zip file is one ZIP for
Every day since we're on day 57.
Right now you want to undo unzip day?
56 has source code and if you do that, you'll be exactly where I am
right now.
So you'll be able to follow along with everything.
I do if you want to sort of see how to do it yourself.
Okay, so let's take a look.
If I remember correctly, yesterday, we had just started finished
pulling things out into handmade World dot h and Dot CPP.
And we were starting to kind of starting to get our entity update
scheme in place, and figure out exactly how we wanted to figure, you
know, move things in and out of our active set.
And so on, and I had turned on smooth, scrolling for a minute, just to
be kind of see what happens when we scroll around.
And you'll also notice that we don't sort our enemies now, so,
It is like the wall entities and stuff.
We'll look clued, the player improperly because like I said, we
haven't done any work on rendering yet.
So we're best entirely doing this in whatever order the end of these
happen to be in.
So what I'd like to do now is I'd like to sort of go through and
continue to refine that code the way that we had it, and what I'd like
to do there is I'd like to start making a world.
That's very, very large.
I'd like to go ahead and start creating a world that's quite sizable
so that we can start to see.
Actly.
What the world, how our code will behave?
Under a heavier stress load?
And we can start to do some things like verify that we are, in fact,
moving things in and out of the active set.
And we're not just
Processing everything through the higher entities and so on.
So I'd like to sort of get into sort of sort of going that direction
and there's one really big thing that I'm not sure exactly how we want
to do yet that also point out while we're doing that, which is kind of
something that I think I'll probably come into into play later.
I don't know exactly when we'll start to play with that.
But let's go ahead and look at that now, so what I'd like to do is I'd
first like to say, well, let's go ahead and start.
Since we know that, we don't apparently at the moment have any real
issues even though we're not doing anything.
Particularly intelligent elegant, with our spatial stored sorting.
Let's go ahead and start sort of creating a lot more of our rooms,
right?
Because we had a thing that would create a screen screens and we could
basically pick as, you know, a number of rooms to create and it would
go ahead and create as many as we told it to.
So I'd be interested to see what happens.
Just crank that number up.
Right?
And I believe, we are no longer creating all of our dummy entities
here.
So we should have plenty of room to create a fairly large number.
So, you know, if we were to say, create something like 2,000 rooms
now, instead of the number that we had been creating.
I'd like to see first of all, what happens there, just to make sure
that that actually happens properly and, you know, I don't have I
realized I don't have anymore a key to like speed this fellow up,
which does seem like something that I probably going to do if I'm
walking through here.
Here it also is the kind of thing where I wonder if I would also want
to be able to zoom in and zoom out on the map or show some kind of at
some point.
We're going to have to have some way of showing the map a little, you
know, clearer for our own debugging purposes.
Unfortunately, since we don't have a render yet our options are a
little bit Limited in terms of what we do and don't do, you know, that
sort of thing but it does look like we don't really have any
particular problems here.
What I want to do though is I want to walk a little bit further away.
I just want to take a little bit of sample here again since we don't
have any
Debugging support or anything in particular.
Right now.
I'm just going to do this by Straight manual inspection.
What I want to do is I want to set a breakpoint just when I'm about to
do some rendering there and I want to just take a quick look at the
game state to see what exactly is going on in the game State.
How many hyades there are how Milo entities there are.
So there's 159 High entities in the in that set right now.
And what I want to do is just I want to make sure that as we Traverse
the world that that number stays.
Early consistent, right?
Because the idea is that things should be moving into and out of.
We know when things are moving into, we know that things are moving in
properly because as you can see, it's still drawing all these things
so they're getting pulled into the set.
But what I want to make sure is that they're also leaving the set
properly.
And like I said in the future, when we have a little bit more in the
way of a renderer, and debugging services will just print those
numbers out.
Just what is overlay them right on the on our sort of our console are
basically our heads up displays will show us this information.
But for now, I just want to make a quick spot check just to make sure
that it's not wildly incorrect.
So that is still going up.
That's 219 now and I'd like to make sure that it's not monotonically
increasing like I want to make sure that that's that's what should
have happened.
That we're just overlapping more things at the moment and that it's
not continuously going up and so I'm going to double check that again
because if it's just keeps going up and up and up, and that means that
there's something
Wrong with our eviction scheme that are eviction scheme is not
actually removing things from the low entity list like it's supposed
to.
Now again, there's also things we haven't really checked for like we
don't know about whether we're getting duplicate things moved in.
There's a number of things that we probably will want to check for
eventually, but for right now, this is just sort of doing a little
minor due diligence just to make sure that we're not really messed up.
So, let's see.
So things look a little jerk you're now.
So I'm going to go ahead and say I think
Unless that's just, I mean, one of the things is, our frame rate is
not particularly good at the moment.
Anyway, and we're running in debug not release mode, but, but even so
I just want to make sure that that's not the case.
So there we go.
We're back down to 168.
So I think we're okay.
Looks like our basic scheme of eviction is working fine.
And again all this is trying to do is just make sure that the entities
that are we actually care about the ones that are around the player.
At any given time are actually of a limited finite bounded number that
we know we can handle.
So what we'd like to
Do is say, you know, we're going to pick some number of entities that
surround an immediate vicinity of the player.
And we're just going to always keep it to that number.
And so 200-300, that seems reasonable.
I think we'll be able to write our code fine.
They'll be able to handle that number of entities, so we should be
good to go.
So, I think that's all working reasonably.
Well, now,
It's all good.
So the next question then that I have is we started to use this.
We started to create this spatial partition.
I wanted to be able to make a spatial partition.
And the reason that I want to make the spatial partition was because I
didn't want our code to constantly Loop over every single entity in
the system, every time the camera moved.
Because I was afraid that that would incur so much overhead that we
would start to pay for it.
Now.
We did a test yesterday and determined, that actually, the number of
entities we could just cold Loop over and not have to worry about too
much was actually pretty high.
We got up to about a million and we were still able to do it.
Okay, at 5 million it clearly broke down.
And again, that's just doing the checking to see whether things need
to put be pulled into the active set.
Now.
It's a little misleading because we don't actually know how much work
we have to do in a nobody.
Relations, but that does tell me that really we might be able to let
this one slide.
I'm not sure one way or the other.
But what I would like to do is say, well for the, for the sake of
actually showing how to do this cleanly.
And well, I think I want to still make the spatial partition on the
one hand not that useful.
But on the other hand, it will also allow us to be kind of crazy
scalar if we want to wear, we can have millions of entities and not
have to worry about it because we will be able to sort.
Of break through that barrier.
Trivially because we won't be paying cost for all those extra enemies
every frame.
So what I was doing here was we were tired of talking about, well, I
want to start storing the entities.
I want to store, which entities are in, which locations so basically,
Our world would be broken up into the same chunks that we were using
for the tile map.
But since we've kind of jettison, the Tom Apple are just going with
straight entities as the way that we store the world for now.
I want to basically take those same chunks and make them basically
entity chunks.
So each Chunk in the world is now instead of being about a certain
number of tiles.
It's about have storing which entities overlap that chunk.
And then when we want to bring things into the hiset, what we can do
is we can go ahead and grab those.
Right off of there.
Now.
The other thing that I point out is I suspect that that that looping
over the million entities thing was also a little deceptive in one
sense, which is that as we get a little further down the road.
We may want to have a lot of entities that are doing things moving
around out in the world in that are sort of autonomous, a eyes in the
world doing stuff.
That's far away from the player and can't afford to be simulated in
that high resolution because all of the stuff outside of the players
area is not being simulated.
Resolution.
And I thought of this last night, I that I wish I had mentioned on
this, on the stream that looping over the million guys was just for
one operation.
We need to do, which was pulling things into the active set.
But what's important to remember is we would have had to do that Loop
over a million for any operation.
That was spatial, that worked on the low entities.
And so, really, that would have gotten out of hand quickly.
Because let's say we had 100 entities that were autonomous and working
throughout the world's moving around.
Each one of those hundred would need to make queries to see what was
around it and where it could be moving and stuff like this.
Those would have incurred that same million time Loop.
And so really the when I thought about it after I was like, oh duh,
like even if we only had a hundred thousand of these we probably would
run into this problem because it would shoot up to 5 million queries
very quickly because if you don't have a spatial partition, you have
no way of cutting them down.
So again, just to be really clear.
About how this works.
We essentially are going to have whoops.
That's not what I wanted to do.
How do I get my color back?
Let's see here.
I don't know why this this constantly switches away from it switches
to the the eyedropper tool for no reason.
That's my only see like we you alt-tab, I guess it's cause the ALT key
because the ALT key does it?
They don't know how to write keyboard handling code on Windows.
Basically what that boils down to
So again what this is for is we have a giant world and we're any given
time looking at a tiny little piece of it.
And we've got all kinds of entities out here, right?
And in the future, any operation that we want to do.
So, let's say one of these entities here wants to know, you know, if
there's anyone around him who is hostile to him, right?
And because he might attack them or he might run away from them.
What we want to be able to do is restrict that query so that we only
have to consider a low number of entities entities, that might
actually be near him.
Because if we crank up that number again to like 100,000, right, then
every single query.
If there were 100,000 total entities in the world, every single query
that he does will touch all hundred thousand entities.
So you end up with what is essentially a no N squared.
I know we haven't talked about order notation much yet.
But basically if you think about how that works every entity that in
the world that might want to do one of those queries, if we didn't
have a spatial partition something of getting the numbers down.
It would have to go check every other entity.
So every entity would be checking every other entity every time it
Ago.
And so if you think about how many enemies there are, if there are n
entities, then if every entity has to every time it wants update,
check all the other entities.
That is an N squared that scales relative to N squared, right?
Because every n everything, every each individual entity does, and N
number of checks, right?
And that as, you know, is a curve that looks like this, which is
totally untenable, right?
You want all of your stuff to scale very flatly so that you can crank
those numbers out.
This is not
Something that scales and that's something we'll talk about a little
more later orientation.
We don't talk about too much now, but point being.
So the whole point of the spatial query is to to get down so that it's
nice and cheap to do those queries to level eyes this number.
So that instead of 100,000 guys each asking questions about another
hundred thousand guys, which results in that hundred thousand squared
which is a disastrous number.
Well over the 1 million that we found we could do successfully, right?
We want to get it down.
So it's just okay the people who need to check they only check, you
know 180s around them.
Right?
Just just in their immediate vicinity or something.
That's much more levelized in an effort to keep it down to this kind
of Number, the total number of iterations.
We need to do through a spatial check.
So that's what we're doing here.
And I'd like to go ahead and finish up what we were doing because we
started most of it but we just didn't actually end up getting to sort
of implement the code, we sort of structured it and then left.
So what I want to do is much like we used to be doing where we would.
Sort of say, I want to insert this particular entity into the world.
What I want to insert this set this particular tile map value.
What I want to do.
Now, just be able to say, I want to insert this entity.
So what I'm going to do is have a function that's called, you know,
insert entity in Two Worlds or something like this.
and what that's going to do is that is going to
Put this entity into it's where it should be in the world entity
blocks where it is.
And to be honest with you.
I think I'm actually going to jump the gun a little bit here and say
that what it's really going to be is change, entity, chunk or change
entity location.
Right?
Where what we basically do is we say we're going to tell you in any
number, right?
We have a we have a low end of the index, one of our entity.
Numbers.
What we want to do is say this entity is going to move from where it
was to where it is now.
Okay.
And so what it's going to do is it's going to take one of these World
positions, right?
It's going to say this is the old position and then it's going to say
this is the nude position.
I'll just do new p and old p and what we'll do for now is Will Allow
World position Old P will allow old P to be zero potentially so that
if you if this
This entity was not and my savior.
I mean the pointer will literally be zero will not point to a valid
will position.
So what this will do, in that case is it will actually allow us to
Just sort of say this is a new insertion.
This entity didn't exist anywhere in the world yet.
Please put it in where the new p is.
So the first thing I would do is I'd say if old pee right?
And in that case we want to see whether the old P, you know, is not
equal to the new P.
Basically, we want it.
We want to be able to do a check and I think we have what we had our
on same tile.
So we want to do something like saying, you know, if these are
In same chunk, right?
So, I want to base to be able to say if if to if the position that
this entity was in and the position that he's needs to be, in are the
same then we don't have to do anything because wherever he wherever he
was inserted in the spatial partition in our in our whichever world
that he blocky resided.
In is correct for him basically, right?
But what I want to do in the other case, so this is leave entity where
it is in the other case where it's different or in the case where old
pee doesn't actually exist at all.
In fact, I guess I could do this slight little bit differently.
I might say, if old P and R in the same chunk, right?
Then.
What I'm going to do is leave it where it is, but on the in any other
case, what I'm going to do is say all right, if there isn't
P.
Then the first thing I need to do is pull this entity out of its old
location, right?
So that'll be what this does here.
This will say pull the entity out of its current entity block and then
I will go ahead and insert it insert the empty into its new interview.
Block should say old to block.
So this will basically a search through the spatial partition to find
out where the entity actually is.
Now will ya.
Ink it.
Then what we'll do is we'll say, okay, let's take a look at where the
energy needs to go and we'll go stick them onto the end of the list
there.
All right, so we know that we can query, right?
We can do a get World chunk here.
So we know, we can grab the road chunk by its chunk X.
Chunk Blanche.
A yeah, so we'll go ahead and do that.
We'll get that back.
And this is going to be the new chunk X, the new chunk.
Why the new chunk.
See now.
What's interesting about this is what we want to do, as well, like a
separate a separate thing that we'd like to do now.
Right?
Is we don't really care about tile indices anymore, which is what we
were tracking before.
We used to be tracking tile indices.
And then offsets, right, but we don't really have any need for that
anymore, because now we just have chunks.
Right.
We don't have any real need to conceptualize where tiles are that can
be strictly an artifact of the world-building.
The world-building can consider things in tiles, if it wants to.
But once it comes to actually storing the world, we don't care.
So really what we want to do now is we want to call these probably the
chunk X chunk, why and chunks D.
So that what we can do is say that the world position is now based
entirely on those.
So we now no longer have any restrictions.
We don't have to even do the chunk shift.
Chunk mask chunk dim stuff anymore.
All we would need is a single thing, which is that, whatever the chunk
side and M is, is, is all it is, right.
So, this is, this is actually can just go away entirely and what we
can say is this is going to be chunk side M.
And we don't care what the tile side of M, is because the tile side
and M, really is just
The world-building will do so, you know, though.
I will perhaps still store it here just so we know and the chunk side
and M will just be some amount above that, right?
So, there you go.
Okay.
So we'll start the chunk X y&z directly in there, and then offsets are
will be from the chunk Center and that is how we will store things as
these nice little chunks.
So if we go ahead and do that, then what we should be able to say is
that we can just directly access off of this world position.
We can direct directly access, what those chunk coordinates will be
and pull the chunk out straight from there.
Okay, so that'll pull that out directly.
And then
We would pass a memory Arena here if we needed to store stuff.
And in this case, we actually do.
So we're going to want to pass a memory Arena like so.
So that we always guarantee that we have the ability to allocate more
space.
If we were trying to store something that, you know, that requires
say, allocating a new, what's the word for it?
And of evil OCH, right?
Okay.
So here we go.
We're going to get this world chunk.
So this is the chunk that we have and then what we need to do is say
for this world Chunk.
We want to go ahead and push this entity onto the like onto it set.
So you remember we've got this here, World them.
Block World entity Block store, some number of entities, as far as
them in blocks of 16.
So what we're going to do is say, if this chunk could have fit a new
one, then we push it on.
So we basically say, you know, if chunk entity count, look we'll check
here at the chunk.
Entity count is is already equal to sixteen or I should say the array
count.
So, however, many it can store of those low entity indices.
Right, if it's equal to that, we're going to have to make more room
for it.
And then afterwards we can go ahead and push it on.
So we're out of room.
Get a new block, right?
So what we want to do here is we want to grab a new world entity
block.
And the way that we're going to do, that is actually a little, not
quite what we will really.
We've got one more thing.
I will show you in, it'll literally be in about 10 minutes.
We'll go back and add something to this.
But I'm going to go through it directly for a so you can kind of see
why we're doing it this way.
So, we're out of room.
We need to get a new block because there's no room left in that block,
or we may find that
That that sorry, this is I'm looking at this wrong.
So it's actually our block here.
So what I need to do first is actually crap that block out.
So real identity block, block equals the address of a chunk first
block, right?
Okay.
So if that block is, is full, we need to get a new block.
So, what we're going to do, there is say
Oh, well, I'm really glad we did this.
So if you remember I said something very specific.
I said back back before we did this.
I said, Royal chunk, a should probably switch to pointers if Thailand
ID block to T.
Be stored on mass directly on the touch up which meant, if this was
not a pointer, then this should become a pointer and we've received
the answer to the question.
So can you guys see what it is?
The answer to the question is?
No, this should stay how it is.
And this should become a pointer.
The reason I know that is because as World entity blocks, fill up,
what.
I don't really want to have to do is I don't want to have to do the
block copy when they fill up.
Now, I guess what I should say is, I guess we don't really know the
answer quite yet because it may be the doing that block copy is
actually not that expensive because we only do it when we fill them
up.
I talk myself out of it.
See what I did.
The thing that I'm considering here just to be 100% explicit is when
this gets filled up.
We need to make a new world entity Block.
In order to avoid copying the block wholesale.
What we would need to do is we would need to have this be a pointer so
that we could then create a new one and point to the new one and then
have the new ones next pointer.
Point to the old block.
So we just basically making a daisy-chain of these things as we go.
And so that's what I was assuming I should do because I was like,
well, I don't want to have to do that whole block copy, but then I
realized that block copies, not that expensive.
We only do it every 16 insertions and it's really only done at
world-building time.
Probably, it's probably not something that happens all that often in
regular play through the game necessarily.
So it may actually be the case that since querying is a much more
frequent thing than
An reinsertion.
Is that actually the decision is that should be the other way around.
We should leave those those first blocks in there.
Yeah, so it's hard to say, it's hard to say, so maybe I will leave it
this way.
Maybe I will leave it this way.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to I'm going to leave it this way
for now and we'll just have to you know, say basically to do profile.
This and determine
If a pointer would be better here.
Right.
So, when we get a new block, really easy, obviously, we're going to do
a push on our Arena at this point because we have to, we have to add
some more space.
So we have to do our push struck.
There we go.
So we got to do a push truck.
And what we want to do on our push truck is push a new world entity
block, right?
So that's going to take that Arena.
That's just going to use up some more of that space that we've got.
And when we do that, push, what we're going to do is we're going to
get that world entity block back.
So this is going to be our new block and then what we'll do is we'll
just say, well, the new block.
That we made is actually I mean really we should we could call this
the old lock in some sense because what we're going to do is were
immediately going to take it and we're just going to block copy.
Whatever was in the in the block that we had.
We're going to slam slap that right on top of it, right?
And then what we're going to do after we're done with that, is we're
going to go ahead and say, all right.
Now, that that block that we've got is now considered empty.
So, we copy the old block and the new block is going to be considered
empty.
So we're going to set it sold.
Pointer to be equal to the I'm sorry.
It's next point is equal to the old block so that you can still get to
it.
And then we're going to say that it's residency, right?
The Entity count is now zero, so there's nothing in it now.
So we essentially just made a copy of the block pointed to it, by the
next pointer so we can still get there if we want to walk it.
And then we just vaporized the one that we had.
So that now it can accept a new one again.
So then what I'm going to do is go ahead and assert that.
If we got here, that we definitely do have room to store it now
because we know that we should
I'd have made room for it.
And then we're going to say that blocks low entity index.
At the edit account is going to be equal to the one we're trying to
store it.
So this reinsert sit, right?
So this does our insertion.
Again, it's a little hard to concentrate on these things while I'm
talking.
So I may have made a mistake in there somewhere, but that's basically
the idea.
Will step through it to check.
And so, now, what we need to do is we need to do something that will
that will pull it out of a block, right?
We need to be able to remove it from a block.
So we've got our old P here, right?
And our old P.
We need to grab that chunk out.
Right?
And we need to go ahead and see, she's me.
We don't need to pass the arena here, because the theory, we should
always get a chunk because otherwise whoever called us is totally
wrong.
Right?
Basically, if somebody called us with a bogus position, we want to
assert that immediately.
Like something went very wrong there.
Since this is not a necessarily a high-speed function.
You know, it's not going to be called millions of times a frame, or
anything.
I'll just go ahead and do the extra if you're just in case.
For some reason, we do ship with a bug where that happens.
Instead of crashing here.
We'll just go ahead and and handle it will say.
All right, the, you know, we didn't find the entity in there.
We'll just assume that everything will keep on running and maybe the
game will still play fine.
Anyway, because we're about to insert this guy into the spatial
partition a new location anyway.
So I go ahead and I check to see.
But again, yet.
I put the assertion in there because I also want to know if that's
happening in a debug build for sure because it should never be
happening.
In strictly a defensive maneuver to sort of prevent a catastrophic
situation that I would be checking for that.
So we get the chunk back.
Now we need to do is basically run over the blocks, and we need to
find this entity so that we can pull them out, right?
Then.
This is pretty slow.
So we're going to have to think about if this is something that we
want to be able to speed up in the future.
We're going to have to profile and see it depends on how often we need
to change.
Because remember we only need to do this when the entity actually
moves from one block to another.
So, thankfully, it's not it's not something that happens every frame
for every entity.
It's something that happens occasionally.
Or entities that move outside of the block that they were in before.
So, we may not have to accelerate it too much, or we may have to.
We will see what happens.
Okay.
So here we are in the the chunk code.
And what we need to do is now run over the the list of these World
entity blocks have until we find it.
And then when we find it, we'll yank it.
So we've got our world entity block that's going to be that first
block, right?
So we're going to start there.
We're going to continue for as long as the block is a valid pointer
and assuming that we didn't find it.
We're going to go ahead and move on to the next one along in the
The daisy chain, right?
This is a singly linked list.
For those of you who like, terminology, right?
We essentially have what is sometimes called a sentinel, but that term
can mean different things to different people.
So, well, I simply will say is we always have one Link in the list.
Always there.
And then what we're doing is we have pointers that allow us to chain
as many additional ones on as we
But the list can never be effectively entirely empty.
Because there's always at least one that's hard code.
Stored.
It stored right in the world chunk there.
So, as we move through this,
But we want to do is we want to scan to see if that entity is in these
this block, right?
And what we can do there actually in the future to is, we could, we
could use wide tests, we could use like Cindy stop, test to test, you
know, for entities at a time or something like that as well.
So in the future, we could speed this up even mechanically without
making the algorithm any smarter, we could actually speed up, just
evil imitation of it as well.
But for now we don't have to worry about that because again, we're not
really at a performance place where we have to think too deeply.
About about minutiae like that.
So when I come in here, what I then want to do is just scan through
inside each individual block and see which, which one of the blocks
contains this particular energy, right?
So that's a simple matter of scanning over what's in here and actually
guess I don't have to go through the array count.
All I really have to do because we've got a member in there that
actually counts them.
Is I can just use that and account that we've got I can go through.
Through there.
There we go.
And I can say for each one of these, if the block contains the entity,
right?
so,
So if we found a match, then we know we can just remove it from this
particular list, right?
And the best way to remove it from the list, right?
Is to swap into this location, whatever.
The sort of highest entity is.
So we want to do that same trick we did before.
Basically, I don't know if you guys remember this, we did this.
I think on the high entities, what we have here is we've got sort of a
series of
Right.
The go like this and each one of those blocks sort of has inside of
it, 16 things.
Right?
So each one of these blocks has has lots of things in it.
When we find the one that we want to remove, what we'd like to do is
keep always keep the empty space at the head of that list, right?
We always want to keep the empty space up here.
So we'd like to do is when we find the one that moves we would like to
go ahead and say wherever wherever you are.
Our head and list was, right?
When we get rid of this guy.
We'd like to grab something from the head of the list and put it into
that space.
So that this decrements downward, right?
So that we always keep our free space at the beginning, so that when
people try to insert the can just insert the head end.
They don't have to hunt to try and find free space.
Now, we could do it the other way around.
We could do the hunt here, but since we're already hunting,
This case, we've already.
We've had to hunt through to find the entity in the first place.
It seems more sensical to do it here than to force the hunt a second
time back here.
So, what I want to do is say all right, when we find this entity
index, then what we're going to do is say, we have two circumstances,
that could be in play here one, is that, we are the head block, which
basically means that we're just going to reduce the count on the head
block or in the other case.
We are some other block.
Lock in which case, what we're going to do is we're going to reduce
the amount on the head block by grabbing something from head block,
and putting it in here, right?
So what I'd like to do is say okay.
Got it.
Let's see if chunk first block equals block, right?
So in this case, we're going to say if, if we're on the first block
itself, then all we really need to do is swap with the last guy in
here, and I don't really know.
I, I feel like I could write this code to just be very aliasing and
let the compiler.
I think we don't have it.
Something to anything turned on, its going to assume, no aliasing like
that.
So we may be able to just let this ride without having to do the
check, but I'm going to break it into case that first and then we can
collapse them later if need be.
So I'm going to do here is say, alright, if the first block equals the
block, then we just have one block to deal with.
So all we're doing here, is we're saying that the entity count on the
chunk that we're on, right?
Whoops, glop.
The end of the count is going to go down.
Right?
And when the enemy comes out, goes down.
What I want to do is I want to take whatever was at the end of the
list and I want to put it in the location where I'm removing the sky.
So basically the low entity Index, right?
Of whatever.
This guy was.
Well, I actually have one of the things that I want to do, right?
I want to see if that first block, and you know what?
I think I'm going to introduce an actual pointer.
Called first block.
So I'm going to I'm going to just go ahead and do that.
So I can say, first block equals chunk first block, right like so so
what I want to do is I want to say, Okay, first things first, if there
was only one entity in the first block, is really what I should be,
what I should be checking in this case.
So if the first block equals the block, if the first block entity
count equals 0, or I should say equals 1, right?
So if me
Moving.
This guy is basically going to cause this block to go away.
Then what I need to do is something very special.
What I need to do is say okay, if there was a next block, that block
is now going to become me, right?
So basically, I need to say if that first block next is valid.
Then the first block,
Self becomes the the next block, right?
Because we would be getting rid of this block entirely.
It just goes away.
So I want to pull that next block up into where I'm at, essentially
getting rid of one of them, right?
So that finishes that off.
But
I have one other thing that I need to do, which is we had memory
stored for that next block.
I'd like to reclaim that, right.
I'd like to be able to use that for further entity block storage.
Right?
So the world empty block next block, right, is going to be equal to
this.
We're going to set that equal to
To it there.
And then what I'm going to do is say well I can I can go ahead and
free that block.
So I'm going to make a note of that here because we're gonna talk
about what that does in a second, but I'm not actually going to
implement it for another couple seconds because I just want to work
out what all the cases are here for doing the storage, the way that
were doing it first.
So the first step is to look at the end of the count equals 1.
If the entity count does not equal 1, that means that we have an
entity that we can Shuffle into this place.
So all we're going to do is we're going to take that entity count and
if you imagine what we're doing here again,
A straightforward.
Oops, I really wish that it would not do that.
I feel like they should fix that bug.
It's a really bad bug.
And I feel like you had to have known that.
It was there because it's anyone who's ever alt-tab to your program
would experience it.
I'll have to send them an email.
Okay?
so,
Essentially, what we're doing is, we're pick that pick it.
There we go.
That's what we're doing is we're going to go ahead and say all right,
we've got some number of entities in here, right?
And again entity count would basically be pointing to some this is the
count here, right?
We point to some location that doesn't exist at the moment.
We are looking at some location that does exist.
And what we want to do is say, all right, we want to reduce the count
by 1, so it'll now Point here, right?
Excuse me.
And what we'd also like to do is we'd like to move, whoever was there
into the the location that we have.
Right?
Does that make sense?
So all we're trying to do here is say, okay, whatever whatever that
first block low entity index is wherever entity count will now be
pointing to, we want to make where we are at right now equal to that.
So use the space that we are.
Pulling the The Entity that we're moving.
We're pulling him out of that, use that space to store, whatever was
at the tail end of this list, right?
And that's that's it.
That's what we're going to do there.
Okay, excuse me.
And so if it wasn't the case, right?
If that wasn't the case, well, honestly.
Are basically it's a posse, right?
It's pretty much exactly the same there really isn't anything.
Yeah, there really isn't anything else to say.
In fact, we don't even have to do this if if we happen to have been
removing it from there.
Really?
Yeah.
I mean, there's really only one sort of iffy Corner case that we have
to deal with.
So let's go ahead and just write them as 1.
If the first first, if the first luck
Entity count equals 1, then we do have to do that shuffle there.
But really the only thing is this guy.
Well, I don't know, maybe it's clear to write it this way.
You can see what I'm what I'm kind of grappling with here.
If we know that we're only the first, if it's only the first block,
then we know that we can just do this and we don't have to do the copy
because we know that there's no room left in the first block.
But if if we actually worked the first block, then we essentially have
to do the same thing.
Right.
I was trying to condense them.
So let's just blow them out first and see if we know, excuse me.
If we know that the first block was not born, we're on but it still
has that then we need to do that copy again.
But we need to do first is we need to salvage that entity first.
So in either case, now, what we would do is this guy always, right?
So what we'd want to do is say, okay, whatever.
The first block edit index is there.
We're going to copy it from the Block that we're on.
Because they're different and we're going to go ahead and reduce that
block.
Entity count.
Nope.
Sorry, did that backwards?
We're trying to copy it into this location.
The one that we're on the one, the, the space that is now free.
We're going to go ahead and grab whatever that last one was in the
first block.
And then, if that block, count has now dropped to zero, right?
As a result.
Then we're going to go ahead and do the free if necessary.
Right?
If it happened to have something down the road from, it will grab it.
So I guess what I was going to say though, is I want would like to
collapse these.
I'd like to get rid of this and so the question is, is
Anything special that we have to do it.
Kind of looks to me like this just works, no matter what, right?
I mean, it doesn't, it doesn't really look like there's anything else.
If, if it was the first block and the entity count.
It would just copy the zero with and index over itself, which is fine.
Right?
So it doesn't really matter.
So, I think we can just say that after all that after thinking it
through, really, that's it.
That's the entirety of the code.
That's really all we need to do, right?
Right, and I don't know if I've got bugs in there, of course, maybe I
do, but but that's it.
And it's once we find it.
We can break out of there but we've got to do a double break here,
unfortunately, because we essentially have two.
Yeah, we got it.
We kind of got to do something like this because we have to be able to
stop searching through the blocks.
We don't want to waste time searching through blocks that don't
actually matter.
So really what we have to do now is just address what happens when you
free a block and this is one of those memory management things.
Like I said,
People don't usually believe me.
When I say that, I don't spend time thinking about memory management
and I really just don't because it seems like most of the time, it
just sort of handles itself.
Usually the things that I do spend time thinking about are things like
this where I like to actually work on the data structures themselves
because I like to think about how things are being stored and I like
to play with those and make things that are custom built as opposed to
just using a generic array and just throw things in and call like
search or a map or something like that.
Right?
I like to do that sort of stuff.
And so that is definitely
Something that I do spend time doing all those.
You can see.
Not that long man.
How long did that take us 30 minutes?
I don't know.
Not very long, but I still like to do that.
But the memory management part of it, that's the thing that people
bring up.
So often is so free compared to the other.
The rest of the thought that I put into any particular system that I'm
surprised is the one that always comes up because in this case, we
have that exact situation, right.
Where we've got memory that's being used, these entity blocks and we
need to make sure that we conserve it.
It but it's so easy to just I mean, this is the entirety of the memory
management we would need right.
All we would need to do is say first free, right?
There's our first free block and when we free a block we just say,
okay?
The world first free equals that block that we just read and it's next
pointer is going to be whatever, you know was there, right?
So base is going to take that and instead of where it was chaining off
before.
We're just going to stick it on a chain.
That's on the
Of thing and then like I said, down here, when we do this push struct
instead of doing that.
What we're going to do is we're just going to say, okay.
The old block actually is going to be equal to
Whatever, that first free was in the world.
So we'll just grab whatever, whatever is on that free list.
If nothing's on the free list, meaning we don't actually have anything
on there.
Up there.
We don't actually have anything on there.
So if not old block, right, or I could even say, if old Buck, right?
We'll do it this way.
Like so.
So if we have an old block, then what we do want to do is say, okay,
then world.
First free is now going to be equal to whatever that.
The next thing was on the free list.
And otherwise, we're just going to allocate right and that's it.
That's the entirety of the memory management for the system right was
absolutely trivial.
And, you know, maybe I made a typo in there.
Like I said, when I talk on the stream, sometimes I can't concentrate
that high, but
I almost never make mistakes in those.
If I do, it'll take us 10 seconds to find.
I mean, we only have to step through two ears.
There's all of four lines of code involved in the memory management
for this thing.
And now there's never a call to an alligator at.
There's never a need to serialize.
There's never a need to have allocation at runtime.
It just works, right?
And
Yeah.
So again, I wouldn't ever really call that out or make a big deal out.
I would have just typed it in but I just kind of wanted to emphasize
that.
That's what it feels like to me because when people ask me these
questions a lot of times I don't have a good feel for where they're
coming from because in my world that's the extent to which I think
about memory management.
It was like that 5 Seconds at the end of something that took me 30
minutes to Think Through how exactly I felt like everything should
work for a number of other reasons that were
Very complicated like spatial queries and how often something to do
something on this.
And I was thinking about how to get a good first pass design that I
could work.
You know, all that stuff is so much more complicated and there's so
many more trade-offs.
The memory management part is like irrelevant.
It's like 10 seconds of typing and maybe 30 seconds of debugging later
to make sure that it worked and you didn't type make a typo, right?
And that's the end of it.
So, that's it.
Yeah, and and and there really isn't much left to say so that is how
roughly will do things again.
Like I said, there's a bunch of it's a fairly nuanced piece of Kobe
just wrote.
I'm sure that there's some typos / bug stuff in there.
Oh, we forgot to do X, you've got to do why?
So I think it's a good thing to start.
Testing it out, just play around a little make sure that we got it
working and we've got a bunch of other stuff that we sort of said in
the meantime, and we've got to
Do that as well.
So we might as well start that process.
I don't think we'll finish it probably in time for the end of the
stream, but we all might as well start it.
And then tomorrow we can finish it up and then our spatial queries are
pretty much done.
So that's pretty cool.
So what I would like to do is, say all right, we've got rid of the
chunk shift and masks and dim and all that sort of stuff.
We've got rid of that.
So we just got tile sided M and chunk side in meters and the chunk
side and M.
You know, is just going to be something.
We'll have to think about what we actually want that value to be.
We don't really care at the moment.
We have to do that.
We also would like to set our first free Block to be 0.
And when we go ahead and set up these chunk ashes, I would also like
to go ahead and set those from first.
And he counts to be zero as well.
And again, this is just so for using some memory that was initialized
to 0 which might be true on second.
Third runs through the game.
We want to make sure we initialize that properly.
So I went ahead and did that.
And off we go.
So now when we're doing the rest of our stuff here, we can sort of
think this through a little bit.
We don't have to do get chunk position for anymore.
We know that that's gone.
So really our spatial partition is really just a hash table, plus a
sort of daisy chain of chunks.
So I guess we've got that straightened away, pretty pretty well.
I think at this point, we know that these do not
These do not belong in a position, your geometry file because they're
really pretty intimately tied to the concept of the world storage.
So I think that's probably the appropriate place for them as well.
So now we just have to do is kind of start talking about these other
things here that we've got.
We had a new sort of sense of are on same tile.
We wanted to change that over to be are on same chunk.
And so let's go ahead and see.
I know we call that somewhere are on same.
Oops.
Could I do.
There we go.
Same shock.
So we'll change this to our in same Chunk.
We take two of them.
And basically this is just going to change that AB style to a chunk.
Oops.
That's not what I wanted AB style to chunk.
So those are placed and that is the definition of whether something's
on the same chunk.
Now, I should probably assert here when it does the check, that these
offsets are within bounds.
And that because otherwise the test would fail.
So we're kind of assuming this is true here.
So what I kind of want to do is say, let's go ahead and assert is
canonical, right?
Let's make a function for that.
And what is canonical do?
Right?
Is is canonical.
Will just take one of these sort of one of these positions here.
It'll take a guess a tile relative offset, right?
So take a real value.
That's basically just
Just like this style Rail, and it will go ahead and and say, whether
whether this is is working or not.
Right?
Fix floating Point mass of this can be exact.
How did we, how are we getting away with these being greater than when
did I win?
Did I switch from it?
Being that?
When did I switch from that?
Because that technically shouldn't be possible.
You should be able to end up.
You have to be able to end up exactly on it, one way or the other at
least in one of the directions.
That's a know why we did that.
All right.
Yeah, that's well.
We've got a nice little to do on there.
So we'll leave that to do on there.
But anyway, is canonical will now.
Basically, give us something like this, right?
Will say, all right, it's canonical if both.
If it's, if it's within the bounds, right?
And so now, we can sort of say we've got that test and we also will do
one where we do are these always done with V2s?
No, they're not, because they are economically as Court separately.
So we do want that to be separate.
So it will do is we'll make a separate one here.
It's basically that which go ahead and says that the result equals is
canonical world.
Set X and is canonical world.
That why we go and that will return the results as well.
So now I've got the ability to just kind of ask at any time really
easily whether or not these guys are canonical.
I'll stick that up at the top and then when we do that, re
canonicalize
What was that peacock?
Last chord we can do that is canonical.
Check on the tile relative position and I think that should be good
there.
And that way, this guy can also basically guarantee to whoever's
calling him that it had been, you know, cut it had been canonicalized
before it was checked.
Right?
So basically, we'll pass the world in there and say, okay, will double
check that make sure that it was canonical first.
Otherwise, we know that this would fail, right?
So we've got that like so,
And there we go.
So we'll double check those.
That seems good.
Let's see where else we're at.
Here are get World, chunk, chunk.
Tim towel.
Count is no longer even a relevant thing.
It doesn't matter at all.
So off we go with that and now we just have to do we have to fix our
economically ization.
Now are we cannot see ization?
Can literally just think of them as same as they were thinking of
tiles.
There's really nothing else that we have to do here.
Essentially.
All we're going to do is just change.
Change from thinking in terms of tiles to thinking in terms of chunks.
So really that just involves me doing this, right?
It just involves me doing doing this and similarly are re canonicalize
right if we want to switch to that.
We just do chunk side and M.
And now I think basically everything is going to be chunk side in
meters.
Oops tile side and beers.
So now we just have to go ahead and say, all right.
These are all going to be the same as well, shrimp side and M chunk
side and M.
Right?
And so tile siding M.
You literally use know?
We're in here now, which is what we want.
So the re-cock lies now will work properly to canonicalize and chunk
space instead of tile space, which is what we want.
Basically just think of them as giant tiles and there's just lots of
entities and any given tile that make up the character of the world
and we done that.
Third tile point is not particularly useful anymore.
But I guess we'll leave it in there for now.
In case anyone's actually calling it.
Is anyone actually calling it.
Let's see.
Laughs.
I guess I can just do a compile.
Let's find out this way.
Okay.
So first subtract, this is again, just the ABS tile becomes a chunk.
So there we go.
And let's see what else we got here.
Same exact thing AB style equals chunk, and this is actually a
centered.
Chunk point.
Yeah, so I don't even want that out.
That's not going to be a thing that anyone does.
Is it really, I guess?
Well, yeah, who knows?
Let's call it Center, chunk point and we'll just, we'll just see.
So, we'll take ABS tab, change that.
There we go.
And are in same chunk.
Now needs to take the world.
I believe is the only difference.
There are in Superchunk role position.
These are taking pointers to the moment.
Not sure if we care about that, but off we go.
And so here, we are with with having to do our
Our Z position, we need to think about that for a minute, but we can
for the moment, we can for the moment change that to be the chunk Z,
but we want to think a little bit more about that because right now,
we don't support offsets in the Z Direction and I think we want to.
So, that's that war.
It's a little bit more thought.
We're pretty much out of time.
So let's go ahead and finish cleaning some of these things up here.
I'm not sure what I want to do here for these guys.
So these are creating entities at those locations and we do know how
to create things at a particular tile location.
So what we could do is actually just allow it to map those in there.
So maybe I'll just do that for now.
That'll be the easiest thing to do.
So, I'll do it that way.
What I'd like to do is say that re canonicalize right that we can
call.
Where is that?
So
so we canonicalize your should have been mapping at a space.
Where is the?
Where is the actual did?
I accidentally delete the one that calls this guy?
I think I accidentally did that.
Was this my bad, you know, didn't mean to delete that guy.
I actually thought he was was totally fine map into tile space is
essentially the the function that we actually would want here.
Yeah, well, well, hold on a second.
Let's think about this just a little bit more.
Okay, so if the camera filing entity, yes, so this is going to be the
chunk Z here, right?
For now.
Let's go ahead and take a look, the Abbe style Z against these.
We're going to have to do some Z handling, a little bit with a little
bit more Pizzazz in a second here, a little bit more thoughtfulness
Chuck Z is not a member of high entity.
That's true.
That is true.
It's not AB style Z.
So that'll be chunk Z for the moment.
We've got abs tile, X Y.
So, these are all going to be essentially ones where we have to
figure out what that what the chunk relatives ocean would be from a
tile relative position if that makes sense.
And that is a little trickier, but what I could do is just make a
function that's called.
Position from tile position, right?
Something like that.
And then just pass these in and that would presumably, just just solve
the problem for us.
Right?
Like so so let's go ahead and take a look at that.
We don't have that yet.
Yes.
I know and if we do hit High into the index, so this is not actually
done yet.
We're not going to do that yet to do.
This is stairs.
Basically abs tilak.
X6, this is searching.
So the set camera now will be this will actually be a thing that we
can we can do in in tile, chunk space.
So I'm going to, I'm going to vaporize this for one second just to
make sure that we're compiling right.
Can you terms of tile chunks?
And that's what we'll do.
I think probably first thing tomorrow because then we'll be optimized
there as well.
We got to implement that and the same thing is true here.
So new camera P.
Will basically be equal to chunk position from tile position and that
will just do what it was doing before.
And so all we really need to do in order to end the day on a working
note is make sure that we actually write this function.
Improperly and I say working note that's actually pretty strong
statement.
I suppose because we don't actually know if we'll be working.
Well at least be compiling and that's what we'd like to be.
Leave us in a good place for tomorrow.
So all we really need to do is make something that will return.
A world position from a tile position so that our old code still
works.
We may never use that but at least we know that it will work in terms
of of our testing and testing the same code that we had before.
So let's go ahead and do that.
There we go.
And now we can Implement that function.
So our result is going to be equal to all zeros at the start.
And then what we will do is we will say that our chunk X right?
Is
I'm to be equal to sort of, we have a definition up here for probably,
how many?
How many chunks, how many tiles per chunk, if you will.
Right?
We've got, we've got this number here.
So I think we want to do is, do tiles per chunk, something like that,
and we'll save it, that 16.
So tiles per chunk equals 16, right?
And we'll just leave that up here for now.
That could be parametrized later if we wanted to, because we
Don't really use it in a lot of places.
It's optically.
Interesting function.
So we got our ABS tie, Lex.
And our ABS Telex is going to tell us where we were and and these were
are going to are sort of signed now, right as well.
If I remember correctly.
I know why they were still unsigned in there, right?
Because
Sort of saying that our tiles now could go could roam positive and
negative right.
There were starting at zero and that sort of stuff.
But yeah, a lot of this code is still Legacy from when we were first
doing our initial testing.
So what I want to do here is I want to just basically say, all right,
whatever you passed me in.
I need to figure out what Chunk we would have been on, right?
And so, if the first chunk is at 0 0, then if that was the center, I
don't know exactly where we want Center, but let's say that our chunks
are centered at 0.
0 0, that seems reasonable to me relative to tiles.
Then what we want to do is we want to basically every time you go nine
tiles, right?
You're going to move when you when you move away from zero, a certain
number of tiles, you're going to get.
Into the next chunk.
So, what I want to do is I want to divide this by tiles for chunk,
that tells me how many tiles I would have to go in that direction, but
It depends, like I said on how I want to Center the world, I guess I
could center it so that the bottom left corner of a chunk.
Yeah.
All right, we'll just do it this way.
So, that's how many away we are.
So, basically, it's this, right.
That's, that's it to figure out what chunk we're in.
And then we have to do is figure out where we are relative to the
chunk.
Right?
And so in order to find out where we are relative, the Chunk, we just
need to then take so that the offset and right now we're not handling
the Z properly.
So this is again move to 3 DZ which we kind of need to do some point
because we don't really have the way to.
We don't have a way to capture an offset in Z yet.
Still so right?
So if we have
if we have these guys, then essentially we know that the the
AB style X, right, whatever, that number came out to be and it could
be negative.
Right?
It could definitely be negative.
We know that, whatever the ABS tile X was - the result, whatever.
The result of the Divide was times the tiles per chunk.
This is how many were left over?
How many tiles?
We did not account for, right?
Whoa.
Okay, my keyboard has stopped allowing me to go upward.
I'm not even joking right now.
I cannot move the keyboard upward.
Why is that happening?
Like, literally the up key has gone away.
That would make it harder.
Well, not that much harder.
So anyway, if I want to do, I can always just do it.
My home.
What did I do?
Did I hit some kind of a control state of the keyboard?
Hold on, hold, please do not know what just happened.
I don't know that.
I want to know what just happened.
Let me plug it.
Unplug it, and plug it back in again.
All right.
Well, it's back.
That's always good.
All right, so just finishing up the offset here is just going to be
however many tiles there were times that I'll sided M, right.
And I think that'll give me the offset X & Y.
Right?
I'm pretty sure that's all we really need there.
So that way, we have sort of that tile difference like, so,
And then we just do the Y.
And again, we're waiting right there.
We want to we want to be able to compute the Z offset as well, but we
don't have that option for moment.
Unfortunately, so I think that's it for that.
And we are probably horribly broken right now, but I will go to the
Q&A anyway because yeah, assuming this won't, this won't run at all
and it doesn't as you can see.
So that's where we're going to leave.
Our poor little hero for today.
But just because you know, what you going to do.
You can't can't.
You sometimes you have to let the hero to sit for a little while.
He has to kind of think about a situation and then, you know, you come
back to it later and we're good to go.
It's alright, so we've done that and we'll leave everything for
tomorrow, which is probably one will just finish this up.
So it seems pretty good.
We will go to the Q&A now, so please prefix your questions with q: and
so that I can see them and please keep in the stuff that we've done on
today streamer on previous streams.
If you want to talk about other stuff like how to get in the game
industry or what software to use for doing something or
You just want to talk about random stuff.
Come we do do those kind of questions, but we do them before the
stream.
So please come about 15 minutes before a scheduled start time.
If you want to chat about stuff, we often do and it's a lot of fun.
So, so come for that for sure.
But for right now, let's just do just a questions on what we've, what
we've been working on for the past past days.
I don't think I can actually trigger the cue and I can, I
I'm not whitelisted on the butt.
So sad.
All right, let's go.
Let's see here.
Let's see what we're doing on cue, a any questions.
Can you please go over the lasagna code again that goes through the
linked list and moves around the entities?
Yes, I can.
And can you remove the note and reconnoiter about Tyrell?
Topology?
Yes, that's good point.
We don't want to do that anymore.
So what we could do there too is we could try to compute what that
safe.
Margin was.
I don't know.
I mean, maybe we want to try and get a little harder core on that in
the future.
Let's see.
Read canonicalize cord.
So maybe assert that we are nowhere near the edges of the world may
be.
Okay, so you want to go around the
Oh, My Stream is out.
Someone was saying my stream was out.
That sounds bad so it actually true.
Uh that looks like my service providers fault as well.
I will have to so I have gone through the process of trying to get a
new internet service provider.
So we'll see if I can get to that point at some point.
I don't know if we'll be able to or not.
The hope is that we'll be able to but looks like not looks like we're
in bad shape.
All right, so
I'll go through the code again.
Let's take a look.
So, change entity location, basically does all the work in our entire
for everything that we need to do.
I like that.
Was someone call it lasagna code.
I'm not sure what that means.
Is that mean that it has multiple layers, I guess.
Not entirely sure.
So changing a location.
We haven't had a chance to actually test yet.
We don't know if it's actually working.
We just wrote it today.
But what it does is it takes an entity which is this low energy Index
right here and it goes ahead and says, all right.
We've got a world position where it was and a world position where it
is going to be and we would like to
Move it between those two in inside the, these World chunks.
So, the first thing it does is it says, okay.
If?
The old and the new are the same chunk, then we don't have to do
anything because obviously you don't need to move something into a
chunk if it's already in that chunk.
So we check that first.
And if that's true, we just skip the whole operation.
Next, we check to see whether old P exist at all because of old pee
doesn't exist.
Then we're strictly inserting because it means that the enemy was
never in the spatial partition.
So it was never in the world at all, and we're adding it for the first
time.
But if it was previously in the world, then we go ahead and say, all
right, let's pull out the chunk that it is in and that's about our
hash table again will give us the chunk back that it should be.
We assert that there is in fact, a chunk there because remember the
hash table might not be filled at that point, and if it wasn't filled,
then we've got an error.
Because someone's telling us that it was previously.
In our world, but we are finding that it is not there and we should
alert immediately on that, which is why I put the assertion there.
So assuming we got the chunk back, which we always should
and the case of an old pee.
Then we go ahead and say, all right, grab the first block inside that
hash junk, that stores, which entities are in the block.
We loop from there.
In fact, I guess I could simplify this here because we already pulled
it out.
We loop from there over every block in the chain of blocks inside that
chunk, right?
For each one of them.
We look through we start at the zeroth, entity.
We look through all the entities that that block has in it at the time
and we see
whether our entity that we're looking for resides there in,
If it does reside there in then it is that is where we remove.
It will remove it from.
And if we are going to remove it, then we will set our block pointer
to 0 so that this Loop will exit and we break so that this Loop will
exit.
So we want to get out of all the loops, right?
So to remove it, what we do is we say, okay, we need to move, we want
the the first block.
So this block right?
We want the first block to always have all the empty space in it.
So if we're removing something from us, what we want to do is grab
whatever entity is available on that on that first block, right.
And we want to put it into us here.
So since we know the reason that this works or at least I'm assuming
Works because we haven't actually tested it.
Since we know that the first block always contains all the empty
space.
It means that if we are a non full block we must be the first block.
So either this is the first block operating with itself or it is the
the first block operating with some future block and that future
block.
And the first block does have something in it, right?
Because if the first block didn't have something in it, then it
wouldn't exist.
Anymore, it would be the some subsequent block if that makes any
sense, but point being.
So what we do is we say the index that we found, we want to replace
because we're removing the entity that was there.
So overwrite that entity with the entity from whatever the first block
had at its last element and its last index and we can even assert here
because we know that this has to be true and so we should just
double-check that.
The first block enemy count is greater than zero, right?
Because if it was Zero, it should have gotten, which should have
pulled in from its next block.
So, yeah, so if the first plug-in any count equals 0 at that point,
that means we removed in this operation.
The last entity that was in that block.
And so now we want to do is say if there were any more blocks at all.
We should get rid of that first block now, so overwrite, the vet, the,
the
Overwrite, what is in that first block, right?
This is what this line does.
Overwrite the memory of the first block with whatever was in that next
block.
We then set the next block itself to point to whatever was on our free
list.
So save, what was there?
And we make the free lists first free Block.
Be us, right?
Like so
Because we are now free.
All our data was copied in here.
We don't need.
We're not you anymore.
That's it.
That's the entirety of that.
Inserting The Entity into a new entity block.
Is a similar procedure.
We got to get that chunk.
It's simpler though, because we're always inserting into the first
block, gotta get a chunk that we should be in.
And again, we passed the arena here because we and we could assert
this as well.
But I mean, we're passing the arena, so we know it'll just allocate
right.
Basically, what we're going to do is we're going to make sure that we
get back a chunk.
So we will allocate one.
Even if there wasn't a chunk of that location yet because maybe the
first entity that's stored to that section of the world.
We assert that we got one, then me.
Alright, Loop over.
I'm sorry.
Not Loop over grab that first block.
And check to make sure that the edit account has room in it.
So this will trigger if the entity does not have room in it.
There's no room left and I'm sorry if the block is not have any entity
any room to store any Manatee, it will trigger.
So what it will do is say, okay.
We need a new block.
Let's find a new block on the free list.
So it'll go ahead and grab that, right.
You here?
Okay, so it'll grab one off the free list.
But remember the free list might not have anything on it.
We may never have freed any blocks.
We may have only used blocks up and then they have been freed.
So we check to see whether there was anything on the free list.
If there was something on the free list and we say, okay, good news
will advance the free list pointer to whatever.
The next free Block is, which is our next pointer.
Otherwise, that's not true.
We will go ahead and make an entirely new block by asking the arena to
give us the next available slot in memory to store it.
We'll then go ahead and say, all right, the old block is going to be
equal to this new block, right?
So the old block is the space that we've prepared to store the block
we were on and this is the block we're on.
So we basically copy over.
We overwrite the memory.
We just allocated.
We stop it with the value.
We then say all right.
Now that we've copied those contents into the next thing in the daisy
chain, we'd go ahead and say the next pointer points to that that
that's that place.
We just did the storage and then reset our entity pointer to be 0.
So we're constantly just basic pushing things out onto the daisy
chain.
At the end of the day, we should
Italy through all of this code here.
We should have always come up with space to store our new entity.
And so that is exactly what we do.
Let's see.
Are you dropping frames?
Things are glitchy.
Yes, apparently, according to, according to this, the dropped frames,
often times.
There will be zero percent and we are at 17.
So it is not great.
Again.
Gotta get a new SP.
Not much I can do about it.
Unfortunately.
I've been trying.
Do I use Bink for videos?
I've never shipped something that plays videos.
So no, I have never but I haven't used anything else or videos either.
For someone who does a lot of coding, nothing seems to be going your
way today.
I wouldn't say that.
I thought everything went pretty well including the stream Integrity.
Well, yet streaming technique.
Can you elaborate on what you will do to avoid this in the future?
Nothing.
There's nothing I can do.
The stream is what it is.
What is your opinion on things?
Like, bunnyhopping or other movement mechanics, that are bugs in the
code, but contribute to gameplay.
For example, if there was a technique for gaining speed in your game,
albeit difficult.
Would you keep it?
That's really a design question, and I'm not a game designer.
So I don't really have an opinion on that.
I really liked ski jumping and in tribes and starseeds tribes.
So I suspect if there was something fun like that.
I probably would keep it.
But like I said, not really a game designer so you shouldn't take
My advice on that.
What do you think about namespacing functions like entity underscore?
Get location instead of get entity location?
I don't I tend to like things to read as close to English as possible.
So I would probably not prefer entity under sword get location unless
I was trying to do it in some kind of Library style that was important
for people.
External.
Like I probably wouldn't do that.
But but I wouldn't be against it necessarily.
But I thought so nice to Purdue.
About push truck.
Isn't it?
True?
That it can actually fail if you're out of P allocated memory.
So when you still have to check, if your custom block allocation
fails, if your world gets too big.
No.
Well.
I mean, yes, obviously, but we will actually take steps to ensure that
we don't do that.
If that makes sense.
We will put bounds on our world generation so that we know that we
always allocate the amount that we need or we can also in the future
do a thing where the push struct.
If like pre allocating memory.
We can also loosen that because if we want to, we could do a thing
where we allow World allocation only,
During World Generation for example, and then if it fails, we just
vaporize that block and so the program won't have anybody Behavior as
a result of it.
So I'm actually okay with that as well.
And nothing that we've done so far jeopardizes that that's all still
very easy to do and clean with the way that we're doing things.
So we'll, we'll talk about those certain things a little bit later,
but no, we're never going to allow in practice.
We're never going to allow.
Those pushes to fail.
Why do you mean if chunk after a search chunk?
Because we don't know that our game will be 100% bug free, basically.
And so, I'd rather not crashed because it's possible that the game
would run.
Okay, even if someone made a mistake and thought that entity was
inserted somewhere and it wasn't
So, I decided to be extra careful.
Can you please explain when you comment your code?
What's the logic of having less comments on very big chunks of code?
Sure.
So comments.
I try to use almost never the only time I put in comments is when they
are strictly notational.
Meaning like the operation I'm doing now, like something like this
pull entity out of its old entity block.
So something that has nothing to do with how the operation is
occurring.
Just a vague notion of what's happening in that part of the code.
Because those are
Unlikely to be out of date.
Although they do still go out of date.
Any other thing I do is when I button down a piece of code, but I'm
like this is exactly how I want this to work and it'll probably stay
this way for a while.
I'll put in an informational comment that explains the rationale
behind how it was designed.
I'll do that.
Sometimes I try very hard, not to put any other comments in because I
find comments are almost always wrong because since the compiler
doesn't compile comments, you will often be making changes and re and
not realize you've invalidated something subtle said in the comment.
And then later someone comes and reads it and is now more confused and
if they're just hadn't been a comment.
So I try to make the code, read relatively cleanly as code, and and I
like people to be able to get it from that.
And honestly, also, if people can't understand the code from reading
it, maybe they shouldn't be editing it yet.
And I don't think they should think by reading a comment that they
will understand it.
So I tend to keep comments again to things that are going to be
either, just purely landmarking so they can tell what's going on each
piece of code.
Before they go and look at it or when I'm sure that it.
Because got stick around for a while.
Then I'll put in a comment that says, here's how this works.
Just so I can refresh my mental state and why I did the code, the way
that I did it.
But putting code in that tries to explain how the code is working.
Like in a line-by-line, kind of ways is a really bad idea, and I would
strongly recommend against it.
I find it usually hurts more than it helps.
When you said the code today, wasn't that performance-critical.
I instantly thought about a machine gun Stone through our battle just
across a chunk Edge.
I still don't think that would be a big deal.
Like, I mean, this will handle hundreds of entities, just fine.
So I don't think it.
I don't think it'll be a problem.
We'll find out.
Certainly
Alrighty.
Looks like we are done with questions.
I think.
Yes.
All right, so we are done with the questions which is good because
it's right about time to end.
Again.
It looks like everything is pretty good.
I'm relatively happy where everything is.
We need a little bit of time to debug everything that we wrote today.
I usually would like to do that right back to back.
But again, try to keep it to an hour a day, always.
So we are not going to do that.
But we will do that tomorrow and then we will be done with spatial
partition, which should be good as well.
You know what?
I just realized.
I think we may not even have any bugs.
We may actually be working correctly because the only reason that we
didn't see things is maybe because we just haven't finished porting
this when we Port, this, we may be fine.
So it could be that we actually don't even have any bugs either.
I don't know.
We'll find out, wishful thinking, probably usually you've got some
bugs.
So everything I think went pretty well today.
I was pretty happy with how that went.
We need to do some testing and some debugging to get everything up to
Speed, but everything looks pretty good.
Well, everything went well today, except the apparently the fact that
my internet service provider is fantastic and can't actually serve a
stream.
But if my internet service provider was capable of actually streaming
stream, then we would be in good shape and everything would be fine.
So tomorrow, we'll go ahead and finish that up.
And then I think that will probably a good time to go ahead and start
adding more stuff to the world.
Maybe some different kinds of entities and that sort of thing.
So we can start to look at the World building process.
I think that's probably
Only The Next Step.
So that's what we'll do tomorrow after we finish up, making sure that
the system partition works properly.
We'll go ahead and we'll start adding some entity types of the world.
We'll see how that goes.
We'll see what we need to do.
We'll start doing some Collision handling logic, like, what happens
when two things hit, you know, hitpoints some stuff like that.
Just to get some of that stuff in there, which I think now is about
the time for, that's our stuff to happen.
So we can solidify that entity update procedure.
So thank you very much for joining me.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, I will be back here, eight pm six center time to do the
stuff.
I just said and I certainly hope everyone will join me.
If you would like to follow along yourself with the source code.
You can pre-order the game on.
Handmade here a.org and it comes a little source code.
You will get an email with with a link where you could download it and
also the test assets that we use on the string.
If you want support the video series, you can subscribe to our patreon
as well, which we have here.
And if you are trying to learn from the serious, you want to go to the
news and Forum site.
It's got a lot of good stuff on it, especially the episode guide which
has all the past episodes you can catch up on stuff and they have some
time coded things for various episodes as well, which makes it easier
to jump around to specific things.
I talked about.
There's also a coding resources page where people have ported.
The code base already to Mac and Linux and other stuff like that.
So you can go check that out if you're trying to run.
A different platform that Windows already.
And we also have a code discussion board.
So if you want to post stuff, if you have things, you want to talk
about questions, you want to ask.
That's a great place to do it.
So thank you, everyone for joining me.
I hope to see you back here tomorrow and, yeah, have a have an
excellent Wednesday, whether I do or not.
So take it easy, everybody.