Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
We ended yesterday's session with and in fact, I'm kind of embarrassed
to say that I think for the first time, I don't know if it was the
first time but it's certainly one of the only times and one of the
first time for the first time
I I should for one of the few times, let's catch our bets.
I couldn't remember.
I was like, I know, I ended yesterday stream was something that I
wanted to do.
And I could not remember what it was.
It's been a rough day.
I don't mind telling you, so my brain was a little fried.
So I looked back and on the priest dream.
I went back and looked at the very end and thank you to my blow who,
of course keeps
Nicholas notes in the episode guide, I was able to just quickly scan
back and look like oh, right, that's what it was.
It was the ability to manually specify overrides to the sort order in
some convenient way in the user level code that the renderer can then
follow.
So that's what I want to do today.
I sketched out a way we could make it work yesterday and so today, you
know, let's see if we can do it.
Today is day 3, 12 so day, 311 source code is what you want to start.
With today, and that's what I'm working on right now.
So if you if you start with that, you're at the same place in the code
base as I am.
so anyway,
let's go ahead.
And and look at what it is that I am concerned about.
So we got our sorting stuff working and we have the ability to do
specific sort stuff and everything is working basically the way that I
want it to so far for a single region single room.
And so we're going to have to do a little playing around once we get
the Z, correct to make sure that these guys were correctly because
right now, these are a little bit weird because of the fact that there
Still being scaled in proportion, they're not supposed to be.
So we've got, you know, once we fix the Z stuff, we'll have to take a
look at the stairs and possibly tweak, the sort rules a little and
make sure that they're okay.
But everything else is working, roughly the way that I wanted it to
work and we currently have one situation which I would like the
ability to manually override.
And that is that if you take a look at what happens with the head on
top of the body of the hero, you'll notice that because
The body is to, you know, the body is two segments at the moment.
Well, three really, the shadow included and they always sort in the
correct order because I manually specify their order.
Right.
And we added the capability to do that with those aggregate sort keys
and it seems to work pretty well, but
Head is a separate entity.
And so the problem that we have is since the head is a separate
entity, we need some way of saying, hey, this and the body are
supposed to sort in a specific order and we need some way of
specifying that even though we're in two totally separate systems,
right?
So, we're trying to pass this information down to the sort of this
order has no idea what the head and the body are, right?
It just sees a bunch of Sprites so it needs some way of correlating.
Basically a thing when the head goes to render, it needs a way to say
I'm in front of the body somehow.
now, the problem that we have here,
is that if you take a look at this,
if you take a look at how this works, we currently don't have that
ability.
And so when the head moves, you can see that it briefly.
The body will flash through as the head gets far enough back and why
to be behind where the body is, right?
And there's really no way we're ever going to fix that.
It's not a sorting bug in the sense of doing the wrong thing, for the
definition of our sort, it's actually sorting those two things
correctly, but the problem is our semantics.
Desire.
Our artistic desire of how we want those things.
Sorted, simply doesn't match where they where the objects actually are
in the world, right?
Those are why Sprites and the head is actually behind the body once it
kind of moves back like this.
And so at some point it crosses over that boundary.
So we need some way of making that not happen.
And so what I need to do is get that information down to the renderer
during the sort and so that's what I'd like to take a look at doing
now, okay?
So what I suggested and there's a little you know it's not completely
sure thing yet but what I suggested was we could have the renderer
keep a little table that allows you to do some Edge specification in
it.
And in that edge specification you can simply tag things and say you
know what we're going to say that there's some number of special
objects and we're going to tag those objects with some ID.
Like will just say you know this is 0, this is 1 this is 2 this is 3 4
5 whatever right we'll tag the
Mix with those IDs as we write them.
And then they'll go into a table at sort time based on that idea,
then, you know, when the sort needs to sort, it can just go through
the manual edges.
And look at those IDs, pull out, which objects that's actually, those
actually are in the table and go.
Now it's a little hackneyed and and stringy, right?
There's just a lot of bookkeeping there, but my assumption is that
it's probably okay, because we don't have to do it for every Sprite,
right?
Like it only has to happen for
I element objects that have a defined sort order.
So it seems like the kind of thing that's not that critical, right?
It's not going to be do done on thousands of entities.
Every frame.
So I'm hoping that's the kind of thing that doesn't really create that
kind of a problem, if that makes sense.
So yeah.
So if we take a look here, let's see.
So if we take a look here, we have in our sort, Sprite bound.
We had this idea of the debug tag I guess what I'm saying is the debug
tag could actually become, you know, essentially a real tag for all
intents and purposes.
Right?
Oh, and I should mention.
Since we're doing this at a time, when we're creating something, in
the render list, one of these can actually just be an actual offset
can actually Point directly at the Sprite bound.
So really it's only one side of the table that actually needs this.
So the hard part of this is going to be over in World mode, I believe,
anyway, or I and I always do this actually entity.
I seem to never be able to remember that.
We moved this code into a separate file.
So you can see here where we do, our begin aggregate sort key, in our
end aggregate sort key to do our peace rendering.
And by the way, I suppose, one thing that I probably should do is just
say, hey, if the piece count
Is greater than one do this.
But there's really no need to trouble.
The renderer in aggregating, a sort key if there isn't actually more
than one thing.
Right?
So that seems like a pretty same thing to do as well just to prevent
the renderer from having to do any work there.
Anyway, so here we've got our Loop and the problem is when we do this,
end aggregate sort key bit here.
I want to be able to add an edge at this point and I want to be able
to add an edge to the thing that I'm on.
Top of if I'm on top of something special, right?
If I'm if I'm in front of something special and you can see why this
is a little bit tricky because we're just an entity in the world and
we don't really know who our parents.
Our identity is, in this case, like we don't really have a good idea
of who, that might be now, fortunately, because our system is actually
pretty flexible.
At this point, we haven't really pushed on it much, but you'll notice
that we can find brains by ID if we need to write, I believe we have
the capability to look up a brain by ID and let me just verify that
that's true.
But you know in
Same region, we have to put stuff into brains and we have to do that
in.
Quick, you know, quickly.
Right.
We have to do that in a speedy fashion.
So you can see here when we come through and we do know not move
entity.
You can see right here.
There we go.
When we come through here, you can see that.
We have our brain idea.
We do brain idea.
We do a get, or add brain call.
When we do that, get her a break, and call, you can see that we've got
sort of the ability to deal with the brains, at that point.
So what that means is that if we needed to, we certainly could have a
way to look it up in here for a special purpose, sort stuff.
We could certainly make that happen in here.
Now, I don't know that, that's
Best way to do it because since our entity struct like, you know, I
guess what I'm saying, is one way I could do it is right in here.
I could just go grab my my brain.
If I'm ahead, go look at the body and be done, right?
But the way that we sort of set up this system, it feels to me a
little more proper to say, well in the brain code, the idea is to have
a large flexible entity, you know, sort of flat entity format.
Right, that we were working with its giant.
The kind of doesn't
decompress stream sort of thing into it.
And what seems to be a little more sensible to me is just having in
their a thing that's like, who I would be on top of What entity I
would be on top of, or something like that.
Having that value in there, seems like a much saner way to go, right?
That seems like the easiest idea.
So, it seems to me that what we would want to do is inside handmade
brain when we're in the hero code.
You know, if we could just have
some concept in here, that we've got something like, you know,
Some kind of thing like that, where we have manual sort in front of,
and we can just write into their the brain can write into that and
specify something for that.
If that makes sense.
So I think that's probably the same your way to do it.
And so then in here, where we have, you know, the type brain hero,
when it's propped, doing all of our hero processing in the case, where
we know that we have a body and a head.
So you can see like, you know, if we wanted to put one in here, we
could just say like oh okay, you know, if we have a head and a body.
Right.
Then I want to tell the head that it's in front of
whatever the bodies entity ID is, or something like this, right?
and so, you know,
Something.
Like this.
Does this make sense?
So basically when we come through, we would say, okay when we have a
head and a body that are linked together, I know that I always want
the head to be on top of the body and in the future, you know, this
could get even more complicated, right?
It could be like, check that we are attached as well.
Yugi, not floating head.
So, you know, we can also have other criteria here.
We can break this.
If the head is a free floating head, not attached to the body which we
could easily do, right?
So in this case, where we have the head and the body and we assume
they're attached like in the future.
Like I said, if we want support Detachment, then we want to say
reserved, a special sort key.
Somehow that says that the body, when it gets sorted will,
That tag, right?
It'll be able to say this is a special sort key.
That's going to be important that can announces the renderer and then
the head can have that information of.
Oh okay I'm a sort.
I have someone I'm supposed to sort in front of and this is who that
is right?
And what's interesting is these are not really supposed to be stored.
So you know
When we actually start doing our packing and unpacking their, that's
the kind of thing that we would not actually want to store.
And, you know, I suppose we could also do
Something like this and inside the Sim the thing that does the pack
down.
We could make sure that we don't actually like, use them ever.
By when we do pack entity into chunk, where's our unpack?
Where is our unpack?
Region.
When we do our unpack here, which I guess.
Would be here.
Good Ash.
My DD region, some region.
This could be the decompression step.
So right here, you know we can
Zero these out just to enforce the fact that they can't persist across
a frame, right?
Which I
I really want them to.
Why did I type that wrong?
I don't know.
All right, so let's keep going here.
So what this means is that the brain, even though it really doesn't
need it for anything else.
Yet is going to have is going to need a way to talk to the render
group because it now has something to say before it didn't, right?
So before those two things didn't have to be connected in any way so
when I called execute brain, I wasn't actually ever passing a render
group.
And even though I could have, right, we're at a point in the code
where it's configured up and proper, so it's not a problem.
But I just generally don't pass things if they're not needed, right?
So I'll go ahead and pass it now that it is needed.
And yeah, I guess I'll pass it after the input seems like a reasonable
place and I'll say that this is the render group.
And reserved sort key.
We haven't already yet.
This is of course spelled wrong.
And so really what we need to do now is just have a notion of that
Reserve sort key somehow which will deal with in a second.
So then when I come through here, you know, how would I use this?
And you'll notice I'm kind of doing usage code in the order in which I
think I understand it best from best.
At least course, I'm always in the wrong file should just move this it
back there.
I always think it's there.
Some reason.
So in here, you know, when we do and aggregate sort key,
I'm trying to think of where I really want to do this.
I think what I want to do is say, well, whatever.
The last piece index is that, we do.
I want to, you know, they're going to render sort of in, in that in
that order.
And so let me let me just double-check this here.
So if I go to world mode and I go to Hero,
Or add player rather.
So in add player, you can see that we do Cape torso Shadow and so like
0 is the is the most sort of the most important part of the entity.
And in fact, if we kind of look down here at the pieces, we could even
note
Hey, zero is the on top piece.
so,
And is the on bottom.
I so we know that the first one we push is the one that we would want
to make a specification about as
Our as being if something was on top of it, right?
So that's the one that we would want to associate with the reserved
sort key.
And then if
We're talking about the person who wants to be on top of another
thing.
Then that one presumably is just going to be based on the aggregate
sort key, right?
But I guess in either case it's it's really the zero with person.
The question is just did we aggregate the sort key or not?
Now one thing that's annoying is, like I said, I feel like we don't
want to force aggregation in the case where there's only one thing.
But the problem is, this would kind of be the natural place to put the
piece of information that I'm talking about.
It would seem so yeah.
Not really sure what I want to do about that.
Nice.
Eh.
Well.
I guess, let me look to see what actually is going to happen inside
the render, group code for this to work properly, and maybe by
switching to the other side of the problem.
It will become clear how that wants to flow down and then that will
specify the other side for me.
So I'm just trying to like ping-pong back and forth between the two
sides of the problem and to make them meet in the middle, in a good in
a good place.
all right, so when we do the Sprite graph here,
So this is the code for build Sprite graph, obviously it goes through
and it does all the crib checking.
And at this point after all, the grid checking is done.
We have edges between all of the nodes that we know we want edges
between right.
But now what I need to do is add some additional edges in that Force
sorts in a particular order.
And so yeah, I guess the question.
In is.
The.
Good news.
How do I do that?
In a clean way.
I think the answer is that since there are a low number of manually
specified edges, what we probably would want to do is let this create
all the edges exactly as it has.
And then, you know in here we would probably want to do some kind of a
for I Loop.
Right?
Where we said something like
oh,
wait a minute.
Am I making this more complicated than it needs to be?
You know, I think I am.
I think I might be drastically over complicating this.
Now that I think about it.
So here is a question for you suppose that we just look at is in front
of.
We know that we have a Sprite bound a in a Sprite bound be if we
wanted to couldn't we just do something like
inside the sort Sprite bound, there's like, I don't know, some kind of
a
sort code or something where I just say like, okay I've got some of
these
I could even have it be a pointer probably or an offset.
Let me just explain to you what I'm thinking.
I don't know why I didn't think of this before.
Is there something wrong with that?
It seems so obvious.
I'm not sure what I'm thinking before.
All right, so basically we're going to end up testing
The head against the body, if they overlap, we're going to test them.
If they don't overlap, we don't care, right?
So if the heads over here and the bodies over here and nobody cares,
we're never going to need to know who's behind who because they're
never going to need to get sort of relative to each other.
So, we know that we're in this scenario.
So we know that we're calling is in front of
Right?
And we have both of these sort keys.
So why don't we just put something in the sort key where you can tag
each of these with a always behind always in front code where if those
match up, that's the sort.
In fact the simplest version of this right is is real real simple.
You can imagine saying like Okay you know, I've got a you 3016, maybe
another you 16 here.
Like this where it's like always in front of and always behind, right?
And you could just do something here where you just say like, okay if
these two things match on you, if my always in front of matches,
you're always behind
We're done.
So, for example.
We could just say be 32 results.
If
if a is always in front of
Is greater than zero.
right, and a
Always in front of equals be always in front of then the result is
true.
Otherwise we do the comparison.
Right.
So in this case and I guess that needs to be inside Sprite bound, so
technically, that's that's here, right?
So, basically, that's saying you can have 65,000 pairs of things that
can have a sort rule between them, you just, and you can't have more
than one per thing.
Now, we could have more here, we could, you know, make some more if we
wanted to, but that we'll see if that gets out how far that gets
But if you take a look at how this works for you say, oh, okay, now we
just say, well, when you render the head just set, it's always in
front of, to be some code.
And the always behind one gets the same code, that's it.
I think that's the entirety of it, right?
I mean, is there I think that might literally be the the complete
solution to the problem?
And it's a little less flexible than being able to manually specify
edges.
But I mean, the amount of complexity savings you get from that seems
crazy huge.
So now really all that happens is you would just say, you know, always
in front of always behind
Oops.
Now, it's trivial you just say, reserve, sarki.
You get one back, you render as you normally would and you just have
to specify.
That always behind and always in front of and, and that's it.
So that seems like, way better than what I was saying.
So, yeah.
I think I may have gone down a stupid path there.
I was, definitely, I was definitely making a system.
That was a lot more than what I think I would have needed.
So I'm glad I thought of that.
I don't know why I didn't think of it earlier.
Anyway, so if we go out to play,
Form.
Since this operates at sort level, we just have a thing here which you
know is is going to be
Emanuel sort key.
Count or something like this or next available.
Let's see.
Last used manual, sort key something like that.
And so reserved sort key is like a really trivial function now that
doesn't do anything even remotely complicated.
It's just going to do.
You know, assert, I get the commands out here though.
It's going to say, all right, you know.
Whatever this guy was.
Assert that the last used manual sort key is less than 16 maximum.
We have that to find.
There it is.
So it doesn't look like we ever did.
So I'm going to say u16 Maximum 6, I thought 35
As long as there's room, right?
As long as I'm not going to overflow then last use manual.
Sort key is is all good, assuming that it starts at zero.
I want to use the pre ink.
I want to use the post incremented value of it.
So the first one I give out will be 10 means don't bother doing this
sort, right?
Don't don't do a more complex sort on this guy.
So I would say the result,
All's the u16 of that and then I returned it.
So now I have allocated those, I'm good to go and I just have to
change these to do like always front of always kind and
The corresponding.
Inside the Sim region.
And off we go now if that's good Define.
So now, I think we're pretty much good to go.
We just have to actually use this.
Let's see here.
It's in front of return result.
Thank you for catching that, mister compiler.
I always blame the compiler when do something wrong.
So I feel like it's good to thank the compiler.
When does something right?
Alright, so now we're all good.
We just have to actually put that value in somehow, right?
We have to get that into the actual renderer somehow.
And so when we're doing that, what we want to do here is I think when
we do these push bitmaps, we want to make sure
That somehow that information flows.
Now I believe the object transform.
This set here might be the right place to do it.
So entity transform always in front of maybe equals entity, always in
front of and entity transform always behind maybe equals entity.
You know, always behind something like this.
And what I need to do there is go like, okay.
The object transform since that's the thing that I'm passing down
inside render group.
I just need a place where those are going to live and then I'll just
copy them into the sort key as we go.
So here's that object, transform always in front of
Always behind, and you can see that those things kind of form a pair
all the time.
So, the other thing that does kind of seem possibly likely is that
they should be bundled, right?
So, it's possible that it should be something like manual sort pair.
Or manual sort.
Manual sort key.
I don't know.
Something like that.
Yeah.
So at that point, we could also say that inside the renderer instead
of those, you know, maybe we've got a maybe I can stick that in here.
And now every time for this object transform inside the render group,
when we do,
There's what is there at?
There's like a default one in here, somewhere, or I'm not sure what
that actually does.
Default, there we go.
So in these cases, they'll just get cleared to 0, which is what we
want.
And then in when we actually go to push, somebody on here, where we do
our, you know, our sort key stuff.
We do sort qsort key, whenever these sort keys are being made, which I
believe, don't, we have a get sort key for computes?
What key?
That's okay.
I don't know what that is.
That was pretty funny.
We have a thing that does the sort Keys here somewhere?
Where is it?
Get Bound for there, it is.
So this guy right here, when it computes the Sprite bounds, now it can
also take whatever the one that was in the object transform and just
copy it, right?
So, the spray found manual.
Is going to equal the object transforms.
Manuel.
I call it.
Sort.
okay, so yeah, I think also, we could probably get rid of sort bias at
that part and use,
This manual sort key for that.
Okay, that that separate though.
Anyway, so, yeah, now that we have that happening, the manual sort
just works.
I think at this point because that'll get copied in and set.
So, now we just have to go through and make sure I didn't mess
anything up, which I probably did.
But, let's find out.
Okay.
Oops, did I make those two big?
And I wonder if I could do.
Just this.
Okay.
Yeah, and I need that to actually be sort of visible to everybody so
that may have to be something kind of moves.
I don't know, maybe
Here.
I really hate this aspect of c and C++, it's the worst other
languages.
I, well, I don't know, maybe some do, but it's just stupid that you
have to care where things go files should be for your benefit, not for
the compilers benefit, you know, I should be able to put the sort key
where it makes most linguistic sense for me to have it and look at it.
And that is not what happens at all.
Okay.
So yeah.
I think we're just about done.
It's just manual.
In that case.
All right, so now in theory, these things are getting marked.
We did do a bunch of changes there, so this is probably not quite
correct.
But hey, we should be able to now, go do some debugging, I don't know
if I can.
Well, I think I might be able to.
I think I just have to trap or there we go.
I'm like, we got to get these sorting in the wrong order first, so I
can watch it happen.
But yeah, that's what we need right there.
So, the idea is that shouldn't really happen.
So,
I want the ability to force the head to still be on top, even in that
situation, right?
That's the goal here.
Okay?
So let's take a look at the code in handmade entity.
Where's where's that?
Or actually I guess in the brain first and handmade brain.
Let's see whether we're setting this correctly in the first place
because that's the first step of this process is this guy.
When he comes through here and decides that he's got both a head and a
body, he's got to set the sort key and is going to sort the always
behind and always in front of
Keys.
At this point.
All right, so we go in here to reserve and there.
It's this should be zero because it's the only person ever calls this,
right?
So the results should be one and it is so off we go.
Then we do a bunch of stuff and really I guess the next thing that I
wanted to see was in the actual sort, I want to see if we ever hit
that case or if I, if I never actually do.
So let's take a look at is in front of here.
And I want to see.
If we get here.
So, the answer is we're not getting there.
All right, so,
Let's test another thing.
I guess I could have used livecode reloading us.
I'm not sure why I probably shouldn't have closed.
It's a force of habit.
So when I'm in the entity code and I set this energy transfer manual,
sort here, I'm going to do a thing here to say well alright in the
case where the manual sort always behind
Is not equal to 0.
This way I can zero in on just entities that have that set which
should only be two of them, right?
Okay, so now we should go into entity.
Boop.
Okay.
So at least now I can verify that we are in fact passing some of it
down.
And so manual sort says, always in front of is one, right?
That's what's going on here?
So presumably this entity.
If it's always in front of number one, this must be the head.
And, you know, we've got brain slot 0 on brain id-1.
Let's see if that corresponds to what we think it should be.
Zero.
Out.
Sorry it's typing index, zero, zero zero.
Yes.
So that's correct.
That is the head so that got set properly when we come through here
let's take a quick look at what happens when we actually push.
The bitmap here goes the push.
That's right.
Get it.
We're going to push it on.
Get the dimensions.
Finally, push it.
Push it as a render element here comes the push and we're going to I
guess it's that sort key that I need to look at.
Does it have it in there?
So it did.
So the sort key is set correctly now
Right.
At least on that guy.
Let's see about the other guy.
This one should be always behind.
Yep, always behind one.
So,
Current.
Yeah.
So, here we go.
I want to push bitmap and
alright, so I've I've determined that I do.
In fact have those values set properly so going into the sort in
theory we have the correct data in theory anyway.
So it looks like I just have a typo there.
Maybe that's our only bug.
Wouldn't that be nice?
This is just supposed to be always behind, right?
If that's our only bug, that will be a very happy camper.
In fact,
nope, not our only bug.
Okay, stay there, mr.
Familiar.
Okay, there we go.
All right, so going into the sort.
I guess what I could do is see whether I'm ever hitting
This case separately.
I guess I could do like,
Right?
So this way I could check to see if either of them.
Oh, you know what?
I just realized, I have to check it both ways.
Don't I
so,
I would have to say if a is always in front of be and I'd also have to
say if B was always in front of a
right.
Like that kind of thing.
So it's really more like this.
I think that's more.
We're looking for.
So I don't have to say, all right?
When I compare these two things, if I have a condition where I
I know that.
See, I also need to know whether there.
I wish there was a way to make it so that they never could be 0.
I guess I could just make it so that they never do equal.
so, since I'm doing this comparison,
I could just make it.
So the default case instead of being zero is a different case where
they're not always going to be equal.
That's kind of complicated.
Let's see if we can make that work.
All right.
So can we do something like this?
If the always in front of equals the always behind, then it's true.
If the always in front of, in the other order equals, the always
behind and I guess I could leave a in the same position here.
Just so it's a little easier to read.
If I always in front of this guy, it's true.
If I'm always behind him, it's false.
Otherwise we do the actual operation.
So in that case, what I would need to do is make it so that there's
not a zero, it's not zeros there.
In the case where it's not supposed to be doing anything.
So, for example, if you're just doing sort of a cleared one of these
and I don't know that this is the best way to do this.
But you know, if you imagine saying that always in front of
Is zero and always behind.
Is the maximum value?
Those would never compare right?
Those would never be equal for anybody so that would prevent the bug
that would prevent the false case.
But I don't know.
I think maybe it's better to just do the extra check.
I'm not sure I really don't.
I like clear.
20 is very important.
I find that it it prevents a lot of Errors so I don't know.
I'm going to go ahead and just stick with what I had before
temporarily and we'll see if we have to do something else.
Alright, so now we are in a better situation I think.
Oh and hey look it fix the book.
So yeah that is and right at the five-minute warning that is what I
wanted to have happen.
Now we added a little extra complexity are sore.
Oh wait, no I still got there was a little bit glitched a little bit
there.
Is that what is that?
Because they weren't quite overlapping.
One thing that I don't know, is how our bounds.
I know, I saw it.
Yeah, like right there.
hilariously eventually, those Sprites get behind the actual
Wall.
I think I need to go fix.
I need to actually fix those Sprite band so we'll have something real
to play with.
I definitely saw it glitch.
There we go.
It's weird though.
It's very there.
It is.
I'm not sure.
I know how that's happening.
It's really weird that it only happens just in transit and I can't
hold it.
Hmm.
Yeah, that's really weird.
I mean, I suppose, one thing that can be happening there is, if the
sort graph is doing something weird.
Amen, Let me see here.
We need to.
We need to finish this part so we can have this up on top.
I don't remember if this is actually valid or not.
It's very strange, it doesn't seem to be very consistent, which is
odd.
I think we must have a bug in there.
Because you would think that if it was something to do with sort
orders, you would be able to make it happen fairly reliably but I
can't.
But it was definitely happening, so it's it's got a bug but the bug
maybe not what I would expect it to be.
There we go.
So yeah, I mean one of the problems with having this much stuff on the
screen is like, looking at that crazy amount of stuff that has to get
sorted in order for this to happen.
You know, but you can see there there.
It's picking the incorrect sort order.
So I guess in this case, I could go see if we ever actually hit those
cases.
So maybe it's just so I can see whether or not the problem is that
they're just never occurring.
So, it definitely knows.
So it's a case of a cycle and you know what it is in a cycle set,
isn't it?
You can see that it's bright and itself up.
So, I wonder if that only happens when it's in a cycle.
Go see here.
We're not going to cycle.
Now we're in a cycle is wrong.
Okay?
So that cycle detection is actually pretty handy, isn't it?
We can see immediately that it happens specifically when we're in a
cycle.
So that's okay.
We can sort of defer that for a little while until we get some real
Sprites in here and see to what extent when the bounds are correct.
How often we get those Cycles.
But at least now we know that there is a concrete explanation for why
we're getting that incorrect sort.
Thank you mr.
Cycle detection.
In.
Okay.
All right, q a we could do some Q&A.
Yeah, I mean I think the size like I think the key is never break a
cycle in the front behind pair like that's not an okay place to break
the cycle.
Like that always needs to be part of the sort.
You know.
Another quiet day on the handmade here, Frontier.
well, since there are no questions, I can take this long question,
which is not really on topic, but
Oh well okay sorry someone just put in a question from that.
Is on topic.
Will there ever be a case?
When the characters facing direction will change?
What we want for the sort order, I can think of a possible case.
If the characters had arms does the current method, take these cases
into account
Yeah, I think.
I think this one since the brain is the thing that can specify out
those sort orders, it knows all that stuff so it knows the facing
Direction, it knows whether the head and the body are attached knows.
Whether there's a glove, there knows everything.
So it should be the case that we can have complete flexibility to
switch mandatory sort rules based on game State.
We don't have to hard code, it like oh, this character is always
sorted this way.
So that's kind of cool.
Needless says looking forward to be watching that syndication from
early on.
I don't think I quite follow that live.
So may blo all I really I realized that I was thinking about it the
wrong way.
I was thinking we have a sort graph.
I need a way of conveying to the renderer that there are edges in this
sort graph that I want it to add but that was a the wrong way to think
about it.
Instead what I should what I should have thought about or what I then
did think about was we always do.
This comparison is in front of to generate the edges at sort time.
So all I really need to do is modify that test so that I can tweak the
sort keys with special pairing information so that when two things get
compared that have to have us for the restored order, they you know,
we'll sort in the proper order.
So it basically just I forced the is in front of to do the work so
that it will generate the right edges rather than trying to pass the
edges down.
That's all.
All right.
So, now onto the long question, I'm the communications director at a
game development studio in Montreal.
I haven't been to Montreal since I was like 12 or something or 14.
How old was I 1450?
I could have been as old as 16.
We went on a skiing trip.
I grew up in Massachusetts.
It wasn't that far away.
I just found your stream minutes ago and it's very fascinating.
Thank you.
Your trailer seems to convey the idea that a game is better.
If it's entirely hand made from scratch.
Do you feel again can't be made with as much love if it uses a premade
engine as opposed to one that's made entirely from scratch.
Do you not feel like Reinventing the wheel may be a waste of time so I
guess there's two parts to that question.
And the first part is the trailer, conveying the idea that game is
better.
If it's entirely hand made from scratch and do I feel like again
camping with much love if it's user prevention as opposed to one
that's made entirely from scratch.
And what I would say is I know I don't think that a game can't be made
with as much love it uses a premade engine because I don't think
That.
So really the approach to the game development precludes?
How much love there is in the development?
I think probably, you know certain things don't go hand-in-hand with
love so if your primary goal is to make money, then you aren't making
a game with very much love.
That's kind of just obvious, right?
So there's certain things about the sort of exterior part of making a
game that could mean that you aren't going to make it with very much
love, but I don't think your choice is whether to use
A premade engine or using a your own stuff really has to do with that.
However, I do have a corollary to that which is I do think that if you
don't use a premade engine if you actually do finish a game chances
are it probably has a lot of love in it, right?
Because in order to do all the work of making a game from scratch,
it's a lot more work, right then going and grabbing a premade engine.
So it
Is probably the case that if someone made everything from scratch, you
know, there's a lot of love in there.
Whereas if someone uses a premade engine, you don't know, right?
Maybe there is or maybe there isn't and you'll have to go see, right?
But you know these days certainly if someone's going to make a game
from scratch I think that is a labor of love and that's kind of the
proof is right there and it doesn't mean it's going to be a good game,
you know, but in terms of whether the person love what they do, I
think they have to endure do that.
Because why wouldn't you just go by, you know, if
All you're trying to do is get a game out there to make money or
whatever, you know, sure.
Go use a premade engine, why not?
I mean, right.
So I do think there is a little bit of a secondary correlation there.
That's sort of like handmade stuff.
Probably has more love into just like in the real world.
You know, if someone, you know, Cooks the dinner from scratch there's
probably a lot more love in there than putting one in the microwave.
I mean, that's just, that's just how that is.
And, you know,
If I don't know how to say it in any other way but like I said, I
think since even if you use a premade engine, I don't want to apply
the microwave thing to liberally there because even if you use a
premade engine, it could be a ton of work to make a game right like
making all the art for it and and that sort of stuff.
You know, there can be a ton of work that goes into that so it can
still be a labor of love even if you use a premade engine, that's not
that doesn't preclude.
Which is why I say well it may be more likely that the game had a lot
of love behind it.
If it's made from scratch, it's certainly not in any way impossible
for there to be a lot of love behind it.
When you use a premade engine and we've seen that, you know, I mean, I
think you can easily go out there and find games that used pre-made
engines, where it was pretty clear that the people who made it really
loved what they were doing.
And you know, I mean, we know that's the case, right?
So that said, on to the second part which is do
You're not feel like Reinventing the wheel may be a waste of time.
I've answered that before on the stream, but obviously, since you said
this is your first time, you obviously haven't heard that I am sort
of, there's, there's two sort of halves to the answer to that question
or rather not really necessarily answer the question.
But to explain to you sort of the mindset here, the first half is that
this is an educational stream so I'm not trying to make this game.
Like as as the most efficient business thing to do.
Right now, I have a full-time job.
I make games separate like I, this is not, you know, this is something
I do at, for at people's educational benefit for, you know, an hour
and a half every night.
So that part is very important to consider.
So when we do things on handmade hero, we're not stopping and saying
at each point, would it be more efficient if I went and bought
something or went and downloaded some code here?
And
Used it because the point of this stream is to be educational and
teach people how to program all the parts of the game, like all of
them.
And so, it's critical that we do each part by hand in order to fulfill
that educational Mission and so that in and of itself precludes.
Even if I separate from the second part of the question, the answer,
which I'll give it a second.
That part means, we're definitely not going to be using anyone else.
Has stuff on the stream because the goal is to show how to do each
part.
And that I think has a tremendous amount of value regardless, because
everything you use was bad to be built by someone and has to be
maintained by someone.
And so educating the next sort of group of people who will maintain
the unity engine, maintain the Unreal Engine, who will make the next,
you know, system for walk navigation, whatever.
Educating those people is of crucial importance, if the people who
don't know, this stuff are ever going to have any good tools to use.
So, I think it's an
Everyone's best interest, even people who think that Reinventing the
wheel is a waste of time.
I think it's very important to realize that some segments of the Prime
Community has to engage in these activities.
If they don't, you will have nothing to use right?
In 10, 20 years, there will be no one left, who knows how to do it,
who knows, how to actually make the things you use.
So I think it's pretty clear from the educational standpoint.
Hopefully there's no argument there.
It's just obvious that some segments of us have to be
seeing these this knowledge on and working on these sorts of problems
ourselves because engine teams always will have to exist.
And although not every game developer has to have their own engine
team, some set of game developers do because they're the people who
make the engines on which the world's games run.
and you know that's something like 10 companies, 20 companies, I don't
know how many companies maintain
Serious engines these days but it's a fair number of them, right?
And you're talking about thousands and thousands of programmers that
need to know this stuff at the very minimum rate.
Furthermore, as a sort of Aunt, like, add on to that question or to
that part of the answer.
Even if you don't ever build these things yourself, I think there's a
tremendous amount of value in understanding how it works because even
if you decide to use someone else's game engine, which a lot of
people, you know, probably
We should do.
If you're using someone else's game engine understanding how it works.
Is crucial for you being able to get the most out of it.
If you open up Unity or unreal and you have no idea, you're just like,
I don't know.
I just know what it showed in the tutorials.
I have no idea how Graphics works.
I have no idea how these things operate.
Then you're often going to find yourself in situations where you're
very limited in what you can do, even in that pre-made tool because
you
Understand what's going on.
And so there's also an educational benefit even if you're never going
to be an engine programmer, you're just going to be a gameplay,
programmer always sits on top of this stack having that knowledge can
be incredibly valuable and it makes you a much more effective
programmer, if you can go.
Oh, all right.
Well, this is kind of messed up in unity, but I know how these sorts
of systems works.
I can work around it this way, right?
That's incredibly powerful thing for you to have at your disposal.
so, when you're working on a game, even in someone else's engine,
And that goes double for things like unreal where your you get the
source code.
I mean you can go in there and fix things you can go in there and see
why something is not working.
If you have the knowledge of how these things work, you're empowered
to be a much more powerful game developer on the programming side.
Anyway, then if you didn't know them,
So the second part of the answer as to whether I think so taking it to
the total face value.
So let's assume there.
This was not educational and the question is do I feel like
Reinventing the wheel is a waste of time?
My answer to that has kind of been said, like I said before on the
stream but the point I would really underscore there is there's an
underlying assumption to that question.
And the assumption is that somebody made a wheel at some point, right?
It's kind of a very leading question because if you think about what
that means, you're equating today's game technology that you can go
download or buy with one of the most fundamental and well, perfected
inventions of like human history, right?
And so you're presuming, we've hit a certain point of efficiency and
elegance that I don't think we've actually hit.
And so if I were to draw out where I
Why?
What?
I think that question.
If you actually apply it to the game industry, looks like it's like
someone showing me this
And being like, I don't understand why you're remaking Wheels.
We already have great Wheels, like, look at how awesome they are.
Right?
And it's like yeah I mean you know maybe if the roads are driving on
look like that all the time that those are good Wheels but you know in
reality my friend you know roads look like this and it's not so good.
Right?
And so I think the the sort of more
Realistic way of looking at the current state of game development is
no one has anything.
Even close to a wheel these days.
I've certainly never seen one unity and unreal and, you know, Source
or whatever.
At the these engines are so far from being in the category of wheel
like like, you know,
This thing can't even draw a good one.
You know this is where we're at and this is what we would like to have
so you know I don't ever feel like making something from scratch.
These days is Reinventing the wheel because the wheel hasn't been
invented yet
Right?
So what you're really doing, when you make something from scratch a
component, a whole engine, whatever it is, is you're trying to invent
the wheel.
You're working on inventing the wheel because nobody's invented a
wheel and, you know, who knows?
Maybe, you'll figure it out.
And if you keep saying, don't try to reinvent the wheel because you
think you have a wheel.
Well, what I can guarantee you is, you'll never get a wheel.
The easiest way to prevent yourself from ever inventing.
The wheel is to think you've already invented the wheel.
But you haven't I mean trust me on this one.
If you think that game development will look like booting up unity in
50 years from now it there's no chance, right?
We'll be so far past that as you know as long as people do keep trying
which I think they will, I mean Unity itself will keep trying and so
will epic and so will other people and so will you know teams all
around the world, right?
So to me,
I definitely think that development, sort of falls into two
categories.
There's the category of trying to push the state-of-the-art forwards
and that is necessarily from scratch programming.
And then there's the idea of just trying to make a specific game, and
that may have nothing to do with it, right?
If that game does not require any improvements to the current
technology, then you can do it without trying to invent.
Aunt.
New stuff.
But I for one have always been a game technologist.
So in my mind, I don't care about those games and it's not that I
don't want to play them.
I do.
I just don't want to make them, right?
I'm not interested in making a game that anyone could just make with
some off the shelf tools right now.
That is a game, I might want to play because I I'm a game player, so I
do play games.
So I like that people are doing it, but that's not what I want to.
Work on during the day, what I want to work on at my job is
technology, that enables games we can't make today, right?
And that's why I say to me it's never been a case of Reinventing the
wheel, it's in case of inventing the wheel.
So that's really where the heart of this dream comes from is that I
would like to share that sort of
I guess that love of of technical programming that's about trying to
build things yourself and see what you can do.
I want to encourage that and share that with people who also want to
do that.
I'm not trying to convince someone who'd be perfectly happy making a
game in unity to do something else.
If you are happy doing that, then that is what you should do.
But if you have this desire to push,
Technology for words, that's the person.
I'm trying to talk to if that makes sense or for who for whom this
stream is designed now on handmade hero.
We don't like drastically push the art of 2D games for words at all
because it's an educational stream.
So you know I'm not trying to say that we're going to make some 2D
engine that does things.
No one's ever seen.
Before although we have done some things already that are kind of new
and novel like our Loop Live code editing was pretty great.
We did we're doing.
Christianity system that are producing.
So we are taking some places where we can show how to maybe try some
things that haven't been tried before, but on an educational stream,
where your programming on stream, only an hour a night, you know,
we're not, we're not trying to push the envelope certainly.
But the idea is to show the act of programming at a serious technical
level.
So that after handmade hero, you've got your compulsories down, you
understand how to build a game engine from scratch all the parts.
And so
And, you know, I hope that people will go out and become technology
explorers from there because, you know, once you've done the
compulsory is with me on the stream.
Now, you have that basis to step forwards.
So I also don't mean to suggest that handmade hero is going to have
some kinds of crazy engine revelations in it.
That again is also outside the scope of what I can do.
But I do think what I can do is encourage people to learn those
compulsories and then go out and
Do great work, right?
And I think there are probably some people who, you know, you know,
will do that.
I didn't know if that would happen.
I started.
But based on sort of things I've seen come out of the community
already.
I think that's actually a goal that sort of becoming realized, which
is awesome.
So, that's kind of the entire answer, the question in a nutshell.
I hope that gives you some better perspective on the idea.
And just to clarify.
Yeah so I do think yeah if you're if your primary goal with making a
game is just to make money, then you're definitely not making it with
love, right?
If a game is being made with love, then it means that your primary
goal in life was to make that game.
And that doesn't mean that you can't, that doesn't mean you can
somehow do it without having money, right?
You need money to survive.
So you still sell the game and you still try to make money with it
certainly.
I mean, you do everything you can to make sure the game makes money in
the end so that you can keep doing what you love, right?
So it's, it's I'm not suggesting that
Should give your games away for free.
I think that absolutely not but yet your goal has to be that the
reason you want money is to make games.
Not the reason you make games is to make money because if you know
obviously that's at that point, just a commercial product to you.
It could have been anything.
It doesn't have to be a game, could be anything right?
And there's no love in that except maybe loving money, which, you
know, is a separate thing.
And I've definitely done both kinds of work in the past.
You know, I've done work, where I've been doing it strictly like this
was a passion project and I've done work, we're just like this was
just it's what I was paid to do and I did it right.
So you know it's also sort of a tracer on that.
Is it?
It is it is in every real sense of the word, a luxury to be able to
make anything.
Not even just
Not even a game.
But anything really, it's a luxury to be able to make it as a labor of
love, right?
Because you know human beings need to survive.
You can't just make getting especially games which require
Tremendous amount of money just to even have the equipment writing.
You have to buy a computer to begin with is a very expensive piece of
equipment, even just for starters and the time and so on.
So you know it's it's an honor a lot of times and a privilege,
certainly, if you can do something as a labor of love and you know, I
wish that that were not the case.
You know, I wish that everyone who, you know, had it in their heart to
dedicate themselves to
Making something artistic like that had the capability to do so but
that's not the reality of the world, we live in.
So you know, it's definitely always if you do find yourself in a
position where you can make something that you love and you have the
financial stability to do that.
That's that's really definitely kind of a
A real luxury.
It's a real privilege to be able to do that.
So
All right, let me go ahead and close up shop.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me, for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and it comes to the source
code.
So if you're someone who wants to tweak with the source code to play
around with it, you can always do that.
It's always available to you.
The forums are also available.
We've got a good site there where people answer your questions so if
you have questions about stuff, we did in the Stream or trying to
follow along at home, that's the place to ask them.
We have a patreon page if you want to support the video series, like I
said, oh, is available free of charge.
So, it's just if you're if you're want to be a nice person and support
us, we also have a schedule bot, which treats the schedule you if
you're trying to catch the stream live and know like when we're going
to be on Twitch live so that you can participate in the chat or ask
questions you can you can subscribe to that Twitter feed or just look
at it on the page and then we also have an episode guide made by the
amazing.
Raising me blow who it's just, it's incredible thing that he's done.
It's basically all of our past episodes with time-coded markers so you
can actually see like, what I worked on and what I talked about.
At each point in every episode, it's kind of remarkable when you look
back at it and and so you know bro he's very thankful to have him
working on that and he has a patron to you can subscribe to for some
reason it still is not in big bold letters, you know.
No.
It's like it's like here, right?
And I keep saying, guys, there needs to be a giant button here because
people use this thing should be like on every page.
There should be a little like support this the yeah.
Oh there.
Oh, hey.
Why it's so dark.
But at least that's their awesome.
I'm really glad that's there because yeah, I just really wanted a way
that people could could support him because basically, like a lot of
people use that episode guide and you can support him by making a
monthly pledge.
Their I I transfer some of the handmade hero patreon to him every
month as part of his patreon.
It's like a little Patron to patreon Route because it's just a great
it's a great service for everyone in the community.
Alright, that's it for today.
Thank you so much for joining me.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, I will see you guys tomorrow is Wednesday.
I and I think I'm at 8 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
So I'll see you guys, then, until then have fun programming and I'll
see you on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.