Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we go to complete game live on stream.
We are doing some work on our multi-plane rendering sort of Z's
situation as everyone probably has ever written a 2-D game knows,
there's certain concessions.
You have to make in 2D game because you're inherently sort of trying
to present something that usually
Has some amount of depth to it, but that depth is obviously not quite
real because all the illustrations are 2D and you don't really rotate.
And there's other things like this.
And what we found on handmade hero through, experimentation and
basically building a bunch of stuff that we wanted to build in
testing, how it worked, and that sort of thing.
Is that we have a pretty solid idea at this point of how we want depth
to work in the game.
And it requires a slight modification to how we submit things to the
renderer to finally sort of solidify, what it means in the world to
have depth.
And so what I did yesterday was I created sort of a example layer and
seen that sort of exhibits, all of the problems that we have with Z
right now.
That we can go through and if you'll pardon the pun, sort them out and
make it so that we can be relatively confident that the interface to
the rendering layer, accurately represents a convenient and correct
way for the game to specify what it wants to do with respect to depth.
So let's take a quick look at where we were with that again.
This is day.
296 if
If you missed the little bar at the beginning.
So day 295 source code is the source code that you want to work with
today if you're trying to follow along at home.
So here is the source as we left it.
There we go.
And you can kind of see here, how we've got a couple things even right
off the bat, you can see that there's a couple things that are a
little bit.
Wonky.
One is our sorting is kind of broken and that's kind of a consequence
of the fact that we aren't currently doing certain Z things.
The way that we should now.
It's not really this.
This makes it look worse than it.
Actually is the reason for that is that currently.
There is no way to say that something is flat or not flat.
This is this kind of gets back to it old thing that we did in the
renderer where we were saying oh there
Things that are lying flat in the world.
And then there are things that are sort of upright.
And these are two sort of different kinds of surfaces.
And the way that sorting has to work has to be different between these
surfaces, and that is something that we haven't hadn't really
addressed yet.
So there's there's, that is what's actually happening here with the
rectangles that are being drawn as the squares that I'm jumping on
sorting in front of some of the character sprites that's what's
happening.
They're effectively is rectangles we never bothered to set that path.
Now, you know, I could be wrong about this but I think and let me just
double-check, I'm not actually sure about this.
So, let's just take a quick look here.
I think it's possible that was actually something.
When we put it in there, it might be actually something you can turn
on for any, for anything, not just bitmaps.
The fact that we just kind of lying down and that's in the object
transform, we've got this sort of upright situation and you can see
that inside World mode.
We had been setting that I believe for things like World chunks, I
guess it's not there at the moment but we certainly weren't setting it
for things like these traversable and I probably should
So what I could do there is take any transform, for example, which is
what we were doing for this object transform.
I could take that.
And when we go to start drawing like these volumes and traversable, I
could right here.
So any transform upright equals false and and so you can kind of see
the difference that that makes, right.
Like if I set that so that those are, it's understood that those
things are kind of lying flat down.
I can see that that makes sort of a subset of difference in how
sorting actually behaves, but still, you can see that we've got other
problems there, that doesn't really fix.
You can see that they're sorting problems here for example and other
things like that.
And again, these are not bugs in the Sorting.
The Sorting is working.
Exactly.
As it should, they're bugs in our ability to specify what supposed to
be where because what's supposed to be, you know, the order that
things are supposed to be drawn is very
Easy to specify if it's always constant, but it makes a bit, it makes
things more difficult when it's a little bit more flexible and can
change such as things like this, you know, stare where we'll, I'm kind
of going up, gradually, and things are getting pushed back into the
distance and you know, I'm under the floor now, but I'm going to be
above the floor in a second and this kind of all these little edge
cases in there and stuff like that.
So anyway, point being, we've got some stuff to address there and the
other the much more major thing that we have to address is the fact
that Z is currently not, doesn't actually do displacement.
Z is currently ignored in for just placements where you have say a
character whose head
Like, bobbing up above the ground or whatever, we would want to use
something like the head.
Bobbing above the ground, we would want that to be a z displacement
because it is actually a height thing.
But right now, displacements and Z don't do anything.
They literally only affect the sort order, they don't actually change
the position at all.
And so what I would like to do there is I would like to fix that so
that we do have the ability for Z to hover.
And furthermore we do also want
The ability for Z to represent things like perspective, changes as in
the case that you're seeing here where I kind of can go up and down
these floors.
We actually want that to keep working.
But the important part there to remember is we want that to occur
specifically for floors and Floors.
Only and I don't mean for the actual floor tiles.
I mean for a whole like chunk of the floor at a time like a whole
basically room, we want that.
Whole thing to go down or up as one can sort of coherent piece, we
don't want like what's happening right now with the stairwell, right?
And the reason, we don't want things like the stairwell is simply
because our art, is or is an orthographic projection.
And it really wreaks.
Havoc, we found with the players sort of sense of what's going on.
When you have some things operating in perspective and some things
operating not in perspective.
And so what we kind of want to do is avoid that problem by sort of
leaving everything on one floor in a way that is in a state that is
highly orthographic and is always going to continue to have that
orthographic.
Sort of style to it without any perspective shift.
And then only when you kind of move a whole floor up, will you see the
entire floor below?
You get, you know, shrunk down and the floors above will kind of come
in in that per standard standard perspective.
Way, furthermore, we have sort of this notion that we've got sort of
far away floors and you can see those kind of at the moment, but sort
of fogging out there, we would like the notion that
Floors above us Alpha in, as they come down, like they are currently
only we'd probably like to do a better job at that eventually, but
those far away floors.
We don't want to Alpha, we want to fog them out, not Alpha them out
because they don't get transparent.
Like, we don't start seeing through them when they're there.
Instead.
They just kind of become dimmer and sort of like give it some kind of
a little bit of a haze effect so that you can kind of get this feeling
that there was like
A painting media there or something that's making it harder to see,
right?
So that's, you know, kind of the whole situation with z.
And so we need to go through and straighten out.
First of all, how we are sending things down to the renderer so that
it has a clear understanding of what we're trying to say.
In terms of Z values of things and where they are.
And then the other thing that we have to obviously do is go and
actually sort of handle that Z in the renderer in the way that is most
appropriate, right?
So we got to add the ability for example to do that fogging and so
forth which we don't actually
I currently have now it's worth noting that even though I don't know
if Global Alpha with such a good idea,
You know at the moment that's how we're kind of doing that that
fogging and we'll sort of see if that holds up.
But something similar to it is going to occur.
Like we're going to want to set sort of a global understanding.
What I'm thinking here is that if Global Alpha was instead of V for
that might also handle our fog problems.
So instead of doing Global Alpha times color where we're sort of
reducing the the the color by that Global Alpha value.
I'm thinking that what we could do there is sort of do a, you know, an
effect.
Where we multiply the whole color that whole Global Alpha, right?
And this would be maybe like Global modulate or something like that,
right?
We multiply the that against the entire color.
So we could change both the alpha value of things and Jimmy
In addition to the alpha value, we could change the color values as
well.
Now it's a little bit it's a little bit difficult to think through
because one of the things that we haven't been particularly good about
and you know, this is another thing that we probably want to do a
little bit of a Tiding pass on at some point is we haven't been very
good about specifying whether our color values are premultiplied alpha
or non premultiplied Alpha, right?
And so, you know, when we say that
This color value comes in here, well, is this color value pre
multiplied by alpha?
Or is it not pre multiplied by Alpha because it makes a pretty big
difference?
And usually what the convention I like to use is that things are not
premultiplied alpha, alpha P.
Multiplied happens.
Later is typically the way that I like to do that and so if we go in
and take a look at like how our bitmap rendering works, for example,
or actually, you know, we can take a look at our open jail for
example.
So in here, if you take a look at what we do with color values, you
can see that we just specify the color value directly.
And since we're using premultiplied Alpha everywhere else, I'm not
sure that this is really correct, right?
And similarly if I go into, for example, our our own renderer that we
wrote
Ourselves which I guess is just render dot CPP, right?
If we take a look at what happens inside, say, the draw rectangle
quickly code, which is right here.
I'm interested to see like what were what were we saying?
The convention was there?
Yes.
You can see us pre multiply the color when it comes in here.
So you can see that this is kind of a little bit wonky, right?
And it seems to me that we should start taking this a little bit more
seriously.
And so why don't we try to fix this whole color path?
Just in one go.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm not going to do the
premultiplied alpha thing yet, although that's important for us to get
right?
So we're going to take a quick break from that and then come right
back to it.
What I'm going to do here is say that when we specify render elements
for entries, I'm
To do something cure like, you know, record color or something like
this, right?
So I can basically say, Okay, I want to store a color value, this is
the input color value and you know we don't really know what that's
going to do quite yet, but we know that everywhere that we're going to
pack a color into an entry, we want to call this store color, right?
So we passed the source, then, we've got some the destination color
and all I'm going to do right now is just pass it directly through,
right?
That's it.
So now if I went through here and I looked at every time that anyone
did a push call and store it a color right, you can kind of see here
at we're pushing bitmaps there so we can pass everything through and
that'll happen but then you can see when we push wrecked.
Well, you know, we should do the same thing there.
When we push wrecked outline, those will go through the same path.
So that's fine.
When we do a clear, we should do this here as well.
Right.
And you can kind of see how now you know, at least now we've got
everybody going through that one store color call.
So now when we do circular, we could say, okay, the convention here is
going to be the one we call store color.
We're going to take the hadamard product of the source with the
global.
So we're going to need the render group.
And we're going to say the group global modulate is going to multiply
the source.
Now, remember, if you're unfamiliar with the hadamard product, the
hadamard product between two vectors is what you might call the most
straightforward product.
That people who don't know, linear algebra.
Don't care about linear algebra, might think, was the most logical one
even, right?
We all because we're Graphics programmers, tend to think more about
products that we use a lot such as the inner product or the cross
product.
Or, you know, even an outer product maybe.
But
The hadamard product is just one word.
If you have X Y and Z and you want to take, you know, the hadamard
product I'm going to say this is, I don't know what the
Actual operator symbol is for hadamard product.
If there is one,
it might take the hadamard product between two things.
I just get the multiplication by the components.
So I'm literally just taking the corresponding elements of each should
probably write those consistently have XA, y, bz C.
I literally just write them.
As direct products of the things I'm multiplying.
So it's like, hey, take the zeroth element X zeroth element first time
went by the first element and so on.
So that's the simplest kind of product really.
It's just one that we don't use very often really color.
Blending is the primary place.
You would use it.
Let me see if there is there.
An operator?
There it is.
So it looks like maybe a little open circle.
Looks like looks like a standard, so maybe we'll just
So that's all we're going to do here.
And that modulation would allow us to do fog effects.
Now, as well as Alpha blending because what we can do is we can set
this Global modulate value to pull down our color values right now.
The problem with this is going to be, we're going to want something a
little bit fancier than this because this will allow us to do fading
out to like black.
But if we wanted to fade out to more of a white color, that's not
really going to work, right?
So we kind of knew we would need the concept of a fog value that we
blend to and you know, that's that's probably a little more, a little
more flexible for our purposes.
So the other thing we could do obviously is we could say well there's
a global modulate and then there's like a global
Sort of global color or something like this.
And so, what we could do is say, well, you know, we'll take the global
color and will blend to the global color from wherever you are.
And then, we can also have a module 8, which is a thing which
multiplies, right?
So we could do sort of a linear, could do sort of a linear blend as
well as a modulate, right?
And furthermore, we could do something where we'd say, oh, okay, maybe
what we do is just each one of these values, is the lerp for these.
so, it's more like
T Global color and Global color.
So here I can say, well alright, the way that this works is for each
element.
We're going to Loop, right?
So we'll do something like
Here's the test and the dest dot x equals the source that X.
And I'm going to go ahead and pull out the T value is group global.
Oops.
T Global color and the color value is going to be Global color.
And so then in here we can do each one of these is alert between
whatever the source color is.
And how far we want to go towards that that Global color, right?
So now if we want to modulate we actually can modulate by just setting
C20 and TV the modulation value.
But if we want to blend towards a color, we can also do that by
setting the color value to something other than 0 and T being the
amount that we should blend to it.
Right?
And if we want to, we can also reverse the sense of these so that,
that if we wanted it to be modulation, but I think I'm going to say
instead of modulation, I'm going to actually make
It'd be sort of the inverse of modulation meaning the higher, the
value goes, the more you blend towards the color because that way I
can do in it 2-0, so, meaning you initialize everything.
The 0d key Global color will be all zeros and won't have any effect,
which is, I think maybe a little more consistent with the way.
I've been programming things.
You know.
I don't know if that'll work properly or not, we'll find out but here
we go.
And you know what?
These should really be our G.
Be a right?
So that is all I really wanted to do with storing the color.
So, this way, every time we put a color on there, we just do a quick
little bit of math op on it there.
And then, these things can be set by the game.
So, inside all of the stores, we just need to pass the group, which is
not ownerís because, you know, we always have that any time that we
were storing anything.
Anyway, we don't have to initialize this anymore because it will
automatically get initialized to 0.
So that's good.
And anytime we're setting the globe, Alpha here, you can see a setting
the global
Four for each entity.
And so in here, what I would say is okay, we don't really need to set
this quite the same way, but what I would say is we probably want to
start by saying, well,
let's see which of the three cases were in because unlike before where
we were always fading, we're not feeding any more were
Feeding on one side or sorry.
We shouldn't I should say, we're not always fading.
We're fading on one side, which is the stuff that comes down from the
top.
But we're going jogging out below us, right?
And just to be clear on what the difference between those two is right
with something like a fade, we're actually talking about being able to
see through it, right?
So we're talking about, you know, if here's the I point, right?
And here is a layer and here is a layer.
What we're talking about here is, okay, we're going to be able to see
through to this layer.
And this thing right here will be at some percentage of pasady like,
50% opacity or something like that, that's layers that are that are
kind of in between the camera and where the player is standing.
So those are actually going to have Alpha fade in them, right?
But then there's stuff that's that's like that we see through down to
their lower levels of the dungeon that stuff should never be
transparent.
You can never see through it but it should get hazier, right?
So what we want to do there is blend to a color so that we're sort of
mixing we're mixing away from the actual color of whatever the thing
is towards a
X fog color, which would be like a dark, Misty, whatever, you know.
All right.
So we want to start by saying that in the normal case where we don't
have any blending going on the render groups.
Global color is going to be, well, we don't care what it is.
We just know that the T Global color is going to be all zeros.
Because we don't want to blend it to it at all.
Then if we do either of these two, we can still keep the global Alpha
value concept here.
Like right the, the T value that we computed, we can still use the
computation we were using because it seemed to be okay.
But what we want to do is now prep these other things a little bit
more appropriately.
So Global color in the case of fading out, the bottom is going to be
our Haze color.
Right?
So you know I don't
Know what this should be, you know, maybe we'll set it to something
like, 0.5, 0.5 0.5, or something like that.
In our tea, Global color is going to set how much of that we want to
contribute and we want all teas, and then a 0.
And the reason we want the zero is, we don't want to adjust the alpha
value anything, right?
We just want to set those, we just want to blend the color.
So this allows me to blend in the color here and not blend in the
Color in the alpha and just leaves the outfit whatever whatever it is.
In fact I can nuke that as if you know those that fourth parameter now
will not have any effect similarly here where I've got
Will color.
I don't really care about what the color values are because I'm not
really trying to change the color values.
All I'm trying to do is is change the alpha value so that it fades
out.
So this is exactly the opposite here.
I'm basically saying, you know, let's keep the T value but let's get,
let's zero out.
Let's get the T value for the alpha but let's do it out for all the
colors, so that we don't affect the colors at all, right?
So, that's how we would set our off.
Up.
And then down here, we're clearing it back out, we can just against it
to you level Alpha equal to all zeros in that will get rid of any
blending that was going on.
Whoops, Global color.
Now what you can see here is that we always use the same T value for
color and Alpha.
So one thing I could do as well as just have, I'm sorry, I always use
the same T value for all the colors and then one t value picture for
the alphas and they're always sort of one or the other, so we probably
could be less flexible than this.
But at the moment I don't know that there's a whole lot of a reason
for us not to be but it's worth pointing out.
Okay, so now we still have a lot of work to do because
We're not quite well, we definitely we have a bug as well, but we're
not quite handling the alpha multiplication stuff correctly yet
either.
So I got to have to go fix that in a number of other places.
So first of all, let me just make sure that these things are at all
correct.
Like I said, we complete compute these teas.
So for example, when we're fading out at fade top, we want to fade
towards a zero Alpha value for whatever we're working with.
and I believe,
That it was a bug in here.
Like I was saying in the opengl layer.
I went looking at it that it wasn't pre multiplying that
So if it's not going to be multiplied that and I think that you know,
looking at this if we want to just set these colors down and not pre
multiply them typically, I think that's going to be a good idea and I
think what we should do is just do it in the pack function.
So I think what we should do is come over here to the renderer where
we were doing that, pre multiplication.
And you can see us pretty multiplying the color up front here.
Where we do this pre multiplication?
I think we're going to want to do is we're going to want to roll that
pre multiplication to the calling code.
So we just don't pre multiply things anymore, pretty much ever, right?
So I'm going to come in here and take that out.
I'm going to take it out of the pre multiply here.
And here.
and,
I should probably also take a second here to label these things
correctly as well.
So, in some of this stuff, when we record these values coming through,
maybe I can go ahead and set them in render group.
So that it says specifically whether their pre multiplied or not.
So, for example, we've got clear, this is pre multiplied, clear?
This is pre multiplied, this is pre multiplied, right?
So it's just n pre-multiply.
Clear doesn't really mean much of anything but it's just so, you know.
Hey, these values are always going to be pre multiplied through the
whole pipe from here on out, so get used to it, right.
So let's go ahead and keep picking that up.
So this is going to be PML color.
And when we do store color, what I'm going to do then is say, well,
okay, what I'm producing this information, what I would need to do is
once I have that Alpha value, right?
Now, need to always multiply that the color values by that, so that
the color values are always premultiplied, right?
So here is my Primo color.
Let's keep going.
Where's my Primo color?
It is.
And now we got to fix it in here as well.
We'll color
Oops.
Color.
Primo color.
And adhere same deal.
And again, you can see all these being used as premultiplied.
Let me look at opengl rectangle.
Opengl rectangle color.
So there's yep.
All good.
And this is a Primo color as well.
I will make that explicit.
And so, let's see.
Color is not a member of.
Let's here we go.
This is mostly just search and replace at this point.
So, let's pop back now and see because I'm sure we've got problems now
to deal with, but I think that's a little bit more correct to the
pipeline so that we can get, we can be a little bit clearer about
where things are supposed to be premultiplied and where they're not.
Let's also briefly
Make sure that our other renderer is working, okay?
so that
Definitely has a pretty significant color change though.
But only for filled rectangles.
Which is a little odd.
So why is that the case?
Who's wrong here?
I suspect.
It might be opengl by the way, so opengl when it's drying and it
disables texture 2D and it's drawing in a color, but blend should
still be on, right?
I wonder if the GL colors are getting premultiplied automatically.
That's a good question.
So if we do a GL color 4fv, does it pre multiply that color?
Well no, no, I'm about to, I'm out to lunch there.
I was thinking of gamma correction, which has nothing to do with that.
But yeah, now that I think about it.
So when we're doing gamma correction on these values I guess I don't
know if GL gamma corrects the GL color 4fv color that you specify or
if it doesn't gamma correct it.
I'm not sure how it interprets.
The color you know when you're in your own Shader it's very clear what
that would do because you wrote it out, whether it does or doesn't
But I don't actually know.
But anyway, let me take a quick look.
After render dot CPP and that'd be in draw a rectangle.
So, let's see.
Draw rectangle.
Draw a rectangle.
Is copying out.
The are why is it doing that?
I don't know why it's doing that.
So draw a rectangle multiplies, the color value by 255 to get it into
the right space, which seems totally fine.
And then,
let's see, set 1ps
It doesn't Square the color.
So the color is not gamma corrected, right?
I see no gamma correction here.
So I think if I'm not mistaken that would probably be the difference,
right?
So this color value is not modulating anything and so opengl would
presumably take whatever that color value is that comes in and when it
writes it out, whatever that color value is, it's going to do the
conversion back to.
It's going to
To write it to the frame buffer, right?
And so, I'm not sure what we want to do with that.
Let me see if we do now, we do.
Okay.
So we m m Square are, dest r, g and B.
I'm just not sure how we want to approach this.
That's almost certainly the difference between the two of us, right?
I would think oh, well, I'm wrong.
I would have assumed that that was the primary difference would be
whether or not we were gamma correcting r g and B values.
Hmm.
this definitely seems like the kind of thing where
We're having a better handle on exactly what open Jill's doing would
have been nice, right?
Like, I'd like to know exactly what it's doing in there because this
looks relatively sane to me, what we're doing is what I would expect.
However, I would think that this, I wouldn't have expected them to do
this, right?
So, if you take a look at what I'm doing in that code, I'm squaring
our colors which is gamma correcting the color.
Basically, I'm doing gamma D, gamma blend re gamma and in
Angele here.
You know I'm specifying this color for a v.
I know it's going to D gamma whatever the results are because it's you
know actually I should say we're looking at this path, right?
It's going to D gamma whatever the results are.
That's true, but I don't know what it does.
With the modulation color, I would assume
It doesn't gamma correct them.
And so I would assume that the problem here would be that we were
gamming it and they weren't.
But that only seems to make things, you know, I guess I wouldn't say
worse, but it certainly doesn't help, right?
You can see the color is very dark there.
And switching this too.
Not have the gamma correction on the way in.
Just really doesn't seem to make any difference.
And as you can see, all of our bitmap paths are exactly as you would
expect.
So those are still exactly the same.
All right, so let's take a look at the open GL code and see if I could
figure out what it is that it's actually doing in there.
It's calling calling opengl rectangle and opengl rectangle is just
setting the color for f with whatever the Primo color is.
so,
Yeah, I just don't see it.
I don't see where we're diverging there.
but we obviously are
And, you know, we've got blend on and we've got one - Source Alpha on.
And that's what we would be doing here, right?
We're doing our blend.
With all of our textiles were textiles is just a solid color now,
right?
It's just, it's just the dest.
Oh, I'm an idiot.
This is the frame, buffer read.
I was thinking of this one here.
Yeah I bet that was dumb.
Let's try that one more time.
So squaring the incoming color.
This is the alpha correction for the incoming color, right?
Not the desk.
It's called desk.
You'd think I would know that if something was called desk that, it's
not the source, but, hey, it's been a long day, that is probably the
problem.
And let me just see her.
Not a good sign Texel are.
Cole's M Square.
So if anything that made it worse, that suggests that they are and we
just need the 2.2 in order to match.
So it's just not enough of a power.
Let's check out what happens if we end this.
Is going to be awful speed wise, but if we actually do a power
function there, right?
So if we just had a better, if we were just closer to the gamma curve,
we could take a, we could take a shot at that and see what it actually
was.
So, okay,
Oh well won't actually cuz we can just do it ahead of time.
So we have our textile RGB here and we're going to
Take that incoming color, which is the RGB.
I don't know why we M square that because the incoming color is not
changing.
So I don't know why, I guess we must have just copied the source in
there because you probably never care about doing this one.
But
all I have to do for that is I can just do you know
this and we should be now exactly the same as we were right.
Or not.
Is this because of the 255?
Color RGB.
These are all set for marjane being a
The max level you should be 25 times 25.
So the squaring
Yeah, of these guys has to be after the X, which is also a little
confusing there.
So I don't know.
It doesn't make a lot of sense to me.
What's going on here?
I got to be honest because that should be like all we're doing is
doing squaring to render to do the gamma correction.
And if you look, when we toggle the colors of the bitmaps that are
going through the same process, hardly changed at all but the colors
of solid fill.
Rectangles are drastically different, right?
And so I don't understand what it is about our past.
We've got some very specific deviation
From the way open gel is processing these colors but I really just
don't know what it is.
And
You know, if it's not gamma correction then I could turn off, you
know?
If it was just that they weren't gamete
Doing it.
Then I would suspect that doing this.
Well actually.
That's actually a little bit interesting.
Now that I think about it.
Hold on one second here.
So in here, when we load the destination,
we're then squaring the destination and we're squaring it in 0 to 255
space which means that the incoming color needs to actually be in
squared space but not gamma corrected if we wanted it to match opengl
which means that the color values would actually all have to be
multiplied by 255 again.
To be in linear space.
Does that make sense?
I don't know if it does.
But I'm talking about this, right?
And that's kind of crazy but that's just what I was thinking and I
wanted to see what it was.
Hey, look.
That's almost exact.
All right.
Did you guys catch that?
That's one of those subtle things.
I'm particularly bad at code like this, probably, because I was never
an old-school rendering guy, but you see what was happening there.
We were in 0 to 255 space because that's the most convenient way for
us to have done the blending.
That's the way we were doing the blending if that makes any
so, you know, we have numbers that are between 0 and 255 to do are
blending
Because we're loading in 8-bit values that are already in there and we
don't want to have to convert them to float for no reason.
So we have numbers that are between 0 and 255, but then because of of
gamma correction we're squaring those values, right?
So that takes it from 0 to 255 to a 0 to 55 squared, right?
That's actually the range now of those values.
So if we Square the values that they're coming in for our color,
that's
Because now those values, right?
We multiply them by 255 and then we were squaring them, right?
And so that would produce the proper range.
So, essentially like times 255 to go from the 0 to 1 range of the
incoming color to the 0 to 55 range, right?
That's a times 255.
That's fine.
But then we need to somehow get to a range between 0 to 25 squared,
right?
And so the squaring used to do that but if we don't want to gamma
correct, we don't want a square but we still have to put it into
Strange.
So we need an extra x 255 in order to put it into the same space as
the as the source dest reads that were doing up from the frame buffer,
which is getting gamma corrected, right?
Okay.
So now we're matching properly and so I think that definitively
answers our question, which is that opengl does not gamma correct that
value, right?
The color value is not gamma corrected at all.
It's just a multiplied.
So basically, you know, like
Doodly Doo be Doo.
This value.
This value right here is never gamma corrected.
Just point it out.
Okay, so now we just have to figure out why we're not setting this
value correctly, because obviously, we are not setting a correctly.
So I need to go into the render group and probably do a little break
point action to sort of see what I messed up here because I have some
mess something up here.
All right.
As you can see us, slurping color values.
All each by component and then we're multiplying by the alpha to give
us a premultiplied version of the destination and that's what our
story.
So, what we would expect here is you would expect to see these colors
affecting our entities as we go through and here we are in World mode.
Setting them up, right?
You can kind of see them getting set here when we have the camera in a
certain ranges, we expect that operation to take place and do its
This thing, right.
And you can see here in the rendering code right here.
We're going to the peace.
All of these push bitmap calls should be inheriting.
This render group information that we set up here.
And so the question is, why aren't we seeing anything?
It's like these values aren't literally aren't having any effect at
all, and that's not what we would expect.
We would expect to at least see something happening there.
And so we're obviously getting something very wrong and so I'm going
to go ahead and take a look here.
Let's T RGB and a two-level color.
Yeah yeah so that I mean it doesn't look obviously wrong.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to set a breakpoint in the
code for sort of what I suspect will be the most obvious place where I
can watch some of that.
Happening Embassy going to see if I can spot some Shenanigans
happening in our code.
That that tells us what the bug is.
So here we are at fade top fade, bottom
And I'm going to go ahead and look at Food top because that's an alpha
fade, and it's the one that's most obviously in our face and wrong.
So we should be able to do something about that.
So let's take a look at a t-value, we've got a 0.3 T value here.
And so we're setting up the render group in a particular way.
Let's see what we're actually getting there.
Here is the render group.
We've got T Global color, we've got that 333333 there in the W
component, right?
And yeah, that's
That's all good.
See here Global colors.
All zeros is what you would expect.
So now we just need to go watch this particular entity actually record
something, hopefully that it wants to draw, and of course, it's not
going to.
So, that's unfortunate.
Let's try one more time.
Here's the T.
Value of zeros, not going to help us.
Come on, give us T value.
Why are these two values always zero?
Probably because this is something that's way out of bounds.
Those are basically all 0 and we need one.
That's not going to be 0.
I could set a breakpoint inside this Loop.
So what I could do is say if T is greater than 0.1 or something.
And now we've got a little handle there.
We can break on
So now we know that t is going to be something other than that.
So let's take a look and see if we can get someone who actually
renders.
Something of course, not.
Oh wait, but dry hit points would if it had well but it won't have any
points.
It's got a traversable do.
Well, this will be fine.
I don't know why.
I was so worried this will be fine, right?
So here's our push wrecked, call here is our called the store color,
you can see what RTC and Source are and here is what our desk will be.
So our T value is what we'd expect the .333 there are C value is 0,
which is what we want.
Our source value is just some input color, which seems totally
plausible.
We compute the destination Alpha,
And the destination is Alpha value is, as we would expect less than
what it should be.
It's point three of the way towards zero, which is
What we would want, we have the Death Star, G, and B values.
And those are getting blended as just the source times.
Whatever that destination Alpha is.
So you can see the destination r g and B.
So let's compare that quickly to the source.
I'm going to go ahead and set the source.
RGB.
Oops.
And the test RGB just so we can verify that they are actually
different and you can kind of see that they definitely did get
modulated down so that desk value does look like a properly Source.
Modulated value the alpha that's coming out in it is obviously you
know less and the colors are modulated we return it and we store it in
Primo color.
So now I'm not quite sure why we're not seeing
Alpha fading that we would expect to see on any of these things.
Right?
Because what we're seeing here is we're not we're not seeing any of
that fade, right?
Right?
You can see everything is getting drawn at full opacity and I'm not
sure why, because we are actually passing those premultiplied Alpha
values.
So what we would expect to see here is we'd expect to see those things
Fade Out.
And I guess I can do, you know, a couple little checks here, you know,
I can, I can make certain that we're not doing anything to incredibly
stupid.
Like in the opengl renderer where we do GL color for Fei.
Could here, for example, just say, well, what would happen if I was to
set everything to 50 percent Alpha, right?
I should see.
Oops.
I should see everything at half a paucity and if for some reason, I
don't then we've got another issue.
Who knows what it is, but we've got one.
Okay, so that oh, well, duh.
That is not the right one.
I want this guy, so in opengl rectangle,
Choose this guy.
If I was to take this Primo color and multiply it all by 0.5, right?
Which is when I pass it here,
I should see all of those rectangles Fade Out at half.
And I do.
So, the question is, why is the entry Primo color on the rectangle?
Still wrong?
Is it something?
Where I forgot one of them in here and we're not calling store color
right?
Which seems pretty plausible.
That we could have forgotten one.
All of those are calling store color though, so that's not
particularly are we clearing that value to soon would be the other one
liked down here?
Are we we're resetting that for for some part of it, right?
Where we set the tea Global value here.
But now, that that shouldn't have any problem with it and I guess I
can check that like, draw hit points or something.
Isn't.
Isn't being weird there.
I don't know where dry hit points.
Actually, is there it is.
That's totally fine.
Shouldn't do anything weird.
So something is happening negatively to this when we're calling to
render the traversable but I don't know what it is.
And
They're both using entity transform.
And they're both using Color values that are totally normal.
So what's the deal?
I'm going to go ahead and set a breakpoint.
In my opengl renderer.
Where is my opengl renderer?
I guess it's not there.
Then I'm going to set a breakpoint in.
Opengl render commands.
So when we come down through here, I kind of just want to see what
these entry Primo colors tend to look like.
Just so I can get a feel for, you know, why are they always the same
thing?
So,
give the thing I could do is tag these guys.
With some additional information.
I will say not seeing a lot of modulated colors there.
Which is a little bit weird.
I don't know.
Is that seem weird to you?
What would be drawing all of those colors?
Well, I guess those
Be things that are we're drawn.
We don't draw, we draw everything kind of further away first and we
draw the top stuff so it would be a little bit difficult for us to
figure out which one those are.
Fortunately, I could use a little trick here.
That would make things a little easier to debug.
What I can do is say all right when we do a render entry and this is a
trick, I use a lot when you don't have good debugging facilities.
like basically, like if you don't have years of debug code systems and
stuff like this to draw on,
What you can do is, when you have a render group entry like something
like this, you can say that if you're in handmade internal mode or
like, I guess handmade slow, might be the best way to say it.
What you can do is you can tag these guys, right?
So, you can introduce a tag value here, right?
It's like debug tag.
And then what I can do is I can just specifically say that I want to
tag some
It goes through the pipe and I want to see it come out the other end
so that I know whether it's doing something weird or not.
So what I can do is say, hey, if entry header or I should say,
If entry header.
like, so if the debug tag,
Equals, you know, whatever number it is, whatever one I'm looking for
then in break here, equals true, right?
So it's like this is where we can stop.
And so what I can do is say, well, when we push that debug, when we
push that entry on, and if I want to, I can go to say, let's see here,
debug a group that's creepy when we do like
Push wrecked or whatever, the render element that we push on there.
We can have that take that tag value, right?
So we can do something like, say okay, there's a render group.
Which is here.
And we can always just do a thing that's like,
Debug tag.
And whenever we push one of these guys, let's see here.
Push render element.
we can do a test that says, if
And been slow is on, go ahead and give this guy.
His group's debug tag.
So now since we're sending so much stuff down the pipe but it's really
cumbersome to debug those.
What I can do is say, well, whenever I'm going to push down one of
those ones that I wanted to look at, right?
So you know something where I've got the fade value stuff happening
here.
So someone were I do Fade top.
Start I can do a thing where we go like oh the render groups.
Debug tag equals 1.
Those and then we push the van, you know, otherwise the you know, we'd
set it to zero or whatever, right?
So maybe like down here after we do the push bitmap calls or I guess
what we want to do bug.
These Guys these are the ones that are that are busted, right?
So now we're just going to get traversable is that have that property
property in theory, so what I should be able to do now is if I go to
open gel dot CPP, I should be able to set a breakpoint here and I
should know that the kind of thing that I got was one of these and it
was one of these where I tried to set the pre multiplied color equal
to something that faded out.
And you can see that it actually is set to something that's fading out
its Point 666666 here, right?
so, the color of this guy actually looks relatively correct,
And unfortunately.
It does look like a fair number of people who entered that path though
are still getting kind of clamped out there or something.
I'm not sure exactly what's happening because those values, don't look
very reassuring.
Let me take a look here.
So when we were taking this.
Well, so you know what the problem is, I bet now that I think about it
now that we look at what's actually happening.
This value of T in the past was actually, it was, it was a modulating
value, so it went the other way, right?
So it probably that those things are close the camera, they probably
would Fade Out as they got into range and then pop, but was probably
too quick for us to notice that was happening.
So that is almost almost
Certainly why we're getting those so we're actually probably doing the
correct thing but we have this the the T sense flipped, right?
And there we go.
I got to fix the the hopping code for working on.
Layers rapidly.
Okay, so that's all good now.
But now we need to do the other, the, the other Fade Out properly and
that's going to have the same problem, right?
This is actually going to want to be 1, minus t, so I think if we
should be able to just say, well, if it was going that way, we should
be able to make it go the other way, right?
Because
Our clamp map to rain should be able to take it in verse range or, you
know, and, and produce the, the mapping from one to the other
correctly.
So, I think we don't really have to do one - we should just be able to
do that.
And now it's correct, right?
So, that should still be the correct thing here.
Yes.
Okay.
So now we just have to figure out what's wrong with our bottom floors.
This T value should be going from the bottom start Z up to
Ooh, the bot down to the bottom and z and so yeah that t gets higher
as it goes which is what we want.
And we should be fading to This Global color but instead we're fading
to Black and fading to Black, doesn't make much sense.
So I'm not sure why we're getting that fade.
Let's just quickly verify that there's nothing else wrong here.
I don't see any lower values at all.
Which does not fill me with confidence.
I guess I'll make sure that isn't because that's that's in the
platform, reloadable code.
So that should have been fine.
So we have some other fun bug there
But I don't know what it is.
So let's see if we've got if we've got 0.5.
0.5, 0.5.
If we've turned off the tee Global color entirely we should see, no
modification whatsoever.
So why are we seeing a modification?
I am not sure.
Because this should be indistinguishable from the regular case.
And so, it shouldn't really be affecting their colors at all.
I should think.
And the way that this is specified.
See here.
The way that this is specified, if the T values are 0, there should be
no change to the source color so it should all it should do is pre
multiply the source color, The Source alpha or rather the source color
by The Source Alpha which is what we always wanted to do anyway and so
that shouldn't have any deleterious effects.
So why are we not seeing anything below the that that first level
there?
Oh, that's just a clear, right?
Because there isn't anything below that level
that's just actually clearing.
The global color value affecting our clear, that's actually what's
going on there.
So that's actually fine.
Okay, so now that we've got sort of a view down, let's let's go ahead
and turn on the correct blending here.
So, there we go and you can see it kind of blending out too.
Sort of a gray color there and I don't know what we actually want it
to blend out too.
I'm not sure, but we probably want to clear the screen to the same
color that were fading out to.
I'm not like I said I'm really not 100% sure what we want to do there.
So when we do our clear which is happening here we need to
set the death of alpha to 1, so that will get that sort of
Hayes effect there, right?
That might be a little bit too bright for Hayes.
I don't know.
That maybe looks a little bit better.
But I'm going to want to to have sort of a background color.
That we specify here.
Because I'm going to want that to be the thing that we fade towards
whenever we modify it.
Yeah.
so now we're sort of getting that that Haze happening and
Now, you'll notice that those are not transparent anymore, right?
Either so kind of is that Fades off into the distance there, it's
pretty satisfying, right?
And kind of see it happening back down in there and that's about
right.
Okay, so I'm pretty happy with all of that.
That seems reasonable.
Totes reasonable.
So, I will go to some Q&A.
One thing you could try is having the center of the perspective
projection be the players position, so other things on other levels
line up straight.
Well, they would only line up straight with wherever the player was
standing though.
They wouldn't.
So as you moved the levels behind you would move, which doesn't sound
good to me at all.
So I saw us the kid that had a hard transfer him.
Seems like could be used for a lot of other things.
What is it doing in handmade World dot CPP in the subtract function?
Well, I'm assuming it's just scaling the values by a non-uniform
scale.
So
I mean, I don't know I'll go look, but
That's probably the wrong thing.
But the hadamard product is sort of a diagonal matrix.
And let me tell you what I mean by that.
So let's suppose that we were going to take a vector and we wanted to
scale the vector and we do this on handmade hero all the time, right?
So I've got a vector, you know, and it's pointing in some direction
and I want it to be longer or shorter but in the same direction,
right?
And so maybe I've got a scale value, right?
And my scale value is C.
Let's say,
And so I'm going to take whatever this Vector is V and I want to
produce a new Vector.
So I do V Prime equals c times V.
Okay so if
You say for example, 2 then V Prime is 2 V.
I have a vector that's twice as long as my original Vector was for my
new Vector, right?
But now, suppose that I want to scale some scale this Vector in a way
that makes it twice as long along X, but no longer along y.
So, it's going to be exactly the same height, but it's going to sort
of skew out that way, right?
Well, you know, in 3D Graphics were very familiar with doing
non-uniform scales as matrices, right?
Because in this equation, right?
What we have is something like, well, my V Prime is like V Prime x v
Prime y, you know, as a vector two components in the vector equals c,
which is a scalar times VX and v y.
And we know that that just kind of distributes inside so we can just
do CVX cvy.
So, you know, we have V Prime x equals c.
VX and V Prime y, equals CB y but what if we don't want these to be
treated the same, right?
What if we want something more complicated here?
Well, we know we can introduce sort of an arbitrary linear transform
by just using a matrix here.
And so what I can do is I can make this a matrix equation.
Well, it's already a matrix equation but I can make it more of a
matrix equation.
If that means anything by having a scaling in x, a scaling, and Y, and
multiplying, my Vector times that, right?
That makes sense.
Now I'm going to write this in the more convenient way for
multiplication where I write the vxvy up here so you can kind of see
how it works right?
But matrix multiplication I touch on do that long time ago and
handmade hero you just take the row and the column and you multiply
them component wise together so CX X VX.
0 times, v y, which of course is nothing and then we do it.
Same thing again here, right?
0 times, v x, which is nothing.
Cy, X VI and hey, I got what I wanted.
A see Y and a CX, right?
So I scales non-uniformly by using this, which is a non-uniform
scaling Matrix.
Right.
So this is my non-uniform scaling Matrix, you would recognize it from
computer Graphics.
If it was 3 d, 1 it would have three components of as modulus.
That would have four would have a one down here, CX Cy CZ and
everywhere else it is 0.
We're very familiar with this and, you know, rotation matrices.
They have all four of them filled in blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
right.
Well, if you look at what that's actually doing, that's basically can
taking the hadamard product of the diagonal of this Matrix.
With the the input Vector.
So, in some sense, the hadamard product is just a way to write.
A diagonal matrix, as if it was a vector, it's a way to write a
diagonal Vector, which doesn't really exist in the real world of math,
right?
So one way I could look at the hadamard product, is to say that if I
was to take a vector and do the like diagonal,
Operator on this thing and produce.
The Matrix that has that Vector along its diagonal.
Well, that's this.
And then multiply it by something, right?
That's the same as taking the hadamard product with that.
Vector.
So you know.
Yeah.
Does the hadamard product have uses sure, they're basically uses where
a diagonal matrix would have would have been what you would do.
And the reason that it's not that common is usually just because
there's not that many times that you want to use just a diagonal
matrix but there are enough.
And that's why it shows up in the code.
Super killing for the record.
A circle with an X would be the tensor product.
I don't think that's true.
My recollection is that, that the thing that I drew, which I always
draw is some operator.
Right.
Like generally every book that I've ever known that introduces an
arbitrary operator uses that.
So I don't think that this means anything in particular.
I think it means something that we were doing in this branch of
mathematics right now, but I could be wrong about that.
So yeah.
Has it probably been used to write the tensor product I bet, but is it
mean that I don't know, probably means a lot of things would be my
guess.
and you'd have to just tell by the context,
JP to would it be difficult?
Implement textured or just different fog colors so you could make for
instance, vignette and fog.
Well, it's not difficult to do this but it's not something that we
would probably do in quite the same way.
And the reason that I say that is because so the reason that we're
able to sort of take a shortcut here and if you take a look, you know,
in render group,
So, here's the store color code, and this store color code does.
All of that work
Just these few lines of code, that's it and it only runs once at push
time.
But if you wanted the code to do something where you were modulating
with, or I should say, modulating fading two colors that are changing,
then we would need to make that be something that happens out in the
actual renderer, right?
So what we would have to do is rather than just setting a single color
here, we would have to set up a second texture unit or a
You know, Shader that had some procedural something in it, right?
Like for VIN getting, we wouldn't really need a texture, right?
We could do that procedurally.
If we wanted to
And then when we would set this value, instead of setting this as the
color that just is straight-up used as a modulation against the
incoming texture, what we would actually be doing is specifying what
we wanted.
The blending coefficients to be to this magical other texture that we
have, that does.
And that operation has to be done per pixel by the graphics card,
right?
So, it's not particularly hard to do, but it's definitely, it's,
you're adding a one additional layer.
Of complexity on top of what you have here which is to say that rather
than just tweaking a color.
Once you start, you have to set up another source of screen space data
to pull from before you could
before you could get that to happen.
How did you finally discover the gamma correction bug?
What was the clue that made you say aha well was I'm sorry was it?
I mean you watch me do it right?
So you saw the steps.
I'm not sure that there is any thing that makes you say.
Hi.
It's just as with any subtle like thing like that where there's just a
lot of steps involved.
You have a certain preconceived notion of what's going on and you
forget some of the little details like the fact that the range is
squared
When you write in that routine.
And so when I tested it by turning off the gamma and didn't see the
right result, I was like, huh?
That's weird.
I don't what's going on, but I knew that something was wrong because
I'm like one of these two should match and neither matches.
So then I know I have to investigate further and when I sort of
figured out the range thing that I was like, okay let me try it with
the right range.
Know gamma correction it's like okay there we go.
And so I don't think there was really a single aha, it's a series of
steps where you narrow down the, like possibilities of, what could be
wrong until you're left with something and staring you in the face.
And you go, oh, that's the one.
All right, I am going to wind it down.
All right, so that's good.
So that's like a more consistent thing and so tomorrow I think we
could maybe start on trying to I'd like to tomorrow get into the
specifying Z4.
Hover versus Z for sheathing so I think that'll put us in good shape
for tomorrow.
Let's go to the web browser.
There we go.
Thank you everyone.
Good, I can talk, it's real easy.
Thank you everyone for joining me for this sort of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along series at home, you could
always pre-order the game, which comes with the source code, so you
can play around with home.
Play around at home with the source code.
Why have I?
I gotta go to bed anyway, play around with the source.
Code and experiment with it and learn from it.
And all this other good things, you can also go to our forums.
If you want to ask questions about the series.
We can basically what that amounts to is sending up a bat signal to
Martin's Mosaic.
Oh who's somehow manages to answer.
Everyone's question on every single, handmade hero forum and he's
seems to somehow know what is wrong with everyone's code.
It's pretty amazing.
You should see it sometime.
We also have a patreon site if you want support the video series, we
have a schedule bot.
Where we treat the schedules, want to catch the seat, the episodes
live like tonight, and then we also have an episode guide.
Go to if you want to catch up with episodes that you missed past
stuff, if you're curious, if something was happening, that's the place
to go.
That's it for today.
I will see you back here tomorrow for the last dream of the week.
No, second.
Last year, we got one Wednesday and Thursday.
So for Wednesday, stream, Thursday is the last room of the week.
Same time.
Same place, a p.m.
Pacific Daylight time, hope, see all here, until then have fun
programming.
And I will see you guys on the internet.