Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we go to complete game live on stream.
We are here this weekend, the previous weekend of coding, not, I was
off last weekend with weekend before that we basically got our opengl
stuff working mostly the way that we probably want.
There's there's some additional stuff that we probably would want to
do eventually, but it's, you know, our game is kind of running pretty
nicely through opengl.
Now, everything appears to be working properly.
And yeah, we just we've gotten it to the point where, you know, the 3D
Miss of the game just kind of works and, you know, we can inspect it
in debug mode and see our Flats rights.
Even ones that intersect are using the Z bias stuff properly.
So we're pretty good to go as far as that's concerned.
So what I want to do this weekend is just sort of finish up some, some
code stuff in that open gel layer, which is kind of, still a holdover
from when we just kind of implement it.
As a basic thing.
NG.
And what I mean by that is right now, you know, we started in opengl
and I showed how to do the fixed fixed function, pipeline, to draw
stuff.
And then we switched because we decided we wanted to actually take
advantage of more features of the GPU.
So, we did actually move to a more modern opengl style where you, you
know, load shaders and this sort of thing.
So there's no more fixed function pipeline, but we still have a fair
portion of sort of the cruft of the code that's going through the
fixed function Pipeline.
And
Don't really want to do that anymore.
We can just get rid of the old fixed-function Legacy pipeline stuff,
which can be a good idea just because it's not what vendors are
expecting you to have an in-game opengl at.
This point is much too sprawling, that's definitely true.
It's just, it's to Legacy.
And as a result, you know, the sort of support surface for it is.
Just massive and it's hard for driver vendors.
To test everything you might do, right?
It's hard to test the using the fixed function pipeline, plus using
shaders set the same time in a mixed way and all that stuff.
And so since most games are not doing that anymore, most games,
especially the games that vendors care, most about which are games
that are Benchmark games, which are high-profile AAA titles that sort
of thing.
Ones where the driver authors know their company's reputation.
Depends on them running these games.
Well they're going to be more heavily testing those paths which are
not going to include stuff like calls to the fixed function Pipeline.
And so one of the things that you typically want to do when you're
using a 3D API in this doesn't is not just opengl.
It's anything any 3D API at all whether it's
The opengl Vulcan metal opengl es anything.
One of the problems is the way that these systems are architected is
just not very good yet.
The apis are not particularly good.
There's no.
I say, it's not like an x 64 chip or stuff or stuff.
We're AMD and Intel has done a fantastic job.
Specifically specifying a, you know a very rigid set of criteria for
what defines an operating chip and how it is tested.
None of that stuff is true in the GPU world.
It's a complete wild West's a lot of stuff just
Doesn't work.
There's no specification for even really testing how it works in.
A lot of cases other than the most basic sort of things for
compliance.
And so as a result you need to be aware of the fact that this is not
like the CPU.
And so, what you need to do is make sure that you're trying to keep
the amount to, which you're using the API as much as possible in line
with what is expected.
As use of the API and you want to try it, unless you really need to
do.
So you want to try not to do a bunch of things with the API that is
not on the common case.
That's not what vendors are expecting to see from various titles,
right?
And so that's just kind of what I want to do here is just do a pass
over it and clean it out since we are using the hardware rendering now
in a sort of more real way where we're actually able to sort of take
Vantage of some of that, of the GPU power.
We really want to go and just make sure that we kind of clean up that
fixed function Miss
So the way I'm going to do that, first of all is we're going to need a
little bit of an ability here to feel debug messages.
Now, I don't know if this driver is supports debug messages, it might
not, but I'm going to try to see if I can get debug messages
registered with it in interrupt mode and I'm going to sort of show you
what that means.
And if I can do that, then what we're going to do is we're going to
switch when we create.
I don't know if you remember this but we created our opengl context.
There's that's this
Elevation process, that needs to happen where we create an opengl
context using the standard win32 API for doing.
So since that API has not been updated by Microsoft and years.
But decades, at this point, you need to call sort of the special
additional command that the driver specifies specifically directly to
you that will Elevate that context to a more modern context.
That's what we had to do in order to access things like frame buffers
and shaders.
When we did that elevation, we specified a thing that said we wanted a
compatibility context and what a compatibility
context is is a context where we can call things like fixed function
pipeline operations that have technically been deprecated in opengl,
right?
And I remember I said opengl is far too sprawling at this point.
I'm talking about the opengl, that's even it's far.
Sprawling.
Even considering the things that they've removed, if you put the
compatibility context of it in now you're talking about a sprawling
API that has a sprawling API bolted onto it which is all the old
Legacy calls that they actually support.
And so again that's just much it's just way too, big of a support
surface to foist on to a driver.
Vendor, definitely not what we want to do.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to go ahead and try to get a
debug call back working, that will let us know any time, the driver
encounters an error and then what I'm going
To do is try to turn off that compatibility context and that way
anytime that we try to call a function that is deprecated, hopefully
we will get a call back from the driver saying that that function is
not supported.
That way we can go through and do a quick sweep without us having to
sort of eyeball it and go wait.
Okay, this function isn't supported right, let's search for that.
Let's Okay.
This one isn't supported, let's search for that rather than doing
that.
What we can do is just go.
Okay, let's go through and see everything that the
Complaints about and get rid of all of those, right?
And that's sort of what we want to do here.
So that's what I'm going to try to do again.
When I say try to get the debug callbacks working, I don't necessarily
mean that we won't be able to figure out how to do it.
What I mean is not all drivers and all come not all combinations of
drivers and cards support the debug callbacks.
So AMD drivers, nowadays on a modern, AMD card do support the
callbacks for debugging,
In jail.
This is a very old card and it may not, even though in theory the
drivers are somewhat unified, that's not actually true.
Like for example this machine routinely, if you try to update the AMD
graphics driver it tells you you're on the latest one.
Even though the driver itself will tell you that there's an update.
So just to give you some perspective of just how ridiculous it is, you
know, it's in a state where older cards can't necessarily even use
newer drivers.
So it's possible obviously,
We that you can get into a situation where even though, technically,
you should be able to access a certain feature.
That feature may not actually be accessible to you or your customers
card.
Now, fortunately for debug callbacks we only need the debug callbacks
to work on the developer machine because obviously we don't need to
ship debug callbacks to the end user in any particular way, I mean
unless you have some kind of logging system that you want to build
based on him or something like this.
But for the most part
We don't have to worry too much about that.
So, let's go ahead and open up the source code here, and I'll show you
what we're going to what we want to do here.
So, if I go into handmade code and locks I guess, I'd open the project
first.
Let's go to the opengl subsystem if I look at this open shell sub
system so you can kind of see what I'm talking about here, right?
Like we have all these likes AGL color for VTEC scored 4 V calls,
these were sort of the old calls we're not even calling these anymore.
Like these are only called if we do the opengl display bitmap path,
which is to draw from our what the contents of our software renderer
showed.
So again, that stuff is not particularly interesting, but I don't know
right now.
If we've got more of those sorts of things lying around.
So for example, if you take a look here, here's a GL, Matrix mode GL
load identity call in opengl reader commands.
That is getting called right now.
We don't need that anymore, right?
That is not an actual thing that we are using.
Because since we're going through the fixed function pipeline, I'm
sorry.
Since we're not going to the fixed function pipeline anymore.
We're not setting matrices through that.
Any for any particular reason, what we're doing is setting uniforms
that are Shader reads that can do transforms for us stuff like that.
That's how we're pushing down information about transforms to the GPU
and so stuff like that.
We want to go through and clean all of that stuff out.
And again like I said, one way of doing it would be to just like roll
the dice and try to get them all ourselves.
But that's obviously more error-prone than if we have some Ironclad
way of knowing that we can just flip a bit and say, Hey Driver, why
don't you tell me anytime you see anything that you think is no longer
in your compatibility context?
Now, again, even that's not foolproof.
So we'll probably want to make a pass over it anyway.
There's no obligation on the drivers part to do that correctly.
Really, you know, yes, the spec probably says, something like they
have to do it but even though the spec says something like that, it's
not
Your driver vendors going to spend their time on right there.
Their time is spent trying to make games, run complete like compatibly
and quickly on their cards.
Not trying to adhere to this extremely complicated specification for
opengl, that's sort of wishy-washy and so on.
All right.
So, in order to get these, I don't know.
I'm pretty sure these have made it into the core at this point, at
least made it into ARB.
So I'm not sure if they're documented on Doc's that GLI.
They probably are.
Yeah, here they are.
But as you can see, they're limited to GL for which, I don't know if
we actually have any way of getting now, fortunately, for us there
available as an extension before gl4.
Sorry, still allergy season here for me.
I'm blowing my nose.
Constantly I even took allergy medication this morning, maybe it
hasn't quite kicked in yet anyway opengl for.
I don't know that we actually can get because we tried.
I think we looked at which version of opengl we can go to.
I don't think we were able to get for, but I can't remember.
So, either way, we want it to be on opengl three regardless because we
don't need up in jail for for anything at the moment.
And we don't want to push that compatibility up to require a card
support opengl for features.
So it might appear that we could not use of these debug message calls,
however, that's not actually the case, these debug message calls are
available as extensions in earlier versions of opengl.
Oftentimes so we can try to query for this extension and get it in a
in opengl 3.
So that's the thing that I'm going to try to do again.
Like I said, there's no guarantee that this driver actually supports
This at all.
So we don't know that that's true but we're going to try because
again, that's probably the most efficacious way to do this.
So if I come through here and grab these sort of guys, like I normally
do, we just have a couple functions to grab for the from the core ARB
header and I'll show you what those are.
This is what we're trying to enable right here.
So this GL debug message callback function
is a thing that says, okay, we're going to give you a call an actual
function that we defined and you're going to call us back from the
driver any time, you see an actual error.
And we're not really going to use this callback for anything other
than to just basically, assert right?
We're just going to Halt the program.
So that's all we really want to do.
Because what we're trying to do here is just halt the program in the
debugger.
Any time?
We do something that the
Doesn't like because that's how we're going to be able to get rid of
all those things.
The driver doesn't like, right?
So if we take a look at GL, debug message, call back here.
This is what we're trying to enable.
We want to be able to pass this callback here and and the user program
would just be if we have some data that we want to go get through to
that call back.
We don't actually have to worry about that because we're not doing
anything in the Callback.
But this is the thing that we're trying to actually Define right here.
So, this is the thing that we want to enable, you can see the debug
message call back.
There we go, has some sort of associated stuff.
You can see, get debug message.
Log is a, an alternate way of using this, which allows you to instead
of getting called back for stuff.
It allows you to kind of get when you're ready like hey, give me all
the message.
You have up to a point debug message insert, lets you put messages to
debug stream, pop and push debug group allows you to like, put markers
in.
We don't need any of this again.
All we're trying to do is just make it so that basically the driver
will stop our program.
Anytime it doesn't doesn't want.
It's just basically, a way of implementing an assertion.
So all we really care about is GL, debug message,
Control.
That's the only other function besides setting the Callback that we
actually need.
And what that is is it's a way of telling opengl what you actually
want it to do in terms of debug logging, right?
So you can see deal deal GL.
Debug message control has tons of stuff.
Source is where the message is coming.
From type is what type of message.
It is severity is what like level of alertness is like.
Is it just a note?
Is it an hard error, etc.
Etc, count is basically like telling it how many of these IDs that are
coming.
Next, they're going to be if you want to talk about specific IDs and
then enabled is enable.
This is saying like whether you want those messages enabled or not?
Now, I don't know if we actually need to call this because I don't
remember whether these will all be
I'll be on by default.
I going to, I'm just going to look through here to see.
Let's see.
The code is just going to shoes.
Do a concert ticket about a reverse so we may never need to call this
one.
I'm just not sure whether or not it's necessary to.
Yeah, I just don't know whether it's necessary to actually call this
one or not, because I don't remember whether or not these things are
just we'll all be on by default.
I assume that that is true, but I can't find anything here that says.
So we'll start out assuming that we don't.
And then if we're having trouble, we'll we'll go ahead and and, and
look a little closer.
Now, there's one of the things I think we have to do which is enable
the message log.
I'm going to leave that up for us, so there's
Those two right there.
I feel like there's a GL enable, 4gl debug message, call back.
And I just want to go ahead and see if I can grab that here somewhere.
Let's see.
No, that's it.
Typo there.
All right.
So, let's see.
This is the spec for the original when it was created.
Let me just take a look here.
So here's the okay, this is the one we're looking for here.
So do you see this debug output synchronous are?
This is kind of what I was wanting to be able to set and it goes
through GL and Abel.
Basically, this is a GL enable bit which tells us.
Hey, I want you to try and generate errors immediately if you can.
And I know that's a little bit of a weird idea.
Son.
Sort of explain what that means, what happens in an opengl driver or
any graphics card driver for that matter.
Is that in order to improve performance or in order to even make the
card function at all for obvious reasons, they have to be delays in
terms of when things are processed.
Because remember, a GPU.
Even in the case where it's on the same die as a CPU, like in a
bulldozer core or in
Tell.
Integrated graphics, for example, even in that case, the operation of
the GPU part of the chip is not lockstep necessarily with the CPU part
of the chip in any logical way.
Meaning it's not like when you say I'm going to do this specific batch
of drawing Primitives.
You don't want the CPU to sit around waiting for the GPU to do those
things, right?
Even in the case, where you could do that exactly.
Because you've got the
Same ship in charge.
That's not what these are designed to do.
The GPU is designed to be processing like streamed processing.
An amount of computational work load for the graphics while the CPU is
doing whatever else it wants to do.
And so as a result, whenever you make a call to a graphics driver,
you're typically talking about a lot of wait, time in turn in CPU land
between when that call gets issued and when the results of that call
materialize, and this can come from a lot of different ways,
One is just waiting for them to be processed by GPU.
Another is that things want to get buffered up into chunks coherent
chunks, that got get handed to the GPU as a batch especially in cases,
where it's not on the same diet where you're talking about a PCI bus
transfer or something else in order to get the data from the CPU over
to the GPU for processing.
And so what happens in that driver is when you make a call, it may not
even have enough information at that time.
Potentially to issue an error because it may not have seen enough
later.
Things about how you are drawing to know that you actually made an
error.
This is especially bad in opengl who still retains.
If you use, if you don't use the most modern opengl 4.5 a zdo stuff,
if you're still kind of like we are in a more compatibility mode where
you're using opengl 3 or something like that, you're still talking
about making calls that set a lot of state and that state only becomes
erroneous at the time, when a draw call actually
Gets executed.
So, for example, if I execute a draw call and that draw call has some
state that it expects to be set, but you never set that state.
That is the time when the error is going to get generated.
Not at the time when you made the state call and maybe set the wrong
state.
For example, it only knows that the state was set incorrectly when it
actually gets the time that you were supposed to do the execution.
And that's the best case scenario, right?
The worst case scenario is during that call, it's just putting that
into a buffer and
Later, there's some buffer validation, that's happening way down the
line and that's when it knows, there's an error.
So again, you have to remember that this the driver underneath you and
that that's, you know, sort of working with this relatively complex
queuing system to get things off to the GPU.
And this sort of State, tracking that opengl voice upon it.
For the older style, three point x opengl stuff.
Again, opengl 4.5 a video and Vulcan DirectX, 12, these sorts of
things have less.
That you're expected to specify more things directly.
But, you know, again, we're sort of a little more compatibility at the
moment.
We're not pushing those this card.
Probably can't the driver.
That's currently on this machine, probably can't do them anyway.
So given all the, that all of those things are true.
What we're setting here is we're setting a flag that says Hey Driver.
If you can, if you have this capability in you which again there's
things called debug drivers.
You can install for
People, which are different than release mode drivers, which may, for
example, have things compiled into enable this more than it would
normally be enabled.
This is saying if you could go out of your way, make performance
worse, that's fine.
Like it's we're not worried about performance right now.
You can make performance worse and go ahead and try to give me error
messages on the call.
They most clearly can be identified on rather than later when they may
actually have been.
More when the error would actually have occurred in a real sense,
meaning when your most optimal path would have detected, something was
wrong.
If that's much later, try to do some checking up front, that will
allow me to know early, right?
And that's what this G of this, debug output synchronous ARB B is for,
and we definitely want that, right?
The rest of this stuff.
I don't know that we need.
It doesn't look like we need anything here.
And I don't see any enable at the moment, so I think, and I'm not
totally sure.
Again, it's been a while, but I believe all we will have to do is call
the debug message, call back function to register.
The fact that we'd like to call back to an errors and then enable the
synchronous output.
So that whenever an error occurs, if the driver has the capability, it
will cause back right on the call rather than some time later.
So again.
With the major caveat that I don't know if this is actually going to
work on this card at all.
Here we go.
So, the first thing we're going to need is a typedef for the debug
proc itself.
The debug proc is the thing that's going to be the function prototype
for our actual call, right?
And so here, is that what that looks like?
Oops, I missed some of it.
Sorry about that.
So, here's what that looks like.
And so this is essentially the
You know, the call that we could put that in there.
I don't like the pointer bind version of this.
I'm going to do it like that.
So here is what a GL debug proc looks like, right?
And this is what we are going to receive as a call.
So we
Define one of these in our opengl, you know, binding layer here right.
Something that looks exactly like this because we're going to have to
pass a pointer to this function to the opengl driver so that it will
be able to call us back at it right?
And there it is.
Now we don't actually have to do anything here.
All we want at this point is just to Halt, right?
That's all we want.
Now since again, I don't really want this to be platform-specific.
I don't want to have to include things like win API in the opengl.
You know, the non platform layer part of things.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to use that trick we use
before where like I can say Shield, debug call back or something like
this and
A name.
And then, I'm going to have this be
That function prototype.
Whatever it requires for this particular platform.
Then in this typedef I'm just going to say, okay, the type of this
thing.
can be derived from that and then anyone who wants to make one of
these can just say GLD bug call back
open guilty about call back and then we'll have it here just the
ability to say like, hey, cert opengl error encountered,
Right.
And there we go.
So that's all we need to do in terms of making a place for opengl to
like actually tell us what needs to happen.
Oops, I've got a
Suspect.
I've got it yet.
Semicolon in there.
So that's all we need for opengl to be able to tell us what to do.
And then what we now need is for the part where we tell open Jill what
to do which is enabling that.
So in order to do that, we just need the two pieces of ice already had
that open my bad.
Oh wait, no, I didn't.
Thought that tab with also it, but it wasn't so all we need.
There is that synchronous bit.
Here it is.
Let's do that.
So we need to pound Define that
and we can put that in here because that's again not specific to any
platform.
So there's the synchronous output bit and we need to Jill enable that.
So we're going to have to at some point.
To a Jill enable GL, not called debug output synchronous.
We're going to want to do that when we initialize.
So basically, like right in here, when we're about to do all of our
setup, we want to get that synchronous.
Debugging.
And similarly at, you know, in addition to that we're going to want
the the debug message call back call right there.
So that as soon as we start, we have that in there.
Let's grab that out.
So, there's two of those.
It says the ARB one.
And the non ARB one, I don't know which one we should be getting.
So this is the one from opengl.
This is the one from the extension.
I think we want the one from the extension because like I said we
aren't using opengl for so we should probably ask for this one.
If they really are different.
I don't know if they are or not, but let's let's just go ahead and
let's go ahead and see.
So I'm going to go ahead and
This guy in here.
So there's that GL.
Debug message.
Call back.
I'm going to go ahead and put type in there.
It's way we're doing it before.
So we've got this deal.
Debug proc our piece
That's just one of these and then we got that user program there.
So that's what opengl expects us to do to tell it.
We got to do our little Global variable piece or open Jill function
bit here.
So, that's let's see.
GL debug message, call back ARB.
And I think that's all we really need.
Now, we can just ask for it and hope that we actually get it.
So, let's look at vertex, a trip pointer.
Go to get opengl function, and there's that.
So hopefully again, we don't really know, but hopefully that will work
and and we'll get some love there.
But I don't know if we will or not.
Let's step through here and see what we see.
So, let's jump in here.
I forgot to call it, that's not going to help.
Alright, so here after the GL enable, I guess or doesn't matter really
where could be in the before or after I don't think that matters.
So after we call gln Able with GL debug output, synchronous, we have
GL, debug message, callback ARB, we want to pass that opengl debug
call back and then we don't have any user parameter to pass to it.
So that's really all we're talking about here again.
I don't know what the knee.
I'm assuming this is the right one to query for we'll see and
obviously this is only going to work in the case where we actually
We got one of these.
So, if opengl debug callback wasn't available, I'm sorry.
If GL, debug message call back.
Our wasn't available.
If that function query failed, then obviously we can't call it.
So, I'm going to go ahead now and just do a little.
There we go.
So it looks like it was available, which is great news for us, at
least.
That means we got a chance of getting it working.
We call enable there and we'll set the call backup.
Now when we call the see if we get it, we did.
So that's actually good.
So now we're actually getting some errors callbacks which is great.
And remember this opengl debug call back here?
I suppose we should probably make it a little easier to look at their
I guess without having to come back here to the name but it's this
message here is the thing that we're actually interested in.
And so if we want to, we can actually do, we could do something like
this.
There we go.
See.
so,
Here we go with the assertion and then if we just want to know what
the error messages we can always just look at what that looks like GL
text image 2D multi-sample parameter internal format has an invalid
enum, oxc 43.
So this is actually complaining about one of our existing calls even
though we're in a working mode, the moment that's actually very good
news.
That's great to know.
It means something in here is failing.
Yeah, I guess this is.
This is actually I guess by design for us though, right?
This is the part where we tried to create one with srgb alpha 8, and
of course it tells us that you can't.
And so then we have to turn it off, right?
So I guess that's an error that we expect to have happen.
And and we don't really know any other way of getting around it.
So I suppose we're going to need something there.
To obviate that for us.
so, I'm guessing that probably, what we would have to do is
Is actually turn this on and off around there.
Right.
So we need this to happen before we set up that callback basically,
which is probably fine, right?
Let's see, Reserve with texture.
So essentially what we could do is say, well, we got to leave this
till here, but everything else is fine.
Let's try that.
So there we are running with no errors at the moment.
Which is sort of what we would expect.
Because presumably, if we had any errors that were at all serious, we
should have seen some kind of a bug in the drawing of our game that
was related to the fact that it opengl couldn't do the thing.
We're asking it to do.
All right, so now let's switch over here and see if we can get this to
tell us some things that it doesn't like about the compatibility
context, right?
If I turn off that compatibility context,
See if we can get some debug calls that tell us.
Hey, here are the places where you're calling things that you
shouldn't be calling if you're trying to use more modern opengl.
So, here's that compatibility.
Oops, if I spell it right.
So, here's that compatibility bit that we're setting, right?
You can see it right here.
Here's the profile mask.
Here's the compatibility profile bit ARB.
So if we wanted to set it to core profile, which is this now we set it
to core profile.
I believe that should complain.
If we are calling a bunch of things that aren't in the core profile.
Now I don't know.
That's actually true.
Does, it does not appear to be true unfortunately.
So I guess that may not actually
Help us.
Well, maybe the forward compatibility bit needs to get set.
I don't know, it's this right here.
We could try it the forward, compatible bit.
I think is supposed to warn you when you're calling things.
That might not be forward compatible with future versions of opengl.
So we'll see.
So, that's good.
We got an error.
Let's hope that that's actually true.
Okay, so here's the open gel in it and we're getting an error message.
Here, that's usually using G, ltch semi and a Core Concepts with
parameter P name.
Is an error that's actually true.
The reason we don't need this anymore.
If you think about what GL, Tex end of I was doing in this call, what
this was doing with setting the mode where the, when the texture got
read, what it was going to do with the color that came out of the
texture and GL modulate, which is the parameter passing there was
telling it.
Hey, I want you to multiply the color from the texture with the
incoming color that I set on the
Text.
That was how we were telling the fixed function pipeline what to do.
But we don't need to do that anymore, right?
Because now we have complete control over the equation in its you know
in all its Glory here in the fragment Shader, right?
So where that got implemented was right here, right here, is that
modulation?
Here's the fragment color that we produce so far and the texture
sample.
That we took from the texture and we're multiplying them together.
That's really all we're
Talking about here, right?
And so, that's just total vestigial remain.
We don't need it at all.
And so, that's a good thing to get rid of, this is exactly what I was
hoping for right, because you can see how this is an easy way to just
get a bunch of these out of the program.
So hopefully this will work pretty well.
So that's just not necessary anymore at all.
Right.
That is a non, it's an ineffectual call.
So what else we got?
Gee L Alpha Funk has been removed.
That's a another good one.
Right.
So Alpha test is a still a thing but Alpha Funk isn't the reason for
that is if you think about what's going on here and we didn't really
cover this into great detail.
Fact, I suppose we probably need to now.
I think about it actually use this in here.
Alright, so this is pretty interesting.
We can talk about this.
So, what happens in here?
You have to go back a couple weeks to when we were first implementing.
This our Sprites have an alpha of zero everywhere that there's no
image, right?
Because remember we're working with rectangles in a lot of these cases
and there's a lot of empty space around them that empty space is
marked with an alpha of zero in the bitmap in order to know that it
doesn't actually contribute at all to that location.
Right?
Are it's only what's underneath it?
That's going to be seen in that location.
So what we did there to make that work with a z-buffer,
Mario's we enable thing called Alpha test and what Alpha test does is
it says, hey if the alpha isn't greater than 0, right?
Then I'm not going to draw.
If it is greater than 0, then I am going to draw.
I'm going to like actually apply this sample in some way whether
that's Blended or whatever else you have set.
That's what's going to happen.
Now why did this get removed?
Why is this no longer necessary?
Well, the reason is because Alpha test is a stage that happens in the
pipeline.
So gln able Alpha test is still
Will there to tell you that Alpha test is on or off?
I believe, I don't actually know if that's true.
Even Alpha test may have may just get implied by the Shader now.
We'll see.
I don't, I'm sorry, I don't remember, but at the very least the
function much like the modulation thing.
Got removed, the function got removed because now you can put that in
the Shader and let me show you how that works because we didn't
actually do that and we should because that's the like I said The more
appropriate way to do it.
So in here you can see
We get a texture sample, right?
And we have a fragment color here.
Now we know we know that we're never probably going to be specifying
fragment colors of zero very often or fragment colors of alpha 0, very
often.
It may happen when something Fades all the way out but really at that
point probably we should have earlier outed somewhere further up in
the pipeline and never pushed down a Sprite that how does alpha all
the way to zero.
So we probably don't need to check for frag color 0 on its own.
Own.
However, when the texture sample comes in, as soon as we get that,
Sure sample.
What we want to do is say, hey, if the tester samples, Alpha value,
Is greater than 0.
Then you can go ahead and execute the Shader as you were normally
executing the Shader right like so but in the case where you were not
going to do that.
So you have the texture sample comes in and it's actually zero.
So we know this multiply right here.
We know will kill the frag color entirely and we don't need to care
about the srgb either way because zero
Squared is still 0.
Then what we want to do is tell the fragment Shader, you don't need to
do anything else.
That's it.
You don't need to apply the blind pipeline to this.
This fragment has gotten killed, it's called Tech skill or used to be
called Texaco.
Basically, What's Happening Here is we're saying checking the off the
value, the alpha value indicates, no drawing.
So just stop, you can save any more work that you might have done.
Don't do it.
You don't, you can save it, it's fine.
And so that takes the place this greater than 0 here.
Takes the
Place of the greater than 0 that we were calling up in the alpha test
case.
So we don't need that anymore.
I believe.
Alpha test is still enable separately.
I I'm sorry, I just don't remember.
It might not be true.
You might always have to have it.
Can I get a?
I want this to show me more of this message.
O XB C 0 so that might be Alpha test so I think it's I think I'm
wrong.
So basically Alpha test is just 100% implied by the Shader.
So basically if the Shader has the discard in there that's Alpha, test
is on.
If the Shader doesn't have the discard in there, it's off.
I think that's it.
Let's say.
Yeah.
Alright.
So moving on past that all of these are still available because multi
sample drawing can be on or off and alpha-2 coverage and that stuff
can all be on or off still same with the dep's test as well.
You'll notice that depth testing doesn't occur in the Shader at the
moment.
That's because there still is a fixed function depth pipeline.
Basically, that does actually that that has a bunch of optimization
minute that still exists.
So typically, you just use depth, testing.
The depth testing doesn't become part of the Shader.
I believe that's mostly because of the way that fragment assembly and
stuff works, there's it's just better to have the ability for the card
to go.
Oh I I know that this entire triangle is all going to be behind
everything that's in this particular region that I'm was rasterizing
right now.
So I'm not even going to like do anything additional and blah blah
blah.
So there's a lot of like early outing that happens there.
So I believe that a lot of depth testing is still fixed function.
The time you can do stuff, where you implement your own depth, testing
in the Shader, if you actually want it to be so, but we don't need to
do that at.
All right, we have no need for that because we can just do it like
we're doing it now in the vertex Shader.
So GL enable texture 2D no longer here.
That's all good.
Because that's again, in the Shader, if the Shader samples from a
texture, then texturing is on.
If it doesn't say over a texture then it's not so we can get rid of
that.
And let's see what else we got here.
Right, so the Matrix mode stuff, that's not necessary at all.
Because again, we're doing all those transforms explicitly ourselves
in the vertex Shader, so that's good.
Let's keep going.
So let's see.
Yes, this load Matrix.
F call not necessary at all.
And proj is still getting set.
So that is our little thing that we need there, so we can get rid of
that.
I think my right about that.
Yeah.
So this is interesting to you can kind of see when we get this running
as well.
I'm going to I'm going to remember and I'm kind of moves over here.
So I'm not behind my own head at all.
So let's go ahead and run that let's continue getting rid of these but
She'll virtue statute pointer in a court kind of called without a
bound vertex, array objects in our card.
So this is a particularly annoying aspect of opengl from this era,
which is that, at some point, they decided that it would be swell.
If you could save the state of vertex arrays by having a Vertex array
object that stored that state,
They then determined a lot of driver vendors did that actually that
was very inefficient having these State changes for the attributes is
actually slower than not doing that.
So then what they recommended you do is just create one and leave it
bound the entire time and it's an error not to do so.
So, we get to go create one of these and bind it during initialization
and never touch it again, just to avoid the fact that technically,
it's an opengl error, not to do so.
I wish I was making stuff like this up.
I'm not.
So what we need to do here is right.
You know, in this before we do any drawing here, basically, we need to
create a Vertex array.
I've been an array object.
I'll show you what I'm talking about here.
How do I get back to the little Mary Go?
So it's this set of Saucy gentleman, right here.
So bind vertex array again, we'll talk about this in a second.
I believe create vertex arrays.
What I need to do to get one of these.
Is that correct?
No.
Jen vertex array?
That's that's what I'm looking at, all right.
Alright, so you can see these are basically just the same as textures,
they're just State.
You basically say I need to talk about an array State and then you're
like I'm going to bind one again, they don't work anymore.
Like they're not things that you actually use.
I Mega saying they don't work is not true.
Obviously they do work if you wanted to actually use them but they're
not efficient to use.
So you just don't use them anymore as far as I'm aware anyway, and
they kind of got leapfrogged anyway because by the time they actually
would have become efficient potentially
We're basically replaced by direct name, buffer, access stuff that
like, you would use anyway.
So I far as I know, these were literally just never a good idea, I
could be wrong about that.
Somebody who's a hard core GPU person?
Probably could tell you a little more about that, then I can.
But basically, we're looking at, literally this, right?
We want to create a Vertex array, and this is basically, like, just a
dummy vertex array, that's just going to be generated.
And then we just want to leave it set.
Right, so after we do that we're just going to do a bind vertex array
on it and that's it.
That's all.
So, we basically have to query these extra two functions for no reason
whatsoever.
They don't do anything for us, except avoid the error, the technical
error of using opengl that way, which you're not supposed to do so.
Oh well, that's that's just.
Let me convert x-rays.
So great, fantastic.
Wonderful.
In fact, I guess I'll just grab these right here.
Fortunately, at least it's a pretty easy thing to fix.
It's just nonsense, but it's easy.
So here's our type def's.
Bloop.
Oops, the up.
Okay.
All right, fine.
All right.
There we go.
And we'll go ahead and slap those little.
Guys on here, delete.
Oops.
I didn't need that one by and vertex array and Jen vertex arrays.
And obviously, we don't need delete because we only create one and we
never get.
It is remains bound the entire time and does not change, so that's
always good.
Debug message, call back.
I should have done this for both of them.
I should have done this for all of these to this opengl get function
is just much better.
All right?
So find vertex array, Ben burtt x-rays
All right.
So in theory anyway we should be able to do that and now I think we're
getting through.
Are we getting through one or maybe we're not.
Let's see.
If I fail because not a lot of specific clients overtakes or element
array.
When a non-default Vertex array object is bound.
But isn't that the opposite of what you just complained about?
I'm a little confused by that.
oh, so is it the case that we must use an opengl backed buffer in
order to call GL vertex, a trip pointer
Because it wanted us to not.
Let me just double check with that error.
Was again, in case I miss understood it, but don't think I did.
If we don't
Bind a Vertex, array, it does not like that, right?
Gee overtakes reporter in a core context called without a burnt bound
vertex array object which is now required for Cora contexts so that's
pretty clear, right?
Did I accidentally not create a Vertex array object?
I thought that's what I did.
I don't think there's such a thing as a Vertex array object like
multiple words.
Just double-check.
Yeah we're just array object name a re-raise.
Blah, blah blah.
Is this thing to portray, if nobody service above change State, it's
exactly what we expect.
So that just seems correct.
So I guess we're in a bit of a catch-22 here, unless I'm missing
something.
And again, I'll just reiterate at least what I assume it's trying to
tell us
so the first era, as far as I know, was telling us that in order to
call vertical
It's a trim pointer.
We need to have an array object bound at the time again.
We don't actually need to use those array objects in the way they were
initially intended, which was just quickly swap between various array
object States.
So for example, if you had like several different, array states that
you're drawing from these arrays and then these arrays and then those
arrays and you wanted to switch, you know, and they were static you
want to switch between those States quickly or something like this?
That's what those were for it turned out to be a bad idea.
So they pretty much
Don't use them and so you just set one at the beginning and go is how
you normally do it.
Unfortunately it is an error not to do it because you do need to have
a valid one bound and that's what it's complaining about.
However once we do bind one,
It's complaining about something else entirely which is that as far as
I can tell.
Anyway,
Unless there's some third way of using the API that I'm not aware of.
Once you do, go ahead and do bind a Vertex array object in place.
It's basically saying you can't pass client-side memory 2gl vertex at
Red pointer because remember, that's what we're doing here.
So if you take a look at what's going on, we've got a real data,
right?
We've got data here that we're passing down and that data, as you can
see,
Is actually being passed out of our memory.
This is CPU side memory.
It's not memory that's being backed by the GPU in any way.
It's just regular old memory.
And what we're saying is, hey inside, this client-side memory again,
client is a weird term.
I should probably pause and mention why if that's throwing me for a
loop?
It's it makes sense.
Why it is in opengl parlance.
The client is the person who's issuing, the render commands?
And the server is the person who's executing them, her go
Client-side memory means CPU side because the CPU side is the thing
that's issuing commands to GPU server side would be the GPU.
That's the thing that's actually doing the execution of the commands.
Therefore, when you actually call opengl with something, it will refer
to something as client-side memory.
If it's memory that you've made on your side that it doesn't know
about and now you're asking it to pull from that memory that is
client-side memory.
It basically means CPU side memory in our case.
So it is
That we're using CPU side memory here.
We're not really wanting to transfer this stuff to the GPU, any sooner
than this.
This is the time when we would like to tell the GPU about it because
it's completely Dynamic.
It's gets created, every frame.
Usually, when you're talking about putting things into GPU memory,
you're talking about stuff that you're going to make once and draw
from several times.
If you're just doing it every frame generating a list of Sprites like
we are that needs to get sent to the graphics card every frame.
There's no bonus in US sending that to the GPU early.
So that's why we didn't bother putting it into any kind of special
memory back area that the GPU is aware of.
But it looks to me.
and again, I'm purely going by what I'm reading on the error messages
but it looks to me like this complaint
Is trying to tell us that is no longer allowed in core.
Our Urban core ARB.
You cannot use a client-side pointer.
That is what it looks like.
Now I don't know if that's true but that's just what it looks like.
I will say that.
I generally don't use client-side pointers when I'm using opengl right
now at all.
So it is true that I wouldn't have known that, that was true because I
never would have hit that in my own programming, I suppose.
So I can't say off the bat that
Driver is doing anything unusual, that may be exactly what the driver
is supposed to do.
I just wouldn't have ever hit that
So, I think that means we're left with having to deal with the fact
that we, I don't think we have a choice here if we want to actually
get rid of all of the Legacy sort of calls we were doing that suggest,
we will have to use GPU mapped memory here.
Right.
That just seems to be what we're saying.
Well fortunately for us we already did all the work for that.
The only thing we didn't do is actually allocate jpu back to memory,
right?
Because you remember I said very specifically when were talking about
this before, when we come through here, in the platform layer stuff,
you can see right here and game render commands.
This stuff, textured vertex vertex array.
That's where all our vertices are getting pushed at the moment is in
to that vertex.
And so that vertex array, very specifically was allocated on the
platform side of things.
So if we want to, we can very easily have the platform side allocate
that out of opengl store so that it is actually backed by the GPU and
can be flushed in that way, right?
We could do that.
Now, we don't necessarily need to go that far and we may not want to
go that far because like I said, this is actually memory that the GPU
doesn't need to know about ahead of time.
It's pretty much this Frame is the first time we've ever had it and
we're sending it down.
So what we can do instead is just create a dummy buffer that we, then
say, hey, here's the whole data for the buffer, by the way, I think
that's what I'd like to do first because I really don't know.
I don't like to do things as if they're a good idea GPU wise, without
ever having a way to test.
That because in general, I feel like you end up doing more harm than
good by speculating.
That something should be faster on the GPU by doing something, like,
allocating the memory from it directly.
That could mean you don't really know that.
That's true.
There's certainly plenty of times in history, where something that
sounds like, what should be the fastest path is in?
No way.
The fastest path and you're actually hurting your performance by doing
it.
So I'm going to just, I think I'm going to avoid doing that just yet.
instead, what I'm going to do here,
Just make a single buffer that we use for this and I'll show you how
that works.
So essentially what we're going to do here,
And it to be fair this is going to give us a think a little bit of a
bonus in terms of it would give the driver something that the driver
probably does want.
So this is not a complete waste of time.
Like the Gen vertex array stuff is because that is a literal complete
waste of time but basically I believe this is correct.
Yeah.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to use the buffer API which
is is the thing that we would use to allocate method do pu.
But instead of allocating memory on the GPU, I'm basically just going
to say hey, we've got a dynamic buffer.
We're going to send it to you every frame.
It's not going to be backed by GPU memory in that sense.
Like it's not going to be direct mapped on one side of the other and
you can kind of see how this goes.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to call this G Elgin buffers.
And we're going to have here in our open she'll sort of State based
information stuff.
We're going to have here a thing that's just like vertex buffer,
right?
And what I want to do is I want to generate that vertex buffer from
opengl
And that's just again like a texture it's like a handle that says I'm
referring to this particular piece of buff this particular buffer that
I'm going to tell you more information about as we go right.
Once I get one of those buffers, it's just like a texture and then I
can bind it, right?
So you can see that here.
Now we only ever going to draw out of just this buffer at least at the
moment.
So what I'll probably do here is just bind it right here.
Now, I don't actually know that that's how we're will do it in the
end.
So I said, I am saving.
It's unlike this one where I know that I never need to touch this ever
again.
I am going to save this buffer handle here so I'm generating buffer
thing up with John W.
I want to start talking about a piece of memory, so like give me a way
to do that.
Again, we haven't talked about the memory at were just saying a name.
Basically give us a name, we can use such a and they're going to bind
the buffer which says.
Okay, now we're talking about this buffer here.
Now, when we bind the buffer, we need just like in textures to specify
what we're going to use it for.
And that in this case is GL array buffer.
It's the thing that will store the vertex array data that we were
passing around, right?
So now we have that bound.
Now when we go to make a call, like GL vertex of trim pointer,
The way that they made this work, was they made it so that when you
call that, if there is a buffer bound to the erase lot, like we just
did.
And again, this API is horrible, don't get me wrong.
It's just, it's ridiculous.
I have no idea what they were thinking when they made these.
A lot of times I suspect it had a lot to do with trying to
incrementally add things without really thinking about how absurd the
result would be.
Anyway,
so,
Can you call vertex of trip pointer the way they sort of jury-rigged
this into place was they said, okay if you have a buffer bound then
you're going to be talking about the buffer memory, not a pointer.
So instead of passing a pointer, what you do is cast to a pointer,
just the amount off of the base of the buffer that you want the data
to start out.
So basically, we just cast the offsets to avoid star and we're good.
I know that sounds ridiculous.
Yes.
But literally again all it's doing is its it was trying to reuse the
API.
Basically this vertex to trim pointer.
If you remember is saying where it's supposed to get the vertex data
from,
And in this case, it now already knows the region of memory to get it
from because we're going to be specifying that with that buffer API.
But what it doesn't know is where the individual components of the
vertex are.
So because remember it has to map those individual components to the
various components of the vertex that the Shader expects to have the
position the texture of the color, right?
So what this vertex, the trip pointer basically is doing is just
setting the stride, which is this, and the offset
Which is this of each type of element in memory already knows where it
is.
So that's why we've pulled the pointer part out.
But since we're still using the older apis, they didn't want to add a
new API set.
Just for this.
They said we'll just cross it to avoid star and we'll look at the
actual value as if it's an Offset, you know?
Scouts Honor.
So anyway, that's what's going to happen there.
However, we need one more thing to happen here, right?
Which is that we haven't actually told it for that particular buffer,
where the memory actually is, and that's done with something called
GL, buffer data, which is a called.
Here, you can see which basically just passes down a chunk of memory
with a name.
So how that works is, I call Gio buffer data with a Target.
Again, that's going to be that GL array, buffer bit.
So I'm passing down that saying, whatever is bound in that slot that
GL array, buffer slot, whatever is bound in that slot.
I'm going to give you a size.
That's how many of these there are.
Now again, we know and of course, and also data pointer, we know where
it is, right?
We know it's here, we know the size of it, right?
Because the size of it is however, many of these things we were going
The send down, right?
This is this is telling us right here.
And in fact, the him a platform thing can see, right here as the
vertex count in it.
So we know that the size is just going to be the vertex count times.
However, big each one of those vertices things was right and then
we've got a usage and the usage is kind of nuts.
It's like this kind of weird thing that's sort of not really very
good, but it's trying to tell open Joe what this memory is going to
do.
You can see here the descriptions of them.
so, stream mode is basically saying we're going to modify something
once and use it a few times static is we're going to modify
Once and use it many times dynamic, as we're going to modify it
repeatedly and use it many times, right?
Now in our case, it's a little tricky to pick what this means because
again this hasn't really stated what it means by modify.
Are you talking about modifying the buffer name or you're talking
about modifying the buffer contents?
Because actually, the buffer contents are never going to be modified.
We're just using this name as something.
We recycle to send you down a different chunk of memory every time.
Technically, I think that's probably stream draw but honestly, I can't
remember what the graphics card actually does with these.
So it might be dynamic draw.
It's definitely not static draw because we know that we're only
sending it down once.
Right.
And then we're well.
Okay, you know what?
No, I take that back because technically each one of these is a draw
call.
So it could be streamer.
It could be static.
Now, I think about it, I really don't know which one will be better.
I'm going to go with stream at the moment.
Oops, that's the wrong one.
I'm gonna go with stream at the moment because every frame, we change
it, but we do draw from multiple times.
So I'm going to try stream draw and, you know, again, this is just a
performance, hint getting it wrong will not cause wrong results to
just make ostler before.
It's the driver, because it may do different things with the memory
map, it to different locations, treat it differently.
Based on that hint is the only reason we even care about it.
Okay.
So again, hopefully you can understand how really I've done nothing
differently.
Here.
All I did was change the way we were calling it.
Previously, we were calling it.
Such that vertex, trip pointer took pointers to the actual vertex
streams.
Now we're changing it so that we're making a GL, buffer data call that
buffer data call will move, the whole chunk of memory over and then
vertex trip planner just saying, we're in that chunk, it is.
Now, you can see that even though this was kind of useless to a
certain extent from our perspective, it actually wasn't 100% useless.
And the reason is you have to
And the subtlety here.
What is there?
There's one piece of information we have now given the driver it did
not have before, and that is a good piece of information.
It's how big this was.
So you'll notice the vertex of trip pointer calls and this is just
because they weren't designed particularly well, the geometric pointer
calls never told the driver, how much memory it would access.
It was just telling it a base pointer and how how big each individual
element was but it had no idea how many it was actually going to get.
The only way it could ever find out how many was actually Gonna Get
You.
To look at all these draw a ray calls that were being used with it,
right?
And see how much they spanned, that's a lot of inefficiency of the
driver now, the driver has to be watching these drawer, a calls.
Probably cuing them all up.
Not issuing any of them until it sees all the uses of this buffer,
then it goes, okay, that's the total range of the buffer.
Now I can kick off a transfer of the buffer and then wait for the
buffer to get down there and then start issuing these calls or
something like this, right?
But now what we've done is this has
Even slightly.
They're right this Geo.
Buffer data call
in this case, this deal buffer data calls actually kind of nice
because what this does is it says hey here's all of the data but I'm
going to talk about here is how big it is right?
Here's where it is.
You can kick off that transfer.
Now if you want to and know that I have promised you, you're never
going to see me.
Call something like GL, draw arrays with an index bound.
That goes outside of this window.
So that's a much more
Size specification, to the driver, whether the driver can actually
make use of it, who knows?
That's their problem.
Not ours.
But you can definitely see from an API perspective.
That's a much more proper way of doing things in telling it.
Here is the memory trunk.
Okay?
Now here's some offsets of them are just going to draw from that's
much cleaner in terms of giving the driver of the information.
It needs to potentially do more sophisticated or more intelligent
operations, which month, which with much less analysis during runtime
analysis that the driver has to do.
On your instruction stream, right?
So what we need to do now is take these calls which at the moment our
oops that's got to be.
There we go which are currently not defined and just add them and then
we've got a couple of different pound Defiance here.
So again just going to jump over to the core ARB situation here and
grab those out.
So here's
Jill array, buffer.
Oops.
Here's Jill stream draw.
And while I'm at it because we don't really know which one of these
guys were going to want.
I'm just going to grab all these
Guess we want to play with them and then we just have these calls, The
Binding buffer data, Jen buffers, and Vine buffer.
So let's go ahead and grab those out.
so we've got find buffer, gen buffer and buffer data there they all
are
And let's grab them out here.
We go.
Okay.
And I guess I don't need either of those so there we go.
That's the thing.
I've got those in there.
And again, just
during the process of putting those in here, we've got healed, bind
buffer,
She'll Jen buffers and Joe buffer data.
and then,
Same thing here.
And then I think we should be good to go.
It looks like size.
I pointer is a new type def here.
Take a look at where that's to find.
We don't have those in here.
So let's just put them in a bind buffers.
Did I spell it wrong?
It's going on here.
Just saying go to line.
There we go.
So I think it's I just spelled that wrong, it should be buying buffer.
All right, so let's see if we've made any progress here.
Looks like we have passed that test.
So, again, just changing this to a structurally different way of
submitting it, which is slightly different, even though it looks like,
it was just busy work.
It does.
Give the size up front, which is really too important.
We're getting down to the end of the errors here, hopefully, because
they're not that much call.
They're not many calls left.
We do have one here that says, the value of this item is stale due to
a problem that occurred while valuing your cursor over the, oh, that's
that's actually talking about.
That's Microsoft Visual storytelling.
So here's what we actually want using geogebra raised in a day.
Core context with parameter mode and em7 which was removed from core
opengl.
Okay.
So that's that's the GL quads problem.
Hmm.
that's,
Tougher.
That's a tough one.
To get rid of my friends.
I'm going to go ahead and just take a look at what happens if we go
ahead and skip that.
Is that the only error we have left?
Let's find out.
Because that one, I don't know what we're going to do about.
That's that's a nasty one.
We'll talk about why in a second.
All right, so that's the last area.
Have is just using GL quads.
But, unfortunately, GL quads is not actually a supported any longer.
Now, this is not great for us, for a number of reasons.
And I can't say that there's really any fix for this.
And here's why.
So other things we can draw.
Quads is pretty much optimal for what we're doing because what we want
to do is be able to specify four points and fill them with a square
texture, right?
Or a rectangular texture.
So, quads is perfect for what we're trying to draw.
It's exactly the it's the most efficient way of specifying exactly
what we're specifying.
Unfortunately.
It got removed, and it got removed because basically, you know, even
in our case, you might argue that the easier way to not the easier way
but that it could be handled by writing a Shader into the other parts.
Like there's there's geometry shaders and tessellation shaders, which
we haven't talked about which work with the topology of data.
You could argue that the geometry, tessellation side of things, you
write something there, that will take whatever you've packed and
turned into.
You know triangles instead of quad, so you can still specify things as
if their quads in the tournament triangles and other things like this.
So you know, is it possible for us to go sort of get the ability to
specify quads?
Yes, a little bit but really it was exactly the most efficient thing
since that's not the common case, most of the time in 3D rendering,
right?
We're drawing much more complicated shapes with triangles and so on
usually index, triangular rays are always what?
You want?
And the reason that you want those is because vertices are almost
always shared.
In the case of quads, we never share any vertices.
A quad is very specifically.
The most minimal way to specify the data that we have.
Because the only time we share vertices is in the two triangles that
make up the quad.
So specifying GL quads is the perfect way to specify exactly what is
shared among any Primitives in our set.
It's, it's happens to be exactly right for what we're doing and it
saves us from having to submit an index stream normally what you do in
3D.
Obviously is you have two streams that you're specifying?
At least 21 is the stream of the vertex data and the other is a stream
of indices into that vertex data because usually you have a lot of
sharing and I could sort of illustrate to you what I mean by that.
So, here's my Milton.
So normally what happens, we'll just call this vertex sharing.
So normally, what happens in 3D rendering right?
Is you've got some shapes, you know, who knows what they are, but
you've got something and, you know, maybe you're talking about some
like cross-section of a curved surface or something, you know?
And you're drawing it like this.
Right?
So this is what, you know, the the actual triangles look like, and you
can see, there's tons of triangles are 123456789 bubble.
All right.
And for any one of the vertices in here, what I think you can see, if
you look at it carefully is that there's a lot of triangles that share
that vertex.
So for example, this is the typical shape, you might see in terms of
triangles emanating from a Vertex you'll typically see something like
This pattern, right.
So one, two, three, four, five, six, different triangles.
And you know these are these are triangles that just Edge.
Doesn't happen to pass through this vertex but you can see that there
is usually like six triangles.
Let's say that all touch a single vertex.
What that means is that if you were specifying the stream just as
vertices, it would be extremely inefficient because you would specify
Defy this vertex, six times, potentially right now.
If you were to send it down as quads, then you could, you could reduce
that amount of time.
It wouldn't be 6, but it would still be for, right?
Because if you take a look at what this would look like, you know, in
that same case where you weren't specifying The Edge going through, it
would still be one, two, three, four times.
That that vertex had to be talked about the reason we don't have this
problem is because we're only talking about one square at a time.
So a quad is
We specified by four vertices in our case and we never have to do
anything else and they'll never be shared.
There's nobody who comes along here and shares that vertex, right?
Now, that's not 100% true, all the time.
I mean, there could be cases where we would eventually share for, I
don't, but I really don't think.
So, even our cubes have different color values, the vertices, for
example.
So anyway, so given that, that's the case.
Normally, the way that things are specified is using an index stream
in Everett Xtreme at a minimum, right?
So, basically you specify your vertex data here?
And so, for this example, if this is vertex a to vertex,
Jim would just have the entry a in it and then the indices when we
went through here, you know, if this was at position zero, the indices
here would have that appear six times, right?
So you would in the index dream.
see, six different times when vertex a is
In that stream.
And if you think about how much of savings that is usually indices are
16-bit.
Roughly, you know, they're 65,000 vertices / buffer or something like
that.
And 16-bit in these, the buffer, various stuff like this.
If you think about how much smaller 16 bits is than a typical vertex,
a typical vertex, Even in our case which is a pretty straightforward
case.
We're not sending down crazy stuff like tangent frames or Advanced
sort of like lighting material info that we might need like you would
in a
So realistically rendered 3D situation if you think of how much
smaller 16-bit is well, even just the position, right?
A 3D position in a lot of cases is going to be 3 floats, right?
So that's 12 B just for the position, this is just two bites, right?
So even if you were expressing any other data you would already be
talking about 6X compression here in terms of how many times you were
saving that, right?
But it's usually much worse than that.
Usually there's texture, coordinates and color, and tangent frame, and
all these other sorts of things that come in here, right?
And so, you're talking about vertices, you can be 32, bytes, 64 by 128
bytes, you can have very large vertex data, so specifying them with
indices really saves, that 6X compression there, right?
I'm only specifying two bites in every time I want specified that
vertex rather than 12 or 32 or
64 or whatever else.
So that's that's a big deal, right?
Furthermore, there is an additional reason why index data helps you.
The reason is because the graphics card doesn't have to do the
transforms multiple times.
So for example, in this case where I have these vertices, let's
suppose that there wasn't really a space savings.
I didn't care about space savings at all for whatever reason.
Memory bandwidth is free all of a sudden or something like that.
So all I care about is computation time.
I still think, you know, I would still care about this index format.
The reason for that is because if this vertex itself were repeated,
many times, the graphics card doesn't know that the gravel start isn't
going to sweep through your vertex list looking for duplicate vertices
and go, aha, right.
What it's going to do is it's going to take all your vertices and it's
going to transfer in them.
So it's going to run the vertex Shader right on all of these vertices.
So if you repeat a six times, you're going to pay the price.
vertex, Shader for a six times on the other hand, if you have an index
Then all the graphics card is going to do is transform a once, right?
And then it's going to use the transformed version of a six times.
Do you see how much better that is, right?
So basically the compression here is not just compressing the space of
the vertex buffer down.
It's also compressing the computation time down because now the
computation only has to happen on each unique set of vertex data and
then we can reference that index.
Data post transform post vertex.
Peter.
And if those vertex shaders, get complicated as they do in photo
realistic, 3D games, you know Battlefield one.
Its vertex Shader doesn't look like three instructions like ours does,
right?
Or sorry.
I should say three lines of code, you know, they got these big things
doing all kinds of nonsense, right?
And so if you can compress that down, that's a real savings.
You're talking about many times the performance in terms of, of how
little
Work has to get done by comparison, right?
Okay, so basically in Cora what they decided is that basically they're
only going to support this really?
So GL quads, they don't care about their like the case where that
matters is so specific to like people throwing Sprites at the screen
or something.
We don't care about that, let them just do it this way or maybe make
some other way of doing it.
I don't know, it doesn't matter.
We don't care.
So the problem for us is they've gotten rid of the thing that happens
to do exactly what we want.
We are already getting all of this for free because GL quads happens
to do the exact perfect sharing for our vertex dream without requiring
an index buffer.
So we're saving the space of an index buffer as well, right?
So quads is exactly how we want to send things down but we can't send
it down that way.
And that leaves us with a little bit of a conundrum unfortunately so I
don't really know what we can do about this.
I'll have to think about it a little but what I want to do first is I
want to come back here and and re-enable this as it is, and I'm just
going to turn off the debug call for now
I'm just going to verify that.
All those changes that we made still actually produce a working image
because I do want to make sure that we're actually getting a working
image here.
Like okay.
So you can see like we're not right?
And so I want to go through and make sure that because we just made
some fairly significant changes.
Their, I want to make sure that we can, you know, look if I go back to
the compatibility profile or whatever that we
That it will work because if we can't do that, then you know, we have
some debugging to do of the changes that we made.
All right, so let's take a look.
Here here's the core profile thing.
I'm going to go ahead and turn off the forward compatibility bit here.
Okay, so that's all I wanted to verify.
Because like that map, buffer stuff that are the buffer data stuff.
Like we didn't know.
If that is going to work, you know, I mean I know that it works.
I just don't know if we maybe had them, we could have had a mistake in
the call.
Or who knows?
What else.
So basically, the question now is, do we want to just leave the
forward compatible bit off?
and use g l quads or do we want to enable the forward compatible bit
and try to figure out a way to send down this data in a way that does
not
It does not run afoul of the corps profile.
Requirements.
Now, this may just be the fact that I'm not a GPU person, but to be
honest, I don't know of a straightforward way to get back the
performance of GL quads.
And here's why.
So if I'm going to say GL quads,
Then there is a pretty easy way.
In fact, let me just write this as a sort of side by side.
So in Geo quads, what I'm doing is I'm specifying vertices 01.
23.
Like so and opengl is going to draw these as two triangles.
Now, I don't remember the exact specification of which way it draws
the two triangles because it could pick either one, right?
But it's going to pick one of those two, and it's going to draw these
this way.
Now, g, l try strip.
Happens to do exactly what we want on the first element, right?
So, if we wanted to GL, triangle strip is something that goes like
this.
Notice the vertex order is subtly different here, but what it does is
it does the exact same thing.
I think it does it this way, though.
Right now, I don't know.
GL quads may also do it that way.
I just, I just don't know.
We could look it up.
I'm sure.
It's in the spec Shield, the trial ship does basically exactly the
same thing.
The problem is what happens on the second primitive.
So on the second primitive after I do 0, 1, 2 3, then as I go four
five six seven, right?
I get another one of these.
And that's what I want.
What happens with?
Four, five, six, seven on Jill triangle strip is you actually get two
more.
So 0 1 2 3 4 5 actually specifies another attached quad.
So it actually uses the previous two.
As a shared Edge.
And then when I specify 67, I will actually get yet another
quadrilateral.
So I've given up the ability to draw separate Sprites and instead I
can draw a strip of Sprites.
You can understand why this might have been useful back in the day to
sort of plaster, over sides of things with you know, continuous
triangles or something, does not help us at all for Sprites because we
don't want them to be attached.
We want them to be separate.
Now, if we were going to be using an index list, then this problem
becomes trivial, there are a number of ways that we could make it
work.
The most straightforward of which is just to actually specify 6
indices per quod and then just draw GL triangles right.
Jill triangles allows us to just go like, oh, all right, well it's you
know, it's 0, 1 2,
And then we just specify it again zero to three.
Right, and then we just specify more triangles later.
So if we did an index list, you know, no problem and again that does
bloat, our space just a little bit, it means that we've basically
added an extra 16 bits per vertex that we didn't have before.
So unlike the index list saving a space which is kind of what they're
supposed to do.
It's actually making things worse for us.
So it's it's worse in our case because we had a perfect case for Jill
quads.
So we're losing to B pervert.
If we do that but it would just work, right?
The other thing we could do is we could use GL triangle strip and not
pay quite as much.
I shouldn't say that it's not, it's actually more than 16 bits per
vertex because each vertex has to be specified on average, not twice.
But for, you know, instead of four things we're sending down six.
So, in addition to each vertex, taking 16 bits more.
There's also 32 bits more of just extra extraneous.
Specified data divided, amongst those.
So it's more like 20 bits per vertex, extra if that makes any sense.
So what we could do even better than that because we can use what's
called GL triangle strip.
With.
And what that is, is Jill, trying to strip with restart.
If you think about how many things would take to specify for geo
triangles here for one quad, we had a specified 0, 1 2, 0, 2 3.
Right.
That's six indices
Okay, what we can do is specify a GL triangle shape with the restart
with that is is it says I'm going to use an index buffer, so I still
got to do things this way.
But there's going to be a special index.
Let's say it's the maximum value of 65535.
Let's say there's going to be a special value that when you see it,
you restart the Primitive sequence.
So you don't attach them anymore.
So this allows you to draw like one, triangle strip, and then issue
the restart and start drawing a new triangle strip.
That's disconnected from it, right?
And we could use that restart on every quad, so that would allow us to
do.
Okay, let's specify 0, 1, 2 3, right.
Then we'll specify
Five 65535 to restart the quad then we'll specify 4, 5, 6 7 right now,
when you look at that index Dream, It's just 0 1, 2 3, 6, 5, 5, 3 5,
4, 5, Loops 6 7.
Right.
That's only five, indices.
/ quad, so you can get better than six indices for Quad.
If you go with GL triangle strip with restart because the restart
allows you to
Do what you need to do there, right?
That's what etcetera.
So I don't really know at the moment.
I think we do have one Saving Grace, which is, we can just cheat the
reason we can cheat is because we change textures every triangle at
the moment.
I mean every quad at the moment, so if you take a look at what we're
doing here,
We always are issuing a separate draw arrays, call every time we want
to do a quad so because we have not addressed that particular
performance issue because in order to address it, we would need to
move to a texture or a texture atlas of very much more complicated
backing system that would, that would actually also require texture
packing and all these other sorts of things.
We'd have a huge amount of work, we'd have to do to get away from it.
In order to do that.
If we aren't doing that yet, we do have the opportunity of cheating
here because, hey, we don't have to represent more than one.
So we don't have to do a restart which means that if we change this to
drill triangle strip, all we would have to do is change the order in
which the vertices are put in there and in
Are we that will just work so we can cheat it right now.
And you can see that this is not correct at the moment because again,
we the order is wrong like that, this is that order.
Where is that?
Let me actually do this the right way.
So this is that ordering difference between this and this, right?
It's 0 1 2 3 in the quads case 0 1, 2 3 in the strip case.
So that's that difference.
You're seeing but we can fix that pretty easily.
Let me just go ahead and turn this back on.
There it is.
So, we have the forward compatible bit on now.
And we're drawing his quads and we should get that error that we were
getting, which is the only area I think that we had left.
So there it is.
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to call GL triangle strip and
now hopefully, this means will now be completely compliant at least as
far as the driver is concerned.
Right.
There you go.
But we're just drawing a little bit wrong.
And again, that's the order difference problem.
So, in order to fix that all we would have to do is inside our render
group where we're doing all of our vertex stuff.
Oops,
It's push quad.
The only thing that we call.
Now don't actually know it.
I think it is.
So, whenever we call Push quad, we were previously pushing the quad in
in this order, right?
We were doing P0 P1 P2 P3 Around the Horn.
Instead what we can do is just switch that order, right?
You can see here, previously, you know, we were doing 0 1, 2, 3.
So all we need to do now is just do 0312, right?
So if we just said, okay,
03.
12 is the New Order.
The quads go down.
Now we're in the right order for triangle strips and since we already
do a restart every time because the draw arrays we cheated out of it
right?
But you can see why if we expanded that batch and there's two ways we
can play in.
The batch one is by again building a texture Atlas and using the UV
coordinates either inside an app, a single Atlas image or Texture
eraser
Both the altimeter and the depth by using UV coordinates to pick out
the part of the image that we wanted rather than switching textures if
we did that.
Or if we use cards, that allow you to specify texture pointer per
primitive which we also could do, right?
Like I'm video cards can do this.
For example, if we did either of those performance optimizations at
some point, this Trek no longer works.
Because we would no longer be restarting.
The batch, every time
So again, I will leave it like this for now.
I would be interested to hear from people who are more GPU familiar
than I am.
So a GPU rendering expert.
Basically, I'd be varied to hear from a rendering expert, what?
They think the best way to do quads, in this case would be because,
you know, assuming that we wanted to fix this.
So that it so that if we were to do some of those performance
optimizations of the future,
How would we solve this problem?
Because even if we don't do those other things for things like
particle systems, we probably will still just set one texture and then
draw many of them.
So we're going to hit this case.
And the question is, what's the best way to do it?
I'm assuming that the answer is probably just switched to a geometry
Shader.
Where it will automatically output the correct vertices and indices or
something like this.
I don't really know though.
So I would really like to hear from somebody who has a lot more
experience working with the high end GPU sorts of stuff to say, what's
the right way to, you know, to phrase that because there are other
options obviously, using an index buffer with restarts is another
option using an index buffer, and just you'll triangles and just
actually building the index.
Buffer is another
And right, it'd be really cheap for us to do, right?
We could do it.
Trivially right here.
We would just do it in this push quad call.
We just have a parallel index.
Are that we're building?
Is that the smartest way to do it, right?
So there's lots of ways we could do it and I just, I'm not sure which
way is smart these days, you know, which way is, which way would you
do it?
If you were going to take your first, what your best guess, right.
And I don't know if we run into actual performance problems, then
that'll be nice because then we could just try multiple ways and see
which one's faster at the moment that seems like a colossal waste of
time because this as it is changing textures.
Every time is actually plenty fast for our purposes.
So, I think that's a pretty good place to leave it now.
So I think we've done what I wanted to do, which was eliminate any use
of the old compatibility context at all.
and now we're, you know, we're totally good to go on the, on the
Core profile.
So for now that's that's plenty good.
I feel like we should now move on.
Probably won't have a chance to do anything else significant today
because I think we've used up most of our
I'm doing that, but that's okay that went quite well.
And so the next thing that I think I want to do is re-enable, some of
the stuff that we lost when we went to the new pipeline.
So we've got I think about 20 minutes left.
I'm going to go take a look and see, can we start re-enabling say our
debug view, right?
Because we lost our orthographic, projection code.
We never updated for the new system in opengl.
So I'd be interested to see if we can go ahead and get the
orthographic projection stuff back online.
So if you remember how this worked right inside our we sort of did
this camera transform stuff and you can see here, we were calling this
and we have flags and so on we would check to see whether we were
doing orthographic.
And if we were doing orthographic in this case, we would do this
orthographic projection call currently.
We're not getting any rendering of our debug stuff at all, so we don't
really know what's going on there.
We, I think we didn't even bother looking at it.
I don't even
Know, if the orthographic projection code is actually implemented, you
know, we have to build a matrix for that.
I don't know that we actually did.
We probably probably built something, but I don't know what that
something is.
Let's see.
So yeah, if you take a look at, you can see what's happening here with
this orthographic projection call here.
You can see that this is not actually doing anything with Z at all.
It's it's just got it passing through directly and that's, at the very
least, not going to work with the z-buffer, right?
We have to still map Z to the correct range regardless of what we do.
if we aren't going to modify the W coordinate for the divide or
anything like that,
So perspective, wise again, if the Divide is going to happen you can
see what's going on here.
You would want to make sure that you prevent The Divided from
occurring.
That's what would happen in this case because we have a w coordinate
of 1 here, right?
And nothing nothing that the Z coordinate so that one is going to be
pretty much what we want.
However, in this particular case, since we do have Z bias values
coming down,
in the orthographic, projection case, I guess there is a little bit of
There's a little bit of trouble there because yeah, those Z bias
values.
Oh well, okay, we've got a Vertex Shader though and the vertex Shader
takes care of those.
You bias value so that that should actually be fine.
So yeah, so it should be fine.
So really all we have to do here I think is actually do that mapping.
You can see here that
Got the near and far clipping plane sort of stuff happening here and
we want that to happen in both cases, right?
We want to be able to set the near and far clipping plane stuff.
To me for orthographic projections as well because if the Z buffer is
still enabled during the orthographic projection pass.
When we're drawing, whatever is coming down that pipe, we still need
to make sure that it is actually doing, you know what it's doing.
Like you know, the words we have to have the orthographic projection
call.
Still produce the values that can be used with the z-buffer unless we
just turn the z-buffer off for the orthographic projection past.
Now, that's not a bad idea because if you think about what's going to
happen, everything that's drawn during that orthographic projection
pass is like our UI stuff, right?
And it's unclear that we really want the Z buffer to be in effect
there anyway.
But who actually we don't know that we don't want the z-buffer on.
It seems like we probably do.
Um, because we could use that for sorting UI elements and stuff like
that.
And since we don't care about the ui's appearance in any way we can
even lean on the alpha to coverage stuff, to give us the eight levels
of transparency as well, which should be sufficient for our purposes.
So really probably just want to make it work.
So since these are basically the same, I believe we can just use
exactly the same code here for the, you know, the
Code that we were using.
So in the case, where we're not dividing by negative Z, right, we're
going to end up with this.
We already worked out with the non perspective.
Corrected terms are right things that aren't divided.
So hopefully we did that math, right?
And we can just use it, right?
So we can actually say, well, okay, here's the perspective ones.
There are the non perspective ones.
Now we never set a near and far clipping plane, right?
At the moment, those are just hard coded and eventually probably we
could just pass those in.
Although to be honest, I don't know that we ever will change the near
and far clipping plane the near and far clipping plane for the most
part isn't something that we're probably going to play with, I don't
know.
So to a certain extent it's not clear what we really want to do with
those.
We certainly can pass them in but we don't really need to
So anyway, if we go ahead and take a look here, what we can do is we
can make it so that as things are passed down, you can see what
happens with the Matrix here.
We basically would be doing exactly the same thing that we'd be doing
in the prospective case, taking the Z and trying to map it in between
the near and far clip planes, so that it basically produces that that
value since we're not dividing by Z at all at, all right?
We're just weird.
Eventually producing a w coordinate after the major transform of 1.
In that case, what we're going to see is that we don't need to do the
correction like these, have that correction baked in for the fact that
you're going to divide by Z afterwards.
In this case, we're not going to do that.
So I believe, this is what we need for orthographic projection, for
the most part, if I remember correctly.
I think that's basically correct.
However, we've got a bunch of other stuff that we're going to have to
deal with and that is that the orthographic projection used to, if I
remember correctly, take care of.
So of the camera part of the transform4, the, to be bug you.
I so what's happening with our orthographic transform at the moment?
If you look at it is, it's not doing any kind of scaling here.
So what that means is that this is not in pixel coordinates anymore,
this orthographic projection, it's going to be 0 to 1, right?
That's what it's basically looking at.
And so that orthographic projection when we do it here you can see
here that we've got this other thing where we've got the camera
transform, that comes in this part right here and the projection gets
multiplied by that camera, transform.
That part right there is the part that's currently needs to get
modified in order for our code to work at all in terms of setting up a
pixel-based.
Like, I don't know how to say it.
Exactly.
Previously, we're trying to map the screen in actual pixel space, so
that the debug you, I would just work in basically, in pixel space,
right?
The, the debug you, I didn't have the idea of a camera transform,
where was actually, like, looking at the screen from somewhere in
particular, or doing any kinds of rotation, obviously, for, you know,
obvious reasons.
But now what we have is, we have a circumstance where the orthographic
projection doesn't know anything about pixel space.
It doesn't know how big the screen is.
So,
As a result, this a b value here.
The only thing that it's doing is correcting for the aspect ratio.
That's the only thing this orthographic projection is doing what that
means is that the coordinates for addressing the screen.
When you're actually trying to draw things in the debug you, I are now
going to range from negative 1 to 1, not from 0 to night to 1920,
right?
Or however many, however, why the screen is so that means our debug
you.
I still needs to.
Now start thinking about that camera transform, and when it calls set
camera transform, it's going to have.
Have to put itself into the kind of space that it's expecting to use
manually because the orthographic transform isn't hard-coded to do
that anymore.
So, let's take a look at set camera transform here.
Actually.
Well, that is, if I can find it.
There we go.
So, let's take a look at this.
This set camera, transform call.
And you can see right now exactly how this is working.
So you can see that you see this with and and that with is coming from
The actual parameters that are passed in here and that width and
height is, is actually, I believe in pixels, right?
And so, it believes that the left edge of the screen is the negative
of that with and the right of the screen is the positive with that's
going to just be massively wrong because our debug you I now is
thinking that it's in a space of you know - half of 1920.
So whatever that would be 960
Yeah, it's going to be thinking, it's going to be negative.
962 positive 960 is that right?
I-90.
960.
I was correct - 96 deposit a 960
But that is ridiculous.
That is 960 times larger than the orthographic.
Matrix is expecting the coordinates to be, that would cover the
screen.
And so, in order to compensate for that, what we would want to do
here, is we want to use the camera X camera.
Why that's being specified here right there.
There's the axes
That are being specified for the camera itself.
They look like this.
I think we could do as a pretty easy way to make this go back to the
way that, you know, being pixel Centered for this part of the UI we
want to do here is say okay, what if we instead, why is there an I
here, by the way?
Also, I think that's a Vestige of remains that's going to go away.
So when we set this camera transform, what we need to do, is change
the size of the X and Y axes here.
So that they compensate for
That width and height difference, right?
So I think what we could do is say well, alright, let's just add in
that scale factor.
There we say.
All right the this length of the axis is going to reduce how big we
believe the screen to be right.
Now, what we want to do is we want to make it so that you know that
that's not exactly the right equation because you think about it, we
were thinking of the left Edge and right Edge, you can see the
equations for them right here.
What we're saying is that the left edge of the screen we expect to be
negative with over to write.
This is the left Edge.
And the right edge of the screen were expecting to be with over to
right now what we want these to do is we want these to map to negative
one and one that's what we actually want our Earth.
That's what our orthographic Matrix thinks should be happening, right?
And so if we want that to occur, what we need to do is we need to make
an equation that works and access that would work.
So what we want to do is say well, alright.
What's the coefficient?
Right.
What's the what's the coefficient that when multiplied by W over 2
equals 1, what would we have to?
Do here, right?
So, you know, if we were to Define an access what's the, what's the
coefficient that would go here?
That would turn W over 2 into 1.
And so, you know, pretty simple to solve right multiply both sides by
2.
Right.
And then divided by w.
Right?
And so that's why I said this wasn't quite the equation here because
there's actually a doubling in there, that's because of the centering.
Okay, so given that, that's how we could sort of compensate for that.
We do have one other problem I believe, which is that the center?
Well,
I don't remember how we were finding the top edge of the screen
because the top edge of the screen is a little more complicated.
If we're correcting for aspect ratio.
Oh, but it should still work because it should still be height.
If we're correcting for aspect ratio, then I think this actually wants
to be this, does that make sense?
Because the aspect ratio correction term, is should not be baked into
the camera because it's going to be baked in here, right?
If we look at the math again, so the aspect ratio with over-height.
The, a term X is Primal, it's going to get mapped directly, which
means that this term should also be in terms of X, because this right
here will take care of the ratio between the width and the height.
I believe famous last words.
All right, so let's try to move a little further down here and see if
we can't get something to start showing up on the screen.
So what we're looking for here is we're looking for,
We want to start to get our debug UI back, right, or debug you, I was
supposed to be fonts showing up on the screen here.
Now, there's nothing drawn right here so we can eliminate, I hope out
of hand.
The possibility that the Z buffer itself, is causing a problem with
not making something draw.
However, we don't necessarily know that the clip plane isn't doing
that.
Right?
So the near and far clipping plane may very well be clipping something
in or out and then
Not seeing it here.
So while we know the Z, buffer is not the problem.
It's not that they don't something here, wasn't drawn.
And then you know prevented the other thing from drawing, right?
If we if we looked at it like this,
Forget how I did this like Zoom.
Oh yeah, if we were looking at a screen like that, then the Z buffer
would still be in play potentially, right?
Because it could be that these things were just in front of whatever
was there and it was actually drawing properly within the Z boundaries
but then you know,
It it turned out to not be visible, we know that's not happening
because when we look at the actual camera view of the game there is
empty space here.
So we know that that wasn't the case.
Okay, so now we have to ask the question.
Well, what are the other sorts of things that could be a problem here?
Well, one of them is that we probably aren't in within the z-buffer,
boundary for the near and far clipping planes.
The reason for that is we've got all this, you know, kind of crap.
We were doing here with backing transforms tooltip, transforms offset
Z stuff, right?
So the problem with that is all of these things, here are all
offsetting the Z in weird ways that we don't.
Like this is all just completely old school stuff that we were
throwing arbitrary values into effect, the sort order.
So we know we're going to have to fix that as well.
What I'm going to do for now is I'm going to turn these off as much as
possible, so that we know that they're not interfering with our
ability to get something, it looks like we probably have to stop here
and Tackle this tomorrow.
Because yeah, we don't we don't have time when we're at the
five-minute warning.
So let me just take a quick look to see if there's anything else I
want to.
I think that's basically what I want to do.
Probably probably stop at there and then we can start looking tomorrow
at how to set up things so that we're actually going to be able to see
them on the screen going forward.
So yeah, let's just go to an early Q&A because I don't want to get
started tracking that down and then have to stop.
Yeah.
I've done something horribly wrong.
I've hidden my hex chat window and now I do not know where it went.
Oh wretched.
Where's the AL bot?
I rebooted the computer and forgot to restart the owl bot.
That's a good point.
How?
We start the owl bot Alba.
Can I can I get that?
Can I add this to the start menu?
I just want to put him.
There we go, pin to start menu.
All right, so maybe the AL Bots online now.
Maybe he is.
Yes there is unfortunately I have lost
Hex chat.
Hex chat is gone.
I do not know where it went.
I accidentally clicked on something in all my stuff disappeared.
That's otherwise known as using the Linux Window Manager.
Yes, I have no idea how to get my ex chat back.
Hex chat.
New server window.
Reconnect to Twitch, Maybe.
all right, I think
Okay all right disaster narrowly averted if you could really answer.
If you had a question that you asked on the twitch chat, please re-ask
it because hex chat went away.
So now I can see just fine and I can answer the questions as I
intended to.
Matilda says about the quad thing.
You might want to do something like this maybe and then he posted a
link
See, it's about subdivision surfaces.
Yeah, so this is this is the geometry Shader approach that I kind of
alluded to.
I don't know if that's the most efficient way to do it.
I assume it is only because
As it means that the geometry Shader, you know, you can still just
feed it the vertices and it would presumably still work but I don't
know.
Like I said, I'd like to hear someone who probably the answer is.
It doesn't matter like either way is probably fine.
and the geometry Shader one, add some complexity, but it means you
don't have to specify a Vertex index buffer which saves some
You know, say some bandwidth, which seems like probably the better
choice but I don't know.
so,
It does not look like we have any questions.
Although it does look like, there's what 156 people on the list.
So people are watching but they are not asking anything.
Elephant says, you could avoid geometry shaders by instancing, a
triangle strip that is just a quad.
That does seem like it would work, right?
You can, as you can specify, I gotta go.
Look at how you specify instancing.
Again, I assume that would work.
Each color.
Use, what do you think about using a different set of programs Shader
a different program basically, for debug text one, which has no
projection Matrix at all.
Would it be bad to switch programs for, GUI text performance-wise?
No, it's not.
It would not be bad because, you know, since the debug you I is
strictly drawn on top of everything else, it doesn't even need to use
the Z buffer if you didn't really want to.
And so on, it is a
Pletely separated will thing, which means that it would be, you
wouldn't need to be transitioning programs all the time.
It's not like you need to switch between drawing.
Bug text and drawing Regular stuff like often.
Because the expensive part of having multiple programs is not, how
many programs you have.
It's how many times you have to switch.
So if you only have to switch programs once it's really not a big
deal, right?
However, I actually don't
Like once you go to the fixed function pipeline, once you go to the
pipeline like we're using it, you really don't have a choice but to do
a matrix transform, right?
Because opengl is going to want clip coordinates.
Always it wants negative 1 to 1, that's just has to happen.
So it's not like we can't have something that does the transform.
So whether we specify in a matrix that's compatible with our existing
Later or whether we write a new Shader to do it, we don't get out of
the work.
The work is the same and that's just making sure that our debug system
now outputs coordinates.
And some way of of transforming those coordinates into opengl as clip
coordinates, that's what we need to do.
And whether we do that via Matrix, or whether we did that by writing a
different Shader, it wouldn't matter.
So as far as I'm concerned, it's just better to do it by The Matrix
because then we only have one Shader and that's just less stuff for us
to think about, right?
You always want to reduce the numbers of things.
You have if you can, if there's no reason not to because that just
keeps things simpler and so I don't think it makes much sense.
Our case to create a different Shader for the debug text because it's
essentially exactly the same.
It would have to do exactly the same things that said, if you wanted
to, there is no reason for you, not to do so.
So if you had some benefits that you thought you were begetting by
writing a different Shader for the
Debug text, you know, we're already very light on shaders.
We've got one Shader right most games, have many, many, many shaders.
And by the time we're done, we'll probably have a few but 2D games
typically have a lot less shaders than 3D games.
3D games.
Can oftentimes have lots of different shaders that are based on
optimizations for different types of physical effects that are trying
to be rendered in that sort of stuff.
And so, even though, you know, you certainly don't want to have more
shaders, you want to keep the number down as low as you can.
It's not a typical for game to have 100 shaders in it, that's you
know, that wouldn't even be considered large.
There is the Third Way of setting the vertex data through ARB separate
a trip.
Format, went to court and 4.3, this separates, the vertex format from
the buffer it reads which is more optimal for the driver.
Yeah, that's probably true.
I don't know if that's supported on this card obviously and also I
probably not something that's
Do if you're looking for backwards compatibility, anything that's like
goes decor and 4.3 might be a little late.
I don't know again that would largely be about driver compatibility,
but yeah, obviously, if you can specify the vertex format separate
from the vertex data, that's obviously a better way to go because
they're not related information.
Robbie when the engine uses a deprecated function like Jill quads,
what are the main issues that people would have to deal with playing
the game because it is running right?
Yes.
And so, you know, one of the things you can certainly do is just say,
hey, you know what, I'll just do a compatibility context and off we
go, right?
I don't care.
But there are some reasons why you do want to maybe think about Cora
profile and they basically are a, it's probably going to be more
compatible across the
Vices, you know, Intel chip versus AMD chip versus Nvidia chip, it's
probably going to be more compatible.
The more you can stick to Just One Core profile because that's, at
least a known Target for the opengl vendor, that doesn't involve a lot
of permutations like oh they're using mostly core but then also
they're calling to yell quads which isn't part of core and blah blah
blah someone like Nvidia, who's very good at opengl drivers?
Is not going to have a problem with that other things may write and so
you just have to be aware of that and so if there's really no strong
reason for you not to do so you typically want to try and limit the
amount of opengl you're using in that way so that you can keep that
support surface smaller.
The other reason is because opengl es is obviously an important Target
for games as well.
The reason that that's an important Target is because mobile devices
tend to use that not regular opengl.
And if you take a look at opengl es, typically opengl es is harmonized
with opengl core.
Not opengl compatibility.
So, when you go to compile something on opengl ES, if you're open GL
Corps already, you're probably going to be just fine.
If you're not, you probably have issues.
For example.
I don't know if opengl es support squads at all.
I think it might not
Right.
I don't remember but I strongly suspect that quads just isn't
supported in opengl es dies at all.
And so at that point you're like well, okay, you know, yeah, maybe on
the PC, I could get away with always specifying GL quads, but then I
go to some mobile device and I'm trying to get this working on Android
or whatever else.
And it just won't be there.
So yeah, so I just could says, is opengl 3.0 the target version.
I would say yeah, roughly probably mostly because opengl 3 is pretty
widely supported everywhere.
It's close to opengl es so it can be done in Mobile as well.
Pretty easily.
And the other thing about it is that we don't need a lot of fancy
features.
So since we're not using a lot of fancy features, I feel like we
probably
Just shouldn't demand a bunch of GPU stuff.
We don't need asking for opengl 4.0 4.5 while I like the opengl 4.5
API a lot better.
Like, not a little, but like a lot better it's opengl 4.5 with the
azd.
Extensions is a very good API, in my opinion, probably the best one,
so far.
Would I fix a bunch of stuff in it?
Sure, but given the landscape of 3D apis opengl es I sorry opengl 4.5.
With the azd extensions is very close to the right API for 3D in my
opinion.
So what I love to use it.
Yes.
Do I think that's a good idea for a game like handmade hero?
No, because Hammond hero just does not need a lot of advanced 3D
performance or features because it's essentially a 2-D game.
For the most rounds of shoes has a light 3D stuff for a few things we
want to do.
I feel like it's just hampering, the game's ability to reach a wider
audience by requiring, this very high level of 3D.
Driver compliance that we just don't need.
Any idea why one can have stuttering problems using opengl dm0 dwm.
Well.
I mean not off the top of my head.
No stuttering problems.
I assume you're talking about, you know, not having a solid, 60 frames
a second or something like this and you know, the reasons why you can
miss a frame in windows are Myriad.
So it's pretty hard to know.
A lot of
Times if you're having stuttering problems, what they would be, they
can range anything from like you doing some slightly bad thing that's
actually just wrong and you just don't realize it because, hey, these
are big apis and it's easy to do something slightly wrong, where you
think you're calling swap buffers at the right time, but you're not.
Are you weren't swapping the right buffers or who knows what else.
But, you know, for the most part,
Part you even if you do everything perfectly, you could still get in
up in situations where you get some stuttering problems depending on
what you're doing.
So you know, windows isn't a real-time OS, its API substrate is is
very bad for games, especially multi-threaded games.
I would I would consider the opengl.
I'm sorry, I would consider the win32 API for multi-threaded games to
be very bad.
Like it is, it is just, I think relatively objectively speaking, a
very bad API for multi-threaded games and probably won't get better.
So, I really don't.
Yeah, I don't think I have much more to say about that other than, you
know, probably if you run an advanced 3D game on your system that runs
through the same API you're using.
So, for example, if you're using opengl, I believe Doom the the the
new Doom which is a very Advanced Graphics engine runs.
You can set that one to run through opengl.
You know the easiest way to test something is can you go run an
existing game through the same path you're using?
If that doesn't stutter, that's a pretty good indication that you're
doing something wrong.
If that does stutter, that's a good indication.
That is something wrong with the device configuration or whatever
you're doing, and dwm and whatever.
So to, what do you like better in opengl a video as opposed to Vulcan,
so Vulcan just has a tremendous amount of business in it, it doesn't
really support like properly.
So I guess the way I would say it is ideally a 3D API, has essentially
no calls, right?
And a 3D API should should have basically, the only calls are like, I
need to map some memory, and I need to execute command, I need to
execute code that I've given you.
Bye-bye mapping memory, Write the past.
And so the a CDO opengl stuff is very close to that you can do if you
are on an Nvidia card.
For example, you can actually do almost the entire 3D Pipeline with
just a few calls.
The calls are basically, like, here's some memory go.
And that's exactly what it should be.
There's a tremendous amount of business, you are specifying, all sorts
of things that don't need to be specified in Vulcan, and the reason
for that is as far as I can tell, anyways, that they really wanted to
be backwards compatible with a lot of stuff.
So, you know, you're doing all kinds of descriptor this and chain
that, and all these other sorts of things that, like, you know, should
never have needed to be described because they are all things that
should just be dynamically.
We accessed in a Shader but they force you to do all that stuff
because some cards can't handle.
Things like buying those textures and so on.
And so you end up having to do a bunch of more stuff in Vulcan as far
as I can tell.
Now again, that was as of the last time I looked at Vulcan which was
before it was officially released.
And so, I guess what I would say is I don't know if maybe they've made
some improvements to it, but the way I would phrase it sort of
In a more abstract way, is all you really need to do in my opinion, to
tell whether a 3D API is even close to being right, is to count the
number of calls you make to it.
If that number is more than a handful,
It's about API at this point in my, in my opinion, right?
The number of calls to the API should be almost done because
essentially what, you know, I mean, how many calls do you make to the
API of your CPU?
None, you compile code for it and executes, that's what a GPU should
be doing for the most part, right?
And so the number of calls that you make to a GPU should be almost
done, everything should be data.
That's placed in buffers that the buffer stood be suspect,
Eventually card should read those buffers directly as much as possible
and Legacy Hardware should have to do software translation of those
buffers.
That's how these things should work.
Vulcan wasn't designed that way, Vulcans designed for good backwards
compatibility in a lot of ways, it's designed to not slow down older
cards.
I think that was a fundamentally bad decision, but I understand why
they made it.
They were trying to do something different than what I would want to
do with an API, right?
There's probably, you know, there's a bunch of things I would probably
disagree with about the vulkan API even for what they were trying to
do.
But I think fundamentally the thing that I disagree with about that
vulkan API is what they were trying to do.
I think if you were going to make a new 3D Graphics API, at this
point, what you should have done is aim for a API that has very little
substrate to it.
It should have been about getting code to cards and executing that
code.
That's what it should have been about.
Wasn't about that.
And as a result, it's a monstrous API with literally hundreds of
calls, most of which, I don't think should be there.
Would it be interesting to implement opengl on top of opencl?
Yeah, it would be interesting.
I mean, you know, we wrote the software rasterizer in
We wrote the software rasterizer in handmade hero for, you know,
obviously, similar reasons, it's just to show.
Here's how you get a rendering works and so it would be a very
interesting exercise right to implement opengl on top of opencl, in
the sense like hey, let's make a graphics API but let's implement the
whole thing.
But we're just going to implement the whole thing on a GPU instead of
a CPU, write it again.
Be very interesting to do.
I don't know that there's any real reason to do it, other than the
fact that would be interesting and educational, but it would certainly
be both of those things.
I would think.
Robinson's Hameed here is using multi-threaded processing of the game
entities.
How would the game stutter when time wouldn't be enough till the next
frame?
I'm not sure what that is referring to exactly what I would point out
is that multi-threaded pressing?
Amenities is not something that we're really doing much of right now.
We did some work to make sure that that worked properly.
By isolating the simulation stuff so that it can be run on multiple
threads at once.
But we don't really use that right now in the future, we met were
probably going to revisit some of those things because we have to
figure out kind of what our budget is for doing updating of the world
and stuff like that.
So obviously, that's stuff that we'll look at later on, but at the
moment we don't really do anything there.
All right, I'm going to shut this down.
Oops.
I don't know what that was about.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here at Oregon.
It comes to the source code.
If you want to play around with the opengl stuff or the other sort
stuff, we've been working on.
It's all included.
There we also have forms that you can go to.
If you want to ask questions a patreon page, you can go to.
If you want support the video series schedule about you can use if you
want to know when we're going to be live and an episode guide, that
allows you to catch up on past episodes.
Speaking of when we're going to be live, we will be back here
tomorrow.
Same
Time.
Same place to take a look at getting the debug you.
I flowing through the opengl path correctly and then I think we should
be mostly done with the opengl stuff that we were doing.
There's a couple other things that we probably want to turn back on.
For example, stacked levels on top of each other Alpha blending out
with something that we had in the previous version, we want to
re-enable that and it's not too hard for us to re-enable that now,
especially now that we have the z-buffer stuff.
And so that's an interesting thing, we could take a look at similarly,
the
Jogging so that distance-based fogging that we implemented before.
It's another thing, that would be nice to be able to implement on the
opengl stuff.
Those are actually much easier to implement now than they used to be.
Now that we're going through a full 3d pipeline, so, we should take a
look at implementing those.
If we have time tomorrow, we'll do that.
If we don't, we'll do it the weekend after.
That's about it.
Thanks for joining me.
And yeah, have fun programming.
I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.