Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
This is the show where normally we could complete game from scratch
live on stream at 5 p.m.
but today, we're doing at 8:30 p.m.
so, it's a weird time and I may just fall straight asleep in the
middle of the stream.
So, maybe like we're typing in the code, we're typing in the code word
and then I just fell asleep.
It could happen.
You never know.
So anyway, where we left?
Things off yesterday is I talked about wanting to do a little bit of a
modification to the way in which the renderer was sort of integrated
into the platform code and I outlined basically what that was going to
be.
For those of you who may not, remember really what I wanted to do was
make it so that the game itself doesn't call out into the opengl.
Renderer the game just produces a buffer of instructions for the
opengl code.
And then the opengl code does its thing.
That's what I wanted to do.
And today, we're going to go ahead and do that.
Not very complicated, right?
It's not a particularly weird thing to want to do.
So hopefully it's it's something that you guys will just be like.
Oh yeah, right I see what's going on.
No problem.
So today is day, 2, 30?
No, it's not days to 40.
And so if you want to follow along at home, use the day 239, source
code.
And and that's where I'm, that's where I'm at.
Okay, so let's go ahead and bring the game back up here.
Right now, we basically have everything working through opengl but we
don't actually have things working correctly through open jail.
There's obviously the architectural change that I wanted to make but
there's also the other thing I mentioned, which is our textures or not
working properly at the moment, meaning, we don't download them in the
way that we might want.
So there's a bunch of opengl stuff that we want to be able to do that.
We're not doing at the moment.
Mint.
And and so we have more opengl work to do.
But before we do any more of that I wanted to take care of this aspect
of it first,
All right, so let's go ahead and do that.
See how we need to do that.
So what I want to be able to do here is I want to be able to carry a
single render group kind of all the way through for the entirety of
the process that needs to happen.
And so if you take a look at what goes on here, like for example, in
debug
Oh, that's interesting.
I guess I pulled that out.
Well, you know what, good for me if you take a look at what's happens
here in debug game frame and you can see that inside here, we actually
do a bunch of stuff.
With our actual rendering in the, in the debug code, right?
And so right now, we actually create and Destroy two, different D, two
different, render groups, essentially one that renders, the game and
one that renders the debug group.
Right now, they both that's all controlled inside the game.
So what I'd like to move to is something we're all of these actually
just take a render group in and do their rendering through the render
group and the render group comes from the platform.
So that, that way, I don't have this thing with the game calling out
to opengl, which is what it's, you know, what it was doing.
Yeah.
All right, so let's take a look at how we might do that.
So first of all inside handmade platform.sh, where we include our
stuff, we would need to start having our handmade our rent, handmade
render group stuff would have to be sort of known to the platform
layer if that makes sense in at least some
Some some limited capacity.
We can start this in something in a way that's not to ownerís, right?
We can start this by saying, well, you know, when we call through, you
know, to the, to the game here, and we pass in, right?
Because here's our game update and repress, the the game memory, the
game input, and we pass this game off-screen buffer, right?
What we can do is say, let's go ahead and take that game off stream
buffer out of the picture, right?
Let's, let's pull that back.
If that makes sense.
And this is a very simple change was going to take awhile to make
because it happens to sort of be in everything appear to have gotten
like, a, i got water on my glasses, let's see if I can get that off.
I drank a little too vigorously from the water bottle.
It would appear.
Much better, okay, so if I want to get rid of that and replace it with
something else, you know, and game off-screen buffer.
Essentially is the thing that now I would be replacing, I would
replacing that with a instead of, instead of looking like this, where
we say what the pixels are and all that stuff, I would be replacing
this essentially with
That game render group, right?
So the render group would actually be what I would be passing in.
And so, let's just start by making that change and we'll see how it
goes so game.
And you can see right here, render rendering specifically will become
a three-tier distraction.
That's exactly what we're sort of doing that, right?
We already sort of started to introduce that with the opengl side of
things.
So this to do is actually exactly what we're doing right now.
So let's just take this one step at a time.
Here's game.
Off-screen buffer.
I'm going to go down here and I'm going to replace that.
And I'm just going to say that we're going to pass render group.
and so, this right here,
The render group itself is exactly what we're passing.
So we're passing this thing in.
Okay?
So let's go ahead and do that.
And now we can sort of see that.
Well, the buffer actually we should probably not call Buffer.
Let's call it render group.
So, so now we have this sort of stuff where we've got the, you know,
widths and Heights in those sort of things that are being dealt with
in here.
And I want to just get rid of those, for the time being I'm going to,
I'm going to get rid of the test drive.
We're drop by 4 size because I don't really care about that.
The moment, we can always add that back in.
We're doing more in stuff later and we don't have to care now about
any of this stuff, either write all of this stuff.
Go away as well.
All right, we don't need to do our render group allocation, either
that can now, again, move outside to win32 handmade.
So, when we do update and render in here, right?
When we do game update and render, we can do the allocate render group
stuff at that point, right?
So we can say, all right, let's go ahead and take this out and we'll,
you know, we'll put in our sort of
Just up there.
So maybe we'd put that, I'm not sure exactly where we'd want to put
that.
Maybe we'd put that in here perhaps.
I'm not 100% certain where we would want to put it.
Exactly.
But it would it would come out somewhere here, I guess, to be honest,
you know, maybe since we have two, we're going to have to do routing
for like the assets and stuff like that.
Really?
What we probably will have to do is make it so that the game can give
us back kids sort of
Well.
I guess, what I mean is, we are going to need some way for the game to
participate in this process, in a way that isn't quite fully.
Not owning the render group because we don't want to move all of this
stuff out.
We only want just a render group so it's going to take us a little
while to again to massage it into a place where these two pieces are
no longer.
You know are essentially abstracted away, right?
Because
Asset part where we call into the render group, that part is sort of
going to have to call through to something.
And as I'm saying it, I feel like maybe that means we should name this
something different, if that makes sense.
Like we could this we might be able to make this easier on ourselves
by saying that really this just the push buffer, part is going to be
out here if that makes sense.
And the render group just takes that push buffer when it is actually
going to start rendering, right?
So it's more like this.
that seems like a saner because I don't want to have to get the
Stuff.
I don't want to have to pull all that out that seems like it's just
going to be a huge pain and it does there's no benefit to it.
It would actually just make things worse, I think.
And so, I think what I really want to do here is actually have a thing
called a like platform or game, push buffer or game render buffer,
something like that.
Game render commands, I don't know, commands commands.
Something like that.
Let's say.
And so then up here, where we're talking about the game output, buffer
stuff the game off stream, buffer stuff, right?
What I could do is say, like, okay, we've got a game render commands
thing and that can still have the width and the height, then it
potentially.
But then it's going to have the part here for the render group where
it had like this stuff where the push buffer information was so all of
the stuff that was for the push buffer, that all comes over here.
But everything else can stay on the other side, right?
In the game where it probably belongs.
And that seems like a better idea to me.
Right.
So there's our game render commands.
That seems like a better way to go there, so I'm going to leave it
like that.
And then here will create one of those.
So we have one of these game render commands things, right?
And this will just be like allocate render commands and it just
doesn't need most of this stuff, right?
So it doesn't need any of this stuff and really I guess when we do
allocate render commands probably this should be something that's in
the platform layer itself.
So maybe that's even something that's
That might even be something that we kind of want to handle
separately, so it may be like that.
It's actually like, okay, we get render commands and we just do
something like, okay, we have a render commands, we say initialise
render commands, and we just say, like, okay that's, that's going to
take, however, big the render commands are and I did and well, that's
probably, that's probably it.
So be something like this.
Where we'd say, like initialise these guys?
And we're going to need some memory, so we'd have something like you
know, render command sighs or maybe push buffer size.
and,
Push buffer, and that would do something like this would be a virtual
Alec here.
And I do this push buffer size,
Right?
And that would just be something where we pass the stuff that we know
that we actually need.
For example, here's the game off-screen, buffer stuff.
And so maybe we pass these guys as well, right.
So in here, we have these and so now we know that this thing can be
initialized in a particular Way by feed forwarding, you know, feeding
forward, the information that we have there and maybe that's just the
thing right here.
That's like a nice little in line.
Any any platform layer who wants to implement this can do?
Okay, so there's the end, I guess we sort of said here.
If this has to be you 32, so I guess we're talking about something
smaller.
It's got to be what we smaller, which, I guess makes sense.
All right.
So anyway, so there's our push buffer here is our width and height?
I don't know why those are ants.
So, let's put that in there, and then we've got render commands.
That is the output of this thing.
So, let's see here.
And you know what, we could do to, we could do it like this.
Because again, it's an inline.
So it shouldn't really be a problem.
It could should be able to
Do it this way.
Now, there is, I guess there is one sort of nastiest there which is
that if we're doing all this in see than the inline part wouldn't
work, right?
So, I have to think about what I want to do about that.
I could make it a pound of fine.
Basically, what I need to do, just to you, if Case, you're not quite
on board with that is in render group, we have the allocate call,
right?
And the allocate call kind of does its thing here, right?
Where it, you know, it initialize all is all this stuff and we need
that stuff to happen, right?
We want all of this stuff to, we want to be able to do all these
things.
And so I want, you know, this, let's see.
I want all of this stuff to happen there.
Let's see clear render values.
So, yeah, clear render values would need to set these things.
Like the push.
Buffer size, push, buffer, base, push, buffer element count, sword
entry.
So it would need to set all of this stuff, right?
So basically, this is what I'm talking about, something that handles
all of this stuff for us.
So it's like there's the push buffer element count.
There's a sort of Entry at here is the size is zero and all that stuff
is there?
So basically all of these things and I guess, you know, in some sense
Yeah sometimes I'm going to have to kind of pull some of that out a
little bit.
Also if we want to keep the ground chunk thing happening which at this
point the ground chunks have been so annoying.
The entire time that I feel like at this point we probably just want
to say not bother with them because like I said, I don't actually
think we need them for anything.
But that's sort of a separate issue.
Anyway, so we want something like this and we have to be able to
initialize the things.
We don't need this part obviously, so we really only need this part
where we say, okay, the push buffer base is whatever is happening in
here.
The max push buffer size is whatever gets passed in is the buffer
size, we've got the width and height.
Like so we've got the, let's see what else we got element count and
the sword entry at.
So all of this, this is pretty much it.
That's all we need to do to initialize one of these one of these guys
right and there really isn't anything else that's necessary.
So if we assume that this was a pound of fine, I guess we could just
make it a pound to find that someone uses to make sure that they
initialize one of these correctly.
It would look like this.
With height, Max put buffer size.
Push buffer.
The push before base the element count.
And the sword entry at.
So we could do something like this where we basically say Okay oops I
should put keep that in there, you know render.
Command struct something like this.
And that's just an easier way for them to make sure they get the
parameters in the right order and stuff like that, right?
Does that make sense?
So now you can do like, okay, you know, I want initialize one of
these.
I've got render commands equals render command struct and now I can
pass how big I wanted to size to be and I can pass to push buffer that
I had and I can pass the width and height and I know that the macro
will like do the right thing there and won't mess everything up.
So now it's time through, we would generate one of these render
commands things.
Then when we do game update and render, we just pass that render
command buffer in.
And then what we can do by the exact same token is as we come down
here.
Our and before that we're actually going to render when we call debug
frame and instead of passing the buffer we just passed the render
commands again.
And then when we get down to the very end, before we start with the
stuff that would be happening with the V blank and all that stuff,
right?
We now have we would have after everyone was finished, both the debug
code and the game code would have stuffed all of their things that
they wanted to render into the push buffer.
/ for the render commands, we would then be able to say, okay now that
you did all that stuff, just go ahead and go ahead and render all
that, right?
So when we do our display but display buffer in window here, instead
of us having to, you know instead of us having to do like the global
back bumper thing where we have a particular back, buffer or whatever
is happening, there are 132 display buffer and window could actually
just
Take whatever the render commands are that are supposed to be
happening now, and then win32 display buffer and window could be
responsible for basically taking care of that process.
So, it would take the game render commands.
Here here are the commands,
Like so.
And then we could go ahead and have
we can go and we can go ahead and have that.
Do the rendering right here.
So, what it could do is it could say like, oh, okay, you know, if I am
in Hardware, right?
If I'm in Hardware
Then here I'm going to call the opengl renderer.
And so now we're basically taking this part here where we had the.
We had this stuff right here.
We're taking this this stuff and removing it back out to where we were
before this, this, this part right here, right?
Okay.
So what I want to do is say all right if we're going to do the
rendering cure, then we have to do our sword entries thing.
We kind of want to do all at the end and so I don't know what the best
way is to make sure that
Triggers.
But, you know, let's just say that would that's going to be in part of
the, the multiple tier thing.
So we would sort our commands, no question, right?
That's going to happen.
So we do our sort our commands, and we have to be able to supply some
temp memory here.
That's not a problem.
Obviously, we'd have plenty of room for temp memory.
So we just have to make sure that we actually have that.
That in fact, we could actually include the temp memory in the
command.
So instead of having that be an allocation, we could have that
actually being something.
That's just we just have 10 men.
Marie that's in the command structure.
So we just like we sort all the entries together.
And then, in here, we would go ahead and do our actual rendering.
So we have like render to open jail and tiled, render group to Output.
Those two things are the two things that we would do in exactly as we
did them here, only.
Now, we don't have to call any kind of a platform thing.
We just have the ability to call the two different render paths that
we have.
Okay, so that's the first thing that we would start to do now.
I want to kind of say again, because I mentioned the three-tiered
architecture thing Way Way Back.
200 days ago, right?
200 hours of programming.
So what is that in work?
Time 40 into, that is what five.
So, five weeks ago in, programmer time, I mentioned this, where we
were going to have a three-tiered architecture, this is where the
third tier comes in.
Right.
So you can kind of see, we've got platform code and we have game code
that tear in the middle is the renderer and it's the opengl part that
renders opengl or the part that renders in software.
You can see, it starting to split out into the into that third.
Tier, everything else stays in one place to the other.
But just that resolution of the render of the render instructions is
in that third tier, which allows you to kind of switch it.
And this is also where you can see how you might Implement.
If you want to implement a
Kind of renderer like DirectX or something.
This is where that would be, right?
You just have a switch statement here of like, which render?
I want to call and you'd call whichever one you wanted.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
All right, so we know, we have to sort, we know, we have to do our,
you know, all of our sort of stuff here.
So I'm going to go ahead and first of all, cut this part out.
So here is the tiled render group to Output, that's going to do it
styled rendering.
And so then I would have this part where we do our stretch TI B to the
window that would happen here.
And then the in hardware part, I've got render to open gel.
Obviously going on there.
That's this part.
We don't really need this code anymore.
We can pretty much get rid of it.
This was just the stuff that kind of does the blit, right?
And I don't know that we super care about that.
We could if we wanted to still do this part, I guess.
I mean, we, you know, we can certainly just save it just because why
not?
I suppose.
And this would be some alternate path.
So, you basically say like, okay, we do to bring your group to output
and then there's another if statement here, which is like, how did you
actually want to display the software renderer
Oops.
Did you want to display the software renderer threw up in jail or not?
This is like, you know, b32 display via Hardware.
So,
And so, this code here.
Where did my swap buffers go there?
I can stay as well.
And so really, this is what we're looking at.
So we've got our Hardware path where we rendered open gel and we do
our swap buffers.
We've got our software under path, where we call the software
underwriter, and then display it either in Hardware, or via, you know,
some kind of a stretch split and letting Windows figure out how it's
going to get down to the hardware right now to our problem with that
point.
And so that's really all I'm talking about.
So, as
And see this is like a very very simple thing.
So really it's just going to take us a bunch of code sort of cleaning
around all the edges now to get this to compile and run properly but
that's really all we're talking about here.
That's it.
That's the only real substantive change that I actually wanted to
make.
So, okay, that's where we're at.
So we have our game render commands.
And when we call rendered opengl,
Let's try to make that function work properly here.
You know what I could also do?
I can have this be an inline here which is like inline void, display
bitmap via opengl or something, I can sense.
This is all open, Jill code.
I could clearly right.
Make all of this.
Being there.
And so this is a little bit more readable.
Now that we just have, you know, display bitmap by opengl and we pass
whatever we need to pass their right.
That's not too bad but anyway.
So if I have game render commands here and I want to do the opengl
renderer to Output.
Now, we're no longer taking any of this stuff, right?
We're just taking the commands and then we need some way of making
this stuff work.
So here is our commands.
Now has the width and height in it, which, you know, obviously was
good.
That's the thing that we wanted to be able to do so, we have that in
there.
And now we go through and we look at what else we've got.
We need to push buffer.
Element fact, let's just look at all the things that render group that
uses from render group and it looks like basically we have them.
All right, so all we have to do is just straight-up replacement.
We take whatever the commands were and that's where all of our stuff
is coming from as you can see.
So really, that's all there is to it pretty much period.
So we've got command sword entry at commands.
There we go.
And let me see what else we got here.
Can I look at the?
Where's the platform?
Where's there it is.
I just want to see what's going on here.
So yeah, in here display bitmap by opengl.
What have we got?
This guy is doing window with window height.
So that's doing a blind out to the whole screen, so maybe we don't
want to do that.
Maybe we want to do this since we're displaying the buffer.
Maybe we do it this way.
The future will do it a little differently.
Well well you know I'll leave it.
Yeah, I don't know.
This is something we're going to want to change a little bit later as
I guess the only thing.
So we want something that looks like this a little bit more.
There we go.
And so, this is basically just going to take one of those.
The one of the buffers like, we had in in here, which is to say, it's
like the global back buffer, whatever.
It's this thing went 3-2 off-screen buffer, right?
So what did the wind 3232 off-screen buffer have in it?
It's just got width height, pitch, B, 4 pixel and memory.
So I think we probably just want this.
We probably just want to say hey here's a bitmap coming from open
Jill.
I'm sorry coming from like a software software renderer whatever could
you please render it and then we just go ahead and say, OK.
There's the the height width height and the memory again, width and
height and that stuff just freely much is all we need.
Now, there is one part that's a little weird, which is that the pitch
pretty much has to be the height and the width times 32.
So we could also say here that
Or at the pitch equals the width times for because we only support
that right now in the opengl path.
Here we didn't, we don't support multiple pitches so that's just a
restriction and we might as well sorted so people who maybe who use it
won't get super confused.
So we also have this screen space thing that we did before
which we could if we wanted to we could now leverage this code that we
had previously.
So here is our screen space texture stuff.
We could just have a thing that's like inline void set or opengl set
screen space.
And that could do the code that could do this code right here.
And so we could just make this opengl set screen space.
And and it would just do that stuff automatically.
And as you can see, we kind of need the, the width height and I guess
that sets free in space, could also do our viewport call for us if we
wanted to probably.
Well, maybe that's not true.
So let's just say that it takes a width and height and we'll leave the
viewport thing a sub because like I said, we're going to probably want
to do something with that, a little later on.
All right, so I'm going to make these
Be the only two parameters to it and so that'll set up our matrices
for us.
That means we can call opengl screen space in both places.
Like so, and I'm going to make this opengl display bitmap.
Yeah, so this goes away and that's all good there and then this lower
triangle GL triangles bit with a color that's just an opengl rectangle
call now.
So this whole thing we can also do by just saying like a minty Max
Speed color, that's an open to the rectangle would get rid of all this
and that's done as well.
So this all gets much much more simplified and and that's nice right?
And then our opengl screen space called here.
We need the commands with the height.
So this stuff passes through lookin pretty reasonable, right?
So now we kind of have our opengl stuff.
Starting to take shape.
You can see how that works.
There's nothing particularly fancy going on here, again.
The texter loading stuff.
Still not right at all but we're kind of converging on something
that's fairly clean and you can see what it does is nothing weird
going on there, right?
Right.
So that seems reasonable.
Let's bounce back here.
Go to Global back buffer.
All right, so win32 display buffer and window.
Now when we get a WM paint message is just not going to work, right?
So I feel like when we get W and paint messages, we're probably just
going to have to ignore them because we won't really be able to do
anything sensible.
There are opengl state will not necessarily be set up for anything.
We won't necessarily even have a back buffer.
Now, we could save a back buffer in opengl for the same case.
But that's something that we definitely don't want to worry about now
if ever.
So for the time being, I'm going to say let's get rid of this and
we'll deal with that.
Some point in the future if we ever even care about it at all.
So here is our win32 display buffer in window.
Call again, where we were working on things.
Again, it has to do, it sort entries.
This is the real third tier coming into play here in a big way because
this is actually a platform nonspecific, but in the third tier
operation.
So that's like handmade.
And you know, we almost might want to rename these a little bit like,
but handmade.
You know, this is just the renderer specifically.
So it's like handmade, you know, render shared or something like that.
Would be what this this actually does.
The Sorting entries part of things.
So if I do handmade render dot CPP here, perhaps again, I'm not really
sure what we want to call it, but this would be like the utility
functions for renderers, right?
And so that sort entry call which were currently doing over here in
the render group that thing has.
Be outside and it has to be.
So all of these sorting things that has to be guess this is where we
merge sort and swap.
That's it.
Yeah, that has to be something that's out here in handmade render and
that can be accessed by anyone who might want to use it right.
Okay.
So much like opengl is used in here.
So now we've got our handmade render dot CPP is used in here.
And again, strictly flowing in that direction.
So that's all fine.
No big deal there.
And so then we've got, we're a little bit closer, right?
We're a little bit closer to working.
Okay, so in with 32 handmade, I'm going to go back to where I was
there just a minute ago.
And so we've got our sort entries, that's just a render call that
perhaps things we come in here.
We can either call render to open gel with the commands that we're
doing and
I don't think we need anything else for that.
We might want to pass the window with and window height.
Like I was saying before that sort of something we probably want to
address eventually.
So I'm going to put that in there.
Even though right now we're not quite using, it will see a little
later on that.
That's actually something we're probably going to want.
Just in case our display, our window with is not the same as our
render.
We may want to put like black bars, you know, like or or change asset
Ratio or crop.
There's a bunch of things.
We might want to do there.
So the render commands and the window with thing may, you know?
Like I said, we may just want that to be a separate thing.
So we're going to do window with and window height here, which are not
the same
Name.
And this, this would be equivalently true for this guy, where it would
have the window width and the window height and, you know, can choose
to use this if it's so desires.
So, so there's what we're dealing with now.
We've got our display buffer and window this passes it to opengl.
And so now, here, where we've got tiled render group to output, and
we've got render queue and, and all this stuff.
So, the render queue now,
Is is actually, oh, well, this is actually going to be really nice.
Now that render queue no longer probably even has to go through the
platform.
Like, it's entirely in the platform layer as well, which is really
kind of nice because now it doesn't have to round trip to the game.
So that's real nice.
That's, that's great.
I didn't even think of that.
As a as a nice reason to do this, that means that thread
Going for handmade hero might, we might be able to keep threading out
of the game entirely and only in the platform layer.
If we wanted to, we may want to keep it in there for SIM for for
accelerating simulation.
And I guess I don't mean threading out entirely.
I mean the low this this part of the threading.
That's interesting.
All right.
Anyway, ignore that for now.
Pretend I never say anything.
Point being here, we've got our thread stuff, where we pass where as
it went through to make you where we have our high priority queue low
priority queue.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that the plaque platform work queue.
Here just gets passed in.
And that way, this guy just gets it directly from here, like so.
These are commands no longer render group, we've got our output Target
and temporary.
NE the output Target is going to be that Global render buffer and the
temp Arena.
Now we shouldn't actually need because the entries are getting sorted
up here.
So if I go back to my rent, handmade render group and look at toddler
group to Output.
I'm assuming that the temper Rina just is not necessary anymore
because it's the sort stuff.
It looks like it wasn't even being used anyway,
Yeah, it was only in the sort stuff.
Anyway, right?
So that's all fine.
So now we've got this function, the tiled render group to output, and
that's obviously going to have to move out into that shared code.
We're like sword, entries and that sort of stuff is right.
So here's our sword entries.
Tiled render group two outputs going to move out as well.
Let's see.
Renter grouped output.
I think all of this stuff should because this is the software renderer
right?
Do tiled render work children trip to Output.
Yes I think all of this stuff kind of comes out here right that all
moves out and let's see.
So this is all this is Sue.
Most of the stuff comes out.
Yeah, I assumed like, this is basically almost everything in handmade
render group that doesn't involve building up the stuff that's getting
pushed should come out and into the rent.
Like, because we're basically moving the renderer out if that makes
sense.
But render group itself doesn't actually need to come out for any
reason.
So I want to be somewhat cautious here in this.
Let's see, get camera, rectangular distance, be converted,
Get all sorts present project.
All of these are things which stay push direct response but bitmap get
back to him.
All of those stay push render element.
Definitely stays it were to enter basis.
Stays orthographic perspective, begin, and end render.
All of these are still the same out here.
Enter group clear, render values will stay but change, but I think all
the rest this is rendering.
So this comes out draw.
Matt change saturation, which you don't call anymore.
So I'm going to ask me to make that quickly and we did one time on the
Q&A.
I think that's
Not even used all of this stuff to our rectangle, slowly sample,
environment Bill, linear blend draw a rectangle on scale and Pious
normal, and unpack four by four.
So I think all of these guys come out, I'm going to rid of this thing.
Or time function stuff for now, as well.
Really want to leave this in here at the moment.
Yeah.
And so now like the render group thing, again is just turning into the
thing.
All this is supposed to be doing is managing is brokering that process
of putting things into the command q, and also notifying the asset
system that we need things, right?
It's still doing that part of the process as well.
All right, so there is handmade rendered again, that's like it's
platform nonspecific but it's sort of a three-tiered thing, right?
Again, like I said, this is the three-tiered architecture that is
Thing, about way, way back.
When finally coming into play, it looks like this, right?
It's
Here is the platform layer.
Here's the game.
And now here's the renderer.
And the renderer is kind of like the split thing that has some
platform-specific code in some non platform-specific code.
Like it may have like an opengl specific thing and that it's also got
some nonstick stuff and you can think of this stuff as really being
part of the game code if you want.
Because it is platform, not sick but I choose to think of it as like
sort of, this is a hybrid layer that has platform specific and
nonspecific.
So this is like purely non, right?
This is purely.
Platform.
And this is like a hybrid.
Right.
And that's just what I mean when I keep referring to a three-tiered
architecture for that,
That's what it, that's what I mean.
So stretching out, I didn't fall asleep yet, so that's good.
So yeah, so I think that's mostly what we need to do structurally and
we just have gonna have to lot of compile error, clean up, that we're
going to have to do to make all this work.
But that's, you know, that's the name of the game.
That's how you make architectural, changes.
You have to do a lot of cleanup.
So let's see here.
I am going to start.
How do I want to start?
Well, I guess we'll just see where we're at compiler or wise and maybe
maybe move along from there.
All right so clear render values.
I would like to find out who is doing clear render values and I think
I may just get rid of that concept entirely.
So if I look so and render does clear render values.
How many times do we do an end render?
That's the only place that actually does that.
Let me take a look at who's doing that.
So, and redditor happens, once at the end of the game, it happens once
at the end of the
Debug code and then it happens.
At the Phil ground chunk work stage.
So really we never
Actually begin or end renders at all.
Yes.
Oh, that's tough.
That's tough.
I think, I think we just, I think we get rid of all that stuff.
I think the beginning and render stuff, I think that all just goes
away.
I think we just have render group and we allocate and deallocate,
their render group entirely.
And so, one of the things that has to happen here is if we want to
use, generation IDs to protect our asset loading.
Which if you remember, that's how we protect.
If we want threaded things to work with the asset system, we have some
protection there to prevent things from being unloaded and stuff.
I don't know that that's the system we want to stick with.
The long run, but it's we should keep supporting it because it's
something that we were doing.
We had that notion of a, that notion of a generation ID, right?
That now has to be something that's pushed forward via the buffer.
So basically, inside
Inside are handmade platform code.
We need in here that that has to come from here.
So that has to come generation, ID, has to come from from that.
So, there's our generation ID,
Generation ID.
So that's how that that's how that has to move out.
Just because since the render since we can't consider the assets
unlocked until the render has completed, we need to make sure that the
generation IDs are / sweep, which includes everyone who might render
to it.
So, beginning render end render now can go away as well.
Those can have been simplified out and we don't have to worry about
them anymore.
So, now what we could do is say like, okay,
when we allocate a render group,
System here, all, we really need to do is just have begin render
happen at the bottom, right?
So now it just looks like this.
Generation, I do doesn't matter.
So it really just looks like that and render does the yeah, basically
end render begin render.
Those two generation ideas.
I'm not sure why the generation is stored on the assets.
Do you guys remember why we put it on the assets?
Is that just because we didn't have a better place for it.
Or what?
You can asset lock.
Oh, because it's neat because it needs to take the asset lock
that looks like the primary reason.
I guess.
Yeah, that looks like it.
So you know what?
Now that I think about it.
I suppose we don't really need to
We don't really need to do it that way at all.
We could simplify this a little bit more instead of having begin
generation and generation.
We could just have a thing where we do both begin in an generation
together.
Where we just have advanced generation, right?
Because what we what happens when we come through, as we take the
asset lock, right?
We then say, all right, let's go ahead and like make a new generation
here.
That's that's in Flight, we then.
And then later on we sort of, we sort of clean that up, but we could
just, we could just do this like this, right?
We could just clean up all the in-flight generations and then switch
to the next
One.
And so, we just assume that there's always one in Flight generation on
every frame, right?
Because that's what's essentially happening for the most part.
So even that seems like it could be simplified.
So right here, this is really, we could just say this is Advanced
generation for the game assets, that make sense and it returns that
you 32.
And that way we just do that at the top of the frame.
And that's pretty much all there is to it.
I think
Yeah, that seems right to me.
Now the only thing that I'm not sure about is how that necessarily
gets communicated at the moment, to be honest.
I don't even know how that was getting communicated to the debug
system directly because the debug system makes use of it to draw fonts
and stuff.
So, I'm not sure how it was accessing that how was it accessing the
assets?
Dare I ask so allocate render group.
Assets.
How is it getting the assets?
Debug start.
So, it gets passed.
The assets by whom.
Debug get game assets.
Where does that happen?
Anyone.
Tepig akima.
So yeah, it just gets the game assets straight out of the thing.
Anyway,
So that's pretty straightforward.
I think we could simplify this quite a bit.
I think in here when we do Advanced generation
I think in here, we don't really even have to do this.
We could just say like okay,
Advanced generation.
Is avoid it advances the thing.
And then what you actually do here is you say like I'm going to say
whatever the current generation is and return that so there's like get
current generation.
You know I'm saying and they're like non-overlapping.
I feel like that's a better.
I feel like that's a better way to do it.
I suppose, one problem with that is you can't be you can't be
multi-threaded on that.
Well, okay.
Here's the what I'll say we can leave it the way it is now and not
have to really do all that much with it.
We can leave it doing essentially.
This what I could do is just emulate exactly what I want by going into
when we actually start game update and render.
When I want to start the asset Generation stuff we can just say, all
right, if there was a generation start the generation, otherwise make
make a new one, right?
So we'd say something like if a generation is in progress and the
generation, right?
and then in here, we just do begin generation because the problem that
I'm having with this,
Maybe that.
The problem that I'm having right now, just thinking it through is
just like the generation ID wants to apply across across the frame, it
needs to apply like outside, right?
And so, I'm just not sure how to do that in any way.
That makes much sense without exporting the concept of generation of
begin and end generation out to the platform layer.
You know, which maybe is a what we should do.
You know, maybe that should happen or maybe this better thing is like
we shouldn't have really ever done this generation.
I do stuff in the first place, right?
I mean it could be that you know, because we did it mostly to support
in fact entirely to support the stupid ground chunks.
So it may be that that's just a huge pain in the butt for no apparent
reason and if we just decide to kill the ground chunks and no one
would care, right?
Because
otherwise, if we
And support the ground chunk stuff.
We just have one centralized time when assets are cleaned up and we
would never have to worry about the Generation stuff at all right?
So I don't know.
It's six of one half-dozen other, it does kind of seem like it
probably wants to go that way like because it just seems like adding
all this complexity that doesn't really need to be there and I can't
think of any reason why we actually care.
So, but, you know, I just don't want to touch too many moving pieces
at once.
so maybe what we'll say is we'll just say something like if trance
State main generation ID, you know, go ahead and let that cycle, the
generations at that time, but I think I might say to do, we should
probably
Paul the Generation stuff, because if we don't use ground chunks, it's
a huge waste of effort.
All right, so yeah.
Yeah.
I'm okay with the rest of that.
So yeah.
So at that point, since the generation ID stuff, would now be in here?
I guess, the command, buffer itself, doesn't actually need to have the
Generation stuff in it.
We can leave that stuff in the render group itself.
It just doesn't do this stuff anymore, right?
But it would still have in it what its generation ideas.
So inside the render group would have that generation ID that doesn't
have to be in here.
Now,
It can have that in there.
And all we would do.
Is inside here where you start it up, you would pass the generation ID
in.
Well actually no you just I guess you just get it.
I know you pass it in right generation ID.
And the trance State basically would pass that in here and so the
render group would have generation ID set to whatever it needs to be
set to.
And that seems fine so clear undervalues, doesn't need to happen every
anymore.
Here is our allocate render group or allocate render group actually
doesn't need to do any of the things that's currently doing it all
anyway.
So it never needs to actually take a memory Arena or anything because
it doesn't actually have to do any memory allocation anymore, right?
So now it's just something that holds the assets doesn't need an
arena.
Doesn't need to push buffer size.
All it actually needs is the game render commands.
Not that it's going to push to that's it.
And so the render group basically has a thing in here which is, you
know, game render commands commands
And then it's like, okay, game.
We got the camera transfer.
Whatever.
And yeah, missing resource count may want to flow through as well.
We'll see about that in a second but I think everything else is pretty
much right here.
We come up with a five minute warning.
I'm going to probably leave things non compiling today because I
don't, we're right in the middle of a bunch of sort of moving things
around, and I want to finish that.
So, we'll do that tomorrow and and continue on with that.
So anyway, inside allocate render group.
We would pass in that generation ID, we'd stick it in here, and that'd
be fine.
And then all the rest of the stuff like sort and should have pushed by
precise with realm account, all of that stuff goes away and we really
are just going to be storing.
Now instead, I guess it's a result here.
Inside here.
I guess what we would probably say is that the commands get stored
just as a pointer
We don't need this and I think that's everything.
Right.
So that looks about right to me.
So we got out our allocate render group, we've got all the rest of the
stuff going answer.
Now I'll be to have to do, is in here where we talk about things like
the render group.
We do reference that group commands, we would take our game render
commands.
And everywhere that we were referencing pushed buffer, kinds of stuff.
We're now going to reference, you know,
That command buffer.
that's,
That's all that is.
I think,
All right.
So yeah so the arena doesn't happen anymore so now we do an allocate
render group, we're not really going to be doing that anymore.
This is more going to just be like it render group or begin render
group kind of a thing.
And then, I guess we'll have an end render group call as well.
So, our begin.
So our previous thing we did begin and render.
We're now we're just straight up doing beginning and render group,
right?
So we we don't we no longer allocate begin end, we just begin end.
And the only reason this is even here is I think we want to do
something like in the future.
This kind of thing, you know, render group commands, missing resource
cap, plus equals
Render group missing resource, can't something like that.
Probably, although, who knows, maybe don't even really need to do
that.
So the push truck doesn't happen.
Now, render group results.
Let's go ahead and make that happen.
There we go.
Inside render.
Let's see, that's not even a thing anymore.
That is commands now.
Allocate render group identifier and I found that's true.
And let's go ahead and grab that out.
Can render group does not need any of this does.
However, need two main generation, ID thing,
All right, this would be its own generation ID right now, so that
would actually be chunk generation ID.
You know, why am I even porting this code?
This ground chunks have been, nothing but Annoying the entire time and
I don't even want them in the game.
I feel like these are just
I do not like,
Do does not want ground chunk.
Of course, probably do that.
At least.
All right.
So main generation ID, right?
We don't actually know what that is yet.
That's okay.
Let's go ahead and do the transient oriented State and we need our
main generation ID.
There and that should do it.
I think.
Yeah.
All right, looks like we're just about time.
Okay.
Trender group not found.
That's fine.
I don't really want to have to change everyone from to put a fan.
So I'm just going to sort of substitute that in here.
So we do render group render group equals begin render group, there's
the Train Arena.
And in the end the those two basically can go entirely away and then
we just passed that main generation ID in here.
Sorry, begin render group.
Okay.
And.
And what else does it need?
Oh, it needs the
It needs render commands, right?
Oops.
Let's see.
Oh and they go in the opposite order as well.
So now we've got the begin rendering now we already do that.
So end render is just and rendered group now and and temporary memory
render memory.
I don't know that anyone's actually using any memory inside this area
anymore anyway.
So I think that might go away as well.
I mean, I guess we might want to leave the Train Arena doing that but
we can probably get rid of that boxing if that makes sense.
So that's probably just a waste of time now.
Anyway, so we got draw buffer.
so, all of these things that take the draw, buffer,
I guess they're probably just taking those two so they have like a
width and height to them.
I'm guessing not really, I don't guess, I don't really know why they
take the draw.
Buffer.
In fact, is there some way we can find out why they take the drug
buffer?
What does updated render title screen?
Need that for
Yes, it's just using that to set the perspective, so it doesn't really
need the draw buffer.
What it really needs to know is just what the render output size is
for the screen, right?
And so, that's actually something that we want to probably be doing in
a different way for the moment.
You know, we can just do that with the render commands.
Because it's got the width and the height in it, so we can if we want
to do like loaded bitmap draw buffer.
To Casey eliminate these entirely and this could just be passing that
through.
But what we can do is just make that be something that's actually a
little more understood through the system.
What do you know, what a like Target area is that it's rendering to so
draw, buffer could really go away.
And no one would miss it in the slightest.
So that's probably something we should change that instead of being a
draw buffer to just being ass like a screen spec like here is the
specification for the output area that I actually want you to do.
So render to Output actually now.
No longer has to happen.
All resources present is something we may want to have happen outside
and that's why I said we may want to
That in there.
Again, I'm going to just put that in here as a little like to do.
Casey, do we want to check for resources like before probably?
So yeah, so then we've got our our debug stuff here at this again is
going to be a begin render group like much like before and in our
debug State whereas our debug states, there it is.
Render group that can actually destroy the render group no real reason
not to.
So that can do a begin render group here.
But that only happens when we're not on ischl eyes, so that actually
needs to happen.
Right here.
Right?
So when we do our render group for begin render, that's going to
happen right here.
And in fact, I guess now with that means I guess I don't know.
Do we probably don't even need to save this, do we?
Maybe we do.
Well yeah, I guess we access it from there.
So if we do debug render group, we do begin render group.
We have the assets because we can get the assets, right?
That's what we were doing here.
So we could do a beginner render group.
We don't need any of the Arena's anymore, which is really nice.
So, those aren't getting polluted at all.
And then we can still use that main generation ID, I guess we could
also just bump
Generation it probably.
No, we can't.
It's got to stay locked till after the render.
So, inside this begin render group here, we need to pass the same one.
So, when we do the assets here, where we doing that,
Debug get assets, get set.
When we do our debug get game assets, it essentially needs it needs to
do this same exact process, right?
So in here we need to do like debug get main generation ID.
And hopefully, like I said, I would really prefer if we could
eliminate that look.
I don't like the fact that we still have to do that generation.
I don't think it's something.
We probably want to keep just based on it's like what I perceive its
main value to be versus how complicated it makes things.
It just doesn't seem like a good trade-off.
So I kind of feel like that's something that we would want to get rid
of
So there's the results and this would be exactly the same as it was
before.
Yeah, to do Casey, really want to get rid.
The name generation ID.
Yeah, oops.
So let's see, can I cover from render group to render group?
That's true.
Should probably stop soon huh.
I hate what I'm in the middle of reorganizing code and I have stopped.
That's the probably worst part about handmade hero.
You gotta say what you gonna do, man, what you going to do?
So, render group,
Just needs to be flattened out a little here.
Know why these guys never yeah.
Quite did it got a pointer to the render group snapped but they
didn't, whatever reason.
There we go.
Actually, that one already has a renter if Y.
Is it still dereferencing?
It does.
Anyone know can't we just do that?
Where is our memory?
Oh, assets, get passed into the debug start, so that's unfortunate
that basically means that we'd probably have to do this here.
So generation ID
so, when we call debug start,
Right would save me.
Well actually, I guess we just do it right here.
Okay, so begin render.
Group function is not take three arguments.
That is true.
And so now, we need to also pass in the, the render commands, right?
Let's get what we called that in the platform thing.
It's game render commands.
So, we've got our game render commands commands.
And when we call into here, we need to pass those commands in
and,
That such the typo.
Push font.
All of these are obviously render group things.
Don't know why, that's not just using the regular asset call, but no,
no bother no worries.
And then, let's see, we've got our debug State render group here.
That's the same thing we were having before.
Let's see what else we've got on Project.
Render to Output doesn't exist anymore and render does, there it is.
And there we go.
So here's our, debug start.
Call our debug start called debug State assets.
It's going to have to pass the commands.
So now we've got render commands in there and so debug game frame and
needs to take that as well, right?
So, debug game frame, and in the platform layer, where's that guy at
process State?
Let's see.
We've got debug.
Yeah, let's see.
Where is it?
Where did it go?
Where is my debug game frame end?
How is that?
Where's that defined?
This is one of those cases too old to remember this, many code bases
at once.
Because shouldn't that be in the platform layer?
It's called from the platform layer, isn't it?
I thought we did.
Oh, I know where it is, right?
It's right here.
We pulled the debug stuff out into a separate place.
That's fine.
I'm fine with that.
So it doesn't need the game off-screen buffer anymore.
It just needs the render commands, right?
So game render commands commands,
Go.
And so now we just say, Okay, render commands and same thing here,
render commands come in here, I don't know why deep what does debug
end?
What does debug I've actually do with the draw buffer, raw buffer,
Absolutely nothing.
All right, so this is actually just render commands within height.
And done.
All right, Sue somewhat, surprisingly, we can now stop and go to Q&A,
but surprisingly, that's actually all of the game.
Structural stuff, the game now, compiles.
So we're only dealing with the other part here, which is better than I
would have expected.
That didn't take too long.
So that's not bad because I ended up deciding to make a lot more
changes than I was originally going to because I kind of wanted to
Clean all of that out.
So now those two systems both pile everything on to their, the render
commands, the render commands them comes out to the platform layer and
then we can do it.
We want with it.
So we now just have to go back and finish up this part here, right?
So,
yeah, I mean basically like
But that doesn't actually have to happen anymore.
Either does it.
So anyway, inside here, oh, hey, look.
And we just need the 10 memory.
So this is going to be pretty if it's really tempting to just finish
this, but I'm going to not.
So, we'll save it for tomorrow.
I'm going to go ahead and, and, and go to the Q&A.
So, if you have a question about what we're doing here, please go
ahead and put it into the chat with Q: front of it, so I can see it.
Martin's, so no more hot reloading for renderer code.
So,
We can, if we want to I guess it's the way I would say it.
If we get to the point where we want to play with that a little bit,
then we certainly can the only cost to us is we just have to make
pointers in other words this stuff here, like handmade opengl and
that's tough.
If we want to we can just actually put that in the game code and and
give a pointer back to the platform Library so that's totally fine.
For the moment there won't be though until we decide to actually make
them call through a pointer.
Let's see, did you see handmade Quake?
Can you confirm whether it's of handmade quality?
I am aware of hammock wake, but I have not seen it myself, so I can't
confirm or anything else about it.
Sheba Caleb.
Casey you seem to have a grudge for the ground chunks.
Do you really hate them that much?
Yeah.
Because basically, they make they force a lot of multi-threading
issues that we wouldn't otherwise have to deal with and so that's fine
if you're getting something of value out of it, like if I really
wanted the ability to do compositing in the background going through
the same render path and all that stuff, right?
If I really wanted to be able to do that, then great.
But I don't really care.
I don't even think I really want the ground chunks anymore.
Like after, like I said on the other stream, I don't think the game is
actually to use them.
So I think it's just a lot of extra complexity that isn't doing us any
good and we could keep dealing with it just as an exercise because
hey, it's an educational stream and so why not.
But on the other hand, it's like, is that really the most productive
use of time and we sort of seen how we do it.
It would be more of that and we'd have to like keep thinking about it
and maybe maybe we can clean it up more and make it less of a problem.
And that's maybe interesting challenge but otherwise it's like, well
couldn't we just spend our time doing that.
Spend that time if we were going to spend it on something that was
more useful to the game solving that complexity, right?
So
Gun games, less of a question.
Where the thanks for doing this.
You've inspired me to pick up C and C will tell us again after quite a
long break.
So thanks, very glad to hear that.
I hope it goes.
Well, long Boolean, what was your original goal at the ground chunks?
And how has that changed?
Also, if you remove them, what will you replace them with?
So originally I was
Thinking that the outside of the game like in the Overworld area was
going to be more free form.
but the design of the game is such that I don't want it that way
anymore, like the outside needs to be like, kind of tile like like it
needs to be
it needs to not be fluid.
It things need to be more like a tile map for the game design.
Like not talking about the engine but the actual game design needs to
be more tile like.
And so I think the art has to back that up, which means that the
splatty ground chunk thing is maybe not really a very good idea.
The other thing would be even if it was a good idea, we probably could
just do it at runtime anyway because
Hardware rendering path is going to have plenty of extra horsepower.
Even the software any path.
Could probably do it at runtime with culling so I don't know.
So, I think the ground chunks are just a bad idea.
Chrome Dragon.
You may want to include a note in today's zip file about how it won't
compile.
You know, we could do
Is there an exit command for batch files?
Yes.
How's that look?
Slayer, why are you wearing earbuds?
Are you listening to something that is actually the microphone?
That is the the headset that I'm talking to you through, you would not
be able to hear me if I was not wearing them.
Canoe close, would you at some point compiled, a list of stuff?
Programmers should know.
I'd like some beginner level pointers like this are algorithms
algorithm types.
You should know sorting being one type and such, I mean, I think
that's a great idea.
Do I have time to do that?
No, because that's a fairly involved Endeavor.
There's a lot of stuff that programmers should know.
So is that a good idea?
Yes.
It is a very good idea.
Will I be doing it?
Unfortunately?
Probably not.
At least not for several years.
Maybe someone else will have time to do it.
It would be a nice resource for sure.
Any other Q: are we done?
Looks like we done.
All right, we gonna wrap it up.
We gon wrap it up.
Save
All right, good to go.
Thank you for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
It has been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to keep up-to-date on handmade hero and
play around with it at home, you could always pre-order the game.
It comes with a source code, I updated every night so you can be
playing with the very latest and greatest handmade code base which
tomorrow
Hopefully we will finish with the render reorganization there and be
moving on to something else.
I'm guessing, probably, we will have to move on to texture downloading
stuff so that's probably what we'll do until then you can always check
out the forums where you can ask questions.
Check out our patreon page.
Want sport the video series.
Art.
We fought so that you can find out when there is going to be live.
It will be live tomorrow, 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time, spoiler alert, but if you want to keep up to
date with a definitely type of tweetbot, because in case I reschedule
streams or stuff, that's always replace.
That's accurate until then have fun coding everyone.
And I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy.