Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero show.
Rico to complete game live on stream.
We are at a point where I think the only thing left on our to-do list
before updating the art is, I was going to do some particle system
stuff.
Because I really don't know.
How we actually want to structure.
Those four are the way that our game works at the moment, there's a
number of kind of subtleties about it specifically because we use a
localized coordinate system for all of our stuff and we want to have
very large worlds and not have particle systems be simulating, if
they're not nearby and all sorts of things like that.
So there's not really very much to say about particle systems like on
hand be here.
In terms of the core particle system aspect of it.
I pretty much we took a two-day break a long time ago where I just did
particle system because we kind of, like randomly said, what should I
do for two days in between some stuff we're doing and we did
particles.
And so those of you who have been following along have already sent a
seen me, talk about the general part of particle systems, the or
larian lagrangian stuff and generally how they work, there's not a lot
to them, they're pretty straightforward.
And then it's just a question of how hardcore into physics.
Do you want to go versus just hacking stuff?
You know, so
So you can start to make your particle systems be relatively
physically rigorous as you go, and then it starts getting more mathy
certainly.
But in general, there really isn't a lot to the particle system part
of it.
It's really just how much actual physics you want to bring in, is what
determines mostly the complexity of the of the math?
You have to understand but the actual particle systems part is not
particularly complicated.
It's just hey we've got a lot of points there, moving around.
That's about all there is to say.
So really most of the complexity for
This is going to come in on the bookkeeping side of things, right?
It's how do we know where the particle systems are that we want to
simulate?
How do we know when we want to simulate them?
How do we make sure that when a particle system comes into view, it
looks like somewhat proper, you know
If it's fog or a waterfall or whatever it is, how do we make sure you
don't like, see it start up.
You know, I'm sure you've seen this happen in games before where
you'll be like walking into an area, and you can actually see like the
waterfall start falling when you get close to it because it's like,
hey, you got near enough to like trigger the particle system to start
or whatever but it was still asleep before.
So now you've kind of got this sort of period so there's a lot of
stuff like that where, you know, it's it's
It's not really Central to the main part of the particle system or
understanding how to implement a basic particle system or even an
advanced particle system, the particle system part.
But there's all of this kind of bookkeeping, that, that is involved.
And that's really the part that needs to kind of get
Get hashed out.
And I wish I could say that was a pun.
I don't know that we're going to use any hash tables, maybe it we will
and then it will be a great pun.
But if not then not it's good.
So yeah, let me quickly on the on the Blackboard.
I don't know that we're going to have a full Blackboard session today,
because I think a lot of this is going to kind of have to be Discovery
sorts of stuff.
So let me just quickly say, kind of what the issues are that we're
facing here.
And then I will I will sort of jump into the code and just maybe start
to sketch things out a little bit today.
So that tomorrow, we can start implementing the parts of it that we
care about.
Okay.
So just to remind everyone of kind of what's going on here.
We've got a virtual coordinate system, a sort of a localized
coordinate system that we do our Sim stuff in.
So typically you know, if we have something that you know, looks kind
of like this sort of a scenario where maybe we've got
Let's say.
We've got, you know, the hero is here and this is a room or something,
you know, and there's, you know, some walls around but you know,
there's exits, you may be North and South exits here that sort of
thing that they can go through and whatever.
They're looking at this particular thing.
There's a simulation region.
The simulation region probably comes out to about here perhaps.
So because there's rooms that are nearby.
We allow those rooms to be simulated so that enemies who are maybe
like in the room.
Next to you might come in or if they're chasing you they could follow
you things like that are all sort of on the table.
So, you know, in this scenario, the important thing to remember
because it's been a while since we implemented the basics of this
stuff is that we really don't have any notion.
Of a world space beyond sort of the tile, like these sort of tile
chunks that we have and things are kind of relative to them.
What that means is that if we wanted to have a particle system that's
persistent that particle system, kind of has to be based around
somewhere so that when it actually gets rendered there's some way
which we know where it's where it is relative to the camera, right?
Because you remember what happened like you know we've got like a tree
or something that tree is packed into
Chunk.
And we know where the chunk is relative to the camera.
So the way we know where the tree is that?
Where when we unpack it, we know it's there, right?
And particle systems are going to have to do something similar.
The particle systems are going to have to get unpacked in a similar
fashion where we unpack a particle system when we know that it's
within our view, or our simulation region, and we simulate it, we need
to do something similar.
I think for the particle systems now,
Thing with, with the particle systems.
Is that unlike our entities which we could pack down to fairly small
and probably will eventually one of the sort of ideas behind the end
of the system.
I was doing was to kind of do a streaming entity system, right?
Where you could pack edit, he's down to small.
Only the part you actually needed to remember about them and then you
blew them out into bigger entities when you're processing on them.
So that you wouldn't have to constantly do loops through property
lists or things like this.
But particle systems are not that way the state of a particle system.
Cannot be represented in a small amount of space.
If it is dynamic right now, there are other things that we could
consider here.
And let me just quickly tell you how that goes, the way that I have
implemented.
I have implanted parks in the past on, on previous projects.
And this is also how particle systems worked in braid is that they're
actually deterministic and based entirely on a single T value.
So, for example, you know,
If you have particles that are kind of shooting out from a point like
an explosion, you actually just to generate the particle system.
You actually redo the entire particle system every time by using a
random seed.
And a t-value that just says, okay, I generate all the random
particles every time I move them, however, far they would have gone in
the time step T.
And that's how I do my explosion, right?
So then all I have to remember is like the location of the explosion.
The T value of
Of the explosion.
And any time I could recreate that explosion.
Now, the problem with this is it means that you fundamentally can't
have very interesting protocol systems.
And what I mean by that is that all of the particle systems have to be
completely based on T, which means that the particles themselves can't
really interact with anything that might be moving, right?
That might be transient.
For example, if I wanted to make my explosion bend around objects that
were in the way.
It could not do that if it was strictly based on T and the reason that
it couldn't do that if it was particularly based on T is because as
things move in the locus of the explosion.
Like, let's say we've got something that's moving this way, right?
Then the particles as they explode, should only be moving around this
thing, when they get here, right?
And as this thing moves over here, if the thing was entirely
regenerate, every time the particles that should have hit this thing
when it was here will no longer.
Or even know that it's there and they'll just they'll jump to a
different location discontinuously, right.
As this thing moves
so you end up in this situation where unless the entire thing is a
function of T which it can't really because this could be a player
with player input and stuff like that and so then you have to record
the player input and stimulate where
Things would have been as the T.
That means you have to individually step the objects which and
quickly.
This whole scheme, like blows up, right?
So F of T particles, like particle systems that work like this, where
you just input a single tea and you're done, they just can't be very
physically active, they can't interact with things in a very detailed
fashion and it's a big limitation for them.
So while we could do that on handmade hero and maybe we will do that
on handmade hero in certain circumstances, right?
Like we could imagine
And so if we just have a particle system for a little torch that
flickers or something, you know, that's something that an F of T,
particle system could do just fine.
If we don't need a lot of dynamic of dynamism from things moving
through, the torture, who knows what happens to this torch?
Then, you know, it's not that big a deal, but
Assuming that we do care more about what happens to those particle
systems.
Then it just isn't very interesting even in the torch case if we want
things too.
Smoothly, animate through it.
And like, cause Poof's and things like this to happen, to that torch.
When something like shoots through it stuff like that.
You just end up in a circumstance where F of T, particle.
Systems are not going to be particularly good.
What that means is, I think we want fundamentally and F of delta T
particle system, right?
Which is to say that each frame, we would input the amount of time
that has elapsed, and we will simulate all of our particles forward.
And while we are simulating them forward, we can choose to do things
like intersection testing and allow them to respond to Dynamic objects
in the scene if we so desire.
Right?
So, a traditional physics update step for the particle systems.
This is how particle systems are often done.
This is probably the more common way.
In fact that they are done F of T, is probably less.
Where, you know, just being able to dial Park system entirely from
just a single time value.
Okay.
So the problem with the F of T system from our perspective, here is
that particle systems might be quite giant.
For example, let's suppose we want 4000 or 4096 particles in a
particle system, which isn't even that many particles for a particle
system.
Actually.
Gpus today are very fast.
You can push a lot of particles.
On a GPU.
So a single particle system of four thousand particles, not
particularly much.
But if you think about how much that would have to, that would take
for storage.
Just that one particle system at 4096 particles.
If you imagine we were storing storing.
Even just say you know 16 or 32 bytes worth of data it quickly get oh
that's great.
It quickly gets quite large right you're starting to talk about.
128k 256k per particle system, that then has to be persistent, right?
Best to be persistent in the world.
And if we are having very giant worlds, we don't generally want, you
know,
There's like four or five particle systems the stream or a screen or
something like that that are now getting saved that's half a megabyte
per room.
If we have even conservatively 500 rooms like okay you can just start
to see this start to multiply out here.
Now we're talking about a quarter of a gigabyte just to store our
particle systems, it's just not particularly attractive.
As an option, right?
Furthermore of this all this traffic of storing it out.
And who knows what else, right?
It would break our chunk system, right?
Because our chunk system is based on streaming things in and out of
it.
Now you're streaming to way too much in and out of it.
So blah, blah blah blah.
So you know honestly it just doesn't seem like a particularly
compelling idea to me to store these particle systems in the world as
persistent things, especially because they don't really matter to the
gameplay in that way, right?
A
Cool.
Particle system is therefore special effects and it to the degree,
which it does affect the gameplay.
Usually, that is at a more granular level than the individual
particles themselves?
For example, maybe I do have a flame on a torque that lights things on
fire.
Typically I don't test every particle to see if something hits it to
light on fire, right?
That could get prohibited expensive anyway, and might be too hard to
simulate, right?
So typically what I would do instead is I'll just test the region of
that thing and say, if something's in this region then I light it on
fire or and maybe add some poofing to make the particles go out but I
don't test every single particle, right?
On that thing necessarily.
You know what I'm saying?
And so, you know, I don't really need them for gameplay purposes.
I don't have to know where every particle was.
So if we forgot,
You know, where those particles were that wouldn't actually do
anything bad to the game.
All we have to do is make sure that when the player is actually
looking at the particles and their inside, you know, like the same
region.
Let's say that they stay consistent because we want them to look
consistent.
Like, they're a part of the world and not all weird.
Jump, be erratic.
So obviously we want them to look consistent while you're looking at
them.
But after you're no longer looking at them, we really don't care what
happens to them.
We just care that when they come on the screen, stay on the screen and
leave the screen for that duration of time.
It always looked right.
And it looked plausible and believable like it was a particle system
that was have been, you know, something that had been stimulating the
entire time.
And so for our purposes, what I would propose and I think the first
sort of route that I'm going to take and we'll see how it works out.
Is I'm going to say that what?
What is sort of like cached?
Particles.
Right?
And I think this is a fairly common technique.
I mean, I couldn't tell you offhand.
How many people do particle systems like this?
But I suspect it's a reasonable number.
We're certainly not.
The first, we certainly won't be the last to attempt something like
this.
And the idea here is just that well, okay, if we already have the
notion of a simple simulation region, what if we just said, we've got
room for some number of particle systems, right?
So let's say we go.
Okay?
What's our biggest particle, you know, how many particles do we want
to simulate at maximum for any particle system?
You know, maybe it's 64k particles.
Let's say how many particle systems do we want to simulate any one
time at maximum?
Okay.
Maybe it's 64 particles or something like this.
And maybe we just say, okay, that's the number of particle systems
that there are
Ever right.
And then we do is, when we unpack a particle system, we use its unique
ID to look up into a particle cache of 64 of these to see if we have a
match.
And if we have a match then it just simulates.
That particle system.
If we don't have a match, evict the oldest thing in that system like
whatever.
The least recently used particle system, was we evict it and
reinitialize?
This one
It's place, right?
So as things move into the Sim region that are particle systems, they
this happens, right?
And it's things, leave the region.
Well, they still stay in the cash potentially for some time depending
on how many other particle systems are actively being used inside here
but eventually they will get reclaimed when there are 64 new particle
systems that have come through the simulation region since it left
Right.
Or rather since it came on, I should say.
And so we can also prioritize these.
If we think that 64 is not enough to handle all cases and maybe there
were you know, we could say that there will never be more than 64
particle systems on one screen at a time but maybe when you get up to
nine screens there could be we could also do sort of a two-level
priority scheme where we could have particle systems that are that are
actively on the screen, are prioritized higher?
Or maybe it just in general, we could
That the further you are away from the camera the less priority you
get in terms of eviction.
So you know it might not be strictly least recently used it may be
more like distance from camera and so if you are closer to the camera,
we will preserve you at the expense of someone far away from the
camera in the event that all of the particles have been touched this
Frame.
Or last frame.
And so we don't have one that we know we can throw away that isn't
going to be touched, right?
So yet what the eviction scheme would be, is probably something that's
a little bit more specific there.
But, you know, we could also just say, we'll just always set this
number high enough so that it can cash it right memory.
We have a lot of it and hey, you know, computers are fast.
So maybe just let the user have some fun with with that CPU.
They paid for and let it just simulate a lot of particle systems will
see if it Boggs things down.
If it does, we'll address it in some other way, you know.
70.
It will do whatever.
Okay.
So I think that's basically it.
That's really all I wanted to say about the particle systems.
Hopefully, you understand roughly what I'm talking about in terms of
the motivation there.
And now, you can kind of see roughly, what?
I mean, in terms of cash particle system or a cash-based particle
system where we're talking about, you know, not really having a
permanent home for any individual particle system, rather just using a
cash to say when they're around there around when they're not.
They kind of disappear from existence then.
All we do is into our game permanent store.
We do have entities that themselves.
Just Mark the fact that there is a particle system somewhere and say,
what kind of particle system it is and then that is all that we
actually keep in the permanent storage.
So hopefully, that makes some sense to you and you can sort of see
where I'm going with that.
I'm going to hop over to code.
I don't think there's anything else.
Of to say on the Blackboard but that is what I'm going to start typing
in is just a thing that kind of does that caching and allows the
particle systems to come in and out of being, then what we'll do
tomorrow.
I think because I've got about I don't know, half an hour or so maybe
a little more, I've got about a half hour to implement that.
Then what we'll do tomorrow is start to talk about.
Okay, let's make some particle system.
And get them kind of functioning so that we can, maybe actually have
some entities that are particle systems, right?
And so this way we can have entities, you know, maybe we'll do some
stuff.
Like I said, look a little like fire, that burns and then I like to do
some that are a little more complicated.
Like maybe we'll do some ground level fog or something like this and
we'll see whether we want to have sort of the like the oil.
Aryan sir.
Out of occupancy stuff that I kind of talked about before we may want
to put in some of that as well.
I'm a little nervous about or larian occupancy stuff only because I
don't really know how well that's going to work in practice for things
like,
Ground fog, I don't know after I'll have to see what we think.
So we're kind of going to have to play around with it and see what we
think about stuff like that.
But point being what play around with some of those and by playing
around with some different kinds of particle systems?
We can then sort of ask ourselves, what?
Actually are the things we want.
These cash particle systems to have in them in terms of capabilities
and then we can build it out from there because the cache Works will
work the same way regardless, so I can Implement that today but then
in terms of what is actually in those particle systems and how
We sort of what parameters we expose to the game model to sort of like
be able to create interesting particle systems without having to go
like re-implement everything every time, you know, will depend on sort
of us.
Implementing some kind of example, particle systems that we think are
kind of like the ones we might want and sort of seeing.
Okay, what kind of support do we need here?
And, of course, you know, it's never the end of the world since these
things are just kind of, you know,
Touring a bunch of data, the cash.
We can always extend to add new types of particle systems.
If we misjudge but we want to sort of put some in there to begin with
that we can use as we sort of do basic stuff in the game so we can
kind of see how the particles look and use them for nice effects and
that sort of thing.
Looks like I don't have a command prompt open so I'm going to go ahead
and open one up.
Today is day 3 36.
So you want to start with de 335 source code, if you're trying to
follow the changes that I'm about to make right now.
So compiling the game, everything I believe we left in a kind of a
relatively done State here in terms of stuff.
We were had been working on.
So yeah, there's my
Little Hero hopping around and having a grand old time and off we go.
So let's go ahead and take a look at the Sim region stuff.
My belief is that this you know if you take a look at the way the Sim
region stuff, these Sim regions are kind of meant to like come and go
very sort of spontaneously throughout the run of the program.
And so the same region itself is not really the right place to put
this cash.
And the reason that it's not the right place to put this cash,
Is because again a Sim region is supposed to be saying that just pops
up, simulates a region then goes away.
And so it can't store data from frame to frame.
That's not really what it does.
And I don't want to make it do that because I want to be able to use
it in ways, where I just kind of like create-a-sim region to simulate
something and then and then have it finished and just be done with it.
It's supposed to be transient that way and multi-thread about in that
way.
So what I need is I need the cash of particle systems to be something
that's sort of a separate thing, right?
So there should be like a separate.
Channel if you will of particle system cache information and when we
run a Sim region, if we give it a particle system,
Cash we then when it unpacks entities, it will go ahead and look in
the cache and update the cache.
If we don't give it a cash, it won't because remember the same region.
Is one of those things that we may want to use and we kind of talked
about this a little bit.
The other day, we may want to use it to simulate areas of the game
that aren't the player can't see where there are other things going on
that we want to know the outcome of so that when the player does get
there, they will see the results of them have happened.
So if we want that capability, we don't want to require those areas to
have their particle system simulated because that will take a bunch of
extra CPU time that we didn't really need to spend.
And because nobody can see those particle systems.
And so, the only thing that we want to simulate about particles in
that case is the gameplay logic part, which is something I want to
keep in the entities themselves.
So we want to make sure to segregate this and as I'm doing it, I'm
going to keep it very rigidly segmented.
In that sense, I want to make sure that the Sim region just uses a
protocol cash.
It does it sort of contain and require a particle cash and so that's
why I'm proceeding in the way that I am.
So if we go in here to to handmade Heroes code here, I want to just
copy.
I want to get a starter file here for like handmade particles.
Like so I still haven't.
I need to someday right?
For a coder.
My custom for coder.
I've never written the thing that like creates a new file and puts my
header in it.
I just I was too lazy for some reason so I just always copy an
existing file that has the header in it.
Real high rent.
I know.
So I'm going to create a thing for particles here.
And what I'd like to do is I'd like to start making that cash and I
want to because I kind of know what I want the usage code to be here.
I'm going to write the usage code first.
I always used to say always right the usage showed first but after
kind of like I think it was Alan kind of asked me some good questions
about it.
I came to the realization.
That really what I do is I write the side.
I know first, if I know exactly how the implementation should work but
don't know what the API looks like.
I use kind of a compression Style.
Game to get there.
And if I know that I want the API to look a certain way, or I believe
I can determine it but I don't know exactly what the implementation
should look like.
Then I go the other direction and so I definitely have different modes
that I go in depending on what I know, right?
And it's worth noting that the hardest problems are when you know
neither side when you neither know, the efficient way to write the
actual code.
Nor do, you know what, it's a pi should look like.
Then you're kind of in this really nasty, no man's land.
And it's kind of this problem.
It's a lot like a boundary value problems in mathematics where, you
know, things sort of
Are you have to kind of have these these guesses about how to get from
one place to another when you don't really know very much about
anything that's in between them, right?
And so those are kind of very hard problems to solve all across the
board.
Putting this case I pretty much do know, I think what I want at least
that cash part to look like so I'm going to start with that and let
that kind of build.
So what I'm imagining here, right?
Is that when I unpack these entities, so here's an example of like I'm
packing, these entities
He's right, we go through and we scream out the end of these.
Are you put those entities in there.
And then what I want to do is say like okay when we have an entity
Source, I'm kind of wondering why is there an if on the source there
Does anyone know can the source ever be 0?
Look, look, I just got it at it.
Like, what?
That doesn't make any sense.
Oops.
How could that Source ever be zero?
Oh, wait, no, it can be.
It's a pointer and if I'm, wow, I'm out to lunch today.
It can be right, these entity data's, I guess could keep it in there.
Your personality index.
Although no, no, no, no, I'm not out to lunch.
It can't be
right?
I mean that's just it's they're all in the block if there wasn't an
entity there it wouldn't, it wouldn't have ever gotten packed.
So I don't know yet.
That's just dumb.
I don't know why that was there.
Nobody knows.
Anyway, it doesn't matter.
So anyway, when we go ahead and do the entity overlaps rectangle test
and we're going to mark this thing as active.
You can see that we do a brain thing where we add the brain in what
I'd also like to do is say okay, let's also say if the dest you know
particle something if it's a particle system then we would want to you
know get or create particle system kind of thing and we'd want to pass
this particle thing.
Probably although probably the ID for the entity might just be okay
because we have these entity ID things here where we can say like this
entity it has a unique ID.
So really, I guess I can just use this so I just need to do something
where I say okay if my particle system
If this entity has a particle system, whatever that means, then I want
to get a create one with the particle system, you know, manager or
whatever.
So we have a particle cash and we'd say, if we had the particle cash
and this is the thing that wants a particle system, then we would ask
the particle cash, you know, to get one for us, right?
And I guess I could just say get particle system because, well, now,
I'll do get our create and I'll pass a True Value there.
That's like I want to create it.
So in case we want to just do a test or you say hey do you have one
here?
Then off we would go right.
Now, I don't know that we need to pass anything else.
I think that might be all we need to pass and so when we do get a
create particle system here that will generate the product system.
Now, presumably the particle system probably also wants to know the
information about its location because like I said, it's kind of got
to do it Sim.
It's Sim stuff, right?
And so it needs to know like where that particle would actually be.
So probably in addition to that I guess and you know what, I could
just pass the whole entity I suppose.
So probably what I do is say all right let's pass Unity.
I guess I'm past the death penalty here.
So instead of the idsa, here's the whole entity create the particle
system for this for this thing and the desk P, it could look up
directly like now, it knows the location of this product go system
relative to the camera can just go ahead and do its thing right.
Okay, so I think that's probably all we really need from.
The first part of the API is to make sure that we do the gutter.
Create a particle system part.
We don't actually need the particle system to your turn to hear
because we don't care, right?
I don't think there's fundamentally anything that we need to actually
do about it yet.
We could.
I mean, in general, I guess we would say, for passing this entity I
suppose we could make this a little bit more generic, you know, maybe
I mean, I guess we could make this a little bit more generic.
We could do something like this.
Say, hey.
All right, here's the ID.
Here's like the data for the particle system in case you need to
create it and we could do something more like you know,
Like that.
So, you know, if this thing had a part of system in it, then, you
know, it gets recreated or whatever, from the base data that it needs
or blah, blah, blah, blah.
I've no idea.
You get the idea.
Okay, so suppose we did something like this.
Then we know that our particle cash would have all of the particles in
it that had actually been activated at that point, right?
And off, they would go.
Now, when I do get her create particle system, I suppose I should also
kind of, say something more like that this touches the particle system
as well.
So I could do something, like, touch particle system.
So, I don't know what I do here.
Particle system.
That that is say okay will touch the particle system as well.
And the reason that that's important, I think is because if we have
this particle system cache, I don't know that we want to always
require all of our entity.
To be intelligent about shutting down the particle systems when
necessary and what I mean by that is just that, okay?
So being a cash scheme, you typically have a situation where something
happens like all right, you know, take the exits, I already gave the
example of a torch, you know, we've got a torch.
And and, you know, it's on fire, right?
Yay.
So the Flames are burning around burning flames and the burning flames
are just like a particle system that we've created here, but later on
somebody like, you know, destroys the torch or I don't know what,
right, well, maybe you know, the person who wrote that code to destroy
the torch, like does something with the particle system to make it do
like a poof thing and make smoke in.
Case it's fine.
And in that case, they could Mark the particle system by saying, this
particle system doesn't need to be touched anymore.
It's on its own cleanup scheme or whatever, right?
But let's say that nobody does that.
Then in that case, we have a bug where when the torch goes away, the
flame will keep being there and it'll be there till the user walks off
and leaves the torch behind that it comes back and then the flame
won't be there anymore because it will
I've gone out of the cash hopefully at that point, right?
And so what typically I like to do in these sorts of cash based
schemes?
Incidentally this is the same way that I do things like that in.
I am gooey style systems because I like to have a notion of when I
have touched things on a frame.
So if I haven't told you anything about this torch on this Frame,
that's a clue to the cash system that whatever the thing was that was
causing this to exist is now gone or is not.
At the moment anymore.
And so you should start to take action to clean it up in a default
way.
So, for example, thing we could do is part of system is just fade them
out at that point, right?
And that means that yeah.
Okay.
Is it as good as if every piece of code that ever use protocol systems
always was able to perfectly, shut it down in some nice way where it
made the particle system.
Do some animation that made sense and then cleaned up or whatever.
Yes our do I want to be do I want to be paranoid enough to make sure
Sure, that that happens in 100 percent of all cases in a game that's
going to be as wacky as a simulation in this game.
No.
So what I'd rather do is design the system so that the failure case of
not doing that doesn't really create much of a visible bug.
It's a slight bug.
It's like not as nice as before, but it's not an obvious in your face.
Ridiculously stupid thing.
Like a flame that keeps on burning arbitrarily long, even though it's
torches gone, right?
So that's kind of more what I mean by that?
And so I just also want to include a that concept here of saying like
I'm going to want to get the particle system.
I'm going to say that it's touched now like whoever this person is is
using it.
So you know consider it an act
Of particle system basically and then you can fall out the code path
and we don't have to worry about anymore.
So now we've got our n Sim, right?
And the NCM doesn't need to really do anything because during the end
of the simulation normally we would clean up these particle systems
but we want them to persist.
So we're specifically not going to get rid of anything that we may
have done with prices.
They're supposed to persist, certainly need to do anything there.
All we need now is a place where these particle systems can be
Ernst, right?
And so what I would say about that is inside our entity system.
You know what we could do is we could Advance these when we simulate
The Entity or we could have the particle system stimulate on their
own, at the moment.
I guess I'll go with entity I'm not sure why I wouldn't.
But
It's hard to say.
Yeah, it's hard to say.
So here's what I'll do.
I'll just say that this get some packed.
And so this will be part of our unpack process.
So I will say like it goes from the source and it's not necessarily in
the dust.
So there's a, you know, a particle spec here.
And then cure in the dust will unpack it and record the active
particle system and and do it like so, I will also test the active.
Well, I guess I don't need to, I'll do that inside touch and so that
way I can say it's an unpack.
And so basically what we do is we have the particle spec it gets
unpacked essentially to the active particle system here.
Which is something that will track in the entity structure.
And so then when we come around and it's time to simulate our
entities, what we can do is during the Sim, right?
So when we're in here, we can simulate the particle system so we can
feel like an advanced particle system or you know, update and render.
Particle system.
Something like this.
So we've got that and that of course will need to take a bunch of
things here but first and foremost it would have to take the active
particle system.
It would also need to take presumably the
Part of cash.
I also don't know.
Do we know what R?
DT is?
Whereas R, DT at?
Yeah, so we also need our time step and we've got it.
So that's good.
We'll need our render information.
But other than that, I don't know how much more we would really need.
That's basically what we're looking at.
So,
But yeah, so now we kind of are starting to see the API.
Take shape a little bit.
We have not initialized this protocol cash and we don't know where it
comes from, but it's a good bet that synthesis.
Something that only happens when you're looking at the world it seems
like the kind of thing that would probably be stored with the world or
the world mode, probably the world in this case.
But I don't know, it's a tough call because really it could be argued
that it's part of the
World mode because it's something that's purely visual.
But we could also say that it's part of the world in the sense that if
we had different modes looking at the same world that they what, you
know.
So six of one half-dozen of the other, I'm not going to worry about
that too much because we can move it back and forth pretty freely and
it doesn't really matter too much to us.
So I suspect the easiest thing to do here would be to just put it on
the world.
I don't see a way to get the world here though.
So I guess I mean, it's just World mode world if I remember correctly.
But
When you take a look at how much sense this makes, so we've got sort
of the, the chunk cash here and the chunk Astros, all the stuff inside
this world.
You know, does it make sense to sort of the protocol cashier?
I'm not sure one of the things that makes that a little bit odd is,
you can see that really, what's stored in the world is persistent
data.
So, you know, maybe that makes a little bit more of an argument
against that I'm not 100% sure how I feel about it one way or the
other, but you can kind of see why I'm a little hesitant there.
I'm just not 100%.
So I think I'm going to go ahead and put it in the world mode.
I'm going to put in the world minute so I'm going to say the particle
cash.
That comes from the world mode and then I think we can get things
started here.
So let's take a look at the particles side of things here.
I know that there's going to have to be some way of initializing this
thing, I guess.
I don't care about that quite yet.
Where's the rest of my stuff?
Here it is.
So, I know I'm going to have to have one of these.
And I know what it takes.
So, this is a active particle system.
Just called a particle system.
We have the DT.
And we have the render group.
So we know we've got those inside Sim region.
We know we've got these two
And we know that this is going to take a part of I'm sorry.
This is going to return a particle system.
And we also know what it takes.
There's the cash.
There's the ID.
And I don't really know if the ID values makes sense to use entity
idea specifically I guess I don't really know.
It might make more sense to just translate it over to you 32, but for
now let's just use any idea that's what they're always going to be.
I think so we'll just we'll just leave it that way.
And then we'll say particle spec.
And then a create if not found.
And then we've got our particle system.
Here.
not a great typing day, and then we've got
Our desire to touch this.
We want to touch it.
And so then we need something here.
For that.
So, yeah, so I think that's mostly what we need there.
And I guess now that I'm looking at the structure of this code, I can
see that actually having the entities render, the particle systems.
One at a time, I don't like because and the reason I don't like it is,
it doesn't allow fading out things past the point where they've been
destroyed or something like that, because of an entity gets destroyed,
won't be able to render its particle system anymore.
So, I think what I'd rather do is use
Of the, you know, I kind of went back present.
I think I can see from looking at the code there that I don't want
this at all.
That's not the way I want to do it.
When we do update and render entities, I'm going to want to basically
take update and render entities here and say, well after you update
and render the entities or whatever, you know, that's when I want you
to update and render the protocol systems as well and update them all,
please, I'm not going to tell you which one of these two do.
Because you're going to do them all and that way you can do one's even
that have not that don't have any entity associated with them anymore.
So you can have particle systems that have had their entity sort of
deleted or gone away and that won't actually affect anything for any
practical matter.
So, if we do update and render particle systems, now, we could,
Do it like this.
And here, they'll be a for I Loop where we kind of go through, you
know, all of our particle systems or whatever.
Right?
And probably that looks more like this.
And the particle system.
Is here and so, oops to move that delete it.
So yeah, when we update and render the protocol systems, we're going
to go through all the ones that we actually have hoops.
For the closing parenthesis.
When we update and render, the particle systems, will go through all
the particle systems.
When we touch them, will make sure that they're marked for the
particular frame.
Having actually just this.
This should not be taking aspect though.
This should be taking a particle system.
yeah, and so that was just a
Wrongness.
And that starts to look pretty reasonable to me.
So, here we go with particle system and particle cash.
And, you know, maybe we just say that there's particle system systems
and there's 64 because I think that's what I said, and I don't
remember what we well, you know, I don't really want that.
I probably want these to be, you know, a
So ways to style things.
So, you know, it's probably pound Define Max particle count and
that's, you know, whatever it is.
And so then we just have something like this.
And so we're going to want will probably.
While we do the Protestants are will probably want to start bringing
in some similarity to the party here and so we'll probably want to
make this a little bit.
Not like what I'm typing in right now but you know, we'll we'll
probably have something like this.
I don't know exactly what but will probably want something that kind
of looks like this but we will want to be a little bit more.
We want to make sure those are 70 aligned and other sorts of things
like that so they won't quite look like that.
But you know something to that effect so we'll have these guys will
have them in our particle system and you know off we will go and then
in these particle systems in addition to all of our arrays and such
will need some kind of a preamble that's like oh hey yeah you know
there's an entity ID here that's the idea of the particle system and
will eventually need something like the number of frames since it's
been tough.
You know, you know, something like this and, you know, we'll do more
in for, you know, we'll do something Smarter with this.
As we go, when we touch a particle system, you know?
Yeah.
Maybe we just say, okay, you know, frame since touched equals 0 and
maybe that's all there is to it for now.
Maybe we'll move them up in a list or a heap or something in the
future.
But then, you know, in here when we've got the sort of loop through of
the systems, will do something like this so that you
No, every time through, we sort of increment that touch amount.
And so then when we do get a crate particle system, what we can do is
when we Loop through to look to see if we've got a match, we can also
see who the oldest particle system is and then we can replace that
particle system.
Right now there's a caveat here, which is that we don't really know if
we replaced a particle system to laughter.
But what's interesting about that is that, I guess if we're not going
to have them be a simulated, we don't really need
To have this stored on the entity.
So we can just say now that, you know, we
Grab that particle system.
And then, you know, we do the touch up for it and off, we go, right?
So anyway, so if that's the case, then we can sort of see how we
would.
At least do the beginnings of the implementation here.
All we would really have to do and it's a little inefficient, but who
knows if we're only searching through 64 of these, it might be hard to
make it that much more efficient at all.
So, I'm not sure like a linear scan of 64 entries, may actually be the
best.
In fact,
we could just plan for that up front and say, hey,
Guess what?
There's just one array of those and we look through them, right?
And you can see like I didn't really, you know, I kind of wanted to
move that outside of there because I didn't want to have to do
when looking to the IDS, I didn't want to waste cash.
All of these IDs if there were 64.
Don't know why I'm going off in this right now but just to sort of
tell you why I just did what I did, you know, we know that it's four
bytes for an entity ID, right?
So for B times 64, particle systems is 256, bytes total luck if a
cache line is 64.
Bytes wide, that's for cache lines that have to get loaded in order to
check.
To see whether we have this particle system.
Now, forecast lines, being loaded is is very cheap.
And so, you know, scanning those is going to be real quick now, if on
the other hand, we stored it in the top of the particle system.
So if I did what I was saying before, now what we know is these
protocol systems are huge, so there's going to be no sharing of this
because this will sort of take up the rest of the cache line that this
sits in.
So, then,
Will happen is, we'll say, well, if there were 64 particle systems,
there's actually 64 cache lines that need to be read.
So it's actually 16 times more cache lines, that would have to be read
into the processor in order to know whether or not a particular
particle system exist.
They're not
And so, you know, it makes more sense for us to say, let's minimize
the number of cache lines and have to come in on that.
We could do that a little bit more in say, like, particle System Info.
Say, okay.
These two things are the things that participate in the scan, right?
And so we've got the info here and then the actual systems themselves
are separate.
Okay, so just thinking out loud, seems like a reasonable thing to do.
So if we were to do that, then inside the particle part of this,
right?
What we would say is like still Loop through the systems, but instead
make it the system infos.
And we just want to check.
Those right?
So we would say okay the system info zaidi.
If the ID equals that one
Then great, we're done our results is just whatever the system is that
corresponds to that one.
Right?
There's our result and we can stop looking now but otherwise we need
to find the oldest one.
So we would do like Min frames since touched and that would be like,
you 32 maximum.
To be nice.
Having you 32 maximum?
Somehow.
It looks like we do not have a u-32 maximum.
Yes, and now we have to do 1 billion, I guess we could just do this.
For 4 billion for billion in binary anyway.
So yeah, if we start out assuming that the max, you know, there's the
maximum there, then what we can do is say, all right.
if the Min frame since touched is greater than whatever this system in
foes,
Frame since touched is then, we want to grab it.
And remember this index?
Right.
So, we would do.
That.
Right?
So since they were saying like, hey, we want to go ahead and track,
which one is which here?
Which one has been kind of the oldest and then when we fall out, we
could just say and I probably want to do it this way, or maybe just
call this replace will take replace.
So if we come down here and we say, we didn't find one.
We just use the one that we're going to replace, and now we'll have to
initialize the
Particle system.
And we could actually do that in it particle system and say, okay,
admit the result particle system in did it with this feck.
Right.
And this ID,
Something like that.
And so in here we would just have another call which is whatever needs
to happen to get a particle system started.
Which we won't really know what that is until we actually start
writing some, right?
But we'll find out soon enough.
So here's the particle system, here's the entity ID and here is the
spec that we will use to actually implement it.
Right and for the moment protocol spec is just going to be you know
empty, we don't know what it is.
But we'll get to that later.
Okay?
So now what we need to do is actually start to fill in some of these
things that are missing and I've got a little, I think I've got about
three minutes left, I think I didn't start till 20 after instead of 15
after.
So it's going to take those three minutes to just tidy up some of this
and then we'll be done.
Now, I said that during begins him, I wanted to make this optional.
So I want to basically say that you can pass a product cash if you
want to, but you do not have to pass one and
Also need to include these things because I haven't included them yet.
And so if I go to handmade H, oops, that's not him A.H.
There we go.
What I want to do is include the particle systems.
So now we've got them.
And now we just need to flush out the and I should probably also
before I forget include them here.
I'm putting them above the stem region so we can kind of yeah.
Oops.
So there I think we're pretty good to go.
I don't know why I called it particle.
Cash, spelled all the way out, when that's kind of a waste of time.
There we go.
How do we compare?
Two entity IDs, presumably there is already a thing for this.
Right.
I mean.
Wouldn't there be?
Something.
Looks like is equal only happens for these guys and it looks like it
also kind of short circuits that test of dot value.
Yeah.
Like this is kind of that test right there.
So I feel like, I kind of want to start using one of these like is
equal entity ID a and of the idb
Result is a value equals B dot value.
I think that makes me happier as a person.
So I can do are equal or is equal.
And be good.
all right, so
frame since touch is not okay.
So yeah, that actually does pose an interesting problem, which I
guess, I don't really know if I care about solving.
So I think what I'll probably do is say we probably want people to be
able to use this pointer.
So I'm just going to use like an index here, which is just the system
minus the particle cash systems.
So it's going to say that's the offset, right?
And so, then if I want the info, I know I can just do a particle
system.
Info.
Info equals particle cash in photos.
So yeah.
Conversion from Institute for.
Yes.
Don't worry.
There will not be that many particle systems.
and,
This was actually system in photos.
So when we go ahead and do these, then in this case, When We're
looping through both of them, we only do this Loop once.
So I don't really care about how accessing is efficient here.
So, I will just say we access both of them.
And I will increment the frame since touch there.
So I think now, we're just down to the entity storage stuff.
I would suspect it looks like we function does not take three
arguments, that's just because the particle cash isn't there?
What is the problem there?
Particle spec, right?
So we need to get part of the spec in their broadcast on a member of
game mode world.
So, we just now are down to just the bookkeeping
so if we come around to entity, what we should be able to do is
include a thing in here,
So we should do like has particle system and we should be able to do
particle spec particle systems back or is it Spartacus back its part.
And that information can be stored.
There particle spec as part of Envy, I guess that would have to sort
of jump up a little bit in priority, their particles would have tricks
to be up here.
That makes sense actually, but the problem with that is that entity ID
isn't there.
That's unfortunate entity ID is kind of a little too Primal at that
point and there's no way to really organize those.
There's no way to really forward declare them because they're actually
included in the particle system info.
So I kind of want entity ID to be moved up a little bit in terms of
its thing there.
How is the brain not use entity IDs?
I guess because it's only runtime so it doesn't need them.
Interesting.
So I want to go ahead and move this end of the IDS up a little bit in
terms of their precedence here in the include order because they're
kind of like things that that are a little bit more used by everybody
if that makes sense.
Okay, so then in here, I can say that I want particles to be above the
entity which cook has that structure there.
The at this point, I'm just down to the world mode, not having a
To cash in it because now we actually do have the the part of cash to
pass here.
And so all I really need to do is have the world mode inside the world
mode, have that particle, cash present.
So I'm going to put it down here at the moment and these particles
cells will go away because those were from our old experiments,
particle systems.
And so all we need to do is create one of these.
I guess this can actually be sort of just created in line with the
with, with the game mode world.
If we
it too.
But it's kind of big so I may want it to be off on its own.
So I think what I may do is say that in game mode world.
when things are,
Getting sort of.
initializing hear what I may do is say, okay, once we sort of do all
this initialization, I'm going to also initialize
Those those particle systems.
So I'm going to say World mode.
Particle.
Cash equals, right?
Oops, push struct cash.
And I don't really want it to clear.
So I think we want to do that, right?
And in terms of where we want this to go, we just want this to be in
our sort of transient storage, right?
Like whatever we're doing as far as our transient State here, we would
want that Arena.
So I believe we would just say
Tran Arena.
Cuz we don't care what happens to these things, they don't get like
saved and restored or anything like that.
So they're not going to be in anything that's supposed to be there.
Yeah.
That is it a sand on it but other than that I think we're in good
shape.
Which functionally in update and render world.
So, yeah, in here, we just need the world, so I don't know why this
doesn't why this does World mode Arrow world.
When that's right up here.
And I assume it's safe to delete that.
And leave it that way.
Yeah, and I think that's it.
I don't think there's anything else we need to do now, this will not
do anything other than crash if we mess something up but you know like
so but that's pretty much all.
We actually needed to do there, I think, but yeah, not great.
There that was not that was not Stellar to say the least but that's
all the infrastructure that we need for the basic protocol cash I
think.
We've got a couple loose ends to tie up there other than the debugging
which we can do tomorrow.
Although I'll do one as I'm thinking of it here when we actually
create one of these particle systems, we did pass a flag that says
whether we want to create if not found.
So we probably want to do a check there to say we won't actually
replace the particle system.
In the case where
No, it's not supposed to be.
Done.
Also I would probably do this say to make sure that the index is less
than system infos go.
And I think that's about it.
I'll check temporarily to see.
Make sure that the
There isn't an obvious bug for me to fix before.
Going any further.
Update render updating render world world mode.
And Sim.
So I'm not 100% sure why we should have done anything particularly
Unusual there.
I will say that this is supposed to be this point.
You should be
Well no, those are actually fine I guess.
Those are all fine.
I'm just going to double check and say well.
Okay.
I was thinking through what I might do there for debugging.
But I also wanted to do since I'm not clearing,
I wanted to do a in it particle cash.
So again also before I forget I'd like to do a knit protocol cash
there so I can kind of do just clearing the parts.
I actually care about because the particle system now is a very large
block.
I don't want to bother clearing the whole thing, 20.
I mean I could but I'm I just don't know that I want to do that
especially because they'll have to be cleared when they sort of change
hands anyway.
Oh no, I've gone too far over time.
All right, I really gotta stop.
Sorry.
I just, you know how it is.
Sometimes you're in the middle of coding.
Something, you're like.
Well, I just need to finish these few other things.
All right?
So anyway, if I need the product of cash, all I really wanted to do
there was kind of go through
These guys and set the infos.
To nothing.
That's, that's really all I wanted.
Was there a null?
All right.
Well, so I guess I'm out of time.
Unfortunately, I would like to debug this.
Cuz I'm sure this is not something particularly.
Hard to debug, but I guess I'm out of time, so I'm not allowed to bug
it.
Looks like that's an entity.
That's
Been borked.
What if no one saw me to bug it what if they just couldn't tell that I
was out of time and not supposed to be debugging it right now and we
just didn't tell them that.
So first thing is first, I just going to go ahead and go
Like this.
also, I think I said,
I was great, except in those there.
And now everything is running.
With the new code zeroed out.
So next, I will say well, okay, what if we do this
And what if we do this?
Explosion.
So, this is clearly not an acceptable thing to be doing.
Which, you know I mean what are you going to do?
Sometimes you just
Doing some unacceptable stuff.
So, we have system infos and systems.
They both have particle systems count worth of things.
So, you know, I should probably assert that
But the only thing that does anything, is this operation right here.
And so if this operation right here is what's happening, that means
that this is being impolite, right?
This is this is fish Ali over writing something, right?
It's doing something inappropriate and so the question is, how exactly
could that be doing it?
But at least now that we know that that is what's doing it, it should
be relatively easy for us to go in and watch it.
Do it right?
Like we should be able to see that happening and yeah so if we're no
we're only doing particles.
Some counts worth of this thing, then it doesn't really seem like that
should be something that same, but we must have messed up where we
place it memory or something similar.
Who knows what
Yeah.
I also guess I should double-check.
Well no, I guess I don't.
So let me take a look here.
So what are we putting?
In the Train Arena.
So I guess I will say that does look like the kind of thing where
maybe I was being a little bit Hasty there.
Like I don't know if we're not really using the Train Arena for
anything at the moment, then maybe I kind of am not.
You know, I don't know if maybe that was not something that we're
still using.
I haven't, I haven't looked at that policy in a while, but if it's
being used for temporary memory only there than maybe this should
actually have been part of the permanent, but I don't really want to
be part of the permit and I feel like in here that should be allowed.
And so let me take a quick check.
Yeah, I mean the assets are coming out of there and so on so I feel
like that's like should have been within the realm of legitimacy.
So you know I do really feel like that's should be something that's
happening but I'm almost certain that is what's happening.
So I guess I just need to be a little bit more.
Careful about that.
But here you go.
Where did my code go?
So inside here, like I'm pretty sure that what I'm doing is.
Well, you know, I must be reclaiming this memory which is not what I
wanted to do.
And so I'm going to just double-check that.
I'm right about that.
All right.
It's in World mode.
so, what I want to do here is say, alright, let's jump down and we
allocate the particle cash and then I want to see
The transient Arena and this is like what the size was supposed to be
at that time, right?
So when we come out of here, let's see what happens.
We're inside the cutscene renderer and then we switch up to running.
The world mode which we just switched to.
And here we come through, there we are.
Then going to begin temporary memory on the transmitter so that got
locked in properly.
So I don't know why that would be a problem.
That seems totally legitimate to me.
to be completely honest with you,
So, it pushes on a Sim region.
Right.
And it's using the temporary Arena, so that should have gotten bigger.
Now, of course, I can't really see it because
visual studio just has no idea where it could possibly be.
But it didn't.
Why didn't it?
Alright, now I'm curious.
So, there's the size that we're passionate on there.
It fits, apparently.
We will not clear it to zero.
Oh, because I'm looking at the wrong variable.
I wasn't it sighs.
I wanted used, ignore everything I just said, don't worry about it.
So there's my used and
now, if I look at the correct value,
it should go up.
So, there we are.
With the memory where we expected to be, which is good.
We push it on and it goes up, which is good.
We come down through here and we start pushing your raised on here, so
it should go up again and up again, and that's all good.
And so now, when we come through here and do our thing in theory,
We shouldn't really have any collision between these.
They're totally non-overlapping as far as I know.
So let's see.
So the entities
Cells are stored in which array here.
So Sim region entities there in this
thing here and so we should be able to see those flags getting like
romped on I guess.
So I'm going to just go ahead and take this pointer and say I'm going
to look at this pointer.
As an entity.
And I'm just going to keep on looking as an entity.
That when we step out of this routine and update those particle
systems.
So we come down here to Hoops update, and render particle systems a
jump down.
The flags are set to what for
Okay, see what happens.
Nothing.
It wasn't to do 0, right?
Second, double check.
And let's also take a look at what these pointers are.
Like are we anywhere close and we really aren't like, we're not going
to hit it.
I don't think.
So that didn't get touched right?
Then we come through and Sam.
Okay, so it doesn't happen on the first frame.
Bam.
That is our problem right there.
So well, that makes it really easy to fix I suppose, but that is kind
of an annoying problem, right?
That definitely makes it sound to me like the transient Arena concept,
really just should be done at this level because, you know, you can't
be, I don't know if you can see what happened there.
So the fact that this doesn't begin temporary memory with this Arena
means that when we end the temporary memory down,
Here are the allocation that we did will go away, right?
Which is not what we want.
So yeah, I mean, this is a problem.
One of the ways that things that we do on handmade hero, that's not
particularly great.
Is we keep the, we don't really have much in the way of Arenas.
What I typically do is
Usually have an arena per thread for temp, stuff and an arena /, like
thing, that's active.
So there's a lot less Arenas on handmade hero than probably.
I would normally use and it really doesn't get much of an issue
because there isn't that many reasons why it would, but you can see in
this circumstance where it kind of is because it's like well at this
point you wish you had a little more flexibility there because it's
not like we need to be that conservative with how many of these things
we have.
Have but we then sort of run into these problems where it's like,
okay, you know, that was kind of a stupid bug that you don't really
need to have as only because you're kind of being more restricted with
these regions than you need to be which you know if we were trying to
Target an Atari 2600 or something.
Well, forget that if you're trying to Target a Converse T4, and we
needed all of our memory W laid out exactly, that way, maybe that
makes some sense but that's not actually what we're doing at all.
And so,
Yeah, it's just kind of a necessary that point.
So I guess what I would say is,
I guess what I would say is the world.
Where is the actual game mode?
So I would say that the mode arena is really the arena, you know, or
rather the something that the tracks with the game mode is where the
particle systems, really more belonged to a certain extent.
Right?
And so I don't know.
You know, these things really I think want to be a little more
formalized here and I don't know to what extent this ever really wants
to be used.
You can see that.
It's kind of largely.
Kind of residual there in handmade dot CPP where it's going to use.
But I feel like there's just a lot of risk there because now people
can't really use that transient arena in that way.
But anyway, so I don't know if motorino would be appropriate here if
we actually do use mode arena in that way, then it probably is right
where we push on that that stuff.
But I don't know how much space we expect to give.
Normally.
so it looks like it takes
pretty much all the rest of the permanent storage size.
Yeah, I'm going to go ahead and add this here.
I think we may change this from particle system week to Arena week
because I don't really, I don't like the way that is and I think I had
it on.
I had had it on the list for a while to do like to show how to make
those things grow dynamically as well.
So you wouldn't have to worry about saying how much memory you're
going to use ahead of time if you didn't want to, since there's a lot
of circumstances and programming nowadays where you don't really have
to care.
You know, you have for all intents and purposes like an infinite
amount of memory.
The key is just to not use
Improperly.
And so, what you're really more concerned about is the pattern in
which you use it and not the amount you use, Etc.
And that's, you can actually use the exact same stuff that we use on
handmade hero, but just if you do some slight modifications to it, you
can just have them grow so it's not really any more constructive.
So I wanted to show how to add that as well, since it's such an easy
add-on.
So yeah, rather than do anything complicated to fix that tonight
though.
I'll just say that we can probably add
The motor Arena as the place to allocate from and we'll take a look at
that in more detail tomorrow.
But yeah.
Yeah, so now we're I think out of size on this guy, right?
Because this guy is really big and Lorena can't can't fit him.
But that's actually okay.
We can fix that until tomorrow as well.
We're not.
Does this guy?
Well actually, I guess the other thing is, does this guy take all the
room in this Arena?
I don't actually know.
Probably.
What I can do that.
Is just this.
So yeah.
So that's fine now but I don't like having that potential for a
lurking bug there for those sorts of real things.
So I might want to just take some time this week to go through and
just like pull out the arena system into something and then finish it
up like add the few things are going to add to it and that way we can
clean those up a little bit and not have them be things that might be
kind of overly obtuse, but yeah.
Well, that wasn't too bad to debug, but I definitely wasn't supposed
to go that long.
So I apologize for the length.
Enos.
We were 15 minutes overtime.
I will do brief Q&A.
If you guys want to, if you have any questions,
Chris, I think you should be searching for Max famous in such know
you're right.
Yes, I would agree with that.
Actually
Why I closed everything down.
Yes, you're correct because Min frame since touched.
I actually want the oldest.
Right?
And that makes it so I don't need, I just still wouldn't have needed
you three to maximum.
yeah, I agree with that because if the, if it goes up every time that
I want, the one that's been around the longest,
Jean, Victor.
So was the problem that the transit memory vaporize per frame while
the product class you say cross arm?
Yes, the problem was just that the transient Arena, it's not only that
it vanishes per frame, it's that people in general we're just using it
as temporary memory so they do begin and end temps around it.
So when things inside there want to allocate from, it won't work,
right?
Because whatever they do, they're not going to
It's not going to persist.
And so since the mode was getting created inside of someone else's
render Loop, now granted we probably shouldn't be doing that.
Like, you know, it's not like that was really a good thing to happen.
So, you know, if you take a look at what's going on in this code, that
did the actual transition, I don't really remember where that was
probably in here.
what was it that we were looking at there, it was
I don't quite remember.
Probably would have been in here.
Oops.
Yeah, it was this.
So if you look at what happens here, you know, we begin the temporary
memory memory for rendering, we do the rendering and then we release
the temporary memory.
So, you know, it makes some sense because it means that we're doing
sort of these were sort of encapsulating or sorry blocking out the
render to make sure that all the rendering that gets used is not going
to go away.
But you know, it's unclear that you really want that to be going in
the Train Arena.
When these people might be using that train arena for something or
blow, you know, it's, it's it's kind of again, it's just unclear when
you have this concept of the transient State and who that belongs to.
So I just would like to
Kind of clean that out and say, okay, let's actually have people talk
about Arenas more clearly where it's like, here is the memory that's
being used for this.
And, you know, here is the memory that's being used for this.
And we kind of know whose is whose, and when these things change and
so that it's like lighter weight to just have Arenas that we don't
know what their size are.
So that we don't really have to care about that.
If we don't want to, we can just say, hey, will we make sure we never
use more than 4 gigabytes, but we don't have to pre parcel out.
Who gets how much of which
At least, not at this stage.
Storing tortoise.
Not sure if this has been answered on a previous stream still trying
to catch up.
Would you introduce the threading model?
You mentioned that we would want one thread per core but since the OS
creates threads for us, so helpful for things like audio, does it
matter that we end up with more threads than cores?
Well, the the answer to that is, it would be great if the operating
system was written in a way that was good and on Windows, obviously,
it's not.
So there's nothing you can do about that.
So there is no way to really make it.
That you actually get one thread per core which is what you want
because like you say the opposite will create more however just
because the operating system will come in and steal time from you when
when you even though, you didn't want it to by swapping in other
threads that were probably Superfluous and unnecessary, that doesn't
mean that you don't want to make sure you're not doing that as well.
Look, you don't want to make a bad situation worse by having more
threads
Then there are cores in your game, right?
You still want to, if you can make it so that your well-balanced and,
yes, unfortunately, you will have to live with the fact that the
operating system is going to steal time for you by swapping in these
other threads that have has.
But there's nothing you can do about it.
If you want, you can try to cross your fingers and hope that maybe the
operating system would always just sit on one core and then you can
like use all the cores
But one and then be perfectly balanced.
But in reality, it's unclear that that's actually better because
chances are the operating system is going to come in sporadically on
any of the Coors.
And even if it was only coming in sporadically on a single core, it
might not use the entire frame time, in which case you still want,
jobs to be able to execute on that core.
So typically the way I usually look at it is you want to go ahead and
take one thread per core and have the operations of know that you have
one thread per core.
Please keep it that way.
So that your maximum efficient and then whatever the operating comes
up and comes in, okay, you lose some work on that core when it decides
to but that's okay.
And by the way, CH I been the answer is, yes, I no longer use emacs.
I use for a coder for everything on stream and off stream.
Now it is the edit the only text editor that I use now,
And it is so much better than emacs at this point.
It's kind of hard to compare the two, like it's not a little bit
better than my emacs was.
It's like 10 times better than my emacs was.
Like especially some of these new features that you can do like this
stuff where I can search for something and have it.
It immediately tell me where everything is like emacs.
You have to remember like I'm coming from emacs.
It's like one of the most Antiquated editors of this point, right?
So, I'm not coming from something modern like Sublime, which might
have some more reasonable features.
I'm coming from emacs and emacs's is really pretty broken and very,
very slow.
And so now like that query
It would have taken many seconds on emacs because it would have had to
spun up.
A fine, stir run the fine, stir capture the output do the thing for
coder, allows me to just write code that lets keep loads all my stuff
in memory and now I can just do a quick query and do that and, you
know, I could have done all that stuff in e-list but oh my God,
programming Annie list by never did it because was awful.
And so for coders much better now I made my own like project thing so
now everything can be loaded in memory and so now like old things that
used to be like a grep of files are now just searching for in memory
stuff because I could implement the project stuff that I want and so I
know that all my files are always loaded in the editor and stuff like
that, right?
The other thing that I printed out for a coder is for many many years
and in fact that even sent Alan when he when he, you know, I did
Even request this feature, it was just something he had mentioned.
He might want to work on and when I heard him say he wanted to work on
it.
I sent him this email to thread that was like, a decade old or more.
When emacs first at its off returns, I was like
I really wish you know, Emax would add the ability to automatically
flow text because if you think about it, like when you open up a word
processor, you don't have to like manually line wrapped
Lines, right?
Like you don't have to indent the first thing of a paragraph and then
like manually Reflow your paragraphs to like line them up, right?
But literally, no editor, no matter how modern that I've ever seen for
code.
Does the indenting automatically, right?
It should.
So, for example, there is no known editor that I know of, that will
take parentheticals like this.
And as I type, if I deleted that just wrap the other two up
automatically to it right or and then if I put it back in flow them
back around, right?
But that's how word processors have worked for Generations.
And so I've always wanted that feature and right now Alan is actually
working on that in for a coder.
And if he ships the version of for coder that has that working in it.
I think that will completely revolutionize, code editing.
I mean, it would save so much busy work to never have to worry about
inserting returns and fussing around with, like the white space in
your code.
Like it's such a pain in the butt.
All the time and yet it's great that you know, for a coder already and
all modern text editors have the ability to Auto indent your code when
you tell it.
But why am I even ever telling it that and why am I ever even having
to decide how long a line is, what if I've got two different machines
that have different sized monitors, I want to see the line go as long
as the line can go and then wrap.
If it has to wrap, I don't want you to force me to pre decide.
How many
Columns, my code is when that's completely irrelevant to the code,
right?
So when that features in for coder, which I guess baby, as soon as the
next version because Allen's got a lot of it working, he was demoing
it this morning actually more this afternoon when that feature is in,
I'm kind of thinking for coders almost a must-have, I can't imagine
doing editing without that.
Once you have it, it's such an obvious win.
I've wanted it for ever.
No text editor, has ever delivered it or even come close that I've
seen.
And so if he, if he delivers that I think
All over.
Like either all the other editors have to add it or you have two or if
you're not on for code or I don't know what to tell you, you're just,
you're, you're a chump, sorry, you know.
So that's going to be kind of amazing if that happens.
We'll see.
Not to mention all of the editing features that can come from that.
Like then you can just do stuff like.
Okay, I no longer have to worry about where I am on my white space
like I no longer have to worry when I cut and pasted this thing that
you know, I'm cutting pasting from the right place on the space or
something because I constantly am doing fiddly things like this to get
in there.
If you start to virtualize the white space which is what islands doing
you can imagine all these other edit things where it's just like, oh,
Now, it doesn't.
There isn't this isn't here anymore, right?
It's like I don't have to tell you.
Oh, I got a cut between like, you know, this part of the white space
and this other part of the white.
So it's like just to give a simple example, right?
If I were to say
Cut this out like this right?
And then paste it in here.
There's an extra piece of white space there but that's completely
irrelevant.
Like there's no reason that I would ever have to tell it that that
that was true.
Like it could just know to not put in more white space there, right?
And so, there's all these other edit features.
You could imagine that start to get level up from there as well.
So I think the further he goes down that path, the more indispensable
for a coder actually would be to become
As all of that is busy work.
None of it has anything to do with your code, like, none of the
layout, you see on the screen right now has anything to do with
anything.
It could have been automatically done 100% by a pretty printing
program.
And so the fact that I spend time at all in a text editor, entering,
any of it is obviously wasted.
And so I think the more that for Carter takes over that, the more it
would be silly to try and edit in anything else because
Now, you're just wasting tons of time on stuff that for coder will
just do for you, you know?
so,
all right, I'm going to go because I got to go to bed.
All right, I'm going to wrap it up.
Thank you everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade here
at.
So, I put a recording with you.
As always.
If you would like to follow along with the series, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here at work.
It comes with a source code so you can follow along at home.
We have a forum site.
You go to if yet when asked questions we have a patreon page, you can
go to if you want to support the video series and we have a schedule,
but you can go to.
If you would like to know when the series going to be live, we also
have an episode guide, you can go to if you want to catch up on old
episodes and of course a countdown timer.
You can always refresh to see when we're going to be live next.
If that's easier for you, that's about it for today.
I'll be back here tomorrow, same time, same place, until then, have
fun programming, and I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.