According so we can get started.
Hello, welcome to handmade hero.
We had a little bit of a Rowdy pre stream, it's true.
I was kind of going off on how I thought that gamers in the gaming
press had done a remarkable League.
Good job actually at creating a positive Market for games.
And I got very excited, saying, how I think, people don't appreciate
that enough and that they should, and so a little worked up, but
that's okay.
So let's go ahead and get things back to Graphics which is our topic
for today.
We are here on day 93.
So, if you would like to follow along at home and you have
pre-ordered, the game on handmade hero dot, or please, unzip date 92
is source code.
And that is where I am today.
All right, so, where did we leave off people?
I hope you remember because it was a lot of fun yesterday.
We left off with a, the first time we actually started filling solid
shapes.
That could be arbitrarily rotated and scaled.
And so what we need to do now to complete sort of our push forwards
into adding more graphics features so we can have a real renderer is
we would like to start filling these shapes and I guess I should
correct that.
That was again, people egged me on in the post.
Dream, people are always like do this, do that.
And then I kind of feel like, oh well, maybe we should do that, right?
We were
Not going to support that.
We are only supposed to be supporting rectilinear Blitz here.
So there we go.
So anyway, what we want to be able to do is we want to be able to
support rotated and scaled and potentially non-uniformly scaled.
So we'd like to be able to scale differently in different directions
as well.
So you know for example we may want to be able to make it so that you
know, things can be oblong as we put them.
Right?
But that's it.
We're not going to support skewing.
Any of that sort of stuff because we don't really need it.
So we're just going to concentrate on this kind of thing.
So we want to be able to do exactly what we're doing right here.
We did the work for a yesterday where we can fill a shape of the solid
color.
What we want to do now is we want to to see if we can move from that
to actually filling it with an image, right?
So what we want to do is we want to start doing texture mapping so
that we can scale and rotate our Sprite.
So like for example this this head here or this tour so we want to be
able to do that.
Um, so that we can basically map any image that we want onto one of
these sort of computing, one of these rotated and scaled
quadrilaterals, right?
And so we're going to do is talk about that in the Blackboard today.
I don't know how far we'll get.
We'll talk about that in the Blackboard and then we will start
implementing it and then next week, we will pick up wherever we leave
off.
Okay?
So there we go.
That's where we're at.
What I would like to do is I would like to go ahead and start us off
by simply saying before we go to the Blackboard, we're going to have
to start passing what we want, you know.
It'll render entity coordinate system here which is like a test bed.
We're gonna have to start passing down some image that we want to be
the texture, right?
Like whatever that texture is that we're going to map.
We need to be able to pass that texture down.
And so what we're going to do is we're going to expand our notion cure
of coordinate system, right?
We've got it in here where we're passing a bunch of stuff to it.
What we want to do is after that color and then I guess I'll sort of
make this a little easier to read there after that color.
We want to pass some text that
Can use to fill things.
And so we've got, you know, we've got a situation where we had in our
game State structure, a bunch of things loaded.
So maybe we'll just grab the tree or something and say that the tree
is going to be what we what we draw, right?
And so, if we go in into our thing here and say game state tree is
what we draw.
Then in our render group, when we push on one of these coordinate
systems, we can pass a loaded bitmap which is going to be the texture
and then we'll just store that on.
To the render State and we'll go.
All right, you know,
that's the texture that we're going to fill this quadrilateral with
right.
And so you know we've got that push down there now and and the tree is
in there but we don't actually have it filling so that's going to be
what we're going to talk about today is how do we start getting that
in there?
And when we do our draw a rectangle slowly call which is this right
here we're going to want to pass that as well right and our draw
rectangle slowly call will.
Now will now take that loaded bitmap as its parameter.
Okay.
So, if you remember the way we were doing this, as we had our Edge
equations and the edge equations for telling us whether or not we were
inside the shape that we wanted to fill.
And that this this test right here with said they all have to be
negative in order for us to be inside.
That would that was what would tell us whether we should take the
pixel that were on and write to it with the color that we had or
whether we should just let it pass pass through, right?
And we also have another mode.
We could switch to here where we do an
A if we switch the f-zero, where we could just see all of the pixels,
we were visiting, right?
And, you know, we haven't done anything smart to do the coming here.
So we're literally just doing the bounding box of those points, sort
of an axial line, bounding box of those points, but that still speeds
it up quite a bit compared to doing the whole screen as we saw
yesterday.
So it's a worthy thing to do the optimization, but in the future we'll
probably have to do something little smarter.
So that we aren't considering so many pixels that are nowhere near the
actual interior.
As the case is, when it sort of gets a little bigger
They're certainly.
So anyway, that's what we're doing at the moment and, and we've got
that going.
So what we need to do now, right?
We know that we don't have to change any of any of what we're doing,
for, filling pixels, because that's all the same.
All we really need to do is this color 32 here, this color 32 is not
useful anymore, right?
That's the color.
That was passed in, and that's not what we want.
We want to be able to put in in place of that.
32 a color that we read from that texture, that got passed in, right?
And so let's talk a little bit on the Blackboard about how that's
going to go.
And what I'm going to do here is I'm not going to try and Lead
anything.
I try to do this a lot on the stream, like I've said multiple times,
I'm not going to try to lead us into the correct answer.
What I'm going to do is show you how I would go about creating a
solution to the problem that we have and then sort of later on, we'll
kind of revisit and talk about solutions that other people have come
up with that are probably
Better than the one that we come up with because this is the sort of
topic that's been studied by many many people over many, many years.
And so the thing that we'd come up with first is probably not the best
thing, but I think that it's good for me to show you how I work
through problems all the time.
And so even though we're probably not going to arrive at the exact
answer that will use eventually for efficiency and all sorts of other
reasons, right.
I think it's beneficial for us to show how we can work through things
from first pencils and come up with an answer because that's always
the start of solving new problems and yet maybe it takes 10 20 years
of people cranking.
To come up with the final best solutions to things but that's not
necessarily what we're trying to teach on this stream, right?
You can always go read a research paper to find out what the current
status of something is but when you're tackling a problem that hasn't
had solution yet.
The important thing to know is how to do that.
And so that's what we always try to do.
So I'm going to sort of say, I'm going to show you how to think about
this problem and start to try to attack it.
And we're just going to go with what comes out of that analysis.
So what we have right is we've talked about this many times now.
We've got our coordinates laid out here.
We have our y axis, and our x axis, right?
And these are scaled, and basically what we're saying is that we're
drawing a rectangle, that looks like this, right?
So by the time we get to the X, you know, this is our origin.
By the time we've moved out by the y-axis, on our origin.
We've come to the end of the bitmap in that direction.
And by the time we moved by the x-axis from the origin, we've come to
the bitmap and in that direction, right?
So what we would like to do
Yes, we would like to take some regular rectangular grid of pixels,
right?
This is our texture over here, right?
This is our texture.
What we would like to do is take a regular grid of pixels and we'd
like to figure out at any point in here where you know what pixel
would map into there?
And we can sort of imagine how you know that that looks just in our
head, we can imagine taking this grid and you know, aligning it in
here, right?
And we can already start to see like it would be pretty obvious to us.
If we were just asked to do this, well, we just kind of move and sort
of rotate it into place and squish it till it fit.
And then, you know, here's a, here's B, here's see, right there, it is
a b c.
And, you know, those things would kind of line up and, you know, I
should actually probably point out that since we're in a bottom
centered coordinate system.
It really be this way, right?
Oops.
A b c.
Like so, right.
So what we'd like to do is say that, well, we've got pixels, right?
And we know how
Address this thing because we've been using these bitmaps a ton, we
know that we can address these by an X and Y that are in pixel
coordinates, right?
But it's confusing, because we also have an X and Y over here.
That's the pixel grid.
That's actually the thing that we're filling, right?
So there's like two grids on top of each other, right?
There's the XY grid.
That's the pixels were filling and then there's this other thing over
here.
So what we're going to do is we're going to try a new standard
nomenclature here which is UV.
Sometimes St, depends on the
Has and what space you're talking about?
But oftentimes people will talk about is they'll talk about UV
coordinates for a texture map and we can also think about those UV
coordinates in two different ways, right?
And so I'm just going to tell you what those are briefly and so we can
use the right moment later as we sort of solve for this because that
will make it a little easier to understand when we talk about other
solutions to this problem a little later on.
So again I'm not introducing any solutions here, I'm not trying to
lead us.
I'm just going to introduce the terms properly so that when
Start saying something we can use them.
So, typically the way that people talk about indexing into these
bitmaps is they talk about UV coordinates.
Meaning sort of the yuan is in the X Direction.
The V is in the y direction and they actually range from 0 to 1.
Okay?
So normally, when we were talking about looking after that texture,
right?
We were talking about having sort of X range from
02 the width, right?
And actually the width minus 1 would be the last pixel, all right?
And when we were doing why we were talking about it, going from 0 to
the height, minus 1, right?
And so that's how we know how to look up into this bitmap.
And so this is this is sort of the u and v paradigms a little weird
for us.
But you know, we've worked with this, it's so much before and handmade
hear things like this, we can already see exactly how we would do
this, right?
We already saw this sort of mapping from 0 to 1.
To do mapping from 0 to 255, right?
When we were doing colors, right?
All we do is we take the 0 1 and we multiply it, by whatever that
range is, right.
So we just take if we have some value here, that sort of are
normalized value.
It's the zero to one value when we want our sort of expanded value,
right?
We just take, whatever that is, whatever that maximum value is.
And it's just n times the max, right?
Because then when it's zero, it's still zero.
And when it's one, it's the maximum value.
And everywhere in between it's whatever the linear proportion is of
it, right?
So it's pretty free for us to talk about things in terms of UV
coordinates.
And because we always know that these are basically interchangeable.
So we can say UV to talk about something in a texture or we could say
like the textures X and the textures Y, which would be like more like
these values.
And really, we don't have to care too much about which one we're
talking about because we know that it's while it may be an efficiency
concern later that we need to think about in terms of conceptually we
know how to address a texture in
Either way, right?
We would know how to get it either way because if we have these then
it's just the same pixel lookups we've been doing.
If we have these, we just first multiply them, by whatever, the width
minus 1 is in the height minus 1 to get out t, x and t y values.
And then we're done, right?
So real straightforward stuff.
So the question is right, how do we produce some u and v values?
Right?
That tell us where in the textile texture we are at any given time.
And if I draw this diagram,
I am a little more cleanly, right.
Let me draw it.
A little more cleanly here.
So I'm going to draw the pixel grid that we're on, right?
Like so, so this is the pixel grid that we're on, and this is the
screen right at this moment.
This is what we're drawing to, okay?
And now I'm going to draw in our are sort of coordinate system, right?
That we're actually filling at least I'm going to try to like so there
we go.
So here is that Y axis pointing out here.
Here's that origin down.
Here.
And here is our x-axis here, right?
And so we now know that this is essentially what we are filling,
right?
We are filling this region.
Oops.
Due to do.
So, what we know is we're going to have a bunch of pixels who fall
inside these lines, right?
Like this, at least this pixel, this pixel, this pixel, this pixel,
this pixel this pixel, right?
They fall inside the lines, right?
So these individual pixels that fall inside the lines, we know that we
are going to fill them in and currently we're filling them with a
solid color.
So what we want to do is say for one of these pixels, what would be
the way to look up into the texture to figure out what color we
actually should put their right.
And what's interesting about this is we actually have a pretty
straightforward way of knowing what that is, right?
Because all it would be is all we have to do if we wanted to solve
that is
Figure out where, What proportion of the x axis, it took to get there
and What proportion of the y-axis it took to get there, right?
Because we already know that if we start at the origin and started
walking out on the y-axis, right?
If we walked out one units along the y-axis, we'd be here because
however, long it is, that's how far we would step.
We Step 1 x, the y axis, right?
And so, what we really want to know is how far along the y-axis this
actually was because however, far
Along the y-axis.
That was, that is how that, that is the value, right?
Because again, if we were to use these normal, is this normalized
thing here where we're saying that you ranges from 0 to 1 and V range
from 0 to 1, then just a v that said, how far from 0 to 1.
We were along this axis would be the correct answer and similarly
mapped onto the x-axis, right?
That would be.
Are you so really this value here?
Normalized for the length of the y axis.
Would be RV.
And this length, here, normalized for the length of the y axis would
be.
Are you see what I'm saying?
So, let's take a quick look at what's going to happen here, right?
So, if we were to take a given pixel position, right?
So there's our given pixel position, right?
That's P if we're to take out, given pixel position, what will happen
if we dot it onto the y-axis, right?
Because remember the dot product is what measures things against it.
So if I want to do is projection, I know.
Oh that if I was to do.
So let's let's in fact, also say that P instead of here, let's pre say
that we've subtracted the origin.
So it's actually this Vector here, right?
We can call that something else.
I'm not sure what we would call it.
Let's let's call it instead of P.
Let's call that R&D or something, right?
So that's D.
So if I were to take D and dotted against the y-axis, so, I've got its
d.y right, what does that equal?
Well, I hope you remember this by now, because we say it so many
times, it's the length of d right times the length of Y times, the
cosine of the angle between them, right?
That's what that's what that actually equals, right?
And so excuse me and so what I'm going to get here is I'm going to get
whatever this value actually would be but with a bunch of lengths
inside it.
Right.
I've got a bunch of links in there that I don't actually want.
Aunt?
Because I don't know what the length of D is and I don't know what the
length of Y is and really, what I wanted is, I want a number that goes
from 0 to 1 that says, how far along this thing, it went right.
And so it's an issue, right?
There's a problem here.
It's not something that I could use directly.
So, let's say, temporarily right that, I were to normalize these
vectors, right?
So I were to take them and I were to normalize them.
So I know that these links are one and one, right?
So I
To say like, okay D and the y axis are now, just going to be vectors
and all I'm going to do is look at the cosine in between them, right?
So all I'm going to do is I'm going to try and figure out what this
length is.
If the y axis was equal to 1, right?
Was it was already unit length.
Okay?
And so if I did that, right, that would just be sort of the normalized
D.
I don't know what, we'll call that we can call that denormalized,
right?
And why normalized if I did that then I would know that I would just
have that cosine term purely because both of these are equal to 1 and
they would go away, right?
And so let's think about that for a second.
Does that actually give us what we you know, the the value that we
actually want right?
Does that actually give us the the V chord
It if you will or the you coordinate, if we were to do it for the x
axis, does that actually give us what we want and so let's think about
that, excuse me.
So
Way to go about thinking about this problem was, if we were to, you
know, if we were to normalize just the axis, but leave the point the
same length, right?
So let's say I was going to do D, transpose transpose, y, normalized,
right.
That would give me the length of D times the cosine of theta, and it
would take this out of the equation.
Write this value would tell me exactly the location of where this was
along that y-axis in.
At distance in actual pixel distance, right?
So in order to figure out how far along the y-axis, we were the first
thing we would do with that, right, is to divide it by the total
length we could have gone.
Which was that length to begin with, right?
So if you think about it, right?
What we really wanted to do here is we sort of wanted to divide by the
length of Y twice if that makes any sense, right?
Like what we
To do was we wanted to say okay we wish we had why normalized?
Because this is the value that comes out this.
This value here doesn't really help us.
It doesn't look like because this value is divided by the length of D
and the length of Y.
But it looks like what we would actually want to figure out this
point, right?
Is we want to figure out the length of tubing
We'd want to figure out that cosine term divided by the squared length
of Y, if that makes sense /, that that y twice.
And so, let's do that one more time.
Just so we can kind of see what's going on there and make it a little
clearer, right?
So I'm going to draw it this way, right?
So here's the the measurement axis, right?
Here's the measurement axis, and this could be y or X, right?
And so, what I'm going to say ahead of time is that this is unit
length, right?
So the length of this axis is going to be equal to 1.
Right?
And then I know I've got some length, right?
I don't know how long it is, but I know I've got some length.
That's the length of my quadrilateral, right?
So that's the length of this thing, right?
So let's say let's call this axis.
Let's say that a is the axis, right?
So the length of a is 1, right?
And then we've got another length, let's call that L, right?
And L is going to equal, you know?
However, however long the texture is.
So this is the actual our story of the quadrilateral.
So this is our actual
Quadrilateral.
Wife.
Right.
So now if we have some point no matter where that point is, right?
Here's our Point p and we projected onto this axis, right?
We know we can do that by saying that that is the point.
And again, this is the point I should do that.
This will do d, right?
So it's the - the origin, right?
So D is always equal to P minus origin, right?
There we go.
So if I take that D and I transpose it by a now, I get the length of D
cosine Theta, and that's what I actually want to measure against that.
That tells me how far in.
Pixel space.
I am over but now I want to turn that into a uniform coordinate that
goes from 0 to 1.
So I'm going to divide by that L, right?
And again you can see that again.
So that L that is just how long the axis would have been, right?
That L is just the length that a would have been if I'd let the It Go
the whole way, right?
So you can kind of see where I'm getting that that.
So really it looks to me like what we want is we want D transpose,
the, the actual axis.
So, whatever, the actual axis, the original version was
For normalization.
So like the y-axis, right?
We want to do that to produce length of d, right?
Length of Y cosine Theta.
When we do that, we can then just divide that axis after we're done
with it.
We can divide that by its length twice, right?
So whatever this length is, we do that twice, divide and divide and
that produces this equation up here, right?
It cancels, the why once and then still leaves that length on the
So that looks like the correct value to me again, I just work that
through.
I have no preconceived notion of what the answer actually should be.
That's just what I thought it should be based on.
We said, I may have made a math mistake or two along the way, but
that's the first thing that I would like to try, right?
And so now, let's talk about how to get that.
So, ink here, when we actually do this pixel P - origin, right?
You can notice that if I actually were to refactor this and let's just
do that.
I said we were going to do simpler origin.
We didn't do it yet.
But if I were to
A factor this by Distributing this negative, right?
If I distribute this negative, that would essentially distribute out
and make this negative here and negative here.
Right, again, distribute, the negative negative, negative negative
should be the negative negative negative, right?
And if I recompile that, you see that we didn't change anything,
right?
So, just to show you that - at what that allows me to do too, is
introduced that value that I just said d, right?
So if I go ahead and take my pixel P -
And make that D.
You can see that these are just all the same thing, right?
We still haven't simplified that but, you know, same basic idea.
Oops, they're right.
But if I do that now, same exact thing.
And there's that devalue that I actually wanted, we were already kind
of using it to compute the thing.
So now, if I want to compute what the texture coordinates are, right?
I want to compute that you and that V, right?
So if I want to compute the you coordinate, well, first of all, I
suppose we should say, we don't need to do this unless we're actually
inside.
Right?
Since they're already doing a test, we might as well not to take
offense.
Extra look up unless were inside.
So we want to do is say okay, we've got that you value.
And when I said that was going to be, as I said that was going to be
the dot product, right?
So we're going to do the dot product of whichever acts try measure on.
So for the you, we're doing the x-axis, right?
And we want to do that D times, the x axis, right?
Then what we want to do is we want to multiply that by the length, of
the x axis inverted, right?
Squared.
Sorry,
Right.
So, I want to divide, which means I'll just I'll pre do a one over for
it.
I want to divide by that X.
Excess length, right squared?
So that's what I actually want to do.
That make sense and similarly, for the V, I would do the exact
opposite.
I'm sorry.
Do the exact same thing, but for the y-axis, right?
And that should produce my un my V, right?
Similarly, I could just think of this as a vector, the UV Vector,
right?
And that's just, you know, composing these two together.
So that when we pass it to a texture sampling function, you know, we
could do that, right?
If that makes sense.
Ence.
So there we go.
All right.
So let's let's go ahead and pre compute these values because we need
to write.
So, when we get that x axis, and that Y axis, if we want to do the
inverse of the length squared, we just do length squared x axis,
right?
That's just the inverse of that and the why, right?
So is one over in both cases, like so.
And then we're Computing r u and v s, at least in theory.
We are Computing them.
And of course we haven't actually done the lookups yet.
So that's fine.
So now all we would need to do is actually look up the UN
Inside the texter.
And so, I'm going to do a function for that now or I guess I don't
really need to do a function, I can just write it in place.
That's fine.
So, we've got that texture, right?
We've got the, we've got the texture and it's one of those loaded
textures, right?
And so I believe is that in here?
Whereas loaded bitmap to find?
I don't even know.
Loaded bitmap, there it is.
Okay, so what I want to do is I want to look up into here to try and
get whatever the actual value is.
Is that the pixel should be to replace color 32, right?
So if I'm going to do that, I'm going to go ahead and say color 32
equals some look up into the texture.
I'm going to first need X Y coordinates.
Right.
So what I can do there is say alright that the x-coordinate is going
to be equal to the you and in fact, I guess this would make it a good
reason to have not bothered to wrap them up.
At least not at the moment.
So I'll go back to using it just like this for now.
There we go.
There is our u and v.
Like so
So that you coordinate I just need to multiply that by however big
this texture actually is right.
So whatever the texture is I just need to multiply it by the width.
And of course I need to subtract 1 from that with first because I need
to make sure that the the final if the value is actually one, I want
to end on that actual final text.
Alright.
I want to end on that final piece of that bitmap, right?
So what I want to do here is just say all right take whatever that you
proportion is and furthermore I could do in a certain here for just
for the time being say that these are within legal range since we're
doing some debugging here, we want to make sure that that's the case,
right?
So what we'd like to do is do that, and once I do this as well, one
thing we might want to do again is is round this properly so we might
want to do something like that right where we go ahead and and sort of
Hoops that right.
I could do that right at all.
There we go.
So texture with times, you know, that's correct, never mind.
Well, we'll deal with the rounding second.
All right, there we go.
Okay.
So when we do this, when we do this lookup or multiplying by the you
that's going to get us all the way there, and then, this is a
truncation.
So what I was sort of saying, as well, once we do that, what I'd like
to do is add the point five in so that we will round in either
direction, depending on which, which one we got, okay.
Trying to think, I'm just trying to think of that ever gives me know
that that will never produce an out of bounds.
So.
Okay, so we're good at least for now and so the same exact thing is
true for the height, right?
No difference.
There exact same thing and we've got the u and v test in here, just to
see whether we're fetching outside at all.
And let's go ahead and compile that and just see if we.
So, we're at the moment, we're never Computing a u and v that's out of
range.
So that's a good thing.
And similarly, we could assert that our X is greater than equal to 0
and less.
Then or not just less than the texture with.
Right?
So that we know we'd never be fetching out of bounds, like so oops,
that's with my bad, I meant height.
There we go.
So now yet we're still not fetching out of bounds.
So that's good, everyone's happy.
And so now what I'd like to do is go ahead and actually do that look
up right which is pretty easy for us to do we know exactly how to do
this.
We've done it a million times.
Well, Millions a little bit much for to potentially but you know we've
done it many times but it that way we start with a pointer to the base
right.
We then want to walk along the rows as far as we need to to get to the
correct row.
So that's just
To be whatever the y-coordinate is times the pitch.
And then we need to walk over right by however many we have with wise.
And that's just going to be however, big a pixel is, Right?
Which we know what the pixels are are 4 bytes per, right?
And so that will give us the correct pixel that we're trying to access
their.
And in fact, I'll do it this way you, and this is like our Texel.
This is, this is the texture texture that we're looking for, right
makes sense.
And then, what I want to
Do is I want to I basically just read that in and so this is the
textile value I guess I'll call us text Will pointer right whatever
the Texel pointer is, I just want to treat it.
Like it was a 32-bit value at that location want to read out.
That's the RGB.
And the a I was going to read that out and then we'll store it.
Exactly right like so-and-so.
Hey guess what?
We've got texture mapping, right?
And there's our tree and as you can see,
See, very simple.
Work.
The first time.
Nothing particularly fancy going on there.
We can look at it a little more closely and you know, that's a that's
texture mapping in a nutshell, right?
We can add the, we can add Alpha blending to this routine.
If we want to still do the Alphabet app so that Alpha blending that we
were doing before, you know, we can we can make that happen.
In fact we probably should Well that took almost no time at all but
there you go.
All right, we haven't handled a lot of the sort of finicky or stuff
and we haven't done any optimization.
So I suppose that's the more fancy stuff but ladies and gentlemen
texture mapping, not very difficult.
So so that's kind of the basics of it.
Let me go ahead and add in that, sort of that Al finesse to it.
It right?
We have the alpha stuff happening here.
So what I'm going to do for now is I'll just go ahead and grab this in
here what we were doing before for the alpha.
And so, if I want to do that when we're in this routine, right?
Let's go ahead and and paste that in there so that we can kind of.
Yeah, so that we can do that editing.
So we don't have this anymore and we don't have that.
We've just got the pixel right going on here.
And so, in here, you know, after I do that textile
What I need to do is I need to go ahead and make sure that we are
reading from the right places, right?
So there's the pixel that's coming in there.
It is, will do that Alpha stuff on it right.
Then we've got the Texel that's coming in and that Texel is our source
now, right?
Like so, and and I don't know if that's it.
Let's see legal in direction of the Texel.
Oh right.
We don't need to do star on that.
It's already been dereference.
So now all we need is that Alpha
that's coming in so that the alphabets going to modulate this and I'll
just go ahead and say that that that's actually because that c Alpha,
we're getting a color passed in that.
Does have an alpha value, right?
It's this one right here and so it will do is, will say color dot a
right there.
That's our, that's our modified Alpha, right?
And that's that color dot a
Corn on a port on it, right?
And so now we are correctly doing the alpha composite to which means
that we have the texture mapping working with all the same features
that we previously had working in our bitmaps.
And that's pretty awesome as well.
And so I do I'm gonna try to think if we should quit while we're ahead
here because the next sort of stuff that we'd be getting into, would
be a little fancy.
But yeah.
I mean.
Let's just, let's just do it.
All right, so what we're going to do next is first of all, we need to
slow this down and we need to do some stuff to kind of get us selves
in position to understand the reasons why we might need to do some of
the things that we're about to do.
So let's let's clean this up.
Let's stop getting fancy in the.
In this place we can get fancy and other places.
So for now I'm going to say let's keep this thing.
Fairly uniformly sized for
What just happened?
I have no idea.
So we have produced, we have produced a hue that is outside our
Precision.
Well, you know, it's bound to happen, these kind of need to be clamped
Or we need to modify our filter rules.
But I don't know if we may have to actually just clamp these most of
the time, that's not actually a problem for us, we can keep going.
I think if that makes sense, I don't think there's any real problem
with that, right?
But because it's not actually going to fetch out of bounds if the you
is slightly over.
But yeah, we're going to have to figure out how you want to handle
that.
In in Cindy, it'll be pretty easy for us to clamp those so it's not
really a huge deal, but yeah, all right.
So if we're in here what I wanted to do was go
Incorrect.
This stuff.
What's the illegal in Direction?
There we go.
So that we're actually doing something.
That's the same size everywhere, like so.
And I wanted to make it bigger so we can see it at a larger scale and
it's going to be slower obviously, because, again, we're not very
optimal, but you can kind of see it going around there.
So we've got that happening and we'd also like to, you know, what we
should probably do too is maybe keep.
Well, I don't know if we do that, we'll say.
For a second, then what I'd like to do to is make that angle go much
more slowly, okay?
So I don't know if you can, can see that well enough on the stream,
but you'll notice that it's kind of, I mean, when you kind of look at
what's happening in there, right?
It's not, it's very flickery and it's not really what we would want
because we're kind of making giant pixels, right.
We're like we're actually doing giant pixels at each step of the way
and it kind of makes it so that it's not really taking into account
sort of where we might happen to be sub-pixel e, right?
And so, what I want to do is start to kind of talk about sub pixels
and sub pixel accuracy, which obviously is going to involve a bunch
more stuff.
So, I figured
Just I figure, I'll just get us started on that.
And then we can kind of, we can kind of, I don't know next week, maybe
we'll try to solidify most of it, but hopefully, you can see, maybe
I'll make that even a little bit bigger.
Yes, I don't care.
So my statement maybe make it a little bit bigger and probably put it
in the center of the screen to.
I think that might be a good idea.
So what I'd like to do here is when we do this what I might do is say
okay the origin of it, I'm going to subtract
Act half the x-axis and half the y-axis from it so that it remains in
the center of the screen, right?
Just offset it like so, so that we're kind of always looking at it
right in that Center and you can.
Yeah, I mean, I don't know.
You can kind of see it.
We basically just get a ton of aliasing there, right?
And that's because we're just drawing pixels and we're looking up
those pixels.
We also have and you know what, let me let me show another thing to
actually this maybe this is the best.
My head is kind of spinning.
I wasn't thinking I was going to talk about this today so I'm kind of
thinking like okay what should I do?
So maybe we'll do one more thing to before we start spinning this
around and doing other stuff like that.
Maybe what we'll do instead is will actually move it along, right?
So what we'll do here is we'll say, Okay, instead of this stuff, we're
not even going to do that, right?
We're going to fix that x axis and the y axis.
Y axis to just be their respective axes, right?
We're not going to
Do anything fancy with those, right?
All we're going to do is do that.
And let's see here, 300 300.
So all we're going to do is, is that we're not going to change the
angle at all.
So, when we draw the thing, it's just a big tree, right?
There's the big tree and you see, it's been magnified, right?
Let's pixels or all kind of like a little rectangles because it's, you
know, the bitmap is taller than it is wide.
And so that's what happened, right?
And what I want to do now is I want to just move,
This guy slowly kind of left to right?
That makes sense.
So I'm going to take this angle value and I'm going to make another
one, right?
Which is going to be like displacement, right?
And I'm going to make displacement be a function of that angle, right?
So we'll kind of wobble back and forth.
10 pixels to either side, I'll take that displacement and I'll put
that displacement in so that it's basically like, you know, a
displacement sort.
Horizontally back and forth as, as the thing goes now.
What?
I want you to observe.
Here is sort of the nature of a thing that we've hinted at a bunch of
times.
And that is that value is continuously moving, right?
I mean the, the sort of speed at which this thing is going.
It's changing every frame its location, but it kind of snaps into
place as it moves one pixel over, right?
Each time.
It moves when actual pixel Over, You See It shift, but that's all that
happens.
And furthermore, you can kind of see like,
Bolinas in here and maybe if I speed it up just a little bit.
So maybe I speed it up just just a bit so we can that motion is a
little more exaggerated there.
Hopefully.
Maybe maybe not.
Oh whoops, that's not what I wanted to do.
One speed it up.
There we go.
So, you can kind of see how you get these like lines of motion, how it
kind of Ripples.
And what you're seeing there is the fact that we're stepping through
pixels right?
And basically the pixel values will change from one Texel to the next
trying to think of a good way for you to pick because like look at
this motion just to study it for a second right and you see how there
are these kind of wavy lines that kind of appear to move through it.
So what's happening there right?
Is that you have a
We should wear the number of pixels and number of texels isn't
dividing out evenly.
Right?
So, what happens is, I've got some pixels right on the screen, like
so, right?
And then I've got some texels in the texture map, right?
In that thing that, you know, these are we call those texels?
They're really just more pixels, right?
But pixels are things around the screen and textiles are things going
to texture.
We just use that namik later to make things clearer.
So we've got some pixels and when we're magnifying stuff like that,
one pixel maps to several texels, right?
So this textiles, these textiles here, all get the same pixel color,
right?
They all get this, I'm sorry these pixels like the same texture color,
So if this is color, a all of these guys get color a right.
And if this is B, then all of these guys get colored be right.
But the problem is when it doesn't divide out perfectly evenly which
it almost never will.
Then really what happens is as we move through the
Pixels.
A single Texel maps to 1 and some amount.
Write it like ends, right there, right?
So that's the width of the textile mapping, right?
And then this next one is going to be exactly as long.
But that means, it ends a little bit further down.
And then, finally, this one ends before it actually covers the pixel
Center.
What that means is, you will see 3 pixels from this Texel 3 pixels
from this Texel, and then only to
Two pixels.
Potentially from this one or four from this one depending on how it
you know it goes out right.
You'll well, no you see 2 and then 4 to 3 3 2 3 3, right?
You'd see like a pattern a beat frequency happen.
As you see, those sort of things divide out and it leads to this
really ugly amateur hour thing which is exactly.
Unfortunately, what I see in a lot of Indie Games, sometimes it's
really depressing When I See This and furthermore, you get the even
worse artifact, which is you will see
This motion as it's moving.
It only moves when it can move a whole pixel, right?
So you get this sort of stuttery motion, right?
That just doesn't look smooth and and you get that, I see that kind of
times.
It's really, it bothers me.
It's some deep level.
You'll see a game and it's got like, a parallax background.
And the cloud layer in the background is like, going well.
Everything else is updating at 30 frames a second.
It's effectively.
E updating it like five frames a second because they didn't use sub
pixel Precision for the rendering, right?
So that's that's that right?
That's that's the situation that goes in there.
So what I want to do is start tackling these problems, right?
What we want to do is start tackling these problems in the first thing
we can do is at least start to look at whether we're being correct in
terms of remembering where we roughly are in.
Axel space, right?
And so the first problem that you will,
Immediately, when you look at the code that I'm writing, is this right
here, right?
Do you see this?
We got past floating Point accuracy for where the origin is, but
you'll notice that I because We're looping over pixels, I just
flat-out ignored it and said, whatever.
The rounded pixel values are, that's where we're at now, right?
But that's not really where we were right, that's not really, you
know, the location of the thing.
That's the location of the
vile.
But I sort of semi redeemed myself because what I did is I then said
all right that's the location of the pixel were on, but I'm going to
subtract the actual floating-point origin from that, right?
This is where we actually were.
So if I adjust done this and then was using that somehow is the XY
coordinates for lookups, that would have been bad but because we're
still doing everything relative to that floating-point origin that
restores back in that.
Fractional value that's actually lets us know where we actually were
right.
And that means that we'll be filling the pixels correctly with the
correct, fractional value with the correct fractional measurements as
well.
So that when we do those Edge tests, we're actually testing the edges
against.
We're actually testing its edges that are properly, moving through
that space.
So this is the thing that saves us right here.
This this fact that we're still subtracting in the origin should mean,
that we at least we'll have the information that we need.
So the question is though, why do we still
Look like that, right?
And the answer is because then we then go ahead and throw away that
fractional Precision by just doing a round operation here.
Right.
So even though we know where we are fractionally in the texture map,
we know specifically that this Texel that this pixel maps to a very
specific specific place and texture space, right?
Like maybe it maps to right there or something like this.
Even though we know that, we always just round to whatever the closest
pixel is, right?
So what we want to do is we want to do something that does a better
job, basically, of figuring out where we are in the texture map, so
that we can produce results that are sub-pixel accurate.
And so let's talk about how we're going to do that.
all right, so what we want to do, we've got our textiles
Right.
And what we want to do is say, okay, we've got a particular pixel and
we know the location of that pixel in the texture.
Exactly.
Because we're Computing at all in floating-point space.
So you know, here's the center of the textile.
Let's say, right?
Like so here's the center of the textile and we now have, you know,
sort of four pixels that are kind of creating a space around where we
want to sample.
And so what we're doing right now is we're just taking this pixels
color and we're using this pixels color and what we'd rather do is
we'd rather lean
A on a linear blend right that linear.
Blend that we've used so many times, what we want to do is is leverage
that linear blend to produce a color.
That will allow us to smoothly sample.
The texture anywhere in this rectangle, right?
We want to be able to say, okay, we know for color values, so if you
want something that's in between them, let's just blend those colors
together so that we can produce a reasonable result, right.
Does that make sense?
So let's say we're going to do that, right?
If we're going to do that, all we would have to do is load these
values, and then blend between them using the linear Blends.
We already know how to do, right?
So let's say, we have, you know, a b c d, right?
So this is our blending thing here.
We've got a b c d.
Well, you already know how to blend between two of these, right?
So, if we have a pixel that's here, right?
You already know.
If you take the number between 0 and 1, we can do the linear blend.
Write the equation.
I say handles just about everything right plus.
Wow!
That's the worst drawing of that equation plus t b, right, this equals
the value.
That's the sampled value.
That's like the a be blend, right?
So, all we need to do is produce that t value, we could blend between
a and b.
And similarly, we would also know how far we would go there.
We would know how to produce the C and D blend, right?
So we know how to do that.
Linear Blend or alert as it were right.
We know how to do a lerp between a and b, and we know how to do a lerp
between c and d, right?
But we don't know how to do is, do a blend between ABC and d and the
answer is you just do the lerp again.
Once I produce the Blended.
Of c and d and a, and b that effectively.
I've created two new points along the border.
And so if I want a point here, all I would need to know is some other
blend.
That tells me how far vertically to blend the two, and then just use
those to.
So, what I can do is I can actually compose lerp on top of itself,
right?
And I say lerp between the result of these two other lips, because all
I'm doing is producing two new points.
That now form a line that I can learn between.
So all we really need to know is we really need to know a fractional
value this
Sway and a fractional value.
This way that goes between 0 and 1.
That tells us how close we are to each of the textiles like an fx and
an F why.
Right.
And guess what?
We know exactly what that is because when we were actually Computing
the u and v we didn't have to round it here, right?
We have the value.
So let's do it this way, right?
Let's do our Tech selects like, so right there is our Tech selects and
our Texel.
Why?
Right?
Those are floating Point values.
Once I round them it's free for me to reconstruct the fractional
portion because I can just say whatever the rounded value is the real
version that I had before that had the fractional part in it.
If I subtract away, whatever the part is I came up with a rounding
should give me that fractional value.
That was left over.
Right so I
No, what I would need to do to blend, right?
Really, really straightforward to do that blend, right?
So let's just do that.
I mean let's just blend those colors, right?
Not particularly hard.
So I've got this text will fetch here, right?
And all I need to do now is do that.
Text will fetch.
I just need to do that textural effect for four things, right?
So I've got like, you know, like this.
And in fact, I'll use the ABC that I did before, right?
If I fetch for textiles it's just a text file pointer right?
With a few
Ins right to it.
The first one we sample right out of the textile pointer.
The next one we sample out of the text appoint ER Plus 1 pixel.
Right.
The next one we do plus the pitch.
So we're on the next row right and then the final one, we just do the
texture of the pitch + + 1 + 0, 1, X and Y and there's our, for
textiles, right?
That makes sense pretty straightforward.
Now the problem is when we do that, we may fetch off the edge of the
texture map.
So what I'm going to do synthetically just for the moment again this
is probably not.
This is not going to be probably the final way that we would handle
this.
But what I'm going to do just for the moment, is it going to pretend
our texture is smaller than it actually is?
Okay, so what I'm going to do is I'm going to pretend that the width
is 2 less than it actually is.
And then I'm going to add one at the beginning, so that way we're
always kind of in a rectangle.
That's a little bit smaller.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
So then in here I'll just
Choose text Olay for now.
So,
And as you can see, we're still getting the exact same results which
is what we want.
And so now we have to do is blend these guys together to get our final
result.
So if I want to do that I believe I finally did add that linear blend,
of course, I've got to actually, I guess I have to actually Loft out
the values as well, which is a bit of a pain.
But let's go ahead and do that.
So this is Tex Le pointer a actually.
Textual pointer be Texel pointer.
See Texel pointer d, right?
So if I actually want to do these, I need to actually do this.
Where we actually extract the color values out if that makes sense.
And so, what I need to do is something here where we actually take.
So this is doing the premultiplied alpha, as well, sort of baked in
there, right?
Which we don't, actually, yeah, we don't actually.
Yeah, okay.
Well, let's rearrange this.
So if I wanted to do this, this is this is kind of getting into some
things that maybe we didn't want to get into yet.
But so if we do this, this sort of operation and we need to pre
multiply our texture values, we'd rather
I have pre multiplied them in the actual texture and unfortunately we
haven't done that yet.
Oh wait.
No, I take it back.
That's just pre multiplying by the color that's coming in.
Totally fine.
Never mind.
We're good here.
No problem.
So what I probably will do is I'm going to take this out for now, so
we're not going to use that color a at the moment and I'll do to do
color a
all right, so if
Want to read out of this texture and I'm going to go ahead and put in
my values here.
So there's red green, blue and Alpha there's my Texel.
A right?
We've extracted the values of it out, and gotten those.
Then I'm going to go in here and get the rest of my values.
So there is Texel, be pixel C Texel D and then I'll just do pointer a
probably should done that before I cut and pasted it but you know how
it is.
Sometimes.
Right.
so,
all right, so we've got our A's, here's our bees.
Here's our seas, here's our Dee's.
So now we have all the textiles and all we have to do is actually lerp
between them and then we have our essay.
When we did our SAR SBR that stuff we can actually just still do those
the same way we were doing them for
All right, so this will just be, you know, our final Texel values are
found, textual values are again just set ourselves up for fighting
feeding into that other equation.
Alright?
So right now, if I set it to just be one of our textiles just to
verify that we were reading them.
Right.
Let's see here.
Before Texel.
Right in theory, this should give us all the values that we need.
You should see the same tree we do so.
Now, all we have to do is produce this Texel by properly doing that,
linear interpolation.
And so, I said, we need to compose the lerp.
So here's our lerp.
There we go.
We need to text and text will be.
We need to do a loop of that with Texel.
See,
and Texel d, right?
And again, we've got our fractional, why that lips between those and
our fractional X, that Loops between these.
And that should give us should put us within Striking Distance of
actually doing that texture filtering.
So, what is the problem here v40?
Right?
We don't have a version for this 4 V 4 operations.
Looks like
And so, I will manufacture wine.
So, really lerp is the same no matter what you're doing, right?
So you can change it to anything else.
Again, if you're a template style person, this is a place you could do
templates.
There should work fine.
I would suspect, let's see here and we don't have multiplication for
those as well.
So scalar, multiply just want that as well.
Let's see, V3 operations.
Real want, I guess we'll probably want all of these.
So, yeah, if you're doing templates, you should be able to
Just just use templates for these guys.
There shouldn't be a problem with that.
I'm going to go ahead and I just don't like using templates.
I find that it's just they're always a headache.
So I stay away from them if you're using ja.
I if I was using J, I obviously
That is the preferred solution and I wish we were, but we're not.
So we got to suffer through for a little bit longer.
We got stuff out through a C++ for a little bit longer but hopefully
not too much longer John.
If you're listening not too much longer, right?
There's going to be a j, i just tribution that we all get to use,
right?
And it's awesome.
I'm sure he
is producing it as we speak, okay?
Yeah, so that looks like pretty much all we would need to do there so
off we go.
So what's the problem?
What are we missing of?
The lerp is before we had put that afterwards so it can access those
functions and there we go.
All right, so now we've got our properly blurry.
Although, why is of course, stopped moving, which doesn't seem like a
good idea.
I don't know why it stopped everything that's
Not a good sign.
Let me go ahead and
all right.
So I don't know what I accidentally did to stop our poor tree from
moving anywhere.
Oh, there, you know what it actually is moving?
It's just our stuff is sub-pixel now, so you can't, you couldn't see
it because it's so smooth.
You can't see the wavy lines that actually was moving.
So that's okay.
That was pretty funny.
So, as you can see, that helps a lot to just with the the change in
the size.
Let me go ahead and and show you maybe with a little
Bit more mean you can see how different that was, right?
I didn't even I thought the thing and stopped moving.
That's how smooth moves.
Now, once you start to put that sampling in there, you can't even see
it anymore.
It totally fools your eye and we're not even taking as much care as we
should in a lot of places.
So I suspect we still got stuff we can do to make it even better than
that.
But let's go ahead and make that a little bit more pronounced.
Maybe so now you can see it moving, right?
And we're still like there's there's still
Uh, choppiness there in terms of where it is.
So I think we've still got some problem although that may just be our
frame rate.
So what I could do is say let's go ahead and make it a little smaller
because since we're not optimized at the moment, our frame rate is
definitely Loops, that's the wrong place.
Our frame rate is definitely an issue.
So yeah, so there's are moving dude, right?
And you see how it's nice and smooth.
That is in fact you can basically see right now that only our edges.
Are a little bit on smooth, you can kind of see them being a little
unsmooth there and so we can talk about some reasons why that is and
maybe fix that a little bit but I don't know if you can see how nice
and smoothly that guy moves by comparison to the old guy just for for
comparison purposes.
If I was to go back to you,
In the old way, which is to do this.
Right.
So
Let's go ahead and compare those two, right?
So here we have it, moving back and forth and now I'm going to take it
out so it's moving in the sort of well, no, I'm not compile your so
this is the guy moving in the old way, right?
And you can kind of see, like, once he's getting moving at full speed,
he Shimmer is a bit which is objectionable, but he doesn't stutter
that much, but when he gets to the end, he's very stuttery, right?
He gets that kind of, really sort of
Stuttery motion at the end.
Whereas when we do it with the nice smooth version, he doesn't waive
when he's moving.
And when he Glides nicely to a stop without ever seeing that sort of
pixel Sutter emotion, let me see if I can make him just a little bit
bigger so you can kind of see a little bit more of that.
Well, a frame rate is just too bad at the moment is the problem, so I
don't know.
We're going to have to do some optimization before we can probably
actually show what it looks like when you make it a little bit.
Larger.
That's unfortunate.
But there you can kind of see it too.
So, let me go ahead and I'll switch it back to the pixelated version
so you can see all that crawling.
That's happening in there.
And you could do see that stuttering at the end.
How, how ugly that looks.
And again, it might be hard for you to see what the video compression
to because the video compression ads as a smoother.
But, yeah, there you go.
So, yeah, we've got a bunch of work to do.
We're far from the Finish Line on rendering, but hopefully you can see
Hopefully you can see that we're already pretty well on our way there
to having a render.
I mean, that's the Primitive that we need, which is filled textured
filled quad.
So we've kind of got, we kind of set ourselves up for next week to
really kind of get, get down to it, right?
And of course, I also need to probably put a thing here that says to
do Casey.
Formalize texture boundaries or something like this, just so we don't
forget about that.
All right, so we're about out of time anyway, so maybe it is time to
go to that Q&A.
So let's go ahead and do that and we'll leave our little tree.
In fact, you know what we should do too.
I think we should get our tree spinning again.
Probably.
Right.
That seems like a good idea to me, just so we can see what happens
there as well.
So there's our spinning version of the tree.
You can see it, it's going there and the spinning version of the tree.
We would also like to check that out in both cases.
So, let's see here, here's our lerp version, right?
So you can
See.
Ugly, that looks when we rotate it, right?
You can see how ugly that all looks.
And when you go to the lerp version already, it just cleans so much of
that up.
You get rid of so much artifacting there.
And so that's by the way, just so everyone knows to that's called when
you're doing texture texturing.
That's that's what they talk about when they talk about texture
filtering.
And so like, for example, if you talk about linear texture filtering,
that's what we're doing right now and isotropic texture.
Filtering is related, but does some more stuff
Cough mipmap based filtering does more stuff as well.
So there's other levels of filtering kits are adding in there.
And right now we're doing the most basic one which is like a simple by
linear filter on the texture, so that we can produce a smooth result
instead of a of a hard-edged result on this pixel boundaries.
We blow will the wall trees be sub-pixel accurate now, so you should
feel answer that yourself, my friend, should they be sub-pixel
accurate or not?
And of course, the answer is no, because we're not calling this
routine to draw them.
Right?
So until we actually call this the routine to draw, like, remember
this is only draw.
We're their only one place that calls.
Draw a rectangle slowly.
So these guys are not are still going through the old drawbitmap path.
So until we get this nice and fast and accurate and everything is
good.
And we're ready to actually call everyone to go through it.
Everything else will not be sub pixel accurate, so you can see that
the head is not so big sharks at the moment, right?
The top of the tree seems to be cut short.
That's correct.
Why do you think that might be?
You have any guesses?
I will give you a hint.
Although could actually just be Boop's.
I did not mean to do that but did I do?
No, don't don't edit the code in here.
While we may have other bugs in there as well, and I don't actually
know remember that.
This guy right is part of ammo and you know what?
I forgot to do we're by linearly filtering map.
So we don't want to round.
So we had two reasons that the tree was cut off.
One is because we actually do cut off the top and the sides, right?
Because we are just, we're just arbitrarily only using one pixel in
from everywhere.
But the other reason is to, we shouldn't be adding .05 anymore because
we're doing bilinear filtering.
So we don't want to round, we want to floor because we're using both
sides, right?
So yeah, so we can get a little bit of that back already just by
getting rid of that point five, but only a little bit.
There's there's another part of it, which has nothing to do with that.
So if we get rid of that point five, which we should have done,
See we get a little bit of the tree top back in but also remember that
Treetop I think that's just the last piece of it right there so I
believe that is just because like I think we're also cutting the this
edge of it as well if that makes any sense.
But I'm not totally sure about that.
So for example, if right here, we were to let it go further, right?
We'd potentially fetch outside the texture but that would bring it
back inside.
So you can see more of the Treetops, but now we occasionally, fetch
outside the texture.
So, yeah.
It's three spinning going to be in the DLC, know that'll probably be.
Well, it might be day one DLC.
like,
Obviously people shouldn't be able to just get a spanning tree.
They should have to pay extra for it so but I want to be there at the
beginning of you know, right from the first time to play the game so
maybe it'll be Dede 0 DLC.
Does it rotate with sub, pixel accuracy?
Yes, it does.
Although, again, we've got more stuff to do before we can really say,
we're sub-pixel accurate, because we haven't really gone through and
analyzed everything properly yet.
So, yes, we are rotating with sub pixel accuracy.
Now
And you can kind of see that to you can see how smooth this looks in
here, right?
Because for example, if I stop moving it side to side, for example.
So let's say we go in here and we get rid of this disc, right?
So we're not moving it back and forth anymore.
So, if you get rid of that, you can see how smooth that looks in
there, right?
It's super smooth, right?
You don't see any real artifacting in there.
So, and we're turning very slowly, so you can see that we've got a
nice sub-pixel thing going on there, but again, we've got more work to
do and we have to do some work for the texture boundaries as well.
Like I said, so that we don't have that tree clipping problem, and
there's a bunch of other things, but again, those are polish things.
What's the most major fundamental thing left to do on the renderer?
Well performance?
I mean that's the thing, right?
It's fine and good to get a nice little spinning tree here, right?
But if we, now need to draw the whole screen using this sort of
technique, and we want it to be fast, and we want it to be capable of
doing overdrawn that sort of stuff.
That's, that's really the next major obstacle that we have.
Now again, we don't really have to be that fast for shipping because,
like I said, will support the hardware path and I guess you could say
that's the other major thing left to do is, is a
Opengl version.
But I don't know when we want to do that.
Like
Depends on how fast our software rasterizer ends up.
Being, because maybe we'll just use that.
Our software is rather for a while, but
And we also have to figure out what we want to do about about clamping
and I'm not sure.
I think we just want to actually do the clamping for those guys but
ought to think about that.
How would you do smooth, some pixel rendering for something like pixel
art, Graphics that doesn't blur, but still moves smoothly.
So the way that you want to do that,
It's a little complicated.
So
I mean, it depends on what you're doing, right?
So how can I explain this?
Let's go to the Blackboard.
It's good.
It's a good question.
I'll start with that.
So this is, this is more of a technique question.
So, I'll just explain to you what's happening.
And then, you can think about the technique yourself, I can give an
example of one solution, but it's not a problem that I've ever had
because I don't really do pixel Graphics stuff.
So, I can't say definitively that I have a solution that I like,
because I'm just coming up with this on the spot, but I can tell you
the nature of the problem.
So the nature of the problem is as follows
Suppose, you have a texture map from a pixel Sprite and these pixels
are meant to be big on the screen, right?
So when we're talking on the screen, you know, we've got our nice 4K
display or whatever, right?
And so, in, in Good Times, it would just feel like one of these pixels
would fill, like, this whole thing, right?
So here's a, and this whole thing is a right?
And then here's be, if it was a line tears, be right?
There's be, and it's all good.
And so, the problem now is
Happens when this moves to the side, right?
When this moves to the side.
So you can imagine, in fact, I probably do that poorly.
Let me draw that a little bit better.
So here's a here's B, right.
So now we start off and we've got a and b are here and here, right?
So here's B.
And here's a, if they felt perfectly on a pixel boundary then
everything's good but let's suppose that they don't.
So let's suppose that we now have it, right?
So we've got something more like this.
Right, same size, still, but they're just off a little bit.
So here is being here is a right.
So, what I want to illustrate here is if we were tutor, if you were to
do what we were doing, right?
If you were to do pure linear filtering, then what would happen is you
would destroy the good case, right?
Which is where you have this, nice solid a, and this nice solid B, you
would destroy that case because it would blend the whole blend, right?
So all these pixels, all of these
would all be blend and you would not see those
Nice hard pixel boundaries that you want with the pixel art.
But at the same time, you've got a case here where these two pixels
you really do wish these two pixels would blend, right?
You don't want these guys to blend, but you want these two.
So really what you want to do here is you want to say, okay, if a
particular pixel would have landed in on, if the nearest neighbor
sample for a pixel on, either side of the pixel would have landed in
either into different textiles, then blend.
Um, but otherwise don't and you could actually do that in a pixel
Shader if you wanted to, that's totally doable and you could
explicitly, write that, so that's the perfect solution, right?
Would be to explicitly, write it that way.
Another solution is multi sample, right?
Turn on msaa and turn off, linear filtering.
And then it would actually be the case that these staggered pixels.
Would pick up the fact that one was coming from either or right, so
that's solution.
Number two.
So here our solution number one, right into pixel Shader to msaa.
3 is by far, the poor man solution, which is often times the best one
because it runs on the most platforms and that is manual pre
upsampling
Right.
So what you do there is you say, you know what?
Okay, so the artist handed me this little 4x4 pixel Sprite or
something, right?
And there's the, A, and B up in the corner.
And the problem is, when we're doing linear sampling, right?
If I was a turn-on linear than, like this pixel shows up as being half
a third of a and I'm sorry, a seventh of a, in the 3rd of B and that's
not what I want.
I want to be like solidly a all you do is you just up sample that
right pre make a texture, that's huge.
Right.
This 4x4 texture make this into a 512 by 512 texture, where all of
these are all a AAA BBB BBB.
So most of the time it is picking between two A's which just produces
the color a and only when you get near the boundary of A and B, do you
actually produce be right?
And that's a really cheap way to do it.
So what I would say is if you're working with an engine, it doesn't
you don't
Any control over it.
You don't want to be fancy because this Burns a lot of texture.
Memory, write.
It burns a ton of texture memory, but texture memory is pretty cheap
nowadays, especially for a pixel art game because there's just not
that much art.
So, all you have to do is blow those art assets up by actually just
replicating it.
So, take this 4x4 and spam it out into a 512 by 512.
Where each pixel, you know, you take 5, 12 divided by 4, right?
And you get 128.
So each pixel now maps to a 128 by 128
block of the same color, right?
And that'll solve your sub-pixel problem.
Just not as perfectly.
Couldn't you use the rounding and truncate to not sample outside the
edges of the texture.
So, the problem is really just we have to have a relatively sane
scheme for how we're going to do this.
This, this evolves, this is an accuracy issue.
So, if you think about how this works right, technically, we're always
doing a truncation and then we're adding 1.
So, like if we wanted to be 100% explicit here, we don't need the Plus
Right.
And we need to just make sure that we're one away from the end so that
we when we do this addition, we always make sure that we're within the
boundary right?
So I think that's the minimal one we could do again.
It's I'd like to go over this a little more carefully, but I think
that's the minimum that we could do.
And you know, I mean that looks
That looks pretty reasonable.
It looks like that top of that tree is back now for the most part,
right?
But again that's the stuff we want to analyze a little bit later
because we didn't really have time to kind of like work it through and
I didn't want to just start going oh we can do this and that so I'd
rather sort of take it a little bit slower.
But yeah, that's
I mean that's the basics of it, right?
Why are still adding 0.5 to 2 x and t y?
So I okay I've seen that question got asked before before I did that.
Is it any faster?
If you just test the domain of UV instead of testing edges?
so, the way that we're actually going to do this when we're doing
performance,
I think here's what I'll say is I don't often write software
rasterizer stuff, right?
So I don't want to answer incorrectly because it's not really my field
of expertise.
But I guess what I would say is I believe that the way that I suspect
will finally do this when we actually write the optimized version
which is like what regretted getting to.
I believe you could say that that sort of is what we will be doing.
We won't necessarily
Be thinking of them as much in terms of u and v will be thinking of
them as Bary, Centric coordinates.
Let me just make sure that that's just the same clamping thing.
Yeah.
Like I think what I would say is yes I believe that's the way you do
it quickly is that because you're looking at the very center
coordinates and your your testing the same coordinates that you're
using for look up.
So
I don't know if the answer is technically.
Yes, in the way that I've structured it, but I think it will.
I think you will see that that ends up being basically what we do
because you will like we want to collapse our both, our lookup and our
Edge functions into the same parameter space.
So I think I think the answer is yes, as I guess what I would say, but
don't quote me on that because we'll have to see when we actually get
there.
It's not something that I write often and so I'm not prepared to say
definitively.
Yes.
Software, rasterization is like, way out of my expertise, look area.
Like this is not what I do on a daily basis, right?
So I'm not necessarily qualified to give Pat answers to things like
that.
Is rendering on the CPU different in comparison to rendering on a GPU
code wise, not really.
So, basically the difference between the two is this Loop.
So the fact that we're implementing this Loop is mostly the
difference, the stuff that happens inside the loop is the Shader,
like, we write Shader, we will be writing Shader code in the GL
version that does exactly the same things that we do in here, right?
So basically, what happens on the GPU is the GPU, does the
rasterization part because it's built in.
So you don't control that unfortunately.
So it wrote this part right and then you do a lot of this stuff and
some of it you can have some of its got like macro it up for you so
like you don't have to manually compute, the u and v s.
It will compute them for you.
Sometimes it's tough like that, right?
Like there's things you can do like the lookups like the txt why?
I mean it's got a texture unit that can do that too.
So a bunch of things are Mac road, but it's all the exact same stuff
which is why I'm going through it with you this way so that you can
see.
Okay everything now you know what the gpus doing, like the Jeep.
You is doing this code, it's doing much more higher-end versions of
this code, right?
Because they, you know, keep cranking on it and trying to do more and
more optimal things that do like, you know, hierarchical calling and
all these sorts of things but they're basically doing exactly what
we're doing now.
Are there performance benefits for using a quad as primitive over
triangles in a software renderer like this?
Yes, excuse me.
I don't want to overstate the case, potentially.
But there's actually performance benefits for using a quad as a
primitive in Hardware as well, like, basically.
the only reason they don't do exactly what I'm doing here and do it as
quads is because quads don't
As well in 3D because triangles are the actual primitive that can
construct everything.
Whereas in a Sprite engine quads are the things you never have a
triangular problem and that gets down to the fact that surfaces, you
know, have extraordinary vertices and triangles.
The only things that can properly tile and all these other sorts of
weird, things like that.
And that the plane equation is only defined on a triangle and all
these sorts of stuff.
So there's all these reasons why they go triangular, but the
rasterization level, if you're a spy,
Right engine.
Even if you were a hardware Sprite engine I would be willing to say
that I suspect the hardware would always be much faster squads that it
was triangles because it be half the throughput, right?
So yeah.
Why do the edges of the tree look like they are feathered?
It's because they actually are.
So, if you take a look at the actual art assets, if we go into here.
So, where are the art assets?
I guess this is it.
so if we take a look at the actual assets, you can see that they
actually are feathered, so I'll create so you can kind of see
Oh, white background.
So you see that that's that's how they're actually made.
So that's just how that is.
See, Bruce the yeah.
With a different render as being the platform layer.
No, because they're platform-independent most of the time.
So they'll be sort of a different thing for renderers.
Where will kind of have will pull them out?
Once it's time to do that, will pull them out into that third tier.
I've talked about multiple times, I said we're going to have a three
tier thing.
so,
I saw a great video on YouTube called computer color is broken from
minutephysics.
A talks about how many cars is usually incorrectly done without
relying.
On third-party libraries.
You have an opportunity to do it correctly.
Yeah.
So we will be doing correctly or close to correctly.
You don't really need to do it.
So they're talking about situations, probably that are a little more
important than the ones that were talking about.
So like if you're doing a lighting, a physically based lighting,
You typically have to take taken into account.
If you're doing High dynamic range has taken into account.
If you're doing Sprites like this, you don't really have to take it
into account, although your edges may look a little bit better.
So like the edge
Improve.
So normally I would not Advocate the thing that they're probably
talking about in that view, video is gamma and normally I would not
Advocate correcting for the gamma in a Sprite engine.
Unless you had a really good reason but because Juan Chun made me
promise to show people how to do correct gamma we will be doing
correct gamma because of Juan and so you will see me when we go
Into our sort of optimization pass and we have SSE in there when we
can actually start to do it without it being in possibly slow, I will
show how to do the gamma correction and you know, you can see what the
results are.
They're not particularly impressive, but they're a little bit better
potentially, Maybe.
Again, really, it's for Lon.
Well, I made me promise to show how to do it.
So I will do it basically just involve squaring and then Square
rooting or using a color table, lookup, it's not rocket science.
remember when you introduced render group the other week, is this
sub-pixel rendering lerp, one of the things that will go in the render
group
Dude, it's already in the render group, right?
Draw a rectangle slowly gets called from inside the wreck inside the
render group, right?
Draw a rectangle slowly is the layer.
Paul here is the render group, so I'm not sure what you mean by that.
We it is, it is in the coordinate system, are little sort of debug
thing we were using here.
If you're asking whether the rest of render people start using it.
Yes, obviously.
That's, that's what we're sort of aiming towards, but we're just got
to get it all working in like a little simple deep.
Case, so that we can get it.
Correct and then we can go ahead and have everybody call it.
And so that our renderer can all go through like a nice, you know.
Useful path.
All right, I think we are at time so I am going to call it for today,
Man.
2 days back-to-back.
We're like nothing went wrong with rendering, guess?
It just goes to show you that programming visual stuff is easier than
programming non visual stuff or something.
Let's go ahead and save off our Mischief there.
But yeah, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
We did linear Blended texture mapping today and it all went great.
Yeah.
What can I say?
That's a lot easier.
I would.
Pat it in my head.
I was like the renderer is going to take like two months.
I think I even
Said something like that.
And yet it really took a week for us to implement mostly all the
features.
And so, I guess we'll see next week.
We'll work on tightening up the math and then the week after that,
we'll start working on optimization.
I don't know at this point who knows, like maybe will be done by the
end of next week.
I don't even know what to say.
I thought so for rendering was going to be a big topic.
It just doesn't seem to be and so, hey, that's great.
I mean the sooner we get
To making the game, the more fun we can have making the game.
I don't know, but I love making rendering stuff so it's 61f doesn't
happen to me.
I guess I'm just happy that's going smoothly so I hope you guys are
enjoying it.
I know I am next week.
We'll tighten up the math.
A bit I want to go through there and start to talk about like pixel
centers, Phil rules barycentric, coordinates and probably some color
stuff.
Maybe we'll get the gamma in there as well and then try to get all of
that in
You know, next week's we kind of have like, this is, you know, the
definitive kind of math that we want to be doing so that we can start
moving on to the optimization path, which is really just, you know,
dropping it down to SSE and making sure that we're doing, you know,
relatively minimal number of pixel tests and operations inside those
pixels.
So, yeah, that's that's software rendering in a nutshell and, and
that's the path we taking.
So, I hope to see you back here next week, probably.
Should be same schedule as this week.
So 5 p.m.
weeknights right here on Twitch.
If you want to follow along at home, of course, you can pre-order the
game on handmade hero dot org and it comes with a source code.
Every night, you can download it and play around with the stuff that
we're playing around with, its great way to learn.
We also have a forum to ask questions and that has forced a Mac and
Linux and an annotated episode guide for catching up on old episodes.
Pretty awesome.
We have a patreon page if you want to support this video series, if
you enjoyed it and want to support it.
That's a really awesome thing we very much appreciate, and we also
have a
Schedule tweeting bot thing that will treat the schedule at you.
If you want to know when there's going to be a live broadcast that
will tell you, so definitely check those out when you get a chance and
I guess have a fantastic weekend.
I can't seem to get to the task bar for some reason.
There it is.
So yeah, have a fantastic weekend and I will hopefully see you guys on
Monday.
Take it easy, everyone.