So, we can get good.
Okay, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero show.
Where we code a complete game from scratch.
No engine, no libraries.
Just our own like sagacious, little fingers typing away.
And basically, we're doing this so that we can see the complete set of
code and know everything about the complete set of code necessary to
run a game on a modern computer.
And right now, we're at the point where we have decided to start
looking at.
We're in the middle of doing engine architecture work, and we decided
to start looking at how we want to handle.
Concept that.
When two things, Collide meaning, you know, like say, for example, a
sword that has been thrown touches an enemy, we want to start
responding to these sorts of things.
You want to start creating sort of that, that part of the program,
which is where gameplay really starts to take shape, actually, which
is interactions between things.
Right.
Most gameplay is sort of developed as the interaction between things
when this touches this this happens, right?
Or when you know you walk over this kind of thing this happens.
And so now is a good time I think for us to start looking at that and
that is what's on the agenda.
For today also have a little sticky note here because someone on the
forums pointed out that we had a cut-and-paste bug lot of times when
I'm reorganizing code on the stream and I'm trying to talk it through,
it's a little bit difficult for me.
So sometimes things sneak by, and I kind of rely on people who are
watching to catch the cut and paste errors that I would normally be
catching, or at least trying to catch if I were working.
Normally, and so somebody, I greatly appreciate this on the farm.
Someone caught one.
For us and I want to go take care of that as well.
But before we do that, let me just remind everyone that if you did,
pre-order the game on handmade here at the org, you should have gotten
an email that gives you a link where you can download the source code.
And if you would like to follow along with what we're doing today,
today is day 68.
So unzip day, 67 source code into a directory that was yesterday,
source code, and that's where we're at today.
And so if you want to follow along with us, that's that's how you
follow along.
You can just, you'll be exactly at the same place I am right now.
Now.
All right, so first, let's take care of this note.
This type of note so that we make sure that it doesn't stay in there.
And cause problems later on what they said was that when we were
rearranging some things in in the move entity call, which is in our
Sim region, code in the move entity called we did a cut and paste
where we were supposed to be using test entity.
You can see it here, right?
We're supposed to be testing test entities, non-spatial, fly.
We're supposed to be doing this test, right?
Here on the same entity and we basically had a typo there.
Now, one thing that's interesting about that too is we haven't quite
worked out, exactly how these guys are going to work with the collides
versus non spatial.
That sort of thing.
We have a number of different types of flag tests that were probably
going to do.
It's worth noting that at some point we may you know to avoid cut and
paste arrows like this but also to sort of Loft these tests out into
some kind of more composite pragmatic call, that's like a more obvious
We might want to do is start making compound test, so we can say, if
this is the type of entity that should have blah done to it, then do
the thing.
And that would roll up these kinds of tests in a way that might make
it easier.
Now, we don't actually know if that's true yet because we haven't
quite worked this out yet.
So the fact that I'm testing the same sort of thing here and here
isn't necessarily a good indication that we should do that just yet,
but it's just something to be aware of as you're going through.
You know, you want to notice these sorts things go, okay.
I sort of seem like a dream, that maybe that's something that we could
take a look at in the future.
And simplify the code a little bit, reduce the possibility of Errors.
Make it easier to read and so on,
But that was the type of that they called to our attention.
So I'm glad we got that in there.
That keep you know that'll prevent it from having a little lurking
problem for us.
Okay.
So if I remember correctly We Believe put put it to do in here
somewhere.
There was for tomorrow.
Yeah.
So the thing that we were going to start out with was our, our
movement routine as it is, has a bit of a limitation to it that we
wanted to address, which is that right now when things move there is
Notion of how far they are allowed to move.
So basically the equations of motion, we compute them for anything it
basically tells us given an acceleration and velocity how far this
thing should have gone.
We move them there and we do Collision detection along the way to see
if there's anything that they would have run into.
That's all well and good, but excuse me, I'm not very sick.
Now I've sort of recovering but so
yeah, a little off from having been sent to the Pascal knows it
happens.
Anyway,
So, the thing that we don't have, though is the concept that things
only exists for a certain amount of distance.
So, that's the kind of thing that doesn't really happen in the real
world.
Obviously, like there really isn't such a thing as stuff that exists
over a distance in the objects that we see around us.
That's not the concept.
But in a game that is a very real concept.
Obviously anyone who has played any kind of a game where, you know,
the hero throws the sword or shoots the gun thing or does whatever.
And there's a limited range of
Travel on it and when it gets to the end of that range, it is
destroying our disappears or whatever it does.
So, obviously, there's this kind of concept in games, which doesn't
really super exist in the real world.
Maybe.
But it's this concept that that thing's only have this limited range,
and it's not as simple as in the real world, things like falling to
the ground or gravity of that sort of stuff.
It's not just that it lands and stays where you threw.
It, it literally like goes away or something.
Right.
And so what we want to do is even for things, look, we don't want
To say that things have to touch the ground.
Maybe we want them to just travel a straight path.
No gravity, no, nothing right there are magical or something.
We want them to be able to go.
And then when they've used up, as much distance, as we said, they
have, we want them to go away.
Now, what we were doing before, which is kind of a little bit of a
hack.
Was we were just saying, okay, every frame will let the move entity
call, take care of wherever the guys going to go.
We'll look at
We're look at where like the sword was and we'll look at where it is
now and will take that distance and will subtract it from however
much.
We said you were allowed to go.
However, far this this sword thing is allowed to go.
We'll, we'll subtract it.
And when that gets to zero, we will know that it's gone as far as it
can and will get rid of it.
Right?
That's what we'll do.
That's all fine.
But there's kind of a hidden in accuracy in that, right?
And that is that if the sword in that time, step doesn't exactly
travel the distance that would bring it to zero if it travels more
than that distance.
Then technically the sword has gotten this little extra this this
little bit of extra motion, right.
That it wouldn't have that it wasn't.
I supposed to have?
We're supposed to only Go part of the distance that it was allowed to
travel that time.
Step not the whole distance.
That's what we'd like to do is tighten up that accuracy.
That's the kind of thing that I guess it's kind of good for Speed
Runners to exploit.
If they know that they fire it at, just the right time or something.
It travels, this extra amount.
I mean, I don't know.
It's it's the kind of thing that happens in games all the time,
obviously, tons of games have shipped with exactly that kind of an
algorithm running them but I we can do better so we should do better.
So what I'd rather do is have the movement routines themselves.
Understand that there's a concept of a resource essentially and that
resource is distance and when it is moving something, it's not that
expensive for us to go into those movement, routines and say, okay,
look
Make sure that you look at what your resource budget is.
And when you're moving someone, don't move them too far.
If the resource budget would run out during that movement, you stop
them there, right?
And that'll make it.
So that no matter what the update situation is or no matter what the
frame rate, no matter what, whatever you do still do, a good job of
obeying those limits, which is what I would prefer to have happen,
rather than sort of this sort of hand-wavy solution of the other way.
So what I'd like to do is go ahead and introduce that concept.
So inside our move entity called right, we already have kind of set up
in a good way to have this work.
And the reason that I say that is because you'll notice that we
already have what we do at the outset is we take the equations of
motion, the physical equations of motion that govern how real things
move in the real world.
We compute where the players, I'm sorry, where the we still call it
player because we originally wrote it for the player but really it's
any entity now where the entity should be, right?
And then we go ahead and we enter this iteration where we're going to
go through and we're going to see if we can move.
Move them there and we test against things that they're going to
collide with, right?
That was how this work, this Loop worked and if they don't collide
with anything then we put them there.
If they do collide with something, we stop them there and we sort of
remove that whatever the sort of angle was the that the thing was that
they hit.
We allow them to keep traveling along that but we'd get rid of their
ability to move in that other direction.
Now, because we did that, that means we've already introduced into
this routine.
The
Woody from the code to handle the concept of not moving the whole way,
because that's what Collision is.
It's the thing that stops you from moving the whole way.
So the question is, can we just go ahead and add something else in
here?
That's another reason.
Another thing that essentially that will stop you from moving that
whole way.
And in this time that thing would be that movement budget that, you
know how much you would be allowed to move, right?
And so, what I want to do is take this team in, right?
That team in is the the T along the the motion Vector.
What I want to do is take that and say, okay, we've got this team in
the team in thing is how far the that it will actually be allowed to
move and we're going to go ahead and make that team in be set to
something that might be less than 1.
If it doesn't have enough budget to actually get to where it should
go, that would automatically handle this for us at some level, right?
And the hit end of
Our will still control whether Collision happens but regardless
because it's only does team in times player, Delta, when it does that
movement?
That's a pretty trivial way for us to go ahead and make sure that
you're not allowed to just keep using it, right?
So anyway, so this starts to inform one aspect of this that we had
different about.
When we originally wrote this code, it actually suggests that maybe we
want to write it in sort of the other way that what we did, right?
If you remember, when we originally writing this code, I said I'm not
sure.
Whether I want T to be talking about the motion along a vector, where
1.0 make will means moving all the way to the end of the vector, and
zero means the start or whether I want the vector to just be a unit
Vector, have unit length and have the T go from zero to the total
amount of meters covered so.
But he's actually a distance value because we could write it either
way and really all that determines about which way we did.
It is
Whether the player, Delta Vector gets normalized first or not and I'll
go to the Whiteboard, just to kind of give you a little bit of a
refresher on that for people who might be a little hazy about that
aspect of the code originally.
So let's go ahead and start a new place here for our day, 68.
So, here is day 68.
So, there's two ways that we could write the Collision routine and I
talked about them at that time, one way is that the motion Vector?
Right here is the beginning p.
And here's the new P, right?
Here's where we go.
I think we also typically recalling these p and p Prime, for example.
So here's where I am.
Here's where I'm going.
And this director here, this this is our, this Vector here was called
player Delta in our code, right?
That's what we were calling this.
This, this, this Vector right here, right?
This guy,
That's the player, Delta, right?
And that player Delta has a real length and so what we were doing is
we were saying T equals zero meant.
You were here and T equals one meant you were here.
So basically T times the
Delta just tells you how far along this you were but the other way
that we could have done it right.
Is we could have gone and said, all right instead of that Vector, that
goes the whole way.
We're going to normalize this Vector.
Now we don't know what you know, we don't know the time step is so
actually that may have made it longer we don't know, right?
Probably it would make it longer given our time scales here.
But point being we produce a vector that's simply a unit Vector,
right?
It has length one.
That goes in the direction of travel.
So it's pointing towards this this other this, this P Prime.
I'm right and then T equals zero still starts at the the starting
point.
But now we have t equals essentially the length of player Delta, right
whatever.
Whatever.
This vectors length was originally, that is now what T goes to and we
now have sort of this this like normal.
This player, dealt a normal if you will play or Delta normal right
here.
It's unit length that has length 1 and we're moving along that and the
The part of that obviously would be like, okay now T really is a
distance so we can just set the t equal to the movement budget at the
beginning, and that would make it so that we could never get past
their, as we go.
So it's something to keep in mind that we've made a decision between
those two.
And we ended up going with this one, but maybe that was the wrong
idea.
I don't know.
So what we're going to see now is, let's try to go ahead and put in
the movement budget concept to this function.
Using the way that we originally structured it and then we'll see if
it becomes too onerous and will make a judgment call about whether it
would be better to write it the other way.
So hopefully that makes some sense.
Okay, so here we go.
You come in here and what we want to do at the outset because we want
to make sure that our first team in obviously whatever, we're
emotionally setting our movement to that our initial team in would not
go further than our maximum allowed distance, right?
And so what we can do is we can imagine passing it in here.
I suppose we're Basics a maximum
Distance or we could say distance limit, maybe might be one way to say
it so the distance limit comes in here.
And what we want to do is you want to make sure that over the course
of iterations, we don't ever use any more than that.
So we could say is like okay distance left equals distance limit,
right?
Like so
And then each time to this, iteration will remove some from that
distance left.
Okay, I guess I can call it distance remaining to make it so that
we've not confused about left and right.
And you know, that's why I think distance remaining sounds a little
better.
So that's our distance limit.
Now what I could do here is I could basically say yeah, I think what I
want to do is I want to set this team in to be only allowing you to
move that far.
And the reason that I'd like to do that rather than dealing with it
after the fact is because I don't want to process any entity.
That would have happened after the movement budget, right?
Because if you imagine the case of the sword, if the sword was going
to move from one place to another during one frame, and the movement
budget wouldn't have allowed it to get to that final place.
But getting to that final place would cause it to collide with some
entity and caused an event to occur.
I want to make sure that event doesn't happen, right?
I don't want that event to trigger because technically the sword
should not have been able to reach it, right?
So that's that's the reason I want to set the team in because the team
in will cap how far the Collision Vector will even check because our
collisions
Vector, only considers it a hit if the Collision happens before the
team and that was sort of how we were sorting, are closer to the first
place to make sure that the first one happened first.
Right which ever had the minimum team in?
That's why it's called.
Teaming.
The minimum t.
All right, so we've got our player, Delta.
And if I wanted to compute how long that was going to be, right, what
I'd have is my player Delta length.
At this point, we have a function for computing, the length of a
vector, we can plaster pass it in you, right?
So if I go in here, and I take my handmade math.h, right, take a look
at my length.
You can see that I've got it.
Now, it forces some stuff.
It's got, its got a fair bit of maths.
It's two multiplied, it's an ad and then it's a square root right now
in the old days, a square root would have been an absolute nightmare
square.
Roots used to be really, really really, really really, really, really
expensive and you almost never ever ever.
I wanted to call square root if you could avoid it.
In fact, we used to write functions that would approximate the square
root, so that we didn't have to call the actual square root.
That's how bad it was.
But nowadays processors are actually pretty handy about this.
And you can actually get square roots in, not that much time.
So it's entirely possible that this is just fine, right?
And so we'll start with that, and when we actually go to start
Optimizer, closing doctor will see, but chances are even though that's
the sort of thing that would have sent off some alarm bells in my head
a long time ago.
Nowadays, it's like yep, square roots, until fixed it for you, right?
Anyway, there's still a little more.
It's a potentially because I don't know if you have to do refinement
steps on them, I don't know how much accuracy you get on some of the
newer processors versus the old ones and all that sort of thing.
But point being no matter what the circumstance is, no matter how
accurate you need the results, it's still way faster than it used to
be because it used to be pretty expensive anyway.
So we go ahead and get that length.
This is how far.
Now the player Delta thing is, so what I would like to do is say all
right, I want to go ahead and make sure that I cap that to
make sure that it's no longer than distance remaining.
So basically what I'd like to do is say what is the ratio?
In fact, I guess might be what I'd say.
What is the ratio or?
Or how much of this player Delta length, can we afford to use, right?
And so if I take the distance, remaining what I'm going to do is I'm
take the distance remaining.
I'm going to divide it by that player Delta length, right?
And what I can do here, I can also go ahead and make sure that that
player done.
Delta length, actually
Ali.
Is has some amount to it so that we would avoid / 0.
AB c--.
Right.
Well, you know, if do I even need to do the Divide of trying to think
here?
If I need to do this by, I guess I could say.
First is let's do that.
Let's do the simple.
Check if distance remaining right.
If player Delta length is is greater than distance remaining.
Then we have to deal with it, right?
But if it was not then we wouldn't meaning.
If the player Delta length
Isn't more than the amount that we have left, then we don't really
have to do anything, right?
There's nothing that nothing that has to happen.
So the only case that we really care about is what do we have to do to
team in if the player Delta length the amount that we're going to move
is too long, right?
And so I feel like all we really need to do at that point is set the
team in which again is how far along the player.
Delta we're going to go.
We just want to set that team in to be whatever the right ratio is
between these two things, right?
So if we know we have a player Delta and we
To move it only as much as distance remaining would be right, only as
much as it would cover.
The distance remaining I should be able to just take the ratio of
those two things I believe and and make that work out.
Now, let me just double check and I'll sort of draw that out for you
guys.
So sort of show you what it is that I'm trying to say here, there we
go.
So if you imagine, right, I've got this situation.
And here is my player Delta, right?
So this right here is the player Delta length.
Okay, so I'll just call that D for now.
We'll just call that straight up D.
And then what I'm also saying is I've got another thing which is like
a cap, right?
And so this is like the remaining.
This is that player, Delta remaining, so we'll just call that are
okay.
And so, what I want to do is I want to say, I don't want you to go any
further than here along that Vector, right?
So if I know that t, which moves me along this Vector.
If I know that this is 1 point 0 and this is 0, right?
Then really all I need to know is what percentage, right.
That's a percentage 0 to 1 what percentage of the way along here.
Could I actually, you know, could actually go what percentage is our
right?
So I want to know how what percentage, how much of the way our is in D
in, if the total area is D, how much of it is taken up by our and that
should give me the T value that I actually, you know, my team in what
I could actually go to
If the furthest I could go right?
And so that's that's the ratio that I'm Computing there to use the set
that team in.
So the only thing that really has to be true here is that player Delta
length has to be nonzero in order for this to work, right?
And so in order for that to be the case, we have to make sure that
we're never trying to actually do a move when the distance remaining,
I'm sorry when the distance when the player Delta length is going to
be 0.
But if the player like was Zero, we don't need to move the player,
right?
Woohoo, or whatever entity were using, we don't actually need to move
it at all.
If the movements going to be 0, that means it wouldn't go anywhere.
So, technically, what we can do here is actually just make this entire
Loop have to be greater than 0, right?
And we just wouldn't have to actually do anything in the case where it
was 0.
We just, we just wouldn't even do anything at all because it's not
possible for it to, to have any effect on anything.
Right.
It's immediately done in that case.
In fact, what we could do,
Is well, I guess we can't really put it up there because we haven't
completed yet but basically, this is almost a loop condition.
If the player, if the amount that we're going to try to move the
player by isn't greater than 0, then we are not going to move him.
So just stop don't do any more computation.
Don't waste any more time thinking about it's not worth it, right?
So that will, that will totally solve our problem for the first
iteration through the loop.
The problem is this distance.
Remaining actually now needs to get updated by however, far.
We actually did go, right?
So at the end of this, when we're about to move the player, what we
Do here is say well, that distance remaining is going to go down by
some amount right now.
It would go down by the player, Delta length, if we actually took the
whole step, but since we don't know, we might have hit something at
the question is, how far do we actually go?
Well, in this case team in is to the rescue again, right?
Team.
In Saves the Day team in tells us how far along we went.
Which again if we take that as a percentage and we just want to know
how far we traveled, we just go ahead and say well whatever the
percentage was here, if we just multiply it by the total length of
Of that Vector, it'll tell us how far along the vector, we went in
actual M, right?
So all we have to do is say Okay, multiply that length, like so and
off we go right now.
What we might want to do as well as we might want to say, we might
want to make this a more to avoid any kind of floating Point
nastiness.
We might want to make this also an Epsilon, right?
We might want to say that in general, you're not allowed to move
people .00, 01 meters or something like this.
I don't know exactly how we want to deal with stuff like that.
But it's definitely something that when we go through the Collision
detector, could detector is a geometric computation kind of thing.
Often times.
Those involve a lot of floating-point nastiness and since we haven't
thought through a lot of these things and we have a bunch of flooding
pointy things, we need to think about.
I'm not going to really push on that right now.
When we actually go do our final version of clutch injector, will try
to tighten up all of our float honest and try to get rid of as many as
we can.
So for now, I'm just going to say to do, what do we want to do for
epsilon's here?
Think this through for the final Collision code, right?
And so hopefully that's all we really need to do for that.
Now, in order to finish our sword stuff here, right?
What we would like to do is we now like to sort of Loft up this kind
of concept.
Of having a certain amount of movement that you could do.
I'm going to go ahead and put that into basically just put that into
my entity logic if that makes sense.
Oops, that's not the place.
I actually wanted.
So we want to do is we want to say that entity is can have this kind
of cap on them, right?
And what that cap is going to be, I don't know if I want to be a flag
or not.
I'm not sure exactly how I want to do it.
There's there's a couple things I kind of have in my head that we
haven't gotten to yet about how I want to do any of the architectures.
As we're kind of putting that off.
I don't think this really needs to be a flag.
So I think I'm going to do something that doesn't use a flag for now,
even though it might be a little bit gross.
Because I think when we come back around to it and I sort of have,
like I said, I have includes of how I want this stuff structured
eventually.
When we start talking about that for real, I think this will cost
shake out.
But anyway, so we'll have this like basically a distance limit will
just be on there and so any entity can take advantage of the distance
limit.
And the way that will do that for now is, Will basically say that if
the distance limit is just set to zero or maybe some other value like
no distance.
No, but I think mr.
Zero, if it's set to zero then that means you can move as far as you
want, but if it's set to an actual value, then you get capped and it
triggers if you actually get down to 60,
right?
So the way that we'll do that is inside the sword ramp, what we'll do
is we'll say, Okay, instead of entity, we already have distance
remaining.
So, here we go.
What will do inside?
The sword is, will say, all right, we don't have to deal with this
manual anymore, but we do have to deal with whatever that exit
condition is.
What we want to say is that if the distance limit for the sword
becomes equal to 0, then we want to make it non spatial and take it
out of the computation, right?
It's gone.
So all
You to do now is that this is remaining when we set it, we need to set
it so that it's on the distance limit field, right?
And now we just have to actually process that field.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to say, okay we've got a distance
limit, it's going to be equal to the entities distance limit.
And we'll pass that limit along, but in the case, for the distance
limit actually equals 0, we're just going to assume that that's makes
people allowed to move.
However, far they want.
It's like essentially saying there's no distance limit.
So we'll just basically put on some kind of ridiculous maximum value
here, like something that you could never, possibly, ever do right?
Yeah.
No one's ever allowed to move.
10,000 meters, that's off.
She was obviously, completely ridiculous.
So, we don't have to care about that.
I'll put a little to do here.
Say, do we want to
As this number, but basically just thing that says, essentially No
Limit, right?
So we'll do that and then we'll go ahead and see, I don't actually
know if we actually put code in here to test this.
I think we probably did, but we can actually go and see what the deal
is.
Oh, and we've got one more thing.
We got to do, I forgot.
We have to actually decrement the distance limit.
Now, I suppose also, I don't really need to handle that outside
inside.
Move entity, if it's actually gonna be something that's on the end,
T.
We could probably just handle it directly in there.
So actually, I suppose, we can just go ahead and do this.
This can actually
Move outside of that into here to be honest right?
We can actually just put that in there so that's probably actually
fine for now to.
Yeah that seems better actually not think about it.
Alright.
So basically what we'll do here is we'll say okay
We'll grab that distance remaining like so well, then go ahead and see
what the distance limit actually is on the guy.
Oops, there we go.
And we'll set it and then this will kind of get subtracted off.
I guess what we can do.
Yeah.
And at the end what we can do is we can just go ahead and write it
back at the end will basically say if the entities distance limit was
not equal to 0.
In the first place, we will just write back, whatever the distance
remaining actually was.
And so now that's their new distance limit.
And so that way it will decrement, as we move every time the entity
moves, it will have its distance limit decremented, right?
As long as it wasn't set to zero, if it was set to zero, that's kind
of the case that says.
Alright, just let them move, however they want.
Don't deal with it.
All right, so let's see how that goes if that does any better for us?
That looks pretty good.
No, big problems.
And so now we've got we're doing exactly the same thing we were doing
before where you can basically spin-off an entity, Let It Go in some
direction and make sure that as it gets to the end it's going to end
when it's moved a certain amount so that's good that basically tidies
up that for us nicely and it makes it.
So it's handled in a nice clean way, that doesn't vary based on the
frame rate, which is kind of nice.
I think that's a good way to good thing to shoot for.
You don't want to have a lot of your stuff in your game, be frame rate
dependent, invites a lot of problems when you're trying to ship on
different platforms and it just means that you have a
Lot less flexibility, it means you can't toggle between 60 or 30
Hertz, depending on the platform, you just get all kinds of nastiness,
right?
So, all right, that's about all there was to that, it looks like based
on the clock 835, we've still got a half an hour, so now might be a
good time to start talking about that Collision detection, which is
kind of what brought up this stuff before.
We were sort of going to go to start.
Take a look at that.
So, if we take, you know, just just sort of a cursory check our we've
already done.
Like I said, we've done some of the work.
Sorry.
Got it HEI here.
Yeah.
Sometimes you get an itchy eye.
Sometimes staring at monitors all day in the heat in the in the
winter.
Dry heat.
The eyes get a little itchy.
It's true.
Oh, all right.
So what we want to do now is say okay we've already got our Collision
routine set up we do we plan for this basically like we knew what was
coming down
So when we hit something, we know we kept it.
We've got a hit entity called, right?
I'm sorry, we've got to hit enter the variable set.
So now we know that that the entity that we were on, right?
This entity that we passed in here, this amenity
We know that that entity and this entity hit each other, right?
They've collided, and so what we want to do now is introduce the
concept of some Collision response.
Now, Collision response is kind of a nasty problem for a number of
reasons.
One of, which is not one that we're really concerned about right now
and that is what you want to happen physically with things.
Like when things push each other, like when this thing hits this
thing, it's supposed to push or, you know, do stuff like that.
That's obviously
A physics problem something that we probably will want to get to once.
We actually have some notion of what sorts of things in the game will
do that, right?
When we get to the parts, may be a little further along.
We're going to be pushing things.
That's something that we want to think about and and deal with.
But there's a separate problem which is sort of game logic, right?
It's like this has nothing to do with physics.
It's just when these two things at each other, I have some game like
this supposed to happen.
Like, for example, when a sword hit somebody, it's supposed to do some
damage or something, right?
and so, the problem with
with handling, these sorts of things, the reason that they become
complicated for people, when they work on them is because it's a
problem called double dispatch, right?
This is what it's called typically.
In programming terms, it's a double dispatch problem because
essentially what you have is an operation, that depends on two
independent parameters, right?
You can almost think of it as a matrix like setup, right.
If you've ever used Microsoft Excel you kind of know what I'm talking
about here.
Where you basically, you have almost like a spreadsheet, right where
you have every type of object coming down this way.
And you also have every type of object going this way, right?
So, I don't know what they are.
They're like hero Monster Sword wall.
Almond milk.
Right hero Monster, Sword wall almond milk.
Blah, blah blah, right.
And what you want to do is you want to say, okay, when two things hit
each other.
I want to write my game logic.
That's like, what happens, you know, when a sword hits another sword,
like two swords Collide.
Well, that's this logic, right?
And what happens when a sword hits a monstar right?
Well, this logic happens.
Okay.
Well, is that the same thing happened?
When a monstar hits a sword, right?
Which would be here?
Presumably they're symmetric, I don't know, they wouldn't have to be,
you could sort of make system rules where it's like there's a
precedence to who got out of value.
It, I don't know.
But basically what you can
Can imagine is most of the time, they're going to be symmetric
meaning, you don't really have all of these.
You only have like an upper diagonal or a lower diagonal system in
math terms, right?
Meaning that basically all of the things that happen if you took the
stair, step of the diagonal, right?
All of the things that happen in these cells are actually the same as
What happened reflected along this diagonal, right?
So when Akira and a monstar Collide, we probably wouldn't do something
different than when a monster and a hero.
Collide meaning in this routine, we probably don't care, which one was
passed in and which one was hit right?
Like, who is doing the movement?
We probably don't super care.
Most of the time.
Now that may not necessarily be true, but it's probably true because
Even in circumstances where you do sort of care about who was
initiating the Collision meaning, I'd like just to give a more
concrete example, suppose we have something where there's like a block
that's going around on a path, right?
So we've got this sort of block and it's moving and, you know, over
time it just kind of moves around and we've got the hero and the hero
is here and, you know, he's can run into the block
And maybe we want some logic that says something like, okay, we want
the hero to have to actually run into the block if the hero was just
standing here and the block collided with him, it would just push him.
But it's only if he pushes into the block that something happens like
the block lights up or trigger something, right?
So even in those circumstances, we probably wouldn't implement it by
making this Matrix anti-semitic.
I'm sorry.
Asymmetric?
Right, we probably wouldn't do that.
Or asymmetrical I should say.
Symmetrical asymmetrical.
So a symmetric.
So interestingly enough symmetric was not ever a word.
It was, it was symmetrical.
That was the word and symmetric is some kind of newfangled word that
people introduced recently.
So I'll try to use the old-school.
Let's learn the old school math, word and say symmetrical course.
Asymmetrical didn't exist for a long time, too.
That's a symmetric asymmetric.
And asymmetrical are actually pretty new words as well.
But anyway, point being
We probably wouldn't implement this with an asymmetric dispatch kind
of a scheme.
What would probably do is when this Collision occurred.
We just look at what the velocity of the player was and ask ourselves
whether they were true or acceleration or something whether they were
trying to accelerate into the block or not, right?
Or whether they had a velocity, that was moving them into the block at
the time or not.
Right.
That's probably how we would make those kind of determinations.
Not who happened to be which variable in
A collision detection call because that just doesn't seem like the
sanest way to do it since that's really just an artifact of how we
choose to process our collisions, we may want to process them
simultaneously.
We may want to do all sorts of things and how we actually compute
Collision.
So it's probably not a good idea to bake how our logic Works into that
system, right?
So typically, if you
About what we're doing here.
We're typically only specifying sort of this upper triangular part of
things and we're just going to assume that when we do things we if we
were going to press the Collision that looked like this, we just
instead do it handle it.
Like we would if it was the other way around, right?
Which is a pretty trivial thing for us to do.
so,
Even with that constraint even only filling in half of this Matrix.
We would ask the question, right?
And you should ask the question, how many dispatch routines?
Do you have right?
How many dispatch routines must you, right?
You right, right?
And you should be able to figure out like this is this is some pretty
basic math, right?
How many entity types are there if you wanted to fill in the whole
Matrix, right?
How many entities, how many dispatcher teens would you need?
Well, you would need the number of entity types, right?
Squared?
Right?
Because what's the area of, you know, a square?
It's, you know, the the side times the side, right?
So T times T would tell us how many discs t squared is, how many
dispatch routines we would need, right?
And in this case, we only need to supply half of them because we don't
actually need
Need these ones down here.
So we actually get to remove a fair bit of them, right?
So we only need half of them but not exactly half of them because half
would cut it right down the diagonal, right, but we're not really
cutting these squares in half.
We actually have to fill out the entire square of the diagonal, right?
So we actually need a little more than half of them, right?
But I don't super care too much about that.
We could even say, let's just say it was even tease.
Squared over 2.
We don't really care too much.
The point is the t squared, right?
That's the part that should scare anyone looking at this.
Because if we were to graph that function and we've talked about this
before, this kind of gets back to the concept of order notation,
right?
I don't know if Google can graph these things, I think so much saying
that it could.
Yeah.
So basically, if you look at what happens when you graph something
like this, right?
And let's zoom out just a little bit here so you can kind of see.
So what you can see when you have a squared function is that it
doesn't take very many entities to start getting up into absolutely
intractable numbers.
If we only had 20 entity types, we would already be at 400 dispatcher
teens that even dividing that by two knocks it down to 200.
Who cares?
That's way too many dispatches for only 20 types of entities, right?
Right.
And so typically what I like to point out and and this is sort of
something that gets at the heart of how we're going to be handling
game logic as we go or at least my approach to it, how I tend to look
at it, is these sorts of things are relatively untenable, right?
And so the
Double dispatch problem is a very real problem.
It's very problematic.
It's a t-square.
It sort of a thing.
It's a know.
Typically also of people will write that like this.
Oh, N squared, right?
We haven't really talked about order annotation much.
But basically, when people use this kind of terminology what they're
talking about is, how does the problem that you're dealing with scale
up as you increase the number of elements?
So you can think of n as basically, how many things are involved.
And oh, something with an n in it.
Is telling you what the curve looks like, right?
What that curve looks like as it scales as n increases.
So basically, our order notation for that curve, looks awful.
It looks like this and somewhere around here, it becomes a tractable
so it's not the kind of thing that we want.
And so one thing that you might ask is like, whoa, how did games deal
with this problem?
And the answer is they deal with it in two different ways and we're
going to be taking sort of out of, we're definitely going to be sort
of focusing on the way that I think is a better.
Way basically, some attack it head-on and they say we're just going to
go ahead and do double dispatch and we'll write code for all these
things.
And what that basically means is, you just don't have very many entity
types right.
Either either the entity types and any types are few.
Or the responses are few, right?
Because you can imagine one way we can do this.
Really simply is saying, oh, well when monsters hit monsters, nothing
happens, right?
So lots of our stuff just doesn't have anything in it.
A lot of these are just null and we don't have to do work to handle
null things.
So what we do instead is we say we don't when things most things don't
interact with each other.
So it's not a problem or we say there, just aren't that many things,
so even if they all do interact with each other Weldon, number is 5.
So we wrote 25 dispatch calls, right?
Divided by 2 and write, whatever, right?
So it's not very many dispatch calls.
So that's one way to deal with it, right?
And, you know, you can think about this sort of thing, especially this
one right here.
This is kind of the AAA methodology, right?
The idea is we actually hand author and most of the stuff that
happens, right?
It's like there's a lot of cutscenes and a lot of custom things.
And like, oh, you went and the helicopter exploded on the roof and
blah, blah, blah, right?
And so the response is, there's not very many responses and they're
just hand authored and we just hire a lot of artists to get that.
Ponce number up to enough things and enough game, scripters to just do
that, and it's fine, right?
But on the whole there's just not that much flexibility if you're
playing Call of Duty.
There's just not that many interesting emergent things that can happen
in that world because there just aren't that many.
You can't script all of those different things.
You can't create for a single Call of Duty level, that you might play
three where Kevin Spacey's coming and talking to you.
Well, everything that Kevin Spacey was going to say had to be recorded
by Kevin Spacey, right?
And so,
there just isn't that much that can go on there and so if you're in
that sort of triple, if your, if your game has a lot of triple anus to
it,
If your game is kind of a in a tripling, its kind of a situation,
right?
Then, the double dispatch problem really, isn't that much of a
problem?
Because you know, that you're just going to have that sort of a hand,
authored sort of script, Ed, kind of a thing happening.
It's fine, right?
Think also Adventure game, right?
Look at you, there may be 20 objects in this adventure game right now
and 30 things on which you could use those objects.
But you know what, only one of them Works to solve the puzzle so we
didn't even bother anything for them.
Some, it just says, I don't think that will work here, right?
And so double dispatch problem solved, right?
Because there's only one thing that actually will make the game.
Go forwards and everything else just wasn't handled, right?
So, we'll call this triple anus or will call this adventure style,
right?
Okay, so I don't think those are very interesting because the least
lately, these days, the kinds of games that I am often the most
interested in are ones that have a lot more richness into the way that
they allow things to interact.
And so, what I'd rather do is focus on ways in which you can get this
Matrix filled without actually writing all of the different things,
right?
So, rather than focusing on a double dispatch problem, where we
essentially have a type,
The interact with each other.
What I'm thinking is more along the lines of you know fundamental
qualities, right?
So, rather than thinking of an entity as a monster or a sword or
whatever, what I'd rather do is just think of them as having
fundamental qualities and we write interactions for fundamental
qualities.
So that the fundamental quality, what we're essentially doing is
projecting down a level, right?
Basically, like our entity types, because we know that, if we wanted
lots of very sort of variety in here, we just have it.
Just be an intractable problem.
Could we just boil it down to some set of fundamental qualities?
And then our entities are just compositions of those
Not a qualities, right?
So let's say we could do you know eight fundamental qualities right?
Which is fundamentally somewhere along the lines of, you know, like 40
different interactions between those fundamental qualities.
And those sorts of things or who knows how we want to write that
exactly, you know, that's a manageable number but then our entities
are described in terms of these things, right?
And those fundamental qualities can be sort of component based in ways
that allows us to avoid the double avoid the double dispatch problem.
So instead of thinking of a monstar
Right?
And a hero as two different things, they're just the same thing in our
system and they just have different fundamental qualities or
properties, right?
Like this is, you know, often times called a property system, right?
And so things will be more defined by the properties that they have,
right, rather than by a single type.
And what that lets us do, is it lets us fight and N squared problem
with an N squared solution, right?
If we want to have
Have a lot of entities.
Types.
But we know we can't possibly write the code that is how all of them
interact.
But we do want to have all them interact.
What we can do is say, Okay, instead of making that many entities,
what we'll do is make smaller pieces, just little fractions of an
entity that you compose together right to build up what the end of the
actually is and there may be a very small number of those but because
there are eight of them, right?
And entity is built out of some number of them.
Let's say, five average, or
Something that gives us right, a 1/8, right to the fifth power version
of of a composition, right?
Because if the first property for any can be any one of eight things
in the second property can be any one of eight things in the third,
probably Community.
One of eight things, right?
And I guess it's technically probably eight, seven six.
So it's probably more of a an 8 factorial kind of a situation, right?
8 factorial is a massive number, which allows us to put a small and in
here and get a large number of potential entity types out.
And so what we're doing here is we're fighting an N squared game
design problem with an N squared game, design solution and that tends
to be the more fruitful place to go.
I think, right?
And that allows us to talk about things like, you know, let's say we
have magical Essence, right?
As one of our things or whatever.
We just write the rules for Magical Essence and how it interacts.
And now, anything just has a certain amount of magical Essence to it.
And that allows us to make very, very many different, every kind of
monster that we possibly
We have in the game, we can now have many different types of them.
There's the kinds that are that, you know, Monster a can show up as
Monster a not magical monster a, a little bit magical monster, a
medium, magical monster a very magical, right?
Just by setting the number of their magical Essence, right?
And so, that's really kind of the interesting part that I think that I
want to go for is what are the interesting components that we can
create.
Such that putting different combinations together yields interesting
types of monsters and
x and then we're out of the business of this.
So we still do have the double dispatch problem, but we have it on a
much smaller scale and that allows us to basically get up two more
sets of possible interactions that the player will witness without
actually having to drive yourself nuts, right?
And so that's kind of what I'm aiming towards.
So for now we will sort of say because we haven't gotten into that
element of any design yet.
When we process, these will do it in the sort of old-school, double
dispatch way where we'll just kind of handle, a few of the things.
We'll do the triple Enos version, right, where we handle?
Only a few of the things but the eye towards how that we're going to
solve this for real, in the future is when we have sort of when we
actually go and do how we want our enemies to be composed and built.
What we'll do is at that point say, okay now what we're actually doing
their pasta Collision is processing the Collision of those properties
not
The Entity.
And so that's where I would like to get to eventually.
But you know, baby steps one thing at a time.
So when we come in here, what we want to do is we want to sort of
handle that.
So I'm just going to make.
I'm just going to pull it out of here for now.
So you can kind of see it a little more clearly and know that we're
going to replace it with something different in the future, right?
I'm kind of putting this in as a thing it's like, hey, we know we're
going to replace it, so I'm just making, I'm going to pull into
separate function because I know I want to write another version that
function eventually and be able to do that changeover.
So, yeah, this is not I'm not making fun process.
I guess I'm not making a function because anyone else is ever going to
call this function.
This is purely me saying, I want to be able to write a second version
of this function and swap it out eventually.
So I kind of want that flexibility there.
All right, so when we have this, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
say all right I'm going to say handle collision and I'm going to pass
that handle Collision two entities.
I'm going to sort the entities by their type so basically I'm going to
say we've got a Sim entity a in a similarity be and I'm going to start
out by assuming that the entity that we got called with is entity a
and assume that the entity that we hit is entity be.
But then what I'm going to do is I'm going to say if entity a
If it's type is greater than and two BB's type, right?
Then I'm going to swap the two, right?
And I don't know that we ever wrote any swap code.
I don't think that we did.
I could be wrong about that, but I'm pretty sure that I didn't
specifically because yeah, we did not ever write.
Once that's fine, it doesn't matter.
We'll just do temp equals a equals B Because temp, something like
this.
Right?
So spot those two guys and basically what I want to do is I just want
to make sure
Right.
That whichever one has the lower entity type value comes first that
way that is how I am solving temporarily right this triangle.
Where did I go with that?
Where is it?
There it is.
That is how I'm preventing us from ever being down here in the lower
part of the triangle, right?
I basically, I'm just saying, let's always talk about the lower Value
First.
So if we got past, if we got past S, as the first parameter, and H is
the second parameter, right?
I'm sorry if we got past.
Betty, how you think of this?
I don't even know which one of these I'm thinking is my row and which
one is my calm.
But point being if we got past this Square by swapping them and
knowing that I always have the lower one in the first entity in the
higher when the second one, I'll be able to do my right, my
operations, as if this always got past, you know, as as its flip
around right as this guy, right?
So we're just we're just doing that flip.
So that everything always gets mirrored up into that upper diagonal if
you will.
So when we handle a collision, we
Handle question between A and B.
Like
And so that like like I said, there's a number of things that we could
do here.
We'll do a really simple one for now.
I'm just going to go ahead and say all right, internal void, here's my
handle Collision.
I've got some entity a, I've got some in a teepee.
And what I want to do is I'm just going to start saying some stuff
just totally randomly typing in here.
Let's say if type A equals something and type B equals, something that
we're going to do a response, right?
The simplest possible thing you could think to do here.
So let's see if the which is the one we wanted, if the entity type
sword, right?
That whereas my type let's see there and maybe oh and you know what I
could do I can make this even better.
Let's do in line full 32 if types match, right?
And that will basically say will pass the am to be
And we'll type pass the types that we want them to be.
So let's go ahead and look at our Sim region type here.
So these were entity type A type, A type, any type B type, right.
And so, what I want to do here is say okay, we'll see whether
What?
I don't want to do is I don't want this code tap to know which one of
these is the lower one, right?
So what I wanted to do was say, okay, it's going to pass these two in,
and this guy will swap them around again, potentially for him.
I'm trying to think of exactly how that would work.
In fact, I guess, I guess this handle Collision called doesn't even
have to do it.
Yeah, so the problem I try to avoid is making you have to presort all
these.
We could just do that and maybe I'll just do that for now.
And we'll talk about tomorrow.
But basically what I'm worried about here is, if we change the order
of these identifiers, then these matches won't work properly, right?
The sword always has to be on be because it comes later than for
example, the monstar, right?
So, what I would want to do is potentially write this in a way that
makes sure that you can always test them and not have to care, but I
won't deal with that for now.
Because we only have five minutes left or so.
Because we started about five minutes late, we only have about five
minutes, so I won't get into that.
Now, that's what I was thinking.
That's what was going on in my head right there.
So if we have a monstar sword Collision, then maybe what we want to do
is make the monstars hit points, go down, right?
Or something like that.
I don't really remember because we've a long time since we did that,
what the hit point situation was but I guess what we do is we scan
through for the last hit point and we would remove some of it, right?
So we take that filled amount.
Out and we would sort of make that go down.
So
But for now, the other thing I could do is just attracting the hit
point Max.
Since again, we're mostly out of time so we could do that.
But eventually we want to do is actually process the hit points.
You know, do something kind of useful there.
So, what we want to do is just say, okay, if the Sword and the monster
hit, then we'll go ahead and do that.
And maybe we also just for now, we'll just get rid of the sword as
well, right?
So we'll make make entity non-spatial will just say the sword just
goes away, right?
It becomes, it goes back to the hilt or wherever swords go, and so
that should do it for hitting.
The monster of the store.
Now unfortunately, I believe this will do nothing when we actually run
it.
At least that's my assumption even though it clearly hits the monstar.
And the reason for that is we have said that the sword does not
collide with things, right?
And that's what we wanted.
We don't want it to stop when it hits things but what we want to do is
still process collisions.
So this was the other thing that we want to do was introduce some kind
of flag that controls.
Whether you when you run into things you stop
Whether you Collide at all.
So, instead of making Clyde's, only mean, essentially that you detect
collisions or sorry, that you were 10 detect and respond to them.
What I want to do is make it so there's a way that say that you
respond to collisions but you don't actually have your movement
impeded by them.
Right?
And so trying to think about how that would work basically if the
person who is being moved at this time, right?
What I want to do is say
Let's let's just say, we don't check that flag, right?
We don't check the Collide slag here.
Okay, everybody always does collides in that way, let's say and we'll
do that processing.
The only difference is when we come through here, we won't actually
set that team in lower.
In the case, where the Collide flag is not set, right?
So basically what we're going to say is that the movement always
actually totally works.
In the case, where the Collide flag isn't set.
So we basically have a thing which is when the entity sort of stops on
collision or something, like this is going to be that flag, right?
If that's that.
So we'll compute this at the outset will just say stops and collision.
That's what set you got.
Some texture in here.
What's my syntax?
Are they okay?
Closing parentheses so we'll say if it stops on collision will find
that out.
And then what we'll do is we'll say when we do our little team in
process,
Here that will be used to figure out who actually is the first one
hit.
But when we actually go through and do our Collision processing, we
will not actually.
So we'll move it to the right location will do the the hint Collision,
but then we'll continue it.
Allowing it to basically go forwards, right?
So, what we'll do here is we'll say, let's see player DP.
So we don't want to actually process any of these things at all right?
We don't want to change.
Of this player Delta stuff to start pushing myself to you.
Well I guess we do want to update it, we just don't want to change its
direction seems about right to me.
So we want to do, we don't want to change its velocity like so right
because this is the velocity change and we don't want to clip its
movement.
So it looks like player, Delta is not being used in here, so I think I
can just do this if stop
It's on collision, we do that.
Otherwise we keep going like, so.
And then we also will have to do a little bit to do.
In this particular case, when things are supposed to keep going
through need a, our Collision table here, right?
Our thing that says, whether you've already collided with someone
because we talked about doing that, but we haven't done it yet.
So, let's just see if that works at all.
So now,
Well we do have one problem, our Collision thing worked.
Okay.
But we have a problem with this guy actually collides.
With when it actually collides it gets stopped because it keeps
hitting the thing that's colliding and we need to we're going to need
the thing that says, don't keep colliding with someone you already
collided with.
So we need our Collision of table thing.
That will be the thing that will deal with tomorrow, so that you can
Sail on through those things.
But, all right, I think we're basically right on time 905 now would be
a good time to start the Q&A.
If you could, please prefix your questions,
With Q: so I can see them.
And if you could keep it to stuff that we've coded on today's stream
or on previous dreams, if you want to ask off-topic questions or stuff
about code, we're going to write in the future.
Please come before the stream.
Do that in the pre stream?
Call about 15 minutes before one of our scheduled start times and ask
the questions there tomorrow morning.
It's early one tomorrow and Friday.
So come tomorrow morning and ask those questions and we will talk
about them but let me see if I can launch the Q&A here.
Yes, I'm so glad that the handmade he robot listens to me.
Now I don't know how I gained this privilege, but thank you, too.
For whoever
Made the handmade hear about respond to me.
It's pretty cool.
Alright.
Okay, so let's see.
Questions questions, does anybody have any questions?
Or did everyone just understand everything and we are good to go.
It could be true.
How long in your opinion, does it take to become fluent on emacs?
I have no idea.
I started programming in emacs in 1991, so I don't remember when after
that, I was pretty comfortable that I don't think it took me that
long, but I don't know.
Could an entity have multiple fundamental Quality Property things?
Yes, my idea is that basically, that entities will be composed of, as
many fundamental properties, as we choose to implement.
So, like, you know, I don't know how many fundamental properties will
end up with, but entities will be able to have as many of them kind of
on them as you want them to have.
Handmade hear about will listen to you.
If it feels like, it seems to be agreeable today.
Oh, so it's at a temperamental.
Bot the bot on it seem to be working for me, work twice in a row.
I feel like I did it yesterday to maybe, Anna can't quite remember.
Do is pee For the Love of Pete.
Are you sure?
It's me though?
A lot of times it's not me but I don't know, like a lot of time.
So for example groups we don't, I don't want that a lot of times, my
internet's just fine.
Like if I go like I actually have full bandwidth.
It's just I can't get to Twitch, you know?
So I don't actually know that it's ever that that it's actually the
ISP.
I don't actually know how to let me put it this way if anyone knows
how to even determine.
If it's my ISP, that would be a very handy thing to know.
Because I don't know how to figure that out because like I don't seem
to be having trouble communicating with other sites and when I go to
try and test it, right?
I don't find that.
I'm getting a lot of indication that it's my ISP like, my ISP seems to
get out just fine and relay traffic just fine from simple.
Thing.
So I feel like a lot of this is just twitch and there's not a lot I
can do about it, but I don't know.
So if somebody knows how to determine that definitively I'd love.
I'd love some.
Some help with that because I don't know.
I don't know how to figure that out.
When are you planning to add depth sorting?
I don't know.
I I've been feeling kind of like we might want to start the renderer
sometime relatively soon, but I think we might do animation first.
So probably will do animation, and then we'll start the renderer and
just do the depth sorting when we do the renderer
Will there be enough?
Entities that some optimization will have to happen?
How many do you expect to have on a screen?
Hundreds, I don't know if they'll be hundreds only because screams
just ain't that big.
You know, looking at it, our hero is a little too big right now, so
he'll be scaled down but the trees you know, the trees would be
roughly that size.
I don't know how many
You know 100 entities would probably be typical but hundreds of
entities maybe not now our Sim region will have hundreds because
there's 100 on a screen and we're like doing nine screens or so then
there'd be nine hundred enemies or something like that so they'll be a
lot but whether we'll have to optimize very aggressively.
I don't know.
You have to remember a lot of the entities are things like trees that
are just sitting there most of the time.
And so if they're not actually being actively used for something or on
fire, or who knows what will allow to
Have happen to trees but you know, it's they don't cost very much to
simulate if they're just sitting there.
So I don't know how much optimization will have to do it.
Really depends on what we see at the time, after we've actually got
real things in there and the gameplay is roughly what we want and
we're like yes, this is good.
What's our performance?
Like who knows?
And it might just be fine, it might be bad, I don't know.
Obviously, we will want to optimize to run large worlds, because
that's something that we did a lot of time up front, to make sure
we'll be good to go on.
So, I suspect maybe that is where the opposition will actually come in
is when we want to start scaling up to like super huge worlds.
Just for fun.
That might be more of the place for that.
I'm not sure I quite follow your argument for double dispatch table
versus fundamental qualities.
Seems to me like you still need to figure out what to do for each
quality.
What to do in the presence of others, still leads to a quadratic
growth.
I must have missed something.
No, so that is correct, right?
The idea is that you can't avoid quadratic growth if you want to have
Rich interactions.
So the question is, what is a type
To the player.
Right.
So, what does the player think of as a type if our type in the code,
right?
Equals the players type in their brain.
That is where we have an unknown.
Sort of what I would consider, an intractable dispatch problem and
attacked.
In fact about this batch, because if we want the player to think that
there are a hundred different monster types then and, and 50 different
swords, right?
50 swords and 100 monsters, right?
Then now we have five thousand different ways that swords can hit
monsters, and we're in bad shape, right?
That is no good.
So, what we want to do, and what games, I think that do these sorts of
things effectively do is they think of things in terms of their
properties, rather than by what they actually work, right?
So, instead of thinking of things as this is, a particular type in the
system
You want to think of it as, okay?
It's actually a composite of several different types of pieces of
information, such as the fact that it does damage physical damage,
magic damage, you'll think Dungeons & Dragons, right?
You've got properties, like, fundamental properties that you broken
down.
And yes, you have to do a dispatch problem, but it's on like ten
stats.
So you have a hundred things you have to write rather than it's on the
individual types of that are there, right?
And so, that's what I'm basically saying is you want to make sure that
this is not true.
You don't want your system types to equal your, your player facing
types.
And so, it's a very simple concept, it's not new.
It's like I said, games do this all the time but we've never talked
about it.
So, so this is the tact that I will be taking is where our types are.
Fundamental things that maybe aren't even necessarily exposed to the
player.
They're our internal model of how things interact.
And then with a
Cease is sort of player facing types which are more fictional and more
meaningful to them, but that are actually not about the simulation
directly.
Write that makes sense.
And so that basically allows you to have a lower number because you
get, if you're your types, composed to build the player types, right?
Then you can have, you know, 100,000 player types.
How would we do that?
You'd be like, well, I just have to have enough of my types.
So that we could build that many player types by composing them and so
eight.
Like I said, I picked that number.
Like, let's say we have eight of our types of things in the system
that can compose new players.
Well, if I wanted to build a player type out of this, you know,
something the player sees.
Well, if I have eight of things to choose from and I want to compose
one, let's say I pick from the eight for the first property to sing
has.
And then I, you know, I set it to have some value.
I got times 7 times 6 times 5.
Let's say so we've got four properties there.
That alone without even considering what the values of those things
are.
Just the fact of which ones I picked right, which in and in which
order I picked those gives me some pretty powerful numbers to sort of,
to chew on but it's kind of a weird way.
It's not really directly that way.
That's not the way.
The commentary is actually work out because it's really the fact that
you can set these things, different values that also makes it
important because you might not care what order things go in.
Right?
The order you, these might not
Not be order dependent when you build things up.
So that may not be entirely true.
But the point is, if these things have different values that actually
mean stuff, then, as we compose them together setting, the different
values to different things is what will determine how these monsters
behave, right?
And so, the example, there is like, let's say we've got, you know, in
the case of let's just take just straight movement, so we've got how
something moves, right?
We've got a speed property let's say.
Hey.
We've got like a, you know, sort of a flying kind of concept may be,
right?
We've got like what they can walk on.
So you know, do they have, you know, can they walk on water?
Like so we got restrictions right?
So like, can they walk on water or fire?
That sort of stuff.
When you take these things together you can start to produce a lot of
classes of things that can move because you've got how fast it moves.
So that gives us a whole range of things.
Right there might be like four or five or six different classes of
speed, right?
So you've got, you know, five things there, you could set, you've got
flying or not, that's a Boolean and maybe there's Heights of flying.
There's like low, flying things, and high-flying things, and non
flying things.
So that's three different settings there.
Right, they got restrictions, can it walk on water?
Can it walk on ice?
Can it walk on this?
Can walk on that, right?
So there's probably, you know, maybe another four different properties
get out of there.
So just for the movement of something, if we're thinking of it in
these terms, we now get five different types of things.
Times three different types of things times for different types of
things, and that right there, right?
Is going to lead us to 60 different types of monster movement,
And so I feel like that's always the way you want to think of it.
If you're trying to write a rich, a game that has lots of different
things, and lots of interactions between those three things, you want
to always decompose it like that and do your dispatching on the
decomposed things because that's a lot more manageable and allows you
to leverage the multiplication to get you up to higher numbers of
player facing types.
Whereas, if you accept to implement each player facing type, you don't
get multiplication.
You don't get that power of
Location.
So you're fighting this problem without the aid of the same kind of
multiplication on your side.
That's the only real thing that I was trying to say
Yesterday you were talking about using callbacks to The Climate
system, will this new system replace the need for them?
I thought, where I landed on that when I was, I thought I was just
saying, callbacks are an example of how you would do that in there.
And I thought, what I was saying is we don't need to do that because
we'll just handle them inside this routine as a symmetric, sort of way
that things are handled.
I thought that's actually what we said.
I'm talking about, if not, then that was my bad.
I didn't mean to imply that we do use.
Callbacks I thought I was just saying, call back to saying that people
often do use in this situation, but I don't want to because they have
flow control problems, right?
Casey, I asked a question in the Twitch app crashed on.
IPad, any chance you saw my questions before it did.
I don't think so because I don't see any of them on here so you may
have asked them before.
I started the Q&A
Traceroute to Twitch.
Twitch.
Windows.
You can see my router will see, will see what this goes to only answer
questions while it's doing it.
This is e.e.
twitches.
Question, Casey has a casual Observer and occasional troll.
Where's the game?
Now, seriously haven't watched for a while.
And how do you find the energy to do this week nights?
I don't know.
It's not that hard to program for an hour on a weeknight, you know?
I mean, I like programming and I would just be doing something on my
computer anyway.
So I feel like that's usually, you know, that's usually how it goes in
terms of where the game is.
Now like I said we're on our 68 hour of programming, I think it's
really more like our 70th, our because we had a couple
One or two streams where I went and extra hour, just like ones that
were on Fridays.
I did a little extra extended session ones.
So, we've programmed for 70 hours, so we're in another 10 days on day.
78 will have completed to work weeks worth of code.
So if you sat down on a Monday, you would have program for a week and
now we're on our second week and we're not quite there yet.
In another 10 days will be at the end of that second week in in those
two weeks.
Time, I think we've actually, I'm pretty darn happy with where we've
come.
We wrote Our Own win32 code startup code and all that stuff.
We wrote Our Own automatic dll, loading Loop, live coding, all that
stuff.
We wrote was good.
We've got our, you know, sort of primitive sound and video output
which we needed to get started.
We wrote Our bitmap learning code, a bitmap building code.
We've now written a system to handle giant world's so we can have
absolutely huge rolls.
Now, if we want to add that we can walk around on.
We can
The scroll, or do room based growing because we sort of decided we'll
do both of those.
We've got a simulation region thing now this design so that we can
handle sort of whole world, sort of stuff happening at once.
So other entities can be doing stuff in the world other than where you
are and we kind of set things up to try and handle that.
And we're right now sort of doing our sort of collision detection,
entity property stuff just a little bit of that before we go into
animation.
So I would say we're
we're probably going to close in at the end of that.
10 days I would say, at the end of to work weeks, I would say we're
almost done with engine architecture as well.
We've got a little bit, I think animation going to take us a little
while but once animations done.
So I would say probably somewhere around day.
Let's say 90 90 to 100, which is not even three full weeks of
programming.
So, hardly any time at all programming wise, right?
We will be at the point where we're totally ready to do the game.
Proper
Have a complete like, sort of game framework running with all of the
pieces in place and we'll just have to go through and then start doing
some of the heavy lifting will have to write the renderer for real.
It's gonna take a while, then we'll have to write sort of the some
sound stuff, which probably won't be too bad.
Sounds a little easier and then we'll have to write and those will
leave like the shipping versions of those things shipping, render
shipping sound code.
And we'll do after that.
Then we'll do start on the shipping.
You know, game basically.
And honestly, yeah, I couldn't be happier with how it goes.
I'm nervous about the renderer.
I know rendering.
It's kind of a big topic and so I'm a little nervous about that.
I don't know how long that's going to take.
That could be something that really derails us.
But you know what you going to do?
I don't really know.
Yeah, I don't really know what to do beyond that.
We've got a right.
So I would say I'm delighted with our progress so far.
I think if you actually map it back to how long it would be if we
actually sat down and code were in great shape and yeah and if we can
keep going at this rate, I think we will.
Actually it'll the project will go great.
But obviously there's plenty of opportunities for us to stumble and I
don't know how we'll do because, you know, programming is always
difficult and unusual and you know, there's only so much you can do
about that but that's
To where we're at.
And I'm I'm really happy with how it's been going.
I noticed, sometimes you try to determine regions for Collision boxes.
Why not Implement basic shapes and use those as debug helpers with
some Alpha percentage?
Just because I don't really care about that stuff right now.
By the way, this is kind of bizarre.
I'm assuming that this is worth.
People started stopped our traceroute.
So twitch is probably somewhere in here.
It looks like this changeover is pretty nasty.
We went from three millisecond pings to 60 millisecond things but I
don't know.
So somewhere, right about here, stuff gets bad, but even so I don't
know who's dropping packets if anyone is but people who want to see
the traceroute.
There it is.
That's what we got.
Anyway,
So, yeah, I would basically say that the Collision box stuff.
We don't really need debug horses because not really writing any code.
That's all that interesting in terms of like nailing bugs and that
sort of stuff, we just want our engine architecture set up.
So what we're going to do is when we go down to do the rendering side
of things which will happen in you know a little bit of a little bit
from now, we will be building out our debug services with the renderer
because the renderer will give us the first opportunity to start doing
a lot of debugging.
Drawing, like debug lines do, but that's our stuff and because we
haven't needed debug services for anything right now.
I don't think it's worth spending time.
Writing some
He bugs stuff of that, in advance of doing it.
Kind of all as one system, that's my opinion.
Do you test for Collision every update interval?
If your sword overlaps in the entity?
Could it happen that a moving entity gets missed because both entity
and Sword move in the same tick above and beyond each other.
Uh, so not right now because right now we actually don't do
simultaneous move.
What we do right now is is in order move, right?
So basically, if this is a frame right?
Well actually no that's not true.
So yeah, I guess what I would say is yes, what you're saying can
happen because right now, we do
Actually do, simultaneous move.
So let's say you have a situation like this, right, where the sword
was going this way and the plate and the thing that was going to hit
the story was going this way and it just so happened that there
velocity was such that they probably should have hit right here.
We would not detect that because first, it'll move this guy here and
see that there's nothing, that's way.
And then it'll move this guy here and see there's nothing in its way.
Now, in order for that to happen, though, the sizes of these guys
proportional to their movement, have to be very small.
Which currently we don't have.
So in practice I don't think you could ever actually construct this
case.
But in theory, if you cranked the size of entities down very, very
tiny.
So they were just like points on the screen or you crank the speed of
entities up very high so that they were moving very fast, then you
could get this situation and that situation is what would compel if
you care about this.
Which when we do our clothes ejector we might decide to care about
this specifically because it's interesting to think about how to
solve.
Right.
And at least, two more complicated thing to solve it.
You need to basically do stuff where you kind of consider the motion
of entities together and say, would these guys have collided if they
move continuously, right?
So yeah.
So so, I guess that's what I would say about that.
I don't, I don't think can actually happen right now because of the
size of the entities, but the algorithm doesn't actually handle it.
And so, technically, you would be able to create things that could do
it.
And so, it might be interesting when we do the full question doctor to
actually,
For that just to show how to do it.
To me, it seems as a sort of solution should be influenced by the
speed of a player movement at the time.
It was despatched, am I, right?
Yeah.
So if you know, we're not actually at the point where we're doing that
kind of code but when things velocity is always relative, so if I
throw something and I am running then when I throw it it should have
my velocity plus however much of velocity.
I pointed to the throw right?
That's just kind of you know, basic physics, physical kind of stuff.
And so if you want to do that, what you do is when you set the sword
velocity,
so like, you know,
Here, when we, when we sort of, when we launched that sword, right?
When we launched the sword forward, I believe what happens if I
remember correctly.
Is it just where does it actually?
Set it.
Here it is.
I'm like we we throw the sword here somewhere.
So when we actually throw the sword here,
that's not it at all.
Until I'm kind of out to lunch today.
This is where we actually show The Sword so when you actually throw
the sword when we set that velocity for the sword, right?
We set it right here.
What should we do?
Is you just add in however fast the hero was moving because whatever
that, but it's not the accelerate, the acceleration doesn't change,
acceleration is independent of that.
So what you actually doing is you take the amount of velocity, you
want the sword to have and you'd add however much velocity, the hero
had at that time, right?
So that's, that's this.
It's like that, right?
And so that way when you're running things now and of course, we still
have our problem with the with it colliding.
I could turn that off for a second so you can see.
Because we until we Implement that table, it's going to keep getting
stuck on the hero basic.
It's like, I can't get out of the hero is actually another way.
We could choose to handle that but I want to implement the table as
well, but we've got, we've got so many things we could be doing.
But anyway, so in the same region,
If I was to turn this off, right?
So if I was to say that that collides thing like we were doing before
where I basically say you know and it stops on collision like we were
doing before.
Now when I when I do those things right?
You can kind of see that if I'm going in this in this that's funny.
I'm going in this direction.
It gets a lot more.
If I fire it in the same direction I'm going it gets a lot more heat
on it, right?
But if I fire it in the opposite direction, I'm going.
So let's say,
Moving this direction and I fire it backwards.
It goes a lot slower, right?
And that's technically how that would work.
So if that's what you were concerned about, that's the way you would
want to do it, right?
So yeah.
But again we're not really at the point where we're thinking about
code that's like when we start to do the animation stuff will start
talking more about like that kind of tuning stuff and those sort of
things.
I missed the part on how many entities you are simulating at once and
where you store them, but won't the dispatch table approach be
negative for cash performance.
Could it simulation be deferred?
So yeah, you know, like it's a little premature to think about stuff
like that because we first have to see whether that's actually a big
deal because what you have to remember is that dispatching, only
happens when two things hit each other, which actually doesn't happen
that often, right?
You're only talking about a few of those.
Those per frame at most probably, right?
So chances are
That dispatch is not going to dominate the run time of the Collision
routines figuring out, who collided with, who is probably going to be
the cost and the dispatch to handle it is probably not going to be
that big a deal.
But that said, I don't know that depending on how we actually want
thinks, it could be the other way around.
So it's a little bit too early to think about that because we really
just don't know and we'll have a better idea later on as we go, what
needs to be optimized and what doesn't.
But, at this point, it's definitely not worth worrying about because
we don't even really know what kind of load is going to be placed on
that disk.
Patch in the first place, you know, and whether we even have to
optimize it at all.
Don't do traceroute again because everyone got to see you freeze.
Okay, I don't know what that means.
But okay.
It seems logical to make infinity, the default maximum distance on
entity and they can travel, but that could have performance
applications.
Can you say something about that?
Well, so the reason that I didn't set it to some random floating-point
number, like infinity or like float, Max was just because you can get
into troubled situations.
We're like, if I go in here and I was going to end up doing something
with the distance remaining, I don't want something that's going to
create, any sort of exceptional floating-point situation, because
since the floating Point units, handle things, special numbers like
infinity or stuff like that or overflowing afloat since they handle
those things specially.
I don't want to put it in a situation that would make it
uncomfortable.
So I just need a number that's large enough that I know that I'm never
going to hit it.
So it's practically infinity and so I find that it's usually better to
do that than to
Actually use Infinity because you don't know on what platforms you're
on.
What's going to happen.
If you actually try to do an operation with infinity and I just I
don't want to bring in that because I never remember all those things
and I don't want people to have to remember those things to write this
code because it's not necessary.
So that's why I just picked a high number instead of using an actual
floating Point infinity or something like that.
All right, last couple questions here.
Could you also do something like that for a I wear?
For instance you can impose simple behaviors on top of each other
randomly to make complex and very Behavior instead of doing the more
common Behavior tree approach.
Yes, that's actually what I was planning on doing.
So, we'll see how that goes.
When I go to do it.
If you do the triple anus way, can you come back to it later and edit
or add more details to it like from six to eight etcetera or will that
cause problems?
So I'm not sure.
I understand the question.
Exactly.
Alright, I think that's it.
All right.
Okay, thank that went relatively.
Well, except for the problems with me.
Sending packets to Twitch.
Unfortunately, which seems to not go as well as I guess I would like
it to.
Okay.
So let's take a look here.
Go back in.
I want to see how badly we ended up doing.
Yeah, we just have we had a horrible.
This was absolutely horrible tonight and I again I have no idea.
Why.
I don't really have any way of figuring out what that actually is.
If anyone has any ideas, if I could figure out if it's an ISP problem,
or if it's just twitch and there's nothing I can do, it would be
pretty great to know because I'd like to get it fixed.
It doesn't happen that often but every and nights, we get this problem
where we just can't seem to do anything, so be nice to get that
resolved.
Anyway, thank you everyone, for joining me, for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure working with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org.
Comes with all the source code.
So you can follow along at home, you'll get a little Link in your
email that you can use to download the source code every night.
And I uploaded after we finish coding.
Every time, if you want support the video series, we also have a
patreon.
You can subscribe to its linked off of handmade hero dot-org.
We also have a tweetbot the tweets, the schedule.
So if you want to know when streams are you can always find it there.
And finally we also have a news in Forum site which I highly recommend
checking out.
It's got discussion boards on it.
You can go to, I answer questions there and so do other programmers.
It's also got ports of handmade hero to other.
Languages and other platforms like mac and Linux and so on.
So if you want to see Community, people have done ports, like that's
our stuff.
You want to run on Mac or Linux.
That's a great place to go to get started on that.
And also we also have annotated archive and episode archive on there
that you can go to which helps catch up with old episodes if you're
new to the series.
So I highly recommend checking it out.
That's about it.
I will be back here tomorrow morning.
I believe it's 9 a.m.
Pacific Standard time tomorrow.
Hope to see you guys there for some breakfast coating.
If not, I completely understand.
Happy Thursday anyway and I will see you guys later.
Take it easy.