I do a little stop.
Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream.
I have some work to do from yesterday yesterday.
We made it so that we could dump data into our debug stream.
Our debug string previously contained, mostly just profiling data and
now we can dump just arbitrary data in there.
And so now that we've done that, what we would like to do is have ways
to gather up that data and display.
It so that we have kind of a nice convenient way to put anything that
we want to put into that stream.
So that's what I've got to do now.
Because we got just to the point where we would start implementing
that yesterday and then we were done with the stream.
So today is the day that we start to tackle that problem.
So I'm going to go ahead and do exactly that, that is after I adjust
my chair which apparently is not adjusted properly, and that's
obviously, no good, you know, nobody wants a maladjusted chair.
All right, so I need to go ahead and get myself.
Up here.
Let's see where we were at.
Today is day 2009.
Which means that if you would like to follow along with with me at
home you want to unpack Day 2008 source code into the directory in
which you are working, that is the source code that I will be working
with today.
I do not know why I find similar results and up here, we could just
pretend that never happened.
I suppose.
Oh.
You know what?
It probably was because we
A little, we probably use the other platform to search for offset of
our do.
Remember why that was there and probably, left it up there.
Anyway, so here is where we left off again, everything running
correctly.
Nothing out of the ordinary and all the stuff is still working.
So, we're in good shape there, but we are not actually, you know,
although we've got our profile data obviously and stuff like that.
That's happening.
We have not yet done anything with that other data.
The object stuff that's that's kind of being dumped out there.
We've got entity.
Information that's being printed out in the Stream and then we don't
actually ever use that information.
So that's what I'm going to try and do today is just get that
information displaying somewhere so that we can look at it.
And again, this is very tricky, code the code that we've been working
on for the past couple days.
It's been about two weeks of working on.
Debug hierarchy stuff.
There's a lot of very subtle decisions and they're very difficult to
get right.
And so it's kind of a iterative refinement process for you.
Kind of have to go through and go through a bunch of iterations to
actually get it.
Correct.
Typically, most people don't bother going through any of those
iterations and you end up with kind of just some code like we have
right now if we were to just kind of stop and just use it as it is,
which has a bunch of drawbacks that are not really that good right
there.
Not something that we want to continue to have
So it's kind of important to make sure that you spend enough time to
sort of smooth out those rough spots until it's actually clear that
it's able to do the things that you really wanted to do and not that
it's able to do things.
You really want to do in a concise way and not that you are able to do
things, you want to do with a tremendous amount of like overhead or
weird work on the usage side, right?
A lot of debug systems, end up with these huge things, you have to do
to use them.
And
they had that kind of defeats a lot of the purpose of of actually
doing the debug system in the first place, right?
So here is the thing that we're doing is in terms of dumping data out
and you can see here that we've got like our data block, beginning our
data block and an in-between.
There we put out a lot of values here.
These values are the elements of the entity that we're talking about,
in this particular case.
And so what I want to do is that, you know, and those are going into
the stream.
What I want to do is gather those kind of back.
Up.
Again, inside the debug code just like we were pulling profile
regions.
I want to gather those back up again into something that I can
display, right.
so, in order to do that, what I have to do here is
inside the debug coalition.
Wherever that lives, there it is inside the debug collation.
I have to do a bunch of work just like I was doing with the blocks
here for profiling.
I have to be able to do that for the data as well.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to basically follow the exact
same process where when I hit an open block, right?
I'm going to say, OK, when a block gets opened, I'm going to allocate
a new one here, and this is going to be for the data.
And I'm going to fill out this information here.
Now, the interesting thing about this is if you look for the most
part, this sort of stuff can be almost entirely again.
Sort of shared between the two pieces of code because all of this
stuff is is essentially the same thing, right?
So the only thing that really changes.
If you look the way this actually works, you can see that there's this
concept of chaining that we're doing here for these debug blocks.
Where in one case, I would be putting it on the
Block.
So, like up in this one here I'll be putting on the code block but in
this case here I would be putting it on the data block, right?
So there's there's a data block cheering in a code Block Chain.
Is that really a change?
Just a little stack I mean it is a chain but it's conceptually just to
stack you know whatever the last one that's open is that's the one
that we're working with or whatever.
So if you if you know how that works it means that probably what I
could do is say that you know
My allocate open debug block, I could go ahead and make that be
something a little more automated.
So if I want to, I can just extend that out into something where you
know, I'm passing.
Little more information here and then it could just do that work for
me.
That's being done here.
Manually, right?
So it doesn't actually have to do.
I don't actually have to write out that code every time that's
something that could just happen in here.
So after it kind of gets the result, you know, it could do this sort
of thing where it fills out all of this stuff, right?
So we have there, we've got our source, that's our debug record,
right?
We've got our frame index like so,
And we've got our opening event.
And since we have those in both cases, right?
It's pretty free to just have those get past and so now when we do
allocate D, sorry allocate open debug lock.
In this case two, I can do the exact same thing and I can just go
ahead and say, all right, we've got the frame index.
Events.
And thesaurus.
And then we still have to do this separately, right?
This is still different.
I could.
However, say well, since the debug block does have a parent there, I
could do something like this where I say, alright, since I know that,
it's a certain pointer that's actually getting operate on there.
I could say here is the place to chain it as well and have that chain
operate automatically as well.
So for example, I could just say, hey, you know,
Something like this.
And then, this code could also go in here, right?
So, I could do that at the bottom, where we say, okay, whatever the
first open block pointer is here, right?
We're going to write to it.
Excuse me.
So, something like this.
And now we should have a situation.
Oops, there we go.
We should have a situation where hmm.
Scratchy throat.
We should have a situation where all of that stuff is now handled
automatically for us in nothing particularly weird is happening.
So, let's see here.
Looks like got a parameter there.
So you 32 debug record, debug Event, open to account for 3, from debug
events, to debug record.
So it looks like these are in the wrong order here, frame, index,
events or astray - with source.
And here, I did them frame index Source event, so that's just a slight
Order problem.
So there we go.
And that's it.
So now that we've got that again, the closing stuff is very similar
but presumably, since all of this interior stuff is going to be
different, I don't know that it's going to have the same.
Kind of a for lack of better term of the same kind of a sharing as the
other one will be.
So I'm going to start by kind of I guess.
I'll I guess what I will do is I'll grab at least the whole thing and
then kind of trim, just so we can see the structure of it a little bit
better.
So in here, right, if I've got this sort of get record from scope
thing, the clocking and all this sort of stuff, we don't really care
about that stuff.
So, in general, I
I'd say that this stuff doesn't really matter here and similarly like
frames in between beginning and spans and that sort of stuff.
This isn't that really a span situation.
So in theory, this stuff is pretty much good to go.
Nothing particularly weird, there, it's all, it's all fine.
So mostly all we really want to do is just do you allocate the open
debug block whenever we actually get here, right?
So assuming that we have an open data block, we want to do is say
whatever the, whatever the matching block is that we've released the
one that we think is going to be the matching block is going to be
that, right?
So we grab that one, we then see what the event is on that matching
block and then we'd be then see if these events match.
Now that I guess is a good case there.
That looks like something we could easily pull out, right?
So this is basically something like inline pool, you know, events
match.
And in this case it's just going to do exactly what it does right
there.
And so that would be something where we have to debug events.
You know, we've got debug event, a and debug event B.
And in this case we would just say like okay we've got a we've got
the, we just want to know if the same a
and B and A and B.
So that is is that, I don't know why bother putting an if statement
there just left over from where I cut and paste it.
So that's whether or not at the events match and so I should be able
to do something.
Now where I just say like, okay, you know, this is really an event if
events match and I could actually cause events are equal.
And so in here I could say like, all right,
Let's let me actually see if I should call it that or match.
So, debug event has what in it.
Exactly platform.
Handmade platform, debug events.
So debug event has a bunch of stuff so so R equals wrong ISO.
Match match events, match is better.
Because in this case we are talking about sort of this like fuzzy
match, they're not actually going to be equal because it were really
just talking about whether some of these things line up properly,
right?
That does seem like.
The way it should go.
Now there is one part of it.
That's a little bit wonky, which is the thread, the thread ID core
index bit here, I feel like that part kind of has to be elevated out
because we need that in addition to the data that's being stored
right?
The thread ID, Corey index thing is, at least the thread ID part is
very important for us to kind of match that stuff out, you know, I
Yeah I guess only the thread ID really is right if we want to get
right down to it, but either or like that kind of has to be something
that would be matchable across multiple different types of events.
So I think you probably want to do something more like this, right?
Where we sort of say, you know, there's a there's a data package and
then there's this and thread.
ID is actually an important thing that kind of has to be in there,
right?
I think that makes some sense, so yeah.
That also suggests to me, that we would have to get that information,
which we are not currently doing so inside, handmade platform.
If we take a look at the TC, like the TC thread ID and stuff, this
stuff here, where we do record debug event you know when we're calling
the common thing it looks like now we could sort of start to talk
about the fact that well really honestly this is actually going to
happen everywhere so we really don't need the common and regular
versions of
This we could just say that now, actually, it's always the common one,
and these guys actually are going to get set pretty much every time
for every thing that seems reasonable to me.
So if I get rid of that, then what that means is the common version
kind of goes away here.
Oops.
And so all these guys record, debug event, common is just going to
become record debug event.
And that's all good.
okay, so yeah, this then becomes
Well, that's actually just fine the way it is right now.
So this guy now is going to say, okay, I want to make sure the opening
event and the event match if they do then off we go.
And again, that's something that now I can share.
So in here I can also say, you know, if events match.
So that that is not actually something that has to be done
differently, right?
And that should pretty much do it right?
This
Again, is the same.
When we do deallocate open debug block.
If you look at how that goes, I feel like that's something where we
could totally have.
We could totally have that.
Threading, the the chain management, right?
I feel like, I feel like something like, this, could easily be done,
right?
So this is first open data block, that's first open code block and now
we know that we just have to make sure that this thing happens right
in that deallocate.
So when we do deallocate open debug lock, we actually want to do
whatever the pointer is.
So, you know, this is a open.
Debug
Lock first, I don't know what we called up here.
First block or something.
Yeah, first open block.
and so, what we would do is say, okay, we've got the first open block
We want that to be equal to whatever the parent is, right?
Well.
Okay.
But hold on a second.
Is that actually always the block that gets passed in here?
so, matching block
Becomes threat.
First open code block, then we do deallocate thread first open code
block.
That actually is the one.
That seems reasonable because the first open code block is always the
one that we're popping off when we get to the end we're going to be
popping this one off.
So when we do this here and I'm going to look at take a look at
matching block here.
So if we take a look at matching block, right, it kind of just does
its thing and then at the end when we say we want to do, okay?
At the open.
Debug look what would be saying here is like, okay, we want to
deallocate matching Block, it's always actually the top one.
So in some sense we could just even pass just a single thing in.
We could do it this way where we say like okay,
We're just going to say here's the block to free.
And so it's something like this.
We have first open block where we just go.
Like, okay, the open debug block free.
Block equals whatever first open, block is so free Block next three
equals.
You know, first free block and then debug say perspectives equals free
Block, right?
So, that kind of like, cleans that up.
And then in here, we say, oh first open block, is now going to be
equal to whatever the three blocks parent was right.
In fact we could do that right?
Right there.
So that would allow us to leverage this.
The code pretty much exactly the same in both cases.
So that seems like a good idea to me.
That's what I at least think.
So I'm going to go ahead and see how that plays out and, and we'll see
you.
Yes.
All right.
So I'm going to go ahead and, and fix these compile errors here.
Just see where we're at, let's find out.
So we've got some array index, multiple definitions.
So our, our thing here, where I did this obviously, I did a slight, a
slight mistake.
There was a slight mistake involved here, record, debug event.
Probably needs to have.
Yeah it does.
It needs to have some kind of a guarding around it so that it doesn't
get multiplied to find.
So you can see in here, like, it's end block, right?
That is not actually, it doesn't actually have a wrapper around this
and so this stuff when it kind of puts forth into the stream there,
you would create multiple defined symbols if you ever called en Bloc
and can multiple times.
So we're just wrapping it in.
Those braces to make sure that all those variables aren't don't kind
of pollute out to the to the outer scope.
So that's all good.
And in theory now, we should still see the same result Loops.
That's the head don't want to do that.
We should still see the same results here where we kind of expect no
changes in our, in our sort of ability to view the profile, which
looks roughly correct.
And so that's it for that.
Now, that
We have open debug box.
All we need to do is actually have a way to kind of, like, put stuff
out, you know, Bill stuff out into them.
Such that the debug system.
Is able to.
is able to sort of
parse through them after, right?
And so what we could do is we could go ahead and try to use the
variable system, but what's going to happen, right?
Is, this is going to kind of and this is why I want to do this part of
it.
What's going to happen here is we're going to come across some things
in our in our variable system that make it harder to do this and those
are the things that we want to fix but it's easiest to do that usually
by just starting and doing it.
So I'm going to actually just go ahead and slowly kind of move it over
and and
And get it to the point where it's, you know, obvious kind of how we
might kind of massage it a little bit more.
So normally, when we do this stuff, right and we have this sort of
variable group, kind of concept and all this sort of stuff happening,
right?
We are creating these Verdi's debug variables, we create them on the
debug Arena and that's all good.
And we can do this exact same stuff we could basically convert all
this stuff over to be stuff that happens at collation time, right?
And that's basically what we want to do because if you think about
this stuff this was just our test code, right?
So this code actually is completely worthless, right?
It doesn't
It's not how we actually want to specify these things.
What we'd rather
You is having specified very dynamically like we just saw, right?
So ideally right.
Ideally we want to basically run this exact same code but we just want
to do it sort of in here.
So we want to be able to add these variables.
We want to be able to do that sort of stuff.
Right?
And so what we would do is we'd have this sort of a thing where we
create debug variable links, we create a bunch of links and then we
end the group.
So we're basically doing the begin variable group and variable groups
stuff, right?
So something like this when we open a data block, right, we would
create a group for it, where we would add, you know, groups and all
that sort of stuff.
And then when we are done with it, we would end the group which, as
you can see, does not actually do anything.
So we're already because we have the open block closed block stuff.
We already handle the sort of stack for granted stuff we were doing
before.
When we want to add a variable, we can come in here and add the
variable just like we would any other variable and just like these
routines you
just call that, whatever that add variable thing was, you would call
that for every different type
now, we should already have the types that we need, hopefully,
If I take a look at handmade debug .h, you can see that.
We've sort of have these types already right here.
They all are.
So all I should really have to do is say, okay, if I want to add, you
know, in our 32 or something like this, I can add an R32.
And then in here,
Let's see where we're at.
Yeah, okay, here we go.
I've got sort of this, this ability to say.
All right, there is my real 32 and I can just put the value in their
right.
And the value comes from the event that I'm working with right now,
right?
I've got this event and the debug event that we're talking about,
It's got this kind of stuff in it, you know I'm saying.
So I could just say, all right, I know that this thing is an R32
event.
I know that are 32 is go into our
32 and so there's my grabbing my R32 out, right?
So all I need to be able to do is do this.
Debug, add variable thing.
I need to be able to do that, in a way, that makes some sense where I
can do it with.
Say, for example, thread first open data block so that I can say,
okay, I want you to add it to the currently open data block instead of
that weird context stuff that we were doing before, the didn't really
have anything to do with anything else.
Right now, I also know the name
In theory because the name comes from whatever the debug record was
right.
Because remember every time we record one of these things, we've got
the debord record index.
The debug record index is already in Theory, been dereference for us.
I think right record index.
Get record from
Yeah, they're not quite but almost right.
So what we would need to do, there is well, I guess now that I think
about it, that's not really true matching block.
Parent is not, that's not what we want.
We want to actually, I want to get the Deep.
How do I get a, how, how do I get the debug record it?
There it is Source.
That's why I'm like, I thought that would have been dereference for
us.
What is going on?
It was I just was looking in the wrong place.
So we've got that Source, the debug record, and in there, we've got
this block named.
The Block name can serve as the thing that the variable gets printed
out under because that's you know what?
We were specifying when we push that stuff on there.
So in here,
When we do our debug, add variable, as long as we can Implement that
somehow, which I'm pretty confident that we can, then we're all good.
And so then all we would need to do is actually have this stuff again
work in exactly the same way where it's going to pull these things out
and then put them back on, right?
So let's go ahead and do it.
Let's just do that stuff.
And there's some more things that we are going to want to do here.
So try not to
Jump Ahead too much because I'm just trying to do this in a slow
methodical fashion.
So you can kind of see how the each transformation takes place is so
it won't be as nasty as this all appears to be at the very end.
It'll clean itself up quite a bit.
I think you'll see anyway.
So just going ahead and filling out these guys.
I don't remember if we support V2s.
We?
Yes, we do.
So we've got, we've got more types here.
We can do V2s.
So, V2 are like v2x?
Probably something like this.
Back are 30, 20, and this is a V2.
So let's go ahead and do that.
And then again, there's the V3 there's the before.
X y, z w.
And there we go.
Yeah, so oops.
So that
Is how we do that and similarly for the rectangle stuff.
I think we have a rectangle to in here.
I don't really remember.
Let's see if that's true.
I don't remember we don't.
So, basically rectangle twos, and threes.
Are not are not.
Sup.
Now we have to actually implement the stuff that actually does the,
you know, the variable adding stuff, right?
And so, what I'd like to do is have some way here of sort of figuring
out.
Where these things are going to live and in order to have some place
for these things to live, I think what we want to do, right, is
respect the fact that debug collation is a frame based thing, you
know, that's how we've been doing it.
So we've got things like a debug frame here in a debug frame has like
regions that are the timing regions.
I would also like it to have one of our groups.
One of our route groups, right?
Because right now we just have one root Group which is like this route
group, for kind of global variables that we sort of were playing
around with and that is right.
Sure.
But what I'd rather do is, I'd rather have an ability to sort of have
that be specified.
Per frame.
So as frames go by, they build up their data inside the frame, and
then, as they go away, they go away, right?
So there's that sort of Route group concept.
When we create a frame, will make one of those route groups and then
we will use it, right?
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to get when we create one of these
debug frames, you know, something like this.
When we grab one of these guys, right, I would like to have
Way of getting that information of sort of initializing that route
group 20.
And yeah so probably frame.
Begin clock.
Equals one clock, here we go.
So you can kind of see here where we've got our debug State collation
frame.
So I want to basically, I want to make sure that when we create one of
these guys so that retires it right?
When we make a new one like we do here.
I want to say that when we create that new one, right?
I want to be able to make the route group be initialized to 0, right?
Or I guess not zero.
What I would rather do is have the route group be created at that
point.
So when it's collating that frame, it will create one of these one of
these guys.
And so in order to do that, I would have to do something
where,
Our, debug variable stuff and I can, I think I can start to safely
kind of move this thing in.
We sort of have this in off in the test code, I think we probably get
rid of this file entirely in a second.
You know, I think we could, we could do that pretty safely.
So, what I want to do is kind of again, move, this sort of stuff over
slowly but have it so that it
You know, have it so that it's now working sort of, in the collation
system.
So, when I do a begin variable group sort of thing, which is what I
would be doing for the route group here, I can just make that code be
something that happens with collation.
So we have this here, begins.
Will Group instead of taking the context, really what I need to know
is just who sort of the parent there is.
So I've got the debug state.
That I could pass directly and that's just like this and then I've
kind of got the the concept of adding the variable to the group.
I'm going to leave that up for now.
This part I don't have to track so really all we're talking about is
something like this.
So add route group.
Is this sort of thing?
That's really what I actually wanted.
I grabbed the wrong guy, so that's what I want.
And that relies on the ability to do a debug add variable right.
So, debug out variable is that again, that's all pretty
straightforward.
The only difference here is instead of using the debugger, we know,
we're going to want to use the collation Arena because that's actually
the thing that we are that we're kind of working with.
So I'm going to actually call that for.
Now I'm going to call that collated variable so I can sort of keep
these guys separate as I because I'm going to probably remove the
other one and I kind of want them to bring up in parallel.
So this is the collation version.
I don't know that we have to push a copy of the string.
But I guess I just will keep doing that since there's no real reason
not to and it might make things a little more robust in the face of
dynamic code reloading which, you know, can cause problems certainly
if we don't keep copies of the string.
So we'll do that.
We'll keep doing that for now.
So, we got begin variable group when we have end rail group and very
group doesn't actually matter here at all.
So, this is more of a collate, create variable group.
Like so,
And really all we need now is just a way to add a variable to a group,
that's about it.
So we just have a thing that's like collate, add variable to group
that would again, just take whatever the group is and the variable to
add.
And you can see it doing a thing right here.
And the only difference is going to come out of the collation Arena
and this is I think mostly all the code that we actually would need.
So in here, when we're going to do the roof route, I do collate, add
or create variable group, right?
Or maybe add variable group, that's probably.
You know what?
This is probably create a variable.
Create variable.
I like that, little bit better.
So when we do collate create variable group, we're going to need some
way of naming this thing for now.
I'll just call it frame but we may want to make an actual thing.
That's like what the name of the frame is or something like that at
some point.
But for now we'll just call it like this.
And then when we actually do this work here,
we're doing the en, Bloc begin block, and that stuff for the data
blocks.
Now, we should be able to have this group stuff.
Sort of start to come in to play.
So when we do open and close data block, we know that we have a
collation frame, which means that we know that we have a route group,
right?
We know that we have a way to kind of add those things in there
because if the frame exists then we created a group for it.
So what we can do here is we can say, all right I know that I want to
add this to the route group, you know, this is this open data block or
whatever.
Although, I guess we want these things to Nest, so really what we want
to do is just have a thing here, where we say, if there is an open
debug block, the open debug block, would have a debug variable thing
on here, potentially, right?
Which is just, what is the group, right?
The things are going into.
And I'll do a thing here with sort of like notes Casey only for data
blocks.
So when we do an open data block, obviously we would, we would always
do Kuwait, add variable, sorry, collate create variable group, we
would always create one of those and presumably cure again.
It's the block name is the source.
So it's whatever we were told.
We are data block, is that we're trying to Output.
We're going to create a variable group for it and we're going to go
ahead and just put that into whenever we create this.
Lock.
That is the new group for this data block, right?
And now we want to see if there was or ready and open data block,
right?
Like if there was one here, then we have a parent.
So, you know, we've got this guy right?
This parent in there.
So we want to say, is if our debug block had a parent, then we would
want to do a collate, add variable to group, right?
And we'd want to be able to add to our debug block parent group.
We want to be able to add ourselves.
So again, just creating a creating that hierarchy as we go
So that's obviously pretty straightforward.
Nothing particularly unusual happening there.
And in fact, I think that's basically all there is to that, right?
I think that's mostly it.
This is actually collate, create variable.
And so in here now, yeah, I guess we actually the open data block.
Stuff is now all good.
So enclose data block, I don't think we really we don't have to do
anything.
Everything kind of would take care of itself there.
However, what we do need to do here is in fact, I guess we could say
something more like this.
We know that we're going to add it to a group, right?
We just don't know which group it is.
So if we have a parent, we would add it there.
But if we don't have a parent, right?
Then we would just add it to whatever the collation frame is.
So the debug State collation frame.
Whatever its route group is, that's the one we would use.
And that's just always going to be true.
So in here, when we do our debug, add variable, this is actually going
to be like something more, like
Kool-Aid, Kool-Aid create and at or create maybe like great grouped
variable or something like that.
And what we want this to do is do all the sort of this work again for
us.
We want it to take this first open block and we want it to
automatically sort of figure out where these things should go.
So I think that's all pretty much.
Really much good for us.
Yeah.
So
So that all looks kind and friendly and pretty much all we really need
to do here.
So I feel like mostly all I need to do is change the name of that
function to something reasonable, and then we can just go implement it
and be good, right?
And everyone's happy and smiling, and everyone is dancing around and
doing things, ridiculous, things, unmentionable things.
And so I'm just going to go ahead and change this guy here.
So that we don't
Have to deal with.
People got variable as a name.
Okay, so let's go ahead and implement this and this should be really
easy to implement on top of what we already have.
Like really, really, really easy.
It's just a question of like, basically swindling the parameters
around.
So we have our open.
Open d block.
We have our data type.
So this is our debug variable.
Type.
And then we have our block name.
Just just a variable name.
So in here, all I'm going to do is first, I'm going to create a
variable
that's very, very straight forward because we have all the parameters
we need.
So we're just calling it.
After we create the variable, we're going to want to add it to the
group.
and we'll do a little if here to make sure if we have a block, then
we're going to add it to the group and we might as well sir the block
How's it going to avoid?
Getting down further into the code and going?
Wait, why isn't there?
What's going on?
Actually, to be honest, you know that I think about it.
You should probably never be calling this, if there isn't one.
So this should probably just assert both of those things.
It's like, you know what, you got to have both of those things, my
friend.
so that
Should be that, I think so that kind of Hoover's up like sniffs up all
that data.
I don't actually remember what the members are here, okay, so it's
Vector 2.
And so now in theory, we are creating those again.
I don't know, you know, we're probably got some bugs in here.
In fact, the fact that we are crashing in here, suggest that we almost
certainly have some bugs in here, that's just a null pointer
dereference.
So somewhere we have made a very erroneous assumption about what is
getting past.
So let's see what's getting past year.
We have our debug block, of course, it can't view it because it's
already thinks that has gotten past that statement.
Of course it
Some even gotten past the statement, but that's the miracle of
Microsoft Visual Studio.
It can't even inspect a variable, that's one line above it, happy
birthday.
So in here,
We can look at these guys.
Let's see.
So the group.
So, what we know is that the group is null.
So this guy right here is actually no.
So the parent either the parent or the Coalition frame Trooper was
null depending on whether this guy has a parent.
So let's see, whether he has a parent.
That's probably the easiest thing to do if I can write, which is
easier said than done potentially, but
C.
So, the debug block thread first open data block, would have gotten
changed to be us.
So, I think I can look at thread first, open data, block to get that
information.
So thread, first open data, block, parent is null.
So we are going to be looking at debug State collation frame.
And yep, the route group is, in fact, null.
So the question would be how are we getting to the point where we have
a route group?
Who is
Null.
That is not cool, it's not cool bro, it's not cool.
And so the question is, how do we get into that situation?
So I'm going to make sure that we actually ever hit that case.
Okay?
So here is US, getting that case when I come into route group here,
what did I do?
I gotta I got one of these guys back, so we keep going here, let me
keep running.
So, somehow in here,
we are getting to the point where even though we saw that that
That collation frame situation where it actually did create a variable
group.
Ah, I'm it Nats type O.
That's a little bit of a typo there.
My friends probably should get rid of that route Group, which is the,
you know, sort of the one that's Global because I don't know that
we'll need it anymore, but, you know, one step at a time.
So, in theory, now again, we're working.
We don't really have anywhere to print print those things out yet, but
everything here is working.
And so, that's a good sign.
And now, so all we should really have
Do if we want to take a look at what's happening is, maybe look at the
frames.
Route group like have a way to display.
The route groups for frames, right?
So when we create that variable set there,
it's going to be a little bit nasty.
In fact, one thing I'm going to do to make lives a little easier on us
for debugging purposes.
Is it going to make it so that our groups when we create them are open
by default?
Which is not what would normally happen.
So when we do create a variable group thing, I'm going to go ahead
there and and sort of make sure that they are expanded if that makes
sense.
So, you know, when I have one of these variable groups at the moment,
we've got this sort of that debug ID concept there, right?
That it's going to be using
To figure out as its walking things.
What it would need to do.
So,
Excuse me.
All this may be the first point that we hit where we have to modify
something.
So if you look,
so you think if you look at the way we're doing this, when we actually
need to to walk one of these guys and we have this sort of this, this
route group scenario, right?
The VAR group thing, when that happens, is just a link chain, right?
So the links are being created when we do the add to group.
So when we do Cole, a create variable group, it hasn't actually gotten
added to anything yet.
And when we do collate add variable to group as the first time that
the link itself would actually have been been set up.
So in order to make our stuff expanded by, oh well, you know what?
I could choose this much more easily, I guess.
Now that I think about it, what I could do is just always have
everything be expanded.
So in the debug draw me menu, what I could do is not bother with the
thing that I was about to do.
And instead just say all right, everything's always expanded all the
time.
So when we come down here and we say,
You know, and expanded always, I could just make it so that that
particular part of the branches, just forget it.
It's like it's always going to be expanded so that we run things, you
can see that, you know, everything's always expanded by default.
That means that now we don't have to worry about that one part of it.
So you can take it out of the equation, which is what I want to do.
Because again, one thing on the time, there's a whole bunch of stuff
in play right now and it's going to kind of collapse down into
Much more streamlined thing over the next couple of days as we sort of
had to completion.
But you really, you know, again, especially if you're not entirely,
sure how everything's going to work, you really want to take it.
That kind of that one step at a time to make sure that you see how
everything is kind of interconnecting and you see how the code is
working, because if you don't, you're just going to end up with a big
old hot mess on your hands.
All right, so what I want to do now is I want to actually see what
we're getting.
I want to see in.
So, instead of doing, for example, the route group, when we do like
drumming menu, right?
Instead of doing that, where we have the trees and all that sort of
stuff, what I'd like to do here is say well, you know what, for these
debug trees, we don't really use the tree pretty much anywhere.
Like if you look
The trees situation is really just something to sort of be used with
with the interactions or whatever, right?
It's like what tree you're in and you can kind of see that the way
that we're doing that invar link interaction, here, that debug tree is
just kind of being used as part of the ID so that each tree gets its
own sort of State for things.
You know, I'm saying?
So it should be pretty free for me to sort of create another one of
these trees.
In fact, I could, I could, I think,
Piggyback ride on top of it.
So when We're looping over these trees way, be one of the ways that
you get the tree.
Is the tree could have some kind of special thing on it that says,
point to this Frame, whatever this frames debug variable is going to
be or whatever.
Right?
So, you know, if I look in here and I see handmade
Debug dot h has the sort of frame set here where those frames frames.
So, here's all the frames.
Right?
What I could do is go through the frame count and and have it.
So that each one of those sort of has a tree that corresponds to it.
It's sort of what I want to do for our you know our printout purposes
that makes sense or actually better yet what I could do is just use
frame 0.
So, you know in here for example, when we do this, this sort of Stack
thing where I've put, you know, push
Of things onto the stack.
What I could do instead there is just say, oh, you know, instead of it
sort of tree Group, whatever I could do something where I say,
alright?
The debug variable.
Group is going to be the tree group here.
and then,
This is just the same code, right?
Nothing nothing.
Weird happens.
but now what I could do is I could say, okay if you know, if debug
state
Ram, count is greater than zero.
Then I'll just again just override it right here.
So, for our testing purposes, I'll just say hey,
The group that we're going to print out is going to be the debug State
frames.
Zero's whatever that frame is.
It's going to be that route group.
So we can just see, you know what?
What is it printing, right?
Okay.
so,
I will point out at the risk of stating the obvious, but that is not
what should have been happening.
As you can see, that keeps adding to the same thing every time and
what should have been happening is each frame.
It should just have its own.
It should not every frame be adding to the same route group.
So something is is quite messed up there and I'm not exactly sure why.
I don't actually remember how we clear.
I thought we cleared the collation.
Every end frames?
Yes, yes.
So we do that right here, so I'm not sure, I'm not sure how you can
keep adding like that.
Although I also don't remember how many frames we keep.
Do you guys remember how many frames you keep at the moment?
I do not.
Max debug event array, count times for so.
Okay, we keep a lot of frames, so we probably just have something
stupid happening with our first open code block situation would be my
guess, but I guess we'll have to find out.
Okay.
So let's take a look.
I guess I should also verify.
That thing is actually closed.
Like meaning that the code ever actually closes it so debug and data
block, for example, I'm just going to verify that and data block
actually ever closes anything.
So we do have the clothes data block event.
It looks like, it should be the same and so that's good.
Events match to do to do.
So I suppose what we could check first is whether we are ever getting
a successful.
Clothes.
So what's interesting here is you can kind of see
when we have begin block and end block in this particular case or ER,
code blocks are
Oh yeah, okay, blocks are doing what you expect.
Data blocks have a sensibly, the same code first open data, block the
checks.
And check to see whether the events match.
Assuming that they do it D, allocates the block, which should also pop
it off the stack, which is good.
So, first open data block right, when I do deallocate open, debug
block that right there, should make sure that the parent stuff chains
properly.
So I'm just going to go ahead and step into the code because I can't
immediately.
See any particular reason.
I believe that that should be doing what it is doing yet.
As we can see, it definitely is doing it.
So let's just find out.
Let's step into here.
So, our events are not matching, so that's, that's not good.
And in fact, I guess what I could say to 2 that is in general.
In general, I don't really think we should ever be seeing that because
our data, like, if we had a data block, that was spanning a frame
boundary, that could happen.
So if we were using the data blocks from other threads that could
happen, we are not using data blocks from other threads right now, so
that's just plain wrong, right?
Like there's no circumstance under which that should be occurring.
And so I want to see why our events aren't matching because
That's just a bad situation.
So, here is our matching block that we're testing.
Here is our opening event.
Here is our event, right?
So here we go.
We have the opening event and this is the closing event.
The debug record index is different, which we would expect.
The translation unit is the same, which is what we would hope the
types do line up the TC, the thread indices are the same.
The core index is the same as so, I guess, I don't remember what would
be happening.
ah,
So, the debug record index is not going to be the same across these
two.
So, I don't know.
I don't know what we want to do about that.
So if you look you can see that in like are timed block or you know
our end block sort of stuff like this sort of thing.
We were careful to meticulously recorded that counter.
And so I suppose what we would want to do here is take the exact same
approach.
You can sort of see how we were doing that, since we're trying to have
those lineup.
I guess we want to do the same thing in here for the most part that
seems that seems like how it goes.
Yeah.
It's a little nasty.
It's just a little bit nasty as all.
So,
I'm not certain.
That I really want that to work that way because really all that is is
a check to make sure that the debug data lines up properly but there
really isn't any way you could do anything else about it.
So I feel like at some level, that's probably just a stupid idea.
Like what's going on there, right?
I feel like, you know, we have that begin block, end block situation.
I feel like almost in some sense.
It's always kind of dumb to have that happen because you pretty much
always want to end the block, you know, the block opens and closes
always have to be symmetric that's the way that we're processing them
here.
So that's really just a all that is is to debug check to ensure that
you don't have an era.
And so I really don't love that.
I'm going to I'm going to table that for tomorrow and I'm going to say
that what we will do here to do remove this checking, I want to see
what's going on there.
I want to think about that in a little bit more detail.
Sorry about that.
All right, so let's see here.
Looks like we run properly for a little bit and then when we wrap when
we do our sort of like our our rap over, we bite it, right?
But you can kind of see that we're actually doing what we wanted to do
for the most part.
It looks like I don't know if we're actually getting the right data
out because I didn't we don't actually know.
Even what the data is for that thing that we were printing the hot
entity.
I don't even know what entity that was and all that sort of stuff that
we're almost there.
And so all we have to do now is just kind of solidify, make sure that
we don't have.
In fact, let's just take a look quickly.
Okay.
So in here we're getting a VAR of null.
So when we get a debug view for a particular link, we're getting back
nothing it looks like oh sorry, no, the VAR from this link from
whatever the Interlink was so that implies that something that got
erased is still on the group.
I'm not sure why that would be.
That seems a little bit odd to me, actually.
So when we're drawing through these here, we've got a tree, right, how
many how many frame counts are there?
We're up to 32 frames.
So why would we be having a situation on the 30 when there's 32
frames?
Why would we having a situation where something in the first frame has
a variable link that is not valid at that point, right?
And I'm not sure
So let's see if I go ahead and check debug State frame 0 and we look
to see what the route group has in it.
So the route group is in fact garbage but I'm not really sure why that
would be how did it end up getting the garbage out since it should
never in general be swept away except when we sweep away everything
including the you know, the frame counter whatever.
Because when we do,
Restart collation, right?
Restart collation.
Should restart everything I'm going to
Do a little check here.
All right.
So we call restart collation once, right?
We set the frame, count up, we then run, we do not restart collation
again but we do get a crash there, right?
So that looks a little nasty.
That looks nasty that looks like that looks like you know, something
that one might call you know, a nasty thing looks a little nasty, it
looks a little bit nasty because our group is like getting corrupted
basically or something.
Bad is happening to the group because we know that in general
We know that in general, the route group itself should never actually
be kind of stand in that way.
So, when we restart collation, let's go ahead and do that here.
We we start collation.
If we take a look at debug State frame 0, there is the route group
right there and and that's going to be equal to nothing, right?
That's going to be equal to 2 and empty group, I suppose.
Suppose, one thing I should also do.
Now that I think about it and this is just a separate thing.
I'm I just wanted to fix while we were here is when we're doing that
tree thing, that hacked tree thing.
We really should still be checking because technically we could easily
have one where this group is, is 0, right?
So, we pretty much want to do something like more along the lines of
debug variable Paki group.
if hacking group,
Through people's have to do, that's really more.
What we actually want to do, but that should not affect this
particular bug, right?
We still have it.
So yeah.
Again.
So symptom is we run for a little while.
Then something goes horribly wrong, and our very our group.
That was previously, fine.
I'll becomes very much not fine.
So what I'd like to do in that scenario is.
Oops, what's going on here?
I'm still running into be still running.
So what I'd like to do here is every time we call debug and for
example I would like to every time we call debug and I want to see how
many frames we have.
So, you know, after we do the collation, like let's take a look at the
collation.
so,
When we're doing this I'm going to put a little.
If at the top here and just say, if debug State, you know, frame count
equals 31 and Y equals zero, something like that.
I want to be able to break right on that.
So inside Kool-Aid, debug records.
Kuwait.
Debug records I want to stop there.
So okay.
So on frame, 30 one, here we go.
We have not hit the bug.
Yet, if we look at debug frame 0, I'm going to take a check out that
route group.
You can see that the route group is is actually now.
Okay, right.
It's not busted, like it was before.
I'm going to go one round further to the debug, right?
And that's when we hit the the bug, right?
So, I now have a way of stopping just before we hit the bug.
and so in here is where the bug will actually occur, and I can watch
the bug occur if I want to, by saying, like, Okay, if I run to this
state and I take a look at the frames, route group,
There it is.
The canary in the mine shaft here right is that this data becomes
becomes dead right?
It becomes corrupted as I come through here I will trash it.
And so I'm just going to go ahead and assume temporarily that it has
something to do with the new code.
We
Did because obviously that code is code that was not running before
and we were not having a problem before.
So we're just going to take a look and see what happens in that code
if any of it destroys our frame and so actually looks like that is
getting destroyed prior to this if that makes sense.
So it actually looks like it's getting overwritten sort of before that
that process even occurs, right?
It looks like it's getting overridden.
I guess, perhaps actually in here.
So, I'm not sure why that actually is.
Collate frame.
What is the actual frame count?
I would like to know.
Max, debug event, array, thing Ridiculousness, right?
So, we do this push a RE/MAX, debug event.
Array, count is eight and that's okay.
So when the frame count gets to 32, that's actually when we would wrap
that array, right?
So that's that's what the bug is, right?
That we just have to figure out exactly what we're doing there.
But now we now we at least know what the bug is.
So how did we actually expect this to work?
Originally would be the question.
In fact is this just
Is this just complete garbage code?
Is this just a just a totally just ridiculous garbage code.
I mean, that's not that's to be expected since we're still totally
experiments things.
So I'm not blaming myself like saying that it's like terrible code or
anything.
I'm because it's supposed to be at this point, but if the frame count
gets to be 32, you certainly can't dereference it, right?
You can't.
If there's only 32 total things in the array, you can't start writing
to it, right?
And so, what exactly causes that correlation restart to occur?
If we look at it, right?
Like, when does that actually supposed to happen?
When we call restart collation?
I mean there was a point right?
Where we sort of
there is a point where I
so, this is just
This is just not correct, right?
This like hockey thing that we did temporarily to make it so that we
don't have to deal with a rolling buffer yet is just wrong because it
will go one over where it should.
So that was just totally bogus, we just weren't hitting it before
because hey, we've got
A big old memory Arena.
So we can go ahead and write right on over it.
But that doesn't really make it.
Okay.
So yeah, alright, so now actually, you can kind of see that this is
working which is kind of cool.
You can actually see that as we Mouse over things, we actually get the
data for the hot entity there and there's two entities, right?
Which is actually kind of awesome.
That's what should be happening because there's we are actually on top
of two entities.
The tree and the
The like space entity that we have underneath it.
So, that's pretty great.
We're getting real close here.
This is starting to feel pretty good starting to come together.
We have a lot of consolidation to do, but I'm pretty excited about
that.
I don't have a whole lot of time for Q&A today.
I gotta go relatively soon, but I'll just briefly.
See if anyone has a very on topic, question that I could answer and
then tomorrow will kind of be like crushing this down some more and
and getting a little bit.
A little bit more.
Sort of I don't like to use the word clean code or dirty code because
again I think it has a lot of bad.
Ramifications of people think about but as you've seen as I can't do
this, debug code thing, it's kind of willy-nilly in all over the place
and that's intentional, right?
It's like I don't want to think about how to make sure that this stuff
all lines up nicely.
Until I see the lining up actually start to click and it's starting to
get to that point now.
So things have to kind of consolidate down now that I, I see if you
will, I see the the
World view that the code is starting to take.
I like that debug buffer concept where everything is running out to
the buffer and then there's this collation process and that gathers up
data and profile together because now, those things can unify.
And we can have things that show us where we were in our profile, as
well as where we are in our data and those are together, and I'm
really liking the way that's coming together.
And so, as that starts to come together, more and more, that's when we
start to make the code more rigorous, that might be it.
Better name for it than clean to start to do some things where we're
not quite so confused about where everything is and how its lining up.
Smarter 37.
We've been on the debug code for quite a while.
How much longer do you think it will take before we
We are finished.
You never know with code if you have a specific deadline.
Where you're like we need to finish this by a certain time, then you
can always decide to cut things and you know scope it to a certain
extent.
But in terms of when you're just trying to work out a system and
you've you know, sort of
Going to spend some time to make this correct.
Then you never really know how long it will take to make it be proper.
Yeah and again, I really don't super love.
The fact that people get impatient when working on code like that.
You know, if it doesn't make good streaming, then, you know, I
apologize for that obviously.
But at the end of the day, this is really what actual serious
programming looks like, right?
This is what you actually expected to do.
And if you can't keep track of this in your head and make this be a
relatively easy, short tasks meaning, if 20 hours of debug code,
coding or 20 hours of coding, which is what this
Probably is.
Well, it depends whether you count the profiling or not.
If that's a lot of time to spend on code for you, that's a real bad
sign, right?
That should be, this should be, this should be like half a week's work
of your programming, right?
It should be something you don't even think about the amount of time
we spend on the debug code right now, should be a triviality to you.
And if it feels like a lot more than that,
if that's just because we only see them in our night, that's fine, but
if it feels like too much or like it's taking too long, that's I would
say, you really either you just don't want to be, you know, an engine
coder and that's fine too, right?
No, you don't have to be one kind of code or another, but if you're
serious about engine coding, this should you want to reassess that
mindset?
Like this should be a trivial amount of code work to you?
It should not feel like anything, right?
So I would say, definitely if
Is feeling like a thing for you assess whether that's just because
it's a stream or not.
But if it's if it's because of the amount of actual coding, that's bad
sign and you should try to figure out a way to fight that feeling, you
should try to figure out a way to invest yourself more in, seeing how
the code comes out and enjoying that process of getting it into good
shape because that's really crucial to being good.
Programmer is enjoying that process of refining, it and working it,
it's sort of like, you know, if someone asks you to model a cup out of
clay and you just like, stick your
Finger in it and go here.
It's a cup and then another person spends like several hours.
Making this like beautiful cup.
It's like you want to be the second guy you don't want to be the one
who's like.
Well I'm just going to drink out you know.
I just want to see some water in it.
I don't care like what it looks like, right?
So it's really important to like get that mindset right.
Steven last.
Do I ever use data breakpoints?
I find them helpful.
When some value is changing somewhere, but you're not sure where, yes,
I do.
The reason you don't see me use them very often on stream is sort of a
holdover from the fact that when I was originally learning to program
pretty much probably for the first 20 years or so, of programming data
breakpoints were extremely unreliable or didn't?
Like they either didn't exist in some you're using, or they didn't
really work reliably, so they were very unreliable way of debugging.
And so I'm used to debugging without it, if that makes sense and the
fact that I'm used to debugging it without it means that often times,
I probably do something by putting code in and running it that way
there by simulating a data breakpoint like this thing that I did just
just a moment ago, right?
This thing right here, you could have done it with the data break
point, which is presumably why you're asking the question.
I tend to just type it in because that's like my reflexive habit.
Now, data breakpoints are much more reliable now than they used to be,
since I again, don't use them by habit.
Unfortunately, I can't say it.
Maybe they still are a little unreliable for all.
I know, I don't know.
They might be 100% reliable though, so I wouldn't have to discourage
anyone for using them.
Be aware that they have been unreliable in the past and if you start
to see that they are like, don't, you know, obviously don't
But assuming that you are finding that they are reliable for you.
They're totally fine and they do exactly what I just did.
So there, you know, it's not because I think there's something wrong
with them, it's really more.
Just because for most, you know, most of my formative programming,
they simply didn't work.
Does the design of this debug system differs significantly from the
debug systems, you've worked on for other games?
Yes, this is completely different from any debug system that I've ever
worked on ever before.
In fact, it looks nothing like any debug system I've ever written or
used for that matter.
Although, there probably are some out there that look like this.
It just I haven't used them.
Chronodragon, not super hot topic, feel free to skip.
How do you treat you'll Handles in your own code?
Are they handled by the asset system or by something else?
That depends quite a bit on the circumstance?
It's a tricky question.
I think probably if you don't mind saving it for down the road, when
we do the renderer, it would probably be better to do it at that time
or you can post on the forums.
We could, we could do it there, it's a bit involved.
All right.
I think I've got all the cues here.
All right, since I said, I like I said, I have to kind of go, I'm
gonna call it and we'll be back to sort of condense this stuff down
tomorrow night.
Anyway.
So you could always ask questions, then tomorrow night stream is
special, like I mentioned before, it will be starting at 7:00, but
then it will at 7:30, after the Q&A, instead of being off the air, it
will switch over to a debate with Sean McGrath he wanted a devil's
advocate for something that he's been.
About lately, which was free to play games.
He asked me if I would mock debate him, there is nothing on the line
for this debate.
It is not actually me versus him because I have no skin in this game
whatsoever.
He does.
He is working on a game and is thinking of making it feel free to
play.
So there is something on the line for him, in some sense, which is
that this is sort of a Proving Ground for his ideas or a way of sort
of sounding them out.
There's nothing on the line for me.
Other than the fact that I tend to not really like the free-to-play
model particularly much so I suppose.
Me arguing against it is sort of a position on principle or something
like that but like I said, in general, I actually don't have any real
horse in the race.
I am simply a sort of acting as the general argue, ER, since I like to
argue for Sean, so that he can kind of Bounce those ideas off, and
maybe explore them a little bit himself in ways that maybe he didn't
think of because he didn't have an adversary there to challenge some
of the
Casey was thinking about it.
I think it'll be pretty interesting.
I don't know, but that's what we'll be doing tomorrow.
You should be able to just stay on handmade hero and watch the stream
at 8:30.
If all goes, well, technical difficulties aside and I also I assume
Sean will try to stream it on his Stream.
So if you tend to watch Sean stream, you hopefully we'll be able to
watch on, they're either both of them would just hopefully, we'll
we'll both sort of work and, and you can watch on whichever Channel
you normally watch on.
Again that's boring technical difficulties because you never know with
computer is trying to run Skype and OBS.
At the same time is probably the microphone fight of the century.
And and you'll no one will hear anything and they'll be no audio and I
won't be able to Sean, and he won't hear me.
And you won't hear him, and you won't hear me, and he won't hear you,
hearing me and everything else, but if we can get it to work, I think
it should be pretty interesting.
So hopefully, you'll stick around tomorrow night for that.
That's all for.
Now, as usual, if you want to follow along at home with a me here, you
can always pre-order the game.
It comes to the source.
Code.
So if your decision that check out handmade here at or can also check
out the tweetbot which feeds the schedule and calls out special events
like the one we're doing tomorrow night.
So you can always keep comprised of that.
We have a patreon page.
If you want to survive video series we also have four arms.
You want to ask questions or view, attitude, episode guide, other,
good stuff like that.
That's about it until tomorrow seven again, pacific daylight time
tomorrow.
Hope to see you all here for that, until then have fun coding and I'll
see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.