Exactly that.
Welcome everyone to handmade hero the show, where we build an entire
game from scratch.
No libraries.
No engine basically, for two reasons, one.
Because it's a lot of fun and two, because it is pretty educational.
I think.
I'm I've always been very happy that I knew how all of the stuff
worked in at a low level for all of game development stuff.
Even when I did stuff that wasn't low level, I was working on projects
where, you know, we were using libraries or that sort of thing.
It's just
It's really good.
I feel like to know absolutely everything that happens in the full
stack of a game because it just makes you a lot more powerful.
And basically, you know, it lets you have complete control when you
need it.
It lets you know, that no matter what happens.
You can always go down to the engine source code.
You can always go make your own stuff.
If you need to work around something, because you kind of know how
everything works instead of having to sort of be beholden to whatever
someone else makes, and having to live with, whatever problems might
exist in something that you're using.
So I'm having a blast so far and we
We got to what I think is the much more fun part of things.
Because basically, we spent basically, I think we estimated it was
about 25 hours worth of time working on a winter day to prototyping
layer because we've basically got to give ourselves some Services.
We can use, we got to write those ourselves that can do things, like
display bitmap and play sound and get user input so that we have
something to make our game on, but we have done that.
And now we're we are in a position to make our game.
Now.
We haven't actually done the shipping version of the of that platform
layer.
Obviously yet.
We only did just a prototype version so it's not
Not the a fantastic platform or anything, but it is plenty good enough
for our purposes of getting the game running and developing the game
to a certain point.
So with that in mind today, I would like, to actually start doing the
game development proper, which I think is really cool, because that's
going to be a lot more fun than monkeying with win32.
So, if you pre-ordered the game on handmade hero dot-org, you should
have gotten a link, an email with a link in it, that email link will
allow you to download the source code.
Road and the source code comes as a giant zip file, which has every
day's state every day.
The source tree like sort of snapshot at every day.
So, if you want to follow along, we are on day 27.
So, unzip Day 26 has source code because that is what I am starting
with.
You always start with the previous day.
So unzip Day 26 is and you will be starting exactly where I am
starting right now.
Okay.
So first things first, let's go to the little diagram.
I did a bunch of talking yesterday, just to kind of get everyone on
the same page about what
Texture is, and that sort of stuff.
And today.
I want to talk very briefly, you know, maybe spend about 10 minutes
here, talking about how we go about doing architecture.
Because yesterday, I basically just tried to get across the fact that
a lot of the things that typically happen with with crazy, like
upfront architecture, and all that stuff is is basically like a
confusing and perhaps non productive way to go about things.
So I kind of wanted people to understand what sort of the you know,
What the basic concepts of architecture are and sort of like how to
approach it.
How to think about it, frame it in your mind, but we didn't actually
do any architecture yesterday or any sort of work like that and I
didn't really explain how we would go about that.
So today, I guess I wanted to take the first part of the stream to
kind of explain that part of it and then start doing it.
So basically, we'll sort of say what we're trying to do and how I
think about the process of doing it and then we will do it.
And then this will be a process that continues for like essentially
the entire length of the stream where we're constantly sort of
Think about as we as we do more code, how it's lots and the
architecture, how we might watch, change the architecture, how we need
to revise things, that sort of stuff.
Okay.
So I want to introduce a concept here.
I guess, if you've, if you've watched my lecture on API design, then
you kind of already know this, but I'm just going to say it here on
the stream because a lot of people probably haven't seen that.
So what I want to talk about here is just a mental model for
understanding the way that projects develop over time.
And what I want you to do is, is put on your imagination cap.
You're a little like a fantasy and Matt like unicorns running around
and trolls under bridges.
And I don't know a wing and Pegasus certainly obviously those would be
there as would a griffin.
Imagine that that fantasy land that we call project.
State space and I know it sounds a little fancy.
But all I want to do is basically just have a geometric
representation.
Just some, totally abstract representation of basically saying you are
here on a project.
So days, zero of a project which is essentially what we're at here.
We made a prototyping layer itself contains.
So we can pretty much think of today, as like, the starting point for
the actual game, the the like the engine of the game, and the game
itself.
That is what we're starting today.
So,
You can think about it as like kind of this product State space as a
like you are here kind of a thing where we have absolutely nothing.
We have nothing right?
And in our imaginary project State space.
There is some like n State up here, right?
Which is what we will ship.
Right?
So there's some you know, imaginary geography of projects and the and
the state of the project what's in it and how it's designed and all
that stuff where we start somewhere and we go and
And we end up somewhere else.
Right?
And that that somewhere is the Finish.
That's that's the full on completed project.
Now as anyone who's ever done a project knows, but of course, some
people have our may be doing products of the big problem for the first
time on this stream, but you know, a lot of people probably have
experience with some kind of programming if they're following the
stream, you know, that it doesn't look like a straight path, right?
It's not like you start with nothing Day Zero, you know, this is this
is day 0 of your project and this is day, you know, who knows what 700
or something, right?
And you're talking about, okay.
I just it's a linear path every day.
I do a little bit of work.
I get closer to that ship State and I'm just done.
That's not
All how projects tend to go.
If you think about how projects go, there's often.
There's a lot of this sort of thing that happens, right?
Like, you know, you know, there's there's all sorts of Meandering and
you go around and and you know, you you make changes that maybe get
you even further away and that was a mistake and you kind of kind of
come back and that sort of stuff and eventually you end up at the ship
thing, but it's not this, it's not this perfect line of sight at day
0.
You often don't even know what this thing looks like, right?
You don't you don't have a perfect vision for
Actly.
What the code?
You're going to ship?
Looks like you have nothing and you have a vague idea of what it
probably looks like but if it's a project of any complexity if it's
not, you know, hello world.
You probably don't really have an idea of what that actually looks
like.
So what I want to talk about this diagram is just how to
conceptualize, what you are doing.
Every day in that drive toward ship, as far as architecture is
concerned and even to some degree as far as just individual pieces of
code are concerned because really the code in the
Texture, you know, it's a it's a blurry line.
They're like What's the architecture?
What's the code?
They're really just what level we're talking about.
Whether we're talking about the fine grain, or whether we're talking
about the coarse grain of how the coop code operates.
So it's almost a Continuum at some level.
So what I want to talk about is the fact that when you are at a
particular time, it doesn't have to be day.
Zero could be any day, like we could be somewhere a little further
along, you know, maybe we're on day 100 or something like this, right?
At any given point.
You can basically think about what you're
Going to do as picking, you know as driving towards some new location
in the state space and you don't actually know where this is.
You don't know the actual ending location of this, right?
You just have some vague notion and maybe you maybe you have a range
you're like, oh, it's I think the thing we want to ship kind of looks
a little bit like something that would be in here.
Right, but you don't actually know where that final destination is.
So, you know, you might aim for something over here.
And then when you start to kind of get towards it, maybe you realize
that what you really needed was was the thing that you end up shipping
right in it.
End up back over there, whatever.
Right?
So you don't really know this like a vague idea of what you're trying
to get to.
You have some conceptions in your head.
But especially if it's something that you haven't done a lot before
you don't really know and this could be a very wide and amorphous
thing, you're aiming towards and you'll it kind of shrinks down over
time as you get closer to it.
You can start to sort of see.
Oh, you know, it looks it looks narrower and narrower where I'm
actually aiming for but at first it could be very broad, you know, you
may have no idea really where that final piece of what that final
structure looks like.
So on any given day, which are sort of doing,
Doing is you're doing like a dead reckoning and going?
Okay from where I'm at now and given the code that I'm trying to write
right now, whatever it is, like maybe I'm trying to upgrade the object
system because it can't handle some of the things that we wanted to do
in the design right now.
Like it or it's really inefficient.
We're trying to optimize who knows.
So we're trying to do something and what you're doing at that point
when you sort of sit down and start coding for the day, is you're
driving towards some new point, right?
In this state space, your kind of like going
Something depending on what you decide to do that day.
And then when you finish that that step, however, much that takes your
going to be at a new point and you're gonna do the same thing again,
you're going to choose to do something and that something drives you
in a direction.
And in that way, you kind of build this path that sort of meanders
towards ship and the better you are with your dead reckoning.
The the sort of less wasted work, the less switchbacks.
There are on this path.
The less, you know of that kind of thing is happening, but that's
basically what's going on here.
So the reason again that I think that just to sort of cement what's
going on here, the reason that I really like again, compression
oriented programming where we just kind of like write code see how it
works at the low level and then sort of Loft it up into designs as we
go and not try to do a whole lot of pre-planning it specifically
because pre-planning assumes, you know what this thing looks like
already, you know what the code is going to look like?
Because think about it, if you have to do a bunch of planning on how
the code will go, the
Way you basically have to say, I know where this is and I'm making the
waypoints along the way that we're going to go to for the design,
right?
If you don't know what this is.
There's really no way to do these, right?
So, usually, what happens when people do a lot of upfront design, is
they pick totally wrong stuff.
They're like, okay.
This is how this is our path, guys.
It's going to be great.
We just go to cure and then we go to here and then we go to hear the,
we go to here and then we ship it, right?
And when you what you do is you end up going to, they're doing it.
And you do it and you're like the whole way you're like, oh this
doesn't feel right.
Okay, things are getting pretty janky.
And by the time you get to hear your like this is a disaster like
this.
This code is awful.
It's we're fighting the design of the architecture of the whole way.
And either you end up shipping something that's kind of crappy and not
even close to what probably would have been optimal or at some point.
You realize your mistakes and you try to start course-correcting,
right?
And so upfront design is basically putting in way points on this map.
But you're putting in waypoints.
Would you don't know the destination?
And that just doesn't work, right?
It just plain doesn't work.
So, what I want to encourage and the way we will be approaching
everything and we have already been approaching things this way to a
large extent.
Although, like I said, it was kind of cheating on the platform there
because I've done it so many times, I kind of know what the end result
is.
So I do really know what this is so I could kind of set waypoints.
And like I said that
Just isn't an interesting architectural problem because that's more
like just cut and pasting from your brain.
It's not even waypoints.
It's just I know what it is.
I'm going to write it.
Right.
So the much more interesting architectural thing in the skills that I
hope to show and encourage you to develop over the course of the
stream is what to do when you don't, when you haven't written the
thing before, that's the hard thing.
That's where the real architecture work exists because if you've
already written it many times before and you're totally know exactly
how you want to do it.
Then that's that's not.
Architecture, that's just, you know, it's regurgitation.
And it's good.
I mean, it's great to go into something and go, you know what?
I know exactly how to do this.
Just bam.
There it is, right.
That's always great.
But that's not being a code architect because you, you were the code
architect.
You were doing that before.
When you learned how to do it.
Right?
And so what I want to talk about is is or about when I talk about what
we're going to constantly, sort of focus on as we go through the
stream and have opportunities to do.
So, is focusing on how to actually do this process, much more
efficiently.
And again, what I want to encourage is not to set those bogus
waypoints, not to look too far ahead.
So what we are constantly going to do is we're constantly
Going to basically a take a sort of an Explorer and then lock
approach.
We're basically going to do the opposite of that way point instead of
picking a set of things that we think are the directions to go right?
Which may turn out to be wrong head of time instead.
What we're going to do is we're going to take our space wherever it
is.
We're going to explore around the space and we're going to see what we
find in that space.
When we find something that we feel is along the path to
Ting.
We will lock that in and make that our new location and then we will
repeat the process.
Right?
So we're constantly going to, I don't know why that just went crazy
there.
So we are constantly going to look at things as this two-stage process
that repeats itself over and over which is start from where we are, do
Explorations that are just us writing.
Whatever code comes to mind for the thing that we need to implement.
So if we need a tile map today or whatever it is, we're just going to
try just flat coating and tile map with
No thought to the architecture whatsoever.
It's going to do whatever comes to mind.
We're gonna explore and see what works in the code.
When we find something that we are happy with that.
We think worked pretty well.
We'll lock that in.
We'll call that the point that we're going to start from now and then
we'll start on the next problem.
And in that way, what we hope to do is basically assume that there is,
you know, sort of a gradient along the path to shipping that you can
learn to sense as you gain, good programming skills that you can learn
to sense when our
Architectures are good and bad.
And you can basically say that there's kind of this trough that goes
to shipping.
Right?
There's there's a like a Hillclimb.
You can do where you can basically say that like this just disappears
to be good.
When we look at the code and this is like, okay and this is may be
fair and this is like bad, you know, and and this is like
object-oriented over here something.
Okay.
I'm kidding.
I've drained people.
I'm sorry, you know, I joke at you a little bit there's bad and then
there's you know, just awful is over here, whatever, right?
And so, I guess what I'm saying, is that what we will assume is that
generally as you become a better programmer and have more experience
with code in general.
You will learn how to do this sort of sensing of where you are so that
you can path find to these things.
Even though you don't know the destination by doing an exploration and
accepting step, right?
Such that when you do architectures, that are new that you've never
done before for things that you've never done before.
You can still leverage all of the experience you've had doing
Other things to get you to a good point, right?
And so that's kind of the model.
I want you to think about in your head.
I don't think you can do way points for an architecture, you've never
done before.
I've never seen it work, and I just don't think it probably does.
But what you can do is once you've had some experience programming,
you can learn to sense the gradient, you can learn to sense where you
are, and you can constantly kind, of course, correct to stay in that
trough of good design all the way to the end, so that you minimize the
degrees out into the bad area.
Has that you would have had if you know you predefined your Waypoint
to be here and drove towards it and just had disaster Zone the whole
time, right?
So this is how I want you to conceptualize what we are doing.
As this project State space.
It's got a channel to good.
Right?
And our goal is to constantly sense.
Whether we are in the channel too good.
And when we sent ourselves going outside, it we just going to try to
course-correct back in and make sure that we stay there.
Okay.
Now, of course, this is all hypothetical.
This is all just my experience of programming talking.
No one has ever proved or analyzed any of this thing.
Nobody whoever does design ever proves her analyzes anything,
unfortunately, so we have no formalism to back us up.
But neither does anyone else?
And so all I can say is in my experience.
This has been the truest thing I have ever found in terms of how to
conceptualize developing the structure of code set with that in mind.
Let's get started on things.
I'm going to quickly say, sort of what our goals are for our game.
Engine at this point.
I'm just in general because since you guys don't know what the game
design is, and I do now is time for me to Carnot sort of say a little
bit about that.
Now, I want to save a lot of the game design stuff for a little later
on.
I'm I want to keep most of things a surprise but
But what I will say is, I'm going to talk a little bit about sort of
how the game looks and plays so that we can understand what we are
building in terms of an engine to support him.
Right?
So I've mentioned Legend of Zelda in the past and I am a big fan of
the original Legend of Zelda.
And I mean, like, original original.
Like the one that was on the Nintendo Entertainment System that you
played with one of those little controllers that looked like a
rectangular.
Rick, I'm a big fan of it because it basically just dropped you down
in a world that had a lot of richness and interest in it, but it
didn't give you any constraints or dictates about what you were trying
to do.
There wasn't like this, you know, little fairy that shows up like
there aren't later Zelda's, who's like, don't go into that Forest yet
because you're not ready to go there.
First, go help the blacksmith.
Smite his, you know,
Make his Smith is little sword and you go to the blacks with a
blacksmith select.
I would love to submit the sword, but I can't because I don't have any
water for my wheel and then the fairy pops up and goes, we should get
him water for his.
Like those kind of Ruin Zelda for me, and I can appreciate the fact
that game design is obviously a personal preference.
So there's probably lots of people who like that sort of thing.
And that's fine.
So, I don't want to say that that's bad.
And like I said, I only need a game designer.
So I'm not trying to, I'm not trying to tell you anything about that
from any kind of objective standpoint, but personally, that really
ruins the Zelda to me, and I don't even play him anymore, because what
I liked about that very original one, that very first Legend of Zelda
was that sort of
That feeling of exploration that you get when you really just have no
idea what's coming next.
And you know, you have this freedom to explore and think about what
you want to do on your own.
And so that is the sort of core concept that I want in the game
design.
That is the main thing that I'm going for.
And I want to kind of, since Legend of Zelda is a very classic game
written in the classic style there, you know, obviously it was a Kart
game on a very limited system.
I think it's kind of appropriate for handmade hero to look to that as
kind of a model.
What I sort of want to do is go.
Okay, what would we do though?
If we wanted to kind of modernize everything that goes on in one of
those kind of old games where I have the you know, Sprite guy, who
walks around a tile map and walks off the top of the screen and walks
onto like another screen and can explore the map and so on.
What would we do?
If we want to Modern all's Nuys, all of that stuff, but still stay
true to sort of the feeling the positive feelings.
Is of exploration and, and sort of the no hand-holding approach and,
and all that sort of stuff.
So, basically, that's the game design that I've been working on in and
that, you know, again, I'll be sort of talking about more later as we
start to talk about actual specifics of game design, but what it
implies for engine is, I want a bunch of things that are going to
support me in, making that kind of experience.
So what I do want to do, right, is I want to have a way for us to
base.
We make a tile map kind of a thing.
Right?
I want to be able to make screens that are like the old Zelda that
have like a tile map on them, right.
Where we have stuff like, you know, this is a water Thailand.
This is a land Thailand.
This is, you know, shopkeeper or whatever and everything, you know,
and this is grass or something.
I don't know, right?
I want to be able to make that kind of a game where it has that feel
of the old sort of Classics, but I don't really want to have to do
tile.
All mapped Graphics, right?
I don't I feel like tilemap Graphics are possibly something that
doesn't really need to be preserved from the old days.
I think that that was mostly just because that's what they could do.
I don't think that necessarily needs to be in a modern game design for
the game design to be good.
Right?
I do however, think there's something perhaps important about the, the
tile map design like
Player understanding that they are on a tile map.
And that like if this tile is blocked and this tile is blocked and
there's a pushable thing here that, you know, they can push it this
way and it ends up here that like leads to important, understanding of
puzzles and it like it simplifies things in the mind of the player in
a way.
That's kind of important.
We're if I just said, okay, scrap the whole tilemap thing entirely and
we're just going to have a free floating world.
You know where everything is just at X random X and Y position.
So if there's something to push, it's here.
I just don't feel like that is worked as well.
I feel like there's something concrete and gamey that gets lost.
When you try to go a little too far in the direction of completely
generic.
So basically what I am going to try and design our engine to do is to
create a playable game on a tile map, but where the tile map is not
rendered directly as a tile map.
Is rendered as something a little more flexible than a tile map that
just Vans take sort of the shape of a tile map.
But so that you don't see like, big obvious repeating tiles, where
it's like, okay, here's the like one tree that we had and here's the
tree again, right?
Or whatever.
So, something that looks a little more flexible, maybe even has a
little bit of smoothing around it.
So it's not 100% hard when I walk into these things, but that still
can preserve the properties of a tile map.
Where the gameplay logic is kind of operating on the tile map.
For a certain set of objects.
Anyway, like maybe there are some objects.
I mean, well we know there are because even the original Legend of
Zelda, for example, your character could move not aligned with the
boundary, right?
So pushable objects had to stay on the Tom app, but the character
didn't have to write and so we will allow certain things to just kind
of be free floating around as necessary and those will probably like
enemies and the main guy or whatever, but then we want to be able to
kind of have this concept of a tile map.
That's understandable.
The player so that they can see it, and we can base sort of gameplay
things on the tile map that are easy to understand for a player and
easy to execute, right?
So I want that, that is the basic thing.
They're going to be doing.
So we need to base the construct.
Something that allows us to have, you know, a tile map underneath,
right?
That can be rendered.
It has to have, you know, stuff that moves around moves on top, right?
Moves on tile map.
Oops tile map.
So we need those things obviously.
And so that's a very traditional thing.
But we're also going to do kind of like a fancy fancy renderer, right?
Or a fancy compositor.
However, you want to talk about it.
We're going to get fancier here.
So these, maybe a little traditional, these will be, like, basically
upgraded versions of exactly.
The kind of stuff you would have seen the snez in as Gamers.
And as game where will, you know, will probably do a better job than
they could have because they had a lot more limited resources, but
This part will be a complete departure.
So when we get to how we're actually gonna present the visuals will go
way, we'll go in a totally different direction than they ever would
have or could have for that matter.
So we want to do that.
And what I would like to do is, I would like to make this game totally
procedural.
So, I want everything to be generated by essentially, a an algorithm
of some kind that will produce totally new worlds, every time.
So I want it to be the case that essentially, for the most part
nothing that we do will ever be like a hard-coded screen.
There will never be like screens, you know, unless they're just like,
the starting screen or the ending screen, you know, some very specific
screens.
That we want to hard code for some reason for the most part, every
last little thing should be procedural.
Such that when you play it you are you are seeing new a new map every
time that you go in.
Okay.
So why do that?
And when I say that also again have I learned anything?
Let's see if I've learned anything.
I want to try and clear out.
Just just this one region will see if my if my working with krita
yesterday has paid off at all.
Can I can I do, like just draw around here?
Hey, we're getting pretty good here.
People.
Wouldn't you say I think?
So.
All right.
So what I wanted to talk about in addition to that, that, that should
hopefully be pretty obvious what we're trying to do here, right?
So nothing, you know, nothing particularly confusing about these
goals, maybe this, this fancy render.
A thing may be pretty confusing to implement because we're kind of
maybe blazing a little bit of a new Trail.
There were some of the things that I'm thinking about trying to do but
on the
You can hopefully this is pretty understandable.
We want to totally procedural tile map, based world.
We want stuff to move on top of the tile map and interact cleanly with
it.
We want a renderer that's much fancier.
So that the thing doesn't look like a town map.
It looks you know kind of more organic and nice and pretty but that
still understandable as a time after the player so that they can
understand puzzles that are based on the time a poor things like this.
Okay.
So the totally procedural part
I would like to basically maintain the sort of Zelda style
conceptualization of a game world.
So I would like to have an Overworld map, right?
Which you walk around on and then I would like Dungeons that are in
there.
So I want to be able to generate something that essentially produces
some kind of Overworld map with these tile.
Without of you know tilemap portions out of which you're viewing a
small one.
You know, you're viewing this one at a time and when you walk
Off the end of it.
You come on to the next one.
Right?
I want to be able to do that and on certain locations on here, right?
I want you to be able to enter something that will then be a dungeon
map that, you know, has another map that you kind of walk around on
that sort of stuff.
Now, I'm not sure.
Exactly what Tak I want to take, but I believe.
So I'm going to put this up here because I this is what I would like
to try first of all, because I don't think there's any reason not to.
So I'm just going to write it down here.
I want to try and make a completely consistent space.
However, so rather than this map and the dungeon map being separate,
essentially.
I want them to all be the same.
So, when you come here, right?
And they're there won't be
Be like this dungeon that's, you know, tons of screens long and why
that just happens to all occupy like one space on the map.
It'll actually be something more like you go down, you know, a ladder
or tunnel you go down into the dungeon through the entrance and the
dungeon is actually like underneath.
So the dungeon tiles actually are underneath the actual real map.
So these are like happening below, right?
And it could be many levels deep.
Let's say, but, you know, they could come back up.
So there could be like another entrance to it here and
If you went into this entrance and followed it through and came out,
you would actually be in exactly the same space that you would think
you would be on the world map.
So I kind of want I want to kind of make the space, be 100% spatially
consistent.
So there's never like any kind of a unrealistic shrinking or expanding
of what a tile is tiles.
Should always be the same size and they all have to actually fit where
they are.
And so the only time that I would want to break that is if we had some
kind of magical thing we were like,
It would, if we were going to break that, it would have to be inside
of some magical context where it was clear, that it was supposed to be
broken.
Right?
And so, furthermore.
I want basically no Dimension limits.
This is a pretty important one to talk about.
So, basically, I don't want to have to say that the whole map or
something fits inside, you know, something that's that's 256 screens
by 256 screens by 256 greens or something.
It's like a giant voxel array or anything like this, right?
I don't want there to be a dimension limit.
There could be a dimension limit.
That's just impractical.
Like, say if, if it was, you know 4 billion by 4 billion by 4 billion
or something.
I'm okay with that.
If that's the ACT, if that's a limitation, because we know that, the
player could never walk across four billion things.
So, I'm okay with basically a limitation, if it's never something we
could ever possibly hit.
It, but I'm not okay, with the limitation of something like this.
So we're not going to do anything where we'd have to like, pack
coordinates into something that would only fit in a 32-bit integer or
any of us.
We're not going to allow anything that would restrict our ability to
basically create worlds that are as large as we want with the
Restriction.
Being that it's okay.
If we know that a single continuous line from one end to the other is
longer than a player could ever hope to walk in, you know, in less
than a week.
Continuous play or something, right?
So if we can determine that that I'm okay with that limitation, but
I'm not okay with any limitations that.
Might actually constrain how the world gets generated in a practical
sense.
Okay, so I think that's mostly everything.
We need to start going in and working on the actual game.
I don't think there's much more that I need to say about it.
But basically, you know, this is this is a pretty straightforward
concrete specification of what I want to do.
I want to make it so we can generate the world.
I don't want them to be really any constraints on how we generate the
world so we can generate giant worlds if you want to and and
No, do whatever we want, especially this procedural, you know, if we
want to, for some reason, say, please generate me this, this insanely
huge world, we could do that.
So I want to allow that and I want to be a consistent space.
So there's that, you know, there's a, everything kind of fits
together, and I want them to kind of based on an underlying tilemap,
but just doesn't render like a tile map.
I want to be able to have a bunch of things that happen on top of, you
know, on top of that tile map.
And then I want to be told a procedural now because this
This is a well both because I want this in the game.
I think it'll be cool as a general thing.
But also because of, this is a series about teaching you how to
program complex architectural issues.
I also obviously, and we don't need to sort of get into this now
because it'll be a little further down the road.
But eventually the core game engine.
I want to support like sort of an insane level of combinatorics.
And what I mean by that is all of the things in this world.
Old, whether their tiles or the things that move on top of the tiles,
whatever is anything that's interactive in any way.
I basically want it to be extremely combinatorially rich, such that
anything, that you can any property that you can imagine about that
thing can be dealt with, in a consistent way that interacts with other
properties.
So, for example, you know, if there's such a thing as a Monster, who,
Has a brain.
Any monster that's like actually has a brain of some kind, right?
That's walking around or whatever.
And there are things that have effects, like, fear or whatever, right?
I always want you to be able to if there should be a reason why the
monster got hit with something that should cause them fear.
I want them to become fearful and this should work entirely through
the pipeline in the sense that if for some reason we eventually give
you something that's like a scepter that allows you to cast spells on
a tile in the environment and the scepter can be
ODed with gems.
And this gem is a fear gem, then if you load the fear gem into the
scepter and you cast the some, you know, you do a cast with the
scepter onto the tile, it should put fear on the tile and if the
monster walks into the tile, you should become fearful.
And if there's cross effects, we're like anybody who's both fearful
and weak suddenly.
You know, runs away immediately or something like this, then that
should happen to him.
If he was a creature whose head was already had weakness, those sorts
of things.
Right?
So we're going to be focusing on combinatorics a lot because they're
the hardest thing to program in a game engine by far.
And so, not only do I think they make for very interesting games.
But I also think that they're going to make for a very interesting
programming.
And so watching me have to deal with
A lot of those Comet or X I think is is mostly what I want to have
happen in the later stages of working on this game.
And so so we're going to focus on that a lot, but we're not probably
going to get to that real soon.
This is we want to try and focus on generating worlds that we can walk
around in first just to make just to get ourselves up and running and
so that we have something to use to drive our renderer design first,
but once all that stuff is working, then we will kind of move on to
the actual game development.
Game design side.
Things.
And this, this will really be where we're spending.
Almost all of our time will be on here.
Okay.
So, how am I going to approach this?
Like I said, Remember the diagram that I drew earlier today where
we're in a space and we're going to try explore around it.
So I know that's what I'm going for.
I know that this is, I have this in my head.
I'm like I can sort of see the game that I want to make, right?
But I have no idea what the code looks like.
At the end.
I've never made even a Legend of Zelda clone let alone.
Own a completely new game whose design is, you know, very different
from something like Legend of Zelda that just happens to be in the
same genre, which is what we're making here.
And certainly Legend of Zelda, had none of that combinatoric stuff
really, so that's all totally new as well.
So we just have a ton of stuff that's totally unknown at this point.
And I don't have a plan for how I'm going to write it at all and I
don't even have a plan.
I don't even know how I want to do this.
Tilemap stuff.
I can you know, I again have a lot of experience.
Lots of different things.
So I could brainstorm right now.
A number of ways that we could imagine implementing tilemap stuff and
all that sort of thing.
So that's certainly true.
But I do not have I haven't written like 50 games that are like this
before and where I can sit down and say, look, I know what works.
I know.
It doesn't work.
You do it like this.
I don't have that for most of the things in this game.
And so I am in the that position that I was talking about the original
diagram Day Zero.
We're not sure where the shipping code is or what it looks like,
right?
And so I'm going to do
Exactly.
The thing that I said, we're going to start here on Day Zero with
nothing.
We're going to start by exploring around the space by just looking at
what it takes to implement basic versions.
How do I get a rectangle moving around on a tile map?
How do I make a tile map?
That's got rectangles are like colored by, you know, what kind of tile
they're supposed to be.
How do I move from one screen to the next screen?
And like change, which one?
I'm on.
Let's just go try it.
We'll see what starts to emerge and we will let sort of the
architecture work itself up from there.
So that each time we saw.
Get something that feels like it's working pretty well.
We'll say.
Okay, that is you know, how will lock that down?
All right, so that's about it for the drawings.
I think.
Let's clear that out.
And let's start, we've got about a half-hour left roughly and so we
should be able to do that.
Probably not a whole lot, but we should be able to do a little bit of
coding here to get ourselves started.
So I did remember there was one thing that we never passed to the game
Loop, by the way, that we wanted, which I don't know if we actually
need to use it at all today, but we might, I wanted to mention that.
I don't know if you remember when we were doing the win32 coding.
Did like the target game?
There's like a Target seconds per frame thing that we computed this
thing right here, which is how much the game was going to update by
every frame.
We never actually passed that value to the game.
Like, the game has this game, input thing, and, and we even have the
to do insert clock values here and we never did it.
So, we want that thing, right?
We want, you know, Target s for frame.
We basically want s to advance, right?
Right over time.
Step or over update.
We basically want to pass that value there.
Because that is the thing.
That's that's actually going to let the game be run on any frame rate
you want.
So I'm going to go ahead and just pass it.
Like I said, we've already got it.
We did all the work.
We just, I don't know.
I probably just because we had so much stuff.
We were looking at, you know, and doing audio and video and all these
sorts of things bouncing around.
We probably just, you know, I'm sure it just slipped my mind.
I was like, you know, because we like I said, we computed it we put in
the timing code and
We never actually bothered to, to ever actually do it.
So for now we're just going to always pass it the same one.
So where's our game input into here game input?
Okay.
So basically I think all I really need to do is just say new input,
Target seconds per frame.
Sorry turns our fingers that so that that we will just pass that in
there and that's, that's all I really wanted.
All right, so I think that's the end of
I think that's the end of the things that I was reminded that I was
like, we never actually put that in there and we need it.
So what I would like to do now is just take a look at what we've got
here and sort of clean this out a bit because we have a bunch of test
code in here that we don't really need anymore or rather.
We don't really want to run anymore because we're, you know, we're
currently generating some weird gradient thing.
For those of you have been following along we were doing like a test
pattern on here.
Right?
So, we have this sort of, we have this thing going on and that's not
all something that we
Actually want anymore.
So, we certainly don't want it to be playing that sort of tone or
anything like that.
So I'm going to actually say that this is debug game output sound
right now, and well, I guess I can even just leave it at that.
It is because we had a switch in there.
So first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and say from
now on let's just output zero.
So it should be completely silent.
And also, I suppose, since we're no longer working on the platform
layer.
I can actually do I believe I can actually just do this from now on,
right?
I can just do, leave the game running and then recompile and it should
just magically work.
Yeah, perfect.
So anyway,
The hot loading, dll thing is so nice.
You never have to do anything.
It just it's just always there and my little guy is still moving
around.
So everything's good.
Yeah, there we go.
Not if I drop the controller, it's not good.
Come back.
Mr.
Controller.
What happened?
Oh, no, everything is falling over here on the stream.
That's no good at all.
That's no good.
All right.
There we go.
So all I really need to do here is get rid of our gradients.
So the render weird gradient call that we were calling.
These will just no longer call.
We'll get rid of that guy.
And so if I, if I, oops, if I do that well, so I don't like this
warning because we're going to have unreferenced local function.
So I think I'm going to turn that guy off.
If you guys don't mind 4505 because I have functions that I don't call
and that's just, you know, that's just part of life.
You know, I might want to call them later.
So we're going to say w 4505 going to say that that's gone too.
Yeah, so now in theory, yeah, we're not drawing anything.
So you can see that the back buffer is not cleared anymore.
Now that I made that change.
So I get rid of the that thing we've got the to render players there
and looks like, we're still rendering a stuff for Mouse testing.
That's what those were up there in the corner.
These guys right here.
So we don't need that anymore, either.
That's that's not.
Important at all.
These guys are sort of showing us the location of.
Yeah, so we don't really care about that.
We don't need any of this stuff.
This is all just test code.
Looks like.
So we have our read entire file stuff.
We don't need any of this at all.
Yeah, this this just looks, this just looks entirely not necessary, so
that can go away.
All of this stuff can go away.
See if there's anything in my
Same structure here.
Game State.
Yeah.
So these things don't need to be there.
None of this stuff needs to be there at all.
And then we've also got.
So, yeah, I'm really all I'm doing is just cleaning out all the stuff
that we had.
I can leave this.
This guy in here, obviously, but maybe I'll move them down kind of out
of the way just in case.
Just in case we want to render a weird gradient.
Again.
I don't know, maybe we don't even need, maybe we don't even need that.
Let's see anything else.
So we got the
the render player call will probably use that because we're turn that
into a rectangle call.
That'll be good.
So we have our initialization thing here.
We have our controller reading which
I guess we're just going to kind of get rid of these things entirely.
Let's see and we don't need any of this or that.
So this is this is really where we're at.
I think if I'm not very much an error.
So let's see here.
This is now not going to be updated either.
And that should be good to go.
So gamestate tone hurts.
We'll just go ahead and say that, that's it.
It's that that is just hard locked to 400 or something.
I don't know.
So now we have something that does absolutely nothing.
We are back to square one, right?
And and what another thing that I guess, I'm not sure exactly what we
want to do with but I should probably think about just in terms of
when we're starting to do testing here.
I should probably think about what resolution we want this game to run
in.
With 3D games.
You don't really have to think very hard about what resolution you're
going to run in because everything is always resampled, right?
You're mapping polygons, you're mapping textures on a polygons and
that sort of stuff.
So you don't really have a need to think about what the target
resolution is other than to think about how dense those textures,
probably have to be versus how closely they're going to be seen and
stuff like that.
But for this game since we are doing a 2-D game, we may want
especially for background elements.
We kind of
The elements to be drawn so that they're the size that they will
appear on the screen.
So that the pixels will be crisp in the cases where the artist wants
to kind of be very specific about what it should look like or things
like that.
So I guess what I would say is we probably want to think about what we
want to run on and I would say we probably want to do like a 1920 by
1080.
So, you know, a 1080p Target resolution for the game and for our
software renderer since that's going to be a lot slower.
Lower than using the GPU.
We would probably want to just, you know, do like half size or
something.
Well, we're getting things working.
But basically what I'm thinking is is that, you know, we probably want
to take 1920 by 1080, right?
That's the that's the resolution.
If you think about like an HDTV, right?
What we would probably ship this game on for people who play on a
normal setup.
They're probably going to play it on a 1920 by 1080 by 60 her.
It's display, right?
So when we're running on GPU, we would probably be targeting to try
and hit that right?
A nice 60 frames, a second.
Full 1080p HD, sort of a graphics system, right?
So for our purposes, since we're going to be doing our own renderer
and it will be much lower than a GPU.
Obviously.
I was thinking maybe we just do essentially what amounts to eight
times less than what this does, right?
We do.
Hurts for our, you know, for this this for the non GPU version.
This is the software version.
We do half of each of these, right?
So this is actually going to be what is that half of 80 sets Nia?
That's, that's 960.
Is that right?
960 by had the calculator up and then I and then I closed it.
Why did I do that?
So let's see here, right.
I always check my math because I'm horrible at Mental Math.
Yeah, 960
And then and then oops, why did I why did that turn into a?
Why is this a help me?
Why is it a okay.
I guess the cursor was just wrong.
So half of this guy obviously is 540.
So 960 by.
540 is a is what we're shooting here by 30 Hertz.
So in terms of the number of pixels per second, we have to fill right?
This is half.
This is half and this is half.
So ideally
This would be 18, the work, right?
So you could think about it as we're writing a 8 times slower.
We're targeting something 8, times slower than a GPU and hopefully we
can make that work for our software.
Renderer.
If we can't, it's no big deal.
Because again, we don't have to ship the software under, it's for
educational purposes.
But you know, I mean we're going to try to do some optimization and
stuff.
So I feel like that would be a reasonable goal to try and hit on a
modern CPU is if we can manage to do something.
Comparable to the GPU.
That's just downscaled by half in in all the dimensions in width and
height and in time, right?
So 960 by 540 I think is roughly what I might like to do.
Let's just say that it is for now because I don't have a better idea.
So 960 by 540 by 30 Hertz were already at 30 Hertz and I believe we
just have a thing in here where we can just basically flat out say
what the actual size of the thing is.
I think it's just that
That's it right there.
So if I want to, I can say we're just past the game, at 960 by 540
display.
That's what it's always going to be and we'll just work on that for
now.
All right, so I believe that is something that I will have to restart
the app for because that's in the win32 platform.
Layer if I'm not very much in in error.
So we'll go ahead and compile that will run it.
And there we go.
So, there is our, there is our our Target, our Target play field size
is about that big.
Right.
Okay.
So first things first, in order to sort of get things working.
I am going to write some kind of a rectangle function where you can
pass a color right, and draw a rectangle on the screen.
And that rectangle will be, you know, properly clipped.
Like I won't crash if I go outside of the of the region or whatever,
so I want to basically make a simple function keys to draw a
rectangle, just so I can have some way of drawing something on the
screen.
As we start to build things, so I'm going to take this render player
call, which basically was drawing a rectangle and I'm going to turn it
into something that is officially trying to draw a rectangle.
So it's going to be something that looks like, you know, draw rect
tangle and draw, a rectangle will take that off screen buffer that's
supposed to drive to and it will take some integer coordinates.
I guess.
I'm you know, what?
I'm going to say that it takes floating Point coordinates.
Because I would like to always be able to take floating Point
coordinates for reasons.
We will see a little later.
But basically, when we start to cover render a topics, a little later
on, you'll see why I might want to start having things, always be in
floating point, because we'll actually be able to do SUB pixel
positioning of Sprites by using, you know, basically interpolation of
colors and stuff.
So, I'm going to say that we're going to pass, you know, an x, a y.
And I think for starting off.
Let's do Min X Min, y Max.
X, max wide.
And there's an interesting thing that happens with rectangles here.
And this is the sort of thing that I'm awful at.
This is the kind of thing where you really want Shawn Barrett to do a
stream or something.
Although the last time I said, we should ask them to do a stream on
software synthesis.
He steadfastly refused.
So, maybe I'm barking up the wrong tree, but there's, there's things
to be aware of and we'll kind of go over them in the render stuff
more.
But I will probably even have to do some
Fresher stuff for my own self for them because there's all these sorts
of complexities that come into play.
Basically, you have to understand that any time you're working with
very specific things like rendering there is sort of the precise
definition of what you want.
Actually matters quite a bit.
So if you think about it,
Like if this is my pixel grid, I should probably make a thing.
That just gets us a pixel Grid in the future.
If you something, I remember to do, see a pixel grid that we can
quickly get to pixel grid.
If you think about something like a pixel grid, right?
Then how you specify how you want.
It filled is actually kind of complicated because let's say that I
number these locations, right?
Like a standard thing like you learned in math class, right?
1?
2 3 4 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7.
Well, it's pretty easy for me to talk about a specific pixel at that
point because I can just say well whatever the two numbers are.
Here's the X.
Here's the why.
So 0.
Comma 0.
Is this one, you know, and 3 comma 2 is this one, right?
Or something like that?
That's not so hard, right, but when you start to say, I want to feel
something in you end up with.
Little bit of confusion because when I specify the pixels, am I
talking about them being inclusive or exclusive?
If I tell you to fill from 11 to 3 3, right?
So if I tell you to fill from this to this, am I talking about filling
these and not the the outer bound or am I talking about including that
outer bound?
Right?
And that may not seem like it's very complicated to understand and get
right and get
Right is kind of a confusing term here.
There are.
When we get again to the rendering stuff.
I'll talk a little bit more about in detail.
What are the things that are reasons for that?
You would care about things in terms of rightness, as opposed to just
whatever you want it to be things.
Get a lot more confusing when you start to allow stuff to move around
sub-pixel on the grid.
So for example, if I have a Sprite and at the Sprite is 3 pixels by 3
pixels.
Well, it's pretty obvious.
What would happen if the Sprite is is lined up exactly like that,
right?
But if the Sprite isn't
End up exactly like that.
Let's say the Sprite is slightly off center of the pixels, right?
You have to understand.
You have to have a good convention for understanding exactly how it
writes into each of these pixels, how much it contributes, and how
this is specified, right?
Because now, if I was to specify that rectangle draw of draw from 32
to 65, well, you didn't actually want to fully draw all of these,
right?
You were talking about only draw, you know, only contributing a
portion of the color of each of these sorts.
Of things.
And so there's just a lot of kind of finicky - that goes on there.
So I just wanted to kind of point out that this is a this what I'm
doing this draw a rectangle here, there's a lot of things you would
think about if this were actually if we were really going to do a draw
rectangle call.
That's our final draw a rectangle call.
I'm not going to do those.
I'm just thinking about purely.
Okay.
What should this?
What does should this do?
Just to get us something roughly that's working.
So I'm going to say that.
Basically, it does.
It does a rounding, right?
So it'll basically it'll take them in X in the Min y.
It will round those two, an integer.
Should it rounder show truncate?
I'm going to round, I must say it roused to integer ill around these
to an integer and then it will fill up to but not including whatever
the final one is.
I think that's roughly what I'm gonna do.
So basically, if you were to do the tile map, you would do like you
would fill from 10 to 20 if they were 10 pixels wide.
The next one you would fill from 10 to 30, right?
So, that they're inclusive that way.
I'm not going to do ten to twenty two like 1922.
30.
And the reason that I'm not going to do that is again because of that
floating point in this.
Really.
If you think about it, it makes it a little bit difficult to talk
about what happens in between 19 and 20.
If you start to think about these things, I've actually having
fractional values.
So I want to make it so that you can pass two rectangles that are but
perfectly, right.
So I want to make sure that
The the rule for how you feel them, doesn't draw over that.
That common, you know, in this case doesn't draw over 20.
So that only one person is responsible for filling thing, 20, right?
So, I'm just going to that's just the rule that I'm going to use for
this.
But again, this is a debug once it doesn't have to be perfect.
It can be whatever.
Alright, so basically we've got this is this is our real version of
these.
We've got our real men's in our real Max's and I want to give us
something where we can basically turn those into integers.
So I am going to do arm in X here is going to be the real men ax but I
need to round it.
So I need to round a real 322 an inch 32, right?
I want to I want to I want to
Out it.
We haven't written that function yet, but we will.
So got my Min acts.
I got our Max X bar, Max y.
So, I'm going to go ahead and do those.
Let's see their ex ex.
There we go.
So Min ex real manex been why real men watch them is rounding all of
the values, right?
Once I have these values, rounded one thing you will notice is that
These could be anywhere and the buffer we are going to again that
buffer is just a chunk of memory that we write into where each 32-bit
value in the buffer is a pixel color.
So what we need to make sure we do is we can't ever right outside of
the legal boundary of the buffer.
Right?
So what we want to do now is we want to clip essentially to to the
actual screen.
So if this is the screen, right, and this is 0 0,
Simple coordinate system here.
Right?
And this is the width and the height of that screen.
If you pass me a rectangle that's like that.
Well, what I want to do is I want to just fill the actual part that we
can fill and never right to the part out here because the part out
here would be invalid memory.
Well, in the way, we've got a bitmap set up this part would crash
attempting to write to that part with just flat-out, crash and
attempting to write to that part would actually that is actually back
here, right?
Because you think that
The memories laid out in a stripe, right?
It's kind of looks like this.
So going backwards off the left Edge, Wraps you around to the right
Edge on the previous line.
So anyway, so yeah, so I just want to clip it and you can see that
clipping a rectangle in that sense is very easy because basically, all
you're doing is saying, if the x value is less than that boundary,
whatever the left side, boundary is you just move it to the left side
boundary because the thing that it produces is still a rectangle, so
you're basically just
Getting and making sure that you push the outer extents to the outer
sense.
And then the, the your, the minimums get clipped 20 and the maxims get
clipped to the width and height, right?
That's all we really have.
To make sure our rectangle comes out fully clip.
So all I really need to do here is say that if Min X is less than 0,
then X is going to be equal to 0, right.
I'm just saying if it if that rectangle extended before the leftmost
side of the screen, then we just go ahead and and make it not do that.
And then similarly for the Min Y is exactly the same.
And then for the Max's, I need to do the same thing as well.
The mac sex, if that's going to be greater than this time.
If that's going to be greater than the buffer.
And I believe the buffer has the width in it.
So we know what, what size it actually is.
Yeah, there it is.
So with if it's greater than the width than it equals the width,
right?
And if it's greater Loops, that's good.
And if it's greater on the Whi, same thing, if that's greater than the
height that it equals the height, right?
All we're doing is clamping those values to something valid, right?
And
What I want to do here again, when I'm doing this, you'll notice that
I left them.
I left it so that it was actually right on the boundary.
Now.
Normally, that wouldn't be a valid pixel, right?
Because if the width is, let's say 8 then 0, 1 2 3 4 5 6 7, the last
valid pixel, I could fill his seven trying to fill eight would right
off the end of the buffer.
Yet.
I am allowing this to be equal to 8.
Essentially if the buffer was eight wide.
Why is that?
Well, it's because I just said before.
That I'm not going to write the rectangles going to fill up to but not
including that final row.
So that's actually okay, if that makes sense.
All right.
So now in order to fill this guy, I'm going to need a color to fill
them with, right?
And so in order to pass the color, I'm going to pass a real value
again.
R, g, and B, and we're going too fast.
So I'm going to go a little bit over to the community.
I just want to finish this one function since we're already here, but
then we'll keep it will keep it brief.
So, what I need to do now is I need to.
Well, you know what?
That's not true.
That's not true at all.
I don't have to do the color.
I'll just use white for now.
And then we will do the color tomorrow.
So that way I won't go any further over time, so that'd be good.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I'll just put to do in here color tomorrow.
They'll be the first thing we'll do.
So then, all I need to do is Step through the pixels.
I know that I want to start.
I don't know why this is by X and then.
By why?
Probably because that's where
Things.
But if you think about the way memory is arranged, our exes are
contiguous, and our wise are not.
Right?
Why is have to step by this pitch value?
Whereas X is do not have to do that.
And so what I would rather do here is I would rather step it the other
way.
I'd rather step it.
Do you think?
I'd rather step such that we were not that we were touching contiguous
pixels one, right after each other and then only doing a jump to the
next row.
I don't want to do it by Rose because it's going to be more friendly
to the cash.
Obviously.
It could be more friendly to touch things that are
Next to each other.
So that yeah, so I'm going to go by wise first and then my exes
because that happens to be how things are lined up.
So we're going to go from in X and work until we get to, I'm sorry.
I mean why until we get to Max, why?
We're gonna go from in Acts through to Max X and then we are going to
write the pixels.
So the first pixel that we write obviously is going to be wherever the
buffer starts in memory.
We going to have to go by however many bytes per pixel.
It is we're going to have to go that far over forearm in X because we
want to start it that far in and the same forearm in y.
So, we need to pre Advance the pointer to our to our pixel memory.
We want to
Advance the pointer so that it's pointing at the top left corner of
the rectangle, right?
So that it's pointing if the rectangle is here, right?
We want to, we want to take our pointer which starts at here on
memory.
We want to point the pointer right there, right?
We want to point it at that point.
So we need to add however, much it takes us to get down to this row,
which is the pitch, which is how much you add pero times.
However, many rows we wanted to go down, right?
Which is the minimum y.
So we go down that many rows and then we have to go over by
However, many, we pixels how many bytes per pixel, there are four the
number of pixels that we are over at X, which is min why I services
mean X.
So we need to kind of bump after we move down to the start of the row
that we start on.
We need to go over to get the start of the column, right?
And that's where we're going to start.
Then from there.
We just fill the pixels when we get to the end of a row, we go down to
the next row, fill the pixels, right?
So what we need to do here and again, this is not how will we won't do
anything like this in the final render, but we're just making a debug.
All that simply that does a simple fill of a rectangle.
So basically, what we need to do is we need to go ahead and fill our
pixels here.
So there we go.
So this I should probably call it the row pointer since that's what
that is.
So this is the row pointer and it will advance every time we advance
and why we would go down and then we will go down one entire row and
then the same is true for X.
We were going to get our we write pixels.
Each pixel is 32 bits.
We're going to write
it to 32 bits at a time.
So now, we have our pixel pointer is going to be equal to our row
pointer.
We're going to cast it up to you in 3 2.
So we can write you in three twos at a time.
We left this one.
As a, you ain't ate because we are adding the pitch is in B, and we
know that C++ and C always do a multiplication for you.
So we don't want it to multiply by anything here.
When it's doing that addition.
We want to just add that that raw B value to the pointer.
So, okay.
So we go in here.
We write to the pixel.
We write the color and I believe that's mostly all we really need.
We do need are rounding function.
So for are rounding function, to be honest with you, I don't know if C
has ever introduced a proper rounding intrinsic.
It probably is.
We should look for it.
But for now we're going to implement it.
The old-fashioned way, we will talk about how to do the rounding.
In fact, I'll put it to do in here to do intrinsic.
Okay.
So this is passes in a real 32 value and it wants to do a result value
that comes out.
So what we if we actually just cast it, right?
If we actually just cast a real 32 and 32, the default thing that c
will do, is it will truncate the value, right?
So what it will do is it'll just Lop off the fractional part entirely.
So if you think about what that does on the number line, right?
If I'm if I'm in here and here's my number line here is zero, right?
Is one two - one - two if I'm in here, right?
And I wanted to round this value.
Here is point five in the middle, right?
If I'm going to round this value.
I want it to go to be one because we all know that, you know, when you
round you take which which side of that dividing line you're on and
you round up or down, right?
Well, I don't want to do that because I want I'm sorry if I truncate
I'll go down to zero because truncation.
It removes, the fractional part entirely, and this was 0.75 or
something, right?
You know, who knows what that was in there.
So, just get rid of 75.
You left of 0.
I don't want to do that.
I want to round up.
So what I can do is I can change truncation to rounding trivially by
just biasing the number before I truncate it.
So for example, if I add .52 the number right, that will push up the
the anything that was in this half.
It will push it up into here.
Right.
And anything that wasn't here will get pushed up into here when I
truncate, then all of the stuff that was in here that got moved to
here.
We'll still truncate back that will still around back down to 0, which
is what it should have done when I do the truncation, but anything
that was in here will be moved up to above one.
They'll be 1 point something and then when I truncate will go back
down to one, which is what I wanted, which is rounding up, right.
So basically by just rounding and truncation for simple values like
that are pretty easy for me to deal with because I can just do
That plus 0.05.
Now there's a lot more to thinking about these sort of things than
just that but for now that's going to have to suffice.
And so that's an easy way to turn that simple.
See truncation operation into something that roughly does rounding for
the cases we care about.
But we'll have to talk about that little bit more when we have time
because there's a whole set of topics to talk about with floating
Point values and rounding all that sort of stuff.
But there we go.
That's our draw rectangle call.
So let's just before we go to Q&A.
Let's just test to see if it works at all.
We could
See if it like, just full-on crashes or anything.
It's got to get out of the way of my head there.
Okay, so let's just see if we can draw something.
That's like this, right?
Let's see what happens if we get anything at all.
Hello, are you?
That's what's going on here.
It was already running.
I
There we go.
So there's our rectangle and I'm going to go ahead and see if it
crashes, if I move it to something.
That's out of bounds, right?
So there we go, and it looks like that looks like it would probably
cause I'm not clearing the screen currently.
So, you know what, I could use this to clear the screen if I could
pass a color, we could pass a color really quickly just to try this
out.
We could pass just a color.
That doesn't get handled properly, right?
I could do see.
This floating Point color tomorrow.
So I'm now I'm passing the color in so I can do something where we do
like a clear 20 first.
In fact, we could clear to something else we can clear to like some
hideous purple and then draw something equally hideous, the cyan in
there and so will clear the purple draw cyan.
So we are 0 0 and we said what was the the well, I guess we could just
say whatever the buffer with and buffer hide our
Like that.
Let's see here.
These have to be floating Point values, but I think other than that,
we are good.
Let's see.
Where is my game that I close the game?
I need to learn to stop closing the game.
So it looks like that's not quite right or is that quite right?
Did I actually, oh, I didn't, I still use that.
So I want to, I want to change to that.
Does that work properly?
Doesn't look like it.
Does not look like it to me.
Think.
I might have a bug there.
It's weird.
Having bugs and things.
I would not normally have bugs in it stuff on the stream because,
like, I don't know.
I don't know if I'm ever going to quite get used to that but I will
say, it's been difficult programming on the street because I tend to
make careless mistakes because I'm talking that I don't normally make
and it makes it sometimes disquieting for me to program that makes
sense.
So, let's see here.
So that looks like it's maybe sort of working.
I don't want to say that, it definitely is.
but it does seem
To be doing roughly correct.
I'm going to spot, check it just in case because again, I just kind of
saying that in there really quickly.
So I have my Min ex, real manex real man.
Wide real max.
Real max y Min, X-Men, exponent Bubba, blah, been X is less than 0
Min, Y is less than zero, and that's all good.
Should be fine.
Max s is greater than buffer, width looks looks at that.
Outright to me.
Oh, there it is.
See that?
That's not actually anything.
We were seeing, that's totally buggy.
What does this rectangle functional later?
Looks good in X.
Yeah.
XX more buggers.
Is there any buggers?
Come out, come out wherever you are.
All right.
Well, I think we're going to have to call that for the day.
Looks like it's sort of working.
But again saying that in pretty quickly would like to test a little
bit more just make sure we don't have any stupid mistakes in there.
Let's try something way off the screen.
Hey, we didn't crash.
That's good.
How about way off the bottom?
Also didn't crash try some Ridiculousness.
No crashes.
So, okay, so I'm pretty happy with that.
So let us go to the Q&A.
I would say don't want to be too much overtime.
I know that going over time.
Makes it hard for people.
Try to catch up and stuff because they have long streams to watch.
So I try not to do that.
Looks like that is good enough for today.
I am happy with that that basically gets us in a position.
Tomorrow.
I've explained all the things that I want to do.
We have a way to draw a rectangle.
So tomorrow I should be able to basically start building tile maps,
and we'll see where that goes.
So totally good.
Again.
It's always a little tough stopping the stream because I'm always
like, well, now let's build the tile map.
Wait till tomorrow for that.
For now.
Let's go to the Q&A.
Basically, if you want to go ahead, and I am pushing the Q&A button
now, so if you want to, go ahead and ask your question, please keep it
to stuff.
We did today or stuff.
We have done in the past, and I added some new features to the
question.
So, from now on, you should be able to just put capital Q: and then
whatever you want, and I should see it.
So you can try that instead of senior ettore.
Never been tested, but hopefully it'll work.
Let's see.
D mitsuki says, what is that fatal link area?
When you compile the code am I going to die?
No, so what happens there is if you remember the way that we did the
build, we build two things, we build the game code as a dll that we
can hot load and then we do the platform layer as a separate thing.
The platform layer is what's always running in the debugger.
So the debugger has the executable locked and we can't write to it.
So this succeeds
This first line succeeds, but this line will fail and we don't care
because we're not actually changing the platform layer.
We're basically only ever changing this code.
Now, when we want to change the platform layer, we have to stop the
app.
But until we change the platform layer, we don't have to what this
fatal error is telling us that it's, hey, I did the recompile step for
the platform layer, but I can't write to it.
And we're like, that's fine.
We don't care.
We only want you to build the other one.
So that's it.
That's all that is.
What sort of things do you think are good to include in a portfolio?
When looking for a job.
I'm a student looking for his first job and would appreciate any
advice.
So, I guess I'd say is that come back during a pre stream, basically,
like for 10 or 15 minutes before the stream starts.
I answer questions that aren't about the code that we're doing.
So if you want to ask that question, come during a pre stream and we
will and I will answer it.
Randolph.
Q: does this work?
Yes, it does.
High technology Road creature.
I see you.
M GARP.
See you, too.
So this is good.
We are good.
Gary Johanson says, thoughts on refactoring.
This to be all functional programming.
Well.
I'm not a huge fan of doing things dogmatically, and I feel like
refactoring an entire game to be functional.
Programming is a bit dogmatic.
Now, if you're just doing it as an exercise, then any programming
exercise that suits, your fancy is a good exercise, right?
Even the worst possible programming methodology.
Like, I really want to write this in in lots of crazy C++ inheritance.
If you're just doing it to see how it goes.
That is a great idea, right?
If you're asking, whether I think,
A good idea in terms of productivity, you know, I'm probably going to
say no, right?
And so thoughts are refactoring at all to be functional programming.
I'd say well, why are you doing that?
On the other hand, as I've talked about in the Stream in the past?
I do think that functional programming is good to do in places where
it makes sense.
Basically, like there's a lot of things I tend to push code towards
functional when I can, I don't try to go all the way in a dogmatic
sense, but the Moores side effects I can get out of the program.
In various places the better because it's cleaner.
And it's easier for me to see what that code does.
And it's easier for you to reuse that code in places.
Because I know that, as long as whatever I pass, it is all that it's
going to need.
It's very easy for me to make it nice and self-contained.
So I do try to make things relatively functional in places where I can
but that's really all I can say about that.
I don't feel like there's a need to be overly functional in.
Your programming style though.
You should be as functional as is warranted and no more.
Okay.
How would you do compression, programming with big teams?
Will the game be random, but always with the same seats that everyone
gets the same world.
Also, will the dungeons change when you revisit them.
All right.
So there's a lot of questions here.
First of all compression, programming with big teams.
I kind of answer that or ready.
If you want to take a look at on Molly rocket / KC.
I actually talked about that.
I don't remember exactly where it is because
It was at the end of one of these working on the witness ones where I
was talking about.
That sort of stuff.
Let's see.
I think it was in this one.
Okay, so if you go here, if you go to stream, underscores.
They're a 20-day HTML.
You will notice that I talked about that in here like second after
last week's article, multiple strings.
It's just that for some reason compression area would only work with
small numbers of people, perhaps one or two, but it's somehow not
possible to do when working on teams.
And so I kind of explained here why I don't really necessarily even
understand why there's a difference between how it works on teams or
not.
So hopefully that can sort of answer that question a little bit.
My feeling is that basically?
You know, you just have whoever is working on a particular piece of
code at the time is doing compression oriented programming as they
sort of get the design together when they are happy like that,
exploration process that I was talking about when you're sort of happy
and feel like you've gotten somewhere, you take the interface on the
outside of it and you export that to your team.
You say here.
Now, you can call these things.
I've gotten to a place.
I'm pretty comfortable with, right?
And that's really all there is.
It's really not that hard and it doesn't really change anything.
Whether it's a big team or a small team in my
Do you think writing structs and Associated functions for things like
vector to and color would be would be good to cut down on boilerplate
code and our show better intent in the code yet.
Well, so we will be doing those again.
It's premature to do right now because if you imagine somebody coming
at the stream who doesn't know what a vector or color struct is, and I
just start writing those.
They're like, why did you need that?
Right?
And so what we're doing first is we're writing everything in the
exploratory way.
Just writing it first and then looking to see what patterns emerge.
And those will guide us in how we make our our utility classes and I
really want to emphasize that.
That is almost always the right way to do it.
It's almost always best to write the code explicit first with no
fanciness.
And then look at what emerges and pull that out words.
That's the compression oriented programming model.
And that's the model that works.
Now some of us have programmed been around the block so many times
that we just know what we would want in a color struct, for example,
and that's fine.
So if you have written it so many times, you just know exactly what
that's going to be.
You probably already have an h-file anyway, and you just grab it and
use it, right, but I want to show the process.
Where when you
Not quite sure yet.
What a color structured have in it or where you're not, quite sure
yet.
What a vector to should do those sorts of things.
I want to show how we arrived at them.
So we will never be prematurely making a struct.
We will always be building our utilities from the ground up so that
you can see how I do it and how I decide what to do and where to put
what and at what times?
Are you going to use linear texture layout or something fancy?
Like a swizzle tile, layout nested tiles for writing that on, Swizzle
on the right to the screen?
Let's wait till we get to the renderer to talk about stuff like that.
If C didn't exist, what language would you use?
Probably would be it as assembly programmer.
I probably have my own tool set for.
Assembly code probably and honestly, I'd probably be a better
programmer if she didn't exist by now either I never would have
figured out that I like low-level programming and and would have just
been some crazy, you know python programmer, who knows what or I would
have found the right way to do things and made my own sort of stuff on
top of as mm.
I probably should do that these days to be honest with you.
I thought about it a couple times.
Because I feel like, I feel like my Assembly Language knowledge, is
kind of weak because I've always had sea, and because I kind of came
at a time when programming the whole thing's an Assembly Language just
simply wasn't done anymore.
So,
Yes, at handmade hero.
Also works now for questions at handmade here at senior Tori, and Q:
will all work.
We have a crazy filter.
Where can we find out additional information about engine
architectures?
I have no idea.
Again, since I don't spend a lot of time reading introductory material
these days because I'm so old and crusty.
I don't have a good feel for what's available.
When I was little and learning this stuff.
There were no books on engine architecture.
There were no books on games pretty much.
I think like the first books on game architecture that I know of that
came out.
We're like, really, really awful and came out in like the 90s or
something.
When I was already 16, 15 16, something like that.
There were good books on like, Graphics programming, like, Bruce are
tricks, like micro computer Graphics displays or whatever that book
was.
There were some books like that, but there weren't and game engine
architecture books.
So I don't know.
I've never even read a game.
Architecture book eyes.
That exists now about know if they're any good.
Do you envision the game world to be generated as you go and stored in
memory on disk to save the state?
Oh, I forgot.
Sorry.
I forgot to answer.
One of the questions from before.
Let me remind you that someone said, will the game be random.
But always with the same seeds that everyone gets the same world and
will dungeons changing your visit them who knows like those are
decisions.
We can make a little later on.
What I would probably like to do is make it so that
maybe that you can export like a seed.
So you can say, here is the get, here's the game state.
If someone else wants to play my game State, I can send it to him an
email or whatever and they can load it.
Something like that.
Might be nice.
Dungeons won't change when you revisit them unless they are supposed
to.
Like I would like the world to feel consistent, so they probably won't
randomly change.
But yeah, there's some stuff I want to do with the game design that
makes it so that it's not quite.
It's not like if you're thinking of like binding Binding of Isaac,
where there's like a seed number that gets printed that won't work at
all.
Because there's something
Is that I want to do that that have that make that not actually be
enough information to regenerate the world.
So now back to Johan over stats question.
Do you envision the game world to be generated as you go and sort in
memory on disk to say the state is
I believe it will be generated in a perhaps, in a background process.
If we can't get it generating fast enough to generate just sort of in
an instant.
Because I don't want the have to wait for a generating screen.
I don't want one of those screens like, you know, when like Don't
Starve you're sitting there and it's like, you got to wait for it to
generate your world or whatever.
I don't want that.
So we probably will have to move it to a separate thread, but it will
basically all be generated at startup, but I just might try to overlap
that with you walking through the first screen or two so that you
don't have to stare at a loading screen.
While the world gets generated, but we probably won't have to save it
to disk, because it probably should never be large enough to have to
save to disk.
I mean, if you think about it, modern computers, have so much memory
on them.
That basically, almost all of our memory footprint, is probably going
to get be taken up by like bitmap graphics and sounds and stuff.
Right?
So we're going to have plenty of room to probably just store the
thing.
So, we won't need on disc for the, for the game World out.
Think
What was the variable thing?
John Blow was referring to on yesterday's Q&A?
So you'd have to ask John, exactly.
But basically, he was kind of making fun of the entire process a
little bit.
I mean, John is very supportive of handmade hero and that he really
likes the project from what I can tell.
So he was not being disparaging of the project at all.
But I think he was just enjoying like asking a stupid question
basically, because he thought that was fun, and I thought it was fun
too.
So way back on the very first stream of handmade hero.
He like,
You like ask some question that was like, will you know, will you be
showing how to program the variable or something like this?
Right.
And I answered it of course and since then he's been asking that
question often and I try to answer it differently every time but yeah,
if you really want to know exactly why he decided to ask that question
the first time you'll have to ask him.
But I think he was just trying to like ask a stupid question.
And that was the stupid question that he happened to think of first.
I don't know if it actually, if the he could have maybe said the
function as well or something, right, but
Let's see.
Are you going to use fixed point?
No, probably not.
Because fixed points just slower for everything.
And so
I mean.
So in one sense, you might say, there are some things that I might do
that look like fixed point.
So I guess maybe I won't say no, but basically no.
That came out weird.
We made, we will do one thing that looks a little bit like fixed wine.
If I remember when we do it, I'll mention that.
This is what I was referring to when we get there.
But no for the most part.
We'll use floats because floats compute way faster.
How old were you in the picture on Molly rocket?
So you're talking about this picture?
I was 2010.
I think so.
I was, I was 30.
I was four years younger than I am now.
So, I was 34 on this.
This is me when I was 34.
Why do subpixels?
How is it better than just pixels?
That's an excellent question and I can't answer it in a short period
of time.
So I would ask if you could keep that in your head if you can remember
and you I will have essentially an entire stream explaining why that
is correct or sorry, why some pixel is better than pixel when we get
to when we start working on the renderer?
Upper and we're not just using debug rendering.
Basically.
The reason is because it makes motion look much more continuous.
I don't know if you've ever seen like, the difference between
something that looks like a perfectly smooth, beautiful scrolling of a
background and it like it like slows to a stop and it's just beautiful
and clean.
And then there's these other ones where they kind of jerk to a stop.
Like, as they get slower.
You can see it sort of
Do this thing?
That's because one of them was sub-pixel in one of those pixel.
So, we want the sub-pixel kind.
So it's perfectly smooth.
Even when it's moving very slowly.
Will I be growing a final dress beard?
My wife does not like beards so seems unlikely.
Okay.
So are you going to use, linear texture layer or something fancy like
a swizzle tile layout Nest until for writing, then on, Swizzle on the
right to the screen.
So,
basically, what I would say about that is
You're going to have to wait and see how we architect.
The renderer.
It depends what you mean by swiveled.
We will probably be doing some things that are not linear layout but
they may not be swindled in the same way that like a GPU, Swizzles
them, if that's what you're asking, but that will be largely driven on
what we find out when we start to do Performance Tuning.
So I'm not even in a position necessarily to say exactly what it will
look like.
In the sound code, we were trying to decrease lag.
But if we just output sound at the start of the frame, that is one or
two frames behind the input.
With the player really noticed a lack of one or two frames.
Probably not for our game.
No, I just want to work on a relatively complex, sound Loop.
That would be something you would do if you were trying to drive the
leg down, because it's just an interesting thing to do on the street
and some people out there may want to learn how to do that because
they may want to make, like, Rhythm games and stuff.
Where it's
Important what that lag is.
So I kind of wanted to go in that direction so that when we try to do
the shipping version,
Went through to sound layer.
We can actually spend a week or two.
However, long it takes actually getting that sound code proper and
actually getting the leg down to be as low as we possibly can.
So I'm interested in that.
I like that personally.
Also, I like the idea of exploring that so while we haven't gotten
there yet.
I think it's better to go that direction and see what's going on
rather than just doing the obvious thing of just writing with a ton of
lag and not caring.
How different would this initial rendering code be If This Were
vector-based?
Well, I mean, I guess I'm not sure what you mean by initial rendering
code, since all we're trying to do now is put debug rectangles on a
screen so we can start to get the game up and running and see what we
want from our renderer in terms of like services and architecture and
stuff.
The initial rendering code.
Probably doesn't matter at all.
Whether Vector, whatever.
If you're talking about what the actual eventual rendering code will
look, like, then obviously Vector based rendering is very different
from blind based rendering.
So it would look
Very very, very different.
Let's see.
Todd Punk says you cut me deep.
What did I do?
I don't even think I would, I didn't even see it.
I wasn't even answering questions from you.
How did I cut someone deep?
That's no good.
I didn't mean to Todd Punk.
Let's see.
Could you explain a little more about the drawback advantages of poop?
I don't mean hoop as in the dogmatic C++ way.
I just mean using Loop abstractions.
When useful.
I don't think there's anything wrong with using abstractions.
When they are useful, the thing more, there is a I might disagree with
people about when I think they're actually useful.
And that's an argument we could have on any specific thing, but it's
not really a general argument.
The general argument that I have with Loop is actually about poop
itself.
Literally not about objects and I've talked about this a little in the
past.
Basically.
I don't have a problem with the concept of an object, really, because
that's very nebulous and we could Define it to mean all sorts of
things and they're not all bad.
What I have a problem with is literally oop object-oriented
programming because that by definition by its very name means
orienting, the way that you program around objects and that to me is a
very bad methodology.
And the reason is because objects are not relevant to how your code
Works objects.
Like the way that your data is actually laid out is usually more about
performance than it is about the structure of your code.
Algorithms are what determine the structure of your code.
Code.
So if anything you want to be algorithmically or anti /, you want aop,
if you will, and I don't say algorithm oriented programming because
it's a little net.
What that would mean?
I say compression oriented programming because I like to think about
it, in terms of you have code that you wrote explicitly and then you
kind of like compress it down into something by pulling out parts that
can be, you know, that can be reused.
And so on much like a dictionary coder encoder would do.
And so I think it's very important to not think about code from the
object perspective and it's less about the code that you end up with.
And more about the process of getting there because I think going into
code with an object-oriented mindset leads to bad code.
Whereas going in with compression oriented mindset leads to good code,
and it's not about whether there are objects in the system.
When it's done.
It's about how you arrived at them, that determines the quality of the
end product, in my opinion.
I'm having a really hard time understanding parts of the sound code
from earlier in the Stream.
Are we scrapping that?
And can I wait until we rewrite it to get an explanation of how
latency works with sound buffers?
Yeah.
I mean, we'll basically if there's anything in the platform layer
right now, that's too confusing or you don't like it or whatever.
I wouldn't worry too much about it because I would we're not going to
scrap anything per se, but we're going to do a pass on it where we're
actually trying to make a shipping quality platform layer where we'll
go through everything in excruciating detail.
And so, you know, you really don't have to care too much about it.
If you don't want to it's really not.
It's really not a big deal at this point.
It's just as long as you're comfortable enough with it to like except
that it's playing some sound or something.
That's really all you need to be worried about.
So we'll have plenty of time to really drill down on that stuff.
Later.
Did I work on Neverwinter Nights 2?
What an odd question?
So, I definitely did not work on Neverwinter Nights 2, but I don't
know.
And this list is not all-inclusive.
So, I guess I'm not, I guess I'm not sure.
So they did use my code.
So they licensed my character animation system for Neverwinter Nights
2, but I didn't work on the game engine or anything, right?
They just use my character Nation.
This is the character animation system.
I wrote, and this is like a partial list of the people who, like, who
the games that it's in, or whatever, and they're, they're on there.
So, I guess they used it for something.
I don't know.
I don't remember what because I don't even know if I ever got any
support emails from them.
I don't recall.
In the red tail drawing code compiler.
Optimize the code on the basis of the pixel buffer does not Alias the
loop counters.
Or does the compiler?
Not know this.
Pixel buffer, Alias Loop counters.
Hmm.
Mr.
Casey does not understand the question.
So.
Just so we're clear.
Aliasing.
Only happens if the compiler thinks that you could have taken a
pointer to something that you are writing to with a different pointer.
And since these are defined entirely within the within the structure,
everything from basically, there are no mutable variables from here
that the compiler doesn't know about as far as I know.
So I don't think there should be any aliasing whatsoever because
there's only one pointer which is the pixel pointer that it's writing
to and it sees
Min y Max X Min, x max X.
It knows their lifetime.
They were here and no one could possibly have gotten a pointer to them
because it never gets past do anything.
So, I'm pretty sure the compiler would never have any reason to think
that anything was aliasing in here, but I'm not a compiler vendor.
So, you know, if you really want to know, compile and release mode and
see what the compiler generates that's the only answer pretty much any
time to a question like that is see what the compiler generates
because until you actually look what compiler generates.
Even if you're pretty sure you could be wrong because there could be a
bug in the compiler for all you know, right like even compiler should
have known it, may not so, you know keep that in mind.
Will it be doing anti-aliasing in the renderer?
Yes.
If you start going bald, when you cut off all your hair or comb over,
I don't know.
That's a good question.
I am kind of you can see I have a kind of a balding spot in the back.
I don't know.
I haven't really gotten to Bald yet.
So I'm not sure which would be more appropriate.
I have to try it and see.
Is it possible to explain the sub-pixel smoothness thing?
You mentioned with an example?
From example, video from other games?
Yes, but I don't probably know exactly which ones would be the right
ones at the moment.
I have to go find some videos.
Is this going to be similar to RuneScape?
I've never played RuneScape.
What do you suggest to develop games on mobile environment?
Well, that's kind of an open-ended question.
So maybe pre stream asked during a pre stream for that.
Let's see.
Can we use DirectX 11 while we work on rendering the windows layer?
I don't know what we'll use.
We probably wouldn't use DirectX 11.
If you're going to use DirectX.
We'd use 12 because otherwise, if we're going to use 11, we just use
opengl.
Will you add Pokemons to your game?
No, there.
We don't have a license.
Disparaging Python program.
Oh Todd.
I was not disparaging python programmers.
I'm sorry when I said crazy python programmer.
I did not mean that the python programmers, were crazy for programming
in Python.
I just meant that python is kind of crazy.
So when you're programming in it, it does kind of, you know, you're
doing kind of wild and crazy stuff, right?
It's like, you know, it's wild in there.
So yeah, I don't think people are crazy for programming in Python.
I think pythons a totally reasonable language from what I've seen.
It's not, it's a little too.
It doesn't quite give you the CPU control that I want in a language.
So it's not the kind.
Language I tend to gravitate towards but you know, I mean, I don't
have a problem with python.
I'm sorry.
If I do that impression, that's not true.
I don't have a problem with python or python programmers for that
matter.
This game featured dinosaurs.
Who knows?
Let's see when we get there.
How can I get a job working?
For some reason, I like you pre stream question.
Please.
Ask those in the pre stream come to a stream early and ask those
questions.
I'm happy to answer them.
I gotta go soon.
So I got a blast through the rest of these.
Well, that sharks with laser is on their heads.
Well, it certainly seems compelling.
I don't know what to see rideable animals.
I don't know about that.
How often do technical limitations and pack game design in your
experience?
It depends on the game.
And the Technologies, obviously, sometimes quite a bit, like you can
imagine games that were based around physics.
Sometimes affect.
The limitations, can really have a big impact there because physics is
sort of difficult to manage technology that often times isn't very
stable and so on.
So there's definitely times that that happens also rendering
limitations can definitely affect the game design.
So games where you're trying to do, like,
Aliens of guys fighting in a giant, you know, battle kind of
situation.
You can imagine things like this.
So there's there are times when it matters but on the whole I think
most of the time good game designers can work within the limitations
pretty well and bad thing.
Bad game designers can't I suppose but so I don't know.
I'm not a game designer.
So maybe you should ask John blow that question.
I guess is what I would say because he's the kind of guy who would
really have a very smart game design oriented answer for that.
Whereas I'm just a programmer and, you know, I don't, I don't want to
speak for design.
Hers on that.
We use member functions.
Probably not.
No.
Certainly.
If we did use them.
They'd be in a very limited case for doing a very specific type of
thing, which we'd see later, but probably not much of a function snow.
Let's see.
Well, the al-sham replace Navi and handmade hero.
I don't know.
I'd have to license the towel of Shame for the company.
I guess we could do something that's similar to the our shame, but we
can't literally put him in the game because he's, you know, he's a,
he's somebody's copyrighted work.
All right.
Let's see.
I think I going to have to end it.
There can show me example of how you were using the game memory.
Block?
Yes.
So guitar freak.
We will be using the game memory block very soon.
Just hold your horses a little bit.
Don't don't really hold your horses justjust rein them in slightly
because they will be off and running within two days.
Let's say so.
So keep the horses like, ready out of the barn, but hold them a little
bit.
And then, you know, by the end of this week, for sure.
Using that memory block.
Let's see here.
Didn't mean to hit, hold that down.
Maybe I'm missing something, but what if both men X and Max are lower
than zero, so the idea is, if Min X is less than 0, it'll get it'll
get moved to 0, right?
If Max X is also less than zero, then when we come in here and it does
x equals 0, x is less than some number less than 0.
It will never enter the loop.
So it'll never do a right.
That's how that works.
If that makes sense.
So if you look here, so if you want to see,
That an action, we should probably test that case.
Anyway, just in case there's something broken in it, but there it is
and you can see that it doesn't crash.
And the reason for that was just what I said.
It's like basically that you're protected because you only have to
clip one of the values and then it will automatically this less than
is essentially the clip for the other value that make sense.
If, if I was somehow able to acquire license for Pokemon to use, would
you use it in this game?
No, I'm sorry.
I would love to do something like that.
But the reason that I can't do that is because I want this entire game
to be released into the public domain someday.
And so everything in it has to be owned by me 100% so that it can all
be released.
So yeah, sorry.
Otherwise, I would love to do that.
Will the game have a moral social message?
Do you have someone writing for, you know, it will not have a moral
social message.
This is strictly about game development, not about game design or
narrative.
And so we are strictly based in the game design on stuff that we want
to program and that will be interesting to program.
So yeah.
All right.
I really have to go.
So thank you very much everyone for joining me on this edition of
handmade hero.
It has been a pleasure programming with you as always.
If you would like to get access to the source code, you can pre-order
the game on handmade hero dot-org and you will have full access to the
source code every night when I upload it, and that allows you to
follow at home pretty easily.
Also, if you want Sports video series, there is a patreon.
You can sign up for by pushing the little handy.
Dandy patreon button.
If you would like to talk about the game, the game, or the code, or
ask questions, you could do that on this news and forums link.
It also has a handy dandy episode guide on there that you can go to.
And it also has ports to other Platforms in the coding resources.
Section which will allow you to do things like run on Mac or Linux.
A lot of people community have done some amazing courting work
already, even though we haven't gotten there, they have, so definitely
check that out.
I have to run, I have an appointment at 10:00.
So I have to have to make my exit.
But thank you very much everyone for joining me on this.
This bright and early handmade hero.
I will see you tomorrow.
10:00 a.m.
Is the time tomorrow, and will be 10 a.m.
Every morning this week.
I definitely hope to see everyone there and I'm looking forward to
kind of making my first tile map tomorrow.
It's going to be a lot of fun, I think.
So, please join me.
And yes, thanks for joining me and happy coding.