Start recording.
Alrighty.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we code a complete game live on stream yesterday during the
priest room.
We had a question about.
Well, not really question.
We had a little quick talk about our Ellie and I decided there's some
stuff I wanted to show about how R ly and LZ are very similar.
So, I wrote One Yesterday, wrote a gnarly compressor, and a little
framework for us to use and we compressed our art asset files with it.
And, you know, as we showed yesterday, surprisingly even a really
really dumb Marley compressor actually compresses our art pretty well,
not compared to a really good compressor.
It doesn't.
But compared to no compression.
It was quite nice.
I think it saved 25% of the file size just from our little really,
really bad.
Our Ally compressor.
And again, I think that's largely because hey, you got a lot of alpha
space in Sprites, right?
And a gnarly.
Compressor can just suck all that up really easily, so it ends up
being pretty handy.
Anyway, what I wanted to do today, was just quickly for this session
show how, you know, a basic LZ compressor or style compressor
dictionary compressors really.
What I should say is not that different from an early compressor
actually, and for that matter, you
Can sort of just treat our Ellie.
You can basically get are really out of a dictionary compressor as I
explained yesterday.
How are really just kind of automatically happens in a dictionary
compressor, because it's just a look back of one or some number, and
it just will repeat that thing.
So, we kind of went over that as well.
Let me go ahead and do that.
Just show how that stuff works.
So now we have it in practice.
If you haven't watched yesterday stream, you definitely want to
because I explained all the stuff about LZ yesterday.
So, you're going to be a little lost.
If you didn't hear that, exploit explanation when we start here today.
Alright, so what we did is we built this little compressor right here,
it is.
And I'm going to go ahead and light on here.
I'm going to go ahead and build it.
I guess I also have to load my project file.
There we go.
And our compressor is very, very simple.
So you can see here is the entirety of the code for it, right?
And all it does is it starts out in Maine and
Loads.
It basically looks to see whether it needs to compress or decompress
the file.
It loads its first argument after that instruction, and then it either
calls the compressor or the decompressor.
And then it writes out, whatever.
The that thing spit out, if it was a compressor, it writes out the
compressed file, if it's a decompressor, it writes out the
decompressed file, that's all the main Loop does.
And then we just have up here are compress and decompress functions.
And right now, all they do is thunk through to the rle compressor
because that's what we wrote up here.
Right, so that's what we got.
So here's our early compressed.
Here's our, our LED compressed.
And one thing you will notice
And this is pretty much.
Universally true of every compression thing I've ever seen.
And again, as I said, many times yesterday, take it all with a grain
of salt because I'm not a compression person.
So, anything I really say about compression is is basic, is is
beginner stuff.
But you know, typically speaking whenever you look at these, what you
generally will see, is exactly what this looks like.
The decompressor for something is usually very simple, right?
It's probably not this simple.
I'll for more complicated compressors.
It's going to be you know, not quite so trivial but it's typically not
that big compared to the compressor which is usually to three times
its size.
And the reason for that is because usually D compressors.
The the formats for things are over specified and and just to give you
a little bit of sort of a feel for that
There are some compressors, such as like, entropy encoder is like
Huffman or arithmetic.
Encoders rants, encoders, or ANS encoders?
I should say those sorts of things that are extremely tightly
specified.
And what that means is that generally, there's only one way to encode
and decode a particular stream right now.
That doesn't mean there's not, lots of ways you could choose to
structure the encoding, right?
Whether or not it's adaptive, whether or not you encode it with
Bit patterns, whether how you're putting certain pieces of data, in
all that stuff is definitely flexible.
So, I don't mean to say that the compressors aren't flexible.
What I mean to say is, once you pick how all that's done, there's no
decisions to be made, right?
So, when a stream goes into the compressor, it's just churning through
it, and it spits out the, the, the stream on the other end.
And then, the decompressor does.
The same thing.
It takes in a stream turns through it and spits out the result, right?
And what that means is that the compressor and
decompressor very often for those.
Sorts of things are not that different in terms of size and complexity
because the compressor doesn't have to think, right?
There's only one way to encode the thing coming in.
So there's not a lot of thinking that the compressor has to do now
with everything else.
You know elzy and mpeg-4 or any of these other sorts of things.
Typically what happens is the compressor actually has lots of options
of how it's going to choose to encode an incoming stream.
There are many ways to encode an incoming stream that will all produce
the same output stream, right?
And that is why the compressor side often ends up being larger and
more complicated and involving more sophisticated algorithms than the
decompression side.
Because essentially the compression side is like an AI problem.
Almost right, it involves like search and you know, graph.
Reversal and things like this, often times to try and figure out what
it should be doing.
And what the most likely thing is that will produce the small-sized
signals the small-sized outputs.
Whereas the decompressor is just wrote.
The decompressor is still just one stream in one stream out.
No decisions to make no thought, right?
So typically, it always does look like this and you can actually even
see just in our
A little rle compressor which is the stupidest possible thing, right?
You can see even there.
We have all these complex decisions to make at any given time to the
loop.
We can choose to Output a new literal run pair or not.
Right, every time to this Loop or making a decision should be do that.
Now, our decision logic is very, very basic right here and not
particularly good.
Like I said before, this should probably be a different number, right?
But
Even in this extremely simple case you can already start to see the
asymmetry in complexity of compressors and D compressors even though
we have done the very stupidest thing.
Possible in both cases we did the very stupidest thing we could
possibly do we still
Are already seeing that difference?
Start to appear, right?
And it only gets worse, so that that's just typically.
My experience is that it only gets worse as you go further and further
down the rabbit hole of compression towards better and better results
and more and more sophisticated algorithms.
It's generally the case that, you know, if I wanted to explain to
somebody how to write the decompressor for a particular compression
algorithm, usually, that's the kind of thing you can do in an hour if
you want to explain to someone how to write a good.
For it, it might take months right up, study, right?
Who knows that may be an exaggeration, but you get the idea, the
compressors end up being sort of very sophisticated and having a lot
of complexity to them.
So that is basically where we're at with that.
So, all I want to do now is sort of expand this out to instead of
doing just are really doing LZ compression.
Now again,
We are not trying to make a good compressor here.
I'm just trying to illustrate the concept.
So this is going to be a very bad LZ compressor.
Not one that that would ever be particularly good.
What was the?
Oh I wish I could have seen with that.
Just what?
Inserted in there.
Oh it was that it was the day title from yesterday stream.
I guess it was still in the paste buffer.
All right.
Anyway.
So here we go with with our early situation.
You know I'm going to just copy this and
It in 2lz decompress.
And like I was saying before,
Really the only difference between our ly and LZ from the base
conceptual standpoint is that instead of encoding.
The thing that we are going to copy as just a single piece of
information that we just replicate some number of times instead.
What we're going to do is encode an offset that tells us we're in the
Stream to look back to grab the thing that we want to replicate.
Right?
So what we're going to do here instead is you see this, this is how
our decompression.
For our Ali was working before we were saying.
Okay while we still have stuff to ingest, let's take a look at how
many literals we expect to see go through the literals and copy them
to the output stream.
Then, you know, because we're always doing it in pairs, then we go
through and say.
All right, what's the the rep count?
And what's the rep value?
And then we rep that we repeat that value going forwards now.
So all we're going to do here is change this to like a copy count and
a copy value, right?
Instead, our copy value will now become a.
Well, I guess I can leave it as
Wait, instead of a single value is just going to be a distance, right?
And so the instead of reading in a bite to replicate, we're going to
read into B.
The tells us how far back from our current location.
We want to go, right?
Okay.
Now what you'll notice here is that the copy distance, we have some
choices here.
If we want to we can simplify this algorithm a little bit.
If we want to one thing we can do if you take
Look at this.
Copy distance, right?
And copy count.
Let's think about what that's going to do and I guess I can, I can
just go ahead and implement it so you can see right.
But here we're going to need a pointer that's like a source pointer,
right?
And the source pointer is just going to be.
Like I said, it's our out buffer - the copy distance.
Right?
Because if you remember how LZ is supposed to work from discussion
yesterday, we are.
Well, you know what?
If we go here to this, This Disaster, where is it?
It's down here somewhere, right?
We're in the output buffer, writing to the output buffer, and when we
get to a particular location, sometimes we just say, hey, go back to
somewhere else in the Stream and copy from there, right?
So it's all happening in our output buffer.
The only thing that we're trying to do here is say like okay when we
have that output buffer pointer which is where we're currently
outputting, we just want to start some distance back from there and
copy, right?
So,
Say.
All right, we're gonna start some distance back from there.
We're going to go copy count and we're going to Output into the
buffer, whatever was in the buffer previously at that location, right?
Now again, this is where that subtlety of how orally can actually be
implemented directly in LZ.
This is it right here, because imagine what happens when copy distance
is just one for example, but copy count is 20, right?
Well, what will happen is, we'll go back one from where we are right
now, which means that the last bite we output is now where
We're looking at for copy and then we're going to do it 20 times.
So we're going to take a copy of that bite and put it in the current
output position.
We're going to move the source point or forwards which is now pointing
at exactly the bite.
It just wrote which is a replication of the previous B and the process
will repeat itself.
19 more times copying that bite every time so effectively we get a
gnarly compressor inside rlz compressor for free essentially, right?
I mean in free is probably not the right term because you are
perhaps giving up a little bit of encoding for a but you can kind of
see how it doesn't really take any special work to get run length,
encoding out of an LZ compressor because effectively if you just give
a larger copy count than the distance that you jumped back, you will
replicate.
Right.
And it also allows you to do something that they are really can't do
without additional parameters.
That would take space to encode, which is you can replicate values
that are longer than one symbol, right?
You can say go back for copy eight and that will do two copies of the
last four in the buffer, right?
So it can do that sort of thing, hopefully, that makes sense.
All right.
So there's our ldl-c decompressor and literally that's all there is to
it.
There's really nothing else that you have to do to implement the
decompressor.
Again, like I said, it's always the compressor.
That's the more complicated.
So even though that's the only change we made our compressor is about
to get a lot more complicated in order to do anything.
Even even a really crappy LZ, compressor is much more complicated than
a crappy lzd compressor.
And so, we're about to see that.
But anyway, so now you can see how this LCD compressor works.
We do the exact same thing, we read in a literal count and off we go.
And then we do the same thing in the early, just copy.
And then we do, you know our other stuff here.
We take, okay?
A copy count or copy distance and we perform that copy from somewhere
Back In The Stream.
Now, what I was going to say is there's another thing we can do here
to simplify this further, actually.
And give us a little more flexibility in the end coder.
We could have done this with our Ali as well.
Potentially, but it costs more in the early to do.
And basically what happens in a an LZ encoder is, if you think about
what's going on here is, we're reading a copy count, and then we're
reading a copy distance, okay?
That's what we're doing, right?
And if you think about what that copy distance is going to be, if the
copy distance were to come in as 0, right?
So the amount to look,
Back was Zero.
In that case, we would know that we couldn't possibly be talking about
an actual copy, right?
Because 0 would not move the pointer at all from
Output location which means that we would be reading garbage because
we haven't seen what happens in the Stream at that point, right?
So in order to not waste one value, which is zero.
In the copy distance lat, there's two choices of what we can do.
One is we can get an extra bite.
You know, of Look Back by saying, when we read in the copy distance
since we know 0 is invalid just add one.
And that way, instead of being able to look 255, bytes back, we can
now look 256 bytes back, right?
So we can steal that value to get a little bit further.
Look back, right?
But perhaps more powerfully in terms of what we will probably
To get in terms of compression, there is what if instead we just said
well, we're reading a literal count or a copy count, right?
What if we just called it account and we read it every time and then
we said when we read the distance if the copy distance is 0 then we
assume right that we're going to be copying literals from the input
stream and if the if the copy distance isn't 0 then we will do our
account.
Our replication.
Right?
And that's perhaps a little bit more.
Interesting way to use that value.
Now, again, this is not supposed to be some deep insight into LZ at
all, because by the time you start doing anything sophisticated with
LZ your way, past the point of thinking about it in those terms
anyway.
But just in terms of the very simplistic, way that, we've set it up,
you can see that there's an interesting choice.
There, it seems like this is probably a better choice.
Given what we're going with two to say like hey well you know, do we
really care about just
One extra bite of.
Look back is instead we could use that one bite to be the thing that
switches between our two modes that way when the encoder wants to
encode things, it doesn't have to encode them as pairs.
It can every time in code which one it wanted to do and we put in one
branch in the decompressor to make that happen, right?
Now, as you can see, that means that essentially we've got two Loops
here, and these Loops are almost identical.
Right?
They're almost exactly the same.
You can see them here.
Right.
We've got wild count - - while count - - and the only difference is,
which thing we're taking from.
So, what I might further say, just to keep this decompressor just to
hammer home, the point that the compressors are so simple, you know, a
lot of the times.
If we were to just say, all right, what if we just made our source, be
dependent, just the pointer dependent on which one we were going to do
here, right?
and, and then,
we could maybe avoid having to do,
We could just have a single Loop, right?
That just one Loop that executes, we don't have to have two different
Loops, right?
And it's not quite as pretty as we might want it to be, right?
And these are actually backwards here like me.
Yeah.
So you know, if the copy distance is 0, then we copy from in.
If the copy distance is is not, then we do sort of our replication.
But the only problem that we get here is that we don't know.
Actually, which of the once we do this, we've pulled the in pointer
out into the source pointer, which means that it won't actually
Advance, right?
And we need it to advance by the count, in the case where,
you know, we were going to actually
In the case, where we were actually going to copy from in, we need
into advanced.
So really, we need there to be something like, you know, that where we
remove it forwards, and I'm not sure there's any really cleaner way to
write that.
Right?
So, I can't quite see how to do,
I mean, I guess we could just do this.
Right.
Yeah.
But I don't know that there's any way to do it.
Any more cleanly than that.
Unfortunately, you I mean, you don't really want to execute the, if in
line, but you can kind of see that it's relatively straightforward,
right?
So yeah, there's something.
Am I missing anything cleaner?
We could do there?
I don't know.
Really what you want to do is just have it be like you know,
There and have this happen after the fact that would be the nicest way
to do it.
But unfortunately, there is no sort of post decrement with a ver with
a variable size in C.
So I think that's pretty much the only way you could do it, if that
makes sense.
So yeah, so maybe you know, it's better to just say like okay, you
know, we've got our source pointer and we just say if the copy
distance is zero then the source
Peoples in and in plus equals count.
And I guess I could just sort of
do that.
So again, not quite as concise as I would like but still very very
small, right?
Very, very simple.
And so we come in here and we say, all right well we have stuff to
ingest.
We grab the count that we're going to use out of the current location
in our input stream.
We grabbed a distance as well and then we look and say, okay, when we
see the distance
We will say if it is equal to 0, then we're going to copy from the
input and we're going to advance the input by however many things
we're going to copy out of it.
Otherwise we're going to look backwards.
The copy distance from our current output location.
Then we're going to use a while loop to go for as long as we were
told.
To go copying from whichever one of those we decided to copy from
Right.
And so there you go that's that's about it.
Now you'll note that in doing so when I said we're going to use that
extra value, we give something up in terms of compression for doing
that.
Because previously, when the encoder didn't have a decision and it was
always done in pairs, doing it, in Paris, has the advantage of not
needing to.
Encode the fact that you were going to do
The other.
So what we did is we gave up a bite here.
Every time we want to encode a series of literals, we will have to
encode a bite and that bite that.
There's a 0 B.
Basically, that would have to be encoded there and that might be a bad
decision, right?
So it may be that it would be better for us to do depending on what
our circumstances are it?
Maybe that would be better for us to always do a where we go literal,
repeat literal, repeat literal repeat right.
Look we're doing a gnarly, it might be better for us to go.
Go like literal copy literal, copy literal copy.
If the data tends to be of the format that allows us to do that
interleave then that would always be better because we're saving 10 B.
Every time we do that internally, however, if most of the time we
aren't doing the interleave, if most of the time were either, we're
doing like unusual like unpredictable patterns like copy copy literal,
copy literal, literal copy copy, copy literal, copy literal.
Our then we've saved quite a bit so it's really hard to say and like
this this is sort of the way compression works, right?
You're constantly thinking about all these sorts of things and if you
were a compression expert, which says I've said many times I am not,
you probably have strong opinions about a lot of these things.
And, and to the nth degree, right?
Like much more complicated sorts of stuff than what we're talking
about here.
But they all follow that same pattern of well, if I encode something
this way, then I get some
Benefit this way but I lose something here is that the trade-off
that's appropriate for the type of data that I'm doing blah blah,
right?
So that's, you know, that's that.
So let's go ahead and take a look at how to do the compressor now as
opposed to the decompressor.
So, here is our rle compressor, and we'll just going to grab that and
start with it like we did with the decompressor because like I said,
they're basically the same but more is compressor that way or that
way.
I don't even
Doesn't matter.
Anyway point being.
So if we have Elsie compressed, we're going to do basically.
The same thing we were doing before, let's start by just making
something which doesn't actually ever encode any real dictionary.
Look backs, we'll just do something that encodes.
Are really essentially but inside LZ, just like I said, we could do
where we're just using L, Z's ability to do rle inside it in order to
compress.
Right.
Alright, so here's our LZ, compressor.
If you look, I have something stuck in my teeth.
I know that has nothing to do with.
I don't, nobody cares about that, besides me.
I just feel like I do anyway.
So if we take a look at the LZ compressor, starting from a gnarly
compressor, you can kind of see that we would have to make a little
bit of changes here because we're giving our LZ compressor of the
ability to decide which one of the two things it was doing.
And if you recall inside our, our LED compressor, the reason that we
didn't really do it that way is because we didn't super have
Any way to encode that, right?
We could have there wasn't anything sort of for free in one of our
things that we might have wanted to use.
All of these values are sort of maximal use.
Now we could have just used a value that was reserved in here.
Where we basically said like, okay, if we do a rep count of zero,
right?
Then that means it's literals coming after it.
And so the rep value would actually be how many there are, whereas if
there's a rep count of
You know, a different number, let's say then we know that it's a copy
so we could have done that as well in the early sort of but it's not
as obvious as in this one where it's like oh hey there's going to be a
thing that's got to be 0.
That that has a big old zero hole in it.
You're going to have to adjust for it, one way or the other there.
But anyway, so yeah, so it's unclear.
I'm not really sure maybe that was a stupid thing to do, but I don't
know, we'll see.
So here's our LZ.
Compressor, we come through here and we're starting to ingest the
data, right?
And we're going to use a literal buffer just like we did before which
is just whenever we see something that we don't think we want to
encode, we're going to shove it in there and then we know that
eventually have to kind of flush that buffer as the case may be.
So what we have here is our is our run length, encoding a right.
It's
Art, which is basically looking to see whether we've got a run of
something.
And so let's use exactly the same logic, right?
Like I said before, let's just encode runs with rlz encoder, so what
we'll do is say okay, if there is a run to encode, then will basically
say like, you know, flush at this point.
Otherwise, we buffer.
So, the first thing we have to do is, see, are there any literals to
flush?
Right?
So we take our little
We'll count eight.
And we say, are there any literals in the buffer?
Because remember, unlike the are released game, we've given ourselves
a way where if we don't have any literals to encode yet, we don't have
to write.
So that's kind of nice.
So we say, Okay, are there any literals to encode?
If there are flushed a little buffer right out it goes,
And so the question is now well, how do we encode that?
We'll remember, we can look at our decoder for that information.
We do account and a copy distance.
The rule is if the copy distance is 0, then it will copy from the
input.
So all we have to do here is say, alright, we're going to Output 2
things, the literal count, which is the count that we actually wanted,
and then a 0 and that tells it.
Okay, we're going to literals are coming next and here they come.
Right, there's our little count reset so there we're good to go and
then we come through here.
Now we've got our run.
We want to Output.
Our run.
And the way that we want to Output the run is we want to say like, hey
output, a copy of the thing that came before us in the buffer.
Now, it's a little bit complicated here because effectively we are we
have to sort of put
How should I phrase?
This we have to
have outputted.
The thing that we are going to be run running with if that makes any
sense before we can replicate it.
So technically we're going to have to modify this routine to be
looking for matches that start with the previous symbol but we can do
that in a second.
It's not too difficult, right?
But anyway, so let's assume that we're talking about a run that starts
with the previous symbol.
In that case, we just have to Output exactly the same thing here.
Right?
That we were doing before.
But now instead of outputting a zero, we're going to Output that run
the Run length, right?
Or I should say the the look-back length and the look-back length is
going to be one, right?
So instead of outputting a starting value, we're just going to Output
a 1 here which is, say, look back at the previous symbol and replicate
that.
For whatever the Run size is, okay.
So in this case, what we're going to do is say, all right, there's a
starting value here and that starting value is going to be something
from the, you know, from the previous, right?
So, the starting value is going to be something from the previous
character and we want the run to start at zero now, right?
Because we're going to look at the initial character and say, okay, is
that
Run from the previous character.
So when we look at the starting value, this is actually going to be
the previous.
Now, we can't.
Look at the previous if we're on the very first one, right?
So we have to do a thing where we're going to be a little bit more.
Careful about when we actually start doing this thing, right?
So if we start off with the run at zero,
we need to now check is in greater than the starting in, right?
And
We just need to make sure.
That we've gotten somewhere first, right?
And that's about it.
So when we actually have to go so this for buffering literals here, I
think this this is probably just
Better written like that.
Anyway, so I think that's really all we need to do.
And so now we should be able to run this and we'll have to cast up
through it because these things are kind of delicate obviously.
So, you know, I can't promise that I doubted, my eyes and cross my T's
there, but now we've sort of got the ability to run this guy as just a
gnarly compressor, which is again, not going to be very good.
In fact, it's probably going to be worse than our other one because
it's basically got a bunch of stuff.
It's baked in there for it to do that.
It doesn't need to do.
It's not using rather.
But we'll get to that eventually.
All right, so let me load up.
I'm gonna step up here.
and,
Let's step into the okay.
Forgot.
We need to call it.
There we go.
And so let's go ahead and jump in now.
And why are we?
Oh, we're on the decompressor.
That's not good.
I don't want to be on the decompressor at all.
You know, what else?
We should probably do actually know, I think about it.
It might be nice.
To just have a test.
If we're going to do test, I was thinking like, oh okay, what if we
just do something where we go?
Like okay, you call test and it goes, give me the data.
Let's make an output buffer and a test buffer.
The test buffer will just be a buffer.
The same size as whatever the input is.
We'll go ahead and say, OK, compress the thing.
So here's the compression, right?
And then decompress the thing.
And that'll run the compressor, then the decompressor, and then we
could even do a mem comp, which I don't think we've ever done, because
we don't normally program using the standard library on handmade here,
right?
We almost always just write everything ourselves, but you can kind of
see here.
We've got the ability to use the C standard Library, a mem Compass.
Just a thing that says, hey, compare two pieces of memory and return
to me a difference between them.
So if there's no difference between them, it'll just return.
So, if there is
Return nonzero, right?
So, what we want to do is say like
If mem comp.
And we want to pass that file size there.
We just want to say hey if our input buffer and our output buffer
match, then we would just say like okay
maybe just a success.
Otherwise, we just say failure.
Right, and so now we can just have a single way to run it when we're
doing development that would just you know, allow us to figure out
what's going on there.
And so in this case, we've got test-1 dot h a and we can just do test
one to speak but the the second parameter would actually just be
ignored, I guess in this case, because we're not going to actually
write it out now.
I suppose we could actually write it out so that we can run the test
and have the output saved which does
In potentially useful.
But man, I'm not gonna bother so really, I suppose, that that's
something better done in an ARG count equals three scenario.
But whatever, don't really care at this point.
All right, so let's go ahead and run this so I can actually get to my
compressor now, which is what I wanted.
So, here we go.
So the first time through the loop, we can't actually have a run
because again, we can't look backwards to see if we've encoded
something that we want to replicate.
So we're going to skip these the first
Time through.
And we're just going to buffer a literal.
And there it is.
Right?
The next time 3, we're going to look to see whether or not.
We have a run from the previous.
And in this case we do because the H is duplicated, right?
So, now, the Run of course, would have kicked in, but it's not long
enough, right?
Because it was only one replication from from what we had output in
the literal, which isn't good enough, right?
Notice again, that's a difference from the rle because like I said the
LZ can only are at least something it's already output, right?
Which is, you know, not not as good, right?
So anyway, so off we go.
And then we're just looking here, we found a much longer run, a much
longer run of 3 and so now we're going to actually encode, one of
these runs here is our output are literal count, right as getting out,
put it down to zero and then we're out putting literals because we do
need to flush the literal buffer right now.
Little buffer is now flushed and now we're going to say, okay.
Now we're going to run that last Saucy fellow for three times.
So here we go.
And then we're going to go forward by that amount, right?
So, I think we're good now.
I think that will do our encoding for us.
Don't quote me on that, but here we are.
Decompressor having have after having done that and let's see what we
get.
So we read in count.
First, in the count is five and the copy distance should be 0, because
this is a literal.
So, let's take a look at what we're going to copy.
Here's the thing that we're going to copy.
Rich.
Is there?
It is HAF.
And then some noise, which is exactly what we want.
So we output that literal right there.
It is.
Now we come back through and we learn.
Okay, we're into account three and we're going to do a replication
from just the previous thing, whatever, that was.
So there's our source, right?
And it's going to copy a zero a couple times.
So there it is copying a zero a couple times and off we go, right?
And it just keeps going.
Now it turns out that
unless I wrote the comparison wrong here,
We should be able to determine whether we succeeded.
It looks like we did.
So hey we wrote Our compressor, right?
The first time right the first time, so that's great.
And let's see, just for our own Amusement here.
Let's go ahead and see what, how well we did.
Right.
There's our test one.
Aha.
We'll start with that one.
So if I want to do simple, compressor, compress test, 1hh, a test
one.you know, simple LZ or something like this.
Or I guess we'll say run length rlz.
Run on the LZ.
Let's see how that.
So you can see that actually amusingly enough, we're still smaller
even though we haven't actually implemented the LZ yet because the
test one, SCP the rle one that we were doing before.
In fact I could
Probably the fact that it had to do alternating pairs of literals and
runs was probably causing it to be not as good as it could have been,
right?
Because now that we've gone to the LZ, we haven't actually implemented
LZ yet.
We're already smaller.
It's probably because it doesn't, it can take advantage of that,
right?
Furthermore, I can go ahead and say, like, okay, intro arced at SCP
here is intro, art rle, and then I can do simple compressor, compress,
intro art, that ha intro art rlz and that'll do the compression on.
That big huge file and then we can see how well that one does.
And again this one is is not really doing LZ at all.
You can see this one doesn't do better, right?
In this case, the rle by itself is actually an improvement, I guess
because again, presumably that alternation happens to fit the pattern.
Okay.
So it doesn't lose anything and it doesn't have to encode that zero
every time.
So you know, who knows?
But that's just conjecture.
We haven't actually looked at it yet, right?
So we don't really know but that's just interesting to take a baseline
of right?
alright, so now let's actually try to implement actual Elsie
compression because like I said, this is not LZ compression what this
is, is
Is strictly us using an LZ backend to implement rle, which is not what
we wanted to do.
I just wanted to sort of demonstrate that that worked.
What I want to do now is extend it.
So that not only can it do runs like that, but it can also actually do
look backs at which is what it's supposed to do.
Right?
The whole point of dictionary compressor is to use a whole bunch of
stuff in the output stream.
From anywhere, not just the most recently output thing, which is what
the only thing we're doing now.
So in order to do this, I need some way of looking back over the
stream to see where in the Stream, we would get the longest match
from.
Now, the first thing I'm going to do is Implement something which is
incredibly, unbearably slow probably and we would not be able to run.
Well actually you know what?
I take that back.
The first thing I'm going to implement is a very slow, way of doing
it, but because we're only talking about B here and the look back.
Buffer is only 255 bytes back.
This probably won't be prohibited slow, because computers are so fast
nowadays.
They can scan up to 55 window, really easily.
So, you know, take this with a grain of salt because 285 285 is only
65536, that's extreme r6i.
534.
That's a
Small number of iterations for something to do on a modern computer.
So surprisingly this will probably actually run just fine, but if we
were to upgrade that look back window to more like 16 bits, which is a
more common size to use and there's a number of reasons we can talk
about at the end of the stream.
If someone wants to remind me about why it's why 255 is not a
particularly good?
Look, back number for graphics compression.
I can talk about that because it really isn't, but we'll just we'll
go.
Ahead with this for now and you can see.
So, first, I'm going to implement the stupidest possible thing.
So how would we look for a run where we could say?
Let's look back over everything in the buffer that we could possibly
access and just see what the longest match is, right?
Well, if you think about what that would look like, we could just say
well.
Okay, let's say we just start as far back as we can and so we could
say like all right, you know?
You know, start of window or something.
Well, that's wherever we are at.
The moment - whatever our Max run count is going to be right.
And I guess we shouldn't say Max, Renn.
Can't we kind of need a new thing here which is like, you know, Max
look back out and we'll just keep that in there.
so we've got our Max look back and we're just going to say like okay
Whatever the maximum value is that we could look backwards.
Let's start with that.
Now the start of the window here maybe behind the beginning of the
buffer.
So we also need to double-check, right?
And we need to say that.
Well if we haven't gone that far yet we can only go as far back as we
have actual data.
So really what we're talking about here is more like, okay
Max.
Look back equals, you know?
Whatever the in pointer is - the in base, right?
So that's how far we've gone.
If the max look back is greater than this value.
Then we use it, right?
So, we're sort of like only using to the beginning of the buffer, but
as we move forward, we may then start pulling that window with us as
we get past the 255, 255, 255, B of the buffer.
All right.
So now we want to go ahead and I guess we'll do it like this.
Here's our window.
We know that wherever we are, we are going to go back.
However, much that look back is right.
And then we're going to step all the way up to, where we currently are
in the Stream.
Looking at each individual B, right?
Maybe we'll call this the window base.
Right.
Or maybe Windows start.
And then what we need to do is we need to do something almost exactly
equivalent to what we just did.
Which is to say, when we encode the, the, when we are looking for a
match, we can only go as far as the maximum run count that we could
have encoded, right?
Because as we're looking for matches, we can't look for any matches
that are longer than we can encode.
We can only encode matches 255 long.
So even if there was like a thousand zeros,
In a run of zeros or something like this, we couldn't, you know,
encode more than that or, you know, any pattern or not doesn't have to
be constant anymore because this is LZ, not rle.
We could, you know, it could be any pattern, any replicated pattern
can only be that long.
So we need to do exactly the same thing.
We need to say, well, the end of this thing, right?
Is in end.
Right?
But we don't know that we can actually go there, right?
So essentially, we have a window size and the window size is going to
be, however, long we have till the end of the buffer.
But if that is longer, which most of the time, it will be, if that is
longer than the max run count, then we can only use the max run count,
right?
So the window end is going to be Loops.
I mess that up its
It's the window start.
There we go.
So from where we're looking to the end that's how big
Window can be.
And the window end is going to be wherever we started, plus whatever
that that size is.
So now we know where we're looking in this particular window.
So now we just need to see how big of a run we can make with that
matching from there, right?
So what we want to look at is we want to look at the test in versus
the window in, right?
So the test in is where we're at right now, the window in is whatever
the Windows start is, and then we're just going to go ahead and say,
you know,
While they're equal.
Right.
We're going to increment them.
And in fact we could just do it this way.
So we will count the run just like we were doing before.
So we're going to look in the window and say, okay, how far can we go
while there while we're moving off?
We go.
But we want to make sure that we never exceed the end of the window,
right?
So we want to say, okay.
Cap the window in to the window end.
Right?
But as long as we're doing that test to see, if the two things are
equal, the the input stream and the the window, you know, are they the
same?
And if they are in, keep the, you know, keep track of how many of
those we could do.
So after we pop out of this Loop we will now know the maximum match we
could do at this location.
So then we just have to do our standard thing.
You've seen on him a hero.
Many times is keep the best one of these whatever it is, right?
So if our best run size,
Is less than our test run size.
Then what we want to do is our best run becomes our test run,
And our best location, equals whatever our test location was, right.
And I guess I'll be really need to know, is what the look-back was
here.
So actually it's just however, far back the window start is.
So we just want to kind of know like, oh, okay.
How far back do we go to get to the Windows start, right?
So, I don't know what best distance, I guess.
We'll call this.
so then all we need to do is actually keep those
Right.
Best run.
Just distance.
And so then we come through here, we don't care about this anymore,
right?
This is not, we're not doing that anymore because or finding the run a
different way.
And then we coming here, we've got our best run and now we're going to
do exactly the same thing we did before, right?
Okay.
So cleaning this up.
We now know that out of this and we'll have to step through this and
be careful and make sure we did everything right.
But coming out of this is assuming that we have our best run and our
best distance.
We now that we can say okay when do we want to encode a run?
Well we know that a run is going to cost us something, right?
And it's going to be a little bit interesting to look at the cost are
but so I'm just going to put a little to do here because we'll do it
in a second.
Think about when to Output but for right now we're just going to use
the if the best run if there was any run at all.
Right.
So if the run is greater than 1 will use it, right?
So let me come in and we need to do our flesh, we need to do our
literal count flushing.
Now, one thing that you'll notice that I forgot to do, when we kind of
added this in just moments ago, is really if the literal count was the
thing.
If the max little count was hit, then we don't actually need to encode
the run, right?
Because if there was no run to encode, you know, if if the best run
was not sort of something we need to encode then we don't actually
need to
Do any of this, right?
If that makes sense.
So if the only reason that we went through here is because we needed
to flush the literal buffer, right?
Then that was all we need to do, right?
That's all we need to do.
And then we just want to restart queuing literals up at the beginning
again, right?
So, I believe really what we want to do is sort of have something more
like this output run.
And I guess we don't probably have a pool here.
There we go.
and then, in this case,
we're now using best run.
And off we go.
Okay, so I guess this is probably a size T here.
That's supposed to be window size.
Okay?
And now what we need to do is just say, all right, now, remember,
we're no longer trying to encode just copies and so we've got this
distance value that we actually need to use as well.
And so, now right here, we need to actually do our distance.
Ay equals U, 8, best distance.
And we want to assert that that distance 8 equals our best distance,
so that we know that we didn't accidentally overflow.
And then we just output that distance.
Right.
And that's it.
So now we've effectively got something that will actually look back
over the entire window.
Find the longest run.
It could possibly output and output that run.
Right.
And now that's of course, assuming that we didn't mess it up, which we
may well have,
now, according to our
We passed.
So I guess we wrote the compressor at least in a way that doesn't
crash but we have no idea if we actually are compressing particularly
well or anything like that, but we can certainly try it now.
So, let's take a look at again doing our simple decompressor.
I'm sorry.
Simple compressor.
To do an actual rlz.
Here's our simple LZ and now it's going to do.
It's compression here it is.
And so taking a look at the simple as Z we have not done a
particularly good job.
It looks like actually so that look that's that's actually bigger than
than our are strictly.
Our run length one which perhaps is not surprising.
Now why is it not surprising again, we could have a bug in here.
So we're going to have to step through.
But at least, I'm going to finish this part before we actually step
through and see if we're working properly.
specifically, if you think about what this is doing, now that we're
looking back over the window,
it's highly likely that we will often find pairs of bytes.
We can replicate and the only thing that we're checking for here is
whether or not there's a pair, right?
It only has to be to before it will do this.
But what that would mean is, if it was going to have to do an output
of 2, it will have to write to B to flush the literal buffer, then any
literals that it has, which of course, we don't kind of gets to B
there then, another two bytes here to do the run.
So it's actually expanding every 2, B, run into four bytes for no
reason, right?
So given that you me.
What we want to do is something more like this, right?
What we want to do is say, all right, first of all, are there any
literals in the literal buffer, right?
Because if there are literals in the literal buffer, it means that the
in order to Output a run, we're already going to have to flush the
literal buffer which costs us to B, right?
We're going to have to Output this and this and then the literals, so
if we're already doing that, we had better, make sure that just adding
the literals that we have on to the end of the litter.
Buffer isn't a more efficient approach, right?
So in this case, what we want to do is say all right, the wrong that
you're going to have here.
Had better be greater than like four bytes, because if the Run isn't
greater than 4 B, it's going to cost us more to Output it than it
would otherwise, right?
On the other hand, if we don't have to flush the literal buffer,
right?
Then technically we're only going to have to do two bites to encode,
whatever this duplication is.
So technically, it only has to be that good before, it's better right
now, when I say better, I mean, in a very, like, loose sense here.
And we'll talk about that in a second.
Right?
Or at least.
Hopefully I remember too,
Okay, so we'll just go ahead and put that in there and let's let's do
these two.
And so, let's see if that improves it at all.
Now, again, we haven't slept through it yet.
Disney
Not sure if we're actually properly working.
Yet that makes it a little bit different, but you can already see
that, you know, if assuming we are working, you can see that with that
change.
We are now down to a much smaller file size, right?
Compared to where we were.
We were worse than the other two before.
Now we're better, right?
And so, that's pretty handy, right?
So, it's like,
Now we can see.
Oh, okay, before we were, you know, 175 now we're down to 158, so
we're the best compressor of the three.
Now, before we were the worst
Okay.
Now again like I said, this is very, very slow because we're doing
that search which is very expensive and we're not accelerating it at
all.
So the downside to this is, if we want to run one of these guys, well
it's going to take a while.
Here's our intro art.
Let's go ahead and run that and we're going to be running it for a
while, right?
It's got a kind of sit there and it's going to like, turn and turn and
turn, and turn and turn and turn and turn right now.
We can fix this a little bit.
If we open our build, we can at least get some O2 on that, right?
We can at least have the compiler optimize it for us which I believe
it's going to do right?
Because we've passed the flags to it.
Do we not?
Yeah we passed common compiler flags and the common compiler Flags
should have that in there.
Yeah so if we do this we should get a little bit of extra speed but of
course it's still going to be very slow because just fundamentally
doing
Search.
And so, you know, we'll just let that run.
I'm going to get a drink while we do that because I am parched, hold
on one second.
All right.
so,
Well our little you know, completely N squared compressor is is truing
through this ridiculously large file.
we can go over here and play with our
Notepad.
All right, so let's talk a little bit about optimal parse.
Basically, the problem that we have here and you just saw me do a
little bit of it, is that LZ schemes have a lot of decisions.
Right.
And this is what I was talking about before when I said like, oh the
compressors, get more complicated because that's essentially an AI
problem.
It's got to do a bunch of intelligence here and graphs arches and
optimization of sort of thinking based optimization in order to figure
out what the best way to do something is it's definitely a
maximization kind of process.
And so what do I mean here?
Well, as you saw when where's that?
Let's go to some compressor, here you go.
As you see here where we've got, you know, literal count and I don't
know why I'm on that side.
Again, as you see here, we've got, you know this if a little account,
then output the run.
If it's better than this or a better than that or whatever.
We already even though we're not together and intelligent, we already
have this concept of trying to wait two different options based on
which one we think is going to be better for compression.
But
Is this the whole picture?
No, it's definitely not the whole picture.
Why?
Because every time we encode something, we affect the decision, making
process all the way down the line, right?
And so, if you think about what happens, let's suppose that we have
something like, you know, a b c, d, e, f, g, h in the buffer or
something like this, right?
This is what we've output at this point, and we're talking about
It to Output next let's say right and well I guess I maybe need one
other thing here.
Maybe I want something that looks like
This is not going to be very good example.
I'm trying to think of exactly how I want to Output this.
So let's say that I've got this in the buffer and then I have another
thing in the buffer which is
Comes from part of this.
So let's say it's
Hmm.
I'm not sure my compression, nah.
Expertness means it's hard for me to come up with a case on the spot,
that demonstrates what I mean about picking the wrong match because we
can pick matches from anywhere in the input stream, but we don't
necessarily always know which one is going to be best.
So
All right.
Here's one that.
Okay, here you go.
so, let's suppose that we had something that was like,
You know in very interleave e.
So it was abcdefgh, right?
And then we had something that was like, you know, trying to encode
something and then we had another one here that was like
Maybe 12, let's say.
A b.
And then we had another like,
Okay, so, it's probably gonna be a really bad example.
Again, this is because I don't do compression hardly ever.
So, you know, I feel like if you were kind of person to do a
compression all the time, you would be able to think of these
examples, much more cleanly but so imagine that we're trying to Output
things right here.
Okay, well if I look back in the Stream and I look at them for the
longest match right here.
You can see that the longest match is this one, right?
Went to a b which is just long enough that we would probably choose to
encode it, which would put us right here.
And then we would look back and we would find that the longest match
was like right here, right.
It's C, D E, F H and it goes that far right.
Well probably if this was a literal.
It probably would have made a lot more sense to just include these two
in the literal right and make this literal slightly longer.
Then include this very long match because that would allow us to only
send an additional two bytes of data to encode this match rather than
having to encode two matches this one and this one, which would be two
extra bytes each, right?
So every time you
Make a decision.
You're making a decision that affects all the future decisions that
you're going to make.
Because you've changed where the like outputs where you're going to
be.
Making your decision points, right?
And so, the concept of an optimal parse is basically the concept that
when you're doing one of these compression passes, there is some set.
There may be more than one but there is some set of ways of choosing
where you broke up the stream like that that will produce the smallest
possible output size.
And lots of other decisions sets you could make will not produce the
smallest possible output size even for the same encoder, right?
And so, that is what this sort of thing is about.
Typically you are making a bunch of pieces of code that operate inside
your compressor, that are much more complicated than this.
Whose goal is to figure out whether or not you should in code matches
and code.
Rules Etc.
Based on heuristics right now you could try to do the actual optimal.
Parse
Because for example, you could just try everything try every possible
way of breaking up the stream, but again it becomes prohibitively
expensive to actually run those things.
So you have to use, you know, dynamic programming or something like
this, to make it a little more tractable and then maybe you don't test
everything.
You just have some things and you can imagine it just getting much
more complicated as you try to make something, which actually does
look across all of those options.
Now that I'm done with the explanation, you can see that we've got our
output here and let's take a look at how it did.
So here's our
Simple LZ compressor and you can actually see it's real good compared
to our other two compressors, right?
It's not quite down in the range of a really good compressor like
7-Zip, but that's pretty great.
I mean, we've, this is less than half the size of our art pack, right?
That means, you know, if it was going to take 10 minutes to download
Before, It's Gonna Take 5 minutes to download or less.
Now, that's pretty great for really stupid compressor, right?
But hey, it took a long time to do the compression.
So, the next thing you might want to do is start looking at how you
would speed it up, right?
So we don't really need to belabor these points right now, but I'm
going to go ahead and put a thing in here.
So let's talk a little bit about what you might do with this
compression code to start to make it better one.
Figure out an efficient way to expand.
Plz.
And
To support.
You know greater than 2 and 55 sighs.
Look back.
And or runs to add an interview back end.
Like Huffman arithmetic.
ANS.
All right, so adding an inch me back end would be another great thing
to do to this code.
Add hash look up for other acceleration structure to the LZ encoder.
So that it isn't unusually slow.
For add better heuristics.
To the LZ compressor to get closer to an optimal parse 5 ad
preconditioners.
Two.
test, you know, whether something better can be done for bitmaps, like
different saying,
The interleaving by for etcetera.
So there's lots of things that you could do and compression, you know,
certainly you want to learn more about compression, if you were
actually going to try and do something good with compression.
That's better than what we're doing here, but the other aspect of
compression that generally tends to be true is even after you really
know what you're doing.
There's just a lot of, you know, for lack of a better term fiddling
and refinement, you know, getting to a reasonable State, theoretically
is one part of the battle and that's Obviously good.
But then just the, the actual like mechanics of how you get things to
be encoded, cleanly.
How you work out all of the details and make them fit the problems
that you have as well?
Possible, those things are definitely, you know, those are a whole
different set of techniques, which is a lot more like optimizing
render code.
There's just a lot of iterations and testing and measurement.
That's necessary to do that, right?
So yeah, I think that's I think that's basically it for that.
I'm going to go ahead and add just a little bit more.
I think to this framework here just so we can maybe like yeah, maybe
if anyone wants to play with it and do some stuff, they'll be in a
slightly better position.
So what I'm going to do here is just say, like, okay, maybe there's
some kind of a way that we expose statistics
out of this, you know, and
I'm trying to think about how I would want to do that.
Let's suppose we did something like maybe an enum here, which is like
stat type and then we would have something like, you know,
Or don't you want to call it?
I feel like you need a different name for like a repeat versus a copy
back.
I don't know that.
We'll call it that way.
We'll call it, something like that.
Stat literal bites.
I don't know, let's say we've got a bunch of Staff types here.
Right.
And I want to print these things out and then I'm going to have a
struct like stat in a struct.
Stat group.
And then I've got my stats here, which is
however, many there is, there are
and then my stat is just going to be a count and a total something
like that.
So basically what I'm going to do here is just create a little thing
that allows me to record information about, you know, what's going on?
And maybe I've got an addition here.
I've just got like
Uncompressed.
B.
And compressed tights.
And yeah, so well actually I suppose the total I suppose, those are
things that we actually just kind of know, so maybe that's not in the
stat group, maybe that's down here.
Trying to figure out a good way to keep track of all this stuff.
So, we've got ya, we've got all of our staff that we might want to
Output it.
We've got the stat group here,
And off we go.
So what I'm going to do is I'm basically just making a little thing
that will make this a little bit easier to use for various purposes.
I'm going to take here and make a compress and an uncompressed kind of
thing into a typedef.
So I'm just going to pound Define like compress Handler.
And decompress Handler.
So here they are.
So I've got the
compressors.
They'll all look like this.
I've got the D compressors.
They'll look like this.
And then we'll just do typedef.
Press Handler.
Typedef decompressed Handler.
All right.
But we go.
And so now what I can do is I can just sort of make these
And we need to actually figure out something here for a reasonable
size.
You know kind of some kind of thing that handles the size more
reasonably here.
But let's go ahead and just say we got compressed Handler our Ally
compress.
you can press Handler, we decompress
Press Handler, as you can press.
And decompress Handler.
I was impressed.
So at that point once we've got those sort of handlers there then I
can sort of also Define this idea of like a compressor and the
compressor can have a compress Handler.
And decompress Handler.
And you'll notice, I want to have both kinds are want to have a
compressor other and decompress Handler pointers because we may want
to use the same decompress Handler for a whole bunch of different
compressors because we might want to have different compressors that
we try or whatever.
So you know, who knows?
And so what I can do is I can say we've got compressors.
And these are just going to be like compress and decompress pairs for
like all the stuff that we've got, right?
So you can imagine like we just say like, okay, we've got a bunch of
compressors.
We've got the rle one, right?
We've got the lz1.
You know, and maybe we want to do a thing in here where we're going to
name them.
Who knows?
okay, so let's assume that that's how we're going to do it and you
know, maybe get rid of these guys and then we go up to our compressor
here, we'll just say like, oh yeah, okay, so the compressor has a name
And this way we can say, like when you are specifying something here,
when we, when you do the arguments or whatever, we can say that when
you do compress or decompress week before that, maybe this becomes a 5
and we do a little check to see which compressor we're talking about,
right?
And yeah, I mean I guess the, I guess the other way we could do it
might be to say as long as it's you know greater than 4 or you just,
we take all of the ones and we use the compressor for each one or
something.
I'm not sure.
We got to think this through a little bit.
I don't know.
We'll do the simpler one first and just see how that goes.
But point being we should be able to say something like okay, you know
let's say you got to take five arguments and so instead of
One two three will do two, three four.
And we'll say here caressed are compress or codec.
Name.
And that'll be the first one.
So the first thing we'll do is try to find the compressor.
So we'll say, compressor,
Press R equals 0 and we'll just go through all of our compressors
compressor.
Index equals zero, press your index is less than you know.
However, many there are in that array.
Right.
And then we'll say, Okay compressors, compressor index.
And we'll just check this the string compare.
So if the codec name and the compressor name or the same Breakout
And that's that.
So this is really probably should be.
Right.
So in this case we only want to proceed if the compressor is known,
like, if we have that compressor,
But assuming that we have it, then from then on out, we will just use
whatever the compressor is that we found.
So now instead of calling compress, we're going to call compressor
compress, right?
Instead of calling decompress will compress or decompress.
And so on.
So hopefully that makes sense.
And let's go ahead and and rename these guys to be base so that they
don't conflict.
And then anyone who doesn't want that can obviously,
Sort of play with that later.
So this is going to be in base.
And same here.
and,
Oops.
And then I think we're good.
So now if we take a look at what's going on here, so let's do simple
compressor.
Compress.
And I think we wanted to say like let's say rle, right?
Compress test one that ha test one are Ali out or something like that.
Let's see if that actually oh
My goodness.
Well, that didn't work particularly well.
Let's take a look at what's going on there.
All right, so in here, we got now.
Let's put something on the front of this here.
So
I'm going to go ahead and step in.
Compress, wait a minute.
also, we got to change the
And we do not need this to be 02 anymore, we can go back to debug
mode.
There we go.
So, let's see here.
What did I need to set the thing to our count?
Five?
One, two, three.
Forgot to put the compress in there.
Yeah, let's step through here.
There's the compressor, and we, oh, that's a nice type of there.
Area.
All right, so let's see how that Rose.
So we go through here, we find our compressor.
We go through, we can press with it and and we're done.
Okay, so that's all good.
Alright, so now we should be able to use any of the compressors that
we want which is nice but we would like to maybe do a little bit more
here in terms of outputting some statistics and stuff like are saying
before, and we also might want to Output the algorithms that you can
use as well.
So we know
we could go ahead and
put that in here where we say like okay, you know, algorithm
Not a particularly good help system.
Let's be honest.
But there's like what the algorithms could be right at the moment.
And off you go.
So now, the only other thing like I said that I wanted to do was have
a concept that Stats come in to play at some point.
So what I'm going to do here is we're going to say that, hey, we're
going to pass
Stats to both of these.
So that basically like if they want to record stats they can.
And then what we're going to do here is say like okay there's you
know, sort of a stat
It comes in uninitialized that we pass the compressor.
I guess decompressor, maybe doesn't need stats now, I think about it
because we don't really care about recording statue, the decompressor.
So probably it's we're only really talking about stats in this case,
where we're calling the compressor.
All right.
So yeah.
So now we're passing those stats through and now we really all I want
to do is have a way to dump the stats out, right?
So I want to be able to take these stats here and and output them,
right?
So it's kind of annoying.
This is one of those.
See things that just really is awful.
About C and C, plus plus.
I just want to be able to get the names of these things so I can have
put them, of course, I can't.
So, that's kind of annoying.
But, you know, I can make a function that does it, you know, that
name, the takes that type.
And then just does this nonsense here, right?
Well, I guess I could even just do
Well, we'll do it this way.
It's a little more robust than using an array because if you or going
to reorganize things, you don't end up with wrong printouts which is
kind of nice, right?
So you can kind of see what I'm doing here.
I'm just saying, hey let's make a macro where we say if we're going to
do this thing, we don't put whatever.
You know, the thing is that we want and we probably don't really need
the stat underscore in front of it.
So we could just say like, you know, go forwards, five characters and
and do that or something like this.
You can imagine that being sort of, a
An amusement that we could do and of course you know how much I hate
const, it's the worst thing ever.
So typically, what I'll do is I'll just get rid of it, right?
You always, I always get rid of const anywhere, I possibly can.
So now we've got a way to print out these stats.
So you can imagine us going through, you know, something like this.
Don't know why I made that in line.
So if I want to do, you know a stat print out, and we've got a stat
group here.
Then I can guess I can go through these in a pretty straightforward
way, right?
And again, I don't know why I'm on that side where my head gets in the
way.
Go over here.
So if I have one of these stacked groups, I can just kind of come
through here and say all right what's my fat index?
Go through them all.
Like so I want to grab out one of these stats.
So I just say, all right,
let's take each one in turn.
If anyone recorded anything to the statistic, we will print it out.
Otherwise, we won't.
I don't know if we want to print these, the standard error standard
out, maybe standard out.
I'm not sure it's a good question.
I'm not sure which is the more appropriate but we're like okay, this
particular stat, right?
And it's going to be I don't actually know how to print out with the c
runtime Library, how to print out 64-bit things, reliably, it changes
all the time.
So what I'm probably going to do is just print them out as doubles.
And say that I don't want any.
Additional number to it, right?
Because that allow me to make sure that it's you know that it's
properly printed out.
On any particular platform you might be on without having to guess
what that platform is going to do in terms of asking to print out a
64-bit variable.
So yeah, so, you know, oops, I should probably put that up here.
First so uncompressed or like maybe we'll do like compression first.
It went from here to here and then, you know, we've got a particular
percentage.
so, what I want to do here is say like, all right, we've got a certain
uncompressed size and a certain compressed size and I, yeah, I could
say if stats uncompressed B greater than 0,
Then we go through and print them out.
So we get our compression goes from, you know, whatever uncompressed B
were to whatever are compressed by its were and there's certain
percentage there.
I'm going to introduce a function just called percent where I can pass
two things that I want the percentage of
And so what, we usually, the way compression percentages are phrased
as what percentage of the original file size.
The output file size, was, I believe.
So, it's like the compressed over the uncompressed is, I believe how
they typically are stated again, not a compression person.
So, I don't really
I don't really want to suggest that that's for sure.
But, you know,
I believe that's how it is.
So we'll do a numerator and a denominator here on this.
And so we want to do is we want to say like if the denominator is not
0 because we can't do a divide if it is 0, then what we're going to do
is return an actual valid results.
Otherwise, we'll return 0.
So in this case, we'll say numerator over denominator off the go, we
are actually, where are we on the timeline?
I don't even know.
We're probably just about done but either way.
Okay, let's see.
Actually wanted that to be that way.
Okay, so that gives us a way to start printing out our stats.
Now, for each of these stats, whatever the stats are here, we don't
really have a whole lot in the way of sort of ways of looking at this,
this data necessarily.
But so, for the first thing I'm going to do, I'm just going to print
out what they are and then we'll start to think about what we want to
actually output.
In fact, what I should probably do is
Okay.
Out of the total, certain ones of these out of the totals of what they
were.
You know, we would want to sort of have internal summing, right?
And, you know, I guess we don't really have a good way of
About putting that stuff.
So we'll sort of start with something basic and then we'll see.
Maybe if people wanted to improve the Stat system, they could do that
as well.
Alright, so inside print stats.
Let's just do the basic thing which is to say for every stat will just
output what it actually is.
So, here's our stat count and here's our stat.
Total.
And then all I really want to do here is introduced and these can kind
of come down now.
All I really want to do here is introduce an idea of, you know, an
increment for the stat.
So, you know, if we have a stack group and we have a stat type and
then we have a value
Then all that's going to do is say hey whatever our stat is that we're
trying to increment here.
We want to increment the count for that and then add to the value.
So this lets us know how many times you recorded something, and then
what we recorded, right?
And so now that I think about it, that actually allows us to say,
literal, repeat and copy are all, actually, we really need at the
moment, because I think that's the only things that we actually care
about their.
So let's go ahead and do it that way.
We'll just pretend that that's good.
So, let's go ahead and put our increment in here.
So, let's take a look at our compressor for our compressor.
Now, we can sort of say like OK, we can now actually record these
things that we're talking about.
So we could say increment stats and then whatever our status that we
want, and then whatever it is.
So, in this case, we've got a literal count, right?
And we can say literal, we've got a run, right stat.
So, and you know what?
It occurs to me.
Also that there is one thing in here that I think we're not doing
quite right.
I should point out that basically like we have to do we have to Output
a final like this little clip off the end.
So we have to kind of input a thing here as well.
That's like, hey, if this is the last thing that we're going to do
Like if n plus 1 equals in, and we have to flush, right?
Meaning, if n plus 1 equals in end,
Like if we're at the end of the buffer, so there's nothing left to do,
we need to flush the literals out that we have, right?
So we should put in a search here.
That like literal count is 0 because otherwise, we forgot a few bites
at the end of the file, right?
And the same would be true of this one.
So output run.
In this case, you know, in terms of the flushing and so on.
It's fine, but we need to do the same check.
So here we need to say like, okay, if
The next one is the end there.
Nothing if there's nothing else Beyond it.
Then we would need to to do it.
And I guess, you know, nothing about that's not quite right either.
In that case, we haven't necessarily pushed the literal into the
buffer.
So I guess really, the way to look at it is more like if it's the last
one, right?
Like if we're on the very last one, then we need to flush and we only
check for runs in that case.
So this is more like that, right?
And I think that should all work because these should all be zeros so
it should be fine.
I think famous last words, right?
but I think that's fine, so we should be able to say I'll go back and
double-check that as we should be able to say while it's just
Less than or equal to.
When we come through here we can say like okay if
We're on the last one, then go ahead and do it.
And in this case, let's see the windows started from looked back and
then that's going to start, so it should be.
Yeah, I mean, I think all that should work just fine.
I believe that we should double-check that obviously.
All right, so
Let's go ahead and clean this up here.
Syntax error.
What is the syntax error?
Missing semicolon before.
Okay set?
There we go.
All right, so I'm not quite sure.
We got all that in there yet, but let's, let's just do one more here.
Let's do a test of the rle compressor first and see if that works,
retry break.
so in this case, I feel like
Yeah, so run in this case because it equals one will still increment.
The in pointer, which we don't want for our assertion doesn't actually
cause a real problem.
But yeah.
So if you look through here, right, our run,
Are running code needs to be slightly a little a little bit smarter,
right?
So we want to actually start it like this.
And actually make it do that copy from the initial one if that makes
sense.
Because that way that way we won't actually get a run in that case.
So when we output this run here, this would be
And an output of 0, I guess, for flushing the buffer.
Yeah, I'm not sure this this is this is just a touchy thing to get
right because there should be a more cleaner way of an easier way of
sort of getting it.
Flushable here.
Because again, starting value is going to be an invalid value here, if
that's the case.
So when it actually goes to Output the run, which it always has to do.
If there was a literal,
Right?
I'm not sure how we get that workout, right?
It you don't well I guess it doesn't really matter because it's zero
so I suppose that's fine.
The fact that it reads, one off the end of the buffer isn't
necessarily A Bad Thing.
You know, but we could do this.
Or something like that, right?
Well, that would work either.
Just kind of ugly is all.
But handling that end I'll have to see if there's maybe there's a
better way to handle that end than that.
Yeah.
Okay, so let's take a look at this.
So when we come through here, I kind of want to see, I guess it's a
little bit hard for me to look at the case that I want.
So what I might do is just put a little
So let's break here.
So if we go in equals an end, then we know that we've actually got the
end of the buffer.
So in this case, I want my starting value to be 0, which it is.
So I don't read off the end.
My run is also zero because it's not going to go anywhere in here.
And then I'm going to come through here and do my output, right?
So, I'm at putting a literal count of however, much is left in the
buffer.
There are no literals in the buffer at the moment.
So, I guess it had been flushed previously, which is a little odd.
I'm not sure why.
Likely, it would have been flushed necessarily I guess because we
ended with a run, which is handy.
So we get the literal count.
We take a look at the the run count, we output it.
And we output the that final value, we then don't go forwards at all.
Oh, right.
We actually would have to break as well at the end of this, right?
We have to actually stop on in equals end.
So yeah not great.
I feel like we could probably code that more concisely.
That's one of those things that tends to be harder at least for me to
do on stream because I need to think it through and it's hard to talk
while you're necessarily doing that in terms of like fiddly, things
like that.
But usually that doesn't it being the case.
In this case, where we have a situation here, the same is true with
the LZ encoder where we're looking at these guys.
We would we would also need to do
I break to get out of the loop, so yeah.
Alright, so here is the here.
Is it doing the rlz test?
Let's take a look at what happens here.
Looks like it succeeds.
Okay.
Which means we get the same data out in both cases.
So that's all good.
And now let's actually call our print stats routine.
So at the end of here, we just do our print stats.
So now those will get outputted.
And when we, what I want to do here is when we actually record the
stats, I'd like to record the input size in the output size.
So when we do like a compress here, I want to do like stats
uncompressed, B, stats compressed B.
Oops.
And so, you know, the uncompressed B is the in file file size, right?
And the compressed B is the compressed size.
And these two cases, and we won't look at the plus four for the, the
size recording at the moment.
We'll just leave that out of there and the same.
We would do the same thing in here.
And I think that's really all we need.
That's Dot.
So now when we call one of these at least in theory, if we do a
compress, we should oops.
We should be able to take a look at that.
What's going on here?
Okay, so clean up a couple things.
In our words, our staff princess.
So yeah, one thing I forgot to in our percentage is multiplied by 100.
Right?
Because typically percentages are printed out times 100 so we got to
multiply it by 100 and here right we forgot to print out the name name
but then I think we're probably done.
Sorry, gets that name, right?
Gets to next.
All right.
So in theory, now we can actually get a little bit of visibility into
what was going on, so you can kind of see for the rle compressor for
the literals and repeats.
You can see how many repeats it did versus, how many little is it did?
And hey, you know, the two are exactly the same in terms of how many,
that's because the rle compressor is an alternating one, right?
So, it has to be the same of each one, but the bite counts are very
different so it encoded 153 K worth.
Of literals but it encoded one point three Meg's worth of repeating
characters, right?
And that's why we got such a good compression ratio here, right,
because most of the file consists of repeats, let's try the LZ version
and see what it says.
Oh well of course I have to actually put in the stat counts there.
So here's our LZ.
version and when it comes through, when it does, it's flush here, will
say okay,
Here's the literal count.
Here's the best run.
Right?
And what we could do is in addition we could say here like hey you
know, if the
If the distance.
That we're doing.
Is.
Less than the run count.
This is a copy, right?
So I'm sorry, then it's a repeat, otherwise it's a copy, right?
Because that's that was like how we were doing our Ali inside the LZ.
So if the best distance in this case is greater than the best run.
Or equal to it.
Then it's a copy but otherwise it's a repeat.
And it's a repeat of that of whatever that length is right?
So yeah, let's let's see how what that will tell us.
So, here you go.
So it looks like here's how many bytes we encoded as basically reps.
Here is how many we encode it as like look backs, but that didn't rep
assume.
I got this right?
If the best is no, I'd this is backwards.
There we go.
Right?
Because if it's greater, if the distance.
Wait, no no, I did it right.
If the distance is greater than the Run size than it is a copy.
Yeah.
So there we go.
That's a little surprising to me actually because I'm surprised that
it encoded so many things as copies that were not reps.
But that looks like the case am I sure I didn't get that wrong the
best distance.
That's how far back we're going if it's greater than equal to the run.
Then yeah then you wouldn't be repeating.
So that would be a copy.
That's that was surprising to me.
I would not have expected that but I guess that's the case.
So
For the sake of argument or slight edification.
I suppose let's also verify that we can do test here.
There's our our success and let's see the LZ passes as well also.
And we'll do our intro art HHA with our Ellie.
Just to see again, what those numbers are.
And while we're running the old l z.
Kind of.
See, that's where again all the questions.
Well, we're running our LZ on that.
Which I was, he takes a while.
Let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
Let's see.
Looks like there are no questions.
That will make answering them easy.
Blow says, I think I followed it, but definitely want to re-watch
during and after granting.
All right.
Forgive me if this information was somehow implicit in today's lecture
and I missed it, but is compression.
Ever used for locality wins.
I guess I don't know what a locality win is but yeah, I'm not sure.
I'm sorry, I don't think, I know what a locality when is in this case?
I mean, I could guess, but I'm not sure, I know what you're referring
to.
Do you know offhand, what kind of compression ratio and decompression
speed or needed before it's faster to load compressed data and
decompress overloading decompressed data the answer, is it entirely
depends on your backing Store Speed.
So, if the thing you're loading from is very slow, then you may get a
win from any compression at all, right?
Like if you're loading from a really bad hard drive like, you know,
maybe something like a PS4 hard drive.
That's really slow.
Old-school 5200 RPM kind of style hard drive, then you may get a lot
of wind out of it, right?
However, if you're talking about a really fast SSD, or the upcoming
xpoint stuff, those sorts of things, then, you know, it's the
compression is going to be a lot less effective.
Right.
So it really depends on how slow like how much compression you need
for it to be a win.
In terms of IO is really all about how fast the io is right.
Neal says in types and pure I, you 64 is probably what you're supposed
to do for % LL.
You search for print test.
Yeah, but that is so variable, like it was, which compiler are you on?
Did this?
Does it have a newer version of the CRT, and all that stuff?
So, I just find, like, printing it out with float.
Always works.
So, just do that, you know.
The only time that you really can't is if you really are using all 64
bits of the 64-bit value because then the float will lose a little bit
of it, right?
Because the double-doubles only 64-bit itself.
Do you still have to uncompress your images for display?
So do you have plans for using block compression?
No, we don't have to worry about that because we're only using whole
images at a time.
So we only need to I mean I guess if you're saying when we compress
images individually, the answer is yes because we want to load only
the images we actually need.
So that's definitely the case, but we don't need block impression like
8, by 8 block compression or anything like that, if that makes sense.
Okay, I see what you're asking now.
Okay, so the question before us from forgive me, this information with
some implicit in today's lecture and I missed it.
But it's compression ever used for locality wins.
And what he was talking about is he means like better usage of the
cash.
The answer is, I don't think I have ever done that, but I suppose
somebody probably has
Really hard to say.
I mean, again, I'm sure there are cases when it could happen, right?
I just, I can't think of a time where I specifically had any
experience with that myself, but yeah.
Sorry, I do not know the case off hand but it certainly could happen.
The problem is just that you know compression is kind of slow like
even very very fast D compressors are still not that fast so you know
cat the cash isn't that slow filling?
The cash isn't that slow?
So
It's tough, right?
It's tough to beat memory speed with it with a decompressor in that
way.
And streaming is like, the best case for filling the cash, right?
Intel chips are really good at knowing that you're like, reading a big
chunk of memory in and out putting a chunk of memory, so you're
actually going up against probably the best place.
You know, in terms of Origins, the best place, the the case that it's
best made to work with because you can issue
Stuff like that.
So it's kind of hard to.
Yeah, it's tough.
I would say it's probably tough.
MTS mocks.
Why is 225 not a good look back limit for images, you want to
elaborate on that.
Yes, thank you for reminding me.
The reason that I was saying that you probably want for image
compression, you want to expand Beyond 55?
It is because most images are longer than 255, bytes per row.
And often times you're going to copy stuff from a previous row to the
next row, if there's a duplicated, like, little bit of the image that
might be similar.
So if you can
Only look back to 55.
You probably can't get back to the same location on the row.
Like to give you an example.
Suppose.
This is my image right?
And my image is 256 by 256, right?
And I've got a thing that's like, oh cures, you know, a line in the
image, and then there's another line here and then it's here, right?
And then on the next row down, it looks almost the same as that,
right?
But shift it a little
You can see how maybe like this could get a whole copy and put it
right here, right?
Because it's exactly the same, let's say, but if it's 256, and 256,
right?
Well, District, this one doesn't matter, but if it's 256 long, well,
256 pixels x 4, bytes, per pixel, right?
Means that we've got 1024 bytes per row,
Right?
So there's no way a 255 look back.
Window is going to get all the way back to here, because that's a
little more than a 1024 look back already.
So, typically you want a 16-bit look back window for images or
something in those ranges, because in order to get back to the
previous rows, you're going to have to go back that far for a text
compressor that may not be true.
25 might be a good idea for text compressor for all I know, but for
image data it's not a great idea.
See, if there's any other things on compression.
Have you ever heard of random seed data compression?
No but that's not surprising because I don't do compression.
So there's most most things that involve compression.
I will not have heard of if that makes sense.
I see if there's any more compression questions.
Probably more of Jeff and fabian's territory.
But is there generally such a thing as a compressor that compresses a
lot and fast with some rad compressor, leave 10% of initial size and
considerably.
Faster than LG, I guess bank is hyper fast, isn't it?
Like live decompression or something.
Well I guess what I would say is yes, oh there is compressors.
That can press a lot in fast, the rad sells a product called doodle
which is all those compressors basically and they actually are the
first people that I know of at all who shipped a compressor that is
smaller, that typically produces smaller output sizes and typically
runs faster than lzn.
A
Lzma right.
They did a thing called lzn a which is significantly faster but
oftentimes as small or smaller than 7-Zip.
So yes the rad compressors are best in class I guess at this point and
they've got all kinds of compressors that are super crazy in that way.
IEEE 754 I meant block compression that's GPU supported like be C1 C1
through C7.
You upload the compressed images, you pu and Hardware decodes, it was
sampled.
Yes.
So I talked about this before, I don't like those compressors at all
because they're lossy and when you're doing it, 2D art in my opinion,
I really care about the quality of the 2D art so I don't like using
GPU compression because it degrades the quality of the image right in
a 3D game, it's not as big of a deal.
Has your typically layering a bunch of shaders on top of it and
there's a lot of like layering of textures and stuff.
So at that point it's a little less important to maintain the quality.
But I don't love lossy compression.
I theese days when you've got so much memory to play with, I feel like
you've got a really, make a strong argument for why you think it's
okay to be lossy on stuff because if you're just doing compression
because you saw that there was compression in the hardware and you
turn it on.
That may be a very bad decision because you'll degrade your image
quality but you don't know that you actually needed what it gave you
you don't know that you need a smaller size, you don't know that you
needed better bandwidth.
So you should actually determine that.
You need those things first before turning it on because otherwise
you're just making it worse looking image.
Like that's all it's giving you right?
Is there a syringe.
So you need to First determine that you actually needed more bandwidth
or more space before, turning something that on I think.
Because otherwise you're basically taking quality hit and you're not
getting anything for it.
And even if you do need it, you should first determine that the speed
when the truck getting is, is worth the quality degradation.
So at that point, even when you've decided that you might need it,
turn it on first verify that the degradation is not worse than making
some other decision, like, using less textures or something that you
could have done, or less passes or a slightly lower resolution or
something, right?
So you always want to like you always want to understand.
That the texture compression that is.
In Hardware right now is lossy compression.
You are taking quality, hit for using it.
So first, make sure that you actually want that before before doing
it, don't just do it right.
Make sure that, you know, make sure you understand the trade-offs
first and that you're making an educated decision, it's not a hard
decision to make because you can just test it both ways and see, you
know, at the minimum
So I think, all right, I think we're done here with the questions that
I was going to address.
So let me go ahead and close this off.
All right, so yeah so that was just a little foreign compression.
Like I said we won't do anything else with that for quite some time.
We might return to it when we're done with the game and just want to
reduce the size of the asset packs that we ship.
For example, we might go ahead and put that in there, if that makes
sense.
So, let's go ahead and and wrap up this stream.
And we'll be back after the after the holiday break with just regular
game coding.
All right, thank you so much.
Everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade.
He rots in a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along with the stream, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here a.org and it comes with a source
code.
So if you want to play around with it, like, for example, if you want
to go play around with the the compressor, and try your hand at doing
some good,
At weeks or maybe learning about compressor and adding some things,
those compressors that will all be obviously included in tonight's
upload.
So if you sink with the source code, you will get that and play around
with it.
We also have a patreon.
If you want to support the video series, you can pledge to that.
We also have a schedule bot, which I will be rewriting soon to
actually work with.
We can streams.
It doesn't properly, mention them at the moment, but we'll fix that.
And then we've got an episode guide, you can go to to catch up on old.
Older streams that's about it for now.
I don't know that we will have a stream next week because it is
Christmas holiday as a deserved here in the states.
So most people are off and doing holiday things.
So we may skip that one but we'll be back the week after regardless.
So either way we we will see you soon and until then have fun
programming and I'll see y'all on the internet.
Take it easy everyone.