Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream.
No engines, no, libraries.
This is a complete game code base from start to finish that you can
compile by itself and it's a whole game, it does not even use a
graphics card.
It actually does all the rendering itself even which is kind of crazy.
But what's not.
So crazy is our asset loading system and we've got some work from
yesterday that we need to do in order.
In order to finish up sort of the basic functionality that we were
trying to put into our asset loading system, which was keeping a
consistent amount of memory used in the asset system while still
allowing the game to run on top of it seamlessly.
And so I'd like to jump right into that because we kind of just
stopped in the middle of it yesterday.
Today is one day 159.
So if you would like to follow along at home and you pre-ordered the
game on handmade hero dot-org, you will want to unpack day 158 source
code because that is a source code that I am starting with.
So I am going to go ahead and pull that up and here we go.
So I will go ahead and compile this little bit slow there.
I'm not sure why it's so slow today, look how slow that.
Look at how long that compiles taking
Because that was just getting things into the cash, what's going on?
Why is that so slow?
Do we know why that's us though?
Do we know?
Let's take a look process.
He's doesn't look that unusual.
That's just been a cash thing.
I don't know.
It's kind of awesome to see how many I write B OBS is done, anyway.
So what we did yesterday is I kind of showed you how to, you know, if
we were just going to punt to the operating system and let it manage
memory for us.
We kind of showed how to do that, but there was a particular thing
that I need to finish up from yesterday that we didn't have time to do
the street.
And that is that even though our system is sort of technically working
at this point, there is a critical bug in it that we already kind of
plan for a new would happen but we don't actually get really use the
things that we did to prevent it from being a problem and that is when
assets are loaded into the system.
Obviously, now that we want the asset system to use, only a fixed
amount, you know, a certain amount of memory
What that means is that assets that are loaded can get unloaded.
So when an asset, the asset system gets loaded in and it state gets
set to asset loaded.
Well, at any time at the end of a frame, right at the excitation
sailing time, at the end of any frame, a given asset may get
jettisoned in order to make space for future asset loads.
So, that's not a problem for any of our normal rendering, but for any
of if
Have any tasks that are running in the background to do rendering,
which we already have.
In the case of our ground chunks, for example, then what we would like
to do is make sure that anything that they are trying to use, can't be
evicted because if it was evicted, then those their code would crash
because they would be trying to be using an asset that doesn't exist
anymore, right?
So, we need to have some kind of a notion of whether or not the asset
itself is actually present.
And then we need to know whether it's being used by one of those
background tasks.
So loaded and locked is what we decided for their loaded.
Just means it's there, but could be unloaded at some point because
nobody no background task is using it.
But lock means some background task is using it.
And therefore, it's not safe to Simply assume that
And get rid of it.
So, what I'd like to do is start by actually working with this locked
flag a little bit.
And what you can see here is that actually locked where we never
really set anything to locked and that's the problem.
So, if you look at, you know, that never actually occurs, and so at
some point, we go in and you can kind of see where we were.
If we were to jettison something, we have places where we actually
jettison it, right?
We have places where we go ahead and unload stuff in evict asset.
so, what we need to do now,
Is make sure that any time, anything that could get in to evict asset.
Is something that would only be set to asset State loaded, right?
And we have an assertion here for it.
So, we know that this routine will assert if we ever try to unload
something that wasn't loaded, but what we need to do now is make it so
that were actually using that locked state, so that we never get to
that point, right?
And we can kind of see where this is happening.
So when we do add header to list, for example, anything that calls,
add asset header,
List like these two guys right here, that should only be happening if
the final state that this thing is going to go into.
He is loaded and not locked, right?
If it's locked.
That's not going to cut it, right?
So we need to do a thing here where we're sort of seeing whether or
not this this assets going to be locked and when we do a load bitmap
call, that's kind of going to be that's going to be something that we
need to start thinking about.
So what I'm going to do here is just introduce a thing.
That's like if this thing is going to be locked then we would sort of
not do that thing, right?
And similarly I want to change this so we're going to do like, okay if
this thing is going to be locked, we're going to set it to lock
otherwise.
We're going to set it to loaded, right?
And so I want to do that and I want to do that in both places, right?
I want to do that.
Here as well.
So I want to do.
If it's locked, we're not going to do it and let's see here as well.
We're going to set it to locked, right?
And then what I'm going to do is inside load bitmap.
I'm going to introduce the notion of the lock and cure, right?
And just sort of set that up now it's isn't the cleanest way to do it.
There's some things that I might want to do differently eventually,
but we're going to take it one step at a time here.
So, let's take a look at handmade assets, load calls.
Here, they are in here.
I don't really know why those are in here.
I guess so that they can be called like this.
But we've got a little thing here that's going to do our locked there
and in our prefetch is prefetch even used.
So prefetch is prefetch is used for sound but not bitmap is basically
what happens.
So that's fine.
So we're going to have those locks in there and we're going to go
ahead and say it I guess to be fair we really don't even need locked
for sounds because sounds can't really be locked.
So it might be the case that actually I just go ahead and say well and
I could even say that prefetching bitmaps you can't lock a prefetch
either.
So we're just talking about bitmap loads.
Those are the
The things there will ever be lockable right.
Well I don't know for completeness let's just say for completeness.
Okay, so let's go ahead and do that and I want to take a look at load
sound here and just say, you know what?
Never mind what I said before was a total lie.
Sound since we never have to lock those, those can just stay
completely unlocked and off we go.
Right.
So there we go.
And now we've got load bitmap here.
Load bitmap is something that gets called in push bitmap.
And what I want to do is say that the render group itself knows
whether or not assets should be locked.
Right?
And what I want to do is I want to make sure
That instead of trusting like the caller to always do the right thing
with locking assets.
I want to basically introduce a thing where well, I guess I could do
this way.
Just say I want to be able to assert that.
If you are in a situation where you think you should always be locking
the assets that either, you know, that's not the case or
The asset itself actually is locked, right?
So if I get the state of the asset, so let's see.
I guess loaded bitmap doesn't have the slot ID so I could just say
this, I get if I get the state of of the of the asset then it should
be locked right asset.
Locked.
Alexa.
you know get bitmap could even do that check as well kind of like the
idea that's a maybe I want to do it this way even
I think that's even perhaps a little bit better, so get bitmap again.
The reason I'm thinking is I'm trying to design a system here, I'm
trying to make it so that it's hard for somebody to do the wrong thing
because it's easy.
It might be easy to accidentally type something wrong in there.
So, what I'm thinking is that, when you start up your render group,
right?
You just have an asset, should be locked setting.
And that way, you kind of know that the render group will always do
The right thing and your code can kind of be stupid and just ask for
assets and it doesn't really matter, right?
So that's my thinking.
So when you do an allocate render group will do a like you know,
assets should be locked, and then it'll say and in here that the asset
should be locked.
And then everything should be good.
So let's take a look at that, get bitmap call.
I think that's actually an h-file, right?
And so what happens here is when we do the get State and we check to
make sure that it should be locked.
What I want to do there is just say, OK, when you get in here, why
don't you also assert on the slot that it either equals asset locked
right or the assets.
Don't have to be locked, must be locked.
So, I want to start that either.
It doesn't have to be locked or actually was locked one of the other
and off we go, right?
So then we can do is when we fill ground Chunk, we can just say that
the assets have to be locked, but when we do our game rendering, we
can say that the assets don't have to be locked, right?
And that way, now, we should have a situation where it kind of takes
care of itself.
So now what we can do is kind of go.
All right, let's yeah.
In fact we can we're already getting the situation where our ass or
catching success.
So now we just have to go through and double check that everything
that we did is actually reasonable.
It looks like for some reason, this slot here, what is the actual
slot?
Say, let's take a look, so that's State 3, which again would be
loaded, right?
If you take a look at the asset file States,
Wait 0 1 2.
3 3 is locked.
Oh, right.
That's what that's exactly what we're just trying to prevent.
It's not loaded, right?
It's locked so somehow somebody got in there, who was actually locked.
And so we need to figure out how it was possible for somebody to get
in that array.
So did I mess up?
Let's take a look.
Unload pit map.
Let's see if it's supposed to be locked itself.
To locked.
If it's not locked, it adds it to the list.
So how did something get into the list?
That doesn't make sense.
How did something get into the list?
That itself was locked.
That's kind of weird.
Don't you think?
I'm going to go ahead and say when something, I guess something could
transition I suppose but I'm going to go ahead and check here and say
Okay, we've got the slot index.
So I want to assert that when we add something to this list, right?
It cannot be set to loaded.
This kind of another weird thing about this, right?
We add to the list.
Single-threaded here, right?
And that's a little wonky because that means that things are in the
list.
Before they've actually been set to loaded, they could be just not
loaded yet and it's almost impossible to conceive of them, actually
being freed before they were loaded, but we do probably need to make
sure that that's not happening, right?
Yes.
Oh, that's a little tricky, but if add asset header to list, take a
look at our two lists.
Like so this one, Ah, that's the problem typo there.
Okay, so that should be fine.
But what I was saying is like, you know, when we go to evict an asset,
right?
When we grab that first asset out of this list, we don't actually know
that it's been loaded.
It might just not be loaded, right?
So what we really need to do is we need to iterate over until we are
actually able to find one that isn't right.
That is actually loaded, just in case they all are.
So I think we want to do is say
Okay, we'll grab the the least reason to use asset will see if that
thing is loaded, if it's not, then we actually need to just go ahead
and say, oh, if it's not loaded yet just abort.
And we'll get it next frame after it finishes or whatever.
So, I'm going to say here, I want to say that make sure that the asset
actually is not just a sentinel and then say the asset should actually
also be loaded, right?
Like that's kind of just another thing that should happen, right?
In fact, what I could do there in evict asset, I feel like since we
need the slot here anyway, I feel like this sort of stuff you see
here.
Slot gets used here.
I feel like we almost want to pass the slot in.
So, in here, I'd sort of do something like.
Okay, we've got the slot there, right?
So we say, make sure it's not the Sentinel, then we do grab the slot,
and we would pass that slot along.
And I'd say if
State slot equals asset State loaded.
Then we would do the call right else.
Well, and I could also just do it this way.
Then the assert would happen there.
So, we'll make sure that it's something about loaded.
So that seems a little bit better to me.
Let's go ahead and also grab this slot index in there.
All right.
The header slot index.
So this is really the header.
I don't know why we're saying asset here, because it's not really
asset actually the header.
So there we go.
Heather.
Okay.
Let's see how that goes.
So that's very good.
That's exactly what we want.
You can see all the crazy flashing because I've set that threshold for
how much to load to basically be too low to even store the assets for
a single frame.
So it has to kind of cycle between them, but that's exactly what we
kind of want to see, right?
So that's all good.
But let's
Let's finish things up here so we've got one more thing we have to do,
which is that right now?
I don't know if you remember, but we don't when we use a bitmap,
right?
When a bitmap actually gets used like if I get bitmap or get sound, we
don't actually move it to the front of the list but we want to be able
to do that, right?
Because that's how we check, what's the least recently used in mostly
centrally reuse things.
This is just view it.
This is just assuming that the list again.
Is in that sorted order and we don't know that it actually is.
So what I'm going to do is every time we access the bitmap, I'm just
going to move it list element to the front, which again, is not a
particularly good way to do this.
But just something that we're going to start with.
And like everything, you know?
You don't really want to go overboard on making things awesome.
Until you know, that the awesomest just is going to pay off.
So if we turn out to do this and it just never ends up being a
performance problem, then maybe we don't address it, but there's a lot
of probably faster ways we can go about doing things other, than, by
doing a move to front linked list.
We could do stuff like having, you know, heaps to get sorted and stuff
like this.
So, you know, take it with a grain of salt but point being in here
when we do our get bitmap, what I want to do is I want to do like move
header to front, right?
Something
Like this where every time you use something, we move that something
to the front, right?
And the problem with this is that, if I remember correctly, our stuff
is kind of tortured right now.
Like, it's hard to get from slots to headers and that sort of stuff,
it's just really kind of tortured.
And this is the kind of thing that I don't usually have trouble with
when programming but on stream, it's really hard for me to Envision
complex data structures while I'm talking.
It's like really, really difficult, whereas normally, they're just
kind of in my head and happy and it's easy.
So things tend to get a little bit tortured.
Unfortunately, and that's sort of the state that I feel like this is
in at the moment which is to say that like we have this asset memory
header thing right and it's got a way of getting back to the assets
lat, right?
Because it's got the slot index but really it's kind of annoying.
But the reason
We wanted to do that is because we didn't want all the slots in the
game to have to have this all the time.
We only wanted the stuff that we actually loaded to have that, right?
And so you kind of see how that's a little bit of of an issue, right?
But we can get back to the header, we can get back to the header,
because we know what it's layout actually is.
So, in theory, right?
We can do a move header to front call and it would actually work.
It's just, it's just a little ugly so I'll write it, but it's
something worth knowing
Can probably simplify this code, a little, by changing our
organization of how things are lined up and thinking about it a little
bit more more sanely, right?
But anyway, what would that look like?
That would just look like us sending the assets and probably the slot
itself, right?
So that it could be determined, which one it was here.
So we call move header to front on the asset and the slot and move
header to front, would kind of do this little dance with it, right?
And so I'm going to go ahead and predefined that one, right?
Internal void move header to front and that's going to be gay, man.
That's sets and asset slot slot.
Okay, so when we compile, it will not find that, right?
And what we want to do here is we want to introduce this function.
Something that will take an asset slot and move its corresponding
header to the front of the list so that it will be like the last thing
freed.
If you were to, then do a free at that time, it would be the very last
in the list of things to be freed.
So when we do move header to front, what we're looking to do here is
we are looking to take
We are looking to take the header and do sort of a remap of it, right?
So we're looking to do a asset memory header.
So we're looking to take that somehow we get to that from the slot,
right?
We're looking to take the asset memory header and we're going to take
it out of the location that it was in, right?
So we're going to do something like we did before where we remap it.
So we say its previous points to its next and it's next
sorry, the the previous
the thing that is after
This link, its previous should point to our previous, right?
The thing before us.
And the thing that was before us, it's next pointer should point to
the thing that was after us, right?
So it's like, we never existed, right?
And then, what we want to do is we want to reinsert ourselves.
We want to reinsert ourselves in a very specific location which is
immediately after the Sentinel, right?
So we want to go ahead and take the loaded asset sense at all.
And say that that's our previous, right?
And our next is going to be that same wood as essential, whatever was
previously, the first thing in the list, right?
And then we're just going to link them up again.
Like we were doing before, right?
So now our previous next points to us and our next previous points to
us as well, right?
And that would be all we really need to do.
So the actual insertion and removal code is pretty straightforward.
We've already done it once and we can coalesce this code.
In fact with the other code if we wanted to because it's basically the
same
But the problem here is that we don't know how to get the header right
from the slot that's actually fairly tricky.
And if you see the way that that actually worked before, you can kind
of see that it did this sort of nonsense, right?
And so in order to, you know, in order to kind of make that in order
to make that happen and you know what, now that I look at it to you
could almost you could almost Envision just kind of doing this
directly, right?
Where we kind of just call Asset a tacit header to list because it
always does add it on in exactly the same way.
So we could just call this, right?
We could just call add a site header to list like so and it would just
be a question of, how do we get the header?
So, move header to front is, would just be this, this call, right?
So, we could do that if we wanted to
Something like this inline void link asset header.
This orb put asset header, insert asset, header at front, and it would
literally just be this code.
So that we don't have to know the slot index.
Right.
And so, yeah.
Insert, Bassett header, upfront assets, memory size.
Alexa.
So we could do that, right?
We could do it that way and I guess we well, we just passed a header
actually, we wouldn't need to pass anything else and so the question
again is just how do we get that that header right?
We just do insert us at header at front.
There's the header, right?
A new, I deleted.
A little more than I should have there because I wanted that removal.
But remove asset header from list already exists as well, right?
So I can just call that and there we go.
So again, I think that's all pretty easy.
That you said that way.
I don't we don't have to duplicate that code at all.
It's all just kind of nice and sane.
The problem is and I can inline these.
So that the zero setting will get optimized out not that we care.
But, you know, it would.
So the only problem here is just figuring out move header to front.
He's just figuring out where that header comes from.
Now we know that we can always do it this way, right?
We know that that that will always work but we don't actually have
this information at the moment and so in order to get that information
right since we started at the end, we would have to sort of do the
same thing that we did before.
So like when we call load bitmap or whatever, right?
When we do, when we do the thing that says get size of a
That or whatever.
Right, we would have to do that thing here, where we say oh okay you
know, how big is this thing, whatever it is and, and which type is it,
right?
Which we could also get so as we could get get type, right, get asset
type, or is it just get tight?
So, we can get the type and we could find out what the let me see.
What gets size asset.
What does it do with the slot index?
So, it just uses that to get the asset handle out, right?
So really get size of asset?
Probably wants to be looking at an actual asset, right?
So, that way, you don't need to know the slot index.
You could just have the asset of course.
In this case, we don't have the actual asset do we?
So I guess that doesn't necessarily help us
Never mind.
It's gonna say we could be a little clever there.
So yeah, let's go ahead and compile that.
So in this case, we don't actually know in order to get the size of
the asset.
We need to know what the slot to the next actually is so, oh well,
still need to know that it's okay.
We have it everywhere.
Who calls move header to front.
We do have the asset slot Index, right?
So that's all good.
And oops.
Actually put it in.
So that's not a problem.
But again, it's just sloppy, right?
It's like, I was saying, I think it's just architected a little wrong.
In terms of the way, the data storage is not laid out in the easiest
in the way that would be easy.
Do this.
So it kind of Warrant some attention the second but again I just want
to kind of finish what we're doing here.
So get bitmap function does not take three arguments that is because I
erroneously introduced slot index into it for no apparent reason why I
did that.
It's just dumb and then this is actually idea that value.
It's been a long day, it has been a long day.
Alright.
So,
really, I think
Insert header upfront takes game assets as well.
I think we are down to just the fact that we need to know the memory,
right?
And in order to know the memory we have that information but again
it's just it's just kind of janky, right?
Because if you take a look at how it that memory is being retrieved or
where, I guess you'd say where it's being saved in the case of a
bitmap we have it here, right?
So we kind of have like a thing where we're like, okay we've got
members
Three and we have to do a thing where we say, like okay, which type of
slot is this, right?
It's
See here.
It's a bit map.
Or the sound.
And in those cases, we have to like, go do the super nasty thing.
We're like, okay, fine, give me the bitmap memory.
In this case, give me the sound memory, right?
In this case,
That's just samples.
So that's everything as terrifying as that is, but I probably made a
little mistakes in there, and then that is the kind of difficult part.
Wait, what?
How is header?
No.
That's kind of strange.
What just happened there?
Get bitmap.
Oh, although one thing that I should think of to is that move header
to front.
Also only counts for loaded bitmaps because other ones aren't actually
in there if that makes sense.
But I don't really know why that that should still have given you a
valid header.
Okay, it does.
So that's all fine.
That's all fine.
Yeah.
So it move edited front.
I also want to do a get State on the slot and I want to make sure that
when I do, it gets date on the slot that's going to be loaded, right?
Or rather just not locked.
Cuz lock things aren't in there.
Right.
Again, yeah, I feel like it's probably just going to be time to clean
up this code.
It's just really too messy at this point because if you also look, if
you look at there's another kind of nasty thing in there, which is
that when things get inserted in originally we don't know, like locked
is really a flag, it's not a state, right locked should just be, you
know, it shouldn't be asset State locked because we need to know
whether that's the slot is locked or not.
Whether or not it has a header.
It doesn't matter whether it's been loaded yet or not.
If it's locked, it doesn't go in there, right?
And so that part is kind of also troubling me.
So I feel like this also is like asset State.
Loaded is just plain, you know, unloaded cute and loaded are separate
things.
And then there's, you know, an asset State locked, which is like a
separate thing.
Maybe we'll change the name of it just so we can tell.
L.
You know, and it's some flag that everything can have on it.
That's way more saying and that would be like you know is locked or
something like that.
And so that way we just always use that and we'd always have a thing
that was like you know is locked on and assets lat.
And that would actually just returned.
Whatever the state of that asset slot was anded with the, with the
lock flag.
And the reason that I want that is again because it's just things can
have three different states, essentially assets can, and the asset is
a locked asset or not, whether or not regardless of which state it's
in, it's not like assets.
Only get locked once.
They're loaded, their kind of just locked period, so it's locked even
when it's skewed, right?
It's still that.
That property, the this cannot be unloaded is kind of just something
that's just true, right about the thing.
And so what I kind of want to do is just say that that's just a formal
thing and like, you know, forget it.
It's like it is or it isn't locked.
Always, and it doesn't have anything to do with whether the thing was
loaded or not or anything else, right?
So that seems like a better idea to me.
So I'm going to go ahead and here and say that what's supposed to
happen is like, okay if I'm going to get a bitmap right, and it must
be locked.
Then what I want to do is I want to say,
Let's see here.
When we get the state, we look to see whether it's literally not.
If it must be locked.
I want to say like is locked.
Right, so that's good.
And these guys don't care about locking.
In here.
Yeah.
So in here, what we have is as soon as you actually try to load a
bitmap, what you want to do at that very moment is immediately set it
state to locked, right?
So it's always going to be loaded, it's always going to be a bitmap
and then possibly, you will, or in also, that lock flag, right?
But before you do anything else, you will also
The state of this thing to be locked, right?
So you will simply say,
Yeah, whatever this this assets lot state is it's it's locked now
because anyone wants to lock it, it becomes locked, right?
So that's all fine.
And so, when we do our move headed to front, we want to only do that
for assets, that are unlocked.
And that seems a little saner to me, that makes sense.
So let's take a look here, step in here and we look at the slot.
We can see that this is a locked one.
So since it's a locked one, it will not actually do its thing.
Let's see here.
Okay, so let's keep going.
We now have a get State equals asset loaded thing.
What I really want is to assert also that it's not locked, right?
I want to make sure we never do stuff.
It's locked.
Everywhere.
So, all of this code, I think we're now mostly at the point where it's
good, but we still have some things.
Like, I feel like we're at the point where it's like, you know, sort
of cobbled together working but it's not good.
Yes.
Is what I should say.
It's not, it's not like what I would like the code to be doing, but
it's almost there.
So we just need a little bit of cleanup and then it would be in a
reasonable State.
And then from there, I think what I really would like to do is just
kind of go through and refine the way.
This sort of slot asset thing is working.
Going to get it into a place where we don't have to constantly bounce
around so much and maybe we can just do something like a little bit
handy or there, right?
Little bit nicer.
Okay, so
Eight.
What?
I don't know.
At this point.
is really like,
So I guess what?
I don't really know how I can test this reasonably because we you know
until we get some debug visualization in there.
It's hard for me to tell whether or not this is actually working
reasonably, right because if I set it low enough, right?
If I set the the actual asset stuff low enough, then it will get into
a situation where it can't really function.
It'll have to page out things that actually needed.
But if I set it too high then I won't know that it's actually getting
hit right?
And so it's a little janky that way.
So let's say I said four megabytes was how much it had to work with,
right?
And that's clearly still paging stuff out and I know because the hero
blinks when he turns right and so it's clear, it is actually keeping
things paged in and out, right?
Which is kind of interesting.
So let's Let Me Take A we'll look at what's going on of handmade hero.
We could also reduce the memory footprint quite a bit of the whole app
and see like what this actually looked like.
But I'm just kind of going to play with it here.
So you can kind of see it working, okay?
You can see this commit size number the covering where it should
hover, right?
It's like going up a little bit and then it goes down, right?
As it sort of pages in and out and tries to keep itself at the
appropriate memory limit, right?
We really need to just load a bunch more assets and that's probably
something we can look at doing a little bit later but that's looking
okay.
Okay, so I'm going to call that working for now again until we have
some more debug code which is kind of the next thing on our list.
Actually, which is kind of nice.
I believe, if we take a look up here at our to-do list, right?
We've got D but well I guess it's not necessarily next on us, but we
could say that that is going to be up there.
Pretty high particle systems hilariously enough, we've already done.
But yeah.
Anyway, if I take a look at this and I said, maybe this is the thing
that we do, we'd fix the audio clicking because well, actually no, it
will do the debug code and we'll use that fix the clicking.
So making debug code.
Next on, this might be good too because that would allow us to
actually take a look at start taking a look at some of these things
and see how
They're working which is something that we can't really do it.
The moment we just kind of go well kind of looks like it works which
doesn't really help us.
So I what I'd like to do now is take a look at what we have and try to
simplify.
There's just too much fussing in my opinion, between like the assets,
Lots the asset, and the memory header, right?
There's just it's just, it's an issue.
And I don't love it, right?
So I kind of feel like we need to start condensing these things.
In some more intelligent way.
Right?
And that, that seems to me like like what we should really be doing.
So I'm going to take a look here at what we actually have to Marshal
and see what I can do if I don't melt first.
It's pretty hot in Seattle.
Again, it's very hot here.
So we have we have the data offset which is where in the file we did
get stuff.
We have the first tech index and one pass.
Last thing I was told to start a grange and then we have the bitmap
and sound info.
Right.
So that's the data that we're actually keeping for each.
One of these, that we got out of the file and it tells us how to use
the thing, right?
So that's all good.
We then have a file index
And the file index.
The file index is really just an index into this, the file, the file
set.
So, what we could do, without really adding any additional memory to
this, if we wanted to write, is we could just say that we have the
slot State and the file index.
Like, it really wouldn't be too much of a stretch to just kind of
merge these two things together like keeping the assets.
Lot separate wouldn't really be a huge deal.
I mean, I mean merging them together because I kind of said, like, oh
we could keep it separate but we don't have any, we don't really know
that we need to separate them and we could save that for later if we
decided, we need to separate them for some kind of reason.
And so cleaning things up to make it.
So there's just an asset and not an asset slot might actually make it
so that there's just a one less thing to worry about and that be a
pretty easy change to make, right?
So for example, a transformation of this code I could make that would
be really straightforward, is just to do that.
Right?
Or something like this and say, okay the assets, lot in the asset or
now just one thing.
Okay.
And so if I did that, let's just see what that would do.
Right?
So now we don't have assets lot anymore.
We just have assets and so everywhere.
That was looking at one of these things is now just only has to look
at one of them, right?
So that's all good.
And we could sort of just say that slot becomes asset now,
Right?
And these are all just asset asset things.
So asset slot comes asset.
So and Slot becomes asset.
So that's it.
Index assets, asset asset, asset asset.
Right.
So let's see how this goes again.
Now, we just have asset we don't have to deal with slots, just assets
and so work asset state to final State.
We've got an asset slot.
This becomes an asset assets again, I guess asset, slot, becomes
asset, asset, asset asset.
So on, let's go ahead and take a look here.
Slot becomes asset.
Slots slots, slots slots, lat,
I think basically just everywhere we were using slot is just now an
asset.
Right.
Okay?
So asset index is not a member of the header that is true, because
it's still called slot and mixing here.
So here, we'll just call it asset index.
And off we go, right?
So, that's all good.
That's index.
As an index acid index.
Okay.
So that's all good.
Nothing strange going on there.
So now let's see what we could do.
What could we do to simplify things further right?
What can I do here?
So, another big problem we have is we've got this offset memory
header, right.
And the asset memory header is stored in.
Whichever one of these things actually gets loaded here, right?
So how do I want to deal with that?
Like, what do I actually want to have happen there?
I think what I want to have happen there.
I'm just gonna throw this out there.
Stop me if I'm going crazy.
You know, stop me if I'm just going banana cakes on you.
What if we were to do the very simple potential transformation of
saying, all right, got the state.
And then we've just got a pointer to the asset memory editor, right?
So, we've got the asset.
We've got a pointer to the mass at memory header.
Any acid memory header is the thing that actually has this in it.
Right.
And in here, we've got a thing that's like the type of the asset.
And so, then we have a thing that's like asset type, right?
It's got sound or bitmap in it.
EXO.
Something like this.
You know, in fact, we could actually make that just be that something
like this.
Tell me how you're feeling about this.
Are you feeling this?
I don't know if you're feeling it or not.
I'll be honest with you.
I just really have no idea at this point but you know, only you know
how you feel about it.
So I do something like that, right?
And now we're starting to get somewhere.
Because now it's very clean, you just say, okay, there's an asset.
It's got an asset memory, header, and that asset memory header tells
you whether this thing actually had sort of in the queue, in fact,
it's almost as if we might, not even really need this anymore all that
much.
But yeah, I don't know.
So the lock would really be the thing.
I think maybe that should be down in here, whether this thing is
locked or not, so we just
Unloaded cute or loaded so, well, I'm not sure about where the lock
goes yet.
So I'm just going to play with this first.
I'm going to see what happens if I just do this.
This one transformation and start to clean up the problems with it.
Right?
Okay.
Oops.
So this is like this can't really be asset type here.
So I don't know what we'd call this asset memory type, something like
that and not a good name, but what do you do?
So in here we have asset.
Type mask, we don't need that anymore.
Because really if you want to get the type of an asset, you need to be
talking about that asset, headers type thing, I'm going to remove this
temporarily and see who calls it and actually handle it at the call
site.
I think because I want to see what they're doing.
All right.
So yes, that's true.
Asset is not a member of bitmap.
So what we can do here is say okay it's just the header, right?
And we can assert that the asset header.
We don't even need to, it'll just be, it'll immediately fault if
that's if that's not the case.
So, when you grab the bitmap, we just get it.
That way, we drop the sound.
We get it out a header like so, right.
And then in here, we would need to do the same exact thing, right?
So we get that out of the header.
Now, the key thing though, is that header doesn't exist yet, right?
So what we would need to do there.
We would need to allocate the memory first.
So we would do the add the asset memory size situation.
We would then sort of get the memory out so we'd say the asset right
header equals.
Acquire asset memory.
Like so I'm liking where this is going.
People are you are because are you feeling this?
I feel like you should be feeling this at this point.
I don't know if you are or not.
But you know, I might suggest at this point that if you're not feeling
it, maybe that's you and not me, okay?
Like I don't want to, I don't criticize you right, you know you have
the right to your own opinion.
I'm just trying to save you that opinions wrong.
Right.
Let's uh put it out there.
Yeah, I mean you gotta call a spade a spade at some point, right?
And you know, you don't get you don't get an e for effort in this
class, okay, you got to keep up.
Alright, so in this case,
when we do,
The asset memory stuff you can kind of see what I'm doing.
I'm saying.
Okay, the header is now Primal.
So we allocate the memory, the, the, the header is the memory and this
is kind of starting to unwind.
That sort of nasty.
Where is the header versus the bitmaps and whatever?
It's like, that stuff is kind of condensing now into its just a
little, all of the stuff that was necessary for when the asset is
loaded is now all in this header and it all kind of is nice and clean
and we know where it is, right?
So just I'm just untangling that mess.
Right, so then it's not a mess anymore, at least to the extent that we
can make that happen, right?
So that's all good, and let's keep going here.
So here is our sound.
We actually don't want the.
Where am I?
Where am I doing the bitmap header bitmap?
Yeah, that's that's what we want.
So in here we're going to do the exact same thing.
I'm going to come up here.
I'm going to say that the asset header is going to be that asset
memory header.
I'm going to get that from this guy, right?
And that's all good.
Everyone loves that.
And then
I can do asset header sound after we get the memory, right?
And then when we do the loading here, where we do the destination
memory thing, that's again, just going to be header plus one.
So exactly the same asset header plus 1.
The extra memory that we allocate is part of that allocation is what
goes in there.
So let's keep going here.
Sighs total, I need to move that guy up here like that and that's
fine.
Fine, and there we go.
Let's see, and so sound at.
Yeah.
Is just going to kind of be is going to be this again, so I guess I do
maybe want to waste our memory to still be defined here.
Cuz it has to happen with this dude.
Like so, right?
All right, so now when we do move header to front, all of this stuff,
gets way cleaner.
I think that's my guess.
Anyway, so basically, you know, we get this thing now, we don't need,
you don't need to pass the slot index because you've already got the
asset, right?
So now you say okay, I don't care what size.
Yes, that is, doesn't matter, right.
I'm going to ignore what type it is.
Even because I already have the header right to get the header.
It's just asset header.
That's it, right?
Bam, done.
And off you got right way, way, way way, way nicer than it was before,
we've had her two front.
No longer needs that asset Index, right?
So that's gone, goodbye.
That is also gone.
Goodbye.
Okay in here.
Exactly.
Okay.
So this is just great, right?
All this garbage goes away, totally not necessary anymore.
Totally not necessary anymore because no matter what the type is, we
already know how to release it.
Although I guess we don't have the size though.
We could keep the size in there now, because again, now everything
shoved out into the header, it's only there when we actually allocate,
so we don't have to worry about it.
Kind of
Itself out.
So, that's another thing we could fix.
But I'll leave this for now, just for now.
And we don't have to do the memory thing so we can just do that,
right?
Can just do that and then come in here and say, okay release asset
memory.
It's going to be the header, so asset header and then that becomes 0,
right?
Okay.
And so now in here if we want to know the type of this guy, we would
just look at the headers type field and then we need to set that.
At some point, we would need to is that the only place now that the
person needs to get that's like the only place.
Right.
I mean that's it.
So, I would say just the heck with it, right?
Don't even store the type.
Then at that point.
If we now, if we no longer care, right?
We just store the size, right?
I mean, total size, right?
That makes sense because now if we just or the total size, then we
don't need to do this anymore either.
We just say okay the asset header total size, right, that's all we
needed to know.
And that's way better.
So then when we do the header stuff here,
I feel like, that's pretty much all we need to do.
We just need to actually save that information.
So at the place where it does its asset index nonsense here, right and
add asset header to list.
It, just needs to do header total size equals size total, right.
It just needs to poops.
That's not good.
Just needs to save that off.
all right, so
Not quite there yet.
All right.
So let's see.
Are how are we getting an asset header of no there?
Get sound.
Everybody should have their header if they're actually valid.
Right?
If they're actually loaded, everyone should have had their header set.
Asset header equals acquire memory,
Lewd sound said header was a car, asset memory, like so asset header
equals when we release asset memory here and we set their state equal
to unloaded.
That should be fine.
All right but we're still a little janky unfortunately.
All right, so what happened there?
Exactly, show me what happened.
Mr.
Coad show me on the code, where we're at, and old you.
So, LED bitmap, we are inside the get bitmap call.
We wanted to call move header to front the asset file, the asset
itself that we're talking about here.
It's not actually in the list.
So it's this guy, remove asset header from list.
Let me see that's okay, remove asset header from last list.
Hmm.
I say.
Oh man.
This this I left this in there.
Look at that.
What is that doing there?
That's just nonsense.
That's total nonsense.
That's just right.
That's just lame.
That's no good at all and so yeah.
That's our problem.
So we just need to go ahead and get out.
The actual header.
He'll be fine.
So now we're in better shape.
Now, we are in better shape and this should not take the memory
because that memory is now, totally not relevant.
All right.
So now we're back to good.
Throwing a little bit problem there, so that's all fine.
But looks like we don't quite have are loaded locked sort of
situation, quite correct.
Although get State asset.
What is our asset state state is 3?
Where's that at?
Oh, and we have to do the asset memory type thing too, right?
That's got to go away.
So this stuff right get size of asset.
This all gets Unwound as well, man.
This just goes, we're just going nuts here, right?
Because we were still ordering in this nonsense, which we don't want
it all.
So yeah, this is just this is just
This is just all going to kind of unwind very nicely.
So we want to get rid of that and get rid of that, right?
And so what we want to do here is say that this this get size of
assets thing, you know, this is just for now I could even just do is
sound something like this right?
And do you know okay if it is a sound then do this, otherwise do this
and off you go, right?
But that's
Art.
I can unwind it further and kind of go back to the original way.
We had things in a second here, right?
So hold on one second while I do that.
And now we should be one step closer Theory, right?
And so there's one of the things that it would nice to be just to
unwind that get size thing, right.
So let's unwind that get size thing as well.
What we would like to do here is instead of get size of asset having
to actually be sort of this separate thing, we just say okay well if
it is a sound, which it is like in this case, right?
Then we're going to compute this stuff.
So we're basically just undoing the code change that we did before.
We're just saying, okay, you know, get get rid of this and the size of
the thing, the asset memory
Eyes of the thing.
Can we compute it in a different way here?
So it would just be saying,
I could even keep sort of this notion around where I just do something
like sighs.
Like so I say the section size is this the data size is this?
And the total size is this, right?
So you can still kind of just cut and paste the code, exactly.
As it is in place and then I do the same thing for the bitmaps, right?
So the bit map would look like this.
So drop that into the bitmap code here and that would just be again.
Sighs sighs sighs.
Like so.
Okay.
Squad compile.
That fix any problems that we've got there, don't need that duplicate.
And results dot sections, that size that section.
Okay, cleaner still less code is better code pretty much always.
And so now we're back to pretty good.
We now you know, we've added that stuff and we're only 500 lines,
which is better.
We kind of where things were getting kind of multiplied out there a
little bit too much, but that's pretty good.
And now we could sort of get rid of asset memory size and return this
code, kind of a little bit back to its furthest day, but I think
that's good for today we're at an hour.
So I'm going to go ahead
And go to the Q&A.
For those of you who have questions now, would be a good time to ask
them.
Please prefix your questions with Q: so I can see them.
Because if I can't see them, I can't answer them.
Your head was over the window when you were looking at the commit
size, I highly doubt that because I have eggs the I don't think that's
true.
Maybe that was true.
Oh man.
No, you're right.
That could be true because this is a non top window.
Hmm.
There we go.
That's a little bit better.
I should probably leave it that way on stream because that way it goes
behind this so I can see what you can't see.
Where is handmade?
There we go.
Although for some reason, it's back to always on top.
I know, I guess there's not much I can do about that other than just
to be sort of semi Vigilant about it.
Santa nipple the linked list way of computing least used asset seems
like a simple and neat trick.
What are its drawbacks really the primary drawback of it is it's just
too much work right?
Because if you think about it, right?
What's the minimal amount of information that's necessary to know
whether this asset was used on a frame?
Like, we just need like one, integer something right.
That says it was you.
Has Don this Frame or something like that, right?
And so, if you think about the cost to update one integer, right
versus the cost to do, the move to front thing the move to front
thing, it writes, the next pointer,
And the previous pointer, right?
And those are.
So this is 4 bytes, right?
It writes, all of these eight byte values, the next and the previous
pointers of the links on either side of it to remove it, right?
So removal has to rewrite, those two.
And then it has to rewrite its own next and previous, right?
So own own, this is like our before.
And this is our after and then we have to insert a we have to tell the
people who were inserting near what to do and that's the same thing,
right?
So we have removal and addition
So we're talking about writing 6x8 best case, 6 by 8.
Bytes.
Everytime, We Touch the resource rather than maybe something more like
4, bytes, or 8, bytes, right?
And you know, these are scattered around memory.
So each one of those is going to make a new cache line hot and so it's
just it's just a lot of extra work and so you'd rather kind of be
somewhere more like this if you care.
Now again, we may not care.
We may leave that in there till the game ships and that's just fine
and it does not matter and the important part of the algorithm is just
that we know that what was recently used.
Because we just don't hit bitmaps that often compared to the rest of
the work, we have to do to make it matter, right?
And so that may be true but
If you're just kind of thinking about what the drawbacks are, well,
well, there's some pretty obvious ones and it's just that it's a lot
of work compared to other things that we might be able to do, you
know, you never know.
So so I don't mind.
I say it's bad.
You know, every algorithm has its usage, it might be fine for us, but
there might be reasons why it's not, it's not okay.
Girl and a blue, maybe two.
I'm today.
Okay.
Well, you know, it's a, it's three hours later where he is and the
kind of time when people might be drunk, can you explain the code in
which you change the asset loading, so that it stops blinking the
bitmaps and sounds sure.
So let's do a simple experiment.
What could we do to bring the blinking back, right?
Well what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and say instead of
evicting.
The assets that were most recent that we're least recently used.
I'm gonna remove the ones that were most recently used, right.
And I'll explain this in a second.
I just want to show you right?
Or not.
There we go.
Mike.
We have to we have to actually just get to a point where we can where
we hid them in barrier, right?
And so you can see how this stuff is disappearing, right?
But in theory, if I go ahead and change that back to the other way, it
was right now.
Everything's fine.
So what's happening here?
You know what's going on?
And you can still see that assets are being evicted because new asset.
Sometimes take a frame to page in.
And as you can see, the little guy blink
But so we still are very acid constrain that's happening to free all
these assets because we made it super asset can reach me at.
Super memory, contains only using like, I don't know how much 4
megabytes for assets.
Three megabytes for assets right now, which is a joke, you know,
compared to how big it will be.
When we actually allow it to use, most of the memory in the game for
assets, which is what we will do.
But let's talk about what happened there.
So this is the piece of code.
And what's supposed to be happening here, right?
Is, we have a recent c-list, basically.
And what the recency list is is it's a sentinel.
Right, that we keep.
Which is basically a dummy Link in our linked list and what it is is
it's the link that sort of the head and tail of the linked list, it
has a previous pointer and it has a next winter, all good.
All right, so the previous pointer
Is pointing to the tail of the list.
The next pointer is pointing to the head of the list, right?
And the list kind of goes on like this.
Right?
It's a big circular list.
In fact, maybe I should draw it a little bit slightly differently just
to make it clear clearer, right?
So let's say this is the list, right?
So, there's the next pointer.
Next pointer next pointer
And this next pointer comes all the way back around.
Meanwhile, the previous point.
Those are like previous.
Previous previous.
But this previous pointer goes all the way over here.
So it's a circular list, right?
I wonder if we could even do it like this.
Okay, next pointer previous pointer.
This is the Sentinel, right?
So we got something that's like you know, next
Previous.
Next.
Previous next, right?
Previous/next
Previous next, previous next previous, right?
So, you can kind of see the previous just kind of wine to the thing
this way, and the next wine through it this way.
So we just have like, counterclockwise and clockwise right.
It's kind of like me exploring ways to draw a doubly linked list.
Here's another one that I was just thinking of as well, right?
You could imagine it being like this, I guess.
Let's see if we can do this.
All right, so you can imagine it being like something like this.
Where you have like previous/next previous/next, right, previous/next?
Not sure.
This is making it worse, previous next.
Previous next.
Previous next, right?
The next I'll go like this.
Ring.
And the previous logo the opposite direction.
Right?
So it's like a little, two wheels, one goes counter, clockwise one
goes clockwise right.
And these are links in here, is our Sentinel Sentinels always there.
It's a dummy.
It doesn't have any data associated with it, right?
But then these guys are actual assets.
So this is an asset, you know, this is an asset whatever, right?
So what happens here is whenever an asset is loaded, it gets inserted
in between the Sentinel and whatever asset is currently.
At the head.
So it comes in right here, right?
So the next pointer of the Sentinel will point to it and the previous
pointer of whatever asset was previously at the head will point back
to it.
So it'll come in right here.
Okay.
Now every time we use an asset, we also move it to the front as if it
was just used as if it was just added.
So if this guy is actually about to be used, we first cut him out of
the list.
And we jump it so that this guy points over him.
And this guy points to here and then we reinsert him up here, right?
So what's happening is the circle is constantly being cycled.
So that the order in which you occur around, the circle, is the order
in, which you were most recently used.
So, this is the guy who was most recently used, right?
And we go down.
Less recently, used less recently, used less recently is less recently
as less revenues, all the way to the person who was added last.
Basically who's the least recently used.
Okay, so what we wanted to do to minimize the Flickr was to make sure
that we never evicted an asset that was very recently used.
And so what we did is we said okay just take whatever the previous
pointer is of the Sentinel, that's the person who was touched the
longest ago, and he will get evicted.
Right?
And if we and we just keep evicting, we keep killing people out.
Get rid of him, this guy would be next, get rid of him, get rid of
him, we keep pulling people out until we see that.
Our memory footprint has gone below the target.
Will there be a concern of cache misses while manipulating the doubly
linked lists every frame?
So there is
The concern is theoretically there in reality will it'd probably be a
problem, I actually doubt it but you saw when I was sort of pointing
out those how there's that those six rights instead of one, right?
You know it's it's 6 times worse.
You might say although the cash because the next and previous partners
are next to each other.
It's really just three cache things probably but it's three versus one
and that's you know, a thing.
but since the next in previous pointers are kind of near to its
again.
Really the answer is.
You shouldn't be thinking about that right now, right?
Because you have absolutely no idea what your cast, you should even is
in any of the code at this point.
So worrying about that is not really very useful.
You need to get to the point where you're actually looking at your
performance holistically and go, oh, I have too many cache.
Misses here
Because of this linked list, right?
And that's really the time that you would think about it.
You've got to do about the size of the audio assets trucked.
How important do you think it is to keep structs compact?
So, at this point, I actually kind of changed my mind about that.
And the reason is because, so I fixed that today, basically, this
stuff now, no longer has to be the case because loaded sound is not in
the slot anymore.
It's often the memory header, right?
So we totally fix this because the reason I was worried about those,
Things before was because assets Lots were proliferating, like,
there's going to be as many assets.
Lots as there are assets and so that's a big concern asset memory
header.
We don't care at all because the asset memory, header only exist for
assets.
They're actually loaded.
And what we know is that the asset size itself of the data is going to
dwarf whatever else is in there.
So now, we actually don't have to care about that at all, right?
And I can go undo.
In fact, that change that we did, before where we were like, oh man,
look,
Bitmap, we got to make these things, right?
It's like math, forget, it doesn't matter, right?
So we don't need like, none of that stuff matters at all.
Load it back and be as long as it wants to be, we can get rid of the
safe truncates.
So all that stuff can just be, you know, whatever.
It's totally dot does not matter, right?
So that was actually a really good aspect of today's change, was that
we move something, and I'll can try to.
I can try to explain that.
The Whiteboard a little more as well, if that makes sense.
But basically what's going on.
Also there was another one to right here.
I'm going to go ahead and get rid of those temporarily and see where
they actually were
Right.
Okay?
So, the reason I was concerned is right, we have an asset slot table,
right?
So, we have an asset table and the number of Assets in here is the
total number of Assets in the game, right?
So this n is large, okay?
If we have 100,000 Assets in the game,
Poor ejection if we have 100,000 Assets in the game or something,
right?
Then we pay, however, big the assets truck size is we pay 100,000
Is that right?
So if the assets truck size is 128 bytes, right?
Then it was 12 Meg's right?
For the asset thing.
So I didn't want those two like peripheral or eight proliferate.
And so the way that we had it before, was that all of the, the data
was in that asset slot, right?
The loaded bitmap in the loaded, sound and stuff.
So I had to worry about how big these were getting.
I was actually starting to think about that, right?
But as it is now, we've put it.
So that the only things that are in there are the state and the
pointer to the header and the stuff that we actually need to load out
of the file again and we could actually do some stuff to even reduce
that further.
I can put it to do there, which is to do.
Should the one should the tag info?
Oh wait.
No, it can't be never mind.
We can't reduce that further.
I take it back.
So this is like not the minimal amount that we need but it's getting
closer.
Right?
Because what we did is we moved all of that stuff out of the asset and
into the asset memory header, and the asset memory header is actually
a very small number.
This is proportional to the loaded.
Asset count.
Right.
So we might only have like, 1,000 assets loaded at a time, right?
And we can control that number very easily.
This number, we can't control.
It is, however, many there are in the game total, but this number we
can just dial because it's just that this are, you know, we've written
the paging system.
We can make this whatever we want.
So I no longer have to worry, really, how big the headers are?
And plus the header is only there, if the rest of the data was loaded
in the rest of the data is huge.
It's like 20 56k or something.
So hey at that point am I going to worry about a 16 extra bytes or
something?
No,
And so moving stuff out of here and into here is a big deal because it
lets us not care about how big it is.
Do you have a hard drive to check this system on it?
This is a hard drive.
I'm not sure.
Are you trying to say versus an SSD drive?
This system is a hard drive.
It's an old-school spins on a platter hard drive.
Is there a problem showing a Sahara to know laughter unlocking?
It I thought there was some background loading of some stuff.
Well, let's take a look at where you're talking about.
Are you talking about here?
right here because in that case, when we evict an asset, we know that
it's not the loading is not in
That's because the loaded is set to true.
So when loading, when an asset is loaded, there's no more background
tasks operating on it, right?
And it better be okay to set the header to zero, because we just
released the memory that the headers in
Is the Heap and the stack just different sections of ram, managed by
the OS.
Also, if so doing do different programs ever.
Share stack space, would you please shut some light on this or point
me to some video of yours that I missed?
Yeah, I mean that's covered in the early, handmade hero videos.
We definitely talked about that.
Basically, the Heap is not really a thing.
The Heap is like, utility code that runs on top of the system's,
actual memory manager, which is like the
Each table which is like virtual a lock, right?
So, like a heap, is basically a utility allocator that sits on top of
your system, operating systems page table.
The stack is basically a reserved memory space that is contiguous and
which gets added to as your program calls into functions and returns
from functions.
It pops it off and we have talked about those on him a hero before.
I'm confused as to what the memory layout will be after using the BB
like this for a while, the memory will fragment eventually as of now
know, as of now common.
Oh well, so to be honest with you, the answer is a bit scary which is,
I don't know.
And the reason that I don't know is because right now we are asking
virtual a lock to get us our memory, right?
So what we're actually doing right now, remember when we started, I
said let's do it first where we asked the OS for memory and release
the
Wes memory, which will be probably fine on 64-bit systems.
I don't know if you get fragmentation of the page table, I honestly
just don't know.
I don't know very much about entities page, table algorithm, I don't
really know.
And so that's why I was saying before those like, I don't think we
probably want to leave it this way because like obviously the next
step for a system is for us to replace the call to the operating
system with our own memory thing at which point we'll be
In a better position to deal with fragmentation.
Could we just use an is locked pool inside asset header?
Yes, we could.
Won't this mess of swapping the assets cause memory fragmentation?
Again, I really just don't know.
I can explain to you why it's a little confusing to know.
So,
Only right.
When you're doing allocation, you're doing allocation in memory space,
right in virtual memory space.
So if you, you know, have 2 gigabytes of memory, right?
And you allocate something here and then you allocate something here
and you allocate something here and then this goes away.
Now you have a potential fragment because if you have something big,
you can't fit it in there and you can't fit in here.
But if you had moved this over, you know, back you could have fit it
down here or something, right?
So that happens but the operating system, you know, cheats right?
One of the the travesties of modern operating system design is that
this stuff isn't exposed to the user space, but the operating system
doesn't live in virtual memory space.
The operating system lives in physical memory space, right?
And so what happens with physical memory space is there's just a bunch
of 4K pages.
Well, or whatever the page size is, but like okay, 4K, 4K 4K, 4K 4K,
okay.
And what the operating system does is the operating system has a page
table.
That just says all right, you know, bro says he wants some memory.
So I like made him some memory.
He said he wanted 16k so I gave him four pages starting at page 2,
right?
So it was like here, here here and here, right?
Makes sense.
And then later, bro said he wanted like, you know, to he wanted 8K.
So I gave that to him starting, you know, right here, right?
So this is 2 3, 4 5 6 7, right?
So 6 & 2, right?
So here's the the count of pages and the index, right?
And because the operating system has the luxury of remapping, these
things
Later on when it freeze this, it could use those 4K Pages.
Arbitrarily.
They don't have to be contiguous right later on.
It could say, oh, you know, he freed these four and you know these
these pages are still used.
So like these guys are used, these guys are used, but these guys get
free and someone needs six pages.
You know, someone needs 12K.
Well it doesn't really matter because
Then what it just went.
What it does is it says sorry six pages would not be 12 guys.
Six pages would be 24K.
What it does is goes.
Okay I'll just give him these three and then I'll give them the other
three down here and it can just go ahead and do that.
Because it can say in is Page table that these guys and these guys map
to a continuous region in the apps virtual memory space.
So even though this is three pages and then three pages,
That are separate.
In the to the app looks like six continuous pages of memory.
That's the magic of virtual memory mapping.
The processor does the translation of the addresses, right?
And so, I don't know if there's a risk of fragmenting the page table,
Because you can imagine, there is a thing here that has to do.
Where it's like, okay, I can't just store account anymore.
If I'm doing this like, you know, thing here.
So I don't know.
I don't know, fragmentation is a lot easier to deal with when you have
virtual memory mapping.
So it may be that the operating system just would never have a
fragmentation problem.
Captain does.
So something like this?
Can't happen asset.
If Vic function is called release happens, unlock happens thread.
Context switches to loader
Something gets loaded into that slot with some header.
Thread context, which is back hetero, no nothing like that can ever
happen.
So you're thinking about this a little bit wrong.
And let me just clarify that to make it very clear.
So when you're doing multi-threaded coding, you have to remember what
is and is not multi-threaded because otherwise you go nuts, right?
In our code, we are not multi-thread happy.
The only multi-threading code is load asset work, right?
This is the only thing that is multi-threaded right now in our asset
system.
What that means is that the only thing we have to worry about is
whether or not
Something load asset work is going to touch data wise could be
problematic and what we know is that platform read data from file.
Well that's just going to read data into the asset block.
So that's pretty much never a problem, right?
The only thing we have to make sure that we do is that we don't
declare that the asset is ready before that read is finished.
That's about it, right?
Or we might get some garbage on the screen when it tries to use those
bitmap dips, right?
So really, once we set the the final State thing here, right?
Once we set final State, the only thing we have to worry about for the
most part is that whatever this guy is doing, it's not going to
possibly right to something that the other code was trying to write 2
as well.
And what we know is that when you kick off a load asset work, right
when we kick off a load asset work, the only state that we do that in
is when we've done an atomic compare exchange to set an asset into
accused State.
And once an asset is an accused State, no one can ever kick off.
Background tasks on it again and more importantly no one could use it
either because it's cute.
So until this actually finishes
And marks it as loaded.
No one else will ever touch it, right?
Makes sense.
So everything else is single threaded, there's no way you could be
calling this code to kick off an asset read, at the same time, as
you're calling this code to evict an asset because they're in the same
thread.
Right?
So they can never conflict with each other.
Does that make sense?
Is it possible that due to the kernel caching disk accesses, we're
paying more than once for each asset.
Like after we evict an asset is another copy of it.
Likely to be cashed in physical memory because of the OS is cashing in
the PAC file.
The answer is.
Yes.
And the reason though, that that's not particularly Troublesome is
because presumably,
Before we get to the end of this project, we will be compressing the
asset file.
So we're really never going to be storing that data multiple times.
Right now.
What we would like is to be able to do non-cash to reads to the kernel
which are switch to something.
We could try doing there are ways that you can sometimes do that, but
a lot of times you really just can't.
And so there's not much you can do about it, other than, if you wanted
to try to use memory mapped files, but I don't really like memory
mapped files because they have a bunch of other problems.
Not the least of which being that you can't load files that are bigger
than 32.
Bits of address space on 32-bit Windows which is bad obviously, right?
So yeah.
All right.
Let's go ahead and close down.
Close down.
Okay everyone.
Thank you so much for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
It has been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, we finish up that round of asset system work, which is
pretty cool.
And so, now we just have to kind of think about do we want to write
our own memory allocator now that we've got everything arranged and
working using the system's memory allocator, right?
And so that's what we'll talk about tomorrow, and we'll think about
that tomorrow.
Until then, if you'd like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on Hammer here at or get get the source.
Code comes to the source code even today in just when we're just
working on the render, you can already working on the engine rather.
You can already follow along at home if you want and play around the
source code kind of experiment with it and learn from it.
So if you want to do that handmade here at org, you can also support
our patreon page if you're so inclined and you can go to our forums,
we can ask questions or get community.
I done asset Community done episode guide and ports to like mac and
Linux and head of when we're doing those.
And there's also a tweetbot, the tweets, the schedule at you, which
you can go to.
If you would like to keep abreast of the series is
Also, if you want to know when we're going to be live, you can check
that out.
But tomorrow we will be back at 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
So that is what will be alive tomorrow.
You will need to check the teapot from that.
I will see you tomorrow when we will talk about, whether we want to go
ahead and take that extra step of doing our own memory allocator and
maybe we do.
Right?
Maybe we want to go ahead and spend a couple days on that, that's
about it.
So I hope you will all have fun programming until tomorrow when I will
see you back here.
So until
then I'll see you guys in the internet and take it easy, everyone.