Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we code a complete game live on stream.
We are going to do some coding on our debug you.
I today we've got a lot of it working and we did the integration with
the game yesterday in terms of like unifying the UI between the two
systems.
And so now what I'd like to do today is just kind of like go in there
and sort of play around with getting it all, you know, straightened
out to the point where we can kind of navigate the debug info the way
that we might want to.
And it kind of looked like yesterday, just looking at it for a debug
you I kind of felt like we might want to also pass some modifier Keys
into the game for debugging purposes.
Such as like whether the Ctrl alt or shift keys were down.
That seemed like something that we might want to do again, not really
for any kind of
Gameplay purposes but actually just as part of the debug packet.
So like when we pass it for example, the mass location and the mouse
buttons which are only really used for debug,
those would also include some modifier key information.
So that's what I'm going to do today.
It's Day 2 13 on him a hero.
So if you preorder the game on handmade hero dot-org and you're trying
to follow along with source code at home, you will want to take day
212 source code and you'll want to unpack it into a directory so that
you can you know match up with what I'm doing and do the changes
yourself or play around with the changes yourself.
So here we are at where we left things the other day.
We did sort of have this this concept of being able to like hover over
entities.
We still haven't really figured out how we want to do sort of the hit
detection when there's multiple entities.
Like there's the space entity that kind of encompasses each individual
room and, you know, depending on the random order in which the end of
these get traversed.
You know, sometimes I'll get pics of him but I can't pick a tree down
here because it picks the space out of the first.
Whereas I can, for example, pick one of these trees and so on.
So, you know, at some point we probably
Have to address how we want to do picking in order to make it more
useful.
We might just not allow space entities to be picked for now or, you
know, something like that.
So that you can only, you can pick the kind of entities that are more
obvious, like these ones, which we can't pick.
Right now.
That's something.
We should probably address.
But then also what we kind of want to do is sort of, have a little
more coherent idea what's going on over here.
What I did yesterday was makeup so that I could kind of like highlight
a bunch of edit of these guys and you can kind of see them displaying
here, but there's a number of things that don't really quite work in
this scenario.
Do you know some of the interaction sort of work where I can look at
some of these things?
But it's not really entirely stable and it also we don't have things
like the collapsible menus and all that stuff and we also don't have
our old debug things.
So again there's just a bunch of code in the debug system now that we
figured out and it's going to be kind of this process of integrating
it all together and making sure that it's all nice and stable and
clean usable friendly, etc, etc.
So, let's go ahead and
Keep going down that that route.
So the first thing that I'd like to do again is I think I'm just going
to pass those modifier keys because right now what happens is like I
just keep selecting entities and they keep getting added to the set of
entities that are like selectable, right?
And you can kind of see what's happening.
Also our frame rate is awful at the moment because if you remember one
of the things that we also have to do is make it.
So our debug system only processes a frame at a time.
We're not doing that currently either.
So yeah, we just have a lot of stuff to do just in terms of
Like basically code clean up.
I think we have all of the pieces for the most part that we actually
need.
But it's just not all working in a nice smooth fashion because there's
just too much Jank Enos in too many places, that's the nature of code.
When you go exploring to see how you want to build something, it's
nothing to be concerned about, unless you then don't actually go and
clean it back up, in which case, it's something to be very concerned
about, but as long as we are going to go do that, no need for concern.
So first, I'm just going to fix that modifier key problem because the
modifier key situation is definitely
Only a little bit busted so I'm going to go ahead and make it so that
we can do standard shift select and that sort of stuff.
This again is going to be really straightforward.
All we have to do is provide some way of sticking that information
into the input system again with mouse.
It was, it's just a side.
Bend stuff sideband.
Thing that comes in here, right?
This is for debugging only, right?
So you can kind of see, even we could stick it down here into say, oh
hey, you know what?
This is for debugging only.
So you know, a platform layer for example,
Didn't want to implement Mouse input?
Or the platform doesn't have a mouse.
It can just leave those things empty and it's fine.
Just means you can't access the debug services with the mouse.
And presumably.
That's okay on those platforms.
So what we want to do now is just have some things here where we have
like shift down you know alt down Ctrl down, something like that.
That would be a really simple way to just have those modifier Keys.
Get passed through the system again.
This is not for gameplay, this is strictly for use in our debug
system.
So in the code where we have, our Mouse x - Y and Z all, we really
need to do to make sure that this stuff works.
Relatively well is just kind of going here and and set these things to
whatever the state was of those modifier keys at the time, in which we
pass through this code and that will be plenty sufficient for our
purposes.
Nothing happens when you like tap the control shift or alt keys, so we
don't need to worry about counting like ups and downs or anything like
that.
We just need to know if they're up or down at any given time so that
we know how to interpret a mouse button, click that's on that frame.
So, if we want to figure out whether shift alt and controller down, we
can actually
actually use the same sort of information that we have before.
We, there's a thing called get key State and also a thing called, get
a sink Key State.
I'm not sure if we use any of these.
Yeah, we do.
So we can just come in here.
and use this exact same stuff that we have been doing our get kise
stuff, and the getkey state will tell us whether something is down or
not, and you can
See that we already sort of have that in here.
We were already doing this information right on the get key state.
So we can we can really literally just do the exact same thing here,
where we just test to see if these keys are down at the time and if
they are down, we set it if they aren't, they aren't now the VK codes
in Windows for these keys are exactly what you'd expect so we can
literally just type them in.
Oops, I think it's actually menu, so I take it back.
I think it's not all, they called it menu.
For some reason.
Don't ask me how I know that.
At and don't ask me how you were supposed to know that.
I think probably what I would recommend doing.
If you don't know what the VK codes are, you could probably do.
Well, there's two ways you could probably get that one is in developer
Studio.
Remember I showed how to make, you know, if you just use the project
wizard to create a project, it'll create a product that has, like,
browse info and stuff like this.
You can do stuff like this where you just do.
Okay, you know, I know one of the VK codes is well, if I just type VK,
you
See them all here.
You know, the browser back button.
Okay, whatever it is right.
If I type one of those VK codes in I can usually hit the right Mouse
button over and say go to definition and you can see that like we've
got all of the VK codes that are not ASCII codes are actually listed
in here, right?
So you can actually see these VK codes, just kind of laid out for you
and you you know could probably tell like you know even this Comet
tells you V KL, V, KR left and right.
All
It's control and shift, virtual keys and you can see that it actually.
Just says menu here, right?
And again with left and right, control keys, and left, and right shift
left and right menu, they have their own unique versions for left and
right.
But there's also a version that just encompasses the key in general.
So you can see, I don't know where it is a pure here it is you can see
that there's also one that's just was either of those down and I
believe all it does is if either the left or right or down it will set
this one to down and since we don't care about
Have to write out.
In this case, we're just going to use the unmodified ones, but if you
cared about like which specific one you were talking about, in that
circumstance, you would want to use the, the correct modifier.
So now, what I'm going to do is just I'm going to assume that work
because it was so simple.
Now, maybe that's a foolish assumption in programming.
Sometimes it's the simplest things that go wrong.
It's true.
But I'm going to assume that worked and I'm going to go to our add to
selection function.
And so in here, you can see we had it to do.
That was like, you know, let's figure out.
A way to do multi-select.
So now I've got that and so I'd like to do is be able to do something
like, say, okay, if the shift key is down, then I want this, this I'm
sorry, if it's not down that, I want to clear the selection.
If it is down, then I want to go ahead and add this election.
Now, I don't know if we actually have that we do in here, okay, just
want to make sure that we had access to the input data.
So now, in theory, I should be able to.
Oops, that's not the project we want to run in theory.
I should be able to now
Do multi select the way that you would normally see.
In any normal application.
If I click the mouse button you can see that I've sort of like
permanently selected, that guy and I can do that.
And you can see that it clears this election each time.
But now, if I hold down the shift key, right?
You can see that I can kind of Stack entities up there and it's all,
that's all well and good, right?
And so that's fine.
Nothing again, particularly odd going there, I will say that one thing
that, that looks pretty weird to me.
And that that I feel like it's kind of cause for concern, I'm not sure
why.
There's such a dramatic speed decrease here when I am.
When all I've done is just add more entities to that selected set and
I wonder if that's just because we don't have anything that's
optimized for font rendering and the font rendering is slow or exactly
what's going on there because it looks like, you know, like that
framerate is pretty slow and then if I switch back the frame rate,
jumps up quite a bit when I reduce the number of them.
They're right.
Right?
It just looks a little bit odd.
You can even see, look at how much that went up.
Ms.
Wise is pretty dramatic.
And so I also wonder there, if we've got a little bit of some bug
stuff happening there and so if nothing else that kind of gives me
motivation to finish the integration work here so that we can get our
profiler niacin and easy to use as well so that we can investigate
stuff like that.
And see like who is actually taking more time when we see that those
those times kind of jump up the way that they do.
But anyway, that was it for adding the modifier keys.
So that's pretty straightforward, nothing.
Particularly unusual going on there.
if you followed him here since the beginning, that was a
Pretty trivial, add.
Okay.
And so now, what I'd like to do again is sort of try to start to
consolidate these things a little bit.
So, we've got the ability to display this data but now we, you know,
we kind of don't really have a coherent story for how this kind of
data and data.
That's say, for example, coming from a different kinds of sources
might interact with each other, right?
It's because we have like stuff like the profile data and we don't
really have any sort of
We really don't have any way of talking about how these different
things interact with each other or how they work for that matter,
right?
So what I'd like to do is again try to kind of make that sort of make
that link be a little bit more.
It's a difficult problem and so I'm just going to try to push through
it you know, in a straightforward away as possible.
So if we look at what happened before,
We used to kind of have this notion that we would build some stuff at
the beginning.
And in fact, we have this kind of this, debug variable stuff here and
you can see that the debug variable stuff is basically all gone.
Now, right?
We've sort of, we've eliminated all this debug variable stuff, we
still like, to be able to have stuff like this, where we set these
debug variables, right?
I mean that's something that we would kind of want to do.
And so we have a couple different ways that we might want to go about
doing that.
And and we can sort of think about this in a little bit more direct
fashion.
Right.
So, what we would like to do is we'd like to be able to have these
like, you know, before when we were doing this, I had to write this
code kind of out of line, right?
So, what we did is we went through.
And in fact, I can do this pretty simply if I go to our debug config
dot h, right?
We have this config file, that was sort of written out by the debug
system and you can see and hear all of the places that we actually had
our our debug system lists, all of the you, I
We're going to do so if I were to turn this off, if I were to say that
we no longer get this, I would get UPS.
I would get essentially compile errors, presumably or I thought that I
would get compile errors.
Or maybe I won't get compile errors.
Okay.
I was assuming I would get compile errors where I saw these debug you.
I fo like all of this stuff I guess.
That's not actually true.
Because I guess they would be, I guess the way we were testing them,
they would default to zero, I guess, I was surprised.
I thought it actually might give me an error but I suppose, I could
actually do something like this.
Presumably, no, I guess not.
So what exactly is going on there?
Why are we getting?
Why is that happening?
I would like to know.
I'm going to see exactly what we were doing.
Maybe we just did, if defined is that what we did?
So you'd think that this would have this would have caused some kind
of a.
Yeah.
Would like I don't know.
Let's see what happens here.
So is there.
Literally, no way that I can force this sort of thing to be erroneous?
Maybe fove for is not a thing.
Let's try this.
There we go.
All right, so that was just not used.
Okay good.
So this is what I can do then.
Sort of give me a thing that would tell me everywhere that I was using
one of these systems, right?
And so here we can sort of see, like, okay, here is, you know, one of
the, the debug variables and so on.
So if I look at this and I go, well, what would I really have wanted
to do here?
Optimally, you know, is there something that's better than what's
going on here?
That I was going to do now?
what we found when we did our testing,
Was that having an if as long as the if was constant really didn't
make a huge deal and so it's sort of like it's free as long as it's a
perfectly predicted Branch to do this instead.
Look like that was fine, right?
It didn't look like that really cost us very much in any predictable
in any real way and so one of the things that we saw
When we were doing our debug system, was that having to wait for it to
recompile?
The game was just too long even though it only took like a second or
two, it's like just not fast enough for what you want to be able to
click the button and just be able to switch and it didn't feel good
and it wasn't nice, right?
So what I'd rather have in the system is something that we're looks
like this, you know what I'm saying?
That would be preferable to me, and the question here is just how
exactly would I go about doing something like this in the most
convenient way, possible.
Cause before what you had to happen is we had to have all of this
stuff in there and this system and was sort of a separate thing,
right?
And we had this this whole thing I had to write there was just a lot
of business involved, right?
And yeah the usage code, the code at the usage site, nice and simple.
No complaints with that really, it was totally fine, but all of this
nonsense garbage, that was happening out here, just a lot of extra
work that I maybe didn't want.
And so since it's clear,
Me that we don't really need to go the compilation route.
We tested it.
It doesn't seem like it's that necessary.
What we could do instead here is just do something like
Like having this dribble all over ourselves.
That's always a good thing.
Just do something like, okay.
If I've got something that I want to test, are you could imagine
something like this?
I don't know, something like this, or like, a debug switch, and then I
just passed.
Like, what the debug switch is that?
I actually want, right?
And then this would explicitly some macro that expands to whatever is
necessary to make this be a switchable thing that I can switch at
runtime and add it to whatever list actually.
It needs to be added to or I can actually sort of say what that list
might be that I might want to add it.
So for example, in fear show letting samples was part of the renderer
so I could do something like saying that it was part of the renderer
like that so I can have sort of a hierarchical sort of a thing going
on there.
I could even do something a little more stringy and maybe do something
that was like a path or even like a DOT sort of a thing or a colon:.
Right?
You can sort of Imagine Me constructing something here and that would
be a lot kind of more interesting because if I had something that
worked like that then it would be self-assembling which is a lot more
like the way the rest of the debug system is going, right.
The profiling stuff just kind of dumps to a buffer it would be kind of
great if this stuff just dumped to a buffer as well, you know what I'm
saying?
So I would like to see if that is something that's that's on the
table.
I don't really know.
Realistically how on the table it?
Ali is, but I think it might be possible to do the only thing that I'm
not certain about.
Is the way that this, if works, I think might be a little bit too
much, right?
In other words this I think could probably work this.
I think probably could not, right?
So it would probably have to look something like that which isn't
really that big of a deal at the end of the day.
But the reason that I say that it would probably have to look like
something like that is because if you look at what will have to
happen,
Oops, let's get interface there.
If you look like what would have to happen in order for that to occur,
we would need to do something where there would be a notion of some
kind of a static variable, or some kind of something happening there,
where we would have the debug system, be able to cash a look up, so
that every time through the code, it would not have to do anything
more than just the basic, if right.
So, in theory, you know, I guess what I'm saying is,
This can't really be if we want this to be a lightweight function that
just kind of does a test and continues, it needs to be something where
the debug system can always access the variable very easily.
So it needs to be something like, you know, it needs to be something
where there's a static, right?
Would need to be something like this.
So there's a, you know, a debug if that's some name and it would
create some kind of a local glow.
No, a variable that was locally declared to be persistent and I don't
remember, I feel like we have.
Yeah right here.
So we have a way to do that.
We'd say this is a locally persistent variable.
It's like you know whatever the debug ID is of this thing or
something.
Right?
I don't know exactly what we would want that to be but we declare it,
some some local, persist debug ID for this thing and then we would do
like
Leon the initialization pass.
Through the thing, we would do like, get debug ID for, you, know,
parameter or something like this for, you know, I don't really know
and we'd pass the name.
That would be something that on the first pass through.
It would call that thing and do the initialization.
That's necessary, right?
And then what we would do is we would switch on the value of that
thing.
And really this, I guess wouldn't be a debug idea, be more something
like a debug.
Value and we would just say like, okay, whatever this debug value is
that we got back.
In fact I might almost say it would look more like this where we would
have liked.
I think you'd want to 0 must pass the address of the debug value.
So we'd say like okay initialise debug value, something like that,
where we just go like, okay, whatever.
The initial value of the thing is it will return it here but we'll
also let
Will the address of this thing?
Because I think the debug system would probably want that.
I think it would be allowed to do that because you can use the value
inside the expression for the value.
All right, so like we need to do something like this, right?
Where if debug you know, if we do a debug, if you know Boolean or
something like this, right?
Where we could kind of switch on that sort of thing and this, you
know, honestly would probably be something like a debug variable, it
be like our debug event, like we kind of have because since we already
have this concept that you can have all of these different sorts of
variables.
If we take a look in here, where we sort of have this debug event that
has all these sort of sets in it, this would probably just be honestly
a debug event.
And yeah that's that's what I would assume would happen there.
And so really all we need to do is have some way of
Of making this the unique, right?
We want to make sure that it's not going to be something that.
Yeah, that that
We want to make sure that that value.
If we were to use multiple of them in the same function, wouldn't name
conflict, and debug value by itself will definitely name conflict.
So, you know, we want to do something like this where we would paste
in to this, some kind of a extra value on their write, something that
would give us sort of the additional, you know, uniqueness that we
need like the counter.
But unfortunately we can't really do it that way.
Because as we've seen many times passing the counter value in,
Directly.
So you need to do this, absolute nonsense here.
I, you know that you've seen me do a couple times where we if we
wanted to do like a debug if or something like that we would have to
be able to create that debug value.
Using one of these things that you pass down multiple times.
So I think it's something like this where you do name right counter
And then in here you pass it, one more time.
And then finally, you get to the actual one, ladies and gentlemen, the
C plus plus preprocessor.
Not not good, not good, right again.
The C++ standards committee has had how many years
To fix this stupid thing, but since through strip hated the
preprocessor, it languished and never got made into something you
could actually use.
But don't worry because they also didn't add any language features
that would make any of these things work so it's all worked out
anyway.
So if we do this stuff we should be in good shape if we wanted to make
a thing where we could sort of replace our stuff with debug if that
look this way.
So I'm going to just see how that
that ends up being at the end of the day.
Let's find out how it goes look.
I need to do that.
Obviously, and this needs to be that I
Leave but I think otherwise we're in good shape.
And then just this guy right here, still needs to be like that, and
that should be good.
One more time.
And to just lazy bug value not found you know, that's correct and
you're also saying that there is an inn single pound, sign that you
don't recognize possible to measures, okay?
Well I'm not sure what the problem is there, but let's fix this part
first.
So this part right here, this would be some kind of an internal that
returns a debug event.
It's called initialize debug value.
And what it's going to do is going to take, you know, a ladybug event
here.
It says this is the location of the thing we're trying to set and here
is the name, you know I'm saying?
So that's all good.
And so now that should be defined this.
Oh, so this is great.
That's just complaining about future stuff.
So now if we want to like with this debug you, I use debug camera
thing and that sort of stuff.
Now we can replace these if you want to, with debug.
If so we could just say you know debug if you know renderer use debug
camera
And now we could do something like that and that would be fine.
This would be something like I want a debug value here.
And I would say that it's debug camera distance again, here it is.
That's the debug value, right?
The problem with this, again, same thing as before, you can't really
cash a static here.
So, you know, this is one.
Where if we started having too many of these debug values, I'm
Not sure there would really be a way to sort of get around this
problem.
Now it's worth noting that metaprogramming solves this program.
This problem like trivially, right?
And you know, a language that wasn't awful would solve this program.
True problems with it as well.
But we'll try to stick.
I was doing it the hard way in something like this, where we have this
debug value.
The problem is just how do we cash the information, right?
And so the, you know, that's, that's really the thing that's, that's,
that's difficult for us to do is not to make this evaluate to the
correct thing that we would want it to evaluate to write.
It's pretty easy for us to do something like that, or something like
this.
Right, that's not hard.
The problem is, just how do we make this?
This debug system thing?
Not cost us a lot of time and energy because inside an expression, we
can't create a static variable, right?
So inside this plus equals, we can't really well.
We probably could nowadays using like crazy Lambda syntax or
something, that's an absolute nightmare.
So I guess with if you were targeting C++ 11, you probably could make
something work.
But in general, in at least a C++ as of that time.
It's not really.
I don't know there's really any way you could really get around that
right.
Because what you need to do is figure out a way to get a static
variable in here of some kind and that seems really difficult to do.
Now, what we could do it again, if we wanted to is, we could actually
just have one more place that these were defined.
And I don't know if it's worth kind of going through that or not, but
that's like, kind of the, that's the trade-off, right?
The trade-off is.
How do we, you know, how do we actually manage this?
This stuff.
Exactly.
How does it get looked up and so on?
And it's pretty easy for our debug ifs to work.
If we write them like that, the syntax is pretty clean and there's
nothing all that unusual about it but on the other hand here, if we
have debug real 32, something like that that we want to use inside of
expression.
It's much more difficult for us to do.
So what we can do, if we want to is we can do something like this
where we do one of those debug real 32s.
And you know, I might even do it something more like that, where it's
actually just the type is in there or something like that.
We'll see if maybe that's a good idea in a little bit but we could do
something like that.
So this way we'd say there's a debug real 32 and we just say this is
what the name of the thing was going to be.
And then we just say what we want to actually declare the variable to
be and that would work as well, right?
So that would work, fine.
It just means we
Can't do it inside an expression.
So then when we come up here, you know we can write it essentially the
same way as this stuff is written.
It's basically and it's actually a little simpler because we don't
have to worry about cracking out into multiple macros in that
ridiculous way, right?
So here we had a real 32, we'd have sort of a name and then we'd have
the the variable, right?
Not the variable but a variable.
And then all we have to do is again use this sort of same syntax here
where we do a local.
Persist this time we have the ability to sort of graft on I believe
one of the parameters that actually gets passed in here.
Although yeah, that I feel like maybe that is not entirely the case
but we'll try it here.
So if we do something like this, right?
We can construct, what we actually want.
And then I guess the only thing that would be a problem.
There is the the real 32 of I mean we really want to do right as we
want to do something like this.
I guess it's weird.
This would be an R32 in our current syntax.
What we really want to do is say okay the variable equals whatever
this thing is.
R32, right.
And you know, I could even imagine something more like this.
We have a debug variable, we pass.
What the type is, we pass the name, and then we pass a where it lives
in the hierarchy, or something like that, right?
Something like that.
We could even do it more like this where those things get added on
kind of like that.
I like what that looks like here.
I could even imagine it being something like this, so it's a little
clearer to read.
It's like, here's where here's the type.
There's a thing that we want to go.
Here's the type that it is or something like that.
That looks pretty good to me but unfortunately again, thanks to the
magic of C++.
I think that does put us back into squarely into ridiculous.
Pastor territory, you know, not the end of the world, but that's just
the way it goes sometimes, right?
It's just the way it goes.
A lot of the time in C++.
Please John, if you're listening, finish your language, sometime soon.
For those of us who are dying out here.
Using these horrible languages.
Ok so inside here, we have debug variable
Now all I'm going to do is exact same thing.
I create a persistent variable of whatever the type is, and then all I
need to do after it gets initialized with the name, the difference.
Now, is that there's a type in here that's being passed.
Then there's the name and then there's the variable that I actually
want to sign to it.
So now, when we talk about the name, it's not just the name.
It's actually also the variable because in fact it's not named, I
shouldn't say it's like path.
Like it's the path to where that thing exists in the debug.
So there's the path and then I've got, you know, this notion that I
want to kind of cap these together.
So I want the path that I want to slash, then I want whatever the
variable name is, that seems totally reasonable for how that will get
stored, this all works.
Now, correctly, instead of an, if now, it's just the type.
Whatever.
The type is that you asked for, right?
It's the type, then it's going to be whatever the variable is.
And then that's going to be equal to whatever this debug value was
dot, whatever.
The accessor type is right, and that would it's something that we
probably want to get used to, for this stuff to sort of start.
This stuff could actually be cleaned up quite a bit if we just unified
or naming scheme.
And this is something that again, it's really worth doing.
I know, it seems like you fought a lot with these sorts of things, but
once you get them, right, it's kind of nice to have them, right?
And so you can see what happened here.
Like, you can see, the way that I was writing this.
I just followed our
Asian scheme, which is kind of nice and it makes things look good and
all that other stuff.
But what you'll notice is these are not programmatically generate
abby'll unless you write a meta program, obviously, these are not
program Matthew genital in the C, plus plus P processor, but these
would be
Right.
As soon as I make the statement that the debug type itself is just the
word debug type with something at the end of it, that is the actual
type.
And if I took it one step further and take these guys here and
actually made, these guys, be something like value.
And then that thing, all of a sudden this becomes a lot more powerful
because now macros can just pick out the thing that they want.
All with one go, right?
They don't there's no name translation going on.
It's always just whatever the thing is you know with with its type
kind of stuck at the end and I guess rectangle two and three.
Don't have that underscore their?
That's My Imagination Running Wild not actually true.
What can you do?
So there you go.
Again, that's just a nice little change there.
And so that's all kind of nice stuff that again, kind of lines that up
really nicely.
And now, when we look at what actually happens in here, in fact, all
of this value, set an event data stuff, right?
Look at all of these things that we wrote all of those.
I think we could probably do in a more concise way.
Now, I mean, we, we probably still, I guess you still kind of have to
have that Cracker in some sense.
But we could, in fact generate all of these guys as macros themselves,
if we really
And to unfortunately again, it can't quite go away, unless maybe use
the type of macro but that a I don't think that'll work anyway, point
being that allows us to stop fussing with what we were fussing with
before.
And we should be able to now have debug variable work, exactly as we
would want it to.
So now, you know, got type path variable,
Type path variable.
I think now we can do is just say, okay we don't need a counter, we
can just use variable as the thing that gets upended onto their,
right?
So that's pretty easy.
And then here, like I said, when we want to access the value, we can
just do value underscore, whatever that type is, and those can graph
together.
You know, I'm saying, here are the same thing, we sort of have, like,
whatever the variable is that we wanted of that type.
That is just going to be.
Oops, I Did it here.
Don't know why.
There we go.
That all works.
And then when we do initialize debug value, we can also pass the type
into that.
So when we pass the type in initialize debug value again.
Now it's easy for us to figure out what the type actually is, it's
just whatever.
The real type was what they said, they wanted an R32 and that's what
they passed us.
No problem.
We just say, okay, we just append.
Debug type to that thing.
And now we have the type identifier that we actually wanted.
Right?
Again, all of this stuff is just nonsense because the C++
Just don't know what they're doing and never really did.
And so you kind of constantly run this situation of fighting
everything all the time, these are just things that should have been
really simple and never to fixed, but
What you gonna do hilariously, they added runtime type information
which doesn't actually work.
So they kind of tried to solve the problem at some point or thought.
Maybe they were going to solve the problem but then didn't solve the
problem, which was pretty awesome.
But anyway, after we have all that stuff set up, we're in a good
position.
Now, in fact, this the way we look at this, this one doesn't have
To do it that way, right?
It knows that what it's doing is doing a bull for to here, right?
So that one's totally fine and this is going to be value, be 32.
So now if we've got that, we can do this, like we did here and it
should be fine, we just have to change it so that these things get
passed through type path, variable type path variable.
And that's really about it.
Now, I've got a bunch of compile errors that I gotta clean up because
we sort of change these names a little bit to be a, you know,
programmatically determinable.
So, they don't really well.
There already were programmatically to terminal, but just terminal by
the non programming language, that is the C++ macro system.
All right, so there we go.
That's those and I suspect I have a bunch more to do.
So these are all going to be like value R32 value.
You 32 value s 32
And value V 2 value, V, 3 value, V 4.
Value rectangle, too.
Value rectangle, 3.
And value map ID.
Value sound ID value font I do.
Okay.
Yeah, function does not take three arguments.
That's true.
We decided it did never actually implemented it, right?
So, let's go back here, and make sure that we actually have that
defined to take the arguments.
That it actually takes, so it's debug of insight or debug value type.
Keyboard type.
I don't even remember what's called that the top of this file.
It's deep uptight.
Yep.
Okay, so now, what are you complaining about mr.
Complaining thing.
What is it that bothers you?
You are complaining about.
Well, actually that should be that, okay, Diva went, should not should
be preceded by a bracket.
Okay, I will take your word for that.
Let's see why you are saying that.
Why should it have been preceded by a bracket?
I don't really follow you.
Debug event should have been should be preceded by bracket.
Mmm.
Okay, let's see here.
Hmm.
It's only on the debug variable path.
And I'm not sure.
Is there any other?
It's just that one.
So local persist debug event.
It already started complaining that it should have looked like that.
Why pray?
Tell.
Write what?
Oh, because I forgot.
That's great.
So, let's see.
That's all correct now.
Okay.
But still the same debug event should be preceded by close bracket.
Don't get it.
Don't know why that would be the case.
What am I seeing here?
So, my variable is that a quoting problem is local?
Persist is defined here?
Or is it not?
Is this is this a figment of my imagination that that's actually
there.
Nope, that's fine.
So that's good.
So I'm not sure why it's giving me that particular compile error.
Again, the wonders of the, the macro preprocessor.
So, let's just see what happens here.
That's the row variable.
Let's just see what happens here.
If I expand this out, so if I've got type path and variable those so
type right is going to be our 32 everywhere.
So that's just our 32 that's
Debug camera distance.
That's debug camera distance.
This is renderer.
That's really about it.
It's not a lot to this thing.
Write debug value.
Debug camera distance.
Debug value, debug camera distance.
Yeah, that's what it looks like, right?
So, what's the problem?
Debug event should be preceded by a close brace, so it doesn't think I
can declare something.
Static here?
I guess or it doesn't know what a debug event is, but it couldn't that
couldn't be true, right?
Because here's the debug event.
It's right here.
So that's fine.
So is the problem that the debug if is setting us up for failure.
I don't think so.
Because it looks like that should have been fine, ah, because I change
the scene.
Axe here.
I don't know why I did that.
In fact I think I can return it to what it was before that was just a
slip slip of the fingers.
Alright.
So debug camera value.
This is right.
That's all good.
Yeah so now we know that that's probably fine and now
You have that working, we should be able to do this debug if
everywhere.
So curious, like, use room based camera, I don't actually remember for
some of these guys.
I don't remember where they were in the hierarchy, right?
Use room based camera was under like renderer camera
I guess so we can do a debug if here and have that.
Yeah, the thing that looks like this, I guess.
Something like that.
Here we go.
Ground chunk checkerboards again, same thing.
Now we just do debug if
And this is just a rare.
Was that again?
I don't remember where we put it.
Use ground, chuck checkerboards, this was in.
I don't know why it says group chunks.
I guess that was just our little, our little exacts, a dental thing
that we did there.
So there is ground, chuck checkerboards.
We could just do ground chunk checkerboards because we don't probably
say ground chunks twice seems a little redundant.
So let's just go ahead and say there's our if
Else we will do the other way round.
Like so, how are we doing here?
So we need V4 color to be defined ahead of time looks like, so I'll
just go ahead and do that.
And there we go.
So recompute ground.
Chunks on XE change.
Again, should just be a debug if here.
We can just call that recompute on XE change and that's again going to
just be ground chunks.
Yeah.
So something like this.
Same thing here.
Debug if
Renderer test very draw, buffer size, feel like that's in the
renderer, right?
Yep.
What else we got grand trunk, outlines debug if ground chunks.
Outlines.
Familiar follows hero.
Debug.
If I think this is what simulation or end.
He's, it's called a simulation.
Familiar, follows hero.
Probably simulation is actually stupid.
Probably entities actually better.
Could do something like that.
Maybe.
Even let Scott AI.
It's artificially intelligent, guys, don't you know?
It's just like follows a guy around, but it's artificially
intelligent, I declare that it is the case.
So this is going to be probably just like particles test or something
like that.
And at the particle test is on and does all this stuff.
There we go.
Can't can't let that stay.
Almost done.
So this is this is debug if particles.
Show grid.
What else?
You space Out Lines.
I don't know what this would be called, exactly.
I guess this is entity.
You say settling or simulation?
I don't know.
I don't know who that is.
That's just kind of.
Like, some guys are outlined, you know, they're being outlined, who
knows why they're being outlined.
Nobody knows, really.
Could be any reason why does there have to be a reason?
No one knows.
All right, so let's see where we're at here.
Debug type R32.
This is in our interface code, right?
When we do debug value,
And we set this stuff up.
You can kind of see here that we're doing well.
In this case actually record debug event.
We set.
This is just a faux value.
Really, this should just be something like, debug type unknown, right?
It should be like debug type unknown because it gets set later, right?
So at first, it really, like, when we do debug value, that should
really just set it to whatever, it doesn't know what it is, right?
And then it would go, it would it would move.
From there.
Okay, so now these are all like really just a wrote just a quick
transform and all of, I guess, probably all of these things to have to
be changed.
Right?
To value our 32, right value be 32
Value be 32.
Value s32.
Value, you 32.
And yeah, value V2.
Value V2.
Value B3, value, B, 3 value B 3.
There we go.
Got a permit to do these little guys and now these are all kind of
nice and harmonized, right?
Value before.
Value before value before.
Are these all?
Are these all correct up here as well?
Rectangle, to rectangle 3, that's not correct.
It's good rectangle to rectangle, three rectangle to kind of busy work
here, nothing particularly interesting but sometimes you got to do it
until mr.
Fourth dimension, finishes his code based editor,
We'll just have to make do.
Okay, so they're getting close here to being all good, but we still
have a little bit more to go.
Let's just go ahead and finish that out.
So value underscore our bitmap ID,
Is what that has to be again.
Same thing here, value underscore bitmap, ID,
And these are just quickly things we have to change slightly value, be
32 value P 32.
And again.
I think.
We're almost done.
There we are.
so oops, one more frame marker Frank, okay, so frame marker which is
in the handmade interface stuff frame marker,
Let's see what else we've got here.
So free marker seconds, elapsed.
Real 32 this just needs to be a value are 32 and then we're good.
Okay.
So I think that's everything.
Now we have all of that stuff working, all that stuff has been sort of
transmuted, right?
So now all of this stuff can just disappear, right?
We don't need this file anymore, we can just straight-up delete it.
The only thing that we need at the moment is this.
And so we can just go ahead and cut and paste that into here.
And then let's just straight-up delete this file, right?
Handmade debug variables is going to go away.
Goodbye and now
Or again, simplifying things even further, you know, trying to get
them down to an even more straightforward version and just kind of
compact compact compact that code.
Now that we sort of see what we want, we tested things, we kind of
know what, you know, what things we want.
We things we don't want
So, we're getting closer, okay?
So initialise debug value is really the only function that we
introduced at all in all.
Of that.
Right?
So now that we have we sort of expect that complete system.
The only function that we actually need to implement is this thing
here right now?
What we do need to do
In this in this other case over here we need to sort of think about
this one more level.
Again before I go off implementing this we kind of need to think about
one more thing which is that how could we get it or could we get it to
compile out?
Right?
Is there a way we could get this thing to compile out entirely?
And so the way that I'm sort of thinking about that is like okay if I
wanted to make it so in fact I could even do this right now.
If I
Make this.
So it compiles out and all of the values that we have before would
just be, you know, any of the debug UPS or whatever any of the debug
variables, those would be set to permanent values.
How would we do that, right?
So if we take a look at the debug, if the big problem with the debug
is and actually all of these is that we don't necessarily always have
any way of really
A really defining exactly what the thing is that we're talking about
other than the string that was given to it.
So that makes it hard to actually compile that thing out.
And so that's why I'm thinking, you know, like a kind of before I go
and actually finish something this, I might want to make it a little,
right?
Because what I'd like to do is be able to do something like, okay.
If we have debug, if here and in fact, I guess, you know, one thing I
could say is also, I might want this to actually always happen this
way.
Right.
So we're just talking about redefining these things.
So in one case I have the one that we're actually going to use, it's
something like this.
In the other case, the one that we're going to use is going to look
like something else.
And what I'd like to be able to do here is instead of doing local
persist and all of this stuff here where we actually Define it or do
any of that stuff, what I'd rather do is have some way of going, okay?
What I really want to do is like debug constant or something, like
just it's a constant, right?
And then we have like a name.
Right?
So that we can just Define we can pound to find that thing and it
would just be whatever it actually was going to be right.
So we would still have, we would still have handmade config dot h.
It would just only ever get used if the debug system was turned off,
right?
So, it would basically be something that looked like, oh, if we are,
you know,
You know, if we are not handmade internal, then we use this
information that we have here.
Otherwise we don't
If that makes sense.
So in here it could do the if on the constant name and then when we
asked for like a debug variable, like in this case, what we would
actually get is this
Or I guess I should say this.
And what you can see if you look at this is we're going to have a
problem with that name with the naming scheme, eventually the reason
we're going to have a problem with the naming scheme eventually if I
literally just sort of did it this way?
Even if we made the ifs work somehow, is that if you look at what the
variable names actually are going to be, they're going to be stuff.
Well, I mean you can already see what they are, right, let's go ahead
and take a look here.
So the names of these debug values, okay, that's not going to work.
I wanted it to just jump me to some of them but I'll go ahead and grab
debug variable.
Okay.
So if you take a look at what happens here, you're going to have
something like ran render a /, you know?
And it would probably be like camera distance or something like that.
Right?
Or deep.
You know, it's debug camera distance, or who knows what it is, or
outlines use outlines, who knows?
Right whatever it is, this may occur in multiple places in our
hierarchy, potentially, right?
So you know, if we did something like this,
Who knows if someone else might want something called used you debug
camera, right?
Or something like that, or maybe we even have it like that, you know,
and it's like use debug.
Well, now this name used debug once we have to make it so that there's
a bunch of constants to find for that thing.
It's no longer going to be unique without these parts of it, right?
So I can't just expect somebody to somewhere to find something like
renderer I'm sorry.
Use the bug.
Zero.
Because it may be that there's someone else in some other part of the
code who's done something like this.
Right.
And that's not not going to fly, right?
So what I need to be able to do is I need to be able to include the
path information which means that things are a little more
complicated, right?
But what I can do is I can revert a little bit back to sort of the
thing that I was saying before where I could sort of go back to doing
something like this that I could probably make work and curious how I
would make that work, right, how I would make that work is when we are
Talking about these things.
Like so we could just string eyes this in debug mode and make it be an
actual struct layout in non debug mode, right?
So let's go ahead and take a look at what that would look like if we
were to do it that way, right?
So in fact, and I guess do, we actually yeah, we still need to do it
this way.
So all we would need to do for that is again, the debug s kind of have
to look the same way.
Unfortunately, it's a little bit annoying to actually do it that way
but again it's not the end of the world necessarily but anyway, that's
what would have to look like.
So debug ifs are going to have to have a path.
And a variable as well, which kind of tell us what it is.
That's the actual thing that's getting use there, but that at least
unifies these guys a little bit.
So that's kind of nice as well.
I suppose at the end of the day.
And so then what happened here is we just do something like this
constant dot path.
That variable, something like that will be fine.
Right?
Or, you know, debug or, you know, Constance Global constant.
Something like that, who knows something like this.
And again, the same would actually be true here.
Exactly.
The same thing would happen here like that.
And then whenever we were trying to access these guys up here, where
the way we were doing before, instead of that /, we would just add
another dot onto their or and that would be how we would pass that
information for words, right?
So here we've got path and variable again.
We don't need counter anymore.
We can just use it variable, like we were doing I suppose and then we
can.
There we go, then we can do the same sort of thing here where we do
the concatenation.
When we pass this stuff down, we're going to pass exactly the same
stuff.
So it's really exactly the same code.
The only difference is one is hard-coded to do that if statement
because there's really not a lot of other ways to do it.
We could actually also have it so it did that for us more directly
I don't know if you want to do that or not, right but you could
imagine doing that I think it's probably good to just let it do the
extra typing in this macro and let it go.
So anyway
That's what I'm talking about.
And so, if I make that work, then you can kind of see how we can start
to construct making these constants, right?
It could just be some giant construct, not nightmare scenario thing
that we create that allows us to sort of create these variables.
And we could even imagine if the path itself, perhaps we're done with
something else like underscores maybe or something else.
That was like a character that was, you know, we wouldn't even need to
create.
We could create them in some other way.
I'm trying to think if there's some, you know, if that's too much of a
limitation, but basically what I'm saying is like, imagine you did
something like this and we just said that, that's how the paths were
defined in our system.
You can imagine everything sort of working through that system, as
well.
Again, I just don't really know what the best way to do.
That is exactly.
I'm gonna go with the underscores for now because I think it'll make
the simplest thing because then these can all be pound to fines and
don't really have to worry about it, which is kind of nice.
So, I think what I'm going to do is let the paste operator work
overtime on this particular situation, and let it do something like
that, which is kind of ridiculous, but you can kind of see where I'm
going with that now, they'll all be variables that have a unique name,
no matter what the situation is, and that seems like potentially a
better idea.
It to me.
And so, then what we would do and I guess this also means that to some
degree, this would just work as well.
Now,
Don't we don't really need a path.
I guess, for those guys, we could just do something like that.
It's just called renderer show light samples and those underscores
would get translated into nests in the hierarchy.
I'm actually probably okay with that.
I feel like that's probably fine for the most part with the way these
are getting translated.
I don't know if feels like, it'll probably look at me.
So I'm just going to say, let's go with that and I'm running out of
time here.
I think I'm a little bit over already, so I'm just going to kind of
wrap this up quickly.
So yes, I think, I think I feel reasonably
Be okay with that.
And like I said, this one can actually be done without that.
We could just use just passed by itself and not actually have to
bother with anything else.
You just ring eyes that directly.
And, and again, let that kind of be its own thing.
And here that same same deal, right?
You could just eliminate a little bit of the complexity in the, if
Case, not a whole lot, but a little bit, right again.
So in this case, we've got the debug up just has a path, there's the
path.
Path is something now that you can use directly.
So it just has to sort of crack that out.
As it goes.
We may not need the second one here because now we're not translating
a variable that actually exists.
So we may actually be able to get away with only one level, but I'm
not going to deal with that right now because we're basically out of
time, okay?
So let's see here.
Debug if we're as our debug, if we can now say the name does not need
to be in there anymore.
Let's see here.
Undeclared.
Identifier that is true and that's fine.
That's what
We want but let's just go ahead and fix these up.
So that's renderer camera, use debug.
This is renderer.
I camera distance, right?
Our debug distance, something like that.
Probably that's all fine.
We then have debug camera distance.
That's it's just going to be debug distance there.
Okay, so this is if renderer camera, we didn't really name this.
It should have been room based camera, right?
Something like that.
I think that's what that was supposed to be so relieved, that their
Global constants, we've got ground chunks checkerboards so that's
pretty straightforward as well.
What else we got here?
Doot-doot doot-doot, doot-doot doot-doot, that's the Price Is Right
theme song.
I don't really remember.
It's something like that.
I'm just gonna go ahead and say it's something.
Like that.
So we're almost there.
There we go.
See here.
Probably could do this Faster by using grep.
Go.
And again, like I said, all of this is just because you're so limited
when you program in C++ due to the.
Again the fact that they just don't know anything about
metaprogramming.
So they miss all of the opportunities to save a lot of time and energy
because the people who design languages, don't think that way, and so,
they just don't know, right?
It's just like a fundamental.
We don't really know how to do this kind of programming, so we never
think to enable it or something like that C'est, La Vie anyway.
So if in here I go in and actually Define these
We're sort of at least get back to sort of parody with where we were
and then tomorrow we can make those all actually generate stuff in the
debug thing and it'll all be good, right?
So this is what we would generate right?
When we go to read our config file, we just write these out and they
wouldn't actually be used except in the case where we actually compile
the whole debug system out and that way we know that it will
completely clean out the code and there will be no actual cost to us
for turning the debug
Come off because they'll all be essentially.
They'll just be constant that the compiler can literally trivially
optimize out.
It doesn't need to do anything at all.
It can literally just go up.
That's a constant zero.
No need to do anything with it whatsoever, right?
Okay.
So let's see here, I'm almost done with these guys and then we can do
some Q&A.
Let's go ahead and just want to finish this up.
So we all compiled properly.
Let's see here.
Particles test.
Particles show grid and use space.
Outlines that we go, right?
So that should all be good, debug distance, Undeclared, identifier
camera, debug distance.
What render camera?
Yep.
That's tight though.
And so then we're all back to render it, you know, we're back to
working everything properly.
And so that sets us up tomorrow that will system is sort of been
exercised and sets us up to just put it through the standard debug
event path, right?
So tomorrow, we'll be able to kind of unify those two systems, which
collapses yet another level of complexity down, which is great.
So again, I really happy with the way this is turning out.
I think we're getting there, but it's time to stop.
So
I will go ahead and go to the Q&A.
If you have any questions about what we did today, please feel free to
go ahead and and I've just looking here, that's pretty great.
I didn't know that you could get the hmh bot to like, say something
flame Beatty, that's pretty great.
That is pretty awesome.
Let's see.
PSI 9 says why
Get key State instead of wmq down, WM key up.
So, the answer is because they are modifier keys.
So, WM key up wmq down is for letting is if you're trying, if it's a
fundamental thing that you're trying to do is detect when key is go up
and down, then WM key up and key down are nice because they let you
just get directly to the Keys as they change right there.
Like okay, you know.
I got a notification that this key change and so that was good and
it's all good.
Good.
Right.
But in this case, we don't actually care about that, right?
In this case, we don't care at all about knowing when the shift key
went up or down knowing when the control key went up or down, or
knowing when the ALT key went up or down.
All we actually care about is every frame.
When we send the mouse info down, we just want to know whether the
Ctrl alt or shift keys were up or down at that incident time.
And that's exactly what get key state is designed to do, is just
designed to tell us that right now.
There's two kinds, one is called get key state.
It's called get a sync, Key State and if you look at the way they're
defined get a sync.
Key State tells you the state as Windows knows it at the time of the
call, whereas get key State, not get a secure State tells you what
your program thinks it was.
If all you had been doing was looking at the key up key down messages.
So actually there's really no difference between you tracking key up,
key down yourself for shift Ctrl and ALT
Since you're not doing anything when they're pushed, they're not a
trigger key.
There's no difference between that and you just, like, manually
tracking the pool yourself and just calling it Key State.
So for our purposes, get key state is basically perfect.
That's exactly what we want to do, right?
So, there you go.
K.
I don't have much experience in it but you mentioned the rtt.
I in C++ is not as good.
Could you explain a bit why?
Yes.
There's a lot of reasons.
The rtt, I and C++ is not as good.
One reason is, there's no way to like macro between the rtt I and the
actual type itself.
So it you know, you can't like have you couldn't
I'll put this way it all stems from the concept that the are TTI is
opaque data that you are have no way of actually using or accessing.
So for example, if you wanted to write two programs one on clang and
like one on em SVC and you wanted them to like, save out the runtime
type information in a way that the other one could read.
I don't know if they ever fix this, probably not, but at least our TTI
as it
Defined was completely compiler in the Pacific so you have absolutely
actually no way of really getting a actual value can use to identify
this type in a way that your program can understand it's strictly like
specific to that particular.
Compilation on that particular compiler of that particular program.
Furthermore, even separate compiles of the same program are not
guaranteed to produce the same.
Rtt, I right?
So, like, it could just be, like, one way.
It could Implement.
Rtt is the pointer to your vtable could be the thing that says what
this type is right.
And so that's just not usable as a basic system for doing
metaprogramming on types because you want it.
One of the first things you're going to do with your types is like
people save them to disk, right?
And restore them or something.
NG across runs of your program.
And that's just not possible with the way they expect the rtt.
I now whether they fix that, and like C++ 2032 or whatever, I'm not
sure.
But at least up until like, you know, the turn of the Millennium,
right?
Or even the turn of this decade, it was not the case.
It just didn't work.
Culver fly.
I don't quite get what you need to Nest.
The do the Mac OS or debug s.
Can you explain it?
Yeah.
It's just because the paste operator, pastes the actual macro,
parameter directly,
So let me, let me see if I can and maybe make this a little more
clear, what would be the easiest way to do this?
Let's see.
So let's suppose we were to grab something the thing with the stuff.
Alright, so here is a way I could show you pretty cleanly what it is.
let's suppose we're in handmade dot CPP and we go through here and we
create
Some macros.
So I'm going to do like a macro called one time and here is the
parameter, right?
And I'm going to say that it is going to be equal to whatever the
parameter is, right?
So now I say, okay, I've got a care star.
One time, result equals one time poop, right?
I'm then going to make a thing called to time, right?
That basically does what we're sort of saying, but with a call
through, right?
So it doesn't call through there.
And then I'm going to make one called three time.
Hard.
I need to, I finally, on my emacs config at work, turned off insert as
a key and it was pretty great.
I will tell you that.
So anyway, okay.
So three time.
Three-time.
There we go, right?
And so, let's see what these actually do.
Each of them produces a string, right?
That's the string I using an operator, so it takes whatever the
parameter is that you pass.
In each case, we pass the same thing which is Foo.
The first one turns it into a string.
The second one calls a macro, which turns it into a string, the third
one calls a macro, which caused a macro, it's called student turns in
string.
And so let's just see what those three things actually turn out to be
equal to when we run this, right?
So, I'm going to set a breakpoint in game update and render their game
update and render.
Here we come through when we step through
Us, right?
We get one.
Time result oops one time result to time results.
Three-time result, right?
Okay, so as you can see in here, right?
No matter which one we did, they each give us the exact same
parameter, right?
It's all, it's all totally fine, right?
So no harm, no file, everyone's happy.
If we need to do something where we just take in a parameter and
string eyes, it it doesn't matter, right?
But now what happens if what we wanted to do, for example, was string.
Eyes say the file, like wreck whatever the we wanted to turn, like,
say or the
Number into a string, right?
So instead of doing pound per am here, right?
What we actually want to do is this, right?
So I want to turn that into it now.
If you see what happens when I compile here,
well, there's there's okay, so that's the first thing I guess I should
mention and I forget about this all the time.
So the first thing is you can't actually do that, right?
This, this pound operator here.
It's just a flat-out error.
If you use something, that's actually a macro thing in and of itself,
right?
So one reason to do just the two-time version is, if I needed to pass
in the file, right?
So if I needed to pass in the file, you can see that.
That would be actually required of me, right?
That's something that I'd actually have to do directly.
But now that I've got those two, you can see that in this case, there
there was going to say, oh I guess this even, this is even earlier
than I thought it was gonna be.
I didn't think we were going to quite need it yet but actually you can
already see it happening.
Okay, so if you look at what happened here, right?
This was actually surprised me.
I never remember exactly again.
That's why I say, it's always kind of an epic night near the C++
preprocessor stuff.
But so, what happened here?
Right is the thing that I was trying to avoid
Calling twice in the other ones.
Because we passed this in as a parameter.
The first attempt in the two-time version, tostring eyes.
It, it takes the actual thing.
You passed in and string.
Is that right?
So it's basically replacing / am with file, the word and string, izing
that.
So instead of getting a string version of the file, right?
And I guess saying the files already a string.
So what I should have done here as I should have done this, to make it
clearer.
Right.
I'm looking for a string.
That is the line number.
That's what I actually want, right?
And so, as you can see, like, the first time three, when you only call
through one parameter, you actually just all you get, is the line
directive turned into a string, whereas if you call through twice the
first time, it replaces, Paramus line.
The second time, it replaces line with the number and then String Line
certain guys is it, right?
So you get that sort of cascading down and so for every layer of
peeling that you need to do for a parameter, you have to do that.
I don't ever remember exactly how it works.
I should probably just go read.
Exactly the C++ Preposterous because probably like oh every expansion
it rewrites each lot.
You know, token one time and so blah blah right?
There's probably a really easy way to remember it.
If you actually go and learn, I never bothered to do so.
But that's the problem that you face, right?
And so sometimes you have to call it twice sometimes you don't and
like I said I don't know that we actually need all three that we had
in.
That's why I saying my type that you could probably get away with too.
For all the stuff we just did because we never had to pass anything
like the file directive or anything into there.
You mind going over your debug you, I plan for those who don't know
what the current plan is, I just want food.
I don't have a plan, I'm just making a debug system and seeing what
the stuff is that I actually want to to know if that makes sense.
So like
I know I want to be able to slay debug data.
I know, I want to be able to splay profiling data.
We now have both of those.
And so I'm just trying to unify them as cleanly as possible and then
make it so that on top of that, the interface is good enough that it's
like fast and fluid to get at the data we need.
So we're pretty close.
It's just the UI.
Now at this point is not as good as it needs to be.
So we just need to go refine that debug system to the point where it's
nice and fluid to kind of get around it.
And then I think we're
It.
But I don't have a plan for that.
I'm just writing the code as I as I kind of figure it out as I go.
Golden, wh isn't metaprogramming a security hole?
I don't even know what that means.
K.
I've been reading about the cost of virtual functions.
Normal non-virtual function is cost a call command, but with virtual,
we need to fetches and a call.
Is that very costly and performance critical areas?
Is that the reason to avoid virtuals for me, I don't like the fact
they introduced hidden costs makes it harder to reading about reason
about your code.
The reason is
Is virtuals is because I find switch statements to be more usable.
So it doesn't have that much to do with the cost of a virtual call,
but yes, it is true.
That virtual calls are much harder to optimize.
You know, if you, if you're in the position where you're using a
switch statement to determine things.
And you find that your code is going to slowly.
It's usually not that hard to make that into some kind of a more smart
dispatch.
And oftentimes the switch isn't expensive because it doesn't have to
fetch anything, right?
It's just the one fetch.
It doesn't have to go fetch and fetch.
It just does one Fetch.
And then at the jump can be discarded like the compiler can often
optimize the jump and so on.
So switch statements are usually a little bit easier.
So it's true that, you know, probably you get some wins with them but
that's not actually why do them because, you know, I just don't tend
to
Virtual functions as I don't like spreading out the code for a single
idea across many files like that.
It, I just don't find it to be that useful.
So I don't like virtual functions as an architectural thing.
It has nothing to do with the speed, but it is true that the speed can
be a problem.
I have never actually had that specific experience myself.
I've had people say that like virtual functions were really
problematic on consoles for them, especially like, older consoles,
like Xbox 360 or Playstation 3.
I've heard nightmares about that, I don't have the personal experience
to know how true they were how relevant that was or if it was for
other reasons and you know, I don't know.
So I don't, I don't pretend to to say that I have had like lots of
experiences optimizing code that had virtual functions in it and it
caused me a lot of problems.
That's not true.
I don't tend to write code that way.
I've not had that experience, I don't know.
So I think that's probably something that's better for someone else to
answer.
Probably someone who's done a supposed big steals project on a
Consul how much of a problem that is these days would be interesting
question for them.
And and obviously to hear the answer, I just don't use them.
So I don't care.
But it's definitely, it's definitely different than if statements.
You know, it's definitely it has a different performance profile
potentially relevant.
I can't figure out for the life of me, a way to draw an empty non
filled rectangle via the win32 API.
And empty non filled rectangle.
Oh you mean like you want to stroke the outline of a rectangle?
It's real, it's real easy.
If you do want to do that, filling a rectangle and win32 you just
don't draw a rectangle, use move to in line 2.
so like, for example, when we put, when we do our stretch lit here,
Right?
If you wanted to, you could pretty easily.
Do move to line two.
And if you look at how this works,
See, move 2X.
You can kind of see how this goes so you can see this here.
You basically pass whatever.
The DC is to try to draw two, which in our case, is this one, you pass
the two coordinates.
So, like, you know, 1010 or something like that, you can then just do
lines to each of the things that you wanted to do, right?
So typical rectangle going to look something like that, right?
Oops?
Leave those there.
And so that's, you know, how you would typically draw a rectangle, you
can see it right there.
There it is.
And that's going to, I believe draw in the current foreground color.
So you know if you if you need to change the color of thing, it's
pretty straightforward to do.
That's just going to be probably something you can.
You can look at in here that would tell you all about, it's going to
probably stroke it with the current pain, right?
And you can probably set the current pain cheaply.
They added some trivial functional.
Sure, that it's like set solid pin or something like this.
I don't quite remember set solid pens and pretty to wear.
As it's not, it's like get solid pain, get solid pain once we do.
I, it's been so long since I've done any of this stuff.
I don't really remember.
But you, you could do all these things.
Solid pen color, that's what it is.
Salt and color this thing, right?
So you can call like set d.c.
pen color.
And, and that allows you to kind of like mess with it.
So I could say, like set DC pen color, device concept RGB, you know,
here's that lovely yellow.
I'm so fond of and I believe I'm not, don't totally remember.
But I believe we then have to select the stock object of the default
pain.
You see it's still black right?
But you can just do a
Like the object at the beginning, before you do anything else, you can
do this nonsense to set, tell the DC that the pain that you're always
going to use is going to be that.
That one that I just looked up here.
So, d.c.
pain, that guy right there.
So you just want to do like like that.
Right.
And I think that's that's it, right?
And so there's that yellow rectangle and you can you can change that
as frequently as you want to and do any of the other stuff in there.
So, you know, once you have that set up that way, you know you can
even do, you can just change it per line Jeannie.
I was actually fine, you know, for its day it was a totally fine.
Right.
You know, is it great?
No, but it's totally usable.
It's not the world's worst graphics API.
So you know, if you, I don't know why.
You would be using.
Because it doesn't seem like these days.
You know, if you could use opengl, you would but but there you go.
You can, you know, change the pen per line or anything, you know,
whatever you want to do it.
That's fine.
So that's you know if that's what you're if that's you're trying to
do.
That's real easy, that's the easiest way to do it.
Too freaky.
What are your thoughts on Twitch starting to affect game design?
You know, I'm not really a game designer so I don't, you know, I'm a
programmer and
and you know, so I mean I like the fact that I can stream development
as a way of teaching, you know,
And I like that aspect to Twitch, I don't know much about how it,
which affects game design.
I mean, I understand the concept that if people are now saying that
liked, which is a big or any video streaming service, really is a big
way in which games get pressed.
I can understand that people might start designing their games to look
good on Twitch or play well on Twitch to an audience or whatever.
You know, do I think it's a bad thing that really because anyone who's
going to do that probably wasn't super filled with like, Artistic
integrity for their game.
Anyway, like that's probably talking about people like Call of Duty
her.
Just like, we're designing games to be like Mass market and super PR
bullet, super marketable, right?
And they were already compromising, all sorts of things that might
have been, you know, interesting about their games in order to sell
more copies.
The fact that they're going to Me, Maybe compromise those to play
better on.
Twitch is
Not, it's just six of one half dozen of the other, right?
They were already marketing different games to begin with.
So people who are really passionate about a particular game idea and
really want to make that game idea.
I don't think those people are going to be super affected by Twitch in
a negative way.
You know, they'll just make their game and if it plays well and which
it doesn't, and if it doesn't doesn't now there's a long-term effect
that could be deleterious which is that if it turns out that your game
has to play well on Twitter,
In order to get an audience, then you end up with those people who do
have an artistic idea and make games that maybe don't play well on
Twitch, if they can't survive, if they can't make a living because now
they can't their game will never sell those people.
Go away.
Now, you have lost something and that's like a systemic effect, like a
long-term effect.
That's a natural selection effect.
That could be bad, but we don't know that that's happening yet, right?
And we don't know if that will happen, so it's premature to suggest
that that's a problem.
So, I would say, the first order effect doesn't concern me much.
It's just people who are already pandering, may be doing more
pandering or something.
So, the only problem would be if it started to cause like a natural
selection effect, where games that couldn't play well on Twitch
disappear, that would be sad, but I don't know that that's going to
happen, you know.
So far, I would say if anything twitch has been having a positive
effect for obscure game sometimes because more people are watching
games which means that more people are seeing game streamed which
means that there's more possibilities for them to find out about games
that they weren't finding out about.
So, so far, I would say, I don't think twitch is affecting
systemically games on a bad way, it may actually be having a positive
effect, but again, a lot of that's too early to tell since I'm not a
game designer, don't have a strong opinion about it, that's just my
knee-jerk reaction.
Boondoggle for you too.
Could you list the important features a good graphical debugger should
have?
I mean what you see me using on handmade Heroes, the bare minimum,
like your things should be able to do everything that I'm doing in
Visual Studio should have the memory display window.
It should have a quick updating watch window, which Visual Studio
doesn't have.
Unfortunately should be fashion videos to do Visual Studio hopefully,
but you have watch window that's really easy to use, saves my state
from run to run, right?
So I shouldn't have to re add my variables, whatever it should be
trivial to close and
Start the program quickly.
It should never crash.
It should never like hang up the graphic system or anything like that.
Linux fails on both of those counts.
It should always be able to inspect all my debug variables.
That's a big problem, with a lot of graphical front ends.
On Linux, is they can't inspect unions and stuff like this, even
though GDB can it's weird, they have these weird, like, bugs, local
variables, cause problems.
So, yeah, just just a reasonable implementation of what Visual Studio
does is the bare minimum and that right now we don't really have
Anywhere other than Visual Studio, which is kind of sad.
Justified are you one of those that thinks that previously DirectX was
better than opengl but now is the opposite.
I don't think I've ever thought that DirectX was better than opengl.
Kemosabe 76.
Do you know how far has metaprogramming come along another Fields?
I can imagine research using genetic algorithms to self enhance code.
I do not know anything about that know.
All right.
Okay, let's go ahead and spin things down.
Okay, so thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on him here at Oregon.
It comes to the source code.
So if you want to play around with it, follow along at home, that is
the place to do that.
So, yeah.
We also have a forum site.
You can go to ask questions and there's an antidepressant guide up
there.
We also have a patreon page, you can pledge to.
If you want to support the video series, we have a tweet but you can
go to
Want to check the schedule and we have a conference now.
So if you want to go to handmade con dot org, you can read about that.
Got a pretty awesome speaker list as well.
It's pretty much my dream list two speakers.
It's basically five people who are really want to talk about
programming who do exactly the kind of programming that we talked
about on handmade hero here and so definitely check that out if you
want to.
It's more informations on the Molly rocket.com webpage there.
So, yeah, check that out.
We still have some tickets left, they are selling off pretty fast, so
I don't know how much longer they will be tickets left, but check it
out.
They're not very expensive.
And we'd love to see you there.
That's about it for today.
I will see you guys back here tomorrow at 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time until then, thanks for joining me and I'll see
you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.