Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show recode complete game live on stream.
We are trying out weekend streaming here and well.
I don't know that it's gonna be that much different than weekday
streaming, but we're going to do two episodes.
Back-to-back is basically the difference.
So, instead of doing one episode every week night, we're going to do
two episodes on Saturday and two episodes on Sunday and see how that
works.
The idea here is just to make it so that we can have a more of a
continuous workflow.
Because two hour blocks, tend to be better than one hour blocks and
programming in my experience, just normally especially when you factor
in the discussion that has to go on.
So, you know, there's certain less amount of coding that can actually
happen when I'm explaining things.
Obviously
And so in order to try and make it more possible for us to do bigger,
code changes, little more smoothly, we're gonna see how that works.
So what I'm going to do today is finished what we were doing before
today is day 350.
So you want to start with de 349 source code, if you want to do that,
If you want to follow along, my voice is in bad shape for some reason.
I don't think it's the talking.
I actually think that it is a little bit of a cold eye.
I got my flu shot so I don't know that I have the flu, but I might
have, like, fighting off the flu or something.
I don't know what anyway, but I hadn't been feeling well.
The past couple days so, so we'll see.
Anyway, what I was working on when we last left hand made hero week
ago, was I wanted to make it so that we could simulate multiple
regions at the same time and we basically did that.
So I showed at the end of last week stream and
Full of stimulating.
Two, separate regions in the world.
Concurrently
And it worked just fine, so that's good but we have a few more things
to deal with here and we have to deal with the SIM region merging.
I don't know that we're going to have to deal with printed clocking
but we need to talk about both of them.
However, before we get to there and this got fixed before we get to
their, I want to do one of the thing and talk about why I'm doing it
and how I'm doing it because it's something that I think is, you know,
important to kind of know.
And be aware of.
So you can kind of, it's just a general, it's a fairly standard code
transformation.
If you're in architecture, kind of person and I just want people to
understand what's going on and why?
So if you remember how we made this work, we have a function called
update and render Sim region.
And what update and render Sim region does is update and render Sim
region.
Allows you to say this block of the world needs to be updated and that
way you can pick any block of the world that you need to update and
have it update, doesn't have to be only one per frame.
We can do 12 for frame if you want.
We could Farm them off to multiple processors.
We can do anything we want, really?
But when we did this, one of the things that you'll notice and a lot
of times people, ask me what I think of functional programming and I
always say the same thing which is, I think the functional programs
really good.
I don't think it's the kind of thing that you should apply everywhere.
Just like, most programming practices, aren't the kind of thing, you
should play everywhere.
But functional programming is definitely something that's worth
understanding and worth applying in a number of circumstances.
Well,
One of the things that you can sort of think of that, even a little
bit more General than that is really just more of the concept of State
visibility May sort of minimization.
And what I mean by that is anytime that you look at a function, it's
very instructive to know what it is.
That that function actually requires to do.
Its job, meaning, what state in the system does this function?
Need to access?
Now, in a purely functional context, one of the reasons that like I
say, functional
I think it's a good thing is because in some contexts you can get, you
can get a function down to the point where it doesn't actually modify
anything it only has to look at things right.
Meaning the parameters that you pass in are immutable.
And the only thing that you're interested in coming back from the
function, is the return value, which you're going to use.
And this obviously, pays a number of dividends any number of such
functions can be called concurrently without any locking or anything,
right?
Because if all you do is look at the state of something and then
return a value, you don't have to worry if two things are doing at the
same time, right?
To things that are doing that.
Same time will still produce completely correct results because
they're not touching.
Any of the things that they're being handed, they're giving their
being given this information as purely advisory and they are not
allowed to go in and muck with it, right?
This is what people mean when they say no side effects of a function,
right?
It means that when I call the function, it's not going to touch
anything.
It's just going to return a variable back to me, and that's the only
thing that it's going to do.
So, that's very powerful for a number of reasons.
Right, another reason that's very powerful is it means that you don't
have to
To wonder about what that function is going to do when you call it.
So for example in this circumstance, when we had two of these guys
here, you can kind of see that when I call this update and render some
region, there's a lot of stuff getting passed here.
That I wouldn't really want to be touched or accessed in the case
where I was simulating, something that wasn't getting rendered.
So, for example, you know, we passed the render group and the
Buffer here, well, the render group in the draw.
Buffer are pieces of information that only someone who's going to
display information to the screen would need.
And so, you can tell right away that this function, really at this
point, isn't quite right in terms of how it operates and what it
needs.
Because sometimes we want to call it in ways that don't involve using
those parameters and those end up getting nullified out, right?
Okay, so when when I look at this, that definitely gives me some
concern and if you look at how the system is architected currently
when we want to call this thing twice.
If I didn't, you know, when I, when I did this before, I'm going to
look and see if I can make that debug camera, be a little further out
as well.
Whereas
I don't really remember what that's called.
Hold on a second.
It's called render camera, debug distance.
so, if I do a search Global under camera, beeps camera debug distance,
all right, or not,
probably spelled that wrong.
Here it is.
I knew I knew it was there any way to know why I search for it?
I missed the underscore.
All right, I'm going to just make that be higher up.
so, if we take a look at what happens here, when I run the program,
And I turn on the debug stream here at that.
Still probably wasn't enough.
Let's make it even further.
Excited.
We don't have good slider so I don't want to have to edit it there as
a pain in the butt, to edit it every time.
So if I, if I switch this here we should be able to see still not
enough far as it's really far.
Okay, so maybe we want something more like 150 200.
So now that I've got the camera far enough out, if I do switch to the
debug camera, there you go.
You can see that s debug region, down here and we do want it rendering
Right.
So it's okay that we pass in the render group there, but now let's say
that I'm talking about the game in a more realistic setting, not in a
debug View and I don't want that to be drawn, right?
Well, what I do when I don't want that to be drawn in the way that we
current have currently have the code structured is I just get rid of
these things that I'm passing, right?
I just say, I don't want you to access the render group and then you
won't.
And now that simulation is still a
Occurring, right?
You can still see, we've got that all that extra work.
Being done here, right?
That hunt, super unoptimized function that takes a lot of time, but
when I zoom out, it's not being drawn and that's exactly what we would
expect to see because we, you know, it shouldn't be right.
And, you know what, what's interesting about this too is you can kind
of see another bit of leakage
Happening Here.
In fact this is a really good example of why I want to do the code
change that I'm going to do to.
You can see that the particle systems are active down here, right?
I don't know if you guys can see that but there's little particles
being emitted here.
And the reason for that is because hey, anytime you're in a
You're in part of the simulation.
It's going to want to generate particles, right?
That's what that's what happens in these circumstances particles get
generated, right?
So, it's not that we can't do what we want to do with this, and even
for the particle system, part of it, I could do the exact same
process, I could make it so that when I call updated render same
region, I have fundamentally speaking, you know, just some stuff that
I pass in here, right?
And that's a totally reasonable way to structure code, if that's the
most efficient way to do it, and we may want to keep it that way.
But there's at least one thing that I think I probably don't want to
keep that way.
But we'll sort of talked about that a second.
So, if we take a look at what's happening with updating, render Sim
region, what we have effectively done is said, okay, rather than
Breaking this up into smaller functions and calling the ones that we
want.
We've kept it monolithic so that it does what it does.
And then inside that monolithic function, we've put an if statement
that says, hey, if you are in a place where you wanted me to process
input, then I will do the stuff that I was going to do for that.
Right?
And similarly, you get kind of a
Similar situation here where like if I go down to update and render
entities, you know, and I look inside that function which is sort of
sub function here of the simulation update.
If we look at what's going on there.
The same thing is true.
The simulation code is here and will do the operations it needs to do
to, to do the simulation.
But then the render group,
Is switched on and says, well, if there is a render group, then I'll
go through and do this rendering that, I needed to do for this entity,
but if it's not, I'll just ignore all of this code altogether, you
know, none of it will become active and again, for the particle system
stuff.
Since we have this problem of spawning particles, you can kind of see
here with the particle cash.
What we'd want to do is the exact same thing here, right?
We'd want to basically say, hey, the particle cash, should be
something that's passed down to us and if we don't
Have one.
We shouldn't be doing this operation, right?
So that's one way to structure the code.
And what it essentially means is that when you are doing this
particular operation, you're going to pass in a superset potentially,
not a proper superset, perhaps, but a super set of all of the things
that you might need to complete the operation.
And then, you are going to selectively switch some of them off and the
code.
Using them will know when you've done that not to perform certain
aspects of their function and it's important to internalize when this
is happening and why.
So we could equivalently say let's break this up into two phases,
update and render, which are separate right?
And if we did that, then we would only pass the render operations to
the render side.
And we'd only pass the update operations or information rather to the
update side.
And if we do that, that would make this code a lot more understandable
and digestible because it means that you don't have the two parts sort
of coming close together.
The problem is, if we did that, we also pay potentially a very large
cost and the cost that we pay is that in doing.
So we would force the code.
To look like this Loop twice, meaning, we would have to Loop over all
the entities that we were concerned about in the same region two
times.
And in doing that, that means we are bringing all of their information
back into the cache.
Both times, this can be very expensive, right?
That can be a very expensive thing to do.
Now, we don't know a priority, which methods Cass.
You cash usage is actually better because we haven't measured it.
It could be that the things that we're doing because we also do the
rendering and have to push things on the push buffer, in that case,
whatever it could be.
That for some reason we don't come out ahead, Cash Wise if we by
merging two together, but it could also be that we do.
And so it's always a trade-off here.
When you look at these simplifying functions down so that they take
less things is definitely something you want to do if you can without
paying any cost but in some cases you have definite cost and this is
potentially one of them.
So what I want to do here is just show how we would remove some of
this.
If we wanted to, I'm not going to split up update and render yet.
Because like I said, I'm not really confident that that's a good
decision, there's nothing wrong with writing code, this way again, you
know, there's obviously a lot of
Doggery in programming and people often say you know you have to split
up concerns or keep things in class and Bubba all of that stuff is,
you know, it's is obviously, you know, not true right?
CPUs are CPUs.
They execute code.
They know nothing of these things.
And so the only thing that really matters at the end of the day is the
shipping product.
Were you able to write it efficiently?
Did it work?
Okay, did it, you know take too long to bug all those sorts of things?
Measurable outcomes is the only thing that matters.
And so in this case, again, with something like
This both ways of structuring the code are totally valid.
They just have trade-offs.
And it's a question of which of those trade-offs, is the right one to
make in this circumstance.
So, here where we have the render group coming in,
And and that's our stuff.
I'm not going to touch that.
Instead, what I'm going to do is just show how we might address this
situation for a part that I think is absolutely of no cash concern is
no perform screen.
There's a there's probably no reason why it would have to do it that
way and that is this part right here.
So you can see that we have looked to see if any players are trying to
join.
Right?
And this is clearly you know if you look at what's going on here,
there's there's obviously no real reason why this would have to
be done in line with anything.
It's not, it's doing its own Loop over controller data, nobody else is
participating in that Loop, there is no shared data here with this,
and the thing that comes after it, there's really not a lot of
argument to be made Regarding why this has to be part of this
function.
It's really a separate thing.
It could be broken out.
But of course, what we find when we do break it out, like, let's just
do the very straight.
Cut and paste here.
If I wanted to start again, taking a small step to remove that from
the code where it was and putting it in its own separate function.
What I will find very quickly is that it relies on something that is
not possible to be extricated directly.
So let's say that we do this and this is I probably should keep the
comment as well.
Let's bring that back up here.
So, put that in there.
Check for joining Players.
Let's say seems like a reasonable name for this function because
that's what we're doing.
And we know in this case that we need to pass the gain input, because
it's going to Loop over that, and you can kind of see some of the
other things that this needs.
It needs the game State because that's where the controlled hero
function array lives, where it can check things out.
And now let's try to, you know, try to put that in here, check for
joining players.
I'll pass that game State and the input and then we'll just see what
we need.
So we need camera P.
Which is where the, you know, the hero is going to show up.
We need the Sim region, right?
And those are pretty easy things.
Again to add in here, not particularly hard.
I want that.
I want the Sim region.
Where did that goes?
Region, region.
And the world mode.
And that's all that that function needs at the moment.
Let me go ahead and pass those in.
Let's see.
I need that same region.
I need the world node.
Remember where we put the world mode?
In the parameter list, it's right after games today.
So there I've called it, right?
And so now the question is well like I said, I don't think that wants
to be an update and render Sim region.
So let's go ahead and move it out.
And what we find when we do this is the thing that I wanted to talk
about and just sort of mention.
So let's say, I wanted this to be moved out.
So I put it here and I'm like, good to go, this is going to be great.
We'll compile it.
Okay, we have the input.
We have the game State and then we get to these two guys right here,
Sim region and Camera p.
And we're like, we don't have
Of them.
Now there's nothing we can do to get them, because if we take a look
at where, what's going on in here, this function that we want to call
that we want that we didn't want to be doing this operation, it's
actually necessary for it to have been doing what it's doing with the
begins him, right?
That's actually necessary.
That's an actually
Required aspect.
And in order to get the camera P, the same thing is true, right?
We need the Sim Center which this thing was Computing.
So if we take a look at what that means, it means that we have a thing
that's optional, right?
We only want to call check for joining players.
This first time, we don't want to do it this time, right?
It's not something that's supposed to happen in all of the times that
we are simulating regions.
So you only want to call check for joining players, just that one
time.
But we find that we can't, because when we call update and render Sim
region, it's going to do some work that's necessary for us to be able
to finish for us to be able to actually perform this function.
So what we need to do fundamentally is Break Up Update and render Sim
region into multiple pieces that can be controlled in a more Dynamic
fashion.
Right?
What we want to do is do something like we have here, where we do
begin Simmons him.
We want something more like that you want to be able to call begin Sim
and Sim.
And in this case we call check for joining players in the other case,
we just call begin Sim and Sim and we never actually call a check for
joining players in between.
Right?
So, that's a fundamental kind of code transformation.
We want to be able to make.
It's the kind of code transformation where you're basically saying, we
have something that all has to happen in line, but some of the parts
of it want to be optional and we don't really want them to be sort of
welded
And to that code because we want the person calling it to be able to
sort of control the order of how they're happening, or have more
control over whether they happen at all.
And we just feel more comfortable with that being the way things work.
And so, what we can do here is, we can sort of expand our notion of
how that begins in and Sim work because if you look at how this
happens, beginning the same region,
Is really kind of a lower level operation.
It's really not begins him that we're calling hear what we're saying.
Open up like a piece of the world for edit, right?
Is what that is.
So really, we kind of the naming here is sort of what's throwing us
off.
It shouldn't really be called, begin Sim.
It should be called like open world region and then we should have a
like closed World region or something like this, right?
And then begin Sim is a higher level thing that happens, which does
the open, but also does a few of these other things, right?
And then inside there we would have
Have thing that's like a call for example simulate which we don't
currently have and and sort of makes this all look a lot more.
Like a sort of a reasonable control flow that we can manage.
So here's begins eminent Sam and check for joining players right?
I know that that's one thing I want to have happen.
So probably if we looked at how this we wanted this to look here, we
could do something like this.
Right.
And maybe, you know, they'd be an opportunity for us to actually, you
know, do do something even more specific there.
Like, for example, the particle system rendering, could be something
that sort of happens, only in one place as well, you know, we could do
something like here, we do render particle systems and then that, you
know, things could come out as well.
Because as you can see, from here, this stuff is all, in fact, you
know,
Right.
This stuff is all kind of
Extractable, right?
It's something that can come out and similarly, like this debug
information as well that we have here that can come out equivalently.
So, you know, if we look at what this is going to look like, you know,
this starts to look a lot more reasonable to me because now we're
starting to kind of get this
This function starting to look a lot more sane and you can kind of now
see much more clearly at the higher level.
What the difference is between these two operations.
You know, one of them is clearly just going to simulate an area.
One of them is going to do a bunch of other things.
In addition to stimuli in the area, it's also going to check for the
players that are joining and it's also going to update and render the
particle systems, and things like this.
So again, just talking about kind of that motion.
Hopefully that gives some understanding of how that's going to work.
So let's go ahead and actually Implement that code change just so you
can kind of see what that looks like.
So suppose that I'm going to take here and and go down to.
I probably shouldn't quite have moved everything out yet, but, you
know, that's okay.
Well, we'll deal with it.
Suppose, I go into some region here and I just, again, call this
something a little bit different because if you,
About this being called a Sim region.
Again, it's not really quite what it what it really means, it's really
more of just an open region of the world, and in some sense you could
even think
if we take a look at what's Happening Here,
In some sense really, you can start to see the same region stuff and
the world are really just probably should be welded, right?
This is kind of a thing that we were working on that sort of how they
sort of pair up with each other.
And what you can see is like the simulation side of things and the
like packing and unpacking amenities side of things.
Is really are really two very different functions.
Right.
You can see in here that really all this is doing is opening up the
region.
It's copying out all of the entities into an editable State and then
giving it back to you, right?
And similarly, then we have when we close it we have all the same
stuff that's happening here, right?
That's exactly what's going on.
And so really you like I said, it's not begins Eminence and that's not
really what's happening here.
It's really more like begin worldedit.
and,
And then world at it, that's what's actually happening right?
And you know we could we could also call it changes if edits a little
too confusing, begin World change, you know, something like that.
And I'm not sure what the best word is for it, obviously, but it's
something along those lines.
So then you know, that's a pretty simple name change all we're saying
is, you know, it's now begin World change instead of something else.
This is n World change again, not particularly strange.
What's Happening Here?
World change and World change and then we're left with just the things
that are actually World Sim.
Right.
Okay.
So now we have to address what this is actually happening here.
So you know, now we have to say, okay, we've got a thing that probably
will return a Sim region.
It's going to be called begins him and then we're going to have a
thing that does and then Sim and if you look at what's actually going
to happen, there you can see that there is a lot of additional stuff.
Right, here we go.
Got our begins him.
Then we've got our actual simulation step, which is this.
And then we've got a sort of our finishing step.
Which is this?
Right?
And you know, if we take a look at what's happening here in terms of
passing down, like the mouse p and the world and that sort of stuff,
probably mostly deal with it like this for now.
Again.
And now we can start to sort of play with the consequences of that and
just like, make sure that we've kind of gotten them under control.
So if we take a look at what we need to pass in terms of update and
render some region, and all that sort of stuff.
So we can take a look at begin secure, we can take a look at this list
and I'm just going to paste that list into all three of these and then
start eliminating things we didn't really need.
So now you can see that NCM itself really doesn't need very much at
all, it really just needs that Sim.
We're going to have to deal with that in a second and then it needs,
you know, the Sim region and the world mode.
So those are pretty easy things to pass it.
So there's the same region
And we're going to have to pass in that.
What is it?
Emory
Do not remember what that's called.
Temporary.
So it's going to need that same memory so it can end that, right?
And then it's going to have to do the the world change stuff.
So we'll deal with that in a second but that's it.
Don't really know what this is talking about per se in terms of the
camera update, I guess that's happening inside here.
So we should probably leave that comment so you can take a look at it.
But here is our simulate function.
Let's take a look at what that needs.
So again it needs Mouse P at the moment so we'll leave all the stuff
in there that it actually needs World mode.
Probably needs most of the stuff, right?
But again, it's going to need some things from up here.
So it needs like the camera.
For example, is something that it needs to know.
And so let's start figuring out how to get that information.
Sort of encapsulated
So I know what we're going to call this, I guess we'll call this you
know, World Sim.
Or something like this.
And in here we're going to sort of store the information that we
needed to flow through.
In fact, I guess, what I can do is I can actually make this probably
contain these two, so it's like a convenient way to pass them through.
Alright, so here will pass this.
The world Sim that will have the region in it.
And the same memory and then similarly, like over here.
Against them would return that.
So, we have our results and we'll just fill it up.
And that's it.
So when we call simulate we're going to have to probably pass in the
same region and I guess the camera p is probably also important here.
And all of that stuff, now can come out from from this system, right?
And similarly, we could save anything that we wanted to save here that
we needed to save here out of things that if we knew to DT is not
really necessary to be passed in here.
I would think in fact, Y in y, just begin World.
Change require the DT.
Does that make sense to you?
It doesn't make a whole lot of sense to me.
Was that something that, you know, used to happen.
And, you know,
Doesn't have to happen anymore.
Is there a reason for?
Oh, I know why, it's because it needs to know how much to widen it by.
So, I guess it does because things that move faster would require
bigger.
Symbols potentially.
All right?
So render group in the draw buffer and game input.
Probably don't need to be passed here, right?
So, none of this stuff has to be passed.
The background color doesn't have to be passed.
So, I think it's only the screen bounds.
Potentially she even the
Oz, I don't know.
Need to be passed.
So just a lot of things don't have to be passed here, right?
It's really just these and so begins in becomes a much sort of simpler
and more understandable thing at this point, which is nice.
And then we can just return this out.
And we can require that it be passed back in.
Now, if I look at the trance State here, the assets is really the only
thing that needs to get passed through.
So I might just say that that's something that gets passed here.
Because again, that would not really need to be passed in
circumstances where you weren't rendering and so that could become a
portent important leader.
All right, all right.
So we want to pull out the SIM region.
Because we need that.
We want to pull out the camera pee.
And that's about it, okay?
Alright.
Now, what else do we need here?
Is there anything that we don't need?
I don't know that.
The screen bounds is necessary.
It's being bounced is not necessary.
How about the game state?
Game say is necessary for brain execution.
We can probably get rid of that eventually.
I think we probably will background color is necessary Sinbad's MDT
symbols not necessary because sorority capsulated in the same region
itself.
So I think that's it, the role Tim the world, note the DT,
everything's good.
That's about it for
That.
So now let's actually go ahead and call these.
So inside our update and render world, we now have this sort of world
Sim that were calling
and we're just going to go ahead and pass what it wants.
All right, so nothing particularly unusual there.
We're just passing what we're supposed to pass and
Then we're going to do is call check for joining players, which we
know we can do now because we've got our world.
So we can sort of pass through the information that we need to pass
through.
We can then call simulate.
Yeah, and we just need to know what that's going to take four
parameters, right?
So, here's simulate.
It's going to take the world sin, it's going to take a world mode.
It's going to take the duty.
It's going to take all the rest of the stuff, the background color
game, State assets input render group, the drop offer.
And you got to spell game state, right?
Not good.
If you don't.
So, here's the DT.
And let's go ahead and correct that out.
Frame to frame.
Camera, Delta P.
I'll be honest with you.
I don't remember where that's computed.
Let's take a look and see.
So here we are, and
Frame-to-frame, Delta camera p is produced up here.
It looks like excuse me for a second.
I want to put on my
my hoodie here.
There we go.
Just getting a little cold.
Okay.
So yeah, what I was saying is I don't remember that was computed.
Well, it's computer right here.
And here's the subtraction frame to frame camera.
Delta p.
Is only used for particle systems, I believe.
Yeah, so the frame to frame
Camera, Delta p is something that probably should be moved because it
really isn't necessary until we actually run the particle systems
themselves, right?
So I feel like that should probably be something that's just done here
because it's really not necessary for anything else, right?
All right.
so, I think
yeah, so I think we're now down to sort of a much
Sort of a much more, much more simpler, sort of structure of this
code, which is good.
We're getting better.
And you can see the, this allowed me to pull out a bunch of code into
the upper level that used to be kind of sunk down in there.
So now if you take a look at this, almost as like of code injection,
almost you can kind of see that between the beginning and the end, we
can now do a bunch of these things that only happen in the main
visible update.
And now none of those things the
Systems the debug rendering the checking for joining players.
None of those are welded into the update anymore which means that.
Now if we want to do a second update down here, right?
Oops.
If we want to do a second update on here, we don't really have to
worry.
About all of those other aspects, right?
So we can come in here and just call simulate.
and I,
Just got past these things in.
Same as we're doing.
So I think we should still be getting now.
Exactly the same results right?
Nothing has changed.
Exactly, like we wanted and if we would like to have these things
draw, well I guess I don't have to do it that way.
We still can
So that's really nice and like I'm feeling better about how that sort
of starting to pull out.
Now what we want to look at here again, like I said is we just kind of
want to take a little bit closer, look at the stuff that we're doing
in here and now asking again our there's other things that we could do
here, is there other stuff that we should be being a little bit more?
Careful about pulling out.
So the
first thing that I point out is if we take a look at Mouse P, right?
Interrupt update and render entities.
So,
Mouse key is really only used for debug picking at stuff like this.
We could use some more water.
So, if we take a look at what happens with something like that, it's
only there for debugging purposes and things that are only there for
debug purposes.
Often times, make a lot less sense to, like, structure code around.
So, the fact that you have to pass in, put something like this right
now for Mouse, be doesn't make very much sense.
So the really the only thing that we should be looking at.
I think in terms of why input is getting past this at all, is in the
execute brain side of things.
So, if you take a look at execute brain here, you can actually see
Why we need input?
The reason is because input is currently getting used in execute brain
for controlling the hero right for controlling any player controlled
character.
So, I'm not 100% certain that we really want that as our model for a
how controller input gets pushed down, right?
We may want something that's going to allow us to do a little bit
more, a little bit more thoughtful, kind of an operation on this,
where the brains pick up their data from someplace that isn't directly
the input.
That's probably going to be a better thing in the long run especially
so that we don't have input code kind of baked down in here in such a
specific way.
Now, I don't know that.
That's true.
It's just a hunch but you can kind of see that.
That's why input is flowing through here.
Right?
Ignore this because this is just debug information and we could choose
to get that to funnel that through in a number of different ways.
In fact, what?
So I'm actually kind of curious about that.
I want to take a look at that.
So, in update and render entities.
What are we doing with the mouse be here.
Exactly.
So we do a nun.
Projective the mouse be just in this one place that correct.
Yeah.
So, all we're doing right.
There is using it for hit testing and envy, right?
That's what that's for.
So again, that's also something that we might be able to for like the
debug you.
I enabled stuff that might be something that makes a little more sense
to kind of pull out separately.
Because again, with something like where we're concerned about the
performance, like I was saying the reason not to Loop over these
entities again for performance reasons, make some sense and we may not
want to separate.
Update and render.
But for debug code, we know that debug code isn't even going to be
shipping in the game, right?
It's going to be disabled.
So, for that, it does seem like a pretty reasonable thing to say,
okay, well, what if we just introduced a new function up here which is
like debug, you know, debug entity.
He's something like that.
What if we just introduced a new function up here for that and said,
okay you know, let's let's Loop through these entities just like we
were doing before.
But now when we're doing this, hit testing, you know, maybe we can
pull that out.
Although actually now to think about to, you know, do we can we just
make this
Well.
I'm not sure yet we may want there to be debug information that kind
of gets output during this is the only thing.
Like, you know, this I would say, let's pull this out completely but I
just don't know whether I think we want to sort of output debug
information about this entity directly during its out during this
phase.
That's a tough call.
I'm not sure how I feel about that.
Because in some sense, what we could do here is just say that the
debug kit stuff and the like unprojected, whatever this could just be
some kind of function like debug mouse that the debug Mouse position
comes back and you don't have to pass it down, right?
It could be totally a separate debug situation, so I don't really know
how I feel about that.
I think I think because our debug system is only so-so like we don't
have a ton of debug system in there.
Maybe, let's go ahead and pull it out for now.
So, let's say that we pull out this one part right here and we say
that that's going to be something that we call externally.
Like, so,
and then,
Depending on which one of them, we pick?
let's see, I guess that's
actually right here.
Do you like nine able to book requested?
There we go.
And yeah.
Just have one more thing to make here.
Debug begin data block.
I'm curious to know, I guess we don't have to specify that we're
ending a data block, I guess the only thing that has to happen there,
Is.
It's just a regular end block.
Right.
Which is this guy right here, I believe.
So there's our begin block for energy physics.
And there's our end block.
There are no other things in here.
So yeah, I think it's just this guy now, I'm not sure why that end
block was there wouldn't that end block have to be after each one?
Seems kind of broke.
It doesn't it?
Like, I feel like the end block should correspond with this.
Then again, the debug requested part.
I'm not sure was this a spurious end block like, how did that get in
there?
There's the begin block, there's the begin block.
There's only two right?
And similarly, there's only two end blocks.
So I guess this doesn't really require an in book.
I'm a little stumped by that I have to admit.
Oh, hi, I'm real smart.
It's right there.
Okay, so this would have to take the same region.
Deadly debug ID, only needs to be created.
Once now that we merge those two code paths, we do need to have the
render group and the mouse P passed in.
and then the entity transform, I guess this is where we decided to put
this entity
So this is a pretty good example, I guess of why.
This would be tougher to put out here, right?
In terms of knowing where this entity is.
Because if we take a look at what has to happen for that to occur, you
can see that like we've got this sort of
You know, relatively complicated piece of code that has to go on in
order for the end of the transform to be.
You know, set up properly.
You can see that it needs like the camera.
I'll ground Z and all that sort of stuff.
So I do, it's tough to say, we can keep it welded in there, but in the
three in in once we have sort of the three dienes of this work of this
working a little bit better, that's not going to
So hard to do.
So it's kind of six of one half dozen of the other, right?
So, what I will say here is like yeah, I don't know about this that
that does suggest just looking what happens that pulls out.
Everything else is very simple.
This is a little bit more complicated.
We could pretty trivially reproduce it just by having their be a call
here, but that gives me a relatively good argument for why I would
want to keep this welded in is just because if that does become
complicated I don't want to have to do it.
Oftentimes right?
So let's see.
or if we can just kind of
Make this a single entity pick.
And when we call through here, maybe we just pass the entity
transform.
Oops.
Okay.
Of that.
And then we're good.
So yeah.
So you can see debug pick entity.
Now isn't something that will just pick a single entity and that seems
a little bit more tenable to me.
So if we come through here and we're look to say, okay, we're doing
the render group, so assuming that we actually see this entity we're
processing.
It will call debug Kennedy on it so that it can be picked.
And let's go ahead and
Pass the right parameters to it.
We need the Sim region, The Entity render group, and then transform.
Okay, so I think everything we need there is in good shape but we
still have this question of mouse P.
Like I said I kind of want to get rid of that.
I don't think I want that to be hanging around.
So what I'm thinking is in general inside our debug interface, you
know we have sort of this ability to get information back from the
system and in fact we see this in a number
Of ways, right?
You can see here, we look at Global debug table edit event, so it'd be
pretty trivial for us to use the global debug table to record this.
This piece of information.
So let me take a look at that.
Here's the event that's being edited.
We could pretty trivial in here.
Say, here's the mouse be right.
Could just put that in there, and so if we wanted to do that, then
it's a pretty straightforward process of just saying.
Well, anyone who wants to know what, the debug mouse key is now can
just get that from the debug system itself.
So, in here, when you say, you know, I want
Debug Mouse P, right?
And you say I want, I want that piece of information, then you can
just say like, okay that's just going to be equal to whatever the
Here.
whatever the global debug table says the mouse be is
something like that.
And equivalent.
So that seems pretty reasonable to me.
That doesn't seem like it would be causing anyone any particular harm
or trouble and we can.
Again also make those not do anything when there is no.
When there's no debug information happening.
So now we can keep those debug things into Global variables.
Again, the reason that I like that is just because I don't want the
debug system and its additional needs impacting, how the code is
architected given that the debug system itself gets compiled out when
things are shipped.
So I want to keep those separate and not creating that problem.
So if we take a look at what we would need to do support this, now we
can say
Okay, we can generate this mouse p and we can set that up.
And then anyone who wants to get it can just get it by asking the
debug system, right?
And that's the thing I could set, like, way up here at the beginning
to, if I wanted to
All right.
So now we're out of the business of having to have this mouthpiece
even exist at all which is good thing.
Again that's just a positive code change because it really had nothing
to do with the actual code that was happening, was strictly there as
an artifact of the debug system, which I didn't want.
So that's all good now to however, I think that code that code was.
I don't even know if he kept up-to-date looks like we did.
Because you can see it's still working now.
So I guess we did keep it up to date and I guess it was in.
In right.
See.
So I guess that code all still works and we can inspect entities
properly, so that's good news.
There's our hero look at him go, so that's all good.
All right, so I think that's it for, for the first wave here of stuff
that I want to do.
And again, like that's getting a little bit cleaner, so that's good.
I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A and then we'll do a second one
hour session after the Q&A.
Ray.
Just in case, anyone has any questions about what we did?
Seth Gartner.
Can you try compiling with debug off?
Yes.
You mean just if we want to clean up our like things that may cause
make call this thing?
I mean, I suppose one thing we should do potentially is
if we want to be able to compile with debug off,
right now, we will need to have debug pick entity be be blocked out
entirely.
Where did that go?
so, for example,
It is this code right here doesn't like none of this wants to compiled
in.
Write all of that wants to compiled out.
So we would want to do something like
right.
Other than that, I don't know that there's much that we'd have to do.
So if we want to compile a debug off, its that
Looks like that's it.
So this has no debug at it.
I also don't really remember I'll be honest if we've used this much at
all.
It looks like it's mostly just used for that one.
Debug validation past there.
And the assertions.
See time stats.
I know it's Irrelevant for the code.
Sure you're talking about.
So I guess I don't ever remember this.
I think I call them .c time on my machine and I must call them
different things on this machine ctm.
Okay, ctm, great.
Nice work.
Casey, and made here at nctm.
Here are the stats at the moment.
Do we have any cues in days?
Not really.
So I guess we can just start
Kiss cam says, what does the dot-dot-dot do in the Define and someone
else asked about documentation in the code?
So,
Can answer both of those.
so,
The dot that in the defying, even if you are an experienced C
programmer, may be surprised you slightly because it is actually new.
So originally
And I guess I use the term originally a little bit Loosely here.
But originally right, we have the concept of functions I guess I'll
just do like Foo.
Right.
Originally, we had the concept that we you know we've got these
functions and we specify the parameters of the function.
So inside the parentheses, we put a list of all the things that we're
going to pass and we all know this, it's in every programming
language.
It's fine C++, I'm sorry cos C had a need sometimes for passing
functions parameters where you didn't know how many were going to be
passed.
And so typically, what would happen is they introduce this notation
Dot dot dot.
Where you could have more parameters to functions and we actually used
this.
So, you know, so just to give a concrete example.
If I was to compile this, this compiles, just fine.
However, if I, you know, is to write that it would say it doesn't
work, right?
But if I said well, you can accept as many arguments as you want.
Now I can pass however many things I want to it and it will work,
right?
So the dot-dot-dot in C4 for, you know, decades has always meant just
this function can can support as many arguments as the color wishes to
pass it.
And it's assumed that inside the
Section.
I am going to deal with parsing there's arguments out somehow it's up
to me how I do it, but that's the idea, right?
Well, see, of course also have the ability to do macros, right?
And they worked pretty much the same way.
You know, I could say Foo of bar and then I would call something where
I would say, Okay, I want to call my macro and it would work, but if I
tried to pass more parameters to the macro, it wouldn't work, right?
Exactly.
Now, just the function, but for the longest time, there was no way to
do anything about that.
If you want,
Need to support multiple.
You know, arbitrary numbers of parameters in a function without
specifying how many there were supposed to be.
You didn't have any option of doing it dot, dot dot syntax, did not
work in macros.
Well, recently, they expanded the notion of macros recently, it's not
that recent, I guess to allow exactly that same thing.
The dot-dot-dot just says, you can put as many additional parameters
as you want at the end of this macro and they will be accepted.
What you can then do much like how the function is expected to deal
with their extra parameters.
The macro expected to deal with those extra parameters, the way that
it works is anywhere in the expansion of the macra, right?
The macro expansion would go here somewhere, right?
You can put the term VAR args like so and it will put the entire
contents of whatever, the dot dot dot represented.
So, in this case, the four comma, the three, it will
Put that in place of the VA arcs.
So example of that would be if I was going to say
Let's say I did something like this.
Here.
I'm going to add three numbers together.
And so I have my results.
Right?
And in this case, I want to be able to add these three numbers.
Well I have, you know, bar here and I say add three numbers and I pass
the results of this macro, this macro is going to be expanded
contextually before the file is compiled.
And what it's going to do is it's just going to evaluate to 5, right?
It's going to be evaluated to bar, right?
And that's not enough, because we need three parameters, the, a, to be
in the sea.
Well, if I was to say, oh also,
Expand the rest of the things that you got past.
You can see that now it works because now this is getting expanded to
five four, three.
Similarly, if I was to pass more parameters here it would then again,
complain that I had too many arguments to my function, right?
So that's all the dot-dot-dot is.
It's really just an equivalent to the dot dot dot Syntax for
functions.
But this way it works for macros now the
Nice Fringe benefit is there are a number of reasons why that's really
nice.
It means, for example, that a function like a very standard function
such as printf, right?
Printf, looks like this.
So if you wanted to make a macro that called printf, you couldn't do
it before, right?
Because you had no way of telling the compiler.
I want to take as many arguments to my macros as possible, right?
Now you can now if you want to
You can make it something that thunks through to printf and will work
and that's very nice for completeness, right?
So it's very good that they added this so that's a nice aspect of it
but also additional aspect of it.
That's really nice.
Is when you have debug functions, right?
When you have a function that you're I'm sorry, macro that's being
used for debugging purposes, oftentimes what it looks like in fact we
can even use the printf, example, let's say we want debug print, okay?
And all debug print is going to do is going to call printf but
I want a way to turn it off.
I want to way to compile it out of my code.
Well now I can say like okay
Know what I wanted.
Use a slightly different example.
Let's say I do something slightly different because it's a makes a
little more sense with what it's more congruent.
To the case that I used it in today.
So I think it would be a better example.
Let's suppose that I make a thing that's like debug print integer.
Right.
And so I'm just going to pass the NT here, whatever it is.
And then I'm going to call printf and I'm going to say like debug you
know D, right?
And here I am printing out my integer, okay, so I'm going to call
debug print integer and my code and I want that to print out the
integer but I only want to do it if we're in like debug mode, right?
So, if someone is pound to find the symbol debug, then I want to do it
but if not then I don't.
The old days, what you had to do, was you had to say this?
Right?
So now I have debug print integer and it takes an integer and it does
the print, then I have debug Bridge, it takes it in the else Clause.
Meaning, if the debug symbol wasn't defined, I'm going to make it
expand to nothing.
So it doesn't affect my code at all.
Well, the bummer about this is you can imagine, you started to have a
lot of these things often times, right?
So there's integer and real and blah, blah blah blah blah, blah.
All right.
There's just all these functions here, right?
So typically what you had to do when you were trying to do this switch
on and off thing.
Is you then have to like cut and paste them all and do this, right?
And that's bad enough.
And unfortunately, we really haven't fixed that in the language yet.
But what do you do?
But the insult to the injury is once you have it set up this way.
Now, what happens, if you decide that this thing needs to take another
parameter.
Well, now you always have to go down and change the corresponding
version to do the same.
And what's worse is because this is only a compile-time directive.
It means that until you actually compile it without the debug flag
set.
You'll never even get an error.
So you
Even though you broke the code, you don't even know that you broke the
non debug build until you actually go build it.
So what's much preference more preferable to do?
Now?
Just as a general coding convention, that's helped save you some time.
Is that when you call debug print and 25, I'm sorry.
When you define the debug print Macro for the non debug case, just go
ahead and and don't specify the parameters.
Just put the dot dot dot in there because you don't care what those
parameters are.
The whole code is being compiled out.
Out and so this way you can basically just say oh no matter what the
changes are, that happen up here as long as the function names.
Don't change.
I'm fine.
So it kind of helps eliminate a few steps to that process and just
saves you maintenance time, which is always good.
Hold on a second.
Okay, so another question is, what about how about documentation?
I see you don't have too much comments in your code.
And yes, that's true.
I tend to frown on comments.
I don't think they're very good, programming practice.
And the reason for that is because I find that comments are almost
always wrong.
As programmers, you know, I think that sort of an underappreciated
thing is, if you're a very productive programmer, you know, some
programmers aren't very productive and maybe for programmers, who
aren't very productive, comments is as a different story, right?
But if you're a very productive programmer than one of the problems
that you have is that you're leaning on the compiler, a lot to make
sure that when you have a piece of code that it actually semantically
checks out, right?
So you're very used to using
That process and also tests right?
Like, you know, maybe you practice test driven development, or maybe
you have a way of testing your code and you run that and that's how
you're ensuring that the code that you're making is working and is
correct.
We have no such thing for comments, right?
The only thing that we have to try and verify the accuracy of comments
are like code reviews and code reviews.
Are there very time-consuming?
They cost a lot in terms of productivity, and they don't even
necessarily verify that the comments or actually, right?
It's sort of just a, maybe they do, maybe they don't,
So that I find that comments are just usually a pretty bad idea, a
comment.
Oftentimes hurts the program are coming down the pipe after you more
than they help, because they send them in the wrong direction, right?
For every correct, comment that survives in your code.
There's probably an incorrect comment and even one incorrect, comment
out of every 10 is enough to really make it hard for somebody who's
relying on the comments to do their job effectively.
So I
A comments usually bad idea.
Try to keep the code is readable as possible and restrict your use of
comments to when you're done with code, when you're finished with a
piece of code and you're not going to touch it for a long time, that's
usually the time to put in a comment.
So when we ship pieces of handmade hero and we're like, we're done
with this.
We're Not Gonna touch it anymore.
That's the time to put a comment in the code because then I know that
that comment at least has a
Really good chance of actually.
Helping someone more than it hurts because I'm writing it at a time.
When I'm pretty sure I'm not going to change the overall architecture
and furthermore, those comments should usually be about exactly that.
They should be about the overall architecture.
Because again, the code is going to get to bug slightly and maybe make
slight modifications over time.
I don't want to put these bad comments and code that are going to
Live longer, then the code, they're describing and become erroneous.
So, what I try to do is I try to restrict myself to those kinds of
comments, and as such, you won't see very many on handmade hero til
the end.
I sometimes receive comments from colleagues or in code reviews, that
I should put long pieces of code into functions for cleanliness.
What parameters goes into your thought process.
When deciding, if a piece of code, should be placed on Jimmy, under a
function.
How do you make the decision?
Well usually when putting something in a function for me is about
whether it's going to get called more than once, right?
I don't think that pulling code out of a function and putting it into
another function increases the cleanliness in any, you know, in any
real way.
It's really just an arbitrary decision.
And you know, it might make it more legible for some people but it
make it less legible for others.
So I would say, typically speaking, you know, your decision whether
you pull something out into a function should be, do I need to call
this in more than one place?
You know, that's that's usually really all that it boils down to if
that makes sense.
So I don't think there's really a lot more to it than that.
If, if all of your colleagues are uniformly, you know, if literally
everyone you work with really did, have a better time.
Reading code, that was
Pulled out into smaller functions then you know, if you can actually,
if you can actually verify that they're not just saying that.
And that they really do have an easier time reading it, because one of
the problems with programmers, a lot of times is that they say things
but they're not true, right?
You know, for example, people often times will say like, oh you got to
put this thing in a class or something, right?
But they have no actual reason for that, they just they think that
clean, code means putting things in a class, but they've never done
any research or provided any data that backs up that claim.
So a lot of times it becomes problematic.
If you're going based on those assumptions.
So if colleagues are telling you to do something and you suspect that
that's why meaning, it's just because they've been told this and they
never really thought it through.
That's usually a poor reason to do it.
But let's say you were in a situation where your colleagues really
legitimately for whatever reason.
The way their brains tend to work is that they likes reading small
functions and can understand them better if that turns out to be true
in some measurable way, then that's obviously a good reason to do it.
It doesn't mean your code is bad.
Bad, if you didn't do it and it doesn't mean that it's always best to
break things up into small functions.
All it means is, hey, you're you're clearly in a work environment
where it benefits your colleagues to do this thing.
So that's a perfectly reasonable reason to do it, right?
Hopefully that's true.
Just in general, right?
It's like if there's some particular coding practice that perhaps has
absolutely no basis or no fundamental reason why it's better
You may still want to do that practice.
If it does, in practice, make your specific team function better
because every team and every development environment is going to be
different.
Sometimes drastically sometimes, only subtle to suddenly
But if you can establish that you that it is definitely true for your
work environment that a certain coding practice helps people.
That is a very good reason to do it.
And the only thing to be sure about obviously is that you've actually
come to that decision in a data-oriented way where you've actually
tried to do some experiments to determine that.
It was not just somebody's arbitrary, you know?
Fanciful notion that this was a better code.
So,
I think I've I got all the questions.
I don't see any other questions.
So I think I think we're good.
I don't think I said I don't see any other questions if there were no
other questions.
I'll start the second block.
How much code is, debug code versus real code?
Well, you know, it's always hard to say.
It changes.
A lot from Project to project, right?
The.
The breakdown on handmade here is probably I don't know, 30% debug
code, 70% actual code, I don't know.
I actually don't know.
We haven't measured it so that that's like a complete guess, on my
part.
You know, I wish there was an easier way to tell you can, obviously
get a clock count on the debug code versus the non debug code because
we have like, you know, these functions here.
Sorry these files here, debug their only debug code but you know,
there's debug code scattered throughout.
These are the things.
And so even that clock count would
Be definitive.
Yeah, that's a good point up, the coder suggest that you could expand
the files and take the diffs of the like pre-processed files in both
cases, one with the debug on and one of the debugger off that would be
that would totally work.
I think.
well, not even that doesn't really work because you need to
pre-process
The preprocessor would expand out things potentially that would skew
that metric a little bit, but yeah, that's probably the bet that's
probably the most accurate when we could hope for at the moment.
all right, let's go ahead and
Get ourselves back to normal state so we can start again.
All right.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
This is our second block of our to Saturday blocks in our first Vlog.
Today, we were just showing how to pull apart a piece of code that did
a bunch of different things where we wanted a little bit more control
over, which things happened in, which ones didn't.
And in the second block here, today I'm going to kind of go back into
that a little bit and just kind of comb over that
Code and do a little bit more restructuring of it.
Till I'm a little bit happier with how everything in it is working.
So yeah, it's the phrase day should probably always have been our
unfortunately, I don't know, maybe I'll change it to our instead but
here on our 350, you want to start with our three 49s source code
because that's what I'm was starting with.
Is that correct?
That's not correct.
It's that's not correct at all.
There we go.
That's what we actually wanted, but I don't even know how to use my
own little advicing.
I should probably, I probably will have to update the update, the
timer to deal with the to block system.
So what I meant to say is today's day 351 or our 351 is, it is.
And so you're going to want to use our 350 source code.
That's what we're starting with the day.
All right, so let's go ahead and and jump back into it here mr.
Timer will I guess we're getting an extra five minutes here.
You know, sometimes we get an extra five minutes, it's always good.
The timer giveth and the timer taketh away.
So let's jump back in here and and take a look at where we were
If you remember, I was dealing with this code in World mode and we
kind of did a nice transform on the code here.
I think because you can kind of see, like, here's the code for
simulating a region.
You know, a non-primary region of the world.
Even including rendering it's kind of nice.
It looks pretty clean here right?
And here's the code for simulating a primary region where I should say
the primary region and you can see that it does some additional things
right, does check for joining
There's it does this sort of frame by frame Delta that gets used for
doing the particle systems?
It does some debug rendering here and these are fundamentally doing
the exact same things, right?
But because we broke it up into begin, Sim simulate and and Sim it.
Now allows us to insert in this, in this case, we're talking about the
primary region.
It allows us to insert this additional stuff in the right places
without having
NG to duplicate the code, right?
So that's kind of nice.
So, that's pretty good.
And what that means is that, now, if we wanted to, we could actually
distribute the work of updating the world, the part of the world.
That's
not the main part we're looking at, we could actually farm that off,
too many threads if we wanted to write
So on a typical four core computer, where maybe we have 8 total
logical processors to deal with, you could imagine us farming off the
update step, and having it be 8 times faster, right probably won't get
a full eight times faster.
But you know, the potential win obviously is, is there and right now
we have a very highly unoptimized function.
It's being called in there, especially in debug mode, you can see it
takes a long, long time, right?
It's called get closest reversible.
And you can see that its way up there.
In terms of amount of time, it takes out of the out of the frame.
Now, granted, if we do compiled in release mode that kind of goes
away.
So it's a bit of a red herring because it even though it's a function
that we really should optimize because it's doing a
Very poor job of what it needs to do right now.
When we do compiled in release mode, you can see that it actually ends
up being a non-issue.
It's down here in the, in the two percent range.
So even though it's awful, it's still not that awful.
But, you know, we can cheat because if we want to see how we're doing
here, like I said, if we just leave ourselves in debug mode, we have a
really highly optimized function that can kind of take its kind of
Ann's in if you will for doing more heavyweight updating in here,
potentially
So we already have a thing where in debug mode, we're not able to hit
60 frames a second in debug mode.
We you know, it's we're hitting it easily and optimize mode but we're
not able to hit it here because of those that on optimize function,
what we can do is say let's use that fact that we've got a piglet in
there, right?
In fact, maybe I'll put the Hat on.
Let's use that little piggy to sort of help us.
Figure out whether we can get some time.
Here by doing multi sort of just distribution across multiple threads,
right?
And so, what I want to do is I want to use this as a motivation for us
to get the code into a place where we can run multiple simulations on
multiple threads if we want to.
I'm not saying we need to do that, I'm saying that's something I want
to make sure this code could do so that if we start to crank up, our
simulation complexity, and we want to be simulating lots of different
parts of the world.
At the same time, we can Leverage
Multiple cores of the CPU, to do exactly that.
All right, so I'm going to call this one first, and I'm going to call
it without any of the, so we're good.
We're going to use this style simulate, right?
The kind that doesn't actually draw anything.
Okay?
And I'm going to go ahead and wrap these guys a little bit.
Like so.
So this is the isolated piece of code that we know we care about for
simulating a non-primary region of the world and now I don't want to
tax your memories too much here.
I realize that on handmade here at this point, we've we've shown how
to write so many things.
I love how much stuff we were able to show how to write in a game
engine so far.
It's awesome, but it does mean that I do ask a lot of people to try
and remember the things that you've already done.
So I apologize for digging.
Back like that.
But if you remember inside want that file, if you remember inside our
renderer, we have this sort of concept of multi-threading.
And I don't know if you remember how we did that.
But essentially what we did is we have these work units, that we
divide things into, and then we have threads that come along and pick
them up and do them, right.
And you can actually see this working right here.
This is the code for it.
So, we have a tiled renderer, and you can see here at Loops over the
tiles in X and Y, however, many there are, and we can control those
parameters, and then it creates a little work order here that says, I
need you to render this tile.
And this, do tiled render.
Work function would actually be the function that would do the work.
And so, instead of doing that, what we do is
We just push it on a Q and say, this is work, that's available to do
and then we trust that our multi-threaded code will come through.
Pick up those work things and do them.
And then what we do is we say complete all work on the thread that
launches all these.
And what that function will do is it will just go look at that q and
keep doing work itself out of that queue until it sees that all the
work has been done.
Right.
So this is a
Very simple way of doing multi-threaded work distribution, but it
works actually very well for a lot of circumstances.
We can just keep leveraging it.
So, if we take a look at what we want to do here, what we want to do
is, look at the do tiled render work function and go, can we go ahead
and make equivalent function to that, that we can use for doing this
simulation step?
And here is our, you know, function prototype for it and we can call
this to work
World Sim or something like that.
We can time it.
Of course like we always do.
So we can see how much time it's taking and then we can go here and
just imagine what we would need in terms of one of those little work
descriptions in order to make this happen now.
Usually, like I said, this is a very straightforward process because
we should be able to see exactly what we need.
Just by looking at the operation we're talking about and here you can
see, you know, this is what we know we need.
It because this is what we were calling before.
And you can see here, we need a boundary, right?
So we need to know where we are going to simulate.
We need to know some information about the world such as the transient
State, the, the world mode structure were working on the DT were
trying to stimulate, and then we need to know some rendering
information and that rendering information.
Thankfully I believe can all be blacked out so we can just get rid of
it.
And not have to worry about it, right?
Okay, so that won't be very hard to package up, but you can see kind
of right off the bat that we have a little bit of an issue and maybe
I'm cheating when I say, you can see because again, I'm the person
who's supposed to be teaching programming on this stream.
Let's just say I can see, and probably the experienced programmers out
there.
Watch stream can see.
That we're going to run into some problems, but it may not be obvious
to some of the beginners out there, what the problems are going to be
well, in a multi-threaded environment, the problem is, you can't be
doing anything where two people can't do it at once, right?
And so if you take a look at what's going to happen here at the
instant, we call begins him.
You can see that it's going to use this transient Arena to create the
temporary memory.
It needs in order for doing the world simulation.
Just fundamentally not going to work.
The reason that's not going to work is because the arena is a
single-threaded construct, right?
If we take a look here at how we wrote the memory Arena, nothing in
the memory.
Rihanna does any kind of locking or prevention of contention for
resources?
So when we do something like call allocate on the arena, it is not
locked right?
There is nothing that would prevent two threads from accidentally
stomping on each other's allocations or corrupting the state.
of the memory Arena because they're modifying different values at the
Same time without awareness of each other so that's a problem but it's
a problem we've seen before we already have the notion that temporary
memory for a work job can come from the job itself.
And we know that this is true because we actually created this when we
did that the work with the transient State originally, what we did,
that's not the file.
I wanted.
There we go.
What we did is we said, okay, when we have these tasks, they have
their own memory arena in the first place, right?
Every task has an arena, it consult sub allocate out of, and it's
aware that it is the only person acts in that Arena.
So it doesn't have to worry about that.
Contention.
So, what we need to do first in order to put ourselves in a position
where we can start to make this code thread-safe is we have to
Rid of that cross dependency.
So that's really, really easy.
All we have to do, we're lucky all we have to do in this case is stop
thinking about the temporary memory part with the begin temp and temp
stuff here as coming from the transient state and instead just say it
has to come from an arena that you're going to pass in.
And so that way, when we're calling it from the external code in the
main line block, we can pass in the transient State Arena.
If that's the arena, we want to use
But if we're calling it from one of our tasks, then we can just pass
in the task Arena.
So here, I'm going to get rid of that and pass the temporary NE in.
Same thing, here, temp Arena and now the trance state is illuminated,
right?
That is not something that's allowed to get passed into that function
at all and no one's allowed to use it in any way so that should help
us out tremendously.
With starting to make this code, something that can be called for
multiple threads.
So here when we come through, I'm going to go ahead and call the task
or any of their.
I don't fully remember the task with memory situation.
I don't to be honest with.
You remember very much about how this gets called back.
Exactly.
I suppose that's just something that gets isolated.
Let's take a look, I don't remember exactly how the begin task with
memory and task with memory system was supposed to work.
You can see here, we call it and then we end
And it looks like it's just so it's just I guess all that's really
happening here.
Is you just use this when you're initially feet farming off the test
and then you can be assured that they have them, right?
It's really it.
So yeah, this you know I feel like this is something that could
probably get expanded and put into the platform side of things.
Now, it seems to me like maybe this is not such a useful construct
anymore, especially that now that Arenas are things that can be sort
of allocated from separately.
So I'm kind of a little bit wondering about that.
Let's take a brief detour here because I want to double-check that
that's really the way that
That I want to do that.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to put this on, hold for one
second and we know that we can still fulfill our previous obligations
to pass things by passing in the trance transient Arena here, right?
So our game still runs just fine, and it's working off of the transit
Arena by passing it in same.
Basic idea.
What I want to do now is I want to look to see is anyone using the
system anymore because originally, it was used for some rendering
purposes.
But it's not being used for that anymore.
The software renderer doesn't need memory.
I don't think maybe it does.
I can't remember, but I don't think it does.
So I want to take a look here and see if anyone's even using begin to
ask with memory just so I can be sure.
So it looks like the people who are using that are in the asset
system.
So here you go, you can see us trying to get begin task memory and its
operating off of the transient State there, right?
So, again, this just doesn't seem to be a smart way to do this, for a
number of reasons.
I understand why we did it this way originally, it's because we wanted
to keep this in the platform independent part and because memory
Rino's worked in a very specific way, we've expanded our concept of
memory is now to allow things like having them be acknowledged by the
platform layer and work with the platform layer.
And so at that point, it seems to me that this is not particularly
smart necessarily, right?
So, I want to see before I say anything about it.
Let me just see exactly what is happening here, in terms of how memory
is being allocated.
I want to see how it's how it's doing.
Yes.
Oh this, this is roughly as I expected.
So, if you take a look at what happens here, you can see that really
in terms of allocations, there's not really any allocations that are
going on besides that asset work structure there.
It.
It's just, it's just the task itself.
That's getting pushed on there.
And then what the memory is actually used for, I would assume is
actually in here.
Right?
So when I come through here and I'm going to do work, it's only really
in here.
I guess the that anything would actually be be getting used for the
arena, in fact, now that I look at it, is that anything even being
used there?
So I guess even the thing that I was going to say about why you might
want a little bit.
This doesn't even that doesn't really seem to be true.
So yeah, if you look at what's happening here really this is just not
necessary like why are these things that this is just not the way to
do these.
Okay.
So I need to I think I need to take a brief moment and explain why I
don't think that's a very constructive.
A to structure that.
So let's go ahead and go to Milton here and, and see if we can't
See if we can't.
Get this going.
Let's go.
Milton.
I think we don't have a working Milton with the hardware vendor,
right?
Yeah, so we're on this one.
Okay, so let me talk for a second about what I mean here and and
And we'll see.
I also don't know.
Are we actually?
So I don't know if we're getting any.
Tablet stuff.
Here are we looks like good pain.
Also, the tablets working now is Milton able to recognize the tablet.
I'm not sure.
But hopefully, yes.
There we go.
Okay, because we were having problems, my tablet, kind of conked out,
but now it's fine.
All right, pretend that's not there.
Forget day, 351.
Right, okay, so let's talk about memory.
And multiple.
Threads.
So, if you look at the way that we're doing it right now, in terms of
memory and threading, there's kind of two ways you can look at how
memory travels through threaded code, right.
And what I want to do is kind of encourage you to think about to sort
of separate axes that are sort of Happening Here.
One is like the task, right?
So, we may have tasks like, a bee.
See.
D, right?
And these are actually things that get queued up and there can be any
number of these, right?
There's an arbitrary number of tasks that can queued up and then
there's threads right?
There's thread 0, 1 2 3, right?
And here, there are as many as there are cores, really logical cores.
We don't really want to make lots of threads that are not
corresponding to anything physical.
We want to roughly have the same number of threads as we have physical
course to have a logical course to do work.
And so we have some number of these and it is not arbitrary.
It is not based on the amount of work it's based on the number of
workers, right?
So this is based on like work and this is based on workers.
Now, Memory for these two sets of things,
Is exactly the same sort of thing, right?
There's memory.
That might be used Briella relative to the work that's being done for
the lifetime of the work.
And then there's memory that might be used relevant to the lifetime of
the worker.
Okay?
So for example, scratch memory
Meaning memory that is only used during computation is really just
memory, that's proportional to the worker.
Each thread needs its own scratch memory for doing work, but that
memory doesn't need to persist outside of the thread having done that
work, right?
So, let's say that task a has three parts to it, right?
There's the setup.
There's the work and there's the completion.
Right?
And this part right here is done by the main thread, right?
The thread that's actually creating these tasks to do, is the one
that's doing the setup.
The work is being done by one of these worker threads, right?
Maybe it's happening up here.
So here's the work, right?
And maybe the main thread or something did the setup there's a setup.
And then the completion is maybe picked up somewhere else by the main
thread, right?
And the main thread during this time would be doing other things.
So we come through here, we do some setup work.
We now have the work, is queued eventually some other core picks up
the work and does the work and then later we look and find that the
work has been done, right?
So if we only need memory during this work part and we don't eat it to
persist from set up through work and into completion.
Then really, what we want is scratch memory.
We just want memory that we use just for a given thread and each of
these threads can have its own scratch memory, and they never need to
talk to each other, right?
On the other hand, if we do have memory that needs to flow this way,
it needs to be there for set up there for work and therefore
completion then we have task oriented or work oriented memory and that
needs to be managed for task.
So what we're doing right now is we're doing memory per task, right?
You can see that we have some number of tasks that we allow here.
Each one of these tasks has an arena and the memory for that task
comes from that Arena.
That makes a lot of sense, if we're actually doing something that
looks that way.
But at the moment, we're not even doing anything that looks that way.
So, that raises the question of do we want to keep doing this or
don't?
There's a certain flexibility that comes with having each task habits
or memory.
Certainly.
So it's not a given that we shouldn't keep it that way.
But what I will say is even if we wanted to keep it that way, it does
seem like a poor choice to have it.
Be some kind of a locked block set of structures.
We probably want to allow us to create as many of them as we want to
write.
That's probably my best, guess there, or at least, have it be
proportional to the number of things we actually expect to Q in
practice, right?
So yeah, so that to me is kind of a little bit of a red flag there,
right?
And it just seems like something where I probably don't want to be
using that kind of a system in cases where I don't want to do that,
whether I should remove it from the asset system.
I'm not sure yet.
It looks like I probably should because it really just doesn't look
relevant.
But what's definitely true is I don't think I would want to do it
here.
So probably what I want to do here is I would want to have my memory
Arena exist only for the lifetime of the work, right?
and so what I'd probably want to do here is say something like
Where is it?
Here.
I would probably want to say, hey, let's make a memory Arena.
And then, when we're done, we'll just eliminate the whole memory
Arena.
So that way it doesn't, it's, you know, the memory itself is coming
totally from inside this safe area, right?
It, you know, it doesn't have to do, it doesn't have to do anything
else, it doesn't have to talk to anyone.
It's like just coming from its own entirely isolated Arena and it will
do allocation as
Sorry to get there.
Now I'm going to put it to do here.
And what I mean by this comment or to do I should say is that we don't
actually want to allocate new memory blocks every time every time we
would open up a world.
Same here using this threaded.
Third, we will have to call the operating system to do a virtual
allocation to get us a block of memory to work with and then at the
end we'll have to re-release it.
There's no reason to do that.
We might as well have each worker thread.
Just have a block that it's virtually out from and then have the
arena, just use that block and only if we overflow the block, would we
ever have to call anything else?
So probably we want each worker thread to just have an arena uses for
Scratch space and would pass it in.
That's a much more efficient way to do this and it's something that we
should probably.
Really do after we finish what we're doing right now.
So inside do World Sim, you can see that we can now sort of work on
the rest of the part that we care about here during tiled render work
here where we're doing this.
This call to get the data out.
We want to do is replace that with our own sort of description of
work.
That makes sense for this.
So this is like World some work or whatever.
So we have this concept of world, some work, that's going to be the
struct that we need to create in order to create a work order for this
kind of operation.
We know that we need the bounds of the simulation so where it is going
to simulate, we know that we need the world mode structure, right?
Corporal, what is it game mode world?
We know that we need the DT.
And yeah, I guess we get the moment.
We still need the game State as well.
And again, some of these things, I think we can start to get rid of
but if we look at what happens there, now we can sort of say like okay
we know we can get the world mode and the Sim bounds and the DT out of
the work order.
So we will
That allows us to call this properly.
Oops.
Nice typing there.
Hand is tired and then game state.
And that gives us all the stuff that we need.
So now when we call one of these weeps, we know that we can
encapsulate all the stuff that we need into one of these work orders
so that that's all it needs to do.
One of its World simulation steps.
So if I want to kick one of these off, now, I can do it the exact same
way that we were doing it inside the renderer.
So you can see here, how we do it.
We create one of these work orders, right?
And then we kick it off.
So, if we want to do this in the update and render World call, where
we want to do a bunch of simulations here, let's say right here, what
we can do is do a for I
And do things exactly the same way.
We don't really know at this point because we're kind of making this
up as we go along since we don't really have the need to simulate
other parts of the world right now.
But let's suppose that we did have some idea of how many of these
things there were going to be.
So we would say something like okay there's the world Sim work and
these are like the some number of them 16 parts of the world that
Not simulation, let's say and then we can say, Okay, Sim index equals
zero.
Some index is less than however, many of these things we wanted to do.
You know, we increment it and then we fill out the structure that we
were trying to fill out.
Now notice, this is, you know, exactly analogous.
It's literally a tiled renderer for the world.
It's up to set of rendering, we're simulating, right?
That's all we're doing.
And so in order to do that, what we need is some way here of going
like okay,
We need to know where we're sort of going to say that this happens.
Let me go ahead and pull our work order out to the H file, so it's a
little easier for me to look at.
There it is.
So, I know I have to set the Sim bounds, I need to say like, here's
one, here's a place that you're going to simulate.
I know, I need to sort of pass in the parameters that it's going to
need to operate.
But other than that, I'm pretty good to go, right?
And then just like before I'm going to do exactly the same thing where
we do add entry in the multi-threaded path and this is going to be do
Sim or whoops assembled work.
I don't know what I called.
That forgot.
Do World Sim.
And then the other case, we're just going to actually call it
directly.
Right now, we need a cue for this to happen on and I believe we have
that already in the in the transient State.
It's just the high priority queue because this is the work.
That happens immediately.
so, all we really have to do here is just
Let It Go.
Okay, so in terms of where we're going to have the world Sim simulate,
it doesn't really matter where we have this done, because we're just
doing the simulation as a test, but we needed to be in different
places.
So, in order for this to make sense, I need just some
Notion of how to displace these Sim bonds and so much.
Like we were doing before I probably just need
You know, pick random places displaced from where the camera is to do
the simulation.
So, what I could do here is I could say something like this.
And then I could do another one I could do.
Like I said kind of a literally tiled render thing like so,
And you know, in this case, let's just say that we were going to do
simulation of the world, sort of Mana, no offset from the camera a
little bit.
So we just say, like offset x equals whatever the sin x is.
And like we just need some way of kind of displacing these things
around.
And so, I don't really remember what sorts of displacement we used for
the
Original sin bounds here, but let's say that we're just going to just
place it by maybe a hundred each time or something like that.
So we could just say, like times 100f
And leave it at that.
so that's our displacement that we would use and that way, we could
say, like offset,
Really remember exactly how this works.
But also at the same bounds
Here.
And I just, I guess I just passed that in.
So that just gives me some rectangle to simulate.
That's not the main one that we're looking at, right?
And that's really all I have to do to set up this thing in exactly the
same way as the previous render.
And now we should be calling that function a ton of times.
That of course, we should hit our profile really heavily and you can
kind of see like just a lot of
A lot of debug events basically being generated by that is mostly what
we're spending our time on.
But now we're actually sort of simulating, all of those right now.
Unfortunately, we can't see any of them simulate which is unfortunate,
because if we come out here, none of them are going to be rendering.
That's intentional, right?
So we might have to add some calls to actually do rendering of these
things.
in order to validate that they're actually being stimulated by
At least we now know that, you know, we're roughly sort of calling
through here.
So, when we do this simulation, I guess our world doesn't really
extend in this direction either.
So I do wonder if maybe maybe this would be smarter, that should also
make it take a lot more time because we now should be actually hitting
some.
Yeah, we should be hitting, more parts of the world that actually do
stuff, right?
And you can see like a lot of these these calls now occurring.
Ng.
All right, so we're still calling this in a single threaded fashion,
right?
I have this if zero going here but all it takes for me to Now call
this in a multi-threaded fashion is to change that to and if one right
and what on Earth did I just do,
Oh, there we go.
Like that.
And it was in the wrong place.
All right.
There we go.
And now, we will actually have multiple threads doing the simulation
of the same time.
It's not going to work correctly.
For some reasons that you'll see in a second but we've at least set up
a structure properly.
So, first question is, well why doesn't it work?
The reason is because now we have multiple
We have multiple threads working on the world Sim, but some of those
data structures that they use are shared, right?
And when you have multiple threads working on the shared data
structures, you cannot just let them do their thing.
Even if the language that you're using or the system that you are
using, has locking built into it for you at the lower level.
You're not going to guarantee that your operations are doing the
correct.
Thing, if you haven't thought through how those threads actually need
to interact and since we're running low level code here, we'll just
get straight up crashes.
If we don't do something smart about, making sure that our code thinks
about who's doing what?
And when
All right.
So let's start with some of the basics if I was to go over to the same
region code, hopefully you can see that it's already set up in a good
way for actually doing the right thing here.
The way that it works you can kind of see is it goes through the world
and it unpacks all the entities into its own working set.
Then it will do a bunch of work on them and then it will pack them
back, right?
the nice part about this, is, it means that the place where we
actually are
Sort of working with the shared data structure that is the world is
isolated to the pack and unpack steps, right?
So we don't actually need to talk to anyone else during the actual
simulation.
So, during the pack and unpack we do during the simulation we don't,
okay?
Because the world data structure is shared all of the simulation stuff
needs to unpack from the world and then pack into the world.
And so we need to make sure that they synchronize their doing of this.
But once everything is unpacked, we should be even in a situation
where all the simulation just happens internal to that system.
All right.
So there's some things I want to look at first.
So what I want to do first is I want to take a look at our simulation
call.
I want to know why our simulation call requires the world mode, right?
I want to know for example.
What in brains requires it?
Like what are we doing with the world mode and and why?
Okay,
So what you can see, here is the only reason that were passing the
world Mill mode at all is because we want a source of entropy, right.
We want something in the system that gives us a random number source
that we can use to progress now, I don't really care about that.
Random number being synchronized across threads, all the threads,
Could use their own random number generator and that's just fine with
me.
So what that means to me is that really this world mode is probably
not a good thing to pass to execute.
Brain.
Really just the source of entropy should be past execute brain, and
then we can break that out and not worry about that structure in terms
of having to lock it across access or us, right?
So let's put that
like on the list just for second mentally and then the other thing I
want to do is now I want to see why was World mode getting past here
right to update and render entities so you can see that it's accessing
some kind of constants.
It's accessing the particle cash.
And then it's used in move entity, which I don't actually know.
Why?
So, here we are in world move in.
Move entity looking at World mode.
Ah, and so it looks like the only thing that that's used for is sort
of the per entity Collision suppression, right?
You can see that that's there's this sort of like Collision rule.
Hash thing that's being used to look stuff up and the can Collide is
That's where that's coming from, right?
So
we don't really need that hash anymore.
I don't even know if we're using that hash anymore and there's a good
reason not to use it.
Which is that it does sort of lock people up if we have these pairwise
rules that can be changed over time.
So that does sort of give us a good reason to step away from that
which maybe we hadn't had before.
So let's take a look and just see what happens if we get rid of it.
as expected that
Sort of piece of code wants it, but add Collision rule is probably the
only thing that we really need to know about where our people calling
add Collision rule.
The answer is nobody is calling at questionable.
Good.
So let's get rid of it.
It's gone.
Oh God.
There we go.
And now that world mode simply doesn't have to be passed anymore to
the move entity.
Call it anyway.
So if I take a look at move entity here and I get rid of world mode, I
should be able to just eliminate it entirely because now can Collide
won't need it.
Because it can be done directly and presumably handle Collision, same
thing.
Okay.
So again
Getting better looking at here, we're just looking at, we're just
reading some of these out.
And so if you take a look at what we're looking at here, in terms of
meaningful changes, it's really the particle.
Cash.
That's important.
Typical floor, height is here for a number of reasons that probably
we, you know, are going to want to step away from a little bit and so
I'm okay with leaving that in temporarily but we can probably
eliminate World mode from this all together and that would be great.
And I think the thing that we can do here is just say
Let's go ahead and pass the particle cash in and then we can just say
when the particle cash is not set to anything, then we won't add
particles.
And so if I take a look at the particle code itself here, when we have
something like spawn fire, I'm just going to predicate these so that
they don't actually do anything when you pass in a null particle
system.
That way, we should be able to prevent that from happening entirely.
Right.
Okay.
So again getting closer getting much, much, much closer to what I want
this code to look.
Like it's little tiny baby steps, you know, always little tiny baby
steps and they, you know, are constantly trying to guide us towards
what we want, right?
So, it's just doesn't need World mode either.
So yeah, what we want to do here is just say alright update.
You know when we're doing our update here we want to pass in that
particle cash and
I guess I don't know why that gets passed to begin World change
either.
Let's take a look at that.
So that's a Vestige of when we used to unpack particle system so that
can get removed too which is great again keeps getting better and
better.
Oops.
We go.
So now we're just down to needing to pass the particle cash again in
here.
And when we're actually doing a simulate, that's actually something we
do want to pass in.
And so, I guess what I'd say there is again.
Let's just let's pass it in here.
Since it is optional.
Keep it down in here.
And I don't really remember where we pass the carrot boat.
So it's right before go.
And now we just have to pass it.
So, in here, we won't pass a particle, cash, right?
We're just not going to pass one because it's not going to get used.
And then in here, we will.
Right.
So in theory we should still be working properly and we still still
should be.
Oops I forgot.
I said sober working properly, what I meant was if we go to here.
And we should still be having particle spawned which we are, which is
good, right?
And so that's all well and good.
And so now we're just a little bit closer to having everything being
respectful of, you know, the data on either side.
Okay.
So jumping back here though to it where we have our like simulate
called, like I said, World mode is still getting passed around and it
really doesn't need to.
In a lot of situations, the floor.
Height needs to come through here.
But in execute brain, it really doesn't.
Need to have that happen.
So, at the very least inside execute bring, but I probably should do,
is pass a random series here.
That's like entropy
Right.
And this is where the entropy comes from.
For brain stimulation and it shouldn't really care where you got that
from.
Like maybe you wanted the entropy from somewhere.
Maybe you didn't, who cares?
That's just not that relevant and to the brain code, it just knows.
It needs a source of entropy and it wants you to provide one but it
shouldn't matter beyond that where it comes from.
So, when you call this, we can save game entropy here and then we're
good to go.
So, again, now, we've almost got
Rid of the world mode stuff entirely inside.
Handmade Loops inside handmade entity.
If we take a look at where that's being used, it's just the typical
floor height.
Now, that's ever actually getting used.
And so, we could even just for now just again, to sort of get us
closer to where we want to be say, all right, until we get rid of that
typical floor height, we're just going to pass in the typical fluoride
directly, right?
And it's not great because we probably want to systemically deal with
this in a much more logical way after we do the 3D move.
But for now whatever, right.
So now we're much much closer because now World mode is not really,
even getting used for the most part in here, it's really just a guide
guidance.
For a very small piece of information, like the entropy and the floor
height, it's only two things.
So we can will be able to pull those out really easily as we kind of
go further in.
But now, the question is well.
Okay, what about the other times when we were passing in this world
mode?
So, if you take a look at World mode here, right?
You can
The in this case, it's probably very necessary.
If we're talking about the the
The camera P situation.
And in fact, you can see here, we really want to abstract this part
out anyway, because the camera stuff.
So really this camera P stuff, we're probably going to have to deal
with outside of this anyway, because the camera piece only relevant to
one of the same regions so that we could probably pull out pretty
easily.
So, all I really need to look at here to keep going down.
This route of like, cleaning this stuff up in terms of what who needs
to access, what?
Is inside begin World change.
What do we actually loops?
What do we actually need the world mode for here?
Right?
And the answer appears to be like nothing if I just get rid of it,
it's not necessary.
Funny how that happens, right?
You end up seeing these things where you're like gee you know like I
was passing these things around because at one point I needed them but
as I start to like you know as this code starts to get bolt it down a
little bit more turns out their stuff getting passed around.
That just doesn't even get passed around anymore, right?
Yes this is simply not relevant.
So now we can see that world mode isn't really even used in here
because it's actually getting used for this sort of completely
ancillary purpose of like camera management.
So camera management kind of needs to be
He pulled out in a more coherent way there.
So we can avoid having this sort of false dependence on world mode
that we really didn't need.
And it's just because it happened to be convenient thing to do at the
time.
So let's take a look at what and Rural change needs here.
And it looks like World mode again.
Like you can kind of see what's going on here.
It's really, there's a lot of camera management happening.
Like all of the stuff for World mode.
Here is camera management, really?
It's just the world structure that this thing needs.
And the world mode is, is there really just for camera management,
right?
So that's again, really big red flag here for us, you know, I think
it's pretty clear that we kind of want to have a way of dealing with
the camera.
That makes more sense than what we're doing now.
Because as you can see, the only reason we have to pass that whole
world mode thing around is because we have on the entrance and the
exit stuff that deals with a camera that's not relevant for any other
part of the world that we're updating.
So the world in general, when it's updating
Doesn't need to know this stuff.
This is only specific to the very, very, very singular case where we
actually care about the camera being updated and there's only one time
that that actually happens, right?
All right, so let's go ahead and inside and real change here, I'm
going to start passing world to it, just because that way we can sort
of see that that's definitely happening.
Fix the other one.
Here we go.
And so, really, I think what we need to do now is figure out how to
make that camera handling be a little bit more reasonable, right?
And then we're sort of down to the, to the part where we were, this is
maybe starting to look like something that can be multi-threaded,
right?
That's not too much of a big deal to multi-thread.
We're starting to get to a sane place for it, right?
And really at that point, the only thing I think we're going to have
to
About is when we take a look at the same region stuff, we're probably
going to have to do a little bit of locking around that world.
Access.
Right.
So you know, begin Sim and end Sim when we do the unpacking the most
sort of straightforward way to do that.
Probably will be to.
Let's see.
Do we have?
Yeah.
The most simple way to do it at first would be to just do it this way
where since we know that these are the two things that actually
interact with.
The sure thing we could just lock around the entire beginning and Sim.
That's a little more coarse grained than we probably want to be in the
end.
So it's possible that we will want to lock the data more closely than
that.
And why do I say that?
Well, if
Take a look at what's actually happening.
Inside handmade world.
You can see how things are set up in here.
We've got a world struct.
We've got a free list and a chunk hash, right?
And if you take a look at how that works, we only really need to lock
stuff.
When we are doing freeing on the free list.
We need to lock the free list.
And for Chunk hashes, we only need to lock the hash line itself.
So, if we wanted to, we could have a ticket per hash line even and
only lock that
Flying when we're working on it.
So, you know, this is
Definitely.
We could definitely do much more fine-grained locking and might want
to write.
But first this is obviously a very simple way that we could make.
This piece of code work.
And then what we would need to do is we would need to have a ticket
that we could rely on.
That would allow us to lock and unlock this, right?
so, let's say that we had the world mode here and we said, like, okay,
you know,
there's a simulation ticket or something like this.
Well actually like I said, it's really it's part of the world so I
think it should probably go in here, right?
so if I want to change the world,
Lofty, aspirations.
If I want to change the world, if I want to change the world, then I
need to be able to say like, hey, take a look on the World ticket and
do what you're going to do, because only one person can edit that at a
time.
And hopefully, that makes some sense.
Right?
So yeah.
So I don't know how much time I've got left.
Probably not a whole, heck of a lot, but the camera situation is
definitely something we want to take a look at here.
So here's the multi-threaded path.
And, like I said, kind of runs into problems pretty quickly.
And you can kind of see where those might be.
Although be honest, I'm not really sure what that problem was right
there.
The world is no.
In begin World change.
Why would the world be?
No.
That seems odd.
Wouldn't you say?
Two Worlds.
That was not really what I was expecting to see.
So the world modes World parameter got set to zero somewhere down the
line here, which is not what I would have expected.
It looks like this is just
Getting overwritten prematurely is what it would appear to be.
Did I mess up the
ah,
well, so
One thing that is good to do when you actually say and then you call X
is to actually call it X unsurprisingly since we did not actually wait
for the work to be completed before moving on.
It should not probably surprise anyone that we end up over writing our
own data.
So, yeah.
Not great.
I said we had to do that when I came through here and I simply didn't
type it in
Anyway, so yeah, in theory.
Now like I said even though this is not really operating properly.
So you have to take it with a grain of salt.
We are now calling the world simulation code on multiple threads, at
least in theory.
And, you know, you can see it happening here just you know, so that we
are aware of it.
You can see that we've got six, worker threads looks like one, two,
three.
A.
Six, all doing that work and each of them is kind of calling.
You can see if we pause.
You can see that the worker threads are doing, you know, more than one
in this case.
And you can kind of see like there's begin World change and right,
it's kind of cool.
I really love this little visualizer that we built.
So you can see all of that work Happening Here.
Meanwhile up here, you can kind of see that the game update code here
is is actually just kind of waiting.
I guess what I would say is I'm a little surprised.
I'm not sure why this thread is not actively doing any of that work.
Oh, I see why.
It's because it's inside game update and render.
If I was to step in here, then I would see it do World soon.
Yes, okay, so anyway,
We are now correctly, multi-threading that update at least to a
certain degree, but one of course, like I said, problem with this is
that certain aspects are still not actually going to be locked
properly.
We did sort of the, the very core screwed locking version where we
just prevent obvious errors from happening in the world read and
write.
But we still sort of have this weird thing with the camera and these
other aspects of it that we're not.
the addressing properly and that we want to be definitely more
hardcore about but hopefully you can kind of see the direction that's
going and you can hopefully you're also appreciate sort of
why I said, you know,
Thinking about things in.
It's not really functional programming, but it's the concept of
that's, you know, I think very closely related which is understanding
specifically what a function does and does not need to access is
pretty critical to moving towards multi-threaded code in a particular
part of the project, functional code is obviously the most
multi-threaded bill because it literally doesn't do anything other
than look at its parameters.
But, you know, even
Is that are sort of beyond that where they do edit things, do
whatever, it's still the same general process.
You're trying to like winnow away at the number of things that you
have to access in order to sort of make it.
You know, something that can be easily run, concurrently with other
things that are touched that want to do like the same sort of
operations.
All right, so yeah.
When looking at this as well you know there's a couple things in here
that probably again we can sort of take a look at more closely but
really I think mostly what we want to do is is figure out how to back
away the back out.
That that sort of camera.
so I'm going to say that tomorrow, probably what we want to do is
Take a look at that explicitly.
So, you know, pull out the camera concept into something we're and
optional.
and then the other thing we want to do is
Where do things like typical?
For height live cetera.
So we want to kind of like eliminate World mode.
From The Sims step entirely.
I think that's about it for today.
So I'll go to the Q&A a little bit early since technically, I started
5 minutes early with the timer there.
So if anyone has any questions about what we're doing here, please
feel free to ask me.
Please prefix them with q:.
So I can see them.
May blow is posting some questions.
Sort of vicariously for are rather.
K'nuckles is asking the questions vicariously via midlow apparently,
so what do you suppose is two questions?
Have you finished sausage roll?
Stephen Sasha will know, Stephen sausage.
Roll is too hard of a game for me.
I'm afraid.
And to, I've been chilling, Shovel Knight for you and you have to add
undertale to list.
That game is a gift from the gods and high.
Alright, so I haven't played Shovel Knight yet.
I think I have it but I don't think I've played much of it.
I might have paid a little bit and I tried playing undertale a little
bit but I didn't see the.
I didn't understand the attraction really.
I could give it another go but those are not really
About the programming.
So,
Let's see.
A posting Mage isn't simulating the world in several threads.
Can't that make the game non-deterministic isn't the point of the RNG,
having a starting kernel for deterministic, play for competition and
stuff.
So I guess what I would say is that depends entirely on the game for a
game like handmade hero, we absolutely don't care about deterministic
play.
In fact, you might say that the point of handmade hero is specifically
non-deterministic, right?
Like you want
Every time you played handmade here for two completely different, it's
very Rogue alike in that sense.
So we don't care at all about being able to reproduce exact runs and
furthermore we
Support variable frame rates on animate here as well.
Which also means that we if we wanted to support fully deterministic
play, we would have to do extra work to make sure that our stimulation
subdivided time properly and never took bigger or smaller time steps,
even if the frame rate was bigger or smaller.
So we definitely don't have any reason to want deterministic play on
handmade hero.
And so we're not concerned about that.
Aspect at all.
However, if you are trying to accomplish deterministic play, then yes
having multiple threads is a problem.
You have to have ways of dealing with that fact and making sure that
your threads don't add non-determinism, if that's what you want most
games, don't try to be deterministic in the way that you're talking
about though because remember
Having a random number generator be deterministic from a colonel.
Usually we're going to care about that more during World Generation
right now.
It's what we might care about is the ability for someone to say, here
is a random seed, generate the world, and I want to make sure that on
your machine.
And my machine, we generate the same world from that random seed, that
is a valuable thing to use repeatability of the RNG.
That's valuable for us, right?
So,
I do care about it.
There it here.
We don't care about it at.
All right?
Because again, we there is no known reason that I can think of on
handmade hero.
Why we care about what the random numbers are that are generated on a
run-through.
Look, I just don't know any reason why we would if we did care about
the RNG on the run through, then we definitely have a problem.
And here is the reason that we have a problem like like I guess to
sort of sketch out the answer to the thing, which, I mean, I think you
kind of already know this answer because your question kind of begs.
The answer to begin with, right?
But let's say that we take
Look at the typical use of some of the entropy that's coming in
through the game.
So, you know, I've got, you know, my my hero cure and he's going to
like punch it somebody right and maybe you know there's there's the
monster here, right?
The spider monster with the big fangs or whatever like or something
like this.
So I'm going to punch it this monster and I hit the monster and so
then we do some kind of a like roll for damage or something, right?
Like I don't know what this is awful.
What is with the penmanship today?
Roll for damage.
So, you know, maybe I'm going.
We're like, okay, I have a certain percentage chance of getting a
critical hit, right?
Well, there's an RNG role and that oops, there is an orangey role that
needs to happen there that's going to determine whether or not, I get
that critical hit.
That's a source of entropy that I would argue you almost never care
about whether it's deterministic, right?
Because two players playing the same seed aren't even going to be
punching at the same spider at the same time.
So there are in G's are always going.
To be in different states anyway, right, they haven't even rolled the
same number of roles at this point.
So that Source I would say is not particularly relevant in terms of
caring about Divergence of the RNG because of multi-threading.
However,
If there's a chest in the game and it's like, what's in the chest,
right?
And the random roll for what's in the chest is dependent, let's say on
something that can happen in the game, like whether you've got a lucky
charm bracelet on or something like this.
There you might care more, right?
You might care if the RNG for chests, is consistent across
playthroughs or something in this way.
So I could see an argument for isolating the RNG here.
And if you wanted to do that, you could because all you need to do for
that is have a locked RNG.
You use for special roles you want to make consistent, right?
But I would say in General, trying to ensure consistency of the RNG in
this way, maybe a little bit of a Fool's errand because again, two
players paths, diverge almost immediately out of the Starting Gate.
So the question is, what are you really?
Ensuring when you ensure that the RNG is consistent, really all you're
ensuring.
Is that for the exact same set of inputs, you'll produce the same run.
How much do you care about that, right?
That's not really the same as saying that it's fair for both players
or
Like that.
Right?
So, yeah, so the thing that I care way more about, I think most of the
time is RNG for the world Jen and that's much easier because we don't
have to multi-thread that if we don't want to or if we do we can take
steps to make sure that it doesn't diverge.
So I think that's the place we're going to care a lot more about that.
The geek part.
When do you go back and complete to do tasks?
You've given yourself in the code is each one going to be completed
before you're done or they simply wish lists basically.
They're just notes to myself for when I go to ship.
So when I'm very, very close to being done, I'll often grep for all my
to dues and then I'll go through them all and decide which one's of
them are still relevant and need to get done and which ones aren't.
So the answer is that some of them will turn out to be wish list
things that just
I ordered some of them will turn out to be priority items that have to
get fixed.
And really it's towards the end of the project that that's relevant.
Is it important for Game?
Preserve to have a portfolio in the same way?
Artists do and if so what would be important to include?
I would say maybe wait for handmade con for that question.
I don't do a lot of hiring anymore.
I'm not involved in hiring programmers and so I am kind of out of
touch with what people screen for your first sort of when you're
trying to get into the game industry.
It's been too long since I've had any contact with that process.
Yes, that is a question.
I ask every year at handmade con this year will be the same as last
year.
I'll be asking in fact the person who I'll be asking that question of
very specifically is the the tech director at blizzard on World of
Warcraft.
They do a ton of hiring, it's the kind of job you might hope to get
when you're starting out in the game industry you know doing some you
know fairly basic tasks on World of Warcraft or something would be a
good?
Entry level position for example because you know they're a good
company.
You know, there's a lot of people to learn from you know it's a famous
game and so I'll definitely be asking those kinds of questions and so
this next week is handmade con.
I'll be asking those questions and we'll have some again difference
any answers.
If your can't wait till then go watch Mike Acton's segment from
handmade Con 2015.
Last year's con he was the
Tech director that I invited last year and he answered that question
as well.
Gary Johansen.
In a tight inner loop.
Do you think these memory copies for the temporary?
Scratch memory could become an overhead concern.
If I understand the stream correctly, that is
I'm not sure what you mean.
Certainly temporary memory copies are always a concern.
So the chances are the answer.
The question is yes but I'm not sure.
I know which temporary scratch memory copies are talking about.
So, if you could be a little more specific on that I could, I could
answer the question directly long billion.
Currently what is the behavior when walking several rooms over into
another chunk?
Well, right now, the simulation stuff is
Is just kind of running randomly out in the world, so you would never
you can't get to a chunk.
That's being stimulated because they're offset from the place where
you currently are.
That makes sense.
Save William.
Bundy just said, save scumming.
I don't know what save scumming is.
Jim Sarah, will there be streams for the job?
Fair people know the job.
Fair stuff is not recorded and really can't be.
There's so many of people there.
So many teams participating in the job for now.
There's like, I don't know how many there are but it's like way more
than anyone could possibly film.
What's the relation between IQ and success at programming?
I have no idea.
I literally have no idea.
I know a lot of great programmers.
I don't know that their IQs are so I don't know.
Well I can point to Great programmers and say these people are really
good at what they do.
I can't then tell you their IQ is this
Ginger, bill has a question off.
Topic questions can be answered later if necessary.
I've been developing a new programming language to replace my needs
for C C++ and pretty much every other language the main areas of
research for me at the moment are metaprogramming, as I say
optimizations, concurrency you being a better, bring an expert other
than compile-time, execution, that is John's language.
What other forms of Mentor program?
Would you like?
Yeah, that's kind of a bigger question.
I probably can't answer that the moment.
William Bonney.
Sorry it was in context if I open a chest and don't get what I want.
Reloading a save given playing slightly differently.
Might get me a different orangey for the chest.
Yes, exactly.
And that's why I say, if you want to be specific, specifically
concerned about specific elements are in gy so you can take extra
steps there.
However, I would point out kind of the obvious thing which is that I
don't know that.
Who's coming is really something to be that concerned about because at
the end of the day, if someone just wants a different thing in the
chest and they're going to be going the like mess with savegame routes
to do it.
They could easily just figure out where the RNG number is stored in
the savegame and edit it, right?
So I'm not sure that that's really all that much different.
You know, people are trying to cheat.
They they can
It and you're really just talking about how much of a barrier you're
trying to erect for them.
I might act as usually I don't really think it's that bad.
Directive to erect barriers to single player cheating because if
someone wants to cheat in single player, just let them it's their
game.
They bought it.
I don't care how you want to play it.
If it's fun for you to play the game that way and you would prefer to
do it, then that's okay with me.
I probably would recommend some level of barrier.
Like I wouldn't just
Have it so you know press X to win the game.
And the reason for that is I want to help people who don't want to
cheat to.
I want enough of a barrier there so that those people don't feel
constantly tempted to do it.
I want to help them have some, you know, step there.
But as long as there is a some significant step you have to take in
order to cheat that's enough so that regular people who want to play
the game and don't want to cheat aren't constantly tempted to do so
then I don't think the programmer really should go any further out of
Way, if someone wants to sit down and start shooting at a game, it's a
single-player game.
So you're not affect anyone else.
Then I don't see the crime in that rights likes their game.
They bought it, you put up enough of a barrier to make it so that it
wasn't trivial to cheat.
So it doesn't become this problem.
Temptation wise for players who don't really want to cheat that, I
think you've done your job and you're pretty much done.
Well, the game have different levels.
Like The Binding of Isaac, where will the entire game be a single
level?
I don't know that we'd have any levels in the sense that there would
be like breaks in between them.
No, so everything is continuous.
You can just go to anywhere in the game.
When you're walking, you wouldn't
Have a loading screen, certainly.
All right, are we basically done?
I think we should probably be about done because I probably,
Should go get some lunch or something.
Let's go ahead and wind it down.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the series at home,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade here a.org and it comes
with a source code.
I keep it up to date every night so you can experiment with what we're
doing on your own and learn from it.
We also have a forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions a patreon page, you can go to if you want
to support the video series and a schedule bot that you can look.
For or subscribe to.
If you want to know, when the series is going to be live.
I will probably be updating the schedule but soon so that it is going
to do the weekend streams properly.
Now that we do the two back-to-back, which previously we had in quite
ever, had support for that because we never did it before.
We also have an episode guide want to catch up with old episodes
which?
Yeah, which is pretty awesome.
All right, thanks everyone for joining me.
I will see you back here tomorrow.
For another 2 episode block, until then have fun programming and I'll
see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy everyone.