Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we could complete game live on stream.
This is a second.
Well, third day I guess of particles stuff that we are doing.
We're just trying to like put in some particle system infrastructure
for ourselves to use so that we can start having particle systems that
actually are in the game proper.
We did a long time ago, some test stuff with particle systems just to
kind of show literally test up.
I guess I just did sort of an introductory.
I think on those and now we like to make it so that they can be in the
game for reals not just as a little piece of test code to show how
they work.
So I thought of something and I kind of wanted to mention it because I
was thinking that maybe it's something that we'll have to that is
Suggest that my Approach may not have been so good so far and that we
should maybe sort of reconsider us.
Think about it in the shower this morning as is often inevitable.
Oops, gotta restart that guy.
There we go.
See today.
338.
So,
This is basically like a particle.
Cash talk.
So what I was thinking about is I was trying to think about what sorts
of things I wanted to enable guys kind of just idly thinking about
them.
And what I was realizing is that the way that I was structuring, the
particle cash was probably not really what I wanted.
And here is why so I had sort of been structuring the protocol cash as
if the main case that we were trying to handle was something like oh
you know here is like a little fountain or something and there's like
some water coming out of the fountain, right?
And
The fountain would be an entity and it would have a particle, you
know, system on it.
Wow.
Okay.
A particle system on it.
And then what would happen is when this came on the screen there, the
particle system cache, would wake up and say, oh, okay, I need to like
have a particle system here for the fountain.
Now that's a perfectly reasonable thing to do.
If what you're planning on is having a few discrete particle systems
around the screen, you know, that are doing whatever they're doing.
But what I realized is that's not really the game that I'm making
here, I don't think that's really gonna hold up because let's suppose
that I want to do something like this where I've got you know trees
around here.
Right.
and I,
Light one of these guys on fire and now there's fire spreading to all
these trees, right?
Well, I definitely don't want to create a different particle system
for each fire, right?
Because you know it quickly would balloon out into way too many
particle systems especially if there were other particle systems
happening like wind or water or whatever happening.
And so what I was realizing as it's like well really, I think what we
probably want is to say that there's just a particle system.
Mm.
That's the full screen.
You know for fire and anything that's on fire responding, particle
system particles into that particle system so that we don't really
care how much fire spreads out throughout the world.
We can always handle it and degrade more gracefully.
Then the problems that we would have, if we had to have each
individual.
One of these fires be a particle system now,
Right.
So I think my Approach was just kind of fundamentally not great in
that sense, right?
and so, what I'm thinking is that actually,
We probably don't need the particle system cache at all.
Probably, I mean we we do need the particle system cache.
We just don't need it to let cash particle systems by entity ID or
anything like that.
Probably all we need to do is have entities spew particles into the
particle system if they're on fire, they just generate particle, fire
particles.
And then the particles system takes care of remembering that and
handling those particles, right?
That's a much senior way to do it, and
Not sure why I wasn't going to do it that way in the first place.
Probably just, I didn't think it through enough for who knows why but
so I think the problem is actually a little bit simpler than what I
was thinking about to be.
Now, there is some
There is a little bit of a caveat here, which is that the particle
system is like going to be a fixed thing in space.
So as we move around, right, as we move, the particle system around
during each pass through the particle system, we have to displace the
particles by the camera because the product of them is just a fixed
thing over the screen.
So if the player walks to the left and the camera is moving, then we
need to shift all the particles to coincide with that because the
particles themselves are never going to really be.
In the world space, they're always kind of just in the local
simulation space.
They never get stored back out or anything like that, right?
Okay.
But I think that's what we want.
I think that's just a smarter thing.
And so I feel like we can just kind of eliminate that part of the code
that we had before, by the way, for those of you following along at
home today, is days is day 338.
So you want to use that.
You want to use three 37's source code if you're trying to follow
along with me today, okay?
So essentially the particle system thing all of this stuff that we
were working on, can stay exactly the same, the difference.
Now is that these particles systems are not going to be things that
are based on some kind of a cash.
You know, they're going to be something based on on how many different
sort of discrete particle, simulation, re Arenas, we're going to need.
Need.
So at the moment we could just say that we just have one kind of
particle system and that's the fire system or something like that.
You don't need this and we don't need this and so because we're never
going to do any of that caching and we don't need the touching the
frame touching and that stuff.
So we can get rid of this, which is nice.
We can get rid of basically every thing that had to do with particle
systems, other than just the basic particle system piece itself that
we were kind of playing around with and yeah and the particle spec
would really be more of a particle emitter specification, kind of a
thing and we don't really even need
That to be in there anymore.
Now, let's go ahead.
And that also means we can unwind one of kind of the, the stupid
things, The Entity ID, B, we had to move in order to make that work.
We can also unwind that and put that back in here, I believe that
should work just fine least, I think so.
And so the protocol system specs stuff can go away temporarily and
we'll continue on.
All right.
So, let's see what we've got here.
All of this stuff I guess is still the same because this is just
operating on particle systems.
It's not operating on the particle system cache, anything, that's
operating the process from cash.
However, is going to have to change.
Get a create particle.
System is never going to be something that we need to do again.
So, in theory, all of this stuff can just go away, right?
I think we can just say, you know what?
That is just a completely unnecessary.
So is touch particle system.
Those are just not things anymore.
So, early, it's only update and render particle systems.
And really, this time for the
Under part of systems.
We would just, I think we've got one here, whatever.
Yeah, we've got that play around thing, really.
We do update and render fire.
Let's say, so if we've got update your render fire.
I'm just going to go ahead and here and say, like, okay, for updated
render fire, we'll just call that in here.
This stuff is not necessary anymore.
And we can just say what is that?
Fire system?
And that will have everything that it needs to work with when we do in
it, the particle cash.
Again, that's something that we don't really have to worry about too
much.
We want all our particles, probably initialized to zero so I at least
our or do we, I don't really know.
That's a good question, probably we do.
Which in that case, I think that does mean we could have left the
right clear in for our particle system.
Was in which case we don't really need a particle cash.
Really, for anything.
I have to think about that.
We can leave the call in, but I just don't know that it actually
matters at all.
But yeah, when we do this World's truck and we do the no clear, I
guess what I could do is as you're I could just clear it here for now
and then if we don't if we decide that we don't need to clear it
later, we can eliminate that call.
So yeah, let's take a look at the rest of the stuff.
The particle spec for an IT product system and it particle system is
not going to happen anymore.
It would be per parts.
We actually did need to do some insulation which we don't update and
render.
Fire needs to take some entropy
At the moment, we don't have any entropy so we probably want to use to
have the cash, have its own entropy Source, I would imagine.
So something like this random series entropy
And that entropy is not gameplay sensitive at the moment.
So this is, you know effects such or particle entropy note, Casey not
we're gameplay.
Ever.
Right, because that's just some go behind my head there.
So, yeah, we want to, when we initialize this, I guess there's
something.
We can do.
That's initialization based.
So particle entropy I don't know what random Series has in.
It probably it's got like a seed or something like this.
Do we know, do we know?
How to seed one of these guys.
Let's see, random, see, there it is.
So we just want a random seed the sky without a 1, 2 3 4 or 4.
Now it doesn't matter.
We just need to get entropy from somewhere.
So once we have some entropy then we will just say okay you can use
our entropy system and go to town on that function does not take four
arguments well why don't you tell me how many it does take?
It takes a system and entropy in a DT, so it doesn't take a render
group yet.
It will, I would think, but we won't pass it yet.
If it doesn't want it, that's fine with me.
so,
moving on.
This comes after, yes.
Yes, so now this thing doesn't have to do anything.
The particle system stuff doesn't have to get packed or unpacked and
then I think we're good to go.
So this is all fine.
Now,
Aw.
That's odd.
This is slower than it should be.
Is update and render fire, actually, that much work.
Let's find out.
That was not what I wanted.
Look at that.
Why is that so slow?
It's not really doing very much.
It is it I guess our little experiment with the sliced.
With, with those sort of ways of doing Expressions, is not very good,
right?
Remember I was kind of playing with how can we write something that's
like friendly in terms of what it says Cindy wise and looks like,
that's not so useful because you can look at how much that is.
We could see if it actually, if it does the right thing in
Release mode.
But definitely doesn't do the right thing.
And
In not in release mode.
Now, it's just awful.
Interesting.
So I guess my little trick is not not particularly good, or at least
it took his ring, unless I'm missing something, but it looks like it's
not particularly good because remember, I was sort of playing around
with.
Can we write these things as math functions?
And it does not look like you can unless I'm missing something.
So yeah, maybe that wasn't so good.
I don't know.
I guess what we could do is say put off the 70 until we're done and
then Cindy eyes it.
Because I was kind of hoping it could just run in Cindy in general,
and we could just have some way of writing the math functions.
Kind of relatively cleanly, but I don't know if that's plausible at
the moment.
If that really is the case now, maybe it's something else that's going
on wrong here.
But, you know, assuming it's not
That's not great.
So
So, what do we want to do?
You know, what do we want to do here?
How do we want to tackle this?
Do we want to write this in in non 71st, and then Cindy eyes it later,
or do we want to try?
Writing it in Cindy from the start and keep it relatively fast as we
go?
I really don't know.
I mean, what I want to do is be able to just write this in a nice
concise fashion, that then can be turned into Cindy code because it's
obvious how to turn to Cindy code.
Like, it's not.
There's nothing subtle about this.
This particle code.
I'm literally just asking it to do for of the same op on an array all
the time.
I just can't think of a good way to do something.
Other than what I did that isn't super slot like sort of difficultly,
sloppy.
Let's think about this.
So I guess one thing we could do, if we don't particularly care about
how wide we go, like if we don't want to go arbitrarily wide, we could
do something else.
So, let's think about this.
So one thing we could do is we could say well alright we've got these,
you know, these guys here that are sort of these sliceable guys who
have an ex-wife who have like a four of each for X is 4 Y is and for
Z's in them and what we could do is say like all right you know maybe
we've got a particle is actually for particles or something and we
just have a V3 for X you know of pv3 4X HD.
P.
You know, so it's the same as it was before but just everything is 4X
now.
Oops.
Right.
And so then, you know, a particle system is just a particle 4X.
and there's, you know,
A quarter.
The number of particle 4X is as we want protocols, you know, and off
we go, right?
And then this thing goes away.
Like we don't need that anymore and we just had these guys that
operate on the bundles of four at once.
Right.
so, you know, if we did something like that,
This either.
So if you did something like that, we could maybe start to get things
into slightly better shape.
We would not need get particle right, that would not happen anymore.
And in here, what we could do is say like, all right, you know, we've
got a particle a and that particle, a is just whatever the particle
that we're supposed to be on.
because that's a, i
So now we've got a pointer and then from there we can just say like
okay we want to initialize all these guys and we can do that exactly
the same way, right?
So, the code looks almost identical.
If we look at it, right?
And now, you know, the hope is anyway, the this will be much more easy
for the compiler to understand what we're doing.
It's not all like super contorted like it was before.
So the hope is, you know, maybe that would take the pressure off it
and allow it to work.
I don't actually know, but that would be the Hope what is this
particle?
4X.
Does not have an over.
All right, these are dots.
So again.
just pull one of these out, and
I think.
This would be.
A lot nicer to look.
That looks a lot nicer too.
So I think all we have to do is add the plus equals operator in there
because we never did one of those.
We had done that for the particle V3 but we've never done a plus
equals 4.
Just the 4X in the 3x guys so if I just go ahead and do that one.
Where are the?
The 4X ones.
We haven't done yet.
All right, let's just say where are the for excellence?
So if we do a plus equals for this guy,
we should be able to just kind of
Do this in place, like so.
And I think that's it.
We're still in.
Sterling.
Optimize mode.
I didn't actually want it to be an optimism.
It's let's see how we do.
So you can see how like, like, basically we were doing exactly the
same mathematical operations, right?
We did we have not changed any of the math but just the compiler.
Could not figure out the kind of machination of you're doing there.
So this is a lot nicer.
Now we've actually gotten rid of the things that it probably thought
it had to do to make things work.
Okay.
And so that's a lot happier right now.
It's a completely meaningless part and it runs just fine which is what
I would have.
Acted.
All right.
So yeah, do we need this anymore?
No.
So, yeah, so that's a lot nicer, I think because now, we now we
effectively have the ability to treat a particle as a mathematical,
like, you know, in fix notation thing that we can actually read.
You know, I can read this a lot better and I feel like that's going to
be important if we want to actually keep it in Cindy the whole time.
So it's, you know, a debug mode, Still Still fast enough.
I think that's just a better way to go.
So, yeah, so let's add the stuff that we're missing here.
I'm going to go ahead and get rid of if because in Cindy, that's gonna
be a little tricky.
So we'll have to see how we want to do that.
Exactly.
But,
Then we can kind of move on to working on some of these other things.
Okay, so I think that's that we should now have to write these
operators.
The ones that we wrote, we should have to write them for the V3 V4,
and that sort of stuff.
So really I think all that is is just, you know, changing these guys
to v4s
I am just adding the w.
That's really it.
And again, if you're a template sort of person, this is possibly a
place you could use those.
Or things like that.
If you have some way of accessing generic programming in your
language, that doesn't make you want to throw yourself in front of a
bus like C++ has.
Does this would be a good time to maybe break that up.
So, yeah, let's see.
Oh right.
These are labeled slightly differently.
Just to make things easier on myself.
I'm going to go ahead and Anonymous Union.
These guys.
Right.
So that way I can access them as either one.
and now,
Still good.
No worries.
So now we're doing part of the updating that we wanted to do for our
particle systems.
The old essentially the old particle code is now symbolized and
Like I was saying before it seems like we can we can do this pretty
easily.
Like this this looks like the kind of thing where I can leave it in
this code and I don't really have to worry too much about it.
I can also now that we've got this sort of a little bit more under
control, I could say like, all right, instead of a, I can actually
make this be called what it actually is.
So we kind of know roughly what we're doing here and everything else
here, I think is fine.
So, that's all good as well.
All right.
Um, so yeah.
So I'm reasonably happy with how that turned out.
This is kind of one of those things at least, hopefully it's
relatively self-evident from
Yep, if you just take a look at what happened in the past 15 minutes
or so, I feel like that's just a good example if in case, it wasn't
obvious of why it's important to actually like do all the things that
we talked about doing on the stream, right?
First of all, the fact that I had heads-up profiling on, there was the
thing that let me know that we were slow right away, right?
Because I never would have known how busted that code was till later.
When I went to try and actually performance optimized it or figure out
why my game was slow, who knows where down the road, but because we
always have our heads up stuff running.
We know the instant something is taking more time than we think it
should be.
It's like what's going on, right?
And we can jump right to it and see like okay, this thing is, is not
performing the way we want, right?
So again, I think we talked about that way back when people were
asking.
Like, you know, why do you spend time with debug stuff before you
actually need it?
It's because deep part of the debug code is about knowing when things
are broken and you don't necessarily always know when things are
broken, you know?
I mean, even just a something as simple as a
I'm rate counter where you can kind of look at how many milliseconds
per frame.
You're taking is incredibly important to always have available because
otherwise, you just never have any idea what your changes are really
doing.
It's very hard to perceive them unless they slow down things.
So obviously that you can't not see it, right?
So, so there's that.
And the other thing is, if you look at the difference between how much
cleaner this code looks than if we were to write it by hand, and
D or even it even looks better than what we had before.
The kind of clunky version that just kind of underscores like how
important it is to just actually take the time to figure out how to
get something a little bit more right before you start writing a ton
of stuff in it because, you know, we could have easily gone down that
route and had the much uglier looking code and then it just would have
been this constantly compounding problem where it's now all the work
we do on the particles, will go and be pretty
Easy to read and we know that it's relatively efficient.
So, you know, we're really set up for Success there in a good way.
So that's what I would say about that.
That's all I would say about that.
Anyway, so now let's take a look at what we would want to do here for
rendering before I get into.
Whether we want to start playing with some of this other stuff.
We got to do a few more things here where we figure out what we want
to do with rendering and we also have to take care of that
displacement thing that I was talking about before.
So essentially what's got to happen, here is whenever we do an update
and render of anything.
Basically, we have to pass both the DT and we will have to
Additionally, a frame displacement, right?
So we need essentially a vector.
That is the thing that we need to displace all the particles by to
handle the offset from the camera.
Now I won't actually do that yet.
I'll leave it out so that you can see what happens when it's not
there, but we'll just have to remember, I'm just going to put it in so
we know that it's there, right?
So when we update the position,
We're just going to put in frame.
Displacement in there.
And then when we do update render fire, we'll just have frame.
Displacement be this thing that we sort of have in there that we
haven't done yet.
There we go.
I'm not move over here so I'm not cramping my style there and it just
won't do this placement yet.
So we'll still be able to see the bug that will happen if we don't do
the frame displacement and then we can put in the frame because this
fancy it.
So I don't want to like Jump Ahead there but I just happen to know
right?
That you know if we don't have that displacement, it's going to mess
this up.
Okay, so
we've got updated Enterprise systems.
Passing that displacement, not going to do anything yet, but we've got
it in there.
So what we need before, we can actually see anything happening here is
oh, and by the way,
That's got to be lofted.
Probably this.
So what we need is just some function.
That can produce these.
From a input.
So if I have a 3 V 3 for X as the result, I just want to result to be.
Replicating, whatever the input was four times, right?
So I'm just trying to stuff the values like so.
Frame displacement.
Let me spell it, right and off we go.
So the thing that we have not addressed yet now is the rendering.
So the first thing that I'm going to do is I'm just going to render
these particles through the standard particle path.
Obviously, the standard particle path is probably not what we want.
It's going to be too slow, I talked about why.
So we're going to want to go ahead and add a special path for a
particles or something.
We've got a lot of ways we get attack, tackle, the problem certainly,
but I think we're going to want a standard way.
That's, it's not really for particles per se, but just for things that
render out of the same bitmap, lots of things rendering out of the
same texture.
Basically, we want to have a path for that process.
Okay, so now we could take a look at this and say, all right, we need
a color here and and we need to push bitmap calls, and positions.
And so on, obviously we can't really do those things because we've got
four packed of these.
So what we really need to do is
So we have a way of actually producing, like I said, that optimize
buffer, we're going to have to go through, you know, each of the sub
particles, right?
So this is like in that pack of four, we got to go through all four
and pull them out separately, right?
So what we need to do first is we need to find the the P value.
And then we need to find the color value.
So each of these
For the entity transform, this should just be something that we don't
really have to worry about that.
Will just be some transform for the basis of the particle system
itself.
So that's actually something that I assume can be passed in.
And just left set the entire time.
Now, the bitmap ID is something that we don't really have yet.
We're going to have to get that from somewhere for now.
I think we'll use the same trick we used before which is to say we can
use the head of the of the hero.
And so when we do our in it protocol cash will kind of do some stuff
here for that.
So what I'll do is say, probably I guess what I've said what I do is
say, Let's Pretend for now, the particle systems have a bitmap
ID, that is, whatever the bitmap that they use.
And we'll just say that you always have that available.
We'll have to get that from somewhere, but we'll cross that bridge
when we come to it.
So to say, use the system ID, the particle transform.
That's just going to be something that is pretty much constant I think
so it could be passed in here.
I don't know if we need to pass it in here.
We could also put it in here but I'm just not sure about that yet.
So I'm going to go ahead and take a look.
At how our transforms are generally created here, we want sort of
vanilla transform so I think probably the default upright transform
would be the easiest transform to do.
If we want its temp centered around the camera.
We would want to do this.
We'd want to do we want to do that as well, because that's sort of
like where the Sim Center is versus where the camera is because the
Sim Center and the camera Center I guess are not always the same.
I don't really know why we do that.
I'd have to think about why we do that.
I think we may snap the Sim Center to always be aligned to a floor
boundary whereas the camera can sort of move separately, right?
I'm not sure about that though.
Don't quote me on that.
So anyway and of course what I say
I think we actually have a quote database so it's kind of a bad thing
that I say, don't quote me on that because someone could be quoting me
on what I said.
Not to quote me on that.
Which is not great if that makes sense.
So yeah let's take a look.
What I want to do is say the default upright transfer, and let's say
maybe that's just what we use here.
And so we'll just say that there's a particle transform in here.
For the particle system and pretty much.
Those will probably just be set and forgotten because they probably
never need to change.
But if we want to do something Fancy with them later, we can.
So I think we want to do something that's actually does that when we
push these bitmaps on here.
Now what we're going to have to do is we're going to take those pieces
out like I said.
So we're going to have to do something where we say, like, okay, let's
pretend that we're grabbing out individual pieces here.
So like rv3 is going to be
Kind of a nasty way to get this.
It's going to be something like a px, you know, the can't even
remember what these things.
See here.
Let me see.
I don't know where our particle systems code is.
It's not loaded yet updating render fire.
So I want to know.
How I access the individual members.
And I never remember because of the weirdest names.
Okay, so it's m120 underscore F 32.
All right, so you can see what I'm doing here.
I'm just plucking out those values.
Again, we don't really want to be doing this but we're just doing this
so that we can use the standard render path first, get the particle
systems working with that.
And then what we'll do after we have the particle systems.
Working with that is we'll go ahead and add a custom pipeline for
getting the particle systems down to the card in a way that isn't too
heinous, right?
So that's what we need to do at the moment, so I think that would do
it.
Let's
get this back in here.
Good?
I don't know why object transform isn't defined yet.
Is that
is that not a thing?
Is that included, our particle system somehow included before the
renderer.
There's object transform and I don't know why the particle systems
would be well, let's find out.
Yeah, they sure are.
I wonder if we can move them after.
That's not a problem because that's just a pointer.
So I think that's all good.
None of the to overloads.
Well yeah, duh.
Okay.
So now that we're in here, we need to pass the render group Mast.
It's actually taking it like, we knew it would but we've never had it
in there before.
When we knit the part of a cache, we now have to make sure that our
fire system, it has to have a transform.
That's the default.
Upright, transform for now, I guess.
And
and yeah, and the
Bitmap ID will have to get from somewhere.
Now, I don't actually know.
We're going to get the bit by D from I guess I'll probably pass
something here to the product system.
So it can do some queries and and get one, you know,
We'll see if we can do that.
The Entity actually, no, it would be World mode.
So when we do add player Somewhere In Here, We Do.
Queries for this.
So here, we've got asset Shadow torso, Cape Ed.
So, I guess what?
We do the pieces, we actually call them out at that time, which I
guess is good.
So, if you want to do that, how would we do that?
Let's see, let's see.
Where's our peace iterator?
There it is.
So yeah, if we want to do that, we get this guy.
Of course we don't really have anything to match on because you don't
have any assets for this but it's okay.
We could pretend and get the hero head or something like we were doing
before, that seems fine.
So if we did that we could just say like okay let's just get like
asset type you know or
What was it again?
Acid head.
So, we'll just get some head out of here.
And call it a day.
Now I don't actually know if that's everything we need because I don't
remember.
But either way we would have to pass the asset system here.
Because without it it would not be able to get any of that.
Now, I don't know if the asset system has been loaded, it would all
would have to be.
So the asset systems are always loaded at that point.
So I think we're in luck there, that's just easy enough.
We don't have to worry about the initialization order of those things.
They'll just work.
Okay, so now we need to do some oh dear.
Oh God.
All right.
Well.
Yeah.
That's going to cause a problem.
I had not thought about that.
This.
I wonder if this is finally the straw that breaks the camel's back and
forces us to see before our stuff which we've constantly tried to
avoid but
That's going to be a tough one to think through.
So yeah, if we push this many things into the sort graph, it's going
to be an epic nightmare, right?
I mean, we can get things working here with just a small number of
particles may be like that, but I had not considered the sort the sort
graph problem that we have.
So yeah, so now I think we are at least in theory generating
particles.
And now we have to just kind of go do the debugging to make sure
they're getting placed in a reasonable location and that we can
actually see them but but that's basically it.
How much time do I have?
I don't know.
I think we've got 15 minutes left.
I need a thing.
I need a way.
I should probably put a countdown timer in here, which is like, says,
how many minutes are left?
Because I don't actually know, I don't remember, we started, I think
we did a start and 8:45 start, which means we'd have 945 Switch
reviews, have 50 minutes.
So I'm going to just do some debugging here and we'll talk about that
problem that we're going to have.
Okay, so
Eight.
Handmade render noted.
Where's my particles?
Why does this thing not leave things open?
I know, we've been in that file, like, can't I just tell it, like,
have all my stuff?
Why can't you just have all my buffers open?
Why can't you be more like for coder?
God.
Yeah, millions of dollars went into developing the software package
and I can't even do like basic for coder things, seriously.
All right.
So let's see.
I need to do up to update and render fire.
So we need to take a look at what we are rendering.
And if it makes any sense.
Alright, so we have our rgba and our p-values, those all look fine.
So it may just be the case that we're just rendering in a place that
we can't currently see because it's too far below something else or
something like this.
I'm not sure.
I'm going to take a quick look up at update and render world so I can
see what the camera location is.
Well, if the camera is it 000 though.
I would think.
That, that would have been sufficient.
Now, what I could do
I suppose is I could Nerf.
Everything else just so I can see.
If they're getting clipped by something else or not, let's take a look
here.
Okay, so yeah.
So our particles are doing their thing and so we're off to a good
start.
So all we really need to do now is actually sort of make these guys
spawn somewhere that we actually care.
And there.
And then we can, we can move on from there.
Kind of a nice little Twitchy head thing going on there.
My goodness.
All right.
So we've got updating render entities.
And really this this bit here I'm going to make into a function called
spawn fire.
And I'm going to go ahead and grab that up here and make it look like
that.
Spawn fire will take the particle system cash.
And it will get the fire system out of that cash.
And if we take a look at the P values here, what I want to do is say
like okay we're not going to touching the stuff yet and it's not fire.
Anyway, it's just, it's a stream of heads.
But what we do want to do there when we spawn the fires say like,
okay, we would like to tell it where where we were going to spawn it.
and then what I can do is Loft that guy up so I can say like okay,
after we compute that initial starting P, we can just add in our at
All right, so now we can spawn fire at a at a location.
We still need our entropy, but the entropy is easy to come by.
Oops.
So that should basically be it, right?
Oops, cash, not system.
So now we should be able to spawn fire wherever we want to spawn fire.
And so what I can do is I can say like okay let's say that there's an
entity that just spawn some fire, I don't know what, you know,
whatever.
So if we've got an entity here and maybe like if an entity is in its
Landing phase, you know?
Whenever it lands, it, spawned some fire.
Why does this bonfire?
I don't know.
That's not my job.
I'm not a game designer.
I'm just a program.
And I decided that it's got a sponsor fire so it's going to spawn it.
Wherever the entities placement is at that particular point in time
and then it just needs to be able to get to the cash which I believe
it can do because I think we've got that in here.
Sorry part of the cash.
So you know in theory
I think we should be able to get that spawning.
A crisis.
I say that I am not seeing any spawning occur, but I'm not sure why.
I would like to know.
The heroes location is the moment.
and I would like to know,
What are particles systems looking like?
Kind of looks like it should be.
Okay.
I'm also going to, you know, what else?
I need to do here.
To make this a little easier on us.
I got to get rid of the rooms.
So we're only looking at one room.
All right.
Okay.
So it was just the problem is just that we have too many particles
being spawned, so it's working just fine.
This is why we need a lot more in 64 particles.
So anyway that's all well and good.
And so now these people are spawning just fine now, of course we still
have a problem and that is as we move the camera, this will not work
properly.
Right?
Because all of these can these things are camera relative.
And so what I need to do is I need a way of moving the camera to the
side quickly.
So, what I want to do is make it so that the the door direction is
going
Be in line with us and there's two screens like so.
And then I'm going to update the particle, count a little bit just so
we can see more.
Right.
So we've got all these particles here, and they're all doing their
thing, or whatever has to happen, right?
You can see them and you see what happened there.
All of them, kind of stay in place even after you try to leave, right?
It's not pretty.
Now, of course, we kind of have to do something.
We have to have these particles, stay around a lot longer and of
course, like I said, we can't because our sir craft will explode, at
least I assume it will like you can see like look at that.
It's just a nightmare because they're all overlapping is the problem,
right?
But anyway, you can see how that kind of is a complete disaster there.
Yes, yes.
I know.
That looks like that.
Looks like a separate problem.
Why are we?
What's happening there?
Why is there?
Why are there two doors like that?
Shouldn't there only be one door.
Well.
Oh because it's okay.
No there's always going to be a next yet, never mind I'm stupid.
Never mind.
Forget it.
Anyway so this is all I wanted to get at here was these guys as they
kind of get sprayed up into the sky like that.
You can see the particles just they stay in one place when I move.
And that's because all of these particles are existing only in screen
space or not actually existing in World space, which is what we want.
Because we only want to be dealing with particles that are kind of
local to the simulation.
Really
And so that's great actually but we need some way of not having that
artifact.
As we kind of go from screen to screen or do any other kind of smooth
scrolling effect.
We don't want to have that happen.
So if we want to fix that, what we need to do is from one frame to the
next frame, we need to remember where the camera was and then account
for that shift by moving the particles by, whatever that change,
whatever that actual change in World space is right.
So somebody
Has to pass us essentially when we do update render particle systems,
somebody asked to pass us the frame displacement in from outside.
So when we call that in here, we need to get
The like frame-to-frame.
Camera.
Like the Delta, right?
So we have to get that summer.
So what we need to do is figure out sort of, we want to do a
subtraction of where the camera was last time and where the camera was
this time, right?
And so if you imagine how we would do that, we would just need to say
something like well.
Okay you know on the first frame we just wouldn't have any
displacement but and every frame there after we'd want to take base of
where the camera like was and do that diff right.
And so to do that,
All I'm really going to do is say well, okay, let's say there is a
last camera, pee.
And so, all I'm going to do is say, well, when we do, when we get that
camera p and that gets updated.
Right?
Let's see, your camera.
So we do begin soon.
So yeah, here we go.
So what we do in Simcoe
Are right?
This is where the camera P would actually get updated.
I believe.
So when we have World mode camera P here, where we can, we get the SIM
Center out of this and the robot camera P.
At this point, what I want to do is say, okay, take the last camera p
and do the diff right?
So, frame to frame.
Camera, Delta p is going to be subtract and it's going to be the world
mode camera p.
And the world mode last camera, pee.
And then after I've done that, I want to do World mode.
Last camera, P equals World mode camera P.
So we can just do that suspect get the got the frame to frame Delta
and be done with it, right?
So now we have to do is make sure that when we actually initialize
things and we set it up the first time that we also set.
Last camera P to that value.
Alright, so off we go with our little particles, they're doing,
whatever it is that they're doing.
I wanted this to be landing and I accidentally set it to hopping.
It looks like, but now we need to do is get the that camera, Delta
working for frame to frame.
That's still in that.
That's not at all what I wanted.
To say the least.
So I believe we have an error here somewhere.
Of course, let me verify that we're actually using properly but it
didn't, it was not very complicated.
So I'm assuming I just have an error.
When Computing, the actual frame displacement but
when we take the finished basement with Place, pass it through,
and whenever we have the frame displacement in here,
We add it right?
Yeah.
Well, so yes, I don't know why that's problem.
But what I was going to say is I also had this, I wanted it on Landing
but I accidentally put it with the one before landing.
So that's an interesting case.
Hold on a second.
The other thing is there before these particles are initialized,
they're all stacked on top of each other.
So one thing I would want to do at least at the time, being is say, if
AC, I'm sorry, if C dot a is greater than 0, if it's not, don't push
it.
That way we won't be rendering like, uninitialized, particles.
So that should be doing nothing.
so I'm wondering why that's actually doing it taking any time, because
I feel like
those Alpha values should all be zero, right?
I want to see what happens there.
I don't understand why we're getting any effects to the product
system.
The first time around
alright, so here's our first time through
Help that's awesome.
Greater than or equal to 0?
Yeah.
Well guess what?
It's always going to be greater than or equal to 0 or at least most of
the time I wanted that.
Yeah.
So there we go.
So anyway, so yeah, so our problem here is just that that is
frame-to-frame.
Displacement is not being applied the way, I would think it should.
So the first thing I'm going to do is just make sure that it's
actually getting imply that properly at all, but I don't see how it
couldn't be but, you know, either way.
So I'm going to do here is just double check that it is getting.
Just, just it is getting done the way that I would have.
Thought it thought it would.
I want to say frame to frame 20.
This is going backwards, so there's that.
Yeah.
Because that's the motion that would take you from the location of the
last camera to the location of the new camera.
Right.
So here is where the old camera is.
And this is the new camera.
And so if I move the camera This way everything on the screen should
move that way but I'm moving the particles in that direction.
So I'm actually compounding the problem at that point, which is the
opposite of what I wanted to do.
So really, we want this to be the opposite, so I think that's still
the right name for that.
but we just want to pass the - so that they'll move counter to
Where that is?
So yeah.
So we'll start with that.
But it still seems like they're staying in one place when I go there.
So I'm going to have to look and see the missing.
I got to say this is kind of funny having all these like particles
I think it feels like the cameras, ah.
I was going to say.
It feels like the camera.
Has an additional displacement and it does, right?
And it actually does the camera and the Sim Center thing, there's the
world mode camera offset, which is a separate thing on top of that,
right?
So we actually have last can repeat.
We also have last camera offset, that's kind of annoying.
What if we can make do without that, I know we had that for animation
purposes.
I don't fully remember why to be completely honest with you.
But anyway, I think as we want to lock
Like to room to room but so we actually need both of these.
We need
We need both of those and so we want to say like, okay subtract those
two and then add to it, World mode camera offset - build mode, last
camera, all set.
So yeah.
So, there we go.
Now our particles are moving.
I think a little more properly.
Chris, I don't really know because it's a very quick transition.
But let's make those guys died out a little sooner, just just for just
for fun.
So when we spawn one of these guys that we have the that Delta I'm
going to just shorten that up a lot.
So the parts one particles will just kind of kick up and just be
really really sparse like that.
All right.
So now we'll see if these particles are.
See, I feel like there's some weird thing happening there.
Why are we seeing when we cross over here?
There's kind of like these old particles that look like there should
have been somebody there to spawn them.
Like they weren't getting updated or something like
But that is really make any sense.
So still kind of feels like maybe there's a bug there.
With the updating.
yeah, so if the particles are being spawned
The transfer of.
Yes.
So I feel like this, I feel like I know what's happening there too.
So I feel like what's happening there is when we do the transform that
camera all set is something that we're actually pushing on
to the entity transform, right?
That camera off set.
Is getting pushed on here.
So that means it's strictly, it's strictly a transform that's being
applied to not to the like the entities themselves.
Their locations are still relative to the Sim center, right?
So
we need to either use the same technique for that, which maybe is the
best course of action.
So always use the that world transform.
Always just use that world transform for the particle systems and then
we wouldn't need to track the camera offset anymore.
That seems like, maybe a better idea.
Because what's happening there, right?
Is that when the screen is displaced by just camera offset, our
particles are spawning in the wrong locations because those particles
are being spawned in the entity space, which is not actually
displaced, right?
So you kind of have this situation where you really don't want, I
really don't want that.
I guess so the camera offset could stay.
And then that way, we also wouldn't have to do this which is nice,
right?
So you can just say like no, that's not happening.
So the camera offset stuff is the way it is.
And then when we do the rendering of the particles, we just pass this
world transform down as the transform to use.
For everybody.
And that way it will get this place automatically and then now
everyone's in the same space I think I think that's a will then be a
much more may be consistent way to do it.
So if we get rid of this, we pass it down.
Like so.
And then we would just pass it through.
And everyone's happy.
Well, I don't actually know if everyone is happy but they might be
happy.
And probably that should be a pointer, huh?
Okay.
Almost done.
Now, I think we're good.
All right.
All right, we'll do some Q&A.
Martin's.
Thanks for the reminder.
He's pointing out that we can't access those.
I think didn't we?
Did we have a way of getting those.
That was like a get thing.
I thought we wrote one of those.
This is it.
Right.
So that's how we were getting around that before.
So yeah, this again is not code that will stay there.
I don't think.
So, we should be able to do ma.
I m,
Ki.
And that will again prevent clang time complaining because for some
reason it's defined two different ways on the two different platforms.
No reason for this.
do not know why, but it just is
Okay.
So in theory we should be able to love this up.
I don't think we probably want these to be called M&M I and I think
now is probably time but we want to start having our own Cindy.
So I'll probably also just say hey maybe we'll do handmade
Cindy.
Dot h.
Dot CPP.
And that way.
We can just go ahead and grab these guys and put them in there.
I'm assuming that we don't actually want these to be MMI but anyway
what we can also do is say all of this stuff can now because this is
sort of 70 based things.
We can put these guys in here.
We can get all their operators in there and that way we can use those
later for anything that we want to 70.
That's not how you spell Cindy.
Not how you spell it.
All right, so this guy needs to include that because I believe that's
not that needs to be included here.
So maybe shared needs to have that.
So maybe
It's better to do it.
And here, let's say.
Oops.
And maybe I'll just go like, okay, maybe I'll say handmade Cindy dot
CPP is not a thing.
There we go.
So, there we go.
So, I suppose, the kid was suggesting to slow down the time to make
sure it is now, right?
We can definitely do that.
Although I should probably get over there first so I don't have to
laborious Lee, hop over to slowly.
All right.
Looks pretty solid.
I don't see like I can't do anything.
I can't tell us.
Are they possibly one frame?
Lagged?
You know I'm saying?
I can't tell.
Right?
Because that could be, that could be a bug if they were one frame.
Laggy.
I will say, they do seem to change position a little bit in a way that
I'm not sure if they should.
The problem is, I don't know if there's e-value is such that they
should, but they do look like they change.
They do look like they
shift a little around in there.
In their grid squares.
So, I'm not sure.
Like there may be a bug there.
Yeah, I think they're definitely because they're definitely shifting.
I think I think I'm going to call that a bug at least till we can
prove.
Otherwise,
And they like waiver back and forth.
The like it's really weird.
So here's the really weird thing about it is while we're in the middle
here, we should not be doing any modifications to the particle systems
at all.
Right?
Because while we're, while we're scrolling to the left, it's just the
camera offset.
That's doing it.
It's only right there at the crossover point that we actually apply
anything.
So it just feels like they're getting transformed on like a higher
plane, you know.
Like they're on like this plane like they're up above.
Or something.
I don't know.
That's a bit weird.
I'm going to I that's going to be an involved, debug, I think so.
We're going to have to save that I think for tomorrow.
Not too long ago, you change real courts PS3 to instead of u-32.
I think they were unsigned originally.
So that overflow would work correctly to have the world wrap around,
but that will still work at the moment.
Since we're centered around zero, I think having them be you three
twos doesn't actually matter.
Like I don't think we need that anymore.
I could be wrong about that though.
Super fun code.
Hobo does the Z position of the particles.
Not get affected by the protective transform?
Well, the perspective transform is,
oh well, you know what?
I don't know that we are setting.
We don't set any floor transform for it so it could be that they're on
a different floor.
Yeah, that's hard to say.
Remember only the floor, the floor relative height.
art of things is the only thing that I'm sorry, the the Which floor
you're on they get set is the only thing that determines how you kind
of slide relative to other things perspective, transform lives and so
your height above the floor, doesn't do that but
I don't remember.
What?
We set these two.
So we set the floor Z here, right?
And
you know, for our particles
I don't really know what we want to do there for those transforms.
That's a good question.
when your position goes from into in Max, when it cause undefined
Behavior,
Why would it cause undefined Behavior?
I don't think so.
But either way, like, you can't get out that far.
You'd never make it.
We'll see.
Ya signed integer overflow.
We don't like if the compiler is not going to treat that properly then
you know, oh well like I said you can't actually get out there so I
don't really care what happens.
There's no way for the player to make it that far out.
I don't think
And if for some reason, we were worried about the player eventually
getting there, we just make our chunk size bigger because that's only
used for the chunk size.
With I sense.
But I just don't I just don't remember if we what we actually use them
for.
Yeah.
See, we're using us 32s for everything.
We're not using you 32s.
So, the like it's been that way forever.
It's just, it was only the code.
The only code I changed that you're talking about was like in the
world in the little like world-building, like, you know, this last
screen Z nonsense, which is just a little, you know, you're relevant
code.
Anyway, it's just, it's just test code to create rooms for us to play
with.
Mmm.
I will say not having real 3D, is just a real pain in the butt.
There are so many things that you just can't do.
When you don't have real 3D.
Yeah.
Anyway, I'm going to go ahead and close things down here.
It's late.
All right, everyone, thank you for joining me for another set of
handmade here.
It's my pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
It comes to the source code so that you can follow along.
We also have Forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions, you have patreon page and go to
transport the video series, a schedule bot that week schedule.
You in an episode guide for catching up on old stuff.
I will be back here tomorrow night, same time, same place, until then
have fun programming and I'll see you guys.
Guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.