Let's go in here.
Hello everyone, welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live from scratch.
No engine, no libraries, just our own code and basically we're going
through every bit of game technology.
Every every last piece that goes into having a game run right from
filling the the pixels to the highest level, like pathfinding AI
stuff, we are doing absolutely everything so that we can kind of see
Last Detail that goes into how a game is made.
And right now we're kind of in the middle of a big change.
We are working our way towards having a solid engine architecture and
what we're doing right now is we are finishing a change that we made
where we said, okay, we're going to have this concept of a simulation
region so that we can have very, very large worlds.
That don't necessarily fit inside a single floating Point variable,
right?
In terms of their spans,
And so you would so that we need more complex addressing tool that to
be able to support them.
Very, very large world and the ability to scale up to basically as
many entities as you want, so like we have two major scaling problems.
So what we decided to do to address that was to basically simulate the
world in little tiny regions so that we can do stuff like have one
high, one, simulation region that we open every frame to simulate
what's around the player, but then we could also
Simulate all the as many other places in the world at any given time
as we want to buy opening, other simulation regions there.
And we'll just do as many of those per frame as we can, and things
that maybe don't need to be updated as frequently that are further
away from you will get stimulated less frequently.
So, this solves, both of those problems and it's our first
architectural attempt.
At solving them and we're hoping it works but we don't really know
yet.
I'm still sick today.
So there will be a bunch of nose blowing on the stream and I apologize
for that in advance.
but,
You can't stop coating just cause you're sick.
The code wouldn't get done if we just took every little excuse to stop
coding.
That's just no good.
So what we're going to do is we're going to dive right back into it, I
should mention if you have pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
dot-org, using this little fancy button right here.
And you would like to follow along at home with your own copy of the
source code.
You can do that that link that you've got in your email gives you
access to the source code all the time.
So, download the zip file in there and they'll be
bunch of Zips that you in that file.
You want day 64 zip file to start day 65.
So, one day, 65 Sunday, unzip day, 64 zip and start with that code.
That is what I am starting with today.
So you can follow along exactly if you would like.
So today,
Our job is basically to tidy things up and get to the point where
we're running with the same regions so that we can start to bugging
them.
And I don't know if we'll have enough time today to actually debug
them or not.
But I would be nice if we could get to the point where we've actually
implemented everything that we need and are at least running albeit,
perhaps running incorrectly.
And that way next week we can start on just debugging and adding stuff
and testing out some regions and so on.
So let's see.
Yeah.
We were in the process of fixing compile errors.
Basically, we made our bunch of changes, and we now have to move our
sim code that we were used to be doing in our kind of janky way.
Our ad hoc way that we were doing before.
It's now time to move those over into the simulation system that we
were doing inside the simulation system.
We've got a bunch of simulation code here.
And what I'm thinking, I don't know, this is just my, my thought is, I
probably am going to have a
A lot of code for entity stuff.
And so what I'd like to do is probably make a file that just holds all
of the behavioral code so that anytime we want to add stuff that about
like how the game World operates, that kind of goes in one file,
that's not in the same region, which is basically like the utilities
and the logic for doing the same region itself.
I think I'm going to keep those in separate files.
Again, there's really no Rhyme or Reason to how you separate things
file wise.
The way that we're doing things, it doesn't matter.
I can pretty much put things in files, however, you want.
So, when I put things in different files, all I'm thinking about is
just how I want to be able to quickly view them and how I want to kind
of mentally compartmentalize them.
It's a purely psychological thing.
The files is not really a development thing because the way we compile
this, everything is all one big chunk.
Anyway,
It doesn't really matter how you break it up into files.
So I'm going to make something here, like handmade.
I guess what are we going to call?
This will call it handmade entity for now not sure if that's a good
name or not.
But
That's going to call it because it's basically like all of the code
that you need to implement those entities.
So put that in here.
I don't think there's really anything for the h file at the moment.
Really?
We're just making those, these sort of update calls, I'm going to move
them in here, so those go in there and then inside, let's see, inside
the rest of this stuff.
I think most of these things are going to be roughly the same, our
draw hitpoints code.
I'm going to leave this code on compiled for now, and we'll switch
back to it in a second, are all of these things that we're doing,
rendering rendering?
I
It should just operate directly on the same region.
While the same region is still open, we do our rendering so we'll
basically open a Sim region for the world for the plates, around the
player.
Simulate it forwards, render it right in place, possibly doing the
rendering in the simulation together and then close it.
Whereas with other SIM regions we won't do.
That will will.
We won't basically output any rendering for it.
How we want to deal with that?
Is again something that we can just do a little bit further down the
line.
So what I want to do here is I want to change this over to be using
the same entities now, and because we now no longer ever work with low
entities, the the basically the storage
Format for enemies.
We just don't touch during Real Running of the game.
Everything supposed to be on cemented, he's except the unpack in the
pack.
So basically everything that was a low entity here is just an entity
now and that's really all that should have to happen as far as I know.
There's nothing else fancy that should go on there.
So that should just work and it did.
Now in here again, we don't have high enemies anymore and the game
State, that's not a thing.
We just have the the sort of the final stored entities in there so we
can get rid of the high-end account.
That's gone.
Anything that was initializing that array is not necessary anymore.
So now what we have to do here is finally, something that should have
been done a long time ago.
Well, doesn't know.
It should have been done a long time ago but rather that's been wrong
for a long time but we don't really have to deal with it.
And that is updating the player updating a hero we had always kind of
done that in an ad hoc fashion.
We did that right in the code that parses the controller because again
and like I said, it should have been done a long time ago, is really
the wrong term.
It wasn't that should have been done a long time ago.
It's that kind of knew that we wanted to replace it for quite some
time but they're really never was a need to and you don't want to do
stuff ahead of when there's a need to because you're liable to guess
wrong, you always want to wait so you can actually see how things are
going to go before.
You make changes like that.
And so, what what we were doing here is we would process the
controller input.
And then immediately after processing the controller input, we would
actually do the updating for the player.
And that's not really what we want to do, right?
We would like to probably do that we'd like to probably do this in a
way, that's more sane.
And the reason that we want to do that again is because she's me
We don't actually know how this controller parsing stuff is going to
work in the future.
It's highly likely that we might do something where boat, like,
multiple controllers update the same player.
Like both the keyboard and the GamePad are both controlling the same
player for example, like if we ship, the game's single-player only and
not multiplayer because we don't know whether we're going to support
multiplayer, not like we right now do but we don't know whether that's
actually gonna be a gameplay feature.
If it turns out that it's not, then we'll want to do something like
bundle the controller stuff together.
And so on, furthermore processing the controller input is something
that maybe we need some logic to do to like figure look at, you know,
maybe we change this if there's just a lot of stuff that goes on in
there.
So we'd like to do is basically have the simulation for the hero
happen in the same place as everything else.
And the controller processing,
To the extent that it happens can either happen outside and build a
little thing that it then passes on to the simulation code that says,
what should happen with the hero?
Or we actually just call out to the controller code in the hero
processing and say, get it.
Now, I'm not sure which one we want to do, but either way, this stuff
here, obviously is simulation stuff and should happen inside the
simulation part of things.
So again, the other reason to is that there might be metagame stuff
here in the controller, stuff meeting that you like let's say we
Have we do have an option menu, we decide have an options menu and or,
you know, some kind of a confirmation for quitting that stuff with
sort of interrupt, this, this processing.
So we also have that concern, so a lot of that stuff's just suggest to
me, that probably what I want to do since I have to start sweating
this apart is I probably want to split apart the same stuff, put it
down inside where the rest of the Sim stuff is and then just have this
get sort of the past like the stuff that wants to happen if the crow
just gets kind of passed down to
The to the same stuff.
So when we do our entity type hero, updating here right we can just
stick in the code that we were using before for now.
And that's going to be how we'll do that.
And then up here, when we do our controller parsing, what we'll do is
we'll just save the stuff that we actually want to do for our hero and
we'll process that later on.
Now, we set ourselves up for success.
Perhaps, accidentally by having this player index, for controller
concept.
We basically said, for every controller in the system, we've got sort
of a knowledge of What entity that maps to.
Well, what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to go ahead and expand
that out.
And so in addition to storing this, this player this entity reference,
right?
This is the end of the index.
In addition, to storing that entity index.
We're also going to store
Along with it, the, the sort of control request, that has been
accumulated for that player on this Frame.
So, we had this this DDP request, right?
Which is the acceleration that was wanted.
And then we also have this d sword request, which is whether they
wanted to throw that sword, right?
So I'm just going to go ahead and put those in there.
And then later on what we'll do is the heroes when they get processed.
They'll basically pick
Out up from the, the player index for controller array.
Now, what I'd like to do to the other thing about that that's kind of,
well, kind of think about this one thing that's a little janky is for
the individual players.
Oh well, you know what?
That's okay.
We can store that binding pretty well as well.
So, never mind.
We'll, we'll deal with that a little bit later.
All right, because we're going to there's other stuff that we're going
to need as well.
Alright, so when we go ahead and get this,
this player index for controller.
Now what I'm going to do is expand that out into this thing which is
Basically like a controlled hero or something like that.
So we'll have a controlled hero struct and that's going to be one for
every controller at the moment.
So when we do the controlled hero, we're going to get one of those
back and this is the controlled hero here.
So, there we go.
Grab that out.
And this is now I guess like just a controlled hero array.
Rolled hero like so right maybe I'll say controlled Heroes.
so we'll grab that out and then assuming that that, that controlled
hero,
Is has an entity Index, right?
Then we're going to do the control policy for it.
Otherwise, we're going to do the same thing we're doing before.
You know it maybe that's a because it looks too close to controller.
Let's do con hero like that makes it sound like he's a convict of some
kind anyway.
So if that happens, then all we have to do is just set up the stuff as
we were doing before so we'll record that entity index, like so and
that's really all we have to do although we could
Out as well.
Here's GDP request like so in fact, I guess we could just do.
We could just zero this entirely
Like so so just initialize it like that when we add a player and then
similarly inside here, when we're actually doing work on the player
now instead the DDP stuff we can basically just to make that change
this so that we're actually doing it directly on the con hero.
One of them.
Oops and I guess there's no route.
The request is just kind of, I mean I look at it for typing residents.
Leave in that way.
We know their requests.
We could even put a note note, these are the controller requests for
stimulation.
Like so okay, so let's see here.
Controller trillion to see Heidi Z equals 30.
So this was we also have a DZ request which is basically our old
jumping command.
Got we had our, we had we put jumping in there, even though, even
though we don't actually think we're ever going to allow this guy to
jump.
We still have jumping in there anyway, but you know, it was kind of a
fun thing.
It allowed us to test some Z stuff, so we'll leave it in for now.
Let's go ahead and change that stuff.
And so now we've got all of those things in there, looks pretty
straightforward.
So now when we go down here and we're actually doing that simulation
for the hero,
what we can do, there's two ways we could do this.
And I'm trying to think of which one I like best.
I think instead of doing it this way,
Basically what I'm trying to figure out is so we've stored this now.
And then, what we want to do is when we actually process all of our
entities, we want to go pick up those requests that the controller's
put in and kind of one of the nice things about that.
Is now they can, we can have, as many things we want sort of add in
there.
In fact, one thing that we could do is clear it first and then add
into it here.
Like we could just clear out these requests fields and then have these
actually add into them, which would be kind of allow us to do the
controller.
As well.
So maybe we'll do that in a second as well, but ignoring that for now,
What I need to do is now go pick them up.
So when I iterate over the entities, what I want to do is see if this
particular entity, this particular hero that I'm on has any control
request, there's two ways I could do that.
One way I can do that is have a mapping that allows me to get from The
Entity back to the controlled hero.
Now, I can do that pretty simply with an array look up, because
there's only like, four, or five of these ever in the system because
there's only like, you know, four or five controllers separately,
controlled Heroes on a single machine.
But the other way I could do it is not doing with a lookup, I could do
a loop over the controlled hero structures and look up the entities
via their energy index and simulate them that way so that they get
simulated first, right?
That's when we do it and then when we when we actually get to them
here, we wouldn't simulate them.
So we would take the code out of here and just do it right here.
Now, I don't actually know whether I should me.
I don't actually know what I think about that.
I think what I'm going to do for now is keep everything in the same
Loop, that feels a little bit better to me.
Potentially just seems a little more rational.
So I think what I'm going to do is I'm literally just going to go
ahead and do it right here.
And then later on, I'm hoping that as we go further into the final
code.
Like, as we get further down the line, it will become obvious.
Some point later in time how exactly we want to do this, right?
So, I don't want to thank overthink it right.
Since looking through four elements in an array or five elements in
arrays so cheap, I think I'm just going to do that.
And then later on, we'll see if there's a more elegant solution to the
problem when things are a little more settled.
So I'm going to go ahead and see about the control index here.
I'm going to go through basically all of the controlled Heroes.
And I'm going to say, let's let's take a look at the controlled hero.
Everyone.
It was here.
I don't know if you can hear it.
It's so loud.
There's so much construction here in Seattle, like they're building so
many buildings.
There's there's Towers going up all around me.
You can hear Construction.
Everywhere.
All right.
Anyway, so I'm just going to look and see if the entity index
Right of this time hero equals the entities storage Index, right?
So basically, if this controlled hero is controlling the same hero
that I am then, that's right, that's how I know how to actually do,
his move call.
So once we get that con hero out, then I pretty much know all the
parameters that we were using before, they're just going to grab it
right out of the con hero here.
And then the only thing that I need to do that we weren't we didn't
use to do in here and of course we actually don't need any of this.
This stuff anymore, the low sword stuff we can just get the the sword
directly, right?
That's going to be kind of the sword equals.
What's our Sim region call we need a zit.
It's it's get entity by storage in deck so we don't even need to do
that.
We actually did a bunch of cool stuff here.
We don't need to do any of this garbage, right?
That's just done all we need to do now is it?
We just
The Entity.
It just has a sword pointer right?
It's just got one.
That's it.
So we just look to see if it's got a sword pointer.
If he has a sword at all we're done.
We don't have to do any of that stuff.
We don't do any of this stuff.
This is great.
See how these some regions are going to be so good.
So people weren't so sure about the same regions.
I understand your apprehension.
We are trying.
We're doing a lot of tricky things with the code or try and do a lot
of tricky things, and it's hard to make them all to satisfy all the
constraints.
Again, we are picking
Finally, much harder problems than we need to solve so that we can
show how to do them.
But it's really cool.
When stuff works out, when you can satisfy those constraints and still
make the code simple, and I really do think we're getting closer
there.
That doesn't, it's not going to be the final thing, right?
Like probably a little bit further down the line, we'll have another
Epiphany and we'll all be like we can do this cooler thing.
That's even more cool with the way the same regions work or replace it
with this better concept, but, you know, you can't always jump right
to the end.
You have to kind of go.
That process and that's one of the big things I want to show on the
stream was going through that process so people could see that that's
how it is.
A lot of times you read something on the web and they're like, here's
how we solve the problem and they just show the solution.
But that doesn't help you get better at solving your own new problems.
And so this is really the kind of thing that I want to do and look at
how nice this is coming out.
Now, now we've you just use pointers, you can just point to things
directly, which is how you would want to write it originally.
Instead of having all of these low high indices that you had to
manage.
And so what we're doing here
Here is, we're getting back to the nice simple way of programming
while still satisfying, all the constraints that we had, which, you
know, we're pretty tough.
That, that sort of imply, you can't use pointers in that you can't use
floats, and that sort of thing, we're getting that back while still
retaining, the things that would have caused us not to be able to use
those originally and that's exactly what we want, right?
We want to get back to having the simplest possible code be totally
just writable.
Still having all of these things that you wouldn't have gotten.
If you had just written that simple code.
And I think that's what the same region starting to let us do and I'm
really excited about that.
So so we don't care about any of this stuff.
Now it's just this right?
But we need to I guess we still need to set its position like so so
basically the entities position and the swords position are going to
get set like like so,
And we don't care about this at all.
So that is how that works.
Oops.
And then we also have to put our jump stuff in there.
Here's our hero, we have to put our jump stuff in there, which is to
say that in addition to moving the entity, there we had a thing where
we said we wanted a DZ and so I think that's just on the entity as
well.
So there's a d z, so we'll go ahead and, and set that.
Now, yeah, we didn't actually have any logic for our jump code yet.
So that's okay.
That will just stay the way.
And let's see what's going on here.
So this stuff that goes away.
Sim region Sim Arena's Undeclared.
That's true.
We haven't dealt with that yet, so we'll do it that a little bit
later.
And a tea Undeclared identifier, that's a Sim entity.
Obviously High entity is not, and we don't need any of this anymore.
That goes away.
We're strictly working on the things in the same region.
Right?
Hi.
Entity Z.
That's just going to be entity.
See, let's take a look here.
This is just going to be the
Same direction again.
All of these things.
Just get simplified.
It's now, just, again, looking a lot more.
Like the code, you could just write directly.
If you didn't have to worry about all these ants like constraints
which again is really good.
I think that's what that's what I wanted and we're starting to get
there.
So let's see, controlling entity canio Undeclared identifier.
So we this is just the entity that were on, that were simulating.
Getting down last.
You compile errors, lookin good people.
So the move entity call, we need to pass the same region to that.
Right.
Let's see functions.
Not take six arguments.
How many does it take?
Move into T?
Sim reach in move into T, it takes the same region, doesn't take the
game State.
That's all.
Okay, so we have our sward, that's another similarity.
you calling it, Eddie I'm thinking the fact that type entity so often
suggest to me that I probably should just rename Sim entity to entity
because it's our primary entity type now and like I was trying to be a
little more clear about the fact that it was for the same region only
but that's the only place where ever going to Opportunities.
Everything else is just for energy storage.
So I
Probably should just rename it entity because I think that's why I
type all the time, and you've seen me type it so many times.
Instead of the right thing, I feel like we should probably say that
that this should just become entity.
So, let's do a to do Casey, renamed, Sim entity to entity, right?
Alright, so we got that Arena stuff to deal with which we're going to
deal with.
I want to keep that to the end because I want to talk about that a
little bit.
For drawing the hip points.
I think we still just draw just the entity itself.
Update sword and update, familiar are the to update and also update
monster things that we have to actually go and do.
Now, these are all all of this stuff is off the entity itself, like
so.
And there we go, let's see here.
Anything else update monstar?
This is just going to draw the hit points.
I think we're all good.
I think we're down to just the simmer Inna and the to update calls.
So, now to get those update calls in, I'm just going to go ahead and
take that.
I had that handmade entity, right?
I've got the those in here.
I'm going to go ahead and bring those into the build by lb including
them, right?
Like so like I said, we compile everything.
This is one Chunk, we don't, we don't compile multiple files.
So I'm just going to go ahead and bring those in.
And now they're in.
And so now we just have to pour it this old code that we had.
And for now, I think that should just work.
We don't really need the game State anymore.
I think we just used the same region, right?
Like so.
And then we've got our Sim entity like this and then the entity we
don't need to sort of grab it anymore.
The Familiar is looping over everything in that same region.
So this is just going to be a test entity Index, right?
This is looping over everything.
And this is not probably how we want to do it eventually.
So we wanted to put it to do in here that says, make spatial queries
easy for things so that we can do a spatial query here and not have to
go through this Loop sort of stuff.
But again, that's a little premature because we're we haven't quite
gotten to too much of our logic stuff yet in the end of these,
So basically we have a test entity that's going to start at the
beginning of the Sim region enemies.
And then we're just going to go through all of the entities that are
in there.
Just the whole entity count and it's going to look for anything that
it thinks it might want to follow.
That's how our familiar was working.
And again, we just want to the reason I'm marking that because we
don't want to Loop over all the entities ever really even in the same
region for an individual.
We want to be able to call some queries that we can accelerate because
we know lots of people are going to want to do.
Do that.
And we just want to make that all kind of Consolidated into one place
so that we can speed it up when when the time comes to kind of get
perf out of it and so on but all right, so when we do this, we've got
our update, familiar call, it was looping over.
Things at that point, we had a closest hero, the closest Heroes, just
going to be a pointer now because we don't need to store a lows and
highs and all this other garbage, which again, is great.
I really like how this is cleaning up.
We had the closest hero D'squared, we're doing the all these, the same
checks just to see.
And I think we did do pull speed out of move entity.
That's the move spec thing, so we did do that, so that's good.
And think that's about
It it so that just has to call the move entity, call to update his
position.
Excuse me.
That looks about right.
Let's take a look again.
That's amenity.
I'm going to enjoy, renaming that.
I think I'm going to enjoy reading these get rid of those High
pointers.
So again this all we're really doing is deleting the old code that was
dealing with that crufty combination of things.
So, default moves back.
We got a, I think we still got that still in here.
We want to move that out.
And that's just it going to be entity data.
They're basically so we'll leave that in there update monstar we
haven't written yet.
That's pretty easy, but we know, we'll take the same region for sure.
It'll basically just look at the same.
As the other calls like this entity.
We had our sword code which basically moved the sword.
Right there, was nothing particularly odd going on there.
And this stuff we basically had a way that it could become after a
while.
Become it would not exist anymore for all intents and purposes and so
we don't really have that concept.
Cept yet.
So we'll have to deal with that maybe as the first thing, maybe as a
kind of the next thing that we do in terms of tracking entities in the
same region, right?
We need some way.
In fact, you know what I'll do.
I'll just place it assert in here.
Assert need to make entities be able to not be there her.
I don't know.
Not sure it will call that.
You know what I'm saying, though?
All right, so let's see.
Entity hypey, don't need high.
No mo.
There we go.
And then we Lo, we don't need any more either, that's all in there.
All right, all right.
So I think thats good Diesel.
Take the same region.
Now, same region some region, and I think we're now back to where we
were.
Okay, so we have a couple things that we still have to do so inside
our handmade same region.
We do have some to dues that have to get done these two right here.
We got to clear the hash table and then we have to work on that apron
stuff which
I'll also dovetail with the sore thing.
But first things first, we now need a place to store the stuff that we
do.
In the same region and this is the first time that I'm going to
introduce this.
So I thought I might take a second and talk about it just so, it's
clear, right?
I'm gonna blow my nose first.
Hmm.
Sickness.
all right, so
Here we are at a 65 right?
Which is 65 hours into the coding of handmade here slaven.
Got into two weeks of coding yet.
So we're actually very early in the development of this game.
If you think about it, two weeks of coding is hardly any coding most
games have many, many, many, many, many, many, many men weeks of
developing in them.
So here we are on basically what is our 65 or so we had a couple extra
hours in there somewhere.
So it's probably more like our
9 or 70.
but if you will remember,
Way back at the beginning.
I said, we have two memory blocks and in fact, I'll draw them
separately because the game doesn't actually know if they're even
continuous.
Right?
We have the permanent store, right?
This on this side.
We have permanent but we have the permanent block.
Right.
That's all that, right?
It's a knee right?
Yeah, permanent block and we have the transient block.
Now, so far we've only ever used the permanent block, right?
And we put like our entities in there, right?
And we put our game state in there and it makes sense.
Right?
Because that's the stuff that actually needs to persist from frame to
frame.
And if we're going to save the game, most of it would be stuff that
we'd save as well.
Although, I don't know what we'd save it out as a block, but, you
know,
But we never use this and you might ask like why was it there?
And the answer is because now we're actually starting to get into
pieces of code that are going to want it.
What the transient block is for is a transient block is just a scratch
Pad essentially where things that only are used for calculation.
Go.
And so what we do is, we're going to divide this up in some ways right
into basically chunks.
And what we're going to do is during processing of a frame.
We're going to allow things to essentially just grab a region of it,
use it to do all their calculations and then get rid of it all when
it's done, right?
So it's basically just a scratch Pad, right?
For this sort of thing.
So this the simmer Inna is about the same region is a perfect example
of how this would work.
What we can do is we can just grab a pointer to a to a chunk, the Sim
region can just start throwing things into that show.
Unk, as much as it wants.
Then when it's done we just vaporize it.
We just say the whole thing is gone.
Right.
So it's basically just a stack that gets cleared at the end of the
processing.
And again the reason that I think this is so important is because a
lot of people, the overwhelming majority of people write code, that's
basically like this this this spider web of pointers write, they write
code where they've got you know the entity has like pointers to other
entities, right?
And then like they've got pointers to like their Sim state or
something and then like there's like you know all of
Is all of this stuff and then there's the tiles, right?
And those Point entities, and all these sorts of things and they, they
allocate when they allocate stuff, they allocate it.
Create these, these sort of morasses, and then when they free it, they
walk them and they do these fries.
Okay, this guy'll free, you know, this guy says free.
So he tells this guy to free and then this guy says to free this guy
and then it walks back up and all this sort of stuff, right?
And they do that whether its permanent stuff or not, right?
So they write this kind of code where you're doing this kind of crazy
destruction.
Even if all of this stuff was only transient for a bunch of
computations like in the case of the same region where all of its only
there just to do our calculations what you'd much rather do is do all
of this stuff in a scratch Pad.
So this is all in some memory segments somewhere, right?
Will you do it all?
And then you never have to care about crawling this list.
Again, you never during shutdown.
There's nothing to shut down.
You just say it all goes away, bam gone.
And that way.
There's no allocation cost and there's no deallocation cost, they're
just gone, right?
Allocation is just incrementing an integer and deallocation is
nothing.
There's little or nothing.
You just don't think about the region anymore, there's nothing to it,
right?
And that's really a much much much.
Much, much much
Much much much better way to write this kind of code.
You can't leak memory anymore and you pay no cost, no performance cost
for it.
So, anything that you can write in this fashion, you want to the only
time you should ever write that morass.
Spidery Crawley thing is, if you actually need that functionality to
be able to delete, just a small portion of collected entities, or
stuff like that.
And the vast majority of systems don't need that functionality
functionality.
So you're you're paying all this cost.
And this is true, whether you're in C or in a garbage collected
language in the garbage collected language, that's where all your
garbage collector.
Proof goes right.
Is if you write this code, that is doing all of this sort of spidery
pointer stuff and the garbage collector is then responsible for trying
to figure out how it all gets pulled back out again when you're done
with it that's that same cost, right?
So it doesn't matter what language are in these costs are real
it's just whether you wrote code, that does it, or whether
You let the garbage collector do it.
But in either case it's worked at the CPU should not be doing and so
we don't want to do it.
And so what we're going to do right now is we're going to make it
memory Arena, right?
Because you remember we have these memory Rena's and we're going to
initialize this imerina.
We will do some more fancier stuff of this later but since this is the
only thing that uses our transient thing yet.
It's hard to put that here.
Since this is the only thing that uses our transient Arena.
We don't have to do anything special just yet.
So what we're going to do is initialize that submarine Arena.
We're going to initialize it to the transient Arenas location.
Basically.
Right.
And I can't remember what that was actually called.
Let's take a look in the memory section.
What was it called?
It was called transient storage and transient storage size, right?
So so yeah, so I just want to go ahead and initialize that Arena and
I'm going to go ahead and give it the entire space like so and then
everything can just allocate off of that and when we're done, we
literally don't at this point, have to do anything because basically,
when we're done, we're done.
We just return back to the platform code and the next time through
will initialize the same Arena to point to the bottom of Transit
memory again.
No cleanup at all right.
There's just no cleanup at all.
So, in theory, that's all we need to do for now, they'll be a little
bit more stuff about partitioning later when we have more things using
the transient area.
But for now, that's really it.
So that's all we need to do.
What is this complaining about transient storage?
I see this should really take a void star so you can pass any kind of
memory you want, and then it'll just do its cast since it's the thing
that wants it in a un 8.
So, we'll fix that.
Begin Sim.
I don't actually remember what this takes.
So let's take a look.
You can Sim it is simmer, Inna game state, which I think I said, I
would like to not pass anymore eventually, but the problem is the low
entities are stored there, and then that's it.
All right, begin.
Send must return a value.
That's true.
It must return the same region.
And add into the must return.
A value that is true.
It should return the entity that allocated.
All right, so we got to do a couple things here.
I think the only one we want to do right now is clear that hash table.
But then we have to go through it step through the stuff.
And basically, we've done a pretty major code change.
I'm sure we've made a bunch of mistakes especially because we had to
do it over, you know, normally I would do this whole code change in
the space of one block of time at work, but since we only have an hour
per stream and I'm talking
in the whole time, A lot of times we have to spread it out across
Couple days and because of that we may have made some oversight swear.
Like I forgot to change something or we said we were going to change
something and didn't
So, we definitely need to kind of go through now.
What all the stuff we did.
Maybe maybe we'll step through everything once and just remind
ourselves whether we've done everything that we thought we were going
to do whether we actually implemented it or whether we just cheese it
out before we start to bugging in Earnest.
Because, you know that I think it's just going to be a good idea to
just make sure there was nothing obvious that we left out in a remind
ourselves, all the stuff that we changed.
So when we do this, push struct here, I'm pretty sure that push truck
Well, clear, that hash table for us or they'll?
Let's double check and see if it does.
Well, the hash is actually in there directly.
So let's take a look here.
Handmade, uh, let's see about the push struct.
Push struct push truck does a push size and push Size, Doesn't do a
clear.
So we want to do a clear here and we don't actually have a clear call
yet, so I think I might do an inline clear call.
Also, this should be, these are all should be in lines.
They don't do anything.
So they
These will be things that should be put straight into the code,
probably.
So I'm going to do a zero size call, basically something that just
takes a pointer, right and a size and just players it, right.
So it's basically something that just says while there is some size
left to do just you know just clear it.
Like so, so we basically have un8 star b equals pointer and this is a,
you know, something that we probably will do a bunch of.
So check this guy for performance because we may want to clear.
We want to write zeros and bigger blocks and do, we might want to do
some fancier stuff there.
Eventually, if this ends up being something, we call it a bunch of
places to clear things to 0, right?
So that's just something that we want to be able to do, right?
So all I'm doing here is I'm just spinning over all of the bye.
Right?
One at a time in whatever block this is clearing them 20 and that's
it, right?
So if this comes in and size was already zero, it'll do a while sighs
sighs is zero so it just won't enter this loop at all.
If it doesn't for the loop it will decrement it each time through
until it gets to zero and clear as many bytes as are there.
All right.
So what I want to do is I want to zero size.
This guy, this hash, right?
And so what I think I'm going to do is just make a convenient thing.
Since I want to do that occasionally, I want to do something I can
just do 0 struct, right?
And I can pass something that I want 0 like this.
So I can just say, OK, clear that whole hash out?
So I want to do is do a pound of 50 struck.
Just like we did up here, which is just a macro that takes some some,
some instance of a struct, right?
And basically, it just says, okay, what I want you to do is call zero
size, don't need that semicolon call zero size with just whatever the
size of the thing is that we're talking about and then the address of
it.
So, just clear it out as a whole block, right?
And that'll work to do that.
Clear?
So that'll clear our hash table for us.
And now I think we've done all the things that we knew that we had to
do that.
We can remember.
Anyway so now might be a good time to again sort of step in there and
see what's going on.
There's one more thing which is I don't know if we ever end the Sim.
We don't.
So what we want to do?
Oh no, we do.
Okay, so we want to do is just make sure that happens, but looks like
it does happen.
Okay, so let's go ahead and do the rest of what we need to do here,
which is actually debug this.
I'm going to go ahead and just step in right from the start to to sort
of go through all of our code again and see what happens.
Now, we didn't touch the adding code, the adding code still works
basically exactly the same way.
So I think that should be fine.
So I'm going to skip over just the adding code and assume that that's
still okay.
Maybe we broke something in there as well.
We'll find out that we can really touch that code much.
So I don't think I need to step through it will just a bug that code
regularly.
So what I'll do here is I'll just go ahead and start stepping in right
at the point where we actually start the simulation part of things if
that makes sense.
So we initialize our Arena.
This is where we're going to be able to store all the stuff that
happens in our Sim.
Oh, hey, look, we're just at the end.
All right, I started 10 minutes late, so really, we've got another ten
minutes.
After the five-minute warning.
So we go into the same region.
Here we go.
We're going to get outs from our Arena.
We're going to get the size of the struct.
And so now we've got one of these.
I don't like the locals window.
I'm going to get rid of that.
Someone had asked me a question about it.
Separately off stream and I wanted to double-check that the answer I
gave them was right so let's get rid of that I'ma watch window kind of
person.
Okay, so we got the same region.
We cleared out our hash table or at least we think we did.
We weren't really able to know till we look, come around the next
time, anyway, because it would have been zero already, but we
initialize some stuff inside the Sim region.
So we set the world pointer we set the origin to like we're we're
simulating around and let's let's take a look at what that origin
actually was.
Okay, so the origins just straight up zeros.
We set the bounds which there we go.
That's just our camera.
Which looks about right, then we set up our entities.
So we're basically going to grab an array with the maximum amount of
entities that we wanted to store this information, which we haven't
really talked about yet.
And
Really care about at this point but you know, later on, we might do
something about that.
So we can store up to 4,000 is entities in this Sim region and then
let's go ahead and take a look here and say, all right, we've got them
in chunk p and the max chunk P.
That's the region that we're simulating.
This is the same code as before.
So we're assuming that it still works.
Okay.
And I don't think there would be much of a problem with that.
Looks like it does.
So we iterate over that.
We get out our world chunks and any chunks that have something in it.
We're going to go ahead and process so we're kind of doing that now
and I'd like to take a look at.
Okay, so we found some entities here in the world.
One of our world chunks, had some stuff in it, so we're going to go
ahead and see what entity it is.
It's entity, 40, we grab out the stored version of that entity, which
is here, which basically has a SIM thing in it.
It's a wall or in our case,
Actually a tree, but we haven't really done that stuff in the end of
these yet.
But yeah, it's a wall tree.
So we go ahead and figure out where that is relative to our Sim
region.
Let's step into that code, we take where the origin of our world.
We make that difference which looks reasonable as far as I can tell
anyway, and so that becomes our Sim Space location, we get that out
once.
We have it, we check to see whether it's inside the bounds of the
camera which it is.
So then we're going to go ahead and add the entity, right?
So we come in, here we go.
Ahead and add that entity, and this is our two-tiered call.
The one that takes a position.
So it's going to call down to the next tier, which is the lowest level
entity addition call.
It goes ahead and checks to make sure that we've got room in the same
region for it.
We go ahead and grab out which whichever one it is an increment that
any account.
So we now are storing one entity in our Sim region.
We're going to initialize the entry in the hash table so that we can
This entity again from its storage index.
So again, we go in to do our mapping call, our mapping call gets that
entry, right?
Which computes the hash value, which right now is just the storage
index.
We don't do anything fancy there and we step through our hash table,
grabbing out the things one at a time.
Now what I probably should have done and in fact since this is the
first time into this code I'm just going to go ahead and do it.
I'll set a breakpoint here.
I'll stop the code.
I want to go.
I want to go to make one change there because I want to be able to
inspect those values and I can't right now because of the way that I
typed in the code I don't like that.
What I want to be able to do is I want to be able to look at the hash
index that we compute after we do this this offset process, right?
I want to look at that just so I can be able to see it in the
debugger, right?
And maybe we'll also go one step further and and compute that mask
separately.
So I can hand verify
By that as well.
And again, this is just making it so that I can
Verify my code more easily when I stepped in the debugger and make it
easier on myself because compiler is going to do the substitution of
these anyway.
So it doesn't really matter how they're set up in that sense.
So we're going to make sure we have the hash mask, right.
We're going to make sure that we have that hash Index, right?
I just wanted to make sure that those were clear.
Okay, so we go ahead and run back to that point.
This is where we were so our hash mask is
Like so, oops, Ash mask.
And if we take a look at that, you can see that it masks out the part
that we wanted, which is good.
And then we compute our hash index, which is also should just be those
little bits for T.
It is like I said, we started about 10 minutes late, so we'll go about
10 minutes late, just to keep with an hour of coding, even.
All right?
So we find a particular entry and there's nothing in it, right?
The, which is what we expect.
So,
Go ahead.
Excuse me.
We go ahead and return that out.
And so now, this person out here now knows that the entry is either 0
or the thing they were looking for.
In either case regardless, it's going to overwrite that storage index
because it knows that either it was 0 or the storage that it was
affecting and then it's going to go ahead and put that entity in
there.
So either, it's just over writing exactly what was already there or
it's going ahead.
And
And actually putting in a new one.
So that's fine.
Like we don't care whether it was there or not.
We're just going to map it again.
So if we actually got back, if we actually got past some entity that
we're initializing this entity from what we want to do is go ahead and
overwrite the entity that we just created all of its data, right?
Which is which should be nothing at this point.
All of its data is going to get overwritten with what the data is that
we actually had right.
Which is not very much, which is just what that collides because it's
just there's not much data in the in the in the trees.
And then we want to go ahead and load the sword entity reference if it
has one, right?
So if it's got a sword in here, we want to load that in as well.
So we load that in and load any reference we look and see if the
reference is index is nonzero, it's not.
So we just go ahead and continue out.
We're done adding The Entity and that's all we had to do.
So after adding The Entity assuming that we actually were able to add
it successfully, we take a look to see whether or not we got a
position that we were supposed to set for this guy we did so we set it
and now we have set where it is so let's that should actually be set
to something now I believe right?
Okay of course we can't see
It's actually dest.
There we go.
There's our position that looks valid.
So we're done adding it, and then we're just going to go through and
add stuff again.
So let's take a look at when we
We add somebody that actually has a sword for that load entity
reference.
I'll set a breakpoint there.
Oops.
Sorry no the sword one.
Just what I wanted when you actually bring someone into the set.
That oh yeah, that's what I wanted.
So what we want to do is is actually break when that actually becomes
true.
So that would be loading derail it be here, right?
And so, I guess I didn't actually want to run.
I didn't mean to run all the way there.
So let's go ahead and, and, and do that one more time.
I just want to set a breakpoint at that one position so that we would
be able to look at that piece of the code.
All right, so after we add all the entities and we're done there,
right?
So now we've got our enemies added, let's make sure that we have some
reasonable values.
Here, we added 95 entities into our Sim set for the camera region.
Which is basically just all the trees, the monstar.
In the familiar, right?
So in our Sim region, we're going to go ahead and return that out.
We then do some regular drawing code, nothing particular thing there,
we then Loop over the entities in this region.
Oh you know what, I just realized?
We forgot one piece of code already which is that this entity pointer
doesn't get updated.
Oops.
That's a bit of an oops.
It's true.
We made an oops.
All right.
So this entity pointer right here needs to get updated each time
through the loop.
Right?
We're stepping through that Loop.
So, let's go ahead and compile that so that we're not stepping through
a totally bogus version of our code.
We don't care about this anymore.
We already step through that.
So we kind of know what's going on in there for now.
We'll step back into it when something's broke.
Once we see what's broke.
So now we're stepping through
the update code for enemies.
So we go through here, we switch the entity type, we find that there's
it's a wall.
So, basically walls just draw stuff.
So, that's really not that interesting.
Here are some update code.
We should probably move this to another location.
Now, that should probably move entity, right?
So we go ahead and do our standard drawing code.
I don't think this really doesn't involve The Entity so much, so
really what we're looking for is we're probably looking to take
We're probably looking to get into a position where we're actually
going to update someone with with some kind of logic, right?
And the monster doesn't have any yet.
So let's go ahead and wait till we actually have one of those.
So there we go.
So if we update familiar that's actually got some logic to it.
So when we come in here, then we have our update, familiar call.
What we're going to do is say, all right, we're going to Loop over all
the entities and just see if we can find any Heroes.
Now, we shouldn't find hero because
There haven't been the player hasn't joined yet, so we shouldn't find
a hero so we should skip over this entirely and then the move spec.
When we pass this GDP the DDP should be 0 which
Is we come into the move function, we're going to enforce a unit Max
acceleration vector, that's fine.
This is fine.
The end of the doesn't Collide does it or it does Collide.
It does Collide.
So now we're testing over all of the entities in the, the test region,
right?
So that's pretty straightforward.
We're just testing all of those things in the test region.
So we'll go ahead and finish that out.
We don't have a spatial partition yet so it's just manually.
Testing them all, which is not very efficient, but
Again for only ninety five.
Entities processors are so fast these days you don't even see, it's
crazy how fast they are.
It is crazy.
How fast computers are?
You wouldn't know it if you used a, you know.
Typical desktop application.
You'd be like, how is it managing to be this slow?
And somehow they managed.
So, alright, we go ahead and do update.
Familiar was not very interesting.
All right, so we've got a problem in.
Where is this happening?
Oh, this is happening at the very end, we already wait.
So we didn't actually ever hit.
Oh, that's right because there's no Heroes at it.
I was like, how come we never saw the hero updates like because we
haven't actually joined the game yet.
All right.
So it looks like we step through everything except for the N Sim and
we're
Assertion in there.
Anyway.
So we kind of know.
We got to debug that one way or the other.
So let's go ahead and finish stepping through everything.
Let's step through that end Sim.
So how is that going to work?
So similarity.
We go through, we grab where we're going to store it back to.
We do store it back right?
And so that's fine.
Then we have to convert our entity references back.
So let's go ahead and make sure that that works logically.
So we've got stored Sim sword, right?
That's so it's got nothing in it so that doesn't actually matter, it's
not going to actually update will have to do that once we actually
have a sword.
Someone with a sword.
So then we're going to take a new position by mapping an old position
into chunks Pace, right?
So we've got an entity P, which is here is a position.
We've got a region origin.
We're going to map these in.
So when we do the map into chunks space, that will go ahead and do
the, the offset from whatever the base was, and then it'll re
canonicalize it so results.
Let's see here.
This may just be a bug in our old code, actually, we may not, this may
not be an actual bug that in our Sim region code.
we never really even went in here and did our
a final version.
Don't get sick.
Kids, it's not fun.
All right.
So inside re canonicalize coordinates, we basically created a thing,
that's got some offsets to it and now we want to go ahead and re
canonicalize that.
So we step in here what it's going to do.
Is it's going to do that, divide to figure out what the integer offset
is the integer offset is 0.
It's the then going to take a look at that sort of quote, unquote tile
index, which is really now, a chunk indexes.
You probably rename these.
So what have we got there?
That's also zero.
So that's not going to change and then the tile relative version is
just going to be whatever it was before - the adjustment.
Right.
So there it is.
And then we're going to take a look and see if that's canonical in
order to be canonical.
You've got to be half chunks Ida M.
Which in this case, we are so somebody who's getting mapped back into
this space is in an unhappy situation for some reason.
And I'm not sure why.
So, we'll have to go through and it looks like because that looks like
it's working properly.
So we'll have to see exactly who it is.
And what's going on with them.
All right, so we're getting a non-canonical on this guy.
What is the world chunk side and M?
Check side in meters.
It's twenty two point, three nine, nine, nine and six.
So this looks like just a sort of this looks like a float Precision
bug to me because the tile relative is right on the edge of that.
So I wonder if this was just a case of this not picking up exact the
exact right number to do, right?
I mean, look at these two numbers are suspiciously close together so I
feel like this is just a case of the mapping not quite working
properly.
but, at the same time, what I am interested about is that Rica
nautical eyes,
Mmm-hmm, I'm trying to think if I care about this at all, I don't
really think that I do.
Let's go out here and check.
So, back in the store or thing, here, we can take a look at the entity
structure will not have had any mapping done to it.
So we can kind of see what we had here.
This was the location of the end of the 33 - 11 and so we want to do
is map that back into the chunks.
By taking those offsets.
So I think what we're seeing here is just a slight error in basically
when you're right on the edge of something that's being mapped in,
You just get a little float Precision.
That's what it looks like to me.
Anyway, meaning this divide is not perfectly going to round out
exactly right.
So it looks like it's just that is canonical, has to be a little bit
more have to be a little bit more flexible and allow a little bit
further off than exactly on.
Right?
Because that's really, really close to what it should be.
So I think that's I think that's basically what's going on here.
So I'm going to say that we're just going to leave that for now rather
than looking into it again because I'm pretty sure that's what
That is, and I don't want to go down the floating Point, Precision.
Rathole.
Just yet, we already have, but to do in here, that talks about that.
So I guess what I'd say is, we'd need an Epsilon here for now.
Right.
Which again, isn't great.
But, you know, we can basically say that, you know, within some
Precision, we're okay, if these things are basically a little bit off.
So, if you basically say, you know, - plus Epsilon, as long as
It's got its, you know, it's pretty close math, wise will treat it
that way.
And then later on, when we come back through here, we can think about
the floating-point a little bit more and make sure that we don't have,
you know, that we are as accurate as possible.
All right?
So
Surprisingly, that actually looks like it's sort of working.
Let's go ahead and, and take a look here at what happens?
Oops, we got some kind of a problem there with the hero we haven't
centered the camera.
On well I guess I don't know why the camera is looking where it is
looking right now, to be honest.
So that's a little odd like I don't know if we've got some kind of a
bug with where things are located, because I don't really know where
the origin is.
So one thing that might be interesting is, let's go ahead and check
that out actually.
Let's do something where we draw where we think the origin is relative
to the camera, right?
Just just, I just
Reference point.
So what I'm thinking is if we just take something where we do that
diff right and we do a draw, a rectangle.
So look at the very end after all this
I want to do a draw a rectangle, we're at basically draw something
that's, you know I don't know, a ten by ten little rectangle in there,
don't like this.
That's just going to be, you know, a bright yellow rectangle that I
can see.
I'm going to go ahead and draw that at where I think things are in the
world, right?
And so this is going to be my origin and my Origins going to be that
that basically that that
If I'm just going to say, let's see, where is it?
It's it's get gets him space, p we go.
I want.
Get some space pee on my SIM region.
Oh I guess I can't quite do that because that takes an enemy.
So what I actually want is this subtract some region world and my
stored P which would be whatever the some region origin I guess that's
not really what I owe.
Yes it is what I want.
So what I want is a world position that's just
the origin, right?
So I want that.
So that's the world origin.
I'm going to pass that and say, tell me where the world origin is
relative to the Sim region the camera, basically, right?
And then that will give me the inside the diff the point that I want
to draw, right?
So that's what I want to do.
I just want to see where that origin is.
And I don't see anything.
So I so I think oh it's the upper left corner, so that's interesting.
I think we may have to call it because I think we're out of time.
Yes, we are.
So I guess what I'll do is, I'll stop here.
That's where we'll pick up Monday.
So, we've got a couple to dues but mostly our stuff work.
So I think we're pretty close.
But we've got two more things to do.
Figure out why the origin is where it is.
So that's one thing we want to do, right?
And then the other.
So we just going to straighten out our origin situation.
That might just be the way it's supposed to work.
I have to think about that but we'll take a look at it more closely.
So figure out where the origin is, where it is think that through and
the other thing we need to do is we've got we've got this when we
actually add a hero in here.
We've got a problem there.
We want to see what that problem is.
And I think that's just the sword basically when we when we go ahead
and get that, I'm pretty sure that that's just the sword causing
problems because we haven't added.
We basically have an added, an actual location for things that don't
exist in the world at the moment.
Right in the sword, is something that comes in that way.
So if you take a look at the, at the entity, the sort of me, I guess
this would, this should be the sort of
City that we're looking at, right?
Yeah, it is the sword.
And so if we take a look at the sword, we should see that.
Basically we've got some kind of nasty.
Where's where's the store identity for the sword?
There we go.
So yeah.
So it's got an invalid location and we don't handle things with
invalid locations yet.
So that's there are other to do that.
We've got to do.
So these are our two importance, right?
Let's go ahead and put those out there.
Add logic to the Sim region to handle unplaced entities.
And that's honestly, it looks like we don't have much, much more to
go.
So I think we're pretty good.
That was much less the bugging than I was expecting for such a big
change.
So, I'm feeling pretty happy about that.
I'm pretty happy about that.
But let's go ahead and get to the Q&A.
Got about 15 minutes of Q&A here.
So, if you could please,
Your question with Q: so I can see it.
And also, if you could, please make it so that your questions are
pertaining to something that we've done today or on a previous stream
if you want to ask off-topic questions or questions about what we're
going to do in the future, please save those for the pre stream.
So come about 15 minutes before a stream starts.
And that's a good place to ask though because we answer off-topic
questions at that point.
So, there you go.
Okay, the Bots back.
Assuming we don't go wandering too much on our own which week has
accumulated enough code base for a basic simple, fully functional
game.
None.
We're nowhere near that yet.
We will, we will probably be.
So if you think about mapping hours, right?
If you think about mapping hours, basically a week of programming time
is, is 40 hours, right?
At least if you're doing a standard work week of programming, right?
So if you look at where we are day 65, that's essentially 65 hours in.
Maybe it's a little like I said, most 70 70 hours in.
If you count a couple of week days we went a little long, right?
So
Hours in here would be week.
One of programming here would be weak to, right?
So you start the project here.
This is the start of the project.
We have done this week's worth of coding and we are almost, we're
like, you know, I don't know.
A little bit further down than that, we're here on week 2.
So we haven't even programmed for two weeks on this game yet.
So we're nowhere near like I would expect that probably fully
functional game is somewhere down here, right?
Where we're like totally happy with our engine stuff.
So we'd have this week next week, right?
This week, this week or something.
So I would expect, you know, we'd be somewhere down here.
Would be like engine, you know?
So yeah, so we got a long, way to go, unless your definition of fully
functional is very different from mine.
Regarding high and low entities.
With the following solution work using one entity struct.
All entities are stored in one array and frequently update the entity
if the entity is within camera bounds and use low frequency updating,
if it's outside the camera bounds,
So that is sort of what we're doing at the moment, but we the reason
that I didn't use it, so that it just isn't place, right?
The same region.
If I understand you correctly, you're sort of asking the question.
Could the simulation regions really just look, just just point
directly into the end of the array and update them there and the
answer is yes, we could do that.
There's a reason I don't want to do that but we haven't gotten to it
yet.
Basically, what I don't want to do is I don't want to say that the
actual thing that we store all the time is The Entity structure that
people actually operate on.
There's a very, very good reason that I don't want to do that but we
haven't quite gotten there yet.
Um, and so, you'll have to wait a little further down the line when I
actually go through.
I have a bunch of stuff I want to talk about in terms of entity Sim
reasons.
I don't want to do that but it would work.
I just don't think it would work for what we eventually want to do
because I want to do stuff.
That's a lot more complicated and any wise than what we're doing now
in terms of what sorts of code you can do and so there's reasons why I
don't want to do that, but if your entities were very simple there
then you could totally do that.
Like if they were just as, if you were making, you know, even even if
you were doing a probably even a straight Binding of Isaac clone, you
could totally do that because their entities are just not that
complicated.
So you won't need to worry about some of the things that I'm want to
do due to how complex.
I think our entities will get in terms of all the stuff they can do
gameplay wise.
So yes, I don't think there's anything wrong with solution, you're
proposing.
I don't think it would work for what I want to do, but what I want to
do, is more complicated than what a lot of games gameplay wise than
what a lot of games have.
And so if your game doesn't have that complexity, then there's no
reason you couldn't do that because, like right now, we already are
using once, like, we already are just using one entity struct, right?
It's just this, it's just some entity, but what we're doing is when we
store it back,
Copy it into here.
So you could just be using one if you want to.
But I think it's going to get there's going to be another step later
down the line and you'll see why I want to do it this way at that
point, I want to keep that flexibility of having to storage States.
Can you give a high level overview of how entities work?
Now I get in and I get in bits and pieces but this week has lost me
sure.
Let's go ahead and do that.
all right, so essentially what we've got
Excuse me, because we have a world.
Right.
And our world right now is separated into two pieces in some sense to
logical pieces, right?
There's the geographic piece, right?
So here is the geography of the world.
And this is stored as a sparse map.
So basically, there's tile chunks, right?
That sort of say where there's actually stuff in the world?
And the reason that we do that is because the world except
expansiveness is actually much more massive than you could ever store
at a computer.
So, we only want to store the places where it actually exists and if
it ends up being sort of long and skinny and snakes through places, we
don't want to pay for storing them as a giant block.
We want to like not store all these are
Is where there isn't stuff.
So we don't pay the cost, right?
These are the tile chunks that we have, right?
It's a stupid name.
Did we rename it to World chunk because it should be renamed World
chunk.
But I don't remember if we actually did that, I hope we did but
sometimes we don't have time to do all the name.
Yeah, so it's just World shock, right?
So let's let's rename that right.
It's, these are the world chunks, right?
Like this.
Now we have so to bar.
So this is the geography, right?
And then we also have another thing which is an array of entities and
this is sort of our logic, right?
So, The Logical stuff basically has an array.
You know, some big long array of entities and each one of these
entities store is a bunch of stuff in it, right?
So entity 0 is the nullity entity one, entity through entity n, right?
Like so and so these are our enemies.
These are stored in the game state right now.
So this is gamestate low entities, right?
And this is in the world.
This is the game state.
World.
So this is how we're storing things.
Currently what happens is, when we actually want to update something,
we pick a region of the world in that region can be any rectangle.
And we then say this becomes a Sim region.
Write this rectangle that rectangle gets mapped out.
Like so.
And what it does is it iterates over the tile chunks that are inside
that region, right?
So, it grabs out these individual top chunks that fall within the
simulation region.
That simulation region is larger than the camera, so that the camera
is basically seeing this, this is the camera area.
But we're actually doing a larger region, so the camera actually maps
to a smaller area of that.
Right.
The tile chunks that are involved here, right?
Kind of map in like this, some of them are filled, some of them are
not.
So, you know, some of these are filled, some of these are not okay,
and for each child chunk, that actually is filled.
We then look at what entities are in there.
The entities are stored in the the entities are stored by index which
entities are in which tile chunks.
So we just go through each tile chunk and we say what are the entities
that are in there and for every tile chunk, right?
So basically, every tile chunk, there's this list of entity indexes.
Right.
Doo doo.
They're in here those entity indexes, right?
They point back into something in here they're just they're just a
number which says which of the entities we want.
So for the same region on Startup, we Loop through these.
We see which ones we've got for each one that we've got.
We then Loop through the entity indices and we pull out of this array,
right?
We pull them out and then we put them into our Sim region stack,
So we basically have this is the entity
This is Sim region.
And he's right.
So we pull them out into here.
So now we have all of our entities that are involved, just the subset
that are in this region, they're all stacked up in here, right?
They all stopped store the index where they came from so that they can
write back into it if they want to so on.
Begin Sim, that's what we're doing.
We grab them all out.
They all come in here.
When we're done, we then write them back, right?
So essentially what I could do is say this is begin Sim
Grabs them in here.
This is ensign.
Writes them back, right?
So, all of the simulation now takes place in this array, it all takes
place in floating Point coordinates relative to the center of this
same region, right?
So that way we a stay in float always, when we're doing our Sim,
right?
No more low positions.
We only deal with that on the map.
So this begin Sim fact, I could say this here so on begin Sim.
Right entity copied into SIM.
Position.
Translated.
To float.
Right.
And then on N Sim.
Oh, and references change to pointers.
Right?
So, like with the sword, for example, when we had the sword slot, it's
storing when it's out in the without in this entity.
It's storing an index into the array of who's the sword was when it's
moved in here, it becomes a pointer, right?
So things that were indexes in here, become pointers and then they,
then they come back, they met back in and then so an instant we do
exactly the opposite, right?
The Entity
Copied to state.
The position.
Translated 2nt.
In + float.
So high res position.
So the low rest position and the ref change changes to back to indices
changed.
Two indices.
Right, that's what we do on N, cm and begins him.
And that's it.
So, all of our simulation happens in this array, right in this sort of
thing where things are just straightforward.
And why do we do that?
We do it.
So we can stay in float and still have giant world's way, way bigger
than could be referenced in floats without losing precision and we
also do it so we can have massive energy counts, right?
Because we only ever simulate a small segment of them.
We don't have to worry about how many there are.
And we can also compress them in here so we can make this be a much
more tighter.
No matter.
How big our Sim state gets four entities.
We don't have to care.
We can store them much smaller than that if we want to and this seems
pretty reasonable to me because then all of the code that we write
will be very simple because it just looks at these entities that are
very simple, they use pointers there.
They don't have they just use pointers and float.
They're very simple.
They're like the code you would write if you didn't have any special
constraints and that mapping in and out is what gets us these things.
So these things come during this mapping in and out.
We don't have to pay for them at any given any other time.
Hopefully that gives you a clear idea what's going on.
I'm not sure I fully caught how short-lived temporary transient memory
is is it only for single frames or longer lived if for longer lived
memory?
How do you make sure you don't wrap around us are overriding memory
still in use, think some homing attack which takes many, many frames
resolved.
So the answer is the transient memory does not last more than a frame.
You can see that right here.
So here's game update and render its called every frame.
We come into game update in render and thus imerina we just sort of
grab it and start writing into it, right?
Nobody ever reads from it.
So there it can't last, right?
The first thing we do inside when we do begin Sim as we just
overwrite, whatever was there, right?
The first thing we do in some region.
Let's see here whereas begin sent you can see him.
You can see the first thing we do is like grab a struct out.
We overwrite we zero the hash table, we overwrite, whatever was there
with new stuff.
Right.
We totally, we just totally romp.
Whatever is there.
So it only lasts just that one frame.
It doesn't in a little tiny last even less than a frame.
Like basically, what we're going to do eventually is it'll only last
between begins him and then Sim the transit memory for the same anyway
and then it will just release that and other people could use it
inside the same frame.
How do you determine, how much time, each some region should be
updated if they aren't updated each frame.
So we haven't quite gotten there yet.
Well, I'm imagining will do is each entity will store its clock
basically and they'll get updated sort of, when you pull out an entity
you'll update for its clock amount.
That's my guess.
But we'll see.
You haven't gotten there yet.
How does the work during this experimental phase fit into the final
code?
Will you be reusing most of it?
Are we starting basically from scratch, the answer is, it doesn't
matter.
Basically what we will do is we will continuously we continuously move
code towards good, right?
And so, when we have things in place that are working, we will just
upgrade those to be industrial strength which basically involves like,
going through all the to dues fixing them and like,
Making sure that eyes are dotted and the t's are crossed.
But in cases where we've done stuff, where we just said, well, we're
assuming we have a thing here that works.
Like the renderer where there really isn't one yet.
We'll have to write a whole system.
We won't really be deleting things though.
In that sense, we won't be like vaporizing stuff and starting over.
Will constantly be we always just move forwards, right?
Alright, I think that's it for questions about stuff.
We've done.
Which is good.
We're right on time.
We are right on time.
So I think we're in really good shape.
I'm pretty happy with this.
I think the same region stuff is good.
I like the way it's going everything about it.
Feels good to me so far.
There's a couple things that I think are going to be tough.
The apron Sim region.
Aprons is really the only thing that I'm super worried about.
So we'll have to see how that goes when we get there.
But, yeah, I love looking at this drawing.
It's already get think this.
Going to be a lot of fun.
Looking at, looking at how this is going.
It's already kind of fun to sort of see the path that things take
through the drawing.
So I'm kind of, I'm kind of psyched that we have found this drawing
package.
That allows us to do that.
I like that.
All right, I'm gonna go ahead and save this off and we are going to
call ourselves done for the day close that down.
And like I said, I think we're good.
I think next week is going to be a good week.
We'll get to do a bunch of stuff and yeah we're going to do a couple
more entity things.
Like I said, we're going to kind of get stuff a little
We'll start doing some Sims multiple some regions and looking at how
to get that working.
Want to get that sort of straightened out, and then we'll move from
there.
We'll probably move on to animation, because that's other big thing
that we haven't tackled yet.
And I want to do that animation sound and then I think it's on to the
renderer.
So, yeah, we got we got some of these stuff to do, then we got to do
go and Tackle animation was going to be a big topic.
Sounds not going to be too big.
Sounds really pretty basic
Writing sound codes is not not too hard, so we'll do some code and
then we can move on to the renderer which is our first really big
engine thing.
So again, looking pretty good to me.
I'm pretty happy with where we are.
No big surprises so far.
I think we're making good time to.
Like I said, only, you know, how many hours were in?
But like 70 hours in not even to programming weeks and we've got so
much good stuff going on in that code base.
So I'm pretty happy about that.
Yeah, if you would like to follow,
Long at home with handmade hero.
You can go to handmade here at uh org and pre-order the game and
you'll get the source code with it.
So if you want to do that, you can do that here.
You'll get a link in your email that you can download the source code
every night I uploaded Ever every time after I finish.
So that's something to check out.
If you would like to be kept up to date on the schedule, you can
subscribe to our Twitter.
If you would like to support the video series, you can subscribe to
our patreon and if you want to check out our episode guides the
If you want to discuss things on the community, forums, if you want to
look at ports to Mac or Linux that Community people have done using
forums is the place to do that.
So check all that out and have a good weekend and we'll be back here
on Monday, I'm not sure it might be an early one again on Monday
because I might not be here Monday night, so we may have to move it.
So definitely check the schedule Twitter
On Saturday or Sunday it'll tweet out when the schedule for the week
is no definitely check that and see so that if you want to make Monday
stream but other than that then Tuesday should be back to the normal
time I think.
But anyway, so yeah, might be a slightly different schedule next week.
Check the Twitter bot for for for information on that.
All right, everyone, thank you very much for joining me.
Have a great weekend and I will see you next week.