Start recording.
Okay, hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream on Twitch.
You know, I am pretty excited about what's about to happen here.
I don't know.
I mean I guess I don't know.
We might hit some snags but yesterday we were just about finished
moving everything over to the new logging system and we were sort of
putting stuff in so that even the old platform layer stuff that used
to kind of go through a different way of logging time, stamps could
go.
You are new debugging system and I'm kind of excited about that
because once that's all working, will be able to make some pretty cool
visualizations of like where the time is being spent in our program.
And that's the thing that I'm relatively interested in seeing myself
so I'd like to get into it right away because we were right in the
middle of it yesterday.
And so I'd like to go ahead and get it finished here today is day 183.
So if you want to follow along at home, unpack day 182 source code
into a directory and that is what we will be starting with
today.
So here we go.
If you remember correctly, we had finished getting everything working
and it actually was running just fine with the new system.
However, we had not yet actually taken advantage of the porting work
that we had done.
So actually, if you look here, we're not we're not actually putting
anything from the platform layer in this actual system.
Yet, we only have stuff that's from the game itself and so what I'd
like to do today is push that through so that we can get to the
situation where we've got
Everything including the platform layer part showing up.
So let's go ahead and do that.
If we go into win32 handmade right, what we need to do here is we
moved the stuff into handmade platform if you remember we sort of put
it down at the bottom here so that it could be accessed by both
systems so we can actually start using it here.
We can start using like time block and that sort of stuff in here.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to just go ahead and vaporize
this thing.
I'm going to vent vaporize this, debug frame.
And info concept is thing where we have like debug frame, timestamp
and, and that sort of stuff.
I'm gonna get rid of that, right?
So that's going to go away.
And instead what I'm going to pass in place of that particular set of
information is I'm going to pass in the sort of array of counters.
For the platform layer translation unit.
So, what it's going to pass here is it's going to pass essentially,
you know, in this in this handmade debug thing here.
When we get down to the bottom, right?
We've got these sort of debug records that we.
I'm sorry.
That's not the one I'm looking for.
You've got these debug records here, where we say, like, okay, we've
got the debug records.
Main count?
Optimize count platform count, right?
And then,
Each one of those has a record array.
Which store stuff like the filename and that sort of stuff, right.
So we have this Global debug table dot records thing.
That's the thing that I actually want sort of to be recorded their
right?
And I guess you know thinking about it a little bit further I guess I
could since since the platform layer would actually have the ability
to access that debug table, it would seem because you know, it's
actually I think it should be able to access it because we can sort of
load the address of it.
There we can get that piece of information out of the of the
Of the platform of the platform independent code.
I feel like we might not even have to do anything specific because we
wouldn't have to pass the records themselves.
We can just write directly into them.
So yeah, that actually seems like it should be, probably pretty easy.
So maybe I can just vaporize that thing entirely, I guess it seems
like I could I don't know.
So I'm going to go ahead and try that.
So if it was going to do that, if I was going to do that,
How would I do that?
If I want to vaporize that thing entirely I can just say, the debug
frame and info is just going to go away like there goes and then we
get rid of this.
And that's all there is to that, right?
And then I would come in here and say, all right, you know, we don't
have any of that anymore, that's gone.
We don't have any of this stuff anymore.
Now I'm not going to delete it because we're going to want to convert
that over because we want to use those bar charts again.
So, at the moment, I'll just if zero it out, it's going to come back
later and it
Not going to be drawing.
The frame infos anymore.
It's going to be drawing something else but otherwise it'll still be
pretty similar.
So once we get into here when we do win32 record time stamp, that is
no longer going to be a thing, we don't need to do that anymore.
We can just use the time clocks.
So what I'm going to do there is I'm going to say that we just have a
Time block here and that time block is going to be our Global running
block.
This block, right, like there, and we're going to want a way.
I think to start naming these things.
We're going to want a different version of time block.
That would allow us to name things more specifically for when we have
these here.
But I'm not going to worry about that at the moment because we don't
care about that too much here.
But what I want to do now is I want to be able to do sort of the
traditional begin end block pair, if that makes sense.
I want to be able to do that a little more manually, so that I can, so
that I can do, like, little Snippets here, like, little little bits of
this.
So, if I take a look at handmade platform, right?
A timed block is really just, you know,
It's one of these and one of these, right?
It's a debug, it's an end block event and a begin block event and a
thing that like accesses the records, right, that's, that's all that
is.
So what I want to do here is just extend this up sort of One More
Level.
So that what's actually happening in here, right?
is, is kind of going to be
Well, I'm trying to think of maybe even an easier way to do.
It would be just to have the exact same thing.
But yeah, maybe have the exact same thing but instead of the time
block, automatically doing it on close, the time block, just does it
sort of at a different time.
So I'm going to I'm going to stay.
We've got another thing here, which is like, you know, a manual block
or something like this, right.
I don't know, Emanuel time block.
And what that's going to do is that one, we'll just do it.
It needs to remember the counter, right?
That's the only reason I actually need an interesting thing here and
what that will do is when you actually create this manual, time clock,
you will essentially do this operation.
So, we'll have something like this and Define begin block, right?
And then, and then an end block,
so,
Let me take a look here and make sure.
I know we had some stuff in.
I think the intrinsics was it it's just want to make sure we got rid
of those old begin block end block one's pretty sure we did right.
They're this stuff.
So we don't want any of this anymore.
Right.
This stuff is all gone basically, goodbye.
Okay.
And global global memory.
I don't remember what we were doing with that.
Debug Global memory.
Was it, was there anything in particular?
We were storing in there?
Look what was that even being used for?
I don't know what we were doing with that.
Debug Global memory, debug Global memory, debug Global memory.
But it never is actually getting used, which is a little bit weird,
wasn't it?
Supposed to be see you bug Global memory?
It's weird.
It never actually gets used.
I guess we were planning to use that and just never did or something
we'll have to, to do Casey.
Actually start using this.
All right.
So that's that's a little weird.
Not sure what's going on there.
We'll take a look at that.
Anyway, point being.
So if I get one of these guys here with the, with the time block
situation, and I guess I can kind of make these two things work in
terms of each other.
So when you do a begin block end block, pair, what that's going to do
is it's literally just going to do exactly this, this thing exactly
what you see here, right?
So I what I probably do is I'd say, all right, whatever this.
Set of events is going to be.
Like that, I probably say.
Thing like, okay, you know, I want to be able to do something of the
form annual times.
Block, block equals begin block, or something like that or something
where I give it a name.
I guess when I do begin block, I'm just trying to figure out like how
I make sure that this counter variable can be stored somewhere so that
it will get used again.
by the end block automatically, of course, I mean,
And I'm not sure, I'm not sure how I would do that.
So, let me just show you what I'm trying to do.
What I want to be able to do is in here.
I want to not have to do this.
Right?
And the reason that I want to not have to do that is because when I
Define variables and stuff, I don't want those variables variables to
be scoped inside.
Right?
Inside this block, I want them to be accessed outside.
So I want to be able to do something like this, right?
I want to be able to do something where I do begin block, and then I
do end block like so and I can just do, you know, okay, this is the
executables ready section.
And I can, you know, just make that be like a known block, a sort of a
known section of this set of operations, right?
And then I can go, you know, another step further write and say, okay,
here's the input process so that's another envelope lock.
Right.
And so up here, when we do this, I would say begin block.
And get that.
And so you mean you can see it's pretty straightforward what I'm
talking about.
There's really nothing particularly fancy there.
So we come through here, we do whatever the input processing is and
that's fine.
Then we would come in here and do the game updated, part of things.
So here's another block.
And then we've got whatever this section is.
It's like the audio update.
Yep.
And block.
And that's what I want.
And I'm trying to figure out.
What's the easiest way to actually make that happen in some kind of
Non non like annoying for the programmer.
Which is, in this case, me not annoying way.
I want it to be able to be written roughly like this without a lot of
interceding other nonsense, right?
And furthermore, I would like it to be able to compile out, so I don't
want there to be a lot of funny business going on, you know, in terms
of stuff that has to be named.
Outside of the macros themselves, I want the macros to pretty much be
to pretty much be all of it.
So, let's see here.
Debug frame end gets called gets called there.
So then I'll just say, I guess, I'll just say right about here.
We'll do the end block and that that'll be the last block.
Yeah.
Okay, well, this will be, I guess frame display, something like that.
So that's what I want.
And then this can live outside it because it's still going to be
included in the overall time.
Block for this Loop right for the whole Loop, but that's about it.
So I don't really know.
I don't really know the best way to get it is, I guess what I would
say, I guess, so, here's here's what I'm thinking, since those manual
blocks probably want to be named anyway.
What I'm thinking is, maybe I don't, maybe I don't do them quite like
that.
Maybe I do them like this.
Something like that, you know, I don't really like the fact that I
have to copy the name into places, but you know, if you had blocks
that we're sort of in closing each other, I feel like you would have
to do that anyway.
So that's perhaps not such a big, big problem, but let's see here.
So we've got audio updated.
And audio updated.
Frame.
Wait, complete and see here.
So this is not really framerate complete its frame.
Wait.
Right.
These are kind of named differently now that their blocks.
So this is the frame display.
Frame display and audio update.
It's probably without a d would make a little more sense.
Now, I think.
Game update.
Audio update.
Input processing.
Like so.
And executable refresh.
Yeah, you know let's say we did something like that in that case we
would have like a thin cut that comes in here that's name.
And so what I was thinking we could do is we could just go like
you know, whatever that name is.
We could use as the timer and I'll just do another thing here that's
like begin block.
So,
So what I'm thinking is essentially we do the exact same thing here.
So this guy does like begin block and it just passes counter as the
name of the counter variable, right?
You know.
And maybe we stick a underscore at the end of that there just to make
sure that it's, you know, not going to be used by anyone or something
like this.
Although I guess we don't have to care about that here.
Yeah, although that may be something that you'd want to do.
I don't know.
We'll see.
So, anyway,
When we start the time block, we do what you would expect.
Here we go, ahead and pass us.
I guess all the information through to this macro here, right?
So this one's going to call it directly and then the external code can
call this non directly.
I think that'll work, we'll find out so this would do begin block
underscore name like that.
Although in this case it needs
it's to do something where it's going to pass, like a bunch of these
things through such as whatever the counter, the actual counter value
is whatever.
The, the file name is whatever the line number is, whatever the
function name is, or I should say the block name in this case.
And then I don't know about the hit count just yet.
We'll see if that ends up being something that we still want.
So, when I put the block name there, the line number, the file name
will get the debug record the exact same way.
We always get the debug record, we got the counter in it, so that's
all.
Fine.
I've got the record debug event which is going to work off of the
counter there.
So I guess all we really need to do is pass the actual counter here.
In fact, I've sort of starting to see how this this pulls together a
little bit better.
So we do the record debug vent, we've got the counter there, so there
it is, we just pass it in and then the name the name bit doesn't have
to flow through to here.
So it's really just going to be the counter.
The founding of the line number, the block name and that's all it
should really need in order to work.
Everything else looks like it should
Be be pretty pretty much.
Okay?
So if that's the way we do, let's see if that's the way we do the
block begin, then what we need to do now is go.
Okay, if that's how we're doing baguette whenever we call begin block,
we need to be able to generate these things from it.
And so, what we want to do there is first of all, we have to, we have
to make something that records with a counter is right.
And so what I was thinking is we could do something like, say, oh,
okay, it's going to be like counter
Or underscore name, so whatever the name.
That's where we'll store what the counter value actually is, does that
make sense?
And then what we can do is call begin block, because now we have this
information, we can just say, Okay, begin block with the counter that
we've stored so that the envelope can use it right?
That this is the I'm worried about this guy being able to use it
essentially.
So we've got that.
We know we can get the file name, just from the compiler, we can get
the line number from the compiler, and then the block name is just
going to be whatever name we actually got past and there's our begin
block and that just should just work right.
Then our and block will pick up the counter from here.
So it will be able to do the record debug event that it actually needs
to be able to do, right?
And in order to do the end debug event, all it actually needs, is that
counter value and so we know that that's it would be this cow.
Our value here would be the name of it so you know again we just make
a second one up here so that it can work in both cases.
I suppose actually I don't really need both of them now that I think
about it.
Well, it doesn't matter.
I'll make them both anyway.
So we've got, you know, both ones here.
And this is just going to pass in whatever the counter is actually
supposed to be.
And so, whatever the counter is in this case, it will go ahead and do
the record.
Debug event, like, so with whatever that counter is and the end block
marker.
So if you are to call it like this, then you get exactly what you
would expect.
If you are to call it down, here you pass sort of counter as like a
special case to it and then it can pass through all the stuff that
came from the other macro, right?
So it's really just a, this is just a bunch of conduit in, right?
It's just a bunch of condo inning,
I really wish you'd probably call this time to function, but that's
kind of another.
Another situation we can talk about that.
Second fact, I'll just go ahead and call this block name and I'll call
this block name and I will say that we are calling this time to walk
thing.
This is going to be called time function so that way it can pass the
function down through everything right.
And then we can just change that so that it makes sense.
And that way, it's not time Block.
It's time for function, right?
Okay.
Because we could then we could have another one where we give it a
specific name and that would be kind of nice as well, right?
So, anyway,
All right, so you can sort of see what's going on here.
This will hopefully makes reasonable sense.
So this is going to call Em block underscore with.
Again, that counter, that got stored in the previous macro, this guy
up here.
And so I think that should basically do what we want.
We don't need the manual time block thing anymore.
That's actually just handled for us here by that sort of name
concatenation.
So, I think that whole thing, sort of roughly checks out, We've Got to
Now handle all of
The the chaos that I will have caused, by making these changes,
certainly, the block name does not exist in debug events because I,
you know, what you gonna do?
I change that.
So we need this to now be blocked name.
There we go.
And then, when we come through here times block, is always going to be
timed function from now on.
And so, this really this guy should be something else.
In fact, this guy we should just call time block.
And we can call this like, you know, pixel fill or something like
that, right?
Yeah.
I'm just going to call it pixel fill for now.
I can't think of a reason not to call it that.
So we're just gonna call it that.
All right.
This should be a time function.
This should also be a time function.
This should be a time flock.
I'll pixel fill again.
This should be a time function.
Time function.
Time function, time function and function, still and function.
These are basically all gonna be time function except the odd case
where we got a second one in there, where we wanted to give it a name,
right?
Okay.
There are a lot of these.
Let's take a look.
Timed block identifier, not found.
That is true.
Timed block should be time function and time function we go.
Okay, pixel fill.
Yeah, I should probably also Define times block.
So if I do timed block like so basically, I'm just going to clone
this.
I could probably get away with actually making these macros call each
other, but I don't really want to think about it.
Too hard at the moment.
So, all I want to do here is say that this function right here is like
block name, right?
And in fact, I guess well, you know, now that I think about it, I
could probably do this pretty easily.
But yeah.
So you just pass in the block name, right?
And so you still get the same exact Behavior, fact.
I think I'm going to, I'm going to put this like this though.
You still get the exact same behavior that macros.
So I think I can just make it I can just consolidate these things
trivially, right?
So you pass a block name for time block, and that will always have
that block named coming in first
So that makes it really trivial to implement time function in terms of
these guys.
I think that means all I'd have to do is say, Okay, pass the function
name first.
And then I get the same thing and then I don't need the rest of those,
right?
So now you can write time function in time, Block, in terms of the
same little weird Mac out, macro cracking thing that we had to do to
get the correct concatenation there.
Okay, so time function, now just calls time.
Block in all cases, everybody always calls time to block underneath,
and so that can go back to the way that it was.
So in the case, where you pass this in here, the block name
I guess I need to, I need to turn it into a string obviously, so we'll
do that.
And then these are going to be again time function, pretty much
everywhere that we had time blocks before our time functions now.
So there we go.
And so on again, same thing, this is a Time block, this is a Time
block for the debug render group, I guess we'll just call it that
Okay, there's a Time function.
And function name.
That's true.
Should be blocked name.
And should be blocked name everywhere now so I never want it to be
function name anymore.
So let's see function function name, got rid of it there and here it
should be block name again.
So now we are in better shape, function name, block, name doot-doot
doot-doot,
Okay, so now we need to actually pass some stuff here for our time
block.
So this is the win32 loop.
I guess we could call it.
Maybe, I don't know, seems like a reasonable name and then we've got
executable refresh for begin block.
Okay, so now we got to go make those macros actually work properly.
Hopefully, let's see here.
So begin block.
Name that all looks good.
It was not expecting.
A string as the final thing.
Is that what I am to be told?
What is the that actually looks like?
What I would have expected.
Let's see, block name is there lb name so I'm not sure exactly what
that's complaining about counter underscore name is the counter and
that's all good.
It looks like record.
Bug event, working out the counter.
So what is it actually complaining about syntax error string and begin
block executable refresh.
So if we were to call begin block with executable refresh, we get
counter underscore executable Reef s equals counter that seems fair.
You have counter extra recess getting called packed into their the
file.
The wine number.
And the and the name String eyes.
So we come up to here to begin block.
Again we've got counter underscore name there, which means it would be
replaced here.
Thanks, Visual Studio, by the way, for, not telling me any information
about this whatsoever.
That's that's always really helpful.
So,
Llvm gives you like the macro expansion stuff.
It's really easy to debug stuff like this.
For all the ways, the visual Studios debugger is way better than the
ones on Linux.
The compiler on Linux, is way better than what have Windows.
So okay, we grab the record out by adding the counter.
I guess what I'm going to do is just do, what I would, what I have to
do here because compiler gives me no choice.
I'm just going to start pulling apart parts of these to see, which
one's it's complaining about, right?
Okay, so that makes sense.
So it looks like that there's nothing wrong with that it's doesn't it
doesn't mind that at all.
So I'll kind of come out a little bit more here.
Move this down right to here.
See how that goes.
So Sinister string, oh it's just that.
So okay, so file name line, different block name.
So I just got a, you know, make some way of these things getting
getting put in.
So they don't name conflict with the members of the struct.
That is me misremembering when it decides to expand and when it
doesn't, so that's easy enough fixed.
So I think that should be it.
Now, of course these
Use of a temporary here is going to be a problem.
So what we really want is to just block these, right?
Put those in a block.
So that way, the, the record itself won't name conflict with anybody
and that should be fine.
All right, so we don't pass frame end in for anymore.
And so now we're pretty much done with that stuff.
There's just one problem and that problem is that we don't actually
have the global debug table when we're in here, right?
And you can see that unresolved external.
So, all we really need to do to kind of finish up to get this.
I think working is, we need some way of the debug table itself
actually have, you know, sort of
Being able.
To write in when we, you know, when we load the dll, we need some way
of grabbing the global debug table.
From the system, right?
We need to be able to say that that Global debug table points to
something, right?
And so I'm trying to think of what the best way to do that would be
I'm thinking that probably what we would want to do is make sure that
When we load it right, we need a pointer to the global debug table.
So let's see here, the global debug table due to hanako platform.
XO.
So when we did this, we have the global debug table.
And we need a way of pointing to that, right?
We need a way of accessing that I guess the only thing that's kind of
nasty about this is the way that I did it here.
It's not actually a pointer that's kind of a problem because there's
no real way for me to have that work that I can think of
Yeah, I can't really think of any way to make that work.
If it's, if it's not a, if it's not a pointer, if it's a pointer works
fine because then I can just point that pointer in anything that I
need to point to, right?
And that's not really a problem.
So I feel like this kind of needs to be that which is unfortunate
because it means there's some indirection to the way that we're
writing things instead of it just being a constant location but you
know, we'll see how that goes.
So if I was to do that, I'm wondering if I can, if I can get away with
it, let's find out what will debug table dot?
We will debug table Arrow.
So, there we go.
Let's go ahead and run that.
So, the global debug table now is going to be, like, debug table
Global debug table, right?
And then we've got a pointer to the debug table, which is just this
Right?
And this guy is actually a static, right?
This guy is actually a global variable and so he doesn't actually
export, but this guy does actually export to the other to their stuff,
okay?
So I think that's pretty much all.
We would need to do to get the main line code working.
However, now we still need a way of getting the this to work, you
know.
So that the external code that the platform layer can get a hold of
it, right?
So let's go ahead and see if we can just finish.
Porting this up.
Here we go.
Events.
And done.
Okay so obviously if I just didn't if I just want it to compile, right
and I don't want it to actually work like I don't want it to to
actually I don't care if I actually get the information, then it's not
so hard because then I can just say we've got a debug table.
This is a global debug table debug table and I've got a pointer to it
Global debug table, right?
And I just Define one in the platform layer.
And now these two sections, the thing on either side of the dll are
actually, you know, writing Loops are actually writing to two totally
separate places in memory.
So when I run this right, well when I run this apparently I will just
crash which is also often, which is which is fabulous.
What is the problem here?
Why is my where's my pointer?
Not initialized Global debug?
All right?
It is undefined.
How is it undefined people?
What's going on?
What is going on?
Let me make sure I didn't do something stupid.
Well, I obviously did something stupid.
So that's that's an incorrect statement.
What I mean to say is, let me make sure I didn't do something
obviously stupid.
I feel like this should have been initialized.
Is it not being initialized for some?
Not sure.
I feel like that should be
Hmm.
I feel like once it gets loaded, that should be correct but it's
obviously not.
So I'm pretty interested to know why it's not.
It's the very first time through.
I don't understand why I can't access it.
My typing it in wrong, Global debug table.
Right, Global debug cable.
I guess I was typing it incorrectly.
So that's so that actually looks okay.
So maybe okay.
Yeah, sorry, don't want you to do that.
I suppose so I guess maybe it's just actually a problem with the way I
implemented time function.
Maybe I'm just being, I was blaming the wrong thing.
It could be that I just made a mistake and here somewhere.
So it does time block and it actually starts us up.
Maybe I was doing something stupid.
Ah, that's the problem, I just didn't
Initialize counter.
That's what that's that, was it?
So that's fine.
Alright, so now we're back to what I was trying to talk about before.
So if I run this it'll work just fine.
But the problem is now, the platform layer is writing into a different
debug memory, right?
It's writing into a completely different.
Area of memory, then where we actually wanted to write to because I
just declared there's one on either side of that dll boundary.
Now, so the ones that the win32 platform layer everything.
It writes to isn't totally separate memory from the other one.
So what I need to do now is I just need to hook them up, right?
So what I need to do is say, okay, on the platform layer side, right,
where We've Got This Global, debug table on that side.
What I can do is if I can just get the debug table out of the
Sort of the dll here, right?
If I can when I actually do this, right?
So when I load the dll, I do win through to load game code.
When I
On the game code, I can just switch, what debug table.
I'm writing into that, would be fine.
So, when I load the game code, what I can do is introduce a function
there, which is like, hey, I need you to give me back that debug
table.
And so I think the way that I'm going to do that the way that I think
that I would prefer is at the end after it does, it's like first
collation pass or something.
Then I will go ahead and get it from from here.
So what I'll do is I'll say Global debug
Debug table my pointer, my Global table.
I'm just going to override it with whatever you tell me to do, write
something like that.
That makes sense what I just said.
I feel like it does.
Except I don't really know.
To be completely honest with you, it would seem a lot more saying, if
what actually happened was it lived in the platform layer side and
then the executable rode into that.
There's reasons why that's not so good because that does mean that
also the strings in it don't map correctly because when the executed,
when the dll gets unloaded, all of the strings that come that were in,
there are going to be invalid, and that would be annoying, right?
So, I don't know.
I'm going to do this for now, we'll see.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to say okay whenever
we're going to unload, this thing when we do win32 load game code or
something, we're just going to turn it off.
So when we do unload game code, we're going to turn off that that
Global debug table.
We're going to point it back at our Global debug table.
Right.
And then when we get it loaded, we'll just reset it.
That seems fair.
Yeah that seems fair.
Now we have a problem which is that we need to reset this but that's
okay.
We can always reset it over and over it so it doesn't overflow is
basically what I'm saying.
So, what we can do here is anytime we get to the end of this Loops, we
can always do our Global debug table, the actual vote, sort of the
stub one that we have that we use anytime that we don't have anything
that's loaded.
We can just go ahead and say, okay, you know, whatever that whatever
that one's event index array index thing is, we'll just, we'll just
clear it back to zero that way.
We know that it's never going to overflow because we clear it at the
end of every frame.
Anyway, right?
So that seems pretty straightforward to me.
I feel like that'll work, there's probably a better way to do that if
I thought about it a little longer, but I'm not sure I super Care at
the moment but that's
That's probably worth kind of drilling down into a little bit more if
you really wanted to make like a sweet system, you'd probably want to
figure out a way to get that, that sharing to be better.
Like, I'm 99% sure I could do it.
I just don't want to spend, you know, 30 minutes or an hour just, you
know, kind of playing with that and going.
What's the exact right way to do that.
So, yeah, oops.
So yeah, I think that's should do it.
And then we need to just when we have debug frame end here, I just
need to return the global
debug table from there and now they should be writing into the same.
Place in theory at least in some kind of a theory, right?
Why is it a void function still?
Where is my definition?
Define, define define, where is debug Frank and there it is.
Debug
Table.
Okay.
And yeah, so I feel like now we're getting a little closer here to, to
success, although we're not there yet.
I don't see our platform stuff showing up in here yet, right?
So it's not it's not we have not, we have not succeeded yet.
So, let's go ahead and take a look at what's happening here.
So, let's go here and let's take stop right there.
So, the global debug table right is, is pointing at well, it looks
like it's pointing at the right thing.
Is it C?
Yeah, it's definitely pointing at the right table, so we grabbed it,
so that's good.
And then we're clearing the one that we're not using.
So, that's kind of unimportant, right?
So, here's our win32 Loop.
Oh, you know what?
It's probably just fine.
We just never actually are printing any of these guys out, right?
So, we just need to finish what we were doing and handmade debug to
actually print them out, right?
Because if I'm not mistaken this part here, doesn't
Actually, grab the the ones from the platform layer, right?
The debug records platform count is always set to 0, which is not is
not what we want.
So, let's see.
What would we have to do to make this happen?
We come to the counter cats.
We clear them.
We do this stuff here, counter States and then we set the snapshots
up.
So I think all we really have to do is now finish the part where we
figure out what the count actually is, right?
And in order to do that, what I think we should do is in the debug
table itself.
I feel like the debug table,
Have that information, right?
Like you notice, we didn't actually, we don't actually have that.
We never actually put that in there because they were constant since
and such.
So what I'd like to do is just say that the debug table itself
This guy, I'd like this, like the fact that's not aligned going to
move that forward.
In here.
I'd like to have the ability to get the counts out.
Right, so something here, where we do this, I'd like to do like record
count like this where we have the record count per translation unit
and that way.
That'll, oh, he's sort of be kept up-to-date by other people who are,
you know, who right into it, or something like that.
And so, the way that, that would happen is, we'd get rid of this debug
platform count thing here.
And instead, what we do is we just go, you know,
The total count total record count is just going to be the sum of all
of the translation units, translation unit index are always called
this unit Index, right?
So unit index is going to be looping over all of these.
It's going to take that debug table.
So Global debug table
Record count for whatever unit we're talking about and it will some
that like so.
So then we just know that the debug State counter count is just equal
to however many records we have total, we then come through and we
clear them all which seems fine, we then come through and we
initialize these and so that the way that we would initialize those
actually, in fact we could, we could even do that up here, right?
So what we could say is, all right, there's an array.
Counters.
The array of counters is however many translations units.
There are like.
So
We won't initialize any of them.
We start off with the pointer that we are talking about is going to be
counter States, right?
So that's basically, debug capture state state like current counter or
something like that.
So, we Define that.
And then as we go through here, when we want to say, which one of
these, you know,
Where the counter start in this flat array, that we've created, we
just say that whatever translation Unit were on that equals the the
current counter beeps.
All right counter and then we just add current counter, we add to it,
we advance it by however many records there were.
And now we just have that working and we don't have to worry anymore
and to trans and now we're generic in the number of translation units
as well, there's no hard coded stuff in there, so you can just kind of
arbitrarily have however, many translations
Yes, there are.
So as we coming here, what I'd like to do
is I'd like to go ahead as well and make sure that we write
We just overwrite these every time just to make sure that their
current.
So we'll have the record count for the translation units that we
actually know about.
And I'm trying to think if there's some way to make this part
automatic because we nice to have the whole thing so that we don't
have to care about that.
But don't know that, that's, you know, actually a realistic thing to
think about, right?
Because you can, so you can see right here.
We've got, we've got these guys.
Okay, so if I come in here and say,
Say we've got the optimized ones.
The optimized one is that is the zeroth translation unit.
If I'm not correct, I'm not mistaken build up that.
No.
It's the first translation unit, right?
Yeah.
That's what I did.
Said, the wrong thing.
And then the the main count is this one.
And so that gets written in there and then we just have to count on
the platform layer to actually write in its actual correct.
Piece of information, right?
So, in order to do that in win32 handmade, what it would need to do,
is before calling in, to hear it would need to say, or I should say,
possibly after calling into their, it just goes.
Okay.
When we get back, the global debug table will set the record count for
our translation unit.
And and off we get, right?
So the record count for our translation unit is going to be whatever
our our total counter count is.
So I guess it's that.
Although it's kind of a little annoying because that means you can't
do it.
I should put it to do here.
I have to say that that it seems like maybe the counter thing is a
little more trouble than it's worth, right?
Because because we do have more than one translation unit, it ends up
not being as clean.
As I would like, you have to do this extra stuff for the multi
translation units.
If we didn't do the dynamic code loading, it would have and could have
the up the sort of, like, windowed optimization where we just
literally only had one translation unit, would have been a lot nicer,
but it's forcing us to do a bunch of things here and I don't super
love that.
It's okay.
I mean every time you find a new technique, you don't really know how
effective it's going to be.
And
There's a bunch of different things that, you know, maybe we need to
think about more carefully about it, but it's worth noting that it's
annoying me.
How many little fiddly things?
There are like that, which maybe suggest that we don't really want to
do it that way, you know, at the end
Something like that.
But anyway I think that should work now.
I believe.
All right.
So now if we take a look at what's going on here in theory, we should
be able to find.
We should be able to sort of see all of our win32 stuff.
You can see now that we've got like, our went through to Loop is here
or executable.
Refresh is here in processing is here.
Our game update is here, audio update and so on, right?
So we've got these things.
We don't really know.
We haven't done much testing of this yet, so we don't know how well
this is working.
But we're basically, you know, we're in that we're sort of narrowing
in on it actually a, you know, working particularly well, it would
appear.
Unfortunately, we're starting to get too many things in here but
that's okay.
That's exactly why I did this whole round of work, anyways, because
now we can start
art to make something that's going to let us see things in a more
intelligent way, right?
So this is, this is a weird number for the wind through two Loops.
Oh, I suppose, that's because it's never going to be closed, right?
It that Loop won't be closed.
And so that's another thing that we're probably going to want to play
around with.
Basically, when we actually run those numbers, that Loop will not have
closed because that Loop actually closes out here.
So it will, it will not actually have closed in that in that time
period.
If that makes sense.
All right, so the last thing I would like to do and that took longer
than I was hoping, right?
We had more work to do than I would have hoped so don't know that
we're going to get to some of the things I would have liked to have
done given the short amount of time that we have still left, but I can
do a couple of things that I wanted.
So the first one I want to do is have some kind of a notion of like a
frame latch so that we can tell in the debug event stream so that we
can kind of tell where the frame boundaries
We occur, right?
So just something that's like frame boundary, you know, it's like
this, this was the end of it or something, right?
Although I guess now I think about it, maybe we don't even need that
because we kind of have that if we just make, sure everything is
always inside one giant block, maybe we just kind of have that.
I don't know.
I guess I won't do that yet.
Let's just let's just continue down the path and see where we go
without actually doing that first.
Yeah, let's just see, let's just see what happens, I suppose.
Okay.
So,
I guess what I'll say is.
Yeah, you know, the only thing is you'd want it.
Well?
Okay.
I'm not sure I'm having like, an internal dialogue here and I feel
like I'm gonna want a way right to Mark something as like the frame
boundary and and because the reason I say that is because we have it
sort of extra information.
It's a thing that says
This is the natural unit I want to like view things by, you know what
I mean?
so I feel like what we actually want
Is a special marker, right?
That says that this is how you should chop up time when you're
visualizing it.
Everything else is a block, but I am actually special.
I'm the special point in time that says, this is a logical frame that
like is what I want you to splay in terms of, you know, it has no
other meaning besides that, but just it's what I want to see, you
know.
And so instead of having this be time flock 132 Loop, you know,
instead it's something like this is the frame marker or something.
Right.
Something like that.
And so what the frame marker is, it would be a very special thing a
call to record debug event.
That would be like, you know, particular very particular.
So when you call this Frame marker function, what you actually would
get is record debug in event.
For like a special record index for something like this, you know?
I guess it doesn't have to be special.
It can still be counter.
I suppose, but you caught you, you know, whatever that one is the
event.
Type of it is not the standard event type right?
Instead of the normal event type, it's actually going to be some kind
of a special marker that we have here.
So it'll be like debug event, you know, frame marker like so and so
that way we can just insert that in there specifically
And when that happens, we could also, if we wanted to, we can fill out
the rest of this stuff, right?
You know, we can do something like this if we want to.
So maybe I just will
I'll say ENT.
Counter.
Equals counter.
I'll say record debug event, you better than frame marker, so we got
that.
And then I'll do this part here as well.
So I'll say OK, debug record.
Oh and well.
Okay.
I'ma keep going.
This is another thing that I could do here that was kind of
interesting.
But anyway we'll get the debug your record out and then we'll just
right in here.
I guess the standard stuff like file lime and then the block name.
Yeah I guess the block name is just going to be frame marker or
something like that, right?
So that's what I want.
That's what I want to have happen.
I need to finish my back slashing there.
And so now I suspect.
Okay good guys going to say I suspect will have to change a couple
things in the printout routine, just to ignore those events for now
since
Actually using them for anything.
So that assertion for end block, that actually needs to be in here if
event type equals and block, and do this.
Otherwise don't do anything, and that's fine.
Okay,
So, now we're back to everything.
I think everything should be roughly correct now, as well.
Like, I don't think we should have any of those, like, forced open
block nonsense, things happening, so that's good and that all looks
that looks reasonable to me.
Okay.
So the next step in this process is, we need to start looking at the
frame.
We want to start being able to look at this debug
log potentially as just one giant log in some sense and
So I'm wondering right?
Like let me just give you a little drawing here of what I'm what I'm
thinking.
I'll go ahead and pop over to the Blackboard.
So, there's day 183.
so,
This is the this is the debug log.
So what I'm thinking right is what's this debug log going to look like
you know it's going to have a marker.
There's the frame marker.
It's going to have a bunch of like begin and pears.
You know that that look like whatever they look like mostly
hierarchical probably you know although they're not required to be
something like this.
Then there's going to be another frame marker and they're going to
keep going.
Now, some of them might span that frame boundary, right?
Because there's there's things that are happening like asynchronous
operations which might span the frame boundary.
So what we want to be able to do is get all the stuff into like a
rolling log and so that we can we can kind of view that even with
stuff that crosses the frame boundary but we also need to be able to
make it so that when we run out of room,
You know, we have a way of clearing it eventually because otherwise
we'll just keep writing log information.
If we just kept writing the same buffer so we have that like ping-pong
steam going now.
But I think what we probably want to do is we probably want to make it
so that we actually let it right for a lot more than a frame.
You know what I mean?
So that we get like many frames of data and then we just read we like
move the sort of the the place where it's safe to read and safe to
write almost more like a
Circular buffer, so that we can kind of like keep using data from, you
know, as it goes.
So I feel like
I feel like in order to do that, I mean, we just need a lot of memory
for it.
It's not like a huge deal, right?
We just need a lot of memory for, if we want to store all that
information which does sort of pose.
A problem for our the fact that those things are Statics, we would
rather be able to have that be Memory passed in that we virtual Alex
or something like that.
Which again does suggest that maybe the part that gets past sort of
forwards, instead of passing backwards like we're doing here, might
have been a better way to go just at least in terms of where the
memory comes.
It's hard to say, right?
But anyway, so when we, when we come through here and that's the, the
end, I guess, we're at where the cute we got.
Like, maybe a minute before Q&A.
So, after wrap up, but when we come in here,
We swap out which buffer that we're doing now, we could do something
like, taking the debug info and I guess we could just copy it out to
some memory and string them together as we go or something like this.
I don't know that.
That makes a sense because then we're wasting a bunch of time copying
when we could have just left in the place where it was
On the other hand, I fear, I do fear that if we, you know, Jack the
the size up too much of the actual debug table that we're going to end
up with some kind of a nasty situation because we're have too much of
the data in the static section.
I don't know if that's still a problem anymore but are too much not
dating the sax section.
But I mean to asking the operation to allocate too much for the
executable.
So like for example, if I was in here and we said events,
Instead of two, we were to say that we want, you know.
Look a ton of these, like, however, many frames we want for our for
our snapshots or something, right?
So this thing is like, huge.
Yeah, that's what I thought.
So you can't exceed your right.
You can't exceed a 4 gigabyte array or something like that, right?
So I don't know, I don't know if something like that is really pushing
the limit.
You know, how bad that's going to be, looks like it's okay.
I suppose for that many so maybe that's a reasonable thing to do.
And so then
Would have effectively 63 frames of look back.
So, it's writing into the 64th frame.
We have 63 frames where we could look at those events over time.
And, you know, be able to kind of kind of go through them like that.
I don't know how necessary that is, but we would at least have it.
And so if we wanted to do that, right?
It's not too tricky.
All that would be.
It's not really very different from what we're doing here, all that
would require
Is when we come through here and we do this, like current event or a
and x dot equal cut, we wouldn't do that.
We would just do current event array index.
We do like a plus plus of it, right?
So we'd say like, you know, go to the next one.
and,
We would just say, if oops.
If it is greater than or equal to the array count that's in the
debugger, a it gets reset to 0, right?
So that's the debug level debug table events.
And so now, I believe that is just keeping that ruling buffer.
So we can actually now look across frames because we just have the
events for everything and it also means we don't really need this
snapshot stuff anymore, right.
We don't really need to worry about that anymore because we could
actually recompute that on the fly if we wanted to.
So, the snapshots are really not necessary at all anymore.
So, yeah.
So I feel like that's probably the right way to go then.
To just take a huge amount of data.
Just take a huge footprint there because again, this is not something
we ever have to worry about running on an end users machine.
It's only for debugging purposes.
So if you want to, we can just say, all right, we'll take a bunch of
will take a huge amount of memory will just slap those things in
there.
As we write them and, you know, it's not as good as if we just did a
circular buffer.
So it kind of feels more like we probably want to write to a circular
buffer there but I don't really want people to have to do the circular
buffer.
Chuck is the problem, so I don't know.
We'll see, we'll leave it like that for now but we'll see because
there's no real downside to doing it this way.
You always want to have a ton of memory in your death machine anyway
for doing stuff like this.
So you can just do whatever.
The most, you know, expedient thing is that allows you to actually
capture the information that you want.
You don't want have to constantly be thinking about is it Frugal on
memory when you're talking about code that's meant for
instrumentation.
So that might be fine.
We'll see.
But now that we have that with that means is I can go ahead and say
ok.
Let me look back across the previous, however, May frames we want, and
I can find the frame boundaries and now it doesn't matter when in
particular you updated, the debug, there can be things that straddle
those markers, and we'll be able to look at all of that data correctly
and there won't be any edge cases where we can't see what happened
because it's like an event that spans two frames or more.
And that's the thing that I was really worried about because I want to
be able to see those those sort of events that
outside of a single frame in terms of encapsulating.
All right, so I think we're good, and I think we're done now with
that.
So we should be able to work on viewing tomorrow because there's
nothing that seems like it's all working.
Unless there's something that we're missing there, so we can do.
So we can do Q&A.
Hotspur, are you going to start the hardware under before starting the
game logic?
Or are you going to wait till the software doesn't cut it?
Or are you waiting for Vulcan?
Yeah, I don't know that I'll ever do the hardware renderer if we don't
need one, right?
So the hardware renderer will happen when we decide that we, you know,
want to do some too much stuff on the screen, right?
And so that we and so we need Hardware.
So I suspect I won't do it pause, I mean, I might not even, I might
have the game essentially essentially be done on the software renderer
and then only do the hardware render as like a thing that we do up as
a like it an additional thing.
But you know, we may be forced into doing the hardware vendor earlier.
If we want to do some things and find that we can't do it because the
software rendering is not fast enough, right?
Did you just use the Blue Line sector and green cursor to make it
easier to follow and stream?
Yes.
Or is that how you normally like it?
I feel like it would get fatiguing to the eyes.
Yeah, I don't normally do the Blue Line.
The cursor May normally be green though.
I don't remember it microscope.
I think my cursor May normally be green but the blue line is strictly
for the Stream.
Elven, when do you think it is a good idea to use somebody's else's
Library System instead of implementing your own?
Well, it's if you think that it's as good as what you would have
implemented, right?
Or similar quality, right?
I mean that's why I use the stb libraries is because, you know, across
all the axes Sean's code is going to be like my code right in my
opinion.
I don't I don't think of it as having to use this crappy thing that
people who I don't trust wrote.
Which is how I feel about most libraries.
I feel like it so it like Sean wrote it.
I know it's going to be good, I know that it's going to be like well
you know, it's integrate well that the API is saying right and so when
you have that kind of a high-quality Library like that it's a very
easy decision to go.
I can just use this and I'm not worried about what's going to happen,
right.
We're and I there's very few libraries that I would say that about but
that's that's the thing.
Another way might say you know
Know if that if the person who wrote the library with someone that
you'd want on your team, right, then that's a good sign that you
probably want, would be happy using their library.
And like, most of the people, most libraries out there are, you know,
written by people who I wouldn't want on my team and I don't want to
use their Library just like I don't want to hire them, right?
But a lot of that takes experience.
Takes experience to know before you actually use something whether
it's going to be worth, whether it's going to cause you some different
problems or not.
So I don't pretend that that's an easy judgment call to make it
something that I feel comfortable making at this point because I know
my development process.
I know what I am and am not okay.
With, in terms of using people's libraries because I've had a large
branch of that and I realize that's harder for people who have had
experience cuz they don't know what they like.
They don't know what will cost them stuffed.
On the line, you know, until you've built up experience.
You don't necessarily know what you do and do not consider appropriate
or what you do or do not think will cause you problems.
I gotta go early today.
I gotta go in like 5 minutes.
I'm just going to quickly, scan to see what we've got here.
Keeper.
Caleb missed the first half of the stream.
Are you saving the past 60 frames into a buffer?
Yeah, I'm saving like, all the debug events now.
And because I think I want to have, I'm just thinking of how we want
to view them and I'm pretty excited about that.
And so I've been trying to make sure that I've been trying to iron out
enough things in the system so that we can really get a view of
everything.
Instead of only like things that happen to like be nicely encapsulated
inside a frame and stuff.
K.
Let's see if a miracle happens.
People to start doing things, right?
And addresses, the issues, the inflation of most their features.
When you use their features like templates or shake to
metaprogramming.
I, I don't think it's probably useful question, answer.
I mean, I think see what's left is so bad at this point, I don't think
they're going to pull it out.
In the deepest way.
Are we going to see something like Brendan Greg's flame graphs?
I don't know.
I have not ever really looked at those.
Probably not what I want to do is more of a like hierarchical Zone,
drill down that make sense.
Although maybe that's what if landgraf is since.
I don't haven't seen my, I don't know.
Insofar, as I think, a lot of people would like to see how to write a
hardware, renderer, myself included.
Yeah, I mean,
A lot of people would like to see a lot of things, but I have to keep
the amount of stuff that we cover to us to certain thing.
Right.
A lot of people would probably like to see how to write a 3D engine as
well but I'm not going to do it right because I have to keep it scope
to something that I can reasonably accomplish in a reason amount of
time.
So in general, I will cover the things that I absolutely know that I
want to cover which is basically how to write
Fleet 2-D game from scratch but I'm not going to add anything on that.
I don't think is necessary for showing that complete process, right?
And so Hardware, rendering in particular, is not really that
interesting to me in a lot of ways because it's super transient.
I don't even think it will exist in 15 years.
I don't think there will be such a thing as a hardware renderer so
it's a very like temporary thing.
Whereas everything else that we've covered I think is
sort of knowledge that will be useful for a very long time.
The only problem with it is that, you know, it's tied to a particular
language, but if you can factor out a fair bit of that, I think it's
more generally applicable to just how to program and that's pretty
important to me.
And so the hardware vendor apart, I feel like is just kind of, you
know, if I didn't think that we might need it, just in terms of the
game, being able to run well, because modern machines have a lot of
their horsepower in the GPU,
Right?
If I didn't think we would need it because of that, I just would have.
Said, we were never going to do Harbor under right from beginning.
But, you know, I assume we will probably hit a wall at some point
where, you know, we just have too much stuff on the screen and
software rendering is not optimized enough or whatever.
And that will have to do one
Captain craft getting good at running game engines, right?
Lots of them or work on a few larger ones and continue improving them.
I would say you don't have to write lots of things in the whole scope.
What you want to do is just make sure that you iterate on the pieces
though or on the architecture.
Like
You want to always wreak reassess and question your initial designs as
you especially as you learn more as a programmer.
So you know you could work on one engine for 10 years.
For 20 years and you can learn a ton and and do a lot of really great
work there.
As long as what you're doing is constantly, like, changing the way
things are done and improving them.
And at, right if you always, if you just let it calcify after the
first year, and everything is just kind of endlessly adding junk on
top of it and ever, you never liked revisit Andre and refine, and
change and improve.
Then that wouldn't be so good and then I'd say, yeah, you probably
want to do multiple game engines because that's, you know, the way you
would learn
earn.
But as long as you're willing to never say something is set in stone,
you can just have one engine that you keep working on and it keeps
getting better.
And I think that's a good way to go to because that way, you know, you
don't feel like you're starting from square one all the time.
You could always feel like, what's the section.
I want to, like, rip up and replace of my engine today, and I'm going
to start working on that for a few weeks, few months, whatever it is.
And then when that's done, I'll say what's the other
Us cutting thing.
And, you know, you keep letting it be pliable and I think that would
be a totally fine way to go.
All right, I am going to close it down.
Early today because I got to go, I got to go.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me, for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with the source
code, it comes with the pre-order of the game.
So if you want to, you can head over to handmade here at Oregon.
Pre-order the game and handmade hero, you can pre-order handmade hero
using little pre-order button, and then you can download the source
code every night after I'm done with it.
You can just go grab it.
There's also Forum site.
If you want to go, ask questions or take a.
Look at the antia depe sewed guide.
The community members have made.
It's pretty cool.
And and getting very complete as well.
Thanks to some dedicated folks.
And the patreon page we have is for supporting.
The video series is just want support the video series separate from
the game or separate from anything else.
That's a place to pledge to do it and it's always very much
appreciated and finally have a tweet pop that tweets the schedule you.
And so, if you want to stream live, that is the place to go for that.
It's speaking of Life.
I'll the last stream tomorrow, Friday, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time before the weekend, break.
We'll see you all back here.
Ali and then I'll finally get to do some of my debug this stuff.
Since I think we've now finished everything took a little more time
today than I was hoping.
I was hoping to do some today but we didn't get a chance to do that.
So tomorrow, we'll start down that path and I think that will continue
for a few days because I think we want to basically spend a bunch of
time now making it so that we can kind of explore our debug
information in a nice kind of Handy way.
And then after that, we'll start looking at maybe how to augment what
we have right now, which is perf stuff with some more different kinds
of information.
Like it'd be nice to get some memory information in there.
It'd be nice to get some diagramming in there and so we'll see if out
like just kind of augmenting what we're already doing with a little
bit more so that's about it.
Hopefully, see you back here for that until then have fun program
everyone.
And I'll see you guys out on the internet.
Take it easy.