Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here on the show.
We could complete game live on stream.
We just finished yesterday doing a sort of upgrade to multi render
Target rendering.
We had sort of went through a couple tranches of doing it first we
supported in the render stuff.
Then we spread our software renderer that we supported in our hardware
renderer and we're basically done with that now.
And so at this point we're ready to kind of go back and start working
on our Z pasta.
But I was thinking today since now is kind of a good stopping point a
little bit I was thinking of going back here in just cleaning out some
of the bugs that we have that are just like typos in places or things
that we didn't quite do correctly.
For whatever reason that we know we didn't do correctly but we haven't
gone around to actually look at and so I appreciate by the way.
Anyone if you have pre-ordered the game there on your send owl
download page.
You can download stuff, there is a code, you can use and some
instructions on that page, you can go look for if you didn't know
already.
There's there's instructions there about how to get on the private
GitHub and that's what I'm on right here.
And a lot of people ask for that.
So I did the work of actually supporting it and it's there and it's
updated nightly.
So it's synced, it's always up to date.
If you go on there, if you've noticed a type or a bug, you can report
it and it's pretty handy because then we have this little list that we
can look at
So that's kind of a nice feature.
I don't really use the GitHub for anything but I do like having the
little bug list.
I think that's pretty handy.
So if you want to report when you can always do it there, if you
didn't know about the private repo, you do now.
And if you pre-ordered, you have access to it already, you just need
to go use your code to authorize whatever your GitHub username is.
So, here is a bunch of stuff we've got.
And I'm just going to kind of go through these and see, like, which
one's of them.
I think we could fix and which one's of them.
I think we might need to leave open, right?
All right, so let's start with wrong GL view, Port parameters, and
we've got two problems here.
So what happens here I believe is that we sort of have a, we have this
notion of what size things are and you know, we're talking about what
sighs we were rendering to originally, but then we sort of were using
the wrong thing like commands with and commands height is
Is the size that we're going to talk about in terms of pixels but we
don't when we're using opengl, it's free for us to just stretch things
out to the whole size of the screen.
So it seems rather logical to just always use however, big the window
is, right?
So we could do that.
And that's what they're suggesting here.
Now, there's a problem with this approach, however, which is what
happens when the screen is not the same aspect ratio as what we're
rendering.
So we kind of need to actually do a little bit more here to fix this
bug, but that's okay.
Today, that's something we can totally do.
Which is to say, we'd like to have, you know, put black bars on the
screen or something.
If we're running in something other than a 16 by 9 display,
Right.
We'd like, you know, we'd like to be able to make it so that it was
centered in the window not stretched and warped in a bad way.
So let's go ahead and start here.
Today is day 3.
22.
So I am starting with the the day 321 source code here, that's what
I'll be working with.
So, if you want to follow along at home, please go ahead and and grab
that code.
Let me go ahead and also just make sure we're running properly and
everything's good here.
Yes.
So I think we're all good.
Everything seems to be running pleasantly and no problems.
So if and I suppose the other thing I can sort of do is say well okay.
If I was to run this here with a with a different size window and like
this, you know, we could sort of make it so,
This worked better.
Like so, for example, you can see here is I'm changing the size of the
window, all it's doing is cropping.
And that's, you know, we could call it a bug, we can call it a
feature.
I don't know what you want to call it.
I'm inclined to agree with this bug and say it's a bug.
So what we'd like to do is make it so that we use that window within
fit their, but as I said, this is going to cause some warping.
So let's take a look at what happens when I do that.
And then I'll sort of show you how we can, you know, why it happened
and we'll kind of go into it.
Into a little more detail.
So I don't think we set the viewport anywhere in here.
Yeah, I think we only send it over here.
Right.
Yeah.
And so if you take a look here, when we do open gel display bitmap,
you can see here that you know, when we do display bitmap, that's the
one, this is the path we use when we are going to do our when we're
bleeding our software into the screen.
But you can see here that yes, we would like to take the window within
the window height and we'd like to draw to all of it, right?
So if it's smaller than what we drew, we want to
Thinking if it's bigger we want to expand, right?
And the same thing would be true when we do our Geo viewport here for
opengl renderer commands.
When we do our viewport here, we would like to do the same thing.
Make sure that we actually are drawing to just however, big the window
with and window height actually are.
Now we do have a sort of problem with that, which is that if we're
doing that, we have to then sort of continue down all the way through
and say that instead of using commands with the command site, for our
render targets.
Now,
We're also.
Going to have to use window with and window height for those targets,
right?
Because we're drawing it, you know, we have to make sure that
everything lines up for all of our render targets, right?
So that's just kind of a requirement that we would have to have there
unless we take some other sort of steps later to make sure that things
go.
Okay, so there's there's kind of two ways that we could do it.
We'll do it this way at first and then we'll kind of go from there,
right?
All right, so if we go ahead and look at what happens, now, you can
kind of see the problem that I was trying to describe before, you
know, pictures always worth a thousand words.
So my description of it probably wasn't that clear.
But hopefully, you can now see what I'm talking about.
You know, if I shrink the window down to this size, you know, probably
the person doesn't want to play this game, right?
That is not what they were trying to see.
They didn't want, you know, a super tall.
A skinny version of the game when they size it, this way probably nor
did they want a long smushy version, you know, if they're going the
other way?
And you know, the way that we've got it, now, it looks like our
pickings also off when we do that.
So we should probably go test some go fix that as well, but that's a
separate issue anyway.
I don't really know what it's this one right yet.
You can see that we still match in both cases, so that's like I said,
that's that GL viewport call.
We did it in both cases, when we switch the suffer under, we get the
same warping which is good.
We want to be the same both cases.
But what we'd like to do is do something better than what we're
getting here in both cases.
All right, so let's start if we can.
Let's start by talking about the problem on the Blackboard a little
bit just so you can understand what's actually going on if you're
unfamiliar with this and then we can go ahead and come up with a fix
for it.
So here we are on day 3.
22, and this is aspect ratio.
Oops.
Not raishin ratio resize and we, I can't remember.
We may have already covered this.
I can't quite remember
when we do our display buffer to window,
So it doesn't look like we.
Yeah, we always split 121 here so we didn't really address this ever
it.
Here it is.
So there's a to do centering black bars.
Okay?
Just wanted to make sure I wasn't telling you something that you
already knew if you watch the series.
Okay.
So here's our basic problem, we have a number of things as game
developers that we can choose to do with respect to supporting
multiple monitor size.
Some of them are much harder than others and we're going to take a
kind of a middle ground with handmade hero and we're not going to go
too far down the rabbit hole but you know, I'm going to least tell you
sort of what those tranches are.
So one way is, you know, no aspect ratio.
For it.
Right.
One way is sort of like a black bar.
And another way is like, you know, actual I guess aspect of where, I
guess we'll call it.
And I'll briefly talk about what these are.
So the simplest thing to do obviously is just not support different
aspect ratios, right.
And what do I mean by that?
Well, what I mean by that is, let's say you made the game and you made
it at 1920 by 1080, right?
That's what you did.
So you decided that's the resolution.
I'm running my game at that has an aspect ratio.
Right?
And you know, if you've never heard of aspect ratio before, it's
probably you have because even if you don't program, you probably
heard of aspect ratio.
Aspect ratio is just talking about how long one side of the monitor,
is to how long the other side is, right?
And so, typically a 1920 by 1080 or HDTV, sort of aspect ratio is 16
on the long side by nine on the on the short side, right?
So we typically call this a 16 by 9 aspect ratio and you can kind of
see that that's you know, a standard 1080p television, whatever is
going to be that.
At as a standard.
It's it's a common thing to be.
It's what a lot of monitors are.
Although there are plenty of other ones like 16 by 10 and whatever
else.
Okay, so one way is to just not have aspect ratio support.
Let the, let the cim the monitor figure it out, just don't deal with
it and what that tends to look like in practice in a game is there's a
Windows called called change display settings.
And what it does is it basically allows you to just straight-up change
the displays resolution to what you wanted it to be right.
So what you do here is you pass.
Let's see.
Where is it?
Hmm.
Got a hot through for it.
Here we go.
You pass a certain pels with and Pell's height, which is the height
and width of the screen in pixels, and you just say windows.
This is the display resolution I want, and you're going to have to
figure out a way to get it, right?
So we would just call that with 1920 by.
An 80 and be like, good luck and then the monitor will do, whatever
the monitor will do.
So the monitor gets a signal at 1920 by 1080, hopefully the monitor
supports it if it doesn't you're totally, you know, game won't even
run.
Right?
I'll just show a screen where the monitor just comes up with thing
that says, like, unrecognized video signal or something, right?
But if the monitors needed of resolution, isn't that?
If the monitor is 16 by 10 residents, say, instead of 16 by 9, it will
figure out something to do, who knows?
Maybe it'll stretch, maybe I'll put black bars on the top and the
bottom.
Mmm, who knows what he'll do, right?
But the point is, you can choose to have no aspect ratio support in
the game whatsoever.
If you wanted to, and plenty of games actually do that, they just said
a resolution and they just expect you to have a monitor that will cope
with it.
And that's it, right?
So, we're not going to do that one.
Okay.
We're going to try to do a little better than that one.
We're going to shoot for black bar and we'll talk about that in a
second.
But then, let me talk about this one first, since it's another one
that we're not going to do aspect, aware games are
Games which try to put a bunch of logic into the game to allow you to
play it at any conceivable aspect ratio, right?
Now, this is very difficult to do with a 2-D game, like ours, which is
why I'm not going to do it.
It's not particularly difficult with certain types of games.
For example, first person shooters are actually quite simple to make
aspect aware.
Now, it may not be so easy to guarantee a fair multiplayer experience
because the fov is going to change and there's going to be a bunch of
like sort of other things.
But as least, as far as a single player, first person game, making it
a
To where it's actually pretty easy.
Now, why is that?
Well, what is aspect of where mean, well, aspect of, where means that,
you know, I've got a game and maybe the game runs on a screen that
looks like this or maybe the game runs on a screen, that's a little
bit wider.
And there's extra room or maybe even a little wider than that, right?
Or maybe it's on a screen that's like taller, right?
And who knows, right?
And again we're specifically talking about aspect ratio here, not
resolution because there are two different things right.
One is about, you know, if it's just resolution, we can just scale.
If the aspect ratio is the same, we can just scale our bitmaps up or
down and me and maybe they look a little blurry or because we had to
do that, but we can accommodate that pretty well.
But the fundamental aspect ratio is like the shape of what we're
drawing, right?
Whether it's wide or not and that has implications hopefully you can
understand
Why that isn't patients.
But anyway, for a 3D game for a free 3D, like first person shooter
now, 3D game.
If it was a 3D game that was just like, ours did solve the same
problem, so it's really not 3D or 2D.
It's more about the sort of type of game.
But for an FPS, right?
All you need to know is that well, there's a gun in the corner.
So we have to kind of put that gun in the corner, right?
And then there's maybe like a health bar up here.
So we need to just put that whole thing in the corner.
But then otherwise, we just render the scene with whatever are like
view for us to actually is and we're done, right?
So in order to make a simple first person, shooter aspect ratio where
it's not that hard.
You just have to know where the corners of the screen are and sort of
like correctly place a few special items and now you're done.
So making an aspect ratio where one of those is not particularly
difficult, right?
The design of
The game doesn't really change that dramatically again for a simple.
First person shooter you could.
Imagine first person shooters that maybe had a lot to do with the
screen size.
So you can't say for all it's not true for all game designs but for a
certainly something like Quake Arena.
Let's say you could totally do this but for a game like ours, we don't
really have that ability and the reason for that is we're kind of
counting on a particular room shape and we need you to be able to see
that whole room, right?
And that room needs to be on the screen.
In the whole time for gameplay reasons.
So there really is no way to make our game aspect ratio aware without.
I mean, it possibly, it might not even be feasible right to do it.
May it may literally not be able to do the design that I have.
May not simply work aspect ratio where so because since you know you
need to see this thing and that is the shape, there's really nothing
you can do about that.
All you can do is just maybe like, you know, pad out by putting some
extra UI on some, you know, you could try to maybe decorate it.
Little bit but fundamentally speaking.
You're going to have to show that aspect ratio image somewhere on the
screen and you're going to be left with empty space if that's not the
shape of the monitor.
Right?
Which is a problem.
You don't have in this circumstance so that's why I'm not going to do
that one.
What I'm going to do is basically the middle ground here which is sort
of black bar aspect ratio where, which is to say that we will ensure
that you get a reasonable crisp, image, centered and stretched
appropriately.
So that it fills your monitor as much as it can given the aspect ratio
that you have and that we need, right?
So what that,
Tails is saying well okay we know that we need to draw a 16 by 9
image.
So if your monitor is actually 16 by 10, we will figure that out.
We will draw the image here, right?
And then we'll fill this in here and here with black so that you don't
see it, right?
So that it's so that it's like minimally invasive.
Just like a letterbox home movie, right?
And again, the reason I think it's better for us to do that then to
call change display settings and have the monitor that is because we
don't know what the monitor is going to do change, display settings is
disruptive to the user experience, right?
And furthermore, it doesn't really address the problem of if the user
wanted to play in a window, which, you know, maybe we want to support.
Maybe we don't, but if we do, if they want to draw on a window, you're
going to have this problem regardless because you can't call change
display settings for the window.
The window is however, big the user stretched it, right?
So that's, that's what we'd like to do, okay?
So, in order to do that aspect ratio stuff correctly, what we would
like to do here is do exactly sort of that procedure.
We have essentially two cases
That we're dealing with, right?
We are dealing with the case where the monitor
Has extra room on the top and bottom in which case we need to fill
those with blank space.
And the other case is the sort of opposite of that where the top and
bottom, fill just nicely.
Oops.
But the sides.
Are missing, right?
And so conceptually speaking.
What we're doing is we're saying okay, tell me how big the monitor is.
We're going to start in here with a 16 by 9 rectangle, right?
We're going to sort of expand the rectangle up until it hits either
the monitors you know vertical edges or its horizontal edges.
If it hits these horizontal edges first then we know we would be
filling here right?
If instead.
If she hits these edges first, that's what would stop it from getting
bigger.
Then we would know we were filling their right?
So that's the fundamental math that we have to do but once we do that
math then we kind of know exactly what we need.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to make a little piece of code
here.
That is capable of determining this I'm going to put it in the opengl
side of things for the moment.
Although we'll probably want to pull it out into something that we can
use elsewhere, don't know.
Well we might have, do we have some kind of a shared?
Got some shared things here, so in the shared code, I could just put
it in here for the aspect ratio.
I could also put it in a render.
That's probably the best place for it.
I mean, it is a rendering only kind of a thing.
So yeah, so let's say that we had something where we were going to to
specify this
And I guess I don't really need a separate type of return for it.
I suppose I can just use regular rectangle return for it that seems
reasonable.
So I suppose I can just say, like, okay, I want to return a rectangle
to I, that is the aspect ratio adjusted location, right?
Aspect ratio fit, something like this.
And so, what I want to do is I want to say, all right?
I've got a, you know,
A render with.
And a render height that I'm dealing with.
And then I have
Window width.
And a window height that I'm dealing with and I want you to do the
necessary fitting to make those work out, right?
Like I want you to sort of return me.
The rectangle.
I would use inside the window to draw what I'm trying to draw.
So since I said, we had two cases, obviously.
We have.
And you know what?
I'm going to do here too.
I'm going to just do a quick check to make sure if render with.
I want everything to be greater than 0.
Because there's really no result and we're going to be doing some
divides.
So, before we go any further, I just want to say everything's got to
be.
We're going to return AB 0 rechtin on blit.
Basically, if you don't give us a something to actually work with
So then, I'm going to basically mirror those two cases.
Like, you know, we have two cases are going to mirror those two cases,
and, by the way, I should add, there's obviously a third case here,
which is, it fits directly, right?
But we don't really have to consider that case because either of these
two cases will work in that if it happened to fit.
Exactly.
Either case will work out to an exact rectangle that fills, right?
So we don't have to the reason I didn't explicitly enumerate that case
is because we won't actually do that case.
so, what we need to know now,
Is we need to know some fundamental ratios, right?
We need to know what the aspect ratio is that we actually want, right?
And then we need to see what will happen if we try to use the the the
window at that aspect ratio, okay?
So let me show you kind of let me just sort of type in the code a
little bit here and we'll sort of talk about the equation that on the
Whiteboard, if that makes sense.
so in this case, I'm going to ask, if I took the render with right and
divided it by the render height,
Okay, this would sort of giving give me a, I don't know what I would
call it.
It's a it's sort of a fundamental multiplier, right?
This aspect ratio, it's a fundamental multiplier that if you gave me
another height, it would tell me what the height would be based on
this ratio, right?
So, you know, just trying to ground it.
A little bit for you here.
If I take some width and I
Divide it by some height, right?
Then what I do if I multiply by some other height,
Here, right?
If I'm going to multiply out by some other height here is I sort of I
cancel out the Heights and I'm left with a width that's in that new
sort of space, if that makes sense.
You can kind of think of these.
Almost, as units might be a good way to think of it, really.
If I take, you know, x with
Over y height, right?
And then I multiply it by, you know, a height.
Right, then my Heights cancel, right?
And I'm left with, you know, a x over y width and that is the width
that a, that a would have implied, right?
If it was at the same ratio as this original ratio.
I'm trying to think of a, I feel like my brains too mushy today.
For some reason, I feel like that's not a good enough explanation of
this.
What I'm trying to say is once you produce an aspect ratio, right?
So once I have with over height,
once I have an aspect ratio, you can think of this as a fundamental
constant that allows me to generate other widths, whatever the
numerator is, it allows me to generate other widths that are in the
same proportion to some Heights as this with was to this height,
right?
So if I have with zero over height zero and I want to know what with
one would be like what is with one?
If I know H1, then the answer is I just have to multiply it by this
fundamental aspect ratio, right?
Because with one over height one, right.
We're saying if it equals if I want the aspect ratios of these two to
be equal, right?
Then you can see if I solved for with one.
I would end up with 1 equals with zero times height 1 over height 0.
You can I
Isolate that term, right?
And say that that's with zero over height zero times height one,
right?
And that's exactly the term I was talking about before.
So if you want to set up a bunch of fundamental similarities there or
if you're thinking in terms of them, it just helps to go.
Oh, right?
Once I compute one of these, I can always multiply by whatever the
type of thing was on the denominator to produce an arbitrary numerator
that goes with it, right?
So, you know, and it's because of this fundamental relation.
That two things over each other.
When I equate them, I know, I can always multiply out one way or the
other I can, you know, I can solve for w 0 or solve for w 1 and you
know, compute one in terms of the other.
All right, so that's what I want to do here.
I want to do exactly that equation.
Like here's that fundamental thing that I produced and what I want to
do here is say okay, I am going to ask if I was to multiply the window
height.
By this fundamental aspect ratio, for my render, what do I actually
get back as like, the optimal window with right?
And then that is the same token.
I could ask what the optimal window height is by applying the same
logic.
If I was to take the window with and multiply it by the same exact
thing just flipped around, right?
You can see I'm doing the same thing, I'm just saying, okay, I want to
produce widths now, so do the opposite thing keep with on the the, the
Divide.
So when I multiply out, I'll get whatever the height should be.
So this gives me two fundamental values back that are telling me what
would the window with be and what would the window height be?
If I was to pick one or the other as predominant?
Rap they may ask.
Why am I doing that?
You know.
Well, the answer is because this is what will allow me to determine
which case I have, right?
So in this case,
I can say, let's see what we got.
When we said what the optimal window with was, right.
So I use the given window height and I said, tell me what the optimal
window with was.
Well, if the optimal window width is greater than the actual window
with right?
What I have to work with, then I know that I must be bounded by that
with, right.
In other words, I would have hit the width first before the height
would have hit.
Otherwise I can assume the opposite, right?
I can assume that if the with would fit, then that means the height is
actually, the thing that stopped it, right?
So in this case, if it's greater, you know, if the optimal window
width is greater than the window,
And maybe I will not think start with it.
So this is a width constrained
Display and this is a height, constrained display.
And so if its height constrained, then I have, you know, left and
right black bars.
And if it's a with constrained,
Right.
Then I've got top and bottom.
If that makes sense.
Okay, so let's think about what ends up happening here.
I want to produce a rectangle to, I, that rectangle to, I is what I'm
going to use to sort of, like, fill the screen properly or whatever.
Right.
I need to, like, put, I need to like, say where the image is going to
be centered or whatever.
So, in a with constrained display where I've got top and bottom black
bars, that means that I know that my result,
Is going to have a very simple structure as far.
And, you know what, I don't really even remember what our rectangle 2i
structure looks like.
There it is.
So I know that since we have top and bottom black bars, I know the Min
X is going to be 0 and the max X is going to be the window width,
right?
I know that I'm feeling my entire width, but what I don't know is what
the Min Y and Max, why are because I don't know where, you know, the
image ends up getting centered.
But I can easily find out.
So what we have is empty space, right?
I know what when I did the optimal window with here, I know that it
didn't fit.
So I know that optimal window.
Height is going to tell me if I was to assume we were with constrained
because that's what I was doing here, right?
I said, figure out what the window height would be if we're going to
stretch to the full width of the of the screen, whatever the window
height is.
That's going to leave some space.
So if I take the actual window height and subtract the two, I will get
however much space is left over, right?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
Now, we have a problem here, which is the optimal window.
Height may actually not be rounded if that makes sense, right?
We may have a situation where the render written render height were
producing a divide that ends up with like a .5 in there or something,
right?
Or something that's not an integral amount.
So we do have a bit of an issue there where we would, you know, we
kind of have to know that we're going to round because this empty
space
May end up being not a whole value.
So when we go half empty
and I divide that by 2 there, right?
I now kind of have to round that value so that we won't be positioning
on a completely bogus boundary, right?
So I'm going to do around here.
Really.
Yeah.
and,
similarly, I'm going to have to round
How much were using for our actual height?
And so we might be off by like a half a pixel somewhere, but that's
okay.
We don't want to render to a fractional pixel, so that's fine.
So now we're in a position to know what R Min Y and Max.
Why, our first of all our Max, why obviously, is always going to be
just the Min, why?
Oops.
Plus, however, much the height was so that's pretty easy.
And the Min Y is just going to be that half empty value, right?
However, much empty space.
We had left over.
We put half of it.
The top half of it, the bottom right.
Seems pretty straightforward.
Okay.
So barring bugs or a logic errors.
That's basically what we're doing and the same thing is 100% true on
the other axis as well, right.
We can assume that if we are high constrained, we're going to draw to
the entire height of the screen.
We can also assume that, you know, any place that we were talking
about Heights.
We're now talking about with
Like so.
And so then the rest of this is just a trivial replacement.
Okay, so now we've got aspect ratio fit and now we just have to use
it.
Well we have to debug it obviously at some point but we have to
actually use it somewhere because we don't actually use it anywhere
that it's not going to actually do anything for us to say the least,
but the place that we probably want to use that is here in our opengl
subsystem.
And so in order to do that, when we pass the window, with that window
height here, what we really probably want to do is, is passed in that.
Tangled to I right.
We probably want to actually do something more like this.
Where we say like okay what's the rectangle to?
I that we're talking about here that's going to be like the draw
region or something like that, right?
And so the interesting thing about that is, once we do the that draw
region thing, then I think 4gl viewport, we can actually just pass
these directly.
But I think since it's a, it's a with and I don't actually know if
you've got this call, we probably have a get dim.
Well, I don't know if we do or not, I would like to get with Anna, get
height on online.
So I'm going to add one of those
Yeah, we don't have one.
So again this is totally trivial, right?
And I'm conveying the up.
The convention that we don't include the final row, that's why it's -
not.
It's why.
That's why we don't add one here.
If the, so if the Max and the Min are coincident, that means it's an
empty rectangle.
Not that it's a one pixel long rectangle, just worth pointing out.
Because there's two conventions you could have followed their
All right.
so,
That's all well and good.
And I think that would work at the start.
But the problem we would have here is that that viewport is not going
to be correct for our for our frame buffers because if our frame
buffer is just used the renderable part, they don't want to use this
Min X Min why they want to use 00 window like they since the render
buffers are only the size that we're actually rendering to, right?
Oops.
They want to do this.
Right when we're drawing to them.
So, you know, when we bind a frame buffer here, you know you could
imagine wanting to do that essentially and you know we could do that
down here.
I suppose you want something that looks like this for the targets that
are greater than Target one.
I guess since this is bound up here and this is only doing new ones,
maybe that's the right place to do it.
It's hard to say, let's do it here.
But the thing that I'm not sure about and I tried to look this up
yesterday and I failed is is GL viewport per frame buffer or not like
where is that state actually stored?
Let's see, GL, you pour it.
That doesn't help us.
Stack Overflow.
Always a little scared to look at an answer here.
So this says, Okay, so this person looks like they actually quoted the
spec which is starting to contain sales the entire State State per
frame buffer object draw buffers and rebuff or viewport isn't part of
it, right?
So if that's the case, then if we want to support the multiple sizes,
we've got to do it here.
So we basically have to do rgl viewport call.
every time we
Find.
So I'm going to have to kind of abstract this, right?
Hmm.
Okay, so in this case, we've got like Jill Biden frame buffer.
If the target is greater than 0, we do this.
Otherwise we do that, right?
That's kind of how that has to go.
And so what I could do here is just do a thing where we say like
internal void, Vine frame buffer,
And when we do that bind I could just sort of grab this out like so so
that it's just used properly in all in both cases.
So there's the target index, it'll just do this and then we know that
we have to pass the draw region to that because without the drawer
region, it won't have the information that it actually needs to have,
right?
So that seems reasonable and then down here.
So when we do that, we'll just call opengl buying frame buffer with
the current frame buffer and that draw region.
Oops.
And the same thing would be true up here.
Let's see, opengl renderer commands is now taking this window with and
window height and we don't actually want it to do that.
What we want to do is we want to have it take a rectangle to I which
is the render region, right?
And for now I'm actually going to just pass it.
What we were passing it before just so we can make sure that our
render stuff works properly because any time you're working with
opengl.
I find it's good to like double-check when you test stuff, not
Just assume that it's going to work, right?
So yeah.
So anyway
That looks the same as it did before.
So, that's good.
So now let's go into here and say, okay, instead of using that to our
region, let's actually go ahead and try out this aspect ratio fit,
call that we had here.
So, instead of doing the stretch version,
We'll call aspect ratio fit and we will pass it.
Our commands render with and commands render height, and then our
window within window height, and we'll let it figure it out.
What we want to do, as far as that's concerned, right, what was
I don't actually remember, oh well you know what should just be right
here, shouldn't it commands with?
So it's not render with, it's just width and height.
Oops, got a little overzealous there with that delete key.
Didn't want to delete that.
Let's undo.
Okay.
So now we're calling aspect ratio fit and you can actually see that I
guess we must have done a good job because it looks like it just is
working actually already.
So you can kind of see what's happening here as we do that.
That sort of scaling as you know, here is the case where we're sort of
well I guess here is the case where we match we exactly fill right.
And I guess I could find that here on the window size as well.
Right?
And so if I were to and you can see that that yellow band is like the
actual border of the rendered region, as I start to smoosh in words,
you can see it adding the bars on the top and the bottom because this
aspect ratio is too tall for a 16 by 9, right?
So it continues to kind of shrink that down and down and down, you
know, which is what it's supposed to do.
Now similarly if I stretch it out, it knows that it's going to hit on
the other direction.
So it just pads on the left and right.
Okay.
Now we're not doing this correctly here with with, let's see here,
Global Runner type with respect to the software renderer at the
moment.
So we need to fix that but that's pretty easy to do as well.
All we have to do is when we do opengl display bitmap, we just have to
do the same.
Thing we were doing before.
So I'm going to go ahead and move this up to the top like so,
So that when we do our opengl display bitmap call and we're passing at
this window with the window height, instead of that, I'm actually
going to pass it, the draw region instead, right?
So then if we go over to opengl displayed bitmap,
Which actually is not in there.
Okay, so if we come over here to opengl display pic map and we do sort
of this window with window height part here.
I'm going to take that out of here and just do rectangle to I4, draw
region.
And we're going to do exactly the same thing that we were doing
before.
Now what I can do, in this case two is I can just lean on the fact
that this call doesn't actually care about whether you even have any
other things, you can still use it.
As you were using it before.
So if I want to I can kind of come up here and just say well you know
what?
Just use opengl bind frame buffer and just buying frame buffer, zero
and that'll set everything up for us to exactly the way we wanted to
write.
so, we can pass the
Our region and we can pass frame by 40 and it'll just work.
So,
now, in theory, let's see here where we do Platform controls
There we go.
Now, you can see the same exact thing.
Right.
Okay, so now we have a couple little tiny issues that we probably want
to clear up and that is well first of all, I suppose are clear color
here, we're going to have to actually clear to something real, right?
So we want this to be, you know, black, presumably so that when we
clear,
See rendering type true.
So this way, you know, it's black bars, which is I think what we said
we wanted, although I suppose we could choose to do gray bars instead.
I don't know what we want to do exactly with that.
I suppose, we could just clear to whatever the background color is
from the render commands.
That seems plausible.
So, when we do opengl display bitmap, we would probably just say, hey,
give us the clear color, right?
And
Then.
Here, we could pass the commands clear color.
And now it's just whatever the user specified which I think is what we
want.
And so let's go ahead and take a look at that platform controls will
rendering type.
Okay, yeah, so I think that's about it.
I also think that we should probably get rid of the outlining in our
opengl stuff because that was, you know,
Not really part of the spec.
And that's about it.
I think that's it for handling the aspect ratio stuff properly.
I'm not 100% sure, but I think that's most of what that bug was
talking about.
So I believe we did that properly and we handled this properly.
I think both of those are correct.
I don't know what this is.
Multiple opengl render targets.
I don't really know what that's about.
So I'm going to say that I believe this is fixed and will let people
sit reopen it.
If I didn't quite right, I guess I need a little more room here.
How do I do that?
Oh, there it is.
It's called clothes issue.
so, I guess I can just say
Believed to be fixed on, day, on day, 22, right?
So you got day 322 by the addition of aspect ratio, we're splitting
and rendering
Close comic.
Okay.
So I think that's correct.
And yeah.
So we have did anyone is this it?
Yeah.
So while we're on it I feel like we should do this one as well and I
guess we already have it open here somewhere.
Where is it?
There it is.
We should do this one as well because we don't really have
Any awareness, the mouse cursor that were passing is not adjusted for
this, where the thing is actually being displayed, if that makes
sense.
So, as long as they happen to coincide,
They're going to be sort of okay, although the stretching even the
stretching, we don't divide by the stretch at all either.
So even that's wrong because the the distance you go will be wrong so
you can see it wrong.
They're right.
So the only time is this correct?
Is if you happen to be running on an actual 1920 by 1080 screen and
and you go in there right now, that's not actually our game codes
fault, our game code, I don't think.
Anyway, I don't think our game code actually has a bug there.
Personally, the bug is in the platform layer because the platform
layer is getting us Mouse coordinates that aren't in the same
coordinates as where it's bleeding.
The screen, right?
We're drawing to a buffer and we're assuming that when we get Mass
coordinates from the game that those Mouse coordinates are in the same
space as the buffer were drawing, but that's not true.
Right there in there.
The space of Windows, which is totally unadjusted, right?
So what we need to do here for our debug Mouse, and again, it's only
for debug because we don't really do anything with the mouse in
production.
We're keyboard game.
So we don't really have to care too much about this but we might as
well get it right when we do our Mouse values.
You can see here, we map screen to client but then we don't have
anything that actually maps from the client rectangle of our window to
where we're actually displaying the bitmap.
So we need to do that mapping now as well, right?
And we should probably actually do a little bit of fussing with that
too but anyway.
So if I wanted to fix that, obviously I'm going to have to have some
way of remembering what that rectangle is that I used to draw, right?
So that draw region that we have here, we're going to need to save
that basically is what's going to have to happen so that it can keep
coming around you know, and and be something that we use in in
multiple circumstances, right?
Now I want to take a look at something here with window within a
window height.
Yeah.
So we've got kind of this old path in your.
I might even just get rid of this old path to be honest with you.
I don't know if I want to support displaying through GDI anymore just
because it's you know, we're going to want to kind of go through the
The vsync path anyway.
So I'm a ditch this.
I think that, maybe, maybe we should.
We can always put it back in if we really want it.
so I mean instead say instead of win32 rendering type on my ditch this
And say we just have D 32 Global software rendering.
and then I'm going to go through here and say, if global
Software rendering, then we're going to do this.
Otherwise we're going to do this.
And in this case here, we're just going to assume that we display the
bitmap.
Oops
Assume we display the bitmap through opengl and we'll sort of get rid
of the notion that we're ever going to stretch.
But it using anything else, okay?
Okay, so that's the first step, right?
And hopefully now the still works fine for toggling our software
renderer on and off.
they were down, and
Global software rendering what I would like to do.
Now is just have the draw region, be something that's actually passed
in because now we got window with the window height and you can see
they're not really used anywhere in here.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to pull this out and I'd like to go
ahead and say we'll just pass the rectangle to.
I of the drawer region will pass that in when we actually call when 3
display buffer and window, right?
So down here, now, we will say, okay, here's our aspect ratio fit
call.
We've got these two variables which tell us what we're talking about
Dimension wise.
So there they are.
And then I will say, this is the drawer region, okay?
And so, you can see what I'm kind of going for here.
Now that I've kind of pulled this out into the outer area of the code.
Now, we have the ability
Ought to just save this value all the time, right?
This can be computed anywhere we want.
We could compute it up before we do the mouse, right?
So in the place where we actually grab that mouse cursor, right?
When we do input processing, we can snap the the region here and now
we know the draw region where we needed to know it, but where are my
render commands?
There we go.
Well, okay, so do I actually have?
I don't think there's any reason I can't move that up as well.
so now if I just do that part early, so now I kind of know what is
going on input processing wise
I can map things into the straw region if I need to.
So, when I actually do my mouse, now, when I have my mouse X, I can
map it into that region in terms of scaling of mapping and scaling the
value, right?
So, how do I map the value, right?
Well, fortunately, in our math, we already have a way and we've gone
over this multiple times.
Right?
Clamp zero to one map to range.
We have a way of, of forcing something in between two values into a
120 range, right?
So I can call it whatever.
The mouse key comes back as right?
This new input mousex mouth.
Why what I could do is I could say well, alright, let's say the new
input mousex and the new input Mouse why let's actually make those be
different things and we'll sort of here.
Here start by taking these base Mouse values and then we'll sort of
modify them, right?
So I can do clamp 01 map to range on mousex and clamp, 01 mapped range
on Mouse.
Why?
And I can take those and map them into the min/max of the draw region,
right?
Because I know where the draw region is
Right.
So what I'm basically doing is I'm saying I'm taking wherever my mouse
was, and I'm mapping it into that range, that's zero to one, mapping
it to be zero to one based on where it is.
So 0 0, is the upper or sorry, the bottom left corner and, you know,
11 is the upper.
So, they're basically UV coordinates now, right?
Then I can just multiplied by the width.
N multiplied by the height to blow them out, to the pixel values, the
virtual pixel values that the game is effectively expecting, right?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
And unfortunately, these are all not, there we go.
Not floats.
And they need to be
Okay, so I can go over that it during the Q&A if that was a little too
abrupt in terms of what I did there, but you can see the mouse cursor
is working.
Okay, now, let's go ahead and change it to something really bizarre
and make sure the massacres are still does work.
Okay, although it doesn't look like it is, so I may have to debug in
to do here.
That's that's plainly bizarre.
What did I mess up?
The mass x is the mouse p and draw a region.
Dot Min x.
Max y, that feels like it should be right.
And then we expand that by however much the width was
Oh I'm sorry.
This is it should not be the width of the draw region.
It should be the renderable with obviously.
I mean we're trying to pass it to the game in in terms of its
preferred render size.
So the that's it's like I undid the Divide I did in the clamp map to
range.
That makes no sense.
Sorry.
Just momentary.
Brain lapse there.
Okay, so here we are, in the normal case.
Let's go back to the window case.
And I'm still fail.
I am still fail.
What did I mess up?
I have to admit, I don't immediately know what I messed up there.
Well, I'm gonna step in.
I realized was just being the Q&A right now, but I'm step in any way
because I want to debug this, I don't think.
It should be so complicated as I apparently just made it and you know
what else I'll do here.
This way, you can see it.
Okay, so let's go ahead and step in there.
Well actually it's not step in yet because it works properly at full
screen.
So I need to First sort of get the window to the point where it
doesn't work anymore.
There we go.
so, we can kind of see like,
It's, it's like I'm at the top right now, which doesn't make a whole
lot of sense, right?
So, you know, this should be the bottom corner.
This should be like, basically 00, right?
So let's go ahead and and see what we actually get there.
So our Mouse V is just totally wrong Mouse.
Why for our region?
And then why are our region now?
Why?
So why is the 0?
Because this is an incorrect.
I didn't even look at the calculation.
We were doing.
This is totally bogus right here.
So that is probably the problem.
So yeah, this this mouse P, this whole thing with the global back,
buffer height, that shouldn't be the global back buffer height.
That should be the actual
But the actual size of the window, right?
That should be the dimension part that should be this.
Right?
So that's just a completely wrong calculation.
It's inverting the mouse coordinate based on a totally wrong value.
So that's yeah.
Well, that's probably the entire problem.
That would certainly do it.
All right.
So now our Mouse coordinates are being passed correctly and it looks
like everything is hunky-dory.
There looks really accurate to me.
We can switch here.
Okay, so now we can go ahead and go to the Q&A.
Yeah, and that's, you know, I I say this all the time, right?
Because I've been asked this so many times.
The amount of time it takes to bug to find a bug is always about where
you're looking, right?
Because, like, I was looking at these lines and going like, oh wait,
but they look right.
It's like yeah, they were right.
You know what I mean?
Like, it's like the part that I was scrutinizing expecting to be
wrong, was not the problem.
It was this part here and that's why it was so weird to see what was
happening.
Right?
Because you always have like these assumptions about
What you were doing and those are when those assumptions are wrong,
that's what leads to more bug time.
Now it's at that bug took, you know, any time to find but you know,
Why?
It wasn't immediately obvious?
So, let's see.
All right, so I think you didn't get to a lot of these unfortunately,
but that's okay.
I mean bug sometimes take a while to find.
So we've got some more to do.
Maybe we'll do some more tomorrow.
Some of these.
Look a little bit simple, some of them look a little more complicated,
but see if we got any qas,
Cubicle that before today, I have a 16 by 9 Monitor and when I change
the code to render that resolution, both the you I Picking, and the
Collision detection for the player, get all sorts of messed up, but I
haven't tested that since you've removed the free moving stuff.
Okay.
Hey I can you make it so that holding shift while resizing the window?
Makes it just scale at the intended.
Aspect ratio.
Oh, do you mean like forcing the window itself to always be at that
aspect ratio?
What did somebody say?
Hold on a second.
Got a lot of questions here so holding the shift.
Let's pause the hold shift thing because I don't know if we'll have
time for that.
At the moment.
But let's see.
You forgot to change use height to use width.
Oh yeah, that's true.
It doesn't affect the code at all, but it's Naaman, clay chur wrong.
so,
so thanks.
Thanks for that one.
Two-parter, if that's okay.
I'd like to start working on a homemade 3D game engine of my own how
much of what you have done here transfers over basically all the all
the code besides the renderer, the renderer is totally not going to
help you, right?
But all the rest of the stuff makes sense.
Be, when do you define how long a second is in the game?
How does the lighting work in regards to time?
I'm going to have to go ahead and say I don't understand Part B.
Those seem to be two totally unrelated things, lighting and time
Like the only yeah, I'm sorry.
I don't think I
and,
How would you suggest a younger developer to get into opengl and all
of its useful extensions?
Well, that's tough.
So, Nvidia has some great presentations on a CDO
which tell you everything that you need to know.
See if they've got a good one here.
Here we go.
So here's the thing, where I and I assume this kind of comes the
opengl a video teams like, hey, you know, you don't really need to use
Vulcan because we got all that stuff in opengl already.
If you just use it this page, basically tells you all the stuff, the
problem is, if you're younger development, don't allow experience,
you're going to read it and go like, I have no idea they're talking
about, right?
So, I don't know how you get to the point where you can read and
understand this page, but if you can read and understand this page,
this tells you
The stuff you needed to know, right?
Because it's got it all on here.
In particular, pay attention to this, this one's a big one.
Our buffer storage is probably one of the coolest things ever.
It's, it's like what you want.
It's great.
It's like it's about time I guess what I would say but yeah.
So in terms of what the useful extensions are there kind of all listed
here with pointers to wear to read more about them.
But how you get to the point where, you know, what this is talking
about?
I think you kind of have to just go do some basic opengl programming
instead, right?
Did you ever go through the Insight plug-in on stream?
No, I can't.
I don't think because this is an AMD card, I don't even think, I don't
know.
If inside even works on AMD, it might I've never tried it but I don't
We can use that.
Off topic which keyboard layout to use.
I just use standard QWERTY.
Have you tried the various layouts?
I've read that QWERTY can be a bit less efficient for programming.
What do you think?
I don't think it probably would matter that much to be honest.
You know, I type pretty fast on Cordy.
I don't know that I could, I mean, maybe a better keyboard layout
would get me an extra 20 percent or something.
But I don't know that that's enough to relearn.
and anyway, if you have experienced an opengl, but
With the extensions then.
Yeah.
I'd start with this page and then go read about all the extensions.
They talk about right.
Okay.
And and like they have like, here's a presentation.
GDC presentation, they did one of their sponsored sessions or
something, right?
You could watch this and hear what they have to say, you know.
So so a CDO is a search term.
I think is what you're looking for and that should unlock a lot of of
hits for you, right?
And so, let's let's take a look at the question.
Someone asked, we're holding the shift key down.
Would constrain the Jimmy.
Would constrain the size of the window and yeah.
So I don't think about that.
I'm not sure what the most correct way to do that is so, so yeah.
I'm interested to see if Raymond Chen has a specific.
Thing where he says the best way to tell Windows the size, but it
doesn't look that way.
Let's see.
So it looks like he is suggesting we do it on, get min-max, info.
It looks like
so I think it looks like we only have to handle that maybe.
He seems to think that should be sufficient, I think.
So let's give it a shot.
And I said this before, when we did full screen, I'll just say it
again.
In case you didn't watch the full screen episode, whenever I want to
do something that has to do with like a sort of Tweaky Windows thing.
I always try to double check to see if Raymond Chen has said the right
way to do it because he is the master of twiki Windows things and he
has access to the source code which I don't.
So when he says, you know, this is probably the most efficient or at
least error-prone really is usually the thing way to tell Windows to
do something.
I always start with whatever.
He says, because it's, I find.
Usually, the most likely thing to just work.
so, if we want to handle, get min-max info, it says that the L / am
points to the min/max info structure, but I don't actually know,
What.
It's even got to fill out in here.
I assume
I assume it's Max position that it cares about.
Let's see, the maximum tracking size, the largest window size be
reduced by using the bar decides the window, the minimum tracking
size, the small sort of the side screws because in the Border size of
the window,
well, see that might work for what he was saying to do, but that's not
going to work for what we are saying to do, is it
Mmm because he just wanted to force it to only size in One Direction
and that's that's not going to work here.
So
So yeah.
Let's see.
so, looking at this,
This might be better.
Let's see.
Okay, when a university different fraction up because could override
these defaults
Well, this message is being processed modifying, any of the ones with
affects the windows new site solution or place in the Z order at a can
prevent change the Widow by clearing throat.
Okay?
So it sounds like what we could do.
Right is we could intercept this message.
So, we know when we are going to have our size changed, right?
And we could say when
Our window posts size is changing.
We have the L per annum, in this case.
Process pending messages is there.
A reason we are?
There's our wind proc want this in the wind park.
There we go.
So this L pram and theory is a pointer to one of these things window
pose.
And then when I can do is just I'm going to pass that message through
to the existing Windows procedure.
Right?
So in theory, if we just do this we should have you.
No no.
No change.
Now if we have Windows post changing and we want to modify this pose,
then in theory week, should be able to just reach into it and change
the the actual CX, and Cy values, which are the width and the height.
So, what we could do here is say, let's just force the aspect ratio to
be correct.
So, you know, whichever one you whichever one got changed, we'll use
the
corresponding one probably or maybe we could just do the closest one
trying to think of what the
best way to us would be.
So I think what I feel like we should do is say like
window wrecked equals get window wrecked.
And we'll just say, like, tell us how big our window currently is.
Well, then look at which one which change was bigger.
so we'll say like, you know, if if
you know, maybe the
Absolute value.
We have an absolute value function.
This I don't even know if the absolute value of CX minus the with
right.
Just compute the with that the window was before.
Right.
So it's like this is the width and height we were before the new pose
has what they will be I guess I could do get window pose.
Today, is there such a thing?
Apparently not.
Of course, there's not there's a set window pose, but not to get
window pose.
I mean, let's not be ridiculous.
Here people.
Hilarious.
Anyway.
So let's take a look and see is the absolute value of the width change
bigger than the height change.
Give me.
So if the, if the width change is bigger than the height, change will
re compute the height.
If the height change is bigger than the with change will recompute the
the with right?
So in this case we'll say the new post Cy schedule say the new post CX
and so if we want to recompute the height, hmm, excuse me, if we want
to recompute the height from the with then what we would need to do is
say well the new pose.
X is the divisor, right?
And what we want to do is take our desired like our render with which
I guess.
I don't know that we've actually really have at this point.
So you know, let's will sort of say we we have it temporarily
Oh wait, I take it back.
We actually do.
Right.
There is
go back bumper.
Right.
so,
Need some more water.
So I actually do have that, right?
If I
If I want to, I can say here is my render with hoops.
Underwear.
There's my render height and so I want to recompute whatever the see
why would be from the CX.
So what I want to do here is is again sort of solve that that
fundamental proportion.
So I want to multiply the the render height right?
Mape sander Freud.
Right.
I've got the, the render height.
and the render width, I want to solve for the
The new window height.
So I'm looking for this right here in this case.
So if I multiply out and I mean, I guess I could just flip these
proportions, right?
I could just flip them around so I could just say HR over W.
R equals h w, / w w, right?
And I want to solve for this, right?
Sorry, I want to solve for this right here, so I just get H, RW W, /
WR, right?
So that is
my, my
My render with right?
X, i render height.
I render height times my, which is this times, the window width that
I'm getting / the render with that.
I wanted to that maintains, the aspect ratio render height / render
with, and that should give me back the value that I wanted.
Similarly, I can do the exact same thing.
Oppositely for the
For the computation that preserves the height and resells for the
width.
Right.
And so in theory that would work right, I think, Hmm.
So I've never really tried to do this before.
So I'm not sure if it actually works or not.
It looks like it's sort of works.
It's a little.
Genki, so not quite right.
But close, right?
So one thing you said is, it's got to have the shift key down.
That's pretty easy.
We can start with that but then we got to address the other thing.
So, get a sink Key State.
Or I guess just get key State because we want it to be synchronous in
this case.
So we want to do get key state with the virtual key of E K shift.
In the words is the is the shift key down, right?
And the higher order bit is whether it's whether it's down or not,
right?
And it's a short that's coming back.
So it's going to be the, it basically is it - right?
It's basically like
that.
So now when I scale it should be normal, but if I hold down the shift
key it's aspect ratio constrained but so we're we've got some kind of
a bug here that I'll have to look at in a second but let me just go
ahead and point out one more thing first.
So there's two things as do one is get to debug.
Why we're getting that word Jitter there.
But the other thing that we have to do is this is unfortunately
setting the client I'm sorry setting the window
Rectangle, right?
But we don't actually care what the window?
Rectangles aspect ratios.
We can't with the visible region is right.
And so since we're trying to adjust to the visible region, that is
an extra part of the computation that we have to figure out if that
makes sense.
so yeah, so let's start by just asking
To be on.
Get or I want to know, is size, changing or sorry?
Window.
Post changing window.
Post changing, I'm assuming that that's the window.
It's part.
There is the frame.
The definite part function says are given is the window is an invalid.
The new substation return for us by the line client by the window and
has a range of different program.
Like it's false well, administering processed by find the values
should fiction z-order an application for educators Terminus by
creating Flags.
So that's fine.
See what window post says here.
The window width in pixels but it says, C and C.
I don't know why there's a sea in front of it.
I guess that just means the width.
I'm not sure.
But what I don't know is is that the clients eyes, or the total window
size, and I'm not sure, of course, it's not documented, because why
would it be, you know, why would that be something you'd want to
document?
Like what the value is at all?
Window width in pixels.
I assume it's just the
I assume that it's just what comes back.
So let's let's try this.
I'm going to set a breakpoint.
I went in there and I just want to see what it says there, right?
I just want to
take a look at code.
So I'm not going to resize it at all.
I'm just going to click there.
Right.
So now what we should see in theory is our window wrecked, and our new
pose, should be like the same thing, right?
And, hey, guess what it looks like CX.
And Cy or actually the client wrecked, honestly, that's way better for
us.
Which you documented that, that would.
It save us some time but all right.
Whatevs.
That makes it a lot easier for us.
So good on you windows for picking the right one of those to do, all
right.
So we still got some weird stuff happening there, that I'm not sure.
all right, so when I fuss with this,
Let's see here.
It's kind of having a beat frequency back and forth.
It's almost like it passes.
The window post changing twice.
Once with the window with and once with the client with or something.
But I'm not sure.
So I don't really see exactly what's going on here.
I want to know.
if it's me who's causing that flicker by something wrong, in the way
that I'm doing the code here,
I wonder if what happens is it then calls me back or something?
I don't think it should.
Yeah, I'm not sure about that's really weird.
I'm not sure what's going on there at.
This isn't something I've done before, so it's a Windows thing.
So obviously it's going to be Tweaky and weird but I'm just not sure I
understand exactly why.
I'm going to print out something here to the log just so I can see.
so I'm going to say, like, okay, the old one
Was.
With that height and the new one CX, Cy.
Okay, and I kind of want to, I want another thing in here.
So I guess I'll do you mean
I want to print out the modification as well.
So I want to do like, bold new requested.
Right.
So, here's the ones that it was doing.
So that I can put them in here.
and now,
I can go ahead and say output debug string.
So, at least, now I can kind of see a stream of information about
this, when it's happening.
So, let's see.
The old was 571 459, it's requesting 587 498.
So then it decided to use the 498, which made it go to 85, right?
Then it had 869, 460
I guess that's just kind of because the position of the mouse cursor
Yeah.
So the problem is the mouse cursor won't snap out anywhere else.
So I need I can't just look at the Delta, I guess.
I have to look at whatever is closest, right?
I have to look at like what would be the closest aspect ratio window
that would fit
I mean that seems to me like what I would have to do.
So it seems to me like I'd have to do this.
So I can compute the new CX and I can compute the news.
See why, right?
From whatever the request is and then I guess I could just see which
one causes the least change.
Like what's the clue?
Which one is the closest?
Right.
So basically like you know is
Is the new cy- the, the Cy.
Oops.
so, if the new CX,
Is closer than the new Cy would be then use it.
And if the new Cy is closer.
Then use it, right.
So we're not using the Delta anymore, we're just using sort of the
absolute and we will see if that helps.
Yeah.
All right, so that's good.
But we still end up with with bars here which I assume are because it
actually is still like the that it is actually giving us back window
positions, maybe not client positions.
Somehow
Or something like a client position.
I'm not sure, but something's a little weird.
So I want to know
I would like to know.
Do I have a sprintf here?
Just the one that's like always complains about like what we're
passing it and stuff.
All right.
So what I'd like to do here is say well what was the aspect ratio that
I'm passing in?
Just to see if if it's a valid aspect ratio, right?
So, I want the aspect ratio.
I want, is the render with
over the render height.
And the aspect ratio, I got is whatever the new width of the window is
here.
Right.
And so, it seems like we're getting basically the aspect ratio that we
asked for.
So it looks like that is not really the client area and that it must
be actually.
It is actually the windows wrecked rectangle area, right?
So adjust, if I remember correctly, adjust window wreck, doesn't work.
Adjust window wrecked in that way, that nothing that Microsoft does
ever works just window.
Wreck doesn't actually work.
If your window is an overlapped window which are is is which is
awesome.
Right?
You have to specify like other styles.
I don't, I don't understand how that's plausible, but that's we don't
even I don't think have to rely on that, really?
I don't think because we can figure out the
Factor.
I believe, right?
So we can figure out the adjustment factor for the aspect ratio just
by looking at what the difference would be at that position, and it's
a little bit janky.
But what I could do is say, well, I've got the window wrecked in the
client wrecked, right?
I get both of those so I know that sort of my my
With ADD and my height, add are going to be proportional to that.
So the window wrecked, right?
- the window, wrecked left - the client wrecked, right?
- the client wreck left is the amount of additional width that we
would get.
And similarly, I can do the same thing for the height, right?
So, I know it's going to pad those like additional values on there,
right?
So, what I want to do here is I want to solve for this ratio now in
that way.
So what I know is going to happen is, is I have a client rekt.
So I've got a height client over a width client, and I want that to
equal the height render over the width render, right?
This is what I'm trying to do.
If this makes sense.
Hmm.
But the height of the client is actually the height of the window -
the height additional, right?
Whatever that is.
And the with the client equals, the width of the window - the with
additional
If that makes sense.
So if we are trying to make this be true, then essentially what we
have here I guess is.
We've got HW - aha / w w- w a equals h, r, / WR, right?
So if we want to actually make these equations work, we have to
multiply by these giant terms here.
So we have to say HR w, w- w a / WR and then we have to hmm.
Well.
So we actually have to compute that I guess if we want to know what
the height of the window is actually supposed to be right.
So anyway, so that means that if we were going to do that, the so
let's do the the width here.
So the new c y is going to equal to the render height times.
The quantity window width, which is this - the window additional
amount, right?
/ the render with which we are doing.
Right, render height.
Is it / the render with plus whatever the h a value is there?
And I'd like to do that on the top.
So I'd like to do that like this because this is, this is actually an
integer divide.
So I have to multiply it by W are, right?
Because it was aha.
So I have 2 x WR, /, WR to give me W RH / WR, so it's actually,
This is the 20 times tough times.
The render with their and the the
Hi Dad.
Right.
So there's that monstrosity there and then for the CX everything is
flipped, right?
So this is the width.
This is the Y, this is the height.
This is the width.
Height.
And one crosses one's fingers.
So, let's hope that some of that was, right.
I don't know if it was doesn't look like it unfortunately.
I guess we could have a bug in our other, the other part of our code,
like
Let's see what the client rectangle actually is.
so, if I take the client wrecked,
Bottom.
Well.
all right, with
and client height.
so, if I actually just do
Plant with over.
Client height.
We can see what we were actually getting.
No, so it's definitely wrong.
No question about that.
So, let's see.
That is the new window with did I do this, right?
I may have messed up this math.
We wanted the client to be equal to the render and we said, the client
was the width.
- the the add the added amount right in both cases.
So that seems right now, there's another way we could have computed
this.
I suppose we could have
subtracted in and then added it back.
Meaning we could do something like this.
This might be a clearer way to debug it, right?
We would say that the, the new one is the render worth times.
Yeah, it's essentially exactly that but without the Plus without this,
right.
That's a little bit easier to see, right?
So you're basically saying well let's solve for the client and then
we'll we'll put it in there, right?
So that's all messed up.
Oh well, that's great.
I never change this to get window wreck.
So those would have all been zero.
Gosh, I wonder why we weren't seeing any change there.
There we go.
Now, it's perfect.
Okay, so I think that's all good.
Now
So yeah, who asked that question?
I know somebody did somewhere.
Okay.
Hi.
There you go.
Does that help?
Okay.
Well, I'm going to go ahead and wrap it up.
And yet for adjust window wrecked, you can pass.
You can pass a set of flags that is equivalent to ws overlapped and
then it will work.
So I think but maybe not.
so,
all right.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the series at home,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and it
comes with a source code.
So you can follow along at home.
We also have a forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions a patreon page, you can subscribe to if
you want to support our video series schedule bot that you could
follow.
If you want to know when we're going to be live and an episode guide,
if you're trying to catch up on old materials, that's about it for
today, I'll be
Be back here tomorrow for the last stream of the week.
5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time, until then have fun programming, everyone.
And I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy.