Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we code a complete game live on stream yesterday.
We covered how to use the hardware renderer to actually render all the
Sprites that we were rendering in software before.
And now what I would like to do is I would like to go ahead and finish
the implementation of that because we did a bunch of of it actually,
Because it really wasn't that much to do.
I'd like to go ahead and finish today.
At least the part that doesn't involve texturing because the texturing
like I said yesterday is really going to be the only part that's
complicated and when I say complicated, I'm not talking about the
drawing drawing.
The textures is as you saw extremely easy, really?
I'm just talking about getting the textures down to the card in a
streaming fashion.
That is really the problem.
We will face so yeah, that's excuse me.
That's where I'd like to be at the end of today.
So I'd like to jump into it right away and sort of get to the point
where we're only worrying about the texture so that we can talk about
that tomorrow.
So day 239 is today, if you want to unpack day 238 source code, that
is what we will be working with today.
Here we go.
So, here is handmade code and a Dusty poppy.
Go ahead and build.
And if you remember, we created an opengl file in the opengl file, we
just sort of started laying out.
What we would need to do in order to make things render through
opengl.
And as I think, everyone hopefully agreed, it's a really basic set of
things like what you're looking at here is the entire thing that we
need for a hardware renderer for handmade hero.
Very, very little code.
At the moment.
And that might grow a little bit over time, but on the whole 2D games,
don't usually have to do too much work to make a hardware renderer.
I mean, let's be honest.
It wasn't that much work to make a software renderer for a 2-D game.
3D games tend to be a lot more intensive because there's a lot more
bookkeeping that goes on and a lot more sort of fuss involved in 3D.
So although pretty much all the principles are the same.
There's there's just enough more in.
Three dimensions to fuss with that.
It can be a little annoying.
But for our case, we don't have to worry about those because we are in
2D at the moment or at least two and a half D at the moment.
And so, all of our problems come typically further up the pipeline
where we have to think about how we want to deal with Judy, and not so
much at the rendering stage, where everything does bass big down into
a Sprite that we put on the screen.
So, here is the rendering code that we wrote, and if you remember
correctly, we had to do some stuff to make sure we would be able to
work in screen space in our concept of screens.
Space, we did that yesterday by setting the projection Matrix.
Up in this way that we did here, right?
We tested it and then used it here.
So really all I really need to do at this point, if I want to make
sure that I can render in Hardware, like, this is, I just need to do
something right to connect the pieces of code that are currently not
connected, right?
Essentially, I've got some code that I would like to run an opengl
right and Architectural.
E, I know,
That if I was just to use this to render that to the screen, it would
work, right?
But what I don't have is a good Bridge from the place where render
group to Output is actually called, which is here, actually.
There's a couple different places called right, there's one here and
there's another one in the for when we do ground chunks and stuff but
that's you know what's going on at the moment, right?
So the question is, how do I Bridge these things?
How do I bring these things together in a way that allows me to have
the renderer be something that works through opengl as well as through
software and there's a couple different ways that we could do this.
I think at first what I might, what I might suggest is I'm going to
kind of do it in the way that people.
Would you do it first?
And then I'm going to maybe discuss a little bit with you.
Why I don't think it's a very good idea that we do that and
how we might improve it just because sometimes on handmade here.
I feel like if I go right for the solution that I feel is the most
effective.
If it happens to be something where I'm fairly confident, that that
solution is Right, sometimes it takes away the benefit of you seeing
the not very good version which makes it hard to appreciate why, the
other version is better, right?
So if it's something that I haven't really done much before and
Get to see me work through it.
That's very valuable because then you can see how I get to a
reasonable solution.
But if a something that I kind of know how I think it should be done,
you don't get to see that.
So, I think, what I might do is sort of avoid the correct solution,
first and sort of show, what most people probably would do in this
circumstance and then we'll sort of sort of try to move to something
that's, that's better, alright?
So
here is our situation.
When we render to the thing, we call this tiled render group to
Output.
Now, that's the only place that tiled render group to Output is called
other than in the debug system, right?
So, if you take a look here, you can kind of see what the situation
is, right?
Tiled render group to Output.
So I'm going to go ahead and just take a look at that and see if we
can, just literally poured it directly.
Okay, so when we call tiled render group to Output instead of calling
tiled render group to Output, what I'm going to do is insert
essentially, a mitigation called a call that sort of hops in between
those two that will either go to opengl or to our software under
depending on the circumstance.
Yes.
And so what I can do is I can insert in here right inside our handmade
render group.
What I can do in here is I can insert a call that will
In fact, you know, I can even do one better than this if I want to.
I can actually I can actually even make a plat version, but I guess
we'll do that second.
So what I'm going to do in here is I'm just going to inside render
group, I'm just going to make a thing here that basically mimics this
function.
So the tiled render group function.
Tata group to Output this guy.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to make a copy of this.
That's basically a sort of a shim that can thicken switch either way.
So instead of calling tiled render group to Output, I'm going to call
something which is just called, like, you know, render to Output or
something like this, right?
And then, inside here, what I'm going to do is I'm going to switch to
see which one of these two renderers.
I'm would like to use, right?
So I'm going to look at the render group and I'm going to see for
example, which, you know, is Hardware or something.
And if it's as Hardware that I'm going to do an opengl renderer group
to Output,
and that's going to take all this stuff.
And if not, then I'm going to do the old tile child call.
Now I feel like I probably, I mean, I could be wrong, but I feel like
I probably actually want to make this one step more removed in a way.
And the reason for that is no matter which one of these are calling,
we would want to call our sort function.
And if you remember, the sort entries, call actually happens in these
two areas.
Here, right?
Child group to output and render group to Output.
That's that's where those get called.
And so really what we want to do is this is what we would like to be
calling.
We'd like to be calling that regardless, right?
So we kind of want that to happen, no matter what it was we were doing
and then we would do these render group to Output is the non tiled
version.
And that one at the moment, we don't really even know if we're going
to keep that one around it.
Hands on whether we leave the ground chunk system in place or whether
we kind of get rid of it.
We don't really necessarily know how we're going to do it one way or
the other.
But, and so, in this particular circumstance here where we have opengl
renderer group to Output again, I'm just going to sort of pass it
through, okay?
So in this case, we know what, all of these things should be right.
We've got render queue, oops.
Render queue are rendered group, we've got our draw buffer, and we've
got our temper Rina.
And then for opengl, we have no real need for the render Queue at the
moment because there's no multi-threading that's going to happen
there.
So we really just have the render group and then we have the temporary
net which it might need.
Honestly it probably doesn't even need that.
So at the moment we could probably just leave it with that.
If that makes sense.
And so at some point we need to call into that, you know, that
function.
Now again, we probably don't want to start poluting the sort of all of
the rest of our code with includes for opengl and stuff like that.
So, what I'd like to do is just do a slight sort of, you know, well,
that off just in a slight tiny little way and say that inside handmade
platform now,
We can do something where we, you know, inside all of our platform,
callbacks through here, we will have one more, I guess.
So we're we don't have too many.
We're pretty, you know, this is a pretty reasonable a small number,
like I said, I'd like to keep this pretty small but there would be one
more that we would add here and it's not too bad necessarily.
So I'm going to add one more here and I'm going to do a to do Casey
temporary.
Because we're going to talk about this in a little bit.
So I'm going to have a thing here called platform opengl renderer
Render to opengl.
And I'm going to go ahead and make a typedef for that and we're just
we're not even going to make a macro for it because this is going to
be, like I said something I want to discuss and I don't necessarily
want to.
I don't necessarily want to expand on it immediately, so we're going
to leave it a little bit as a little bit of a zygote for the moment.
So, okay, so we have our struct render group and cures that render
group,
And now we've got our platform opengl render.
That we can call, right.
So that in our open GL code here, that's going to be this.
We don't need the output Target or the clip direct.
Obviously, those aren't even used and so this already fulfills exactly
this signature.
So, in theory, all we would have to do to make that actually work is
actually registered.
The is hardware part and then go from there, right?
So let's go ahead and take a look at render group.
I'm sorry, at opengl renderer grouped output, let's change that to be
our platform code.
I don't remember exactly how we Define that stuff from working, but
we're just going to call this front open shell.
I don't know if we call it platform API.
Hi, or what it was.
I guess it was platform.
Yeah.
So we're going to call that off the platform and now we just need some
way of doing is Hardware.
So for right now I'll just lock it to calling as Hardware.
But we'll take a look at that in a second.
All right, so now if I went ahead and ran the game, obviously we'll
just we should just crash at that.
Call immediately because it's a zero, right?
It should just jump, 20 and and die.
Okay.
Some of my tell me how that just happened.
What?
What what just happened?
How did that not crash?
Set a breakpoint.
Set a breakpoint people win.
Maine
Where is that actual code?
Where is the code?
Where I ask you.
So, here's the game code.
Here's press begin messages.
Am I Wrong?
Should that not have?
Just jumped straight into nonsense land?
I feel like I should have recorded input game update, that's what we
actually want right there.
So inside game update in theory.
Now, right.
Weird.
Well.
Yeah, as you might have expected.
If you never actually change the call site, you don't actually call
the new function.
I know that's pretty shocking.
Alright, let's try that again.
Okay, that's what we actually wanted because we haven't set this yet,
right?
So now what we should be able to do is we should be able to come in
here, in our win32 handmade.
We should be able to include our handmade, this this file right here,
handmade, opengl dot CPP,
To put this code into our game and we're going to have to go fix all
the compilers there, but once that happens then we will have like our
you know, all of our, our thing where we fill out all of our platform
pointers this right here, can go ahead and fill out that platform
pointer as well.
Right.
Render to opengl.
Oops.
And that's going to be well.
It's just opengl.
Let's call this opengl ready for group tablet, okay?
So all we need to do now is actually make this stuff compiled
properly.
Obviously this time function B should go away for now.
We need to include handmade render group here because otherwise we're
not going to have any of those specifications the output targets.
I guess.
That's true.
We don't know what the width and height.
Actually is if we don't have the output Target so maybe we actually do
need the photo output Target there anyway, but that's kind of
something that again will I guess we'll sort of see why that's
something that we probably want to address again with some of the
changes that I said I wanted to make but okay if we pass the the
loaded bitmap output Target to this guy anyway look so then that would
take care of that temporarily anyway.
But we need to add that to the, to the
Stuff that gets passed here.
Okay, so yeah, getting closer, our output Target should just have I
believe just a regular width and a height.
Probably I'm guessing.
Yep.
And it does, let's go ahead and fix that here as well.
And then our opengl rectangle call everything needs to be V2s, but of
course they're not show.
We should be able to take care of that pretty directly like.
So I just picking out the 2D portion things that aren't 2D.
If that's actually what it's complaining about.
What is it complaining about X Y, is not a member of V to?
It's not.
Really.
What did I do wrong?
Oops, that's not good.
So those guys are in handmade platform right in here somewhere.
Oh, okay.
So I never did the XY versions so now they're there.
So is that not a?
Number of V2.
So which one of these guys is a V2 that actually shouldn't have been.
What was the complaint?
What are we complaining about?
Oh, well.
All right, I just misread.
The are those guys are v4s.
Why are they v4s?
That doesn't make any sense.
That's just a complete nonsense thing that we typed up there.
Alright.
So now we have an opengl renderer group to Output version that we can
call.
Which in theory means we should possibly be able to run now also
hopefully without
Crashing.
But we don't actually have any texture is enabled.
So the only thing that will actually work is is solid, rectangles,
right?
That's the only thing we would ever actually see on the screen in
theory.
because, you know, see if I can actually
two things about that.
That is true but we actually have to call it.
We actually have to display the opengl if I remember correctly.
We never actually switched back to this path.
Yeah yeah.
So this is all still running at the moment, right?
Which is not what we want.
If this will clear, this was the thing that was drawing our buffer,
which were no longer updating.
So we need to get rid of all of that.
So that now we should be able
To see a bunch of sort of solid nonsense on the screen if that makes
sense.
Yeah, so that's exactly what we should see for now again because
almost everything on the screen is something that we don't actually
have the ability to draw since we don't have any of our texture stuff
working but at least we're we should in theory be going through that
path.
Now like I said at least in theory so let's do a very simple way of
just sort of getting the texture.
Working just so we can take a look at what that might entail so that
we can make some educated decisions.
Like I said, I want to kind of talk about how we do the integration
here, but until we actually get it working a little more solidly.
That's not going to be very useful, right?
So we have our clear, that's probably correct.
We have our rectangle, that should be.
I believe also working correctly.
Although I don't actually know.
We would have test it.
Certainly so the main problem we have is just this part right here
where we're trying to draw an actual bitmap and
Remember we actually do know exactly how to draw the bitmap right?
We have it here.
So what we could do if we want it to be extremely slow is we could
actually just find a texture and submit the texture.
Every frame.
Right incredibly slow, incredibly bad idea because we don't want to be
sending the texture down every time but we actually could totally do
that, right?
And so the way that we would do that is again right before we call our
rectangle call.
All we would do something like this.
Where were literally just going to do exactly what we did before we
combined the texture, as we found out which I didn't realize you don't
actually need to allocate these.
So we can just pick an arbitrary texture.
Handle to bind, we can submit whatever the image texture is that we
want, right?
So the entry bitmap, we can literally just send it down right now and
say, hey, send it over the bus, every single frame.
Like, so set it up turn on texturing and render, okay, and again,
absolutely awful idea, but in terms of actually getting something on
the screen in theory, it should actually work and as you can sort of
see it almost does.
There's a reason why it doesn't quite.
But as you can see, very, very slow.
So it probably wouldn't be quite so slow if I switch to the game
because then the textures are smaller.
Although for some reason, I don't see anything when I switch to the
game, although I do see things when I switch to the cutscene, I don't
know if you can see it, but you can actually see that the
The cutscene graphic start to come in here incredibly slowly, right?
I mean, you can see, just how just how slowly that is is doing its
thing there, right?
Really, really bad.
But it's working, right?
So, I guess another thing that we should mention, you can kind of see
what's happening with with the screen here.
If you notice, we're not getting any of that transparency, we're not
getting any Alpha blending at all.
Right.
So that's something that we have not discussed how to do in opengl,
but it's something that we're going to have to turn on right if we
want that to happen.
So I would first go ahead and explain let me first go ahead and
explain how that works and it's actually quite simple and then we'll
turn it on.
But again, like I said, it's not just me saying that this is a really
bad idea.
You could see just how incredibly so that was the reason.
It's so slow, is every single one of those plates of the cutscene had
to get transferred over.
The bus every single frame, which is just way too expensive for this
card to handle, all right.
And to be clear, it's not just the transferring over the bus, it's
also the remapping of it into the format, the card wants, and all
sorts of stuff like that.
All right, so let's go ahead and cover.
Blending here.
So as you saw right incredibly slow but it was working, not doing any
Alpha blending and obviously we need Alpha blending for our game.
So what do we do about that?
Well, the problem with Alpha blending is as follows we have.
Like, I was saying before, when I sort of Drew out the GPU diagram of
how everything works, we have a couple programmable pieces, right?
They're sort of like a geometry portion if you kind of looked at the
stack of like, stuff comes in, and stuff comes out of the GPU, right?
This is the GPU, we have a geometry portion, right?
And this is a bunch of Shader code.
This is a this is Shader here.
And when I say the geometry portion, I don't mean geometry, I mean,
everything involved in Geometry, like tessellation Shader is all those
sorts of things that we haven't cover and maybe will never cover on
handmade hero because they're not potentially,
Relevant to us but maybe you know, you never know.
We then have code that operates two on vertices
In here.
Right.
We then have code that operates on pixels.
Okay.
And that forms the full programmable stack of a GPU pipeline, right?
Something comes in here, it gets munged into a bigger something here.
It gets transformed in some way here, turned into 2 pixels like where
the coverage is and each pixel has whatever happens here, executed,
which then produces color values and something happens for the color
values.
All right?
Very, very broad overview.
We talked about this a little bit.
We'll talk about it again.
But point being that sort of the very, you know, the the sausage
pipeline if you will, of a modern GPU.
Looks a lot like this and what happens is in the way that we're doing
things now like I said, this is the programmable version, we are do
using the fixed function version which basically has pre-loaded.
You could think of it as pre-loaded programs for everything in here,
right?
So, we don't have access, we can try
Any of these shaders or anything?
Because opengl with the version we're using even doesn't have support
for any of that, right?
Later, we will load in a higher up version of opengl and we'll put
some shaders in there.
So later we will be using this but right now we're not.
Okay, but so this is basically like open jails code is doing all of
that portion and opengl Es code is doing all of this portion as well.
Okay.
So, the reason I bother to draw this out is because of this part right
here, which actually even on today's Hardware is often very, very
similar to what it was in the fixed function days.
Meaning, all of this stuff became programmable, the part right here,
Still Remains very non-programmable on a lot of GPU.
Some gpus is more programmable.
But on a lot of gpus this part, not programmable.
What that means is that after the pixel colors are determined
What happens to them as compared to what's underneath them?
Right.
So remember how we do our drawing?
There's like here's our frame buffer.
And this is just like when we wrote it, here's our frame buffer.
Here's our Sprite that we're trying to render on there.
There's stuff underneath your already right the degree to, which the
stuff that is underneath can be fed into this.
Shader is actually extremely limp.
Well, I even shouldn't say limited, it doesn't basically it's a fixed
thing that happens in here for the most part.
You just simply don't actually get to use it in an arbitrary way.
That's just the way these work.
So what ends up happening typically is if you want to do arbitrary
operations on things are in the frame buffer, it doesn't work this
way.
What actually happens is the frame buffer is actually another thing
that you're writing to and you it actually has nothing in it and you
pull from a texture that is the existing stuff in the frame buffer and
whatever.
Are doing and you like pull from two textures and combine the two
textures arbitrarily and then output them, right?
So actually the the degree to which you can work with the values that
are in the frame buffer as they exist, is very limited.
It's not arbitrary.
Like almost everything else in the program of a pipeline now is what
that means is there is still a concept in opengl and pretty much
everything else.
Every API of the blending stage, which is this stage right here is
still a very fixed function thing.
The blending stage still looks basically fixed function pretty much
the entire time
Even if you're on very programmable, Hardware, although like I said
some Hardware, that's, that's starting to change, but a lot of it's
not what that means is the equation for how you interact with the
frame buffer is actually fairly fixed.
It typically looks very, very similar to the kinds of stuff we were
doing where you know, the output pixel, right?
So the color that comes out has to be equal to let's say,
The color of whatever we're doing right now.
So let's say, like the Sprite color, you know, plus whatever.
Well, I suppose a source and destination because we use those terms of
for.
So, you know, I've got the frame buffer,
And that's going to be equal to.
That's my destination, that's D.
And then I've got the Sprite, you know?
And that's my source.
Whatever I compute for the source color that I'm doing and the
destination color.
Typically, I end up with the result and I guess I could call that D
Prime.
The new result in the frame.
Buffer is basically just some combination of these two values.
And really all you get to do is choose these things.
Now, fortunately, for us, that these two things can be chosen to be
based on whatever based on the SDS themselves, a lot of times.
So we don't have to pick constants thankfully which means that if we
want to reproduce our blending equation because I hopefully you guys
remember this.
I've said it so many times the blending occasion, right?
Do you remember this one - tea?
Plus t, write the linear blending equation, which we've talked about
so many times.
The thing that I said was the one equation I take with me, I desert
island with somebody asked, write the linear blending equation.
We can create that by an equation that looks like this.
If we can set a equals to 1, minus T and B equal to T, right?
We could do a linear blend and to do an alpha blend.
We kind of know what that looks like, right?
We know what an alphabet looks like the destination color right?
Whatever.
The destination color value is that we want to write to the frame
buffer, we know exactly what that would be.
It's whatever the source value is in
Case, if this is the whole premultiplied member we did premultiplied
Alpha.
Versus non premultiplied Alpha.
In the non premultiplied Alpha case, it would just be whatever.
The source is Alpha value is times the source color, plus 1, minus
whatever the source is Alpha is times the desk color.
So basically the alpha value of the source would blend between them.
But since we're using premultiplied Alpha, as for all of our Sprites
reasons, we talked about back in the premultiplied alpha discussion.
We don't need this term here, so it's just SC plus 1.
Sa DC that would be the equation for a premultiplied alpha blend,
right?
So going back to this equation, we know what we would set a and b
equal to if we wanted this exactly.
Well, a is right here, it's just one right?
And B is right here, it's 1 - Source Alpha.
So we know we could set up a blend with an equation that looks like.
That that would be just like our premultiplied Alpha blend.
It just looks like this.
So the question is does opengl give us a way to set exactly those
things and as you may have guessed, it actually does.
So what happens is 0 texture?
2D is on by default there.
That's not what I was expecting.
Let's let's turn that off by default the moment.
Well, you know what?
Let's turn it on by default and what we'll do since we mostly texture
is we'll just turn it off when we're not texturing.
Okay, so yeah.
So that is how that that would work.
That's all good.
But point being.
So we now need to look at this blending thing.
The way that that works is you have to say that you want to use
blending because by default, the blending is not on.
And you get what we saw before, where the, the, like our Sprites just
kind of rendered to the screen completely opaque.
There's no transparency at all.
So if we enable GL blend, everything is great.
Except we need a way to specify that equation, and the way you specify
that equation is GL blend Funk, it's like funky
NGO, blend Funk allows us to specify what we want the source factor,
and the destination factor to be okay.
And so if we say Gom blend Funk, we can now specify essentially the
Alpha and the, the, A, and the B from our equation before.
Remember I said, I wanted the a, which is the source thing
multi-source to be one.
Well, you can see that gl1 is one of the things that we Define that is
defined.
So we could set that.
And then the destination Factor.
Oops.
I mean you hit that hot key.
The destination Factor.
What we said we wanted, right?
Because let's go back to our board.
Here was one - Source Alpha, right?
So let's see if we've got that.
Well, hey look GL.
One minus cos Alpha.
Right there.
It's almost like the hardware setup to do this parentheses it is
because this is one of the main things you might want to do.
So if we enable that and then we run, then you can kind of see that
now.
We're successfully.
Reducing our image again.
Yeah you can kind of see what it looks like when we when we look at it
there and
Now we really just have that problem that we're super slow because
we're sending the texture down every time, but otherwise, we're
correctly reducing it and I say correctly, there's a couple caveats
there too.
So we have some work to do but you know that's a that's a pretty good
approximation, okay?
So let's do one more thing so that we can get to the point where the
where it's not so slow as that, we want to kill ourselves and and
there's a pretty easy way that we can probably do that as well and
that is that in our asset.
Freight where we have this concept of a loaded bitmap.
And I don't remember where that actually was.
Here we go.
Excuse me.
So you can kind of see are loaded bitmap is a thing that shows up in
the asset memory header.
Right, what we could do is, is go ahead, and I don't remember exactly
where that is defined.
I think it's in the platform file.
Let's see, grip.
There it is.
What we can do is just cheat here and say, all right?
There's just, there's just going to be a handle.
Right?
We could just say there's just a handle value and so that we can
totally cheat and know that we're going to be able to submit it
whenever we need to.
Okay?
So if we wanted to do that when we actually do a loaded bitmap and we
set the pitch, we got a little thing that says get rid of pitch here.
But let's go ahead and see about where we actually load in a line
percentage.
So inside asset, I'm just going to take a quick look at where a line
percentage gets loaded in.
Um, it looks like right here.
All we would have to do is here set this handle to 0, so that we know
that it hasn't been submitted yet and then what we can do again, as a
very, this is a very stopgap kind of a measure.
Like I said that not actually trying to Advocate anything like this,
but all of this code when I'm teaching you, opengl is really just to
give you the basics.
So that you'll understand what we're going to do as we sort of move up
through the complexity.
But so take it with a grain of salt.
But if we know that
The case.
Then now all we have to do is say oh well if the entry bitmap has a
handle already, right?
If there's a handle set then all we have to do well either way we're
going to bind it, right.
So really what we are?
No, that's not true.
That's not true at all.
We want to see is if it's got one set then we can bind it and refine.
If it doesn't have one set, then we need to set it, right?
We need to generate a handle.
For it.
We don't know what this is here yet necessarily but we need to
generate a handle and then we need to submit the texture but then
after that we don't ever have to submit it again.
So we only need to do it the first time through we can submit it and
then the graphics card has that handle and we're good.
Right.
And that's a pretty easy thing to do.
Like, there's that's not very difficult obviously because inside our
code.
In fact, we could even do this just with a global variable.
It really just doesn't even matter at all, right, we could just do
something here with a global variable to do Casey.
Get rid of this.
We just need anything at all that will do it.
So this is like you know you through to next texture handle equals
zero or maybe just texture bind count something like that.
How many we've found so far.
And so then here we can just say oh the texture Pine Cat.
We increment it by 1 and use it in off.
We go right?
You notice I pre incremented it because I want 02 mean we haven't
found anything yet.
Look
That's not a included thing in the entry.
So let's go ahead and fix all of those.
And then this should only submit it just that one time.
And then theory in theory, it should be able to reuse it after that.
So there we go and now we can sort of see that we're no longer having
any trouble with the speed anymore.
Everything is is much zippier but there is still one more problem with
what we're seeing on the screen right now as
compared to what we were seeing with our software.
Renderer, our software renderer looked a lot better than this, which I
know.
See, I knew we had a bug in the sort key thing since we happen to hit
this, maybe we should debug it.
Let's just take a look, let's take a quick look.
I just want a quick look, because remember we talked about this at the
day and then I was like, I don't want to wait to try and have it
trigger again, but I'm like, I know it's there.
So let's see if we can take a quick look.
We go.
Oh, that's just it.
There are no entries.
Hey, look, you can't subtract 1 from the count.
If there are no entries, that's just a straight-up bug in the
validation code, ladies and gentlemen.
That's so that's always good.
When you have a bug in your validation code
So, this is really an, if count.
There we go.
Fantastic.
All right, so anyway, as I was saying that was nice that turned out to
be easy.
If you look at this, you probably can't see it on the stream because
of the video.
Quality is probably not that good when it's getting compressed and
everything but when I'm looking at it cured natively, it's really,
really ugly.
It's got this sort of shimmering look to it.
And if you remember I discussed all of that back.
When we implemented, bilinear, filtering for all of our stuff and
Pointed out the fact that bilinear filtering is what allows everything
to look really nice and smooth because you don't get these like these
sort of rounding errors that you see that you end up seeing on the
screen.
So the question is, hey, we got this fancy Graphics Hardware.
Why am I not getting as good of results?
I want this to look at least as good as our software under come on.
This is dedicated Hardware people.
Why is it uglier than our software under the reason is this right
here.
So, when we set these
up, we didn't talk about them very much.
But remember, I said these were what were used for filtering.
The textures both under minification and magnification.
Now modifications, when I'm taking a texture that's smaller and I'm
drawing it on the screen larger than that minification is the
opposite.
I've got a texture that's larger and it's screen area is smaller.
So it's whether I'm shrinking or growing and I can pick two different
ones depending on which ones happening.
Now I pick nearest and what nearest was was the original whale.
If you'd be well, if you go back to our software renderer, that's the
original way that we used to do things.
What before we implemented by linear filtering where we just grabbed
the closest Texel in our texture and use that to draw.
And then we did bilinear, filtering, which grabbed for textiles from
the neighborhood of, where it should be and Blended based on how far
between them it was.
Hopefully, remember, all that, that's what we need to re-enable, and
we can do that trivially by just saying to opengl
Tell the filter we want you to use is linear which, in this case means
by linear.
Filtering of the texture.
The reason it's not called by linear and just linear is because this
setting is the same no matter whether it's a 2d one 1D 2D or 3D
texture.
And technically, if the texture was a 1D texture, it would be linear
if it was to D&B by linear and if it was 3D, it'd be like OCTA linear,
right?
So they're just saying linear to let, you know, that's what it is, but
it's going to take as many samples as it needs to get the one on
either side of the Texel for as many
As this thing has one two or three D, right?
And in our case, we're only two days.
So we're always take talking about by linear, but you can understand
why they wanted to be a little more generic there.
So now we look a lot better.
Now we look a lot.
More like our software renderer, there aren't those ugly Jitters in
there and we're back to being, okay.
So, that's basically the the hardware renderer in a nutshell.
Okay.
So this is a pretty reasonable looking thing, but you can see that our
ground chunks are kind of messed up, right?
And the fact that our ground chunks are kind of messed up is actually
somewhat to be expected our ground chunks.
Do
Saying some very unusual things obviously and they reuse their bitmap
handles and there's just just a lot of reasons why our ground trucks
are going to be problematic but our graduates are a little messed up
but everything else is looks about right, right.
Everything else looks fine.
Everything else looks looks good.
We can we can walk around here off we go.
And so for the ground chunks, I feel like we have some sort of a bug
there.
But I'm not certain I know exactly what it is.
We should probably look into that because that looks like some kind of
a submission bug.
I'm not 100% sure.
It's kind of weird so yeah, I don't really know what's going on with
that ground chunk.
That's a very good question.
So we may have to look at that because I'm not sure.
But obviously, everything else is pretty reasonable.
I don't see anything else that's obviously messed up, right?
Yeah.
But why those are our purple like that?
I don't I don't suppose I know
Hmm.
So that's interesting, that's something that probably merits looking
into.
However, I don't know that we want to look into it necessarily right
now because it might not be the best thing to do at the moment.
So anyway, point being this is the the the hardware renderer running
The game now.
So our software rasterizer is not operating at all.
What you can see as I sort of suggested even though this is a graphics
card from 2010.
So this is a six years old roughly graphics card at this point.
In fact, it's almost exactly six years old, I think I got it in March
was when it would have been purchased.
It was a yeah, I think so.
This is a six year old graphics card and although it was top of the
line,
Years ago, it was six years old.
You can see that it has no trouble rendering our game, which is why I
was sort of trying to impress upon people.
When they were sort of talking about, is it, you know, do you need to
use vertex buffer?
Objects are blah, blah.
2D games are very, very straightforward and if you don't do anything,
overtly, super stupid.
She really don't have to worry that much as it turns out because
Graphics Hardware is sort of so overpowered for what you're likely to
do that if you just think it through, you tend to not have too much
trouble.
So yes, there are things.
We could do.
That would tax the graphics card in a 2d games.
Certainly usually it has to do with a lot of overdraw but at the end
of the day, if you're talking about the kind of game that you see,
normally when you know, just random unity game or something.
You know, graphics card, should be able to run those.
It just trivially, Without Really optimizing the renderer at all.
As you can see, we've done nothing to our render whatsoever.
It's a little weird took us 10, you know, 10 minutes to write that
little loop.
I don't even know how long that Loop took.
When we wrote it, that's the entirety of our render and it just, it's
fine, right?
So yeah.
So at the moment,
This is all good, there's really nothing problematic about it, but we
do have a an issue.
Multiple issues and like I said before, they pretty much all revolve
around textures and that's going to be sort of our our big problematic
thing.
We're going to have to manage.
I think which is this this process right here where we buying the
texture handle and submit it that is really the thing that we are
going to have to work around in the game because cards are bad.
Hitting things asynchronously and our game is set up to stream its
Assets in incrementally and that's really the part that's going to be
problematic.
Okay, so we'll tackle that will probably tackle that starting Thursday
because what I want to talk about now and probably do tomorrow is talk
about why I don't love this particular architecture for how to do
things.
And again, this function is fine, no problems what we did in this
function, other than the texture binding part, which is a total hack
with the with the global.
There.
Because that texture binding has to be something that gets moved out
into our asset system, right?
And that's the hard part.
So, that's the part that's going to be tricky.
But if you're not, if you're putting that aside, the rest of this is
totally fine.
The only problem I have with it is how it is called, right?
And you can order, you sort of start to see the cracks showing a
little bit, even just when you look at it, how we implemented, a
currently couple different reasons, where is our debug code at the
moment, right?
Um, you know, our debug stuff, if you look isn't there, right?
Where's the, where's the debug overlay?
So the debug overlays like, oh right there was somebody else who calls
render her up, right?
So, I got to go down there and now, and now change that call.
Where is that tiled?
There it is.
So this is render.
Script output we go.
Is that what it's called?
It's in your summer.
Render to Output gonna have to work on our naming a little bit.
So yeah, I got to go in there and take care of that guy obviously and
then maybe we'll have.
There we go.
So there's our the rest of our stuff sort of working and presumably, I
can go up here and interact with these and whatever.
But like I said, the cracks are already showing a little bit because
really, we're sort of doing a bunch of stuff that doesn't even make
any sense.
Like we're passing a bitmap that's the output Target that doesn't
really
Make any sense, right?
So we would need to abstract that away and say there's this notion of
a Target, but the target is not really the target is some abstract
thing that we did isn't the same as a bitmap.
So that part's a little bit janky but that's not necessarily so bad.
The big thing is, you can kind of see how this creates this concept
that the the game again
Is sort of round tripping through the platform layer, which means that
the platform layer itself has to be setup to service opengl rendering
in an arbitrary fashion from where the from the game.
So there is no way in the platform code to dictate when rendering
happens through opengl, right?
There's no we don't control that anymore.
So, rather than before, what we had is, we call the game, it does
whatever it wants.
It pretty much never calls us about anything else, right?
And then it, when it returns, it returns to us the bitmap.
It wants to have displayed.
Well, more specifically, we pass in a buffer for it to fill.
We could have done anything we wanted with that buffer, right?
We could have saved it to disk to capture it for like video.
We could have looked at it and tested it against something for a
regression test.
We can display it to the screen.
We can do all sorts of things about about planning.
When that gets generated, we could save a couple of them all sorts of
stuff.
So it was kind of really nice and very clean the way that was
separated.
It, it didn't the rendering didn't involved as far as the game knew
any platform stuff but now
It does and the game has to be aware of this sort of stuff, right?
So what I'd like to do is is see if we can maybe restore some of that
process by considering the by considering the render list as the
output rather than the bitmap.
In other words, just to give you some perspective on what I'm talking
about.
Right now or I guess we say here's what we have.
Previously.
Here's what we have now under Hardware.
So previously what we had is we have the platform stuff, does,
whatever it's going to do, right?
Then it calls the game.
And what it does is in through here, it passes a bitmap, right, the
game renders to the bitmap and then it comes back to the platform
code.
Okay, so it's a really nice flow.
There's nothing weird happening here at this bitmap gets filled out in
the platform.
Can use it.
What we have now is we have the platform code,
Calls into the game.
And now the game essentially has to call back out in a round trip.
Through the, the platform code to do the rendering right?
This is rendering here
And then we come back through the platform code.
So it's like a platform game.
This happens twice, right?
Once for the game render, once for the
once the debug render says happens twice and then we come out through
here and this part is now completely the, the timing of this is now
completely out of the hands of the platform code and completely in the
hands of the game code, which means if there is special knowledge
about the platform about when these commands should be issued for any
number of reasons, the platform code will get much more complicated
because it now has to do stuff like
Fur rendering that comes through this thing.
Blah blah blah, right?
So what I would prefer if possible is, I would prefer treating our
render group more like the bitmap.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to see about getting it to the
point point, where we got a platform we call into the game and just
like before we were passing a bitmap.
Now what we're going to do is pass a render buffer so like the render
group becomes a buffer, it's basically our bitmap, the game is Just
expected to spew anything.
Wanted to render into this big render decision list.
Basically, a big thing that says, here's all the stuff to render, but
it never calls the platform code and then it comes back through to the
platform code again and says, okay, you know,
Now, I'm done and the platform code can then go look at this decide
what to do to it either.
Dump it to a bitmap render, if it wants to or dump it to opengl or
direct3d, or anybody else for that matter.
And I feel like that's a much cleaner separation.
It also allows you to do stuff like capture the output of the game
here in a way that you can reproduce offline, very trivially and very
concisely which is kind of nice.
And it also lets you do stuff like render two different ways if you
want to, you could render twice if you were trying to render like, you
know, I don't know.
You could even imagine doing some stereoscopic stuff automatically if
you wanted to buy shifting, if you record enough information in the
here, right?
So, I don't know, I it's not a big deal, but I like that flow a little
bit better because I feel like it further isolates, it further draws a
boundary here because I really don't like
Um, I find that it makes it harder to pour it.
The more things you have in here, the harder the porting is and I feel
like we've already got more than I would like, I feel like actually
this part right here, probably should be improved.
Honestly, I think that should probably be improved and so I feel like
eventually what I'd like to have is get rid of this probably have at
entry complete, all work allocate deallocate and maybe that would be
it, right?
So and of course, the the ones that are just like, for debug stuff.
Those are okay.
But, you know, other than that,
So I'm going to call it there because what I'd like to do is that's
tomorrow's, thing will be sort of maybe making that change.
So that's all fine.
But let's go ahead and go to the Q&A while we are at it.
Q and A does anyone have any questions for me?
You can pee fix them with a Q:.
I see no questions.
Is there any questions?
Questions.
Questions questions.
Unicron, why did you choose opengl over DirectX?
Well, so there's, I guess there's two sort of maybe answers that
question.
What answer is, why did I choose open to jail over direct extra
handmade hero?
And that's a very easy question to answer.
The reason is because there's a lot of people who follow handmade hero
on other platforms already, even though we haven't ported to Linux and
Mac.
Because one of the things we
I'm here with make a very clean platform layer separation, so that
it's very easy to port to other platforms on the whole people follow
along on Linux.
They follow along on Mac.
They follow along with sdl and so, opengl is kind of a very natural
choice for us because opengl will work on all those platforms.
People who are do using multiple platforms on him.
A hero don't have to go, I don't, I can't like, I gotta go learn
totally thing, that's not being taught on the stream.
Just, you know, I got to go learn up in jail even though he taught
DirectX so that I can copy it.
So handmade here, it's kind of a no-brainer for an educational series
open jails, the obvious choice because it's it runs everywhere.
Whereas DirectX doesn't run anywhere, it's like Windows is the only
place you can do use it or maybe if you're an Xbox.
Developer if those even exist anymore.
Assuming that any one ever buys an Xbox again which they don't seem to
be doing but that's I guess in the US, they do so.
So if you're not, if you're in the US and that's fine, if you're in
Europe, I don't know that.
Have they even sold it Xbox in Europe?
I'm not sure.
Anyway, point being, if you take a look at the broader question of
why, why a developer might choose open Jill over DirectX?
That answer the answer that I just gave is partially true.
Meaning cross platform is one valid reason to do it.
Like DirectX is a very pigeonhole thing.
It only works in really one place, so it may not make a whole lot of
sense for you to invest time in creating a renderer for platform that
only exist in one place.
But to Windows is credit, it is 97% of the PC game market.
So it wouldn't be that big of a deal at the end of the day to maybe
use DirectX.
Right?
So the question then would be, why would you might you choose open
Jill over DirectX.
The primary answer, there is, obviously that if you want to use the
most direct way of rendering on say and video Hardware, then open gel
is, like the right choice for that, right?
Because the extension extended opengl for specific for specific to
Nvidia, you can do a ton of stuff with like, by endless Graphics that
you just can't do any other way.
As far as I know, like you can't do them in DirectX at all.
Even DirectX, 12 doesn't have support for all of the stuff that you
could do, right?
So having access to those might be one good reason, but is there a
really strong reason to do so?
No, you know, I wouldn't say that was true so you know, if someone
told me I'm making a game and I'm going to Target DirectX.
I wouldn't be like, what are you crazy?
That's stupid.
It's like no totally reason was Vision again.
These were surgeon because all you 97% of your markets on the PC if
you want to Target DirectX and you don't care about porting very much,
you know, go nuts.
Also, you know, there are rappers that can, you know, you can write to
DirectX and then wrap it with something that will allow it to run on a
Mac through like a sort of an emulation layer.
And those aren't that bad because the AP is at the end of the day,
aren't that different DirectX.
12 is quite a bit different than opengl but but like DirectX 11, which
is what you'd be writing to nowadays since
Twelve doesn't even run on Windows 7 so that's like a non-starter
obviously once 12 more adopted, but assuming you were talking about
DirectX 11, you know, they're not that different opengl and DirectX
11.
So, you know, you have options there.
So could you do DirectX?
Sure.
Is it a reasonable decision?
Yes.
Do I ever bother?
No, because I just assumed keep things as cross-platform as possible,
and I've never had a problem using opengl, but you know, your mileage
may vary.
So,
This Isaac, did you notice that the ground tiles change when you
should sort of?
Yes, we descend.
We discussed that on the screen because they were never sorted before
and you know the Splats whenever sorted and they are sorted.
Now I don't really know if we care about that one way or the other.
Like I said, I'm not even sure.
We're really going to use the ground tiles.
We may just pull them because based on the design of the game at the
moment which is pretty much the final one, as far as I'm concerned, I
don't anticipate changing it very much.
You never know ground tiles.
May not really be a thing but
that's sort of a separate issue.
Mr.
Fourth dimension, I've asked this before, but I want to hear your case
again, what specific things make a data protocol based interface
better than one with function calls, okay?
so, I guess I would say that
It is a very complicated issue and I would not say that I would not
say that data, Protocols are better or worse than function.
Call based protocols.
What I would say is they each have very specific advantages and
disadvantages that you want to weigh.
A database protocol.
The primary the primary advantage is the ability to nonlinearly and
repeatedly access what it did like, what was recorded.
So if I go and I you've already seen this happen in the renderer if I
have a thing that says, here's all the Sprites and where I want to
draw them right and I don't execute that instead I just keep it in a
buffer I can then do exactly
Did which is sort those and then render them.
So it gives the it gives the API abilities never would have had any
other way, right?
Because the
Anyway, to do sorting in a function called based interface is to do a
recording in the interim.
So you're going to end up making that buffer one way or the other,
right?
So, the ability to nonlinearly access and to access more than once,
At different times, the information contained in each call to the API
is a very powerful part.
Being able to more easily record.
What happens is a nice bonus.
But you know, that's largely because you already did this work of
capturing, so you could argue that you could just add that to the
other API and and, and get for the same amount of work, right?
But that's really the big one.
And so I tend to like database protocol data based protocols, rather
than function called these protocols.
Because I think they're a happy medium between
It mode and retain mode.
I don't like retained mode because I don't like the
I don't like the synchronization that has to happen, but I don't like
pure immediate mode because it doesn't allow enough thinking, right?
It doesn't allow that nonlinear access and stuff like sorting, those
sorts of things are very difficult to do.
It prevents a lot of optimizations but it's a lot of things.
So I tend to like the middle the in-between of those two which is like
an immediate mode style, a thing that looks like immediate mode to the
caller so they get all of the benefits.
Of immediate mode, but with recording underneath.
So, it ends up being like retained mode, in terms of what it can do,
power wise, and as an aside, that's why I always say people.
I think tend to misunderstand me greatly when I said the thing about
immediate mode, graphical user interfaces,
What I always meant by that was that it appears immediate mode to the
caller.
That's the important part.
I never meant you don't track state because tracking state is
obviously very important for anything.
The immediate mode part is about allowing the caller not to have to
care about synchronization explicitly just like in our renderer even
though we record everything and do the sorting and then draw as far as
the caller can tell.
They don't have to worry about anything.
Just called draw, right?
And they know that that bitmap will show up at that place.
It's as if they had not a care in the world, they don't have to
synchronize anything.
They don't have to manage lifetimes, don't have to call free on
anything.
And that's very important.
So, I hope that gives you the perspective that you're asking for, I
don't know if that answers the question, but hopefully, it does at
least a little bit.
How is vsync controlled?
How is Visa and controlled?
Vsync controls.
Opengl vsync is controlled by extension call.
Which I have intentionally not talked about yet and that is because we
haven't talked about how to get extensions.
So in a couple days after a kind of done with the rest of the stuff
that we need to do, when we do extensions, will be able to turn vsynch
on.
Kubrick.
Caleb does the GPU.
Do srgb correction automatically?
Yes, and no, it depends.
What you mean by automatically right now?
It will not be meaning.
Right now we are srgb incorrect, if that makes sense.
When we start working with extensions, in fact, I should probably just
write these down so we don't forget the ones that we need to do.
We never talked about Hardware rendering, we just kind of did it.
So here we go.
Srgb frame buffer and textures and then we have vsync background
texture downloads render to texture question.
Mark.
I don't know what else but probably those are the ones that are
feature-wise obviously stuff like shaders, but shaders is not a
feature.
It's just something we might want to do eventually, but we it's not a
We actually need because we didn't do any of that in the software
renderer at the moment.
So yeah.
Pseudonym 73.
I wasn't paying close attention but has the opengl texture name thing
broken, hot reloading.
Well, it involves a static variable with the stupid way that we're
doing it right now.
The way that I said, we weren't going to keep, so that should break
because there's a static variable, other than that, no, it would be
fine.
I think that's the only thing that you would have to be concerned
about
Does the GPU do, srgb?
Correction, I'm a clear?
Yes, what languages do?
You know?
I know a little Japanese.
There are any performance.
Are there any persons reasons to choose compatible, opengl API versus
core?
Or is it just the fact that we get to use programmable shaders in
So I'm not sure I totally understand the second part of your question,
because
In opengl both the compatibility version and the core version allow
programmable shaders.
I'm assuming you're talking about, if you do a, if you do a query
wiggle create context at Rib ARB call assuming, that's what you're
talking about.
If you which we haven't covered it in the Stream So if you don't know
what that is, don't worry.
Ignore this answer will get there.
If you do one of those calls, if you pass the compatibility bit versus
not passing the compatibility tab, it has nothing to do with whether
you get access to shaders.
The reason, the only reason that I know of why you would not pass the
compatibility bit, I typically don't anymore.
But the reason why you might not
Is to avoid not running on cards which don't support it because not
all drivers have to support.
Drivers are under no obligation to support compatibility.
So
Yeah, that's that's what I would say about that.
Like, NVIDIA drivers just work.
You can just ask for a context that supports both shaders and the
fixed function Pipeline, and it just works.
But at least that was my experience last time.
I tried that but, you know, not all drivers have to do that.
And so to remain maximum compatible, I just feel like it's safest, you
know, it going forwards to ghost, just go to court because there's no
real need.
For the compatibility context.
Evine.
Is there any good reason for desktop?
GPU to not have programmable blend modes because I've seen that most
mobile gpus have that.
Yeah, there are a lot of good reasons.
So not being a hardware designer.
I'm not really in a position to like, rigorously defend that position.
But what I will tell you is that
The the place where triangles actually get resolved.
I go ahead and talk about this here.
So you know, if we're talking about a entire frame buffer here, so
there's two ways of rendering this, right?
There's tiled and non tiled.
Right.
So a tiled renderer is one that looks like the one we wrote okay where
you divide the screen up into tiles and each core is like working on a
tile or something right?
And then like some other cores like working on this tile.
So here's quartey is working on that and corby's working on that or
whatever and off we go.
And that's the way a lot of mobile gpus work.
So mobile gpus should write this where it actually belongs.
Mobile gpus are usually are usually tiled.
And to be honest with you, I don't really know the reason for that but
I believe it's because the of the memory architectures.
So what happens is, if you don't have like, giant special memory,
Controllers with tons of special memory.
You know, with tons of wattage and all this other stuff, I believe
it's a lot easier.
You're to have each of these cores have like one tiles worth of frame,
buffer memory on the core where it can just quickly read and write
from the frame buffer.
Because remember every operation you do like reads and writes in the
frame buffer, right?
It's the one piece that just gets read from read from read/write,
read/write, read/write, read/write, read/write read/write, every
pixel.
Every time write read, write read write read it, read it because even
if you're not reading the color value, you're definitely reading the
depth value, right?
So it's and so I think on on chips where they're more resource
constrained like they are on mobile less, wattage less memory,
bandwidth, less memory
Specialized memory controllers, whatever else I don't really know.
I feel like that's this big boost to be able to have that small piece
whereas on regular gpus on the desktop.
They don't typically do that.
I don't think I'm pretty sure they're non tiled and they are more
arbitrary access based so they can do a lot of things like unordered
access views, right?
I don't know if you've ever heard those uavs for compute, shaders
would be
Other one where it's just general purpose code, it can scatter can
read from everywhere, can write from anywhere, there's no coherence,
do it.
Implementing these sorts of things, right?
There's reasons why doing these sorts of things, incurs a bunch of
performance problems, right?
And by having blending be a thing, like I guess there's two things I
should say.
So one thing is desktop chips.
Can certainly do those things and they can they can do those things
specifically because they don't need to be tiled but they're
definitely a much worse thing to do because any time you're talking
about stuff that's kind of scattery gather like that you have these
sort of contentions we're different.
Horrors of the GPU are contending for the same resources at the same
time.
Like somebody's trying to read from here, like someone's trying to
read from this point on the screen but someone else is trying to write
to that point on the screen, right?
And like what happens, you know, so anytime you're in, those
general-purpose kinds of things you have you know you have to start
dealing with things a little bit more seriously.
Anyway point being in order to get good performance.
When you're talking about something, that that doesn't involve
breaking.
The thing up into tiles, based on ownership, and not really letting
things go outside of the tiles.
What ends up happening is you have to start having ways of resolving
all of the stuff that has to go test a come from and go to the frame
buffer.
And if you allow arbitrary code execution to happen at that stage,
when things come from and go to the frame buffer, which is the blend
stage,
Those two stages actually it's the it's the alpha test stage and the
blend stage.
So it's like the pre and post part of the Shader.
If you're in a business situation where that's programmable, you have
no ability to build special purpose, Hardware in either the memory
controllers or like welded into the chip for, for very fast,
execution, or whatever, the ability to negotiate that very very
sensitive.
Part of that, part of that process, which is extremely heavily used,
right?
So I think and I could be wrong, but if a hardware vendor, if you were
to ask a hardware vendor, why they don't want program over blend.
I think it's because allowing that to be a very well.
Known equation, allows them to move that to places that allow them to
do very fancy.
A lot more general-purpose stuff and allow them to not have to break
things up in the way that they have to happen on mobile.
For example, I would also say similarly,
That is why you don't see arbitrary texture unpacking.
So for example, why do we have texture formats at?
All right?
Why do we have DX TC texture compression?
Why don't we just have a Shader?
That's like code that says, how to decompress a texture and then you
could Implement whatever texture you want.
Same reason that's such a heavy band with part of the pipeline pulling
those Textures in.
That a lot of stuff like I think like bilinear, filtering and stuff
potentially.
But also like more importantly, the texture unpacking and like stuff
like this really has to be in a, in a very tightly optimized piece of
the Silicon, that's able to do that specifically.
And that doesn't have to worry about stuff like arbitrary code
execution,
So I don't know.
You would have to ask a hardware designer for the real complete
answer, but my suspicion there is that because they allow this more
broad thing and because they want to be able to be fast, they need
those two critical parts of the pipeline to really have an own
behavior and I think eventually they'll become programmable, but
that's why they're kind of long holdouts.
Let's see.
Do we get gamma correct rendering for free now?
Yes, but not till we load extensions or rather not till we use
extensions base opengl did not have the concept of srgb so we have to
actually turn it on but yes, we will get it for free.
Well, I mean, as far as we know the graphics cards typically don't
have a cost for that.
They usually have color look-up tables and stuff to handle it.
To become doesn't the u.s.
automatically vsync you or does that only apply in?
Dad mode.
I don't think the OS automatically V6 opengl normally opengl is
allowed to tear unless you ask it not too.
So I'm pretty sure we're not V sinking at the moment.
Robbie, so gamma curve is also opengl extension.
Yes, it is.
Lung billion.
I know you're probably sick of all the Vulcan questions, but here is
another one, a lot of places online from Vulcan, it's the next version
of opengl there thought, being
That once Vulcan is released development adoption of a gel will
dwindle the point where open to adoption along developed by graphs the
manufacturers could this happen.
And in the event that it does, what is your?
And then that's the end.
Oh cute plan.
Let's see.
Let me see what this one is but she doesn't mean she'll source and
children programming playing a shooter source files Etc.
Know where that question from Elvin was.
Oh, he was talking about my thing of shaders, right?
Okay, so, yeah.
So to answer your question, long, Boolean.
So, my opinion is that, there is no way, open jail will go away.
Yeah, I don't think it's kind of at a minimum you will still be able
to get an opengl layer, that's implemented on top of Vulcan but
there's just no way it goes away.
My period.
I just I just don't think it's going to happen but I can't really say
more than that.
I mean maybe maybe like after several revisions, Vulcan could replace
it or something like maybe 10 years from now, but in the short-term,
no, no way.
Let's see here.
I pressured.
And then you see that EPS are very that.
The apis are is similar.
But is there a visual effect that can be accomplished on DirectX and
opengl or vice versa a visual effect?
T', I'm not sure what you mean by a visual effect.
Probably not.
But there are definitely things you can do with opengl that you can't
do on DirectX.
That's definitely true.
in terms of, like, features of the hardware that you can access,
And as e, is there a good reason?
Why Windows opengl headers only offer the old Legacy stuff while other
platforms add new stuff?
Yes.
It's because they they want to force you use DirectX.
It's the same answer.
It's always been.
They wanted to kill open Jill entirely, but they failed?
So if if they had their way, there'd be no way to to load up until at
all.
But yeah, that's why they haven't been supporting it and it's
It's lame honestly, but that's just the way it is.
Key Club.
At some point, can you go over the pros and cons of the different
graphics apis?
To be honest, I really don't think there's that much more to it than
what I already said.
Like really like opengl has better access to Hardware features because
it allows drivers driver writers to expose extensions more.
Readily DirectX integrates with some Windows features better beyond
that.
There's really not much difference DirectX, 12 is more equivalent to
Vulcan than opengl.
So the comparison there is probably between
Vulcan and DirectX 12, whereas DirectX 11 is comparable to opengl, but
really, yeah, I mean, is there a strong reason to use DirectX and
opengl?
If you're only on Windows, I would say really just does not matter
very much least.
I can't think of, a lot of reasons why you would care that much.
I guess one thing about opengl is it's more compatible even on
windows.
So for example, opengl you can Target any version of Windows whereas
DirectX you can only target the windows version it shipped with.
So for example DirectX 12 only runs on Windows 10 or whatever it is, I
guess.
Is it 10 or 8?
Whatever it is.
You can only run directors, 12 on that DirectX.
11 only runs on like Windows 7, right?
And up
You know, nine only ran on XP and up or something.
I don't know what, I don't know what the versions were, but Windows,
they never back port or they didn't used to.
So that was another reason why you might want to open jail because you
can keep one code base across all your versions of Windows.
And you don't have to have dx9 and dx11 for example, like the witness
had to ship with the x 9 and 11.
Support, I think for that reason, which is really annoying.
So yeah, so I don't really know.
To be honest, I don't know why you would use direct X because I can't
think of a positive aspect of it.
The only thing I can think of is maybe it's a it runs better on some
machines.
If like amd's DirectX drivers are better than their opengl drivers or
something.
Maybe would be one reason to other than that I don't I don't really
know of of a I can't think offhand of a positive reason to use
direct3d rather than opengl.
But at the same time, I also can't think of a huge number of, like,
overwhelmingly important reasons why you have to use opengl.
So, so I say, if someone wants to use DirectX, I can't think of like
some
Super important reason.
Why I'm like, oh my God.
No.
Don't use DirectX.
It's like now.
You know.
All right, I'm gonna, I'm gonna call it a day here.
I'm gonna call it a day, folks.
Let's wrap this up.
Let's wrap it.
Like vanilla ice.
All right, I'm going to close this down.
Let's see.
Close close.
All right, everyone.
Thank you very much for joining me for am a hero.
It's been a pleasure working with you.
As always, I hope you have enjoyed this foray into Hardware
accelerated rendering.
As you can see, there's not really that much to it.
It's not some big mystery.
It's just a simple matter of piling up a bunch of commands that you
want your gravatar to do.
And it does them, we will be exploring a few more issues with this
tomorrow.
I think I would like to do that pipeline, abstraction that I talked
about, just to kind of rearrange by that works.
And then we'll have to start on the what I think it will be by far.
The hardest thing we'll have to do for our Hardware rendering support
which is just how we want to get textures downloaded in an efficient
and reasonable manner.
So that part will be a little tricky but I think that's the only part
if you want to watch that.
Be sure to come back tomorrow.
I think we're 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time.
Check the tweetbot for sure but I believe it's 8:00 p.m.
tomorrow.
For the stream.
Love to see you there.
Until then, if you want to follow along with series at home, you can
obviously go to handmade here at Oregon, pre-order the game, it comes
with the source code.
If you want to play around with it and follow along at home, it's a
great way to learn from it.
Also, you can go to our Forum site where you can ask questions and
talk to other people that serious.
We also have a patreon page where you can support the video series by
subscribing and we have the aforementioned tweetbot which tells you
when we are live.
It's a good thing to check.
So you know, when the series is going to air if you want to catch it
live, that's about it.
It until tomorrow have fun programming, guys.
And I will see you guys on the internet.