Okay, hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we go to complete game live on stream.
We got our debug system, sort of in good shape over the past couple
days and wanted to probably start doing some feature clean up like we
have profile information, currently being gathered but we don't really
have any way to look at it or use it productively and so I'm not
exactly sure what we're going to do today to be honest, but it's going
to be something.
Along those lines either.
We will start in making the profiler or try to start working with that
to see, like, how we're going to actually have the profiler work in
practice will either do that or we will do something.
With just cleaning up, sort of the way that we're drawing things.
Because right now there are still some code in there.
That's pretty janky in terms of how we're displaying stuff and how
things is being, you know, laid out and all that.
So we will give that a shot and we will see what actually happens.
And, you know, it's wherever the Muse takes us, it's where the Muse
takes us, because there's plenty of finishing things, we can sort of
do here in the debug system to get it into a good State.
And the question is just, which ones at those do we actually want?
Do.
So I'm going to go ahead and launch everything up here and let's see
going to load our handmade project.
Oops, that's not good.
so,
In the handmade project.
If I run what we currently have built, we've got this sort of
situation happening here and and all that sort of such stuff and
whatever.
And so like we've kind of just got this this window here and we still
have the ability to like resize the window and we kind of have like we
don't really have any good drawing of like Borders or controls or
anything at the moment, but what we don't have is any like profile,
contents, right?
and so one of the things I want to do is be able to get some profiling
information here, and there's two kinds of profile information that I
probably would like to have
One is memory one is time.
Spent.
And so what I'd like to do here is get the profiling system back in
some semblance of working order here where we can draw something into
the profile and what I'd like to do.
Because typically there's there's really two kinds of profile
information that I want to see one is just sort of an a generic
profile that just kind of gives me a rough idea of who is taking what
time.
And so you know, I'm thinking like I want something that just
generally tells me the frames, take this long generally speaking to
complete and so much of it is spent in the renderer so much of it
spent in the simulation.
So
It's been to the input processing whatever so that I can ensure that
each of those things is looking roughly.
Correct.
And I don't ever like cafta wonder about, you know, is there some
weird Spike happening where all of a sudden the simulation takes three
times longer than it should and we don't know why.
So I want that right?
And that's a very sort of high level.
You know.
I want to be able to sort of have one of those in here where it's just
going to show me that.
And I can have that piece of information available.
So I want that.
The other thing that I want is I want the ability to when we are
actually optimizing a particular piece of code.
So for example, if I'm, you know, if we find that there's something
slow and I want to fix it, then I want to be able to have something,
which shows me a detailed breakdown of what's Happening inside that
code.
Right?
So we essentially have two types of profile information that we want
the high level overview.
Information.
And then a like sort of more detailed profile, which will tell me the
information for up an area that we happen to working on and generally
speaking.
I don't really need those two things typically at the same time,
right?
Meaning, I don't need the ability to just like arbitrarily navigate
down, and check out some particular thing or any of that stuff.
I don't need that sort of thing all the time.
The most important thing is high level overview that we can just kind
of leave up on the
screen anytime we want.
And then once in a while, when I want to optimize something, I just
want to be able to insert something into our debug blocks that says,
hey, you know, show me the profile for this piece of coat in detail
and and it'll, you know, give me all the stuff that I want for that.
So, that's more or less.
What I, what I want here and so I think the probably the most logical
thing to do would be, since we sort of started on it before would be
to start with something that shows us, you know.
The profile information for the high level.
So so kind of like an overview based profiler and maybe that would be
something kind of like the standard sort of profile or that you'd see
like I prefer whatever.
Like for example John showed the one that Sean Barrett wrote and John
had poured it to Jay.
I that's a one that I think a lot of people use and it's basically
like a list of functions, you know?
And it says like, okay, here's a list of functions and how long they
take and how long, their
Then take or whatever and probably how many times are called that's
like a standard kind of listing based profiler.
So, you know, something like that, that just kind of giving me a heads
up view of, like, who's taking the time on the whole seems like a
pretty reasonable place to start for the overview base profiler and
then you know, the other thing is we sort of have, you know, I don't
know.
That profiler is only really works with single threading, which is
Not so useful anymore.
And so, you know,
Possibly, we want something that does like what we were doing with the
bars where we can sort of see when things were happening.
So that we have a little bit better idea of like the overlap.
And when when stuffs triggering that's on multiple threads, I don't
know.
So, that's generally where we're at.
And that's, that's like, probably what we should work on today.
I think the other thing we could work on is like right now.
We see this stuff is sort of a little ad, hoc, right?
Like we have the ability to tear things off here.
But they're sort of janky and we just have these little Nubs that you
move around or whatever and you can't necessarily read this very well.
We don't have a way of like drawing you know, we don't draw like
backing around it or anything.
So for example, when we come in here, we happen to have a white
backdrop here in this particular thing.
Now that's not going to be common, will probably fill that in
relatively soon, but it just underscores the fact that if things are
bright, it becomes like harder to read this and it would be nice if we
had some kind of a dimming
You know, something that would sort of dim that area more while you
know, while we were working with it, if that makes sense.
So, that's really what I'm talking about.
Just these sorts of things, some way of sort of, clinging, that sort
of stuff up.
That's really what we're looking to do.
So let's take a look at the profile stuff that seems to be.
You know, the most underdeveloped thing at the moment and we have to
kind of go back and sort of figure out what we want to do there now in
the debug system currently where we're doing our collate.
We've got Seco late.
Debug.
So in our collate, debug records code, we can kind of see the residual
of the profile stuff.
We're doing here.
Are the frame markers, right?
And the frame markers, we know what the wall clock elapsed is?
That gets recorded with those frame markers.
So we have the walk locking information.
We also have in here are begin block, end block stuff and you can kind
of see when we do our begin block and black stuff.
We figure out what these matches are and
We did this thing where we would build up regions.
I don't really know if that's something we want to do quite yet.
And in fact, I think maybe that's something I will sort of defer to
later.
I'm just going to go ahead and get rid of this for now.
And well actually you know what, let me just look at what this is
doing in detail first.
So if there's an open code block and we have an end block, then we're
going to make sure that they match.
Now, it looks like if spans go back before where we have where we've
got, we will ignore it.
And that's fine.
That's just if our debug information is passed where the thing
actually started, but assuming that that's actually the case and we've
got a starting frame.
Name index, that matches, our frame index and you can, you'll notice
here.
We don't we don't sort of measure though.
Or we don't process those that have started in one frame and ended
another which isn't great so you probably want to fix that as well.
Then what we do is double check I guess here, what the name is and we
only record a certain one that's, you know, being talked about in this
particular case.
So
I don't really know what to say about this.
I mean, that's certainly fine.
There's a couple different ways we might want to go when we collate,
the debug records at the end of every frame.
We're running through these events and we're sort of pre.
We're sort of baking them down into something that we want to work
with.
And the thing that's interesting about this is, we've got all of these
events here.
I don't actually know to what extent we want to bake them down into
what extent.
We want to leave them sort of more open.
Now, we certainly could if we wanted to instead,
You can see here, we've got like store event.
Right?
And so you can kind of imagine us taking a slightly different approach
here when we find these data blocks for.
I mean these code blocks.
We could treat them more like data blocks, where we're just saying,
oh, okay, we have these two blocks, let's go ahead and consider that
span of time.
Just like an event, basically, that we're going to store, you know
what I mean?
That seems like a pretty reasonable thing to do actually.
And so, I don't actually, I don't know, maybe we're sort of
approaching this the wrong way by when we do this collation, maybe
that's really not what we want to do at all.
What we're doing here.
Maybe we want to store these more, like the data blocks may be.
In fact, we don't really want to treat these all that differently at
all.
Maybe the begin and end block can be unified in a way that would make
it.
So that both, you know, both of them go through the same sort of
system, you know, or at least
A similar system.
And it seems like that could be possible, right?
Because both of them could work sort of the same way they could have a
debug element that was, you know, for whatever that code entry point
happens to be and, you know, it could work from there.
It certainly tempting.
And then these sort of Records, you know, each one of these would be
its own habits own element.
So every time we come from that we see begin block, we're going to
find an element for it.
And so we could just store the event to that element.
I don't know.
That seems really enticing to me, I kind of feel like that's the route
we should go.
It will certainly eat through our debug store faster, but who cares.
It's debug, we can allocate.
Thing GB for it and just be like, hey, guess what we can store as much
as we want, because this is a death machine, and we can just stack it
full of memory.
If we want to track thousands of frames worth of debug data, for some
reason, and if we don't doesn't matter, we'd only just have a few
frames of look back with.
That's okay.
That to me sounds like a good idea and I guess we'll find out why it's
a stupid idea in a minute when I try it.
But for now we're just going to go ahead and do it.
So here's store event.
And I feel like Loops, that's
That's not right.
What's going on?
Why am I not able to switch into edit mode?
What, what's happening?
Something real strange is happening, my shift key was that was weird.
My shift key was like locked down, huh?
I've never had that happen before.
I've never had them on this machine, or with for coder.
I wonder if that was a keyboard bug.
This is the old an old Das Keyboard 3.
I've switched to the razor's everywhere else.
I just haven't bought one for the handmade hero machine yet so I don't
know.
We did have a problem.
The previous sadusky board for totally had a sticky key problem.
So who knows?
Who knows.
Anyway it doesn't really matter point being I'm going to go ahead and
edit this so I want to keep store event and I'm just going to say like
okay whenever we open one of these begin block, end block situations,
I'm just going to store whatever the event was.
To that element, right?
Because we made the element and we have the event, and I'm going to
store it in this case, when we do the matching events situation here
again, I don't actually know why we're double checking these.
I guess it's just because we want to ignore the ones that don't have
an open block, but assuming it has an open block.
Now, I don't care what the frame index is to be honest with you, at
this, at that point I don't care what the frame index is.
I'm going to go ahead and do a store event and I'm going to store
event to the element.
That was in that matching block, so whatever the one was that we
opened.
Originally I'm going to store it to that element.
So now we basically have each element is going to have a like, you
know, open-close open-close, kind of a thing.
Right.
Now when I store these, when I store these events, there's sort of
this, a one additional piece of information.
I kind of want and I'm not 100% sure how
I want to store it but what I would like to store and this by the way,
now can all go away.
This is this is goodbye time like goodbye.
so, this is
This event that happened is telling us when in a particular point.
In time, like when dysfunction got called right?
That's or it doesn't have to necessarily a function, right?
We can time a block that's not a function, but when we entered this
block, so here, we're storing an event for when we entered the block
of code.
And here we're storing the event for when we left the block of code.
So we will have like a little linked list in there of just entry/exit.
Entry/exit.
Entry/exit, entry exit, right?
That's what we'll have now, that entry/exit, entry/exit pattern that
will allow us to know every time this function was
called and how, right?
But we wouldn't necessarily know is who called it, right?
We don't necessarily know who called it.
Now, we can reverse engineer who called it.
By sorting these things in temporal order or something like that but
we don't necessarily want to have to do that to sum up like who's what
children were who's and that sort of thing.
So what I suspect we probably want to do is we probably want to do
some sort of a like
You know, when we store an event of this type, we record.
Who the parent was?
Does that make sense?
Like we record which debug element was the parent.
So we know which function I'm basically talking about call
attribution, right?
You go ahead and make this a little more explicit here.
So, what we will have is we'll have a debug element.
Right.
And the debug element will have a like thing that looks like this.
So such that if we wanted to we can basically draw a profile that just
tells us every time it was called because we know each of these and we
now know how long they are as well.
And we know what frames they were on.
So we have all of that information now in that like linked list, but
what we don't know is who actually called it because for all we know,
you know, a particular function that can get called from different
places.
We don't know, which of those places was actually the call site that
caused say this one like maybe.
This is a call.
If this is a debug element for the function Foo, you know, maybe bar
called Foo and and cause this one, but maybe Boz called, you know, Foo
to cause this one.
And so if we later wanted to look at bar and baz, in terms of like,
oh, how much time is spent in fou on behalf of bar or on behalf of as
for whatever reason?
If we want that information,
It might be nice to say like oh okay well we know that now, right?
Look, we
I actually have some information in here that says here is the debug
element bar or here's the debug element bass and that's who it was.
So like an additional pointer that we could use depending on what our
circumstances was in the event storage, might be nice.
At least, that would be my guess.
So if we look at handmade debug dot CPP here, oh actually that H.
And we look at that stored event,
So in here, you know we've got just the frame index and what the event
was if we wanted to store an additional piece of information here,
that might be nice.
We don't have to do that quite yet, but I'm going to just make a note
of it.
Because we have that information here but we won't have that
information at any other time, right?
Because the matching block could know who is parent was because in the
middle of this collation pass, we do know the answer to that question,
but we won't know the answer that question later when we're doing
drawing because we don't have any, we don't have an inference, the
information has gone, right?
Because that information is only coming to us complicit in Walking,
the array of events because we saw the opens happening order on this
thread, and then we saw them close in order.
So we know who called who
But once we leave here, we don't know that anymore because this array
goes away thrown away, right?
Never to be seen again.
So that's, you know,
That's how that works and you know again it's just it's sort of again
an open question of just like you know, could we possibly do this a
little more efficiently by just doing a giant stream out where we just
write the events forever and so then you just in there and you could
seek backwards to look who called you maybe but I don't know.
It seems like you probably want to collate periodically and produce
these intermediate structures because otherwise it just takes too much
processing power if that makes sense.
So I think that's why we ended up sort.
where we are with you only want to collate the new ones for this Frame
and you can't really afford looking through these giant array buffers
all the time to figure out pieces of information you're trying to draw
So I think that's roughly it.
I think that's all we're looking to do here.
so,
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and get that compiling.
There we go.
And now I'm going to go up to the profile situation and I want to
start looking at how I'm going to
I'm going to make this work so after collation and I guess once we're
sort of once were drawn, these guys, then if I do debug draw main
menu, oops, that's not actually it.
That's the call to it.
Here we go.
Why do debug drumming menu?
And here we are doing that.
Debug draw of the main menu.
And we come in here and we're doing our and we're going to draw the
element when the element turns out to be a counter thread list or
other sorts of profile stuff.
This is where we need to start making these things work.
So let's think about the different types of things.
We want to view.
The counter thread list.
I feel like is probably a good thing.
Let's take a look handmade.
Debug interface.
Let's take a look at what we've got here.
We've got counter threadless, kind of functionless.
We don't really know what these are are yet.
I'm gonna, I'm gonna go ahead and comment this out for a second and
just see where we're using these.
So, we've got debug profiled, got counter thread list.
Here, for just the, when we're printing things out,
That we don't want to print out kind of function list counter thread
list is there, okay?
All right, I don't really know why element and event are even
different anymore to be completely honest with you.
Do we ever actually call debug draw?
If element versus debug draw event,
So these are the same function.
Right.
Like we don't this is only from before when there was a question as to
how we were going to segment this data up.
So at this point we really can just make this a single function,
right?
We can take this and we can stick this in here.
Temporarily just so we don't lose the code if we wanted.
Although there's really nothing there it's the same as this code so
it's irrelevant anyway but really we don't need this.
Any more we can just say that we've got one function, the function is
debug draw element and the stored event that we're actually passing
here.
It's something that we can just get.
So we'll go ahead and say that that's that.
And that simplifies this down, so we don't have multiples of these.
So and I guess we've got in element here somewhere, right?
Yeah.
So that's going to be
I guess I'll just change that to be element.
So if I call debug draw element like that, then really all we need to
do is take a look at this, this most recent event thing.
That's the one that we were drawing.
So let's go ahead and just pluck this stuff out here.
Get a great view for we, don't pass the view down, so we really don't
need that either.
So we're really just talking about this, right?
That's the that's the sum total of what we
Do therefore, the stored event.
So there we go.
so,
what we need to think about now is
what we actually want these to be.
So what are the different kinds of profiles that we're going to do?
So, the first one that I want to do is, I guess just that overview.
So, this the overview I think, should probably just be kind of like,
the basic kind that we were doing before I feel like.
Because again, since it has to be threaded, I think it should probably
look like it looked before and so the way that we might want to do
that, I guess is trying to think of how we would do that.
So if
Here's the profile view.
What we want to show is we need lanes for our threads.
So maybe that like this is how we're doing that, right?
So we have like threads going this way.
And then we have like clock going this way.
You know, I'm saying?
And then in here, it's like function name, it's here.
Right.
I think that's what we wanted to do.
That's what we were doing before.
That seems like the smartest thing to do.
And so what we would do there is we just use that open and close block
data to draw these in.
Now, like I said, it's a little bit tricky, because, what we don't
have is a necessarily A hierarchical.
We don't really have necessarily a hierarchical layout of these yet,
which is why I was thinking, it might be nice.
To sort of have that, that can build that kind of flow graph up.
And so, I guess as we sort of implement this, that'll give me a good
feeling of how we want to do this.
So, what I'm going to say here, is I'm going to call this.
I'm going to say that I want this to be a debug type like a, we call
this a thread.
Block graph.
I guess.
Chart.
How about a thread?
Interval graph.
Maybe.
Yeah.
It's red interval graph.
I feel like a thread interval graph.
Sounds good to me.
And so, we'll go ahead and make that happen in here.
We've got this debug profile thing.
That's the way we were saying what we want to do there.
So what I want to do here is say, like, okay.
I just want, I don't really want anything specific to happen here.
So I'm going to actually make this very explicit and say that this is
debug thread, interval graph.
And what we would
Last year as a function name is, if we pass, let's say, you know,
nothing.
So we pass an empty string, then maybe it just means show us the whole
thing or if we pass a specific function, it would just give us show us
that function down, right?
That seems like pretty useful to me.
So, here we go in debug type red interval graph.
Passing that through, we get the debug name of this thing and then
that's where we're at.
So that will put it in.
There for us to use.
And in this case we're just looking at game update and renders of the
platform code is not included and maybe that's fine for now gives us
something to debug gets.
I'm not entirely sure.
That's what I would do in the long run but you know for now that's
fine.
I messed.
I'm not sure that's what else actually want up as I guess what I'm
saying?
So I suppose in this case we would never get to hear anyway on these.
So I
Would probably be a good thing to print, actually, probably, so would
open data block to be completely honest with you.
So let's go down here, counter function list, this is not really code.
Like I said, this code is not really proper so we'll we don't really
care about saving any of that and there's our interval graph.
And so now we got rid of a function there.
So we don't we got rid of a redundant function so that's good.
And now we should be oh, so I guess we do print out like en Bloc
At the moment.
Hmm, why are we printing that out?
That's interesting.
That is very interesting.
I guess that's because we're calling store event.
That's my assumption.
Also, why is that Twitchy?
Did you see that?
That's very peculiar.
I don't really want to know what's happening there.
Whatever happened when I'm paused.
because right now, the debug systems, updating
Hmm.
So that's really
Your I don't honestly know how that can even happen, that is a real
Puzzler.
So,
That that warrants further investigation.
However, what I will say now, is since we're almost down since we only
have like maybe 30 seconds till we run out of Arena space, I'm going
to let it run out of Arena space as well because I want to see what
happens.
Right, five mags to go.
For Max to go.
Almost there.
Wait for it, bam.
That is so peculiar.
Let's make sure everything works.
Besides these weird people here.
Interesting.
There isn't Handler perception.
The programme said the continue right.
X-Files really location.
So there's a null, so the oldest so it's just an assertion.
The oldest frame.
Somehow got set to 0.
So there's something wrong with our oldest frame handling, not sure
exactly what it is but we have a problem with it.
So when we call store event and we come through here and we free these
frames, right?
We must be doing something wrong.
Let's take a look at free.
Oldest frame.
You know what would you be a lamb and jump me there?
Why can't I ignore this?
I don't.
I don't care about that set next statement, there we go.
So, all this Frame goes to the next frame.
Which presumably should always there.
Should always be room for right?
Hmm.
Yeah, I'm just not sure what's going on here.
So we grabbed the oldest frame, we say whatever the oldest frame was,
it's going to be the next frame.
After it, which makes sense.
And if we're out of memory, which is when this happens, that means
there should always be frames to free.
We check out the most recent frame and we see if it is also equal to
us.
And in that case, we would, we would set the most recent frame 20 as
well, because that means there are no frames left at all.
Now, that's really probably something that we should have cert on in
general, because that should never actually happen.
Right.
We should never free all the frames because we would never be out of
memory in that state.
So this was like this is like a thing that should never really happen.
But anyway, then we free.
So this would have been the line assuming that there isn't some other
kind of bug this would have been the line where that would happen
frame next would be equal to 0 and we would free the oldest frame when
we do new frame.
I mean, yet.
I'm not sure how that happens.
I'm not sure how we end up in the situation that we ended up in.
Where the per frame Arena?
Were there was nothing in the free store.
Like, how is that possible?
Interesting.
So I'm going to do what I said I was going to do before and force that
to happen sooner because I don't like the fact that there's a bug
there and I'm assuming that that's actually not just a bug in general.
Because I did do I suppose this
Ah, okay, so we just have a bug bug.
It has nothing to do with the arena.
We just happen to inch have introduced a bug recently that occurs when
we go into the game.
That's all.
Okay, well, that's a lot more heartening.
So I'm guessing that we've got.
We've got something, we're part of our change, too.
Maybe how we were doing those events tours.
Maybe there were just to, you know what, I suppose there could
technically actually have been so many events on a single frame that
we couldn't store them all.
Seems really unlikely but I suppose it's possible.
Like it's possible that actually could be an accurate assertion.
And that would be terrifying but I guess I don't know how many of them
there are.
Right.
I don't know how many events there actually.
Actually are coming through so let's take it.
Let's let's test it.
I suppose if we go to begin, block end block here.
If I'm not storing.
These events.
Then we're fine.
If a store, only one of them.
That's half as many.
Still fine.
And if I store,
Both of them or rather just that one.
Yeah, so I think that's actually an accurate assertion.
It's just not enough memory.
32 Meg's is not enough memory to store.
How many events we actually wrote?
Which is kind of crazy.
All right, so I guess that just means we probably have too many zones
and things but I mean, I guess that also means that
When we do our debug start here, Global debug storage size.
We could just make that significantly bigger and then not worry about
it, but that does mean we're probably processing too many events.
So here is our debug storage size If instead, I said like oh yeah you
know what?
That's going to be bigger much bigger.
Holy cow.
Yeah, I mean take a look at how fast that goes down.
Right.
This thing just choose through the memory.
Mmm.
Very interesting.
But once you give it enough memory to hold a individual frame, it does
appear to be fine from then on.
So that's good.
Alright, okay.
So the next thing we need to do is we need to fix this situation here
because this I don't actually want those to show up in this hierarchy.
They need to the so the things that are
those debug elements, right?
Because we have
We have these.
We actually don't want those to be added to the group's, right?
We don't we want those to sort of the handled separately.
We really just want those to all go into a single group really and
never actually be, you know, always have a particular parent.
And so in here, where we do get element
We're in the wrong file.
We want to be in here.
So when we come in here and we do get element from event, we want to
be able to make that we want to be able to force that not to do a
hierarchical search for this thing and to instead use a specific
parent for its operation.
And so you know, when it's doing this sort of situation, it does the
the parsing this get group for hierarchical name, we don't really
want.
That to happen.
At all and I don't really know.
to what extent we really call this
So it looks like we pretty much never.
Really wish I could see what was going on here.
Let's try again.
Get element from that.
There we go.
So
default parent group is what comes from what the data block is.
And so, I guess what we need to do here is get element from event.
Honestly, probably is just a little too heavy weight.
Probably, what we need to do is something where we we can specify
whether or not we actually want this to happen or not.
So if we have the parent here,
I mean we could just add another yet.
Another thing I don't know if it's going to be a little too bizarre,
if you have too many of these but we can do something here where it's
like, you know,
Add directly.
To parent.
So if we know that that's the case, then whatever the parent is that
we're going to get, we know that we can say, like, okay, when we do a
when we do a get group for hierarchical name, instead of
Actually ever calling this.
We can just say, like, oh put it in the parent by default and then if
add directly to parent, you know, is it's not true or I guess we could
say, maybe do it the other way around get hierarchical hierarchically
or create hierarchy.
You know, if that's set to true, then do this.
Otherwise don't.
And that would work fine.
So, yeah, if I want to keep them out of the hierarchy, then what I
would do is when we call get element from event and I pass it the
event here, oops.
And I pass at the event, then what I'm going to do is I'm going to say
create hierarchy is false for this particular circumstance and the
place that I want to put it is probably some special holding tank for
these which is like you know profile group.
And so the route Group which is here and holds all the stuff that
we're actually looking at that's actually going to be
Complemented by a profile group of just holds our profile blocks.
And then I don't actually know create variable group.
This just telling the size of this so that is 7.
All right.
Profile group is not a member of debug State.
You're correct about that because I actually have to go in here and
add it first.
So route group is here.
So profile group should be here and compile get element from event,
get element from event is an ambiguous.
Call is that so well if it is
Can I just realized?
I have to overloaded versus that function, which is part of the
problem killer from event, everybody cover not to find, right?
That's the problem.
We predict we forward declared that that fellow
So now we need to make sure that we update the one of those.
This right here is the thing that actually has to have the create
hierarchy,
And it.
There we go.
All right, so let's see here.
This is tooling along.
And so now we're still recording all that information, but now it's
actually being recorded into, like, the background where we can't
actually see it, which is what we wanted, right?
And so, now in theory, anyways, I should be able to draw those things
out by having whatever is going to happen in these.
Groups sort of look into that profile data and pull out whatever.
It is, the part that they actually wanted, that makes sense.
So, in order to do that, we already have this profile thing here but
we're not actually showing anything, right?
so, this information here, that's actually that sort of thread list
business, we can now go and
Start to actually try to implement this.
So, in the thread interval graph, what we can now do is we can Loop
over the members of that, that group, that, that element group and we
can actually draw those out.
Now I don't actually know how to figure out what the latest frame
index is but I'm assuming that that's actually something that we just
stored here because that's what I would have done and I wrote this
code.
So I'm assuming that
Like frame count, for example, is just telling us what the indices
are.
And so whatever the most recent well you know what, we can just look
at most recent frame.
Probably, and whatever.
Most recent frame is most recent frame.
Probably has whatever its index was right.
Most frame
I meant.
Yeah so it's got that.
So yeah, so I feel like that would do it.
Now frame bar scale doesn't what do you?
I don't know why that's there.
What that was supposed to do?
I'm assuming that had to do with storing.
How many threads were seen at that time.
But this is probably just garbage now, right?
I think that's just a strict doing some straight porting of the code.
So, yeah, that's, that's just I don't even know what that's supposed
to be other than stupid, so that's fine.
So,
yeah, so I think
For draw a profile in.
What we want to do here is figure out how many frames to draw, how
many frames we're going to draw, I guess.
I guess maybe we'll just try drawing just one frame for now.
And we'll try to adjust this so that it actually does something
useful.
So, intra profile in here is where we draw sort of our background.
Then here is where we
Loop over the frames and I guess we Loop over all the frames that we
stored.
That's not going to be very useful at this point because looping over
all of the frames that we stored is going to make it kind of
prohibitively expensive or not expensive.
Yes, expensive.
But it's not gonna be enough space.
I guess is what I'm saying, so we're not going to draw all the frames
recorded because now, we've drawn too many frames basically.
So we'll have to figure out.
So what we want to do with that but point being we'll go through here
and do maybe just one frame or something like that.
And try to keep this a little bit simpler.
I'll re-enable this here.
I don't know what this is supposed to be in a group chart lift chart
height.
So this was drawing some kind of a
look up, underlined
But I don't know why chart left plus 0.5 times start with in this
drawing chart with chart, man plus.
So it was just, that was just the outline, never mind.
So we don't need that anymore.
I can go away.
All right, so let's see.
Here's our
Bar scale information.
I don't know that we care about most of this stuff but I think
probably what we want to do is is just simplify this down and say okay
the frame that we're going to draw is the most recent frame.
and I don't know, since the most recent frame,
Thing that I'm not sure about is, is the most recent frame actually
not filled in yet, because we've or by the, when we're doing this
drawing.
We've already Advance one frame.
So, we really want the frame before that, or do you want this Frame?
And I'm not totally sure about that.
I should look probably and went through to handmade at where the frame
marker happens.
So, the free marker happens after the debug stuff is drawn.
So that means the most recent frame is really not done yet.
Right.
So, how are we counting for that in the current system in handmade?
Debug dot h?
I'm assuming that collation frame is actually the one that's being
filled.
So I'm assuming that most recent frame is the most recent frame.
We actually have data for, in which case, I think we're okay.
So we'd start with that frame.
And then what we do is we'd say, well, we know how long the frame took
Right, because we've got a beginning and clock.
So, the maximum like amount of of time that a function, could have
taken that's inside.
The frame is going to be between that begin clock in the end clock,
right?
So
We probably do something here.
Like, you know, R32 totals first frame span, you know, equals the
frame and clock - the frame begin clock.
Or something like this.
Right.
So if that's the span of the frame, then we now know that every piece
of information that we might have coming out from those open-close
blocks, each one of those is just going to tell us some place inside
that frame span, right?
And I don't know.
We've got the profile wrecked.
So we have like our pixel span which is just the width
Of the profile wrecked, right?
I don't know about the lane count and so I guess I'm hoping that that
is still a valid value if that makes sense.
And so if that's the lane count, then the rest of this stuff should
still work, I think frame bar scale, I don't really care about at the
moment.
I'm going to, I'm going to get rid of these and take a look at this.
I don't care about the max-frame situation.
Pixels per frame, plus spacing.
Yeah, so I'm going to I'm just going to get rid of this at the moment.
If the lane count is greater than zero, then I do want the lane height
to work.
so, I think
I think all this is
is reasonable here pixels per frame if I link out that, that seems
like that's not what I really want.
What I want for the lane count is, I want to just take the total
height of the thing and I get, this is the right way to do that.
I just want to take the total height of the thing and divide it by the
lane count.
So I'm pretty sure the lane height is just get dim profile wrecked.
Why / the lane count?
I don't think I want any of that.
I think that's really all I wanted.
That makes sense.
And that's how high the lanes are.
So that's it.
I don't think I want the rest of this stuff at the moment.
And let's see if we come through here again.
Don't really want to do multiple frames.
Don't want any of any of this at all.
Oh, did I do?
Okay, there we go.
Some reason I think I hit the wrong key.
Okay.
So now what I want to do is I just want to spin through each of the
things in the profile group, right?
I want to I've got that profile group that has
essentially, all of the
this right here has all of the things that are in the profile.
So, I've got debug variable link and that's going to be profile group.
Children next.
Link is not equal to profile group.
Children.
Blink blink.
Next that's going to be each of the elements that comprises a function
call or a timed block, if you will.
And
So really all we want to do is recompute this part right here.
Based on.
The open close block information rather than the the other bits.
So for our
Stored events.
Here we go.
For are stored events.
We have the oldest event and the most recent
But they're not a doubly linked list.
They're only a singly linked list which I don't know if that was a
particularly smart idea because it seems like you want to be able to
walk them in either order.
But for the time being, we can still spend through all of them.
I suppose, what we want to do is we only want to know what the
We only want to know what the most recent and the one just before that
was or rather we just want to walk the ones that are in this
particular frame.
So I'm not sure exactly how we walk those.
Cause like I said, we haven't really dealt with these in a while.
So let's take a look at who actually uses these.
So if we go to the most recent event,
Doesn't look like.
Doesn't look like we ever actually iterate over them anymore, but here
our store event.
So you can see that if there's a most recent event, then it's most
recent event equals most recent event, next result, if there isn't,
then they're both equal.
So what that means is the most recent event is the tail pointer and
the oldest event is the head pointer.
So it starts at all this event and goes to most recent, I don't know
why, we didn't doubly linked those so that we can walk them in either
order.
That's kind of not clear to me to be completely honest because it
seems like we would want to do that so I don't know.
Me might want to change that to linking them both directions but who
knows, maybe we want to do the build them in some more complex order
just in general because it is true that maybe we want them to be in
the more hierarchical.
Maybe we want to build a tree out of them or something in the future
to accelerate these sort of things, if we were being fancy.
Anyway, so who's to say?
But anyway, so if we're in here and we want to draw, rectangles, what
we would do is we'd say well, okay the debug element which is the
profile element for these guys.
We want to make sure that it always has one because that's the only
thing these links are always supposed to have those and assuming that
it does, then what we're going to do is we're going to say for each of
the store at events in here.
As we go through the events, what we want to do is we want to look to
see if the event is what its frame and X is the frame that we're
actually on.
and if it is,
then we want to either draw it if it's a closed event or
Set like keep track of what the interval is, if it's not.
Right.
So trying to think here,
If it's a frame, if it's one of these basic, what we'd say is, it's a
debug stored event you know, open Event equals zero.
And so we'd say if it's a frame, if it's one that we recognize, right?
If it's something that we recognize and I guess we can we can even
move this, this guy can be inside here if it's one that we recognize
how much time I got four minutes.
then what we want to do is say, if, you know the event
Type is an open event.
Don't really remember what that's called.
Begin block.
If it's a begin block.
Then the open event is going to be equal to this event.
And I guess we can dispense with the stored part of this, probably.
If it is.
Close block.
Then we would just say like, if there is an open Event, right?
Then we can draw and I suppose we could even do it this way.
Then we can draw it.
So if you know, if we had a previously had an open Event.
Now we've got the close event that goes with it and so now we know
exactly what the interval is and we can draw it on the chart.
So if that's the case, then we know the, we know the clock, right?
We know the clock value here for it so we can use the clock to place
it directly into the location that it should be and we know the frame,
I'm sorry, we know the thread ID.
So the thread ID can also tell us where
Would go in the in the region.
So, I don't know.
I don't remember how to look up the lane index for things.
That I don't recall.
And one thing that we probably would want to do, actually, is replace
these thread IDs.
When we store them, we would want to replace that with a ordinal for
Red rather than thread ID.
I think because the thread ID is coming from Windows, we want to
rewrite that with some well-formed ordinal so that's probably a to do.
Casey replace thread ID with a well-formed ordinal, at collation time.
Because that seems like something.
We don't really want the windows thread IDs.
At that point, we want to regularize the thread IDs down to something
that we can use.
So, let's ignore that problem temporarily because I'll do that
tomorrow.
We don't have time to do that today.
I don't think it won't take long because we already do it in the
collation.
We just don't store it.
But anyway, if we find them then we would know like, okay, the place
where this thing is going to be the Minix and the max X are just going
to be placing those clocks that the frame span.
We just need an inverse frame span here.
Right.
Or rather the frame scale, right?
So to compute that frame scale, we just need to know that the pixel
span is.
I'm sorry that the frame span is nonzero.
so, assuming that it is,
So that we took some time, assuming that it is, then what we need to
do is we need to say that whatever the pixel span is.
Is how big we want things to be if they take the entire time?
So we want to do the toll pixels fan and we want to shrink down the
frames time to equal to the unit, right?
So you want to say like okay?
However, big the frame span is we divide by that to regularize,
everything to be between 0 and 1 and then we multiply by the pixels
fan to blow it out to the right number of pixels.
So that's the entire thing for the frame.
Scale going from the frames fan to the pixel span.
So all we have to do here is just say like the min max is just going
to be whatever our profile wrecked exes.
And then that's going to be plus the, the frame scale.
I guess we just called it scale here.
So I'll leave it that call that.
We're going to have that scale times, for whatever the open event was
that clock - the frames?
Begin clock.
Because that gives us the sort of the ordered version at right that
the based off of the beginning of the, of the frame and suddenly the
profile wrecked wise scale.
We want that to be
I'm sorry, the max X rather we want that to be the
Close the vents same thing.
So that's, that's that.
Just going to change that scale, not a great word and a great a great
word but oh well.
So that's scale.
Then let's see what else we've got.
Is we have the wise, have to be fixed.
So let's see here.
Oh let's debug state.
Oh right.
Okay, so yeah.
Region.
I don't know that this is something we can really do much about it at
the moment.
So I'm going to leave that as an undone thing profile wrecked.
We need our, I guess it's be armed in Acts left of clock.
I agree with that.
It's that.
And that.
So, we need our open event.
We should probably just also introduced a
This event.
Which is just.
The one we just found.
Stack.
Why is Undeclared identifier?
That's true.
So how is this working here?
We've got lay night, the lane index.
So we don't know the lane index at the moment.
So that's just going to have to remain like so.
Something like this.
And we know the lane height.
So this is this this is just going to be the profile recommend why?
Or it looks like we're coming down the lanes from the top.
So it's actually going to be the max.
Why is the way we did this?
Right.
Missing parentheses is that.
So,
so,
push wrecked.
We've got a region ranked 00 before our to V4.
What's the problem with that?
Render group is first.
That we're talking about.
Render group star object transform, we don't have an object transform.
So this is actually just old code basically.
So here's what we actually need, right?
And we've got this this no transform thing here, which is what we
would want to use.
We go.
So in fact we could just do this right?
Can look at this here, that's what it actually has to be.
We've got no transform or region erect and then our colors.
So there we go.
So, that's all good, this record.
I guess we just use open event at the moment and see what else we got.
Block names, not a thing.
In fact, I don't really want to look at this right now, to be honest,
this is just really going to format the information for the record so
we can do that.
In a bit.
Let's go ahead and recompile.
All right, so that's where we'll leave it for today.
We won't go any further there.
Oh, that's amusing.
That's actually correct hilariously.
I think
You can see that it's a yeah.
We don't have any way right now of actually ensuring that we're
drawing in the correct order to say the least.
But okay, so I'm going to leave it here because we've got more work to
do to do a bunch of stuff, we have to get the Sorting order, right?
And like I said, probably have to do some hardcore stuff because we
don't really know in order to draw these.
We don't really have any information, unfortunately, about like,
We don't have any information about who calls who and so stacking.
These up is going to be a little bit tricky to say the least, but
we're getting there.
So we'll pick that back up tomorrow.
And for now we'll go to some Q&A for a brief period here.
also, I suppose
if I take a pointer and I convert it down to something that we can
use, like,
This.
Must have.
Okay.
Could you answer, what do you think of using call tree to track
dependencies across multi-threading?
Well, if you're talking about the profiler, so the problem is a call
tree doesn't really help you.
What we actually need to know is which set of calls goes with which
parent call, which is kind of tricky.
I mean, we can actually have like I said, I'm thinking of storing
actual parent pointer each one which at that point is sort of a call
tree, but it's actually like a, it's more like an act.
Actually tracking every single call as opposed to just a call, call a
typical call graph.
Just has this function gets called from this other function sometimes,
right?
So yeah.
What command do you use to change from cutscene to game?
I was the spacebar
tomorrow's episode 0xff.
That's true.
Expansion pack.
How do you handle tasks that run in separate threads would take longer
than a frame to compute?
For example, I heard that in the New Forest of the rearview mirror
updates at half the frame rate as everything else, that's totally
fine.
At the moment, we wouldn't be drawing those, but we can do that as
soon as we get all this stuff straightened out.
It's not very difficult.
Because if you look here where we'd say, like, oh, if we found an open
Event, if we didn't find an open Event in this Frame, but we found the
close event in this Frame, that means that it was running since the
His frame.
So we could just draw from the beginning.
We just hard set.
This clock value to 0, right?
Or sorry, this offset 20
Necessary.
Why was I not informed?
That Krampus is in this game.
Are you kidding?
Dude, I sent you the picture of Krampus.
Before I think even was shown on this.
You have like an email in your inbox of Krampus.
I'm pretty sure maybe not.
I know, I thought I thought I sent you the picture Krampus
But he's in the game, man.
Krampus is not just in the game.
Krampus is like the reason the game even exist because Santa Claus is
basically just a dick, right?
Which is true.
And he doesn't like understand that a little boy, that doesn't have
any arms is not going to be very happy.
Just getting hats all the time.
Like he needs to be able to like, get out and like do stuff in the
forest and like have adventures.
And so when Krampus comes and he notices that he like, totally
Saves the Day by giving the kid because, you know, as you know,
Krampus dismembered his children.
That's what he does.
So he'd have a lot of hands around in his sack to give to the little
kid so that he could have a hand now.
And that's exactly what he does.
So it's basically like Krampus is like is great.
I mean, that's basically the moral of the story.
Too.
Freaky is talking to the chat, while coding helpful to work things
out.
No, it's the opposite of that talking, while coding, makes it really
very, very difficult to code.
And I find that a lot of times it's hard to do complicated stuff while
I'm talking, but I do the best I can.
Do you have a problem with Santa from your childhood?
Yes.
Actually I do when I was little like my mom took me to the grocery
store and I was in the little cart.
You know, how I'd like you to sit like a kid in, like, like into the
cart and they are, like legs dangle through and they like sit facing
backwards.
I think so, they can see their parent.
Who's like, pushing them around and like this weird, like, dude
dressed as Santa?
Like, wave to me and said, ho ho, ho or something at Christmas time,
and I didn't know.
that was and I freaked out and I screamed and I like banged my head
like my, my
Like my mouth on the bar, on the, like, bar of the grocery cart, and I
let it, like, my teeth went into my lip and I like bled everywhere.
So like Santa's like, no good like, Santa is just not good.
We should we should have Krampus mostly and celebrate Krampus things.
And then Santa is like forget, Santa is not good, Santa should not be
allowed to be in games, other than, as a villain.
All right, John is saying that you didn't get a picture Krampus it did
I just send?
Did I only send Santa?
I sent a picture.
I'm going to go back and find it but I sent a picture and I thought
had Krampus in it but I guess I'm wrong.
I'll look though.
Did you consider visualizing timing using flame graphs?
But well in case you haven't noticed we're just starting to draw
profiles now.
So something as advanced as a flame graph, is going to require a lot
more code to write for an in, you know, in thing profiler so we could
consider writing a fling graph further down the line.
I don't think I will because we certainly don't need one and it's just
going to, you know, we spent a plenty of time on the debug system
already.
It like I wanted to spend time in the architecture of it so you can
kind of see me working through a bunch of weird trade-offs and see how
that goes, but spending a bunch of time making like, you know,
gratuitous graphs is not probably a super good use of stream time.
So I don't think we would probably ever write a flame graph.
They don't give you very much actual information.
As a visualization, they're kind of like I said a little gratuitous
it's not to say that they aren't helpful but it's like in terms of
actually needing a fling graph to do a profile to profile your code.
code, it's
There's almost no case where it's like I couldn't have gotten the
information.
I needed from a simpler graph and I think a lot of times, the only
reason you would ever really need a flame graph is if you're in some
kind of nasty, super nasty crazy code base, where you couldn't tell
what was going on.
Maybe that helps you.
I don't know, but they're not super necessary, right?
Is this suffering the same time as tank?
No, it's not suffering.
I think it's just going through the like ridiculous number of debug
for elements, right?
We just have way too many, debug elements to sift through at this
point because we're recording, we're recording arbitrary numbers of
frames.
Right?
That's why I said, like, we kind of have to not do this the way that
it's being done.
Because this has to Loop through every frame.
Every time every event every
There's just there's hundreds of thousands of them at this point.
So it's going to be way too expensive so that's why it's a, I'm not
really sure exactly what we want to do about that but we'll need a
faster way of querying.
The information that we need because basically all of the time is in
this.
If for example, you were to just get rid of this
Right.
Then I think you would be fine.
Why did that?
Not reload because it's saying,
Trouble code.
Thank you so much for telling me that that code is unreachable and not
actually building my game.
That's that's what I wanted you to do.
There we go.
So you can see if you just disable that search, right?
Then then you're okay.
but,
We definitely have some kind of a string problem because our strings
are guarded now, like we do push them on here, but you can see that
we're not actually getting like that, got across the reload, it broke.
So something is not getting pushed on properly, and we should figure
out what it is because that's that's a bug.
Right, because code reload should work now and it mostly does.
But that's these are not being pushed on properly.
Looks like we're done with Q colons.
I need to scroll back through and see.
See here.
Yeah, I think we're good.
All right, so let's go ahead and close down here.
There we go.
And yeah.
So this is what we'll work on tomorrow.
I'm going to get that going.
I I think really we just need to figure out what data structure.
Lets us draw some useful things that doesn't throw out too much
information.
We definitely can't afford to search it all.
All the time, we could just double link those list, so we can just
look at just the current ones or whatever, but I'm not certain
That has to go if that makes sense, Agnes hold heard, you have a
secret phobia of writing game code, not really a secret phobia but I
definitely don't like it.
Like that is, there's no question that that will be the least fun part
of the stream for me.
I don't really like game code because that, in my opinion, is for a
game designer to do, and I am not a game designer.
I'm an engine programmer.
So,
you know, will
we'll be out of things to do in the engine before too long.
But yeah, am I interested in running game code?
No, I don't really want to do it because that's not what I like to do.
And so typically like the, you know, the parts of game code that I'll
enjoy are the parts that were actually just actually implementing em
engine pieces but which are
You know, premature to do prior to the game code.
So like some animation code and code for how we handle, you know, just
storage of the entities or like that that's you know, code that I like
to write.
But code that's like actually gameplay code like you know what should
this enemy be doing at this point like I don't find the I don't like
writing that code at all.
like I said that's that's really for game designers to do and not me
that makes sense game code is for game designers
Not for engine programmers.
So I'm going to close this down and yeah, we got like I said we still
have more stuff to do before this debug system is really correct and
to sort of I guess answer this the baby, perhaps just a question is,
I'm not writing more debug code because I don't want to write gameplay
code.
I don't want to write gameplay code, but that's not actually why the
reason it just because until the D-backs system is, is satisfactory to
me, I don't consider it.
On right?
And I don't plan on really revisiting the debug system.
Much certain things like Collision detection, we did a little bit of
just to have it in place and sort of see what was there, but it's not
like done right but I'm planning on wanting more game code in place
before we go back and make the final one of it.
Whereas the debug code should just be this is this is we know what
it's going to do.
So we don't really have much more too much more information, we need
out of it.
So, I want it to actually be done to my satisfaction before moving on.
And, like I said, this was one where I decided to do things, I wanted
to show how to work through architecture stuff.
So this is stuff.
That is not the way I've ever done it before.
Possibly not the way I would do it again, either.
I just decided to try some different things and see what we would end
up with if that makes a sense to y'all.
So, yeah, so no because there's plenty of
Engine stuff we can do.
It's not like I have to do the debug code and the only other thing to
do is gameplay code because we've got a couple other things on the
to-do list that are definitely not gameplay code, that makes sense.
So,
Gary Johansen, can we make games and Game maker and submit them to you
for the final game?
No.
The game is designed.
I did that, it's done.
And that's what it'll be.
And like I said, the gameplay code is, is not that interesting to me
because that's basically like, you know,
What was I going to say?
Yeah, it's just like oh you know how exactly should this thing, do
what it's doing in terms of feel?
Or should this enemy like attack?
This guy, how frequently or something like that, that stuff is, you
know, you can't design that on paper or anything.
Anyways and you, you know, you've tip you want like a game designer do
those things like that.
That's what they're supposed to do.
That's their job, right?
And so I don't really want to do those things because
As that's very game designee.
And so normally I would just say that's the game designers job to set
all that stuff.
But in this case, there is no game designer here because I'm doing the
whole stream obviously.
So, you know, that's the way that is, in terms of tuning, we can
always.
If there's things that are easy to expose as just a variable, then
that's simple because then you can always just leave that and send it
to somebody who's a good game designer after we're done and be like
tree tune, these variables as
Necessary, but that's not, that's like not the hard part.
The hard part is more, the more intricate decisions about what's
happening in the code.
Like, you know, about the actual maybe like, I don't want to say AI
programming because that's kind of a loaded term, but I mean, they'd
like game Behavior programming.
Having making the decisions about what the enemies are going to do.
And when and how exactly right, there's how do you program that?
Well and I can show you how to do that.
But there's how do you make decisions about what it should do in terms
of making the game the best game and that is not in my purview, right?
I don't that's not my area of expertise so that's the sort of stuff I
just don't enjoy because I'm not versed in it and I don't have
anything to add.
So it's going to be
I'm a stream.
It's gonna be like, well, here's what this enemy does because I said
so, and if you want to know what the enemy actually should do, you
should go talk to somebody who's a good game designer and ask them and
hopefully, they can explain it to you because I'm not going to make
sense.
Abner's asking me to for people to stay on the chat.
After I am done, which is?
I am done.
So, I guess he wants me to say, stay on the chat.
I don't know why you should stay on the chat.
Abner, do you want to tell people why they're so stylish it?
I don't think people are going to be that interested in staying on the
chat.
Just because I said, so, because I'm leaving the chat, so it would be
weird for me to say like, oh, hey, you should stay on the chat while I
don't do that.
Abner coimbra.
It has to do with Juan 3D and an interview with him.
Well, why is that not just announce then?
Just someone wants, what's going on?
Why would you have a secret interview with One Chun?
Why wouldn't you just say we're going to have an interview with?
Wanted a here is when it is.
Something's up, what is up?
So me, tell me what's up.
Okay, wait.
You're going to stream an announcement of an interview?
It's not alive and what I don't even know what you, okay.
Ladies and gentlemen, I'm going to close down the stream.
I have no idea what's going on on the chat.
I feel like probably what's happened is that Abner is had too much
chocolate wine and now, believes that launched on is talking to him
from New York City.
It's sad, really, but that appears to be what has happened, I don't
know.
I've been asked that to ask you to stay in the chat, so I asked you to
do that.
You should feel free to assess the level of drunkenness that Abner is
currently at for your own.
Make your own using your own judgment and then you can decide whether
Sanchez.
I will tell you that one Chun.
Is somebody worth watching an interview with?
However, I don't.
This is the first.
I really have heard that there was even going to be interview.
So I don't even know what it would be on or what's it's about, I have
nothing else to say, but if one is going to be doing an interview on
something, that is probably going to be interesting, he knows a lot of
computer science, see stuff.
And so any sort of theoretical things, it's usually I would assume if
you're going.
Talking about anything computer science theoretical that.
That would be pretty interesting.
But I don't actually know because Abner hasn't said.
So anyway that's what's going on.
And now, I will close the chat down and let the I'm sorry, I will
close the stream down and let the chat do whatever it is that the chat
is going to do, and I'm mildly terrified, but I have to go to dinner,
so that's, I guess I won't even get to find out.
The situation is thank you, everyone for joining me, for their sort of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with source code,
you can always do so by pre-ordering the game on handmade here at org
comes to the source code so you can follow along.
You can also go to our
Forum site to ask questions.
If you have questions, you want answered.
That's a good place to do it.
We also have patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, we have a tweet bot.
You can tweet.
The, you can subscribe to that if you want the schedule tweeted to you
so you can catch the live stream.
And speaking of the live stream will be back 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow until then have fun programming and I
will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.