Recording.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The sure we could have complete game live on stream and yesterday we
went ahead and implemented multi-threaded texture downloads but we
didn't have a chance to actually step through and debug any of it.
So our textured downloads are definitely not working yet.
All we did was write the actual code for it and that was because we
spent most of time yesterday talking about what those even were and
describing them on the Blackboard so we didn't have that much time to
code.
Maybe 30, 35 minutes on 034.
Probably 45 minutes cuz I went late long because I want to get it all
done.
So we did it all but now we got actually two buckets.
That's we're going to do today.
If you are trying to follow along with today's stream and you're
someone who pre-ordered the game when you download that source, code
today is day 2 44.
So download day 243 source code out of that source code ZIP and that's
where I'm at today.
So let's go ahead and get that going.
Let's go ahead and load up our, handmade code situation here, handmade
prj.
And if I build and run, you can see where we're at, which is, we're
not like crashing or anything, but our textures just don't get
downloaded.
Like they don't actually get through to the card so that when we run
the game, as you can see, like we end up in this circumstance where
it's just like clearly drawing with just a white texture.
Doesn't actually have any content in it.
So our job today, which is always an unsavory job.
Anytime you're trying to debug anything with Graphics drivers.
It's always an epic Nightmare.
And the reason is because, of course, it's much, like, debugging
things on Windows.
You can't actually step into their code and see what's actually going
on.
So you have to kind of treat it as a black box and sometimes, you
know, you can get errors back from the black box that will help you
and we will
I'll probably try to do some of that.
Potentially today to get some errors back from opengl.
Maybe that might give us some information about what's going wrong,
but in general it's just a much harder problem than when we debug our
own code.
Because when we do about our own code, we can see 100% of what's
actually happening.
And that's actually one of the really nice things about programming,
you know, a whole game engine to is that drastically limits, the
amount of stuff that you don't understand, and you don't know, and you
can't step through it right on him a hero, we kind of had it easy
because we invented everything.
Even the renderer.
So when a pixel looked wrong we can step in and find out exactly why.
Unfortunately.
When we decided to add Hardware acceleration and we knew this was
coming.
I mean we knew we had to take advantage of the GPU if we want to ship
a game that that is comparable performance to, you know, games that,
you know, other games that you can buy.
We know we have to use the GPU because it's where most of the graphics
horsepower the machine and we can't not use it.
But the trade-off is, once you start using the GPU, there's this huge
driver in the way and
all this graphics card.
Specific stuff in the way and you lose that all of that, nice ability
to see everything that's going on.
And so in some sense, it puts you more back into the shoes of, you
know, of JavaScript or Java, those sorts of things, where there's this
whole system beneath you.
That you can't see and you can't step into that one part of our
program that handles the graphics now has that same problem.
It's very frustrating, right?
We're spoiled again.
When we do see stupas us because we can literally look at the assembly
and see exactly what our codes.
Doing when it goes wrong.
We can see exactly why.
And that's just so nice and so convenient.
With unfortunately, as soon as you start using that Harbor
acceleration, it just hasn't gotten to that point yet.
Someday, My fond hope is that I will live to see the day.
When graphics cards are.
No, don't exist anymore and you just have a processor and you program
that processor.
And it just happens to have a lot of really beefy, ALU stuff in it
because then we would be able to have just, you know, our software
renderer could have been the actual renderer and it could access all
that horsepower and we could have
It'd be something that we had complete control over.
That's not the world.
We live in, what you gonna do?
So we just have to live with it a little bit.
It's not like our whole programs that way.
So what we try to do is isolate the amount to which we talked to the
driver, right?
We try to keep the graphic systems kind of carp compartmentalised
because it is this thing that we just don't have access to and it's a
very frustrating part of the code if you're used to having that Total
Access.
So that's just the reality of where we're at.
So now we're in a black box that bugging scenario.
We know that we're not seeing anything on the screen, we will be able
to do some limited stepping to see like whether or not.
For example, we're actually creating the context that we thought we
were creating or other things like that.
But beyond that, we will have
A very limited ability to step into any code and so we're going to
have to start using debugging techniques more made for sort of Black
Box.
The bugging again like the sort you would use for when you're dealing
with the windows platform layer and you can't see in there or when
you're in some higher-level, language python PHP Java whatever where
there's a whole system beneath you.
And you can't actually see how you're talking to the CPU because it's
somebody else who's talking to CPU, write on your behalf.
So that's the situation that we find ourselves in now.
So diving into this, the first thing we should do obviously is just
take a stroll through our new opengl code and see if there's anything
that's obviously a missed because it might be that we have some rather
obvious bugs that are not at all subtle or or complex, that won't take
very long to debug.
And we should try to get those out of the way first, so just take a
look through.
We made some changes.
Let's just make sure we're still doing things that we roughly
spect to do.
So here we are in in the opengl code where we create that context
initially and one of the things that you can see and I just kind of
want to emphasize this again and I know this sounds like I'm sort of
bad-mouthing Graphics drivers and that is exactly what I am tending
to.
Actually, it's bad about them.
Not so much this early because I think that they're sort of written
poorly or anything like this.
It's more just because that whole ecosystem is actually kind of an
epic disaster.
What that means is that just the act and you saw there, just the act
of initializing that opengl context was like, a noticeable delay.
Like, I don't know if you saw that, but I can step back in gear.
Right here we are.
And I'm about to initialize opengl watch how long it takes me to step
over this line.
Did you see that that's like two seconds or something?
Right the whole startup time for our app was like instant before, most
of the time was waiting for me.
Blows the fade are memos fade that he wanted to do.
Right?
If we took that out, it just comes up like that.
Now all of a sudden all we do, all we did was ask for Hardware
acceleration to get initialized and all of a sudden our startup time
got, you know, what 10x worse?
I don't even know how bad it is, but it's way worse.
That's just, that's the kind of thing that just drives me insane.
It's like and there's nothing you can do.
There's nothing we can do about it, right?
If we want to talk to the hardware, we have to go through the driver
layer.
There's nothing we can do.
And so that's unfortunate someday, like I said, Someday, I'm really
hoping that I, I don't want to die programming computers like this.
I want to, I want to like code my last lines on something, where I
actually coded the hardware, and there wasn't two seconds worth of
startup time, just to get a display surface.
So here we go.
Go.
We've got back our context and we can see that it actually worked in
that.
We got a context and we were able to make it current.
Now, that's the same code that were using before.
So that makes sense, that that worked.
And what we're doing here is you can see, we're kind of storing this
off.
So we're storing this open, Jill RC to a global, there it is.
And you can see, it's the same one that is the modern one, which is
what we want.
So that's all good.
And then later on down here, when we get to the bottom, we're going to
store off that window DC as well, right?
That's the DC of our window and I believe we have a CSO DC window
which means that that we don't have to worry.
About ever releasing that.
But I'm going to go double check because I don't actually know if
that's true.
So I should double-check that, just in case that's a possible.
Like problematic thing.
So, yeah, it looks like we don't have a CS phone DC here.
So, I'm a little nervous about that.
I'm just a little as have a twinge of nervousness about that because
if we don't have a CSO DC here then I don't think holding the DC open
like that is a good idea.
Now, granted we don't really hold it that open because we could
actually release it like right here because we've once we've we're
just doing it saving the DC and we could release it right here.
And then we wouldn't need to see us on DC.
And in fact, that's something that I could totally do like, right
here, maybe I should, but I'm going to go ahead and see what happens
if we make that a CSO DC win.
Do I need to do?
You know what I'm not gonna do that.
I'm not gonna do that.
I'm just going to go ahead and do the the open and close.
So the way that I'm going to do that is temporarily.
I'm just going to go in here and say okay we've got this Global DC
thing happening, right?
And what I think I'm going to do is I'm going to make these a little
less, a little less specific there.
And I'm going to go to the part where we initialize opengl.
So I don't know where that actually is.
There it is.
So in win32 in it, opengl what I'd like to do here is I'd like to make
this actually return the open.
Lrc.
So that hdlr see that we create whichever one we decide to go with.
I'm going to have that return it and so I'm going to have that be
something where we sort of take down here instead of assigning it to a
global.
I'm going to make that just return the thing.
And the other thing I'm going to do, I'm going to get rid of this is
I'm going to say that this thing.
When we pass in the window, in fact, I don't even know when we pass in
the window, do we even use the window?
Whereas I can't see.
It's behind my head.
Do we ever use the window itself?
So we never even used the window itself.
So what I'm going to do instead is I'm going to pass the HDC in and
the reason I'm doing this again it's just a sort of lift this code up
just a little bit more because I don't want it to be too Global and
stringing you know in a platform layer the platform that you're on top
of is typically banana.
And you can see that we're going through all this ridiculous stuff for
no good reason, right?
And so, I don't really care about having global variables in the
platform layer or crazy.
Spaghetti code.
The platform there because typically that sort of has to happen and if
you try to over engineer it you end up to spending a lot of time for
no real reason but just because that's the case doesn't mean I
shouldn't take the opportunity to make things a little cleaner when I
can just to keep it.
So it's readable and we don't accidentally make some weird mistakes
when we're changing things.
So,
I'm gonna go ahead and make that change and and sort of make it so
that we passed that, that DC in.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to say let's get the DC
right here.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to say like that Global DC, I
think is what it was called.
I'm going to get the DC here for the global DC and then I'm going to
release it after we're done.
And we could make it so that we pass this stuff through.
Now, like, I sort of, almost did before, we could definitely do
something like that if we want to in the future because now I know
that I was a little confused about how the platform stuff worked, the
platform cool stuff because I didn't quite remember how we were
dispatching those and so at this point, you know, that's that's
reasonable and I'm okay with what's happening here for now.
So I don't need to like go the full, the full nine, but I just kind of
want to make that a little clearer.
So
We get that DC and then I'll just get that Global heo, the global
opengl RC right here as well.
And so now I can sort of see that code a little bit more cleanly.
So let's go ahead and compile that information.
Some of the errors that might be there.
Let's see.
Oh, right.
That's that actually take that Global DC.
So, so that's just a little that was just a little cleaner.
So, oops.
That's a speaking of times to go fix that code.
It's not
There's Valeria.
So here we are in the ended up in jail again.
Like I said we're going to do go through here and and go ahead and
look at all those delays God look at all those toys.
All right, so anyway we can return up until our see here so now
hopefully both our Global DC and our Global up until our C are both
valid and I think they are.
In this case, then we go ahead and create these work cues and the low
priority
Q needs opengl.
We set that to True.
Right?
So now I'm going to go ahead in there and we're going to go ahead and
create this now.
Actually.
So now that I look at this though, to we even really can't quite
release it here because we don't actually know that the cues are done
using this yet, right?
So we could there's two ways we could sort of do this and it depends
on which way we want.
But we could create the the opengl context outside of the cube but
I don't know if you noticed this.
I can't I can't actually release this here because if I go into winter
to make you right, what's going to happen is when I call create thread
that's going to start that other thread running and that other thread
is going to do in the thread proc, it's going to potentially do this
create opengl concert or worker thread.
I'm a race down to release the jeep.
That that window DC before, it has a chance to actually create the
context, right?
And so I actually can't
You that release d.c.
That's just not something I can actually do.
So I think that does mean we got a hold that that open.
Which means I'm going to.
I'm going to go ahead and claim.
This is a known to you as the CSO DC window for now.
Which allows us to hold that, open permanently if we want to.
So yeah, so let's go ahead and jump in here and, you know, and like I
said, there's some ways we might now that we're seeing that that's
kind of a little bit of a pain and create some problems for us.
We can take steps to avoid it.
So, you know, I wouldn't worry too much about that, but it's just, you
know, for now, it's fine.
So, let's go in here and take a look at what happens when we actually
need to create the opengl context for one of these worker threads.
This
Should be hopefully one of these ones that has a needs opengl set.
It should be one of our low priority queues, right?
And so if I go in here,
To where we're going to create opengl context for worker thread.
We just got to.
See, do we have the ability to open the will context?
We do.
We've got that Global DC still around.
We've got the open, Jill RC still around.
Now, we're going to try and create a shared context with it, by
passing the DC and the context.
What we are sharing were then passing those at ribs that we know that
we had and then we're just going to see.
Oh, and now we got, we've got another thread.
So we don't really, we haven't done too much thread to bugging, so let
me just explain what's going on here because you may be a little
confused about what just happened.
So we created two threads.
I mean, we created eight threads actually, but we created two of those
threads are for low priority work, which means they just sit in the
background doing stuff like loading files off disk and submitting
textures opengl.
That's all they do.
Those ones because they need to submit text, opengl have to have their
own opengl context.
So we're going through the process of creating them.
That means there are two separate threads, which right now are
executing this win32 create opengl context for worker thread.
Now, the way the actual debugger works is when you step in the code,
it's actually going to show us different threads executing, right.
And so what we're trying to do is we were trying to follow
One of those thread prox through we were trying to follow.
You can see these are the worker threads, right?
Can you see all these guys here that aren't opening up in jail?
They're all sitting there waiting for a, you know, they're just on a
delay, right.
This guy is the one we were just on and this guy is the other one
who's about to come through.
So these guys are both going to initialize opengl.
What we want to do is say I only want to see just this threads
execution.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to essentially say, actually know
if you can do a freeze all but
I don't actually remember, I thought you could, I don't see it there.
But anyway here I'm just going to say freeze This Thread.
This is the other guy who's actually doing this.
They freeze that thread and freeze the main thread because then I
don't have to worry about seeing them their paused and they're not
going to do anything.
Okay?
So now I should be able to do that step where I can step onto in
through the main domain.
Proc, if that makes sense, at least I think I can maybe not.
What's the problem?
Here, I thought.
Are you waiting on this guy?
What is the problem?
Why can you not step?
well, I was going to do that, but I guess now I'm not
What exactly did I do that?
Made you so upset?
Can you tell me why can you tell me what you are?
What you are grumpy about?
I mean, this is the person who has the execution right now, right.
You can tell that by that little thing there.
So I'm not sure why that isn't
All right.
Well that did not go very well.
That should have worked but I don't know why.
So, let's try that one more time.
Okay, there we go.
So now we're almost through to create opengl thread.
I'm going to go ahead and freeze the other thread before.
It has a chance of do anything.
I'm not sure why this is in the CRT or what?
Exactly it's doing in the CRT.
I'm not sure about that.
I don't know if that's part of the thread startup or what's going on
there.
So, that's a bit weird.
But anyway, here we are in this code.
So I'm going to go ahead and step in here.
I'm going to let it start to create that context.
We're going to switch out to this, this guy's going to come through,
he's going to try and create that context as well.
And so I just want to see if we got anything back.
So we did get an RC back which suggests that that worked right?
And then we're going to do a wiggle make current with the window DC
and the module are see.
We're going to see if that worked.
We're going to do that on both threads, right?
And then I guess what?
A problem is we don't actually have a line of code here so we can
actually see
That worked.
And so maybe one thing I could do, now that I think about it, that
would make it easier for us to actually edit that is I could do where
we do our wiggle make current.
I could actually have a thing that, that sort of
Where is that?
Here it is.
Inside are BOGO Mei, current.
If for some reason, we don't get it.
We can like fail loudly.
So we know that that it actually is, is broken.
So let's just see what actually happened.
I'm set a breakpoint there and see if that actually ever occurs.
So we don't ever get there, which says, to me, that we are actually
able to set up our opengl context, they are actually working.
So again, that doesn't actually tell us that we've set them up
correctly.
So, there may still be problems that we are.
Not aware of that, are going to come back and haunt us, and that might
be wired to start downloading, but we've at least done the due
diligence to know.
Okay?
Nothing is obvious.
We failing when we create these extra context and make them current on
the threads that were using.
So we at least know that much is happening.
Now, let's go over to the opengl bit here and I guess I should
probably do this in the
in the debugger because that's what we actually want to step through
it.
Well so what I want to do is I want to see now.
The texture download went three to allocate texture and D
architecture.
What I want to do is I want to step through those
and I want to see what happens in those.
So if I run now as soon as
Somebody tries to actually download a texture, we should get that
call.
All right, so that's a good sign.
If we're never hitting that break point, then that means we just have
a bug in.
We're never actually trying to initiate the texture.
Download right some but thing is failing we're we're never actually
getting that that call through.
So this might just be a real simple bug on our side and that would be
great because if it's a book on our side like I said before that keeps
us out of the whole Black Box to bugging thing that isn't particularly
Ali fun.
So I assume that when we come in here,
I assume.
Oh, you know what?
This is the problem right here.
We never said that finalized operation.
So we're never accessed.
We're never asking for our our thing to be downloaded, so it's just
never hitting that path.
So if we're supremely lucky and I'm not trying to suggest that we will
be here.
But if we were going to be supremely lucky right now, this would be
our only bug and then everything else would work great.
So here's our finalized asset none.
We're going to say that it's a bitmap now, so that we're in load
bitmap, it should actually.
Now
The actual download.
So now let's let's run and see what happens.
Super long startup time brought to you by AMD, then we can go ahead
and jump in here and say, all right, we got that bitmap.
Now, we are actually in the finalized path, which is what we wanted,
and we're going to call through to load texture, right?
Okay.
And we've never actually loaded that pointer.
At least.
I don't think we did.
So back here.
Went through handmade.
We never actually, did we have the allocate memory call back?
Right.
So that was where was that?
That's right here.
Just roll it up and place.
So yeah, we just never actually we implemented the functions.
We just never put in the pointers.
So this is allocate texture.
And so is this.
All right.
So now what happens when we try to allocate texture?
Do we actually call through it?
Looks like we do.
So here is US trying to get a handle for the texture.
We got back handle one, which makes sense is the first time we're done
with a texture.
That seems like the thing.
The driver, we return.
We bind that texture.
We try to send down the data to it, which is what we're doing here.
We bind,
The texture and set the parameters for it like we did before we, then
say, we're no longer a talk about that texture on this thread, and
then we leave, right?
And, and that's it.
So that's our texture.
Download in the background and hey, look, it actually worked.
So, now in theory, we should have gotten ourselves potentially out of
the situation where we have the stars in the fact we didn't, we did
not have that frame stutter, which is pretty great.
So now we're downloading our textures on a separate thread.
And it's in that whole queuing system.
Being kind of overlap with everything else we're doing now.
Is it 100% efficient right now?
Is it doing everything as best that it possibly could?
I don't know we don't have really any visibility.
We're not we don't have any GPU visibility right now.
There's there's tools we can use to like visualize what the GPU is
doing and when so we don't know very much about what's going on right
now, but we do know that we're at least nominally having our
architecture work properly in that, it's going to allow the driver to
overlap those downloads.
If the card can do it, which is what we wanted.
So, that's
Okay.
So here is our game, right?
And our game, of course, is now runs.
Kind of a little bit.
Ridiculously smoothly on Hardware, certainly, I guess what that means
at the moment.
Are we done with our Hardware acceleration?
I think we might be.
I mean that pretty much handles everything.
We now have full asset streaming through the graphics, hardware, and
all of our Sprites are rendered through the opengl path.
Now, everything sorted correctly like we're pretty much good to go.
I don't know, I think we might be.
So yeah.
Is that if that, I guess that might be it, there was one of the thing
that we kind of wanted to do.
Which is to set s RGB mode on the frame buffer and we didn't really
have a chance to do that.
So since I think that just kind of is it, I don't think there's
anything else that we actually needed to do.
I got 30 minutes left so I don't know what else to do.
I mean I was planning on debugging the textures this whole time, but
it turns out there was nothing to the bug.
All right.
Well, that was an unexpected gift from the gods of programming instead
of bringing us a lump of coal.
They yeah.
Well all right you know what I'm gonna say anything about it.
Who knows don't know why that happened?
That's not how Graphics programming ever goes when you're working on
Graphics drivers but I guess it just because well no it's a
multi-threaded texture download it's really not that simple.
Actually I don't know.
I don't know how that ended up working all
so,
Just want to mention something to make it.
Absolutely clear what's going on here as well because there's a very
important thing that's underlying.
What's going on that you may not be aware of that.
You probably should be aware of.
And what that is is that if you look at how we're doing our texture
downloads,
We're doing the texture.
Download from a separate thread.
Right?
And so, inside handmade asset dot CPP.
You know that the actual texture download is happening right here and
this is a threaded function.
So the worker thread, those low priority worker threads are actually,
what's doing the download.
Now when that happens, what that means is there is no synchronization
between the this part of the code.
This part that's actually doing the finalized asset, there's no
synchronization.
Between Matt and the rendering, okay?
As far as opengl is concerned.
Meaning as far as opengl is concerned when we are submitting that
texture, that is a totally separate thing from when we're doing our
drawing.
So it will not attempt to serialize those operations for us at all.
Okay, what that means is that there's nothing preventing the opengl
from trying to render with a texture.
That is
Not yet finished downloading.
So that can happen.
In other words, if let's say we start a texture download and we don't
finish by the time we actually need it.
So it's like the cutscene.
We don't quite get it loaded and sent to the GL in time.
So we loaded up, we started sending and it hasn't transferred in time
and then we actually get to the frame where we need it and we issue
the render command.
If those were on the same thread, meaning, if we were only using a
single threaded opengl opengl would wait, and it wouldn't render until
it finish downloading the texture.
Since we are multi-threaded and have two separate context only
operations on opengl which are in the same context are serialized.
So it doesn't feel any particular need to serialize the download of
that, texture with its use in the other thread.
I think.
I don't really remember this.
What the specification says, it might be allowed to serialize them.
Meaning it could decide to do that, but it's not required to do that.
What that means is that we may just draw garbage on the screen,
essentially, if the texture hasn't gotten there in time,
I would prefer to leave it that way and just try to make it so that
our code is always enough ahead that we don't get ourselves in a
situation where we're rendering something.
We haven't loaded because the only thing that we could do in that
situation really is either render the wrong thing.
Like, try to substitute some other bitmap in which is going to be
wrong or pause the frame creating a hiccup, right?
Wait till the actual thing goes and neither of those.
Those are good, right?
What we want to do is always run at 60.
60 frames a second.
Always have no load screens and always have the right bitmaps.
So that's our goal.
And if we have to give up one of those, I think I would rather just
have it not draw anything.
Like the drawing is just garbage or missing or old data, whatever have
a little glitch.
I think I'd rather have a little glitch, then a frame rate hiccup.
Like I'd rather someone sees a little glitch then stutter because it's
if an action game, I want it to always be 64 as I do.
I want that kitchen there now.
Really we don't want anything, so our goal, the whole time is going to
make it so that it's incredibly rare that we ever Miss forecast, so
badly that we can't pull those things in.
In time.
So, our goal is never have any of those things happen.
But if we had to give one up, I don't think I want it fenced.
I would rather still hit 60 hertz and just have a drawing bug.
Then have no drawing bug and drop to 30 or 15 frames a second for that
little period where it had to wait to catch up, right?
That's just my opinion.
And you know, if you want to make a different decision, I'm not trying
to tell you.
That's the right way to go.
I'm trying to tell you that you have to pick one.
You have to pick some way to fail.
And so when you're going to pick that way to fail, pick the one that
you want, but understand what the trade-offs are and what's actually
happening there, right?
If we wanted to design a more sophisticated system, we could do
something where we try to swap in other assets, that are closer to
what it is to minimize the amount of the graphical glitch, but it's
just a bunch of work and you still don't really quite fix the problem.
So unless you really do, I mean, a good example of this would be
Be rage like ID software is Rage.
I mean, that's an example of a system that tries to use lower detail
textures when it hasn't page in the text, you need people still
thought it was super glitchy, right?
So you know the degree to which you can really ever solve.
The problem is is unclear, if that makes sense.
So really our best bet is just going to be like, hey, let's always try
to be really out in front with the streaming and the prediction and,
and try to make sure that we're just always on time.
So we just never have that problem.
And also you know, it makes Gamers feel good be like yeah you got to
have an SSD to play this.
You have got to have a sweet gaming rig to play this game, man.
You're going to get, you're going to get graphic glitches.
If you have a hard drive, hard drives like to to Old School, although
this machine has a hard drives but that's beside the point.
Anyway, point being that's pretty much all I wanted to do with the
texture streaming and maybe we'll revisit some of it later if there's
anything else you want to do.
But I that's basically it.
So I think the only thing that we're not doing now is we're not
Don't actually have srgb support on the frame buffer.
We are enabling srgb rights to the frame buffer back in here
somewhere.
I don't remember where
Yeah.
I don't actually know where that is but I know that we were somewhere.
Maybe it's over here.
Let's see.
I don't care about any that code that is not.
We're talking about this is what we're talking about.
So this right here, this GL and able g l frame, buffer, srgb.
Tells the GL to do those operations like we were doing in our software
rasterizer.
I hope you all remember this, the whole reason we did the software
rasterizer, if you remember because I didn't think it was gonna be
fast enough to run the game, but turns out it was probably but with
some point was to learn about gravity our stuff.
So if you remember we wrote the software rasterizer.
Remember there's two places where we did like gamma correction which
is the srgb thing.
One place was in the textures, so we read out of the texture, we
convert the textures, srgb to linear light by performing that mapping
on load.
So we load in the texture, convert it from srgb to linear, but the
other place we did, it was the frame buffer.
So, when we were loading a frame buffer pixel to blend with a pixel
that were drawing.
We also had to convert that from srgb to linear.
Now the degree to
Which that matters is like almost none because it's really only for
super translucent things that were even going to know or just like
around the edges of things where there's like the alpha values.
Right?
Because normally we don't actually see what was in the frame buffer
because things stack up on top of each other and we only see the last
one.
And that last one was coming from a texture read.
But if it happened to be transparent or it happens to be right around
the edges, then we are seeing a little bit of
What's underneath and that blend operation is wrong if we don't gamma
correct.
The thing we pull in again very, very subtle.
No one will ever know.
But it's a good sort of technique to kind of understand.
Because in the future, if you know, you're someone who follows
handmade hero and your goal is to do a 3D engine one day.
A lot of the stuff we do in.
Handmade here are kind of translates over but you kind of have to do a
much more complicated Graphics layer, right?
Um, that that that technique of knowing when gamma correction has to
be applied, becomes much more important when you're trying to do
things like multiple light passes that have to combine with each other
properly, things like that.
And for all we know we might add in some.
Let when we do a little more with lighting, we may add in some things
that also have that that characteristic.
And at that point again, it becomes a little more important.
So what we want to do here is try to figure out a way to tell
tell opengl that, hey, I
We enabled frame buffer rights here.
If the frame buffer is in Sr is is an srgb frame buffer.
Unfortunately we have not yet told it that the frame buffer that we're
drawing to on the window.
Should be srgb.
Okay, now you might ask, why are there two separate enables for this
thing?
And the reason is because open just a little wonky, this way, opengl
tends to set State on both the objects that exist in the system and
the system itself.
So basically what happens is, if you have a texture, there's typically
two ways you can set how that texture is sampled one way is on the
texture.
And another way is in the actual like blood, like in the actual
shading code, right?
Or the actual shading setup and those two things typically combined to
produce how something is actually sampled.
Now, in our case, it may seem odd for the frame buffer to have two
ways of setting it one on the frame.
For itself.
And one in the GL, it's sort of shading enables.
But the reason for that is in opengl, you can create multiple frame
buffers.
Like we could create back buffers to draw to that we use as
Temporaries or something like this.
Write it as part of a more complicated render pass where we might
render multiple passes and then recombine them or something like that
into the final image.
And so what they wanted to do with opengl design is make it.
So you could set some of those frame buffers as are srgb and some of
them as linear and then when you bound a frame buffer to draw too,
If GL frame before srgb, rendering is on, then if the frame buffer is
srgb, will use that if it's not it won't, right?
And so it allows you to kind of mix and match.
I don't care for that design.
I don't think it's good but that's what it is.
And it's not like a totally stupid design.
If there is a logic behind it, it's just not what I would have done.
So anyway, so that's why we have to enable it in two different places.
We have to enable it once to say hey do srgb, be blending.
If you
Happened to see an srgb frame buffer and then the other side is we
actually have to get that srgb frame buffer so that when it looks at
the frame buffer that we happen to be using and it says oh I mean
that's RGB mode is this something I should use srgb on?
It actually goes, yes it is.
So that's what we want to do here.
Now in a perfect world, all we would have to do is right here with PFD
support opengl or PFD type srgb, A or something, we be able to just
set srgb and be done.
That would be
eight.
Unfortunately, not going to happen.
What actually happened is all of the stuff that you might want to do
to frame buffers that happened after opengl.
One point x in wiggle, was actually implemented as an extended version
of this whole choose pixel format.
Like, you know, this whole thing
This thing where we do the choose pixel, describe pixel steps weren't
that stuff.
Actually got extended versions and it's in those extended versions,
were all of this takes place.
So what we need to do is go look at yet another extended situation
here.
So here's we will choose pixel format ARB.
For example, this sport format.
Sorry this extension provides the functions that actually allow us to
use any of the more modern features of
Of a back.
Buffer, a frame back buffer.
So you can kind of see that it's basically just a whole nother
specification that specifies almost literally exactly the same
functions but now with like some additional sort of stuff in them,
right?
So this is what we would have to implement to do that.
And what you can see here is we have, for example,
This get pixel format and choose pixel format, those are basically
analogous to these things that we're doing here.
So the, the choose pixel format will replace this call with the
extended choose pixel format.
And then we've got this describe pixel format and we would replace
that call with the describe physical format one, right?
So hopefully that makes some sense you know, hopefully that that makes
them some reasonable sense to you.
All right?
So that's what we actually need to do.
And as far as I know, I guess.
I'm not sure.
Let's take a look here.
I don't think.
Yeah, I don't I don't actually know if we ever actually have to
replace set pixel format I think we can just still use the same call
to set pixel format.
I think it's only the choose and describe that are the ones that we
actually have to replace I believe because set pixel format still just
takes an integer and I think it just takes the integer that comes back
from one of these.
So when we call
When we call these functions, I think it's still just works.
So let's take a look at what it says here and we'll see, doodoo will
uses pixel form Inc.'s, refer to pixel formats Centre.
Pixel format function, is described as towards Bob, La Follette types,
of formats, using piss-poor description, layer table and just a set of
functions may be used to Korean spices for My Tattoos, by name
grateful, for my attributes, find two functions can be used and and
here they are right?
So then we can do our what attributes we want and they can be done by
name.
I think that's what we need.
So, I think that's what we should do now, granted, I may be wrong
about this.
You may not have to go this whole route, but I'm pretty sure you do
choose to before it will never s of formats from either group 2 or 4
2, x 0, plus 1, star displayable, which have sent attributes.
Let's see.
We don't care about any of that stuff.
I don't think.
Yeah.
So, that's what we need to do.
So let's do it.
So here's our functions.
We have, we will get pixel format at Rib.
Well, there's two of them, there's two different kinds, right?
If you look at the actual functions here, they basically gave us two
pixel format things.
And there's F&I and so, there's float, right?
And there's n t, if that makes sense.
I'm not sure what we would need float for.
It seems a little bit crazy but yeah, we've got a.
Let's see if this actually has the srgb stuff that we need, let's see
pixel type ARB.
So wiggle pixel type ARB is probably what we actually need there.
Right?
Let's see here.
Wiggle wiggle.
We're just a big old pixel type actually know where it is.
Type herb.
There it is.
So that's not quite it, that's not necessarily be.
So this doesn't look like it actually has the one we want to me.
I mean it should have unless we it well unless it just uses a
standard.
It might just use a standard identifier from different part of the
spec and still be in here so that I don't actually know that I'm not
sure about.
So let's actually take a look here.
Let's take a look.
So this I don't think well there you go.
Accepted by the atrabilious parameter of Jill, excuse visible and she
likes, get config.
That's the X version and accepted by the pi attributes parameter of
will get pixel format, a trip IV, EXT and wiggle, get picked.
So those are that would suggest that we do call those and just you
also in addition to that one have to have our frame buffer srgb
available in order to
Actually do this, right?
So we actually need this wiggle frame before srgb capable ARB, and we
need to pass that into
To the function, we did it.
So I believe that is the that's the whole thing that will have to do.
Unfortunately, and so let's just give it a shot, let's just see.
So here is our functions that were actually going to need, and I'm
going to go ahead up and end up.
Put those into our opengl.
Let's see here.
Handmade.
And here are our.
We go calls.
So we've got type 2 pool and we've got wiggle.
Get pixel format.
That's one heck of a name.
Ivy ARB
And that is that function got one of these guys.
And last but not least.
There we go.
So that's
The functions were actually going to need oops forgot to win API and
that guy for wiggle.
And we have to get all of those the same way we got.
We got these guys, right?
I don't know.
Why is that the trip?
TS is that supposed to be a tea?
I don't think it would be.
Do you attribute ESR?
That seems wrong?
Where is that defined?
By the way, is that to find it in win32, handmade?
For an opengl.
I don't know where that's defined.
Just you see what I'm talking about.
We're gonna create oh it's right there.
Duh.
Yes, I think that's just a typo.
That's just a bad type of.
So here's our other wiggle guys.
So I'm going to go ahead and get those guys in here.
So Global variable wiggle, get pixel.
Format at Rib IV ARB.
We're go.
Get pixel format rib IV ARB we've got Global variable, wiggled, get
pixel format at Rib, fer
Pixel format rib, FB ARB.
And finally, we're gonna choose pixel format ARB.
And all of those folks need to get loaded as extensions.
So when we do a wiggle, get proc address right here.
And we load those guys in we then are going to want to do sort of that
that elevated that elevated querying, right?
So I guess actually no that's not true.
We kind of have to do that really way back at the beginning, right?
Because we need to actually do that before we do the pixel format
choosing stuff.
So in theory, I think we would have to do it here.
Like we'd have to do it right?
Right away.
And I see.
Goes to some extent.
We don't need this big Global actually, right?
Because we're only going to ever use them.
Like we don't actually need these to be to remain around because we're
only going to actually use them just at one time during their during
that, that process.
So I think and I'm not quite certain about that.
But I believe we, since these are wiggle calls, we should be able to
get them even though we don't have a context yet, right?
At least that's my guest, don't quote me on that, but that's what I
think.
So I'm going to first see whether we can get any of these.
Ins and if we can, then I think we're good to go if we can't then you
know what you going to do.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Okay.
We go.
And so each of these is literally just going to be exactly the same as
what we did before which is just to say that this is just going to be
a wiggle.
Get crock address and we just pass it.
The name of the thing that we're trying to get, right?
So it's exactly the same as this thing down here, right?
Exactly.
They're all, they're all just that same exact thing.
So we go get proc address and it'll get
So let's just see if that's at all.
Correct.
It's like, that's why wasn't this indented did?
I accidentally leave something open?
I don't think so.
I think I may have confused for a coder.
Did I or maybe not?
Maybe I actually maybe I've got something that wasn't supposed to be
there.
So 561.
Nope, looks like that was fine was just that think we changed.
So let's go into win32 in it, open GL there and let's see what what I
guess we could do here is we can now know if we got all of these
yeah, I think for coder is now confused indentation wise
Think don't quote me on that.
I know Alan was working on the lexer today, so I assume that means
that the lexer is far from from ready to go.
So it's surprising actually that we had, we don't hit we don't really
hit much in the way of bugs with it yet which I guess it's great.
But anyway, so if we get all these guys then we know that we're good
to go.
I think
And we should be able to actually make this thing.
Do you know what we need to do?
So
Is the code that actually check to see if we can get, these will use
the path where we call set, pixel format sort of the old school way,
and then I guess it will do.
Here is just say, oh, let's see here.
Yeah, so what we can do is say, well, we're going to call set pixel
format either way.
So we'll just have two.
Branches will have one which is going to use the old format because
hey if it doesn't support srgb, rented, the frame buffer.
We don't really care like it's only a Minor error to not have that.
So we don't want to like cause the whole game to like not be able to
run just because like that thing wasn't found seems like a poor
choice.
So
We should probably still make it work.
Right?
So what I'd like to do is say, okay, if we do have the extended
versions,
Then we'll use them if we don't end the extended versions, then forget
it, just just don't worry about it.
Use the old way.
And so when we have, I guess describe pixel format, we can also call
that back in actually remained as well, right?
So, it's literally just
This part here, I think.
so if we did this, where we just said, okay,
Here's one path.
And then now we've got another path which will also do.
You know the hole?
Pixel format selecting thing, but it will do it the other way.
Let's see if we can make that work.
So I'm going to try calling.
I think we want wiggle, get format, a trip.
Ivr.
I don't understand why there's a float in an inversion.
I because you need to pass all the parameters to one of the versions.
So I kind of probably need to look at the Docks little bit on that
figure, what's going on there because I'll be honest, that doesn't
make a lot of sense to me.
And if it doesn't make a lot of sense to me intuitively, that usually
means, unless the spec is somehow broken that, I just don't
understand.
The point, right?
I'm like missing.
I'm like I'm thinking it's working one way, but actually it's not
working that way.
And so that usually is a bad thing.
But for now let's just go ahead and actually see if we can do the
basic implementation of it.
So here's truth.
Pixel format and we have the corresponding call to to Circle for down
here.
We were passing this pixel format as a struct with a bunch of stuff in
it and now we're going to do is we're passing it as like a list of
parameters essentially, right?
Oh, I see what this actually is.
This is just querying.
What they would be set to.
So we really only need this one.
Okay.
So these are not, all right, never mind.
These are not necessary at all.
That was just, that's why there's two versions because those are just
the query calls.
This is the only one
Actually need.
Okay, so we don't need that.
That's that's good.
That makes sense.
That wasn't.
That was bugging me a little bit there.
I was like, what is happening?
Okay, so if we do, we choose pixel format are what we need to do is we
painted past the DC.
Now we know what the DC is this, the same DC where were using before,
just that window to see we now have an enlist and afloat list, right?
So we have an input attribute list and afloat at Rib list and then
we've got like, Max formats
It's and how many formats we want out.
Which I believe is just sort of saying like, hey it's going to chew.
It's going to give us back as many pixel formats I guess as as are
necessary here that makes sense as matched.
And I don't know that what we would do.
I don't know how we would distinguish between them.
Meaning, I don't know, I assume we just take the first one or
something, right?
Because we don't have any other criteria to judge these.
We just know.
We want one that follows the criteria that we have.
So I assume that's the
Thing to do but I don't really know.
So Pi attributes is this set of things which are all things that we
might want to specify.
So let's just take a look at them.
So we have number of pixel formats.
We don't really care about that draw to window.
Does need to be there, right?
So we're going to need that.
I assume that's the GL true.
True.
It just is true.
I assume feel true but I don't really know.
We will draw to bitmap.
We don't care about that will acceleration with pissarro supported by
the driver.
It's the set to no acceleration.
That only software under supports.
This pixel format generic, a certain format is supported by MC driver
isn't set to full acceleration by an ICD driver.
Obviously we want an ICD driver, right?
And an ICD driver.
And then CD driver is like a subordinate driver that runs through the
Windows driver and an ICD driver is one that actually is a complete
implementation of opengl which is all we would really be interested
in.
We don't need a pallet, we don't need system palette.
Swap player, buffers truth mr.
Format supports, swapping layer, planes independently of the main
planes.
I don't really know what that means.
Layer planes.
I'm not sure.
I'm not sure if we need that or not, that's very ambiguous.
Well let's see what else it says.
Wiggle swap method are up if the pixel format supports a back buffer,
then this indicates how they are swapped.
If it's actually set to swap exchange our than swapping exchange the
front and back buffer contents.
If it is such a real swap, copy ARB, then swapping copies, the back,
buffer contest.
The front buffer, if it is set to wiggle swap, undefined arms in the
back over, connoisseur, copy the front buffer, the back, buffer,
connoisseur, undefined
The operation.
So we don't really care about any of those.
I don't think we don't care.
Laughs as long as it does overlays we don't care about under those.
Don't care about transparent.
We don't care about it.
All share depth.
We don't care about any of these things.
You don't care about sharing death.
Don't care about the stencil, you don't care how the accumulation we
don't share about GDI a drawing.
We do need opengl
Right.
That's obviously true groups and we also need double buffer.
Because we do want to be able to draw to the back bumper.
While we're seeing the front buffer, we've got stereo.
We don't care about that pixel type, we do care about we don't want
color index.
Obviously, we want to do full RGB rendering so we're going to want
that.
Wiggle color B, the number of color B planes for srgb is the size of
the color buffer, excluding the alphabet planes.
So in this case, that is going to be 24, right?
Number of red B planes.
Well, I mean, this is, I don't even know why were bothering with this.
But, okay.
So, red bits and I assume you want to specify all of these guys.
Do we actually care about this though?
You know, do we don't care about any of this.
Like, we don't care that it how many bits of color there are to be
honest.
I mean, if it wanted to give us a 16-bit back buffer, fine, we don't
care.
If it's or is it a more Precision?
So do we actually need?
I'm going to say we could just skip those.
We don't care about depth is we don't care about something, but you
don't care about this.
I think that's literally all we care about.
That's it, right?
I think that's all there is.
So let's read this thing.
And see what it says.
So let's see.
Wiggle cheese, pizza format.
So, so list of attributes have like type value pairs containing
integer or followed by a corresponding, the, this determinate, with a
zero.
So all we have to do in here is just say, like, okay, here's our
integer list, right?
Here's our NT NT, a Tribble list,
And here they all are right.
Each individual pair, we get down to the bottom.
We stick a 0 in there for a terminator, and that's all there is to it.
So there's our in touch with list, and then we come down here, and we
say, like, mx4 mx4 mats.
So list of attributes of, I was participating.
Floating-point, the floating Point values, I don't know where those
are, what those are?
I don't, is there a floating point.
I didn't see anything.
We care about, that's floating point.
So I'm just going to assume that the float trip list is actually
nothing.
Although actually, I guess we have to do
zero Terminator, right?
Because if that's all that, it knows if we don't send it an array
count, it's got to go.
It's a zero.
So if we do, we will choose pixel format ARB, we've got Max formats
play formats and I'm formats.
We got to find out what those things are.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So in choose pixel format are when we have n Max formats, the maximum
pixel formats to be returned.
Pfr us went through an array of return, indices, the match piece of
quartz, the best pixel formats are the head of the list.
The caller must look at this array num for us was the number of
matching funds, all right?
So basically what we want to do is say look we can't tell the
difference between special for us.
Anyway we just don't know.
So we only want one, right?
And then we want to to say essentially that suggested pixel format
index is actually going to be the one.
The place to put it, it's the only one, right?
And then the count is just that some ignored thing that we don't even
care about right?
Like so although I guess we could say count or like, we could do, we
could do this, you could say extended pick equal 0 and then here we
could say extended picks.
So if it found one that will be set to 1,
And then what we can do and this seems like a good idea what we could
do here is say, Okay, if that extended pick equals 0, then we know
that this code path failed.
So, just fall back and try the old one, right?
So, that way, we'll always actually do the other one as well.
So, now let's see whether we can get this working at all and probably
all we actually need to do.
I think is
Is defined, you know, copy these constants over and then we should be
good to go.
What is this complaining about me about something will choose?
One cannot convert.
I'm going to six from into UNT.
Oh well, excuse me.
So what we're saying is this is actually a you end or Jill.
You inte is that we're saying that is what we're saying.
So all we really need to do is make sure we can Define all these guys
and so that's just something again that can be put placed in here.
Because it's just an extension.
It's an open G extension, and we just need to know what those
constants actually are.
And they should be defined in here.
I would think.
Yep.
Looks like they are and so we had draw to window.
So we got, in fact, I guess we could just copy this whole thing.
Well not really.
So let's go ahead and and just paste that in there.
Draw two window we had
Double buffer, right?
Support opengl
Both of those guys are in there.
We got pixel type.
In there and think, is that it?
I think that might have been it.
Let's see.
Draw the window acceleration.
I get that.
Yeah.
Acceleration.
So we had brought a window acceleration support opengl double buffer
and pixel type, right?
And so now we just need the actual settings and those are this guy
which is the pixel type, you actually used and the full acceleration
ARB
Okay, so there's guys are both there.
And I'm over time here so I gotta wrap it up.
I gotta wrap it up folks.
We didn't really, we didn't really start late today.
We started on time today.
Okay, so there's the, you know, the stuff we actually need.
So now if we go into the, the code here and and and win32 in it opengl
If I step into that code to see what's going on, I should be able to
see whether we actually are able to get a that function in the first
place.
And it looks like we're not.
So, we don't even we can't even get that function.
So now, my only question is can we not get that function simply
because we haven't created an elevated context because I don't know
what the rules for that are so like if we go in here and we do create
context at Rib like so I'm curious if now, we jump back.
Mike is here.
We've created that that fancy conducts.
If I jump back what I get it now and I don't know.
So let's find out.
So I'm gonna do a set next statement and then I'm going to run to it
and hey, that totally worked.
So now I'm not sure
what to make of that, right?
If I have to call wiggle make current
In order to get that function, but we're gonna make current requires
me to set the pixel format of my DC first, which I thought it.
Did you see the Dilemma there?
Let's see what actually happens here.
By the way, though.
So
Extended pick use 24.
I said the max was one.
I guess that's how many there would have been.
Well anyway.
Whatever.
So point being
I'm not exactly sure, that's a subtlety that I'm not sure about, it's
pretty clear that we need to actually have wiggle configured up at
least, to a certain extent before we can call that wiggle.
Get proc address.
Now, I don't actually know to what extent, we need that to happen and
so maybe there's a limited amount of start-up.
We could do.
That would make
At work.
Let's let's do another test here.
Oops, it's not what I wanted to do at all.
So let's, let's hop in here.
Let's go ahead and let this dude, do its thing.
I'm just going to have it do just create context, so there's just an
opengl context that exists, right?
And I'm going to call Nick Hern on it.
So now, we're not using extended context, we're just using the regular
context and now I'm going to jump back up here and force it to try
that call again and see what happens.
Okay?
So it just needs opengl to have been started at all.
It does not need to have been elevated.
It needs to have been started.
So we can't call wiggle.
Get praa dos.
Which I guess I sort of knew that's why I structured this code this
way.
So I guess I knew that you had to, at least have it set up first.
But the problem is now, I just don't see.
Do we re pick?
Can we reset the pixel format.
Does that work?
Like can you call set pixel format another time?
Because that's a bit of a mystery to me.
So what I would say is, let's go ahead and break for today because
we're out of time and let's come back to this tomorrow, because that's
an interesting conundrum.
I don't actually know or if I did know, I forgot how we would make
this
Do what it needs to do, right?
And for what it's worth, I don't actually ever do what we're doing
right now.
Which is why I don't know, because I actually usually render to a
separate buffer and have to do like a separate sort of resolve pass to
draw to the actual buffer, the front buffer, which means you don't
need srgb on that buffer.
So yeah, so I actually don't know.
So this will be interesting for me too so I'm just going to put it to
do here and be like this needs to happen after we create the initial
opengl context.
But how do we do that given that the DC needs to be in the correct
format first, do we just wiggle make current
Back to zero and then reset the pixel format or what.
And so that'll just be, you know, obviously that, you know, there's
some defined way in which, you know, you're supposed to like, oh yeah,
just create the contacts and unset it and then reset it, and it's fine
or whatever.
But I don't know what the magic incantation is and so we'll have to
figure that out.
All right, so let's go ahead and break for now and we got time for
questions so let's take questions.
UNIF.
And don't you have a race condition according to the C11 and C++ 11
memory models?
When you set the texture handle from the worker thread and read it on
the rendering thread.
Without any synchronization, I think you need to use an atomic
operation.
Are the compiler could mess up the generated code?
How would it?
I don't understand how it could possibly mess up the generated code.
Yeah, I mean no I don't think so that that doesn't sound right to me
at all.
Now granted the C11 C++ 11, memory models.
Are God knows like they're complete nightmare, right?
They're the ones that have all the weird undefined behaviors and so,
technically, none of handmade hero would run, right?
Because we do all sorts of stuff like sub, allocating out of ranges of
memory, which the switch see, doesn't even let you do it.
All right.
And and all that stuff is just ridiculous nonsense that I don't pay
attention to.
So, in that sense, maybe there is something, but in the sense of like
could any actual reasonable compiler, that we would ever actually use
legitimately generate wrong code here because it doesn't know what
we're trying to do.
I don't I don't think there's any possible way.
but,
Q4 Caleb.
Why don't you render directly to the back buffer at Molly?
The reason is because you have to do like typically you'll end up with
something like a, an example would be lets say that you have, you
know, two
You've got like, well I'll give you extremely simple example.
Let's say, you're you want to support rendering at a lower resolution
than the screen.
In case, the user's computer is too slow to render at their full
resolution and that's really common, right?
Because maybe the users monitor is, you know, super high res, it's
like a 4k monitor or something but they're gravis card isn't even
close to being able to actually render the game at 4K.
Just it's not a powerful enough graphics card for that.
Then oftentimes, if you don't want to set the resolution differently,
what you can do is you can just render to a back buffer, that's like
1920 by 1080 or some regular HD resolution.
And then you have a final pass that scales that up to the actual size
of their monitor, right?
Obviously, it's not as good as rendering the actual home monitor, but
they're gravatar isn't good enough for that.
So that's never an option.
So you got to do something and this is better than sex.
The resolution because at least it doesn't run the whole thing of
like, oh it messes up the icons on their desktop or does all the other
weird things, right?
Windows is real bad setting resolutions.
So at that point, you know, there's a pass that just copies from one
buffer to another with some limited upscaler.
Something that never reads from the actual back buffer, right?
And so, it's not that you don't render to the back, but are you always
actually do end up drawing to the back part of the question is whether
you have a readout of the back buffer?
Because the only time the srgb flag actually does anything is if you
actually read out of the back buffer, right?
So, you know, well that's not actually true.
if you ever read out of the back, buffer,
And use that you need srgb.
Or if you ever write to the back buffer out of a Shader that is in
linear light space, you would need the srg, right?
But if all you're doing is copying from something.
That's already an srgb to the back buffer, which is in srgb, you never
need to Mark the back buffer as srgb because no translation has to
take place, right?
So, yeah, so that's one thing you can do.
Now, to be honest, when I, when I'm thinking about this, I feel like
it might be that Molly.
We might still want it like now that I'm gonna know how to do this,
but I've never actually tried doing this before because I've never
tried saying the bankrupt srgb if it works relatively.
Well, I might do it at Molly anyway, because technically
If you set srgb on the street, if you were doing a stretch and you
said Archie, Archie be it should be more accurate.
The stretching should look nicer in theory because the bilinear blend
would be done in a more accurate space.
so,
You know.
Broken up code FYI?
No you can't change.
Pixel format.
What's been set?
You need to create a temp window and contacts get the wiggle.
Our function pointers then destroy Cox and we don't create a new
window and connects with Michael are very annoying, but that's how it
works on Windows far.
As I know, it wouldn't surprise me if that's the whole answer, right?
I mean that's the kind of thing.
Like I said, Microsoft doesn't support opengl.
they would rather you use DirectX so they don't do anything to make it
easy on you and so the driver vendors have to do kind of to kind of go
around their backs and that sounds like the kind of thing the driver
probably like probably the driver doesn't get loaded until someone
creates a context so you can't call, we will create context and so
Don't have any other way to do it, you know.
But that's okay because we can create a dummy window and we can do
that.
That's not hard.
So we'll try that tomorrow and go from there.
Will we be back to the debug code and finish it up after this?
Or have you finished it?
Now you know we'll be back on the debug code as soon as we're done
with this probably or I don't know if there's anything else we have to
do.
Probably not really.
Cooper, Caleb, thanks for ruining the in-depth explanation.
We be going over modern Geo later.
Probably not, I'm not sure.
We might probably, we might do some shaders, because we probably will
need them for lighting.
so we're probably do some shaders, we will probably never do vertex
buffer stuff because that we don't need
and it's rather than be absurd, but
Set it for cues.
On topic use.
I mean,
Cuz I ain't seen no more cues.
That look on topic.
Apparently, in DirectX, 12, you can select a separate context for
different gpus.
Yeah.
I mean,
I don't actually know.
To what extent you could do that in DirectX 11 as well.
Like I don't program DirectX.
So I only know an opengl, you can't do it in Vulcan that you can at
least you could the last time I saw it long ago and so directx12.
Presumably you can as well because they're not that different, but I
don't know.
And like I said, I didn't know if direct II figured maybe DirectX 11,
would let you do would already have let you do that, but I guess it's
not true.
Just 25.
Where did you up before?
A crowd of videos, I'm not upload the fur coat of yours.
I just have them on this machine and I'm waiting for Alan to tell me
where he wants me to put them, or what he wants me to do with them.
But they'll they're saved.
I just haven't put them up anywhere yet.
Do you censor my guest?
You 3D 11 to.
Yeah, so that's why I figured I was like I figured d3d would have let
you do that for a while because Microsoft wants you to use that and
has you no control over the platform.
So I figured they would have done that eventually.
I don't know what version of DirectX added it but
Couldn't you use a pb0 for streaming in textures?
A pixel buffer object.
I mean, I guess you could, I'm not sure why like what the goal
necessarily would be with that.
I mean I don't I don't know that there's any real benefit to using one
thing or another.
I mean, one thing you can do if you want to avoid the possibility of
any fragmentation is.
You can also just allocate like a couple large textures and pack your
textures into them and you just use instead of calling text image 2D
like we are we call text sub image, 2D and pick out a smaller area.
But I don't know that.
There's any real reason why you would do any particular thing until
you had some strong opinion about what your game like that.
Your game was having some problem doing it.
One of the other ways, right?
Like, I don't know that you would really, I don't know why you would
switch to a pixel buffer object for any particular reason.
Or what you thought you were getting from.
That that make sense.
Alright, let's wrap it up, folks.
Let us wrap it up.
All right, everybody.
Thank you for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, we are now doing background downloads or textures, which is
pretty great, which pretty much wraps up anything.
We really need to do with opengl.
Maybe we want to load shaders because like I said, I think we're
probably gonna need those for lighting.
I mean, I'm not certain, but I suspect because we'll probably want
some effects that are just good with, you wouldn't want to do them
without a Shader.
So we might want to load shaders at some point.
But other than that, I think we're pretty much everything that we
really need out of opengl.
We pretty much got it ready?
And like I said, it's pretty nice because now we actually can just
toggle a Boolean and render through either our software under or in
jail, so we kind of have the best of both worlds.
We can have suffer enduring if we're
Want to play around with it and we can have Harbor, rendering if we
want to get the speed of the graphics card involved every everyone
wins.
So, tomorrow, we'll take a look at that srgb thing.
And we'll try doing the maybe like a dummy window, like someone
suggesting because that might be our only way of actually making that
work.
So, we'll do that tomorrow and we'll get that working.
And then I think we can sort of move on to finishing our debug layer
and just tidying up.
Anything that we need to do before we just do gameplay programming
because it feels like it's a good time to start that and I had said I
want to do that somewhere around a 200.
And so we're right about day 250.
It seems like we're you know we're a little over but that's fine with
me.
But I think it's probably a good time to transition over that because
we've made most of the stuff we need.
We don't really need to belabor most of the point.
We can kind of kind of start doing gameplay coding.
Sometimes, you might think.
So, we'll do that.
If you'd like to do that, we'll be doing that tomorrow.
Come back and check it out.
And you can see this sort of as the wrap up of this this wave of
opengl coding.
As always, if you want to follow along at home, you can if you
preorder the game on handmade here at org comes with a saw.
This code.
So you can follow along every day.
So if you want to learn from it, that's a cool thing to do.
We also have Forum site.
You can go to ask questions if you want to, you know, sort of work on
the series sort of off stream and have questions about it.
That's a great place to go.
We also have a patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, we have a tweetbot, the
tweets, the schedule you.
And if you want more information on the editor that we use on stream,
it is actually written by someone who is a handmade here.
Our viewer, mr.
Fourth dimension on the chat on Webster.
You can go to his patreon page and you can
And get your own copy three tiers.
There's a one dollar per month, tier of $5 per month to attend our
month of here.
One dollar month is the editor to $5 a month includes programmability
and C so you can make your own basically completely customized version
and $10 a month.
Gets you like Community contribute like basically like I send him my
config file that I use and less Fu.
And and if you do the ten dollar or two, are you get that all that
code as part of it as well?
So it's pretty great.
Check it out and support a good.
Project.
Highly recommend it.
It's coming along pretty nicely, that's about it tomorrow.
We'll be back here at 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time.
Hope see here, finish up our opengl and have a little party, until
then take it.
Easy.
Have fun programming and I'll see you guys on the internet.
So long, everybody.