Here.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could a complete game live on stream.
I believe we had last Friday, we did some stuff where we wanted to be
able to edit some, some debug values.
And we had a little bit of work to do to make that happen.
Essentially what needed to occur.
There was the debug values needed to be when an if an edit was going
to occur that edit needed to be stored as something
In the debug system that could then be picked up later by the debug
output code when it sort of sweeps through, you know?
And knows when it can can actually overwrite debug values.
So I'm going to go ahead and get started on that today is day 252.
So if you're following along at home, you want to unpack day 251
source code and that is what I am starting with today.
I'm going to open up for a coder here and load our project.
Let's go ahead and do that, handmade prj.
And I do wonder, I don't actually know if it would work for me to not
include the total paths here, because I suppose it might be nice for
people.
Not have to have the total path but I'm not sure.
Yeah, maybe someday we'll make it relative project files relative once
I have some time to maybe play around with the for coder thing and
ensure that that actually works because I don't know exactly how
weird, you know, treating those internally.
So anyway, where we were with with the debug stuff before was we had
it listing here
And we can go in and we can see everything getting filed properly,
including are non-existent profile window that we want to re-enable.
And we have a bunch of stuff here that we can click on as well.
But all of these things are not actually editable at the moment.
So you know, if we go to click on them, nothing actually happens.
They don't highlight even though we have code in there to do stuff
like that.
And so the problem is, if we were to actually edit these values, the
values themselves need to get set somehow.
And right now, we have
No way to actually do that.
So because the debug values exist in the debug system, sort of as
copies of the data that was written out in some frame at some point.
But that doesn't tell the debug system where it would actually go to
write individual values if it wanted to change one.
So what we need to do if we want this to work is when someone edits a
value we have to let them, you know, edit the value.
But once they edit the value, we need to just store the fact that it
was at
added and then later on when someone comes through and actually does
an operation to Output that same value again, it wants to be able to
get back at that point, a change that it can apply.
So that's really what we're looking to do here and that's a little bit
complicated, right?
Because essentially what has to happen is there's a grid here that
these things are sort of hashed by right.
What we have to do is look up using the grid and see whether or not
the value that we're looking for, is what we, you know, has an edit
pending on it and so I sort of you can see that I started to do that
here that I just put it to do in there.
I basically just made a piece of code that sort of says, well, you
know, we're going to have to call the debug system and we're going to
have to say if you wanted to
Edit it now would be a good time to edit it.
You can see the debug candle value.
Edit piece of code here is passing the address of that value and so by
passing the address of that value, that is what allows us to, you
know, actually right into it at the very moment when it's actually
being outputted so it will log what the value was and then it will
give the debug system a chance to overwrite it.
Now I don't know that we
Actually want to do specifically what I've written here.
And the only reason I say that is because, well, you know, the debug
system at this point, may may not want to have a ton of different
calls into it to edit every different possible value.
It may just want to do something like return a union, right?
Which, you know, has the different values in it that we can copy over.
So you know, one way we could tackle this instead would be something
like, okay, maybe there's just
One call which is like, you know, debug get updated event and that
takes this debug name that we've got here, which I think I could
probably also sort of consider locally.
Like, I could do something like this where I say like name and then I
grab the name so that we can use that a little more clearly, right.
So there's the this is like the debug would basically.
In fact, I suppose I should just call it with you bug, quit, because
that's what it really actually is.
So if I have the debug grid, I can go in here and I can say record the
debug event with that grid and then also like I can use that grid to
say, please look up, what the actual value is and if you get one back
then I could use it.
So maybe what I would say here is, you know, debug event star updated
event.
Equals that.
So I've grabbed it and then I can say, if updated event, then I want
to overwrite the existing event with the new event, right?
So I want to say something like, you know event, I don't know if we
have a way to do the entire data block.
So probably
How would that work?
Exactly.
So it would probably be something like this, we'd say get updated
event.
You know what?
I guess I really don't have to do that.
I could just do it this way.
I could just say, like, debug edit event and I just passed the event
that I was that I was using and that is actually just since it doesn't
have to take different kinds of things.
That would actually be fine, it'll take the event and it can write
into it as necessary.
So, I think it back, that's really not necessary that you can still
use.
Just one entry point.
This entry point doesn't have to be specialized on, which type of
value or editing, it can just take the event.
And
Internal to that, it can do whatever it needs to do.
So, that actually should be fine.
And that way it knows which one we're talking about.
And then, it has the actual event itself.
I prep, presumably would want to pass a pointer to the event which is,
I think what event already is.
So I think that's really all.
I probably need now.
That entry point needs to be defined somewhere in the debug system,
and I don't really know the include order for the debug system at this
point.
So you may have to put a function prototype for this in here because
unlike everything else, which is just streaming out.
And, you know, remember all of our debug stuff is made to just stream
out into a buffer, which then gets looked at, by the debug system,
after the fact, this, because it has to happen right at this time.
Because that's the only time when this value may even be valid, right?
Yeah, at that point we sort of need the ability to to handle it, you
know what?
We still do need one more thing, right?
We still do need the ability to copy back out of the appropriate Union
portion here, because we're going to have this value and this value
needs to actually get set still.
So we still do, I think we really do need to do this but we can do it
externally, right?
And then there's it, can we don't have to add up your points or
output.
Where are going to have to do, basically this exact same thing.
I think.
I don't really see any other way to do it.
Right.
So, mmm.
Just trying to think of the most efficient way to do it.
You see what has to happen here, right?
We after we record the value of the event, which is right here and
that's writing directly into the debug buffer.
We then want to have some way of setting the event to a new value and
that includes needing to pass it back to the program which means that
whatever this value actually was, whatever type of variable it was, we
need to be able to write a line of code that looks like this.
Or something, right?
Where?
This is the correct.
Did I put things either sauce, makes very difficult for no real
reason.
And so the only real way to do that as far as I know, you know, is to
basically sort of overload the to make another set of overloaded
function that does the setting, right?
That does something like debug, you know, value set or, you know, get
event data or something like this where we then say like,
Okay, we've got the event and then we're going to pass the address of
the value.
Something like this, you know?
And that way it can we can have one of those that writes back to it.
And it's just a lot of meaningless typing for no real reason but yeah,
that's kind of what you have to do.
So if we did something like that, then we would do, you know, it would
just be, like, okay, whatever the events, oops.
Whatever the events value was.
That's what this thing is going to take, right?
So yeah, I feel like that's annoying but only a little bit, right?
Because it's really just a series of these things here that sort of
bust out the values.
We actually need.
Oops, that's not what I meant to do at all.
I want to cut and paste this.
So if I did that set event value, I can then do it for whatever these
guys are.
Let's go ahead and change that.
You 32 to V2 and same thing here.
And clear.
And here.
Not sure why that one didn't replace properly.
What happened there?
I'm kind of curious what happened there.
Because that one worked properly, right?
Replace both instances of the V4 and I must have typed something
stupid.
So let's paste it here.
There's before rectangle too.
Hmm.
G4 rectangle, too.
That's weird.
So that seems like a bug as well.
I'm not sure what the bug actually is because it works most of the
time, but in that particular case, it looks like it doesn't did.
Replace the V4.
But I don't know why.
Right.
Where were place?
In region, doesn't seem to replace all the occurrences.
And the region.
Yeah, not a huge deal.
We can always just do this.
And look around it but it is a little odd.
Don't think I've seen that before.
I'm not sure where why it happened.
And see there.
It just work totally fine.
So it's something very specific.
I'm not sure what.
And there were sea.
We're totally fine.
So most of the time it just works.
Maybe I've got confused and type something weird.
I'm not sure that had happens but hey, we've got a video of it so I
can go back and look, which is, I guess, the best way to do bug
Repose.
We actually can reproduce bugs with for coder, 100% accurately because
I can watch exactly what I did on the stream.
So I don't have to give one of those bug reports.
It's like, I don't know.
I was using the thing and some things have
Bend and then broke which is always fun for people to get on the other
end of the SEC support where they're like, okay thanks for that,
that's great, I'll get right on that.
So I think that would work.
At least I assume it would do not know why that didn't give me an
error because I should not have been able to compile something with
debug edit event in their life.
That did we turn off?
He couldn't have turned off.
Yeah, that doesn't make any sense.
We could not have turned it off because we wouldn't be seeing it.
So we know that we are still running with handmade internal and that
is definitely true just looking at it right there.
So why aren't we getting a debug edit event?
Link error.
Did I like already Define that function in some kind of weird?
Like, premonition thing that happened?
No I didn't.
So what's going on?
Do I want to know?
ah,
handmade debug interface at H1.
There's two of these.
So maybe this is what the bug was.
Is there something weird about is there?
Some thing confusing about the fact that
Is two buffers suppose I kill one.
It killed both of them.
So they were both viewing the same buffer.
Let's load it back in.
And it's got that one on it again.
And it looks like so.
So, yeah, that just like, it doesn't seem to want to actually let me
edit this buffer, but I have no idea why.
I'm very confused right now because like now the buffer is gone.
If I do this, I can switch to it and now I've got another one I guess.
but,
Yeah, I'm not sure I guess because I hit Z, I must have hit Z instead
of B and then it loaded the same buffer twice.
I don't know.
No idea.
I mean, this is just kind of what you would expect.
This is The Growing Pains of, you know, and editor, that's an alpha
that's in pre pre Alpha state.
So you know,
That is certainly to be expected.
But to say the least, I have absolutely no idea what exactly was going
on there.
So, yeah, but I don't actually think it's too much of a problem
because again, I think all we really need to do is just do this, which
is not particularly hard and it should work.
So, let's just do one of these, right?
Looks like that.
And before I spend the time actually making the other ones, I want to
make sure I can actually save and build the file and all that stuff.
So when I called,
Value now and I do record debug event and I do set value event data.
Now, in here, I want to be able to, to, you know, that that creates
the event.
I want to be able to do something where I do, debug value, get event
data and I'm going to pass the address of the value there and the
event.
Like so now I can't even just do it, just like that and not actually
have the edit take place at all.
So we'll just start with that, get rid of this, get rid of that, and
And, of course, in here, it would do the same thing.
It would then just do a star value, or rather value equals event value
be 32, right?
Again, those those literally don't do anything.
They just reassign the value back, but so I can just make sure that
this is working at all.
So there we go.
Okay, so can't convert and that's great.
That's exactly what we want.
It basically said like hey you don't have ones for the type that you
were just talking about.
So I think that's good I think that so
So, that must have been the problem I guess was that I just had
multiple buffers.
So bug, we're opening the same buffer produces like, or
The same buffer with open file leads to a confusing situation where
you don't know what your editing or something I've no idea.
So that's certainly not something you would ever want to have actually
happen like in order to get in the situation that I got in where you
might because you could totally lose a lot of work that way, right?
So we need some way of making sure that that never happens if you open
a file that's already open you.
I'd have to take Extraordinary Measures to get a second copy of that
file in memory because then when you save them, you're going to,
they're going to overwrite each other, right?
So I definitely need to, like, protect against that, which maybe I
could do it my own thing, but that's probably best protected inside
for a coder directly because I think in general people would never
want that to happen unless they explicitly asked for it in some very
like, you know, very like
Dramatic confirmation oriented way that.
That could go wrong accidentally.
You can also see if this still happens.
The edit thing the where it wasn't replacing when I got to rectangle
too if that still happens.
So weird.
That's so weird.
So that is still a bug.
I don't know what that is bug.
We're placing.
It's like only that V4 with rectangle to only replaces some instances
that's just super strange.
I'm really curious what that one is.
It must have something to do with what the, what the string is are.
I guess.
Because it only happens in that one circumstance, like we've never
seen it before.
It's very reliable because we just did it.
Exactly again in a totally different edits scenario.
and,
Then everything else works, right?
That's so bizarre.
That must be a very, very interesting, like little corner case, or
something.
Oops, it's not font ID.
Font ID.
Alright now, let's compile.
So what are we missing?
Here, we are missing trying to show entity type star.
Entity type star.
Oh, is it having trouble converting that to something that it knows
how to edit?
Why was it not having trouble converting at the other way?
Oh, because it's an address of.
So we probably need to do something.
You know, where this is actually getting used in a different way I
guess.
Yeah, that one's a little problematic because the entity type is going
to be an enum and so if you want to pass it, it will be able to
convert itself.
Yeah.
So that's a little tricky.
Does that mean, does that perhaps mean that these should be a, well
that wouldn't help because making it a reference.
I don't think C++ is any smarter about how that works with making it a
reference?
Yeah, I'm not sure how I would work around that really
I don't have a lot of I don't have a lot of good ideas for that.
I mean short of actually making one for entity type.
Let's see here compilation.
And when 3D renders those are just.
Those are basically like enum problems if that makes sense.
And I don't know any real way to get around that because the problem
is while it's fine, when I call debug value this way round, I can't
really pass address here.
So well.
You know, I suppose I could do something more like this.
Then it would sort of bug me about the cast though.
So it's still wouldn't quite help, right?
Because it wouldn't allow me to to take like a u-32 return type, for
example, and and change it to a value.
So I don't know how exactly I would get that to work.
I mean, I guess we could do something like this which is absolutely
absurd, but
You know, C++ is kind of absolutely absurd.
That's the kind of language it is.
So I suppose you could do something like this where you were like,
hey,
I'm going to pass you the value, and then a past few, the destination
like, this is basically ignored, right?
And then I would just say like, oh, okay, well it trust me, it's an
R32.
So like just actually write it that way, that's hilarious.
Hilarious.
Oops, not.
Do you do that?
Or rather it would be hilarious if it weren't for the fact that it's
so depressing.
But yeah, I can do that, right?
So I can just come in here and say like okay you know, ignored ignored
Nord.
Ignored Nord.
And that would do it, right?
So, all right.
I guess I'll go with that.
Why not?
So this guy needs to actually have the right cast though.
So let me stick that in there quickly.
And it compiled first to make sure it works.
Okay illegal and Direction yet so that looks fine.
So should be good.
That's a v 2 Star.
This is V 3 star.
This is a V4 star.
And my rectangle 2 Star, a rectangle, 2 Star is Born.
Ladies and gentlemen, presenting the rectangle to rectangle, 3 and
bitmap ID.
And sound, idat.
All right, so now we can get and set debug data, so that's fine.
And so really all we would have to do in the middle of those two.
Things is now insert the call that I was talking about before which
is, like debug edit event data and that just gives you know, that
would pass whatever that debug name is.
So we've got the quid and it would take that event and say go ahead.
And if you want to update the event, update it before I rewrite this
value.
That's really all I'm talking about.
So the same thing would happen here with the Boolean situation.
Debug name, pound value, and that's good.
And then, right here before we do,
That one we would do the same thing.
So now these code paths are the same.
So I think that's really, oops, that's not good.
So I think that's all we really need and we just need debug edit event
data to now actually exist.
Which is the part we need to write inside debug dot CPP.
And so that's going to be the one that's like does the hash situation?
So when we where, is that guy?
It's in here somewhere.
Not quite there yet.
No, no, no.
So here's store event, its get element.
It's like it's get element from it.
That's the one I'm looking for that one.
So get element from event is actually
The part that I need.
So when it does the like name parse, right?
And it produces that hash value.
That's actually the part that I need, which also kind of means at that
point to we can, if we want to just restore just the hash value,
right?
We could, we could hash the grid ahead of time and just write the hash
value in now.
I guess, well, we need to do the matching.
I guess what I should say is we could have we could write the pointer
to the debug element, and if we needed to now because we're already
doing that work on the first, on the, you know, on the
Through it.
So yeah.
Because you can kind of see that.
That's it's we're going to have to do this work when we set, Because,
unless we do that work will have no way of actually knowing if this,
you know, if this thing was edited.
And so once we've actually done that work by looking at the grid,
It seems silly to do it a second time anybody system, but yeah.
So anyway if we want to do that, that's kind of annoying.
But again, this is just for debug output values.
It's not for profiling, we don't ever have to actually take a hit for
any profiling base code.
So presumably it's fine to do it to put these debug values in here
because we can always turn them off if we don't want to have them.
So for example, the debug data block stuff, could if we wanted to just
turn off and then we wouldn't have that problem, right?
We wouldn't
It wouldn't.
The debug data block could say like I just don't want to record any of
these values and that's something that we could actually probably make
happen.
Yeah.
So anyway I'm a little nervous about that you know it's a little bit
nerve-racking and it does make me wonder if maybe you know storing the
pointer just storing the pointer to write to would be something to do
if we did that though, we can't ever pick these things up again and
that's kind of unfortunate.
In it, and we also couldn't do anything like having the data block
control it.
So
it's really tough to say.
Because we could just decide that the only values we can edit our ones
that can provide stable pointers, which would be fine for the kinds
that we're trying to edit right now, which are just like Boolean
values that you toggle on and off because those Boolean values aren't
going to disappear.
Whereas, if we want to edit these, we need some way of actually
accessing these specifically.
And in order to do that, I don't actually know.
Yeah, I don't actually know any other way that we could do.
So I think we will have to do that.
So let's just try it I guess.
And then we'll see.
We'll see if we have any problems with it, in terms of like speed wise
or anything like that.
Since we're calling it for a small number of things, I suppose we
don't have to be too worried, but it always just makes me a little bit
nervous because I would rather have the debug system.
Just right.
Things to a buffer and forget about them.
I don't really like I don't like the idea of it doing like a ton of
work, right?
I don't like the idea that's going to sit there and do
You know, a bunch of bunch of work, so, alright, let's take a look.
That would just be debugged edit, event data, and debug edit event
data.
It's going to take the Grid in.
It's going to take the debug event in and what it would do is it would
say, well you know I want to do the exact same thing I was doing here.
So I want to get the parsed name out and then I want to look up, you
know this this piece I guess.
Is to make it easier there.
I could probably just take this part out, in fact, this could just be
something that expands in line.
This would be the debug element where
This code here if you actually already have a hash index.
Like so.
You can do just this part here.
Oops, so yeah.
If you pass in the index,
directly and I suppose, you could even just pass in the hash value and
assume that you know when you know
Everyone's going to probably just get it from parsed name.
So you're going to pass in the hash value that you already gotten,
then it will go ahead and map it into the hash
it'll try to find it and if it finds it, it'll return it
So that is that.
And this would just take first name, hash value.
All right, so this guy can do the same thing now which is good.
And if it gets something back, then it can go from there.
Now, it needs a way to get the debug State out.
And so that's like a thing that only sometimes actually exists, right?
Because you may be in a situation where it hasn't really started up
yet.
So we need to call this thing with the global with the global debug
memory.
So right.
Oops, quite want to go that far.
So it's this one right here and this may not actually
In a debug state.
So we don't want to like assume
We can get.
One of those.
We just want to see if we can get one of those.
Like so, so, yeah.
But you can see.
Hopefully, you can see why I'm worried about this like this is a
really expensive operation, right?
I have to find the debug State first, which is not too much, but then
I have to go through and like parsa name out and like match it with
the hash value.
I could, you know, make something that's faster than get the hash
value.
But regardless of even, no matter what I do going through that,
You know, series of things is going to take awhile that hatch, getting
that hash value.
And then I've got a match it against other strings to make sure that
I've got the right one.
That's just really, really expensive and so it, take it makes it
moves, debug value from something that we could probably call with
fairly Reckless, abandon to something that is actually relatively
concerning and I don't love that.
So it does sort of suggests to me that it's not maybe the best thing
in the world, but I don't really know much we could do other than
Say you've got a store the pointer into the event, and then it'll try
to edit it, and if it's not there anymore, you'll crash or who knows
what you'll do.
Which is also not fabulous.
So, I don't know.
It's kind of one of those situations where I'm not sure.
There's all that much.
You could do to improve it again.
If you've got metaprogramming, then all this goes away because you
just write permanent values in there that you could just hard, hard
index directly, like, we almost had, but the counters, but, of course,
we couldn't quite do that because it was sort of
This really janky.
It was really very janky especially when you have more than one
translation unit but what do you do, you do the best you can and C++
it's always a little bit of a try to do the least bad solution because
the good solution is never actually available to you.
So if we go ahead here and do debug event data and we get a result
back then at that point we can do a relatively cheap operation.
So once we've done all that heavy work, then it's actually not so bad
but unfortunately we just
Getting up to that point where we actually know the value.
That's, that's the difficult part.
So if we have an actual debug element, then we can store whatever we
want in here.
So we can store for example, just some very simple Boolean, something
like you know, value was edited.
Oops.
Something like that where we just look and say, oh okay if the value
is edited, then I'm going to actually replace the contents of the
debug event that I was given with like the most recent debug event
that I saw.
Because that's the one that I actually want, you know, that that's
what I actually want to.
To have happen.
So that would be something like okay, if there's not a result, I mean,
if I got a result, I'd say if the value is edited, then this event
that I've been passed in, just overwrite it with whatever the most
recent event was.
And I also know, I can assert here that the most recent event is an
actual valid value.
Because, you know, if somebody set value was edited there, had better,
have been a most recent event
You edit I guess.
Another thing I could do is if we just want to be extra safe in the
case of like, when things are getting cleaned up or something I could
also do this.
And say, okay, you know, if the if there if you say the value is that
it there also has to be a most recent event when there is a most
recent event.
Then off we go either way we've observed the edit now so I'm just
going to say that that clears out any anybody who was going to look
for this event.
Again, should not get a second edit.
We only want to edit like one value, right?
We don't the next time through, we don't want to re-edit the value.
So I
Leave.
We want it to remain roughly like this.
Now, this has to actually exist this call has to exist in the debug
interface, so before we call it, obviously we need to announce it like
so.
And let's see here.
What is this?
That is the quid.
So we need to pass that.
obviously, so that's going to just be
Prevent weird.
And in this case, the same go.
That's not quite correct.
I admit that because I believe that's a stored event, which means that
this is actually going to be that
Illegal indirection also true.
I don't deny it and then in here where we do the element hash.
Hmm.
Okay so I do actually need to do this outside of get element.
So the hash value this part right here, I suppose would be nice if it
was computed outside.
Mmm.
So it's not actually done twice, if that's the case you would need to
do it in two different places, right?
We need to do it here and here and then this would passion the index
like so which I could have suppose.
I suppose parse name could also do that but I don't know whether I
want.
Do that or not.
So I'm going to say that this actually passes the index indirectly now
like so and we'll leave it like that.
So this is just parsed name.
Cash value and same here.
Oops.
Can't see where that is.
But I can guess.
Declared but not defined.
Hmm.
Okay, so that is a true.
Actually, I believe you because there's going to be a call from that
from the
There's going to be a call from that from the platform layer.
Right, which is also not great.
You can see why that happens, right?
Anybody inside handmade dot CPP can call this just fine, but anyone
who's in the platform layer can't because it's inside the dll.
So, the platform layer, if it wants to announce a debug value, which
we wanted to do, it can write to the buffers just fine, but it has no
way of actually invoking that call, so it can invoke that call if it
actually has the game loaded, but it can't evoke the call.
If it doesn't have the game loaded.
Now again not really a huge
Deal because it's possible for us to patch through that.
But again, it's just another thing that I really don't like about the
way.
This is unfolding, I don't know.
I don't know how else I would make that system.
Operate anymore.
Yes, I do.
That was a lie.
I was about to say there.
I think I do know how this would work.
Okay.
Are you ready for this?
Because this is ridiculous.
so, if I am editing a value,
Then one thing I do generally know, is the debug system only really
has to edit one value at a time, probably forever.
But even if we did want to edit more than one value, it wouldn't be
ridiculous for us to then just only edit one of those four frames got
to do five.
We takes five frames to edit the five debug values.
But in general, we're only edit ever interacting with one value.
You know, we go up on the thing and we like slide values around or
something like that.
We're only ever editing one value.
that means is, we could instead just have
One place where the debug system basically, latches and says, here, is
the event that's getting overwritten and then it never has to actually
look at the hash value where the elements are any of those things
never has to spend any time.
Hashing never has to do anything, it can just look to see if the two
pointers for the guids match because we know that doesn't have to.
The edit doesn't have to survive across a dll Reload.
So that's not a problem because you're only editing on the same frame
that you're actually on.
And so, we could just say forget about this entirely, right?
Does not matter.
Okay, that's gone.
We go back here and we say, okay, in the debug interface code,
when we're actually going to do, debug edit event data instead we
don't really call anything at all right, we never actually call it
instead.
We would just do
I guess we could almost just use debug value set event data just by
itself, right?
We could just do, we could just say that it looks like that.
Okay.
so, if we did this,
If we did this.
We would be able to get rid of all these.
So now we only have one, we only have one of these happening, right?
So essentially it would look like this.
This is so crazy, but I kind of like it.
So, we'd be calling debug value set event data and it would be passing
in something like this, right?
It would be like value and, or source and desk, something like that.
So, we would say, like, okay, we're going to set the value to the
source value, and then we're going to set the the vout the the depth
value.
Whatever comes back here, right?
so I think what we do here is we say, okay
We know, we want to set the event type and then we want to do an if
statement to see whether or not we've been edited, if we have been
edited, we do this.
If we haven't been edited, we do this, right?
So either we
The Source into the event that we have or we get the dust out of the
other event, one, or the other.
Seems relatively straightforward.
In fact, I think we can clean this up even further.
So all we need is some Global pointer.
That is the global debug value.
And then we can always just pull that out of the system, fairly
trivially.
It still means that we do have to negotiate one pointer with the
platform layer, but I think that's it.
And then this becomes almost free again like it was before.
So what we would do right here is we'd say debug Global edit event or
something.
Like
We'd say if the global, if the debug Global edit events grid equals
this event squid, just the pointers, no string.
So we just a one single comparison, then we know that we're being
edited and so we would take whatever the value is, that's in that
event, that corresponds to what type we are, and we'd write it back to
our destination.
That's it, right?
And then at that point, we could also just equivalently do the reverse
and say, okay.
At that point afterwards, we always write back, let's say what the
value is.
So maybe this, this thing doesn't even get used anymore.
This is just like the type Handler, that's just an automatic type
thing and I guess we could leave it as ignored, it's just to figure
out the type and this is this is the actual value.
What do you think of that?
I feel like it's crazy town but it seems like it's better than all the
other stuff.
Right.
So now we just have just one if, and we have complete editing
capabilities after that, to edit all the values without actually ever
having to store a pointer to them.
So they can be transient values.
If they need to be, meaning they can be in inside like a simulation
entity where you've unpacked something and you're doing stuff to it,
it can pick up an edit even directly into that, which is something
that doesn't even exist.
By the time, the debug system runs later on and is processing the user
interface which seems kind of cool.
So if we were to do that, this would be the new format for everything.
We would have to have one of these for each.
But I think that's all we would really actually need
I don't see a lot of downsides to that, that seems really good to me.
I like that.
And I also think that presumably, I feel like since the only
difference here is the type parameter, I feel like and I'm not sure
why we didn't do this originally.
I feel like it would be relatively easy here to just do, you know,
Some kind of thing that was like a macro, right?
That just said, like, what's the type.
And then this whole thing is actually just macro eyes.
Don that
Right?
So we can just say like alright yeah you know, we've got one of these.
And that's like for R32 and that way we just don't have to type it
like a billion times all the time.
And there really aren't that many places we even need to know, right?
So they're pretty straightforward, something like that.
And so that means then we can just say like okay there's you know how
many however, many there are of these.
You can just put them in here, so we know we've got and I guess I can
just say your face up here, whatever they are, right?
There's be 32 R32, you 30?
Yesterday to V2 although I guess I don't know if I can actually do be
32 that one might have to be special case because it's the Boolean
one.
So there's that good man tidy that one might complain and we'll take a
look at that in a second and then all this stuff just goes away.
Oops, not quite that much.
Yeah.
So
There we go.
So, debug Global edit event is just like, you know, and extern here,
debug Global edit event.
And let's see and I suppose in some sense maybe we can't really make
this a non pointer, you know.
Ideally it wouldn't be a pointer, it would just be an actual one of
these, but I don't think there's really any way to do that, because we
need the pointer to point into the platform layer.
If we didn't have to worry about the platform, they're accessing it
that, in theory, wouldn't have to, but I think that has to be the
case.
So, yeah.
So the b32 one can't actually.
Do its thing, right?
It has to not that esta, not be the case because it's, you know, it's
it's a problem.
All right.
So debug edit, event data.
Wait, we need to clean up what the actual macros calling now, it's
debug value, set event data there is no edit event data anymore.
So this is
Diva value set event data.
That's exactly what this one has to call as well.
So this has to call debug values set event data and presumably that
could just be done with an R32 dummy, right?
So like are 32, I like that, right?
Or I guess maybe just an s32 dummy.
Something like
That and that would work.
None of the 11 over, those could all the argument types.
Well, trying to match the list.
Okay.
Well how about that?
Isn't there one of those there should be for Rather.
That should be.
why is there not an S3 to in a void star thought there was
Right.
There should be an S3 to and avoid Star right there.
And in fact, it's listed
Ah I see because we're still passing the wrong thing to it, my bad.
It's actually that.
Yeah, so we don't need to store this grade anymore either.
So this actually I think doesn't have to be here.
This can go back to the way.
It was where it's only ever done this way and that's good.
Same here.
I like that.
Yeah.
So this since this set, if we actually call this, this will actually
overwrite the type field though, which is kind of annoying.
So, I feel like this also has to be done, like, sort of, in that
order, if that makes sense.
And
So I think that probably has to look like that.
We'll take a look though.
So, there we go.
Now that I think that actually yeah, that was kind of crazy.
I hadn't really thought of that before.
It's a bit weird, but I think it's relatively reasonable.
So if we now Define this thing,
We can Define it to point to something inside the debug system.
So, in handmade debug, that's a groupie.
We can have this value.
I don't know if we actually Define any other debug things here.
I don't, I think we used to, but I think we kind of got rid of them
all, didn't we?
So there's not really
It's all just part of.
Debug State now I think but I could be wrong about that.
No, it's not.
So here we go.
This thing here has to get defined and weary be doing exactly the same
thing that we did before, where we say, like okay, there's a debug
event and this is the global edit event underscore and this is going
to be equal to the global global edit.
Event underscore, so that would be the way we would initialize that.
So everything there is fine.
And then, the only problem is our win32 subsystem doesn't have a way
of getting that, and you can see that.
It's exactly analogous to the global debug table situation.
That's the exact same thing.
So, since that already exists on the other side, I wonder, could I
just make that I wonder if I can just sort of piggyback on top of
that?
You will.
So, for example, inside the interface layer, since I know, I'm already
handling that debug table.
If I take a look at the debug table definition,
what I could do is say well, I've got all this gigantic array of
events.
Anyway, why don't I just have at the top debug event, like, you know,
edit event, something like that.
Because then I wouldn't even need to worry about treating it any
differently.
It can just, you know, it can just live at the top of that thing
because Global debug table Arrow.
The event is actually.
Now the thing that I need so that seems pretty compelling actually.
I like that a lot.
So I think that's what I actually want.
So instead of debug Global edit event, I think I would just do this.
Right.
And so it's a little pointer Chasey but it's okay because getting the
grid out of it after that it's a hard reference it's not actually
following a pointer at that point right this is a DOT and this is a
DOT so it's really just that one jump still so it's not doesn't seem
problematic and then I wouldn't have to worry because the global debug
table is always handled everywhere.
So that's pretty satisfying.
I like that a lot.
Now, if I run in theory, nothing should get edited.
Because right now, none of those values are being placed at all.
And so now I think
We're in good shape, right?
Because now all we have to do is set that event.
And when we set that event, the edit will occur.
So, for example, if we now go in here, to handmade debug dot CPP, how
much time?
I got three minutes.
Okay, if I go in here and actually set an edit event, then let's see
here.
Where do we actually do that?
Auto.
Modify.
So automata five variable, I can't see it because it's behind my head.
Maybe I should switch over here to pee.
Auto modify.
What a modified variable automata 5 variables.
So here we go.
So we got like toggle value.
So let's just assume that taco value is currently nerfed.
Yeah, so this toggles, the actual value inside the event itself.
So I think all we have to do, I'm don't quote me on this but I think
all we have to do at this point to edit it.
Then is we would say like, Global debug table edit event equals event.
And if we just copy that in,
I think it would work well.
So not there's one caveat and that is we need to preserve the original
string pointer if that makes sense.
And so yeah that's that's the only last thing we have to do which is
pretty easy for us to do, but we were intentionally not using that
anywhere else in the debug system, so that everything else would work
properly.
So yeah, we do need to do, you know Global debug table edit events
that hmm.
excuse me, you know, dot which equals some preserved version of the
actual
of the of the actual
grid here.
So yeah, not sure the best way to do that.
You can see what I'm talking about, right?
So the debug system just using the pointer its original pointer that
it was using.
So in here where we store these events, the debug event which is this
thing.
Look, it's written to the log.
It has this squid here and we want to make sure that we preserve that
grid so that it can be used for checking if that makes sense.
But there's no way for us to use that here because we've replaced it
with our own string.
That's a copy, so that, if the dll gets reloaded in between times,
when, you know, at some point during the, the run the grid is still
valid, it still points to reasonable data.
But when we do
Do the edit event here, we need some way of restoring what that value
is.
And so, inside the debug system itself, we would probably need inside
the element to keep that information.
And so, inside an interaction, we
Try to find a way to keep that value around, right?
And I suppose, the easiest thing to do is inside here we would have
inside debug elements.
We would have like original Grid or something like this, which we
don't even really want to be a cached are like, you know, note can
never be printed or something like this and because we don't know that
it will ever, you know, might have might Point into unloaded.
Or something like that.
So every time we see one of these, we can refresh the debug element
with the latest grid that we saw for that debug element.
So we would know it in here.
And then the question is just, how would we actually get that grid?
And I guess the easiest thing to do here would be to say well, okay, I
mean just get the element from the event that we have because we know
that that should work.
And so if we get that
Element.
From the event which we can always get and then just ask for the
original grid, that should be sufficient.
In theory.
And we'll want to clean this up tomorrow, but just in order to make
that work I think that's okay.
So whenever we process one of these debug events, what we would want
to do is we want to reset that original grid.
Like we always want to be setting that because we always want it to be
set to the latest one that it possibly can be set to.
So like whenever we call ladybug records immediately after doing one
of those queries, right?
Immediately after getting an element we want to always reset the grid
every time.
So every time we do get element from event I guess anyone who does
that oops that function doesn't exist in for a coder yet.
You can't call it Casey.
Okay, so anytime we call get element from event.
Any time we do that, we would want to overwrite the squid.
So we'd want to say like the result original grid equals whatever the
event quit is so that just stores that pointer permanently.
Get element from events.
Are we?
What do we not have that here?
I see, I see.
Yes.
Well, in that case.
I will move it upwards.
Quite a bit upwards, I suppose because we're going to need this for
other things as well.
And then we should also be able to get rid of those IDs and stuff,
right?
I mean,
I feel like we've got redundant systems in here.
Now that we've got a stable grid for things, but let's see.
Maybe that maybe I should not do that.
Maybe I should just put this in here.
So we can call it get from event.
There we go.
And definitely want to remove.
I feel like the debug IDs thing.
There's now just like too many different.
The I don't, those are like vestigial remains from a, you know,
different paths that we did over it and so those should be removed
now, right?
I mean those should not should not be there anymore.
Oops, I copied the wrong one.
That's the one.
I actually wanted.
All right, so I think that's correct now unfortunately.
Yeah, I don't actually know
if we'll be able to quite finish today because I don't think.
Now we have to do the final recovery enabling the editing stuff after
all this time because I believe, although I don't actually know, but I
believe since there are stuff is not highlighted in that listing, that
it never actually tries to do the edit.
I could be wrong about that, but that's just my assumption.
And so, I mean, I'll take a look here and see in the debugger where
we're at.
Because maybe it does, maybe it doesn't, but
I'm not, I'm not super certain about that.
So if we do toggle value,
And we look through here.
I'm going to go ahead and set a breakpoint on that.
And see if we ever actually get there.
Like
Would be this.
So we do actually get here.
So let's take a look at whether this works.
So we have events ab32, it's set to 0.
We have toggled it.
So that's excellent.
Which is what we want.
We then are going to overwrite the the global debug tables edit it.
You know, event that's used for editing.
This thing here, we're going to overwrite it with ourselves so there
it is.
And we've got this grid here and this is the parsed grid which is not
the one we want.
So then we're going to overwrite that
Hopefully I'll do that.
Totally did not overwrite it.
That just did work at all.
So that's our problem.
Probably I'm guessing that I didn't read that properly so this
probably updates the Grid in the event itself.
Does it?
Let's find out.
Yeah, it probably does.
So I think what I probably need to do here is like just snap this car
star
Original grid.
I'm just going to see if that helps me.
Go.
See, why am I not?
That's just bogus.
So I gotta go see why that's happening.
Sorry, I don't think there's gonna be any Q&A today because I just
want to.
I want to have this done and it's almost what I wanted, but it's not
quite there yet.
So I wanted to take a look at get element from event.
And I want to see what actually happens in here.
See, that's what I expect to see, right?
That's what I'm actually.
That's what I want to see.
And so what I want to know is when I come down through here, why am I
not?
Yeah, I don't need to really don't need to see that.
Thank you.
There it is.
So it is setting that original grid the way that I wanted, right?
So, that's good.
But then for some reason, when I actually
Edit the debug element.
That's not what I'm actually getting.
Let's see why, let's see why not value.
We go dude.
So alright.
Oh duh, because this itself will overwrite the quid.
Hmm.
Touche.
Right?
Because now I'm going to actually overwrite that so I need to have get
element from event, not be the person, whoever writes that because I
only want to overwrite it if I actually got it from collation, right?
And get element from event, I guess is happening inside here not, it
doesn't do it for open data blocks and so, it only does does it for
our
For these to hear.
Those are not editable.
So, I guess really at the moment anyway.
Can do something more like this, where we're just going to say, okay,
you know, the original grid equals the event we had for now and then
when we're actually in, kolding, the debug records, this one here,
when we do a store event, the store event is actually the one that
puts it in here.
So the element, you know, original grid equals the event grid now, I
don't know.
if that sufficient or not, but
we'll take a look.
Looks, okay, so let's try one more time.
Am I getting a good Grid or not?
And no, I'm not.
Let's try that one more time.
Well, probably have to
Compiled here.
Alright, run.
And toggle.
So, let's take a look in here.
Let me actually get one of these.
It was not able to find one.
Mmm, because it doesn't know the original value.
Mmm.
Hmm.
This is really not a problem at all.
It's mostly just a well I only have an hour to do stuff and it's
really hard to do something as complicated as this system.
That state, right?
We just need to clean up one more thing and then we're done which is
that?
We now need to be able to track both the, you know, sort of common
name of this thing.
And the sort of the more weird, the more weird version and in order to
figure out which debug element, we're editing, that's a problem.
Now, I suppose the other thing we could do there to is since
During this in the debug element we could just avoid actually looking
it up.
And instead of doing that when we do the interactions, the
interactions could push the element instead, right?
Instead of the event.
But it would be nice to always be able to get back that original grid
value.
I mean that seems like something you would want to do anyway.
So it feels like you want to be able to to do that from the event.
So,
We really just don't want to actually do that rewrite, their, I mean,
that could actually be we may want to just actually have that still
point to the grid.
So instead when we do store event, right of what we were doing before
is we rewrite the grid, to be the event get name and we could just say
like, all right, we're not gonna do that anymore.
We do, we'll do that at print time or some other, you know, some other
thing that's similar to that.
So,
that when we actually go to do one of these and we want to look up the
value, we will actually get the value right, like we do in this case
and
So, yeah.
So
That actually works just fine.
So now we can, actually, we can actually edit these values.
Okay?
we don't actually have editors for non Boolean values, yet I believe,
No.
These are not listed as Boolean, so I can't edit them yet because I
don't know that we actually we haven't done any edits for other sorts
of things.
But, all right, I'm pretty happy with that.
I'm reasonably happy with that.
And so if we actually go change, these other ones that are in fact,
billions to be billions.
which all of these actually are, we're almost all of them are
Then we should be able to edit all of them.
I should think.
Oh dear.
I do not know what that was bad.
It looks like the graphics driver was not particularly happy with our
textures on that particular run.
I suppose that's not surprising, we're still using that kind of way
that we did not determine was actually safe.
So yeah.
All right.
So I'm okay with that.
Oh, I forgot.
I yeah, I forgot about the particle system.
I forgot that it was using the heroes ahead.
And he's fuse that particles that are facing the direction that he's
facing.
Which is even weirder.
All right.
Well, that's fine.
And then in theory, now we can edit all of these things.
If we want to write little editors for them, which is kind of crazy.
So, what happens if we switch the rendering type, so if I go now into
win32, let's see if we can edit from both.
But value.
So these now like pause and that stuff are actually oh but Global
rendering type is not actually a
It's not actually a Boolean so we would actually need a real real.
One of those, we can only switch between the two opengl ones.
If we call it a Boolean, we wouldn't be able to switch to the third
value.
So that's, you know, something we would have to address.
So, for example, we can switch to that which renders through software.
Or switch back?
Yeah, there we go.
So we're getting there.
I guess I should call it because we're already over time, but and I,
we also probably need to fix our srgb.
So that this we don't get the washed out version, when we switch to
software.
But otherwise, I think we're okay.
Google pause seems grumpy though.
I wonder why.
All right.
Well we're getting there but we still got a ways to go.
What do I Global pause is unhappy.
And we got any ideas on that.
Pause I guess we haven't done anything with them out.
So P.
We had a toggle on pee.
Oh, you know what?
One thing that is a little bit odd is really the edit, at the moment
would be sticky.
So we would also want to make sure that every time through we clear
out the debug event.
So whenever we start debugging, like when we do a debug update
basically,
which I assume is just, you know, any time we're in debug start and
well, actually guess it's just the debug frame.
And in here, every time we come through here, we would want to stop
the edit, I believe.
So, you know, whenever we get the global debug table, right?
We would do Global, debug table, edit event,
We'd want to do that because we don't want the edit to like keep
applying.
We wouldn't really hit any bugs with that at the moment, but we don't
know.
So I don't, I don't really know why that was happening.
Everyone else seems to work.
Okay.
But I don't actually know.
Yeah, I don't actually know why.
That one's not.
Okay, but it's definitely not right.
Yeah, because it immediately switches if you set positive, immediately
switches itself off of pause.
And let me see if that actually works.
So it still works if you do just pee, if that's it.
Yeah,
So I don't know, I'm not sure why that is, but we'll have to take a
look at why?
Because that must be, there might be some problem with the edit, which
is we only just got it working.
So that makes sense, but I'm not sure why only the global pause
version would be broken but everyone else would be working correctly.
That's obviously a little bit odd.
So we should take a look at why?
One of the thing trying to think of something was one of the things
that I might want to do well.
I guess we can do everything else that we were going to do tomorrow.
So I think that's fine.
But for the time being, I think maybe I will switch the.
Well, you know, we could do
it would be interesting to see because we haven't switched in a while
if we have full
Autumn has a shinzon.
I wonder it's probably fun to switch between the two renderers, in
that case, right?
So
So it was worth doing, open gel, right?
I mean for our situate because with all the ground chunks, the ground
chunks are really the thing that kill the software renderer because
we're drawing tons of them on top of each other.
We can tease.
They're all in the pink thing at the moment.
Can we turn off the ground chunks?
I think about to we have like outlines recompute unchanged and all
that stuff, but we have don't really have a way to turn off the ground
chunks daily.
Should we should have a way to turn off ground chunks.
I feel like
let's take a look.
Round chunks.
Where are the ground chunks?
There we go.
So when we render these ground chunks, this is the updating for the
ground chunks.
I guess we could say if round
honks on something like that.
You know, you could almost do too well about that.
So, where's the rendering for the ground chunks though?
Where is the rendering?
Because that's just the updating that's fulfilling the ground chunks.
But there's got to be
Somewhere that we render them.
Yeah.
Do we update them after we render them, we do.
Well, that's surprising.
But I guess that's what we do.
Alright, so if this is global ground chunks on, don't know what
happened, here we go.
Indent.
And
we know why the global Alpha I guess.
We cuz we're setting the glove off.
Uh yeah I guess because we set the rule off a
Maybe something like this.
Then we have ground chunk updating.
I'm going to keep all of this inside there.
So if I then made this guy,
you know, chunks on
How is that Hoops?
How is that an Undeclared identifier?
Again.
Alright, so that gets me a lot.
It would seem
If I accidentally hit load file instead of switch buffer I create a
new buffer.
I gotta I should basically just make sure that doesn't happen because
I can do that in my own config just make sure that can never happen.
It's probably a good thing.
All right, so in here.
Yeah, we've got those ground chunks happening.
Then, if if I want to, I should be able to say,
That this is debug value.
Let's run.
and,
you know, I just realized I did not actually put it anywhere.
I need to put it in the old menu so that should be in here.
Presumably right.
Don't know why I keep saying the process cannot access the file
because it's being used by another process permission denied.
So now if I'm here, I can turn them on or I can turn them off, right?
And then, if I come in here, I should be able to say, like, okay, I
want to render in software, so, there we are.
And then I can turn.
Yeah, either on or off.
Good deal.
Alright.
Alright, I'm happy with that, got away.
Go here.
But at least a starting to converge.
I feel like we need to clean out a bunch of like the crafty debug ID
stuff from the system.
Now because if we're just have, if we have a particular grid now that
we know we're using everywhere then we don't need to have like
multiple ways that that can be edited.
So I think that's probably okay.
We don't have time for any Q&A today so we'll have to put if you had
any pressing cues, you can go ahead and queue them up for tomorrow.
Oh, that makes sense.
And we should have a Q&A tomorrow.
So I'm going to go ahead and close this down and go here.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's in Powder Coating with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on Hammer here at or get come to the source code.
You can also go to the forums to ask questions.
You can support us on patreon.
You can go to the Tweet bot which has a schedule that's pretty much
you know.
That's what you should do.
It's all right there.
And also there's this little Live Now button, which if you refresh the
page at any time, it will show you the latest countdown to when we're
live again.
Which will be tomorrow at 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
Hope to see you here for that.
I want to kind of clean up the rest of the debug system.
So I'm anxious to kind of get all of that buttoned up so we don't have
to really think about it anymore and now that we've got edits in I
think we just need to put the profiler back together.
That's the only other feature thing that we need.
Before we can call it, call it quits.
So, that's about it.
I hope you guys have fun programming this evening and I will catch you
guys tomorrow on stream, until then take it easy and have, I guess
I'll see you on the internet.
Take these everyone