Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we could a complete game live on stream.
We are mucking with our camera code and yesterday we cleaned up a
bunch of stuff that I wanted to clean up with camera code, which is
good.
So now I think it's going to be a lot more useful and a lot easier to
work with, but we didn't really get a chance to do some Advance some
more interesting stuff with it.
So today, I think basically what we want to do is
Just get the camera code into well, add basically to the camera code
that we had from yesterday to make it.
Do a bunch of things that we wanted to do for real.
So for example we want to be able to walk from room to room and have
it look nice and we want to be able to potentially scroll inside of
rooms if they're big rooms.
I don't really love that idea necessarily but you know, I want it the
capability to exist at least so that if we do want something like
that.
It will work.
And similarly, we want to be able to do things like have the camera
potentially line up in certain circumstances with where the player is.
If we want to stuff like making going downstairs, work a little bit
nicer or other stuff like that.
So that's the main goal for today.
I just want to basically start adding some real camera code to the
camera system where it's actually going to think about what it should
be looking at and how it should.
Looking at it and that's really about it.
I'm sure it will take at least today to make that work.
So today is today, 378.
So you want day, 377 source, code.
If you we open up the project and just do a quick check of where the
camera is, at the moment, you can see actually that it's working
pretty nicely at the moment in terms of just being able to do the
basic stuff, we wanted it to do but it doesn't do any interpolation or
anything so we're not we're not really at a usable game camera yet so
you can see for
Example, I've got this camera volume and if I start going down the
stairs, you can see it switched to a different perspective there but
it's just jerking around to, you know, whatever random place it is
told to be at any given time, that's all it does.
And similarly it doesn't you know, if this room is large and the view
it doesn't track the hero or anything like that and you know, we don't
have going from room to room or anything.
So although we got the chemical into a nice place in terms of being
easy to specify what's supposed to happen.
In now and it's not so weird with the room apron and all that other
sorts of stuff in terms of like movement of the camera.
We still have to figure out some good ways to put in the logic and
interpolation here.
That will make it nice and easy to use for and make the like visual
effect.
Nice.
We can start off with a pretty simple scenario actually, which is that
if the hero wants to go down the stairs, we already did a kind of a
little cheesy version of that where it just like centers around the
hero when the heroes going down it and then comes back when it's not
we can do much better than this obviously.
So what we would like to do is something where, you know, as the hero
comes here.
If the hero starts to go down the stairs, we would like the camera to
interpolate over to the stairs while he's on the stairs.
And then when he comes off,
Off the stairs, for example, he could it could sort of slowly recenter
to wherever that is going to be.
So maybe that's the center of the room or, you know, whatever it's
going to be.
So I think that would be nice.
That would probably be the best thing to do here and I feel like
there's a couple different ways.
We probably want to make that work one is we have to have the
interpolation code in the other is we probably need to make more of a
structure here that says, where the stairs are versus, where the start
of going down, the stairs are, so we probably want more camera,
control volumes as well.
Just to give the camera a little more information about what we would
like to have happen there.
another thing that might be interesting is like if the player lingers
in an area for a while,
it might be interesting to have the ability to do camera things
they're using.
So like for example,
In this case, maybe if the, if the player comes over here and wants to
look over this Edge, you know, the camera could could kind of come in
there and and look over the edge or something like that.
So there's a bunch of stuff we can do and I guess all I'm saying is
let's go ahead and do it and let's use those things as reasons to
exercise the camera code.
So we know that we've got it into a position where it's going to be
able to do the things that we're going to want to do.
Because we're going to constantly have desires for the camera where we
want it to do specific things as
Get through the game design of the game and we're like, oh, you know,
it'd be nice if the camera will zoom in on this.
It when I said the camera would follow this, you know, Bubba blah.
And we don't want to make it.
We don't want to have it be this huge headache.
Every time we wanted,
Muck with it.
So we want the camera to be a lot more facile and be able to do a lot
of these things easily by adding code to it in a nice simple fashion.
So let's start with AB really simple.
Maybe we'll put a simple proportional derivative controller on it.
I talked about Springs.
We've written Springs couple times before.
Maybe we'll just do something really simple there to get it to get it
going and that way we have an interpolator and we would know that we
always have the ability.
Or the interpolator to be replaced by something better later on if we
need it to be but we still have one in there so we can get
interpolation working in a relatively consistent fashion.
So if I go
/.
I believe this is in the same region.
Kind of have this.
Oops.
Interesting and World change.
Can't we just have in here?
We don't need that anymore.
So here's update camera for entity movement, and you can see here,
what we used to do.
And the reason that we used to have smooth transitions from room to
room was because we actually just put the code for interpolating room
to room, right in here, where we would just go.
Look, where are you?
Let's interpolate, what I'd rather do?
Here again is sort of have the notion of a target for the camera.
And what I want to do is I want to pass in a DT as well.
So this is basically part of the simulation step, right?
So I want to do is have a DT here.
So,
And rough day in the camera friend to movement that we have a certain
amount of time.
We won't update it for.
So, like here, for example, what we do Target P, basically what
happens is we then slap Target P directly into where the camera is,
right?
And we just set the offset directly we set these things directly.
What I want to do instead is I want to have those be explicitly, sort
of targets that the camera is trying to hit.
And then I want the camera to gradually get to them and this is like a
very common thing, right?
It in in sort of games, you often times want to say, like okay, I did
a bunch of reasoning.
Maybe it was really simplistic ifs.
Maybe it was a complicated, a, I don't know.
But then I came up with some Target that I want this thing to go to
and then I don't want it to just snap there, right?
Because it's supposed to be like a thing in the real world.
And so then typically you have some kind of a low lower level
controller there, which could be very sophisticated in its own, right?
Depending on how complex you want the motion to be, or how complex the
activity has to be.
But still basically the same idea that you made a high-level decision
in this case, where the camera supposed to be.
But then you want to go ahead and put something, um, into the lower
level of that.
That's like, don't just immediately have that happen.
Have it happen gradually over time because that's the more consistent
thing that a player would expect to see or that makes the graphics
more pleasant to view whatever.
So if we take a look here,
If I make sort of a Target offset Z and a world position Target P.
Like so then what I can do is say well okay, you know in cure what
I've got is instead of setting the the camera p and the offsets, the
to be things that are going to immediately take effect.
What I'd rather do is set the target position, right?
And the target offset, see
Now, what's interesting about this is, if you look at how this is
going, I really don't need to map these in like that because since
they're set repeatedly, I could just leave them in their own space,
but what?
I kind of want them to be in this.
I kind of want them to be in this permanent structure in case, I don't
want to set them every time.
Like I might eventually set a timer on here that says Don't reset the
target for n frames or something after it's been set, I could do other
things there.
I don't know what they are.
So even though I don't really need to store this at the moment, I'm
going to store it anyway.
Okay.
So now what I want to do is what you'll notice is.
If I set these targets, then what's going to happen in general, is if
we look, I gotta pass the DT here, obviously do.
Can I pull that out into DT?
Okay.
All right.
So if I pull that out, now what's going to happen is we're going to
get no camera movement at all, right.
The camera just going to stay where it was created and not do
anything.
Why?
Because now, all we're doing is, we're just going and specifying in
the Target p and Target offset Z where we would like the camera to be,
but we not have any way of actually moving the camera from one to the
other.
So the next step we have to do is we have to actually make some code
that will attempt to drive the camera from its current location
wherever that is towards
The Target location.
So, in order to do that, what I want to do here is I want to map those
both as if they were sort of around the Simulation Center, right?
I want to basically create two positions and then I'll repack the
cameras information afterwards, right?
So what I want to do is say, all right, there's a, there's a camera.
P and a camera Target P or N?
I guess in this case, since we're only working with the camera, I
could just say a p and a Target P.
I know that, basically, all I need to do to get those in to a local
space is for example, use the Simulation Center which I store.
So what I can do is say, all right, take the camera, Simulation Center
and find out where the camera location is relative to that.
Find out where the target p is relative to that.
Like so,
And now, I have two local frame versions of where the camera is, and
where the camera wants to be.
Now, what I can do is I can move the camera, you know, in that
direction and you know, do that in a consistent rate over time.
Now, let's start with a really, really basic version of that one,
that's not particularly complicated or interesting, but that just gets
the job done so we can see that it's working at all.
So, what I want to do is I want to figure out what the Delta p is.
So I want to figure out where I would have to go.
That's that a very simple equation.
Right?
I'm just going to say, if I wanted to go from P to Target p, i just
subtract B from Target p and that's a vector going from P to Target
be.
That's my Delta B by Delta p.
Then what I want to do is if I wanted to just go there if I want to
set directly to it, right?
And we can even run this first just to make sure it's working.
I could just add that in and that's the same as setting it right?
Because I've just added the difference, says the same as setting it.
So in order to test it, we could do that.
And then I could then I know that I can Muck with that equation and
add less of it over time and be in a good situation.
All right, so let's say I did that, then I would just do map into
chunks face.
I would just do the Simulation Center but here, right.
With the p like so and off, we would go right.
All right, so that would map it back in.
Now I also need that Target offset see or rather the offsets D to be
set somehow.
And I know I have an offset, see in the camera struct and a Target
offset, see in the cameras direct.
So I can load those two in like so and I can do the exact same thing
here.
So if I want to mess with the target, see, I can just say Delta, I'm
sorry offset.
See, I can say Delta offset, C equals Target offsets, the - offset see
and then I can add those as well.
So I can say offsets the
Plus it goes.
Delta offsets it, right?
So now we are in a situation where I'm just, I'm taking the difference
in them.
I'm adding it in and then I'm setting it.
So this should be the same code as before essentially.
Right.
This should, this should give us essentially just cold setting, the
position because all we're doing, is adding the whole difference
together.
What is the problem?
You're, oh, yeah.
Gotta pass those by pointer.
And so now if I run it, I should in theory, get what we had before,
which is that when we go somewhere, and it's supposed to change, it,
just straight up changes, right?
Just like before.
Okay.
So now suppose we want to make that change more gradually.
Well you know that like obviously if I want to do something totally
random, I could just say well you know whatever the time step is or
something you know multiply the time step by it or something like
this, right?
And now we would be adding a fraction of whatever the motion is were
supposed to do.
We're only adding a fraction of it, right?
So now when we come
Come through here.
If I'm going to go down the stairs you can see that it kind of slowly
interpolates at any given time to where we're supposed to go.
In all I'm doing there is saying okay let's just take a portion of
Our, I think we're supposed to go.
And add that in, right?
So if you look at what's going on with that, then the idea here is
that if setting it directly, if setting, Delta P directly or rather,
if adding all of Delta P directly, just moves me instantaneously from
the point to the new point because that's the entire Gap.
Then all I have to do is just create some kind of a rate at which I
could go there and I will get smooth interpolation right now.
The reason that multiplying by tea,
DT works is because this is basically a simplification of a more
complex equation that, you know, just happens to fall out.
What do I mean by this?
Well,
if you think about what's going on here, if you imagine, we've got
again, these points here, here is the target P.
Maybe I'll call this.
P Target and I'll call this P camera.
If we want to figure out the Delta between these two, right?
Obviously we know what the Delta is, the Delta p.
And this case, like I said, is p.t.
minus PC.
That's this Vector here, right?
And that's just the difference between the two.
So we know that if we were going to add PC, Plus Delta p,
We would get PT.
You know, why do we know that?
Well, that's just this equation, right?
That's just if I took this equation and I add PC to this side, I get
this right.
So, it's literally just the equation of this Vector.
So if I want to move along a vector, right?
If I want to move along a vector, we already know what the equations
of motion are four points in space, right?
We've done this before.
We know that the equation for a position at time, T is equal to 1/2,
write the acceleration times, the x squared plus, the velocity times
the time, right?
Plus some constant, which is the location it was at before and that
constant is, you know, P0 write the P at time 0, right.
So we know this equation,
In and what you can see, when you look at this equation, is that this
acceleration and this velocity right?
You could imagine those two as being vectors that are pointing in the
same direction as this Vector.
Like let's say they were both Delta P, right?
Well, if they were both Delta p
And well I should be more specific so if they're both pointing in this
direction, so I'm accelerating potentially in that direction or not,
you know, either way or I have velocity in that direction or not.
Either way, then what this, what is this equation and up?
Like right, will it ends up looking like 1/2?
Delta P times, whatever the scalar acceleration is, right.
So you have to imagine this in fact we could write this as like a
capital A as a vector or something in a capital V and we would just
imagine a, is the length, right?
So the length of the, the acceleration is a, and the length of the
Velocity is V if we want to write it that way, right?
We'd have 1/2, we know this is the, the Direction coming out.
And it's got some length, whatever that length is.
We then know that some, you know, we've got some magnitude here.
Another way I could do this is we could pretend this was unit length,
right?
If we wanted to in fact, I'll go ahead and do that for you.
So, Delta P, right?
Is equal to some length.
Whatever that link magnitude is times itself over its length.
Oops.
Right.
So in other words, if I was to normalize this Vector, if I was to make
it this long, that would be Delta p over
The length of Delta P, right?
And so whatever.
The actual Delta is, is just some scalar times.
That it's some magnitude here times the normalized version of my
Vector, right?
So really, you know, this is not quite the proper way to write it.
You would have to say something more like
Okay, so 1/2 Lambda Delta, p over the length of Delta P, right times.
The acceleration Plus
For the velocity term, same thing.
It's going to be this normalized Vector.
Oops, I'm behind my own head times Delta P right times, whatever the
length of the Velocity is, plus the original
Okay, so that's what we've we would get now, if you look at what
happens when you group these terms, you get something pretty obvious
here, right?
If I group these terms together, they've got this in common.
And so what you would end up with is, you would say well, okay, you
know this this 1/2 a here I can pull out the
The common term, which is this term, right?
Oops.
And then parentheses this, I'd get 1/2 a + V.
Plus p 0.
Right.
Well, what you'll notice about this is that all of this, this whole
thing is just a scalar value, right?
It's just a scalar value.
Oh, and I forgot my teas.
How did I forget?
My teas.
T squared.
T.
Here we go.
I can't believe I dropped.
T, my time, I've dropped my timeout of the equation.
How could I do that?
And it's easy to keep up back in.
There's a tea here to there, right?
All of this is just one giant scalar, right?
And it's proportional to the time step, which you can see here, and
it's proportional to the square of the time, step in the acceleration.
Now, what you'll notice is we don't have any acceleration on this on
this camera.
The camera is a resolved rate, basically, right?
And what happens here,
Here is it's got a constant velocity that turns on and that velocity
is based on how far away the the thing is, if it's far if it gets
close, it moves less as it gets further away.
If it's further away, it moves more quickly, right?
So we don't really have an acceleration here.
We've just got a term, you know, we're not doing any kind of measured
acceleration all we've really got.
Is something that looks like this.
But instead of actually letting these two things cancel each other out
and having an actual velocity, we're actually pretending that our
velocity is encoded in the length of P, right?
So what we're basically saying is, oh, okay, so this whole part of the
equation, we're just going to ignore and say that we're going to set
these two cancel each other out.
So basically that
Equals this so that these terms all go away, our acceleration is 0 and
for whatever reason, we're going to say that our velocity we could
solve for the velocity, the velocity that we're going to go at right
is going to be however, long our Vector is over its own length, right?
So yeah, it's basically going to we're just going to set our velocity
equal to whatever it needs to be to make that ineffectual, if that
makes sense.
Yeah.
So anyway, not particularly interesting here but
Oh no.
Well it's having a bad math morning.
I take that back.
This should look like this.
We don't want to add the lengths back in.
Explain that one more time.
So I did a pretty bad job that time I did.
The work here saying, okay, this is what Delta p is.
But what we want is only the directional portion, right?
We don't actually want that part involved here.
When we're trying to make the length, be something else.
We're trying to make it be in this direction but with this
acceleration in this direction but with this velocity.
So that was a very poor explanation.
I apologize for that.
Bit of a slow morning.
I blame it on Jesus.
It's his Rising day-to-day or whatever.
Right.
So here you go in this case, right?
Again, same, everything I said though, still applies, we've got
basically the direction times the time and you know you can think of
this either way you want.
It's the direction times one half ay t squared plus v t or you can
pull the teeth out either way but we don't have an acceleration in
this case because we're not encoding any of that we just have
instantaneous velocity there.
As far as our current model is concerned.
And what you can see here is again if we take a look at what that
That ends up being, it's the direction times the velocity times the
time step and perhaps.
Let me just since I made such a mess of it, there, let me write it one
more time for you, so you can see it a little bit more clearly, right?
We have 1/2.
A t squared plus v, t plus 30 is our equation.
For this point, the point of the camera overtime, right?
And what we want to do here is say, well, okay, we know that the
direction is always going to be this direction, right?
We're just saying that we're basically to turn this into a scalar
equation, because that's the direction, always, write, whatever that
direction happens to be, that's going to be where we're going.
So that means now, instead of vectors for acceleration and velocity,
we just have scalars.
And we're going to say it's going to be 1/2, Delta p over the length
of Delta P, right?
Times the acceleration magnitude
Times x squared plus the velocity term which again is in the same
direction.
Times the velocity times time.
Plus our starting position wherever that is.
So now our equation right?
Simplifies out again exactly the way I did it before we just pull that
part out and we would say, well, first of all, we can do a little
simpler.
This time we don't have an acceleration, we're not modeling it right.
As I'm trying to explain what we just did with the DT.
We're not modeling acceleration so that goes away.
So all we're left with is this equation?
Right.
And so what were effectively doing if we just solve for what we did,
right?
We did this.
Oops.
Right.
That's what I typed in.
And so the question is where what is that actually end up doing well?
You can see right here, the p 0 term is the same.
Write the Delta p over.
Well I should say the t is the same.
Write the Delta p over length of p.
V term is replaced by just a Delta P term, right?
So then the question come becomes if Delta p over the length of Delta
P times V is just being
Scented by Delta P.
What does that mean?
That V equals?
Right?
Well,
Can see, in this case like so what's the velocity of our camera,
right?
And what you can see in this case is the Delta PS, dropped their on
both sides.
So you divide both sides by Delta p, and you just get equals one and
you multiply this over their side and you get V equals length of Delta
P.
So what we have done is written a resolved rate equation, where the
velocity is, always equal to the distance of to the Target, right?
That's the velocity.
So the instantaneous velocity of our camera at any time, is just
always equal to the distance.
Away from the Target now is that a particularly good velocity to use?
No, I just wanted to explain why that was working there.
But so you can kind of see that's a that already gives us an
interpolating camera which is good, right?
We now know that our stuff is working properly, it's just not a
particularly Pleasant interpolating camera.
It doesn't really do exactly what we want in terms of like Behavior or
anything like that, but it's a good start because now we can start of
work with that equation more.
now, here's the thing, like I said,
In here.
We've got kind of a situation where, in fact, let's maybe break this
down a little bit, let's not do the stairwell first, because it's kind
of a two-part thing.
Let's do something first.
We're we're just if we're sitting here, looking over the Press apiece,
or press a piss, however, you want to do that, let's say if you come
look over the precipice and you just wait there, it'll kind of move
over and show it to you and then if you start moving, it will stop
right.
It'll go back to the center.
Let's do something like that.
So what I want to do is inside the entity, I'm going to stop making
this a flag and I'm going to make it an actual camera Behavior thing.
So instead of controls camera that's going to go away, and what we're
going to do here is we're just going to have a enum called camera
behavior, and I'm going to have a thing here, which is like cameras.
I don't know.
Inspect
Something like that.
And then I'm going to put one of these camera behaviors in here, so
we'll just go ahead and throw that in like so,
Although actually I guess I think that this is like a real thing.
So I guess it's supposed to go up in the part that we actually want to
stuff to have like this.
I also suppose this can go away, huh?
All right.
There we go.
So now in here, what I want to do is say if test entity camera
Behavior,
Is not, you know is nonzero and it overlaps, then we're going to do
something, right.
That's really all we need to know at the moment and let me go
And set that here properly.
And this is going to be.
I guess this will leave us inspect for now but in we're going to want
to do a custom one like I said, for that stairwell Behavior.
So we'll write a different one in a second.
Here we go.
Okay, so now we should still get the same behavior, right?
Like we were before.
Yep.
And so now, what I want to do is I want to come back here and say
well, okay, in addition to this camera volume that we're doing here,
I'm going to do a second camera volume.
And I want this camera volume to be where this whole, the left hole is
right.
So, I want the left hole between negative 5 and negative 3, that's
where I want that to be.
And so, we'll just say,
He had notes hole.
Stairs.
Like so.
So in here, if we said, okay, begin ground identity is Cameron's fact,
we know that the X Dimension here is actually two tiles on either
side, right?
Because it's negative 5 to negative.
That's that was bigger than that.
I guess it's - oh it's less than equal to so it's five.
Four three it's only three wide so I guess it's actually one point
five tiles in either direction.
I guess the why dim will only be one tile wide and then we do rectum
in Max here.
I guess what I want to do here is say okay.
This is not, this is not quite what we want, we don't really want to
recommend.
We want Rec Center gym.
So in this case, what I want to do is say, Okay, so the dimension is
going to be and I guess the dimension that we don't give it half.
So, in this case, it's just one in three, right?
So it's X then y dim.
And then this is a pretty reasonable dimension for the height as well.
So, what I'm going to do here is say, alright now, we need to place
this thing.
Is somewhere.
And what we want to do is we're going to center it.
I guess in terms of its placement we would need this is a little dicey
because in this case we need the placement to be offset by half a
meter.
Right?
Because in the middle of a 3 sort of thing but I guess that's okay.
In fact, I guess what we could do.
Is I guess, in this case, what I could do is still use the min max and
Center it sideways.
So I don't have to
An offset to this.
So anyway, if I want to do that to be centered around negative 4 as an
offset,
And it would be centered around I guess for why it would be at Y 2,
right?
Because it's going to be just below where the hole is and so if I did
a recommend Max in this case yeah I want to do a - wide and wide them
there and in the case of the X dim it's a little bit more specific.
So I want to do that a little bit more carefully.
This one's just going to be at zero.
And then typical floor height so that part's all fine.
So it's really just the X dim that I care about.
So in the X damned, if we're centered at negative 4 and we want - 50,
I guess this this just does work, doesn't it?
Because if we're centered on that and I do
Hat.
Yeah I think that actually does work if this is centered on the tile
so that's actually fine.
I think about it.
Hopefully that will give me a camera at the whole.
Oh I'm on the wrong side of it though.
So I really want - one here, forgot that y goes up.
Old CRT mentality.
So there we go.
And so if I come over here and I do the sort of weird head jerk and
here you can see that, it does what I expected to do and it's also see
here.
At that's also the right height, which is basically most of the area
Maybe I should tone that height down a little bit, maybe it couldn't
shouldn't be quite so much.
That's a reasonable camera region.
So what I want to do now is I want to actually make some code for that
inspection area.
And so, what I'm going to do here is just say these entities, I
believe if I'm not mistaken, they always have IDs.
So, what I can do is I can basically track inside the camera.
If you're inside, one of these special camera things, I can basically
track that information.
So what I can say is like, you know, entity ID,
In special or something like this, and I can do T in special.
So what I can do here is I can say, all right, we have a special
camera.
I'm not going to do this part at the moment.
I'm going to
get this out of here.
So at the moment, I'm just going to that was the code for doing the
only.
If you're going up for the stairwell, will put that in when we do the
full stare stuff.
So what we do is say, okay, the special camera is equal to whatever
the test entity is that we overlapped.
And then, when we come down here, what I'm going to say is, all right,
if there was a special camera found in that path,
Then what I'm going to do is I'm going to compare its ID to the ID
we're currently tracking.
So I'm going to say all right the camera was tracking a special ID if
that is the same as the one from the camera.
And I think we have a like are equal for those.
I don't really know.
Do we?
Yeah, there it is is equal.
So we have a is equal.
So if these two are equal the in special and the ID, then I know that
we are in the same camera as we were last time because we're going to
set that, right?
We're going to say, you know, we're going to remember
Right.
And we're furthermore, we're going to clear it.
Anytime we don't find ourselves in a special camera.
I don't know if we have a way to do that.
I think we do.
But we do now.
So anyway.
What we're going to do here is I'm going to say, all right, every
frame we're going to track.
What?
Which of these volumes if there's a special camera, which one you're
in.
And we're going to use that as a piece of important piece of
information, right?
We're going to check to see On Any Given frame.
Are they the same if they're not right?
So, if this is a new one, well, I guess we could do it this way.
So if they're not the same so we're in a different one as last time.
Then what we want to do is clear, the amount of time that the counter
that's going to count.
How much time we spent in particular one, we're going to clear that
otherwise we're going to add the Delta time to it, right?
So basically, we're just keeping an accumulator of how long you've
been in a inside a specific camera.
If you've been in an inside a camera long enough, let's say, then
we're going to actually use that special camera as an alternate
Target.
Otherwise not.
Okay.
So in this case, what we want to do is say, well, okay, if the T in
special is over a certain value, then we'll use it.
So we could do, you know, if, for example, special camera and
Camera.
Tien special.
Is greater than one second, or something like this, right?
And this isn't quite what we want yet, but it's getting closer.
So, for example, now if I came over here and stood in here, you can
see after a little bit, it will come over.
And if I hop back outside, then it won't.
And we can make that a little bit longer.
Even, you know, it could be 5 Seconds.
So here I come over here, I stand by The Edge and then it goes like
okay 1 2 3 4 5 and then it comes over right just so you can exaggerate
the effect.
I don't think you'd actually want it to be set to that high, but
that's the idea, right?
And then if you leave this area, it will go back to viewing the room.
As you would normally view it.
And again, you can come back in here and wait for a little bit and it
will go view that location.
Right now, furthermore that could control the zoom as well if we
wanted to.
So, for example, inside this, the entities if we had
Let's say The Entity had been here, a camera offset Z.
And so if that was the case, then in here, you know, we set the target
Z like this.
What we could do instead is say all right the target offset C equals 8
.0 otherwise the target offsets.
The in the case of the special is going to be the camera offset, see
like that.
And then we would have that information.
So what we want to do is in this case, say well, okay the Target off
set C is going to be either coming from our expected, offsets the or
it's going to come from whatever this entity is and so that would
allow us to zoom in as well, right?
So what we can do here is in the world where we create this thing set
that as a behavior.
Furthermore, what we could do in this case is we could say
All, you know, maybe behavior is actually has a couple different
components to it.
You know.
Maybe the behavior is actually more of a Flags field.
So, you know, the camera Behavior has it inspect, it has a zoom
Right.
So maybe what happens.
Here is more like if camera
Behavior.
Sorry.
We set it in otherwise we don't right?
So then in here we would say it since this is that's
Hole cameras.
Listen here.
So that's an inspect and it does affect the zoom Etc.
So something like this, right?
And let's go ahead and
we're set up.
There we go.
So now when we come over here after 5 Seconds, elapsed is, we should
zoom in.
Now granted we set the zoom to 0 which is not a particularly good zoom
so we should probably set that to something else.
Maybe that, and maybe that special.
Let's set that something more reasonable.
So now after 2 seconds it will zoom in still seems to be zooming in
quite a bit more than I would have expected.
Did I that see?
That still looks like it's is more set to 0.
Did I miss something?
Well, so if it's eight, it should not zoom in at all.
So I'd be interested.
Let me see what happens here.
Maybe three is not high enough up.
Snow.
So we have definitely have a weird situation going on there, right?
It should not be zooming in nearly that much.
It's as if the camera off set, C is set to 0.
Like completely set to 0.
Yeah.
How about I actually get it off the camera?
I was actually getting it off of the hero, which doesn't make any
sense, because unsurprisingly, the hero doesn't have that set given
that the hero is not a camera volume, alright?
So in this case, we can zoom in, right?
And if we wanted to we could even have more of an offset.
In this case, we could make it.
So that for example if we wanted to really have a very specific
Way in which this was working, we could make it so that this offset is
a full offset so that it can specify all, you know, exactly how it
wants to be placed.
So for example we could say well the offsets going to be you know
nothing in X but in why we do want to go
You know, two units up for something like this.
So you're looking more down at the whole in particular, something like
this.
So in that case you end up with a thing where it's like, all right,
you're going to get a Target offset?
See, it's going to come from here.
You're also going to modify the target.
The target P.
Its XY is going to get offset by whatever the X Y is in here, oops.
And now you can slide the camera around as well by saying here's where
the target should end up relative to wear this.
You know the here is that time, right?
So now if you want to write, you can kind of do this thing where the
camera will zoom in when the hero is, is kind of over the whole, so
you can see down.
It does occur to me that our fog are layer picking is not picking far
enough down.
The moment because of the change we made in how hot big floors are.
But now that's kind of fun, right?
Where you can sort of.
If you happen to be looking down over there, you can can see what's in
there, and that's kind of fun, right?
Don't know if that will actually work for gameplay.
It might be too difficult.
Maybe you do it only.
If all the monsters are dead or something like that, so it's, you
know, it's not going to be a problem, but it's kind of fun, right?
I mean, that's just kind of a nice.
It's just interesting, it's games.
Seems, you know, a lot of times are about having lots of little
interesting things you can do.
And so again, this is just a nice thing.
Once you have a 3D camera and everything is 3D ish, you know it's just
kind of nice to be able to play with it in that way.
Yeah so that's pretty great.
I'm into that.
I mean to that as a feature I like it.
I think it takes too long to kick in
There you go.
Alright, so
what we could do to is make it, so you have to actually stop there at
the moment.
It's just however long you're in this thing, but maybe what that
should do is, it should have to have a trigger in terms of your
velocity and that velocity has to be 0, right?
So we can do that too, we can do like, you know, velocity measure
something like this and maybe inspect just knows that the velocity
measures that.
So, you know,
In this case, we would say camera Behavior inside here.
If it overlaps, we would say, well, okay, if the camera behavior is an
inspection Behavior.
Then we've got some other sort of modifications that we're going to
have to do.
So, if the camera havior is camera inspect, which is the only kind of
when, we know at the moment, then what we need to do is we could even
set this by default.
Then do it in here.
What we could say is if the entity
DP.
There's nothing.
or should I say is greater than
Anything done a special camera is 0.
So, in theory, now if I like going through here and I'm like, playing
and doing stuff and like fighting people, or whoever knows what it
won't do it, but if I stop in theory, we should go in there.
Of course we don't, I wonder if that's because the velocity never
quite goes to 0.
We may need a little bit arms there.
Let's say something like that.
So again.
There we go.
so, I think
To me.
That's roughly what I'm looking for.
and so now we just kind of need some more stuff in here that's like,
you know, ways ways of handling the stairwell specifically.
So the stairwell right now has been changed so that the stairwell
actually will do exactly the same thing as the inspect does.
So if I'm in the stairwell and moving, it won't do anything, which is
not what we want.
And if I'm in the stairwell and just waiting there, it'll kind of come
over, right?
But that's not what we want.
What we want to do is say, well, okay, if the player is moving down
the stairwell, then we want, even if they're on the top square, we
probably want to focus in once they get on the actual stairwell.
Then we never want to do anything other than being stairwell, Focus,
right?
So, we want to force you to stairwell Focus.
Once you get once you get to that point and then only once, you're
actually out of the stairwell, Focus region, do we want the camera to
return to what it's doing?
So what I want to do here is say, like, okay,
in the stairs cam, I want to basically
All right, much better.
So no one had better.
Use those terms now because those are like, fully trademarked
All right, so in here, we basically have begin ground entities.
For the for the stairs.
Exactly.
Like we do for the whole where there's just one, but for the stairs, I
think we probably want to different ones because if you're on the
actual stairs, we always want to be in Starck at mode.
There shouldn't be any way to get out of it but if you're just passing
by the top, right then we don't really want to be in stairs cam mode
so we probably want to create two of these.
I guess what I would say.
So what we want here is we want to do like, you know, second one of
these.
I end, we'll figure out what they're supposed to be in a second.
All right, so for starters, let's just do the main stair area and this
could be just a force.
Two player or something like this.
This is basically like if you're in here or like you know if you're in
here you're just going to view the player like immediately something
like that.
If you're here, I guess in this case, we also would do view player but
the difference in this case is just going to be that we would add a
the velocity constraint, right?
So in this case, we might have to add an or here to like choose
whether the velocity is happening or not.
So, all right, so we have begun an entity camera, babe, your view
player in.
And all we need to do is adjust
These Dimensions.
So, in this case we've got a
I guess what we want here is to say.
Let me give me one second here because I don't really remember exactly
what the layout of this looks like.
So if we come back here as well, look at this.
So we've got four
And I guess that one is shallow enough that maybe you should have to
be going the right direction to, I don't know.
So maybe we cover these two with the directional one and these three
with
With the other we were and, you know, it might be that we want.
It to bi-directional.
First of all, we got to make those go lower it out.
All right, hold on a second so we got to make this a little bit
different here.
So let's let's start by getting these stairs to be the way stairs are
and also the stairs probably to be longer.
Now that I'm thinking about it.
I mean, if you look at that, we probably need the stairs to have more
steps to them.
Because there we don't want to be too steep.
So I feel like that's got to be.
Yeah.
So all right, so what we want here is we probably want to take this
off set Z and we probably want to first of all set it to be consistent
before.
It was actually picking up the noise values here and so we probably
want to do is actually stop that and just have it be non noisy.
So the stairs are even going all the way down.
That was not what I wanted.
Should that not have done?
What?
I just what should that not have reproduced, but I had there.
Correct me if I'm wrong, I'm taking 0.5 plus a random unilateral.
So the minimum, this could be is 0.5 and I'm subtracting this from it.
Right.
So shouldn't that
I guess I don't understand why that?
Why that modified anything at all?
Here's my current version.
All right, that is the complete puzzle to me.
I have to admit, I do not understand why that did that.
Because the offset Z here was already going to be 0.5 up.
And now I'm over writing it with essentially that same amount minus
this, that should have been the same, right?
I mean, maybe I'm missing something but I don't understand why that
would actually be different.
I want to know what's going on here.
So this should produce the correct thing will correct but it should
produce the old thing.
Right.
So now I want to set a breakpoint there and I want to see do that
because I want to know what's going on there.
Oh, and I'm going to
Excited.
Release mode build so I can do about that code.
Alright, so in this case test Z is 0.5 which is exactly what we would
expect it to be.
Let me see what key got off set.
Ah, you know what?
No, it's because this world position P has an offset in it already.
That's that's why.
Never mind, never mind.
This is not zero up here.
It could be some arbitrary value, so not not quite the case.
Alright, so in terms of the noise here, I guess what I need to do is
I'm going to need to put the noise in here.
If I want to turn it off for the stairs.
so hopefully now we have even stairwell
And now, the problem is just it needs to go down a little bit more,
right?
So it needs to be, maybe more like that.
Or there need to be more steps, one of the other.
All right.
So yeah, I feel like there's maybe should be just more steps.
Going down.
Like, the stairwell should be a little bit longer, you know, like
maybe at least one more.
So like maybe the offset y from negative 2 to 2 actually goes you know
from negative 3 to 2 or something like this.
And that one there is like too high up.
So because this is going to have to be plus three now.
There we go.
So now the stairwell starts there.
I'm goes down.
If I take a look under here, you can see that's a little bit smoother,
right?
So alright.
Yeah.
All right, so I don't really know whether that's still too steep.
I mean we could make it a little bit less steep still, we could make
it
be more like that.
And now we've got just a big old stairwell.
Can see it go down there.
Maybe this needs to be a little bit less too.
All right, so I think now I've got a stairwell that's a little bit
more sensible.
Perhaps,
Right, in terms of of gradual in this of steps.
And so now we just need to make it so that when the hero comes over on
there again, we don't get that that clipping artifact, by moving the
camera into a good position for it.
Which I think should be relatively easy.
And maybe, you know, maybe the stairwells could one.
Another thing we could do is make the stairwells be too wide.
You know, the other thing I haven't really thought about this, but we
could do something like this.
Would be another way of treating it.
So if you had a larger stairwells, right?
And you made it so that the hero was centered on those steps which we
could easily do then there'd be a lot more clearance to when going
down the stairs, which might be all we really need and that could be a
more compelling way to deal with it as well.
So maybe that's a good idea.
And so really what we would do there is we create the stairs and sort
of a slightly separate pass.
So really, what we would say is, you know, something like, okay.
so we'd say something like okay, the left hole right whole situation,
these are both Knockouts and then if you make it through the end up
with this
And so now there's just like nothing in either of those two places.
So maybe now you say, okay, you know the stairwell is narrower, it's
back the way it was.
So now it's just a hole there in the floor and the hole is, is a
narrower hole.
That's still seems a little large, doesn't it?
So why is that for?
Because in theory, that's negative 1, 0 & 1 & 2, so that's four wide.
Okay.
Yeah, so if now, if I wanted to, I could go ahead and make instead of
like in this circumstance, where we're making these specific size
ground tiles, I could make some stair tiles.
That are different, right?
So what I would do there is I can just say, okay, we take the offset,
why
And I'm going to go ahead and make some stair tiles.
Exactly, the way we were making them.
before, but this time, we're just going to hard-code the offset X
And we have to do a little bit of offsetting here.
You'll see this in a second but we can take care of that a minute.
So, whatever the offset X is, what should it be here?
It's between three and four.
So it's like, 3.5, right?
So anyway we're going to have a thing where we say, all right, we want
you know, offset x 2 B 3.
So it does that offset X of 3 but then we want to do like an offset of
P where we're going to add half a tile, right?
In fact, I don't even know.
What is this function?
Actually do see there.
It's got an additional offset right here.
So what I can do is say all right, in addition to that, I want you to
do half a tile.
it's to put it in the center of the stairwell, basically, and then I
know that we're just going to create
one of these deer pieces.
All right, so in theory now we will create an actual stairwell in
there and you can see it.
Well actually let me just go ahead and flip to the debug view so you
can see it.
You can see that there's the stairwell there.
and actually,
Creating way too many.
So I don't really want it to be radius.
Why?
I just wanted to be between negative 1 & 2.
Right.
And so, now, what we want to do is we want to make these also be
wider, right?
We just want the stairs to be whiter, potentially.
They don't really have to be necessarily whiter but they can be right
and so if I don't guess, I think the other problem is I guess I don't
know exactly how to get down to one of them but yeah.
So basically what we've got here is those stairs are kind of in the
middle right there like they're in between the two and we probably
need them to be spaced out a little more than they are right now and
start a little higher.
So I don't know, that's another option for stairwells and then, you
know, the hero is pretty safely.
Even if we don't adjust the camera the hero wouldn't clip through,
right?
I don't know how I feel about that.
It's an interesting idea hadn't thought of it.
It's just a little weird that that join point to.
We're getting kind of a loop here.
Yeah.
I don't know how that would feel, right?
It's gonna always create a thing here.
Where you're on between these two I guess, no matter which one
Are you go, you hop, you're going to hop kind of down to that middle
square and maybe that's fine.
I don't know graphically speaking.
We can also make it wider.
You know, we can we can double out how wide they are so that they feel
like a double like there that the width of both of them like so,
right.
And then the hero hops down like so on the large stairs, I suppose
that's also an option.
course, I guess, since we don't allow you to have different
Since we currently only pass down an X and a dimension for the Square
Tile and we don't we don't allow to be wide and not yeah.
We we currently don't actually draw those as having different width
and height.
They only have different depth basically.
So we would have to add that if we actually want to just wide stairs.
So I don't know.
I don't know how I feel about that.
I'll leave it in for now.
It's just an interesting thing to do when we actually go to do World
stuff.
Obviously, we'll have some stronger opinions about these sorts of
things.
When we're starting to build the actual world, but let's just go ahead
and do the camera stuff for now, since that's the more interesting
part of this.
So, here we are in our stairs cam.
What we need now is the thing on the stairs and the thing at the top
of the stairs, presumably.
So if we want to do that, we could basically say like, okay, we've got
the stairs part.
The stairs part is going to be centered around.
I guess centered around one for the radius part and it's going to be
one tile in either direction.
The X dim in this case could be half a tile because now we're sort of
centered.
And the location here.
Is actually going to be offset slightly, right by whatever that stair
p is.
And what I can do here, if I want to use?
I can also do something like say,
I can I can use this exact.
This exact set of things here to store the.
So if I want to, I can say, oh, the stair P, so I don't have to look
them up.
Again, I got to say the stair position stuff is going to be, you know,
an array of what is it - 10?
And so, four of these guys, and I can just say, stare pee,
Offset.
Why?
Let's be so I can record those as well.
And then that way when I'm creating these here, I can pull that out.
Oops.
So the stair placement, in this case, I guess I just want the second
one, third one, I guess in.
And yeah, that's roughly correct, I think.
So that why is that so tall?
That turn.
First of all, start by turning this off.
And so I don't understand why that's quite the way it is, but I guess
it makes some sense.
Hold on a second.
Let me
So you can see that it's being created, like, I guess it's right about
there.
But I'm not quite sure that's why it's because we don't actually, if
we're actually going to put it at that height, then we don't want it
to extend down, nearly that far.
Let's try that one more time.
all right, so again a little strange because I'm not sure what the ABS
tells e and this case is
I guess we're getting the ABS tiles e of this floor, and then we're
going up from there.
So, we really want to do.
For a given stairwell.
Is it wants to be much lower than that.
So I guess what we really want to do is for that part of it, since the
stair is going downward, what we really want to do is say well, we
probably want to end actually pretty pretty low.
Write this, this hit region, generally speaking.
Why did that not do what?
I thought it was going to do.
Oh, because I'm editing the wrong one.
That's why
Sir.
I think we want this to end pretty close.
To the floor level of the floor above, right?
Because that looks like more of the region that the player would be
in.
It probably needs to be a little higher than that, and then it should
probably be up a little bit more.
So we probably want something more like this.
That looks like about the right region.
Maybe it needs to be a little bigger.
So I think that's about, right.
And then, when I hop down here, I'm only in it if I'm actually on
these stairs.
Right.
And that's the actual stair region.
So really, this is the stairs camp.
This is the like,
Is like the top of the stairs.
So let's go ahead and add Boop's one more for the top of the stairs.
That one's going to be centered around, stare P0.
And in this case, I guess I want to
I guess I wanted to make it the whole size and
I don't know that it goes down particularly far.
I'm not really sure what we want for this.
So, okay, that's a little too large, but other than that, that's
actually pretty good.
Turn it back a little.
So that seems pretty reasonable right?
Like, that's
That's I think about right there and, you know, we can sort of tune,
those a little bit more as we go.
But now, we just need to actually have some logic in here.
Let's just double check that.
I didn't mess up this guy.
I think this, this one's still correct, right?
And now I just need this one to be like if I'm needs to kind of get
over there, right away if I'm if I'm going toward the stairs, right?
If I'm coming up this way and then it needs to not if I'm doing
anything else.
All right, so let's upgrade the camera Behavior here to handle all
that stuff.
Right?
Because now we need some better behavioral code, because we've got
kind of a lot of different things that could be happening.
We're going to have to make this be a little bit.
More specific, right?
So essentially what we've got here is we need to determine a couple
different things we need to determine whether a particular camera.
Entity is controlling or not.
And so, what we want to do here is probably not set the special camera
because if anyone if any of the peoples who are overlapping if any
overlapping camera region, it would have tested positive.
We probably want to use it right?
So what
White here is probably something more like this.
Where we say like, okay, if you know, if you're conforming to the
velocity constraints, then off you go.
So how would we encode some velocity constraints here?
I'm assuming what we want to do is say something like, well, okay,
let's say that there is a
Like a DOT product here, where we say like velocity measure.
And we do a velocity measure of the test sanity.
We'll take the entities like the players motion vector.
And we'll say, okay, whatever there's going to be some thing will
inner product with here, that's going to measure this thing and then
we'll do that first and then we'll take the length of that, right?
So we'll say whatever the absolute value is.
Of that velocity measure.
That's what we use right now.
I guess that's not quite what we want.
I guess we more want instead of a DOT product, we want more of a a
coefficient I think we still want the length to be in here.
So they can be really want more of a hadamard product here.
So basically you can multiply the X, the y, or the Z velocity is buy
something, and then get out what you're then going to look at.
Right.
That's probably more what we want and so we'll leave it at that for
now.
And so, then, what we need is some kind of an interval, right?
We need some way of saying, well, you know, if the velocity at that
point is a certain amount.
Then that's what we want.
Now, I guess, in this case, we could also just, if we know that the
velocities that we're going to be checking, or always in the primary
directions, we could just bound them explicitly, right?
We could do something like
This sort of thing if that makes sense.
And furthermore, we don't really have to do that.
We could just do with point in rectangle.
Right?
We could say if the velocity point is within the camera wreck is is
within the cameras controlling entities velocity rectangle because we
can use you know we can have rectangles in velocity space just like
everything else.
So if it's within could say there's a velocity requirement if it's in
there.
Then off you go furthermore we could say whether there is a relative
velocity requirement or not, could be a thing.
So what we could say is all right, if it overlaps, you know and
So we test for overlap first because everyone has that.
Then we see whether or not you've got velocity constraint,
And I guess the thing is we've got two kinds of velocity constraints.
We've got
You must be greater than a certain amount or you must be less than a
certain amount, right?
And it's a little bit hard.
So we're creating a rectangle.
I guess we can just put that rectangle anywhere we want so we could
make it, I guess, I guess you could probably do most of the things
you'd want to do with a rectangle.
The thing is, you can't really invert a rectangle very easily.
So if you wanted to say, the player just has to be moving a certain
amount that's harder.
Right?
So I don't know.
Maybe this isn't the best way to do it.
I'm just trying to think of what
Good ways to do it are because like in one case we want it to say, if
you're not moving another case, we want to say, if you're moving in a
particular direction, I'm just trying to think of like, what's the
easiest way to provide some easy controls.
So that when you're creating entities, you can just throw in some
Information, and not have to add a new camera Behavior.
Every time you have a different thing,
it's hard to say.
I'm not not sure about that one.
My gut says, most of the time we're going to care about.
A particular direction of motion.
Or no motion doll.
Right.
Are we care whether you're going towards something?
Or whether you're stationary or whether you're moving.
So there's like is my speed greater than this is my speed less than
this.
And then also am I going in a particular direction?
All right, I think that's what we want.
So I think baby of a rectangle is not such a good idea, shouldn't he?
So I do think we want the other kind so if we want velocity
constrained then we want to again like I said do a test here but that
test probably shouldn't be is in rectangle.
It should probably be something like you know and isn't range.
And then we would have test entity Min camera Min velocity.
Whatever the thing is, we're going to use tests entity camera, Max
velocity.
So it specified the like Min and Max velocity.
And then in here we would need some way of figuring out.
what the velocity is along a particular vector and the problem here is
like, Well, we'd like to be able to do something where we just said
well,
It's the length squared of, you know.
And we can
Sweaty as well.
Keep it on the same space.
We know that the entity in the case of we just wanted to do the the
speed by itself in whatever Direction The Entity was going.
We could take the length squared of its velocity and be done.
Then this equation works just fine and we could figure out whether or
not it conformed.
The problem is if we want to know if it's in a particular direction,
then what we have to do here is say we want to take the inner product
of the entity with some kind of
Velocity direction, right?
And the problem there is that we want that.
Like, once we do that, we have lost the ability to ask the question
about how fast the entity is going in any particular direction, right?
Because now it's going to collapse.
That down to a scalar and we can't take, we won't have any ability any
longer to ask a question about that about arbitrary motion.
I,
So we pretty much need to things here.
I mean we could do something absurd, the could do something like this.
So that's basically allows the person to construct an equation.
Where they basically have one term, that is the length of the Velocity
Vector of the player.
At the time, they have another term that is the length of a lot of the
Velocity Vector of the player along a particular axis that they
specify, right?
And then they are able to set these coefficients to see which ones
they want.
So if they only
An equation based on this one, they set a 2, 1 and B, 2 0, and vice
versa, they could also have both of them involved somehow, which I'm
not sure why you would want that.
But you could have that.
Furthermore, you could clamp the inner which would allow you to do
that a little bit better if you really wanted to, I don't know.
So you could do something like this where they can actually pick the
merits and what we could do.
All sorts.
Roses have have flags at do that.
So maybe that's the right way to do it.
Maybe we say, okay, if the camera velocity
like General, velocity constraint, something like that.
Then what we do is say well that's just just that's just this
Right.
So
and I guess the other thing I could do is make this a little cleaner
to read by doing something like
So we start out by saying well it passes, if it overlaps and then we
have to start doing our constraints.
So then we would say well if there is a velocity constraint on this
thing, then we do this.
And we can just freeze it in the, in the in the pasta goes pass.
And so if any previous pass had not succeeded, then this one won't
succeed, either, right?
So then we can just say, okay?
That's if we have a general velocity constraint,
if we have a directional velocity constraint,
then we use the other kind.
Like so.
And then that's a little bit more understandable right in this case.
Now the entities have to have those so they've got they've got to have
camera velocity direction and Camera in velocity.
Camera Max velocity.
And we need those.
General.
Velocity constraint.
Directional.
I need to be in there.
I think that's more or less it right.
We don't have an it is in range.
Call I don't think yet so I'll just add one here.
Well, is in ranges, is just a way of saying, there's a Min, there's a
value.
There's a Max
and I just want to say,
Result, equals min.
It's less than or equal to the value.
And
Max value is less than equal to Max.
It's really just a interval inclusion, right?
Like it's a one-dimensional rectangle.
Is this point inside these two bounds?
All right.
So now we haven't actually used any of this stuff yet.
So in theory, when we hop in here and nothing difference, going to
happen, same exact thing, but now what we should be able to do is
inside World mode is actually use those.
So now when we have like the top and the stairs here, the stairs is
going to be view player and we kind of want like I said we want to.
I don't know if
I'm not sure how we should phrase this, but we've got view player and
inspect inspect is going to.
I think what we want to do here is have you player and inspect be
different in terms of how they're actually handled in the part at the
bottom?
So for example in here where we have special camera, camera Behavior
equals Zoom.
We also want camera behavior and view player.
We want these to be
Distinct.
So, what I want to do here is say well, okay, in the case where I've
got the camera inspect flag, I really want to take the camera itself
and I want you to look at the camp, where the camera is specified to
be not the camera, so that the controlling box, right?
The box of control the camera, I want to look there.
But if I'm doing the player, then I want to use the players actual
position.
And then when we're applying the offset here,
That's a thing that can happen separately.
So if either of them can have that in it, right?
And that's just a separate flag that you can control with with no
other concerns there.
So now you know, when we come over here and you're inside here, when
you're moving around, it should it shouldn't follow you, right?
It shouldn't go left to right.
It should just stay there and then come out.
And when I'm over here though, this one should follow me.
So when I come in here, now you can see it actually moves left to
right with me.
So there's a difference, I wanted there to be a difference between
viewing, the player and viewing area.
And those should be like, actually sort of separate ideas, right?
If
Sense.
Okay, so we got that under control and then the other thing I want to
do now is I want to actually clean up this timing bit because again
the timing part is going to be specific as well.
So in this case, we can probably put anything here that's like oh hey.
In addition to a minute, Max velocity, let's have a camera meantime or
something like that.
And so it's going to be in here where we do that sort of special
camera if you're if you're greater than or equal to a certain
accumulator this accumulator will always happen, that will be camera.
T and special is greater than
Special camera Cameron in time.
And that way when we're creating these for the whole cam, we know that
we want the camera to have a minimum time that's not zero.
You know, we want that minimum time to be one s or whatever it is but
for the stairs, we don't really want there to be a minimum time.
So for the stairs that should happen, as soon as I'm in there, right?
And as soon as I'm out, it just an in, it does it?
But for this one, it should wait, right?
And not do it.
And furthermore, while I'm moving, I don't want to do it.
So now I have to start using those velocity constraints because those
have gone away now.
So, what I want to do is I want to put a general velocity constraint
on this one.
I want to say, okay, for this particular camera, I'm going to have a
Of the last 3, constraint, where the Min velocity can be as low as you
want.
But the max velocity can't be very high, right?
And then on these, for example, on the stairs, I just want it to
always, if you're on the stairs, you view the player like period.
I don't really want anything to interfere with that, but in this case,
I do want a camera direction of velocity constraint.
Where I would say, okay, there's a camera velocity direction of moving
in, why down the stairwell I want the Min velocity to be 0 and I want
the I'm sorry.
I want the minimum velocity to be like something in that direction and
the max velocity can be whatever you want.
Is it like maximum or something?
Where the max where are minimum and maximum values?
Still a little quick.
Whoops.
Just do a little quick update of these names to the new shorter names
which are nicer and they have nice syntax highlighting and for coder,
which is good.
Okay.
Where's the other one?
Third is
All right.
So now in theory anyway, when I come over to this thing, I should have
to have some velocity in that direction.
Before the camera moves in theory,
However, that theory appears to be wrong.
It seems like as long as I have any y velocity that that worked.
Which is not.
What I wanted at all.
Let's double check that camera velocity constraint.
They've got some buggy buggy booze in there.
See.
So, here's the directional.
Velocity.
Oh well.
Okay, so for starters, this is not correct now because
Yes.
Oh this inner product will not give you a square.
It'll actually just give you the the actual length along that vector.
So that shouldn't have been squaring it.
I don't know, F32 Max is probably a problem for squaring, not sure
what happens.
If you square the maximum value.
That could be a problem but and I guess also in here we would have
that same problem if someone used one of them ends with the Max's for
length squared.
So what I could do is say well alright let's just we'll do the actual
square root there, it's not that expensive anymore.
And leave it like that.
However, I don't know that that was really the bug.
So we're going to have to take a closer look at what's going on there,
but
maybe that was the bug.
So now it seems like it's working.
There's a little bit of a weird there shouldn't be any hard edges here
but it felt like there was one there.
The jerking back and forth of is natural because we're not modeling
acceleration yet but they're felt like there was actually a snap and I
don't feel like there should never be a snap at the moment because I
don't think we let there be any snapping.
Do we like there was definitely a snap there.
Right, you saw that.
So I feel like we still have a bit of a weird thing going on there.
I do wonder if that's the simulation region thing.
Because this should never really be doing any snapping.
It's only ever going to move by a small amount towards the Target in
any real case, unless these blue up somehow, maybe if these got set to
some really weird values.
But
But there should not have been that snapping, so that concerns me a
little.
I don't know if we have time to debug that right now, but that
shouldn't really be the case.
If something weird was happening there,
So that's also a problem.
Is the restoration, we almost need to look at the heroes push
direction because the what else so happens here is if I go downward
and then snap back, that counts is forward velocity.
On the hero, which we don't actually want to count for the stairs.
But anyway, what I'm working certain about the moment is that weird,
snapping Behavior.
And I do not know what that would be from.
Like I said, I can understand why if you're in overlapping.
Is you could get Jitter with the velocity because we're cold setting
that right now, but that snap seems excessive, it seems like we're
actually changing the position discontinuously not not through this.
So let me take a look at this here.
so, when we coming through here, you can see as we're doing this,
we've got
We're looking at all of these in World space.
I'm sorry.
In simulation space.
Right.
So all of this code is all in.
It's all in the space of the of the current region, all of this stuff.
And we set the Simulation Center based on that we set the target based
on that.
But this right here is
Is not really right?
Is it?
Because the cameras position?
Well, I guess it's okay because the cameras position has never really
been considered yet.
This new camera p is not a thing.
Right, that's just not involved at all.
So really, this is the first time we look at the camera position and
We should be able to unpack those relative to whatever we want.
We can certainly compact the Miller to the Simulation Center.
I don't see why we couldn't.
and then when we map the P back, it should just work that that does
seem
That does seem like totally reasonable thing.
Hmm.
I don't know.
it's it happened specifically when the Simulation Center changes so
that does give us a pretty good clue because you can see right here
that this little this
Yellow box anytime that discontinuous, jump happens.
That's what's going on, right?
You can see that happening.
So, I wonder if changing the Simulation Center definitely is part of
the problem.
I wonder if there's something happening outside, the camera code.
I don't remember how we're really doing anything outside with the
camera.
That would cause that jerkiness to happen.
Here is how we determine that Delta P when we do the simulate.
So it looks like what we're doing here is we're saying, alright, we're
going to simulate the world forward.
For some reason, we update the camera down here.
Which doesn't really make any sense.
That means it's going to be a frame behind, right?
Which is a little weird, so you would think you would do a begin Sim
then update the camera.
Like
Simulate update the camera.
And then set the camera like viewing right here.
I feel like this is kind of all a little bit tangled up to completely
honest.
Then we get the frame to frame camera, Delta
we would know what that was.
It would be.
You would just take it around here.
You wouldn't have to save it from frame to frame.
You just know what it was.
Directly there.
And I feel like that's a standard way to do stuff.
You know, if I look back here at when we're doing this, I don't I
don't really see any particular reason why this stuff can't be done
inside here.
Right.
Inside that cimmeria look like there's no and the Sim bounds like we
don't really want the same boundary based on the camera anymore.
So I feel like that was why that was happening before.
So I kind of feel like I want to untangle that a little bit as well
because I feel like that could easily be causing problems as well.
That it's also going to make the camera lag which is not great, right?
So I do think yeah we would want to do something like okay, you know
you want to simulate the world's here.
You want to update the camera?
Are you don't need to store this.
I don't think for any particular reason, I think you would just say
well
We can snap the location of the world's camera pee.
Before we do the update.
And then get the new one because that's in World space.
So it's always going to be the right amount.
And that's how much the particles would have to move.
Right.
So don't really know if this is a good time of doing this.
We don't have very much time left but you know what you going to do.
So if I did do that in here, you can see that we would do the update
here.
Then we do the update.
This is not right yet.
Because now we actually need to this as well.
We need to
Have the camera.
We have to have the camera Matrix stuff like that.
Get built after we actually do this.
Because now this is going to be wrong but at least that's in a senior
place.
Go ahead and hop down here.
See that shirk is still there.
Very interesting and yeah, so what I would need to do here is I need
to pull down this code.
That's actually setting the camera stuff up.
All of this stuff is fine because this is just default parameter
things.
I don't know about this part here.
again, we probably want to make this stuff a little bit cleaner, so
There's just a ton of camera stuff happening in here which is just
mostly for the debug stuff.
But then this is the thing that actually does the camera transform
creation.
This stuff here, and
The sun project is just some test codes.
We don't really need that in the moment.
So let's see.
The Sim bounds are just literally doing that.
So, we should be able to basically take all of this code and actually
We do it later, right?
We should be able to do that.
After we update the camera.
However, I don't actually know.
When we call simulate, I'm guessing that we're all.
So we have to have set the camera by that time.
Because otherwise I guess that's the best thing that'll get us.
That's actually going to do the rendering so we would rather set the
camera after we update, right?
Where the cause otherwise we're always a frame behind on the camera.
Now, go ahead and undo that because I won't have time to really do it
today, but I think that's worth disentangling, right?
Because I feel like we want to make sure that in simulate
In here update and render entities.
I feel like what we want to do there is we want to be able to do the
camera setting the camera.
After we've updated the entities basically we want to move them all
and then set the camera and we can still do that in a single pass.
If we want to write like we can still write out all the positions of
where we're going to draw the entities and just not have set the
camera transform yet, right?
I mean, that's still totally possible.
So I don't really know how we want to do that, but I feel like we will
want to do that.
Again, that's just my guess.
So I'm going to go ahead and put it to do in here and we'll look at it
next week.
So, inside here, where we are.
what I would like to do is say like okay yeah, you know, could we sort
of
And I feel like what we would want to do with that, right?
Is we'd want to say okay we're going to, we're going to go ahead and
start our quads.
Will push all the entity quads out in the you know, will basically
output all of our vertex buffer data but we just won't set the camera
transforms on the Viet, right?
And we'll want to set the camera transforms after we've already.
All that simulation.
And now we know where the camera should be will set it then.
I feel like that's what we actually want to do.
Now that doesn't even do it, the bug we were seeing necessarily it
just something that I think we would want to fix.
And so we'll fix that or at least we'll try to fix that next week.
I suffered V there seems to be a second problem with Starck, M1 versus
stare cam 2 IU.
You need to be moving even though you're on the first are so the
Collision areas are out a bit
I'm not sure I quite understand what you're referring to yet.
We haven't really gotten to the point where it's there.
Came one answer came to or done.
So there's a couple weird things about them, but I'm not sure what you
mean by.
The Collision areas are out a bit.
Brooke tag are the trees below smaller than the trees up top.
They should be because of the angle, right?
Yeah.
So these are a little steeper angle wise if that makes sense, although
it's hard to tell which one's taller really, but the reason is,
because these are pointing more directly up at us if that makes sense.
And the reason for that is we allowed there to be the, we allowed the
trees to be tilted in perspective.
So we don't have to, and
Know which one we should go with in the end.
But if you look at when we did our push quad, basically, what we did
is we allowed the z-axis to actually have some three dimensionality to
it.
So that's the completely orthographic tree where the tree is just
slapped on directly and then they're the same size on both of them,
but if I get rid of that, you can see that they're tilted and that
gives them a little bit of a perspective to them, right?
and so like as I go, you know, over to other places, you can see as
the camera moves, you know, the trees kind of shift a little if I
Make it so that I it's the camera was always focused on me directly.
which would basically be
This.
So now you can kind of see like if I'm walking along to see how
there's a perspective shift in the trees as we go, you can kind of see
how that that works.
That is what you're seeing there.
So you know, it's certainly a matter of preference which of these we
should go with again, if I was to turn that off in the render group
and just say no, then when you can see is kind of as I am
Walking around here, the trees, while they their positions relative,
to each other shift, based on how high up the block.
Is that they're on, they themselves will never shift their just strict
Sprite stamps.
Personally, I think I do
Prefer them shifted.
I don't know, it just that that extra tilt, add something.
For me visually.
So I kind of prefer it, I think, I don't know.
We'll see what happens but that's what's going on there.
But why not are you going to experiment zooming by changing the fov
rather than changing the distance?
No, probably not.
I am not like, I don't know that the fov really wants to change their.
We don't really want to compress the field of view for any particular
reason.
Like we're not going for a disorienting camera effect or anything, so
Why use velocity and not for instance, acceleration as a constraint
parameter, no particular reason we may we may want to use
acceleration, I don't know.
I'm just adding some stuff to the camera and it seemed like velocity
was the natural thing in this this particular point.
But we got a ways to go before, we're like having a nice camera.
So, you know, maybe we will use acceleration for things.
Why are the health bars flickering seems to be most notable because
that's just Z fighting right now.
We the health bars are kind of, we have not really done anything with
the health bars.
I don't even know why we're still drawing them because they're not
actually there for any particular purpose, but they happen to be
Right on the ground plane, which is, you know?
So you end up with with two things that are at the same Z and the
z-buffer can't resolve to things that are slightly off like that.
So what we want to do if you want to fix that, for some reason which
like I said, is not really important at this part point.
But if you take a look at the draw hip points thing here, when we're
doing this, I all you would need to do is make sure that they had some
Z to lift them up off the ground.
It's probably all you would really need to do.
Oh, so I don't know like a probably that would be sufficient.
Right?
So that's that's all that.
That's just the very traditional Z.
Fighting the same kind that you would.
See anywhere.
That's that's all that is.
Radovic or radovcich.
I don't know how you pronounce that off topic.
Is it normal for a trivial code change to lead to a 250 MB difference.
File is this an optimization mips architecture weirdness?
I guess I'm going to have to stop you right there.
And ask, are you saying that your executable is a quarter of a
gigabyte large?
And not just that it's a quarter of a gigabyte large.
But that it's actually a quarter of a gigabyte different in size than
it was previously, who knows how a big it actually is but at least a
quarter of a gigabyte.
Is that actual actually, what you were asking that sounds terrifying?
Brooke tag asked, what do you want to fit in the camera view, the
whole room or some amount of tiles?
So, camera movement per room is needed.
Again, I don't care yet.
I, I don't have any particular Desires in that area.
I just want to make sure
I just want to make sure that we support whatever we want.
So it should be easy to make the camera code do either is I guess what
I would say,
In the push bitmap function of the handmade render group.
You have a shadowed V4 parameter color.
That is masked by the youth.
You color compiles as a warning, which is an error in vs 2015.
Yeah.
If you want me to get rid of that for you, I can what function you
talking about.
Push bitmap
so, you're talking about this,
Well, yeah, but that's inside a new scope.
Why is it complaining about that?
That's not an error.
That's that's just anytime you open a scope.
You're allowed to override variables, that's just kind of dumb.
I mean, I'll change that, but I don't, I would just turn off that
warning because that's not a, I'm not super into that.
But here, if it helps.
That should get rid of that for you.
The other thing there was another thing that I remember recently that
we could take care of if we're doing that right now.
When building the platform, where you see, complains about the use of
push set up in handy, right?
- eh, push it up, is to find anywhere to CBP, but not included in the
platform layer.
And so what we need to do there is go, I think it's the problem is,
it's up here, right?
Yeah, this is transient cliprect that's doing that push setup.
So I suspect what we should probably do.
I don't know if we can do this or not, but let's
Try it.
Anyway, if I move this down here, what happens, okay, so I'm going to
move that into here and hopefully that solves the problem.
I moved push setups.
Usage into under group.
Hopefully, that will fix Kim's issue there.
She also might today.
All right.
Team R&B does the profiler still work?
If not what is a quick overview of the work?
That is needed to get it working again.
And was it purely a display issue that we could not see it?
Yes, that is.
That is correct.
So,
if you take a look at
It is display.
If you take a look at the profile here.
What's happening is this?
We we don't really use cliprect very often they're mostly used here.
But what you can sort of see, is we have a bunch of like you can even
see the profiler is popping up a tooltip here, right?
But basically, what we have is for one of two possible reasons.
Either a we are because we are drawing this background.
And in the wrong order, the Z buffer is preventing the actual text
from showing up, right?
Is thing.
One thing too, is if the cliprect setting is wrong, then we would have
that as well.
And in fact, that looks, you can see that looks like a cliprect
problem there because hey, that's that's, um,
That's some profile data right there as well.
So I believe the problem at the moment is just that when we're doing
our clip rectangles for whatever reason our clip rectangles when we
updated the renderer to the 3D renderer we are no longer processing
clip, rectangles properly.
So we need to handle those, right?
And there's two places if we wanted to fix them.
I'm not gonna fix them now, but there's two places that we have to
make sure we get bright.
So one of them is like you can see in the debug assume, it's in the
debug you I let me look and see where we're setting it.
So there's one of them.
So here's like some of that profiling stuff, right?
And you've got the clip rect here and it's doing this call with the
backing transform bounds blah blah blah, right.
So when we do that Gap, get cliprect call.
That is something that needs to be done correctly.
So you can see.
And here we have again, cliprect call, that's doing whatever it's
doing here, it's then producing.
Result that has to be used as a clip.
Rect, the problem with this probably at this point, is it probably
needs to get fed through the actual transform.
Right.
We now have that camera transform from set up.
None of this stuff is going through it, right?
So I think that's probably most of it.
You know, just looking at this here.
Yeah, so my guess is right inside the render group, we've got the
render transform, I would probably want and also last setup.
So probably what we want to do is is actually use that last set up.
This thing here probably want to do is use the projection Matrix and
actually do it.
So you probably want the offset and the dimension, right?
I don't know what space.
The dimension is getting passed down by.
That's a good question and we should figure out how we're doing that.
So here we're doing bounds the bounds.
So the
Boundary that it's using is actually going to be in World space.
It looks like it's an XY boundary.
So presumably what you want to do there say like okay, you know, the
Min corner is the offset, the max corner is the offset plus the dim
And then presumably you want to transfer these to, right?
So you want to do something like group last set up Raj times.
So, you want to like push?
The corners of this new clip rectangle through.
We also have an object transform.
So if I remember correctly, the up transformed just has all that has
an is an offset now.
So you'd want to do like offset pee.
And then I think you'd have everything you need because once those go
through the projection Matrix now they're in clip space properly.
So all you would need to do is do a min max
And you'd be done.
The problem is you need to adjust for the window bounds here because
this again once this comes out of here it's going to be in the
negative one to one space and so you need to do
The divide the perspective, divide and then you need to do what, you
know.
Again, we could do.
But then you need to actually adjust it out to the window rectangle.
And so we probably want to actually we probably want a utility
function for this as well but you know that's that's actually known it
since it's screened in here.
So we want to like produce.
We want to put these into two screen spaces so you know probably we
want something like this where we just be able to say, you know,
Cat screen point.
something like that where you'd be able to just pass one of these in
and say, like okay, you know,
Here's the world pee.
We transform it.
And you know do the synthetic divided we then say all right now we
have to transform it to a screen space so we're going to take the the
PX and that's going from negative 1 to 1.
We need to go from 0 to 1 basically, right.
So we need to do like one point 0 plus and we need to do half of it
right because we want the negative one to one map 2021.
We want to add that to the screen dimension
Or rather, we want to multiply that by the screen dimension.
We also have the problem of wanting to be
Centered, it's going negative 1 to 1 which is 0 to 1.
I think that's it, right?
So, it's, it should just be the screen dimension.
X x.
Yeah, I mean, what you're looking at here,
I think.
don't quote me on that because it's probably all wrong, but when you,
after you've got that with, any can just do get screen, Point group
table, transform offset and the max corner is
Group transform.
I'll set plus GM 0.
0 0.
So, something like this is what you're looking for.
And let me see here.
Offset P must have caught.
Yes, that's true.
And this is a transform.
No.
How to do the 4 by 4 here.
Poop.
Although actually do I even need to call transform, does it just do
it?
If I put in a for element one?
They're probably does.
That's probably how I wrote it right.
Yeah.
Scream dim is Undeclared.
That's okay, I just got access it off of the group so that should do
the transfer and map it to the screen.
And these need to be rounded after that.
To force them to integer coordinates.
So that's not going to work because I mean, I just slammed a bunch of
stuff in there and it's going to be wrong but that's roughly what
you're looking at.
So now you got to go to bug that path and and get that, you know, you
can see it's getting closer to working, right?
But it's not quite there and so you just got to look.
Yeah.
And see what's, what's up here?
But that's should be what you need to do.
You do the transform?
Do the synthetic divide?
Then you're in - 121 space.
Did I meant that correctly?
Let's see if I did.
So I have a equation here, right?
Where I am going to pass in and f of x and I want f of x.
To equal something.
We don't see with that is quite yet.
I need f of negative 1 to equal 0.
I need F of 1 to equal the height of the screen or the width of the
screen W.
And so I want this equation to look, you know, it's just going to be
some kind of linear equations so I want it to be like an ax.
Plus be right.
So substituting in there.
I have ax plus b, if f of negative 1,
Is the equals 0.
That means I also equal a or negative a plus B has to equal 0 and F of
1 means that
A plus B has to equal W.
So in this case, I could say, for example, if I just solve this guy
here, what I end up getting is a has to equal be right?
That what that looks like, that's what that looks like to me.
And in this case if I can sub that in then I basically know that W has
to equal to a right or a
Balls with over 2.
So it looks like anyway.
So what the equation would be that does that mapping is just going to
be with over 2x plus with over to, right?
And that does look like it works because it's zero.
It you just get the middle of the screen which is that I want negative
1.
I get zero at positive when I get, right?
So that's, it's all right.
So, let's see if that's what I actually got here or what I was
actually doing.
There's the with over 2.
And so if I wanted to pull this out, I would just get with over 2x
plus 1.
And hey, that's exactly what I get, right.
If I just rearrange these terms,
So, I'm pretty sure that mapping is correct.
That all looks good to me.
So, yeah, there's something more subtle wrong here.
Like I said, I don't know that I super have time to debug it today
because I wasn't that wasn't one of the main things.
We're going to do an episode.
But we do we, you know, once you get a reasonable thing, working here
forgets, Greenpoint,
You should be good to go.
I
guess I don't know what they're doing in terms of Z coordinates that
they're passing in there.
Hopefully they're passing in reasons because but it's worth the
graphic, so it shouldn't matter.
Yeah, so I think that's all reasonable.
The other question that you have to look at two after you can, if you
can verify it, it's pretty easy to test get screen point because you
should be able to just
look at what some scream points end up being equal to
like moving asking about the corners was going to say, is the other
thing you have to do is the clip.
Rex are done with the GL scissor call.
and so, the GL scissor call is going to
You don't care about this.
This is the one care about the GL scissor call is going to be
interpreted.
I want to say relative to the viewport
Or rather that the viewport.
Yeah.
The the scissor and the viewport interact in a weird way as well and
so you'd have to double-check that that's
but that's getting set in a reasonable way to
But I think that should be fine.
I'm not sure where clip scalex and clip scale.
Why are coming from here?
I don't know what this is for.
The width of the drawer region.
Versus the width that the thing is supposed to be.
So that looks like, we're just accommodating for the fact that we
might be drawing.
I don't know why that's there.
I understand why this is here because this is in the case where again
we have, yeah, that rennet are zero, we're not doing this anymore.
Either because we're you know, we have a multi sample buffer so that's
doubly not relevant.
So I do wonder about this stuff because we'd had this in their before
for dealing with clipping rectangles.
When we weren't drawing to particular size, frame buffer, but that's
not what we're doing anymore.
So I feel like those are not relevant super relevant.
They don't have anything to do with this probably but we just we just
see
We have some interesting stuff to look at there.
We should look at this because that's we should look at both of these.
Because we also have this
Is there anything like it leaves?
Previous copy getting listed on there, I guess.
That never gets cleared.
She should also take a look at that.
But again, it doesn't look like we need those cliprect.
It doesn't look like this is relevant anymore because since we have to
render to an off-screen Target now.
We should probably get rid of this.
So yeah, I think again, like I said, Timur and be, that's really what
you need to debug.
If you want the profiler back, the other thing you can do is turn off
the clip.
Rect for, in short order, right?
So like if you really just want it there and you don't want to have to
debug the new render stuff for the clipping code.
What you can do is, you know, I pretty sure that nobody really uses.
Transient cliprect except that a bug system.
So what you can do is just not do it, right?
You could just say
Oops.
Like so and then I the clipping is off and so then, you know, you can
get the print out, just fine.
But it's it's going to, you know, it overflows by why, it doesn't clip
clean to that location.
But yeah.
So, that's what you got to do, if you want that working properly
again.
You probably would also want to go fix the text rendering order, so
that it's easier to read and stuff like that, but that's about it.
Can you click threads on the profile window?
You mean with with the clipping disabled or
Oops.
Is this this?
What we're talking about?
Um, so yeah.
So that's it.
It's just fixing this clipping rectangle, that's it.
All right, I am going to sign off now.
And the mouse over text.
Again, I it works just fine except for the fact that the text draw
order is backwards.
I think a lot of the zebras are.
So I think it's underneath, when you Mouse over, I'm pretty sure
you're always getting
You be pretty sure you're always getting the situation where you draw
them, hover text first, and then back.
So all that stuff had to be cleaned up if for the 3D render in the
future.
All right.
Okay.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for those sort of handmade here at
sort of pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
order the source code or rather, you can pre-order the game which
comes to the source code on handmade hero dot org and play around with
it yourself.
We also have a forum site and go to if you want to ask questions to
patreon page, from us about the video series, the schedule bot that
lets, you know, we're going to be live and episode guide that you can
go to.
if you would like to catch up on old episodes,
that's it for this week.
I'll be back next weekend.
Where we can do some more camera code and get that working a little
more cleanly and maybe add a couple more things like room room to room
movement and zooming to the right level for various rooms or other
things like that we might want to do.
And again that's just to get us in a place where we're comfortable
that the camera is performing reasonably doesn't have to be perfect
shipping quality camera but it has to be relatively close so we know
that that's going.
Okay, that's about it.
Hope you all have a good week of programming and I'll see you on the
internet.
Take it easy, everybody.