Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here on the show.
We go to complete game live on stream.
We are going to do a little bit more debug code today because we did a
bit of it yesterday and we have a little bit more of it to do.
I believe what we wanted to do was to make it so that we could edit
some debug values, which I think we already kind of have the structure
for that in place in the actual debug system itself.
So it's really just a case of going through and cleaning out some
stuff and doing some wiring.
I don't know that we have a whole lot of new code that has to be
written to make that happen.
So that's what I'm doing.
And today is day 2 48.
So, if you're someone who pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
dot-org and you want to follow along with the source code, you want to
start with a 247 source code because day 247 source code is what the,
you know, the code base that I am starting with today.
So when you see me like load files and stuff, that's what I am loading
out of.
All right, so let's go ahead and launch for it here and get ourselves.
Get ourselves into position, get us.
I was into compromising position.
Let's see.
We got our piace file.
And we are building.
There we go.
So if you recall from yesterday, we left it with us.
Being able to Output debug data, but we haven't really done much
beyond that, right?
So we have a course, really long startup times.
Now, which is really unfortunate.
Our startup times opengl on this platform.
Takes a long time to start up, which is kind of, which is too bad.
Not sure there's much, we can do about that.
Although we could, since we don't really know what our final needs are
going to be in terms of texture.
It could be that we can create less context which would help.
Because that's the slow part.
So here, if we take a look at the platform stuff, you can see that we
actually have the the stuff that we wanted to edit, which is inside
this platform, drop down here, you can see, we've got like this block
that we output and we never really did anything for prettily printing
blocks or anything.
But we are out putting the values that we had and what we want to be
able to do is like click on these values, right?
We want to be able to click on these values and have them toggle and
so I need to go into
Code and figure out how to make sure that that works both basically.
Like I said, it's going to be mostly just archaeology because I think
we already pretty much have the code for doing this.
It already exists inside our our system.
All right.
So let's take a look because I think mostly, like I said, this is
going to be a plumbing exercise might be expensive, Plumbing,
exercise.
Like I said, we're trying to finish up that debug system.
So we kind of have a have our work cut out for us because there's a
bunch of stuff in there, and it doesn't quite do yet, what we want to
do.
So here's the debug interface and what we're doing right now is
The debug system works entirely For Better.
Or For Worse is every time a debug call gets made essentially goes
into a giant buffer, so it's just like kind of rolling log of
information.
And you can kind of see here that we can output a bunch of different
pieces of data and they sort of store a type with them that says what
the data actually is.
So at any time when we do this, we get sort of a, you know, we get a
rolling event log.
That has that piece of data in it, but what you will notice, is that,
that data is copied into the event log by value.
So, you can see that it no longer.
It doesn't actually remember where that thing is, right?
It doesn't know if it was going to edit it.
It doesn't have any idea necessarily how to, like, get that value
back.
And so, what we need to do and that's not actually a bad idea, right?
There's two ways to sort of do debug systems like this one is to snap.
Pointer to the thing that and that's a little bit easier to do.
And so, for example, in here, let me look at the win32 file.
Where this is actually happening.
Did you handmade?
That's okay.
If I was to go to debug value, so you can see what's going on here.
Every time through this Loop, we are going to issue one of these debug
value commands once for Global pause and once for Global rendering
type.
Now, the important thing to note here is that we are not starting
The pointers of those, we're only like, pushing their values into the
debug stream, which means it's trivial press to print out what they
are, but we can't actually ever modify them right now.
Like I was saying, one way to make a demon system is to actually use
the pointer here.
So when we call this, we actually record the pointer so that when we
want to edit it we just go back in there and write it.
The reason why we're not going to do that is because if we were to do
that it would mean that we could not ever output debug values that
were transient because once we snap the pointer, that means that we
have to leave that memory round.
Till after the debug systems done with it and our debug system right
now is set up to record frames basically forever.
And so we don't want to have to deal with a situation where we could
be generating tons of debug data and all of a sudden all this memory
that was Associated like, you know, entity structure.
Something that we would have liked to get rid of and not keep around
suddenly have to sit around until the debug systems are them, which
could be never, right?
You know, we got a lot of memories this machine.
We don't really have that much so we don't want to just keep
generating it things out of an item.
So what we'd like to do is only store the parts we actually want,
which in this case is just maybe an inch or whatever like this.
So we don't necessarily want to snap a pointer and have to make sure
that the whole memory blocks are pieces of things are retained.
Now, what that means is that we need some other mechanism.
If we're not going to go the point around, we need some other
mechanism of doing the editing and we kind of built in a mechanism
exactly like that which was this debug ID thing.
So this debug ID thing was a way of
of saying, hey,
I'm going to tell you that there's this kind of permanent identifier,
you can use to know what I'm talking about.
Civic block.
So that later, when I come back round, when I do these debug values,
if you have done edits to them I could pick up those edits now
Right?
And so we kind of already put ourselves in a position to we set
ourselves up for success.
As I sometimes like to say, we are in a position to do that now
because we have a coherent explanation of how that might work, but
it's not trivial but, you know, we have a common explanation.
And so, if I remember correctly, we had something where we could get
data out of this thing and this is why it's going to be archaeology.
Because I just don't
Remember everything about how that actually works, but I believe we
had something like that.
I don't know.
That was actually exposed here in the interface, so it may have to be
pulled out a little bit more, but we'll take a look.
So here's where these things sort of get set up.
Debugging issue, lies value is no longer a relevant thing.
I don't believe, we don't actually ever use that anymore if I'm not
mistaken and you know what, we don't need this stuff anymore.
Either, write these things are that so deep
Bug initialize value.
I think we can also get rid of that guy.
So I'm going to I'm going to prune this stuff first because I don't
think this stuff is relevant anymore.
So let's see here.
Debug initialize value.
That was for if we wanted this to devant to define the values itself,
right?
So we can get rid of that, no longer necessary.
So what we need to do is we need that that function, that looks things
up.
And like I said, I don't see it there.
So I'm going to take a look and see if it's if we still have it, I
think we might but we'll find out.
So, here we go.
We've got, we've got our debug code.
I'm just scanning through it to look to look to see if I can see it.
We don't need right handmade config anymore because we decided that
that's not going to happen, right?
So, this is this guy can go as well.
You can just be can be eliminated.
Oops, we've got this on it.
I need to work on my editing commands.
Something that I really need to do.
I need to upgrade like how my edit commands work.
Now that I do this modal thing, because it means that there's a bunch
of things that I do.
They're stupid like, what you want it to do, is you always want to
clean up the white space for you.
Like I have a specific way.
My code is already set up.
And so, for example, in this circumstance, if I was going to do
something, like, I'm going to paste something in here, you know?
Like, I'm going to paste something.
I'm trying to think of what the, the right example is, but if I'm
going to pay something, I always want a space after the comma.
Ah, and so I get in these situations where I'm in the mode and I do
the paste operation, probably that was a bad idea.
Like let's say, I grab this, I do the paste operation and now it's
Hard for me to fix up the spacing for no reason.
Like all I should really have to do is do that and everything should
be fine because I just need the syntax but unfortunately, I have to do
like a bunch of stuff here, where I do this, and then switch.
Back to this mode, then switch into this mode, hit the space, right?
And so, I feel like if I just made some smart stuff, it could be a lot
easier but that's neither here.
Nor there.
That's just notes.
Now, that now that I have for coder and I can program it and see
there's all these things that I couldn't like interested in going to
Do because I could never programme Lis well enough.
I don't think to do a lot of the stuff I would have wanted to do but
see I could, you know, I could make some pretty good stuff.
So
It's kind of on the table.
Thank you, Alan, for that anyway.
So here we are again in the debug code, I'm just looking to see cuz I
thought we had some stuff that could do those look-ups for us or
something, similar to that.
So, here is an example right here, get our create debug view for, and
you can see that, you know, it's passing a debug ID, and it's looking
to Hash that value, right?
And when it hatches that value, it creates this debug view thing.
And the debug View
Is, you know, one of those like, like this drop-down things, it stores
that state.
So, what that means is that we already have a way of saying, oh,
there's a way to, like, look up the debug view, for whatever this ID
happened to be.
So, that's thing number one, and we'll look, we'll sort of look at
that in a second here.
And then I think, once we're in there, there should be a way to, to,
like, sort of get things by hierarchical name because we're sorting.
Those things into a hierarchy that kind of has to work right
otherwise, we wouldn't be able to do that.
So we know that that also is there.
Okay?
So here is an example.
Right here is a variable group thing that creates Veracruz find name
and you can, it can create things.
It can it can sort of access things with names and stuff like that.
So we've got to sort of things here but that one that one is really
more.
that was really more, I think for
I think that we sort of had these as two separate systems, right?
One was for creating sort of a hierarchical menu of stuff and one was
for doing the output in the other way.
And so I kind of want to smush them down, right?
I want to smash them into into one and so I think what I might want to
do is just sort of again, like
What I might want to do here is say, okay, if I do this, debug begin
data, Block B.
And then I do this this, you know, this stuff here where I've got the
debug pointer ID thing here.
What I want to do, I think is sort of take this code that used to be
sort of a separate system and sort of make this code work.
Inside these data blocks.
So, basically, the application is responsible for being able to being
able to produce
Some sort of an identifier that can tell you that you're inside a data
block.
And then in there, everything else is just sort of done by name inside
the data block.
So it can like go and do lookups there.
And it could find out like what the latest state would be for that
thing or stuff like that.
I think that's where I want to go with this because, like I said, I
kind of want this to sort of collapse down to something a little bit
more manageable, and it was just a little too sprawling before for our
purposes and a little bit, you know, like I said, I like
Code by exploration, which means you take some time to go figure out
you know to play with some things and see what happens.
But at the end you don't want to just like leave it that way you want
to you know start condensing it and figuring out what you actually
needed and then make that stuff work.
Well otherwise you just end up with this giant sprawl that, you know,
is tons of code.
You baby don't want or that isn't working particular efficiently or
who knows what else?
So, I think that's where I'd like to go with this and I think that's a
reasonable way to approach this problem.
Potentially what I want to look at first before I make that decision
though, is we are using in some other places we are using debug values
in some slightly different ways we are doing like, ifs on those
values.
So for example, you know, inside the renderer, I guess we are using
some things like yeah, like Global renderer show, lighting samples.
So the way we're doing those right now is we're just placing them as
Global's.
I don't think there's anything wrong with that though.
So I think what we would do is we just have a place where there was a
data block that out, put those things and off you go.
So the only thing that makes me a little bit nervous about this.
Right is the whole the dynamic code reloading.
Like normally, if we just want to create some kind of an ID here,
It's pretty trivial.
In fact we could just use a counter variable and the file in line.
You know.
We could just use the file on a counter and that could be sufficient
to create our debug ID, right?
Because it's a unique place in the code.
So we would have the ability to create ones that were based on
locations in the code as well as ones that weren't the problem is when
we do Dynamic code reloading, those things will move potentially,
right?
So we're in the middle of the running.
Game.
We reload the code and we really need like some kind of a grid, right?
We need something here that's like a grid that we can actually hold
onto.
And I'll be honest, as I'm saying that right now, I'm kind of
wondering.
if we would just use a quid because we could just
Rate, a random 64-bit value.
And that would work.
You know, I hadn't really considered that before.
I had not really considered that before.
But that would totally be fine.
For example and and I'm like this is a very strange thing, but I'm
just going to point it out.
So for example,
if we just took this table and every time we wanted a new one of
these, we just grabbed the, you know, one of these guys out of here,
that would be that
I've never thought of doing that before, I'm not sure why.
Because then, if you just throw that into that line of code and you
just always, you know, as that coat piece of code moves around, it's
always uniquely identified.
What a strange idea.
I'm not sure how I feel about that.
It doesn't seem like, it's that different, from maintaining an h-file
where you would, just put the, the squids like we were doing before.
And it's certainly not as good as some kind of thing.
Where we would met a code, where we could just know that it would,
they would all be extracted and matched by name in some way.
Hmm.
Well, to be honest, I guess now I think about it, I don't think that's
really necessary because now that I think about it, that may be going
a little bit overboard because really, since we know that we want
these things to be displayed to the user, they would need unique names
which means that when we call begin data, block, whatever this string
is here, that could actually be used as the ID if we wanted to write.
So we could to choose to just hash that string, which is something
that we sort of were talking.
That doing before.
So since this is 0, this is not a performance thing, that's not
performance critical.
This is not something that's used in.
This is used to output.
Table of values is not used in like site inside the loop or something
weird.
Like that, where we would care about the timing.
I guess probably what I would say is the most logical thing to do is
just to actually hash the string there because we know that string is
essentially also a
Is also going to be unique.
So that seems like an interesting idea.
I think that's what I would like to try.
So basically that would involve and I think we already do a little bit
of that, right?
Let's see.
So it looks like we have a grid That's Unique, file counter string and
unique file.
Counter string is is unique, applying this thing based on
Its location.
And I don't know that that we really care about that too much, right?
Like I said before, that's not particularly useful.
So,
So yeah sorry I'm just trying to think this through to see exactly
what I want because interesting decision.
So I think what I specifically want there is when I do a begin data
block, if I have this ID and you can see that you know, I do the
record debug event and I put the ID in there if I perhaps do not
supply and ID.
So there is no actual ID given to this thing.
Whatever it is.
then that to me suggest, you know,
That I could just leave off the ID, and it would use the string.
So, in cases, where I'm not trying to associate this, with some actual
data that I have, that's real, that seems like a reasonable way to go,
I don't know.
So that that seems reasonable to me.
Now, this one in particular, doesn't matter because this one actually
is in the platform layer and cannot be dynamically reloaded.
And it's possible that maybe we never really need to fight that
because it may be that we always actually have a pointer.
We can use
So maybe even now that I'm thinking about it more, maybe we don't even
care literally at all.
So yeah, but anyway, I just wanted to think that through.
So what we would do in the case where, if we want to make it so that
we're not going to pass any kind of debug ID here, right at all.
In that case all we would do is we would just use this string I think
and we would snap an ID for that string.
Like we'd actually hash that string and and remember
Idea of it that seems like the smartest thing to do.
Alright, so back to the task at hand, here we are in
In our debug value thing, we're going to be outputting this Global.
Pause on-site inside this platform controls bit here.
And like I said, what we want to do is start to make this.
Have what?
When we're out putting those debug blocks, we want to start making
this have the overall structure of the of the stuff that was doing
this.
Get group for hierarchical name, right?
That was doing this sort of stuff.
Now, the problem with this stuff is that this was made for building
things that are stationary.
and I don't know that we necessarily want that specifically, but I
think
For the most part we probably do.
Meaning there are certain circumstances where maybe we want data, that
would be there on some frames and not be there another frames.
Maybe we would just gray that out but I think we probably want to
create the hierarchical structure permanently anyway as if it was
going through this thing.
And so I think
Just my assumption, but I think what we do want to do is just take
this hierarchical stuff here.
and I think we want to just bring it up above and actually use it
specifically for the
For the, for the outputting of the, of the debug blocks.
That's what I think we actually want to do.
So, let's give that a try.
Let's see where those debug block things were happening.
Right here is our see here, debug
Let's see here.
So here's where our debug block stuff is happening.
So I'm going to just, let me just put that in drop that in here for
now.
And we'll get rid of right hand.
Make config because that doesn't happen anymore.
What is this right here and interact?
Okay, we don't care about that.
So when we create one of these blocks, right, we sort of see these
blocks come in as we go.
And I guess what we want to do, as we see a block come in and we want
to sort
Put that into the place where it was existing before.
So I want to sort of add here, where is it?
I want
at element group.
I think this is what we're talking about here, right?
So here you can see it.
Looking up to see this, get element from event if you can see what's
going on.
And then it will sort of push the thing in it'll sort of push it on
the stack and use it.
So this get element from event is the thing that does the Coalition.
You can see it happening here.
And so, what I want to do is I want that to happen, I guess, for
everything that we might be doing now.
It's not immediately clear to me, when we actually do the debug block
stuff, because here is the the begin block.
End block stuff.
Right when we do begin, block, and end block when we come through
here,
I don't actually know.
Oh, sorry data block is long?
Actually about I don't actually know, since any time we come through
here.
We've already gotten a debug element which means it already should
have taken its name and done, you know, and done this to it.
So I feel like that should have meant unless I'm missing something
that we should have actually had those things hierarchy, placed
properly, with the underscores parsed out of them.
But it doesn't seem like that's what actually happened.
You know what I mean?
Like, so I feel like I'm missing something about how we were doing,
what we were doing, because it just feels like, it feels like
something is a little out of place.
Maybe I'm forgetting.
But my recollection was that like?
So, for example, platform underscore controls, right platform
underscore controls would have been parsed into platform and then
controls underneath it and I guess that's not what actually
How it actually works.
I guess it did parse out the platform part.
So now that I think about it is doing the first part of that plan
parsing, and I guess what happens is, when it gets to a debug block,
it doesn't print the element name.
It prints, the debug block name, that might be the case, but let's
see.
So let's actually find out.
So it looks like it's actually already doing what I wanted it to do
for the most part.
And so, let's take a look at what's actually going on there.
Because I think, I think this is actually in pretty good shape.
And like I said, this is mostly archaeology because I think
Have most of the code, we actually need.
We just have to remember how it works and then sort of tweak it around
a little bit.
So if that's the case inside here, where we, where we do the opened it
about closed 8:00.
When we're running through here.
The events that we get are presumably going to be debug value events,
right?
Because inside the interface code if you remember the stuff we were
just looking at this debug value set event data.
So what actually happens here is we call record debug event with debug
type unknown and then we call debug value set event.
And that sets, the type to whatever the thing was going to be
whatever.
The actual thing we want to record was
And so if we come through here, that's gonna fall into this case here
which puts things inside these these data blocks, right?
And it calls, you know, this storage element has been called.
So in theory, that parsing should have occurred, right?
So I want to just take a look, I think the easiest way for me to
understand what I was doing at that time.
It's just a look in the debugger for that because I kind of want to
see what happens there.
So that's Kool-Aid, debug events.
Because I want to understand a little bit better.
Why the parsing isn't doing what I would have expected it to do.
Of course, it helps.
if I actually set a breakpoint,
Cool 8, debug records.
Better.
So in here, I'm going to just start taking a look at some of these
things as they come in, just so I know what's happening.
Okay, so let's see, we've got a grid, it's coming in from debug
interface, study H, where's the like filing line and or is that just
what this is?
I guess we don't actually know the file online information of this or
do we debug event?
Does not have one of those.
Let's see here and what is the element that it got?
Let's see it, God.
I'll begin block.
To begin blocks.
Oh, these are those are those are not the kind of blocks amount that
I'm going to skip right to here.
So let's take a look at what the event is in this case.
So the event in this place is the global pause.
So that's good.
This is the one I want to look at.
And so this is going to store this guy.
Let's see here.
So there is a first did lock.
So it's going to go ahead and
It's going to go ahead and use inside the state of block.
It's going to use the storage of that.
It's going to put it underneath that data block, which we open, which
is what we want, because that's the data block, that's for the
controls.
So when we call store event,
Looks like that.
Just goes ahead and puts it in there, which is pretty straightforward
and yeah, nothing else to it.
So that stores the data from the particular frame of that we have.
And so I guess really at that point, it all came through get element
from event and and that was it, so,
And what does it do with the event information at that point when it
gets back the element it actually stores that element, right?
Yeah.
Okay, so no, it doesn't.
Hmm.
Okay.
So I guess
I guess that's a little confusing.
I feel like this code because it went through so many iterations is
sort of like unnecessarily obtuse, right?
Because there's just a lot of stuff going on here that maybe doesn't
necessarily need to.
Now the store event stuff makes sense because you can see that what we
need is we need a way of recording information that never runs out of
space.
So the way that this works is it just goes well if I don't have room
to store the value of this variable that's
Really a big deal.
All I really have to do is
overwrite some old thing, so that's totally fine.
And that seems reasonable.
So that store event thing makes sense.
What doesn't super make sense is the element part?
Because the debug elements, I don't really understand exactly this
part here, where like it gets stored underneath the block that it was
in, which is fine, but that doesn't seem to
That wouldn't do sort of that parsing into the hierarchical stuff so I
guess we just count on the listing later to do that.
I don't super understand though because if we are calling get element
from event here, doesn't that mean that we already gave this thing?
Okay, I see.
So we only parse out the enough to make the parent.
So we just look at whatever its immediate parent was, which I suppose
makes sense, right?
And then then we would just say where we're going to put it in that
group.
Try to decide whether I'm okay with that or not.
Yeah.
Yeah, so then I assume most of what we're getting in terms of how
things are printed out, then actually has to do with when we sort of
call this main menu situation, right?
Because then we come down, we come into that.
And we're doing sort of are walking here of the stacks and we look to
see what we've got in here.
And we call debug draw element and presumably.
So what's
Opening as we're getting to.
Here, when we're going to draw this data block, and we Loop through
these things and we print them out, right?
So that's presumably, whoa.
So, we actually Loop through to find the oldest event every time.
That seems like a bad idea.
Debug type open data block.
When we call debug draw element, we then look to see what the oldest
one is.
Yeah, that doesn't look super sustainable to me.
I mean, I suppose it's fine if you cap the total number of frames that
goes back but you can see why this is kind of not particularly great.
Because what
Happened.
Here is as we store more events this will continue to get older and
older.
This will get longer and longer that traversal and you'll spend all
your time sitting in these Loops doing nothing.
You know I'm saying, and that's not particularly useful for anybody.
So that seems like a really bad idea to say the least.
So I think we want to kind of clean this up, right?
Yeah, so I think what we're going to have to do
Is we're going to have to clean up the way that we sort of manage
these things, and make something a little bit more, make something a
little bit more clean, for building a building that, and also storing
it how we're thinking about storing it.
So, I feel like the store event stuff is probably where we want to
start and I feel like we want to clean that up a little bit.
So when we're calling the store event stuff,
I think that's going to stay and I think this get element from event
B.
This that's going to not, not probably stay.
I'm assuming
So, we'll see.
But anyway, so when restoring an event, and we're storing it inside an
element here.
The element part is just for keeping things together with stuff that
we care about.
So this stuff here, where we where we sort of look for things to free,
and then we store them, this part seems reasonable because it means we
can take as many events as we want and just sort of store them.
And we know that they'll just grow and grow and grow until we run out
of space and Willie told frames that seems like the right thing to do.
What didn't seem so right to me, is the fact that we seem to be the
way that we're storing.
Multiple events of the same kind, is by that linked list and we don't
have any real way of of, navigating that particularly well, right?
So I'm not sure what the best thing to do here would be.
It seems like maybe a better you know this maybe is trying to be too
clever because this is not going to be able to kind of just jump
around inside wherever that list is where as if this was just a fixed
size thing where we just said oh you know, we're going to store the
past 200 of these are the past thousand of these.
It would have just been an array, right?
And that makes it
Easier to do stuff, like, say I wanted, you know, Loop over them and
and talk about the, you know, talk about the first one, the last one,
the nth go back to frame X and see it.
So I
I'm a little torn on that.
You know.
A little torn.
I wonder if it wouldn't make much, wouldn't make more sense to just
say, all right, in this case, where we're going to store an event
maybe that event
just gets inserted into a slot.
And I feel like we've played with this before and we decide to do this
but I think maybe I don't know how smart that was of a decision,
right.
I feel like that may not have been such a good idea, because we're
kind of going to end up with a standing structure that just has all
the stuff in it that we ever, you know, that has like a sort of
standing debug view, sort of thing to it.
And I feel like that we want that too.
Have an own frame look back.
That you can just quickly access, right?
And I just worry about, you know,
I worry about how to manage it if we don't.
I like the fact that it can just sort of take reclaim memory as it
needs it, but I just worry that the linked list is going to be a
problem there.
You know what I mean?
I mean hopefully that it's relatively clear.
Why that why that's a little troubling.
And I know we played around with this a bunch before and this is
definitely the only I would say logical solution to
To having it always reclaim.
And I mean another thing we could do is say we could just store a
pointer to the most recent or a cursor that says, here's where we're
viewing in that can move forward and backward or something, but I
don't know, I just, I really just don't know.
You can't have all the things all the time.
Unfortunately, I wish you could but of course you can't and
It even looks like here.
You can see that we were storing the most recent event which is the
one that we write.
And in fact, I guess I don't know why when we output that open block,
I'm not sure, exactly why we even wanted to do it that way that we did
it.
Kind of curious.
So we start at the oldest event, we go through, I guess it's because
there's events in there in the events that are in.
There are like open data block.
Here are some values, close data block.
I see.
So really the main change.
We need to make
Just for starters is that we should no longer be storing data, blocks
as data blocks, probably, what we actually wanted to do is make that
be part of a standing structure.
Now, I can see why we didn't do that.
We didn't do that because
we wanted to be able to Output like multiple, like if we had multiple
entities selected, maybe wanted to Output multiple entities, but I
think the UI for that still probably wants to be
Constructed, as a standing set.
you know, that can be looked into and then you would just have like a
next and previous on it or something like that, where you could move
through it, but I don't think you would so much want to have
It like this where it's a stream that has to kind of be parsed, right?
Yeah.
I think that's what makes the most sense to me.
So, what I would say is open data block as a debug type and I'm
interested to know to about the debug type sir.
So here they are, right?
Open data block as a debug type is really not something that I think I
want to store in this way.
That this is stuff that we actually print out, right?
So when we come through these debug elements,
And we're taking a look at these.
Don't really know why we're checking the oldest element here by the
way, but apparently we are
You think we'd check the most recent one, wouldn't you?
That seems like the most logical.
But anyway, so checking the oldest element like we switch on this.
And so, depending on what it actually is, that were outputting there
Oh, this could be kind of cool.
Alright, so I'm sorry it takes so long but we parsing all this back
into my head and deciding what to do with.
It is takes a little bit of time.
So I think this is this is you know, we were maybe a little misguided
men were doing it before because again we were tired of trying things
we didn't necessarily know exactly what we wanted to have happen.
So I think in this particular case we sort of have a situation where
maybe we were we were trying to do a little bit too much in this place
and not really maybe thinking through what would be a good.
Sweet spot.
So what we were doing here when we got an open data block, close data
block pair and we streams of into it is we just kind of stuffed all
that into a big old stream.
And if we had multiple data blocks, that came through the same ID,
they all just kind of got stuffed on there as a stream.
And I think we don't really want that to happen.
I think what we would rather have happen is just treat that as
multiple frames basically, only, they're not actually multiple frames,
right?
So I think what we want to do is still consider values to have
You know, ranges.
And if we need to special case the fact that some values occur more
often than others, you know, maybe can occur several times a frame,
maybe treat that as like, a sort of a separate thing.
so I want to just, I feel like that's, you know, maybe how we want to
approach this and so that this, when we're doing, you know, this stuff
here, we're printing things out, I think what we would want to do is
make it so that
This stuff is not really stored this way and doesn't, you know,
doesn't work quite like this.
Now, what?
I don't know.
It looks like the way this was working.
Is it just says like okay I want to I want to scan for words to find
the last open block.
And then I'm going to just print out one blocks worth of data.
I think what I'm trying to say here is this should no longer really be
something that happens compartmentalize that way.
I don't think I don't know that we really want that to happen, right?
Because as long as that happens, then we won't be going through the
central system for parsing or any of that stuff and
They're more like as data.
If data isn't display, isn't present on a particular block, the block
will like the debug display would like jump in size and do weird stuff
like this where I'm not really sure that's how we want it to work.
I mean, maybe we do, but that just seems a little bit, not what we
maybe would want.
It's hard to say.
I'm spending extra time thinking about this because I'm assuming that
we were smart in the past, right?
And I don't want to necessarily dismiss what we did.
So I'm trying to think of maybe other Arguments for why I went might
want to keep it this way.
So yeah.
So since this is calling debug draw event, by the way, when we kind of
look in here and we do this default, if we didn't want the clothes
block, I mean, I'm just so now I'm starting to pick up like little
things and I'm just going to like do a little playing around with it
so I can see what I actually think.
So, you know, this end data block, I don't obviously would never want
to print that out.
So presumably if we didn't want to print that out.
Oops.
Casey, and his doesn't really know how to do modal editing very well.
We have 15 minutes left on the clock by the way.
So I'm not going to stop quite yet.
So in here if we were to say we had an open data block,
Or here where we say, we have a closed beta block.
Then I believe that would be sufficient for me to do.
Essentially, what I wanted to do, which was to prevent those from
getting printed out, maybe in the same ways that were happening
before.
So for example, for open data block, I could do this right, do me.
I could do this.
Think for coders indentation is very unhappy right now.
so I could do this and
I don't really know, I guess.
I don't really want it to do debug event to text, to be honest.
Although I guess debug varda text, maybe I do sort of want to do that.
Here is the the code for placing this interaction and this would be
essentially a collapse expand, kind of interaction, I guess.
So what kind of leave that for now?
What I don't know is when we do sort of our, when we do our
indentation, I feel like we are our layouts.
Direct knows how to do indentation which means that we could easily
make our data blocks, be indented as well, right?
Because I think.
So if we do open data block here or well, I guess, debug drumming men.
You should have that in it.
So when we do our
Backed up stuff.
You can kind of see here that we should have a thing that allows us to
sort of indent or not indent and so
Where do we draw our children?
Oh, this is an inorder Loop.
So this isn't even recursive so we don't require us.
We just kind of call straight through, so that's kind of crazy.
But anyway, when we come through here, there should be a way for us to
draw our children, indented or not indented.
So when we do, let's see,
when we do depth,
I guess it's just this, that's it, right?
So the layout depth gets incremented or decremented so if we wanted to
we can push these people sort of in and out as we go through.
So for example in here we could say that like everyone who's
underneath this guy,
Gets incremented.
And everyone who's underneath this guy, the opposite is true.
So yeah.
So that is more what we want, right?
That allows us to put things underneath in the indentation area where
we wanted and presumably that works regardless of the situation.
So yeah that's that's all good there.
And what we would expect.
so I think mostly the question I have then is just yeah, I mean, I
guess maybe I just don't know, maybe my concern isn't that warranted
but
Well, let's just keep going with this for now.
So if I want to do that and I want to make this collapsible, then I
would need a way to get a debug view for this thing, right?
I would need a way to find out sort of like yeah when we do debug draw
element, you can see that we do this thing.
Get her, or, or create debug before, for whatever the thing is that
we're printing out.
And when we, when we do a data block, we don't ever actually
We don't ever actually do any of that stuff for any of these guys
inside.
Debug draw event and I'm not really sure why we decided to do it in a
tooth tear in a two-tiered way that way, but either way.
Oh, I guess we do have you here as well.
So, since we have a view for open data block, I assume that that just
means that we could, if we wanted to do the exact same sort of expand
and collapse Behavior as we were doing for the other stuff, right?
So,
Inside debug dropping menu, where we have the ability to sort of do
this toggle interaction in theory.
We could just make that also happen for open data blocks.
What seems like what we want.
So if we want to do that for open data blocks, we would need to do
sort of the default interaction stuff, right?
We would need to have whatever the item interaction for that was going
to be.
And I guess, in this case, we do an event interaction, that's an auto
modify variable, we don't actually want that to be the case for open
data block, what we want to do instead is say that the item
interaction for this is going to be a toggle expansion.
So what I also don't know is when we do get a, create a debug view
for, oops, that's no good.
Yeah, for create a bogey for.
I don't know how he knows what kind of debug view information.
It's going to actually store.
I'm assuming it's go ahead and
I thought I do not have that bound.
I guess, I don't.
very confused right now, that know,
That know.
Huh.
That's weird because X is supposed to do something that is not doing.
I wonder if my for coder, config is busted.
It might be my take a quick look.
so, if I look for,
Corresponding.
So, KC chorus, find corresponding file.
And Casey open file your window.
Yeah.
So that's not what that's supposed to be.
That's supposed to be fine, corresponding file, other window and so I
have to fix that.
All right, well, that's a to do.
Anyway, so what I wanted to find out here and so I guess what I'll do
is I'll switch to this again.
Handmade H manually.
What?
I'm not sure about is in debug view, like, which one it is going to be
inline block, or, or collapsible to be honest.
I'm not sure.
We don't want to just fat in this up and put all that stuff in there.
Because why not?
But who knows.
So anyway,
Either way, we would have that collapsible.
And so we could just make it so that whether or not we show what's
under the collapsible is actually just used by by the system, right?
So I could make it so that when we do that, let's see.
So we got bitmap, ID close, datablock opened, do Mi.
So when we do open data block week, when we do that printout, we could
make it expand or collapse based on that.
Now, the problem is, we actually want to do it here to be.
Just so really, I suppose the proper place to do this stuff is to say
you wouldn't ever really do this.
You would probably just do it out here.
When, you know, you've got an open data block, before you draw any of
these events, you do this stuff, you know what I'm saying?
And
The layout depth increment decrement stuff.
Same way.
So in here, where we do open data, block print this out before we're
going to
Do any of these guys here?
We are I guess really we're really brutalizing for coders inventor.
It is not happy right now.
So inside here right I guess the item interaction has not been created
yet so I would create that that interaction myself right because it's
getting created up here one of these one of these guys.
So yeah, I'm going to create whatever the interaction is that I wanted
this guy to have
And that's the toggle.
I'm going to go through here and do the printout, I'm and all that
stuff.
And then what I want to do is if it's not collapsed then I would do
this stuff but if it is collapsed that I'm not going to do any of that
at all.
It's we're not going to look through any of its events or print out
any of that stuff that seems
That seems fair, right?
So in this case, do we ever get a view for these guys?
We do.
So I can look to see if the views the collapsible part of the view is
going to be expanded.
Always, I guess.
Not really sure.
It's a good question.
And then what's the ID is just debug ID here?
I guess.
And let's see.
So we got d by D.
We have some event that we're going to use here.
So, debug event to text the event that we actually want is the, the
one that we were going to draw.
So it's the last open block, is the actual one.
So I believe it's last open.
Block is the one we wanted to actually make
Store, debug event.
If that's loops.
So yes, that's true.
I agree with you mr.
Compiler.
It's actually last open block event.
Although, it's winter.
we then have debug text out at
Connect apartment 3, and I agree with that as well.
Let's see, one, two, three,
Well, that's actually the to so it's actually the item.
Wait what?
Oh, we're looking at item Claire's under code in a fire.
Okay.
Well I don't really know what the item color should be, to be honest
with you.
I guess we want to do the same stuff here.
I'm not sure, that's a good question.
So I want to know whether or not this item color is hot or not and
then do what it's going to do.
View is Undeclared identifier.
That's because it actually gently got lower case for some reason.
so, in theory,
Yeah, so actually, this thing is kind of Handy.
I like how this is working.
I think there's just a little bit too much code in there.
We probably need a little bit more utility functions because it's just
a lot of cut and paste that has to happen there, but otherwise that
actually works relatively well.
So, that's kind of nice actually.
And similarly, I guess now that I think about it,
So we also know that the reason that we can't edit these is just, I
guess we would actually have been able to edit those values.
If we had ways of editing integers, which we don't get.
All right, so maybe there's really not that much stuff to actually do
in the debug
We just need to clean up some of this code and maybe it's actually
okay because that actually just does what we want.
Pretty much straight up straight away, right?
I mean,
pretty much does what I wanted to do and so we just need to make some
interactions for these guys and then we'd be done.
Also the way this is being printed out is dumb and I don't know why
it's being printed out that way but I don't want it to be printed out
that way.
So I think we would also want to make a thing over here that would
chop off.
That would find the last underscore there.
You know I'm saying?
So yeah.
Yeah.
Not 100% certain how I would want to do that.
I mean the most trivial way to do it, I suppose is to say, you know,
when we take the event name, there's a thing that's like
In our ridiculous set of flags that we have here.
we could do a thing which just goes ahead and
and truncates.
So in add name, which is this, for example,
We could just scan for the last underscore.
So, you know, we could we could totally cheese this if you wanted to
and say, Z budvar to text start at last underscore, or something like
that and then we could just say, oh, all right,
Batman value.
Is actually not we're going to use directly.
We're just going to say that while or four star scan equals use name.
Star scan.
Scan.
And then what we'll do is say that use name equal scan if it
Equals underscore.
And also I suppose and it's not a trailing underscore.
So if it equals underscore and you know the thing after it
Is.
Not equal to 0.
So it has to not be the last character in the string.
Then will allow it to use that as the name.
So in that event, it will update the name and then we should
Able to pass that and have that work?
Where are we?
Where are we people?
That was in debug draw bent.
There.
Yeah, so when I pass these things,
It's past that, I don't know why pretty bulls and stuff is in there
because obviously that doesn't need to happen.
We cut and pasted that but doesn't actually need to occur at all.
But that's all we really need and then we just have to add it to our
list of folks that you can do here.
So like start it lasts underscores now with thing and that I think
would make it so that we would actually have everything but the
interaction.
Yeah.
Well still prints that so that was right but it's actually got a value
on there.
I guess I'm telling it to print out a value and its value is just its
name so I'm not sure how to actually say don't print the value.
That looks like we didn't actually have one of those.
Which that would be nice as well.
so in here this part, this should be if flags and
Include her.
Add value.
Right?
Because they're should.
If you have ad name, you should also specify add value.
I feel like that's kind of how that should go.
I mean, I could preserve the current way of working by making it so
that it was don't add value and do a not.
But that doesn't seem like a very good idea.
So I'm going to just look for everywhere.
We use debug bar to text at the moment.
And I'm just going to add the value part to it.
That's the one where we don't actually want it.
And that's it.
All right.
So, that seems reasonable.
And that would allow us to Output all of our control variables now.
So, for example, inside handmade dot CPP, if we wanted to, you know,
at the top of this thing, we could just go ahead and put all that
stuff in there.
And so, you know, I don't know something like
where we do this, we can just put in
Everything from here.
Can just be added.
And so this would just be begin or debugging data block.
And then these would just be debug value.
Oops.
and,
And we can make these a little bit more.
We can make these a little bit more organized to if you want to but we
don't have to at the moment anyway.
So I think inside begin data block, I guess the ID here is going to be
exactly the same sort of trick that we did before.
But like I said, it's it's it's got the live coding stuff and we're
going to have to start thinking about that a little bit more carefully
when we actually do this, this is just going to be, I guess, like I do
just game for now.
Debug pointer ID as long as the points into something in our memory.
That's fine.
So, what we can do here, for example, is we could just use the root
pointer for the, for the memory, for our game memory would be fine.
Because we know that.
So we stable.
So if I come through here, now, I should see those values show up in
here, if that makes sense.
So, there you go.
Yeah.
So interesting, so it actually is still creating just like I remember
I was asking, does it still create that hierarchy?
And the answer is, yes, it totally does still create that hierarchy,
right?
So this will be good, this is what we'll do.
Tomorrow is kind of finish that unification so you can kind of see
what happens right where I was saying like, it's looks like it still
creates our key.
It does look great, the hierarchy.
When it parses these names,
And I don't think we want doing that for stuff that's inside a data
block, right?
So we'll see we'll think about that a little bit more but based on how
this works I'm not sure.
Maybe we want to just leave the data bus, maybe we don't want the
hierarchy parsing stuff to ever actually do any hierarchical parsing
unless it's actually parsing the name of a data block and then the
data blocks are hardcore and everything else isn't
Does that make sense?
So yeah, so now I think we're okay like, we're pretty, we're actually
closer than I thought we were in terms of stuff, we might want in
here.
So that's not so bad.
All right, I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A now, time
relatively satisfied with that.
Hots for the per frame Arena space remaining.
Debug counter is always going down, is this okay?
Yes, that is by Design.
So, basically, that's the like amount of memory that was reserved for
debugging and it will just count down to zero and then when it gets
down to zero it will just start recycling that memory.
So basically what you want to do is you want to see it go all the way
down to zero and then it will stop.
Carrie Johansen, you mentioned a book that introduces relational
databases I lost the link it's Jim Gray is the guy that I was talking
about.
In his book is I think transaction processing.
This is the one.
If you kindly remit, put the fire out.
I think the profiler is still there.
Really.
We just have to finish the navigation of it because I'm pretty sure
the profiler actually if you just inserted one would actually just
show up, maybe I shouldn't have closed the editor.
So prematurely
meaning, I
if you take a look at
Is it in here?
I think if you take a look at counter thread list,
And you go into handmade dot CPP.
I think if you were to somehow do this here,
And I'm not sure.
Well, I guess the answer is that something we should do tomorrow
because I really don't want to spend too much time doing that now, but
essentially all we have to do to get a profiler still is inside here.
We just need to actually insert one of those counter those counter
thread lists or counter function list things.
We just need to insert them.
And so what we should do is an
Fact, I'll just put that here.
For tomorrow.
We should do that.
Tomorrow's what we should do?
Because you had the first flower still in there and we just never
inserted in our hierarchy anywhere.
Casey how do you implement easily the standard output without using
the iostream library?
It depends what platform you're on.
If you're on windows, they're actually just file handle.
There's, there's just file handles.
You can get called, get standard handles.
Its, I mean, I'm not sure exactly what you're asking, but I think it's
get standard handles.
Yeah.
Or handle.
Sorry.
From the win32 platform layer.
You just call get started handle.
And if your process has been launched for the console, you'll get
these handles back and then you can just do file reads and writes
directly to them to Output stuff that you want.
Which you prefer and why pound if lb F deaf pound?
If defined I tend to prefer pound if to pound if death because I like
to be able to pound Define something, I like to be able to do a pound
if deaf to mean, did anyone know about this value and set it?
so the pound if death is really just to make sure that default values
are set for stuff at the top of
Thing.
And then everywhere else, it just use the pound.
If on the value and assumes that it will have been set to zero or one
based on which one it should be right.
That's how I tend to do it.
I never use pound if defined parentheses unless I have some more
complex.
Thing that has to happen.
Danna 27 1988, can you tell me the version?
You just said, but for Linux and now Windows, I'm on Arch, I'm pretty
sure that on Linux on Linux, you can't really not linked with Jewel
it.
Well, you can.
But then you have to use sis calls.
To be honest with you, I don't know how to get this directly out of
Linux.
I don't do much Linux programming.
so,
let's see.
I think you would need to know the syscall.
For the syscalls for reading and writing and then you would need.
Yeah, I don't
And I don't even know if anyone ever wants you to do this anymore, but
if you were do it, if you're trying to go around the C runtime
Library, you would need, you would need to implement it via syscalls
where the handles come from.
I'm not sure the handles that are that initialize the standard, the
standard I/O stuff.
Those handles have to come into your process somewhere, but I don't
know where they come in.
Maybe there's a syscall, that gets them for you that get
There might be a syscall way to get like your process startup stuff.
In terms of interaction with a debug settings, what do you have in
mind for modifying the value switches or sliders?
Yeah, probably just a switch.
I want to just at least be able to like click on the value for the
boolean's and then like drag a value to like change it if it's a
floating point or something.
True blue.
What does a for each Loop?
Do a for each Loop is not a see thing.
So there's no such thing as a for each Loop in C.
Basically because see only had regular for Loops, but in other
languages besides see what a for each Loop is is it's a shorthand
notation of saying that you want to do a loop as many times as there
are elements in something, you're going to pass it.
So for example if you pass it a linked list data structure or, you
know, a hash table data structure or some data structure, that
presumably the language understands and you do it for each, then what
it's going.
To do is it's going to go.
Figure out how many things there are in it and then do that many
iterations.
Giving you one element every time.
It's a handy thing because it's basically just it's a lot of times
when you do a for Loop you're just trying to iterate over all the
members in something and C++ I don't think ever actually added good
ways to do that.
For whatever reason.
So maybe there are as in like C++, you know, 20 25 or whatever.
Let's see.
This not really today's topic.
When do you think you'll be designing your game instead of writing the
engine?
Well honestly, never liked the whole point of this is that I'm not a
game designer so will you know will be implementing game features
fairly soon.
Like I said there's not that much stuff left to do but we won't be
doing any design.
Like we're just implementing a fixed thing that I have written down.
It's like this is what we're going to implement and so this is not
Design stream and never will be, there's not gonna be any discussion
of design.
There's not going to be talking about design is not going to be any
game design happening on stirring.
There's just going to be, here's the thing.
We need to like Implement specific game thing.
This guy has to hit this other thing and we'll do that.
So we will be doing a bunch of that code but there's no game design.
I'm not a game designer and I don't want to talk about game design
because I don't have anything to say.
What language do you think is best for programming games?
See at the moment.
I'm not happy to say that the best language of tournament games is a
language.
That's like 40 years old or 30 years old, 30 years old.
It's 30 or 40 years old.
I don't know how old it is.
Now, I don't want to do the math, but it's very, very old.
But most new languages are just really bad for games.
Anyway.
I think most languages are actually just really bad in general, so I
don't really know the better language than C4 program for programming
games, but I wish there was a better one.
And maybe if John's new language works out, maybe that'll be it.
Because it certainly focuses on focuses on.
making a language that's like see but has a bunch of more powerful
features on top of it, that can do all the things that that secant do
well, you know,
John McGrath, oh my God.
See is 44 years old God.
Yeah.
So, yeah, I don't know.
Maybe we'll get a new language for game sometime soon.
I bet I know it's been 44 years and we haven't gotten one, so I don't
know.
Easy side.
The handles are just inside.
He's never heard from zero which map to purposes at the table courses.
Okay, so you're saying that in Linux, when you start up the handle,
IDs are guaranteed to be numbered that way.
So that you know that you can just use the, you know, like one or
something always Maps.
The standard error or something like that.
Diana 27.
I cannot consider using John's language because he has not released it
yet.
As far as I know,
Until he actually puts it out as like, here is a thing to start using,
obviously, I can't really use it.
So I'm going to go ahead and close down because we're a little over
time here.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for another 72 handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with the code,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade here at our org and it
comes to the source code.
So you can play around with it and learn from it and conduct your own
experiments.
We also have a forum site, you can go to ask questions a patreon page,
you can use to support this video series.
A pot.
You can use to find out the schedule and if you want to type for coder
into your search box, you can find the editor that we use on handmade
hero now which was written by someone on the stream, in fact, on
Webster and you can pledge to that and get your very own copy of for a
coder and the custom config that I wrote for for coder is also always
available now it's in the handmade Miss directory.
So if you pre-ordered
The game, you will get that.
That will just be in there for you.
That's about it.
I'll be back here tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
Hope to see you there.
And maybe we'll get some of our debug values will Implement some
editing for those.
And we already actually have anything in there.
So we're Leo.
I think we have to do is just enable editing for those and then we're
good to go.
So that's it for today.
Hope you.
I hope see you guys tomorrow until then take it easy.
I'll see you guys on the internet.