Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here on the show.
We go to complete game live on stream yesterday.
We did some work on our debug system and we got up to the point where
we pretty much a done.
The work we'd want to do except for one little part, which is about
hierarchical e organizing things.
And we kind of came to a point where one of the other things that are
debug code that is still on our list of things that needs fixing.
Pretty much blocked us from making any progress, we definitely needed
to address it before.
We could go any further with the thing we were doing and it's just
A holdover from when we were sort of figuring out what the debug
system was and how he wanted to work.
And so we need to do is we need to kind of go back.
Now, take a look at that code, and actually, write that part of the
code for real, right?
We got to do a reasonable job on that piece of the code instead of
kind of leaving it the way that it was.
So that's what I'm going to do today.
Today is day, 2, 15 on handmade hero.
So if you want to follow along at home, please unpack day to 14th
source code, and you'll be exactly where I am today.
So, if you remember where we left things off yesterday,
when we kind of run our game, you can see that mostly, we're getting
the debug output that we expect, but it's all done.
Like, we getting it many times, right?
So, we're seeing this kind of, you know, any given line that we might
look at is actually appearing lots of times.
And that's obviously not at all what we want to happen.
So what we would like to do is, you know, get that bug fixed.
But the reason, the only reason we have that bug, it was not, I don't
think actually in the code that we wrote yesterday.
That code is probably working mostly as it should.
And so the real problem was in the fact that we still don't have a
coherent story for how we're dealing with the actual state of the
debug system as new frames come in and they get processed.
And these frames get kind of collated and stuff like this happens.
And so what we need to do is we need to sort of come back here.
Now that we kind of know how the debug system works and what sort of
stuff gets stored in it.
And how that goes, we need to kind of come back here now and go.
Okay, wait a minute.
What are we actually going to do now?
In terms of processing, debug records as they come in, right?
Like how is that going to work?
What are we going to do here?
Because we need some sort of a plan.
You know what I mean?
To make sure that we actually store debug events and store.
The data that we're trying to store in a smart way, in a reasonable
way and and sort of make everything, you know, work correctly.
So, if you remember how this worked, we essentially have a table of
debug values, right?
And these debug values are in the up in here, we sort of have this
concept of a debug table.
And what this debug table had is it had a maxi bug event or a count
and then I had a Max debug event count and the Maxi Buck event count
is how many events you could have on a frame.
And the reason that we have these buffers and the reason that they're
sort of stationary buffers that just sort of sit there is we didn't
want there to be really any overhead in, right?
Into the debug system.
So we could we are refining with arbitrary amount of over
I had kind of at the end when we go to pick up the debug events and
see what they do.
That's fine but we don't want any real overhead in the streaming out
of the debug events themselves so that there's no cost for us to sort
of increase the amount of debug traffic there.
It's kind of like free Beyond just the the simple Act of writing it.
There's no more cost that kind of comes in there.
And so what we kind of did is we made these debug events and we store
it as many of them as we thought we might want in terms of how many
arrays.
So we've got sort of eight copies of the events, which I guess would
correspond to write like eight frames worth of data potentially, you
know, 8 sort of clicks of the debug system.
And so, the thing about this,
When we look at it is we have a number of for lack of a better term,
we have a number of options now now that we know how things work.
So we know that things stream out into this the into the system and we
do use the data that's in the Stream itself.
And if we want to sort of save the amount of traffic, in terms of
memory, traffic of copying debug vents out of this array, then you
know you could easily argue that maybe we just want to leave things in
here and view them directly out of the
Right.
But we could also equivalently argue that may be what we would rather
do is just use these events as a temporary holding ground, there's
only two of them.
So, instead of, like the max debug event count being too, I'm sorry,
the max debug event, array, count, being eight, it would be something
more like two.
And then what we would do is we would have, you know, just a ping pong
buffer kind of situation where we write to one while we're collecting
the other and collate one while we're riding to the other, right?
We've kind of just flip them so we could do that and then that would
entail kicking the data out and putting it into some other storage
somewhere else.
And there's really no difference between those two.
Other than in the one case it would allow us to do things, like, save
specific frames.
If we wanted to like,
sure, that Frame data if we wanted to in a more specific way and you
know at the expense basically of having more memory bandwidth in that
copy,
Now, there's a reason that that kind of interest me, the reason that I
find that to be somewhat interesting.
Is when you take a look at how this events thing works here, right,
what I want to emphasize is that even though these are split up that
on a frame-by-frame basis, right?
And and you know if I if I were to draw this out for you here you
could sort of see perhaps what I'm talking about here on Day 2 15.
Go.
If I were to sort of draw this out here, what you can imagine
happening, right?
Is there these debug buffers and, you know, we're we've got sort of
this giant set of debug memory.
And, you know, there's there's I think we said there were eight of
them, right?
And then each one of them is like the max events, sighs, long and each
thread.
You know there's all these
It's out here, right?
And each of them is just kind of writing in here as they go right and
they all they use a locked increment to ensure.
They don't step on each other's toes but they just basically fill this
up, okay?
And then when this thing is, when we get to the point in the loop,
where we're about to display the frame, we latch it we call the debug
system.
And we say, Hey, you can advance the next one, yet it does.
Again, a locked increment of the frame number to move so that the all
the threads start running into this one,
which leaves us with a series of at this moment, a buckets.
Each one representing a frames worth of data, but
But it's not really a frames worth of data.
It's not a frames worth of data because the debug system actually
fires before the actual end of the frame occurs, right?
So really, what happens is the frame Starts Here.
We do a bunch of work, the frame ends here, the debug system takes
over and does some work and do some drawing, then some stuff to
happens to display the frame and then the frame is actually displayed
to the screen and the
When the debug buffer flips is actually the time when the debug system
is first called.
So actually, I guess it would be more appropriately be here, right?
So if you look at how these buffers work, the actual Frame data is
actually more looks like this, right?
If that makes sense.
Adding to the problem adding, you know, making things even even more
complicated is the fact that there are events happening asynchronously
here, like, let's say, we're going to load a texture off of disk or
something like this, and it's like lasts this long, right?
Well, we may have is timing zone or something like this.
That started in this Frame, right?
This is frame 0, but ended in frame 1.
So, the data for this particular, event does not actually exist.
Holy constrained to a frame.
It actually
This across more than one frame.
And so again, we see sort of this problematic scenario where our Frame
data is not really, you know, it's not really coincident or doesn't
mean the same thing as the buffer there the frames and the buffering
are not really the same thing.
And that's one reason why it's very appealing to me to say, I would
like to make this just the attempt, very buffer and I'd like to pull
things out of it.
It and put them into the permanent storage in sort of like a different
way rather than trying to keep it around like this.
Now, I don't know if that's a good idea or a bad idea.
Again, the increased memory traffic is a concern.
Certainly, there's reasons to be worried about that, but I don't know
at this moment, if I have to make the call and I do have to make the
call, I feel like what I would rather do is see this get go down to
two arrays and just an, a, a b array that get flop between.
And when we go to process one array, we pull everything.
Of it and we copy anything that we want into our sort of permanent
debug, information storage.
And then later when we want to throw that information away, we can
throw it away on an actual specific frame basis and not on a basis
that has to do with these buffers, which are not really all that
related to the actual events themselves because events could span them
or whatever.
And so yeah, it's basically just about
Removing one of the additional overlaps here by saying it's just a
scratch buffer and that seems like a good idea to me.
Maybe I will regret that decision, I don't know, but it does seem like
the kind of thing that I should look into.
So my first thought is what I'd like to do is kind of stopped that
whole concept in entirely, right?
I just want to get rid of the concept that we ever actually use the
debug event stored in this array.
And rather it's just a scratch buffer and when we collate it we are
copying out the information we need and throwing away, everything
else, right?
Everything else is gone.
So let's try that.
Let's just see what happens there as a start.
And and so in here I'm going to say, like, we're just going to reduce
this, to to, right?
And then in theory, if that array is used to our debug system should
still run.
I would think and, of course, I'm already wrong.
Right.
I don't actually see any debug information happening there and I
believe that the reason that we don't see it is because we actually
would always be right at the end of things and we had a check in there
to prevent that from happening.
So yes you can actually see.
We need that one extra frame to prevent the restarting.
The collation restarting from triggering early, right.
But the oh that's okay, right?
Because we're going to change that in a second.
But you can also see that this is consistent with what we believed our
bug to be.
You can see how it definitely looks a lot more, like, what we expected
it to look like here.
And our debug system appears to work, particularly does appear to work
correctly as well.
I set the use debug to true.
For example.
Here's the
That distance and you can kind of see.
Now I can play with it in real time.
So again, the code that we wrote for this over the past two days
actually appears to be working quite well.
Right.
No surprises there and that's pretty awesome.
So really again we're just talking about this debug storage.
All right, so let's hit this a little harder.
Then we're going to drop it down to two.
We're going to go ahead and say.
So now this thing is just a ping pong buffer, right?
And in fact, Max, debug array event array count.
We might want to get rid of now, and because I think,
We might want to start treating this specifically as a ping-pong
buffer and not a cycle, not a cyclical buffer at all.
Anyway so I'm going to take a look at what happens here.
Yep I know I'm going to get rid of that.
I know I'm going to going to get rid of this and that and that and the
so I think I can pretty safely say this.
Just going to go away and this right here, this events situation is
always going to be just something that looks like this, right?
So you're always going to have an event count and events.
There's always just going to be these two and that's all there
actually is in the system.
Now this part I could even say we could take this a little bit
further, we could actually say that we're just going to store an event
count.
That's all we're going to store.
And then here in this adventure a we could have something more like
this.
This where we just have an A and B pointer and two of these, I guess I
don't know.
I think about not sure I'm not sure that actually needs to happen that
that could actually be incorrect.
In fact what is it that I don't event count actually isn't even
necessary right?
Because event to right index is what stores that?
So yeah, so all this I think can just be simplified in its entirety
that to do still applies and it's not a to do that.
I think we'll ever probably address.
It's just a note there in case anyone's wondering why the system
misbehaved in some weird Corner case.
They wouldn't be wondering.
They could see that like.
Oh right.
That's true.
All right, so I think this is, this is what we want here.
I don't know where Max debug event.
Count actually is applied or what that's actually used for.
It looks like it's only happening.
When we actually sort of do this right here,
So, it kind of seems like we could even use the array count there, you
know, we could just say, like, you know, something like array count,
will do events zero, right?
We could just say that's what we want to do that assertion based on
and I think that would compile just fine at least I suspect.
So and so all of this stuff.
Yeah we don't care about.
So I think that's all good and that means we can now get rid of this
defined as well.
And we can just get
Down to basically, just like we've got an array here.
Happy birthday, everyone's fine.
And it's great.
Now we've got Max-D Bud, thread count.
I do not actually remember what we needed that for.
I assumed it was some kind of a stack thing when we were doing like,
checking some going to take a look and see that doesn't even get used
anymore.
So it looks like we can really simplify our debug table down to
something pretty nice and clean.
Really, the only Oddity here is that there's got to be those two
ping-pong buffers.
I don't think there's any way we're going to get rid of that because
of the multi-threaded nature.
Of the program even this early in development when we are not trying
to do anything too.
Fancy with threads we're already got, you know, our render is
multi-threaded in our loading system is multi-threaded.
So, you know, even just with that, we're going to want that ping pong
stuff, to keep us thread safe.
So we're going to leave that there.
And now I'm going to go ahead and start moving over to porting the
rest of the code to something.
Where we know that that event array is not actually going to be there
for us to use.
So everything in our debug system is going to actually use copy out.
Into some kind of a more sort of generic ways.
Permanent records sort of free list.
Happy Funplex thing.
This will probably it probably sounds like it's going to be a little
bit of a nightmare, because we've got all of these things with
referencing each other and stuff.
But honestly, I think it probably won't turn out to be that bad famous
last words because the, the sort of scope of what it's trying to do is
relatively narrow and easy to understand.
We just have frames that were buffering up, and that's not so hard.
So let's take a look at what we actually might want to do here.
In our debug system.
I think what I'd like to do is I'd like to be able to have when, you
know, our debug state so in handmade debug .h wherever that ended up.
Yeah, so in our debug State, you know, we have a thing of frames, and
I think what I'd like to do is be able to.
I'd like to still have that sort of debug frames this concept here.
This this, like, array of debug frames, I'd still like to have an
array of debug frames, and I'd like to have sort of this concept that
we have n frames of back storage.
And so really the only thing that I want to change about that
particular process is the fact that instead of these things being
collated and piled up on each other.
I want to every time a new frame comes in.
I want to just sort of push that data into the permanent store and
like, get rid of one of the frames of back storage that we have,
right?
Or something like that.
So yeah, so we'll see how I want to do that in a little bit.
But point being here, the debug frame think here.
Probably I'm trying to think of how I might
I'm not, I'm just not 100% certain yet exactly how I want to store
those.
I might want them as sort of a linked list where you're not
necessarily that you actually pull out of the, the middle of.
I'm just kind of in that way that I'm just in my head, I'm sort of
thinking, I'm not sure exactly what I want there.
But if we take a look at this debug frame, for example, I'm going to
what I'm going to do here is just a minute, going to have a next.
And then here, I'm going to have like
You know, earliest frame and then latest frame.
Or most recent frame.
And so this will be like a pointer to the very first frame that we
captured in terms of the earliest.
Now, as we sort of move through the game, it'll throw frames away.
So that won't be all the way back to the beginning of the game.
Although maybe when xpoint memory comes out, we'll just or all the
frames because you'll have one terabyte of memory in your machine or
something, but at the moment, you know, we'll just have the oldest
frame and that'll be, you know, eight frames back, ten frames back, 16
frames back, that could be parameterised, right?
I have kind of, an idea, something I want to do that.
We'll see.
That's kind of fun that maybe makes it so that that doesn't have to
parameterize anyway, but yeah, it's, you know, get, don't get too
ahead of ourselves.
So then, you know, on the sort of debug frameset that we have the most
recent frame as well and so we'll just sort of
That.
As our option here.
And then I'll also have one here that's like first free frame because
you know how I like my free lists and so will kind of have that there.
And so what I'd like to do is sort of have a system that's going to
push these frames on, it's going to work like that and do its little
thing.
Do its little happy dance.
It's a little happy.
We're dances around like a little dancer and then stops dancing
because it runs out of wind-up toy energy as all dancers must do
eventually now.
So what I want to start doing now is start peeling away, sort of,
Stuff that was in here before for this.
And you can kind of see when we do our our drawings and stuff like
this.
When I do something like drawing the profile or stuff like that, what
I want to do instead of doing these frames this way.
Now I'm going to just Loop through all the frames that we have, now
that may end up actually being a bad idea.
And I could also, I could include a frame count here, right?
Which, you know we were already had one obviously but I could I can
include a frame card account here which is basically just a thing that
tells us how many of these frames we actually have right and you know
this Coalition array index and the collation frame and all that stuff
collation frame is is probably still a thing that we might want to
have.
I don't actually know if it's one that we want to have or not but it's
probably something we want to have.
And what it would be, is just the frame.
That's not quite done yet.
We haven't seen the end marker for the frame.
Now, there's two ways I could do that either.
It can be the collation frame or it could be
The most recent frame, but I think we probably want most recent frame
to actually be one that we know is done.
So that we're not displaying like partial frames or something like
this, that's just my gut feeling.
I don't actually know if that's an accurate thought or not but that is
the way that I happen to be thinking about it, right?
So anyway,
Excuse me, if we look here at collation array index, that's going to
go away obviously because we're going to collate these one at a time
when they come in Kool-Aid Arena and collate temporary memory.
I don't think we're going to need anymore because again those are
things that we're going to do permanently frame bar, link out and
frame bar scale.
And paused, you know, obviously pause this sort of more of an
interaction thing and it's something that will probably want to
revisit a little bit in a bit after all this other stuff is done.
But frame bar, lean County.
Frame bar scale to me.
Those seems like things that maybe should actually be on the frames
themselves potentially, but you know, outside here.
In addition to the frame count, I could see having like what's the
maximum one we've ever seen?
Because that would maybe inform the profiler.
I don't really know.
So maybe for now, I'll just stick them up in the frames themselves and
assume that those are like computed per frame, right?
So be something more like this.
okay, so that's what I
To sort of set up here.
And and so I'm going to sort of try and push forward a little bit more
on that and I think yeah again some of this this is getting a little
unwieldy here too.
If you look like there's just a lot of things happening in here and so
at some point we probably want to organize this a little bit more and
do some other things there.
But, you know, again, one thing at a time, you don't want to do too
many things at once, especially when you're first starting out, you
don't really want to, you want to kind of make sure that you're
staking taking steps and taking them, small enough steps.
As you can see,
How they went without jeopardizing, like the whole structure of your
system because you may make a wrong decision somewhere and then you've
like wasted a lot of work and have to kind of unwind.
So okay, when we come through here,
I can now do this iteration in a slightly different way I can
essentially say, Okay, I want to start at the debug State, oldest
frame and then I just want to iterate until I get to the most recent.
And that's really all I have to do.
That will give me the frame.
I can draw the frame and then in here where I was looking at the debug
State before.
Well, that actually doesn't happen in here.
It looks like, but I would went when the time comes to look at things
like bar scales, like that, I can obviously do those a little bit
differently if I needed to.
Okay, so frame bar link out.
So for example here, when we're doing draw a profile in like I said,
so that link account, you can see actually does get sort of used in a
bunch of
Aces here.
Yeah, you can sort of see all the stuff all of this stuff really kind
of wants to be inside, probably looks like
Although, you know.
So so the thing is it wants to do the lane count there?
I don't know, I could do something like this where I just pre step
through so I say, hey, for each of these
I guess I'm missing semicolon there.
There we go.
You know for each of these as we go through I want to see what the max
Lane County is.
So I would just do something like setting the link account you know 20
or something like this.
Although I don't know if we were divided by link out now we don't we
guard by it there.
So as we go through here, you know, looking at the frame bar link, I
can do some sort of a Max thing.
I can just do like, you know, if
Lane count is less than whatever this frames one was.
Then I'll make that be the max, right?
And so that way, we can still do all of the same stuff we were doing
and frame bar scale.
I guess probably would be the same as well.
So frame bar scale I don't really remember that's I guess that's how
long the thing was okay.
So frame bar scale is just kind of nonsense here, frame bar scale
actually was set.
We didn't actually ever do anything useful with that.
That's
Which is kind of unfortunate.
But yeah, so frame bar scale.
We just want to get rid of now.
And replace with something.
Little bit better, right?
Excuse me.
So what we want to do with frame bar?
Scale is the same thing, right?
That's so here.
Just frame bar scale.
And I believe we want the minimum one, so it's the one that's going to
be the smallest so that everything fits.
So, the frame bar scale would be something like a float Max, right?
Or rather it would sorry, it would be something like zero.
No, we want the minimum so I'm write something like the maximum value.
And then, basically, if frame bar scale,
Is going to be less than whatever.
The frames frame bar, scale is
Then we would set them equal and as we work on our profile rendering a
bit, maybe those change a little bit later, down the down the line.
But you know, for right now at least this keeps some reasonable
feature parity to what we had.
So in here are framing next we can still keep right?
We can still have a constitutive frame index and we can still say we
know which framer on relative to the other ones for drawing it and
that's all fine.
So what we need to do now is we just need to have some way of of doing
this collation out to the to these individual frame things instead of
doing them sort of haphazardly.
So the first thing that we're going to do right?
It's get rid of that concept of the collation Arena and actually use
real allocatable values.
And so, when we take a look at this stuff, we're allocating the debug
threads, debug threads are already.
I think, don't they already go back to a
Or don't they how did the house of the debug threads work?
I don't actually remember, debug thread, debug thread.
So we do need a, debug thread, right?
First free thread.
And what's interesting about this is we will have a few free list
here.
This is again.
Something that I would probably, you know, normally I would be
generating and if you want to do this in
There's just not a enough to it.
But you know how we did our d-list thing, right?
We have our D list, insert, do you listen it for doubly linked list,
right?
We just have, that's, that's that whole situation.
We could, you know, sort of do something where we have something like
that happening.
So the push struct, it would do a sort of like, can I get one from the
free store?
If not do the push struct, right?
But basically first free thread.
Would be used if.
That didn't work, then it gets one from the actual debug Arena.
And that's it, right?
So then we go ahead and fill it out and that's all that happens.
Again, nothing particularly unusual here, and we just need this to
actually do our free list EQ.
So, in order to do that after we actually have this thing, get pulled
we need for a 3 thread to be whatever the thing that was that was
after the
Now since we don't know, if there was another one or not, like if
there was actually one on there, we need to make sure that we actually
DQ it, you know, sort of the way more like this.
So basically what we're saying is okay, give us the first free one.
If there is, you know, if that worked, then we want to advance the
free list pointer.
If that didn't work, then we want to allocate a new one, right?
So that their shows, you the pattern for D cueing off of a free list
version.
Do we want to wrap that up?
I don't know.
It's not very much code to wrap up, but you can imagine doing
something like that, right?
So maybe if we want to do that free list, you know, a lock or
something like this.
And if I wanted to do this, I just need to figure out exactly what all
this stuff would be.
And so, what we want to say is, first of all, like, what is the
actual?
You know, what's the actual value that we're trying to create, right?
So we have like, you know,
The value or you could even call it result.
Potentially, so we have the result.
The result is trying to get something off of the free list pointer.
So this is like the free list pointer.
And so it's trying to get something off of that, assuming that it gets
it.
It's going to use the next right to get it.
If not, then it's going to do a push struct.
Let's try and get it.
We need to know the arena and it needs to know the type of the thing
that's going to be got the thing that's going to be retrieved, right?
And I think in C plus plus eleven thousand .96 revision 12 I think you
can do a thing that's like decal.
Right?
Where you say like oh you know whatever this thing was like actually
pointing to, right?
Get me that thing.
Of course I didn't spell it, right.
And that would prevent anyone from actually having to sort of put that
in there and so a free list allocation it just looks like this.
I can make this a little more concise like so, right?
And so again really really straightforward?
We could I guess we could even do this if we're just absolutely
ridiculous about everything.
You know we could just say like okay this equals this thing and
whatever the result of that is if it turns out that that's true then
we're just going to do this.
Otherwise we are going to not do that, right?
And that's, that's all there is.
so yeah, if we want to do that,
We can just macro that up and say, okay, here's our free list a lock.
It just looks like this.
Six of one half-dozen of the other, but you know, it should be fine.
So, let's see pointer to reference is illegal.
What are this is, probably my not non familiarity with the new C++
nonsense, but I do believe you can do it free of this pointer.
Free list pointer is actually the thing that we want.
Right, first free thread although wait a minute.
Did I ever actually make a first free thread?
I did.
Okay, so yeah.
So I wanted that to allocate.
They worked for me.
I'm going to look up.
I've literally like I don't even know if we've ever used this on
handmade here.
I just know that it's there.
So here we go.
Decal type, the argument is a, non-print size, ID expression.
Or and I'm Princess cast member, and I call them use the type, its
argument is an expression, the value categories, X value targets, I
please T address address then is to address.
I don't actually want it to.
I'm not a dress T reference.
I don't really want it to yield a t reference though.
We want to reference what?
Why did they do it that way?
Well, let me see what happens if I
Just do this.
Hmm, pointer to reference is illegal.
What happens if I do that.
Yeah.
So
can I convert run from memory into memory in a star?
That's all fine.
That's just means that has to do that.
Here we go to do both wrists are.
Yeah.
So I mean that's what I want it to give me the Dakota.
The decal type of is the free list pointer.
So let's see.
Why can't I do that, right?
Why are you complaining about that mr.
Fancy Pants.
Do I have 2 parenthesis it parenthesize?
It know.
All right, so tell me why you don't like it.
Note that if the name of that I've just been the size is treated as an
ordinary of expression.
The steckle Type X integral type precious that parentheses parentheses
x are often different types.
You'll have to someone declaring types of difficult or impossible to
Clarys and sanitation like land related types.
The pit.
Okay.
Well, that's unhelpful because I just want that type.
I just want you to tell me what that type is, but you don't seem to
want to do that, do it?
You know, if they've always got to make a complicated, the
As people, it should just be an expression according to this, let's
see here.
So do they have any time
Yeah.
So I wonder
if they had a different keyword for things like I want to dereference
this thing.
so, what's type of
let's see here, I don't want Visual Basic
Give me something.
I can work it with your C++.
I don't really care.
I mean, I'll just type it in at the end of the day.
So let's find out if there's any way I can actually just get what I
want.
Like you know, something a little bit better but anyway, it's tight.
What is it type ID?
That's but that's just a runtime type information.
Is it?
There's got to be something people, come on.
Like seriously, I mean I guess I could do this in a ridiculously
roundabout way where I declare one of these, I mean I could do this
Right.
Or something like that.
I guess so but I can't do the cast.
Mmm-hmm.
Well, I don't really want to do this right now.
This is typical C++ nonsense that should have been easy, right?
But of course, no, I'm going to have to go read the stupid spec or
something, to figure out how they Define that thing in such a way that
it's, you know, Annoying and doesn't work.
But anyway, point being, I can just do something like this where we
just say, like, what's the type, you know, whatever the type is.
So then we just do that, right?
And then our stuff will work again.
Not the way I would have wanted it to work, but not really the end of
the day.
It's not really the end of the world.
It's like it's fine, right?
I don't care.
Okay, so now we want to do is there's a bunch of things here that are
working off of this sort of frame, based assumption, and I want to
actually be able to use that there.
So maybe will, you know, will have this collation frame thing.
Like I said, so the anything that we use to be doing that was on the,
the debug say itself, we're going to do on that collation frame always
right?
That's just how we're going to do.
It restart collation is not going to be a thing anymore.
That's just going to be what we do at startup.
So we're always going to be collating, right?
24.
Seven, we are going to be collating, right?
That's just a thing that happens and really what that's going to look
like.
For example when we do debug start, right, really?
What this is probably going to look like is it's going to be something
here and instead of being something called restart collation, what
it's going to be a something more like, you know,
You know, new frame, right?
Or something like this, and it returns a debug frame.
And what it would do.
Is just create all of the stuff that was supposed to happen here on
this on this guy.
All the stuff that was supposed to do to create one of these new
frames, right?
So debug frame.
Let's see.
Debug frame.
Results equals how we're going to get the frame.
We then have our results here does its thing, which is none of this
stuff is necessary.
Where is our actual Frank?
And also, what are these things?
So, first thread, so threads in this case are probably per frame.
Well, mmmm,
Maybe not.
So maybe I was wrong about the frame bar Lane count.
The frame bar scale is obviously per frame but the frame bar lean
count.
Maybe that's just how many threads there are.
I'm going to say I'm going to say, ok, I'll leave that out here.
I'm going to say that these things actually do, do it that way.
So, that's fine.
So, this stuff when we actually initialize things will initialize
these threads or whatever we're going to do here, right?
Would you say that those things get initialized frame bar link account
will equal to 0.
We've got first thread, we've got first free thread.
First, three, block, all that stuff.
That's all fine.
We've got all of these guys, we want them initialized as well.
We've got debug State oldest frame equals, you know.
Debug State, most recent frame equals debug State versus free frame 0.
I think that's what we want.
And that's, that's all there is.
It's a good.
Okay, so that's all fine.
And then, our new frame.
What that's going to do is that's just going to go ahead and get the
memory for a new frame, right?
So that's just going to be a push struct again, everything comes out
of the same Arena.
Now,
And that's just going to give us a new debug frame.
The debug frame itself.
Have some stuff on it that we're going to initialize here.
So we want to just set this stuff up.
We've got, in fact, I think I might do a zero struck down it just
clear everything and then only initialize the things that I actually
care about.
I'll say for now that the frame bar scale, I don't know what the frame
bar scale should be, maybe it's 1.0 to start out with the route group
is going to have to be initialized in some way to be something the
region count.
And the regions that I think, I don't know exactly what we want to do
with that yet.
Again, we'll find out in a second here, but I'll initialize it to.
Well, they'll be in a size 0 automatically, next won't do anything and
then we sort of got well, that's about it right, this, we don't care
about anymore at all.
We don't
Sure about that.
This we do.
And in here, when we add something onto this, we're going to need to
deal with that.
But until now until then we don't actually have to.
So when we do our route group here, this I want to create a new one of
these groups.
So I want to I want to be able to do sort of a
a.m.
A new group, every time for these guys.
So we have click create variable group so I want to do that, right?
So I want to do a click create real group and now, these don't have to
be Kool-Aid anymore, either.
Write these can all just be, we don't have to really name them
collate.
They're just, it's just create variable group or whatever create
variable group.
These are all just like, create variable.
Add variable to group, right?
And these are going to all happen on the debugger Arena.
Now.
So all of that's you know, unified again, this actually gets rid of
that all that stuff that we said we wanted to, to do wise all of this
stuff can now happen on the debug Arena and we don't have to worry
about that kind of weird nonsense anymore.
Which is kind of just a temporary solution to see if our stuff was
working and it was, and then we had some bugs like this one that we
now have to go fix for real and it's all good.
So that's what we actually want to have happen.
There then we go down here, cold, ladybug records.
This thing is just going to have to take all those collate ones.
If I should get rid of the word collate, this is going to take those
people who are doing collate stuff, it's going to change of this.
We don't need the parameter for permanent anymore so we can basically
just back out that change which again like I said I don't really like
and then yeah, everything else that happens in here.
Can always be happening on the debug Arena.
That's all good.
And so on and so forth.
Okay.
All right, we don't need the collation Arena anymore.
That stuff is all entirely gone and that's all good.
What we do need to do of course is create the the starting frame.
So we need something like collation frame equals new frame.
So we need to like make an initial frame that we start with and that's
what things will get paddled into at the beginning.
So that's all fantastic.
And happy and wonderful.
And then up here, where is our new frame?
Yeah, up here.
What we will want to do is every time we get into a situation.
We'll want to do something like or frame or finish frame, something
like that.
Something like this but we'll want to do is take that collation frame.
And retire it I guess now I think about I probably don't need a thing
that actually I probably don't actually need that.
I can probably put it right in here.
So when we do event type equals frame marker, for example, what I can
do is say okay let's assert that the collation frame exists and then
what I'll do is I'll push that collation frame.
I'll basically add that to sort of our list this here.
I don't know why.
We got rid of this thing to be completely honest with you, I'm not
sure.
Why that wasn't working or why we perceived it's not be working.
So we should probably re-enable this to do Casey.
Can we re enable this now or something like that?
But yeah, once we receive this Frame marker, we can increment the
frame count and we can take debug State and we can go ahead and put
onto here or oldest frame most recent frame.
That whole thing.
I can just kind of move the frame onto their so we can say, all right,
basically, if we had a most recent frame, we're just going to
daisy-chain if not, then we're not.
So, in the case, when we had the most recent frame, that means the
most recent frames.
Next one is going to be this one.
You bug.
Eight collation frame.
And in the case of me,
Hmm.
And in the case where we didn't then what we would do is say well both
the first are sorry, the both the oldest frame and the most recent
frame
are going to be equal to our collation frame.
So that's just puts it onto that list of frames that we have.
So that's again, pretty straightforward and what we want.
And then, you know, no matter what happens.
I was through the frame, count goes up and that's fine.
Again, like I said, we want to know if we can re-enable that thing.
We'll think about that a bit later.
And then what you want to do is this stuff here is again the stuff
that's sort of happening.
It looks like, oh so this is actually the stuff that we actually want
to do in our frame creation but point being so the collation frame.
Now, we want to create a new one, right?
So
We want to create a new frame for collation from now on, because we've
retired that like previous frame, right?
So in new frame that I guess we've got that.
Don't need this.
We're doing.
Begin clock.
So if there was a clock to let us know when to start that begin clock,
I guess that's a
I guess that's kind of a thing here.
Now that I think about it.
So we don't know what the begin clock would be.
So we kind of need to pass the begin clock in here, right?
Because we don't know what that would be otherwise.
So if we pass the begin clock in here, all the rest of this stuff
would work properly, I believe, we'd want to leave this.
I suppose the way that it was working and whatever this part.
I think, probably needs to get done in a little bit different way, but
let's see to do Casey.
Regions need to get fancier.
Obviously.
Okay, so what we want to do here, like I said is we want to figure out
a way to get new frame to get some information there.
What I was thinking is I was going to do it this way but I think
actually what I'm going to do is let that get initialized to zero and
then what I'll do is when we first come through here, right?
Whenever we see one of these, debug frame markers will assume that
we're going to retire the frame.
But what I'll do it.
In fact, anytime just straight up.
If I see an event at all, I'll just assume that that event should have
a collation frame.
So if the collation frame and not to make sure that we never have
some, it doesn't fill out its clock value, which I think we might not
do in one place, which is probably a mistake.
But will double check that.
So what I want to do here is say, okay, this collation frame, if I
don't have one, I want to make sure that a get one and when I get one
because I'm doing it, lazily like this, I know that I'll have it in a
clock, right?
I know that I'll have a clock value to pass it so we'll just say the
first time we ever see an event, if we don't have a frame, it becomes
that becomes the new start time for that thing, right?
So again in this case pretty easy, I can also say that in this case
the event clock is there so that's all good.
And from then on I don't really need to do an else.
If collation frame here, I can just assert that we have one because
now it's a requirement that there's always a frame being collated.
You can never have anything other than that state.
So we'll just assert that that's fine.
When we call collate, debug records, what that's going to do.
Obviously again this this we can sort of change the way we're looking
at this entirely instead.
This looking at collation arrays.
Specifically it's really just only going to ever look at one of these
specific guys.
Right here, it's going to go through the whole array and consume all
the events and retire all the events, right?
So, what we want to do is just say, all right, here's the debug State,
we just want to pass it in event count.
And an event array.
And it's just responsible for killing that and whoever's going to
call, this will call have to call it with whatever the correct buffer
is for to Coley at that time, it would just let that be an upstream
issue.
Right.
Okay.
So let's push forward a bit here.
So again, when we're doing this our frame Darlene count, now no longer
has to do what it's doing here anymore because that's actually
something that's that we that is set on the debug state.
And Lane index.
Rain bar link count in here yet.
This is actually how that's working.
Any time, it has to grab one of these guys, this is correct.
It's not actually on the collation.
It's actually on the debug State itself.
When we allocate debug blocks again, now, we're always doing the debug
Arena, you can see that this code right is just the same code that we
have now for doing free list stuff.
So here it is for this a lock, you can kind of see, it's got the same
thing.
Take out that free list pointer.
If it's there, we advance the pointer.
If it's not, we allocate again, it's exact same thing so we can if we
want to just go ahead and say this
Right.
There's my free list pointer and here is my Arena.
There we go.
And that's all good.
Oh,
got to actually declare it.
There we go.
So next free is actually the value here.
And so I feel like I don't actually know how I want to do with that
specifically probably what I would want to do or rather.
I think probably what I want to do for the free thing is, do something
like this.
So in handmade debug .h, I probably want it always to be called Next
free.
So in something like debug
Frame.
I would probably want to do something like this.
Just you can kind of see that when it's on the free list.
It's using some different space, right?
Well, this one doesn't actually matter.
And so in this case like for example in this open this open debug
block one, it could just be shadowing another thing right?
It could just be that like okay yeah you know the parent pointer or
something is is only you know we just used that space so we don't have
to make it doesn't need to be bigger in order to have a free point or
the free pointers just the
That, you know, we use off of it or whatever, you know, something like
that.
So that's obviously just a pretty straightforward thing that I can
kind of just do hmm.
For anything that's on that list.
Okay.
So, moving along our free list Alec now.
it has to be something but takes
Next free.
That's it.
Okay, so create variable group.
I don't actually remember what that actually takes.
No idea.
So it's still got that permanent lying around.
We're gonna get rid of that, that's not necessary anymore.
Missing an equal sign their frames again is not a thing, obviously
that's fine, but we can still do this thing which is to say, if most
recent frame, right?
We can do that.
So we can still do this sort of thing.
Pretty easily refresh Coalition is not a thing that we need to do
anymore.
I don't think because hopefully we'll be doing things in a little bit,
smarter way, maybe not, we'll find out, but okay, so then we've got
our event count
Our event count, this code has to change slightly because now we're
just ping-ponging.
This is not the case anymore, right?
So what happens now is current event array Index, right?
If we take a look at how this is working, current event re-index
That is just ping pong and back and forth.
So, current event array.
Index is always just going to be that.
It's just going to flop between 0 and 10 and 10 and 10 and 1, right?
And that's all in here.
This wrapping code does not have to work at all.
That doesn't have to do anything at all.
Right?
And yeah.
And really so really the way this
That works too.
This this doesn't actually have to be a, you 64 anymore.
It could be you 32.
And just the high bit, could actually tell you which one you were
looking for.
Do Casey, this could actually be a, you 32 Atomic now, since we only
need one bit to store, which array, we're using.
Just a little note there course that that was actually true before.
This could have been a u-32 as well because there was no way we were
going to have so many events.
We weren't going to have
You know, 24, bits worth of events anyway.
And there were only eight of these week and 52 could have more than
that.
So yeah, we could have done that a while back but we didn't doesn't
really matter
One way or the other, but point being.
So we do the atomic exchange here.
All of that should be fine.
I don't think there's anything particularly unusual going on there.
The event array index, equals event, array indexed.
This, this thing here, is whatever we got back from the atomic
exchange.
So this is the Venture industry could assert that event array index is
less than or equal to 1 because it should either be 0 or 1.
We got the event count there and so now the event cow
Count is just what we've received here.
And so, yeah, again that is just really straightforward, nothing weird
happening here, really, really basic stuff.
So when we do our after we do our debug start, what we can do is we
can just call collate frame, or rather collate, debug records.
And we can pass that the event array indexed event array.
So that's the events to do.
We know how many to do.
And we know that you know we are we right?
This doesn't have to happen anymore.
Goodbye this doesn't have to happen anymore either.
So really all we can do is just say, okay, if we are not paused, then
collate, otherwise don't collate, right?
And we could actually, you know, I would almost say let's do this in
an even more Hefty.
Special-purpose way there, which is to say,
I'm gonna make that sort of your to do because what I'd rather do than
that is when we retire frames, just throw the frame out so that we're
still.
So that way any frame that wasn't done yet.
We'll still collate.
It's stragglers even after a pause and just we'll just throw a new
frame stuff.
So I think what I would rather do here, right?
Is when we do this and we sort of push that frame on there.
I think what I'd rather do is say okay,
you know, if we are paused
Then we throw the frame out otherwise then we you know, we use it,
right?
So it looks like that in the normal case, right?
And so this would be a to do Casey throw away or I could even do it
here.
Free frame.
Write debug State collation frame.
So, basically, every time it finishes collation, it just going to
throw it away but it's still kind of going in the background with that
correlation if that makes sense.
I think that's a reasonable thing to do.
I don't necessarily know.
Yeah.
I think that's the right thing to do, anyway.
So here we go with free frame.
That's going to be a little internal void here for you frame.
That we're just going to do a cert and not implemented for now.
Because that's the thing that will probably want to get to when I
return.
And what else we got?
Debug.
That's not Global.
Debug table.
That's what that should have been and event.
Array is not a member of debug table.
Really.
You know what?
I believed you, it's called events.
So assignment within condition, especially, oh.
Well, you know, if it's going to come complain, it's going to
complain.
I believe these days you can silence that Warning by doing that.
Or not.
I wanted there to be an assignment or think it is.
That's why I put it there.
Fine, Mister poopy pants.
Stupid, poopy sauce.
Poopy pants.
All right.
So, there is the version that you're happy about compiler person.
I hope your generated such much better code now.
anyway, so I think
That's all the busy work, we have to do.
But now if I'm not mistaken, we will just grow our frames will grow at
infinitum, right?
We'll just, we will use up all of the memory that we have in our
buffer and we'll just get to an assertion when we get too many frames.
Right?
So, just add it.
Will add add, add, add add, add, add to the frames, and then, just
just halt, it'll be like, hey, I got nothing right.
I believe, that's what should happen.
Of course, we may have other bugs, but, you know, we'll see.
Oh, that's some copypasta there, as you guys call it.
That's not supposed to be collation, frame.
That supposed to be result.
Here we go.
That'll be handled by the zero struck.
There we go.
Okay, so now in theory, like I said, we're there we go.
That's why I started.
I was like, in theory, it should, it should get to a point where it it
goes.
Hey, you ran out of memory.
What do you want me to do about it?
And that's exactly what that is right there.
So, all we need to do now, to kind of finish this up.
And I'm almost out of time.
I don't know when we started 617, something like that.
I'm not sure all we do now is a way of reclaiming, some memory, right?
We need a way to reclaim some of the memory.
And this is the first time we've really, ever done this in handmade
hero because like I said, 99.99% of the time your memory just
management.
Just isn't a thing you ever think about once in a while it is.
So this is like the first Destructor style thing, we will do.
And you'll notice it's not even in the game code, write it.
In the debug system, which is kind of amusing.
But point being.
This is something where we actually want to go through and we actually
want to free a thing, right?
And so here in free frame, you know, and I might even make a note of
it here.
I might even say something like important
okay, see this
actually gets
read as a set in three frame.
Because, like I said, so much of the time.
I don't actually ever get rid of things in that way.
It's something that's potentially worth noting for that reason, right?
So what we would need to do is have some way of freeing a frame.
Regions are a little bit of annoyance here, but debug variable group
is the other part that we can take a look at.
So if we want a free frame, how would we do it?
Well, first of all, we would want our to be able to put it back on our
free list.
Certainly
Lee, right?
So you know, since it's coming from a free list, presumably we want to
put it back in my face so we'd want a frame free list so we'd want
free wrist di Alec
Try something like this.
And if you're going to be like ate something from the free list that's
again, really, really straightforward.
All that's going to happen.
There is you're going to have something like this.
Which is like the pointer in the free list pointer.
And what you would do is, you'd say, okay, the free list pointer,
whatever the pointer is that you've given me and I'd probably check
it, I just say, okay, if the pointer if you actually give me something
nonzero, then whenever the next free value is,
Right.
It's going to be equal to whatever is on the free list right now.
And then the free list is going to be equal to the pointer.
That's it, right?
That's all I actually need to do to free something.
And so, you know, we would we would free list, you allocate this
thing, you put it back on the on on the free store, right?
so,
What do I want to do about the rest of it, right?
So it's because we still got a few more things that we need to deal
with here in that in that guy.
So route group, we would need to free.
So we need to do free variable group.
And that would just be the route group that it's freeing.
This is going to be debug State first free frame.
And in here, you know, now what we'd want to do is do the free, the
free list allocate situation in here.
Now, there's a bit of a problem with it as well.
Something I don't super love and this is a thing.
We could we could decide to sort of
modify a little bit if you will, which is we could do something like
this.
But I want to know when something's allocated new meaning, I want to
know the, I want to differentiate between something that I'm getting
that was from the free list versus something that was not from the
free list if that makes sense.
And so that's kind of again, something that I may want to modify this
a little bit the way I would do that, right?
Is I would get rid of this.
Of it.
And one of the nice things about that is it would mean this would go
back to just being this.
Right?
And I could do something more.
Like this would be a little bit better, potentially, right?
So this would be something more like okay, you know, here's my debug
result.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to say free list allocate
Whatever the free this pointer is, which would be debug State.
Like, first reframe,
I want to allocate that and then assuming that I don't get it then
I'll do this stuff, right?
Something like this.
I feel like that's what I would mostly want to do.
So yeah, so the only you know, but even though even though I look at
it, it's still not going to be enough.
It's kind of annoying because I think I actually just want this to, to
do its thing directly.
So maybe I will just leave this because the most of the time people
will do it.
The other way, I don't know.
I'll show you why it's kind of a little bit janky, just the way that
you're going to want to do this, at least for the time being, but it
might be something that collapses a little bit.
When we change the way regions work, it'll probably collapse.
Oh, I'll be okay.
That it's just a little annoying.
So what we want to do here, right?
Is we want to be able to say, okay.
Do you bug State first free frame?
Right?
I want to say if the result then do this thing, you know?
Oops.
Do this thing else, do this thing and I want to actually put stuff in
the in the block, right?
So
This if we got one off of the free list, then I want to do a zero
struct but I want to save the region pointer, right because I might as
well just use the memory.
I might as well keep that memory, right?
So what I want to do there is say okay, you know, do a zero struct.
I wish you could do clears easier and C++ like clear this thing but
not this member or whatever because I find myself wanting to that all
the time.
But anyway, debug region.
Where is that at?
There it is.
So I want to do something where I say, okay, the frame.
That was there.
The one that we got?
I want to store save its regions pointer after I zero it out, then I'm
going to set its regions pointer.
Back to the old one.
Whereas in the case, where I get this new one, I want to be able to do
this, right?
So that's again just kind of an annoyance.
We can certainly fix it later but that's the reality of what it's
going to look like at the moment.
I think so.
Here's our push Direct.
Everything else should be fine, right?
So, that's how that would work and all we would really need to do now
is work on our variable groups, how those are getting freed, right?
So, let's take a look at this in here.
Did I reorganize this?
What did I do there?
How did I, what did I end up doing
So we've got our free list allocate.
There we go.
Through this Kate.
Free variable group.
So now free variable group.
We've got these guys here.
So free variable group obviously is going to have to be probably wait
till next week because I am out of time.
Unfortunately.
But we're mostly done.
So that that went a lot quicker than I thought it was going to.
I thought it was going to take a much longer time but it didn't
So we'll get in there.
We're definitely getting there.
For right now, you would not be able to actually still quite get
there.
Like I said because this will hit that assertion as soon as it gets
enough memory.
It's going to hit that assertion right?
So we're almost there we will take a look at that when we come back
from break it's more or less done.
It just needs a little bit more love to sort of get across that finish
line.
Also, we would need to when we're doing the collation, we need to like
do the trigger for this.
So like to do
Also remember to trigger freeing frames.
During Arena pushes.
All right so I think that's roughly it.
Let's still go to a Q&A.
What I would like to do just to make sure that people who are playing
around at home, who want to play with some other Parts.
Source Code don't have to deal with the fact that our debug system is
kind of still in flux.
What we can do is go to handmade debug interface and we can make sure
that this stuff can be compiled out, right?
So what we can do and here is say like, all right,
Let's update our macros to make sure that building out works.
Okay, so if we look at handmade internal, if I just get rid of that we
should be able to sort of clean this stuff up, right?
And this shouldn't be defined should just be that, right?
Yeah.
So what's happening here?
Debug ID is what syntax are missing something?
Yes, that's true.
Okay.
And so that compiles, all our debug code out.
And so then we're just back to our super Speedy.
Nice little soft for rendered World here, and everybody's happy right
now, so that's all good.
So let's just make sure that that's that way.
And now we can sort of go to Q&A and leave it for next week.
I mean, two weeks from now.
So, I'm pretty happy with that.
That went pretty quickly will be done with that and another hour and
we'd be completely done.
And then, you know, we'd have a pretty nice.
Pretty nice Diva.
Collation, it wouldn't be taking any extra time per frame to because
we'd only be doing just that one frame.
So it should probably run pretty nicely.
I would think.
But yeah, we have to because we have to do the copy outs as well.
So we'll yeah.
We're getting there.
Any questions?
So that's good.
Everyone is totally done.
I've rare once collation is done will be get hierarchies going next.
Yeah, hierarchy is really doesn't is really easy because we already
implemented all the stuff for our keys.
All we have to do is just do the little search for the string.
It's just, it's really just the string.
Search is all, it is, so that's pretty, that's really trivial.
This is the hard work, is making sure that all the collation stuff is
Now is working in a sort of a permanent
Memory.
Cycling way.
So any programming questions?
Do we have any programming questions?
It does not look like we do.
Quarter Tron.
Are you going to do some tricks for compile time?
String searches.
I don't think so.
What do you mean quarter Tron?
Gragas the Lesser come.
I worked at you.
Would fail a code review.
Mr.
Lee right now.
How do you feel about those practices?
I find that the more like the more overbearing, a company tends to be
at code review.
The more ridiculously terrible or software, seems to be like I know
like for example like Google is super, super hardcore about like
having every piece of code be reviewed and everything.
And there are software is
Incredibly buggy and it takes them forever to do anything and like,
you know, bugs and feature problems in Gmail will last, you know,
years, you go on like their forums and people have been complaining
about the inability to set like a calendar date for, you know, for
years or something like that.
So I'm just like,
You know, it the proof is in the pudding.
and, and so, I would say like,
If you want me to start believing in some of these techniques that you
Advocate, I want to start seeing you ship quality software in a timely
fashion, that's performant and they do none of those things.
At least.
Most of the places that I've seen that that are very rigorous about
code review as well as the same time.
A lot of places I know that are not rigorous about code reviews.
Like video game developers ship things that are vastly more
performant, that ship every year that are completely different every
year.
And I'm just like okay
What's the deal?
Like like where there's a disconnect here?
You know, it looks tint from the outside perspective, what it would
look like, is that people who do code reviews, ship, were software at
a slower rate with more bucks and so I'm just like, I don't know how
to and it's less complex software as well, which is interesting,
right?
So I don't know.
That doesn't really say anything about code reviews, you know, maybe
they're actually great and it's something else about the to, but code,
reviews, have, just not looked particularly great to me, and
You know, I think they have a place even you know I even might
sometimes if I really wanted to ask someone about a particular thing
that was working on, you know, maybe I would want them to review it.
I could see, you know, having a second pair of eyes on a problem, can
be pretty useful, but systemic code reviews are pretty useless in my
opinion.
Brutal BK, do you use SQL?
And if so, how do you structure your databases?
I I mean I have used SQL.
I'm not sure what you mean by.
How do you structure your databases?
That's a pretty open-ended question.
Where did you run?
I imagine that all the paths will be known at compile time so you
probably don't need to do a stir comp but I'm not sure if this using
the addresses we work.
Now we'll have to do a stir comp because the addresses will change
when we re when the executable reloads and stuff like that.
So we will have to do some of that.
And we also need to parse, we need to parse the paths to line things
up inside.
To line things up like inside of the hierarchy, because because we use
like underscores to indicate hierarchy stuff.
So we need to parse that
Easy side, by the way, I tried decal type on clanging, it worked in
the same kind of context.
I think CL is probably broken that maybe true wouldn't be the first
time
Clang is usually way more flexible than CL.
Case the heck can you give us some programming challenges for until
you get back?
So I'm pretty sure I've said this before, and if you haven't done it
already, this would be the definitely one to do it in the renderer.
There's a draw a rectangle function that we never optimized, right?
It's just a solid filled rectangle Cindy, optimize that.
Time it find out how long it takes Cindy.
Optimize it see how fast you can get it compared to where it started.
That would be like a really good one to do, right?
Would it be viable to write a game that uses a database model and its
logic as database Transformations?
I have done that before.
Actually I do not recommend it databases have some pretty severe
problems that make them not particularly suitable for the things that
games typically want to do.
They are actually the same reasons that databases are bad for a lot of
things.
And you typically put up with the fact that databases are bad at those
things because they debases have certain other things.
You want?
They have like like Strong's sequencing and they're, well, there's the
number of things I won't go into why databases are good for certain
things, but point point being fault.
Tolerance.
Bubble Up point being databases while they do work for some very
simple stuff.
The the graph like the connectivity nature of most gaming data, makes
it.
So that databases are pretty poor fit since databases traditionally
relational databases have a very hard time.
I'm with graph theoretic operations.
And so, the kinds of things that games might do like a star and these
sorts of things where they're searching spaces databases tend to break
down, pretty pretty hard there.
And so when you're talking about using a database for something like a
game, if you're not just talking about something that stores basic
back and information like people's scores or the results of matches
which you can totally do right.
Like that's fine.
Databases are made for that.
It's great.
If you're talking about something richer like the actual game logic
itself, you typically are talking
Looking at more a post sequel for lack of better term, database
technology, meaning you be looking at more avant-garde stuff, sequel
is the old-school basic data row, kind of stuff, if that's what, you
know, what I mean.
Rows and columns relations kind of thing, and that just doesn't handle
graphs the way you want it to.
And, you know, there are there's plenty of database research on graph
theoretic sorts of stuff in that would be, you know, I would say that
if you were going to try and do something that you'd have to, you'd be
talking,
Talking more about that sort of more, modern branch, and not sort of
the older, like calcified sequel stuff because that's just not going
to fly.
Martin Cohen, my mind cannot stop thinking about the scratch memory
thing.
You talked with John the other day on the pre stream, I'm sorry.
If this law of topic, it was a piece of memory that is Kept For Thread
and grows a little.
Do I understand it correctly that?
You're passing it down the call stack so that each function going to
push and pop a piece of scratch memory from it.
Yes.
Basically what that is.
Is, if you want to ensure that you can always work without having
thread-local storage, which you don't necessarily always have,
although they like, like shared libraries, for example, can't
necessarily have it.
And there's, there's a bunch of things about it, but if you're worried
about thread-local storage, then if you just have the first parameter
to all of your functions via context, and that context is per thread,
then you can have your own like, memory Heap per thread, so that
Only when there's contention on actually getting more memory for the
Heap.
Do you actually hit anything?
And what I typically do is I have that buffer kind of be expandable
and it usually persists across the thread so that you know it grows to
the size that thread typically needs and then just stays that size and
never has to be fussed with.
That's a common thing I might do, it's pretty handy.
I use it for a lot of stuff.
Mysterious J.
I've never thought about metaprogramming much before it sounds real
interesting.
Do you have any recommendation for more information on it?
I do not.
It's a fairly it's a fairly obscure thing.
People don't talk about it very much.
I like it a lot but it's both kind of old school.
It was more popular.
I think in the old days but I like it quite a bit question.
What happens to the particles more simplified close injection?
If you at the same time, hold and drag the window.
Title bar.
This is the game timer will be paused when the window is in the drag
size, mentioned message, Loop built into windows.
So,
I guess what I would say is I don't think you really care.
You're just giving that as an example like, right the this
This sort of thing because I don't actually know.
In fact, let me see if this is true.
Oh wait, I don't have handmade internal turned on so I can't actually
do that.
So, I don't actually know if we actually pass down.
Yeah, we don't keep the game running during that time.
It looks like.
So, I don't think the particles would do anything differently, but if
you're asking the more general, question of what happens to simplified
Collision detection during frame rate spikes?
The answer is yeah, they would break down, right?
And so, one of the things that you have to architect, when you're
doing stuff is like, we don't actually have a particle system in the
game, like I showed some basic particles.
Some stuff like just as a 2 day.
Excursion thing, we did at one point but if we were actually putting
particle systems into this game, which we probably will do at some
point, we would need to Define what the maximum frame rate spiked.
Be and cap are frame rates to never Spike above that, you know.
That's and then you just have to make sure your algorithms work that
way because it's very easy.
It's definitely very easy to define a, you know, some kind of a
What's the word I'm looking for?
It's easy to Define, some sort of a function physics wise that will
not work particularly well, across frame rate spikes.
And so you do have to be, you know, you do have to be aware of it.
Dragon Master 47, how would you abstract a math Library?
As in the game engine uses a V2 V3 V4 class and you have to do,
Graphics lives, the predefined vector class.
They use for rendering, but you don't want a couple your game with one
of those Libs, I don't use libs that make me use a vector class like
that.
Just I, that would be that would I would immediately not use that
Library full stop.
Like, if it can't take a float pointer, for whatever it is then I not
going to use it.
I think that's about it.
Okay, I'm going to close down.
Let's go ahead and shut things down here.
Save our lovely drawing high quality, high quality.
Okay, thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of hammy
hero too and pleasure cooking with you.
As always, we're almost finished learning about collation, so it's too
bad.
We're going to be off for two weeks but that's just the reality of the
situation.
We'll pick it back up and we're done.
Like I said there's not really much left to do on that anyway.
So it's, you know,
Besides we left like right in the middle of some crucial thing, it's
going to page out of our brains.
We're not going to do, it's like should be pretty fine because it's
just some very basic stuff left.
So anyway, we will be taking a two-week break because I will not be
here so I cannot Stream.
So if you are trying to follow along the series, now would be a good
time to catch up on any old episodes you missed.
You'll have two long weeks to do it and then we will be back after
that.
As always if you want to follow along with the source code you can
always
Go to the game on hand me here at work, comes to the source code, so
you can play around with it for two weeks while you wait for the next
episode, you can also check the tweetbot.
So when you want to find out when we're coming back, you can always
subscribe to that.
Tweet by they'll tell you.
We also have patreon page to want to put the video series and a forum
site, which allows you to post questions like that, all of that, good
stuff.
Also note that in the Forum site, we've got an episode guide here.
That may blow and several other people from the community have been
working on.
It's pretty great, it's got time like you can go to something on it
here and it actually has like Jump Markers for time so you can kind of
like go to different answers to questions or things that I did on the
streams pretty handy and we will soon be updating this video archive
link to point probably directly there because it's been going for a
while now and it seems to be pretty high quality and pretty up-to-date
all the time.
So I think maybe it's time to get rid of the YouTube archive link.
And just go directly there because it's the better way to view it for
sure.
So, that's about it.
I will see you guys in two weeks, until then take it easy.
Have fun programming and I'll see you on the internet.