Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero show.
Rico to complete game live on stream last week.
I believe, we got to the point where we have sort of a pretty clean
version of our rendering system working, where we really eliminated, a
lot of sort of the weirdnesses that that we had inherited over the,
you know, over the work on our renderer where we, you know, kind of
had had a bunch.
Stuff we were doing to support you know, 2D sorting and all these are
the sorts of things.
We went to the 3D pipeline 11 stuff was necessary anymore.
And so we kind of cleaned everything out and we now have stuff working
in.
What is a pretty sane fashion?
You can actually see that.
Now, we've just really only got one basic operation that we asked our
renderer to do.
And that is to draw a series of textured quads, which is what you'd
expect in a Sprite Style game and it to that end.
We've been able to implement some additional features like we have
now, depth, based fog.
And so this weekend, probably, I think the best thing to do would be
to just look at some of the rest of the cleanup that might be implied
by this.
Transition and to look at other things that we may need to do along
those lines.
So for example, one of the things that we had working at one point in
the original, renderer was the ability to Alpha Fade Out, the sort of
part of the, you know, the I'm not sure how to describe it really.
But in the case, where the game had a stack of levels on top of each
other a stack of
Rooms on top of each other.
So, you know, you'd imagine stairwells going up and down in between
these rooms or something like this and the player being able to
navigate through them.
In that case, you ended up in a situation where you could have a room,
you know, completely obscuring, the view of the player and obviously,
this is not good.
So one things we put it in the older version of the render was the
ability to Alpha Fade Out that top level room.
And the problem that we face now is we don't have that anymore.
And in order to implement that, again, the way that we implemented it
originally would require adding in a lot of these sort of elements
that I don't think are very useful such as sorting Sprites or
introducing some kind of a partition where the people who are
specifying the Sprites artificially.
Tell you, when you've hit the set of Sprites that's going to be in
that top part verses in the part that shouldn't be elevated out and
stuff like this.
And so what we're
Kind of interested.
Here is looking a little bit more closely at how we would Alpha fade.
Something out more automatically right like what can we do in this
case to prevent things from obscuring the player in a more automated
way.
Right, that's what we're really looking for.
So what I'd like to do today is start to investigate that a little bit
more and I think we've kind of got two things on the table that we're
going to need to sort of work on with respect to that.
The first thing we're going to have to work on is just how we will
approach such an alpha fate.
The second thing that we have to work on is our camera.
We kind of need to upgrade that to 3D now obviously our renderer
supports a full 3D camera our game at the moment doesn't really have a
very solid.
Understanding of what the camera is or where it's looking, it's kind
of ad hoc and always has been so now, would probably be the time to
upgrade that to something a little more intelligent, little more
sensible.
And so we've got to deal with those two and then eventually, after
that is done, we probably have some other like sort of remaining
issues to deal with such as finishing up our cliprect support.
Because right now our debug UI
So it is re-enabled we don't we didn't fully Port.
Some of that stuff like the cliprect stuff is not properly working in
there.
If I remember correctly.
We've got to deal with our particle systems, right?
Right now.
They are not able to Output efficiently.
Really, you know our renderer now has the ability to intelligently do
things such as not, switch textures every particle if we wanted it to
so we could patch up our particles.
A large groups and submit them much more efficiently which seems like
a pretty good idea because particles probably at the end of the day
are going to comprise a lot of our draw calls.
If we were actually changing textures, every particle, right?
That's a very expensive thing to do.
And it's not at all necessary.
Now, that the Z buffer is sorting things.
So our particle systems probably want to come down in a very specific
additional way that would add one more set to the render is, or it
could even use the same thing that we've got now.
But just a Boolean that says, whether the texture changes, every quad
or not would be sufficient for us to make sure that that wasn't going
to happen.
So we've got a lot of stuff we can look at now and I don't have any
real opinion about anything needing to happen.
First, we're just trying to sort of sweep through and make sure our
new renderer is working nicely.
And everything is good.
So I'm just going to jump in there and start doing stuff.
If you would like to jump in with me, it's 376 today.
So used a 375 source code as your starting point, and that is what I
am going to be working with as we go.
So, here we go.
in terms of just checking out where we are at at the moment, if I open
up the code as it stands,
Let's go ahead and run that.
This is what we're looking like right now and everything is pretty
good here, there's nothing particularly problematic as we go.
You can kind of see that actually you get a pretty nice 3d effect here
again.
At some point we're probably going to have to you'll notice we're not
getting our 60 frames a second.
That's because again of that function that we have in there that does
the get traversal, stuff is kind of bad.
So what I could do is I can just compiled that
violations on to fix that for the time being while we're playing
around with it, but it would be nice to run at 60 frames a second and
debug mode and really there's only a few small reasons why that's not
possible at the moment.
Okay, so anyway, here we are at 60 frames a second and so if I kind of
come down here, you can see, you know, some of the problems that we do
have.
So here I am, you know, bouncing around at the bottom level and you
can kind of see that you'll have to ignore the fact that currently we
allow familiar is to float.
In between levels, which is not particularly good.
So that that dude right there is literally just kind of floating up in
the air, which he's not really supposed to do, but you know what, he
gonna do anyway, you can see that when I get down here, it's very
problematic because, you know, obviously we would like the upper area
to kind of go away at this point or something to happen here.
And again there's just a whole host of problems here.
We also don't really prevent you from hopping up in.
Through the ceiling.
Like, you can see this happen a couple times here, right?
Where you, we allow you to pick stuff that this not even really
connected.
If there's something blocking your ability to jump, we don't really
prevent it.
So you know, if you're coming along here and you know this guy's in
your way or something.
Well or I guess that guys in my way when I hop I'm allowed to kind of
hop up.
I believe here I'm not actually 100% sure if that's true.
Yeah.
Well looks like it skips over there so I'm not sure why it did it
there but point being
Popping stuff is completely, you know, just placeholder at this point.
So we get some weird stuff like that.
But in terms of the renderer that's really not a an issue.
What is an issue in terms of the render is what we're looking at right
now, which is a situation that will absolutely occur, even if the
hopping code is all quite correct.
And that is specifically that when I'm hopping along down here, if the
camera was, and again, the camera is just kind of picking randomly at
the moment.
But if the camera does decide to be up here, which is a reasonable
Place, potentially for it to be,
We would like this to go away and more specifically, you know, as you
come up and down those stairs as the camera moves in and out, we would
like it to go away in a nice clean fashion, right?
So I think the first thing that I want to do probably is fixed the
camera code and so there's a couple different things that have to
happen there.
But basically what I'd like to do is make it so that the camera is
doing really, you know, more more.
What we expect it to do.
In the final game, right?
So, you know, actually I have the camera code properly follow the
person around properly, understand what room it's looking at and
properly, understand when would need to transition between two rooms
in order to better support the players view of things, right?
And we don't really have that right now, largely, because when we
moved to the 3D system, we haven't really finished upgrading our
notion of rooms in order to really like allow the camera to think
about them properly.
Okay.
So let's see what we can do with that and you know, with an eye
towards actually having the camera, be proper.
Now I'm going to go ahead and eliminate some of the rooms that we
have.
Just a weekend, keep things a little more straightforward for
debugging.
I want to get us down to a simpler case rather than two rooms.
You know, let's just try.
I'm sorry.
Rather than 10 rooms, let's try two or three rooms here, which again
will also speed things up because
That one function that costs all our time.
So we'll least be a little bit faster too.
So what we're going to look at cure is just this one case, you can
kind of see what we're looking at here.
In terms of, you know what else?
I probably do turn off fog when we're in debug mode.
So Fox should probably only be on here and when we're out here we
should probably turn off that fog.
Its pleasant though, isn't it?
I like it.
It's just not really conducive to debugging.
That's relatively straightforward to do, thankfully, because the way
that we've structured, the fog is that when you actually do a setup
push, right?
When you come in here to the camera setting code, which is here, we
actually know which one we're doing, right?
We know whether this is a debug camera or not because you can see that
we set the flags here.
So we could do is say that.
In this case, the fog start distance, and distance and Direction
there.
We could go ahead and
Let's let's only do that in the case where we're actually not debug
you know?
And so in the case where we're not debug, I'd have to see here.
It always uses the last set up so we probably want to do here again is
make sure that the fog direction is is getting cleared.
So I think we'll probably want to do is say in fact really I guess we
don't really need to worry about setting the start and end distance
really.
All we need to do is worry about that fog distance.
Because remember, this fog distance is what is the vector that will be
used as a DOT product to determine how far away something is from the
camera.
And again, we've set it to the cameras location because we set camera
P, right?
We set camera P right here.
And we're going to measure along this Vector that camera P, right?
But the crucial thing to understand there is that when we do that
measurement,
At that point, we can just say well okay if it's a debug camera is
just measure along something that never will produce any value at all.
Right.
If we give it the zero vector and say measure how far away something
is along this, it'll say well it's zero along it because the dot
product with it is always again, A B cosine Theta.
Remember I say that every time that a b cosine, Theta, in this case,
if the a or the B where zero length, then the whole term is zero
length.
In this case, we're just giving
A Direction with zero length, with means that when you specify debug
camera, you will get no fog at all and you can see that.
Now, when I switch between them, right, there's the fogging you can
see that it gets darker as it goes back and closer to the gray value
when I switch the debug camera.
Now, they're all the same color, which is exactly what I want.
And so now if I want to look at things like so I can look at them
without them fading away, which is what I wanted.
And so there's my three rooms stacked, on top of each other.
Then I'm going to use here.
And what I'd like to do first again is kind of return us to a sort of
a more rigorous way of defining, what a room actually is.
And I'm going to have to think about that a little bit because in
order to really figure out what's going on with that, I'm going to
have to start thinking a little harder.
About how we're defining some of the things that were defining.
For example, I think our Collision volume stuff is kind of a little
crappy.
It's not very good right now and the way that we're sort of doing that
is probably not the best way for, you know, defining something like a
room.
We kind of just want to say here is what the bounds of the room are
and I don't know that we really want to go into all that much more
detail than that to be completely honest.
So I feel like there's
Is a certain degree of bogus - to how we're doing that.
And we'll have to, I have to double-check and make sure I don't want
to change a little bit of that as well.
But what I'd like to do now is basically have something that, you
know, creates sort of boundary right.
You know, a bounding box here where I'm going to draw, you know, a
volume that shows where each of these rooms considers itself to be an
One of the problems with doing this and I don't really know what our
definition of it should be, but one of the problems with doing this is
I don't really know how to define the extents of these rooms all that.
Well, but what, I think should probably be the case.
And again, I'm just sort of speculating here from looking at.
This is what I think, should probably be the case, is that a room
should be defined as being the lowest point, that any of it, of these
sort of, you know, standard standing pieces.
Probably the lowest point of one of those up to where the Next Room.
Started.
so, like the lowest point on one of its to the lowest point on its
upper neighbor,
You know that's the size of a room, right stated alternately.
If each room was going to be the roughly the same size stacking wise,
which again we don't actually require them to be for any particular
reason and so we don't have to do that necessarily we can have some
rooms that are taller than other rooms in order to make that a little
cleaner.
I just have to figure out some way of saying, okay, let's just make
sure that when we Define what a
Is when we place the standing blocks on it, let's just never put any
of those down low enough that they, you know, cross through the bottom
of the rooms lower plane, right?
That's just one intuitive idea about how those should be specified.
I don't have any real reason for picking that.
Just a purely can, you know, it's pure conjecture on my part.
I don't have a lot of and I mean the back that up.
So I don't know if that'll actually be what we do, but something like
this needs to happen and so what I'd like to do now is get to a place
where we can see that happening maybe add the ability to draw that.
I don't know what that's doing there.
All right.
Maybe add the ability to draw that in so that I can see it.
As I would like to be able to verify that as something that's going
on.
So I would like to be able to see those boundaries.
And at the moment, the only thing that we have right now in terms of
what we can draw our these sort of flat rectangular outlines.
And so I think what might be more interesting to do at this point is
say let's add something that can draw a volume.
I want to say that my blow actually requested this last weekend and I
believe at that time, I said that would be a very good idea.
Not only do, I think it's a very good idea, but I think we should go
ahead and do it right now because I'm going to need exactly that.
So let's take a look at how that would work so you can see on here.
We've got a notion of a push wrecked and we've got a notion of a push
wrecked outline.
And the interesting thing about the push wrecked in the push wrecked,
outline is at the moment.
They all
Assume that they're going to draw a rectangle which is flat to the
world z, right?
In other words,
if you were to take,
If you were to take the flat sheets of the of the game, like a flat
sheet, you know, wherever you want to imagine it and you imagine us
sitting here at the top looking down on this here with our little
camera, you know.
I'm going to draw an eyeball because I'm we're used to drawing that.
So, if we're looking down on this with our eyeball, previously, all we
could really do is say, let's draw.
You know, a thing that looks like this and the way that we were
drawing that is either we'd solid, fill it.
That was pushed wrecked or push tricked-out line with just draw
several solid, filled ones that just expanded along sort of the, the X
and y-axis to produce for filled rectangles, which made it look like
an outline.
So, the
Question I have here is, can we just go ahead and say let's get
something that's like push volume outline that basically does exactly
the same thing.
So if I want to hear, I'm going to try it.
I like that that expanded too inefficient in line.
There are definitely a lot of things we do that are inefficient here.
Maybe someday we'll fix those, I don't know.
So if we have a push volume outline and I take, you know, basically
the same parameters here.
So I've kind of got an object transform and then instead here I guess
I would take a rectangle three assuming we have one of those and
remember forever to find one of those.
So there'd be nosy, they're just be a color and a thickness and that
would be it, right?
And and so this would be what we would be looking at.
Okay, so if that was what we were going to do and also these other
transforms are probably things we could possibly get rid of by now as
well.
I should just mention that because we're sort of since we're fully 3D
now.
The app transform is really all that necessary to take a look at
what's actually in there.
It's got almost nothing in it.
It's really kind of a relevant and so this maybe
This may have become irrelevant.
So at some point, we're going to probably want to do one final pass
over this stuff.
We're we're just like, okay we're done with everything.
Now let's just do a cleanup pass on anything that we think is kind of
dumb because at some point we probably, you know, after you do all
your experimentation and work and you're like, this is what we're
going with.
You typically need a little bit of time to sort of straighten out the
Legacy vestigial remains.
So if we push a volume outline here than what we can look at and say,
well, okay, we've got
This ability to push these rectangles on here but these rectangles are
not really exactly what I want because we look at how they work again.
They they're very heavily, biased towards having the Z values, be a
specific thing and that's not really what I want.
So what I'd rather do here is I'd rather start looking more for
example, like at push Cube and say, let's let's start with the push
Cube code because push cube is really more.
What I'm, what I'm looking for.
Right.
And, you know, in fact, Let me let me kind of
Move this up here to where the push Cube stuff is and we'll take a
little bit more of a closer look there.
So I'm going to go through here and say, all right, let's go ahead and
grab this squaws group here.
And I'm going to go ahead and put that into push volume outline.
You can see that we've got a bunch of stuff here like texture
coordinates and stuff which won't really, really be necessary because
we won't really be using a texture here.
But that is kind of neither here nor there what we will be doing.
In this case when we is will be following push Rex example in one case
which is that we will not actually be setting any particular bitmap
color, sorry any particular bitmap value will be using the white
bitmap so that we don't get any contribution at all from it.
It.
So we're going to we're just going to go ahead and do it that way.
So what we'd like to do here is we'd like again to pass a rectangle
three down.
I don't know if we have one of those.
Let's I hope we do.
I thought think we do.
Yeah we do.
So what we want to do is take this rectangle 3 and we want to be able
to draw something that looks to the viewer.
Again only for debug purposes.
So it doesn't have to be perfect but that looks to the viewer like a
Outline of a volume so you can kind of see where the volume is, right?
And so if you look at what we're going to have to do this, this set of
push quads is not particularly useful to us.
And the reason for that is this set.
Of course quads is drawing faces, right?
And so there's six of them because it's drawing six faces of a cube
but we would rather do right?
Is we want to draw the edges of the cube, right?
So instead of drawing 6, there are 6 faces to a cube 8 vertices but if
you look at how many
Just there are right.
There's one, two, three, four on this face.
One two, three, four on the back face and then for attached, you know,
connecting each one together.
So there's actually three times 4 or 12 edges, right?
You know, we've got eight vertices.
Six faces 12 edges, right?
So we want to do is we want to draw these 12 edges.
And we want to enumerate what all those 12 edges are.
And so what we could do here again is is sort of figure out a way to
push some kind of a line segment that you can see.
And so instead of a push quad, what I want here is push line segment
or something like that, where I passed the group and the bitmap and
then I pass two endpoints.
And probably two pieces of text or data or something like this, or
maybe the texture is inferred because it goes along the line at it and
then fact that's probably what happened.
Right.
And so, what I want to do here is have the ability to specify for each
of our points on the cube.
What's going on.
So, if you take a look, we've got Negative X positive x, negative, y
positive, negative positive Z.
And then we built these up.
P0 P1 P2 P3 P4 P5 P6 p7 as the combinations of those things, right?
And so what happens is in this case, we're getting them from a
different place, but other than that, everything can stay the same.
So if you look at this, we can just say like okay, all of these values
we can still extract out of our rectangle 3.
So here's our rectangle, for example, this is just going to be Minn
dot X.
This is going to be Max X, right?
Because the positive X and then these are all going to be basically
equivalent.
This is the why version?
This is the Z version min-max, right?
So then these P numberings can are all totally reasonable and can be
the same thing.
And in this case, we don't really have in terms of top color and
bottom color, we really only have one color we could make the color
vary across the line, but at the moment we don't really need to.
So all I really need to do
Is specify one, oops.
But that did there we really only need one of those and I don't need
to vary that at all.
So, all of this stuff can kind of be ignored.
The same is true for the texture coordinates at the moment.
Although I guess what I could do here is well,
Well, you know, I'm going to, I'm ignore it.
So, anyway, so when we want to draw the line, it's now what I want to
do is I want to draw a line segments between each of these that's
relevant.
And so we kind of need here is just a reason why or how to know like
which to do, right?
How to know what we want to draw.
We've got P0 P1 P2 P3.
How do we know which ones to draw between?
Well, what you can see here is essentially there, I know this is going
to sound a little weird, but just bear with me.
Take a look at how the edges of a cube are formed.
What you can say about it is an edge, a cube has an edge between any
two vertices who differ solely by the positive or negative version of
one of the variables, right?
Like we were talking about before this being Center and dimension or
maybe we're talking about Min and Max.
And so we basically have, you know, to Define where all these are.
We're always like, oh, okay, the vertices.
These of a cube right that.
Wow, that was good.
The vertices of a cube are defined by the enumeration of all possible
combinations of the Min, and the max for each coordinate, right?
So if I have X Y & Z, I end up with Min, you know, Min Min, you know,
Min Min, Max min, max Min blah, blah blah, right.
And there's eight of these because
Specifically two possibilities for each of these Min and Max, and I'm
doing all of them.
So, it's 2 times 2 times, 2, or 2 to the third, which is 8, right?
So vertices is basically the like, 2 to the Third
It's all the possible combinations of Min and Max.
Right, that's what vertices are and that's why there's eight of them
edges.
On the other hand, which is what I care about now is slightly
different.
There is an edge between any pair of vertices where only one of these
differs.
Right.
So, if I'm from this particular Edge and I've got, you know, let's say
this is Min Min Min if I want to go to another
Tell you, I have to go to Max Min Min, Min, Max Min or Min, Min Max.
Those are the three I could go to.
Right.
And so if you think about what that means is that means for each
eight, you know, for each of the 8 vertices, there are three different
ones I can go to which would appear to be equal to 24 which is not
what I said, right.
I said there's 12 Y and that is because the edge that goes in One
Direction doesn't need to be drawn in the reverse Direction.
So this Edge which went this way doesn't need to be drawn in that way,
right?
Because I've already drawn it.
So I only have to consider half of
Goes right?
And that's where my 12 comes from.
So, if I want to draw these, all I have to do is start with each of
these and do exactly that process that I just said, which is go to the
ones that are one different from it.
So, let's just start at P0 for example, and I know that p 0 is n and
p.
So, p and p would be one of them.
Right, PPP would not be one of them because that's which has two of
them.
NPP would be one of them and now I know there's three that should come
out of P0.
So what's the other one, right?
N and n would be the other one and then the rest of these won't be
right, like that one switches to that once which has three and that
one switches to.
So, there's three of my edges, the ones that come off the pp0 right
now to maximize things here.
I know that if I pick the P0 this time, right, what I should probably
do is make sure I pick one that hasn't been talked about at all.
So P2 has not been talked about here.
So let's go to P2.
So here's Pichu, that's positive.
Positive positive.
So negative positive positive.
That works.
Oops.
- - does not work positive, doesn't work.
Positive.
Positive negative does.
That's P 6.
And similarly, positive negative positive work.
So that's only one switch.
So 13 and 6, all valid there.
Right, and again, I never talked about P2 here so there's no risk of
duplication.
All right, so one more time you notice we have p 0, 1, 2 3 4.
We've never talked about five.
So let's go ahead and talk about five.
Here's P5 positive negative negative, right?
Never one that we've drawn to.
So here, we've got positive positive negative, that counts.
So, that's P 6.
- positive - that counts.
That's p7.
and now, we've got
Let's see here, positive negative negative.
There we go.
Positive negative positive.
That's P1.
Right.
So now I've got all these guys drawn, P0 to P1.
P0 p 3 p.
0 to p 4 2.
2.
P 1.
P 2.
P 3.
P 2 p 6, P, 52.
B 65-57 P5 to be one, right?
So we've got all those guys drawn and again, don't have to worry about
any duplication there because they're, you know, we basically picked
people who didn't have any overlap in common essentially.
If you imagine, let's see if we can draw this out here.
In fact, why don't I go ahead and do it so you can see what we end up
drawing.
All right.
So if you take a look at how this worked, right?
We can look at what these were set up, to be P0 P1 P2 P3, right?
So, I'm going to draw the little axis here.
I'm going to assume that we've got this.
So here Z, here's X, here's y.
So, like this in the corner?
For example, actually, I guess would be this in this corner.
This guy is, you know, - - - right, that's like - in all directions.
And then if we picked this guy here, this would be positive.
Positive positive.
Right.
So anyway, if we take a look at where these guys are p, 0 is negative
negative positive Z, surround the positive Z.
In fact, if you look at this, this is all the positive Z faces it
starts at - - so it starts at down here, right?
This is p 0 and then we go to positive negative positive, right?
So that's that's going to write here for P1 again, because it's that -
is it's not going up in y.
So, this is p 3, this is p 4 and
Then, oops, P2.
P3.
Got to make that a little clearer there.
You too.
P3.
There we go, and it certainly got the negatives here.
We had negative negative positive, right?
So we were doing exactly this.
The same process.
So this down here is P for, right?
And it went P, 508.
Know, we probably went the other way around, right?
So p 4 is negative negative negative.
This is p.
5 is positive negative negative.
So it goes down X.
Now, I guess what that is, what we did Q5.
So P, 6 P 7.
So, presumably in that case, negative positive positive is p 6.
Yeah, positive positive negative.
All right, I guess that's what we did.
So anyway, those were our points and if you look at what we're doing,
four line segments here, it's P0 went to one.
Three and four.
So P0 went to one right?
Three and four which is exactly what we'd expect.
We then move to P2, which is this sausage gentleman right here and as
P 1 p 3 and P 6.
So that's P 1.
P3.
And P6 and then we then move to P5 which is six seven and one, right?
So there's one there's six.
Wait, how do we get 7?
That's just did I mess that up?
I've drawn something wrong here because that would go like that.
According to this diagram 7 is negative positive negative.
Right.
Which is there?
That's correct.
P5 is positive negative negative, which is this.
So these two should not.
Yeah, that's a double switch, that's just wrong.
That should have gone to 4.
But we use a diagram folks.
There we go.
And that would leave us with p7, which is what should have happened
there, but of course, I misread my own chart.
I misread my own code here.
Anyway, p7 in this case.
I need to go to anyone with one change away from it.
So here's p7 negative positive negative.
So, positive positive negative would be one switch.
That's P6.
What else we got here?
That's two.
Here's one soapy for
and finally,
We would probably expect what negative positive positive.
Yeah.
P3.
So 64 and three, there's three, there's four and there's six and those
are all the sides of our Cube.
So now that we've got all that underway, let me just sort these by
ascending order here.
Why not one for 63-46?
So, those are all of our line segments, we would need to draw to form
a complete volume.
And so, if I want to complete this here, all I need to do is figure
out how to actually draw a line segment, given the information that
we're past here.
So I'm going to need that line color, right?
And let's see here.
There's my push quad.
Here's my push quad.
So actually, I suppose this push line segment, should probably come up
here.
Let's see here Squad
And it's got that packing going on there.
I'm going to do the same thing down here.
So here's push line segment.
It wants exactly the same stuff right.
So we're going to do gamer commands commands, render touch quads
equals current quads.
We're going to add a quad per line segment.
We're going to add a bitmap to it, which is whichever this bitmap, is
that we're getting past, we're going to add four vertices, which is
correct, but the way that we're going to add these vertices is now
going to be different, right?
So really what I could do because I'm going to you know because we're
going to essentially use exactly the same code.
What I could do is just push a quad here and put an end just
Compute the values that I would push to the quad, right?
So what I can do here is say alright we're going to go from this P to
this P using this color and I guess in order to be a little more
consistent here probably should do this.
Right?
That's a little bit better.
Similarly, I don't know if we want to specify UV coordinates, it's a
good question.
I'm not really sure but at any rate, we're going to have to specify a
thickness, as well.
So looking at this, what we need to do now is compute how to call this
with what were given.
So here's the values that we're actually going to need, right?
We have the group in the bitmap, so those are obvious.
So now the question is just how do we compute the rest of these
values?
and so we could say is, you know,
go ahead and
move these out a little bit here.
There we go.
So this is what we want to figure out.
And I'm going to have to name these slightly differently because it,
since we already kind of have a nomenclature for these in the quad.
I'd rather sort of have, you know, this be, you know, maybe this is
from from sea or from P2P.
Like so just you kind of say like okay I'm going from this point to
this point kind of a kind of an idea, right?
So, that's what we're looking at here now.
We've got a bunch of work to do, obviously to try and figure out how
we would make these values.
Given what we have, some of them are a little, are easier than others.
So for example, in the UV case I think we don't probably want to
support a lot of UV stuff here because we're probably never going to
be really doing anything with these.
So what we could say is well it's just going to be you know, the
basics UV.
It's just going to map the entire texture to the line.
Whatever, right?
And maybe that's a dumb idea but until we actually would have some
reason
Why we might think of doing something else here?
I guess I should probably do it this way.
Until I think of some reason why we're going to actually use texture
mapping with lines.
I don't really think there's any need to get fancier here, right.
Similarly, with our colors.
I think we can just always use one.
In this case, we can just do one single pack down.
Oh, well, I guess what we said is we could do it from C and A to see.
So I guess in this case, I'm going to do a pact
So let's do it this way.
You don't call that f.
Floating-point version.
So we'll pack those two down, and then we know that like anything
that's going to be on the, from side, which I guess, is these two here
will get that color and anything that's on the two side will get the
other color.
All right.
So, our main goal here is just to figure out what these points should
actually be.
And so, let's take a look at a diagram.
So we can figure out what we're trying to do what we've been given.
In this case is a situation that looks like this.
And what we want to do is we want to draw a line segment something
that will allow us to get, you know, some thickness here, right?
So we want to dress something.
Now, that looks like that.
Now, there's a lot of ways you might approach this problem if we were
trying to If This Were part of the game.
So if you're trying to push line segments as something that we wanted,
like a really good-looking end-user anti-aliased like beautiful line
segment thing.
What we would probably do actually is Implement a some kind of a
distance field in a Shader, right?
Honestly is what we do that way.
It would be per pixel accurate and all this other stuff.
Always correct, no math involved.
Outside of it.
And off, we would go, right, glyph drawing by using shaders is a kind
of a well-known thing right now and that's something we would
investigate if we were trying to draw like really pretty lines for the
game, but in this case, we are just in a debug scenario.
So really all we need to do is figure out what direction the line is
going and construct.
We just need to construct these points.
Right.
So what we know is we can compute this Vector, right?
If this is p 0 and this is p 1, we can certainly compute P, 1, minus p
0.
And furthermore if we were to normalize that, right, we would get a
vector pointing in this Direction.
With that information, it would then be relatively easy for us to walk
out the perpendicular of that and construct, something that looks
exactly like the diagram that I have drawn here.
So if we assume that this is actually from P, shouldn't say p 0.
And this is 2p and we want P0 P1 P2 P3 to, you know, prepare a proper
quad.
Then you can see that in this case, if we walk backwards along the
perpendicular by the thickness, right?
This is the thickness value right here.
Or half the thickness depending on how we want it.
Whether whether thickness is our radius or diameter, I don't know
whether which we want to consider, it's up to us.
But anyway, from p, in this case, if we walk backwards along the
perpendicular, by from P, we would get to p 0.
If we walk forwards along it, we would get 2 p 3 and the same would be
true from to pee.
So really all we have to do is produce that little perpendicular,
that's our entire job and we
Haven't talked much about the cross product here, but that's actually
what we would need to use.
In this case,
Technically, we wouldn't necessarily have to use it.
There are other ways that we can go about Computing.
This that would involve mapping onto the screen, axes first, and then
doing the dot product but probably the easiest way is going to be the
cross product.
So probably the best thing for me to do is just kind of briefly,
describe what it is and how it works.
So you can have a little bit more.
Of it.
All right, so the cross product is kind of usually talked about in
terms of vector products with the dot product.
In sort of the old notion of, I think, I think the correct term is
Vector calculus.
I think, but don't don't blame me if that's the wrong term.
In general.
There's been a lot of movement away from these, these ways of looking
at vectors sort of over the course of my lifetime actually not to
things that have been invented recently, but actually two things that
have invented a long time ago, but that we're just not the predominant
way of looking at things for whatever reason, Vector calculus,
Kind of dominated the engineering literature.
For the better part of the 20th century.
I don't pretend to know why I'm not a math historian, but there are
other things.
There's, I believe, differential geometry, Seth.
Is one of them in computational Geometry or sorry, geometric algebra.
There are these other ways of thinking about Vector spaces and stuff
like this that have been pushed as more modern or more useful.
Alternatives, even though again like a lot of them were actually
created quite some time ago.
They were not inventions of the 1990s or so when I think I sort of
first saw them being pushed in a wider sense.
and you will see a lot of things that sort of talk about the, the
standard Vector calculations which are DOT product, cross product
gradient Divergence,
And curl.
these folks, as kind of being very old school,
And new school is like all a whole other set of things that I'm not
even remotely qualified to say, whether they're better or worse.
I can simply tell you that there is a great deal of discussion about
it and that if this is the sort of thing that that you're interested
in, you probably would want to take a look at some of these things.
Differential geometry specifically is the one that talks about these
Saucy gentleman right here.
Gradient, Divergence and curl.
And geometric algebra is the one that talks about these sausage
element.
Obviously, there's a plenty of overlap in between here, but geometric
algebra is basically, a way of of no longer conceptualizing things.
Just in terms of vector, it's more about sort of like plates and
But by factors and by vectors and they have by vectors are sort of two
vectors together that Define a like a parallelogram kind of a thing
and it's sort of a more unified way of looking at a lot of these
things.
Differential geometry, I know almost nothing about.
But you know, for example, there is a book, literally called grad, dip
and curl are dead, um, and I don't know if it was ever published.
The guy who I think the guy who was running a died before finishing
it, he had published.
Stan earlier one though that was talking about that.
But anyway, it's neither here, nor there.
So, you know, depending on how much you want to understand sort of the
the all of the powerful ways you could use a lot of this stuff.
You may want to look a lot deeper into this stuff than then I'm going
to mention it all today.
But before I mention something like cross product, I just feel obliged
to bring this up because while the dot product or inner product is
more of a fundamental linear algebra operation.
The kind of needs to be understood on its own terms, regardless of how
you wish to build up the rest of your Calculus or geometry
understanding.
The cross product is not really that way.
The cross product is kind of like a
It's kind of a special case kind of the thing that's sort of really
only useful in three.
Dimensions and isn't really probably the right way to think about
stuff.
Most of the time, if you have a better understanding of these sorts of
things, and it's the kind of operator that is specifically, why a lot
of people would tell you to take different approaches to learning
these sorts of things than the traditional method of the vector
calculus.
On a style, which emphasizes things like Dot and cross products as the
fundamental way of thinking about things.
And so I feel like the dot product kind of survive scrutiny.
No matter how you wish to conceptualize Vector spaces and how they
work.
But the cross product I guess I would say doesn't the cross product
can kind of be thought of more as a special case, thing that falls out
of these other kinds of ways of doing things.
Things and that probably you should understand those maybe a little
bit better if you really want to understand what was going on there.
I think that's probably pretty fair to say, I say that as someone who
isn't super familiar with all the math.
So you know, take it with a grain of salt but I guess I would just
point out that the reason I didn't mention this stuff very much when
we were talking about the dot product of so I feel like the dot
product is kind of universal and the cross product really isn't, it
cost product kind of a hack and there is an on hacky way of
conceptualizing these things if you wish to kind of dive deeper into
it.
Or at least there are alternatives, there are proposals of ways that
might be less tacky.
All right, so, all of that sort of front loading, out of the way.
Let's talk about what the cross product actually is.
And why you might want to use it.
Bearing in mind that a deeper theoretical understanding of the math
here, would lead you to other things.
And the cross product would kind of be sort of just this one form of
the equations that you end up with if you're only considering a
special case
All right, so we know that the let's take the inner product or dot
product on this side, just so you understand what I'm talking about
here.
You know, as we said, I write it in its standard Vector form.
If I have two different vectors here, x let's say well that's not news
those.
I guess.
Let's use a and b a transpose B for the dot product.
In this case, it's the length of a time's the length of B times the
cosine
No sign of the angles between those two that we've said many many
times on handmade hero and again, very easy to understand.
Once you kind of get used to it, it can construction wise, you can
kind of think of it as if you have say, for example, a b, which is
unit length.
In this case, equals 1.
And then you have your a out here, you can think of it as sort of
projecting onto
This right, right here.
Again, it's that cosine Theta term here is the Theta and this is sort
of that projection onto their forms.
The cosine Theta, length of a term again, a being the hypotenuse of a
right triangle, the right triangle, being constructed in such a way if
you think about that fundamental document.
And I'm saying it quickly, because I'm, we've said it so many times on
handmade hero, that I hope everyone is very familiar with this if
you're not.
I don't know how to say it any more than I have already said it
because we've talked about it so many times, so hopefully you're very
familiar.
You're not
Please go back to earlier episodes where we talked about the product
may be using that really cool tool by ASF Gartner to search for inner
product or dot product.
So, hopefully, everyone's comfortable with this, what I'd like to
introduce today is the cross product cross product usually.
And again, you can sort of see right off the bat.
It doesn't really make any sense.
It's written.
Like this often times, you can notice not a linear algebra.
Operator here, really, this is a matrix product.
I mean, this is a very fundamental kind of product in linear algebra.
This is not, this is just kind of like, and it's kind of like a
Sort of a something that almost a descendant of of the determinant of
a matrix.
It's it's really like I said, I just want to emphasize the
uncomfortableness of the dot product not that it's not very useful to
just kind of know how to use one now into that again but just to keep
you sort of with the understanding that there's better math out.
That sort of postdates or whose acceptance anyway, postdates.
When I learned a lot of this stuff
That can help you get more traction on it.
Anyway.
It's written like this and it's actually very closely related.
It's basically this it's almost the exact analog.
It's basically this length of a length of B sine Theta.
And so in some ways it's extremely close to the dot product but
there's one really big difference that makes it not exactly that.
And that is that it goes in a Direction.
So if you take a look at this, in this case we have a vector here and
we have a vector here but this contraction of the two vectors together
produces a scalar on this side.
And so if I wrote
Equation.
Exactly like this.
That's exactly what we would have for the cross product.
We'd have a vector here.
And a vector here.
And we'd have a scalar on the other side, right?
A single value, because remember, the dot properties is a single
value, right?
And we know how its produced, right?
It's ax BX + a YB y, plus, AZ, bz, right?
So you can see it's a scalar.
It's just a sum of a set of terms.
There's no Vector here.
There's only one value.
So, no matter how long these were, this could have been nine, thousand
units long.
And this could have been nine thousand units long when we transpose
them together.
We just get one big long thing of 9,000 terms that all smashes down
into one scalar, right?
So no matter how big the vectors were to begin with the dot product
always works and it always produces a scalar and it always produces
the scalar that follows this rule.
And again, it is dimension free in terms of its operation.
The only requirement is that the length of the, the number of elements
of a, the dimensionality of a has to be the same as dimensionality of
be.
So I can't dot product of three dimensional Vector with a 12
dimensional Vector, but I can dot product, a 12 dimensional Vector
with a, with a 12-inch elector.
So, as long as they're, they're sort of dimensions are equivalent,
then I can do this.
And why?
Because the matrix product, right?
It's fundamentally something that looks like this, right?
It's some number of elements here, some number of rows here, some
number of columns here, they both have to be equal and then I produce
a scalar
Okay, so the cross product is not that way.
It does not produce a term, that looks like this.
Rather this term is actually the length of the result.
And the length of the result is actually, the result itself is
actually a vector.
It's a vector where this is the length and the direction is some
Vector is along some Vector C, right?
Which is perpendicular to A and B.
So, C,
Perpendicular to A and C is perpendicular to B, right?
So if you imagine the diagram for this, you end up with a thing where
this part here, this this diagram, this right here is going to be the
sine Theta times a.
For example, if we had b as a unit length again, and we applied the
cross product.
We would get this same term for the length, sine Theta, a right.
But rather than just producing that length, we end up with it going in
a particular direction and the direction it goes is perpendicular to
both of them.
What that means is no matter what these two vectors are, right?
So here's the two vectors, let's say and here's Theta, right?
We're going to get this this as the length, but we're going to get it
in a vector that goes in a direction.
And that direction is coming out of the plane that contains these two.
So, whatever this plane is that these two vectors are.
And I don't know what that plane is, but whatever the plane is that's
formed by these two vectors, right?
This result of the cross product comes up and out of the plane.
So it's actually another three dimensional Vector that we are
producing.
We have one three dimensional Vector, a 1 3 dimensional Vector.
B, we cross them together, we end up with another three dimensional
Vector C and you know, it's time, I guess you could say, depends on
what to do it, but we have
Some director Vector, it's going in the perpendicular Direction and
it's going to be this long.
Right.
That's what the cross product actually does.
And then there's the question of, how does the cross product actually
do it, right?
How does the cross?
But how do we actually form a cross product that satisfies these
things?
And you know that we're going to have right three elements.
So we're going to have one term two terms, three terms.
And we know that the length of these things is going
To come out to be.
Is going to come out to be this and it's direction is going to come
out to be this.
So we know ahead of time, for example, that whatever this result is
this a b sine Theta, C, if we were to, then cross it with a, I'm
sorry, if we were to dot product, it with a or b, we would get zero.
So, regardless of the length, actually, even if we just took just the
C term, which is the directional term here.
If we said c transpose a, we would get 0 if we said see,
E transpose B.
We would get zero.
That's that's just something that we know by the definition of
perpendicularity.
And so what we could say, is that, whatever we ended up with here, in
terms of our values, whatever X, Y and Z were in this
Is we would end up knowing that once we dot product, done with our
original vectors, we would end up with zeros.
Now, the I don't know, I've never tried to solve for the dot product
in that way.
I wonder if you just could do that.
I know this is probably what no one wants to watch today, but you
know, it's unfortunately, my show which means I can do whatever I
want.
And so I guess I might just ask that question because I don't think
I've ever asked that question.
So I know that
That A cross B equals.
A bee.
Sine Theta times this C term here, if I know that that has to be the
length of it.
So what I could say is the length of a cross B equals a b sine Theta.
And I know that this C term here.
Well, I guess what I could say is, I know that A cross B.
Transpose a equal 0 and a groups.
A cross B transpose b equals 0.
If I know all of these things are true.
In theory, there are only three components to a cross product.
Could I just solve
After a long bout with mathematics, for what they had to be.
It's intriguing to me and kind of want to see if it's true.
So let's suppose that instead of looking at see this way, let's
suppose that I just start off by saying that C equals A cross B.
That is what C equals.
So what I'm really saying here is the length of C, whatever that is is
a b sine Theta.
C transpose.
A is 0, C.
Transpose.
B is 0, right?
This is what I'm starting with, in this case and so I can write these
down, right?
I can just say that c x ax, + Cy, b y, + CZ.
B, z equals 0.
I can say that CX.
BX + C, YB y + C ZB, Z, Oops.
Why did those change I'm bad at math?
We go.
This is why I can never be a mathematician.
All right, so I know that those two things are true.
And furthermore, I know that this is true and that's a much more
Fancy equation, certainly, right?
But I could in theory if I want to
I think.
I feel like I can just Square those two, right?
I don't think there's any particular reason why I couldn't.
So I could say for example that this term here, I believe, if you just
multiply both sides by themselves, since they are equal, that should
be legitimate, you'd get cc equals a
The B sine Theta, sine Theta, right?
Which contracts to just you know, c squared.
A squared, B, squared sine squared.
Thank don't see any reason why not?
Which is to say that I could rewrite that as just see x squared plus,
c, y squared, plus c z squared,
All right, that's this term here.
Equals ax squared, plus BX squared plus CX squared.
I don't know what I just did there.
That's nuts.
I meant a y squared, plus a z squared.
Yeah, be x squared.
Plus b, y squared plus DZ squared.
Sine squared, theta.
Right?
I mean again like can't say I want to try and solve these equations.
But in theory, at least,
This is just a known quantity.
These are the only unknowns, right?
So I've only got in each case.
I've only got three unknowns
And I have three equations.
So in theory just based on the definition although the plug-in
chugging in this case would be extremely onerous especially due to
this Saucy gentleman right here.
it sure seems to me like, you could do it and
Yeah, I don't see a lot of reason.
Why you couldn't
So I would be interested to just shove this into a computer algebra.
I don't have any desire to go through it.
Actually try to do that.
I would love to be able to solve that in a computer algebra, which I'm
kicking myself right now for not installing one, because actually
someone sent me one recently and I wish I could remember it, there was
a freely available one that people had recently been pushing
That I was wondering if we could possibly get to work.
I think it was say age was its age.
You take a look here?
Yes, this was it.
So I wonder if we just read, you know I don't know.
It's a it's a it's kind of a saucy Saturday at this point.
I wonder if we could just figure out how to use one of these and you
could help me write, we could learn it together and then we could have
it solve this equation for us because it's not a particularly
difficult equation.
I don't think it's just a lot of symbol manipulation in this case.
And so I would think that we could get a computer algebra system to do
it.
I should imagine.
Let's see what happens.
Here is some download information.
I am in America.
North the University of Washington in.
Seattle is actually, in my hometown.
Is this something that would run on say, windows?
I don't know.
I have no idea when OVA is, so I guess that's kind of confusing.
It says, download binaries for Microsoft Windows.
So, presumably the OVA is
I want I just don't know what that actually is.
I guess I'll just click on it and we'll find out.
So yeah.
Can't say that's going particularly quickly.
And also, if I'm reading this correctly, I guess that's trying to tell
me.
That the computer algebra system is 3.2 GB.
Is that possible?
I,
Todd.
Well, okay.
So that's a little more troubling.
Let's cancel that.
Wow.
Okay.
So do you have to run it in a virtual machine?
Is that really the case?
I, it's a computer algebra system.
How is that even possible?
I don't know.
Let's take a look at some of these other things.
Is there anything else we could do here?
So that's 57 MB.
Let's go with that one, shall we?
Let's since we don't really need anything in particular.
Let's just see if we can get this one to work.
Now, bear in mind.
The last time I did a lot of serious math work, I use Mathematica.
That's the program.
I'm most familiar with.
I have no idea how to use this, who knows if it'll work.
Cannot.
Your guess is as good as mine, but I figure we should at least start
with one that doesn't require installing a virtual machine to run an
equation.
Solver
I your guess is as good as mine, apparently.
That's where we're at.
That's where we've arrived.
In terms of our ability to program things these days, is it requires a
virtual machine of 33.6 GB, install footprint to run up, you know
program.
They used to be like a megabyte long and and there that's just.
Okay, that's where it that's where you go.
Hoof.
Okay, I don't know what to make of that.
I mean, I'm just thinking trying to put that in perspective, so 1935
right now has a footprint of 120 gigabytes of uncompressed data and
our current shipping footprint for that is one point six gigabytes.
So the actual thing you need to download is 1.2 gigabytes for 160
gigabyte footprint game in terms of uncompressed art assets, which of
course you'd never really do, but that's how big the actual data pack
is.
So this thing to run a computer algebra system is
twice the size roughly of a game that has 160 gigabytes worth of art
assets in it.
It's impressive to say the least.
I should think I don't know what they're doing with all of those, but
there you, there you go.
Okay.
It's so here we go.
Let's see if this works here.
It's doing its thing, right?
You can see it's uncompressing some stuff.
Got little cutie going on there.
Always good sign.
Here's the here's a program.
Got some got a gooey here.
See what it does.
There you go?
Looking good?
I mean, that's that's a right I mean, that's something looks like it's
got something going on here.
I don't know.
Let's, let's see what happens.
We should probably read it tutorial first but maybe we can say, you
know, in this case, Q equals 5.
False.
Maybe I have to set P recall 25.
Out five.
Okay, so, you know, this shouldn't be too hard, that's pretty
understandable.
What's going on here?
I guess, right?
This is this must be equivalents, like, does q equal 5 and it's like,
no, it doesn't because you haven't told me what Q is then.
I said Q was equal to 5 and I just guessed that.
That might be the syntax that use for assignment.
I turned out to be right, that was pure conjecture on my part.
So then I said, okay what's q?
And it said Q is equal to 5, I can work with this.
Right.
This seems reasonable.
So let's see here, if I can teach it some of these things, I've got
some equations here and so I guess, I guess what I need to know is how
you do solve, right?
And so, there should be some way to ask it to solve a system of
equations.
And that's all we really need to know.
So, here's some solve, it looks like you've got solve equation
variable, that's what we need.
The only problem is we need multiple variables, right?
And so we need
System of equations.
So, it looks like this is the only one that can solve a system of
equations.
The fact that they call that old solve doesn't fill me with bristling
confidence, but maybe I'm missing something.
Let's take a look at what else we got here.
So, let's see.
Here's the definition of it.
So it looks like this is all we would really need.
So I'll give it a shot.
I mean, according to that documentation there, right?
I can just put as many equations in here as I want and I can put in
the variables that I'm trying to solve for here and it should do.
So now it doesn't sound like it's got a particularly good solver
engine, so there's that but you know, we'll give it a shot, right?
Let's try it.
So, let's say, CX X.
Ax.
+, Cy x, a y, + CZ, x, a z, equals 0.
That's equation.
One equation, two is just the same thing but with B
And then equation.
3 is this god-awful monstrosity here, namely CX X CX.
+ Cy X Cy + z z times.
Z z is equal to ax times ax plus.
Ay, y x, a y, +, AZ X, AZ that.
Plies be x times PX, + py x b--, y, plus Z times bz.
And then finally, we've got sine Theta, which I'll just call St.
Because in this case, we don't need it to know that what sine Theta
is.
It's just a term between the, you know, in this case.
Oh well, you know what?
I guess that's not true in this case sine Theta, that is a bit of an
issue because Theta is the angle between the two vectors.
So actually, I guess that's a tougher.
Thing that I had been anticipating, because in this case, we don't
really have a way to specify what that actually means in terms of the
variables involved.
So, that is tougher.
I wonder if I can do something simpler first because if you think
about what this means, right, I have these two things and in this
case, we're talking about this part between them right here is
difficult for me to tell it how to construct.
Its this equation is just far too complicated.
These two are really easy, right?
These to involve nothing but the scalar terms without any real
understanding of the relationship between them but
This one is much tougher and the reason that it's much tougher is
because of this term right here, if we could get rid of this term
entirely, then we would be in good shape because then it would still
be very clear what was going on.
But because this term is there, we have this issue of not really
having any way of defining what Theta is because the angle between the
two vectors.
Well, how do you define the angle between the two vectors, right?
How do you compute that angle, right?
So, when we could do that is by turning to the dot product, right?
We could say something like oh you know in this case we know what the
angle of the thing is because we could take the dot product of these
two vectors together and use a b cosine Theta.
Which we could compute, right?
Since it has both of these terms.
The only part that we don't know again, is that, that final part, I'm
trying to think if there's an interesting way we could go about
producing the transform between these two because it's got both of
these terms in it.
So the A and the B, stay the same.
And then the cosine is the only part that's different.
I can't think of any real way of doing that off the top of my head
though, again, seems pretty complicated.
So, yeah, I can't, I honestly can't say, I can think of a good way to
do that cleanly, since we know that these two are our the case.
Right since I knew that these are the conditions that have to hold
true in order to solve for this Vector.
Really, what, you know, I could say here is that, maybe Let's ignore
this part for now.
Right, let's just see if we can get it to solve for something that
goes in the correct direction, which is what this is about this.
About the correct direction.
This right here is about the correct length, right?
So, in order to sort of start with, I wonder if we can get something
that figures out how to solve for something that goes in the correct
direction.
And I had to think about how I would specify that.
So in terms of the length here, I guess what I'll just say is let's
pretend, there's some additional.
Let's like I said, let's just pretend we know what that value is and
we prescribe it.
So I think I'll stick with what I said here.
This
it won't be exactly what we want, but at least it's a start and we
don't really know if this can solve it anyway, right?
We don't know if this thing actually has a reasonable enough solver to
actually do this equation, but we'll try
It's thinking.
Well.
Hmm.
I can't say I know what that is supposed to be, did I input the
variables wrong or something?
The list of results returned at each result is a list containing the
values of the variables in vilest.
Again at most a single solution is returned.
Task of solving an equation is simply delegated to such that equation.
We solve recursively first.
See because this is not, it doesn't make any sense.
C y, equals c.
Why is hardly a solution?
Because we know that's true all the time.
this starts to look a little bit more correct here, but
It's still a bit odd.
I'm not filled with confidence here so I don't know about this.
I don't know about this gentleman, maybe this is why you need the
three point eight gigabyte version.
Well, we tried let's at least just say that we tried.
Let me see if there's anybody else we should try.
That's not quite so large.
I have no idea what's going on right now, sourceforge, ladies and
gentlemen.
We're probably getting all kinds of viruses right now.
Delivered to our system.
Hello.
Okay.
So I don't really know, we'll try one more to see cuz we should be
able to get just some simple solves going here.
We weren't even really trying to solve the whole thing there.
I was just trying to ask it for a basic preliminary solve that I feel
like should have produced something.
Maybe I'm wrong about that, but we'll see, I certainly think it would
have in Mathematica anyway, using the power of Stephen Wolfram.
Who personally solves all the equations for you in Mathematica.
Let's see here.
There we go.
Okay.
Let's get our, let's go ahead and get our sourceforge.
Iris is installed.
Just some good, you know.
Excellent virus.
Nice.
Tasty viruses.
Viruses within viruses installed on our viruses.
Good luck.
Getting some python in here.
For our previous one was in Java.
It looked like or JavaScript.
I don't remember maybe JavaScript this one's in Python.
So just having some different bunch of different languages.
Working on our math here.
I don't know if this is actually something that's meant to be end-user
facing, but we'll see.
Give it a shot.
Here's gooey.
All right.
So let's take a look.
Here, here is a command.
Let's let's see if we can do the same thing we did before.
Argument cannot be an atom or subscripted memoizing function.
Alright, well let's get some help first.
Let's see if we can solve because all we're again, all we're trying to
do is solve an equation here.
We don't need differential equations solve.
We just need a basic silver.
Maybe that's what we need.
Let's just see what regular solve does solves the algebraic equation.
Expression of variable X and Returns the solutions.
Equations in X if pressure is not equation.
Equation is for certain is assuming its place so it looks like this
can take a series right?
and so, if that's the case,
It solves it simultaneously on a pond of equations.
By calling wind solve or excess returns, a list of solutions.
This case didn't solve, this addition to this argument.
So that's looks like what we would want their.
So maybe I can try that.
Now, the format of the equations, it would be nice if I could get an
example of this.
So let's let's just see if just so I get the syntax correct, that
makes sense.
I just wanted to see if I could sort of get an example of solving.
See if I can can I search inside here?
Not really, unfortunately.
Back substitute Dimension solve Global solve.
Let's see.
So here is an example.
There's there's an example of exactly what we need.
Global sulfur's are trying to Susan for this file in sulfide.
Okay, now we might need some tweaking here but we'll try.
So here is a solve, right?
Let's go ahead and see if it works.
So it produced an output where it's solved for these for these guys.
So in theory, I should be able to sort of put what we wanted to put in
here.
And see if it works.
Right, and so let's go ahead and try that.
And we'll just give this one a shot.
Maybe it'll be maybe we'll have better luck this time.
So in this case we want c x ax plus Cy, a y plus z z a z,
Right here, I want c x BX plus C.
YB y naught plus c z BZ.
Equal 0.
Zero.
And then finally got the last equation here.
Which is the one that's not really correct that c XC x + Cy, Cy, c zc
z and that equals ax ax plus BX Loops.
+ 8, y KY, plus a z, a z times BX BX plus Q by B.
Why?
Plus.
Easy peasy, Bzz Bzz.
And again, I'm just numbing in that this term sine Theta, which is not
really correct, right?
And I want to solve it for those three variables.
I'm going to hit shift enter and see if it can do anything here.
The answer appears to be no.
I guess.
It looks like it's telling me that it can't find any solutions.
I'm not really sure if that's what it's saying to me.
Italy honest with you.
I wonder if I change this term.
What if I just said that the sign between them always had to be one or
something?
Could then it do it.
Holy cow.
Well, can't say the layout looks particularly good on that one, but at
least it sort of did something.
Okay, well, that has been our foray into computer algebra systems.
I guess what I would say is
A little rough.
This is kind of experience.
I often have with computer algebra systems, which is to say that the
notion that they're kind of these things that maybe you could have to
just help you out with stuff, is a little bit naive.
You kind of have to actually take time to learn to use them really
well like possibly those ones could have been used to help us here but
it's pretty clear that like the idea that you could just enter some
math into them and say hey could you give us some insight into what's
going on here?
It's kind of not true you kind of just get
Spammed.
And either you get nothing out of them, are you get craziness out of
them?
So that's not really super useful.
So, maybe I will abandon this for now, I was just kind of curious if
we could do that.
I was kind of hoping that maybe we could do something along those
lines, but it looks like even even if simplified version, where, I'm
not even asking it to do, sort of the full solve for the cross
product, is maybe pushing the limit or maybe, you know, maybe I just
missed under misunderstanding, what's happening there?
That could also be
We could also try the 3.6 GB one at some point, but I don't want to
try that right now because we have to wait 30 minutes for it to
download.
And so yeah, that that's probably not the best use of our time.
Anyway, we tried, we failed.
That's just how that goes, sometimes not a lot, you can do about that.
All right, so I guess what I'll do here is let's just start with the
actual textbook definition of the of the cross product I'll show it
working and then I will maybe try to think tonight and maybe people
can post what the best way is for us to derive.
This I could look up some good derivations of it and just see what the
simplest one is.
Because there's probably something that's a lot simpler than trying to
go.
This route that we could do to sort of get into it and maybe that's
Easiest thing to do is since sort of the Brute Force approach.
I was just curious about took too much time in is not going to pan
out.
Alright, so let's skip that for now.
And we will simply show you here what the actual definition of the
cross product is and you can see here there's that diagram, that's
very much like what?
Wrote and you can kind of see here.
The actual definition of the dot product is actually very simple.
This is what I was hoping we'd be able to solve for and you can see
here, it looks like they've got a reasonable derivation.
That's not too bad.
I mean, it's a little lengthy in terms of this looks like what they're
doing, is they Define a few basis vectors and what the rules for the
basis vectors are and then they can produce the results.
They're so maybe we could work that one through tomorrow.
And and show how that works.
Here's the part I was talking about it falling out of the determinant
as well.
But anyway, so maybe work through that tomorrow and that can be the
way we'll drive it instead rather than trying to derive it from the
from the, from the properties that we wanted, we can sort of, you
know, I guess you could sort of still say that this is driving it that
way.
But
It's definitely sort of showing a level of understanding of it that
you'd probably only have after you already knew what it was.
So it's a little less appealing to me than a way where we literally
just State what the properties are and then out pops the equation.
So I was kind of hoping we could get to it from there but you know
maybe that's just too complicated and requires too much.
Working it through, I don't know.
But anyway, this is the actual standard form of the dot product as you
when you actually get through and figure out what it actually is.
And you can see here, it's again, 3 element Vector.
It only really works in three dimensions and you need to go into those
other sorts of branches of math.
That I was talking about to start working on ones that work in more
dimensions and you can see here, it's actually got a relatively simple
form.
It's basically, you know, these 12s and 3 Sr X y&z, right?
Our case, and you can see here that it's y, z minus z y, right?
So, whatever your first, this is a univee, it's kind of hard to see
here because you, and these look very similar.
But, you know, if this were an A, and A B, let's say right.
It's y z, minus z y, right?
Then, it's then it's z x.
Minus x z and then it's X Y, minus y x, right?
So at the end of the day, even
though, like I said, I'm not sure there's a really straightforward
derivation for it.
Even this one is kind of assuming that you already decided, you've got
these basis vectors and here's the rules for them.
So, hey, you know, you're kind of already kind of already.
Have figured out how it works, in a sense, assuming that you actually
do work at three, you end up with something that's very, very simple
and very easy to code.
It just may not be obvious exactly how you get there, right?
But at the end of the day, like I said, it's not owner, it's only
onerous to derive in that sense, it's not owners to actually use.
And so if we go to our inner product here, where we've got inner 3,
inner V 3, V 3, if we want to do,
Adopt product version of one of those.
I'm sorry I cross product version of one of those.
It's very light on the computation it's not hard at all.
So the result again is just going to be equal.
In this case, write it out this way.
To some very straightforward terms is it as simple as the dot product?
No, but it's, you know, it's pretty close.
So in this case, I'm just going to end up with an AZ b, y and, and I'm
going to subtract this from an A Y bz, like, so.
And then I've got an ax b z, minus AZ, b x.
And then finally, I've got an A why?
BX.
- A a x b y and let me just double-check that I've got this terms.
Correct.
Their said so it's 231 right 231.
Okay.
So no, not quite right 231.
I had these guys backwards.
There you go.
Yeah.
All right.
So yes, we have a y ZX Z, XY.
And again, these always go in the same order as well.
You can kind of see here that it's always XYZ.
It's just rolled around.
So it's x y, z, x, y, z, x y, z, x y z, right?
And again, that's just, this is just has them numbered, instead of,
instead of, as the actual values.
So it's one, two, three.
One, two, three,
One, two, three, one, two, three, and they just swap from either side.
So, it's y, ZZ y ZX ramp.
And again, it's very similar to The Dot product.
In the sense that the actual reason why you want, it is very difficult
to understand from the final form, right?
And so, these equations that I wrote, originally are the ones.
These are the ones that actually tell you why you care about it,
right?
Like this stuff right here is actually the important part.
But the actual implementation of it doesn't really show any of that.
So it's hard when you start, if you just were to look at this or same
with the dot product, we were just look at this.
You'd be like, I don't know why I care about basically squaring the
values, you know, are doing x times, x, y times, y, z times Z, I don't
know what that gives me.
What you know, why do I care about that?
Similarly, you'll care in your like I don't understand why this would
actually matter.
But the reason that it matters is because what it computes
is again something that's perpendicular to both A and B, both the
input vectors and something, which has a length that's proportional to
A b sine Theta, right?
And so, any one of these properties may be valuable to you and in the
case just in the interest of finishing up quickly in the interest of
doing what we want to do here.
Again, the reason we care is because we want to be able to produce a
perpendicular.
So, if we have this cross product available to us, what we could do,
in this case is produce a perpendicular, that does exactly what we
want.
Now, if you look at it, you might go well, how do, how does the dot
product mean?
How does the cross?
Our to help me.
What I said is I wanted a perpendicular to this Vector, but the cross
product requires two vectors and I've only got one.
I've only got the directional Vector, that goes from the starting
point to the ending point, right?
How do I end up producing this other one?
Well, if you think about it, really, this is a three-dimensional
construction.
I've got this line.
In 3D and I'm viewing it from somewhere, right?
And I want this to line to be flat onto the screen.
So I actually know another Vector which is the vector coming out of
the screen at me.
That's the cameras Z Vector.
So, if I was to cross the cameras e Vector with right that other
Vector.
That to Vector here, I would get this Vector coming up out
Right?
So the cameras e.
Cross the line vector.
That is going to give me that perpendicular value that I want, right?
Because fundamentally this
Right here is the line.
Here's the Z this cross.
This is going to give me something that's perpendicular to both of
them.
Which is exactly the value that I want here.
Right?
Exactly that vector.
So the cross product is actually perfect for this.
The only problem is its length is not perfect for this.
We know that the length will be proportional to the length of these
two vectors.
The line Vector.
If I just used this whole Vector here is whatever the length of the
line is and the cameras e Vector is a unit length, so I'm going to get
something that's as tall as the line, right?
I'm going to get something that would draw a square as tall as the
line.
But that's okay, because I can just normalize that Vector down to unit
length by dividing by its length, right?
I have the
Normalize the vector.
So what I can do is just start with the vector there, normalize it
down and then have the vector that I actually need to be able to draw.
My line segment, right?
So in this case, what I want to do is I want to form that perp, right?
And so this is going to be basically my, I guess my, I don't know, I
could say the vertical or lime purp like this.
and this case, what I want to do is they want to take the cross
product again, of that sort of the line Vector itself, which in this
case is going to be, you know, the going from the front point to the
two point, and I want to cross
With the cameras Z, right?
So, if I go here and I say, you can look at the
The camera.
Now since this is for debugging, what I would assume we would want to
do here is in the, in the render setup.
Right?
When we're doing here, we're storing the transform for both the
debugging game.
We probably want the debug transform because this is again for
debugging.
So we probably want to draw those in, in terms of facing our, debug
camera.
Not our game camera, I'm guessing.
So, what I probably want to do here is say all right, I've got the cam
Z Vector, the
Vector is going to be whatever.
Again, the debug transform is, I'm going to want that, that Z value,
right?
In this case,
look so, and
I'll have to also make sure that that debug transform gets set
whenever the game transform would get set to.
So, we might have to take a look at those just to make sure that
they're all kosher there.
But anyway, so that's what that value should be.
And like I said, we want to take that camera Z vector and cross it
with the line Vector, that's going to give our line perp.
But of course, we also want to do a normalization on it.
And of course, we have that ability to do our normalization on it.
You can see here, we've got our normal
Is now again, we want to avoid dividing by zero and we don't know how
long the line is.
Maybe someone gave us a degenerate line.
So I'm going to go ahead and say normalizer 0 on this cross product,
so I can get back my perpendicular like so, okay from here, it becomes
fairly academic.
Like I was saying before we know the construction as long as we have
that perpendicular, it's just the thickness times it.
So what I can even do here is I can just pre multiply by the thickness
as well, right?
So now I know I'm just adding my line
A poor subtracting, my line perp.
So what I want to do is I want to start at the front P, add my LINE,
perp right for P0 actually subtract the the purple line prep.
I guess I'm going backwards along it.
Like so the P 1 is just going to be the same exact thing but it's
going to be from the, to pee, right?
It's going to be out here and coming backwards.
Oops.
Similarly here.
I'm going to add the line perp and again, add the line perp and that's
really all we need.
That's everything we need.
And then we can pass everything that we've computed to the push quad,
to just push the standard quad on because now we know all the values
that the quad has to take.
And that's really it.
So now moving on, you can see we need for element vectors obviously
and that's fine because those are just the the only reason we're
pushing for element vectors on, there is specifically because we need
that xevious component.
In this case, we're never going to buy us disease.
So we just put a zero as the as the final one and we're good our line
segment in this case
It's to have that line color here.
I'm going to just call this C for now because we only have one of them
and I'll go ahead and put that on.
You can see if I go back to where our push line segment call.
Was it needs a from in a, to, in the sea case.
So basically, we need
See here.
Something like this.
And that just allows you to draw a line that would go from one color
to another.
In this case, we don't ever really need to do that.
We're always going to be using just one color for our volume, but you
can see how you might want to have that line be different.
There we go.
I don't know why I left that in there was steak obviously
I really need to modify my for coder config to suck up white space
when I do a delete it waste so much time.
That I don't do that and I just haven't done it yet.
I need to do it.
All right, so let's take a look here at that.
Push line segment line.
And really we should be in the Q and A now, so I should stop soon but
I think the only thing I need to do is now pass the thickness down.
There we go.
Oops.
Okay.
And these don't need to be the forest anymore.
Because that expansion gets taken care of a little later and we don't
really want them to be because again they need to be cross product and
so on inside there, so there we go.
And now what I'd like to do is just briefly test it before I go to the
Q&A and maybe do a little debugging of it just so we can get it
working.
Inside cure, for example in when we're doing this world transform,
what I'd like to do is just say like okay let's try drawing a
rectangle, just a simple rectangle that we can look at.
So if I was going to push a volume outline on here and I just did you
know rectangle min-max for example and I did two of these for you know
and just said something that was going to be very simple like - 11 1
to positive 1.
One, right?
And I'm going to draw that as a purple rectangle in this case and I
don't know what the thickness is going to be will do 0.1 F4.
Now I don't know if that's about even remotely Reese.
Well that's in World space.
It's probably a little too thick so there's that, but whatever.
So let's go ahead and see if I can run that now and we can just take a
look at what that
Us.
So, I'm going to move back here and take a look and you can kind of
see what we've got here.
It's not quite right.
It's, it's, it's not awful, but it's not quite right.
You can kind of see some rotation, they're happening.
So I think we're not quite doing the right dot product, there in all
cases, but we're closed right.
You know, we're just drawing little like line fins, which is exactly
what.
We had wanted to draw, but we do have a little bit of an issue there.
So let's just
Let's just go take a quick check.
Push line segment.
I'm in the wrong function.
And let's just take a quick check to make sure that this is, is saying
what I was doing.
Here, we have the camera Z value, and the line Z value, we should
double-check our cross product are normalizing your 0 in our thickness
for that.
Seems to make pretty good sense.
Here's our to pee and are from p.
And so, in theory, I would think we should get something relatively
stable from that, I'll have to double check just for me for my own
purposes, to make sure that that's really going to give us.
what we want, but I feel like
Just think about this for one second.
Just a hot second.
So one of the things with this,
is, you know, if we've got
This in the world and then I've got something coming directly out of
the screen.
It is true that the tilt of this Vector Z wise is probably going to
be, is going to be dependent on how this is, you know, it's really
hard to draw these unfortunately.
But, you know, let's say this was the cameras e vector.
And this was kind of pointing off in that direction versus pointing
off in this direction, the tilt of this
Is going to vary a bit there.
So it is also the case that we may want to
confine this to only being in the plane of the screen before we do our
cross product for example.
So we could do this in a slightly different way that wouldn't involve
You know, that that wouldn't involve that that extra tilt, right?
We could do it sort of a way that pre projects down to the screen.
I have to think about
I have to think about how that would work.
Exactly right.
But for example,
Here is the line equation that goes to P from P if I wanted to remove.
For example, the Zeke and the component of this that is outside of the
if I wanted to keep this in an XY plane relative, the screen I could,
if I wanted to, for example, subtract away the portion of it that
that actually fell in line with the cameras Z axis, right?
I could do that.
And I should probably explain a little bit more about what's going on
there, but hold on one second and let's actually see if this is more
what I had in mind, but I don't, I don't know that it actually should
matter all that much.
You can kind of.
See I'm still getting sort of
not exactly what I would have expected there, right?
So I want to look at that a little more closely.
And the other thing I would like to do is check that off for now.
The other thing I would like to do is check my
I cross product, which we haven't actually done to make sure that that
the terms and here are correct and that there's nothing.
Nothing weird happening in there.
They look right to me.
At the moment.
So I'm pretty comfortable that we have that correct.
X y, z.
X y.
Yeah, so that looks, that looks correct to me.
I'm pretty sure get rid of this now.
And so, my only question is, whether or not we need do anything
fancier here.
I feel like these should be more stable as we go, especially if you
were to remove.
Like I was saying the,
If you were to remove the part that is, you know, remove the part of
the, the line that isn't in the plane of the screen, which this should
do.
I would think that would give you a very stable perpendicular for
purposes of the line, but that one looked like it was tilting in a
way, that was sort of counterintuitive to me how that would work.
So I'm just not sure exactly why that would be the case.
I'd have to think about that a little bit, a little bit more closely
here but again you can kind of see
Yeah.
How that construction plays out again?
It's pretty straightforward.
So what, you know what I could do to here?
Let me take a look.
If I remove just for
person inspection, if I only have one of them,
So here it is.
So you can see the part that's kind of a little bit weird to me, which
is that I would expect this to be.
Kind of there should be a place where it does become singular when I'm
looking directly at it like this.
It should be wrong because, of course, it can't find, there is no way
to like really produce a line, in that case because I'm just, I'm
looking straight down at it.
There is no span of the line in the space of the screen, but pretty
much everywhere else.
I would have expected it to be better in terms of that.
So, in this case, for example, you know, where it's coming out here,
and so, if you imagine that in the plane of the screen, that
A pretty reasonable perpendicular.
I suppose.
But it just
I don't know, maybe that is a pre pretty reasonable perpendicular.
I don't know.
I guess now that I look at it is behaving relatively good in terms of
facing at the screen and it's really only when I look at it quite head
on that it becomes sort of tilted like that.
So I don't know, maybe that actually is relatively reasonable.
And again, all this is trying to do in this case is really, just make
sure that we're always getting some kind of width towards where the
camera is facing, right?
We're just trying to produce a 3D with that's oriented towards the
camera, which I guess is exactly what it's doing.
So I guess I don't maybe have as much complaint as I thought I did
originally with it.
That actually looks pretty good.
So maybe that's fine.
The thing.
I'm not sure about again to is whether we
Actually care about doing that.
That step of removing, the non-sweet space portion, that might not
really be so necessary, but
So here that is again.
And yeah, I mean, I guess that is pretty good.
Now that I look at it, those things are always turning to face me
pretty much most of the time.
So that's not bad.
I don't think about whether there's maybe it should be done a little
bit better, in the case of sort of those ones.
Again, the kind of spin around when we're looking kind of dead off
them because it doesn't create a particular usable version there.
But other than that, yeah, I suppose that's fine.
Again, this is only for debug purposes, so I suppose, as long as
they're
Always sort of orienting roughly towards me.
That's okay.
The thickness in this case.
Like I said, it's probably too high.
We probably don't really want that kind of thing.
Probably want more like this, right?
Certainly.
And so
Really more, what it's supposed to be drawing.
And again, when you look at it that way, now it becomes a lot less
objectionable that sort of rotation because they're not really
particularly big, but you can still see the problem right?
When its head on like that, it just has a really hard time generating
that that value, right?
That perpendicular value.
So what we could do in that scenario also is, we could, we could try
to compensate for that, right?
That, you know, we could also try to produce something that's a little
bit more aware of
That situation.
So for example, when we do push the line segment
On what we could do here is say, well, you know, when we, when we
produce this line, whatever it's going to be.
We could then say, well, let's take the line length, right?
And take a look at what it is.
So in this case, we take the length squared of the line, although I
guess we're always going to need the length.
So we might as well just take the actual length.
So we take the length of the line and we know what it is and then
inordinate, you know, in ordinary circumstances.
Answers in this case, I guess.
Now I think about it, we don't even really needed quite do that.
What I can do instead is wait till we're done with this, right?
I could take the lime purp and say, well, okay, you know, take the
cross product here of the line, perpendicular out.
What that is, and then, let's take whatever the
The line Pro length is.
There we go.
And then I'll take the line prayer and I'm going to, you know, divide
it by whatever that is right.
That's exactly the same thing as we were doing before.
And so that will produce the exact same result, right or should.
Anyway.
Let's go ahead and zoom in there and make sure it does.
Oh, and I forgot, I still need to do that thickness multiplied.
Okay, so that would produce the exact same results as before.
But now instead we have the opportunity, right to modify this as as
necessary based on what the length is.
So what we could do is say, well, if the line perp length, so, you
know, if this, if this result that we're getting is just very, very
tiny, right?
So let's say, if the line perp length is like less than the thickness
or something.
We'll do something else.
Otherwise we'll do you know what we would normally do or something?
And so we could say is well there's some thresholds here which as that
cross product to generate.
So, as the, the values come together and you can understand
mathematically, sort of what's happening there.
Right?
I've got a sine Theta term in here.
So I've got my two vectors and right, this is the definition of the
length of that cross product term as this sine Theta term goes to 0
which it will as these two things collapse.
Right as these two things come sort each other we end up with no.
Through it all.
And so that's not going to be very useful, right?
It doesn't matter what the length of the two vectors are that come in,
if the angle between them collapses to zero, the sine becomes 0 and
then we lose our term.
So as this collapses towards 0, what we could do is say let's
substitute something else in there for the perpendicular that we can
use, right?
And that might help us a little bit.
So what we could do is just say, well, whatever, you know.
Okay, fine, let's just use, we know the cameras Z axis in the cameras,
x axis or perpendicular.
And so, we'll just use that or something, right?
The, the x axis can be the thing we use for our perpendicular, in the
case, where we start to generate down below the thickness threshold,
right?
Or whatever, something like that and maybe that'll help us.
So now if we take a look at what happens there, I don't know if we get
really a much better, it doesn't look like we get particularly better
here.
I'm going to see what happens if we do something.
Maybe.
Maybe in this case a little bit above that so I don't know.
Let's let's, let's do something a little more, more thickness wise.
It doesn't look like we're really getting that case happening much at
all.
Me to see if this is happening at all here.
There we go.
So, there's what happens if you actually just always substitute in the
x-axis, right?
And similarly, I could alternatively, you know, use the y-axis, right?
And that looks like this.
Some kind of see there.
And so what I could do here is just say, like, okay, yeah, I want to
substitute that in, why?
I'm not getting more substitution of that.
I'm not sure because it looks like that's never substituting in, but
it should any time the perpendicular length is less than this.
This seems like a very high value.
A high bar to set, it looks like it's get.
It doesn't ever seem to be actually Crossing into that territory,
which doesn't make a lot of sense to me, because the length of this
line purpose,
Cross product here should get pretty tiny once we get to that case.
So I feel like this is an absurdly high value to have to set in order
for that to actually be true, which strikes me as kind of a little bit
odd, right?
So I feel like there's something bizarre going on there, so maybe I'll
save that for next time.
We can look at that in a little bit more detail for now.
I'll just leave it going with the way that it was going before and we
can, we can sort of escalator.
So this one will still have the problem of the lines, kind of
degenerating.
and when they get a little bit too head on,
Or when they become a little bit too, coincident, right with the
directionality of the, of the line.
In this case, I suppose, when I look at it too, I suppose part of the
problem there.
so,
using the cameras Z axis.
Also is kind of is not necessarily what we would want for projection,
right?
So if you think about it,
Sorry, I'm not still not taking questions by just one thing through.
So if we take a look at something on the screen, right?
And you think about how this is getting projected down out there in
the world, I've got something and I'm looking at its projection here,
if I want to create something, you know, and then I've got, you know,
I should say, I've got two things, right?
One there, and one there, and I'm projecting them both onto the
screen, and I'm drawing the line between them.
If I want to look at a perpendicular to it, to this.
Line.
In either case, I guess one problem here is that direction itself?
Do I actually want to use, for example, the vector to the camera from,
you know, the end points of the line to determine where those, those
perpendicular values should be.
So, you do two cross products, produce a separate fin in both cases
because the fin is going to be projected as well.
And so what is perpendicular to the camera?
Either point.
It's hard to say, right because that line, that gets that gets
projected into the screen.
Yeah, I can't decide on that.
Maybe I'll go to the Q&A first because I feel like this is too big of
a topic.
I kind of want to go into this in a lot more detail actually.
Now I think about it because of the geometric construction is a little
bit more.
Interesting.
So let me go to the Q&A and we'll deal with this more tomorrow unless
the Q&A is all about it and then we can keep going.
Oh no.
Why is the Q&A button?
Not working is in sabac gone.
What happened?
I hit I hit exclamation point Q&A.
But there's no.
Does anyone know what happened in sohbat?
Oh hm.
D-bots handles the Q and a message and seems to be dead.
It does see we did like hmd Bots, not on there.
Like it's not on the list.
So I don't know what happened to hmd, but hmd bot is dead.
That's unfortunate but well, alright, you know, that's just that's
just what happens sometimes.
All right, so apparently, okay.
So just so you says, you can solve those equations in Maxima.
It looks like somehow your Maxima is actually able to lay out the
results properly which is nice.
Engineer, what would be the downside of drawing your debug lines as 3D
cylinders or extruded rectangles.
It seems like that would look a little nice.
When viewed from all angles we could do that.
Yeah.
If you'd like.
So a cylinder in this case would be relatively simple.
The hardest part about the cylinder is going to be the end caps of it,
which I suppose we could you know maybe avoid to a certain extent but
yeah, cylinders not too bad.
A cylinder is just, you know, a circle with stuff on either end if we
wanted.
To do that.
Let's see.
so, if we wanted to draw line segments, that way, I'll just if 0 this
part out here,
if we wanted to do it as a cylinder, then basically what we're talking
about here.
Is just some number of angles around sort of a radius Vector, right?
And we need to do sort of some, of the same things.
So we still need to do this, right?
We still need to come up with this because that's going to be sort of
the central Direction.
You know I shouldn't do this in the Q&A because the the same problem
is going to occur just in a slightly different way which is that we
have one axis and we're going to need to produce
two more axes to use as the basis for the cylinder and we'd have to
talk about how to do that.
So I think I'd probably rather wait till tomorrow to do that.
It's not quite exactly the same but we still need a way of producing
the cylinder basis.
And so we're still going to have to have, we still have the problem of
producing two other coordinates via its in easier problem because we
don't have to care about the camera facing Miss of it, so that has
nothing to do with the camera anymore but it's still a problem.
And someone was saying we should go ahead and do the lines around
rooms and yes we totally could do that.
Pretty simply right, let me see.
Where that happens.
Not sure.
There's a traversable is here, our volumes.
So what I can do here is just say, like, okay,
push volume outline.
And I don't know, let me just check to see here.
I don't think there's anything in particular that has to do with rooms
here.
I think it's just part of the Collision volume.
yeah so the Collision volumes right are getting pulled out here and if
I do a push volume outline I need to
Put these on this way, here's the color.
I'll copy the same color we were using for them before.
And then direct min-max.
What I want to do is just take the volume offset p and the volume dim
and just say,
Volume offset P.
I think I want Rec, Center Dim, volume dim.
I think that should give
The rectangle that want.
And I can delete this.
So I think that should draw Collision volumes around everything.
And we should be able to see those in theory here.
Now, whether or not that's actually working correctly, I'm not sure we
would have to because we don't actually I think have all the Collision
volume set correctly at the moment.
I don't really remember so we'd have to go.
See I feel like people have I don't really remember who has Collision
volumes and who doesn't
Oh, I suppose, the other thing we have to do is actually use the
entity transform.
So one of the things that we weren't doing in the volume outline case
with the object transfers, we're not actually using the object
transform here, right?
And we would need to, it's got that offset p.
And so that actually has to be taken into account here.
So I suppose we would need to do something along the lines of
Abyss.
And I think the the scale probably also would need to be taken into
account here.
So that's, you know, the actual Collision volumes there.
I think that are involved, you can kind of see that.
The heads got one too, that's moving around with the head at the
moment, which is again.
Correct, I think because it's, you know, we're drawing it here but
actually is
Correct to where it should be and so yeah you can kind of see where
all those are.
And those look, you know, pretty good those that's those are
definitely the tree ones look right to me so I think that's pretty
close again.
I think we gotta, we want to eliminate that object transform scale bit
there.
So little by little we're getting back to something where everything
is relatively sane.
Now, one of the things that we don't do it currently is when we're
back in the game view.
We
Don't set the debug View at.
All, right?
And so I'm not sure how we want to handle that.
Like, you can see here, we got the use, debug camera thing.
I don't know if we want to do something where we just set the debug
camera to be the same thing as the game camera.
I mean, one way to do that and I said, I don't know to what extent we
want to do at this.
But I'm just gonna throw it out there as an option is when we actually
do set, the camera transform.
If we're not, if we're
When we do a push set up, you know, if it's a debug camera or as it's
not a debug camera, we also set the debug camera, right?
So we do, you know, render group
Debug transform.
Equals render group game X form.
So, basically, any time we set the game transform, we also set the
debug transform, but you can then override the debug transform and
what that does, right.
Is that just makes it so that we can, you know, render our our debug
stuff in the game view as well, so you can actually see them all.
So, you know, here's here's the debug camera, right?
And then we switch back, we still get, you know.
Actual placement for some of this stuff.
You know, and again, that's just sort of a way for us to make that
stuff flow a little bit nicer.
This.
You said you mentioned that you use discriminated unions.
Have you seen rust implementation of some types?
I have not, I have not really looked at rest so I have not seen
breasts implementation of anything really.
Jesse 23.
I was looking at how the vector types are set up in handmade here, as
unions.
As far as I know, it's undefined Behavior to write a value to one type
of a union.
And then read as another type is doing something like this.
Well, defined Veeck, l, dot x equals 5 and then read as veck.
L.E 0, or is it one of the cases where we rely that a reasonable
compiler?
Will do the right thing.
The answer there is I have no idea.
I pretty much just use see as the best thing I have for an improved
Assembly Language.
And so I can guarantee that that works just fine on all the platforms
that you ship games on.
And so, that's pretty much the end of the inquiry for me, as to
whether the spec allows it as far as I'm concerned, the C plus plus
spec is just terrible.
Like, I hate it.
It doesn't guarantee any of the things that I usually want to
guarantee.
And so there's tons of cases where
There's stuff in there that I'm just like, I I don't know how you're
supposed to write reasonable code.
And make use of these features with the way that it works, right?
And so, I don't know.
I have no idea what the latest version of the spec says about that
aspect of unions.
If you can't do that, then unions are kind of useless.
And I don't know why you have them, right?
Because if you can't use the values in Play It's really just a space
saving feature at that point, which is a very limited which is very,
very limited.
In terms of utility, especially nowadays, when computers have so much
memory.
The idea that the only thing you can use a union for is to Overlay Two
Types on top of each other in a space-saving way, seems incredibly
misguided.
So, I would sure hope that the spec doesn't say that, but it wouldn't
surprise me if it did.
Because the spec says, some pretty ridiculous things that I feel like
a reasonable.
No reasonable programmer.
Could ever really say was a good idea.
Would you describe discriminated Union to the general public?
Sure.
Sue.
You know.
In programming.
Even practical programming, not just theoretical programming.
A lot of times were pretty concerned about the idea of defining
collection of named elements that oftentimes, you know, take up space
or whatever else.
And so, a pretty common thing that we would do, you know, in any
programming language in C C++, there's a notion of struct, right?
And we might Define one structure and we say that that structure
involves some variables like
Context, you know, float.
Why
Well, that's really good writing there.
Right?
So in this case we've got struck Foo index float.
Why it's fairly understandable?
What we're doing there?
Everyone knows what that is in.
Another case, we may have some other thing here and maybe that's got
something else in it.
Maybe that's got like Kara star.
Name.
Right.
So when you look at these two things, what we've defined here is two
separate bags of data.
They each have sizes.
What are the sizes?
Well, in 64-bit worlds on an x 64 machine, for example, this is 4
bytes,
And this is 4 bytes.
So this whole structure takes up eight bytes of space.
This guy right here is 8 bytes by himself.
He's a pointer.
So, he's bigger.
And so, this whole thing takes up, eight bytes as well.
These two are the same size, so a single chunk of 8, B could be talked
about, in either way.
And really what we're saying is that we've got something of 8, bytes,
right?
0 1 2 3, 4 5 6.
Seven groups like dude, one more than I needed.
Seven right.
Really?
What we're talking about here is this is memory.
We can talk about this memory into different ways, right?
One way is the Foo way and the foo way looks like this.
This is the Foo way.
This guy here is X, and here is y, another way is the bar way.
Right.
And the bar way is saying this whole thing is the name pointer, right?
It's a pointer.
Called name.
In this case, it's an inn called X and a float call why.
Now, hopefully, we're all very familiar with this idea that basically
programming languages, give us ways to talk about memory in a
structured fashion that lets us quickly refer to some portion of that
memory and have the compiler understand the way.
We want that memory treated as an end as a float as a pointer,
whatever.
Right so this is just a general thing that basically every programming
It has is the ability to talk about a chunk of memory in a structured
way.
That's more than just, what are some bites that are in that memory,
okay?
so furthermore, we can usually in most programming languages and see
it's called a union
We can talk about something that could be either, right?
And the way that we do that is we say okay, we've got a foo
Here.
And we've got a bar.
Now, we got some Union, that's like, you know, Foo or bar, and it can
be either of these two things and then what happens in the code,
right.
And we've seen ourselves use these.
And in handmade here.
All the time is now when someone has one of these, when they're using
one of these, they can choose to refer to the food section or the bar
section, depending on what they believe, the one they have is, right?
So a union is just a
Of representing exactly what I just drew here.
A union is a way of saying I have a chunk of memory.
I might talk about it in one way.
I might talk about it in another way, it's up to my code, which way it
wants to talk about this same piece of memory.
And now it's worth noting.
Before I go any further that these two don't have to be the same size,
the union will, but just be defined to be as big as necessary to hold
the biggest one.
So if this one had a second pointer in there, Kara star name to, which
would have blown this out to be another eight bytes long.
Even though Foo ends here and bar ends here, it wouldn't matter.
We could still do this Union it would just be a 16 byte Union with
eight bytes of nothing at the end.
if you were using it as a foo or all 16 B used is, if you were using
it as a bar,
Right.
So structured data, Union is a combination of structured data where we
say we can look at it in one of two ways or n ways we can add more
than 2.
And so then that finally brings us to the concept of a discriminated
Union
A discriminated Union is exactly what its name implies, it is a union,
whatever that means in your programming language and see it is
generally talking about literally a union like the keyword Union, but
it may be called something else in other programs, right?
That is include some way of figuring out, which of the ones that's,
which of the elements of the Union is actually, the one being used in
this case.
So, it looks like exactly like what we had before.
Right.
It looks like that but now it is wrapped inside a struct.
And that struct has in it, a type field.
This is the discriminating part.
It's saying that I'm remembering which of the two I was, and I'm
writing a code into the memory that is reserved for this to specify
which one it is.
This is typically an enum
This flu or a bar type.
Typically then says, okay, you know, I am type.
Fuu, you know is one let's say or maybe I don't even specify anything
say type Foo type bar.
So this gets assigned to a one.
I'm sorry a zero.
This gets assigned to a 1 and so then in the code, what I do typically
what the programmer does not me specifically is they look at the type
field and that lets them know which of these they're going to be
looking at.
Right?
So this is how we get a discriminated Union.
It's a union of things, but rather than just being candid and having
no idea, which of them might be the one that was actually intended by
the person who originally created this memory, somewhere early in the
program, whoever created the memory is now telling you which one it
is.
And that's very useful.
So typically that's get used with the switch statement.
So you say in this case, you know, I get one of these past in, you
know, maybe it's a one, you know, I get one of these discs Foo or
bars, right?
So I have a discriminated Foo or bar.
A I have that here and then I'm going to say a DOT type in my switch.
And then I come through when I say, case, you know,
type Foo, and in this case,
I use it as a foo.
So I'm going to see stuff like a DOT Foo something, right?
And then I have a case for type bar.
As well.
Right.
and so this is how a discriminative union typically is used first,
there is something that checks the discriminate or write the thing
that tells me what the type of thing is, and then I do different code
based on which type it actually is
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
Now, it's worth noting that, you know,
I don't know why I imagine that somewhere.
There is some record of Darkness, true stripper, whatever explaining
why he didn't like discriminated unions.
I have no idea why because rather than properly just supporting
discriminated unions in C++.
He instead chose to use inheritance as the primary model for sort of
the Poor Man's discriminated Union and it took a long time to even get
to the point where it could do, the things that has remained.
Union can do it, required are TTI before you could ever even.
Get to that point.
Our T t.i.
and and, and casting.
Are the only way you can really emulate them and at that, even at that
point it's really weak and isn't as good as the manual implementation,
which is the one I've written here.
So for whatever reason, he failed to appreciate the necessity for or
underestimated the degree to, which category Theory demands this and
and can clearly tell you that inheritance is not a substitute for
discriminated.
Unions.
At least not the kind of inheritance in C++ provides I suspect.
It was just a lack of understanding of the fundamentals of how
programming Works, which, again, is endemic to C++.
And one of things you can say about the design of C++ pretty much
across the board, is that it lacks any real understanding of the
fundamental principles of programming, I would say either practical or
theoretical, like I suspect that a theoretical programming
perspective, person would have no end to the Greet, which they thought
C++.
Awful.
And the same thing is true of practical programming.
They're just so many ways where you're like, I don't know how you
didn't understand how important discriminated univer, but you didn't
and that's just unfortunate.
But, you know, you can construct the manually and that's what I do in
a better programming language.
These would be constructed automatically for you.
You would just say I have a discriminated Union.
The discriminating Union is of these types.
It would automatically create the type field for you in a stable way
that you could control and blah, blah blah, but
But C++ is not that language and it cannot do that thing.
So that's where we're at.
G 1642.
Can you give a motivating example for these discriminating unions?
Yes, I can.
So typically, the, the point of a discriminated Union is, is really
very straightforward, and it happens everywhere in programming and if
I could summarize, I'll go sort of explain the importance of
discriminated unions by
Sing them to with.
With say inheritance which specifically doesn't support the thing that
I'm talking about.
So, suppose that I have two pieces of code that are separated by
control flow in my program.
So I have, let's say to make it very straight forward.
I have two pieces of code I have startup right and I have shut down,
let's say, right and so, in start-up what I'm going to do is I'm going
to pick whether or not my back end.
To the code, right?
Is going to be Vulcan or opengl.
Let's say right?
So I'm going to create a renderer and I want to create and start up
one that's either going to be Vulcan or opengl.
So I'm going to have some preference, let's say maybe and I'm going to
do an if on that preference and in one case I'm going to do like, you
know, renderer
Equals Vulcan and in the other case I'm going to do and you know I
guess like maybe let's do it this way render equals in it Vulcan that
returns you know, one of these things.
And in the else Clause I'm going to do render equals in it opengl
right?
Because maybe you know, I've got an opengl path but it's not as good
and I got a Vulcan path.
That's like more highly optimized because I got, you know, more
control off of it or whatever.
Who knows, what?
So some stuff happens here and I'm trying to figure out which one I'm
going to dump to, or maybe it doesn't even matter.
They're both good paths but the opengl one requires some extensions or
I don't know what like, who knows.
But I've got a preference here, maybe the user even pick.
At which one they want to run.
Okay, so now in shutdown, I want to call some shut down.
I need to call like d in it Vulcan or D init opengl, right?
and so, what I want to do here is say, you know, if you know it was
Vulcan
then I want to do like d in it or you know, do unit Vulcan
Renderer.
And here I want to say,
Gian it opengl.
Right.
Very straightforward.
Now this is the case where both techniques work equally.
Well okay, so if I want to implement this by a discriminated Union you
can see how I would do it.
The renderer just has a type field in it which says which one it is
and then it has some data that comes after it that is completely
specialized to Vulcan or completely specifies to opengl and the
Then who's using it doesn't have to know anywhere in between here
what, which one it actually is right?
And when it gets to the end, it can switch on the type.
Similarly, I could implement this using inheritance by having.
You know, I've already said how to do those criminal Union when I just
said that right.
But I could do one by inheritance by having you know a struct renderer
That's some Base Class here.
Right here is the base class definition and in the base class, I would
have something like in it.
And T in it.
Right.
And these would be virtual calls.
Okay, and then I would have a struct Vulcan renderer.
In a struct.
Opengl renderer.
And both of these would have a public in them where they inherit from
renderer.
Okay, right.
We all know how that would look.
And what would happen there is the startup and shutdown instead of
doing this, right?
You would just have to in this case, still switch on the preference
and you would create one of these derived classes here, right?
But then when you get to shut down, you never do this.
If instead, what you do is just renderer Arrow right d in it and you
trust that the virtual function, dispatch will call down into one of
these.
You Saucy, gentleman here that actually handle the call, right?
Hopefully, that makes sense.
So what C++ decided was?
This was the only one you ever needed.
They were like, I don't understand why you couldn't just Implement all
your code in terms of this.
Look at it works, just fine in here.
You just create one of the derived classes and then at the end you
just called e in it and you don't do the if right off we go
everything's fine.
However, this is a really shallow understanding of how code actually
works because what it assumes a priority is that you always have
what's called single dispatch.
Which is to say that the only thing that ever determines, how a code
path will work, is the type of one object in the code path, right?
Why?
Because virtual functions can only dispatch on one type.
There is no such thing as a union virtual dispatch that dispatchers
off of the type of two things, right?
And furthermore, this gets into a really sort of
Deep, very core aspect of programming that.
Everybody should understand, and the people who design C++ should
understand, but didn't which is that single dispatch is tractable
because it is 0n, right?
Single dispatch is tractable to write as a systemic sort of stupid,
derived version here, right?
Because it's 0n, there's only ever as many dispatches as there.
Are derived types, right?
So the end here is how many different derive types we have.
And so that's pretty tractable, on the other hand, a double dispatch
or worse yet triple or quadruple.
Dispatch, or God knows what?
Right is N squared, right?
Which is completely intractable in most cases and we can talk about
why it's so important to have discriminated unions in order to be able
to support and square it and I can talk about why?
So let's say why so what's doubled
Patch double dispatch occurs in situations for example, where you've
got something like, Collision detection, right?
So, let's say I've got something where I want to do, you know, a
discriminated Union and I've got, you know, struct
Collider.
Well, the C++ inheritance model would have us believe that everything
that you wanted to support to describe in terms of collisions, right?
Could be described in terms of like collider, you know, cylinder.
Let's say,
Collider volume Collider.
I don't know.
Cylinder volume and sphere.
Blah, blah blah, right?
So when you have these situations, you've got cylinder, volume sphere
at cetera.
And each one of these is going to be public collider.
You end up in a situation where you're going to have something like
you know, you know.
Intersex.
Or, you know, does intersect, right?
And you're going to have to test for intersection with to colliders
collider a, and collider be.
And right here already, we're in a huge conundrum.
As far as C++ has original conceptualization of how type should work.
And the reason why you're in a huge conundrum here is because you
cannot dispatch at all in a
Double way, right?
There's no way for you to say, I would like to do a double dispatch
here, where I want to collide two, two different types with each
other, right?
And I want you to pick the right, one in this Matrix, that looks like
this right cylinder volume sphere.
Cylinder volume sphere like so right.
There's no way to do it.
It's literally not a thing that they support originally, right?
And the reason for that is because if you just have to colliders you
have no idea, you can't call a, you can't call a function on a and
habit, know what the type was of be because you can't know what the
type is of be the whole idea of C++ has inheritance model is you don't
know what the type is.
They didn't have our T, t.i.
at the beginning.
So you couldn't even ask what the type was.
But you know, and you couldn't do sort of a dynamic cast later.
What they did is they added Dynamic cast,
Civically for these kind of situations where it's like, well, somebody
at some point it's going to have to figure out what B is.
Right?
Because at that point, we've got a problem.
So the poor man solution to this and C++ and I can't believe I ever
thought this was good, but this is what you had to do.
Was you had to do sort of a round tripping thing.
What you do was you'd go down and say, all right, for each of the
derived types.
I'm now going to write a function on those derived types that calls
back into the main type.
Where was my?
Yeah, that calls back into the main type with the
Up early typed parameter.
So what it does is it says well okay the first virtual function call
is like begin Collide or something.
I don't know what I'm going to call this, right?
But something there's a virtual function when it gets down to one of
these types.
I have to implement that.
Begin Collide in each of these guys, right?
And then in each of these guys, I call back into here to a like
continue Collide call or something, or the actual Collide call with
the first parameter of that Collide call or the thing that I'm
colliding with is now fully typed.
So, I've got collider cylinder in here.
Collider volume collider sphere, right?
So the first virtual call is the thing that discovers what the type of
a
Is let's say right and then it calls back with its type.
Now determined as the first parameter and the undetermined type of B
is the actual virtual call now because you call it on be.
So first you call A's begin Collide which then calls the Collide on be
with now the correct type.
Okay, so basically the way you implement a double dispatch is you
first dispatch on a to get you into the right row and then you
dispatch on
Be to get you into the right column and then you finally get to a
freaking function that actually does some collision between two
things, right?
Now if that sounds absolutely ridiculous to you, I would say that's
because it is when you want to collide.
Is what you want to be able to do is just look at what the type of the
two things are right.
What you want to do is you want to be able to write a function that
just says Collide.
And I want to be able to say collider a
collider be and I want to put all the code in here.
This is where the coach should go for Collision.
I don't want it spread throughout code base in two sets of virtual
dispatches that are used to discover the types of things and have to
go like RI you know, Jigger all of those to have.
Make sure that every single one of them has a call for each different
type that it could have ended up with and blah, blah blah, right?
It's awful.
I just want to write it in here.
And what I want to be able to do in here is I want to be able to
compress my O N squared Matrix.
However, I want and this is really, really, really crucial.
Right?
This is the fundamental thing that they didn't get when they were
designing C++.
I don't know if they were, like aware of it.
And didn't think it was important or just had no idea.
I suspect it was the latter but you know, who knows.
The problem here is as these matrices get really large, right?
So let's say we have 32 types by 32 types here, right?
This would be impossible to implement the C++ way.
You'd be typing in so many virtual function, signatures all over your
code that you would just be crying yourself to sleep every night.
Even thinking about the disaster that you had created.
The point here is no one is going to ever be able to write code that
actually involves 32 by 32 different cases, handled uniquely, right?
It's nuts to think about this, right?
That's 2 to the
Times two to the fifth right?
Otherwise known as 2 to the 10th.
Forget it right?
You know no one's going to be writing this many pieces of code.
Uniquely.
So what you're always talking about in the case of a no N squared,
dispatch is you're talking about a sparse Matrix, right?
You're talking about a sparse set of cases where only certain patches
of the Matrix actually involved uniqueness and everything else Maps
into those cases in some way.
And discriminated unions are by far the most efficient way to write
that code because it lets you think about what you want to think
about.
You can do any arbitrary Turing complete analysis.
You wish to generate the actual cases you care about.
So for example in this case I can say stuff like if a
You know, if a is type is a cylinder, you know and you know and B's,
you know and and could you know and and sphere.
Close, which is some function.
I'm defining that says whether it's close to being spherical or close
enough to be, you know, then I want to do this thing.
Otherwise I want to do something else, right?
And this thing may not even be the Collision routine, it may just be
something that sets some variables here that later are defined to do
whatever, right?
And so you can write incredibly complicated Preamble code.
Working with the types of the different things, solve exactly what you
want.
In terms of figure out what you're going to do, and then do it, right?
And it's very clean, very easy to read any program can come come, come
through now and see how the collider actually works.
Take this.
And imagine it getting dispersed out into tons of virtual dispatches,
on all sorts of different objects strewn throughout the code base
often in multiple files.
And you can quickly see why this is just an untenable way to try and
write a complex, sparse Matrix contraction, using the tools that C++
gives you discriminated, unions are very, very good at representing
complex interactions between varying types.
And there are able to do that in more ways than one.
This is one of them the other way is the memory way, right?
That they happen to also be the same size because they overlay on top
of each other which also allows you a lot more freedom with how you
work with them in other ways.
So that's also a plus but that's a separate plus that has to do with
memory layout.
That's not really related to the bonus of the discriminated unions.
And so, the takeaway here, if you believe nothing else about what I
said, hopefully at least, it's put the thought in your head.
That being able to write code complex code, which looks at the way, in
which types are set between more than among more than one object.
Is crucial to well-functioning code and that is where discriminated
unions.
Really shine C++ is sort of procrustean, you know, sort of I guess I
might call it, you know, amateur conceptualization of how types should
have been discussed.
At its foundation is really just way too primitive and forces you to
use something much much weaker than a fully full Turing complete
language.
In order to, I should say filtering complete one.
That makes it almost impossible to access the Turing completeness of
the language.
You can probably eventually if you wanted to construct everything you
needed out of virtual functions, right?
But it's just not a good way to write it.
So what I should say, is it robs you of all of the
Expressive power of your language and forces you to create the
compression of your dispatch Matrix in terms of incredibly convoluted
set of calls that can only use one thing, which is a virtual dispatch,
why would?
I want that right.
There's literally no reason for it.
It doesn't give you anything in return.
And that's the really cool.
Part of it, is that if you go down that road of thinking, you're doing
an incredible amount of work, you're not getting anything back.
The discriminated unions.
Give you everything that you could have wanted, you're not, you're
giving that up.
You're not getting anything in return, right?
And so that is the really, really crucial part of.
It is just that ability to talk about the types using plain language
with a power of functional decomposition and equivalences and being
able to look at the state of more than one thing at once.
Being able to write that code, very cleanly is the real power of
discriminated unions and I cannot stress enough how much more powerful
that is than inheritance.
Which is very, very weak by comparison.
Now, like I said, unfortunately, C++ because at its outset, it
believed in this inheritance model which is in my opinion just
complete, it just complete Amateur hour.
It's just it's bad, it's a bad type system, it's just not very good.
You don't get the benefit of having the language help you with your
discriminated Union, construction, which I think is one of the reasons
why people don't like it as much in C++ or think that inheritance is
good.
Is because the language doesn't really
View any any real support for discriminate units Beyond just the union
keyword which was already in.
See but again other languages that are that are have a more deeper
understanding of what types are and why they're important don't make
that mistake.
And in those languages discriminated unions should shine.
Even brighter, they already even even though C++ did not appreciate
them as never supported them properly.
They're still actually one of the best ways to do types in C, and C++.
Plus, despite the fact that the designers are language, never
understood them and I think that's also a testament to just how
powerful they really are.
But you can imagine how great it would be if your language actually
supported them.
Some people in the chat I've been suggesting that rust is a language
that does support them properly.
I could not say I have not programmed in rest, but again, I would
encourage you to look to other languages where people designed them
who had a better understanding of why types are important in how they
work.
Because those languages always do
For it discriminated, unions and they are going to support them a lot
better than C++, which is never really embraced them.
All right, I got to wrap it up soon.
We're way past the point where I was going to be done talking.
Cuba cab says, how would you feel if you wrote the functions for
colliding, each pair of types and allowed the compiler to generate the
sparse Matrix of function calls for you?
The answer is that
What this is right?
This, that is what this is.
This Collide function with a switch statement is exactly what I want,
right?
And the reason for that is I don't want to just write a few sparse
cases here.
I'm the whole Matrix needs to be full, a lot of the time.
It's just that I don't want to actually have different pieces of code
executes everywhere.
I oftentimes want subtly different ones that just set some variables
different or whatever.
And that is what this gives me write a Collide function, which reasons
about the types sets up some State.
And then as a switch statement, that does a few different cases
depending on which one I'm doing.
Is exactly what I want.
Right.
If that makes sense.
so yeah, and again that's that's just
I would highly recommend it.
Also if you think that it's a matter of opinion, whether discriminated
unions are good or not.
I would highly highly suggest that you define sort of maybe look into
category Theory because my understanding is actually that
discriminated unions aren't a practical question.
You can actually theoretically prove that they are required to do
computation the way that you want to do it.
If this makes sense, like, discriminated unions are like a fundamental
Concept in terms of how to do efficient Computing.
So, I am not equipped to make those kinds of arguments.
So, I certainly would not be the one to make that argument at all,
rather as opposed to convincingly, but my understanding about
discriminated.
Unions is actually, it's not just like a oh yeah, my sort of opinion
is they're practically useful.
It's like no, no.
Oh, they're like theoretically required to properly, think about
programming.
You actually need them.
They are a fundamental part of the math.
And so, you know, I guess what I would say is ignore them at your
peril because I don't think it's really a case of like this guy says
they're good.
This other person says that they're not
It's more.
It's a lot more fundamental than that.
If that makes sense.
Close some of this stuff down here.
Let's see here.
This is not going to give me very much information.
I assume.
So this is mainly the computer science part of it.
I wish we had maybe suited him 73 on here to give you a good reference
for this because I don't really know where it is.
And this is kind of a really Bare Bones.
Sort of a bare-bones one but really like you need to get a little
deeper into this to get be able to give any kind of really sort of
deep understanding of why they're important.
But like I said I feel like this.
This goes into the math it's not just a matter of opinion and
I guess I would say, like, if you want to know a little bit more about
that aspect of it, hopefully, there's some way we could get some
references on it.
Unfortunately, a lot of these things that a lot of these things that
are sort of about the sort of fundamental truths that they are sort of
start to discover about programming are not always made available to
practical, you know, practitioners such as as myself.
Are the other folks in the chat a lot of times you know, the
literature is just extremely impenetrable and it's like unless you
really devoted a great deal of time to, it's very hard to really
understand what's being said.
And so unfortunately you end up in this scenario where like, you know,
learning about how essential some of these things are can be
incredibly difficult to, you know, release us out.
So I'm just going by, what people who know category Theory have told
me?
Me, and like I said, it's something that I've never had the, I guess
time to really sit down and decide to pursue, so I cannot give you
even remotely a way to think about that.
End of it.
All I can tell you is that practical programming wise is extremely
important.
I can guarantee you that
but you know, that's that's very different from saying that that it's
theoretically important because that involves a lot of things that,
you know, our way out
My area of expertise.
And somehow Quran says, are you hoping J?
I will have discriminated unions.
Certainly, I am but I haven't been.
I'm not very up-to-date on j.i.
at the moment.
It may already have them.
You know.
So, all right, I'm going to wind down here.
Thanks everyone for joining me from those sort of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want follow along series at home, you can always
pre-order the game on hand made her a torque.
It comes with a source code so you can play around with it yourself.
We also have a forum so you can go to if you want to ask questions a
patreon page and go to if you want to support the video series a
schedule.
But you can you can look at it.
Find out.
We're going to be live and an episode guide that lets you know, sort
of what's happened in the past and allows you to catch up on old
material, that's about it for today.
I'll be back here tomorrow at the same time.
I'll be doing a later stream again, tomorrow, 2 p.m.
Here in Pacific Daylight time.
Until then have fun programming and I will see everyone on the
internet.
Take it easy, everybody.