Start recording.
Okay, everyone.
Hello and welcome to what is really, I guess, in some sense, the very
first day of handmade hero programming, where we're actually going to
be talking about programming the actual game because obviously, we had
to spend what I guess is about 25.
I guess there's a little, maybe a little more than that, but something
like 26, 27 hours, writing ourselves a prototyping layer that we could
use on.
Which we have mostly done.
I mean, there's plenty of things that I would probably if I was
programming full-time.
In my real life.
I would clean up a ton of stuff, probably still in the, in the
prototyping layer, even though it is just a prototyping layer, but for
the moment, it's plenty good for our purposes.
And since I know, we will be going back there and doing a real like
serious pass on it later.
When we go to make a fully shippable win32 layer.
I figured I don't really want to belabor the point, you know, cleaning
up stuff in the platform.
We're at this point, specifically the
Obviously we kind of it wants a couple more days of like solid work to
like nail everything down and also to kind of you maybe use on
platforms where Core Audio exists and stuff like that, you know, to
use it because the direct sound latency was pretty darn high, and I'd
be interested to know if we could get a lower latency outputs that
sort of stuff.
But for the most part, I mean, for the most part, we've got a pretty
solid prototyping layer that we can easily use to make the game.
It's just not the kind of thing you would ever ship to end users
because again, it's for prototyping.
So we
Done the work necessary to make a really shippable win32 platform
layer and we'll be looking at that in a bit.
But for the next couple of months, what we're going to be doing is
actually making the game, which is kind of the, the most interesting
part of the programming.
I think, almost always because playing around with platforms.
Sometimes it can be fun.
But a lot of times it's just drudge work of trying to basically figure
out exactly how to get something that, you know, is possible to happen
on the platform and your kind of
Ending a lot of your time working around or experimenting with some
stuff that some other programmer, wrote.
You might not have been any good and isn't very well documented and
blahblahblog.
So that's a lot less.
Satisfying.
It's also even it's harder for me to to sort of do these streams
because these are educational streams.
And when I am explaining something that we wrote entirely ourselves, I
can do a much better job of explaining to you, why everything works
the way it does.
Whereas obviously when we're doing, it went through two platform layer
or a Linux platform layer or Mac platform layer.
I wasn't the
The guy who wrote the operating system.
So when we get to a certain point where ever that point is in, you
know, sort of, you know, when we go down the levels of what's
happening in, you know, in the code, there's a certain point at which,
you know, I have to just go and we don't know, we call windows and
this seems to be what it does.
So that's what it does, right?
And that's that's just kind of unsatisfying.
So I guess that's just a very long-winded way of saying now, we are.
Finally getting to the point where we will know everything that
happens because we have put ourselves in a position to basically write
everything ourselves with without having to.
Now think about any platform in any way.
And since we'll be doing the first version of the renderer in software
ourselves as well.
That means even rendering will not be hand wavy, because we will not
be relying on anyone's driver or GPU to do.
The rendering for us will be doing ourselves.
So we can literally know how every last little pixel.
Got onto the screen, why it was there, why it looks?
Like it does how it was, computed where it came from.
Everything will be something that we can look at.
And I'm much more excited about that because I think that's going to
be really where the interesting stuff.
Lies me platforms.
Come and go and there's a million platforms out there.
They'll be a million more.
And so really that's not that exciting of a part but it's just
something kind of have to do.
So with all of that.
I guess I should do the standard p.m.
On case, we do some code today.
Welcome to handmade hero.
We are on Day 26.
Right now, which means we're about 26 hours into programming this
game.
If the, I guess if it was a Monday that we started.
We're on Thursday or something in the working week, something like
that.
If we are program in 7 hours a day or something like this.
I don't know how much you guys program a day.
But however, much you program a day.
You can figure out where in the week that is after, you know, 26 some
odd hours.
We are building an entire game from scratch and we are building it
from scratch for two reasons, one, because it's a lot of fun.
Actually.
And I think as we now kind of get
Away from the win32 side of things to which, you know, like I said,
makes things definitely hairier.
Now, that we're in our own code.
It's going to be a lot more fun because everything is under our
control, but it's just kind of fun to have complete control over thing
and to be able to do whatever you want.
I feel is like really very empowering.
I kind of like that a lot.
So I think it's a lot more fun.
And also, I think it's very educational.
So one of the big reasons I want to do this, obviously this series
where we did everything from scratch was because I really want to be
able to show how every level a little last thing works because it's so
Things sometimes to find out how these things work, and a lot of
times.
Now, if you just use a Prefab game engine or something like that, you
don't really ever get to see all of the stuff that happens, so you
don't get to learn about it.
Also, you know, I think it's really an important thing for everyone to
do, who's a, who's a, you know, game programmer to do, once to kind of
do the whole pipeline.
Once they can just kind of see it.
It's super educational and cool.
I think so.
Yeah, so I'm looking forward to it and I hope you are too.
If you pre-ordered the game on handmade hero dot-org, you should have
gotten an email.
Email with a link that allows you to download the source code anytime
you want that source.
Code ZIP has days in it each day corresponds to one of the days you on
the stream here.
So we're on Day 26, so you will want to unzip yesterday's Source day
25 unzip that into a directory and you will be in the exact same state
that I am in right now.
So if you want to follow along at home, that's the easiest way to do
it and you will be all set to go.
Okay, so I have a bunch of things that I want to talk about tonight.
And like I said, I don't know how much coding will get to.
I said that was talking about this in the freestream.
I have a bunch of things that I want to explain because I think that
game architecture is not very well understood by a lot of people.
And I would also say that just architecture software architecture in
general is really not understood that.
Well by a lot of people, a lot of a lot of people in the programming
world and I think there's a lot of misconceptions.
I think there are a lot of dogmas out there that can be very
counterintuitive and
And also perhaps harmful to productivity that yield a worse and
product and so I kind of just wanted to talk a little bit about
software architecture, what it means, what the actual sensible things
are there and kind of then move from there into game architecture
specifically and kind of how to think about it.
Okay.
So what I want you to think about for a second if you will, is the
term architecture.
Because what's interesting about the term architecture is if you
actually consider.
Am I going to painting mode here?
There we go.
If you actually consider what the term architecture comes from, right?
It was something that that comes obviously from building buildings,
but if you think about the
Process.
What happens when you build a building is an architect, right?
They the person who does architecture they make a blueprint, right?
They make they make designs for the building.
They make a bunch of These Blueprints.
I don't know if you've ever seen them.
They're, they're all in a big roll.
There's, there's sometimes they're printed out by the hundreds for
complex buildings and like one blueprint will have like where the,
where the plumbing supposed to go.
And another blueprint will have things like, you know, how the floor
is laid out or where the
Asset egos, who knows?
They've got blueprints for all sorts of things.
Well, the Architects make These Blueprints, right, nowadays, they make
them on CAD things.
And then what happens is, at some point.
They hand these blue printers off to like, you know, like a
contractor, right?
There's a contractor and they've got carpenters and stuff, and they
actually build the building using materials, right?
So the contractor actually builds the building and building the
building, involves lots of stuff, right, building in the building
involves like nailing stuff in, right?
Stuff together, right?
It involves like, you know masonry involves cranes and Hauling stuff
around.
So when people say architect, you know, and and they are talking about
what we're doing in programming.
It's kind of a little it's kind of a little confusing to understand
really what this means, and I think that it may be puts up a few
barriers to understanding, because one of the things that's true, if
you take a look at this whole process,
In sort of, in the world of construction and we were trying to, like,
use the metaphor directly.
Is that this right here?
Pretty much tells you everything you need to know to build the
building for the most part.
Like, if I hand two different, you know, two different contractors,
the same set of blueprints modulo like, how much, you know, how
detail-oriented they were when they're like nailing a stuff in like,
you know, what other little gaps or something like this, you know, how
carefully they are doing their job.
I'm substantially going to get the same building out the other side,
right?
Like I'm not going to
A situation where like, you know, one of the buildings was, you know,
sort of this long rectangular thing.
And another one was like some kind of spherical Omni Dome.
When I hand it off the same blueprint, right?
And so if you think about that and what that entails, a lot of people
who talk about software architecture, take that metaphor kind of
literally, like, if you think about things like uml diagrams.
I don't know if you've ever seen these sort of things.
Basically, there's a bunch of architecture software.
Architecture methodologies that really do try to reproduce this
process.
They try to make it so that when you are doing the work of software
architecture, whatever that means.
And we haven't really even defined what I think it means yet, but when
you are doing what they think that word means, they essentially
believe you are producing a thing, which when handed to people who
literally do not have any knowledge about what you were trying to do
with the architecture, potentially or how you wanted it done.
Which subsequently build the same essential program out of it, right?
So the blueprint is essentially the the program, you know, definition
or spec, right?
This is basically, you know, the family of architecture that a lot of
sort of like hardcore object-oriented style stuff goes a lot of
Hardcore like pre-planning diagramming all that sort of stuff.
That is how they look at it, right.
Now in my mind, I don't think that makes much sense at all.
Personally.
The reason that I don't think that much makes very much sense is
because if you look at how this tends to play out in practice, really,
what ends up happening when you try to do things this way?
Is that programs are so complicated and involves so many moving parts
that if you could actually make a blueprint that actually does specify
the program.
To a sufficient degree in necessary to make it.
So there isn't any variability in what comes out the other end.
Then you have essentially just written the program like these sorts of
things.
If you were to actually diagram them out to the level necessary, which
allow some people actually do with these crazy tools, right?
You would essentially have something that is more or less the program.
Like a programming language.
Sufficiently Advanced could probably just spit out the actual end
result.
On that process, right?
And I feel like and I could be wrong about this, but I feel like,
nowadays certainly in game programming.
But also, I think the sentiment that I've heard from most of the
people who watch handmade hero is, they either explicitly or
intuitively and someone implicitly have that feeling as well.
Like, if they've seen these sorts of things, they have had the
experience that these do not tend to work very well, and that they
caused basically a lot of upfront work.
That just doesn't pay off very much.
Each, right.
And I feel very strongly about that because everything that I've ever
seen that tries to go in that direction where you have this sort of
heavy upfront, architecting of things tends to fail at producing good
quality programs in a reasonable amount of time in my experience.
They tend to take too long to produce to pour of a program.
So, what I would actually propose is that this, this phrase architect
or architecture, right is actually
Kind of bad and misleading just to begin with.
And if it were up to me, I don't think we would even ever use that
phrase.
So what I want to propose, oh dear, I don't know.
I'm new to this this drawing program.
So let's see fill with background color.
There we go.
So what I would like to propose is just briefly a way of sort of
Thinking about this.
If you were in the same metaphor, I'd like to say where I actually
think the sort of the, the act of software architecture comes in.
Basically what I think it comes in, as more like urban planner,
honestly, right?
Like, I think urban planner is actually the job that we're actually
doing when we talk about software architecture architect, right?
Whatever.
The architecture is Right.
Wow.
We're just, we're just having all kinds of
I don't even I don't even know how to erase that we're having like
spelling problems.
All right, let's see.
Do we have an eraser tool?
Is there a way to erase things?
I don't even know if there is help me.
Help me create a, I should really practice with this program first.
It's the only one that seemed to actually be working for us.
So I assume that it's the one.
Is that not selection.
How do we select things?
I don't even know.
All right, fine.
We'll just we'll just undo their you've made me do it.
Carita.
Okay, there we go.
So if I have architect, wow, it's just like I can't draw today.
All right, there we go.
So if we have an urban planner, we have Architects, we have
contractors, right?
I actually think of what people call software architecture as being up
here.
I think that this is like programming, right?
This is design.
Right?
And this is like the compiler, right?
So basically like the stuff where the stuff.
The thing where things actually get built, that's the compiler.
It's basically taking the blueprint, which is our code and it's
turning it into actual something you can actually use.
Right.
So I say this is the compiler, it's not programmers taking a blueprint
from a designer.
This is actually what the compiler does.
The architect job in real in like real life where you're making this
blueprint that's programming.
And the reason that I think that's like, actually what we do day to
day when we sit down to program is because programs are very, very
malleable, right?
The reason that architects
In the real world don't program, you know, don't change their
blueprints continuously.
As they build a building is because it's impossible to do.
So, it's much too costly.
It's not because it's better, right?
It's not because it's easier to have to pre-plan entire building.
Before you build it, if cost was an time were no issue at all.
You would much rather have the architect.
Be able to just constantly fuss with the structure of the building
through its entire production.
So they could build the lobby.
See that the lobby was like oriented, not quite right to the Sun.
So like change it and just move the lobby over to a new place so that
it gets better sought, right.
That's what they would.
They would love to be able to do that, but they can't because building
things in the real world is just cost, too much money and takes too
much time.
So the act of pre-planning, the architecture of a building is entirely
because of real-world constraints in programming, we have much more
malleable.
Structures of things.
So the concept that we would want to do what they do and fix, you
know, sort of the blueprint ahead of time just doesn't hold water.
We want our thing to always be malleable because we will be able to do
a much better job.
Just like an architect would be able to do a much better job designing
their building if they had the ability to constantly mutate it, right.
So I think that's actually what we're doing here.
And I think we would apply the same principles during programming.
Like I talk a lot about
You know compression oriented programming right?
Where we sort of just flat things out and then we see how they take
shape and then we sort of abstract them as necessary.
And like, you know, rework things, all that sort of stuff very fluid.
I think that's the same way.
You would build a building.
If you could write, it just would result in buildings that were so
much better than what we have today for the same basic amount of time
because again mutating code isn't really that difficult as long as you
don't try to prematurely sort of factor it into pieces.
So this is actually
Part when we talk about architecture and I feel like you're really
more like an urban planner, right?
You're really one level above blueprint.
You're not talking about a specific building.
You're talking about like how the City Works in some sense like
zoning.
This type of thing.
How tall one building can be versus another because of various
concerns that sort of stuff.
Why do I say that?
I say that.
Because if you look at how people normally talk about software
architecture, when they like just talk about, I'm an architect.
This thing.
I'm telling you about the architecture of thing.
What do they draw?
They draw, they don't draw things and look anything like blueprints
compared to code, right?
They don't, they don't draw something that essentially sketches out
the exact structure of the program as the CPU X would execute it or
anything like that.
What they do is they draw these kind of diagrams, they'll do stuff
like they'll draw something that looks like this, right?
They'll say, oh, here's the win32 part, you know, and here's the
engine, right?
And here is the, you know, the, this is the game and here is this
library that we licensed or
Whatever and it calls down to this, right?
They draw what essentially look like street maps, right?
I mean, that's that's what people do.
When they talk about architecture.
They make diagrams that are very much about traffic flow and the rough
relationship of things to each other and what their responsibilities
are.
That's it.
That's what they really talk about when they're talking about
architecture.
Right?
And I think that's the natural intuitive thing to do and I think it's
the right thing to do.
So when you're thinking
Thinking about architecture in software.
Don't think about architect.
Don't, don't think about that in the real world.
Right?
Don't think about that metaphor, because it's wrong.
When we talk about sore for architecture.
Unfortunately, we're talking actually about a completely different
thing in the real world.
We're talking about the high-level zoning and traffic strategy for our
Virtual City, right?
We're talking about thinking through roughly where each thing has to
be and what it should do and
And how much it's going to cost us and how efficient it's going to be
for us to move things between them, that is really what we're talking
about.
Right?
And I feel like that's an important thing to kind of get straight
especially if you're a beginner, because a lot of times, you're going
to see people use this architecture term and they're using it to talk
about many different things that aren't all the same.
And some of them are good things to pay attention to.
Some of them are actually very deleterious and you should avoid.
And so I just want to kind of
It a little bit differently.
That's typically framed as we go into this.
So that it's a little clearer in people's heads who maybe aren't
familiar with some of these processes.
Okay.
So what are we trying to do?
I'm going to now going to go ahead and get a little more specific.
We're in metaphor land here.
And I'm I only wanted to do that because people are often talking in
these metaphors and I kind of wanted to confront those up front.
But from now on we don't really need much in the way of metaphor.
It's because I can talk about actual specifics.
Now that you know, that we're trying to do.
So, basically in software architecture, just architecture in general.
You are trying to come up with strategies for doing what essentially
amounts to separation of code.
Right?
And there's a number of reasons that we do this but basically
separation or boundaries, right?
Great, depending on how you want to think of this.
This is mostly what we're doing when we're talking about code.
And again it fits with the urban planning thing.
Very concisely.
It's about drawing that property map that says, here's where
everything is going to live.
They don't overlap cures, the traffic patterns that connect them,
right?
And here is what each thing is supposed to be about.
You know, what is this?
What is this section of our city?
Do you know that sort of thing?
Architecture is mostly about defining these and the reason that you
want to Define them are usually for either reuse, right?
That's a big one because I want to be able to have components that are
easy to reuse for example, so maybe I want to separate my code in a
way that, for example, on handmade hero with our win32 prototyping
layer, right now.
It really doesn't know very much about the game whatsoever.
So, if we wanted to turn that into a reusable platform layer, it
wouldn't take very much work because
Done a good job, separating it out from, what's going to be the game.
So, if you think about that, that is a compelling reason to draw
separation, you know, to put hard separation into large chunks of your
code because then you can take those and reuse them and don't have to
write them again.
That's one reason, right, another reason is division of labor.
Right?
So basically, if I think about, you know, trying to write this code,
handmade hero, I'm writing it all by myself.
So that's
It's, you know, not really a problem.
But let's say I had two, three, four programmers on this team or, you
know, worst-case, you've got some like, project that's like an
operating system product.
It's got 500 people on it or something.
Well, we need to kind of have different people working on different
stuff so that the communication requirements between them doesn't
overwhelm the entire project, right?
If each of us is all working on, whatever code we want, anytime we
want, when things start to get,
Scale up in the number of programmers that becomes prohibitively
expensive because we would constantly not know what each person is
doing and we constantly work at Cross purposes.
So division of labor is.
Another reason that software architecture typically comes to place
another one is simply like mental Clarity, right?
And it's weird to list that one but it really is a sort of important
part of things which is that when you tackle very large programs and
this actually is true, regardless of how many people you have.
Whether there is a division of labor or not, when you tackle, very
large programs.
There is a challenge to most people, most programmers in keeping the
entire thing in your head.
As you get up to larger and larger programs in larger larger
complexities.
Sometimes your architecture is more about keeping things separate so
you don't have to consider them at once.
And the reason I say that is because if you imagine
that there was no separation between anything in the code and every
Little thing has a bearing on something else and how it works.
If I'm if that is constantly in flux, then any change I make to my
program has consequences for the rest of the program and that is
essentially you could think of it as an N squared.
We haven't talked about this yet.
But for those of you who know what that is, you could think of this as
an N squared problem for your brain, your brain, every time it makes a
change, has to go consider all other possible.
Port parts.
The code.
And so for every, you know, for the total number of changes that you
have to do for the project, each piece of code that you make a change
to essentially affects all the other pieces of code.
So if the pieces of code were numbered n then each, you know, if you
have to do a change to however my I guess it's it's it's and square
but it's really, I guess you might even say it's worse than N squared
because if n is the number of pieces of code and M is the number of
changes which is often actually higher than n.
So it's really actually worse than N squared, but it's
Easton squared.
Because the number of changes times, the number of pieces of code is
what you end up with as you get towards the end of the project is, is
crazy complicated, right?
Every time you make a change, you have to consider every piece of code
in the system and how it might affect it.
So, sometimes we do that kind of Separation simply not because there's
any actual practical reason, but rather just because doing anything
less would be simply too much brain power for to make progress.
And
Either you will spend too much time thinking about each individual
change and that will slow your rate down or you'll just make mistakes
because you forget to consider certain pieces of the code that are
depending on the thing that you're changing.
Okay.
So this is typically why, right?
This is why we do suffer architecture, right?
And then we also have other things to think about here.
Which if that's the why this is sort of the how, which is things we
want to accomplish or I should say how it's not really how this is
sort of, like, our goals.
I guess you might say in terms of like while we are when we are doing
these things, right?
When we are trying to accomplish these things, even goals is a bad
word.
I don't know what I'm going to call this.
I'm going to list them.
First and then maybe we can think of what the word is because I'm not
sure what the word is that quite encompasses, what I'm talking about.
But basically, I guess, you know what?
We could say, me could maybe say there are some metrics, there are
some things we could measure right.
There are some measurements that we're trying to think about.
As we're doing this, that have some bearing on when we do these, these
sorts of separations.
And typically, these are things like, like, sort of temporal,
coupling, for example, right?
Like when I am making, and you can think of this, this is
Like, thinking about the sort of the quality of our little city that
we're building here.
One thing we could think about when we're actually doing this thing,
and we're kind of starting to break up stuff into pieces.
We have a bunch of different things that we need to think about
between those pieces.
So, temporal, coupling is like, I have two pieces that I've sort of
separated.
I've drawn boundaries between them.
When they occur.
And I mean literally the time at which they can occur in the program
that may not be arbitrary.
An example would be lets say I have a physics system and I've drawn a
boundary around that, right?
I've said this is one component.
So I've separated it out, right?
And I have a renderer, right?
And I've separated that out.
Oops, renderer, right?
So this is responsible for drawing the game, you know, and this is
responsible for moving the things in the game.
Okay.
Well, if that's the case, then.
Obviously, I can't just run these two things completely randomly.
There's some kind of a temporal coupling between these two that says
something along the lines of this has to produce data, right?
That this can read.
Or something, right?
Because if this is what's moving things and this has to render them,
then, we know that we can't render the stuff for a frame until the
physics.
Has computed, what that thing has done for the frame, right?
So there's all there's often a temporal coupling in there.
Similarly.
There's like layout coupling as well.
Right?
Like, basically, if, if this has to spit out stuff that this can read,
well then there's a directional coupling, this way that basically
says, ok, whatever data this.
Spits out.
This thing is now dependent on that format of the data and that could
have implications for performance.
Maybe this thing wanted in a different way, and this thing wants it in
a different way.
And now we have to figure out, do we translate between the two ways or
it is we try to make one work with the other ones way and blah blah
blah, right?
So we can have a coupling like in the layout
Of things, right?
We can also, you know, have some other metrics up here, right?
Which is sort of, just the, I don't know what you want to call it.
We could call it sort of an ideological coupling, right?
Which is to say that we met, especially when it comes down to this
reuse thing.
We may have some things to think about that are just about how, what,
what is sort of the way in general, that these things work and
Does that have a bearing on where we could possibly use them?
Some examples of that would be like, you know, is this thing
multi-threaded does it have to work with a job system?
That sort of thing?
There may be stuff.
That's just how you wrote the code in general internal to this has
sort of a bearing on what sorts of systems it can slot into just you
know, you know.
Basis, another one would be, you know, so some examples there would be
like threading memory.
Like how, what kind of weight is look at memory.
How does it use that width of computation?
So like, is it Cindy?
Does it use SSE, these sorts of things?
Can it, you know, those sorts of things?
When we write things.
We've got a bunch of things that, that sort of have to that may tie
code down, to a particular way of working that we need to be aware of,
right?
So we have lots of, you know, stuff,
To think about here.
And this is by no means exhaustive, but it's just an example of the
sorts of stuff that we're thinking about when we go to actually do
sort of the software architecture.
If you will.
Now, there's one more that I'm going to put on here, which is not a
coupling thing and this is the metrics.
But this is basically like I'm going to just say fluidity, right?
Fluidity is very abstract and difficult to measure.
It's one of those things where you know, it when you see it, but it's
pretty hard to say like what you would
Sure, exactly or how you could really say ahead of time what it what
would or would not be fluid?
But what I mean by that is there are architectures that may do very
well by all of the metrics that you might look at here like in terms
of coupling and you know, they perform well, they're efficient.
They were written well internally, that sort of thing.
So everything about them is good.
There's nothing.
The architecture is not doing anything wrong in terms of providing
these things to that in terms of setting the stage for the particular.
Parts that it didn't have to get implemented inside that architecture.
It's done a good job.
Setting the stage for it to all be successful and it can be written
very successfully and you're done.
Right?
But it might be very fragile or I should say perhaps to sort of stuck
in the way that it's designed such that.
If for some reason, some of those architecture decisions, turn out to
be wrong.
Changing them becomes disastrously difficult, right?
It could be that you've made it.
Such that everything has to work.
The way, the architecture was designed and any change to it.
Everything comes crashing down.
Then there may be other architectures, which, you know, maybe don't
score, quite as highly on some of the other things you might measure
but they may have a great deal of fluidity in them where they can
basically handle like, oh, we got kind of part way through it and
turned out.
This was a bad idea.
And so we, you know, could rework it very quickly, that sort of thing.
That can be very, very valuable on projects, especially if you're not
sure what the architecture should be.
And the first time you do any type of system.
You're probably not sure what the architecture is going to be.
And so that fluidity much like with, you know, when I say this sort of
the semantic, the sort of the compression oriented programming, right?
Having the ability to constantly rework things quickly.
In your architecture is very valuable as well.
If you can get it.
Now sometimes because you're at such a you're talking about such big
pieces that may not be easy to do.
That may be very difficult.
And so it's by no means necessarily true that a architecture that
isn't fluid anymore is bad.
It may be just that you've gotten to the point of complexity where
fluid, he's just not possible anymore.
And so again, one of the things you try to do much like with the
Samantha programming approach, is you try not to lock things down in
the
Sure any earlier than you have to until you've sort of tried some
things and seeing you know that they work at least in one case before
you start to make steps in those directions, specifically for the
same, the same exact reason you don't do it when you're when you're
talking about just regular ordinary code, right?
So, with that in mind, let's talk about a few specific sorts of things
here.
I think it's, I think that's a good enough.
Sort of a good quick background on software architecture.
And what?
What sort of going on there.
So I'm going to talk about the actual game architecture now.
And and sort of how all that applies.
All right, so game architecture, you now.
No one part of how I think game architecture should go.
And again, like architecture is one of those things that you kind of
build up over time techniques on how you like to architect things much
like how you build up over time techniques on how you like to write
code at the lower levels.
So what I wanted to kind of talk about is how that sort of game
architecture process works.
And one thing that you've already seen, though is you've kind of seen
me cheat a little bit and this is because I don't even know how to not
do the cheating anymore, but basically
I already know what I think, is a good architecture for a prototyping
layer and a platform layer both.
So, you know, we have down at the very bottom of everything, right?
We've got win32.
And we've got, you know, opengl or direct3d these sorts of things,
right?
Oops, direct3d.
So we basically have some stuff underneath us that we can't do
anything about it.
It's there and it's designed the way it's designed, right?
I already showed you how to basically make.
There's a platform layer here.
Right?
And I already showed you basically, how I think that thing should be
designed that.
We didn't code a proper platform layer because like I said, we only
did the Prototype version will do the more proper version down the
line, but the architecture the way it's structured is roughly what I
would normally do, you know this platform layer talks to in 32 and
talks to whatever the graphics library is eventually right?
Now.
We don't, we are fortunate in that.
We don't actually have to really do that because we're just pushing a
a bitmap.
So we're kind of just doing it to the win32 API, but eventually, we'll
have to deal with that because we're going to need to use one of these
guys for Hardware acceleration.
So eventually this will be there.
But, you know, we wrote this code and we basically had two ports in
it, you know, there's game update and render was right, was game.
I saved game update and render say, guar game update and render,
right?
We have game update and render and we have get sound samples, right?
Those were the two things really where data is flowing back and forth.
And you might actually I don't know how you
I never find these diagrams to be all that necessary to be specific.
I'm just going to point to them, to talk about parts.
So I don't even care, which direction these arrows are going.
But one way we might say, is that it actually looks like this, right?
Because really game update, and render these things.
Go back to the game, right?
And get sound samples.
Yeah.
So basically these things call into the game.
But really with no loss of resolution here, this is essentially what
we've already done.
Right?
We have the operating system.
This was written by Microsoft.
All right, we have this platform layer, which we wrote the Prototype
of, and we wrote that for the first 25 hours, right?
That's what we did.
And now, we're going to talk about doing this part right here, right?
So the reason I said that I cheated is because I didn't have to go
through this.
The learning steps on this screen on the stream rather of how to
design a
In platform layer.
I just already know how to do it because I've done it.
Probably something like 15 times.
I don't know.
I've written a lot of platform layers in my day.
So I pretty much know what makes me happy about a platform layer and I
pretty much know exactly how I want it to look.
So when I sit down to write a new one, it's really kind of just a rope
process at this point.
I just know what it should look like and what it should do.
And it's just a question of me fussing with the OS to get it to do it.
That's it, right.
So I really couldn't show you anything about the architecture process
in here because it was just a given and I couldn't even really there's
be no way for even me to really pretend that I didn't already have a
goal in mind because I do right with the game.
We're going to be much more fortunate in that respect because I have
no idea how to architect this game.
I mean, that's not entirely true because since I've written game code
before engaging,
System code specifically.
I do have experience architecting games, but every games architecture
is usually a bit different depending on sort of what genre the game
is, what sorts of stuff it needs to do.
And so I don't know a priori exactly how this games architecture
should look.
So over the next several months as we build the game.
I will be going through the same sort of steps that I normally go
through to improve and
Refine on architectures specifically, as sort of like part of the core
gold.
The stream is
Show that kind of stuff.
So we will actually be doing a lot more talking about that as we go.
So, the only thing that I really want to talk about tonight in our
last 20 minutes is sort of what are some of the principles of game
architecture, things, you know, that I have learned and that I kind of
think are true from past experience to sort of set us up for as we
start to go through and do this kind of programming.
What are we looking at?
What are we trying by default first?
What are some of the techniques that were going to use that sort of
stuff?
So I'm just going to
to talk about that a little bit.
Okay.
So, inside the game, oops, what is the hotkey for fill with background
color?
Backspace?
There we go.
All right.
So let's talk about that big old block, that just said game on it.
Right?
That big old block that we had.
We're now inside that block.
Right?
Well, so one thing that I talked about originally or that I did I
should say is game update and render, right?
That's our one of our M3 points.
Right?
In fact, I'm going to keep using guar from now on, I think.
So, we kind of know, right?
I'm going to invert this from the diagram before.
So we can have kind of a downward flow of things.
Or maybe, you know, what, maybe we'll do, maybe don't miss, I don't
know.
So we're going to get a game update and render call from the app,
right?
So we basically now know that our game update.
I'm sorry are
Our game architecture is based around getting a call that says, you
know, here's a T4, how, you know, how much time basically has elapsed,
how much time do we need to advance things by?
So, we basically need to do a tea update to advance the state of the
game, right?
We need to do a rendering.
So we need to render to the to the bitmap that it gives us, right.
That sort of stuff and implicit in this, here in this tea update
Advance is that we have to process the user input that it passed us,
right?
Because it's going to pass us, the keyboard control and the GamePad
control, right?
That's that's what's going to happen here.
In that sort of advanced thing.
We're going to run to the bitmap and then when we get really we don't
even have to do you think of this as a separate call, you know, we
have to be able to handle them separate call, but the get sound
samples stuff really is just an
Extension of this, if I would have preferred it.
And in fact, we had it this way, originally, if I felt like, we could
get away with it and maybe we will eventually depending on how we go.
I would actually have this be right here.
I'd actually have output sound samples actually be something that just
happens as part of the game update render call and not have a separate
calls.
So, really, I like to think of the game as getting a single sort of,
you know, point in time where it goes.
Okay, Now's the Time to do all your work.
Work from the platform layer, and there's nothing else is going to go
on here.
Right?
So let's talk about these things because I think
They're basically endemic to all games and I'm going to sort of I'm
going to look well.
I guess I'll keep them separate for now.
You say AV output can kind of usually be lumped together because
they're very similar processes.
Sound is usually basic a subset of the complexity of graphical
rendering.
But so what actually has to go on in these things and what is our game
architecture going to be concerned about?
So I'll just State some pretty straightforward stuff right off the
bat.
So, regardless of how much money
Multi-threading, we do or anything else we might do, right.
We know that essentially, if our game Loop has user input in it.
We want to process the user input.
First.
We want to update the state of the world and we want to render right
now, the user input.
We always want to process as close to the updating as possible to
reduce input lag, right?
You could imagine us processing the input like we could update the
world render the game, right?
Not do this at the outset and
Take a look at the input and process it here.
If we did that, we would essentially be introducing a frame of lag.
Right?
Because we did an update even without considering input that we
actually had at the time.
So definitely what we want to do.
Right?
Is we always want to basically say, Okay input gets integrated in the
update right away, right?
We don't want to hold it over.
So we know that basically this update, whatever we do to update the
world.
We're going to have to take into account the the input right there.
So the question is right?
Or I shouldn't say the question is, but basically, we know that if we
look at our sequence of operations, we know that the ferry first thing
we're going to do is look at that user input.
Right?
And then the next thing that we're going to do, is, is something else,
right?
And we don't know exactly what's going to be, but we know that we want
this to be as close to the Head end as possible.
Right?
So, let's talk about update and render, a lot of games will do
something where they have like update, right?
And that's that's something that they do.
Up, and then they actually have another step that's like render.
So, rendering and updating are totally separate, right?
I can appreciate that from a ideological standpoint, certainly saying
that I want to be able to update the game separately from rendering
it.
Makes sense.
In terms of a desired set of operations.
I might want to update the game.
I might want to render the game.
Maybe I don't want to do one of the other.
Maybe I want to do both that sort of thing.
Maybe I want to update the game two times and then only render it
once.
Blah blah blah blah blah.
So, if you think about what this means, you may write the code, the
way I just said, where you've got an update step that you call
separately, right?
And a render step that you call separately, and these are different
functions.
So essentially, when we start to think about the things I was talking
about in the architecture, your drawing one of those
You're drawing a boundary between update and render.
I never draw that boundary if I can help it.
And here's why if you think about the way modern computers work.
A lot of the times is they have very high penalty for missing the
cash.
Right?
A CPU really likes to be able to do things in its cache.
A CPU has some amount of cash.
However much it is it pulls things into that cash when it's working on
them.
And while they're in that cash, if they do not get evicted as long as
you could press up within that cash.
You get massively faster, you know, you're talking 10 20 times faster
sometimes more, because the time it takes to go out and get stuff from
memory is very long.
So unless you can accurately predict exactly what memory you're going
to need quite a bit before you need it.
There's not a lot you can do to work around those kinds of problems.
Since that is true.
I usually find that it is not a good idea to say that as an
architectural decision, you're updating and rendering are split.
Take for a very simple example.
Let's say I have some kind of fancy particle system in my game.
And so there's 16,000 particles and I have to Loop through all 16
thousand particles and I need to do some kind of physics update on
them.
And then I need to produce some stuff in a Vertex buffer, that's going
to get sent to a graphics card to render them.
Right?
Well, if I actually Loop over all of those things twice, once in the
update to update,
Are and then once in the renderer to render them?
At the, very least position and probably velocity, probably,
potentially, also color are getting pulled into the cache and evicted
from the cache two times, right?
They're getting done on the update pass and on the render pass, so it
would be much more efficient.
If we just did it in one pass to produce both things, right?
And so I do not like to draw that boundary for some things.
It's fine to have that boundary happen but at the game
Architecture level, I never draw that boundary.
I don't like to put it there.
I like to have update.
Render.
Basically be one coherent step, right?
That happens together, if that makes sense.
So this is actually what I do.
I do not ever.
Do, you know something that looks like this.
I never do that if I can avoid it because basically I feel like this
is a much saner way to go in terms of when you need to actually start
optimizing for performance acknowledging.
The fact that there are many types of things that want to get updated
and rendered together, and render is kind of a difficult term here
because render in the final version of the game.
Name is not really about rendering, it's about stuffing things in
buffers that eventually go off to a GPU, but you know what, I mean, so
sort of this term render think of that more as render prep because
nobody actually does rendering anymore.
And in our case, we won't really be doing that either.
It's up input, update render.
And then like, you know, GPU or whatever is doing.
Its thing.
We will also have that.
That step right?
Only in our case.
We implemented, we will be implementing the actual code that, you
know, and on the CPU.
So it won't be on a GPU, right?
So really, there's that final step.
So when I say render, I just want to make it clear what I'm talking
about.
I'm talking about the thing that prepares all of the buffers for the
graphics subsystem to handle, which is normally, on a GPU.
But in our case, for the first couple months, it's going to be our own
renderer.
Okay.
So this runs sort of in parallel with another part of the game
architecture, right?
So we have our input, that's got to come in and be integrated first.
That may be integrated directly into this, but I think, actually
probably most of the time it won't be.
I think it'll be a separate step that happens here, just because
there's not a lot to do with input processing.
It's not a performance critical thing.
Usually you're just setting some State then gets used by the update.
Later, so this will probably be a separate part.
That's just like the player control code that, you know, the next
question like that, you did the update and render.
And then basically, we do now know that architecturally speaking,
we're going to get some other call down here.
That's a separate list of things that have to happen, which is you
know, sound output.
Right.
And so these things have to pull from somewhere.
So what I want to talk about now is where these things pull from.
Basically.
I really wish.
I knew how to erase stuff in a diagram.
I realized that maybe too much to ask here.
Take a look.
Nope.
That's not it.
Try again.
There we go.
Can I select like deselect stuff?
Is that on the table?
Select control shift.
A troll ship day?
There we go.
oops, close
All right, so
Basically, I'm saying that our architecture would draw boundaries
roughly like this, right?
We have to draw this bound because the platform layer do it for us.
We have to draw this boundary because this is Art.
We don't draw this boundary, but I'm saying, I probably will.
So there's another boundary that we have that is kind of a parallel
style boundary.
And what I want you to think about is basically where this stuff is
getting its data from, right?
So there's one form of game architecture.
Which is sort of the loading screen architecture, I would call it.
Okay, the loading screen architecture is the one where you have some
event, which is your change level or something event.
And you go into some kind of a loading screen and the loading screen
then goes through all the assets that it thinks that's going to need,
for whatever it is that it's doing, whatever.
It's about to do like, whatever game level, you're about to play that
sort of thing.
And the user gets to sit there and watch a little spinning thing.
In a quote, from one of the characters in the game or something like
this or a pro tip like press real.
Would quickly to reload quicker or something like that.
During that time.
What happens is the resources for the game are being loaded from
somewhere, right?
So resources are coming in.
Usually they're coming in off of a disk of some kind, oftentimes its
Optical if you're on a console, but then it's like HD or SD drive.
If you're you know on a if you're on a PC, right?
These things are coming in.
Sometimes they can even come over a network and get a little close to
my head there.
I don't know if I can.
There we go.
So essentially what happens is, at some point, you've got to get these
resources out because steps here, depend on it.
At least this step does, right?
And possibly this Step 2, depending on where how we choose to do our
sound output, whether it's buffered.
But if we decide to do a way where the output just does a quick thing,
there would be a three in here, which is sound prep, Right Where It
prepares the output for what this will get handed back.
So either way somebody, you know, sound-wise is pulling off of these
resources.
So basically we have AV resources here, right?
At the very least.
Now, we may have other things.
This is a procedural game.
So we probably won't.
But so in addition to AV you may have d as well audio video and just
data, right?
Like gameplay we could call it G like level structures that sort of
stuff that that can be in there too.
Right?
So we've got these resources.
Make a call mess structural resources.
I don't know because they could be.
Structural for audio videos.
Well, like here is a graph of different meshes that have to get
loaded, you know, who knows?
So this resource part is also an architectural part and I'll kind of
try to explain why in the loading screen style of doing things.
There really is no architecture concern.
As far as the loading part goes.
I mean there is a little bit, but not very much.
The reason is because essentially you're not talking about one
integrated system.
You're talking about two systems that run completely separately.
So there isn't much of an architecture concern.
When you
To load you.
Load and none of this stuff is happening.
Right?
And when you are done, loading, you do this and then you never load in
here.
Right?
So, the full on loading screen mentality is one where you basically
don't really have to think too hard.
About how this architecture is going to work.
But there's another way of doing this, which is the streaming
mentality, right?
So if I go ahead and say let's not do that, you know, oops, never
gonna get used to that.
Let's say we don't want to do that.
So what we want to do is we want to do streaming now.
It's streaming is is streaming is something where we say.
Okay.
I don't want the user to have to sit through a loading screen and I
want to be able to maybe
Have very large worlds as well.
So I don't want them to have to like, hit Parts in the world where
they like have to stop and it loads like, you know, I don't know the
old Half-Life kind of a walk Round a corner and you go, it's got a
load, you know, whatever.
I don't want to, you know, have any that I want the game to just Boot
and run and it always just goes and get the resources that it needs
kind of in the background using, you know, because there's obviously
lots of resources now, for doing that sort of thing on the computer.
There's a lot more Firepower that you have in terms of being able to
run things, concurrently.
So assuming that that's the case you want to make money streaming
things, you do now have another architectural boundary that you have
to draw here.
Right?
You've got an architectural boundary, where there's essentially a
two-way communication.
There's this side of things has to be able to tell this side of
things, what it needs.
And then when those things are ready, there has to be a way to
communicate back so that it can actually know that they're there and
can use them right now.
Is a fuzzy back and forth because what you choose to do their effects,
how you might think of those arrows.
But this is basically, you know, the situation, you've got a, you've
kind of bi-directional linkage that goes with these sorts of things.
This is going to be a very, very important part of our architecture to
think about as well because a lot of people do this very poorly this
part and it's also where, you know, I know a lot of people have asked
about is
I am gooey, right immediate mode graphical user interface.
Well, I am GUI, is really just a special case of I am design, like,
you can design any architecture to be IM or RM.
Basically, I am is immediate mode.
Those of you don't know and our m is retained mode.
Okay.
Immediate mode is is a way of describing an API boundary where the
calling side does not have to remember.
Handles to the Target side.
So the classic example here would be like in a rendering API where
these terms first came from to the best of my knowledge.
Are?
I am nrm, if I have to call you to make sup like a scene graph.
I say like create a node in my scene and it
This transform and give this mesh and then create another node.
That's a child of that mesh.
And I create this like seeing graph and then I say render right at the
end and it the library is responsible for doing all that traversal and
rendering scene graph.
That's an example of retained mode because basically, the retain is
talking about what happens on the other side of the boundary, its
retaining, all the structure, basically that you shouldn't even say it
that way.
So I want to just slightly finish this, but we're going to talk about
this in a lot more detail on future stream.
So I won't belabor the point the term retained mode and median mode
are actually bad.
I mean, I'll say that out up front because this retained part is
actually not important.
It's the API part that's important and I will be showing you this in
very explicit detail later on when we actually do some of these
systems, but basically the way
Think about this is probably not too quite, think about it, the way I
just said, unfortunately, the way to think about it is actually about
lifetimes.
Right?
And I was trying to explain it the way that these things originally
worked in renderers, which would have been true for the way I was
saying it, but I'm not going to use them that way because it's kind of
weak sauce.
So, we'll have to wait till we actually get there.
But the right way to think about these things, actually lifetimes.
So, in immediate mode, the calling side does is unaware of the
lifetime.
I'm of anything in the system.
They just don't know, right?
They are unaware of how long something exists.
But in immediate in a retain mode they are.
So again, the example would be in that scene node architecture, or
anything else, really you could even imagine.
In fact, we could we could do a pretty good example with say opengl or
a direct3d if I have to create a texture binding, right?
I have to say, I want to create a texture binding.
Please give me a handle to a texter and later on.
I'll tell
I need to release that texture.
That's definitely retained mode, right?
Because I have to mirror across the boundary this notion of this
object lifetime.
The application that's calling direct through.
Your opengl is aware of and manages, the lifetime of that thing and
that's retained mode.
Immediate mode are like.
So those parts of like opengl and direct3d are retained mode.
Immediate mode is when I don't have to care.
So for example, let's say I do something like in the old
Fixed function pipeline where in opengl directed.
Yeah, I would say, I want to set this blending mode, right?
I would say here's what the blending mode is.
Well, when I set that blending mode, I don't have to care how long
that's true for, right?
I just know that I set this blending mode and I do some operations and
the operations that are done.
We'll have that blending mode later on.
Someone else will change the blend mode to something when they want to
do a different operation, but I don't have to actually
I'll undo that blend.
Set.
I don't have to like destroy the blend mode after I'm done with it or
anything like this.
I just say I need it and it's there and later on.
Someone else says they need something else and it's there.
That's like immediate mode.
These things have a lot of consequences, your choices, of which of
those two things you pick any point in any one of the layer boundaries
is definitely going to be crucially important to how well the system
functions because there's tons of trade-offs that occur for each.
One of the decisions that you make so we will be harping on this.
A lot will be harping on it.
Here will be harping a lot on it in here as well.
And so that will get a little more detail.
All right.
I think we're out of time.
I saw the timer pop up there and the timer like I said, does not lie.
So, I believe we are now officially out of time.
So I will finish.
I will say that that is all.
We're going to talk about architecture wise today.
Hopefully, you've got a reasonable idea of what I'm talking about now
on.
About architecture things.
So, really the next thing that we have to talk about is sort of how
we're going to structure these sorts of things and that will, again be
something that we can actually start doing code.
So tomorrow we should be able to actually start doing coding on these
things because this is like I said, I don't really like to do
architecture like a super high level pre-planning sort of thing.
I like to sort of do it more organically like I do the rest of my code
structuring so that's okay, but
But I felt like it was important to kind of give this General overview
of how we're thinking about things, just so we can sort of have a
little bit of hang out.
So tomorrow, I'll start off by redrawing.
This diagram, basically in a little more detail of just how we're
going to try to approach things and then we'll Court of dive into
doing code on this sort of stuff.
All right, that brings us to question time, please.
If you could keep your questions to things that we covered in today's
stream.
Or in previous streams and put seem your ettore in the questions so
that I can see it because I've got a little thing that basically says,
you know that filters questions for me based on on whether or not my
name is in them.
So I won't see it if you if you don't.
Okay, let's see.
Let us see questions.
Does anybody have them?
There's no questions.
We all go home early tonight.
Remember it's not handmade hero with the app.
It's senior ettore handmade hero.
I won't see although you know what I should just start scanning for
that as well.
So it's like should I'm going to make a note of that.
All right.
Is it beat?
It may retain mode.
Like ioc dependency injection?
Inversion of control, dependency injection.
I'm afraid, I don't, I'm not familiar with those terms so I could not
tell you.
The one qualms, I still have with the fixed time step style update
render.
We're using is that I don't understand how it reacts to missing is
Target frame rate.
What if the end user machine is slow enough that we missed 30, 60, or
30 FPS.
Can we build in say cards about that?
So no.
Basically if you can't run at 30 frames a second, you shouldn't be
running a game because anything less than 30 frames a second.
We'll look choppy.
So you shouldn't do that.
Ever never write a game that
Runs less than 30 frames a second, unless you are intentionally doing
some kind of strategy game that just doesn't care, I guess.
And the way I would say that was, if we were going to plan on running
at sub 30, we would, at the very least, still run the game at 30.
We'd only we'd have the renderer in, like a separate thread or
something.
That would update the graphical bitmap, only every other frame, or
something like that, but you never, ever, ever, ever ever, ever, ever
want to
We run the input at less than 30 for sure, but I would argue you never
want to run the graphics at less than 30 either.
What I would point out though is we're not.
Architecting the game around a fixed time step.
The time step will take the T.
So our game can actually run it any frame rate.
Just to be clear.
The game architecture runs at any frame rate because if you are Pat,
you're going to pass in a T2 to update the game with.
So you would be able to run the game of 50 frames a second.
Just don't.
If that makes sense and if its graphical quality that is that is
causing you to not hit 30.
What you want to do is you want to scale back the graphics so that you
do hit 30, that make sense.
Are you going to work with virtual file systems to store data
resources?
Well, I mean, sort of the phrase virtual file system is really
a little bit of a pet peeve of mine, like almost no games ship with
virtual file systems.
A file system, is a very like specific thing that has a bunch of
capabilities.
Usually, what people do is, they just essentially have a zip file, you
know, they have like a pack like where they pack things end-to-end.
That's not really a file system.
I understand your argument for blending update and render for
particles in general.
Don't, you want many things to update before rendering though?
For example, if we update and render the player only to later update
the bullet and find it hits the player.
The players reaction animation is a frame off.
So I think
I would caution against thinking about updating in that way, because
you've basically baked into that question the assumption that the
That you update things like bullets and players is that you Loop
through a set of entities and whoever happens to be first in the list,
gets updated first or something.
That's usually not a very good way to write your update loop.
I realized that is the way a lot of games right there, update Loop,
but I would never do it that way.
So when we get to sort of how we write those things, I'll show you how
to structure things.
So that we update things correctly.
Because the other way too.
I would I would point out that in that situation.
You talked about you actually have another bug which is that?
What if you were to like, what if you were to update the player,
right?
And then you update the bullet and you find out that the thing that
has happened with the bullet, should imply, that the player couldn't
have moved to where they're going to move, like the bullet hits a
button, that opens a door and the player hit the door.
When they were updated.
So at that point, when the player would have been going through the
door, they actually stopped, which is a bug, right?
So you can't just think about things.
Even in terms of update than render, you have update dependencies in
general and update dependencies, have to be handled.
It usually has nothing to do with rendering or not.
So if you have things that are dependent on their order of resolution
and you care, those have to be baked into the update understanding
itself, and it really doesn't have much to do with rendering and you
can leave rendering out of it entirely and you still have that
problem.
How strong is the notion that you perform the update and render steps
together?
What about, a situation where update order requirements differ from
render order requirements?
Well, so, the idea is not that it's a strong division.
The idea is, I'm sorry, but it's a strong blending.
The idea is that architectural.
You don't make the distinction, so you don't want to pre say a
priority that update and render can't happen together.
And so that way, anything who can be updated rendered correctly
together.
B and anything that can't won't be right.
But there's a great many things that can be and so not making an
architectural division, there helps you increase performance.
Let's see.
Okay, so Jonathan Blow is asking to explain the variable in this
session.
And one of the things that I didn't talk about when we talked about
game architecture, obviously, was where the variable fits into all of
this.
The reason that I didn't do that is because still, I mean, I've been
programming games for like 30 years now, I guess.
I mean, you know, I was little when I started, so I don't know 20
years professionally.
I've never actually seen a game engine successfully create a variable
for more than, like, you know, a fraction of a second.
So, we really just have not been able to
Study these variables if they even really exist.
I mean, we only see them indirectly, right?
So again, Jonathan, it's a good question, obviously, but I just don't,
I feel like it's impossible to really explain its like a frontier of
computer science.
How do you handle update versus render for a game that can run 60 or
120 FPS depending on the user's display?
Well, it doesn't really matter.
I guess.
There's so there's some, if you are concerned about wanting the game
to always run at the same time step, even if their rendering is having
a different time step, then that's a sort of separate question.
But assuming you just mean 60 or 120 FPS.
It's just this T variable right.
Either the T variable comes in as 1 over 60.
As the amount to update or one over 120.
That's the only difference between the two scenarios you just
described.
So you don't really have to change anything.
When you say you like to do update ran together, are you implying that
you do it on a per object entity basis?
No, you do it at whatever granularity makes sense for the system.
So, like for particle systems, for example, you would do it for the
particle system at once for objects.
There may be a dependency graph that has to get traversed for the
update.
You never know.
So it's, it's about not drawing an architectural distinction, so that
every sub portion of every portion of the update code.
Choose to have the rendering Bound in or happen later depending on
which one it wants.
Are we planning on networking with the game Loop?
Well, we we may do networking as a separate stream some day after the
game is done, but no there will be no.
We're not going to do networking because networking is a whole
separate topic that I don't feel like we'll really have time to do
within any reasonable sort of size of this stream.
How are you going to handle?
Shaders in handmade hero?
Well, we will cover shaders when we get to shaders.
But see what language are using primarily.
Is there somewhere.
We can review these streams.
We are using C with a little bit of C++.
And yes, if you go to handmade hero dot-org you can go to a number of
places.
There's a video archive, which is the direct YouTube archive, for all
the things.
And you can also go to this news and forums link, which has for some
it lags a bit because people actually manually do this work and
there's a lot of work.
But on the episode guide here.
If you click on these reforms and episode guide, these are annotated
ones where you can actually see stuff like timelines of what was
covered.
So if you would check here first, if you're trying to catch up with
older episodes because these have a lot more information in them than
just viewing it directly on the YouTube, but if you're trying to
Look at one that just got posted.
They aren't quite in the episode archive yet.
So
Would a memory mapped virtual file system?
Ba.
Ba s move them?
I have no idea what that means.
Sorry, I do not know.
Oh, bad would be a bad move.
Well, memory map virtual file systems, have some problems.
The first thing that that there's a problem is you can't run on 32-bit
because if you have more than four gigs of audio visual data and you
want to run a 32-bit system, well, you can't memory map the file.
Right, so you'd have to memory map the file in chunks.
And if you remember having the following chunks, you might as well
just load it right with traditional, loading code.
So very at virtual file system.
I don't know.
I mean on 64-bit memory mapping.
I don't know if I like it.
You don't have control over when the operation was doing that paging.
So I don't know.
I don't love memory mapped files.
To be honest with you.
I like them for certain things.
We use them in the recording.
Certain things they make sense when you actually have something that's
basically memory backed by a file.
But in this case, that's not exactly what we have because we never
right to it even.
So it's a little, it's a little unnecessary and if you lose a little
control of when the operating system goes to do the actual reeds.
Will handmade go with a loading screen or streaming method resources
streaming.
So definitely definitely not loading screen.
Can you go over how streaming fits into the guar?
Yes, so basically, what will happen here and we'll see this in a
second.
But what will happen on the diagram is very much.
Like what I've drawn here.
We will be in the inside guar, right?
And I talked about this way back when I talked about the platform
layer, very at the very beginning.
And if you remember, I talked about that we had.
We Implement like a debug.
In file, debug save file thing that we have in there for now and
that's what we'll be using to load assets just to start with.
But when we go to actually do our streaming, what will happen is
basically there will be a queue exposed.
So when the guar calls in, it's not passing one currently, it'll pass
a queue in here that the game can write to that basically will allow a
threaded resource loader in the background to load things.
Things for the game.
So a cube will come in here and it'll do rights to that q.
That is how it will.
It will.
That's how it will kind of come in on Gwar.
Game engines, often Run update and render prep in separate threads in
order to exploit Hardware.
Parallelism.
If you combine update and render will that prevent you from doing
this?
No, and often.
That is not a very good way to split those two things actually because
of the cache coherency problem.
I just mentioned.
So if you imagine, I mean, it depends in streaming scenarios, maybe
doesn't matter.
So I shouldn't say it's that says, that was I over spoke.
I wouldn't say it was bad.
I'll simply say that it's not relevant.
In terms of performance, the reason why is because if I want to write,
if I have something where I've got a bunch of stuff that has to get
updated, right?
I can choose to split it.
Either way.
I can either say, like, you know, each, one of these things has to get
updated and rendered, right?
So I've simply got, you know, object 0, 1, 2 3, whatever they are
particles, who cares, right?
So I've got update and render.
If I choose to do what I choose to do my threading, I can do that.
In one of two ways.
I can do it using one of these vertical lines here like and you could
almost imagine.
It's not updated render.
You could imagine this was any number of tasks, right?
You've got you could you can think of it like a matrix?
Let me just draw this out for you.
I think it's pretty important to understand.
So I'm going to go ahead and draw it.
Okay, so you got your code right and you wrote it single-threaded.
So you just wrote it.
You got it working right now.
You want to think about it?
In terms of how do you get threading performance out of this code,
right?
So here are the like elements so I have element zero element 1,
element 2, element 3.
And these can be whatever they are right there objects.
They're particles.
I don't care what you then have steps.
There's step 0, Step 1, Step 2, and so on.
Right?
So all of these sorts of things, each one of these boxes has to happen
in single threaded code.
You can think of traversing The Matrix like this.
Right.
I start with them at zero, I do Step Zero.
I do step one of you step, two, I go to Emma one.
I do step 02, step one.
I do step to write whatever those steps are and these steps, you know,
maybe it's just updating render.
So there's only two, maybe it's update render and like, you know,
write to disk.
I mean, I don't know, who knows, right?
Whatever it is.
I've got three steps here update, you know, frob indicate because that
happens.
Obviously everyone from Decatur.
Things once in awhile and then render.
So I've got I've got steps that can be
What up, right.
So one way, is that zigzag pattern?
That's the single-threaded way.
And that's obviously the slowest way because you're not taking
advantage of any of the cores, the processor, but sometimes, that's
the best way to do it because if, you know, you have lots of things,
other things that we're going on.
At the same time.
There may be no reason to write something multi-threaded.
So obviously, you always want to think about first, whether there's
even a reason in your particular game, given your in your target
platform profiles of stuff, whether you need to, but this is single
threaded, right?
That's how that looks.
Then if you
Read the way you were suggesting where you say, you split them into
two parts.
That looks like this, right?
The threads, go and columns here.
Right?
So one thread does the update one thread.
Does the Frog indicate one thread?
Does the render, right?
So there you go.
That was the thing that you were suggesting.
Well, I don't think that's a particularly compelling way to do it one
because we know there's a dependency here, right?
So now I have to have job control understand that this update has to
happen.
For this fraud indicate, which means that I can't even actually run
them together.
Like you were suggesting, they can't actually be paralyzed because the
updates have to happen before the from.
Okay, it's happened and the renders have to happen before or after the
fraud.
Mc8.
So job control is actually going to have to serialize these things to
a large extent, which doesn't sound particularly good to me, right?
So that's bad.
The other thing that's bad.
Is it pulls it into the cache multiple times?
So, whatever, element zeros data was any data that might have been
shared between these two things now has to get pulled in by each.
Thread, so it's gonna get pulled in twice right or three times.
Potentially furthermore, if update produces any residuals that frog
indicate needed, right?
Let's say it computed something that fraud mc8 also would need to
compute.
Well, either it writes it out to element which now burns are right
because it would have just been on the stack or it.
It has to be recomputed in front of Kate which wastes a bunch of
Cycles, right?
So I don't love, you know, sometimes that's appropriate but I don't
really love that the doing it that way.
What I
Fur to do is break it up this way.
Right?
So basically there's somebody doing one zigzag that way and then
somebody doing a zigzag this way, right?
Basically break it up.
Bye.
Bye rose, right.
Because this way, the dependency is inside the code still and it looks
exactly like the single threaded code looked, right, but now you just
break it up by.
Which one is by what group of elements.
It's actually working on so, I don't know.
So,
So personally, I tend to prefer writing it that way if you can, if for
some reason you have to write it this way, well, okay, but I feel like
a lot of times it's better to write it the other way.
Since the human eye can only see at 70 frames per second.
Is it worth it to put in a Max FPS allowed?
Well, we will put in a Max FPS, but
Because of that reason will be putting in a Max FPS because at some
point are floating Point values, will break down.
And so we need to make sure that our time step is not doesn't get any
smaller than whatever that is, but I would point out that the human
eye can actually see greater than 70 frames per second.
It can see at least 90.
So, you know, I wouldn't, I wouldn't go so far as to say that 7B
frames per second would be a maximum anyway, but yeah.
How are you going to handle vsync?
Well, we already kind of do handle.
These think, in some sense, meaning that we have the code structured,
so that when we switch to D3 and opengl, it'll just kind of work
because we're actually doing our own spin lock.
There waiting for the mythical 60th of a second.
But what we will do in the future is just actually called d3d or
opengl, and it will do the vsync on the flip.
So our codes already set up to handle it.
So we won't really have to do much to make that work.
Let's see.
For avoiding cache.
Misses when you separate up it rendering, can't you store the same
types of components together in memory.
So, for example, you would Loop through and update the physics
components.
And then the render components for all entities will know because
they're the same components, right?
Whatever physics is creating, right physics is going to, right?
I'm going to do the physics code, right?
I have to update the position the velocity right at the very least, to
possibly some other things, the position and the velocity are probably
need to buy.
Under the position at least is needed to know where to render the
thing.
Right?
So I need the position velocity is probably needed.
If I'm doing any kind of motion blur or other sorts of effects.
I might need that as well.
So they're not separate sets of data.
They're the same set of data.
Now, there are some things that the physics will use that, the
rendering won't use.
And so yes, that part you don't have to worry about because you're not
polluting the cash with that, in the, in the multi in the case where
we're doing like this, but you are
You are definitely wasting cash band with reloading these things.
So it's just not, it's not as efficient.
If you can make it work, if you can do it this way instead.
You said tasks?
Does that mean a sink job system?
I don't know if this game will actually need an async job system per
se.
I think this game is probably going to be scoped such that it doesn't
require a full async job system.
And the reason for that is because, of course, one of our Target
platforms, which is the Raspberry Pi.
Has one core, if I remember correctly.
So we really can't go crazy with multi-core.
We've got to kind of stick to
Something reasonable.
So the things that will multi-thread or mostly going to be like the
renderer and stuff that will then use GPU on other platforms and that
sort of thing and asset streaming which is not really about threading
so much as about overlapping disk I/O.
So
Let's see Panda.
Tipper.
When will we see you actually creating the game.
Well, we'll start programming the game tomorrow.
So I'm not sure what you mean by creating the game.
But starting program in the game tomorrow, but we're going to be doing
rendering work as well interleave.
So will I mean, if you're talking about when will we actually be
mostly working on just game code?
It'll still be quite a while because we got to do rendering work
interleaved with our game work at the moment.
Because we haven't written any rendering code yet.
Will you be making a physics engine during the series?
Yes, but not I mean it depends what you mean by physics engine will be
making a gay any engine that does the physical stuff that we needed to
do for this game.
But, you know, we're not trying to make Havoc or something like this,
since this is a 2-D game.
It wouldn't be 3D physics.
Anyway, it's 2D physics.
That makes sense.
Is there any issue with posting AJ's HTML5 port on my GitHub?
Um, so basically, the way that the code is still copyrighted until
eventually, we release it into the public domain, which I put a time
limit on that has to be two years from when the game ships or earlier,
basically, so you're not supposed to be posting handmade hero code to
GitHub.
If you're just trying to post a ported platform layer that you did,
then be my guest.
Because hey, you wrote that platform layer, right?
And I don't have any interest in stopping you from posting it because
other people can learn from it.
And you know, that's been great.
So there's been a bunch of people who have posted platform layers.
They all asked me for permission and I said yes to all of them.
So, I would basically say that posting platform layers is okay.
Please send me a note and let me know where it is because we probably
will want to put it on the handmade hero site and point to it.
But what I would like to avoid is posting this
Source code to the game anywhere that's not allowed primarily because
that's like one of the benefits you get for pre-ordering.
So that's like part of the product is the source code.
So that is not supposed to get ported posted anywhere, if that makes
sense.
When things do get released into the public domain.
I will make it very clear.
So I will be announcing any time.
I take a chunk of code and released to the public to make us some.
I may release some code earlier into the public domain.
I will, you know, make it very clear what that is and the license dot
txt file in the
Distribution will change to reflect, which files are are allowed to be
sort of done.
What with what you will.
Right.
Looks like we are done with questions right on time.
29, 28.
All right, thank you everyone for tuning into handmade hero for
architecture discussion tomorrow.
We will start actually programming the game structure.
So will kind of be like making some little things and kind of, you
know building the architecture by doing the same kind of process that
I was encouraging for.
Just writing the, you know, the basic game, the basic platform error
code, where you just kind of write the first thing.
That comes to mind when you're trying to build something and then you
kind of Loft it up into an architecture as we go.
We'll be taking that exact same approach.
And as we go, I'll be constantly referring to the stuff that we talked
about today in terms of reasons why I'm making certain decisions as we
do the lofting.
So I hope you'll join me tomorrow.
It is going to be at an odd time.
And let me explain one thing really quickly to people since we're on
holiday hours.
Now at any time, if you go to the news and forums link here on the
front page, the very front page always has
Schedule.
So if you want to know what time it's going to be, you can kind of see
basically, what the what the times are.
You'll notice.
This one is at 8:00 a.m.
Tomorrow.
So we have a very early stream happening tomorrow morning.
So be aware that tomorrow stream 8 a.m.
Which again, is because of holiday hours.
I've got events during this week, that will be taking place at times,
that would have been normally where the stream would normally be.
So they have to be moved a little bit and then for the rest of the
week, it will be at 10 a.m.
So it's definitely going to be a lot of earlier times.
Now, if
If you can't make those on Twitch, no problem, everything gets updated
immediately thereafter.
So, in fact, the stream should be uploaded to YouTube and watchable on
YouTube.
Even not even on Twitches replay, but on YouTube, by the time, the
normal 8 p.m.
Slot rolls around, so you should be able to watch it, just as normal
it just unfortunately, you won't be able to ask you a.
But if you do have Q&A, you can always go to the code discussion thing
here that we have and you can you can put it in right there.
Okay, so if you would like
To work along at home.
With the source code, you can pre-order the game and you'll get a
download link that allows you to download the source code.
And if you just want to support the video series, we have a patreon
that you can subscribe to, I think that is absolutely everything.
That's on this page.
Obviously.
There's the Twitter feed which I try to tweet whenever things are
happening and the live link to twitch, but you must already know where
that is because you are here.
Thank you everyone for joining me.
I'm kind of excited to about tomorrow to start typing in some game
code.
I think it's going to be pretty fun, and we
Will ya?
I think we will probably make pretty good progress.
I'd it only took us 25 hours to do the prototyping layer.
Roughly.
That's pretty good time.
Like I said, that's not even a week worth of full of a full-time
coders time.
So, I'm interested to see how much progress we make on the game code.
I'm interested to see how long it takes because I've never programmed
livestream game code before.
So I don't know what the, you know, the time difference will be but I
think it'll probably go pretty well, but we will also be trying to
take it slow so we can explain absolutely everything unlike the win32
platform.
It's not really that important to understand how Windows works,
because it's just a just yet another platform into multiple platforms.
You have to ship on and nobody ever understands all the complexes or
went through to anyway, we will certainly be spending more time on
explaining stuff in the streams for the gameplay code, just because
it's stuff that you can understand completely and we will be writing
all the source code for yourself.
So I think that'll probably be pretty interesting too.
So thank you very much for joining me and I hope to see you all
tomorrow bright and early at 8 a.m.
But I suspect I may end up.
Mostly seeing people from Europe who are already up at that hour.
But either way, if I do, see a good if not, I hope to catch you on the
replay and thank you very much for joining me.