Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here on the show.
We code a complete game live on Stream.
So couple things I would like to go work on the profiler today, but I
feel like there's a couple things we should clean up first.
And here is what I'm talking about.
So I realized we don't really ever do this on handmade hero and you
know, it's not like my primary concern or anything, but I do feel like
it's worth doing down.
Again, if anyone, at the moment was going to try to run the current
version of handmade hero, there's a couple things that we've done.
Make it kind of difficult for them to do that if that makes sense.
And specifically what I'm thinking of is the crazy hack that we had.
Do in order to keep OBS correctly streaming our program, even though
it's an opengl.
And so, if you remember how we did this, you know, on when we first
went through this and go ahead and load our prj file.
If you remember how we did this inside the build bat file,
This business right here, what we did is we had a handmaid streaming
equals one thing and the handmade streaming equals one, controls the
code in handmade us UT, which is totally bogus very bad idea code,
right?
It's this thing right here, where we actually set the double buffer to
false, even though we're using the double buffer, which should just be
straight up a legal.
Don't even know why it works.
Well, all we know is for some reason when I did it.
It allows the streaming to work in a nice integrated way that doesn't
Require us doing anything crazy with OBS, so it's good for us on
stream but anyone who tries to build a game, it doesn't know.
They have to turn that off.
Is going to be very sad because they're going to get totally broken.
Open job, put or a crash, or who knows what else?
So what I'm thinking is, could we take some time today to figure out a
way to make it?
So that in general, only on my build, does this default to 1 but on
everyone else's build, it will default to zero if that makes sense.
And so what I was thinking is we could do something where maybe I set
an environment variable and only if that environment variable is set
does handmade streaming end up getting set to anything if that makes
sense.
Now,
Don't actually know what format would take.
Exactly.
But I'm thinking something like this so you know, the simplest
possible version would be that the environment variables, right?
Like, you know, we've got this whole big stream of environment
variables here.
Maybe I could bring in one of the environment girls or see if that
environment variable is set and I don't need that browser.
I don't really do that sort of stuff very often but I'm pretty sure
that's not a huge deal.
So like check if an environment,
Aunt.
Variable is set MS-DOS, right?
Like shouldn't be a big deal.
I'm assuming you're, here we go.
There you go.
Right, so like, well, no that's somebody saying.
Here we go.
Here are some stuff that looks ridiculous.
I don't think that's true.
Why do I even look at stack Overflow, God people seriously.
Anyway, let's see here.
There we go.
That looks more like what I was looking for.
So what we can do is we can say, all right, let's check whatever the
environment variable is and see if it has a non empty value.
Then that means maybe we'll do my thing.
And if it doesn't right, we can say it.
Other people won't have it set and so that'll be fine.
So, if I do this format, I think in this batch file, I should be able
to do something where that would would would happen.
That's my guess.
So, for example, in here, you know, I could just do something where
I'm like, okay, if you know handmade streaming, which is just
something, all only I will set.
If that equals nothing here, then we will do well.
I guess what I would rather do is do a not.
So what I could do to pretty trivial say, you know, then go to, you
know, no streaming or something like that, right, no screaming.
Aiming.
And then I can just put one of those labels here.
So that way if this is not defined it'll jump over the next statement
and then in here, what I can do is say, well, let's take the common
compiler flags and I will add to those flags, right?
Oops.
That's no good.
I will add to those flags.
Some thing like
This.
There we go.
So this way are common compiler, Flags will have handmade streaming
appended to it, but only in that case, where I've actually defined it.
So if I compile
Did I do that wrong?
This is cannot find the batch label specified.
No streaming.
Is it actually this way?
Yeah, that's how you do the sorry, I missed it.
The labels and batch files.
Have a colon 3 getting C has the: of the end, so Leah.
So if I do that, I believe what will happen is, I'll get the handmade
streaming will be not defined and so we'll check right now whether it
is by going into just going into win32 handmade where we're using it,
Right here.
And the handmade streaming case, which is this case.
I'm just going to put some garbage in there.
And so there we can verify that that's not the case.
we're using and that this is the case we're using
Right, which is that's what we wanted.
So, now we know that that's working.
Let's now test the other side of that, so that's what normally people
will get, so that's good.
Now, they don't have to care about that right now, they don't have to
know to do that, if they can just build and it will build normally,
right?
And so if we've got that now we'll try saying, like, Okay, let's close
this down and see if I can set environment variable that will make
that happen, right?
So I can close this.
And I can close this and I can say, all right, inside my computer, and
I'll go to the settings for not, that's not it.
Where is it?
It's in here somewhere.
I never remember where there it is.
Okay.
Or not.
That's permissions.
Where are you, mr.
Environment variables, is it not?
Why isn't it there?
What, what for crying out loud?
They're okay.
To have to do this.
Got like it's this, my computer is because it's a link or something,
you don't get the settings.
This one, you do, of course, then I go to Advanced system settings and
there is
Tables of course, right?
Where you would expect it to be or not.
So anyway, use a variables for me.
I can go in here and say, all right, well, there's a handmade
streaming variable and it's going to be set to 1 so buckle up.
There you go and hit, okay?
And now I believe if I go back here I should be able to see that it
has been set.
And so if I do set I should see him a stream because one there it is.
And now if I go back to what we were doing,
And reload.
Reload our editor in here.
Oops, that's not how you spell, handmade.
There we go.
And build up that and I'll do the project file.
Here we go.
So if I build now in theory, I'm building that other code path because
I've defined the environment variable.
I don't actually know if that's true or not.
So I'm going to do the same trick.
I just did to see if that's actually true.
So here is handmade streaming.
This was the case that now should be shut off.
So we should not get an error and we do
That's great.
And so that means this case should be going correctly.
It is and so I think that's just a cleaner way to handle that, because
really no one should ever build with that on.
It's not something that anyone actually should ever use.
We definitely don't want to ever accidentally ship the game that way
either.
So we would want to be very careful about this and certainly no one
else should ever be doing that.
And so I think that's a reasonable enough solution to the problem.
And so let's double check to make sure.
We can still stream.
So I'm going to launch, Ms.
Dev here.
There we go.
And I'm going to run it and can everyone still see this?
Okay like what do you think?
Anyone.
Yeah, okay, so I just want to make sure that that was seeable and all
that, so that's good.
And that's just one thing that I wanted to quickly.
Make sure was working.
Okay.
The other thing that I suppose that we probably want to do at the
moment, I think in the build-up at is I don't think we're not really
using the preprocessor or anything, this stuff is not actually
happening.
So I'm going to disable this stuff as well because it just adds
Another thing for people to have to worry about and so I'm going to
just leave that from, I'm going to prevent that from Ever Getting
called.
And similarly I'm going to take a look at handmade generated there and
I'm going to just Nerf that guy because we don't use it at all.
Right?
Like, I don't think we actually use any of this at the moment.
So I'm going to see if we can just get rid of that entirely.
And handmade meta dot CPP as well.
Cannot open include file with that's because I deleted it.
Weren't you watching?
Oops.
I just thought that was a mistake.
Why did I closed everything?
I don't know.
It's just me being stupid.
All right.
Handmade meta, get rid of that and I don't even know what this is, but
I don't care.
Okay.
All right.
All right, so what is this code?
Debug dump struct.
Do we even call this anymore?
Nope, that's what is get rid of all of that, goodbye.
Okay, so I think we're good and yeah so that's at least cleaner so now
they don't have to worry about that either because I think that has
some stuff in it, that was a little bit tricky for them to do or
whatever.
There was also in the opengl side of things.
My understanding was that casting this bit of casting here is
problematic for Jeep for like jeez.
C or somebody was having trouble with this.
So we might as well get rid of this one because this one's pretty
easy.
This is basically just a like pointer
Well actually you know is it a void star?
I don't actually remember what we even Define that to be the texture
handle.
I guess what's that in?
I don't even remember what that's in here.
Not really remember.
One of the things I really want to write for for it is a grep for all
the files like basically find all the file look through all the files
that I have loaded because right now I have like everything loaded for
the whole project and so be really trivial for me to do a find
everywhere but I just haven't written it yet and be so simple.
I'm really excited about it because it would be like instant you just
do it and it would find that for you, but I never remember to do it.
I got it.
I've been so busy lately.
I haven't had a chance to really do anything with it.
So many .h, we still got a medal.
H.
Oh no, we don't.
That's math.
That age metadata H.
There It Is So Meta, .h, we don't really need either, these are all
things we can get rid of.
So, I'm gonna get rid of that as well, well, and made metadata H.
Yeah.
All right, but I still now need to take a look at that, the bitmap
stuff so, oops.
So in here, I have to do
Where's that going to be?
It's not in file formats it's in in not an asset.
I don't know where it is.
I don't know where that went.
Oh, you know what?
It's in render, its in render group dot h, isn't it?
It's right here.
So since that's a void, start extra handle.
That's basically, you know, a thing where you can stick a pointer in
there.
And the problem with that is, GCC is like super overzealous about
checking whether you cast from a pointer to other things.
I have no idea why.
Because it's not like there isn't a cast their like, it's not like I
just did an equals, I told it to cast, but it's like, that's not good
enough for me.
I don't actually want you to cast.
So it's like all right so I can do like a you 32 from pointer kind of
a thing.
I guess.
I don't.
I feel like we had one of these.
I don't really remember what we called it but I feel like we have to
do it.
So here you go pointer.
So it's corner too.
I might change that to be.
You 32 from pointer.
So I think I like that better.
Let's see here.
You're to from pointer keep going.
You 32 pointer.
So yeah, one more time for the world youth into from pointer.
Yep.
And the other thing that Loops that's didn't mean to do that.
And the other thing that I might want to do is do the reverse, right?
Because inside assets of sleepy, I'm assuming that it will also
complain about the this one.
So we probably also want to do pointer from you, 32, or actually, to
be honest.
I don't know what is allocate texture.
Actually return.
I don't actually know.
So it returns a void star.
So actually, the only person I guess that would end up getting
complain about.
It was, was in here where we do winter jacket extra this, by the way,
should not really be called button through axis.
You should be.
This should just be a allocate and deallocate texture.
Now, I think about it because we move them out of the win32 section.
I think someone was like, hey, they're not platform so that you can
move them out and that's true.
So this year we want to do the cast as well.
We want to do pointer.
From you pretty to for this one.
So that it goes the other direction as well.
And probably inside here, we need to do the same thing.
So we need to you through to from pointer like so, and so, yeah.
That's just again, just to clean up.
Just furious compiler warnings for people to make it a little easier
on them if they don't really know what's going on.
And let's see if I go to platform here, we've got that those casts.
So these
R.
To find pointer from you 32.
And you know what I could do to?
I don't know if this is particularly, you know what, this does seem
kind of nice.
If any point if I said, what type you want the player to be.
And then I said, value here, then what I could do is say like, oh,
it's going to be a type star and then in here will do the cast.
So to do the cast we would say whatever the value is we're going to
elevate the value to a memory index size first, which I think is what
we need to do.
I don't really remember what it wants us to do and then it could cast
it to a
star.
I think that's what GCC wants to see.
I don't actually know or I should say clang GCC and clang kind of
mirror each other I think intentionally.
So yeah, so I can just do that and say I want to void out of that
thing and then I can go in here and fix these guys up.
Right.
so,
So that's that and that goes a heads and runs and looks fine for what
we're doing.
We seems like it so that's all good.
And yeah, so that gets rid of some of those things I suppose
technically I should probably look at the GitHub to see what some of
the other ones were.
But I feel like I wanted to just get those out of the way because
those were easy ones that have been kind of sitting around that we can
sort of get rid of if that makes sense.
So yeah, what time is it?
How long did that take 540?
And we've got that's 20 minutes, plus the 20 minutes on the clock.
So we've got 40 minutes left.
What do I want to do with that 40 minutes?
I think I want to go do more profiling but I'm trying to think if
there's other stuff that I want to do in here, that makes some sense.
So there's there's fader uninitialized.
The fader uninitialized, variable, some of the thing that Martin's
pointed out that I would like to fix as well.
And then people were also trying to talk about
How to keep the fader working, now, that we're using opengl.
And here's the thing about fading in and out is I don't really want to
support that.
I think I added it specifically because midlow wanted to know how to
do it, but I feel like it's just a really bad idea in general because
you're basically taking something that's often very nasty, which is
initializing the 3D card and now you're adding something else that can
go wrong on top of it.
So ideally I would say, just the fader should just
Removed, right?
I mean, I showed how to add it, you know.
Now if you want to do that in your name, you've got it, you've got the
code, but I feel like you probably are going to be on her own for that
one.
So I really don't particularly want to continue supporting that.
I feel like what we should really do is just get rid of the fader
fader is gone.
And, you know, if you want the fader, you go look at sort of the code
for the fader, and you can implement it yourself, if that makes sense.
Because I don't really want have to ship it.
Game with that fader in it.
I don't think that's a good idea and if we're saying that my hair is
going to have it, then that means at some point we're going to like
put it on Steam and it's going to have the stupid fader code, right?
And that's going to be like something that I've got to support now
with overlay windows.
And whether that screws up the graphics drivers ability to initialise
like blah blah blah.
So I think that probably wants to get get iced.
So I'm going to go ahead and get that out of here.
That's going to go away if that makes sense.
And we're just going to take a look at what that used to be doing in
here.
So I'm going to delete that out of here as well.
And the begin faded desktop, if quit requested, I'm just going to set
Global running at this point to fall.
And I'm going to delete this stuff here.
I don't know what handle debug cycle counters was doing there?
I don't know why it was there.
I'm assuming it can be removed, and so now I think we should just
start up hopefully or not.
Oh cuz I still have the thing for like, setting the, the window to be
visible.
Where is that stuff happening here?
Let's see, let's see.
Yes, we still have all this nonsense.
So what we actually want to do is do the show window.
We need to get the show window code working.
So we need to do this, basically, if that makes sense.
And I pretty much don't need any of this stuff.
I don't think all of this stuff doesn't need to be here.
So so this can all go away.
Goodbye.
And let's see.
So inside here where we're actually doing this, we would now just go
ahead and show this window after we're done.
So when this stuff all sort of happens and we get everything up to the
point where it's ready to go, right before we start the game, we would
do a show window so you know, that's what she's not there.
So something like here.
All right.
There we go.
So that's correct now.
And if we exit we can exit instantly so that's good.
Yeah.
And so that's like, you know that's that's it's in there and if you
want to try and ship a game with the fader go nuts, I don't want
anything to do with that because I have no idea what that's going to
do.
Two graphs drivers on a whole variety of machines, trying to have like
the fade out over the desktop and then create the over to.
Like I don't want to know.
Not an effect.
I care about it all.
So I'm just not interested in making ourselves have potentially a
worst time of of things, but you are welcome to it.
If that makes sense.
The other thing that I am wondering about here is also
that we could do is we could undo the multi-threaded opengl part of
things.
I don't know to what extent we want to do that.
But from what I can tell and asking around on like the having the
multiple opengl context, really doesn't get you anything if you're not
on one of their special high-end cards.
So like
The like, if you're on an Nvidia Quadro or something like this, you
get access to these actual copy engines, but apparently that's not
actually true on the lower end consumer grade cards.
So really that extra complexity isn't getting us anything.
So what that means, I guess, somewhat
Oddly, is that we don't actually need those contexts for anything.
And what we would want to do is we would want to specify those
textures.
We'd want to basically have a way of specifying those textures upfront
and putting them like using.
For example, we mentioned the pixel buffer objects we could use
something like pixel buffer objects to prep the textures ahead of time
and then we don't actually ever try to submit them in any other way.
We just do it GL.
Tech sub image at the time.
I mean, Jill text image and then, that's and that's it.
And we don't ever really try to do anything else.
So, you know, we could do that as well.
I'm not sure.
Whether we want to do that today, I guess we've got maybe have enough
time to do it but I'm not sure if we want to do it or not we could can
leave things kind of going the way they are at the moment but I'm not
sure it's a particularly efficient way to do things.
It's hard to say, while I'm sort of doing cleanup oriented stuff.
But anyway, now that the fader is out of there that's good and I'm
trying to think if there's any other things in here that I wanted to.
Oh yeah.
You know what's one thing that I've believed?
That we had a reproducible bug that I want to look at no one actually
mentioned this bug.
Specifically, in the GitHub.
But I had noticed it is, if I remember correctly.
You know, we weren't, we didn't finished a bugging.
We've got, we did some stuff here and we were starting to start
working on this, but if I remember correctly, we did something wrong
with our strings that I wanted to look at.
Because if we took like, for example, here I am in for code or if I
was to do a rebuild and have it reload.
I seem to remember us like on reload, losing our strings.
That's why I remember we lost our profile that happened and if I like
let me go actually make a change here just to see like
CPP.
So let me make a change of some kind.
Yeah.
So
Course, it's not doing it now, but there was one I probably have to
make a change that will actually be somewhat substantial.
Let's take a look.
So, here's for coder and what can I do?
So first of all, why isn't my profile working would be question.
Number one, right?
So, I am interested to know why my profile isn't profiling, but the
other thing, right?
Because that should be showing something here, you know?
I mean so that's odd and the other thing that I wanted I thought there
was some string problems may be there, maybe we accidentally fix them
or something but I don't see how we would have.
So I need to make some changes that will actually do something.
I don't know what.
Well, here we go.
Let's go to render.
Let's go to world mode.
I think what I was doing at the time to play around with it is, I was
fussing with some of these variables here, so maybe we can do that.
So here's her a bit maps and let's see where we're doing these Maps
here.
Maybe I can go in here.
Here, we are doing some stuff and then I can change this to like cape
or something.
That didn't work.
Why aren't you breaking?
Yeah.
So this is not breaking and that's problem because can't bug out.
If it doesn't break, I suppose that's sort of good and sort of not
good.
All right.
What if I were to just delete the code for like rendering trees
entirely like this stuff just goes away like walls are gone.
Swords are gone.
The Familiar is gone.
The monsters gone, all of it gone.
Goodbye.
Well, that's fine.
Yeah, I know.
It's invalid, code path, I don't care.
Ignore it.
I would like you to ignore the code, please, all right.
Here's the disassembly.
What is the problem for this?
I can't ignore it, right?
Because I guess we don't have that and then we jump here, we test this
and jump if equals to cure and then we do R&D, would pour into, right?
So all right fine.
What if instead we just didn't do that.
So for example, in this d word pointer the jump, if equals can I just
overwrite this value with something else.
Let's see, can I can I what can I do here to make that not happen?
What can I do here to make that not happen?
Because I just wanted to keep going.
That's a valid assertion and I'm happy it happened.
Let's take a look here.
Kind of want an OP but I don't remember what the instruction is for
it.
Which I would if I was an Assembly Language programmer.
Of course.
um,
although actually this would probably be fine as well.
To be honest.
I suppose I don't need an OP.
An OP.
I could just do something.
I could just do some more of these actually.
Why didn't I think of that before?
What I could do is just repeat this instruction like ad infinitum,
right?
I could do like, you know,
Memory.
Let's get a little scrub that there.
So there's C70 425 like 0000 doesn't start to do the x or again till
here which is the 33 C 0.
So what if I just instead, just patch that over with like 330, 330,
330, 330, 33, C, 0.
Oh, it's the wrong parody.
Oh, that's a bummer.
I just need something.
Oh, well that one is three.
Would that have been enough?
Could I do just the test the test instruction for 85 C, 0, 4, 8, 8 5,
C 0, 4, 8, 85, C 0 and then I can do the xor.
All right now the code is okay, right?
Perfect.
So now we can just go ahead and go there.
So we have surgically removed, right?
You saw what I did there, right?
It was that was our assertion because hey, like we assert that we
always handled that and I updated the code to make it so that it
wasn't handling, a bunch of cases.
And so, we would get in here and say, hey, this is, that's not legal.
You didn't handle one of the entities, and I didn't want it to write
zero anymore.
So, I had to write over the instructions in memory.
With something that would not harm it.
And so, I just did a bunch of tests instructions, which is fine
because we already executed, that's not going to do anything different
and then I put the x or in there, I had to make it work out to the
right instruction line because of course x64 is a variable instruction
sort of thing but you know as long as they don't do anything harmful,
then we're fine.
So in theory we should be all good.
Now I think I don't actually know but let's find out.
There we go.
Alright, so now we're not drawing anything and there we go.
Good.
Yes.
See my string is got messed up.
Right?
So I have verified that the strings in fact are getting messed up and
so I want to go take a look at why
We're having our strength that messed up because my understanding was
we wrote it, so that we actually saved the strings properly, and so,
they shouldn't be getting messed up.
But since they are, that means, obviously, that's not true, like our
strings actually are bogus in some way and we should go figure out
why, okay?
That was a lot of fun.
Okay, so yeah.
Now we know now we know now we know.
Where was that?
I don't even know where that was.
There's monstar.
Here we go.
So this stuff, this is going to come back in.
We now know, we can turn that off to get the strings to break.
Hopefully, I'm going to comment that out for now, so we don't have to
keep doing that rap every time because I took a little while, in case
you couldn't tell.
So in here, when we're doing our Thang, we're doing our Thang
If I want to I can come back in here set this to 0 and I'm hoping that
that will.
Yeah and so there you go, that corrupts our strings.
And so now we've got a Repro case that I can work with to figure out
why our strings are being corrupted.
It presumably, it's something pretty simple but you never do know.
But either way right that code reloading is very delicate with strings
and we want to make sure that we're not screwing it up because I want
to be able to use that with the debug system without having to worry
about it.
So right now when we print out those strings, right?
We do that in the those are headers strings.
The the ones that are getting corrupted, right.
I think our header strings.
So those are going to be in when we print out our debug groups.
So inside this debug drumming menu nonsense here.
What we're actually printing is this stuff I believe.
And so,
Where is it getting that?
Right.
It looks like it's getting that from.
The links, the, the name of the group that is in, you can see this
here.
That's the name of the group that's stored in the actual like,
hierarchy tree, which is different like the it's not the debug
element.
It's actually the the debug tree which has that.
So it's this debug variable group thing.
So it's going to be this name and name length business here.
So I actually you can kind of see already.
This is probably broken.
In fact, we probably should not be doing it that way at all, right?
This is probably pointing into the original instead of into the grid.
There's probably no reason to do that anyway, and we should probably
just be doing it like this.
So my guess.
Let's take a look here.
We do this whole copy with the nameless thing.
We probably don't want to do any of that.
Really, we'd probably rather do something like this.
Where we just say the text equals the link children name like so.
And we just, you know, we just get rid of all that.
That's probably just better here.
We're doing the name and name length and we do create variable group.
I want to take a quick survey of just who is actually doing that just
to make sure so you can see it doing the Clone there, which is fine.
And thin in here where we do get our
Create, you can see it sort of doing it out of ya and I'm just
guessing that that's probably out of the wrong place.
So I think I'm just going to change those just to be safe since we
don't care that much about the amount of memory used by these things.
I'm just going to clone those strings.
So that here where it comes in and it's doing this getter create, I'm
sorry, create variable group.
This this bit here I'm going to make that just do a push string.
So instead of doing the these name likes here it's just going to do in
here a push
ring, it's not going to store this and it's going to do just to push
drink your
Do we have a pushing copy and made?
Not.
H.
There it is.
So we have a push size and we have a push copy.
Right.
So what I really want to do here is I want to do a push, I actually
want to do like push and null terminate, right?
so, this guy here,
This guy here is really probably wants to be like, you know, push
handle terminate.
Something like that.
And this would just take.
the length of the string to push and it would do the copy and they'll
terminate the name for me, I don't really know that we're going to
really use that multiple times but
Just in case we might as well, we might as well have it.
So here when we do this stuff, we'd no longer have to get the size
because the person's telling us what the size is as it comes in.
So when we do the push, we know that we're just going to push the
length plus 1 because we want to null terminated obviously and we
don't want to clear.
Then we're going to go through and we're going to copy it in.
And the only difference between these two is at the end, we would just
stick the null Terminator on, right?
So pushing L terminate.
That's all that's going to do and
And that's fine.
So in here where we do, oops.
Let's see pushing all terminate function does not take two arguments,
right?
You are sir.
This is going to be our debugger Arena that those go on to because
those are permanent names that they want to keep across the entire run
of the program.
We've got the name length here, where we do a create variable group in
here really.
When we do the Clone, we don't really want this to work this way, we
don't actually want to.
We don't actually want to clone the string because the string can stay
the same if that makes sense.
So really what we would want here is for this to be an actual push
struct and for for Deaf children here to actually get initialized the
same way as the previous one was and then inside when we do our
pushing null terminate.
We instead of doing that, we just hard set.
The the link to to what we were calling, right?
We just say
So we want to just point to the same string because there's really no
need to copy it twice.
Yeah.
Oops, that's dust children name.
So let's see.
Name length, what is this?
That's true.
So this is just strings, are equal, we no longer need this there.
We can just do it as a single comparison.
I don't know which normally comes first, though, in the way we do it.
I don't know if we have this, this strings are equal.
We may have to do it this way, so there we go.
But I think that now cleans it up so that we're not using
Is that we need?
We're always pushing them properly.
I think now.
So here is our debug situation and we should still try to fit while, I
don't know why our profile went away.
So that's another good one to look for as well.
But anyway, so we've fixed that, we believe, let's take a look and see
if.
Now we go back to the render group and and test that change of that,
if
oh wait, not render group its role mode.
So I'm going to go ahead and recompile that.
There we go.
We compile it again.
So now we're all good and we're stable across friends.
We don't mess up any strings and everything works as necessary.
Let me go in here to make sure that's true because it was actually in
in this in the game mode that we were actually seeing the bad
behavior.
So maybe slightly different, let's take a look.
Hm.
Looks like we have a bug here, though.
What happened?
This is an odd place for us to crash.
Collation frames.
Don't really have anything to do with strings.
Yet, here we are.
So we do the reload.
Who is wrong thread?
The thread is valid the first open code block.
Also valid
But the opening event.
The opening event does not have to be valid.
Is the thing.
Yeah, that's actually true.
So is that actually the case though?
Because the opening event is still inside the buffer.
But I guess that buffer is actually a static buffer.
So here is the question riddle.
Me this Batman.
Why did we make it a static buffer?
Is anyone now?
I feel like that is probably a hold over.
Like what why did we do that?
Because here is, I mean,
Correct me if I'm wrong but here's what I what I assert is happening.
So we have a static buffer in here.
It's the global debug table.
Right here.
We have a static variable in here, its Global debug table, it's where
everything gets written and you can see it in here.
it's, it's
It's right here.
It's one of these.
Right?
And we know we always have a pointer to it.
But why did we declare it a static?
I have no idea.
I do not know why we devoted a static, it seems like that's just
asking for trouble because that's going to get relocated potentially
when the DB the dll gets reloaded.
And so at the very least, if it was going to be static, it should
actually be in the platform layer.
Like why is it?
This is just stupid, right?
This is just dumb.
It's the wrong way round.
Like you don't want this to be in the game.
You want this to be in the platform layer and the platform layer would
pass it to the game, right?
That's what you would do.
If you had any idea what you're doing, which I obviously don't because
I wrote it this way, which is stupid.
So what you would, what you would do?
And by would do, I mean what we're going to do right now is in the
win32 layer where this actually gets
Defined, as something the game passes.
I think what we actually want to do is say well, hey, this one that's
that's created here.
This is actually going to be the authoritative one.
Right.
That seems like the smarter way to go.
This is the authoritative debug table.
And then when we actually call, the game will give the game our debug
table for it to use rather than the other way around.
Because right now, it goes the other way around, right?
Right now, what happens is,
In here, we do this.
So nonsense where we like look to see when the game.
Does this debug frame end?
We like get the debug table back from the game but I have no idea why
we do that.
Like, why are we doing that?
I literally have no idea why we did that.
None whatsoever.
I also don't know why we set event, array index underscore event,
index 20,
I guess that's because
I guess that's because if we don't have a game, we don't want to blow
out the end of the table.
This is just bad, that's what I've decided.
I don't think we really knew what we were doing when we did this.
I think we were like still working our way through it and I'm not
confident in the decisions we made here.
So I am going to consider this something that I can rewrite right now
because I don't think if we actually wanted to keep this I feel like
we had an onus on ourselves to write some kind of a comment that
explained why?
Because I don't see it.
And so I don't really think that it needs to remain.
I think it was wasn't thought, through as opposed, to it being thought
through particularly carefully or
Something like that.
I think what we actually want to do is pass this in here where we're
going to pass the global debug table into the game, more specifically,
probably what I'd say is, let's, we would actually pass that in
probably at the head end, right?
So like the very first time we call the game with something, which is
going to be, like, probably up here, right?
We do win through to load game code, you know what I mean?
And right there, like before we've
Actually called anything at all, we would want to set that that debug
thing up.
So the first thing we call is the update and render.
So I feel like that just wants to take the global debug table as a
thing.
Right now, we can just stick that in the memory that could just be in
the memory itself so that we don't have to care, we don't have to like
write it can just be in here.
And I think that's the right thing to do.
So we'll have that debug storage size thing and we might be able to
condense these down.
So this would just be like, debug table and it would be Global debug
table.
That would be, what would be in there.
And then, in the platform, you know, when we're passing this nonsense
around inside the where we have the the memory bit.
Where's that at?
Memory.
I like actually start using this.
Probably see what that does is.
Well, let's take a look here.
There we go.
So here is game memory.
And I think, what we want to do here is just say, like, okay, we got
the debug storage size and the debug storage, I'm going to put the
debug table in here.
We can do a handmade internal.
Because we wouldn't need it if it wasn't and so we could predict eight
this on that.
Right.
So that seems like a good situation to me.
Now it will just compile in theory.
It will also just work.
I can eliminate the concept that we ever return that information.
From this.
So that now, when we're doing that and frame stuff,
I don't remember where that is.
It's in here somewhere.
Let's see and whips and frame.
I know we've got that in here somewhere.
So here's game update and render.
Where's the debug frame end is that in the interface code?
Huh.
I'm very confused by this.
I feel like it should have been defined in here, but maybe it's not.
Let's take a look.
So here is debug game frame Endo, its frame end, perfect.
Wow.
All right, that's fine, doesn't matter.
Frame.
And
There it is.
So this thing is not going to return a debug tables.
Basically, what we're saying, it's just going to look like that now.
And now this thing
Is not going to return anybody at all.
And now everything is all set to go.
All we have to do, if we want to make this work is in update and
render, which is here when we initialize, we would just do Global
debug table equals memory, debug cable.
And that's it.
And then we just have to actually Define that somewhere.
We could just do that here.
Certainly.
And we could condense these two down into something as well, right?
Global debug table.
But I think that's better.
So here we go and we're up and running and everyone's happy and that's
good.
And I'm going to try to get this to crash or rather.
I'm hoping it won't crash but I want to twiddle it a little bit.
Just give it a little, you know,
Get get all up ons there.
See what's going on?
So, I get this going.
Here we go.
Okay.
And that's looking nice.
Yeah.
Cool.
So now our debug code reloading
In case we weren't already ridiculous enough, we can live edit debug
code.
That's being re round at the same time while having the full debug on
multiple threads being captured.
Even if they are going across the frame boundary and apparently will
report it correctly.
like I said, I like engine programming do
They care about game programming.
What can I say?
So now my only question is, what is wrong with our profile?
So we have one more Live code edit.
Bug here with the debug system that we want to address which is why
our profile disappears because our profile definitely does this appear
and our profile should not disappear.
Because as far as I know, I wasn't actually relying on anything in the
debug system for that purpose.
So something
is messed up.
And I don't know what that something is.
So we should find out what that something is.
At the risk of stating, the overwhelmingly obvious.
So let's start with that now.
So first of all, when we do the debugging stuff, we're talking about
that profile group, right?
And so when we do begin and end blocks the way that we're doing that
is I guess we're just sort of getting these event elements and we're
setting up the route profile node for collation frames.
You know we're just checking to see whether we've got one of these
open or not.
So it occurs to me and I'm just going to throw this out there as an
example of something ridiculous, that could be happening, it occurs to
me.
That one way to get what we're seeing is if we never actually created
a route profile node after the code reload.
So we're going along, just fine, were, we've got open thread block,
you know, we do begin blocks, we do clothes, blocks, begin blocks,
those blocks, begin blocks, those blocks, and they're properly.
Matched such that.
We are always
Closing a block that we've opened burgo.
We are always at the root level correctly when we restart a frame.
And so, when we open things up there, we're seeing that we don't have
anyone sitting on the, debug thread list.
So everything goes to the root level, but if during the code reload,
that was not true.
And so, during the code reload, it somehow messed up, who was the open
block at that time.
So that we always have an extra open block sitting at the beginning,
then we would never get to this.
This case.
Right.
We never have this case where we actually set the route profile node
for a collation frame that would never happen.
So that's one example of how this could occur.
I can test that pretty easily.
But the first thing I want to do is I want to look to see how I
believe that would be happening so that I can just educate myself
about what I expect to see.
So that when I go looking for it, I will know whether I'm seeing what
I think I should see or not.
All right, so normally when we blazed through here, we do.
Do a begin block of the executable refresh.
So, during the time, when the executable is itself, refreshed,
We are actually inside and open debug block.
And then when we come back out, well there's Bears our answer right
there.
You're looking at it, you seen it?
So presumably, what's happening?
Well actually, no.
Wait I take it back.
This should still be working.
There should still be working because we don't rely on the game to
close that block.
So, this should be fine.
This should be fine because if all were queues are completed, that
means that no one can launch an asynchronous background task to be
loading anything, they're gone, they've been drained out.
The code, has been unloaded, everything's out of memory.
When we end of this block here, we are doing that locally so that
should actually do an end block using the global debug memory.
That should work.
We then do a begin block, we open that up.
We do what we were normally doing here, that's all fine.
We call the update, everything should be fine.
So, all of that, looks reasonable to me,
So, that seems okay.
That seems okay.
So let's take a look at this.
The other part where we do debugging frame.
So here's the up, again, frame this.
What is this doing?
Why is this year?
Because that doesn't make any sense at all.
I'm very curious about what that's doing there.
And I do wonder if that, that, in theory could also probably be part
of the bug and fell, although that should be causing about all the
time, shouldn't it?
I don't know why that's there.
So if we are in the debug code, and we do a frame end,
Right, here's where we're updating these things.
You can see that we're, we're doing an atomic exchange on the array
event index.
We update it each time.
Right.
I mean we are doing the update in here for what we want this to be.
I don't understand why this is getting set to 0.
I guess, because we want to always set it to 0 regardless.
But it shouldn't be okay.
It just it shouldn't be 0, right?
Am I the only person who's concerned about this?
Maybe I am.
I don't know.
But here is the bug interface, right?
And I realized been a long time since we put touching this stuff, but
let's take a look at that.
Where's that debug table?
There it is.
So, here is the debug table.
And you can see event index event, array index event index.
And you can kind of see here that we've got to event arrays and we
ping-pong between them, right?
We collate one while we write into the other.
Right.
I mean that's what we were doing.
And so when we, when we set this to 0, that suggests that we're only
using one of them,
Which means we're going to miss.
Like, I don't understand, I don't get it.
Why would that?
Why would we ever want that to be true?
Like what what is what is that for?
That seems like that's just never you good, right?
That seems broken.
All right, so let's try to, let's try to ascertain whether we're
correct so you can see in current event rednecks.
Here we just toggle back and forth between it.
So every time through, we're going to pick a different one, when we do
in our Atomic exchange, this Atomic exchange will clear it out.
Will clear out this value and it will set this to the correct thing.
So this, this is just probably was only their back from when we might
have been when we were sharing deal.
Tables.
And this was just clearing the one that was for that would not have
gotten cleared if we you know when we call debug frame end or whatever
so I would say probably what we would want to do is if we failed to
load the game then sure we zero it out.
But any other condition where the game Got Loaded correctly we
wouldn't want to.
So I think right?
For some reason, the game didn't load, make sure we clear the debug.
Event array.
So it doesn't pile up on itself.
But I think that's more correct.
I don't know what, I don't know what was going on there, but that was
bad because that would have that meant.
We were always running into the same array, which meant that are like
other people who might have still be running into their would we would
miss them more weird stuff would happen if we did that.
That was not great.
I don't think
All right anyway, let's see what happens here.
Presumably that doesn't fix our profile bug though.
But I'm pretty sure that wasn't a bug that we did not want.
All right, so pound, if one there we are.
Let's go ahead and take that out.
So maybe that was our bug.
Here's our profile.
Yeah so that was our bug because that was clearing I guess that
Now, there we go.
So that wasn't the book.
All right.
Good.
So it's just a question.
If we got to catch it at the right time, that's going to say.
It didn't seem possible.
To me.
So given how finicky that is.
Again, it really does feel to me, like the problem is, we're like
leaving.
There's like a hanging thread block that's open or something.
So, since we're in that condition right now, I'm going to just go
ahead and step into the code that's doing the tracking, so I can
verify, I can see if that's actually the case.
So, all I'm going to do is I'm going to look to see when we go to open
one of these begin blocks.
I'm just going to look to see what actually
Is in there, right?
So here's one of them threads, in fact, I guess we could also say
here's the debug State itself, here's all of it.
And we can see here on our our thread list here, right?
Here's all our threads and this is the thread that we're that is
actually active at the time.
It's Lane index zero.
So it's actually going to be, let's see here.
Come through, right?
So it's the third one on the list here.
So in here, we've got first open code block and we can see what, oh,
what that event actually is.
well, I could if there was a scrollbar on it,
So it's the open block.
It's the debug collation block.
That's actually what's open, which actually is I guess.
Kind of amusing.
So the debug Collision block is open.
And thusly.
That's inside.
Hmm.
it looks like this is some kind of a
it looks like that's a block that's like never closed or isn't getting
close properly.
Right?
Like during the reload, that's not getting close or something because
you can see it's parented to itself which is just obviously not good.
Because while you could get that case in a recursive call, we
shouldn't be getting that case because that isn't a recursive
function, right?
So, where is that?
Where is that block?
looks like,
Handmade that CPP.
It's actually the one it's actually the one out here so it's actually
this one.
It's this one right here.
So basically we come through here, we've got to begin block and then
we're going to do an end block like so and it looks like this one is
for some reason on the reload, not getting closed properly.
Now, that makes a very good bit of sense, because this is where the
table gets reset.
So, that's the block that's going to be hanging.
But hopefully, you know what?
I'm getting at here, right?
That's the block.
That's going to be hanging.
When the reload happens because I come in here, I've had this begin.
Block, I collate everything.
I've got that block still open on the parser that's running.
The end block, it's written in.
But the the next time around the reload will have happened before, I
get too close to look at the actual end.
Block code.
That closed it, right?
So I'm not 100% sure why it's having that problem.
But that is the most logical person to have the bug that we have
assuming that I'm right about what the bug is.
So when we do our win32 unload game code here,
Right.
It does, this block will always be parsed together so it's even though
this one's around the one around the refresh.
That's not the one that's likely to be bifurcated.
So is there some reason why reloading the game?
is messing with the game's ability to process that
When it comes back around.
So I guess the first question
Have his, how is it matching?
Those two is it accidentally matching them on something that it
shouldn't be matching them on.
Like,
It's matching them on.
It's matching my grid, the grid could change, and that would be wrong,
but in this case, the good shouldn't have changed.
Nope, that's what it is.
That's what it is.
The grid changes.
So
Well, okay, maybe I take it back.
Maybe the good doesn't change.
Let's take a look.
So it's here.
It's handmade CP24 1234.
Right then.
Let's take a look at what this one is.
24 1234.
What's this here?
132 zero and debug interface.
So, that should still match if we were doing correctly.
So let's take a look here at how we're actually doing that matching.
So to check if two events match, what are we doing?
I don't care about you.
If the thread ID.
Equals the other thread ID than the events match.
That's what that means.
Hm.
Okay, I don't see any reason why the thread IDs would not match across
a Reload.
So that's a bit odd.
I can't say I know why that would be the case.
Why wouldn't match?
That seems like that should match just fine.
That's a very strange call to be making.
So I want to take a look at this, a little more closely and I know
we're out of time but that's just the way it goes sometimes.
So assuming it's I'm going to change this temporarily to just be like
in assert
Because I just want to know.
I want to know what's going on in there, and I'm not sure I do.
So I want to set that to an assertion and I want to see like when does
this not happen, right?
So there we've hit it once, so here's an opening event.
And here's the event.
and we've got a thing that's like record span that goes to the
beginning of the frame series and it's like, okay but that's not even
disk
It's not even valid anymore, like that's not what's Happening Here,
Right?
Least.
I don't think so.
So let's see.
This is handmade code, 1320.
Which ones are these?
Are these both.
There's the opening event and there's the event.
The opening event.
The opening event should not have an end block as it squid.
Right.
I mean that doesn't make any sense at all.
To say the very least the opening event should have an open like a
block, an open block as it squid.
So I'm not sure what's going on here.
That's very bizarre to me.
Take a look at the thread.
Opening event.
And what's the debug element for this code block as well?
It's load asset work directly, which is what we would expect, right?
But why is the opening event?
Bizarre, why is this the opening event?
We're setting it correct?
Aren't we?
Or maybe we aren't.
Let's take a look.
Do we set that properly?
So, here's the debug block.
Here's the event that we set.
When we open it, we do allocate it and we do pass it.
And when we call allocate, debug block, I'm assuming we actually
correctly, set it.
So, there's a point to the event.
Right.
oh,
but that is the wrong pointer to the event that is not stored.
That's not start at all.
This is the actual event.
We want to store because anything that we take, that's a pointer into
their is going to go away, right?
So that's a bug, perhaps the bug, and I don't know if you follow me on
that one.
The event that we're processing here, right?
Is transitory after we process it.
We can't count it being live anymore.
So since we're now parsing, this incrementally, this event is going to
disappear once we flush the buffer, so
So the only thing we can actually reference is the stored event
version of that event that we copied that we can look at all day long
because that's permanent, right?
Or at least it's very long lasting certainly longer lasting than the
block, right?
We know we can store several frames worth of that and I'll make a note
here no case.
And you know what?
Actually now I think about to it might actually be a better idea to
keep this.
I'll make note of this.
It might be a good idea.
To actually just copy the relevant block information into the open
debug block.
Directly because really stored blocks can get freed eventually to so
stored Event Event isn't really what we want.
So technically, I think this code is not so good, right?
What we really want to do is copy it, what we wanted into that, debug
block, and then use it.
But yeah.
so,
Okay, so let's take a look.
Now where we're at?
Wait did I actually make sure I did that right stored event event
Element framing decks first up.
Go block.
Yeah.
That's all good.
Okay, all right, off we go.
And so now, let's take a look at these guys.
Of course, we still may have other problems here, but I that was
definitely just wrong.
Okay, so we've got an opening event here.
Write the grid.
Well, why would the grid be zero?
Something very strange is afoot, the grid should not be 0.
I mean I suppose it's not a problem that it is but it shouldn't be.
There's the end block.
Show me what's Happening Here?
There we go.
I want to see what's happening with Stuart event.
okay, so inside stored event here is our event handle
And why is there no good to it?
We called stored event.
We called store event and we stored this event.
Right.
So what happened here?
Oh, right, that's actually fine.
So complicated.
I rather enjoy it though.
So the reason for that is just that in here, we're actually just using
that to double for profile nodes.
So yeah, this does not want to be doing what it's doing is basically
what it boils down to the correct way to do this is just to say the
open debug block does not store the event, get stores anything that
you needed from the event, right?
Here in end block, when we do the end block, anything that we actually
needed to do, we had better do now we had better have stored.
So instead of ever looking at open event, we want to do something
where we can actually, where we can do whatever check-in, we need
events matches.
The only place that we actually used it other than the clock.
So I'm going to say that we put the begin clock directly in there.
So, this will just be the matching block.
Oops,
And I can get rid of this as well.
So, I'm just going to say that, instead of opening event clock, I'm
going to say that we have the matching block.
Begin clock.
So in here will store that
And then this events match all that was actually doing was checking
the threads.
So I think what I want to do here is say matching block or rather the
thread ID.
I want to make sure that that thread ID matches, this events thread
ID, and that's it.
That's all that should be happening.
And I think that's just an assert.
I think these always have to close.
That's just like, got to happen.
And so all this stuff goes away, right?
And that's all fine.
So yeah, so up here, we've got our begin clock and now we just say
like whatever the event clock actually was is what we store.
The first open code Block open Event.
Clock.
Now is again, that's just that begin clock.
When we tried to get this, we no longer want that to be something you
can even access.
And this right here, I don't even know why we have this at all with
the matching events match thing, because it's just the thread thing.
Again, we don't even need that.
So this is really just an assertion that the thread ID matches.
All right, so that's just cleaning out some code.
Alright, now, let's take a look at what's going down in here.
okay, now we are in better shape, I suspect
Okay, so everything seems to be working.
Okay?
And there now and I'm going to go in here and I'm going to switch back
to the world mode stuff.
And I'm going to go like this compile and hey, we're still losing her.
Profile.
Well, we're out of time.
So I'll say
It for tomorrow.
I'm kind of interested to know what's going wrong in there, but I'm
pretty sure we'll figure it out relatively quickly.
That was all just kind of garbage stuff in there.
So I'm glad that we clean that out because that's not, that was not
correct in any way.
But yeah, I'll take a couple brief Q&A as but might want to save most
of them for tomorrow when we actually finish finding the bug and then
we'll be in good shape.
Just used, would it be reasonable to separate the debug UI into a
program that communicates with the game over pipes or sockets?
The game, will the debug data and won't waste Cycles on debug
collation?
Debug rendering, if game crashes, you can still expect frames or even
save them to the disk independently of the game running.
Yes.
So that's
so that's totally a good idea.
And probably if we were going to do like eating, you know, a
commercial version of the debug system, you would probably want to do
that.
The other reason why you would want it to work over sockets would be
so that you can debug a machine that is not the machine that you're
on.
So, for example, if you had a console like stack, like like the, you
know, I got my PlayStation 4 dev kit or whatever, and I want to view
the debug stuff on another machine.
In that's, you know, kind of the classic use case.
So yeah,
And we've kind of set it up to do that.
Like, the way we've got it, where it writes to the buffers.
It's not, you know, you could easily switch this over to something
that did that.
If you want to start writing some Network code, we're not going to do
that.
On stream but you could imagine it right?
We sort of architected it so that that wouldn't be a huge deal, but
that's not a, it's not a most.
It's really just that collation part that you would at Cochin display
part.
You just move that out into your separate program in that.
Be all you have to do.
Referring to Global debug table outside of handmade internal guard.
Yeah I mean there's probably a ton of those will clean them up when we
actually start turning that off again.
He's in your stream.
Overlay disappeared, at some point during this evening.
Well, it only disappeared because we ran out of like it ended at 6:30.
Elvin, how are you finding modular editing so far?
I'm still pretty slow, but I think that's because I have to do some
more work to make it easier for me to do cleanup edits without having
to switch modes.
So I think I'll eventually be as fast as I was possibly even faster
when I actually do some more work on it.
So,
I don't know.
We'll see.
Well, I'm waiting for another questions.
I can fix the one from the question for taking a look at Global debug
table outside of a internal guard.
Where am I doing it though?
You're referring to go.
Buddies are outside a total guard.
We initialize it in update and render, okay?
So you're talking about in here,
Cubicle up.
Why don't use debug break instead of insert, which will allow you to
step over the surgeon because Depot break isn't platform.
We'd have to do multiple uncertain platforms.
That only works on Windows.
There's an equivalent one for Unix, but it's different.
Or da minha the handmade Twitter account says, tomorrow is an off day.
That is correct.
Bad fly dog.
What exactly is modular editing?
I don't think it.
I think they meant modal.
It's modal editing.
It's just the it's like VI style.
So like when you're in the green mode, you type, but when you're in
the red mode, all of those things are actually commands, right?
So, I'm not actually holding down control or anything when I do that,
that that's that's all it is.
Alvin when you're writing your own renderers to go for left handed
coordinate system or right-handed.
I always use right-handed cuz that's just typically what math uses so
I figured no real reason.
That makes sense.
Something I noticed when you disable the trees, rendering the white
dot used to resize.
The profile view is hard to see over a light background like the text
was hard to read before adding a shadow.
Yeah, well that's like I said, if we get to the point where we do a
beautification pass really there's a bunch of things you want to do.
So first of all, we want this to actually come up large to begin with.
And the other thing is we want this to be bigger as well.
And it's not currently.
So this, you know, we didn't really do any work to draw this
correctly, we would want to write.
How many profiles should be open at?
Once is really the question.
I think we probably just want a ton of profile views
Zack to 11w do you find that commenting as you work helps?
You reason or helps you overall when programming I find that
commenting is really just if I'm trying to make a note for later like
I think I'm going to forget something really is mostly why I put it
there.
K.
Do you think for a coder is good enough to switch to coming from
emacs?
Or are you finding it's missing some stuff yet?
Right now the there's only two well I guess there's three reasons not
to switch from for from for a coder from emacs for a coder.
They are the indenting and for cutter doesn't really work right yet?
I think it just has some bugs in it.
Alan was suggesting that it was because he
Did had a person in the beginning of the buffer to get it.
Right.
But that's not actually true.
Like it's, it's just not working quite right yet.
Like, it doesn't pick even in obvious, cases it often picks wrong.
So, I think actually, it probably wouldn't be that hard to get as good
because emacs pics wrong, a bunch too.
So I don't think I'd be as hard to get it as good as you might, but
right now it's not.
So, I noticed that a lot
The autocomplete doesn't autocomplete stuff, that's nearby so it's not
really that usable.
So the autocomplete at the moment is a pretty is is pretty noticeable
and I have a lot of trouble with it and the third one is just macros.
So if you're going to ever do a big text edit with macros, it doesn't
have the ability to the macro record and replay.
Those are the only three things right now that I find to be worse than
emacs.
Everything else is either the same or better.
So I don't really know what Alan schedule is like he's in school at
the moment, obviously.
But I would be pretty surprised if in a couple months for coder,
wasn't at the point where there's literally no reason to be using
emacs at all, unless you just really like programming and lisp.
Which I really, really, really don't case anyone's wondering.
K, vertical, Block, kill selection.
I don't really care that much about that.
I use it on occasion but honestly macro recording is usually what I
even use, most of the time for that sort of stuff.
So I don't even care about that.
I don't even know.
We might even have that for all, I know and if it didn't have that you
could actually write it yourself.
At the moment.
so, if you really wanted it, you could add that
Kb3 off topic.
I noticed that pragma pack will change the alignment of the struct is
their way of keeping the original alignment, will know.
I mean, that's the whole point of pragma pack,
I'm not sure what you mean.
That flight I could you share your for credit customers.
EP it is, it's in the handmade here, directory already.
It's already
It's already in there.
so, if you, if you pre-ordered him a hero you've already got it
I also send it to Alan every time and I gave him permission to
redistribute it with for a coder but I don't know to what extent he is
doing that.
So I either
You can also get it there, or you can only get it here.
But either way, it's freely available somehow to some in one of your
free.
Or if you pre-ordered both, you definitely have it.
If you've only pre-ordered, if you, if you only support for coder, I
don't know if you get it or not, but if you preorder handmade hero,
then you get it.
That's for sure.
That makes sense.
And yeah, and like I said, I gave Alan permission to redistribute it
with fur coat as well, but I don't know to what extent that actually
happens now because he told me to distribute it originally, I said
just distributed for a coder, give people another reason to buy for
coder because I want them to support for a coder.
But he just said Not, Just Give It Away with handmade here as well.
So I was like, all right.
Beach and games, do you think it would be neat to save a debug UI
layout with torn Ellen's open as they were last?
So I think it would be neat but I probably won't bother what I think.
I probably do instead is just make it so that we can, we can do that
in code.
And I'll just make my own ones in code for that, like, we'll just have
a way of creating extra views and code, that's what I probably will
do.
But again, if we were, if this were like more of a commercial system,
like, we were trying to do, like here's this thing and we're shipping.
The
Debug system as a separate thing than you would for sure want to do
that.
Right.
Announcing in the chat that if you are at, if you subscribe to the ten
dollar patreon for for coder then you you get the four coder Casey as
well.
So basically there's two ways you can get it.
One is by supporting for a coder at the $10 a month to your.
And the other is, if you pre-ordered handmade hero, both of them will
come with.
It sounds like
and yeah, you can use it with the five dollar build.
so,
all right, I'm going to call it a day.
I'm getting tired.
Tired, I don't know what's going on here.
There we go.
All right, close you down.
Thank you, everyone for joining me.
For another episode of handmade here.
It's going to put the coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game at hand made here at org and it comes the source
code, so that you can play around with it yourself.
We also form site, which you can go to, if you would like to ask
questions, we have a patreon page, you can use to support the video
series.
We have a tweet bot, the tweets, the schedule at you.
And if you are interested in the editor, we were just talking about
which
The one I use on stream, you can type for a coder into Google and it
is available.
If you support Allen's patreon, then you can get a copy of it.
Now while it's still in Alpha, the one that we're using is the $5,
tier one that allows you to build your own customizations in C, which
is pretty rad.
So, I would say, definitely check that out.
Like, I answered just a few minutes ago, it's at the point now where I
actually use it instead of
X.
Everywhere at the moment and there's only a few things really left in
it that are not as good as emacs.
And so for the things that I use anyway and so it's rapidly
approaching kind of a no-brainer switch and I don't think it's going
to take that much longer for it to get there.
The big reason that I changed to it actually was because emacs when I
decided to switch to a modal editing layout Emax is awful at that.
It was just it was horrific and there's so many bugs I encountered
trying to make a list thing that would do
modal that I just couldn't, I just couldn't do it.
So I switched it for a coder and it's been much smoother and so like I
said, now the only things are a couple things that aren't quite as
good as emacs is version of the features and when those are done than
it's just pretty much, it's pretty much just better across the board,
and it's definitely better for modal because oh, my God, trying to use
emacs and modal was was a nightmare.
Anyway, tomorrow is a day off.
It is Molly.
That movie night tomorrow.
So I will not be streaming handmade hero, but I will be back on
Wednesday.
And again, if you ever want to know what schedule is, you can always
check the tweetbot.
It tells you what the schedule is.
If you want to know what the week schedule is or even that day
schedule, it'll tell you if we're on or off.
So check that out.
I'll be back here.
Wednesday.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time until then everyone, please have fun coding and
I will see you on the internet.
Take it easy.