Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on Twitch know, libraries.
No engine it's just us and we are going through all of like every
little last piece that makes up a game from the thing, that puts the
pixels on the screen, all the way up to the the artificial
intelligence that runs the enemies and that sort of stuff.
Basically, the entire gamut.
And you know, it's been a lot.
Fun doing it so far.
I'm having a good time.
I hope everyone else is having a good time because honestly we just
show no signs of stopping.
We're just barreling through and and speaking of barreling through we
are in the middle of doing some Collision detection updates and
specifically what we've been working on recently is extending our
notion of what the world is and how you move around it into three
dimensions.
So that basically we can have a 2-D game which is our goal but that it
handles 3D in a rich way.
So that anything
We want to do in the game world that needs a little more concept of
height to.
It will be able to work well and not have to have a ton of hacks piled
on it.
So we're basically kind of going through that sort of putting it in
and perhaps doing those hacks early now so that we can see what they
look like and then start to pull them apart and go.
Okay.
How can we make this more General more complete easier to use for the
code that will have to use it?
That's going to be layered on top of it and really kind of nail that
down.
Down.
So where we've come to is we're actually in a pretty good spot with
that stuff but we have one major concern left in terms of our
representation of the world that we want to iron out and that's what
we're going to be starting on tonight and that is that we don't
currently have any real philosophy behind how we're representing where
the ground is and you know, in a straightforward 2D game that has
absolutely no interesting depth effects in it whatsoever.
There really isn't any notion of where the ground is.
You're just moving Sprites around on a plane and you never really
think about the concept that there is this depth to it.
But we want a game that is more advanced than that and we want to be
able to have layers on top of layers in the world so we can have multi
story rooms or Towers or you know Ledges that sort of thing and we
want those things to work intelligently and furthermore we want to be
able to have gameplay.
And rendering that that work seamlessly across these.
So if you want to be fighting someone on a stairwell, we want that to
work.
If you're going to be fighting someone from a ledge that's two stories
high like a giant monster, we want that to work and we want you to
know that you're hitting him like up in his head as opposed to if you
were down there and hitting him as feet if you were on the lower level
or something, right?
We want all that stuff to be represented, sort of in a nice
If I'd clean way, and we've done that for most of the things, but we
don't have now is just, how do we know what sort of the the walkable
area is when there's stuff on, you know, if we're going to have these
multiple layers?
How do we know what's walkable?
And there's a number of ways, we can solve that problem.
I'm not sure what the best one is.
So what we're going to start doing today is drilling into that and
figuring out, what we need to do to tackle that problem.
Okay, before I get started, if you have been following along at home,
if you pre-ordered the game on handmade hero dot-org, you should have
gotten a link in your email and that link has the source code in it.
If you want to follow along at home unpack, the source code for day 78
from the source code, ZIP file, and that is what we will be starting
with here on day 79.
So if you want to follow along with me, that's the way to do it.
All right, so let's probably I think we almost don't even need to fire
up the editor yet.
I'll do it anyway.
But really, this is going to be a little bit of a Blackboard
discussion at the outset because we need to sort of decide what it is.
We're doing here.
I'll briefly check our to-do list just to make sure there wasn't
something I wanted to do before, talking about any of this, but I
don't really think that there was, I think for the most part.
Yeah, we got.
We've basically got, we could go do this, the ground.
Oops tough but I think maybe doing the ground getting a handle on the
ground.
First.
Before we try to solidify, this is actually going to be the right
order to do things in because I feel like getting our ground Concept
in the Collision.
Loop straightened out would be helped if we had a notion of exactly
how we want to handle the ground in general.
Since those two things are kind of interrelated and this one's kind of
the more sort of systemic picture.
So let's talk about this for a second.
I was thinking about this a little bit today.
I'm not really sure why.
It just, like I said, a lot of times stuff just pops into my head that
stuff.
I've been working on.
So let's see here.
Where are?
We were day 79, right?
All right.
So here on Day 70, 90, let's talk about the ground.
The ground, The Ground Round.
It's the ground.
That's around us.
I don't know if you guys have gibber, have that that restaurant, it
was called The Ground Round.
I don't even know if they exist anymore.
They probably don't.
They were a Massachusetts thing.
I think they existed outside of Massachusetts.
I think they were, you know, at least East Coast or at least New
England but I don't really know.
Anyway, don't think it's strictly good restaurant, probably.
I don't know, I don't even know if I ever ate there.
But you know, what can we say?
You know, I'm sorry, even wrote the ground.
I it's bringing up things that just aren't relevant.
Anyway, let me start.
By talking about the thing that I thought of today, it's a little bit
of game history.
And I felt like it had something to say about how we might handle our
ground problem.
And that is sort of the the Quake versus unreal.
Oops, unreal model right now, I'm not talking about the game, Quake
versus the game, unreal, which is what it would be if this were a
title in a game magazine where they're going to be like exes awesomer
than why.
Because of some reason, I'm actually talking about how they
constructed their worlds.
And if you remember
Well, probably a lot of you maybe work too young to remember but the
way that these games used to work is they used to use something called
constructive solid geometry, right?
So constructive solid geometry, is this notion that we sort of build
the world out of these things?
They called them brushes often times, which is a really bad name but
really what they are, is polytopes, some kind of shape.
In 3D space you know like maybe I've got something that's kind of like
a little thing that I'm going to you know, create here and it's it's
some polytope or whatever, right.
And maybe it's got a little hidden line service me over there.
And what I do is I like to stamp this down and I say whether this is
an empty region that I'm carving out or whether it's a filled region
that I'm filling in.
And so, the way that you created the world is you might say okay, like
I want to make
A room that has some pillars in it and I have like one of these
brushes, right?
That's like, you know,
I think that looks like this or whatever and that's like my really
lousy column but I'm going to stamp that around in like a couple
different places to make a room that has like three pillars in it or
whatever, right?
And it's called constructive solid geometry because there actually was
a notion of inside and outside of these things they were closed
bounded solids that actually existed as solid geometry.
Unlike in modern games were often times, there's sort of the
you know, a
Something that's typically called a polygon soup, right?
Polygon soup is when you just have some bunch of triangles that an
artist made that doesn't necessarily have any content.
You know, notion of inside and outside, there's there could be holes
in it.
There could be cracks in it.
There could be just fins sticking off it like at where what a tree
might have four leaves things that don't represent a bounded solid.
And so, this constructive solid geometry was sort of a more robust
Ian of a world.
If you will, then what we often use today within the polygon soup way.
Because this was actually creating a world that always had a
consistent notion of what was solid and what was inside and outside of
the world what was empty space and what was filled?
Base, right?
And so, both of these games actually use the constructive solid
geometry approach.
Obviously, it was pioneered by John Carmack in the game industry space
and and people followed suit including the folks who made unreal, but
they picked different paradigms when they actually made their level
editors.
So the Quakes way of doing things,
Was to start filled and carve.
Right?
So, the definition of the world was that the entire world is a giant
filled block.
Basically, everywhere is solid and then the way that you make a world
is you start carving out.
So if you imagine like if we did this in 2D I've just got this giant
solid block almost like I'm you know, some kind of a sculptor and the
first thing I do is start to
Carve out a room.
So maybe I carve out a room that I'm going to create here and then you
know, I go ahead and I carve out another room, right.
And then maybe even a hallway in between those rooms.
And what I've got now is I've got a definition of where is empty space
because it's everywhere that I've carved out and anywhere that I
haven't come to out, cut carved out is solid, right?
And it's worth noting that there was no nothing that said that, you
always have to carve out.
You could then add a brush in that was designed to fill and refill in
back some area.
So you could always add and subtract.
But you started with everything being solid unreal.
On the other hand was the opposite unreal started empty.
And filled, right?
And so the way that they would do things they would say, well, the
universe is Giant, open space.
And so if you wanted to make a room, what you would actually do is
you'd actually Place wall brushes around the room that you were trying
to make and they would fill it in.
So now you would, you would never get this sort of thing.
You'd get this sort of thing where there's empty space all throughout
all of here.
And there's
Based on the inside and then there's just a solid boundary that in
cases things, right?
And these are very different ways of doing it.
Now, this was a very long time ago, and I'm quite sure that the Unreal
Engine Bears up today Bears.
No resemblance to this at all that.
I'm sure that people don't even use constructive solid geometry
anymore.
I'm not sure when that went away, but it was probably sometime in
2005.
Most things that were using is resolved geometry.
Started to stop
Or had stopped.
I should say.
But you know, from 1995 development Cycles through 2000 and
something's this was still an active way that things were done.
And even in some Quake Legacy engines like half-life
The concept that there was constructive solid geometry.
Underlying the game actually persistent for quite some time.
I strongly suspect that Half-Life 2 may even have shipped still with
all of that such kind of in the underpinnings of it.
And it wasn't till later that they actually finally got rid of like
the last vestiges of this concept and moved over to more of a polygon
suit based representation.
But so given that fact
I want to talk about the difference between these two things, right?
So I want to talk about the difference between this model where the
thing that I say is that we have emptiness and this model, which is to
say that I specify the filled part and there's emptiness on the inside
of the outside.
So, and we'll save, this is the unreal way and this is the Quake way,
right?
So what I remember at the time being an important reason, why I like
this method better, the Quake method is because it meant you could
never accidentally fall out of the world, right?
The world is completely solid and so anywhere that you could move
through had to be something that someone actually carved out at some
point, right?
Whereas in the unreal method, it was actually pretty easy for some
level designer to maybe not quite realize what had happened and when
they were making stuff, they made something that looks like this,
right?
And there really was a little hole here, that was just big enough for
a player, jumping at the right angle, at the right time or whatever to
fit through and end up outside the world where they would fall
infinitely forever.
Never really hitting anything until maybe they hit.
I don't know if unreal had some kind of a catch-all kind of thing that
would happen but this is, you know, they would be outside the world
but you could never get outside the world and Quake because there was
nothing outside the world.
The world was actually solid.
So the only things that you could move through were things that some
levels on her head actually carved out
And again, this is the very early days.
So all of this stuff may have changed with say, quick to, and real to
write.
Like, so, I'm talking, I'm talking about early early, like the
original versions of the level editors of these two things.
and so this,
maybe an important lesson for us to take away from gaming history and
say, well,
You know, as I've said multiple times on the stream, I am hesitant to
make something where we specify where the ground is.
And the reason that I was hesitant to that is because most of the time
there is ground and a lot of the stuff that we decide is just where
ground isn't right?
And so that's the route that I was kind of taking my head because I
thought it would be more efficient or whatever, but
Efficiency is an interesting concern but I tend to rank them more this
way.
I tend to want this first and then this second in terms of play like
playability concerns.
Like if there's a if there's a chance that the player could encounter
a game breaking bug, I'm probably not going to do the efficient thing
that might introduce that bug or that makes me concerned that I might
have that bug.
I'm going to have prioritized robustness first.
And accept a less performant game in exchange for not having that
game.
Breaking bugs.
Now, again, like games are extraordinarily complicated, will we be
able to ship handmade hero with no game breaking bugs?
Probably not, you know, has anyone ever even done that?
I don't know.
But that doesn't mean we don't try right?
Like even though we're doing something very complicated, I feel like
it still helps to prioritize because we'll have at the very least if
we have a mindset for it.
Well, at least have less.
And the chance that a player encounters, a serious bug that ruins,
their play session will be much less.
And so that matters a lot to me because I really don't like players to
have to go through that.
And I realized this is this is actually fairly rare of a
prioritization.
I don't see a lot of game industry, programming focusing on that.
And so, I don't pretend to speak for the industry at large in that
way, but that's just my personal opinion.
And so what that means for me, is that
Maybe I should rethink the way that I was thinking about the ground
and that I really don't want to do the the most efficient thing there.
And instead want to focus on something that will be as robust as
possible and minimize the chances that the player can ever find
themselves in an unwanted circumstances, such as getting outside of
the world.
Like this case,
So what that led me to consider and what I'm going to propose now is
perhaps what we could try for ground.
It's instead of thinking of ground,
Or floors, even because someone yesterday had suggested, maybe if the
ground was like a solid, you know, like it was like had depth instead
of just being a plain, right?
What I'm thinking is maybe we turn this around a little bit and maybe
we say that we're not going to talk about ground and we're not going
to talk about floors.
What we're going to talk about is rooms,
So what we will do is we will place regions in 3D space that we
consider to be walkable space.
You can move around it.
So you know it's not solid, it's empty, we're specifying the empty
space and the player stands on the empty space.
If they would have fallen through into non empty space
That is where the ground is.
So the ground is just somewhere.
That if you were to go blow it, you would no longer be inside one of
these empty space regions.
And so what our world would look like at that point is a series of
overlapping empty spaces, which form the continuous area that the
player can move through.
And they are always also subject to collision with entities like our
trees or other things like that but they can never
Collision detection will literally never allow them to be placed in
any circumstance, where they would be outside of one of these regions.
It will literally be impossible.
So, like at the end of the time step, it is just going to be a hard
guarantee in our Collision Loop that you are not allowed to be placed
in a location, that would be outside it.
And if for some reason, we detect if that's true, we disallow the
move.
So we just won't, we won't allow you to actually do your move, if it
would have put you outside as a Fail-Safe.
So even if for some reason the cliff
Messes up would have put you outside one of these things.
We just say that's not allowed, right?
And so our definition for ground at that point is going to be
something along the lines of, you know, if this is a side view and we
have two overlapping things here and you know, we do something like
this.
Then that's okay if we do something like this and you know, I don't
know, maybe we'll collisions act against it too but I'm not sure if we
want to do that or not.
We may not need to because close protection may just be for enemies,
whose who knows but something like this would not because this puts
you outside it and that would project you back up kind of into the
place where you're allowed to actually stand.
And so I think I'm leaning towards doing this method and the reason
that I'm leaning towards this because I think provides us an extra
Level of sort of failsafe - I don't know, you want to say it provides
us an extra layer of robustness.
Let's say, we're we're going to, we're going to have some some
insulation that that will catch if we forgot to put a tree in some
place and the player can walk outside of it.
They're still at least an invisible wall that will prevent them from
walking out and falling into nowhere or walking out into nothingness.
It wouldn't be as good as if we always obviously.
I didn't have that problem, but it would at least give us some notion
of sort of containment.
And we could also do something where instead of those walls being
invisible, we could do something where if you are outside of that
region, we draw in some placeholder pattern that's like trees or rocks
or whatever so that it even looks kind of, okay?
In the case where there's a problem, right?
And so I feel like this is a pretty good solution.
I think it's probably something that I'd like to pursue first and so
what that means is that our definition of ground is going to just be a
very simple.
Very basic game style.
Probe, we're at any point.
We will simply look downwards from where that point is.
And we will see where the first part place is where you would pass out
of one of these regions into space.
That was not considered empty, right?
So, the first part place that you would pass out of one of these
regions and not into another region, right?
And so,
It's a little bit tricky.
I haven't thought through exactly how to do that, part of it yet and
the reason is it's very easy to do that kind of a check for just you
know for a
For a box whether we're leaving it or staying in it.
It's exactly the same as what we did in the Collision detection,
right?
But the thing that's a little more confusing is that you're allowed to
leave a face of this box as long as there's some other box that
encloses this other area, right?
And so it's a little confusing because I guess what we need to do is
every time I'm just thinking this through
You imagine, we have these boxes, we just see which box you are
inside.
And then when we do our raycast, where Ray cast against that box, when
you leave that box, we would, then do another query to see what box
you would be inside, right?
And if there isn't one, then that's a collision point and you have
would have to stop there.
If there is one, then we simply change to doing casting against that
box now.
The reason why I say it's not immediately is it's not necessarily.
100% clear, is because you can imagine some relatively complicated
scenarios.
Like let's say I have two boxes, right?
And I'm trying to get outside of them.
Well, if, if I constantly did this query, if these two ended right on
that line, I might oscillate back and forth between them and never
Escape out of it, right?
I might be like, oh, Clyde against this box.
Okay, I'm leaving this box.
What box am I in?
You know.
This is box a and this is box baby.
Oh, I'm in box.
A i Collide against the wall of box, a I leave that.
Well, I find what new box.
I mean, it says I'm in box.
B, I'm in box B.
I do the Clyde it collides against this wall.
I leave that.
Well, it says, I'm now in box a and I just can go back and forth and
back and forth back and forth, right?
And that is exactly the kind of thing that happens with kind of the
fiddly math of collision detection.
If you're not careful.
And so I do think that maybe we will have to kind of think it through
a little
Lil Bit to see, what is the most elegant way.
We can reduce that sort of process to something that doesn't have a
lot of nasty failure cases like that.
Obviously we can cap the iteration count, very trivially and make it
so that we don't have like an infinite Loop bug or anything like that.
But we may have a bug where there was actually another box and you
could have gotten further through it.
And you simply couldn't one way, you know, even as I draw it I'm kind
of thinking about what it would be, and I'm kind of thinking maybe
here's the thought, bubble, maybe the answer is, you know, pick the
box with
The furthest the farthest Dot.
And what I mean by that is let's say I'm exiting this and I want to
pick the new box that I'm going to travel along.
What I could do is say well, what if I took this Vector, right?
That I'm moving along and I said, which of these boxes has a point
that whose dot product is the largest along the
Direction of the vector that I'm traveling.
Because that would eliminate these kinds of vectors.
They're right.
Because they're never going to be further than say this guy, right?
And I don't know that has some promise, right?
That's the dot product.
Of this on this is going to be like here.
But of course, the dot product in here is going to be here.
So it's a little bit hard to say, the dot product may not be the best.
Choice for us to think about this.
I feel like there should be some kind of measure.
I mean I guess what we could do is it's more expensive but we could
just run the intersection test.
So basically what we would do is we do it intersection.
We find that we're leaving a region.
So then we do an intersection test on all of the boxes that we now are
inside.
And see which one of those was actually farthest.
Right?
That seems pretty straightforward.
I don't know how expensive it will be, but that seems pretty
reasonable.
So it's something like, you know, for each box we're inside.
Right.
Pick farthest intersection.
And so in some sense, this is the exact opposite of our current
Collision Loop.
Right.
Our current Collision Loop is pick the earliest Collision because
that's trying to stop you from moving and this is the opposite.
This is trying to allow us to move and so now that I think about it,
we actually could basically just perform that constructive solid
geometry in the Collision detector, right?
We have some number of boxes.
Yeah.
See if you're, if you're with me on this, we have some number of boxes
that are marked as in boxes, right?
And so these are in boxes.
We have some number of boxes that are out boxes, right?
And these are our entities that were colliding with when our Collision
detector goes to do its Collision detection.
Could we not simply say that we have two t values essentially?
Right.
Um, or not even to teach values, we just have one t value for the
intersection, right?
No, sorry we do have we have two t values.
We have our tea for in boxes and rt4 out boxes, right?
And the T4 in boxes and the T4 out boxes are both.
I guess what I would say is the T4 in boxes, they operate in exactly
the opposite fashion for in boxes, we set the T to be right at zero.
So, the T4 inboxes is zero at the start, the T4.
Is right.
Is one at the start.
It's the farthest.
We could move.
Then for each of the things that we are checking against we say, is it
an inbox or is it an out box?
If it's an out box, we do what we were doing before we do our
Collision detection, we see whether the collision with it happens at a
tea, that is less than the one that we have.
And if it is we accept that as the new T4 out boxes.
So this is starting at one and it's moving towards zero with each
Collision, right?
It's getting closer and closer to 0 with each collision.
And the closest thing that we hit, we know that that is as far as
Could go before we hit something.
The T4 inboxes is the opposite.
It's going to go ahead and save for every box.
That we are inside, right?
See how far we could go.
What's the first intersection with one of those boxes walls and that
moves toward one, right?
So that gets higher and higher.
So the furthest out we could go, that's the one we pick.
We then have these two t values and we say, whichever one is minimum,
right?
So we take the smaller of the two.
That will give us our Collision.
It will give us the Collision that tells us how far we went, right?
And it seems to me.
I could be wrong about this but it seems to me that that is
essentially a complete solution, perhaps for our ground problem, as
well.
I don't actually know if that's true, I'd have to think about that.
I mean, essentially ground could just be thought of as after you do
your lateral.
We just move you down however much, you know.
So, you know, you move.
This is a side view.
Again, you move sideways.
And then after you're done moving sideways, we move you down as far as
you can go Collision detection as well.
So we basically have two Collision steps, moving you laterally in the
moving, you sort of down.
I don't know if we want would want to try to do something fancier
where we moved you where we try to do movement in sort of a more
sensible fashion.
This is where collisions
Action gets kind of wonky again, I tried to solve this stuff in the
witness, using a much much more, much more odd scheme than what we're
working with here.
I'm trying to do a more traditional Collision detection scheme here
because I feel like this game will not require such heavy artillery
but you know that does come with the fact that certain things are a
bit odd.
And so, for example, movement on ramps, when like, when you're coming
up to the ramp, you know what?
Is when you're kind of coming up the ramp here, when do we kind of re
put you back down on that ramp right?
And so, I don't know, I don't know exactly how we want to handle that
and I don't know exactly how we want to look at some of these things.
But for the most part, since almost all of our motion happens
laterally in that way, we could pretty easily just say that, that is
how we're going to do things.
Now, we have another question to answer.
And this is a gameplay question.
So I'm feeling relatively good about this.
This seems pretty solid see where we're probably taking a lot of time
of year, where half hour in and all we've done is is talk but
sometimes you got to talk it out.
You got to talk it out.
So we have one other question to answer.
And that is this one what happens when you step off the ledge, right?
So, if I'm here and
I walk off here.
Do I fall down?
Or do I stop, right?
And I don't know the answer that question.
It seems like.
It seems like we might want to let you fall down.
Because if this actually were constructed will think about the case
where this would happen, right?
We're not talking about something where we've constructed a room and
then we have you know some Bottomless Pit in it, right?
Because if that were the case we could just mark this this wouldn't be
carved out as empty space.
We'd mark this as actually
Lighter so that you can't walk into the bottomless pit, right?
So we're not really talking about that case.
We're talking about a different case, we're talking about the case
where you can see, you know, a monstar down here whatever and you're
up here and the question is do we let you hop down there and
I mean, it seems like the natural thing to do.
and if we didn't want you to,
It seems silly to complicate the Collision Detector by making it have
to think about this.
So we could just put a synthetic collider over the top of it that was
raised up and so that you would just hit it, you know?
So I feel like the answer is for this, don't care, right?
We don't care about this, the we're not going to handle that case.
We're just going to let you fall and you fall down to whatever the
ground is that.
So
Beneath you always, right?
That seems like a pretty reasonable thing.
So I guess what we would say is, yeah, basically, let's do this, let's
do exactly this.
And so we'll have it so that you, you can.
Yeah, let's do exactly this.
We're going to do this exact algorithm that I described and we're
going to say that afterwards.
We do a probe downward to place you on whatever.
The first thing is that you would have hit
How's that sound?
Is everyone down with that?
I don't know if everyone's down with that or not.
It takes too long for me to wait as well to see whether people are
down with it because of course there's the twitch lag' and so on.
So I have to kind of wait and see.
Oh did what's going on?
So, I don't know, but it seems to me like that is that is a sensible
way to go.
So I think that's what I will do.
I think that is that is what's going to happen.
So let's let us see.
I am going to start by making those room cutouts because that seems
like the most sensible thing to.
It we need to make a room in order to walk through it.
So we're going to call this an entity type room, maybe or space.
Let's call it space, because that's what it is.
It's space.
So we have an entity type space and that's kind of going to be a very
special type of entity.
It's going to carve out pretty much all of our world there.
So that's kind of interesting and
I guess one of the nice things is we've already kind of introduced
this notion that we
Sort of complex Collision volume.
So we can actually have a single space entity can actually be concave
as well.
It can sort of be shaped every want.
So that's kind of interesting to some degree.
I don't know how much we'll take advantage of that necessarily but
we'll see.
So I'm going to go ahead and give us the ability to create the space
entities and then I guess I'll just render them kind of ugly.
Uh, I'll go Lele, don't know how to say ugly in that way.
Ugly, I want to say ugly lie and and so we can kind of see that we in
fact you know, do have them in there and that they are really in the
place.
We think they are.
Let's say
So, if I go in here and copy one of these rectangle calls, right?
I'm just doing a basically the same stuff that we did with the oops.
with the
Stairwell, we're drawing those rectangles.
I'm going to say that this is our enemy type space.
We're going to go ahead and push some rectangles on that Define where
this guy actually is.
And so, what I'll probably do is say for each of his Collision bounds,
right?
Each of the things that are in his whatever, the the Collision group,
Sort of for each volume count, I am going to, I'm going to draw
Volume.
Okay, so to do that, I'm going to say Loop over these guys, right?
Pretty basic here.
This is the entity Collision.
Volume cap.
Wow, not a good.
Tap completion day huh.
You know what I'm feeling?
Constrained, really constrained here.
People like to be constrained.
There we go.
Let's get this.
Let's get this going.
All right, so I'm gonna go ahead and pull out those volumes one at a
time.
And we are going to draw them one at a time because computers, pretty
much have to do one thing.
Some you can do multiple things in parallel, but each one of those
Things is still doing it one at a time.
Very, very single single Focus, these computers.
These these computers are so I want to take this volume and I want to
figure out where it is.
I feel like one thing that would be nice and I don't know if this is
going to be.
I feel like this has happened enough times.
It's going to go ahead and do it instead of accessing them these this
way, I want to do something where I can say get
You know, camera or get get region Space volume where I just say,
look, here's a collision.
Here is a volume index for this entity, right?
Just just give me back.
What it would be in region space so I don't have to do the thing where
I add the offset and whatever, right?
Just just give it back to me and so I can use it directly.
So that way it's offset p is just its actual position and I don't have
to deal with offsetting it by the anything or if the entity had some
scaling could scale the dimension for me to or whatever else, right?
So I'm going to do that just to give myself a little more leeway.
So if I do that, right?
Oh, you know what though?
I picked a really bad time to reduce that, because it turns out, I
don't even have to do that because this will do that movement for me,
my bad, because these are already in entity space.
This this push wrecked actually takes me in any space.
Well, so much for that.
I thought I was going to try and I was trying to be helpful, you know,
shows you what you get, you try to be helpful and it turns out,
nobody, your help is not wanted, right?
Your help is just not wanted.
And you know, you feel feel bad about it afterwards, but that's just
how it goes.
So, if I go ahead of here and pass the volume Dimensions, I can pass
just the X and Y of that, we don't care about the Z so much right now.
And then if I pass, that offset as well, again, don't really care
about the Z at the moment.
I just want to see the rectangle at the location of the entity.
I feel like that should be sufficient.
This is going to be pointer now because I didn't do the little
Thing that I was going to do that would have been cool and then it all
came crashing down.
So that's offset p and there's our program.
So now we need to do is actually make one of these entities.
So when we're actually creating rooms, we got a create some empty
space for our rooms.
And so really, that's pretty straightforward.
All we have to do is just make a series of these that overlap at.
We don't even have to be particularly conscious about it right now
because that's really something more for when we do for World, Jen,
you know, when we actually are going to start placing those things,
We get think a little bit more about it, but so if we go ahead and
cure and say, all right, we've got tilak style.
Why that's going to Loop over this before we do that for a given
screen, right?
We should go ahead and add this empty space.
So what I want to do is I want to instead of add Walter.
I want to be able to do ad space where I can add in some space that is
don't know how I want to specify this.
I guess I want to specify an ABS tile X AB Style.
I like range basically, right?
So I want to do something like this.
Where I'm going to go from the Min and the max, you know, between the
Min and the max kind of a thing.
So ABS tiles E I think is just yeah.
So that's where we're at there.
So it would be something like this.
We want to go from tilak style.
Why?
ABS tiles e-excuse me?
Hello Morty.
I want to be able to go from this point, basically, to I guess how
much empty space do we actually want.
So, for width and height, I guess we would just maybe we just specify
the corner and then we specify the width and height because the width
and height is going to be like that that tile depth in meters, right?
So we probably have something like this where we're going to say.
Yeah, here's that.
Width and height.
Now, of course, this would be passing that in is M, which we don't
really want.
So maybe I'm going to just I'll say that.
It's one of them high or something like that.
That seems reasonable.
Yeah.
Although now that I think about it, we probably don't quite want it to
go that high, right?
Because we want some space that solid that you're not allowed to move
through and that's the floor, right?
So there's, you know, is essentially, the floor is not infinitely
thin.
We might as well give it some thickness because we can't.
So if I was to do that, I guess I would say, you know, let's say that
it's you know, 9f tall, and that'll be in tiles, right?
And so because these are all in tiles and this is in tiles as well,
right?
So yeah.
So let's take a look at that and I'll pass these in so that you're
allowed to pass in fractional tile with if you want.
I don't know.
Not the best way to specify this.
I admit that.
But again I don't really want to spend a lot of time on the world gen
stuff now, because that's going to be a whole big thing that we do
that will kind of get into that will be a lot better than what we're
doing now.
And so I don't really want to spend a lot of time thinking about it
right now because it's just not that productive to do so.
So alright.
So
Let's go ahead and put that in here.
We'll we'll make an ad space.
It does exactly what we just said.
And all this is going to do is just carve out a region of the room
region of the world and say you can walk here and that's going to be
sort of our ABS tile X, our ABS tile, y or AB style Z.
So this, I guess we should say.
This is the mint ilex mint, I'll Y and mint.
I'll Z like so, and I do
really know to be honest with you,
I kind of feel like, I kind of feel like we almost want that to be a
little more.
Yeah, I don't know.
I'm not loving this.
I'll be honest with you.
I'm not loving this way of specifying.
This.
It's giving me the creeps.
It's true.
But you know, what do you do?
So with or I should say Jim X or tiled in Excel?
I guess.
Tile count X.
That's good.
One tile count.
Why?
Tile count.
Z.
Like so and so yeah, the reason I don't love this is because we're
typically using this chunk position from tile position.
That's used to add entities into the world like that and we presumably
would still want to do that but then we just want the size to be based
on these two things.
So now we got a situation where we have to think about that and that's
kind of annoying, so I don't know like maybe let's for now again, to
keep things simple.
Maybe we'll do it the other way.
We'll say.
This is going to be like a center tile point, right?
Like this.
And then this is going to be sort of more like this and maybe that's
this way.
So DMX dim light.
So it'll go from that Center out and maybe that'll just be a little
bit easier for us to specify again for.
Now, we're gonna have to think through much later on how we want to
actually do this.
Generation when we kind of have the world generating will have an idea
of what will be easier for us to do and and how we want to do it.
All right?
So,
I suppose in this case, we can actually reuse our room Collision as
well, like basically every room could use the same collision and that
would be kind of nice so we could just call that the standard room
question.
I have thought about that.
That would actually mean that when we add space we don't have to do
any of this stuff.
We can just have kind of the standard a few brushes and they just get
reused which is kind of interesting.
How did considered it?
I guess that is kind of nice actually.
Yeah.
I like that.
So let's go ahead and say
That this actually maybe.
This actually just works literally exactly the same way.
Everything can just work, there doesn't have to be anything,
particularly special going on here.
We'll do it exactly the same way that we were doing it before.
We'll get the absolute Position will add the space to it, and we will
use the standard room collision.
And so, we'll call this ad standard room.
Yeah, I had not had not considered that.
That's kind of interesting.
And so we'll add a flag here and the flag will be
Something like empty space I guess, right?
Or like
Traversable, I don't know something like that traversable.
Is that an eye or how do you spell traversable?
Traversable.
Traverse able.
Of course it's an abl, alright?
Traversable.
So I had it right.
Then that's it.
That would just work.
I think.
So then what we need to do is we need to add that traversable flag and
that'll be.
thing that we
When we're in the cliche detector, that's actually gonna be in the
same region.
Obviously let's see here, Z supported and then we have reversible,
okay, these are going to definitely have to be cleaned up a little bit
because we've got more stuff now than we probably need.
We've kind of Unwound, some of our hacks, like Z supported probably
won't have to happen anymore, right?
That will probably just go away.
And and so, you know, we'll probably be able to do some stuff.
Like collides probably won't need to be there either because now
entities have a collision volume.
You could just set their volume count, 20, and they won't collide with
anything.
So, you know, to do, Casey collides and Z supported.
Oops,
Collides and Z supported.
Probably can be removed now soon.
I would think so.
Now that we said this thing is traversal, we need to do is make that
standard room Collision, right?
Because that's not there yet and we also have to do in here.
We're gonna have to change the way we're doing this a little bit.
We would not be passing this anymore.
Were you passing that Center?
So with that's going to be is that is going to be this this right here
tiles per width tiles for height.
It's going to basically be we we want the screen X plus I
Half, right?
We want to basically make, we want to basically be the center of the
room is where this empty space actually is right.
So you want to go to the corner and then a half more if that makes
sense.
So let's do that and leave that as our room definition.
And then we just need to make that standard room be corrected.
So this is standard room.
We know we've got a
Standard room Collision here.
And then when we do our wall Collision, we just want to do that.
Same thing again, standard room.
And that's going to be the tile depth in meters times some smaller
amount, right?
We said nine something like that was what it was going to be and then
the tile side and M it was going to be in our weird kind of notion.
Here are car sort of crazy, constants tiles per with and towels for
height.
It's going to be that many wide and high, write something like
now, that doesn't give us any overlap, you know, if you think about
the way this is going to work, if we have two rooms that are next to
each other,
There there isn't any overlap here at all.
There's just infinitely Thin Line and I don't know if to make it
easier on our Collision detection math.
I don't know if we want to do something where we would actually make
it you know, a little more forgiving than that, write something where
we're going to allow you to make the rooms.
You know, the rooms would have a little bit of overlap there so that
it was easier to make that transition on the math.
But for now we'll just start out.
With making them exactly a but and then will you know, will look at
that math later on when we're being a little bit more robust about
things and thinking through a little bit better so that makes that.
And now in theory we actually should see some giant rectangles if we
didn't mess anything up and hey look we do of course it makes it hard
to see anything else but that is sort of what we wanted to see and
they look like they are Maybe
Not quite in the right place though.
On the top of it.
That may just be because of the Z.
I'm not entirely sure.
Let's hop up to the next level and see if that's in a more sane spot
and it does look like it's in a pretty soon spot.
Actually, now the question would be what happens here.
I'm not sure if I actually colliding with that entity, what is
actually happening there like why can't I go?
Go through there.
Does anyone know?
I have no idea.
I'm interested to know.
Let's take a quick look.
I want to know if I'm actually colliding that because we didn't set it
collides to be true, right?
So in theory, that should not be the case, but I want to see
If that's actually what's happening there or if we had some bug, but
from before that we weren't handling.
So what I did is I hopped up to the next level, they're like so and I
tried to go through here and I could go through.
So it seems like we're Collision detecting against those entities,
even though collides was not set which suggests to me that we have a
bug in there, which is that collides is not actually being checked
properly and and so I would like to see why that is
Let's let's double check to make sure we're not we're not setting
because their standard room and just traversable as being set.
I didn't do something stupid.
Did I like make traversable be the same value?
Oh, why did I set the?
Why am i setting these that way?
We don't need to set those to go up by powers to but yet, even so it
doesn't matter.
We weren't over writing this, or anything.
And so, as far as I can tell,
That's just a straight-up fun.
So, let's see why we're actually colliding against those standard
rooms.
It doesn't seem to make much sense to me.
So, let's see where we checking the Collide slack here.
So we're not even checking the collides flag, that we don't even check
that flag anymore.
We were just full on
Ignoring that flag entirely.
And so, when we call can Collide I strongly suspect that what we
probably should have been doing here is saying something like, you
know, if, if, you know, if a something like this, right?
If a collides and be collides,
Then we can actually do this termination, this determination, right?
Otherwise, we just assume that they can Collide because we really
don't want anyone colliding with those things.
That's not good.
So that's fine.
There we go.
So, here we are.
Oh, I fell through the stairwell.
Whoops.
So there we go.
Much better now.
It's going to be impossible to see.
So what I would like to do is I'd like to make something that allows
it a little bit so that we can see our Region's a little bit better.
And so what I'm going to do is just kind of make a real simple
modification to our push wrecked call as soon as the five-minute
warning subsides.
I don't make a little modification to our push wrecked call and that
push wrecked call is is going to
Essentially do a series of push Rex, so like push wrecked, outline
something like that.
And what that's going to do is that's just going to do a push piece
for each of the four walls, four lines of rectangles going to push
like four separate, rectangles, basically so that we can see an
outline of the region.
Instead of this big solid region that obscures everything that we're
trying to look at.
And again since we don't really have a renderer yet, this would be the
kind of thing.
The renderer would take care of it for us but until we get there we've
got to make do with
We have so it looks to me like the way this is working is it just
pushes the location of the thing and then add an offset that's going
to spread out from and so in order to make this work, what I would
want to do is I'd want to do, you know, two batches top and bottom
right and left and right.
The top and bottom are going to be wherever I was the offset.
I want to basically,
Move over by whatever.
I want to basically move up and down by that dim.
However, however, big the rectangle was, right.
I'll draw this out for you.
For those of you who don't write this kind of code, very often grab my
color back.
So what I want to do here is I've got a rectangle and I want to make
rectangles that go around it like this.
So I want to make like a rectangle here.
Right?
And a rectangle here to start with.
Like so, and so I've got this and I've got the dimension.
So what I want to do is I
To move up to where the rectangle was its Dimension, right?
It's Dimension y.
So, this is the dimension in y.
Well, it's half the dimension in y, right?
I want to go half the mention, a why up?
And I want to go out to the along the dimension, X back and, and
forward.
So it's Dimension in X is going to be the same, right?
The thing that I drawers Dimension X is going to be the same.
It's Dimension Y is going to be however
Thick.
I want that line to be and its position is going to be whatever
position.
The rectangle is in - that Dimension y, right?
That's I'm just constructing that case.
So what I want to do is I want to again take that offset.
I want to move it, by whatever the dimension is, and why that I've
been told to draw, and then instead of the dimension that I was going
to draw, I want to take the dimension in X, leave that the same and
then do like a thickness parameter, right?
And for the thickness parameter, I don't know what this would actually
be.
It's a good question, the dimension.
I don't know that the dimension.
What is the dimension since?
This is all really ad-hoc.
We've never defined.
Like what is the dimension even in when it draws the rectangle?
I'm not sure.
And so we kind of have to see.
Is that in pixels?
It is in pixels, I'm sorry.
It is not in Texas, it's in meters.
So we want something very thin right.
We want not very many meters at all.
We want like a centimeter let's say or
Or a dam?
I don't know.
Exact time around.
Let's say a centimeter for now is how thick that's going to be.
And again this is just going to be something that we do for both
directions.
So we want the, the top and the bottom, and those are exactly the same
just offset that this accident kind of rectangle and then we want to
do the same thing again but this time we want to do it with the X,
right?
Instead of the Y to make the left and right side.
So this time we're going to have that y Dimension becomes the
thickness for us.
Right?
And so that's that's all I want to do there.
And now when we do push wrecked, we can also do outlines of rectangles
and, and that'll make it easier to see that stuff.
So, let's see if that worked at all.
Right, we're kind of running out of time here.
That's it.
Not I do not see any rectangles.
Oh, because
Too thin looks like well, let's take a look.
Let's make that a little thicker.
Push wrecked outline like so just want to make sure it also is offset
when I do a push piece.
Offset is Multiplied.
Me those pictures in there, right?
Yeah, it is.
So in theory, that should be okay.
So I'm just going to go ahead and make thickness little thicker.
I just want to see what happens there.
All right, so there's and
We're still a little buggy here because that's just drawing one line
there.
That doesn't make any sense.
So, let me double-check what I have.
On incorrectly.
As I have done something incorrectly, I can tell you that right now.
Let's see.
So we've got thickness.
We have the dimension in X, we are drawing.
So I'm not sure why we're not seeing more of that show up.
We're only seeing our left and well, I guess just are left would show
up.
We're not ever even seeing any of these show up at all, which is kind
of a little bit odd.
I would say.
So I'm not sure why that actually is the case.
And our Q&A is supposed to begin now.
So I don't know.
Can we debug this in just a few seconds?
I'm not sure.
But maybe we'll just take a quick look and see because like I said, I
don't like to really leave bugs till the next day, if I can avoid it.
Unfortunately, when you're only programming for an hour on stream, it
can be kind of tough to actually make sure that you get everything
that you want it.
So push wrecked outline, here we go.
Right, let's see what we end up with here in terms of our pieces.
So here's our piece group, right?
And there's our pieces.
So we're going to go through and push these, we push on a piece, a
piece, a piece, a piece.
So we do have four pieces that got pushed and let's see what they are.
So we have two of them.
We've got one with that y offset, one with this way offsets.
We have now is the offset.
We have to make sure that the offsets actually still in meters.
We want to make sure that the offset is not getting multiplied in some
weird way I suppose, but it's getting its get multiplied up in here so
that's should be fine.
Right.
Is there something?
I mean, let me double-check something.
When we actually draw our pieces, what's the definition for the
rectangle?
Let's go take a look, because I believe we said before that, it was
all janky.
Remember, I think, I think we talked about this before.
So, when we draw a rectangle, we do the center - the half Dem, ah, I
did forget to multiply the dim by half, so there is that.
I don't know if that's in the entirety of our problem, though.
But let's see Center - half Tim Center Plus
After him the center is what I think it should be the entity.
Ground Point does look good.
But I did forget to multiply, I said that it was half, but then I
didn't actually do past so we should actually fix that.
Like so, but I don't know that that would account for the entirety of
our problem.
Unfortunately.
So let's go ahead and keep going here.
Let's run that and and recompile.
So there we
Is that the entirety of our problem?
That was the entirety of our problem.
All right, so that wasn't so hard to debug.
There we go.
It does fit the room nicely, so that's good.
And we can go ahead and go up here that the top ones drawing wrong
because it's not using the Z fudge.
When we go upstairs it should be drawn right there, it is and we can
go through and into the next room.
So now we've got those boundaries in our room set up so that sets us
up for tomorrow doing what I said we were going to do where we can
actually now treat those as
In out and that'll set us up pretty good for creating some multi-stage
rooms and so maybe that's if we have time tomorrow to do, that will do
that.
If we don't that'll be our Monday thing as well.
Alright, so now we can go and actually start things up.
Let me
Get the Q&A go in here.
Let's see here.
How do I start the Q&A Q&A?
Here we go.
The QA has been started.
So yeah, if you could, please keep your questions and stuff that we
well you know what, I'm suspecting that if it's been relatively quiet
that I see someone saying where are the trolls today I'm guessing that
the questions will be pretty reasonable today as opposed to days when
sometimes it's a madhouse.
So but yeah, prefix your questions with Q:, if you can try to keep
them on topic and and I will answer on-topic questions.
Obviously.
Play.
So anytime I see a non topic question.
It takes priority over anything.
That might be off topic.
Let's see.
Let's see, so I don't see any particularly on topic question.
So I'm going to answer some off-topic questions until
Until we get some on top of months.
So what setup do I use for debugging on Linux?
Unfortunately, the answer is printf Linux the buggers don't actually
work at all in my experience, especially not on laptops if you have
optimists which all laptops, all dead laptops.
Do I mean, I said about with printf, I use QT Creator to some extent
But it can't even really inspect variables, it doesn't work properly
most of the time and even GDB doesn't work, a lot of the time.
It's just it's too fucking on.
Linux is a very sad and very unfortunate experience.
So I mostly just use my own debugging, you know, I do it old school
style.
Like I mean, when I grew up programming without it about her and
No, I just I wing it.
It's by far.
The worst thing about Linux right now is the debuggers are awful.
And I think that that's something that really could make a massive
difference on for developing on links as if someone came along and
made an actual good to butter, but it hasn't happened yet.
So hopefully it'll happen in the future because I like Linux
And I would like to see it have a good development environment and
right now it does not have that.
It might have that for other languages like maybe the Java debugger
let's say is is good, you know, if you run a Clips or something, I
don't know.
But the C++ de bugging is real bad.
And especially C plus plus plus C, plus plus, and opengl Optimus is,
is really bad.
Let's see.
Can you upload the video somewhere else?
YouTube is blocked in China?
I would like to watch from the beginning, so it's on my list of things
to do.
I just haven't gotten around to that yet, basically their Italy really
isn't anywhere else.
I can put the videos that would allow as much data as we have, but I
was going to try to set up a BitTorrent sync that people could like,
you know, get on or whatever.
So, it is on my list of things to do but I have not had a chance to do
it.
That I'm sorry to hear that it is blocked in your country and I would
like to fix that eventually but I just haven't had time to really
figure out how to do that.
Let's see when doing the vertical movement, would it be reasonable to
take two measurements, one at the current position than one at final
move position and average the movement.
I'm not sure what you mean by average the movement?
I'm not sure, I totally understand the question.
I suspect.
The answer is no, it doesn't sound reasonable, what you're saying?
But I'm not sure, I understand exactly what you're saying.
So maybe that you are saying something that I would think was
reasonable and my answer your question would be, yes, it is reasonable
to do but I don't know.
My gut reaction is know if I'm interpreting it correctly.
Our walls going to be entities or just byproducts of subtracting of
the room volume, we will have the freedom to do both.
So I suspect which one we do will depend on the type of room, forests
will probably be like entities for the trees because they'll form a
very irregular border that we probably want to capture with entities
but like dungeon rooms.
Maybe we'll just be cut out.
I don't know.
Devil DB works better than GDP if you can deal with the command line,
interface.
Well, you know, if once you're on a command line for debugging, it's
so slow that I'm usually much faster with printf than I am with a
command line to butter because the only benefit that I really get out
of a debugger is fast, visualization of values and that is exactly the
thing that GDB and LL to be, don't do well right, they're really bad
at giving you a good, snapshot a good visual, snapshot.
Of what everything's doing in your code.
So I suspect that like I just wouldn't I just probably keep keep
printf and I'm saying
D, Johnstone 8, should you have been able to jump up to a level above
the player?
Now that you have a point nine value for the Spacey volume?
Well, you should be able to answer that question.
but just in case you cannot
the reason that it doesn't matter what we said that value to it,
because we haven't done the Collision detection for in boxes yet.
So they are literally non-participatory, right?
They don't.
We just drew all we did was add them and draw them.
Tomorrow will be the time when we add in the closed loop and then if
we can jump up, it's a bug.
But right now, not a bug,
Well, the entities not at the Players sea level always be at the same
Alpha transparency or will they be slightly less visible to show that
they are on a different sea level.
My guess.
We'll, we have it to do, right?
Which is probably the very next one.
After all this stuff is working to our satisfaction is, how is this
rendered?
And my suspicion is, what will basically do is anything that's on the
current level.
If you're standing on the ground is probably solid, anything below.
You is solid and everything above, you is invisible when you start to
walk.
Up a ramp will probably move the camera up and fade in the top level
or something, that's my guess.
But that's the kind of thing that we're going to want to play around
with.
Like I said, I've never written a 2-D game before every time I've even
made, like I guess I guess I did do one 2-D game for the game Jam,
Even but all the rest of my game Jam, games were all 3D even and so
anything that I've ever coded is always been in 3D for the most part
and so I don't have a lot of
Of strong opinions about how I want to do 2D things.
So it's very exploratory for me.
And I'm going through and saying, all right, what do I like about
this?
What do I not like?
You know, so that's my, my gut feeling about how I'm going to do it,
but we'll have to see when we actually do it.
What we like, what we don't like.
And maybe we'll have some thoughts about how we want it to work, I
don't know.
Why should anyone trust you to annotate a game when you have no
published success?
Purring a full-fledged commercial game.
Whoa, that's them's.
Fightin words, I probably have code in more published commercial games
than almost anyone.
I know, besides maybe Jeff.
So I don't know what you mean by that.
If you're talking about the fact that I don't design games, that's
true, but this isn't a game design course.
This is a game programming course, so yeah, I mean my code runs it.
A lot of games certainly in the thousands.
I would say at this point between granny and big to ya in the
thousands
if you were a software programmer her, how many apps could you have
done in the same amount of
Time you have put into this of handmade hero.
Well, you know, we haven't put that much time in so 80 hours 80 hours
isn't that much?
It depends on what you mean by app right?
Like you know and it depends on what quality level you're talking
about, right?
I mean you're talking about slap slapping together.
Some little thing that shows your Twitter feed and you're just going
to like you know, you know call some pre
Library code to put it up there, whatever you could probably kick out
a lot of those, right?
Because they're not really doing anything and they're kind of slow and
bulky and whatever, right?
But if you're talking about making something really good, you know,
are you talking about like a cool pink package or something?
Well, we probably wouldn't gotten very far in that, you know.
So it's hard to say
hard to say.
Will there be water and how would it affect movement?
So I think we probably should have some water.
Maybe I don't know how it would affect movement because I don't really
I don't super love swimming in games.
So I don't know if I'd be inclined to add water but it's worth noting.
I hadn't been thinking about what our I've been thinking the game is
mostly like maybe it has some impassable water, like the water is just
something you can't go across.
So it's just a it's just another type of wall that looks prettier
right.
That's how I have been thinking about water, but thinking about it
more carefully.
It is true that now that we're going with this sort of in and out box,
thing we could Define some of these boxes to be water in which case
you would like to sink in them and you could swim, I don't know.
It's a good question, I'm not sure about the water situation so maybe
I want to add that to the to do list.
I'm going to add that to the to list because I haven't thought about
it but we've kind
And of added something now where you know where we have water in here?
Let's see.
Air water that you can swim in maybe with currents to that kind of
pull you along.
I don't know, could be interesting, could be interesting.
To the system used for the ground.
Now make it harder to have things like moving platforms.
The player can stand on.
I don't think so because that would probably just be a moving entity
and so, you know, if we wanted to do that, I'll add that as well.
While we're all, since I already have it up moving platforms, the
player can stand on will add that in there.
Just as a thing when we do our Collision sector, as a good test of the
Collision system.
I don't know how much of that I want to actually have in the game, but
I could totally just just show how to do it, right?
Because we should our engine should support it.
Actually
Was the use of calculus involved in your programming.
Actually, the use of calculus happened on the stream.
In fact, if you would like to see calculus used in programming, you
can actually go to the video archive, and you can go back to the day
called equations of motion, and you can actually see us do a bunch of
calculus on there, and I'm not very good at calculus, so it's not
going to be very good calculus, but here it is day 43.
The
Of motion that is calculus going on right there.
I believe.
For this game.
Will the room geometries need to overlap in order to move between
rooms?
Or can they just a?
But that's what I was wondering too.
They should technically just be able to abut and it'll be fine but it
depends on exactly how we write the wall intersection code to handle
them.
And so it may be that to make our lives easier mathematically
speaking, so that we can be sloppier in that code.
We may just want them to be slightly overlapping, right?
And so
I don't know the answer to your question yet.
We shall see.
Can you illustrate how they do the level editors World layouts in
modern engines?
Now
Um not really because honestly the very latest ones I have no
experience with.
So like for example
in, you know, in like how does frostbite currently do their level at
out or Snowdrop or whatever it's called?
I don't really know and those are the two most recent engines, right?
Frostbite 3 or something like this snowdrops, very recent as well.
Unreal and unity are obviously pretty.
At this point and presumably have a lot of legacy and how they Define
things.
So I don't know how those guys necessarily do it.
I can't tell you that in the witness.
It's essentially a, a geometry instancing, kind of a thing where
people make meshes in Maya, or, you know, a 3D 3D package.
Basically.
And then we, we basically have a world editing tool where you bringing
those messages in and you place them to construct the world
All right, so there is no notion of solid space.
There is no notion of constructive, knowledge is just polygon soups
that gets slammed together and then the way that you determine, where
you can walk is by having essentially meshes that are marked as
walkable.
And those are things you're allowed to move along.
That's, that's how it's done.
But I don't know how similar that is to some of the newer engines out
there because I haven't that work with them directly.
Are you going to use files to store levels if so, will they be custom
format?
We probably will sort of end up storing levels.
But if we when you save the game,
And yes it's all obviously custom format because we're not using a
library.
So I guess.
You mean we we starting like XML like no we want something to be fast.
Will the combat algorithm in a 2-D game?
Differ from a 3D game.
Well, it depends on what you mean by combat algorithm, you have to be
more specific about what you're talking about.
Some of it might be the same.
Some of it might be very different depending on what part of what
algorithm and what combat mean to you.
In this case,
Let's see how can I work with other programmers?
When our coding Styles Clash?
Well, I don't know.
I mean what do you mean by your coding Styles Clash?
Are you talking about like they want everything to be super
object-oriented and you want everything to be Super C style or
something like this.
If that's the case I would say yeah it's probably going to be pretty
rough.
You'd probably try to divide things so that
You carve off very specific separate chunks of the code and don't
really work on the parts of the other person's working on.
If you just talking about like, they don't like having lines be more
than 80 characters and I do or something.
Then just like, you know, everyone just get over it right?
Just deal with it.
It's not that big of a deal because it doesn't really affect things.
So, depends what you mean by coding Styles?
It can be a big problem or it can be not that big of a problem.
Should there be walls around stairwells now or will we still just used
to Collision rules from before?
I don't know what we'll do exactly.
But we won't have to add walls around.
Stairwells will just have stairwells be in boxes in such essentially
probably that do a little bit better Collision detection than regular
boxes because to account for the ramp area
Are you going to procedure to build levels or predefined levels their
procedurally built?
The whole game will be procedural for the most part, except for the
art, which is obviously hand drawing.
Will we see stuff like light sources rate racing surface mapping Etc.
At some point in the Stream you have to be more sit about what surface
mapping means.
That's a pretty ambiguous term.
Light source is definitely yes Ray tracing it depends on what you mean
by that.
If you're talking about runtime sparse voxel, octree, tracing or
runtime KD tracing?
No, probably not.
If you're talking about rate, receipt Racing for other reasons,
possibly,
Have we started doing Collision detection and handling?
Yeah, that's how our guy runs into the trees right now.
I don't understand the question.
Yes, we've done a bunch of work on collision detection.
We have not tried to write the final Collision detector yet, but we
have one in there that's running at the moment.
What do you think about storing game data in code?
I think it's fine.
There are some obvious things you have to be aware of if you do it.
Obviously, it can't be paged in very efficiently so you can't store
very much data in code.
Like I wouldn't recommend storing a lot of data in code.
It is harder to deal with edits when the data lives in the code, if
you want to have gooey editing of that data.
You can still do it and I have done it.
What you do is you put the code in its own C file and you have the GUI
editor, rewrite, the C file and it works pretty well, but it also
often end up being more trouble than it's worth.
So it's, you know, it's six of one half dozen of the other.
I don't have strong feelings about it other than I would say no the
advantages and disadvantages before you go that route.
Proton gaming.
So will you continue complaining about Windows while making money
programming with it and visual studio?
Yes, of course.
I'm not sure, I understand the nature of the question per se.
I guess, what I would say is, it's, it's sort of an unfortunate mental
trap that people fall into that, they believe that somehow complaining
about something is, like, problematic and that if you use something
that you shouldn't be complaining about it, but the opposite is
actually true.
Right?
One of the reasons that Windows is getting worse is because the people
who are, you know, in a position
Going to do something about it, aren't complaining about it enough,
right there, not seeing the negatives in the thing that they're doing
and really seeing the negatives and things is what makes someone a
good engineer?
Most of the time seeing the positives is almost useless in
engineering, right?
Like seeing whether the thing you made is really good, doesn't help
you because all that tells you is what you've already accomplished.
But what you've already accomplished is not actionable.
I can't do anything about the stuff that's already done, right?
It's done.
It is what it is.
So, what I need to be able to see is I need to be able to see the
problems.
And there definitely is this sort of there are really like, I guess
they're probably too mentalities.
I think both are very harmful for the Improvement of software.
One is the one you're evincing with the question, which is, you know,
suggesting that maybe the fact that you make money by working on a
platform.
Means, you shouldn't be complaining about it.
Making sense the platform that you are making money on.
Is the one you should be complaining about the loudest because that's
the one that's your livelihood, you should care.
The most about the platform that you're making the money on, and you
should be as upset as you could possibly be about problems with that
platform because that is the risk the real risk to you.
Right.
In some sense.
It's no skin off my back.
If Linux never gets any better, right?
I don't make any money.
Well, I mean, maybe I make a little bit of money off, selling things.
I'm going to
So I guess that rad maybe we sold some Linux licenses, right?
So I didn't maybe maybe I had a little bit of skin in that game at one
point but I have very little skin in that game right now, right?
And so it makes very little sense for me to spend a lot of time
complaining about things that are wrong with Linux and hoping that
people will listen and fix them or to try and Garner momentum around
changing the prevailing attitudes about something that Linux is doing.
It doesn't make sense for me to spend a lot of time doing that.
Because at the end of the day, I yeah, might have lost in that game,
windows iot on us.
Getting that kid, that's where people buy games.
Ames.
And so the thing that I need to complain about the loudest and what
everyone should complain about the last is the things that Windows is
doing very poorly and it's increasingly doing more and more things
poorly, right?
And so this notion that somehow you should be quiet about it because
you are using it.
It doesn't really make any sense.
And you know, I don't want to
Dismiss of your question but honestly yeah it's sort of the attitude
behind the question is is not only I think wrongheaded but also
somewhat harmful in terms of, you know, if you want to get quality
software at the end of the day, right?
And so that the other one that I see happen, a lot which is, which is
problematic
Is this sort of notion that like, if you're going to complain about
something, you should be doing something to fix it and that makes
doesn't make any sense either.
Right?
If someone is literally sitting around, not writing any code ever.
I totally understand, right?
It's like if you're just sitting around all day and you don't write
any code, you're browsing Facebook and you're doing whatever, right?
Then yes, if you go and say get sucks and someone says, well why don't
you go fix it?
Totally makes sense, right?
Makes perfect sense.
You're not doing anything right now.
Nobody needs to go read the buzzfeed's, the top 10 cutest cats or
whatever.
And that's what you were going to do.
So why don't you go take a look at how to see if you can.
I mean, not get up, get and see if you can fix it right?
Makes perfect sense.
On the other hand, if you're already someone who's working on a lot of
code trying to make better software trying,
Do useful stuff.
And you complain about something.
It doesn't make any sense to tell that person.
Why don't they go fix it?
It's like, it can't be that person's job to fix everything, right?
They can't be expected to go fix everything.
Somebody is working on get and those people should pay attention to
the complaints that people have about.
Get not tell them that they shouldn't be complaining about it, right?
Complaints are valuable.
They are the most valuable thing that you have in software.
They
Tell you what's broken and the concept that you would want people not
to voice those concerns, simply because they don't have time to go fix
whatever the thing is, they're complaining about makes no sense.
That works for nobody.
All that does, is it lets a bunch of people go around feeling better
about themselves.
And if we all want to have a little kindergarten where we Pat
ourselves on the back and we feel real good about yourself the other
day, good job Windows, you did great with 8.1 if that's the world you
want to live in, I understand.
Okay right?
I understand why we would want to stop complaining.
If the world you actually want to see is one where the software isn't
awful, then the complaints are in some sense.
The price we have to pay is feeling a little bit bad about what we did
because it was lousy, that's important, right.
We have to do that that feeling that we didn't do a good job.
It's important to make us do a better job next time and it happens
even in the small like on handmade hero.
I don't want to sit around telling myself.
I did a good job on this Collision Vector.
This isn't a good Collision of sector.
We have a
Out of work to do on this.
And we should feel that way, right?
And until we get it toward, we can't see any more serious defects.
We shouldn't be stopping working on it, and we shouldn't be
We shouldn't be feeling like we did some kind of great job, right?
That's not the way things work in my opinion.
So with that, I think that's probably a good thing to end the topic on
if that makes sense.
So yeah,
I'll see if there's any last-minute ones.
Let's see.
Think there doesn't seem to be any one thing left.
Can even name the stream to KC's little kindergarten.
No, because I'm not going to tell everyone that it was a great job and
we should feel great about ourselves so it probably wouldn't be good
to call it Casey's little kindergarten, but there could be a stream
where that's the case.
But yeah.
So let's say
One day, you said you lost.
Hope in Microsoft but now you can play in so they can fix it.
Well, no, that's not exactly what I said, but, yes, that's true.
I don't have any hope in Microsoft.
I don't think they're actually going to be able to fix.
I don't think they're listening is basically what I think, right?
But that doesn't mean I'm not still going to try, right?
Like that doesn't mean that I'm not going to say here's all the stuff
that's broken.
Case you want to know, right?
If anyone ever does start to listen, then they could fix it, right.
But do I have hope that they're going to know?
But I don't have hope in a lot of things like there's a lot of things
I don't have hope for but I still you know I'm not going to not still
do the thing right do?
Do I have hope that the world won't run out of water?
Do I have you know hope that we're going to have a sensible solution
to our world's energy things?
No.
But I still recycle and I still walk to work.
I still do the right thing, even though I'm not optimistic that it's
going to have.
Happy ending, right?
So I realized your kind of trolling and that's fine.
You know, people people kind of have certain things but but your
question actually does have a real answer, right?
And so for people who are actually interested in the answer and not
the trolling, it is true that just because you don't think that
something will work out, doesn't necessarily mean that you should stop
taking the positive action, whatever that thing is, right.
And so, if you've just said, you know what this suffer is
Not going to its, you know, I've lost faith in this company.
I don't think that they're ever going to be delivering something that
we can use.
That doesn't mean you shouldn't keep pointing it out but doesn't mean
that you shouldn't be there.
Going look.
This stuff is still broken just so everyone knows it is broken because
you never do know, right?
It could turn around.
And the sad fact of the matter is, we are stuck with the operating
systems.
We are stuck with, you know, it's Linux Windows and Mac right now, and
there's not a lot of
There's not a lot on the horizon that's other than those things.
And maybe the market share of those things will vary whatever.
But that's what we're stuck with right now.
And so barring, some fairly big changes in the market going forwards.
We kind of have to still keep taking whatever, positive action we can.
Because at the end of the day,
we don't have a lot of options.
Am I hopeful for the future?
No, I mean, to become the house with, you know, I'm not hopeful.
That Microsoft will ever ship a good operating system.
Again, I literally have almost no hope that they will do that.
I have a desire for them to do that.
I want them to do that.
I want them to turn back into the company, they were in 1990, but you
know, do I think is going to happen now.
I think there's almost no chance, but I'll keep on saying it and you
never know, maybe,
Someday, they will hard say.
Was getting example, or do you feel?
There are problems with it, curious to hear?
No, it was just an example.
I, I don't use get, so I don't have any strong opinions like,
basically sorts of control, I use my own.
I'm sure I would have some issues with philosophically.
How get things does things maybe but I don't know.
I think maybe I'm sure did is probably good for what it does.
A lot of people use it seem to like it so it must have a certain
philosophy that works well for them, from what I've seen of it.
It doesn't seem to be the way I would do things, but that's not really
something I necessarily complain about because typically the things
that bother me are when something isn't working properly or isn't made
well, right?
I don't tend to complain when something isn't the thing that I want it
to be right?
Like I'm not going to go complain that a you know, certain paint.
M doesn't allow me to do you know, natural media painting if that's
not what that paint program does right like guess it's you know,
different products and different spaces and so, yeah.
So I don't have any problem with get, I don't use it.
I don't know.
It could be great.
It could be awful.
I have no idea.
I kind of randomly set it because I was kind of in my head that
everyone always says switch to get.
They say it to John, blow all the time.
When he talks about source, code control things switch to get, is that
common thing that people say,
And so, I think I just said it because of the switch to get thing, but
the switch to get thing is not really has nothing to do with this.
That's it.
So, yeah, I have no complaints with get, I don't even use it.
I don't know if it's good or bad and so yeah, what can I say?
so,
So I think that's about it.
I'm going to I'm going to call it there, doesn't look like there's, we
didn't have too many on-topic questions today anyway so I don't think
we like missed anything there.
So I'm going to go ahead and wrap things up.
We will close it down.
And here we go.
Okay.
So, thank you everyone for joining for another game for another game.
That's good for another episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always.
And yet we had pretty off-topic questions tonight, that's just how it
goes sometimes.
I guess, what do you do if you don't have on-topic questions, you
answer, off-topic ones but I'm pretty happy with the actual
programming we did because basically, you know, we didn't have a whole
lot of time to do code.
But we did sort of work through what I think is a reasonable solution
in terms of how we're going to handle our move.
Moving in terms of our definition of where like the ground is and
stuff like that and so I'm pretty optimistic that that'll let things.
Get cleaned up a little bit in the cliff Schecter, let the notion of
ground work a little bit better.
And you know I like when we make that kind of forward progress, so I'm
pretty happy with that and hopefully you'll be interested in coming
back tomorrow.
It'll be a morning swim tomorrow.
9 a.m.
I believe is on the schedule.
And so that will be when will actually go through and Implement that
in box, checking in the Collision Vector, which will allow us to kind
of get that sort of ground testing that we wanted to have happen on
the actual Collision stuff.
So right now all we're doing is we're adding those entities but we
haven't actually done the work.
Text check against them so that is what we'll be doing tomorrow.
I hope you'll join me for that.
If you want to follow along at home, you can always pre-order the game
on handmade hero dot org.
And
That gives you access to the source code so you can download it and
you can follow along with everything we do which is kind of a fun way
to learn from the stream.
If you're interested in that.
We also have a patreon page and subscribe to.
If you're interested in supporting the series, we have a news and
Forum site where you can ask questions and you can access resources
that people have from.
You need to put together like ports to Linux and mac and episode
guide.
That's pretty awesome.
We also have a tweetbot newly updated to say whether it's pacific
daylight time or Civic Standard Time
So it's even Daylight Savings Time aware now.
We don't know how long that'll last.
It's kind of a, you know, it was kind of a very quick project I hack
together.
I don't claim it to be particularly.
Well, engineered, let's be honest with that.
But anyway, if you do want to check out that tweetbot, it tweets the
schedule you.
So if you want to follow along with a series that's a good way to make
sure you always know when it is.
In addition to kind of like, you know, you can subscribe on Twitch but
that tells me tells you when I go live.
It doesn't necessarily tell you when I'm going to go live right in the
future.
So that's pretty handy.
So I hope you'll check those out, and I hope you'll join me tomorrow
at 9 a.m., but either way, have a wonderful Friday and I will see you
guys on the next ring.