Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
This is the second day of sorting, because yesterday, we went ahead
and implemented sorting in the renderer, because it's something that
we've needed to do ever since the beginning, really.
But it just was never the right time, and it finally was the right
time, for whatever reason, just got the whim, the urge to put sorting
in.
And so, we did that yesterday, but we did it with an extremely simple
sort one.
Has a few problems with its runtime potentially, although it's hard to
say definitively.
So we'll kind of talk about that a little bit more later on.
But we did a very simple sort yesterday and we talked about the fact
that what we really need to do in order to use any sort, even our
simple one is, we need to have a thing called a sort key.
And the sort key is the thing that allows us to know what elements go
in front of what other elements when we are rendering.
And we did that but we didn't really think too hard about it.
We just basically putting a stand in one so that we could work on the
sort.
And we got the start working, just fine.
But now it's time for us to take a closer look at that sort key and
actually make something that's going to work a little bit better for
what we actually want to do or that's going to give us the features
that we need.
However you want to look at it.
So, let's let's talk for a second about what's going on with this sort
key.
This makes sense.
So essentially what we've got is we have a problem of needing to sort
our objects in two different ways really here on Day 2, 30.
So, let's talk about the sort key for rendering.
So thus our key for rendering needs to do two things for us.
First of all, it needs to be able to do our sort of our fake, you
know, our fake sort of Staggering of things as they get closer to the
camera.
So as we have these sorts of things where we got trees here and trees
here, you know, and we've got our little dude who's walking around,
obviously, we want this to draw so that this draws first, this dress,
s this draws third, right?
So, you know, it's one, two,
In our current skin because we want to draw back to front at the
moment, if we wanted to draw front to back which, you know, we might
switch the render to do something like that later, who knows we would
need the opposite order, but either way we want this order and then
it's just a question of whether we Traverse it this way or that way,
but this is the order that it's always going to go in.
Okay?
So we need to do that and that's a simple matter of looking at the
screen, space y, right?
That's the screen space y-coordinate essentially as it goes up and
down but things are not quite so
so simple, because what we don't really know is if
Was actually some elevation change involved as well in the placement
of these entities, because we might want to do things like, have
multiple stacks of things.
So, for example, you know, we've got house or something and there's
the upper level of the house and then there's the lower level of the
house, right?
And if perchance you can see through like a hole in the floor, or
something like that, or a stairwell, if you can see down to the lower
region, obviously, all of the
Is that are down here.
Need to sort of the things, I'm sorry need to sort like further back,
they need to be drawn earlier than the things that are up here no
matter where the thing is.
So even if its y-coordinate, like let's say it was here and there's
another thing that's here.
So this this thing is, or I should say here.
So this thing on the floor, like this thing here, there's a box on the
top floor and then here there's another box on the bottom floor.
This things
I mean, why would obviously be closer, right?
It's going to be further towards the camera.
So we draw this thing.
Last normally, if we were going to all these two, we draw this one
first and this one second, right?
But that's not really correct.
Because we know that this thing is actually always going to be on top
because it's on this higher plane.
It's on this thing that's stacked on top and that's always going to be
closer to the camera and that was that becomes a problem.
As this thing is closer to this thing as it gets down to here, we're
going to have it so that they would occur.
Glued in properly.
So we have to take Z into account as well as why we can't just use one
or the other.
And you can actually see this happen even on a single plane.
And this is the problem that we were having with the ground chunks,
which is that if you take a look at the ground chunks, you know, a
ground chunk might be some patch like, you know, like a little square
on the ground like this.
And then there might be somebody who's standing on that, right?
So if we have like a thing that's here, like that's on top of that
ground patch, all these
We know that we would always draw this ground patch first because
actually all the ground gets drawn before.
Anything else gets drawn the ground, never occludes, somebody who's
standing on it.
It doesn't even matter if they were all the way back here.
It's still would never really be in front of this guy, right?
They don't overlap so it doesn't matter but even if we were to
consider that case, logically like it extended all the way back here
we still render the ground last underneath.
So we drench the ground first, then we'd run to the guy on
Top of it, right?
So that's a problem because normally, if all we were to use was the Z
and these guys are both have the same Z and then the, why the ground
patches will come out on top.
And so as you can see again, there is really what we need is.
We need a more sophisticated concept of that.
Sort key for our two and a half D stuff and really I think what we
probably want to do is treat Z as something a little bit more magical
than
I've been treating it so far.
I think what we probably need to do is make Z be purely semantic and
not be an actual continuous value.
And the reason that I say that is because no amount of of fussing with
the actual sort orders of these things is going to make it.
Do the right thing in all cases, other than simply saying ground
chunks always render before anything that standing on the ground,
right?
I mean, that's just
That's just how it is.
So what we need to do is we need to consider that a little more
carefully, right?
And one thing that we could do for example is we could call all of
these things.
We could call these at some Z like let's say this is equal 0 and then
we could call things that are standing on the ground at Z equals 1 and
then we could call anything that's flying at Z equals 2 or something
like that.
Although I guess.
No we don't really want to do that.
That's these are still even if it's flying as long as it's still in
the same plane it should still be at Z equals 1 and then anything I
guess that's up kind of that's that's on top of these things.
Is that Z equals to on that floor and then
This whole process would like repeat again.
So then we'd have Z equals 3 would be if there's a floor above this,
that's their Z equals 4 would be something that's standing on it and
so on.
So we just have our Stacks, have this Z to tell us how they stack up,
right?
And similarly, we'd have here, you know, this would be negative 1 or
negative 2 or whatever.
So we'd have a semantic Z value, that set very specifically, and
doesn't really have anything to do with any continuous value that
we're tracking, whether it's physics.
Or anything else.
It doesn't matter at all.
And the interesting thing about this is I also feel like this is
really what we kind of want to be going towards in general for our
system because we played around with doing things in full 3d.
And what I think we found over and over again because we've run into
this many times is that it just doesn't work that well to treat things
as full 3d inside a game that is inherently not full 3d.
And so I feel like at some point we need to do a appropriate amount of
back off where we say, okay, we're not really.
Using a real Z coordinate, you know, we've got something else which is
like X Y on the ground and then Z that's off the ground but it's still
just like how you're hovering or something.
Right.
And then we actually have like what your plane is or something right?
Which is this thing over here, you know what I mean?
And this is what we track this never is involved in any kind of
perspective, right?
And you know so if something is floating up and above something else
and going up and down
No, it never goes in and out of whenever it does any perspective?
Foreshortening it just hovers there, right?
But then this does so anything.
That's using that plane value, right?
That
In value does create the perspective foreshortening so that if we have
a level above, you know, we want to do something like that that works.
Now, the reason that we were trying to avoid doing something like this
was, because we wanted to try doing some things where we had
continuous motion up and down a stairwell, right?
And we actually implemented that, right?
You can you can actually see that happening here if I
Go into.
The code here and turn off the ground chunk thing that we were working
on there.
Let's see.
Where was that?
My brain still always wants to look for handmade World mode stuffy and
handmade dot CPP because that's where it used to be.
Yeah.
Anyway, ground chunk.
So let's see here right there.
So in this, right?
If I am to take these out for a minute,
Let's see here.
Run that
There we go.
So, if we are to look at this, right?
You can see that we actually implemented.
Continuous motion between the two levels just fine, right?
And now that we have sorting it, even all works correctly as well.
Like you can see that the top room sorts on top of the bottom room and
all that other kinds of fanciness.
So that's all fine.
But, you know, the problem with doing that is that when we introduced
this concept that we can smoothly transition
In the two levels, we introduce just a whole other series of headaches
which is that what happens to the guy when he's standing like just
right in between there?
You know we don't necessarily have a real concrete idea of what's
supposed to happen and so I don't know whether we want to actually
handle that or not.
On the plus side we can handle literally just you doing it right?
We can special case you doing it because that's not that hard.
The problem would be if we allowed everything else to work as well,
like Monsters being able to like fly up and down the stairwells and
stuff like that.
I just don't know about that because if we allow all of that stuff to
happen then we really do need to remain basically entirely in 3D all
the time and it becomes very difficult for the renderer to figure out
what to do.
Because it doesn't
Actually have 3D models for anything so it's constantly got to make
these decisions without actually the information that it needs, right?
So I don't really know what we should do about that.
I don't, but I'm just kind of pointing out at this point.
How it feels like we need to do something about that situation.
Probably, we're getting to the point since we're running out of like
Engine, speculatively things to do, we kind of had to start
implementing specific game.
Things to move forwards, we need to figure out some way that we're
going to marry those two and I don't really know exactly what it is.
But with something like the sort key, we can kind of see where this is
already important.
Because you know, we've got this sort of nasty situation where we sort
of have all these things that need to
Need to work within this framework so I don't know.
I don't really know how we would deal with that.
I guess one thing we could do to support this and maybe this just
works is if you have a ground position that is full 3d, we just snap
you to the closest one for your sort key.
That may just work.
I don't know if it does or if it doesn't, but it might, it seems like
it could.
And to be honest, snapping probably isn't going to work.
What we would probably have to do is we'd probably want to do
something like a ceiling, a slightly biased ceiling because like, for
example, when you start walking up the stairwell, the instant you get
a little bit of this up to stairwell.
You need to start a cluding things that are
On the one, a front of you.
Mmm.
Yeah, I don't know.
Like, I just want to make sure everyone understands.
It's like, I hope it doesn't sound like, I'm just throwing over
nothing, but this really is just a really nasty problem when you have
to deal with with sudo stuff.
And I guess there's other ways.
We might be able to deal with it to.
We could do sort of a zebra free thing with it I guess.
I don't know.
I don't know that we want to get into that but I'll talk about that in
a second.
Alright so here is the the
That I'm thinking of in my head.
So let's suppose that we took the case of the stairwell.
And so, here's the top floor, right?
And here is the stairwell going down
Then we got the bottom floor.
So as this person is coming this way, obviously this part should
always be occluding him, right?
The top floor should be including him as he moves this way until he
moves into here at least, right?
So anytime you hear he's got to be included.
But then as he starts walking up here, when is ground point, is like
there when you standing roughly on that, his head is definitely going
to come up above.
It's going to like poke up, right?
And now it is occluding things that are on that plane.
So there's no single rule that says exactly what has to happen.
But I think something like as soon as I'm standing on the stairwell,
I'm going to occlude anything on the I'm technically like on the next
level, right?
Because as soon as I'm standing here,
I think you want to start processing in that way.
I suspect that works.
I don't really know.
And so the other thing that I was going to say, is another thing that
you could do in theory is if you use a z-buffer for rendering, I know
there's people who try tricks of like, making everything actually
looks slanted from the side.
So you know, you look at on and it's and here is your guy and he's a,
you know, he's a little sprite card like this, you know, and there he
is.
And we render them, right?
And this is obviously
SLI all transparent.
So you don't see it but when you look from the side, it's actually
slanted like this.
And the reason that that helps out is because it makes it so that the
guy gets higher and further back as he goes which makes it a little
bit easier for it to to sort situations like this where part of him
should be above stuff but maybe part of him should be below stuff.
It's again, it's kind of a weird trick that they use for like two and
a half D sorts of games.
It's something.
But I don't think something we really want to get into.
So yeah, so I feel like we could do something like that.
Not this something where we just say like okay we could still preserve
some continuous motion there and maybe we're tracking the motion, but
as soon as we go to render, we immediately snap that to whatever that
sorting plane is, that gets snapped in some kind of a, like,
discretized way so that the planes of Z are actually known in some
very specific fashion.
I don't know that just seems like something that we probably want to
be able to do.
I don't know.
And again the same
True for the for the ground chunks.
Those would want to be, you know, specifically set to occur in a very
specific plane which is like the underlying ground plane.
Not the things that are standing up on their, on their end, right?
And similarly, like this thing,
This this solution that I was sort of alluding to here where you have
kind of things that stand up like that, the ground chunks would be
lying down flat, right?
And so, this would include the ground chunk properly, even though
they're at the same Z, because one is standing upright and one is
lying down.
That's all anyway.
Ignoring that.
For now, we need to start moving towards something where we can get
the that sorting stuff work properly.
And as you can sort of see when we're doing a rendering, we kind of
would need to know even if we were going to do a system like the
Tilted card thing.
But certainly also if we're going to use sort keys that do some kind
of magical stuff there, where they've got more information them, we
need to know for anything we're drawing which type of thing.
It is and we sort of talked about this before.
What did I do?
I don't know what you're
Happened.
I have no idea what just happened.
We ran out of size for our push buffer.
How is that possible?
What did we do?
That's right.
Interesting.
Let's take a look.
Push bitmap.
Debug Tech Stop.
Hmm, what were we displaying?
That's kind of interesting, right?
Inside our debug and frame end text out thing.
That just displays it, we ran out of room in the push buffer for a bit
Maps which is kind of odd.
I'm not really sure how we have that many fonts.
Let's take a look.
I'm interested to see what this says.
Let's see.
Sword entry at push before element.
Count.
97.
How big are those tiles?
Sword entries, and how big is the max put Versailles?
How what?
What, what are we what?
How is that possible?
That's we must be initializing this value totally wrong.
Look at that.
There's no way that could possibly be true.
I know what their problem is.
We never actually clear that.
Do we
Can allocate render group?
If I could go the right file.
We never actually reset this stuff, which, which actually brings up a
good point, which is we should probably keep track of all the stuff
that needs to get reset essentially.
Yes.
Oh, like, because when we do, when we render all our stuff and we do
an end render, doesn't that we reset the push buffer but we're not
resetting the tiled entries.
So did you guys see what was happening there?
Basically, like our sort just kept getting bigger and bigger and
bigger, and bigger and bigger.
And bigger and bigger forever which is kind of hilarious.
That would also explain why our frame time was slower potentially
Yeah, hold on a second.
Let's take a look here.
I want to show you guys what I mean.
So here's our push buffer element count, right?
And, you know, in allocate render group, we were setting it here and
we were also setting sort entry at
These things go together, right?
Meaning this stuff all has to get set this way.
You'll have to be kind of initialized this way every time, but I
believe when in N render, yeah, as you can see, an end render.
We actually reset this stuff, but we didn't actually reset the other
value.
And so I feel like we want to do something where that's just like to
avoid that kind of situation because we could accidentally forget that
again.
I think we want to do like an initialized push buffer value or render
values or something.
We're like clear render values, something like that.
I feel like we want to do something like that because otherwise we
could make that that's a mistake like many times, right?
So what I'd like to do is gather up all of these and and maybe see I
don't know if there's other ones of these that we would want to treat
that way, I suspect.
We might just want to do them all because I can't really think of a
reason why we wouldn't.
So like, you know, probably actually, all of these are things that
would make sense.
Yeah.
Even the missing resource count, I would think we would want to reset.
So I think we really want all of this.
I think all of that wants to be there and this stuff obviously is only
done once.
I like so, and we can also do that, right?
And so, all of these guys would come in here and we'd say, you know,
clear render values, right?
Before we go any further and we'd have our render group here.
Brenda group.
And there's the result and there's been to group and hoops.
And yeah, so that would be nice.
And then down in here when we actually do our when we finish up we do
clear render values again just to leave it in a pristine State.
Like, so I think that's a good idea.
It just seems to make it a little bit more, a little less error-prone
than, trying to remember to set it at the two, different places all
the time, right?
I don't see anything else in here that would want to do that.
I don't think we're is render transform.
Does that have surrender?
Transform has a lot of stuff in it so I think I may also want to do
render transform a little bit more completely.
So when here we'd say, like we've got the offset and the scale, all
the rest of that stuff, I guess, I don't.
know, if we want to reset it because the user kind of sets that stuff,
So so maybe we don't, I don't know.
We'll leave it like this for now, but we may decide we want to move
some of those in there a little bit later.
I'll say to do reset more of the transform.
Should it be sticky?
So yeah, so I feel like that was just an obvious thing that we would
want to do because now we just don't have that that bug and hey
Colombian there's your answer from the pre stream.
The reason we were slower is because we kept having more and more
stuff in that buffer, we kept adding things to it, right.
So, I think that probably had something to do with it, although, well,
now I guess is the push buffer count now.
So that wasn't true, never mind.
And I guess we aren't, we are not actually fat back to faster.
For some reason, we were temporarily down at 16.
I don't know.
It's very flickery.
We're going to have to re-enable the profiling to get any more
information about that.
I think it's too hard to tell from here.
Because again that also could just be the debug system stuff that
takes up that extra time.
So yeah, so it's faster when we go up here because it's got less stuff
to render.
Right more stuffs off the screen, but when you're right here and
you're rendering the maximum out of stuff, it's slower.
Anyway, ignoring all that point being I think that's better because
that is a bug.
We could have had for any number of things in the render system and
now they're in one place.
So that we're less likely to make that mistake.
Which is a good thing.
Okay, so back to sorting keys.
So, yeah, we have the capability to create our sort key here, right?
And that's great, and all.
But we also need now some way.
Oops, that's not what I wanted.
I wanted in the basis.
There it is.
Nope, where is the sort key?
It's in the get entity render basis.
That produces it, right?
Yeah, that's what I was looking for.
So our sort key.
We are producing it, but we're not producing it with what we want.
The py I think is, is roughly correct.
Meaning the py part is what we want.
The problem is the pz part is not really what we want and we're going
to need some way of handling that a little bit more delicately and so
I don't know.
Like I said exactly how we want to do that.
I think what we want to do is sort of treat it as something that's
again like kind of a truncated
Or rounded kind of value that allows us to do something a little
Smarter with it but I'm just not sure I'm just not sure exactly what.
So one example would be we do know for example in handmade
And handmade world.
We do have the concept of how high it is, like how high it is to the
next floor, right?
We've got that sort of Chunk demand M sort of situation and the chunk.
Demon m is like, you know, we sort of said that these were blocks and
you know we can introduce the concept certainly that like the floors
are at a certain place and we can figure out like how we would go
ahead and round those that sort of thing.
But my no matter what we do, by the time we get to render entity
basis, pee,
P.
We don't have enough information, really?
Right?
We don't actually know at by the time we get here.
What that, whether this?
Was like something that's like a ground chunk, that has to be rendered
early or something that's standing on the ground.
That would be rendered always later.
And so, since we don't actually know that,
It means that either way we're going to have to get more information
in here.
We have the transform in the original P but we just don't have any
piece of information that says like whether it's standing up or not so
really like that render transform is going to have to have a little
more information in it.
And I think what we need to do there is say like okay that render
transform has something in it, you know we've got the orthographic,
for example we would need something as well which was like, oh is this
thing?
Whatever this thing is, is this thing a upright or not, right?
And the other thing about this is that this is sort of starting, you
can see it kind of breaks down a little bit here.
The render transform has everything in it, but all of this stuff is
pertaining to the camera.
Whereas this stuff is pertaining to the entity, you know what I mean.
So, at some point very soon, I think that should probably be right
after we finish the Sorting.
We probably want to do like move this out to its own thing, right?
Because it's something that we kind of had been having troubles with,
and I think we want to make it.
So it's something that's a little more explicit in the calling code
where it actually creates one of these and passes it when it's going
to.
So, it says, like, here's a transform I'm using or whatever.
So, yeah, so in this render transform, if we had something that was
like is this upright or not, we would know whether to bias the Z.
No one way or the other if that makes sense.
We could do something here with that right away just to see if that
would work.
We could do something and I guess this gives us a good chance to use
our clear render values.
Exactly the way.
I just said we wanted to, which is now here, when we're doing this
transform thing, we could reset the transform upright to always be
true because most things are cards that are upright.
So when we're rendering the floor, we would set that up right to false
and then when we rendered, it would know that that was what was
happening.
And so when we do that, let's see here.
Let's
So when we do that in here, now we have the option of adding to our
sort key.
The concept that something here is going to be like in addition to
that Z value, we're going to have this ability to sort of toggle which
plane you're on, right?
So I can keep kind of doing this in a ridiculous way.
This is not quite correct but I could say here, like for example,
well, whatever the transfer I'm says, if I'm up right, you know then
I'm going to do something where I add, you know,
No.
You could imagine this.
So now anything that's like upright is always going to be one, you
know, biased one up from from this, right?
And I guess what I really want is I want it to be inside here, right?
I want it to be multiplied by the, by the larger value, so something
like that, right?
Of course, you have to spell transform correctly, but something like
that, introduces the bias there.
And then, that way out in world's mode, when I'm doing that,
Quote, unquote bias.
Like here.
So when I'm doing this, now I've got the ability to say that I want
this thing to be flat, and it will should render behind other things,
right?
Okay.
So yeah, so now you can see, we no longer change what the Z value of
that ground is, but because we had bias it backwards to be a flat
thing, it now, sorts properly with everything else, right?
And I can still do this ground sort of sorting stuff here.
I can still do it for upper levels as well.
Now, what this brings up that's kind of interesting now that we have
sorting, we can actually do something that we've wanted to do for a
while and get continuous get
Round chunk thing working where you continuously go between 2 and
we're relieved all hole where the stairwell is, which is probably
something we should do pretty soon actually.
Now that I think about it because that would be kind of fun.
So maybe that's something we do after the Sorting as well right now,
I'm not sure why we do the flashing.
I think it's because we only really handle one level of ground chunks
right now.
And so we'd want to do a thing where we actually did more ground
chunks.
We're different planes.
But yeah, I forgot we never did that because we didn't have sorting.
Now, we've got sorting, we can fully make our 3D stack stuff.
So yeah, we should probably just do it, we should probably just do it.
So anyway, yeah, now we can transition smoothly between the two.
Everything sorting properly are sort key is not as good as I would
like, but like I said, it's something that we kind of have to probably
keep pushing on a little bit, maybe we should go.
How much time do I have?
Probably not much because I had
Go explain the render thing there.
Oh well, no I've got I've got 20 minutes.
So yeah, maybe we should try doing a thing where we like have the
stairwell.
Let's try getting the stairwell thing working a little bit.
So first, let's try to have our ground chunks work continuously and
and I don't know exactly how we were doing that because it's been so
long, but I believe, the problem there is we just we only do ya like,
you can see here where we do our grand buffers, right?
When we do our ground before updating, you can see here, we do like a
Min chunk.
Thing.
And so I'm assuming that when we do that the the camera bound
situation here, where we do the min/max thing.
I don't actually know, well, I don't know, shouldn't that do
something.
What is that going to do for us?
This is a good question.
It seems like it should be doing a few different layers of these.
Well, let's find out, I don't know what the camera Bound in M actually
is, so let's find out.
So it looks like typical floor height minus three and one.
So that should be giving us multiple levels.
So why does it do our ground chunks disappear?
You know, what's the deal with that?
Why are we getting that happening?
And I'm not sure, but I feel like it should be easy enough for us to
figure out because all, we've would really have to do right.
Is there's a time when, when we're moving where we don't see any?
Like here I am on the ground floor and I see it, right?
I start walking and and they disappear entirely right there.
Now there's again, there's a couple things so
Can see our sort key.
One thing that are sort key is not handling and I guess I don't know
why, it's not handling that as we get up, I'm not sure why those
ground chunks.
I suppose this is all related to because the ground doesn't seem to be
moving with the camera properly either, right?
You can see how it's not.
It doesn't get smaller.
And it should.
Like it should be, it should be scaling away from us and it's not.
So that also is a problem.
And why is that happening?
Okay, so that is also, that's also happening because of this
situation.
So that's because we're just not when we do our ground chunk
rendering.
We're not actually giving it an easy, right?
Because here is the transform that controls the Z, and it's not going
to use that.
All right, so we need that week.
Yeah.
This is the same old problem, which is why I say we want to do that.
Sort of we want to probably fix the way this stuff gets handled sooner
rather than later.
But yeah, this offset, really should, you know this whole thing here
where it's doing this Delta, this whole situation.
And I don't even know what is this.
Delta Z greater than or equal to negative 1.
Delta Z less than y was the rendering.
This must have been to restrict it to stuff.
We could before we had sorting.
Because why would we ever restrict it?
Based on the Delta Z have no idea.
So
Think this is all this code is just all from when we didn't have
sorting and really probably shouldn't even be there.
So that's probably part of the problem for starters but then another
part is we're not actually offsetting this.
So this is Delta, this Delta
Not being here.
There really should be nose Delta.
The Delta should be what we actually pass to offset, right?
It should be this.
Right, that's what we should actually be doing.
I believe.
And we don't really need multiple semicolons.
So let's take a look at that.
So yeah, that actually is what we would expect.
Unfortunately, our ground chunk.
Yeah, our ground chunks are now.
The topmost one is rendering in front of everybody, which is what it
should do.
We need that to Alpha Fade Out and I don't really remember how our
Alpha fade was working there.
How were we doing that?
Was that manual in here?
Yeah, it was
Yeah, so that's less good to right.
Because we were doing that man doing here, which means if we want our
ground chunks to work with that, we'd have to do it.
We'd have to do it up there.
Now we could write we can cut and paste this code but we really want
that to be.
Yeah we really want to clean this stuff up now that we're starting to
do this a little bit more for real so we probably want.
Maybe what we'll do is when we get this kind of to a point place where
we're relatively happy with it, we'll go ahead and we'll go ahead and
After the Sorting, we'll go do the sorting and we'll come back here
and actually make this code nice.
Because at this point, when we've got sorting working properly, we,
there's no reason not to.
There's no reason not to do this.
Do this code for real now because we can actually start rendering
stuff, right?
babe top start Z is
Is some constants which should come up here.
There we go.
Oops.
And I guess those will just be set here for now, but we may need to
make those more of a render, a thing at some point.
Let's see if that helps us at all.
So we come up here and yeah.
So now we're actually much more correct.
You can kind of see
They're in much better shape, right?
Everything seems to be rendering properly.
Now,
And so, that's actually great.
I'm pretty happy with that, unfortunately.
Like I said, we now need a way to actually see our stairwells.
I remember where they are sort of, so I can probably get two one.
I hope maybe.
Shouldn't it be here somewhere?
All right, it's on this side.
There it is.
Yeah.
So that all works great actually.
And so really what we need to do now is we just need to actually leave
some, some some viewable space.
We need to be able to see down toward where the stairwell is so that
we can actually use it, you know, because otherwise we'd never
actually see it.
We wouldn't know that it was there.
So, yeah, that would just involve having the ground chunks know where
the stairwells are and not put them in there.
Now, we have another problem at this point to that hopefully is
Parent and this is one of the reasons that I was sort of saying before
that you know, rendering back to front, may be a good idea.
Now we don't really have to care because honestly 3D acceleration
wise.
We're always probably going to be fast enough without doing this but
if we want our software renderer to run fast enough for example,
rendering back to front would be important because what you have to
remember is right now.
We're drawing the entire screen.
Many times for every level of ground chunk.
We're drawing the whole screen again.
Right?
And that's just a ton of work that doesn't need to happen because the
only ground chunks we can see are the ones that are like right on
this, this very level and the only time we can see down to other ones
is when there's some kind of hole in the ground for something like a
stairwell, right?
And so what I'd like to do, you know what I what I would do if you
know if we want to accelerate the software under which you know, like
I said maybe we don't want to do maybe we've got enough software
rendering under our belts that we don't need to spend any more time on
it but if we wanted to make it better, what we would do is make it so
that we render instead starting with the earliest items and going
backwards and as we do that, we remember what chunks?
Rough chunks of the screen are fully occluded
That's what we would do now, unfortunately.
There's a lot of work involved in that so that's why I say, don't know
that it's necessarily worth it to do.
But it's worth noting because like you can see our frame rates not
particularly good at 1080p.
Now granted, we can always choose to run our software renderer in less
than 1080p, right?
So you know, we were running in 1080P because it happened to be so
darn fast that we could but we can always decide to drop down to to
something that's more like what a software renderer might have done in
the old days which we have more than enough power for certainly right?
So we can go ahead and yeah.
Go ahead and run it back.
And you can see, now, we're back up to 16 fish.
I guess hard to say looks like we're that's an oddly consistent top
frame rate, but yeah, I guess we're at 20.
So we're still 30.
We're not 60 though.
But yeah.
That's yeah.
So that's actually totally fine, right?
And that's pretty usable.
So, who knows we could just do that, but it is, obviously, always
tempting to go.
Since I know there's plenty of performance left on the table for our
software, renderer, it's always tempting to kind of go do it because
hey, this is game programming, not game design.
And so it's always tempting to go solve a tech problem since that's
what we do here anyway.
But I'm really satisfied with all that.
And so I think that's actually probably enough to satisfy me actually
that sort Keys, okay?
And works for the purposes that we needed to at least for now.
So, yeah, let me take a look at how much time I have left.
I've got 10 minutes left, probably a little more than two minutes.
What I think I'd like to do is I would like to actually go.
I'm going to put this back to because I don't actually care if the
frame rates low, for the time.
Being what?
I'd like to do is I'd like to go to our handmaids render group here
and I think I'd like to actually pull this thing out
I think I'd like to actually do that.
We have some time, we know we have to do it because it's leading to a
lot of ugly things.
The fact that it's the sticky mode in there, right?
The way that all of our stuff works right now.
Like if we go to where we were just drawing those, we have to like set
stuff and then unset it and it's just kind of ugly.
And that's there's really not much of a reason to do that.
There's no point to it, right?
Because all we would have to do to make it
Cleaner to use is just have a regular transform where we do like,
okay.
There's a, you know, an object transform or something and a camera
transform, right, where we just have two of them.
And then this is here in its own thing.
So this guy attracts others up, right?
And whether where it is offset is and what its scale is right?
And and this guy tracks, you know, whether he's worth the graphic and
what the m 2 pixels is and the focal length and all that.
Stuff.
You know, I would also point out that distance above Target is pretty
dumb.
I do not know why we have it because it's should just be something
that's in everyone's object transform.
Probably like, it's just, it's kind of stupid, but we'll leave it in
there for now.
But it's just it's not necessarily like all it is, is just a value
that gets added to offset P, right?
So it's, yeah.
Anyway,
Dumb, but whatever.
Anyway, I think this might be a more interesting way to go.
And then, inside here, we've got the camera transform, but, but we
don't have an object transform and that'll cause a ton of compile
errors, but they're not going to be ones that are particularly
difficult to fix.
So I would say, let's do it.
Let's go for it.
Why not?
So, the way this would work is we'd have some way of getting like a
default transform or something.
Maybe something, you know, like this object transform.
Default transform.
Something like that, you know?
And then we just say, like, okay, whatever the result is.
We make into this.
Maybe this would be good too.
Or.
That.
Flat, something like that.
Flatten up, right?
And so we would have something that looked like this.
Where you can just get, whatever the default is and then you modify
it, however, you want.
And you just throw it away when you're done with it so that you don't
really have to do anything fussy.
Right.
We don't need to realize that because already initialized for the flat
transforms, we don't have initialize that.
So we'd really just be talking about this is all we would actually be
doing those would be our default transforms and now everywhere, we use
this stuff.
Oops, it's no good.
You turn everywhere.
We
This stuff we can to make that happen.
So okay these guys are all camera.
Transforms obviously.
Like so.
Those are not actually a transform.
So, so the camera transforms in here.
When we do entity basis P, that's going to need both transforms and I
don't know why we pass an address here.
I don't know if we had a reason for that, but I'm not going to do that
anymore.
I'm just going to pass these by value object transform.
Like so, so doesn't have to worry about whether they point to the same
thing or aliasing or any that stuff, it just knows, it doesn't have
to.
And so, then we'd have the object transform as their, the camera
transform is it's getting this information?
Yeah, camera transform.
So, that's all good.
This is the camera transform.
Again, it's looking at the orthographic bit, and this is the camera
transform as well with that.
This is above Target.
We then have the object.
Transform coming in here, at some point.
Or is it only with the Ossipee of the scale?
There should be in here somewhere, right?
We never use the scale.
At all.
Okay.
that's,
Probably.
Okay.
I'm guessing that that's used elsewhere.
Do we really just never use it anywhere?
Was that just like oh we could use it so we stuck it in there and
we've never used it.
Well, alright, we don't use it, we don't use it.
We can always get rid of it or actually go in and put in the multiply
here at some point because that probably would be good thing to have.
I mean scaling who doesn't like the scale stuff?
Everyone likes to scale stuff.
All right, so let's see anything else here.
Ah, there it is.
There is a result scale in there.
Oh nope.
That's just computed.
No, so no, we don't, we don't touch it, we just straight up, don't
touch it.
Who knew?
Learn something new every day about your own code, which you wrote.
All right, so in here when we do this, now we have two sources so we
always need to have a way of getting whatever the object
Transformations.
So I'm just going to say that that gets passed.
So in here we've got the object transform like so and we just pass it
on through.
Now every time these people get called, that means that every time we
do one of these that gets passed.
Now, I don't know if we still want offset to be passed or not, how we
want to do that.
Exactly, because we can, we can now make that be a little bit
different than what it was before, but I'm going to leave it the way
it is just for the time being
And just add literally the new part to it.
So here's object transform and that will now get past here.
Here is object transform again.
And that would get past here.
Let's see everyone who calls push bitmap has to think about this, a
little harder here.
So now this is object transform.
And that would get passed in there.
And just takes an object transform as well.
And that way.
Past here.
and,
Again this is really just totally wrote.
I'm just making this be something that flows down the pipe.
Instead of something that gets set globally on the render group.
So, let's see, we've got a render transform.
For on Project is actually camera, transform.
And I'm going to go ahead and make that not be a pointer anymore.
Hi there.
Okay.
Initializing.
Yeah.
That's not an address anymore.
And what else we got?
Transform offset p z, transform focal length.
So offset pz.
So in this case, the offset pz we need to know what that was.
So we need the object transform to be passed here.
Yeah, same here.
And what else we got?
I'm project-- old, transform, focal length.
That's just the camera transform.
Get camera rectangle.
That's the camera transform.
Again.
All right, and so now these guys like for draw hip points and stuff,
so what we need to do here for the render group that we're doing,
these guys need to know when you're doing stuff like drawing hit
points and that sort of stuff.
These guys need to know what the object transform is now.
And they would just be passed through as as with everyone else.
What's where are we here?
These are for chunks, right?
Let's see, push bitmap.
So these guys are not really doing much.
These guys don't actually touch the renderer transform, right?
They don't actually do anything and so they can just use and this
shows the first way that we would actually use this.
This would just be like default flat transform meaning.
I don't actually want
I don't actually want to transform these guys at all.
They're not actually being they're not using anything other than this
offset.
So I'm just going to go ahead and let them take no transform.
Like so, so that they will not actually modify the location at all.
Since that's what would have been happening.
Then, in here, we've got so again,
This is object transform.
Default flat transform.
so in here now we can do what we actually wanted and not have to do
that sort of craziness and say okay, you know, the object transform
Is just whatever the default is, and then I'm going to get that offset
p.
Right?
And then all this crap goes away.
Now we still have the alpha, which we don't really know what we're
going to do with the alpha.
Because that's a separate thing and like I said we don't we don't
really know what we're doing with that yet.
So we won't try to tackle that for now, but we kind of got
I think I've still got like five minutes left or something.
So I'm going to keep going since we're right in the middle of this and
got quite a few guys to go.
So I want to finish this up.
So again, okay so foreground chunk rendering now we just go.
Okay, we've got the transform their past, the transform in and that's
good.
We've got pushed wrecked outline, which can use the exact same
transform so that a lineup
And then out here, this would have been using no transform at all.
So we could actually just right here, do like default flat transform.
It's just call it right in place.
We don't even really need to do anything else because it'll just go
struck the 0 value for us.
If we want to hear when we're doing this render group offset P.
This is a perfect example.
Now, this Global in this kind of goes away, we can just do object,
transform entity transform and actually do default, upright transform.
And then we just set its offset p and now there's no
Leftover icky State nonsense.
And then everyone just passes this one when, as they're doing their
push bitmap calls, right?
Super straightforward.
Here we go.
And so, this is a really basic code transformation, right?
All I'm doing is I'm taking Global variable and I'm making us a thing
that gets passed as a parameter.
That's it.
But in doing, so I get rid of that weird, like state that sits around
and in that way, you can have multiple ones in Flight, any given time,
and there's no weird confusion.
Oops,
Cuz there.
So yeah, I don't know where the particles go.
We're not really I don't even think we kept the particles working.
So I'm just going to go ahead and stick that stuff in here for now
that goes there respect outline.
Okay so for this one project render group Mouse P, this will also be,
I believe I'm projecting The Entity transform, right?
Because this is trying to in be in that
At space.
And since the Transformer hasn't been modified here,
That would still be the end of you transform as well.
Push Vector, outline is this is for the mouse P.
So this is with orthographic.
So this is just a default flat transform rights.
Not going to try to, it's not transferring that at all.
And so then, where are we?
This is just our, this is our our cutscene code.
And so this would be a default flat transform as well, right?
I've been transformed.
Transform equals default, but transform.
And then here, anytime we would have touched the transform, we would
just get rid of the render group part, and we just use our own local
one.
So again, just nice getting rid of like stuff that was sort of being
in this weird Global State and who knows what was happening to it.
Just feels better and safer to me to always pass it through, so
there's none of that weirdness.
All right, so none of the to overloads for the argument type.
That's true on push bitmap.
What is the transform situation here?
I don't actually know it's not used at all, so that's again, we're
just be a get default.
Flat transformed.
There's nothing.
Right.
Get bitmap Dimensions.
So that also does need to take it, I guess.
Draw a profile in.
Yep, this is just a default flat Transformers.
Well, no transform.
In fact, these guys probably just want to have a no transform of at
the top.
Transform, transform to fall flat.
Transform.
and,
Put it in there.
Okay.
Yeah, probably still just want no transform because these guys just
don't get these guys just aren't using transforms.
Good, good.
Probably should just make that some kind of constant.
There we go.
And last but not least.
Okay, and so now hopefully everything's exactly the same.
Like all we did was just remove something that
a little worried about, but
it looks like the mouse is still working properly.
And all this stuff is working properly.
Doesn't look like our picking is working.
So hot.
Oh wait, no.
That is how it used to work because we don't sort the entities so that
actually is fine.
Yeah.
Good, good.
All right, so I'll go ahead and end it there.
I'm glad we did that because that had been bugging me for a while.
So let's go ahead and go
two.
the Q and the, a
If I can.
I'll try.
Abner coimbra a brace yourself.
For what?
That doesn't that sounds ominous Abner.
What is your preferred sorting method?
I don't have a preferred sorting method.
I'm not, I I don't really find that sorting is something.
I spend a lot of time working on so typically like, like honestly, you
know, we could ship this game with bubble sort.
Honestly, honestly, we probably could.
So like there are plenty of times.
There are plenty of problems in the world.
We're sorting is really important and it becomes something you really
want to know how to do correctly.
I almost never face those problems and so I don't really have a
favorite sorting method.
I find that.
I just don't spend that much time on sorting tomorrow.
We'll go over a couple different sorting methods and I'll talk about
them but I'm not going to like pick one and say you should use this or
something.
I'm just going to be like here's sorting every single one of these.
Would work for our purposes.
We just won't have a million entities on the screen that need to get
sorted.
Like that's not going to happen.
So you know you're not trying to figure out how to like do the
ultimate sorting thing.
and I think part of the reason for that is in games, you have such a
tight time budget that usually
Ends up happening, is if you really need a huge number of things
sorted, you can't afford to sort them every frame.
Anyway, you've got to keep them roughly sorted and only deal with the
Deltas.
So, you end up using something more like a binary tree that keeps
things sorted all the time.
If you're actually talking about getting to enough elements where you
start to care, but who knows that maybe just because the stuff that
I've worked on in games doesn't happen to use it and you know, maybe
someone out there it's got a
Better example of where they use it in the game.
Hi Kasey.
I'm currently working on an opengl framework for games.
Wanted to ask, whether I can use the code up to De 23 with the intent
of making a commercial game.
Eventually with it might be important to note that I'm also streaming.
So the code might be visible sometimes when I stream framework
development, yeah, if you want to use, if you want to use up through
day 23, that's totally fine.
Gimpy.
CPU, I know you said you really like discriminated unions.
But how do you deal with managing the big case?
Which they may cause that is usually handled by the up model by
delegating to the object.
Well so I guess I would say
I guess I would say.
It's six of one half dozen of the other, right?
There's to me there's no difference between like you know, let me let
me take some place where we have a switch statement.
So let's take like here.
So here is an example like of a switch statement, right?
And and here I'm going to go down to the bottom of this.
And I'm just going to take it, right?
So here is the switch statement.
And what you're sort of saying is like, well, how do you deal with
this switch statement?
Now, first of all, my first question is, why is the switch statement
of problem, right?
Because I don't know it's not a problem for me.
So you must have some reason why it's a problem.
I don't necessarily know what that is.
So I would come need to know what that is first.
But the second thing I would say is why do you think that dispatch
solves any problem?
That a switch statement might be, might have there really isn't
anything that it does, because all it does is.
It means,
You have to now take what used to be here?
You're going to do something like this.
Right.
You're going to you're going to replace all this code with something
that looks like that.
And then, you're going to have to write this.
now, if you'll note,
What you end up with is exactly the same thing.
It's the same, right?
There's no difference between these two pieces of code, you had to
write exactly the same code in both cases.
So for some reason, people like can't handle the concept that a switch
statement.
Just has the code one after the other.
Instead of spewing it out to a bunch of unrelated files which to me
seems strictly worse.
But I just want to underscore a switch statement and a dispatch are
exactly the same.
There is absolutely no difference to them other than
Back that the switch statement has the advantage of putting
everything, the programmer needs to know about that operation in one
place.
So they know if they change something about it, how it ends up going
together, right?
Whereas this one might have a potential advantage of, putting
everything for a particular type of thing in one place.
So if you change something about that type you can change it.
Right?
So one is one is Operation Centric and one is type Centric and I find
that typically I'd prefer type sent.
I prefer operation Centric because it's
The operation that tends to get changed as a whole, much more than the
type tends to in ways that need to get seen together.
Right for me.
But you know, your mileage may vary in the case of this sort of code,
I also really don't like separating it out like this because now
there's no shared variables between this code, right?
I if I want to share anything, I got a pass it so I can't do.
Stuff.
Like just have a bunch of things up here, like, null pixels to meters
or something.
It's just defined and everyone can use it or they gets computed or a
piece of code that happens the same between everybody that always
happens before.
And after I have to start making like base classes to do that and all
this other nonsense, when it would have just been right in line.
So I tend to really hate this.
I don't like the fact that programmers do this and I actually prefer
this way.
So my sort of long
The answer to how do you handle such things as I like switch
statements?
I think they're great.
I think they're the correct way to program.
I actually don't think this is a very good way to program.
I think it's got a lot of drawbacks.
Colonel Dragon obviously we lost some performance of the last couple
streams.
Are you playing to try to optimize it back down or just leave the
software under as is and move into GPU rendering?
I don't know, I think probably what I would like to do is use it as an
impetus.
After we're done with a few more things to go back and finish, the
Debug view stuff because so that we could actually investigate like,
where the performance went, right?
Obviously, we know a little bit bit of it went to the fact that now we
draw way too much stuff and that will that's a majority of it
actually, but we also don't know if we did other things and so on and
so forth.
So, you know, I would like to do that and then I would like to at that
point make a decision.
Do we want to do optimization on the software under?
I do want to move on
Elven a lot of times when you develop something, you write is the
simplest way.
A lot of times you develop something, you write it in the simplest
way, that just works.
Then you polish it to something good and we're finished.
EG what you did with D sound.
I don't think we ever finished anything with D sound, but okay, for
someone catching up.
Do you think it's good enough to just study and focus on the better
version?
Or is there value in writing the initial version ourselves?
Yeah, you want to go through the whole process.
That's the reason why I'm doing handmade hero is because it's the
What you need to learn like you need to learn how to do that because
if all you do is study my finished version, the only thing you're ever
going to be able to write is that finished version, but you don't want
to do that.
Like, you want to be able to adapt and make new things and make better
things than what I wrote and make things that are better for your
specific case than what I wrote and you're only going to do that.
If you know the steps and then you apply the steps but you apply them
to a different problem or a different way or towards a different end
or with more cleverness than I did.
Right?
And you get a better result for a more appropriate result or anything
else, right?
So yeah.
Snuffy crystals.
Hey Casey, I just found your series and was amazed that you're
creating entire game without using external Library like sdl from what
your episode 1 said, at least.
I really wanted to watch your progress through the series but I have
no idea where to start in the 200-plus episode since I'm already
working on sdl opengl game.
What is your suggestion?
I would say, probably.
I would say probably you'd have to go by the playlists that are on my
YouTube channel and try to work for that because we don't tend to
really segregate stuff.
We tend to work on stuff as I normally would, which is bouncing around
to whatever needs doing at a particular time.
So it doesn't tend to be super segregated.
Like, you know, sometimes we're working on the software renderer and
we'll might go do something that's in the debug system or whatever.
Like we don't necessarily
Always go in chunks.
So you may have to lean on the playlist.
A little, if you're trying to avoid stuff like software rendering
because you don't want to know,
Quarter truant.
I can't remember if you discussed this when I first cropped up.
But when you are halfway up the stairs and blending, the trees, you
get a darker area, where they overlap, what's the fix for that?
so unfortunately, there really isn't a fix for that other than using
two-stage blending, which is
Not great but it's really simple.
It's just expensive.
So anyway, what happens is we talked about this?
I thought at the time but I guess I may be in there.
So what the solution is.
So if you've got two trees, normally what happens is you draw this
tree and you draw this tree on top of it.
But if we then take an alpha value and we Alpha those together so that
you know, they're these are translucent.
Now, what you'll get is to get a darker, it part thing here.
So when we want to fade out an entire level, we don't really want to
fade out each thing individually.
What we want to do is figure out the whole thing as a as one giant
sheet.
So what you need to do first is you need to First composite everything
that you're going to fade out, right?
And then you do the whole thing as one giant Op with a particular,
Alpha value of whatever it is, so that it all gets faded out as one
sheet.
That's unfortunately, the only way to do it,
Let's see, it's standard qsort worth using compared to Rolling your
own.
Um I guess I would say as quicksort is pretty simple to implement.
so, like
I don't even know if the questions worth asking.
It's so easy to write a qsort that that it doesn't matter.
Like you could call the C runtime Library one, if you're using C
runtime Library already or you can just write your own and
I mean, quicksort is not complicated, will do one.
We'll do one tomorrow will probably do mergesort tomorrow but we'll do
a quick sort, as well.
Or at least I'll say how to do it and you can see that's not very hard
and like anything else.
You could write it once and just save it in a file and then have it
forever.
So, it's not like you have to write it like every time, right?
NORAD 91, how would you deal with collisions between multiple
entities, in terms of collision resolution, not detection like
deciding, how to resolve conflicts to be, multiple moving things.
I kind of hit a wall.
They're not seeing solutions that aren't very ugly, especially moving
or dependency to be honest.
I don't think there is much of a great solution to that problem.
You tend to have to introduce some kind of logic for it that involves
like precedents or something like that.
Because computers just aren't good at doing continuous.
Solution of things.
They always want to do discrete things.
And so it's really very difficult.
I mean, even the universe doesn't solve this problem might be one way
to say it.
Even the universe boils down to a bunch of molecules that have
discrete kind of collisions with each other at some level.
I mean, I guess we don't know.
We don't really know.
We have no idea what makes up gravity and those sorts of things, I
suppose.
So it's far be it for me to say.
But I guess what I'm saying is even the universe, doesn't try to
actually resolve rigidbody multiple rigid body collisions at once.
It thinks about it in terms of atoms and like sums, all those up to
get the rigid body collision, right?
And so you're inherently working with an abstraction over the real
physical occurrence.
And the only way that you can really
Handle that abstraction is by having some kind of rule about how
things resolved.
And so typically you know the one way to do it that's fairly
reasonable and not to physically and accurate is to use actually use
Mass.
So when you move things you you know you're moving things and you try
to resolve their collisions based on mass and collision actual cousin
response.
So that heavier things, take precedence over lighter, things
precedents, in terms of how much they move out of the way and that
sort of stuff, right?
Robert you said scaling value is not used with the camera transfers.
Everything what is the difference?
The difference is we use the camera to do a perspective transform to
scale things and that scale gets used.
But we also had a scale value, we passed in but as far as I can tell,
we never use that's going by you.
So we don't ever scale anything everything's always the same size I
guess as far as its passing through the transform but I don't actually
know maybe
That's not true.
I didn't actually go investigate.
That can delete all this here.
I don't really know.
I think the scale we do allow skiing.
So the scale I think what happens is the scale takes effect earlier is
probably what happens, right?
Yeah, here it is.
So this is where it happens.
So really what we do is we just pretend the bitmap is larger so it
does get used it just gets used before that part of the pipeline.
Car.
1948.
What keyboard are using these days, huh?
I'm using question.
You said I know your kind of Sir.
I'd love to hear Recreation my recommendation is the razor Stealth Pro
tournament Edition?
Absolutely loved it.
It is not what I'm typing on right now.
Why is it that?
Right now because like an idiot, I spilled water on it and destroyed
the thing.
And they're relatively expensive, they're like 70 bucks or something.
So I haven't bought a new one yet, but if I had infinite money, I just
would have bought a new one because they were my favorite and
And that's my current recommendation for the keyboard.
I like the most
Culver fly, how would a front-to-back render actually work but it test
every pixel before writing to it.
No, there's two different ways that would work.
One is that they just work in blocks of the screen and they do it
semantically.
So you use rectangles basically, you take your bitmaps and you assign
rectangles to your bitmaps.
That's the rectangle that is the fully opaque part, right.
And you can assign multiple if you want and then you just Union those
rectangles together and make sort of a
If you sort of a mask, if you will, in rectangle space so that you can
just clip things directly to that mask and never even start rendering
them, if they are behind stuff, that's the way that you do it
semantically, or you can do it inside the rasterizer, by having a
flag, that says, whether all the pixels in some chunk are filled and
it's like a mask.
So it's like, you know, imagine a 6 and 8 by 8 square.
And you have one 64-bit value that says, which things are filled and
you look at the mask and if, if that mask says, you know, everything
is filled.
You just don't you just skip that chunk entirely, it's early out.
That's how that's more how a graphics card actually does it because
the graphics card has to do early easy stuff and it doesn't have the
luxury of doing weird like Symantec things like we could do.
Mr.
First Dimension does multiple dispatch come up for you much as in and
types with N squared branches, how do you handle it when it does?
No, it doesn't come up very much.
And the reason for that is usually N squared in programming in terms
of code, is usually just as bad as N squared in programming in terms
of actual like, algorithms.
If you have something that's an N squared, dispatch it won't scale
because you know, if you
N squared, different things.
That means if there's 30 different types in your system, you have 900
pieces of code, you have to test it, right?
And test and make sure work, right?
And that's just really difficult.
So, typically, if I have something that looks like it's going in
squared, I try to break it into some kind of more fundamental set of
types either where the types are much smaller.
So that the branch count is low enough, meaning, okay?
There were 30, but I broke it down to four fundamental categories with
parameters.
So,
now, it's only 16 total things, so the n
Not so bad so because the ends lower or I try to make it so that it's
not squared anymore by again refactoring, what I'm doing into a way
that allows it to not work that way.
I don't find that comes up that often, but that's not to say that
doesn't come up.
So you do have to think about it.
And, you know, like I said, there's, there's different strategies for
approaching it, which one would work?
The best usually depends on the situation.
Narada 91 would you rather have an explicit fall through statement
with an implicit break?
Instead of standard switch statements?
Yes, I would seems much cleaner to me.
Or am I missing something?
I don't think you're missing anything.
I think that would be much better.
In fact the probably the way I would do it is the break would always
be implied, it's always there and then yeah you would do something
like fall through like that and it's a different thing, right?
Something like that.
Especially since I usually don't use it.
I hardly ever use that really, I could get by almost probably entirely
with just this something like that.
Where you say, here's this, this is a bunch of cases together.
That's really all I would need.
I don't, you know, usually when I use fall through, I'm using it like
this, right?
Which doesn't really even need the fall through part of it much.
I'm just saying, hey these two types, both are the same result.
That's what I was afraid of a thought.
Maybe you had some trick, like a messed-up precomputed Alpha.
I don't think there is a trick.
I remember, I think even asking Shawn Barrett since he's like mr.
Alpha oh, mr.
Old-school, Alpha guy.
If there was anything, and he didn't seem to think so.
And if he doesn't think so, then there probably isn't
Alrighty, I think we're out of time here, so let me see if there's any
other last questions.
I know we just got over the holiday break, but will there be a
break-in handmade here when the witness launches?
Probably not know,
Robbie, are you productive feel good at programming?
No matter how many hours you work per week.
I don't think the number of hours.
I work per week, really have anything to do with it.
It's how many unknown problems I have to encounter really
That's that's mostly it.
If I just have a bunch of stuff to do that, I know how to do.
I can just work all week and it's really not a problem.
Usually what, what slows me down is when I have to hit something where
I'm just really, not sure what the right answer is and I need to play
around with it and sometimes I'm not sure what to do to play around,
sometimes that can be difficult and that is usually easier.
When you're fresh to like, push through those, it's usually easier
when you're fresh and so that maybe would have more to do with like,
oh, too many hours of that could be bad.
Where it's like, if it's just stuff I just you know just got to do
this code, it's not always.
So it's not always really a problem for four hours.
All right, that's it.
I'm going to go ahead and close up shop here.
Save the old Blackboard.
Thanks everyone for joining me for this episode of ham be here.
It's been a pleasure working with you.
As always.
If you want to follow along with serious at home, you can always
pre-order the game, but handmade hero dot-org and it comes with a
source code, so you can follow along and that's a little button for
that right there.
Also, we have a forum site, you can go to if you want to ask questions
about the series, we have a patreon page, you can sign up for if you
want to support these videos which are and will always remain free of
charge to everyone.
And we have a tweet box which treats the schedule at you if you want
to stream live speaking of catching the stream live you can catch it
live tomorrow at 5 p.m.
I will be right back here where we will talk about.
Honestly I think you know we're going to do tomorrow because we're
going to talk about sorting.
I think we're going to I think I'm going to actually talk about order
notation for reals.
Like I'm actually going to explain how I think about it and why you
should care and why it's not just something for your CSS class.
So we'll probably talk about that in the context of sorting because
It makes sense to talk about their it's a classic problem for order
notation seems like the right thing to do.
So order notation starting tomorrow and probably the next day as well.
And then that then we'll move on to some other.
I don't know what but something.
All right, thanks everyone for joining me until tomorrow.
I hope you have fun programming and I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy everyone.