Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero show.
Where we could complete game live on Twitch.
We do not use any engines or libraries here.
The only thing that we use is the platform that we're forced to run on
top of which today is Windows.
What you going to do?
That's what you got to ship games on these days.
So that's what we use.
But other than that, it's all our own code and we show basically how
to do absolutely everything.
We don't even use the GPU.
We actually did.
All of the rendering ourselves, write down every little pixel.
Something that we put there and thought about how it was supposed to
work.
So we're in pretty good shape right now.
We've done a bunch of the stuff that we need to do to get ourselves
into into the state of having an engine.
And I don't know today, I'm just kind of, I don't ever, we've said
this multiple times on handmade hero.
I don't really ever feel the need to try to stick to any kind of
schedule because I find that programming works best when you are, when
you tackle whatever.
Ever is the most logical program problem at any given time and so not
sure exactly going to do today, but I think we may do something that
we weren't supposed to do or something like that.
I'm just getting that feeling so that's probably what's going to
happen anyway.
If you'd like to follow along today is day, 132 so unpacked a 131
source code from the zip.
If you have pre-ordered, the game that is the source code that I am
working with and if you would like to follow along at home, that is
what you should use yesterday.
We did a little bit of work to get ourselves background.
And for graphics, resources and stuff like this.
And so, as you saw yesterday, we now don't have problems with hiccups
when week recompute background Graphics, so that's always good and to
a large extent, that means we pretty much our stall free now.
But there is a little bit of sort of a hidden stall in there that we
haven't really addressed yet and that is sort of asset loading.
You can see that when we are starting up the game we actually
Load all of the bitmap bitmaps when we use see here.
It map.
You can see in here that we actually load all the bitmaps manually
because we haven't really ever thought about what we want to do.
As far as that's concerned and we did have a thing on here that's like
got asset streaming as a thing and I don't know.
We made some thread stuff.
I feel like we might as well just go for it.
Why not just say this asset streaming is incredibly trivial?
There's almost nothing to it.
It's an increased extraordinarily simple.
You've already seen me do almost absolutely everything that you need
in order to ask the streaming.
So we might as well just move it out there and just like say that's
what we're going to do.
I think that's probably reasonable and if we don't do all the SS
streaming, that's fine.
Because at the moment, we don't necessarily know if maybe there's
going to be something other than bitmaps and sound files that we might
have to stream in, but, you know, as far as I'm concerned,
Like I think that's pretty much, pretty much all of it.
I think that's mostly everything that we would need to stream in.
And so I feel like we can probably just go ahead and do that, right?
We know, we don't have any 3D assets because this is supposed to be a
2-D game.
And so pretty much loading bitmaps and and sound files is probably
most of what we would want to do.
And in addition to that, we are trying to do mostly procedural
animation.
So it's highly unlikely that we're going to be doing something like
streaming in anime.
Ation files.
Now we may have some things to say that we want to access that are
like structural in case we want the game to support like, you know,
sort of mods or downloadable content or stuff stuff where there's like
some kind of package that comes in and it augments the game that
doesn't actually change what's currently on the disc that you just
kind of add into it or something like this.
So, you know, maybe we want to do something like that, maybe we don't,
I don't know.
But at the very least, we can put in the
Basic stuff of streaming in a pretty straightforward fashion, to
really not particularly difficult.
So,
I am going to go ahead and start doing that.
And what you can see, actually at the moment, you can already kind of
see that we've got a concept of asset streaming already kind of in
place.
The most important part of thinking about any asset system actually is
kind of already in place just by what we wrote naturally.
And it's kind of important to sort of sit there and go, okay, I see
what's going on.
So I'm just going to mention it quickly.
And that is that the primary sort of boundary layer in your game code
that you have to worry about when you're thinking about how assets are
loaded and managed is the place where the game code.
And the assets have to agree on the name of something.
Okay?
And you can see that we've already done that here, this code right
here, is the place where those names are essentially.
Pound, right?
You can see that our game talks about the grasp, it Maps the stone,
the tuft right as these loaded bitmap things, and it's accessing them
off of game State and saying grass.
That's how it refers to wanting a, you know, that grass bitmap or
whatever.
And you know, here in the debug load bitmap, you can see that we have
what the asset system, essentially considers the name which is a file
like a file path on disk, right?
And so this is the code right here.
The very simple code.
In terms of asset loading that we have right now, which is doing that
binding.
It's saying here is a way to refer to actual data somewhere.
And here is the name that the code is going to use to refer to that
data, right?
So that's what's going on at the moment now.
What I want to emphasize here.
Is that really all you need to do to have a reasonable asset streaming
system?
Is you need to make sure that the names that the game's refers to are
things that are always in scope, essentially that cannot become
invalid or crash, able right like a pointer could, for example, like,
if you're referring to your assets by a pointer, you have a problem
because if you're streaming and you're pointing into something and
that thing,
Gets evicted, you've got problems, right?
So, you know, things like a pointer to memory, not a great way to
refer to a particular asset.
So you have you have that sort of thing to worry about and the other
thing that you have to think about is how those things get, sort of
resolved, like how you can, you know, how is the game going to be able
to give it a give it some kind of identifier and name and say here's
what I want.
Here's the thing that I speak about my semantics what I'm trying to
ask for and you need to kind of go grab that thing.
How is that?
You know, process sort of working
And so that's what we're going to start thinking about what I want to
do here is just point out that we kind of have a pretty simple sort of
set up going and we can almost see just from having written this usage
code.
The sorts of things that we want to talk about here, you can see that
we essentially have, if you will three kinds of of elements already
happening and they happen to be the three kinds of elements that I
strongly suspect, we will see over and over again.
So even just just from having
The code in the most obvious way, which again, I always emphasize just
removing written the code.
In the, most obvious way, we already see pretty much the sorts of
stuff that we're probably going to need all throughout development and
that is, we're going to have an array of options for things, right?
So an artist May specify, some number of bitmaps that all correspond
to the same logical ID in the program, right?
Meaning the engine wants to think about
out grass.
It has a way of referring to grass and it needs to be able to know
what are all of the options.
The artist has supplied in terms of grass right now, right?
And you can see that we did our very simple, very basic implementation
of this was just, you have an array of bitmaps.
So that we know, there are two grasses and we said the two grasses
came from these two files, right?
So a very simple way of handling that, but again, a very important
logical concept that is is action to carry.
Four words, it was not.
The concept itself is not trivial.
The concept is important and will carry straight to the development.
It's just our implementation of it here.
That was simple because we were not at the point where we're thinking
about asset loading.
So that's a very important concept right concept.
The, the second concept of course, which actually, I guess I probably
explain these in the opposite order is
The concept of a basic bitmap right that we want to load and so this
is really an extension of that.
It's saying that there are several objects options for that bitmap,
right?
And then the final thing we have is sort of a the concept of a
structured set of bitmaps and you if you heart it can kind of remember
back to when we did this hero bitmaps thing, the reason that we wanted
to do that was because our hero had several facing directions, right?
He had left right up and down in each of those facing directions
actually had in it a
A set of bitmaps.
They had a head, a cape and a torso, right?
And because there are several sets of bitmaps
We wanted to make it easy to have routines That animated these sets of
bitmaps together without actually knowing with which direction it was
going to go, right.
We wanted a thing that could could draw it here on the screen without
knowing which direction it was talking about.
And so we created a structure that allows it to do exactly that by
having like head cape and torso here.
Right.
So I think that is sort of very much.
So with with the with the exception of fact that we don't have sounded
here yet, which is, you know, something obviously that we have to work
on the exception of the fact that we don't have sound in here yet.
We've really seen pretty much exactly what we want out of the graphic
system at least at a fundamental level in terms of how we're going to
talk about Assets in that respect, okay?
so,
what we can do now is we can say, how do we again, you know, sort of
using the principles of, you know, incremental, you know, compression
oriented programming.
How do we take what we've already done and sort of build upon what we
know, we actually want in the code to do something that gives us that
flexibility.
But also allows us to trivially stream the Assets in if we want to
write and maybe while we're at it, maybe try to look for a couple
opportunities.
To expand some things that were previously hard-coded into stuff.
That's a little more flexible such as the engine.
Not having to know, you know, not having to hard code here, that there
are two grasses, maybe it would be nice if we could say when it goes
ahead and loads its resource pack, you know, in at the beginning of
the game or whatever, it's just has a number of grasses in there and
however, many grasses there are, that's how many the engine will use.
And so that's another thing that would be something that would be
nice, sort of to keep an eye on as we go.
Can we start to maybe remove some of the restrictions that just having
typed it in as just straight, see with nothing fancy going on?
How you know, how can we maybe get rid of some of those restrictions
or limitations that, you know, would sort of as we go forward that
would, you know, potentially present themselves
So that's what I'm going to do.
I'm just going to focus on that.
And again, we want this to be able to work in the background.
So I'm going to keep that in the back of my mind as we go.
But the first thing that I
Do is really to take one small, sort of compression step and to just
move out the things that we were using into one place.
And you'll sort of see why I want to do that as we kind of go
forwards.
But this is basically trying to get these out into a place where we're
starting to think about the assets separate from everything else in
the code.
So here is all, you know, all this stuff is not assets, right?
These are not loaded, none of this stuff is loaded from disk, okay?
But this stuff is right, so you can imagine we had like a game asset
structure here and now I've got this game asset structure.
I'm just going to go ahead and say, we've got game assets down at the
bottom.
Right there we go.
And all I'm going to do literally is just fix this, this thing where
we've got, you know, I've got to put assets, doc grass in there.
That's literally all I'm going to do, right?
It's the it's the, you know, the dumbest of the dumb.
It's
Dumbest possible thing.
Let's see.
Here assets assets.
so,
Here we go.
And these are all going to be assets as well, right?
And again, not, I'm literally not doing anything here.
There is no code change.
I'm just slowly putting these, you know, kind of into a more, you
know, a more isolated State just kind of really really straightforward
fashion there.
Okay, let's go ahead and do that.
And
Like so it's like you got a few more in here in the drawing routines,
okay?
Go.
and,
Oops.
It's wrong.
Okay, and again, this should, you know, just run shouldn't do anything
different than what it was doing before, it's all good.
So, now I've got these guys out here right now, when I want to do is I
want to observe for a second that I want to start by taking the
simplest of these assets, this back drop, shadow, tree, sword, and
stairwell.
Because remember these guys, I'm going to kind of break these up here,
right?
These
Are arrayed assets, right?
And these are structured assets, right?
Whereas these guys here, these guys here don't have any structure to
them.
They are just a plain vanilla bitmap so they make sense for me to
start with them first because they have the least amount of metadata
associated with them right there.
Yes they're a bunch of bits and yes they have a little bit of metadata
which is like the width and height of the bitmap for
People or you know what the sort of Hotpoint is.
So there's some but there's only one, you know, sort of logical unit
of rendering that the renderer looks at their right?
Is that that that just that one piece?
So that is a lot easier than starting with something that has sort of
a number of things or that has a structure to it, where we know that
it's got different components.
So I'm going to start with the simplest one first and going to
abstract away, sort of, sort of some of the, the shouldn't say
abstract.
Yeah, but I'm going to kind of make it change its form if you will.
Okay.
So what is the fundamental problem that I'm looking at here when I
think about asset streaming and I look at what's right in front of me
in terms of game assets.
Okay the thing that's that's there's there's something to things right
that are that are problematic about what I'm looking at.
I guess the way I would say it.
The first one is that you can see that like the data that I'm actually
talking about all has to be here, right?
Like I'm talking about this whole loaded bitmap and it's got its width
Heights and everything.
It's all the spaces, reserved essentially.
And maybe yeah, there's a pointer to memory in here so I could set
that pointer 20 but I can't actually get rid of the whole bit map
itself and if you know that could actually be an appreciable amount of
memory, you know, I'd like to maybe make that boiled down to
something, you know, something smaller if you will right or maybe boil
down to nothing at all.
Potentially.
So there's our, there's that the other thing that's obviously
problematic about it.
It is that anyone who's going to refer to this thing is going to refer
directly to it, right?
It's going to refer directly to, you know, sort of the
It's going to it's going to, it's going to directly access this, this
particular piece of memory which means that of course I don't really
have any way of knowing who's using what or whether or not something
has to, you know, whether something could be evicted.
There's all sorts of things that are just problematic about that,
right?
So what I want to start doing is I want to start making it so that
people are going to talk about these things.
In a slightly more indirect way so that I could,
So that they could talk about them without ever necessarily knowing
where they were or what they were, they could just use some kind of
other name, right?
So what I'm going to do first is I'm just going to introduce the
simplest possible thing again.
I want to introduce an ID that allows the game to talk about something
like one of these guys, right.
I want to be able to, you know, maybe I'll say game asset ID or
something like this.
I want to, I want to have some way of referring to these things in
here.
That do not actually, you know, use the pointer of the thing that
we're talking about, okay?
So, you know, I'm
Do something like this where I've got my list of names that the game
could use to talk about something.
And then what I'm going to do here is I'm going to say, oh I've just
got an array of bitmaps now.
And I've got this game asset ID.
I know Hoops, that's no good.
I know I've got as many of those as as there are IDs.
I know, I'm going to need that many of them.
If I want to implement this, again exactly the same way, but just
pulling out, one more level.
Well, I'm just saying.
Okay, now you don't access it by the name that way you accesses it in
a slightly different way, right?
And since I know that people are all going to be you know accessing
this as a pointer there, I'm going to say maybe we just have some way
of saying that you get the bitmap, you know, from from the ID, right?
So I say, you know, pass me the game assets structure.
Tell me which I D.
It is you're looking for and I will go ahead and return that one to
you, right?
So that you don't exactly directly access out of it anymore again
because this is in preparation or the fact where there won't be
anything to direct access and so you will have to call to a function
that actually does work.
There will be no way to directly do it.
So I'm going to do it that way.
I'm going to go ahead and return that there it's just that wrong.
There we go.
So I'm going to go ahead and compile that
And oh and I forgot one of the thing I guess.
I need a way to actually store these as well for the loading but I
guess I can just really because it's returning me a pointer I still
probably could go ahead and do it by just just doing it this way in
the future.
That's going to we're not going to care because the stuff is going to
get loaded in a different way.
So that's fine.
So I guess I can just do it this way like so on right, I suppose that
will just work, right.
IGA I grass?
What oh wait, no grasses grasses.
Should still be working, just fine.
So I'm looking at the wrong one here.
Sorry, that was my bad.
Got a little ahead of myself there.
We haven't gotten to that yet.
So there we go.
That will set the backdrop or at least it should
And I gotta pass the address there but I think that should give me
essentially what I'm looking for for this next step.
Right?
And again, just trying to do some simple transformations to slowly
move the code into a new sort of position that gives me a little more
power than I had before.
So alright, let's take a look here.
Got to put those a saint
There we go.
And again the same is going to go here.
We've got that, get bitmap, a Sanjay.
Shadows, that gets it there.
And now we will do the same thing.
Get bitmap assets GI tree, and same thing here bitmap J, eyeshadow and
last one.
Yeah, I sword.
Okay, couple more down here.
See and again, nothing strange going on here.
I'm literally just translating these calls directly, I am not changing
them in any way and I'm essentially I'm not really even changing how
the codes working at all.
It's just going through a slightly more indirect route because we're
sort of making a little.
We're basically like sort of separating it out in a preparation for
putting something in between it kind of thing.
Right.
Okay, so that's all well and good, right?
We've got those those guys in there.
And, and so now I'm able to talk about game assets by ID rather than
by B that pointer if I want to because I can always get the bit that
pointer out later, which is, you know, kind of one step there.
but,
Now I kind of have another question, which is like, oh, you know, how
do I, what am I going to do for these other guys here?
Right, these sort of array assets and these structured Assets in here
where I've kind of got other stuff going on.
Well, like I said, I don't really want to talk about those yet.
I think that it might be a little premature to to really kind of deal
with those in any in any significant way.
So what I'd like to do temporarily again, this is just
This is this is not how I want to deal with it at the end of the day.
But so that we can make everything kind of flow through a little more
appropriately.
What I want to do here is I want to be able to refer
I want to be able to refer to those bitmaps so that they still have
some kind of a slot.
Kind of think of whether this is a good idea or not.
Mmm-hmm.
You know what?
I'm not gonna do that yet.
I'm gonna wait, I'm gonna wait.
So, all right now that I have this, what I'm going to do is I'm going
to just wait on those guys because I feel like it's probably just
better for me to wait until I Implement one of these.
I think it's going to be clear explanation wise as well.
So I'll just put that aside.
So what I want to do now is the push bitmap call.
What I'd like to do with the push bitmap call is I'd like to make the
push bitmap call.
Actually take one of those, right?
So we're going to
to do is essentially the same thing that we have here in terms of what
the the bitmap takes in, right?
It takes in this render group and the load a bit Mouse of right.
And all we're going to do is we're going to change this to take a game
asset ID, right like so on.
And again, game asset ID is probably the wrong thing to use here.
Technically speaking, because we're probably going to want something
that's like a bitmap ID, which is not exactly necessarily the same as
the game asset idea.
We'll see.
But for right now it's fine because we haven't actually made that
distinction.
So we'll sort of will expand that distinction when the time comes and
not get ahead of ourselves, right?
So what I'm going to do there is I'm going to go ahead and take that
that get bitmap code and I'm just going to call it in here instead,
right?
And I'm going to assume that the render group has been set up so that
has a specific place where it expects assets to come from, right?
So we're going to say, all right, we've got an asset pointer that's in
the render group.
We're going to ask for the the bitmap that corresponds to a particular
ID.
We're going to, you know, sort of go forwards with that.
Right?
And I guess I'm gonna, you know, I'm also going to maybe pull it out
here just so I can do it this way.
Like so, okay.
Okay.
And we do this look this bitmap.
Loading we get a look at the assets.
We got the ID there.
That all looks good and trying to think if there's anything else that
I care about here.
No, that looks about, right?
So once we get that bitmap act, then we're all good and you can call
this function, just fine.
So, what I need to do again, to make that work, is I need to look at
the render group, right?
And I need to make sure that the render group has a notion of who it
gets its game assets from, right.
So when you're rendering any particular, there we go.
Any particular group knows who it's going to ask for assets, that will
be something that when you create an out, when you allocate a render
group, you are required to pass in, right?
So game assets assets.
So you, you have to pass those in.
That's just a flat
And yeah, I think that will do it.
I just have to actually store it here, like so yeah.
Okay, so if I go ahead and compile that
Looks like that.
Sonata Moon thing at the time, that's fine.
Okay.
And
I need to pass it here.
I also don't know if it should really be in the game State.
I feel like it's kind of a transient thing to be honest.
Now it's going to be transitioning.
Because it's going to fluctuate.
So I feel like game assets to be completely honest with you, is
actually something that should probably be in the transient pool.
So I'm going to go ahead and stick it in there, okay?
So in here, when we allocate the render group, we're going to pass the
trance State assets, along with it, there we go.
And all of these guys, for game State assets, they're all going to
take trance State assets like so.
There we go.
Lobos in there and so on.
And of course, we have to actually, if we're doing that loading, we
have to do that out where we can actually make that stuff be in the
transient state.
So, I'm going to grab this out here.
I don't think there's any real dependencies on that anywhere, but I
can come in here and then after we've sort of done, the ground chunk
stuff, I can put that in there and in theory, that's that's all going
to be totally fine.
And nothing weird will happen.
Hopefully, that's, you know, Famous Last Words, Right?
Famous last words.
So, here we go.
We've, you know, we're working just fine loading as expected.
So now, I'm going to go ahead and in those push bitmap calls in the
ones where I can, I'm going to go ahead and make all of the push
bitmap calls.
Actually just use those bitmap IDs if possible.
Right.
So anywhere that can use a bitmap ID at will so you can see that we
were previously calling get that map here instead.
I'm just going to call.
I'm just going to render with the actual ID that I was trying to use
to render this thing, right?
And so there we go.
Like so again, this is really really straightforward.
I'm just moving it slowly slowly, one step at a time down into sort of
The renderer doing that query and again, no, big surprises games,
looks the same.
Everything is loaded as we would expect.
Okay?
So now we have, the renderer is actually the one who's talking about
these assets and the important part about that, and the reason that I
am sort of bringing it to your attention,
Or rather that I, you know, I'm sort of doing these slow things, you
can see how they go and and see each individual step of the process,
is that what we have now done?
And this is a very crucial step in my opinion, to doing background
screaming properly, because a lot of people say, background swimming
is really hard.
And I don't really know why that is.
I've never found it to be difficult.
I've always thought it's very straightforward and so I feel like it's
important to kind of go through all of the, the steps and just show.
How they work and how they logically follow from each other, just in
to clear up, whatever the confusion is about background stamp.
So anyway,
So what we've done here now right is we put ourselves in a position
where the renderer is getting an asset ID and it's asking the asset
storage to give it back the bitmap for that ID.
What we can now do is, say if, for some reason that bitmap was not
available, we can just not draw it, right?
So we get rid of one of the critical failure cases, which is that
somebody goes to render something and they have a pointer into some
invalid data or worse case or whatever.
And we also get rid of the problem of over trying to render something
and maybe it's off screen but we don't know that.
And then we end up in a situation where we're trying to run or
something that hasn't been streamed in yet and it causes this problem.
And locks up the frame because it's waiting for that or whatever.
We can actually just get rid of all that and say, look, when we try to
render something, if it's not there, we just don't render right.
And in my mind that's actually always the right decision because, you
know, your game should be set up so that the streaming is always ahead
if the streaming ever falls behind.
I would rather not have the frame rate.
Take a hit.
I mean as far as I'm concerned, that's just a bug.
Because the frame rate should just shouldn't slow down.
There are ways that we can make it so that the frame rate does stall
by basically here if the bitmaps, not there you basically.
Oh you know go ahead and stall stall the frame but I usually just do
it this way.
And I just say okay we always make sure the streaming system is fast
enough to keep up and if for some reason to keep up, the worst is
you'll get some kind of flicker where a bitmap That was supposed to be
loaded wasn't loaded and there's other things we can do to mitigate
that by using fallback that Maps as well.
And so on,
But yeah.
So now we've got a situation where we could just not return something
if we have it loaded it, right?
They couldn't just full-on return 0 and the renderer just won't render
it, right?
No, big deal.
What that means is, I can now go up here to my game assets.
And what I can do is I can change it.
So that actually now we don't necessarily have all of them loaded,
right?
There's maybe maybe we don't have them loaded, we just have a pointer
and that pointer is going to be null when we start out because there
are no bitmaps yet and off you go, right?
And so what would happen there if we were to do that is when we when
we do this here, right?
We would actually grab out the pointer.
ER and the pointer may be known.
That's fine.
And we return it.
Okay.
So I feel like now I mean this
Still work just fine, right?
Oh no.
It won't because we haven't actually we haven't actually allocated
space for those guys yet.
So we need at least some kind of a little debug loading guy here.
Alright, so I'm going to grab these guys here.
All of the things that were in the assets.
These are the guys that are in the assets, right?
I'm going to grab them up and I'm going to put them in in a separate
routine here.
Right?
This routine is called you know load assets or something, I don't
know.
Kick your favorite name for it.
And what that's going to do here, this is going to take a game assets
structure and it's going to go ahead and do the loading.
But again, what we do now, when we do debug look bitmap, what that
actually does is that gives us about a bitmap structure.
We haven't actually allocated space to store any of these.
So that's a little bit of a problem.
Oh whoops.
I grabbed the wrong, guys.
My bad.
Sorry about that.
Nobody saw me just pretend that never happened.
All right, so if I go in here and I just sort of clean this up a
little bit, right?
The only thing that we would need to do here is we need to figure out
again some way that we can.
We can make these guys allocate actual storage space and that's not
particularly difficult, right?
In debug load bitmap, when we're calling it here, I could just go
ahead and and allocate the extra space for the bitmap by making sort
of a temporary.
in here, which is like
You know, allocate or debug allocate load bitmap, something like this.
Let's go ahead and put those in there, okay?
Little bit map allocate, the bitmap, allocate load bitmap.
And what this will do is this will take the transient state so that it
can go ahead and allocate space for bitmaps as it loads them.
Okay.
So there's the trance, State and off we go.
So, we've got that in there.
This function is just going to call debug load bitmap.
It's going to pass all of the same stuff that it got right in here.
Line-X top down a line.
Y and all I'm going to do is I'm going to take that transient State
and I'm going to use the transient Arena to basically get ourselves
some space for that bitmap structure, right?
So I've Got Loaded bitmap, like so,
Okay, I've got my load to bitmap that I'm going to allocate here and I
essentially want that to go put this little do a little result here.
And I guess also, this will just return a pointer.
We're not actually even going to have to do.
This is call anymore, right?
This is just going to be assets bitmaps.
There we go.
Oops.
Doodoo text transformation, just enough to be annoying, but not enough
to try and wrestle with an E Max macro, you know, it is.
All right, so what I do that, I'm going to try to allocate one of
these bitmaps here by getting it off of the transient Arena.
I'll you know, take a look at bitmap and that'll be fine.
I'm then going to try and do the debug look bitmap.
Call I have the result that that I want.
So that's I'm going to
Oops, I'm going to write into that with debug bitmap, whatever comes
back and then I'm going to return the results, right?
And
What did I do?
Wrong loaded bitmap illegal.
Use the type of expression is push size.
Not the right function?
It's push struct.
That's videos.
I don't know what the name of this arena is.
Actually I guess it's Train Arena, so that's fine.
And the thread, when we call load assets, I guess I have to pass that,
I guess.
I have to actually pass both of these, unfortunately.
So we'll go ahead and put those on there.
And then, I think we should be good memory.
Oh, right.
So, this can just be read entire file.
Go read entire file and there we go.
All right, hopefully not too many, more little things to do.
There we go.
And it does not take four arguments.
That is true.
I guess there's a default parameter on those guys, debug or maybe not
one, two, three.
So if there's no, default parameter what was test background.
Previously using it.
Is there one?
That's now.
There it is right there.
So it's actually doing these guys here.
Yeah, it's using .5 and point.
Five is the aligned percentage in the case where nothing was
specified.
That's frustrating, but that's okay.
Again, this is only a temporary routine, so we'll just Spam it for
now.
It's totally fine.
Not what I would prefer but it works.
Alright, so now we should
Nothing right in the places where there are where we were where we're
going through that path because we've never called that loading
function, right?
So we're never going to see those, okay?
And we don't and that's correct.
And now if we actually call the load assets function, we should, we
should see them show up, right?
So here we go.
There's that brand state with the assets and thread context.
And I saved this here because I never remember what it is.
There it is, that read entire file, okay?
Oops.
Load assets can iron it to.
That's true.
That needs an ampersand.
And so now those guys should be loaded and show up and they do, which
is what we would have expected and that's good.
So we've got our trees back and so on and our shadow and all that
other good stuff.
All right, so now that we've got those assets, loading this way, what
we can also do now right is we can make those assets if we want to.
We don't actually have to load those assets until somebody actually
asked for them, right?
We're now sort of in a position to actually start implementing a
little bit of that delayed loading.
If we sow toes.
So the question is, how would we go about doing that, right?
And here's the part where we probably want to start getting into the
operating system stuff because we would like to be able to queue up
the disk reads, but we can sort of simulate that because since we
actually do have a task system.
Now we can kind of put that we can kind of use that a little bit.
I just want to emphasize the fact that at least at the moment it's not
really.
Case that we want to necessarily use the task system and let it block
for some reasons that we'll talk about a little bit later, but we can
start by doing it that way.
And then maybe go into the OS layer and add some additional support
that we're going to want for doing loading in a smarter way than
then this way.
So
what are some things to think about here?
So when we're doing load assets, right?
We're loading all these assets at once.
What I'd like to do now instead is have a way, have a function that
just loads an asset.
And again this is going to be probably like one of the dumbest things
that you've ever seen.
But we're still again like I said one step at a time very very
important to do one step at a time and so that's what we're going to
do, right?
I'm literally just going to wrap this in a switch statement.
So that we're literally calling the exact same code.
We're not doing anything else one step at a time.
So we're wrapping it in the switch statement.
And so now we know we can
Just one of these.
And, and again, the only thing that's changing here is that the switch
statement makes it so that it only calls one instead of calling them
all in a row, right?
So what I want to do here is say, alright, we're going to call load
assets, and instead, it's just going to be load a set, right?
And it's going to take in here some ID, right?
It's going to take a game asset ID, there's the ID, and it's going to
Live it, right?
So
This call goes away now.
And again if we don't do anything since we're never calling that
function, we don't see anything at all but if we go back in here now
we can opt to actually make that call at various times if we so chose
it's a little bit what we probably want to do because it's a little
bit gnarly to actually call is we would like to be able to have our
load asset call.
Actually do something you know
Oh, maybe it keeps a couple of these things, kind of a little more
understood so that doesn't have to have them all passed in all the
time, right?
Especially because I yeah, like we're not really going to be calling
this debug allocate load BMP thing.
So it kind of just gets annoying to pass all these, all these things
in here when we're going to probably go ahead and get rid of this and
switch to something that we can use a cue for, right.
Okay, so let's see.
What do we want to do here?
I guess what I'd like to do is say, well when we call in here, I guess
we will pass.
Maybe the transient state will pass the game assets thread context.
Yeah, yeah, hmm.
So for the next step, I have two choices and I'm not sure which one I
want to do.
Choice one is to have the renderer directly request assets to be
loaded.
And number two is to have them go into a queue to be loaded later.
I think what I would like to do is probably I think I would like to
make it so that the render requests access directly, even though
that's a little less clean, I would say that eventually, I feel like
we're going to be in a situation where certain background render
processes are going to have to block on assets that they need loaded
in order to do compositing properly.
And so I think we're going to want the renderer to be able to force
That issue if that makes sense.
Although we could force the issue from outside.
Hmm.
Man, that's a tough one.
That's a tough one.
Well,
I guess I'll just have to experiment a little bit and see but anyway
for the for the time being let's let's try to make a little bit of
forward progress there.
We only have about 10 minutes left on the stream anyway.
So let's just keep going with where we were and you know as we sort of
root around in there a little bit more hopefully it'll become clear
what the correct choice is for that particular thing.
So let's say we were taking one of these guys and we were going to do
this this this push-fit map call right.
And this push bitmap call again.
Needs the the game asset system needs to be able to do this stuff.
The only thing that I'm not crazy about is this thread context thing
here.
And so I think I'm just going to go ahead and just cheat about that
because I really like, I said, don't want this guy to ever be talking
about a threat.
I don't want them to know about a threat.
I don't want any of that stuff happening in there, but because of the
way we set up our debug allocate little bit map, it takes it just as a
dummy, which probably was a stupid idea.
But, you know, sometimes,
Stupid ideas.
So anyway, I'm going to go ahead and say that we've got an arena in
here.
In the game asset Arena.
So this is going to be a memory Arena asset Arena.
And that's where it's going to get its assets from.
So it's going to get rid of the trance State and it's going to instead
of passing trance State here, it's just going to pass an arena
directly.
So it'll pass a memory Arena.
Here's the arena like so on.
There we go.
And so this will just pass that Arena directly through.
And we will store read entire file.
For now in here.
So the fats in there as well, that way that goes away and then thread.
We're basically going to put 20 to do.
Get rid of this thread thing when I load through a q instead of the
debug call, right?
So anyway, got our game assets here and we've got the ID.
So now it only needs those two things, which is what I wanted.
It goes to heads and passes, I guess we'll just say this is the arena.
Let me know it's the assets Arena because it's in the asset structure.
So we'll go ahead and make all that happen.
There we go and continue on assets Arena.
And read entire file.
I'll just dear f it out here assets.
The entire file.
And now I would like to compile.
There we go.
And when I set up that game asset structure at the beginning, now I
have to actually I have to actually do it.
I have to actually get that stuff initialized since right now, it's
not set in anything.
Right?
And so inside our transient State initialization here, I need to do
game assets.
So oops, I guess I should do it.
Probably up a little higher, huh?
when we initialize this stuff, I'm going to go ahead and say,
That we have our game assets.
Has it Arena and that arena is a sub Arena like so of the trance State
Tran Arena.
And that's going to be at the moment, you know, this is going to be
eventually our biggest thing because it's going to store all of the
assets that are loaded.
But at the moment, we will not actually be doing that.
So I'll just I'll keep it a little conservative here, but eventually
we'll make that pretty large.
So we put that in there.
And then we need to set up read entire file as well.
Oops should be trance State, trance State assets, read entire file
equals memory debug lead.
Entire file lat.
Lat for me entire file.
And that's the only things I think we had to set up.
Okay, so now it's as simple as just calling that load assets, right?
That load a set function.
And so if I want to do this now even though it's synchronous inside
render group, I can go ahead and say, you know, if the bitmap isn't in
there.
Well, that's okay.
Why don't you just go ahead and tell somebody to go get it right?
So that it'll be there next time, right?
That seems
Good idea, load asset.
Now needs to be something that can be called externally we go.
And so now in theory, when we run stuff, stuff gets loaded, right?
And off we go.
Okay, so furthermore, we can even probably now if we really want to,
and we're not quite in the full position to do so yet.
But if we want to, we could probably now even make this, the
background loaded thing, right?
What we can do here is we can say, okay, if we want a background load
this, remember how we did our background stuff for say doing the
ground chunks, right?
We had something that looked like this.
And so, what we could do is we could say, you know, we have a thing
called load asset work.
And the load up 5-minute warning.
The load asset work is just going to take the stuff that this thing
means.
To actually do stuff.
Okay, so it's going to need the ID.
It's going to need the asset structure.
It's going to need that fake thread, right?
Which like I said, we'll need to go away, it'll need read entire file,
but it can get that just out of here.
And then it's going to need the file name of thing that's supposed to
load, right?
So I think that's
So most everything that it would need there.
So if I went ahead and said that we had load asset work and I grab
that out, then if, as long as I have, I think really all I need is
assets and the file name, right?
So it really just be that thing.
Oh and the ID, right?
I think that's it.
And then that would ya be just about everything, right?
So we'd have we'd have became assets.
Pointer.
We would have the file name.
And we would have the game asset ID.
So if we wanted to then fill ground chump work, we can look at how
that was happening here, right?
We have some some little bit more work to do to actually get it out
there asset.
We would need it to do something where it actually gets a struct to
fill out the work order and then actually does a platform, a tend to
entry on it.
Like, so.
And that would need
At that priority queue I'd put that in there.
Our asset load Q, something like this.
And this would use that load asset work function.
So there is load asset work.
There is the work order.
There's the cue that it would use.
And what I want to do here is say again, we need to do that sort of
begin tasked with memory thing.
So if we're going to do a begin task with memory like so,
Then if I remember correctly, the task has its own Arena so we can go
ahead and grab that in here.
There's nothing special we have to do there.
The work order for this guy is assets, file name, right?
So it's assets.
Filename and that'll actually be what's handled here, right?
So assets, file name, so
Keep it going.
Almost there.
Again, just not quite enough to make an emac Smacker out of it.
Just a little more than his fun to type in what you gonna do.
Maybe mr.
Fourth dimension will finish his editor and will fix all these things
who knows?
You never know.
All right, so we need to specify the rest of the stuff here.
We got task, what was the other thing that we needed their?
Oh, the ID, right?
So there is the ID.
So if
We go ahead and do that.
Now, Technically, when we go ahead and do this, this debug allocate
stuff that'll happen on the separate thread.
The only thing that we don't really that, that's not particularly good
about that, and you can kind of see it happening here.
Is that if we do this, we put ourselves in a position where
oh, you know what I lied.
I lied.
There are a couple of other things we need here.
There's the alignment stuff.
So not quite we need the alignment.
So we need work file name equals, there we go.
But we also need these guys, right work groups.
So now, it maybe would have been good for new, Max macro see work file
name.
So I'm not going to worry about this just yet, but I want to leave him
here since we did the work of actually figuring out what they were,
right?
I don't want to, I don't want to delete those.
So,
Otherwise we just have to go look at a previous version to get them
back and that's no fun for those of you who source code control, you
know how annoying that is.
Oops.
So that one doesn't have it, I guess.
All right.
Well,
I guess that's another one that does not have any kind of censoring to
it.
This one does though,
so that's really all we need to do to get that jobs fall on the only
thing.
That's a little nasty about this that I don't like right.
Oh, and of course I got to fix this part right here.
Work ID was ID, work tasks equals task work file name, equals nothing
till it's get set.
So, the only thing that's a little bit annoying.
There is, I don't actually want this guy to be playing with the
transient Arena while he's working that.
It's no good.
I don't like that at all.
So what I would rather do here is I would rather have him do something
where he does not actually take the arena.
I'd rather have the loaded bitmap result thing.
Outside right.
I'd rather have it happen here where we do like the bitmap and we do
that push struct.
I'd rather have it happen here where it does assets Arena here because
that way nobody is touching that, that asset Arena multi-threaded
because right now, we don't actually have any kind of synchronization
happening with that Arena.
So I want to make sure that only one thread can ever touch it at once,
and that's not really too much of
a big deal and that also means I can get rid of the other thing that I
was doing here that can go away, which is I can go ahead and make this
guy actually just take that
Just that take that bitmap and right to it directly, right?
So it'll go right to the bitmap directly and then once it's done,
writing to the bitmap directly, I'm also going to make a little to do
here fence.
Then we can go ahead and say oh whatever the assets are now.
Go ahead and make sure that they point to that to that bitmap.
So that's all we really need to do there.
And these guys, now, I believe go away.
Because we can just call debug load bitmap directly on them.
Right?
Just by taking the thread entire file and work file name.
Now, we have to pass that a line X align.
Why eventually so again that'll be our task for tomorrow.
I'm not going to do it now but now I'm just going to go through and
clean up and then we'll call it a day.
So loaded bitmap, there's bitmap
Begin testing a trance state.
Do we have a trance State here?
I guess.
In order to begin a task, we need the trance state.
So I suppose that fine kind of puts us in a position where it seems
kind of clear that the game assets kind of need access to that trance
State kind of annoying.
It's nice to not have to do that but what you gonna do, right?
So we have our our transient State here.
I'm just going to add it in there and we'll make that happen like
that.
So we've got assets game assets, not be filtering.
That's because that's not what I was trying to do.
I wanted a load asset work.
There we go.
Good asset work.
Push size needs to take the arena there and the asset load Q.
I guess it's not such a big deal anymore because we can just now use
the low priority queue for that.
And then finally down here where I do the trance State asset stuff,
which is right here, I'm going to go ahead and make it so that it has
a pointer back to trance State.
Not thrilled about that lot to think about that to do Casey, not
thrilled about this back pointer.
But that's okay.
It's not going to cause us any any real grief.
All right, so this probably won't work because we slammed a lot of
stuff in there at once or just will work.
So, hey, guess what we background load now and happy birthday.
So now all of our assets are streaming, there's a bunch of stuff we
haven't done yet.
As you can tell people are in the wrong position because we haven't
passed their alignment through, but that's just a little bit more
typing that I have to go and do.
There.
You go.
Ask the streaming in an hour.
So really all we have to do, there's no not that much more to it
really.
That's that's most of it.
But we have some things with resource reuse that we have to worry
about.
There's some there's some things in there that are kind of tricky.
So we've got a little more to do but for now we'll go to
Go ahead and go to the Q&A here so we can make that happen.
All right, so anyone has a question please prefix, it with q: and try
to keep the questions to stuff that we just did.
There's a ton of stuff.
I just did there with asset streaming if you have questions.
Now is a good time to ask them.
Robbie says, is it useful when assets can be modified from outside
file on disk over, right?
Maybe even in memory and still work in game.
Is it now supported after an asset is loaded?
As I could not see any call back to check if a file is modified as
your glazing, speed refactoring, was way too fast for me.
So no, we have not added that yet.
I think you're referring to kind of hot loading, right?
That's obviously very easy to add in a system like this, the way that
you do that is you just have
A secondary check that goes through periodically and looks at dates,
you just or the dates of things, then you to reload them.
If you want, we are probably never going to implement that here
because all of our art comes from an artist and the artist isn't
running the game and in fact, the artist can't run the game because
there isn't a game yet.
And so she makes them before.
We actually have the game right now, maybe we should add that sometime
just for fun, but we don't actually have any use for that feature.
So we probably won't implement it till much later.
If we implanted at all, that's just nature.
Right, if
This were a different type of game where I was actually able to work
40 hours a week on it as opposed to having to wait to do it in an
hour.
Long trunks on stream, I would absolutely implement the feature you're
talking about because it doesn't take very long to do.
And then it helps the art artist to do it.
But because the programming is so slow on this game because it can
only go one hour a night.
You know, she's probably has to do a lot of art assets without
actually playing the game if that makes sense.
In load asset work.
Where is the memory for the file name?
Stewart, it is not there, there is no memory used for the file names
in addition to just their the string
Since.
So, those string constants are just they're just being used in C++,
right?
They're stored in the in the executable and they get loaded in as part
of the executable and they get used as front of the executable.
So there is no storage for for that.
These will go away eventually because once we have an asset pack,
there won't really be file names anymore.
So even if we did have to store space for them, you wouldn't really
have to think about it too much if you
wanted to store them.
Anyway, it'd be pretty easy to do.
So what you would do here is you just have the file name right here.
You just push it onto the task Arena.
So, you know, in fact, I'll just do that for you.
So you can see right.
We have a task Arena, which is just a little area that scratched base
for the task.
So if you wanted to, you could truly trivially, just go ahead and do
that, right?
That's all you'd have to do, and that pushed in would just be a thing
that copies the string on there, but
You don't have to really care about that at the moment.
If we were going to leave those in their long-term, I might do what I
just did permanently just for the sake of our of our code hot reload
because those strings will move and so if there's a background task
loading an asset that string would move and that would cause a
problem.
But since we're not going to leave those things in long-term renet,
that's just not a case we care about fixing
What are the trade-offs to give him?
More power forcing render pushes out of the rendering Q order.
I do not understand the question.
Sorry.
You said, we got assets treating done in an hour, but do we need to do
multiple passes on it if so why.
Yeah, so when I said asset streaming in an hour I'm just kind of being
flippant.
I don't consider us done all we did was the first part of asset
streaming which is to actually get our assets, loading deferred,
right.
But there's a bunch of things we want to do which is how to assets,
get evicted.
So that if we want to run in a fixed amount of memory, like, right
now, we
We can only run if there's enough memory for all the Assets in the
game but I feel like it would be more appropriate for us to be able to
just set a memory budget like say this game runs into and 256
megabytes of memory or a gigabyte of memory or whatever and then the
asset streaming just goes ahead and uses that size and in fix things
when it needs to, right?
There's that.
And then there's also the fact that I was saying, I want to go ahead
and Tackle these guys as well, so that we can have ways of streaming
and more complex objects.
So basically, like the bass extreme,
My stuff is done but I want to do more.
There's more things that I want to add features, right?
I don't that's not all that.
I want out of an asset system.
I want additional features.
Where are you?
Check if an asset
Will you check if an asset is already loaded or not?
If an asset would take a very long time to load?
Would it check if it's loaded again to try to live the asset again?
Not sure if that makes sense.
Yes, so there's a couple things again, that we're not act that were
also not doing it all here in any smart kind of way.
Right?
Which is that when you call load asset, we don't Mark that asset, as
already being sort of loaded to give you a preview of what we're going
to do tomorrow.
We will probably do something like, you know, asset state or
something, right?
And the loaded bitmap will go in here, right?
And, you know it's cute or something.
They'll be like a thing in here.
Will it actually be asked?
It'd probably be more like this asset handle or something like this,
right?
Right.
And so what will actually happen is that when it goes to load an asset
it will Elevate the asset handle to mark it as being queued so that
other people won't launch another task to load it.
Because you're right it'll just try to load it again and you could
fire off multiple tasks right now.
We're kind of Saved by the fact that we have a very small number of
people in our work queue.
So it wouldn't it doesn't, you know, immediately cause this disastrous
problem
of like a bird trying to load 32 trees and we are trying to draw 32
trees and we loaded the tree 32 times but yes that's that's exactly
the way that we will do that.
Also can let me make sure
Yeah, I said I didn't want to make sure that I left the code and
compiling state.
Do you consider terrain and asset to so that it can stream?
Well, our terrain is is dynamically generated.
So
I mean it's kind of a separate.
It's not loaded in that way.
Constantinople asks about just the way that I structure my ifs.
He was saying why do it this way instead of just doing it this way.
Right.
Same.
Same basic idea, right?
The reason that I never ever, ever ever write code that way, I think
you have probably seen me do a lot of coding now.
And you've never seen me do that.
The reason is because I always like to have a clear exit point from a
function.
So that if I have things I want to add to the function when it is
done, I know that they always will happen.
And I don't have to worry about if someone put a little bungee pit in
here to thwart Me by returning out from the middle and it won't
happen, right?
So I never ever, ever use that other format.
Let's see.
What are the trade-offs to give the rendering Cube?
More power forcing render pushes out of the ready queue order when it
is multi-threaded.
So the rendering can be controlled more 500.
Okay.
Okay, okay, I think well, I think I understand what the question is
now.
So, I'll answer the question.
I think you're asking because it's a good question.
If this isn't the question please, please rephrase it.
One more time and we'll see if I can get it that time.
Well, I think you're saying is okay, we have threads, right?
And those threads are doing work, but there's a lot of different work
to do.
For example, there's threads that are rendering the game.
So they're, they're trying to make the images that were using, right?
We have the rendering threaded.
There are there threads
Are doing background work like composing ground tiles and now asset
loading.
And so the question is like what what are we going to do to like
balance that and like what can the render queue?
Can we have the render queue maybe take threads when it needs them to
get more rendering, power, whatever?
And So my answer to that is I don't know that.
I don't really know.
That there's all that much.
We really want to do there because at the end of the day you know the
performance of the renderer seems pretty good.
I don't know that it has to do a lot of work stealing and when we
want, if we really find ourselves in a position where we need that
performance boost, we have the GPU, right?
We aren't even using the GPU yet in the system because our software
under was so darn fast.
And so, you know I think maybe
It would be better to concentrate our task stuff on, not on having the
renderer be something that steals tasks.
I think that may just be kind of a waste of time even though if we
were going to Target software rendering as our primary shipping
platform, maybe that would make sense.
So I don't know.
I don't really have a lot more thoughts on it at the moment beyond
what I said, previously, on other streams.
How much of the DirectX opengl typical pipeline?
Are you preemptively?
Designing into your code now, none actually.
If for no other reason that no one's going to be programming DirectX
or opengl in a year, right?
They're all going to be using Vulcan d3d, 12 or metal, right?
So, the DirectX opengl typical pipeline is, is gone.
It, it's out in the back waiting to be put down.
Any other questions that are on topic?
I will answer some off-topic ones here that I see if no one has any.
I don't see any other on topic one.
So, so I'll answer, there are a couple of programming questions on
here that we're not on topic.
So somebody said, what do you think about Microsoft's Vector call as a
calling convention for Speed?
I don't think I've looked at Vector call specifically.
I am happy to do.
So, what is that?
Calling convention?
Hello.
Okay, ventricles knife is artist.
Two functions are used to faster registers when possible.
Well yeah, I mean
That's fine.
So, so all this is, is normally the x64 calling convention, already,
specifies.
That arguments are passed in registers, but only up to a point.
And so really, it's about the trade-off between leaving registers free
and, you know, whether you have to save, restore them stuff like that.
I usually find that this sort of stuff is just not that, interesting,
right?
Like why are you making so many function calls that this is going to
be a big deal is usually my
Thinking right?
If the if it's really a big deal that you're calling functions that
often that you gotta worry about the calling convention, I usually
feel like, maybe that code was not structured properly right now.
That's not to say that there aren't circumstances where it could be
true.
So, I'm not trying to say that.
If you use Vector call, you're stupid or something.
That's not true.
I'm just trying to say that my first thought on things like Factor
call is that like usually those tend to be patch ups for situations
that probably shouldn't got yourself into
In the first place, and the coach be restructured that said, like
anything else, if you look at the code and you've determined that, the
problem is stack pushes and pops, and that's why it's slow.
Hey, doctor call me help you, right?
You know, so so yeah but not a lot.
Oops, not a lot to say about that.
It's kind of an old concept.
It's been around for a while.
Is it possible for the OS to lose track of memory that you asked for?
Um,
I guess, I'm not sure how to answer that question.
What I would say is that obviously, if the operating system has a bug,
it could, it could miss fill out the memory, like the page tables.
And then when they get, when your process gets swapped in, it would,
it would have the wrong address layout.
That's certainly possible.
I mean, but if that was the case, you know, everything would crash.
I mean, there's nothing you can do about it, right?
I mean, that's just a straight up bug and it's game over that point.
Could you elaborate on opengl and DirectX death?
Well, I mean there's not a lot to say about it.
Other than the fact that the the models that DirectX and opengl we're
using, we're just somewhat Antiquated in terms of how they map to
Hardware.
They were to their, to based on setting individual pieces of state and
not in in sort of having those things, be more structured.
The
The card actually thinks about them.
And so the reason that Vulcan and direct3d 12 have to happen and, you
know, they're kind of based off of what was happening with mantle, and
then metal, same way is just because they're trying to realign how you
talk to graphics cards to be more like what the graphics card actually
needs to do.
And that way, you eliminate, just a huge amount of overhead that
drivers were previously doing to turn opengl and DirectX calls into
the actual stuff that the graphics card accepts, right?
so,
It's like that is the end of the questions, Maybe.
What would be a good way to expand asset stripping to support,
increasing level of details?
What I'm thinking of is loading a smaller version of the asset first
and then bigger size resources
so if you're yeah, if you're doing that, then what you need to sew
I can I can sort of
Explain that here.
So hopefully we can see what we're going towards here.
Like what we did today, you can kind of extrapolate out words how this
is going to go.
We won't really be dealing with the level of detail thing because
we're a 2d games, so level details and make a whole lot of sense.
But in a 3D game, you would have the situation.
There are actually times that it does make sense in 2D, but I won't go
into those.
So anyway, when you take a look at what's Happening Here, essentially,
you have
People talking about a game asset as just an ID.
And so if you wanted to update this, to be more about getting a
particular level of detail, you would just need to upgrade this notion
so that the asset handle right would also know what level of detail it
was loaded at.
And then when the renderer goes to render, it would say.
What level of detail it was wanted based on the size of the bitmap was
being drawn on the screen.
And then the, the game a
That would go.
Oh, is that the level of detail?
I'm at if yes, just return it.
If no, then cue up a load for the higher level detail.
And if I have a low level of detail return that right?
So it's really pretty straightforward.
Like, there's not a whole lot to it.
Hopefully you can see how that would go.
so,
I recently started from the beginning of the series on 13 at the
moment.
Do you suggest watching all of the q&a's are just going episode to
episode?
I mean I think it probably depends on how well you understood all the
episodes.
If you feel like you totally understood all 13 episodes, you probably
don't need the q&a's because most the time of people ask about the
q&a's is something that happened on that episode of previous episodes.
And so, while there is good information in those q&a's that if you
have the time to watch them, you probably.
Would learn some things, maybe because people sometimes ask questions
that are sort of tangential, like the person you just ask about level
of detail, right?
So that's good.
But if you feel like you have a really solid understanding of what I
did, then just in terms of being able to program handmade hero, you
probably don't need the Q&A is because the stuff that's going to be
about programming your here on there is you've already got it, right?
But if you find yourself, you feel like you're a little shaky that I'd
say, watch the Q&A because people probably asked the questions that
you have.
Right.
And I'll take one last question here because it's kind of funny.
How infuriating is it to deal with massive asset pipelines?
Dealing with dozens of pieces of software on large asset, large AAA
project.
Absolutely infuriating.
It's, it's just awful and because invariably, these these pieces of
suffer are incredibly unwieldy and have all sorts of problems with
them.
And, you know, they don't support running in an easy way.
And they come with all this digital Rights Management nonsense.
So like the build machine, like can't run the thing unless the license
server is on there, but like it's a Linux machine and they don't ship
the thing for that or like, they're just all these really awful things
that happen when you bring software into your pipeline that you didn't
write, like not invented here.
There's a reason for it.
And it's because
Because nowadays the software that you buy is by and large awful, and
is really hard to deal with and comes with a bunch of restrictions
that are hard to work around and yeah, it's just, it's awful.
So you're right.
The answer is very infuriating and I try to keep that stuff to a
minimum.
Now, on the current project we use Photoshop on their next product,
I'm hoping very much to eliminate it.
Because it just causes headaches like everything else.
Fortunately with Photoshop you can read its files directly.
So that gets you out of the business of having to do exporter plugins
and stuff like that.
For 3D software, you're often not so lucky for 3D software often
times, you have to write an exporter that's like welded into that
version of the software and when that version of the software upgrades
you got to redo your export plugins and there's just it's just just
awful.
So yeah, so large AAA projects, you know?
Those devs go through, a lot of crap.
I mean, they Wade through a lot of crap for you, to be able to play
those games and
Yeah, it's not fun.
It is not fun.
All right, looks like we're just about out of time.
So let's go ahead and call it a day.
Let's go ahead and call it a day, that was pretty good work.
Today, background asset streaming in an hour, not bad, got more work
to do on it, but hey, that's going to be, I don't know, a couple days
and we'll have a whole that whole to-do item just gone, right?
It's just out.
So, hey lot easier than the renderer, right?
And again this is why I say it understand why people say it makes your
architecture weird or that it's hardness of, I have no idea like asset
streaming has always been something that you just do and it takes, you
know, a couple hours of work and then you know, maybe there's some
debugging at some point but it's like asset streaming is Trivial.
And yeah, if there's someone out there who knows why it's supposedly
hard?
I don't know.
Maybe it's because you just got too much of a pointer Festival
happening or or
I don't know.
But anyway so hopefully that's good.
We got a little more work to do so it's not as easy as I made it look
today because we do have some other things that we got to do.
So it's a little more complicated than that a few more hours that we
want to put into it.
And so if you'd like to see those, please come back tomorrow.
5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
I'd love to see here and I will show you the other parts that we got
to do to kind of make it a little bit more of a real system.
All right.
As always if you would like to follow along at home, you can pre-order
the game on handmade hero dot-org.
You can pre-order with this handy, little p R2 button and it comes
with all the source code so you can play around with it at home.
I uploaded every night after I'm done so you're always current.
We also have forums you can go ask questions through the episode.
Guide with annotations, you can get ports to Mac and Linux that.
Community members have done.
If you're trying to do that.
We also have a patreon page.
You can support the video series.
If you like what you saw, we're always very much appreciated for
people who subscribe to the patreon.
It's a super nice thing for you to do and we also have the tweetbot
with to schedule at yourself.
You're trying to catch this live and you want to know what Scott is
going to be an advanced.
That's the place to do it.
That's about it.
Thank you very much for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's a pleasure coding with you as always and I hope to see you all
back here tomorrow.
Take it easy, everyone.