Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
Sure, we could a complete game live on stream.
We are actually back after a pretty long break.
We were on our soil, you for a little while and then we did some
streams that were not specifically coding on the game.
We just did some chat stream so I could rest my hands.
And then we also did one where we switched over to for coder and that
was precisely
Detained by the fact that since I was on RSI break, I took that
opportunity to switch over to a Moodle keyboard binding which is still
kind of in progress.
Like I only just did the basic work of switching to a modal keybinding
which is sort of switching to a Moodle version of what I already was
using for my emacs key bindings which is that really the best model
keybinding certainly.
But it's what allows me to keep editing on a daily basis without
losing too.
Much speed over time.
I would like to mutate.
Eight The Binding around a little bit because now that it is modal,
there's things I could do like things from VI, that are cool that I
could borrow like, you know, that are based on the modality that I,
that really maybe wouldn't make a lot of sense before because I didn't
have a Milky binding, I can start using those and I'm not using those
yet.
So, anyway, I switched over to that in trying to do is Middle key.
Bindings in emacs was a nightmare.
There were so many problems with it.
I did get it working and I and I am using it at work right now, but I
wanted to try
Switching over to for coder because Alan Webster who's one of the
people on the stream.
Mr.
Fourth dimension.
If you don't already know, made a pretty cool editor that he's been
working on, in his spare time, he's a student but the editors are
ready better than emacs in a lot of ways.
And mostly the only thing, in fact, the only reason right now that I'm
not using it, even at work is just because there's like a few bugs or
missing.
Think there's like a few little tiny things that have made it so that
I can't quite such over there.
But it's like shockingly good for how long it's been in development
and I'm really pretty excited about it.
So we switched over to it here on handmade Heroes.
So for those of you who didn't follow the streams, that were sort of
not handmade Heroes dreams with just me like going over for a coder
and implementing some features.
Like in the customization thing, that's what this sort of new editor
situation is and so I can sort of show it to you real quickly here.
If we're in a handmade hero, right?
This is the actual editor.
And I made a batch file.
Like we had the old emacs one to load it and essentially, like it
works.
You know, it, it looks like a standard editor.
There's nothing in particular that I think will be confusing to people
on the stream but in general, you know, it's, it's very much does the
same sorts of operations that I typically would have done Ani.
Max.
And
Also allows programming program ability in see, which I've sort of
leaned on pretty heavily.
So there's a for coder Casey file that I've made which is basically
like my C code that does all the things that I wanted it to do to
basically copy what I do in emacs.
So yeah this is basically it's a long-winded way of saying that's
what's going on differently here and this is a program that you can
also get yourself.
So if you want to, follow along with this instead of with emacs you
Can actually type in for a coder to your search window and there's a
patreon page for are here to support Allen's development on it, which
would be awesome if you did.
It's a great editor.
I am really happy about its development and so if you want to support
it, that would be awesome.
But if you support it, even I think at one dollar you get access to it
and if you supported that $5, you get the whole programmability thing
and all that stuff.
There's even a $10 tier for people who are awesome.
And I contributed my config to this.
So if you want to be a supporter of for coder, you can also get my
config included with that at the at the height are so please check
that out.
Like I said, I'm it's, I think it's a really awesome project and it's
it's been really helpful to me.
And I'm really hoping that other people in the community take to it.
So we can sort of have our own editor.
That is sort of nice for us to use and nice for the sorts of things
that we do.
Do as opposed to other things, like Adam, or whatever, which are
clearly targeted at very different way of working and a very different
set of priorities.
So that's really it for the changes other than that.
Nothing is different.
We're just go back to programming handmade here.
Exactly the way that we were the only thing that is going to point out
is in for coder.
I actually kind of I probably should have done this in emacs a long
time ago.
I didn't, I just never got around to it.
But in for a coder since now, I can program in C,
It's really easy for me to add things in emacs.
It was always very laborious for me to add things because I don't
program list natively and I barely know my way around lisp.
So you know if you look at what I did in my emacs config file, it's
this really kind of janky like Casey tries to sort of make lists do
things but he doesn't really know how to program list.
So it's obviously stupid kind of stuff.
But since I know how to program, see, I can always hack something
together and see.
And yeah, maybe it's not going to be the greatest code in the world,
but, you know, it's my editor.
I know the boundaries of what I'm trying to do.
I'm not trying to make some kind of robust code that I'm, you know,
shipping to people or doing whatever.
And so, when I can just open up a C file and edit it my editor, config
and see, that's pretty great.
So, one thing I did really quickly, as I just made this notion of a
prj file, which is literally just a list of
Basically paths so that I could make it so that it would automatically
like load a project for me like load all the files.
So I don't have to
It's like loading the file.
So emacs, I never had the concept of a project.
There's even like Stephanie Max I think to help with that, and I never
did it.
So one thing I wanted to do is just get that into handmade hero.
So in handmade code, I could just do handmade prj as an actual thing.
Of course, I actually, I always forget, I've never actually made a way
to open to create new files for some reason.
In for a coder, there is a command for it and I never bound it to
anything eventually.
I will, when I actually remember, but point being I need something
there to open, there we go.
Okay, so let's see, handmade prj.
So in this project file, all you have to do is list the directories.
You actually care about now in for in handmade hero, we only have one
thing we care about which is this directory, right?
So
Can just say like, oh yeah you know, there's the handmade code
directory and that's it and then you can also do a thing where you can
set the compilation directory.
So, the first line in the file, I think I did is always the
compilation directory, I want to say and so basically like you, this
is where you want to run the build from and this is then everything
else after it was what directories to load.
So it works as kind of nice because I have a couple of different
directors or stuff is in.
And I just
Those directories and everything gets loaded and it's kind of cool.
So anyway like I did that for for for coder and it's just been kind of
nice.
So I wanted to do it for him here even though it's kind of not that
necessary, not as necessary because there's not as much stuff, it's
just kind of nice to have that and then when you load a prj file it
like automatically does that load for you or at least in theory that
was how it was supposed to work.
So I think if I'm correct now and I actually wrote the code properly
then
Whenever the next time you're in here and you run 4head you can kind
of go in and say like okay I'm going to rut load handmade out prj and
then if you look at your buffers their oral pre-populated with all of
the stuff and it looks like H is and CPS I probably should have made
it load bats as well I didn't but you know we could always add that at
some point we want to.
So that's it.
Everything else about it is the same and a lot of its I made pretty
similar to emacs.
So like I said, everything should look pretty familiar when we're
working.
Like
If I hit, you know, the build key it builds on the other side and it
does exactly sort of what you would expect.
So the the difference and this would have been difference on emacs as
well that will take perhaps a little bit of getting used to.
If you're trying to understand what I'm doing on the stream is like I
said, I switched my emacs and then correspondingly for a coder.
I switch them to be, to be modal.
So what that means is that, you know, when I was in emacs, you just
Type keys and you know, the text would come out and then you would
hold down like the control key.
The ALT key and I would push something.
And then that would write like that would actually do the special
function, the idea behind a modal binding is to try to keep your hand
not be doing so much with your hands and so you don't want to have to
ever hold modifiers.
If you don't have to caps lock, I have controlled bound to caps lock
so I don't know.
That control key was particularly bad for you but alt is a real like
bad motion with your thumb, kind of, I suspect.
So I definitely want to get rid of that but since I was going to do it
one way, I just feared get rid of both of them so now it's just
completely modal.
And the way that I have that work is I can go in and out of the mode
and you can see the I change like the
The color of things on the screen to say, which mood I'm in.
So right now, if it's white, I'm in that mode of just like typing and
keys like you would normally but then if I leave that mode now I'm in
a mode where I can issue commands like undo or something or build and
that's all that's happening there.
So you'll see those things change from a color and that that's all
that's happening there.
So again, it's a little bit different than what you're used to but
otherwise there's really no.
Prince, the operations are all the same.
I haven't.
Like I said, even gone in and tried to take advantage of that
modality.
So you'll literally see me doing the exact same operations.
I've been doing in emacs.
The only difference now is I'm doing the modally instead of with the
modifier keys and to that end, you'll have to cut me some slack for
being a slower editor now, because since I've switched key bindings,
it's like, you know, I have to kind of relearn it, so things will go a
little slower than they used to I suspect.
But other than that, that's where
We're at, so if I remember correctly and it's kind of hilarious that I
would even remember correctly.
Considering that it's been a month where we were what we sort of left
off on is I decided that it was a good time to sort of have Hardware
acceleration in the game.
So we have our software renderer which of course we wrote ourselves
and which kind of surprisingly at least to me ran very quickly, it
could even run the cutscenes reasonably dot great.
So we didn't ever really had to address the need for 3D Hardware
acceleration, but then we were sort of like, well, it's probably time
when we're going to do game tuning.
We'd like it to run at 60 frames a second all the time without us
having to stop and optimize our software rasterizer all the time or
things like this.
So, you know, maybe it would be nice if we have the ability to access
Hardware acceleration.
So we did opengl implementation and we pretty much did all of the
stuff to implement opengl for our purposes, which is actually right,
like very simplistic.
There's not very much work that
it has to happen to do that which I kind of showed it just not
particularly involved.
But what we did not ever do is we did not ever actually finish text or
downloads as an actual first class citizen.
So what happens right now is the texture code is just
The placeholder and this means two things and I'm going to go over
them on the Blackboard so that you can understand what they are.
And then there's one thing with getting srgb that will probably do
today as well.
In fact, you know what, how much time do we have?
So we've got, I guess we're Refugee Ministries, we have about 45
minutes, so I'm trying to think of which way we should go because I
probably won't take 45 minutes to get the RGB stuff.
I'm going to do the texture stuff, I think that's probably a better
idea.
So I'm just going to really quickly just explain what was going on
with the textures and you know, because people probably have forgotten
or
Maybe don't even necessarily know some of the stuff that I was needed
to do with them and that they weren't doing and so hopefully we can
kind of get that squared away.
All right.
So what sorry what was it day to 44?
Why is that?
That's a weird color?
Here we go.
All right.
Okay, so what was happening before hand, right?
And you're going to have to kind of pull back into your memory or
pause this and go re-watch the videos.
If you don't remember, you have to pull back into your memory, the GPU
conceptual GPU stuff that we talked about, right?
And specifically, you're going to have to remember the stuff about the
fact that there was GPU memory
and CPU memory.
And these were not necessarily the same thing, right?
Especially when you have a discrete graphics card that's plugged into
a slot, the GPU has a set of memory chips.
They're totally its own, it doesn't, it's not even remotely in the
same physical location as the CPU memory, they're totally separate.
And so what happens is, you know, we go from the disk we load a
texture into CPU memory, but that is not accessible by the GPU.
The GPU is over here, and has to be able to read out of this.
So we need to get the textures onto the GPU.
Somehow have to move be moved over there.
And so there is a degree you know like we talked about immediate mode
versus retain mode.
Things like this there's definitely a degree of retention that happens
with GPU programming.
For this very reason, we cannot send the whole texture down to the GPU
every time because it could be huge, right?
A single one of our plates, for the cutscene could be something like
six megabytes when uncompressed, right?
That's just a lot to send down every time if you're talking about lots
of these different place that I
Go down there, right?
And so, we don't want to just spend all of our time and all of our
bandwidth of the graphics card sending down the same textures over and
over again, it would drastically.
Limit how much textures we could actually use in a given frame because
instead of it being about how much memory is on the graphics card.
It would suddenly be about how much bandwidth can actually go to the
card during a single 60th of a second.
Not what we want.
So in pretty much all ways, you can think of that GPU memory as sort
of like a cash, right?
It's a lot.
Like the way we think about the cash on the CPU, when the CPU is
operating on something, it you want to have all of that stuff there in
the cache so that when its operating on it, it's nice and fast.
It doesn't have to go out to me, remember to get it.
The same is true of GPU memory.
When you're drawing a frame, you want to have all of your Textures in
GPU memory.
That doesn't mean that all the textures for your game are necessary.
The GPR, because you may have too much textures, like, too many actual
images to even fit, like maybe you have 2 gigabytes of images, which
the GPU is only, 1 GB worth of ram.
Well, obviously that's not going to work.
So it's very much like a cashier trying to put the textures that are
relevant to the current, you know, time in the game, the current, you
know, 20 30 frame Horizon, you're trying to make sure all the textures
that are necessary to render that set of frames are actually on the
GPU for
In time for it to work with them and in order to do that, what we need
to do is a have some opinion about what textures need to be in GPU
memory and then have some concept of how to get them down there or at
some point when they're no longer necessary, remove them to make room
for another texter.
Okay, now,
To a certain extent.
Like a regular cash GPU memory can be sort of virtualized in the sense
that you can over.
Subscribe it right?
Meaning I could, if this was one gigabyte, it's entirely possible on
in certain circumstances.
And given the way that opengl specified and stuff like that, I could,
for example, create 4, gigabytes of textures and tell it to the card
and if I did that, what would happen is the driver would sit there and
it would basically try to
Do a sort of best, guess of which, you know, quarter of this 4 GB.
It was going to put on the card.
And then when we invest in Ewa tably, tried to reference a texture,
that wasn't in there, it would pick somebody to evict and then pull
somebody else in.
So it really does work a lot like a cash.
When the driver the driver sitting there will actually start acting
like the cash that be fine.
If this were an application like 3D Studio or something like that,
where we don't care about hitting a hard frame.
Limit.
Then we're talking about wanting to render 60 frames a second and that
have a bunch of study stuttering happening.
All the time.
We want to make sure that the driver is not doing that.
We want to make sure that we are not over subscribing, the texture
memory and that we are knowledgeable about when our textures are going
to be used.
And that we
Them down there before that happens so that we're not in a just like,
oh, darn.
I'm using a texture that I didn't know about yet, right?
Or that I need to get down there.
So that's something that we have to do now.
Unfortunately, graphics cards, don't make this easy for us and this is
a little bit of an unfortunate scenario, which is that this sort of
swapping, where the drivers swaps for you unfortunately, is actually
more efficient in a lot of ways than if you try to do it yourself.
And the reason for that is because you don't actually know the format
in which the driver needs to store the textures in order for the GPU
Texas.
Them.
And what do I mean by this?
Well,
there's something called swiveling.
And we sort of use this term in the past because whistling just really
means rearranging things.
So, in some sense, when we were talking about Cindy programming,
right?
We would talk about things like, oh, there's four lanes of this CMD
and maybe like a typical way of using the word Swizzle might be that
I'm going to like rearranged, you know, some set of these things.
Like this is going to be a swizzle where I do see be a
Something right, where you kind of have see bad.
That's my rapper name.
Maybe so like you can sort of see here.
I start out with some ordering of things and then I rearrange the
order of those things to give me some New Order that's often called
sizzling.
Well swindling happens for textures to and the reason that's whistling
happens for textures is because graphics cards are not set up to
actually to be optimized.
For the case that we actually are talking about in handmade hero in
hand me a hero, we're talking about a bunch of, you know, 2D cards
stacked on top of each other, right?
And the heroes, one of those cards, you know, and trees and stuff or
one of those cards and whatever, right?
And we're always talking about using the entire texture in the order
that it was drawn in exactly as a rectangle on the screen, right?
That's what we're essentially doing.
And so,
Degree to which you would need to do swindling to support that.
Kind of operation is probably not huge.
It doesn't necessarily mean that you couldn't do some sizzling to
help, but we'll get to that in a second.
However, the point that I'm that I want to get to First is just that
what they're normally trying to do is they're normally trying to take,
you know, like a triangle.
And a triangle is like assigned to some region of this texture, right?
Like texture mapping in the traditional sense is pulling out a region
of this and putting it onto a triangle.
That's from a
3D model, right?
So they're very much pulling from Little sections all over the
texture, you know, that really don't have anything to do with using
the whole text.
In fact, a lot of the times, there's no way the whole texture would
get used because part of its on like the back of something that you
can't see the whole of the texture.
On one frame, etc, etc, etc.
There's there's just tons of reasons why a texter is not getting
access to in the same way.
When you're talking about just stamping it down on something versus
when it's wrapped on the surface of a 3D model for actual texture
mapping.
So, in order to best support texture mapping textures are often
Swizzle 'd:wz way that if you were to take the original texture and
you look at it like this, you know, I've got the little Hero on here.
Here it is.
The actual way that it's stored is some totally other way like, you
know, the in memory we think of this as a row, right?
And we think of this as maybe like 0 I guess we did it bottom up or
something, right?
Is how we stored it.
So, like here is the first, here's the pointer to the first pixel and
they go all the way across this row.
And then we come back up here and go all the way across this row,
right?
That's how it's stored in memory.
So it linearly in memory, you'd be reading it this way, right?
I mean, we all know this, we wrote the routines to read and write
them, we didn't implement it all that, right?
That's what we did.
Well, if you think about what happens when you're trying to talk about
a little square here, that might map to a particular triangle, right?
Something like this, if that's what we're talking about and we're not
typically processing, huge runs of things like that.
Then if you think about it, the cache coherency of this texture is not
particularly good.
If I'm only going to talk about grabbing this much of a line typically
when I'm operating on it.
Then what I would rather do is have it more looks toward like this in
memory, right?
Like maybe little squares of textures, right?
That were maybe like four by four or something.
So that when I load 16 pixels, instead of loading a big long line of
16 here, I'm instead loading a little square because the chances of me
using everything from that little square.
When I do that load are much higher, right?
And furthermore, I probably
I am going to use things in this area, right?
Like, if I'm looking at this image, I probably going to use a bunch of
things in this area if I'm using something in this area, but I might
never use anything in this area, right?
If I'm going to use as much stuff in this area, I might never touch
this area.
So they also tend to continues whistling to pack blocks instead of
going in memory this way, they might go.
Like in this this way, like this block, then this block, then this
block, then that block, then this block to try it again.
Max
Some eyes, the chances that were hitting things in the same.
If we're pulling, you know, from from different regions.
It's easier for the memory controller to grab these things out.
Now, to be completely honest with you, I have never studied studied
textures whistling at all.
When I worked on larabee, that was just something, I never actually
saw the texture unit stuff.
I did not know how they did this whistling and I never really looked
into it.
So unfortunately I can't tell you any more than a hand, wavy
explanation like that where I'm like, they're trying to rearrange it
to make memory access and computation easier on the critical path.
Which is sampling textures for triangles.
How that, actually breaks down.
I don't know.
Like, I couldn't tell you the like hard proof of.
Like, here's exactly why.
Here's the exact format their store.
And here's why I don't even know if it's the same from card to card, I
suspect, it probably isn't, I suspect?
There's
Grunts whistle formats depending on which graphics card drawn.
Anyway, what that means is when you submit a texture.
So you have a texture you load up disk and then you hand it over to
opengl.
What's actually going to happen is opengl is going to Swizzle that
texture.
Now maybe that texture gets whistled on the card.
If the card has some way of swindling, the texture on it, meaning it
can do the remapping but maybe it doesn't.
And so what that means is this CPU itself actually has to rearrange
all that.
Memory at a very expensive cost, right?
It has to actually go touch, all that memory and move it all around.
So what that means is, if you've submitted a texture to opengl, even
if it didn't go to the card, it has gone through the swiveling stage
and could remain in memory priests whistled, which saves time on the
transfer because instead of having to Swizzle and transfer, it just
has to transfer memory, that's already been swindled.
So unfortunately even though we do want to get rid of this, because
it's a bit unpredictable.
We do lose something because that how dismissal the texture is not
exposed to us.
I wish it was.
I wish they had formalized that sometime in the past couple years and
said, here is how everything will be swindled so that when you do your
own stuff on the CPU side you can just submit pre-social textures.
I don't think they have.
Even if they have plenty of grass cards, in circulation, don't have
any sort of thing like that, so I don't really think there's much you
can do at least at this stage in the game but okay.
Now.
We may get away with not having that because we are using rectangular
textures.
Which are tend to be treated somewhat differently in graphics cards
Square textures are the more common thing or more particularly not
square at or not rectangular I should say power of 2 and non power of
2.
So, most textures that you would use on a graphics card for mapping
onto a 3D model, our power of 2.
And what that means is simply that the sides are a power of 2 in
length.
So if I was to, you know, draw you one of these it would always be
like 256 by 256, or 512 by 256, right?
So doesn't it can be a rectangle but
Actual Dimension is 2 to some power and never anything else.
It's never going to be 540, right?
It's gonna be 512 or 1024, but it's not going to be this.
Originally, that's all that grabs card supported originally gravis
cards.
Could literally not do any other shape nowadays, they do and certain
ones supported more than others, like some actually secretly end up
using a power of two texture anyway.
And just don't tell you about it in the space is wasted other of them.
I think actually do.
But either way, I want to say that the rectangular texture paths
nowadays, don't go through the same kind of sizzling and may not have
as much.
Cost associated with them.
And the reason for that is, of course, that they are expecting it to
be something like a video, download or something, where you're trying
to send over a thing that you're going to rectilinear blit.
And you want to try a say the time on the submission and be, you're
not going to be wrapping around a 3D model anyway, and blah, blah,
blah?
I don't know.
That's all minutiae that, like, only people who follow GPS tough, very
closely could tell you.
And, you know, if there's someone on the street who happens to be a
GPU expert, that's up on the way that they currently work.
They could fill you in.
If not, none of this really matters too much, we're doing, this is
only, if you're going to be one of those people who's a serious
serious GPU, programmer, all of these things are things that you
should know.
Right?
If we, if, you know, if I was a serious GPU programmer, kind of guy, I
would know these things, or at least, I should say, if I had a GPU
person on my team, I'd expect them to be up on all this stuff, if
you're a generalist and you don't have to deal with like squeezing
every bit of performance out of a GPU, then you'd really don't have to
know this stuff.
It's good to be aware so that when the time comes and you do have a
little something that needs to get tuned or whatever, your you kind of
have some idea what's going on.
And then you could ask the specifics.
You can ask someone from Nvidia, someone from ATI, whatever.
You can say, hey, yeah, I kind of remember the rectangle texture thing
and I was wondering, is there what's going on in there?
My, I seem to they don't seem to be downloading the fast they could,
is it's literally problem.
You know, just having an idea that something that might be happening,
is really all you need to probably know as a generalist if that makes
sense.
Okay, so anyway, so that's essentially the situation and so we have to
do is figure out a better way to deal with this.
Then what we're dealing with what we're doing right now because all
we're doing right now is when it comes time to draw.
We just look to see whether we've ever submitted a particular bitmap
that we have in our asset store.
If we've never submitted it, we submit it and we draw it.
Otherwise, we just used the handle that we've used before.
There's two problems with this, and they both need to get fixed
problem.
Number one is, it's, you know, just too late, right?
Meaning we only do this when we actually go to draw.
So, if we have some huge texture here, that's like, you know, some 20,
I don't remember what they were other 1920 by 1080 right or more,
right?
So we have some big 1920 by 1080.
Graphic that was for the cutscene that we want to draw here, right?
It's like the house.
Or whatever.
I don't know what it is.
We want to draw that.
We co it hasn't downloaded.
We download it right there and draw it right there.
What that means is it creates this sort of bubble where the graphics
card can't start rendering the current frame.
That it's supposed to be rendering that we're like, we need you to run
to this right now.
It can't start rendering that current frame until after it finishes
downloading this gigantic 6, MB texture or something.
Now, that's a real big problem for and I'm actually might be an 8 MB
texture.
What is I, don't remember how much that is.
How much is that 1920 by 1080 by 4 8 megabytes?
So we sent down this 8 MB texture and we're sitting there.
Waiting for the grass.
Try to transfer it before the graphics card can ever even start
rendering that frame.
And that's no good.
What we would rather do is, we'd rather have the graphics card be
transferring this.
While we're drawing frames, we do have the textures for such that when
we get to a frame where we don't have the textures, it will have had
that whole time to put it in.
And hopefully by the time we get to that frame the textures there.
It's exactly analogous to what we were doing with our assets, where we
load them off disk.
And this is just another step in the process.
So before, you know, we
The thing where we've got the disc version of the texture, we've got
the memory version of the texture and then we've got the screen,
right?
And we were just like, okay disc fills to memory, memory fills to
screen.
This is instant, and we do it on every frame, this takes time.
So we overlapped it on a thread.
All we're talking about now is essentially there's another step in
this process, right?
It's the GPU.
We've got to get the texture into the GPU or we could open the
windows, start menu, always fun.
Yeah, so we've got to get into the GPU and this is also not instant.
So what we want to do is if possible put this on a thread as well,
So that's what we're trying to do.
Now.
There was a time when this was more or less impossible.
Like, if you tried to thread a texture, download, you haven't helped
you.
It was not going to work, don't try disaster and and off you go
nowadays, most people try to stream, textures down to the GPU
dynamically because essentially, it really reduces load times.
And also drastically increases.
The amount of detail that you could have because obviously, you can
have a
Any 7 GB Game or something like this where you're free roaming around.
You need to be updating these textures because the graphics card might
only have 512 Meg's or GB on it, right?
A lot of that's taken up with textures.
So nowadays while it's not easy to do ever to ship anything on a GPU
and windows, because you have tons of driver compatibility problems.
Anyway, while it's not easy to ship threaded texture, download it's
not so much more difficult than anything else to get, right?
Which is to say that it's not that hard potentially to get it working
on your machine and then when you go to ship it on Steam, everyone and
their grandmother has a problem with their 12 year old driver.
Her and they're weird graphics card that they overclocked and
everything else, right?
So now, on the PC, it is generally possible to thread on most systems
and you are not necessarily opening yourself up.
As far as I know, anyway, in my my understanding, you're not opening
ourselves up to drastically more driver compatibility bugs than you
already.
Were going to have anyway.
However, unfortunately, that number is still probably quite High
because yeah, drivers and windows drivers and
They conspire to help you.
So anyway,
That's the situation as as we kind of have to deal with it.
That's the primary problem and solve the secondary problem that we had
to solve.
And we read pretty much get this.
I think for free by anything that we do that addresses, this is it
right now.
We're never removing anything from texture memory and what that means
Is that depending on how much text remember, you had we're just going
to keep on filling it up and eventually we might overflow it or worse
yet.
Right now, we have an eviction scheme for our CPU memory for textures,
right?
Like, we're loading in various bitmaps from the asset store when we
evict an asset from the storage.
We never go back and delete its corresponding texture, right?
Because we just did the little hack.
To get this working, right?
So what will happen now?
And like I said we don't really have to think about this as a separate
thing.
I just want people to understand it was happening.
Because when we do this, it would fix it.
But what's happening right now is we have a fixed size CPU asset
store, right?
And then we have our GPU texture memory.
So, what will happen is, we'll fill, you know, texture able coming
here, will do Phil.
Here's the disc that is coming off, textured be will come in here
texture.
See, will come in here.
And every time we're drawing, we're sending these down to the GPU if
they're not there, right?
And they're not.
So they all go down.
Now, the next,
And we draw for children with a b and c, that's all great.
But now we get d.
Right, here's a b and c and d on disk.
Now we get D weld.
He's got nowhere to go because the CPU cache is full, there's no room
for the asset anywhere so it might decide.
Well.
Okay we're gonna, you know, we have that least recently used kind of
thing going on in there.
So it's just like, let's get rid of B because we don't need it.
We're not going to use it.
We haven't used it for several frames.
Now, let's just get rid of being.
We'll put
It's place so be gets removed and D gets put in its place, our CPU
side, memory stuff works nicely, we debugged it and it works so that
just happens but it never tells the GPU that it did that.
So this is still here.
So Wendy comes in, it gets added to the GPU memory, which eventually,
you know, just keeps filling up that GPU memory till it's completely
out if this was where it was now, the driver has to keep backing store
of this thing, which further fills up main memory until all the
Main memory is gone.
And then if you're just done, you're just out of texture memory and
you'll just get gray images or something, right?
So we have a situation that would be untenable in the game right now
anyway.
So at a bare minimum, if we wanted to ship what we have now without
doing something, that was a little more coherent for prepping the GPU,
we would, at least have to add something to our asset code.
That said, whenever we evict an asset from the CPU site asset store,
we also have to evicted from the GPU side asset store.
Which brings us to one more point that is probably worth mentioning.
So right now if you remember the way our CPU asset store works is,
it's essentially a general-purpose allocator like it just puts things
in and then when it frees something it remembers that it's free.
And if you free enough stuff again to make space for another asset,
It'll like use that up, right?
It'll then put something in there but that's what we have right now
and that's it's not particularly well implemented, right?
We put it in there and I said, this is just a basic thing.
This is not a very good allocate.
We're going to save this till we actually have some performance stuff
to run through it and then we'll see if there's anything smarter that
we want to do there.
Because again, you don't really want to over engineer, something like
that because you don't know what it's demands are.
And if you try to over engineer up before, you're actually running
your game through it, you might make bad decisions and you have to
throw away, all that work because it turns out that what you did was
not smart.
It doesn't solve the problem that you actually end up having.
So you don't want to do something like performance upper, optimize
your CPU asset store until you actually know how you used your CPU SS
store.
Kind of obvious, basic programming principle.
Premature optimization is the root of all evil.
I think is the knuth quote perhaps and that is sort of what I'm saying
here.
It's like you don't want to start optimizing something till you
actually know a, whether you need to optimize it unless you're just
trying to do it for fun in which case fine.
But more importantly, if you are gonna spend the time out doing
something, even if you are just doing it for fun, you need to pick the
point in the project where you actually have the data that you can use
to optimize a properly, and we are nowhere near that, right?
We just don't even know until the game is.
Totally Running and you're actually playing it and doing whatever you
don't want to do something like that.
So that's where CP U.
S-- is Taurus.
The GPU asset store.
Obviously also a general purpose out here that GPU the driver
micromanages, this, right?
And like uses regions and the same sort of stuff that we're doing
here.
If we did not do any software rendering, we could turn our CPU asset
store into a fixed size, free list based allocator and it would be
100% efficient because all it would have to store is the handle that
the GPU gave us back for where we put the actual texture.
So what that sort of means, is, if we want to in the future, if we
don't care about how well our assets or performs under software
rendering because at the end of the day software, rendering is purely
an educational feature, like, we don't really need it for anything.
We're always going to run through GPU if it's there because it's going
to be faster, right?
What we could decide to do is change the CPU asset store to actually
just be a fixed size out.
Later that just holds the handle for the GPU side and then what we
would do is just use like virtual lock and virtual free at the OS
layer to allocate and free the size of our things.
If we are on the software renderer because it's we don't care.
That means we don't have to bother actually doing any sort of
optimization for that thing.
So, in some sense,
That might be the right thing to do and we might want to eventually do
that and the reason for that is you don't want to Stack a
general-purpose allocator on top of another general-purpose allocator.
If the driver already is going to do it and we can't stop it.
We might as well, right?
So,
That.
Is that?
All right, so I think that's just about everything that I wanted to
say about texture downloading.
So what we need to do now is put ourselves in some position that we
can start to download these sectors on a separate thread and then use
them in the main thread, right?
So we need some way of sort of getting that feeling to happen and
thankfully for us we already have our loading threaded and we know
that every time we load a texture we want to send it to the GPU at
least at the moment that seems like something that we would want.
To do because if we thought we were going to need it, we pretty much
want to get it to the GPU as fast as possible.
So what we can do is just start to look at that code and see if we can
formulate a good plan for how we're going to make that start to work.
We only have 15 minutes left.
Sir probably not going to implement very much.
But as was anything on handmade hero, anytime?
We're about to do a complex topic, we cannot spend some time with the
white board.
So whatever is on the same page.
You know what we're about to do, instead of just seeing a bunch of
code whizzing around.
So,
All right, here we are in handy, dot CPP, kind of good to be back in
the code base.
And if you remember properly, we have this opengl file and here is
where that stuff that I was talking about, actually takes place.
So if you look in here under render entry bitmap, you can see what I'm
actually talking about.
When I say that we just kind of did this just in time, hacky thing.
Like I said, you may not remember it.
But GL binds texture here.
This is the thing that says we're going to be drawing with this
texture and you can see that what it is predicated on is the fact that
the
Map that we're going to draw, has a handle associated with it.
That handle is the thing that the driver gave us back when we
submitted it.
So if we have one of those, we just bind it and say, hey graphics
card, you already have the section.
We're going to use a section of drawing a second.
So get ready on the other hand.
If we find that there is no handle that means we have to actually bind
a new texture and send it down.
We asked it to do that.
And then we submit the texture.
So this is actually right here, the part that I'm concerned about
again.
There's the part about never freeing them, that's obviously something
that's separate but what I'm talking about when I'm saying
overlapping, the texture download, this is the part we're talking
about this text image to D, is taking the memory for our texture.
So all of that stuff that we loaded into memory off of the drive,
we're trying to submit that down to the graphics card and we don't
know how long that's going to take and we want to give that the
Not only can, we don't want that to potentially cause a hiccup.
If we have to do a bunch of these, we want those to be overlapped.
And what we also know is a lot of modern graphics cards.
Everything, probably from a G4S 500 model and up for example, around
that time, period.
So quite some time ago, I mean they're on like G4S 900 now, right?
Or something like this.
So quite a while ago they have things on them called copy engines and
those copy engines are actually pieces of the graphics card that are
that do nothing other than transfer stuff like textures over to the
graphics card asynchronously while the graphics card is doing other
things.
So
We know that there's plenty there for us to take advantage of and that
we can, we are not like interrupting, the rendering of our frame by
asking the graphics hard to do this transfer on lots of different
Modern Hardware.
It's actually set up to do exactly this.
So,
What we want to do is figure out a way to move this GL text, image 2D
out to somewhere where it can actually happen in an asynchronous
fashion and this is going to turn out to be a lot more difficult than
you might think.
And a lot of that has to do with the fact that the opengl API was not
designed with anything like this in mind.
And so the way that you end up doing it is kind of a little bit janky
but
So back to a little bit more of a fresher, if we go into our handmade
asset that CPP, then you know that we've got sort of this, this
concept here of the asynchronous loading and you can kind of go in and
see, we've got like, like load bitmap here, right?
And this is the code that gets executed when we need to load one.
You can see what happens.
We say,
Okay, I need you to like to sort of create this job like this this
sort of work structure.
We called it right like that asset work.
And I here's all the information you need to go get off the off of our
out of our asset file.
Here's this information.
You need to go and load that asset, right?
And so then it calls dispatches up to here to load asset work
directly, I believe is the is the actual dispatch, right?
Because here's the load asset work, and it just calls
Is that load s at work directly?
So if we call, if we look at load a server directly, we can see what
happens.
All it does is first it reads the chunk out of the file that we want
it and then it looks to see if it was able to do.
So what would it actually need to do in order to finish making this
asset like usable?
And you can see that for a font there's some stuff that it actually
had to do so we were already in a position to say
If this was a bitmap do some extra stuff like submit GL, text image
2D.
So we are actually we put ourselves already in a very nice position to
write this code properly because what we can say here is like I want
you to do a finalized asset, you know, texture on this thing or
something.
We'll call it image or bitmap because I think we'd want to just keep
using that terminology rather than use the graphics card one.
But if I come down here and say like okay, you know, in this case I've
got
Another thing that I want to do, when I have to finalize something,
then what I, what I need to figure out is some way to move that GL
text, image to D over here, to this other thread.
So in a world where we didn't have like all this driver complexity and
whatever we would be able to do exactly this because if you look at it
we've actually got essentially all of the information that we need
right there.
There isn't like we have the width, we have the height, we know it's
be gra, we know it's unsigned byte we have the memory so we have
everything that we had here.
Right.
That's all the same in the the GL, I forget what it is that GL Tech.
Where is that thing?
There's a default internal texture format, see your default default.
Internal checks in for Matt.
Yeah, that's just some arbitrary thing that we defined and so we could
we just need some way of like, passing this piece of information down
about whether or not we want it to be srgb or RGB.
And that just depends on whether we saw the extension.
So we have one piece of information that we'd have to conduit in here.
That's not particularly hard.
It's something that gets set once.
There's actually no race conditions accessing it.
So it's threading threaded access to a thing that's essentially
constant.
We don't have to worry about it at all so we can fix that no problem.
What we can't fix.
Is the fact that this GL text image, 2D has no notion of where or when
or why it's executing.
Because if you remember, when we talked about how opengl works,
there's essentially a opengl context, associated with every thread.
And when you issue one of these calls, like GL text image to D, what
it's doing, is this looking up in the thread-local storage?
What context that is
And executing things on that context, opengl does not allow the same
context to be active on two threads at once.
So the main thread, which is calling these GL text operator, these GL
drawing operations
cannot be using the same context as this so we can't just call GL text
image to d right here and expect it to work.
It will totally fail, right?
It will not work at all and just to kind of underscore that I'll go
ahead and show you what I mean.
I guess we also probably want to do this, huh?
So let's say, we move all this stuff out there, right?
This is all going to be out there.
So when we come through here, we would just do instead of this, if
entry bitmap handle stuff, we would just always bind the bitmap
handle.
We just always find it.
If it happens to be 0, that just means that this texture isn't there
yet?
Which means that we won't draw anything, which is fine.
That just means the asset.
Wasn't there, we missed the cash.
What are you going to do, right?
We could choose to stall at this point, right?
We could choose to hold the frame to do Casey, you know, hold the
frame.
If we are not.
Ready with the texter.
So, we could choose do that in the future.
If you want to or we could say 60 frames a second, is more important
than having everything lasting draw properly.
So just don't and it's always go.
Right, we could do that.
But then the code essentially looks like this and now this code is
over here.
So again, two problems with this first problem is, we don't want to be
calling GL code in the middle of our of our code path here, right?
Because for all we know we're not even running on opengl, right?
So we want to have something here.
We need this to be a little more clean and we need this to be a little
more platforms separated.
We had all our open GL code, kind of isolated we want to keep that
being true.
So really what we're going to have to do is sort of pull this out and
make it a little more isolated first.
That's obviously going to have to happen.
Ian butt.
Beyond that, what we need to do is figure out some way to make an
additional to make an opengl context that this thing can actually use
to download the texture.
So we need to do that as well.
That's what we need.
You and we have seven minutes, so forget it's not even remotely going
to happen but we can start, we can get a little further.
So, let's talk about what happened in here.
I don't know if we actually put the make, I don't think we did right?
Because the wiggle code should be in win32.
Yeah, here we go.
So, win32 handmade dot CPP.
We have the wiggle make current
Or we should.
Oh wait.
That's the H file my bad?
so we go make current
here is we go make current
You can see this is our opengl startup code and so what we did with
the opengl startup code, as we said, all right, we need to create a
context and then we did what was called context Exploration with our
beliefs, what I call concentration, which is saying when and I'm not
going to spend all that again because we have a whole episode about it
but basically we start out with an opengl one point.
Next contacts we want an opengl more modern, one opengl 3.0 so then we
escalate to and opengl 3.0 context and Africa.
Right now when we did this
Yes, I sort of hinted at the thing that we would eventually have to
do, which is that when we do this wiggle, create context of trips are
right.
You can see that there's this thing called the share context.
The share context is saying when I create a context, I may want to
create another context who shares memory with this other context.
So that if I download a texture to one of them, it's accessible in
either.
And that's exactly what we want to do.
So all we need to do to start setting ourselves up for calling GL.
XO image on a separate thread is make sure that any thread that could
call GL text.
Image 2D has a context that is shared with our context and then all of
them can be downloading textures and we would necessarily have a
problem now.
Whether the driver freaks out if we have four threads trying to
download text at the same time, I don't know, we're certainly going to
find out, but there's no technical reason why we shouldn't be able to
do it if the drivers written properly, then that would work.
So if we take a look at when we do our create thread, and I'm sorry
that I'm jumping around here a little bit,
But a lot of pieces come into play here.
So I'm just trying to give you what they all are.
You can see that when we do win three to make you you asked for a
thread count and we go through each of the threads, creating a new
thread, which goes ahead and calls into the thread proc.
And that thread proc is the thing that sits there and waits for a work
queue entry every time that it basically sits there waiting for work
to do.
Now, when it gets work to do, it will do that work.
And when it does that work, one of the pieces of work.
It might do is to call through here and call finalize as a bitmap.
Which means that any thread that is created on our work system needs
to have an opengl context associated with it.
Otherwise the GL
Image 2D call Will Fail.
So what we need to do here before any thread proc actually goes into
service, we need to make sure that it has created its own context.
So we need to do something here.
Like win32 create opengl context for worker thread.
Once we have that then these threads will be able to perform those
downloads.
Now we don't actually want them to perform the downloads directly here
like I said because we probably don't want opengl code sitting in the
middle of our otherwise platform independent code.
But that is a problem.
We can easily solve later by having this code, either use something
that calls the platform where to download, or we can do something even
more ridiculous.
In fact,
You know, this might be the better thing to do and I don't really
know.
So, the other thing we could do is actually just put this on a cue for
another thread to download and have it picked up.
It just seems like too complicated, so I feel like this is probably
the better way to go and we'll see.
Alright.
So what we would do is we'd say, hey create an opengl context is so we
know that it's already set up for that.
And then when it comes through here, to finalize bitmap, it knows that
it will always work properly, right?
Okay, so let's go ahead and see what we would need to do for that.
So I'm going to go ahead and take this guy here and take a look at
that wiggle.
Make current
So, here we are.
And here's our win32 in opengl.
So what we need is essentially another one of these, right?
We need one of these.
We're all it's going to do is it's going to do this, right?
It's literally just going to do just this one part right here, and
that's all
Like I said, you have to bear with me on the editor, I'm still
learning the modal.
Like I'm still learning the modal ropes if you will.
So when three to create up until context for worker thread, it just
needs to come in here and do exactly this thing.
Where, instead of passing the sugar context of 0, I'm going to
actually say that it you know you just need to tell me what that share
contacts actually is and then you know I would I would be all set,
right?
We would just do exactly this and off we go.
Now the window DC part, I don't actually know whether we need to ever
pass this window.
Do you see, we certainly could pass the window DC, but since this kind
of can never draw to window DC.
I don't actually know if it's more appropriate to actually just use 0
for it.
I couldn't tell you like I feel like you would probably want to do
something more like this and
Again, I'm not 100% sure.
Totally honest with you.
So what I would say is we probably want to check
For example, I have a particular presentation in mind.
And we just want to see what they would recommend.
Because basically, any time your program, your GPU, you want to see
what the graphs card, vendor people say, because that's usually the
best, the best option, right?
So, let's see.
So to them, it would appear that they want to pass the windy see,
right?
And so because that's what they're saying, I'm just going to assume
that that's the right thing to do.
And then it sets it up in the right position this, by the way, is
presentation specifically about this, about the copy engines on the
fair me and up, which you could look for if you want to know more
about asynchronous texture transfers, right?
So anyway so we we
You want to do this, we do want to have the windy, see in there, so
we're going to have to pass those two things to this, which means that
we actually need some way of getting them.
Now, we know that we can always get the DC of our window.
So, in theory, we could even save the DC of our window because if I
remember correctly, we actually do CS own DC.
So we actually always have the DC of our of our, we know.
Anyway, the point being
If we do this, if we have the window see and the sure context, then
all that's missing is those a trips?
So these art ribs, we can just move out, right?
And and save them because we know we want them to pretty much always
be the same.
I think.
So if I just put those guys out here and we call this, you know, win32
open Jill at ribs.
We can just make that be something that everyone has access to.
It looks like I'm out of time.
So we'll probably have to stop for today.
Which is fine.
All right, so we've got our went through to open till at ribs this
down here.
Should also be the win32 opengl at ribs.
And I think that's pretty much all there is to it.
Now, if the wiggle make current doesn't succeed, then there really
nothing we can probably do about that.
I mean if for some reason, it doesn't want to create another one for
us.
I think this is probably just going to be like a fatal error scenario.
I mean the game just if we can't get a download context there's really
nothing we're going to be able to do.
I mean we could try to engineer some kind of crazy backup path for it.
But on the whole I think it would be pretty important.
Possible.
So anyway, this is really what we need to do, and once we have this
such that, we've got our open gel DC set for every one of those
contexts.
We're pretty much good to go.
So we just need to save this in this, these pieces of
Formation.
I think we might have a global window handle.
I can't quite remember whether we do or whether we don't though, do
we?
Let's see, I guess we don't so it looks like we never actually store
that unfortunately.
So what I guess I would say is maybe we want to just go ahead and be
relatively careful about this and go ahead and pass it through a
little more cleanly.
So what we would do for that is where we call create window.
PX.
Which is here.
You can see us creating our window.
Now, when we create our Q is a little bit earlier, we've got this test
code up here and we do our make you stuff.
What we can do.
I believe I don't think there's really any reason that we would need
to do it at a different time.
So I believe what we could do is move the cue creation down such that
when we make the queue we could we could have the window handle ready.
So when
Create this window we could go ahead and create the cues afterwards
such that when we create the Q, we are in a position to pass the
window actually to it and we could even initialize the opengl I guess.
I don't know if we can initialize the open till after.
Or before before or after the toggle full screen.
I think we could do it at either time.
But yeah, I guess we can even move this down even further, right?
So we've initialized opengl here.
And when we initialize opengl, we could just pass the HCL RSC.
This is the opengl RC
And then these guys can get that past.
So when we call make you, in this case, I believe the low priority
queue is the one we're concerned about.
There's two of them and so here, I can pass the opengl RC and the
window handle like so.
And this one could just have those be sort of nullified out, if that
makes sense.
So that would be the signal that it doesn't ever actually need to do
that.
And if we go, so let's say that that
True.
In fact, let's let's I know I'm over time here but, you know, we
haven't done handmade here in a while, so I feel like I'm entitled to
a little extra programming time.
Let's just do one last thing.
So all I wanted to do here with say that when we actually do create
that, so when we do our win32 make you obviously the thing that has to
do the we're going to make current is actually the thread proc and we
have this this parameter, which is the platform where Q thing does the
cue on it, right?
It sets this stuff up.
That's the thing that we actually want to probably put the data in.
Right.
We probably want to put the data in there.
The platform work queue though.
I guess it's not really a win32 thing.
I don't think it's not defined in the winter to layer if I'm not
mistaken like platform where Q is not a thing that makes sense.
So what we probably want to do is actually extend that notion a little
bit
And see that there's actually another piece of information there,
right?
Another like thing on top of it.
And so what I'm going to do is say okay there's you know, struct win32
thread startup or something like this and in there will have stuff
like platform work queue.
But then we'll also have the window handle and the opengl RC.
Here we go.
Make sense.
So that's our, you know, that's our game plan anyway with that.
And so then when I'm in here, I can make one of these guys went
through threads win32 thread startup, and I'll just call this thread
startup.
And in this case, we'll just pass the thread startup.
Code with nothing in it.
And in this case, we'll pass the thread startup code with something in
it.
There we go.
So we've got thread start up that window, red startup dot opengl.
I see.
so,
Now, we're in position 2.
Excuse me.
I don't know why.
I feel the need to type that whole thing in.
Now, we're in position to have this guy.
Fill out the startup structure.
So basically, if startup and in fact, we know we always need one.
so if we're past the startup in it,
You know, I think we are always passed one.
Never mind.
We were always passing.
Yeah.
So now when we go ahead and do this whole Q thing, right?
And we passed the platform work queue thing there.
Oh and now that I think about it I guess this stuff actually kind of
comes in like automatically so we don't even need that part of it so
the Q can just come off of the start up like so.
And then that startup will just get passed through directly.
So instead of, passing the Q handle here, we passed the startup and
excuse me.
And then when the thread block actually does this and it gets the L PP
parameter thing out here, then that LP parameter is actually a win32.
It's the last it this still has to be.
I have to make.
So that we actually use a fixed one because obviously each time
through the stuff's going to get grabbed out of there.
So it actually needs to be different for every thread.
If that makes sense because we don't know that it's actually gotten
the information out of there yet.
So in order to pass that extra information through but this tends to
be a real pain for passing this information through.
I feel like this actually introduces more bugs than I thought we were
going to say by doing it because I would actually need each of them to
have their own one.
Otherwise you can't
Don't Go Changing it, right?
So maybe that's actually dumb.
Now that I think about it.
Maybe we don't actually want this to be the case, maybe that's just
stupid and maybe the better way to do it is just to say, like, hey
those are actually just Global last variables if that makes sense,
because all of a sudden, it seems like that's actually a lot, a lot
uglier.
That makes some sense.
So here, if we did something, like, before we make these work use, we
say like global
and Jill are C equals 132 and it opengl
and like, you know, Global DC equals get to see window.
That's totally.
That's probably actually.
Just ironically quite a bit safer.
It seems so maybe we will do it that way.
Let's take a look.
So up here, we would just Define our Global variable for each GRC.
What was I call?
It was an open field as.
Yeah, and
What will be see?
Like, so and those would essentially just get lashed, they just get
set.
And then when we do our thread startup,
It would just work.
Where's my will make current.
So let's see here, we go.
Create opengl context for worker thread.
In this case, it doesn't really have to take it either of these guys.
Now, they're not going to be parameters.
There's going to be here and we'll just make this Global DC and this
be Global opengl RC and that actually should work.
And again, I don't know, maybe it wouldn't be a big deal to pass us
that I just didn't love.
That was like, well now it's actually getting kind of more drink.
Then if they're just set because they don't change and so it seems
like until we actually change them around.
We don't actually want to.
Oops that's HTC.
We don't actually want to introduce that complexity for no reason.
Just seems like a bad decision.
So I'm so like - well not.
All right, so what we call we will create context tarp.
Here we go.
And that's another thing.
We actually that's a pointer.
So we're gonna have to save that pointer as well.
So, let's see.
Cannot convert from void, right?
So we need that guy to save it.
And one thing we could do is make this stuff actually gets toward I
suppose up in win32, open, chillin it, if that makes sense.
So, what I could do is say that this is actually responsible for
storing it.
So if I actually go back to Winter to and it opengl right here, what
we could do is say that this actually stores that DC.
So instead of releasing
Sing it.
We actually store it.
So we say like what we'll do sequels window DC and never allow that to
be released.
And then similarly, the global
Global from glr sequels.
Opengl RC
Here and we will create context arbs is going to have to do exactly
the same thing as well, right?
So we will create context, our has to be something.
That we would keep so that other people can call it.
So I think that's basically it.
But, excuse me.
All of this of course is predicated on whether or not we ever actually
got that function.
If we didn't then we would not be able to run, right?
We would not be able to run at least not through up in jail.
All right, so I think we're good.
I don't know where wiggle conducts.
There it is.
There we go.
And so now I think we gonna win three to make Q.
Has some probably wrong signature here.
What are the what was that?
Passing it?
The window is not getting going to get past.
That's just dumb.
Alright, so now we're compiling again and in theory we can run but of
course we won't see anything now because we don't download any
textures, right?
So we're creating a bunch of sort of workers and stuff, but we don't
actually ever download any textures which is not particularly useful
if that makes sense.
And as you can see there's actually nothing on it so we'll stop for
today but we're pretty far from actually being in good shape at this
point to say the least.
So we have to actually go do the work of actually coming here into the
asset file and actually making this actually do something and then we
have to actually make
That we did everything correctly and that we're actually getting the
context, and that we're actually having those guys have what they need
for for.
We're gonna make current and all that other stuff.
So that actually has to happen as well.
Okay, so last thing is last, I guess when we do our, we will make
current here in our win through to create opengl context or worker
thread.
We know that we only do the asset work I believe on the low priority
threads, right?
So we actually don't need to create these for the non
high priority threads.
So if we actually take a look down here when we're in thread proc, we
want to have some idea of whether or not this particular threat is
high or low priority.
So that platform work queue, where we actually Define that, which is
in here, I believe.
So the platform work queue.
Is that actually to find out?
It's not.
So, who defines it?
Is that actually defined in the open in the wintry to side of things?
If so I'm going to feel pretty stupid because I just was like well
blah blah blah, and then it's not actually anything and whatever.
So, let's find out.
From work puffer, more queue entry platform work you.
So it's actually right there.
So actually the entire time I could have just left it in there.
Brilliant anyway, doesn't matter, point being here is our platform
work you
And what I want to do in here is I want to have some notion of whether
this thing is ever going to download anything like that, right?
So, I want something in here that's just like a bull 32 or something.
That's like, can download textures or something like that because if
it doesn't have to do this, maybe I should say like needs opengl or
something like this.
And so that way if you know, if it wants to do that, then it's going
to do that.
If it doesn't, it doesn't.
And I could, I guess at this point also,
Go in and clean up the other part of it and have it passed through
there.
But anyway,
Time is it?
This is for a sec so I even have 50 minutes left, really?
All right, so all I need to do is now when I Define these things those
the high priority queue and and what and low priority queue and
whatnot.
When I do win32 make you on these.
What I can do is just say like okay we'll set whatever the the Q needs
opengl thing is we'll set that before we call it, right?
So when we do
Since you're to make queue.
Which is right here, we will just set it I guess before we pass it in.
So let's see went through to make Q on high priority queue and I guess
these high
the high priority queue is just
it's cleared out to 0.
So what I could say is the high priority queue, we know that it
doesn't need access to opengl the low priority queue.
We know does so we need this to be set to open Jill, right?
so now we know that that will be set properly so that when we do our
make q and we call into the thread code, we now know that that thread
code, that's a good cook can basically understand
Whether or not it needs to do this.
Oops.
So right here, I can say, if the cue needs opengl then get it opengl
otherwise don't bother, right?
Because we don't need to do anything if it's not going to do that.
So, so I think that's all we really need to do to make that a little
bit cleaner.
And now, yeah, like a since I kind of messed that up, I probably
should have made it so that just get past the gear, but doesn't
matter, it's all fine.
Anyway, so now, I think we're a little
More correct.
The only are creating to opengl context, one for each of those.
And off we go, unfortunately, we don't really have anything at this
point.
That's going to actually download the textures, but we could do that
tomorrow.
So you know, we're not in bad shape.
We've actually got an opengl.
So really all we need to do is just make it so that the asset
System now has a way to actually make this call.
What the heck?
Let's just do it.
Let's just do it with a trivial.
Callback for now.
And and then if we want to do something fancier, we can might as well.
So in order to do that, right, in order to call finalized bitmap, we
just need some way for the platform code to to be triggered, right?
We just need some way for it to actually do that.
That download
And right and we just need some way for it to affect that change to
the graphics card and so in here when we have our very stuff we've got
kind of like our our calls that we actually use.
These are the ones that are only for debugging.
These are the ones that we actually expect to expose as sort of like
the platform for the game.
So these are the actual apis that the game is allowed to call and we
try to keep these pretty minimal, right?
We try to not have a lot of stuff in here and and yeah,
So I think I can actually I wanted to actually eliminate these a
little bit.
I think I can actually cut down.
These are there's too many here that there's probably shouldn't be but
so if we want to do a sort of this concept that we're going to
actually submit a texture we need a way of setting and unsetting
textures or basically like saying what's going on here.
So what I think I would probably say is let's do something like
Let's do something where we just have.
One call and that call can either allocate or deallocate the texture,
right?
Something like this.
So in opengl we have a feed forward because mm, I guess, the only
thing is we don't if you want to deport certain like d3d where you get
back the handle and it's like an address or something, we probably
don't want to do that.
So we might actually want the too but we just do, I guess allocate
texture.
And platform deallocate texture.
So we just need both of those things to work, right?
And so then the actual cost of these
Are pretty much equivalent to these guys here where we'd say like,
okay, we're going to give back a void star for platform allocate
texture.
And instead of passing a size which is what we'd normally pass
allocate actual memory.
Instead we're going to do is we're going to pass this information that
we needed to pass down here, right?
So we're going to pass that the width, the height and the rest of the
stuff doesn't really very.
So then we and we just have like the actual like data.
So we're just going to pass that down and that's all we currently need
and we can
Span this obviously in the future.
But that's basically all we need for our purposes and then we can do
Platform deallocate to.
Oops, have it there.
So then we can do Platform.
Do you like a texture?
Like, so, and when we delegate the texture, all we need to do is pass
back the handle that it gave us and say like we're getting rid of this
now.
It doesn't shouldn't need any other piece of information, right?
Because if that's all it handed this back so we don't need to tell it.
Anything else should be able to you know eliminated with just that
All right, so if that's what we've got then in here, after we do our
platform, we did it from file, we should be able to do our equivalent
platform allocate texture.
Here and we're just going to pass it.
That piece of those pieces of information that are the, the new pieces
of information, like so and we don't need this and we don't need
these.
That's all we need.
So, with that piece of information, it should everything it needs.
And so we just need to now on the win32 side of things actually, place
these calls in to actually give these calls some some
Somewhere to live.
So where we got our callback specified, I believe is up here somewhere
somewhere.
I don't actually know where
It's up here somewhere.
If we just keep looking, so there you can see the callbacks right that
we Define for debug.
So let's do, like, let's see, platform allocate memory.
So if I just stick these guys in here, then we've got sort of our
function definitions.
So,
And so if I do Platform allocate texture I'm just going to call this
locate texter and if I do tlk texture here then we can just go ahead
and take the opengl code verbatim and just have it happen in here.
So, inside here, when we do, what we're going to do.
We need this to basically return avoid star, that's kind of the
texture information.
What I'm going to do here is I'm going to assign the handle to that,
right?
Because, you know, we had that entry bitmap handle
and I don't really remember why exactly that.
There's the entry bitmap handle thing.
But point being
Right because I guess I'll just explain that a little more detail
because I kind of said that without saying what it was when we call
load when we when we grab the Centre here, right?
That was actually code from a previous thing.
That's okay, that's why I got confused.
I was like, why is there an entry handle here?
That's because it's totally different thing.
So when I'm going to actually finalize the bitmap, I only presumably
have just the the actual
The actual.
Stuff that was stored in the work, right?
Which would be the asset header.
Presumably I think so.
We're going to have to figure out a way to kind of store that bitmap
stuff in with what we create.
So if I look down where we do load bitmap load that I gotta remember
to change search to be case insensitive because the New Mexico is case
insensitive, I'm used to not having to put in the correct.
So when we, when we do this thing here.
So we've prepared the bitmap and here it all is and there's that
handle so I think after we do asset header bitmap, we should be able
to just claw that back out.
Let's see because the asset assets ID value.
I like how we recreate that for no reason.
It's right here.
That's just asset, right?
I know why we're doing that but point being so we can get the bitmap
out.
Really trivially.
It's just like this so the work asset header bitmap that's the bit map
so we can do like and I don't remember exactly what that class is for
us.
I guess it's
It's going to be.
Loaded bitmap.
So I just need to start one of those.
So if I grab out this bitmap, I can store back to the handle and now I
can get all of those pieces of data that I was getting off the bitmap
as well.
And so now we're pretty good to go, right?
That's that's everything we needed.
So this would allocate the texture that would do the download and
everyone would be happy, right?
Everything is Peachy.
So in that circumstance, of course we need to actually return the
handle.
And so when we do this GL text image here, I'm going to have to do the
bind, that would have gone with it.
So the GL buying texture, 2gl texture.
2D I need something here, that's going to be the handle.
So if I'm going to do that that I need I believe it's a
Jie Lun.
So I think I need a handle.
I need some way of making that handle work.
And then when I return it, I can always just cast it to avoid star to
return it to the caller, and I can put an assertion here just to be
doubly safe.
I can be like assert that the size of a handle is much, like the size
of handle is less than or equal to the size of a void star just to
make sure that it's going to fit.
But point being, we can always do that and then we want to deallocate
Here we can deallocate.
So in this case we've already covered the thing that we would need to
use here.
There's a thing called GL Jen textures that will just give us back a
texter handle.
That's known not to be used, right?
So we can say just give us one.
It'll give us that one.
We then use it.
We give it back.
So now we can always be used for binding and everything else that it
needs to be used for.
And after we do the submission we don't really want to leave the
texture Bound for any reason because this is a download thread.
So you might as well also just unbind the
Texture.
So it knows we're done talking about it.
Oops, meanwhile and here we want to deallocate.
There's the equivalent college is Jill.
Delete textures which just says hey that handle.
So in order to get the handle we do exactly the same thing we were
doing before we just say oh that thing that we pass in here,
the texture that you're going to free, I know it came in as a void
star treated instead as GL unit,
Right.
So hmm.
This is probably going to be a saint.
Yeah, so that handle that's on the loaded bitmap, which I don't
actually know where that even is anymore.
This is the problem with not every parent while.
It's like, where do we store that I'm guessing?
It's probably in the render group and hey, I'm right.
So, this handle is not going to be one of these.
It's actually going to be like, one of these, and we probably should
call it like some kind of a texture handle.
So that we know what we're even talking about here.
So I might go ahead and do that and then say that anyone who
references, that should really call it a texture handle proper, if
that makes sense.
Which I guess would include this dude.
Oops, that's no good.
What did I do?
Oh, you know what?
I just realized?
I don't really remember how to redo.
Okay, there we go.
Now I do.
Yeah, perfect.
Okay.
So
This handle is now texture handle.
And stream actually has intended.
That's the funny part.
Mr.
Counter person.
So yeah.
And here we've got, let's see.
Hold the frame if you're not ready with texture.
Yeah, so this is actually still texture handle.
Does anyone else have anything to say about that bind?
Texture cannot?
Okay.
Yes, that's true.
So, this is just a jewel.
You ain't so,
And off we go.
So, in here now we know we've just got these, we don't have to read
out of an entry or anything we cut and paste this code from.
Before we know, we pretty much have all this information.
I think we called this the data, this opengl default.
Internal texture specification is going to have to be a global.
I would believe, although I guess it already was a global.
So off we go.
And so now in theory, we're downloading these Textures in the
background in theory, right?
Pretty big caveat there.
We're still not actually deleting them yet, but in theory, we're
downloading them.
Now here's the part where the graph the whole machine probably crashes
on us or something equally, horrible happens, but it looks like not.
Okay.
So all we should have to do now is the bug this which might be a
little tricky.
And the other thing that I might want to do just before I get any
further in, it is, when we do asset eviction, we want to call that
Delicate texture, right?
So in order to do that, when we actually evict an asset, which is
going to be allocate game assets and I like that.
We have Snuffleupagus oriented programming written in there when we're
going to evict an asset.
Then in here.
Let's see where we've got.
This is not.
This is not that's allocate all game assets.
I want the actual
Where's the actual thing?
Where we evict an asset?
Font load bitmap, acquire asset memory.
That's what I actually want.
So when we do acquire acid memory and we do all this merge as possible
stuff.
So in here, when we're going through this stuff, this is the part that
actually matters to us, right?
So when we do remove asset header from list, we're taking this guy out
and we're changing it back to us.
Used normally we don't have to do anything because we're in control of
everything is nice and clean.
But
in the case where this was actually a texter, we have to tell opengl
about it.
So what we want to do here is something like okay we're about to like
free this dude, right?
He's he's been removed from the from the list and let me double check
to make sure that that doesn't do anything particularly bad.
So I will go ahead and say asset CPP but remove asset.
Whoops move.
I said Heather from West.
Where are you in?
Uh-huh.
There it is.
I said doesn't do anything, so that's fine.
So basically, when we remove it from the list, all we have to do is
say, you know what, kind of texture actually was this
Which I guess now that I think about it that might be is that
something we even know?
And I don't actually know because we didn't do anything in particular
to store those things in a way that was was marked.
But I suppose the AHA probably has it right because the AHA.
I needed to know what kind of a set each individual thing was so the
HHA probably does actually have the type.
So we're kinda out.
We got a little bit of a get-out-of-jail-free card there.
I suspect if we actually store that if we didn't, then we're in a
little more trouble because we don't actually know which kind of
asset.
This actually is, if that makes sense.
So, right here, when we're about to actually free it, we need to know,
should we call the platform?
And should be called deallocate texture.
Right.
Mmm.
On the bitmap header.
Something like this, that make sense.
So assuming that we have to do that, excuse me.
We need some way of knowing, you know, what's going on there.
So let's take a look at at that asset header.
So here's the asset memory header.
And here is the asset index, total size generation ID, right?
And here's all the various stuff for it.
So we know that if we, if we did know that it was a bitmap, all we
would have to do is
The allocated thusly and we'd be done but since we don't actually know
which one it is, we have the acid index.
I'm not sure how we would tell what type of a sighted actually was
because I don't know that we have any more information in there.
Other than that we've got the AHA that doesn't have it in it, right?
I just looked at that.
It just has the offset the tags, and then a union, you know, one for
each thing.
So, if I come back here to the asset and we look at it, I don't think
there's anything that I could use, that would give me a clue.
So we probably would have to store in order to support that shut down
properly.
We'd probably have to store some piece of type information.
We just straight-up have to augment it so that when we have asset
memory head,
It actually stores a type in here that tells you what it was actually
being used for if that makes sense because I don't know any other way
to get it.
So in here we would actually need something.
Oops in here we would actually need something that's like asset type.
and that would tell us, which I think we had tried to avoid doing
because we really just didn't need that information in any other
place, but
I mean, if we need it, we need it.
And so here we would say if the asset header
Asset type equals h.
A bitmap we have I believe we have an actual type field for this sort
of thing, right?
I assume.
So we actually got away with never storing the type at all anywhere
and this would be the only thing that actually needed.
But that's a bummer.
I wonder if there's any way we can avoid.
Like it's kind of funny that we never had to do that and now we would
have to do it.
Kind of a bummer, right?
Yeah, that's really too bad because it looks like we don't ever even
have to know and
Through the entire thing.
It was always just assumed which one it was, and it all just worked
somehow magically, right?
Which is really kind of cool, but I guess, I mean, not in any real
concrete way, but it's just like, hey, that's kind of neat.
But unfortunately, looks like we wouldn't be able to get away with
that anymore.
That makes sense.
What just happened?
Okay good.
Hmm.
So yeah.
I don't really know what else to do about that here.
then say like asset type bitmap like that and just
store it because I don't see any real way around it.
And
And I think that just has to be that just has to be stored.
So I'll come in here and say enum asset type
and I'll just say there's an asset type bitmap and asset type none at
the moment.
In the future, maybe we'll actually track them all, but for now, we
don't need to.
And so then when we do sort of the the obligatory linking in which I
guess is, is sort of the stuff that we do appear, we do insert asset
header at front.
Hmm.
I guess.
Well I'm we probably won't even really need to do it quite at, then we
probably just need to do it at in that actual allocator itself.
When we do, when we load the actual
Stephen, so when we call load bitmap,
Where is my load?
That meant, there it is.
So when we call the bitmap,
I would need to set it in places like this.
So when it comes through here and it says like, okay, we're going to
load this asset in when we set these things.
So in here, when we take that, that asset header and do a choir, a sad
memory, I guess an acquirer asset memory.
We should force it just to make sure everyone sets, it set the asset
type.
So, acquire asset memory.
It's right here.
It's going to take an asset type.
and so, then when it actually gets the memory,
Whenever that actually has to happen when we come down here and we do
result acid, index result, total size.
And so on insert header at front when we do the insert header at
front.
Mmm,
We then be set to go, right?
Because that's the asset, the asset memory header is the thing that
sort of the type in it.
So we would just say, Okay, assuming that we got one at the asset,
type is whatever it is.
so,
Oh, right, can't quite do that.
Oops.
Or to use that name.
Let's see.
Little bit map does not have an overloaded.
Remember.
You are correct, sir.
I do not mean to suggest that it does, and this
Is an asset header type.
So then we might as well finish these guys, so this would be an asset
type sound.
And this would be an asset type font.
And that's it.
I think except for the typo.
Thank you, compiler.
So that that's that and we'll leave it at that at the interest of
closing reasonably and I so I think we're all set up now, we just need
to do our debugging to figure out like when we're not getting stuff
and whatever and then we should be good to go.
So I'll end it there and we'll see if anyone have has any questions.
But that's, that's basically the infrastructure necessary to do the
texture downloading.
We just got a
We just got to actually set it up.
Now, there is one more thing we can choose to do if we want to or not,
which is we can fence the downloads.
I, that's why I put that to do in there.
We can do something called fence fencing, the downloads, which makes
it so that the opengl will just pause.
If the texture hasn't been downloaded yet, we can do that.
I don't know that we actually want to put we can
If we always hit our texture download times, we never have to do that.
It doesn't matter but you know,
Are we missing a day in the episode guide?
The guide only goes up to day two for a two-bit.
Today's overlay was saying day 244,
I don't know.
No, I think that counter was just busted.
So this is day this is actually day 243.
Sorry about that.
Just correct that.
Yeah.
What do you mean?
Said, they 243 the whole time.
What's wrong with you guys?
You're obviously mistaken.
It never said 244, don't be ridiculous.
and and just look over there, a seagull outside flying around and then
See.
I know, I don't know what you guys are talking about.
You just totally confused.
Gary Johansen, is it possible to tell opengl which graphics card to
use if you have more than one in a given machine?
No, it is not so
So the answer to that question is a little complicated.
The short answer is no.
The long answer is actually it depends on whether they are by the same
manufacturer or not and if they are by the same manufacturer, then you
may be able to
If they aren't then.
No.
So for example, if you have like an ATI card and an Nvidia card in one
machine, only one of the drivers will get loaded will be mapped to you
as the driver you're talking to when you ask for opengl.
And there's no way to say give me the opengl context that corresponds
to that guy's card.
So whoever is set up as like, the primary display driver is the person
who you'll actually be talking to.
If you have to grab, as far as the machine and they're both by the
same vendor, then it's the same driver.
Anyway, in that case, opengl will by default, just do whatever it's
going to do.
Meaning if the user has set it up as SLI, it'll SLI.
If the user has set it up as like, just separate and don't use the
other one it then that's what it will do.
But
If it is, for example, Nvidia card and it's a Quadro card, there's a
graphics API that allows you to iterate over, which cards are in the
machine and say, which one you're talking to for any particular
context.
If it's not a quadrille, you can't.
And so you just don't have a, there's nothing you can do forget it.
If it's an ATI card, I think there is a similar one that works on all
their cards.
So I think on a TI, you can actually
I'm trying to talk to this card and I want to use each card
separately.
That's all I know.
I don't know about Intel.
Since they're integrated Graphics.
I don't know if there's such a thing technically, as having more than
one, but it occurs to me that you could duel socket a Skylake in which
case you do have two gpus and I have no idea what happens in that
circumstance.
It's never even really crossed my mind.
But in theory, you could I don't know what happens.
so,
Kubrick Caleb.
Is it really a good idea to keep the DC round forever.
What if the user changes their monitor?
Config while handmade hero is running?
Well, that's the least of our worries because if the DC has to get
rebuilt, the opengl context is no longer valid.
So it's really the opengl context that you'd be worried about, but if
they change their Monica fig in theory, it it's not going to affect
the opengl context.
In theory, it should still work actually.
So really we just have to reposition our window or something.
Pragma script wouldn't the allocate and deallocate texture fit better
in the open Jill there instead of the platform.
Yeah, I think so because we don't I think that's a reasonable idea
because I feel like we don't call any platform specific stuff in
there.
Right?
I mean that looks totally fine for moving so I feel like we could
share them with any platform like if Linux or whatever wants to use
this.
I think that's fine.
So I think that's a totally reasonable thing.
So let's let's go ahead and do that.
Should be fine.
What is Microsoft's rationale for not allowing exclusive full screen
mode for universal windows.
Platform games seems like that would just shoot themselves in the
foot.
I mean,
What is Microsoft's rationale for anything?
I have no idea, they're a large organization with a lot of people in
it.
Some of whom are probably reasonable Engineers.
Who want to make a good decision?
Some of whom are probably just too inexperienced to make a good
decision.
Some of whom are like actively malicious and just want to win at all
costs and will intentionally make bad decisions who
And that whole mixture plus deadlines.
Plus, whatever comes out to give you stuff like universal windows
platform.
And then we have to live with it and that's life and it's not a great
life.
But why those things happen
Who knows?
I don't even know if they do or don't.
I mean I'm never going to ship in the Universal Windows platform game
unless it literally is the only way left to ship on windows.
So I don't care.
But, you know, I don't know.
Easy site.
Is there a way to preload vertices normals and colors to the card in
the same way as textures EG before a GL drawn?
This is called or is that usually never an issue?
No.
Actually it's exactly the same.
It's exactly analogous.
And the reason that we are not doing anything like that here, is
because all of our information that has to do with vertices is
actually Dynamic.
Like everything moves around on on a frame.
But if we found that
Really needed to care about something like that.
Like let's say, for example, for some reason, like the background
elements that tend to be in the same place like our trees.
Let's say that those were really expensive like lots of vertices and
we wanted to try to minimize that bus traffic.
You can actually create a buffer for vertices the same way that you do
like a texter and transfer that I think receipt as well if you want to
It's exactly analogous.
So in general,
You can kind of think about this is just the general way that you
would do stuff that is expensive to transfer.
Our vertices are mostly Dynamic per frame, and there's not that many
of them.
So it's really not something that we have to care about most of our
data lives in textures.
And so, you know,
could you invite Jeff to supervise and micromanage you while coding
sometime?
I he'd be a bad one to invite for that because he's actually a very
hands-off manager.
He doesn't supervison micromanage people which is, you know, one of
the reasons I like working for him.
So you'd probably want to ask somebody else.
To do that because he probably wouldn't be interested.
Hubert Keller for 3D Mi.
Isn't it?
Typical to upload the mesh to the GPU once?
And write a shooter that takes a
For Matrix for transfer drawing, each model?
Yes.
And like, that's why I'm saying so, you know, in our circumstance with
Sprites, it's just a card on the screen, it's four vertices.
And if we found that specifying four vertices per one was to owners.
We actually don't even have to do that because there's a thing called
a Tessellation Shader and a geometry Shader and various other things
that can actually blow out vertices to get you things by specifying,
only a single vertex and then
matically generate the four vertices that would create the card.
So in actuality we just don't have to worry about vertex traffic.
We can specify all the all the positional information.
We need every frame very easily and the the size of a transform that
you normally send down for.
Even a static mesh, is bigger than the amount of data we send down for
our Sprite cards right now.
So we're just not even in that same realm but in a circumstance where
you have tens of thousands of vertices hundreds of thousands of
vertices,
Models.
Then the same thing you have to do for textures here are that you have
to do for your vertices.
It's exactly the same.
We just don't have any data in vertices.
All of our vertex data is dynamic removing.
The whole point of specifying, the very famous to move things around.
And so we wouldn't get any savings by taking a transform because a
Transformer, you know, is just as big as the actual vertex data or
very
aunt in size essentially, you know, and like I said if we did want to
compress down that data instead of just instead of sending the four
vertices, we could actually just send the center in a scale and have a
A geometry Shader blow that out for us.
FSS dries, it was just very reasons.
I wasn't implying anything else Jeff saying, you know I really don't
like the name of that variable.
So the funny part about that is Jeff would hate the name of all these
variables because you can actually understand what they mean.
Jeff only likes like ABCDE like four, variables, he and Sean like
don't like to named variables, like actual names very much.
They like them to be short and concise and hey, there's something to
that, right less typing.
I was just on RSI break.
I can
Really appreciate.
That there's power, perhaps very good reason to do that.
That has nothing to do with the code even so
She become.
How the heck do you even read code with one letter variables?
Well, you know, I mean, you can sort of you can sort of do this
exercise for yourself if you want.
So, here's stb.
Truetype right?
Which I showed how to use on the stream a while back?
I was like if you want to read fonts
So you can look at Sean's code here and you can kind of see what it
looks like, right?
He's, you know, they they still put a fair number of variable names in
there eventually, you know, it's not, it's not all it's, I mean, I'm
exaggerating when I say that, right?
So you can kind of see that it's not it's not so so much that way,
right?
It's just a lot more concise than my intend to be like, you know,
you're not going to have with spelled out.
You're just going to have like w or something.
But assuming you know what your short hands are and you do use longer
ones in places where it's important, it's not that, you know, you can
still read this, right?
And this is probably a little more verbose than I think Sean's code
normally is maybe because it's in the sdp library, I don't know, maybe
not.
And I think this is more of a post maybe than Jeff Code would be,
which might have it be even more truncated.
But you can see that even when I'm saying, like they're more targeted,
it's not they still have if it's something that needs an explanation,
they still kind of put it in there, it's just you'll see a lot more of
like if something could be abbreviated it was and there's a lot more
like for things that are clearly just iterators.
It's just
JK and whatever, right?
They don't name them.
What they were they just assumed you could tell from the context which
is usually true, right?
It's not that hard to usually sort of suss out, you know?
What's going on?
So yeah.
So is that a about all?
There is to that feel like we've gotten through all of the questions.
All right, I'm going to wrap it up.
I'm going to wrap it on up.
Hello.
I'm going to try to anyway.
Thank you for this dream, you're not doing good job, asking real
questions.
I was there was
because, I mean,
At the end of the day, you saw what I did, it's just really
babysitting the driver.
I mean, the draw.
All the complexity for programming graphics card on Windows is in the
driver.
There's nothing you know.
Even if you use Vulcan, it's still just babysitting the driver and the
driver actually does.
All the actual complexity of like mapping figuring out like how to
talk to the graphics card and synchronization and all that stuff is
actually really still mostly all in there.
So, you know, Graphics programming is largely about if you've already
worked out like we did on handmade hero, how we wanted everything
done, transferring it to programming graphics card is, is really just
about figured
How to babysit drivers properly to, you know, feed them stuff in the
way that they want them fed.
But that's but that's it.
So there isn't a lot to it anyway.
I think we'll wrap it up for now.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It has been a pleasure coding with you, as always, hope that you will
join me tomorrow for going through and stepping through our texture
download stuff.
So we can get it all working and then check that off of our list of
things to do.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home of the source
code, you can always pre-order the game handmade Hero on handmade hero
dot-org.
And it comes to the source code, which you can download at any time.
If you would like to use the editor that we're now using, it's called
for a coder.
You can get it by typing for a coder and returning here.
I'll try to put a link on the web page so that we know that it'll just
be up here.
Eventually that's editor.
We're using, if you would like to do it, you can support Alan Webster.
Who's the developer on patreon, and you can have your own copy of it.
That is the same as the one that I am working with on stream, that's
about it.
We also have a patronage whilst worth of video series for a forum
site, if you want to ask questions and we have a tweet, but if you
want to know the schedule, please go to him a hero dot org, and check
those out.
If those are things that interest, you, if not, and you just want to
hang out here on the stream, we will be back here tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time to do the rest of that texture programming.
Hope to see you here, until then, please have fun programming and I
will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.