Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here at the show.
We could a complete game live on stream, two things.
One I have been asked and I don't necessarily know specifically why.
But I have been asked to issue a reminder to folks that the source
code to handmade hero, which comes with a pre-order, is not in the
public domain yet, it is commercial source code and you're not allowed
to redistribute it, as you can see down here.
There is actually a thing that says
This specifically, it's how it sort of could be license and it says
that it will become public domain after two years.
So basically, two years after the game is released, it'll be public
domain.
I should say in, at least two years, meaning I could choose to release
it sooner, but I can't choose to release it any later than that.
So there you go.
Public service announcement
for whatever reason it was requested.
And the other thing I wanted to mention is I'm awfully, sick, feeling
today.
So if I decide to, you know, just vomit all over the screen in the
middle of this stream, that is just how that's going to go.
That is not me, reacting to the wonders of Visual Studio, I've used to
it, and it no longer nauseates me in the way that it probably should.
This is actually just legitimate not
You're coming from, you know a virus or something like that.
I have not been sick in like a year so I certainly can't complain.
It was not like when I first started handmade here and I got sick like
three times in a row.
So anyway I want to go ahead and just dive into what we were doing
yesterday and just get it finished up.
It was basically doing some an architecture shift for how we have the
render isolated.
It's not a particularly difficult one.
I explained it yesterday but we just
Have to kind of finish up that architectural shift.
And so it's just, you know, it's just fussing, it's just a bunch of
fussing, it's the kind of fussing you need to do when you decide to
pull some code out from, you know, place that it used to be.
So I'm going to go ahead and get started on that.
And if you are trying to follow along at home today is day 2 41.
So you want to start with a 240s source code.
And if you remember correctly, we didn't want anyone to be confused
because normally almost every day, which is kind of weird.
Because a lot of times isn't true and Commercial Source spaces, code
bases.
But after we've never really ended an hour without stuff that still
worked.
But we yesterday since we're in the middle of a refactor, we actually
put
We actually put a notice in here that prevents you from building so
that you can know that we're doing that.
And so now I'm going to go ahead and remove that and we'll be back to
what we were working on before.
Right?
Okay.
So really all we have to do here besides the inevitable debugging of
making sure all our changes and
really work which I'm sure we'll have some of that to do later on,
really, the only thing we had left to do in terms of actually just
getting everything compiling properly, with the change state of how we
wanted things to work, is the win32 platform code, which now calls the
renderer directly,
That code needs to be fixed because we have not finished it yet so you
can kind of see in here.
It was still working off of stuff like the sort entry stuff, taking a
memory Arena.
We want to just be able to pass 10th memory in directly to it now.
And so what I'd like to do is just go ahead and finish that clean up
and then we can move on to the debugging phase of things which is
where we'll finish today.
All right, so when we call our sword entries call, right?
When we have to actually display stuff, we go ahead and we do the sort
here, we need to pass some temporary memory so that the Sorting can
occur.
So we need like temp memory, or sort memory, right?
Because we don't currently sort in place and our sort of temporary
assessment, although we didn't really do any, you know, particularly
Fancy work here or anything.
But one of the things that we did was, we said, well, it looks like
pretty much no matter what we end up doing, for sorting, it'll
probably whether it's Radix or merge or whatever else.
It looks like, it'll probably be faster with temp space, like doing it
in place, generally is just slower.
And so since we can easily afford the extra space, it's not, we're not
talking about GB, we're talking about MB or less since we can probably
Afford the space on just about anywhere, we're going to be running
this game.
We should probably use temp space.
So I'd like to always provide temp space to the sort thing.
And if we want to do something that sorts in place, sometimes as an
exercise, that's fine.
But I think our final sort will almost certainly want some temporary
memory for Speed purposes.
So I'm going to say that there's like temp.
Or sort memory that comes in here when we call win32 Slade, buffer
window.
And that way, when we call sort entries, it just gets some sort memory
that it can use and so it won't do any of these things here.
And it'll also take a look here at guess there's nothing really the
temp.
Space is just looks like this put that in there for now so it comes in
here.
We got the short memory.
I'm not sure.
Just temp space.
The call for there.
So we'll just replace that with certain they're made for now.
There we go.
I don't know why.
This stuff is still here, and now we'll recompile and see where we're
at.
All right.
So on start entries, the push, buffer element count.
Apparently, not a member of render group.
Hey, that's not an accident.
In fact, these are not really supposed to be taking render group
anymore.
All of this stuff that was taking render group.
Previously, should now be taking one of those command sets.
Right?
Because
All of this stuff again, we kind of pull it all out.
So we really don't want to see render group out here anymore.
Render group is a thing that the game uses to batch up
stuff that it wants to render.
So we're really talking about game render commands.
And so render group, anything, that was happening in here in render
group.
We would like it to, to instead happen.
Oops.
Although that probably actually is what we would want to call this
function instead of render group to Output, but that's fine.
So maybe this is, you know what, maybe let's just change it while
we're in here.
Let's let me see.
Let me see.
Look a little too high up.
Just not not adjusted.
Well, I need to be better adjusted.
There we go.
Much better.
All right, so, yeah, like I was saying we've got, we've got sort of
this thing that will switch between, which way we want to render.
And now, it's really probably not correct to call it render group to
Output or any of these things, right?
Talbert appropriate, we probably just want to call it, you know, tiled
commands render or something like this.
And that will take
Game render commands.
Like so and yeah, that that feels to me like a better idea.
So here's our tiles command render.
There we go.
That's going to take the commands it.
And oh yeah, and the render queue whoops.
So I didn't mean to delete that guy.
That's fine.
You can take that Q.
It's this guy.
That's going to be different.
And so that's all good.
And then when this guy calls through again, he's not just, just in the
exact same way, he's not going to do any of them.
You know, and we don't need this guy anymore either actually so he's
not going to do any of the stuff with render group anymore either.
He's going to exclusively do stuff with those commands.
So the work thing is going to take the commands and it looks like he
doesn't really touch anything else, so that's fine.
So, here is commands and tile render work where we, I don't actually
know, that's probably still defined over in render group.
Let's see tiled render work.
Yeah.
Yeah, so this time render work stuff to that's going to come out here.
Presumably, we could make a separate H file if we wanted.
I'm not sure if we want to or not, but this is going to be in game.
This is gonna be game rendered.
Ants and there's that loaded bitmap output Target in the clip.
Rect so this is the stuff that the, the actual renderer uses now,
okay?
So let's see.
This is our sort memory.
This it wants to have it cast to that, so that's fine.
Inside here we've got our push before elements.
And that stuff, okay?
So all of our render group stuff again, is just going through command.
So that's just a case of telling it to use something different here.
And this will, of course, be
Render commands to pit map.
That's probably the right phrase for this, okay?
And yeah, you're like, that's really what we need for the most part.
So platform add entry.
So this is nice because now we can also just cut we can really, we
don't really have to access platform anymore.
We can just use the add entry called probably directly, right?
We wouldn't need it to be exported to us because we know we're being
compiled as part of the system that said, you know, we can continue to
go through that platform that concept if we wanted to.
And I'm not sure which way we want to do it.
Relatively straightforward to make it work.
Both ways to make it irrelevant like, which one you happen to go
through.
Because if you remember, the way that we did that is we have the
platform thing was a global variable with the platform API in it.
And so we've got that same thing.
We should have that same thing available if we want to outside of it,
right?
Because that's in that's in
Hamid platform.sh.
Right.
That that platform API, we create one of those for our.
We must, I mean, how do we not create one of those?
Oh, you know what?
It's probably, it's welded into this guy.
So it's in-game memory there, right?
So if we wanted to, we could easily take the platform API there and
have that be available outside in here as well.
So that, you know, like the render and stuff could get at it.
Meaning, if we wanted to
We could make the platform API be something that's available out here.
So, maybe we'll just do that, because that way, we don't have any kind
of weirdness with, with, you know, when we move code back and forth
between the two, you know, it doesn't matter.
Does that make sense?
It's basically, like, just makes it so that it doesn't matter where
code exists.
They can still call through it if they want to.
That way, we can cut and paste.
Code into the platform layer and out of the platform layer and we
don't have to like poured it every time or change the way that it
works, you know.
And that seems like a good idea to me.
Okay, so let's see.
Temper Inna is, it's going on with temporary NE that we don't really
want to use it all.
We want that to just be our sort member here, right?
So our sort memory comes in and we just use it.
Render to opengl identifier.
Not found.
Well, we should have opengl rendering support here summer.
So it's this, let's see, enter commands opengl renderer commands like
that.
So this would probably be like software.
Render commands.
You know, I'm saying?
That seems better.
All right, so there's open gel, there's yeah, there's that.
And then I can just sort of come in here and say, okay, tell commands
render is actually called out and then they're uniformly named, it
seems reasonable.
All right, so then we get an output Target, the output Target is going
to be our Global bitmap.
I believe.
Right?
Is probably the thing that we want to Target there and that and then
we would want to
Yeah, and then we would want that to be workable as well.
So let me take a look here at where we're at opengl display bitmap.
So, display bitmap via, opengl is not an actual thing.
We're talking actually about this is what we want and here is all of
these guys with tight memory pitch window, with window height, right?
And software, renderer commands, that guy takes
That guy takes a loaded bitmap as the output Target.
I don't think we have one of those.
Exactly what we have instead is a win32 off-screen buffer which is the
global back buffer, right?
And so that guy the global back buffer, we can just use directly to.
We can we can just basically make a loaded bitmap that points into
that because it has all the same stuff, right?
It's got its got the exact same stuff in it.
So the global back buffer,
And the output Target we can sort of do.
Both of them output Target, memory equals Global back buffered up
memory.
And then we can just do like, Whit height pitch.
and I think,
That should be roughly what we want there.
Similarly, we can kind of just do this.
Now.
And that will do our bitmap display for us as well.
So that's now plumbing.
Plumbing wise, correct?
This stuff I guess is really buffer is just output Target.
I could I suppose just say buffer Arrow output Target Dot
And I think that's roughly, correct.
oh,
So that's got to be from the go back before because we don't keep that
anywhere else.
Let's see here.
All right.
With memory.
And these I guess maybe I should have those be the global back buffer
as well instead.
Like maybe that's a little bit more correct.
Since it has to be that since we have to have the input info for it,
we could replace
Seer, I want to do output Target dot with global.
Global Tobacco, you know what's probably back buffer with the
lowercase b, because I'm the worst at being consistent with my camo
caps.
One more time, there we go.
All right, so we don't have this anymore, it's gone because now we
don't pass that through.
And so I don't even know if that was still in here, it is.
So that's got to go away goodbye because we don't call that anymore.
In now went through to display Byford window, that's got everything,
an easy set.
The temp memory now, right?
Because the win32 display buffer and window has to take that temp
memory, right?
And that's to take a couple things to it as to take the render queue.
Exactly the highwomen.
Priority queue.
So, it's got to take the render queue.
It's got to take the render commands and use the device context window
width and height and then it needs attempt memory.
So we gotta pass the temp, memory here and the temp memory.
Really wants to be a thing that's however, big it needs to be for the
render commands, right?
And so really, I guess what we want here, is something like this is,
this is our sort memory.
We want something like, okay, if
You know, the sort memory.
You know, needed sort memory size and current sort memory size.
We could say, if the amount of syrup member, we currently have is less
than the amount we need.
Then we'll get the
What we need instead, right?
So, we'll virtual free and virtual Alec Neu sort memory.
So that way, we'll make sure we always keep some.
We always grab as much memory as we need.
So, you know, we, we could just say we just fail or don't sort if we
go over is the other option.
I'm not sure which one of those makes more sense dynamically growing.
It depends what you want to do.
Dynamically growing means that probably you're always going to be safe
on most machines, but it does mean that, you know, in theory, you
could overflow your memory for some reason, you do so many things and
need to sort them that you allocated more memory than you were
expecting or something.
I'm not sure that's really possible.
And we could always, we always know what the upper bound is because it
has to fit inside there, but I'm going to do it as allow it to
dynamically grow.
Because like I said, I wanted to show you guys later.
To make the Arena's grow dynamically as well.
And so, I feel like we probably want to just make sure that everything
can be flexible if you want to, and then turn it off if we want to
lock it to a certain size because it's we could always just stop doing
the if, right?
And don't render when we can't sort or something.
Anyway, so we'll free the sort memory and then will allocate the sort
memory again.
That makes sense.
And so that's really all I wanted to be able to do.
So basically like we would say, okay the current certain memories.
Sorry the needed sort memory size is going to be however, many render
commands.
There were right.
So it's render commands push buffer, element count,
Times the size of the tile sort entry.
And so that is how much memory we would need to sort.
And so if we don't have that much, we can just allocate some more.
Right?
And that way, once we hit our high Watermark will never allocate.
And in fact, we can just allocate off the bat something very high and
make sure we're in there, right?
So yeah, we have our win32 allocate and went through to deallocate.
I guess, I'll just call those right when three to allocate memory.
350, allocate memory.
Yeah, that's seems fine to me.
okay, and so then we just have
Our current sort memory size and let's just say that we start with
like one megabyte of sort memory or something like this.
Like I'm not going to waste be tuned to something later if we want,
which is so that's more than presumably we would ever need.
So this case would never get hit.
And then we just say, our Ford Star sort memory equals win32 allocate
memory current members sort size and think that's it.
Seems reasonable.
So yeah, that's all we need to do course, obviously, we need to do
this before we you know, start the game running.
Certainly so we you know we want that to be something that happens up
here and side to know what else we would do.
You M&M's are not defined to the platform there.
A weird.
Well,
They are now.
That's a memory size unsigned integer.
I've been using it recently.
I guess it's something I started doing.
Don't know anyway.
So let's see.
I think we're almost there.
I think we've got most of the things we want to do here.
Pretty wrapped up.
So, yeah.
Okay, that's all good.
Let's see.
Needed.
Certain memory size, etc, etc.
Yeah.
Feels reasonable.
I feel like you could make an argument that was okay.
So let's see what do we got?
For unresolved symbols draw, a rectangle quickly.
Where is that?
That's in here.
So we can finally get rid of all this stuff, too.
I think, now we should be able to just go ahead and grab this out from
handmade hand optimized and put that in here, after draw a rectangle
slowly, right?
Could just put that in here and we can, you know, choose to optimize
this or not.
But I think we're all good.
So here we go.
We've got
The ignored function stuff.
I think this doesn't need to be there.
Let's go ahead and compile this pixel fill nor timed block ignore time
block.
We go.
So now we're compiling and in here, we can go ahead and get rid of
half of the optimize thing in here.
I believe this guy I think we can just get rid of that for the time
being because now we have the hardware renderer
So if we want fast rendering in a debug build, we could always just
use the hardware renderer and we don't have to worry about having a
special code thing.
That forces something to always be optimized, which seems like good,
right?
Because now we can just build the whole thing and optimize.
If we want to see how fast the software rasterizer runs, we don't have
to always have that because we can't even do any development if we
don't have an optimized, right?
So that seems like a pretty good thing to me.
So I'm going to go ahead and say let's just
That change and we can always use the pound pragma trick that people
figured out how to finally, do correctly on the forums.
Remember because we try it on stream, it didn't work, but turns out,
it's because you have to make sure you have in lines and the right
place and stuff.
But anyway, separate issue.
So we can do that now which is good because that gets rid of a little
bit more complexity there and it also means that we can delete that
file entirely.
Like we don't need a handmade optimized whatever nonsense that can go.
So that's gone now.
Goodbye
Make sure it's killed from the buffer as well.
Alright, so now we're like structurally, sort of working but we're
probably not actually working because we made like a ton of changes
and we've got, you know, some debugging ahead of a certainly.
But, you know, we've got 30 minutes, 35 minutes.
So hopefully, we'll be able to make some Headway into that.
So let's start by seeing where we like Crash and Burn first.
All right, so I think the first thing is we probably don't initialize.
Yeah.
We so we aren't we don't initialize or reset or do anything for for
our actual render command.
So we got to take care of that first.
Let's see here.
There we go.
So we've got this push.
Buffer size, push buffer thing.
Oh wow.
The we never this is awesome.
It's actually we never finished typing this in.
So this virtual a like is actually just it's setting the void push
buffer to point to the address of the virtual Alec function.
That's amazing.
But anyway, yeah, so we're going to do a went through to allocate
memory here with the push buffer size and this is something that we
can move.
Also, back up to the sort like this, the same place, we're gonna sort
memory.
So that seems like a reasonable
Nothing to do, okay.
At, let's push a little further through there.
Oh, all right.
Well that was somewhat surprising.
I wasn't expecting that to work the first time but I guess it did.
Yeah.
So that's fine.
I guess, weird.
Well.
I wasn't faking that to work.
I don't know.
That that takes a little window sales.
Got a bit that, you know, wasn't expecting it to work, it worked, it
worked even the debug code worked.
So even the fact that we're now aggregating and adult, it all just
worked everything just worked, which is crazy.
And I don't know what to say.
I guess we just had good luck.
Maybe they were taking it easy on me.
The gods of programming, looked down and said he's sick today.
We won't give him a bunch of debugging to do.
Thanks guys.
All right.
So that's
I would say is I would have something more attention to say about that
if I wasn't feeling ill.
All right, so I guess, let's at least test the software side.
Probably that maybe that needs some debugging, and here's win32
display barford window, right?
And so this is currently going through hardware and doing so, this
Branch, we're not testing at the moment, so maybe let's have a global
variable that allows us to switch between hardware and software
rendering or something.
Don't know.
So here we go.
Let's just have a global variable.
B32 use Hardware rendering.
and we can just say like, okay Global use Hardware rendering is here,
or maybe we'll do Global use software rendering actually
That way, the default value of false will be the one that we probably
want to ship the game with.
Boop.
And poops.
And so display via Hardware equals true is still one that we use here.
But this in Hardware now goes away.
Okay, so now we've got a global variable for that and I have to
actually declare it correctly, use software, rendering, and so now in
theory, I should be able to change between hardware and software,
rendering software, rendering by editing the value of that variable.
So for example, if I came in here, right and set
Break point or something?
Well, I
Set a breakpoint somewhere.
It's actually going to be hit.
Which is like here.
Let's say then I should be able to do something like saying Global use
software rendering and you can see that it's set to zero so it's using
the hardware.
I can probably set it to one now and then something will happen and
Hey look it's software rendering right now it's expected incredibly
slow suffering because it's not being compiled optimized but it is
actually in software.
So what's kind of nice about that?
Is the other thing that you know, is kind of cool.
If you now, look at how we've got our architecture, it means you can
just switch it run time if you want to write.
So, you know, now we can just say, like, oh whatever you want to do
with use, you know, software or Hardware rendering.
In fact, I don't even know, does our debug system because we have to
finish the debug system at some point.
I don't know where we left that.
Can you edit true, and false values in here?
I felt like we had that
at one point, but we like, you know, we had sort of changed it around
and did all this other stuff, right?
So I don't know if we can do something like this here, where we have
like a debug variable type path, sort of thing and you know, we had
some stuff for like we would do.
Debug.
Variable.
We did some stuff like this.
Right?
And I feel like maybe we could do that with the with the hardware
rendering.
I don't know.
We never, this is why we got to go back and finish this stuff because
I really want these things to all actually be done.
But most of them, you know, we kind of just stopped in the middle when
we went on break and we never came back to actually finish this code,
which is unfortunate.
But yeah, I mean, in theory like if that debug, if that stuff actually
worked,
Then we could actually have that, you know, BFB a thing.
So that would be Global use suffering.
We could do.
I don't notice that work.
Global constants.
Render use software Undeclared, okay?
Better.
So, I don't know what happens now.
Because I don't remember.
So, I don't know if we can't.
We can't actually click on this kind of way, because we don't actually
have that stuff.
Yeah, it looks like we almost had this stuff working like it displays
up there.
Hmm.
Well, let's take a look.
you know what actually
No, I think about let's not take a look.
I got a better idea because we want to go finish the debug system at
some point.
There's no point in opening up that as a can of worms, Let's ignore
that for now.
I've got a better idea, let's Implement vsync because one of the
reasons I wanted to do all the hardware stuff.
Now anyway, besides the fact that we have get a lot of free speed from
it is that I wanted a vsync and so we could get Visa Inc pretty in a
pretty straightforward fashion and there's some things that I want to
explain about how you do that anyway.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Okay, so why don't we have vsync at the moment, right?
First of all, does everyone know what vsync is, might be another good
thing and I kind of take it for granted that you do.
And the reason is because even if you're not a graphics programmer,
you if you're even if you just, if you just play games, you probably
know what vsync is Right, Sophie sink.
Is really sort of an old school Concept in the old days, right?
On a CRT, on a cathode ray tube.
I don't know if you guys remember these guys things.
They were like the old sort of TVs that are super long, right?
The way TVs originally were, and there was like an electron beam thing
that would like, literally scan across the screen in like this zigzag
pattern like this.
Lighting up, the phosphorus that was on the coded, on the front glass
plate, right?
And those phosphorus, when the electron
Phosphorus it would admit a color, and that's how you know, they're be
look, a little red green and blue dots, they would light up those with
certain different intensities, and that's how you would get
Television, right?
And so the reason that it's called vsync is because as this happened
at the end, it would get to the bottom and it would have to the, the
gun thing.
This, this is electron gun.
That's like letting up.
This play would have to kind of come all the way back and start again
at the top and during that period where it comes
It's back to start at the top, was like the synchronization period
where you would start the next frame.
It was called vertical sync or vsync.
And so what happens is that phrase became known as waiting for the
right time, whatever that means in your current system, waiting for
the right time to update the frame.
Such that U such that.
The thing displaying it, whether it's an LCD or a CRT, like the old
days or whatever, doesn't like end up showing the user half, the old
frame, and half the new frame,
Right, because what happens if it's in the middle of updating and you
change the frame right in the middle.
You'll end up with some portion of the frame as the old one and some
portion is the new one that the user actually sees and that manifests
itself as like a tear, right.
It's called tearing
And so you end up with a thing that's like, oh the handmade Heroes
moving across the screen.
And there's this little like line where his his bottom part is like,
is moving ahead of his top part or something right happens.
Because this is from the next frame, and this is from the previous
frame, and you end up with the or this is from the current frame, this
from the previous frame, right?
So vsync.
It just means that, right?
And we want it for a game to prevent tearing certainly, but we also
want it to
Tried to get steady timing so that our timing is synced with the video
properly and so what we can do is we can ask opengl for it.
There's a thing called wgl swap interval or it might just be a GL,
swap interval.
I don't remember.
I don't remember whether it's a Windows call or a regular call.
I think it might be a regular call.
So Mike, just bgl swap interval, is the GL swap interval call and what
you can do is you can pass a value to this here.
Which says, how many frames do you want to wait before you swap,
right?
So when we call our, like our well, it's not a GL call.
When we call our swap buffers call that we were using right to display
our frame and GL.
If this value is set to 0, then it means, as soon as we call swap
buffers, just put it on the screen, just do it.
I don't care if you're in the middle of this thing in frame, I don't
care whatever just do it, right.
If this value is,
One.
It means wait for the next vertical.
Retrace, if the value is 2, it means wait for two vertical, retrace
has right?
So it's like every other frame.
And three, four, five, six seven, right?
It's all very predictable at that point.
Now, it's important to note that this is simply a request.
So, when we make this call, what we're saying is this is what we would
like to have happen.
But opengl look for all we know, we might not even be on a card that
even supports vsync, like vsync is
Not a guarantee, it's just a hope.
And so, for shipping the game, we will probably also have to have some
logic that tries to look and go.
Oh, hey, it looks like we're not really getting any vsync because
like, you know our frame rate is you know, is two milliseconds, a
frame.
So obviously that's not happening.
And so try to, you know, maybe insert some delay to try and get us to
a 30 frames a second or whatever we want, our 60 frames a second
whatever we want our speed to me.
So GL swap interval is is a request but it's a request we want to make
and it's on most users machines.
If they don't disable it in their control panel will work and give a
reliable vsync.
So, it's a good thing to use.
okay, so here you can see if
Go.
Someone told me, docks dot g l was a good place to go by the way and
it is it does look pretty good so I don't know if it's in here if
Wiggles in there or swap intervals in here.
It isn't.
But this was a pretty good site.
People recommending for the regular opengl calls.
It's a pretty nice.
It's a pretty nice collection here.
I don't know if you if you've ever played with it, I was I was pretty
happy with it anyway so it's probably wiggle.
Swap interval then I'm guessing that's what I thought but I wasn't.
Sure, let's see.
W GLX swap control.
So this is the extension, all right.
so the way that opengl works like I saying before is on Windows,
There's the wgl stuff, which is the windows bindings for up in jail.
And then there's the GL stuff, which is the actual opengl, right?
And so, what we are actually talking about here is a wiggle side
thing.
So it's a window side thing.
And what this means is that we have to call through wiggle to
actually, you know, to.
We have to work for calling Through the Windows, part of things, it's
part of the windows thing.
It's not common.
Won't work on OS X to make this same call, for example, right?
And so, what that means, if we actually do it this way, and I can't
remember if there's a ARB swap interval.
I don't even remember, but there probably isn't any way.
So point being, since we're doing that, it means that we have called
your wiggle.
Now, the problem is, I believe this swap interval was added after the,
the version of opengl.
That's that ships in Windows, the version of the bindings, the windows
bindings.
So I believe that if we call W GL swap,
It will be an unknown identifier.
So like for example, we will create context, right?
Which is a function we are using in wiggle.
It's just there, right?
And your of course, is telling me that I it doesn't take their
arguments, which is true.
But you know, it's there wiggle.
Swap interval is not an actual function that was in wiggle originally,
and that's totally fine because there is an extension mechanism inside
wiggle to get new functions that you can then call.
And so what we want to do here is inside our code, right?
Here's our swap buffers.
All when we in it, are opengl.
There it is.
When we in it are opengl what we want to do is after and I guess we
don't need this anymore either.
What we want to do is we want to go ahead and get any of these
extensions that we might need.
And these extensions work.
Almost exactly like what you've seen me do in the past for getting
win32 functions that we need, right?
Basically, if there's a function that we need,
Wasn't in the base services, that were linking with what we can do is,
we can call, you know, get proc address like, for Windows, we call get
proc address and that basically says, Hey windows, I know.
There's a function named this, do you support it and if you do, please
return me a pointer to it, so I can call it.
And so what happens in in wiggle, right?
Is you call the exact same thing, but I believe you call will get proc
address.
Not regular, get proc address.
Right?
So it's it's own query extension.
So you call wiggle get proc address and it sends you back in an API
pointer that you can then use.
But other than that it's all exactly the same.
So I can call wiggle get proc address.
I can ask for the function that I actually want.
Which is this?
Right?
And then it will give it to me if it is there.
So I can have wiggle swap interval, EXT.
Will swap interval equals?
We get proc address if we're gonna swap interval.
We will swap interval one, which would set V.
Think for every frame.
Okay.
And so, what I want to do here is I would like to be able to take the
function prototype and just make sure I can keep it, which is what
I'll do here.
So I can say, okay, here's the function prototype.
Again, this is exactly the same thing as I've done many, many times in
the Stream already.
Okay.
And so I'm going to go ahead and put that up at the top here where we
kind of do this, this sort of stuff, right?
That we commonly do, and I don't really know that I need to do
anything fancy with this guy.
I don't think I need to use any sort of macros for him or anything
like that, because I'm not actually going to create a stub for this
particular guy.
So we just have to type def in like this.
Now we can load him when we do wiggle swap interval, EXT.
The other thing I should probably do is Mark it with a win API call.
Because it is one that won't matter in 64-bit code.
But if we ever compiled for 32-bit, might matter because the calling
convention anyway.
So what I want to do now is I want to go to that, we will swap
interval, and I got to do the Castor
And I guess I should just do this as if this could just be a global
right where we check it and we use it so that we can keep the value of
it around.
All right, so I'll do wiggle swap interval.
EXT will swap interval.
And that will be a global variable.
So,
and so now when we run this guy, I should probably step through the
code and show it to you.
Now you can see that we're running at a locked 60 frames a second,
right?
You can kind of see that it's a 16 milliseconds and everything's
running at the correct speed and that's because opengl is waiting to
do that flip until the frame boundary.
Makes sense.
And so if I didn't call that again, just so you can see what happens.
If I don't call it case, you missed it from before, or I call it with
zero, for example, which says don't think, then we just go at the
maximum possible speed the graphics card allows.
And you can see that it were running away faster, right?
We're running it about eight times seven seven to eight times faster
and so the game would just run like it was on you know, speed or
something.
Yep.
So that's you know how that works but we're not we're not quite done
yet.
For a number of reasons like first of all we don't know how long this
actually is because it might be that the swap intervals actually like
maybe it's 120 hertz display in which case, it wouldn't be 60 frames a
second for frames.
It would actually be 120 frames a second, right?
So we have more work to do there.
We're not done yet.
And the other thing that's worth noting is the way that
The opengl extension mechanism, technically works.
Is that calling wiggle get proc address is not technically sufficient.
What we're supposed to do is check for the existence of Extensions by
checking a string and you can see here like that they talked about
this a little bit because there's no way to extend wgl.
These calls are to finding the ICD and can be called by obtaining
post.
We're going to get progress because this extension is a wiggle.
In.
It is not included that you extension during its existence can be
determined with a wiggle ex extension.
Strings extension.
So technically what you're supposed to do is ask the driver for this
wiggle, ex extension string, which you can do look to see whether it's
extension.
String is in there, right?
Which is this one?
I believe, and if that's there, that it's there, and if it's not, it's
not.
Now the stupid thing about this.
Is that you don't actually know that you can get it after you see that
string, you start to make this function call and who knows what the
function call is going to return and we're still return 0.
Right?
So I find it's usually better to check this way.
I like to check this way better but it's not technically correct.
Because in theory if the extension string isn't there, then in theory
you could be getting the pointer to some other wiggle swap interval.
Function.
That does something different right in theory.
So it's kind of
Worth understanding that, that's their right.
So if we wanted to, we could make this a little bit more technically
correct by getting the extension string and then doing if stir stir,
you know, on the extension string, well, I'm not really stir stir, you
need to actually parse it and see that you didn't get like a partial
match, right?
So you need to actually parse it and then say, you know, is it found
in there and, and that would be a little bit more correct on Swap
interval.
That's really not necessary, because that's the only way that you can
ever have this function.
So I don't know how
Useful, that actually is, but it's just worth understanding.
Okay?
So that's one type of extension down, which is wiggle extension, and
we needed that for a v blank, right?
We needed that for for this but there's another type of extension that
we want because remember, right now on a rendering is actually wrong
in Hardware.
It's actually our rendering and software is actually more correct than
our rendering harder at the moment.
And the reason for that is our Hardware renderer doesn't understand
the fact that we're using
GB at the moment, right?
We're using
We're actually using a an encoding, right?
An srgb encoding for our textures.
We're not quite exactly srgb.
We're actually using squared a squared mapping.
So we Square values in the textures, which is not really the correct
gamma ramp at least not quite so, you know, it's it's it's not exactly
correct to say that it's srgb.
But we would like ideally
Eight, the graphics card to be doing sort of the srgb rendering for
us, right?
And so, that's another thing that we could, if we wanted to turn on.
And so let me, let me at least point you in that direction, we have a
little bit of a, sort of a issue to work out there that we can talk
about.
But we'll talk about little red later.
So frame buffer.
Alright, so here we are with our bed frame before srgb, and you can
kind of see in here.
There's just a bunch of verbiage talking about the extension, but
basically, what happens is, when you actually create a pixel format
like we were doing before, you know, you remember, we did this in an
it open gel.
Where we do this, this thing here, where we do describe desired pixel
format, and all that stuff.
When we do that, when we're in the PIR choose for amateur for for I'm
sorry, that's not true when we're doing choose visual, right?
We can pass this sort of this sort of stuff.
Now this is looks like the Linux docks.
It's actually the wiggle our lab frame of a srgb one that we actually
care about here.
So I'm not sure if they document that one specifically, let me see.
Doesn't look like it.
Let me just let me see if they've got it.
Let me see if they've got an example somewhere and if they do if they
don't.
But basically when we create our frame buffer, we can make it be srgb
if we want it to be.
So it's this is our
Capability flag.
But where is the actual
Where is the actual?
Let's let's see here.
Let's see.
That's not reassuring, but okay.
Well, I can't actually find really anyone.
That looks like he was talking about this, which is unfortunate, but
what are you gonna do?
So, we'll just kind of, we'll just wing it, which will be fine.
So the point is anyway, ignore all this stuff.
Sometimes I'm able to find things on the web show you.
And sometimes I'm not the point is that like we handled gamma
correction basically in our software renderer, which if you don't
remember that, please go back and and watch.
Those because I it would take quite some time to go through it all
again.
But like we tried to handle gamma correctly.
There's a couple things we can set in opengl to try and handle gamma
correctly in opengl and right now we're not setting any of them.
So as a result like I think in particular, there's some things we
should probably able to notice that it'll be like too bright or too
weird.
Like in general, the the colors shouldn't be quite what they are now.
Unfortunately, I this is why I kind of wish we could toggle between
Our software vendor and not because that way, we could sort of see
what the actual difference was color-wise between them but point being
right now, even though we're feeding it squared values for everything,
it doesn't know that.
And so we don't actually ever get that that
When it's doing the blending, we don't get that srgb awareness.
So in order to do that, there's two different places that we have to
make sure that the srgb stuff works, right?
And it's exactly the same as what we had to do in our renderer.
So if you go look at how our renderer was working, you can see that we
have our M Square PS function, right?
When we load it in the frame, buffer values that we're going to blend
with, right?
We squared them.
Make sense.
And when we did our texels,
they are already.
In school.
How do we do?
Our textiles?
Our textiles are encoded in srgb.
So how do we convert them?
Okay, so we shifted them just how we did it.
It said so the reason we're not squaring them as because we actually
just used shifting to, to make that happen.
It looks like right?
Weird texture from srgb to linear brightness space.
And so those are the two things that have to happen at draw time,
right?
When we grab from the texture, the texture that we grabbed from has to
be converted from srgb to linear.
And when we grab the destination that has to be converted from srgb,
Linear as well then after we're done, right?
Well after we do the combining, then we have to square root to put
things back into srgb space.
So we need to tell opengl to do those steps.
We need to opengl to like change the textures into linear space.
Change the destination into linear space and then change the dust,
change the results back to srgb Safe before writing them out.
and so, really all that has to happen for that is, we have to tell it
about the
the textures.
And so in opengl, when we submitted the textures, you'll notice that
we said what we wanted, the in internal format to be was GL r g b A8,
right?
And so when we submit the texture, what we actually want to do here is
submit, I don't know if there's a good listing of these guys but what
we want to do is like, actually just submit the srgb version of this.
Which I don't even remember what their?
Let me see if I can.
There it is.
so, it is
Let's see.
Dependencies overview texture.
Archie codex controls.
Whether the coding of the sample time to Shriners separates.
Where is the actual value here?
It is.
So it's srgb eight, right?
It should be srgb A8.
There it is.
So it's srgb, 8 Alpha, a text,
Right.
Is I think what we actually want could be wrong, is what we actually
want.
Which unfortunately, I don't know where the values are.
Let's see, sorry, this is a bit boring here.
It is finally
Texture image specification.
And so you can see the internal formats listed srgb, a text srgb
Alpha, a text.
And so instead of telling it that we have a GL rgba 8 texture, we want
to tell it that.
We have an srgb.
Aah.
Alpha 8 x 10, EXT texture, right?
So really what wants to happen here is we want to do something like
this, right?
We want to do something like whatever the type of this thing is, I
believe this is a glue in, right?
So we have our default, internal or opengl.
Default, internal texture format, right?
And that format is going to be by default rgba 8.
But if we detect that the extension is present, then we will set it to
srgb.
A alpha a text which means now our textures will always be sampled
properly, right?
And that doesn't actually help our
That doesn't actually help the frame buffer part of things, but that
will fix the texture part of things and so again I can go in here and
make that the one of our Global's here for the rendering.
Like so.
And then I can go ahead and make that.
Be something that we do.
Okay, then we do with 22 in it opengl.
So when we do win32 in opengl there and we go ahead and make this
happen, we can say, okay, the default route extra ferment is that if
the extension is present, then it's that right, or something like
this, that'll work, just fine.
And then the other only other thing that we're going to have to figure
out
Is we're going to have to figure out how to turn on the the frame
buffer.
So like srgb frame, buffer opengl.
And I don't remember what the enable B is for that, right?
It's I guess a steel frame buffer srgb, it's that guy right there.
So we need to also do call that V 0 and able to make sure that that's
on.
So, we need to do another thing to say, like the, do we have that
extension and if we do have that extension, then we're going to try
and enable GL frame.
For srgb.
Let's see here, GL frame buffer.
To tell it that.
Hey, by the way, we would like that to be on, right?
Let me see here.
So Jill frame buffer.
Srgb is from this extension.
Let's actually talk about anywhere, not really.
So anyway, so that's essentially what we have to do.
Like we have to do something like extension open GL.
Extension is available.
Like this in both cases, and then we would just do that switch.
Now, these values are, of course, not don't exist in our unknown.
No extended version of opengl.
So we will have to Define them to be something to be whatever their
actual values are, right?
And I thought the extensions were supposed to have what they are
defined to be.
I thought that was supposed to be in the extension, but I don't
actually see it here anywhere, but I suspect he'll extension header
file.
We could just use
Some stuff here.
So for example, Geo frame buffer srgb.
And what I've done here is, I've just gone to someone's header file.
Like the opengl core arm extensions, they just have them all in one
giant header file.
We can just grab the ones, we actually want.
So we want this one.
And we want srgb alpha 8.
Oops.
Let's see where that's at.
S, RG abuse to be 88.
There it is.
So that's a those are the two that we actually want now GLS.
Rgba alpha 8 is not the EXT 1, which I wonder if that superseded, it
may well have because these sorts of things as they go through their
little
Yeah, it did.
So the way that the opengl ARB ARB
Explain this.
Barb, I believe stands for architecture.
Review.
Bored.
Right.
So what happens is, the way these extensions work, is somebody
proposes an extension and implemented in their Hardware.
So like Nvidia says, oh I want to implement this srgb thing, they do
it and then they propose it to the ARB as an extension.
It's already implanted in their drivers with their name, right?
It'll have like an Nvidia extension or something.
If it gets extent if multiple vendors decide to implement it, the name
becomes EXT.
And then if the architecture review board says, we want to make this a
permanent.
Part of opengl going forwards.
Then it becomes an ARB and so the names change a lot, they go from
like vendors to the Vic to multi-vendor than to ARP and then they're
just integrated into opengl entirely.
And so this is the final one that got actually in put into our and so
those are the the values that we actually would want to ask for, I
believe.
Now I'm going to actually comment these out so we're not going to even
check to see if these extensions are available.
We're just going to go ahead and call these right now.
Which is not safe.
So we don't actually want to do that tomorrow.
We're
I want to actually make something that does check to see if it's there
but for now we don't actually have to do that.
We can just call it and blissfully unaware of it, right?
So this guy, these guys, if these people want access to these
Global's,
we're going to have to do something like that.
And this guy is this but that's really it for turning on srgb.
It's just a question of setting, some Flags like in that fashion and
this might just work or it might not will find out so that I believe
is the more correct way of doing it.
Now our textures aren't really srgb their squared which is not quite
right.
So really what we probably want to do in the future is I'll modify our
art packs.
Use actual srgb.
So that it'll be 100% correct.
And our software renderer will be the one that's less accurate,
because that's really the way it should be.
I mean, the hardware should be the most accurate version.
Our software under should be the one cutting Corners, right?
So, now we've got actual srgb, rendering happening.
And I feel like it, you can already kind of see that the alpha is a
little bit better, right?
So it definitely looks a little less janky to me as it is at the
moment.
Anyway, so that that's again, the just the basics of the extension
stuff will get it into a little bit more extension stuff, a little
later on, but that's that's basically what that's about.
And yeah, and now we'll go ahead and we'll go to the the Q&A perhaps.
And yeah you can sort of see that there's like I feel like there's a
lot less sort of fringing around the alpha as well, which is nice.
But again, it's still going to be a little bit wrong.
Just because of the way the because we're not our textures are not
actually srgb.
Okay.
So yeah, let's just put it to do in there.
Let's see, will you be implementing multiple render pass depending on
your opengl context version or available extensions at run time?
Probably not.
Because I don't think we're asking for like in a 2-D game, it's pretty
hard to ask for extensions.
That aren't there, right?
So I doubt it.
I mean, if there might be like, if we find, there's one thing.
We want to use that.
We just don't know if it's there, then we might have a little
predicated thing that's like if it's here do this.
Otherwise do that.
The size it, can you fix the Santa sorting?
Yeah, we can fix the Santa sorting.
I don't actually remember how any of this stuff worked, but I assume
that it's just like, because of this situation here.
So what is which one is the Santa situation?
Is it is?
It intro layers for think it's this one.
So, I'm not sure.
I think it's just because this is at negative four and so are all
these
I think that's it.
So we have two choices with, for how to fix that, right?
We can just change the order because I believe our sword is always
stable.
So that would fix the Santa sorting the other way to do it is put the
other one, two, slightly different Z.
Just wait for it.
Wait for Santa.
There he is.
Why is he all?
I don't know what's going on there.
Did I do something weird is changing?
The order of those.
Does that do something strange that?
I don't remember.
It's very confusing.
I really know why that was happening.
I'm going to try.
Putting the background at a slightly further distance, just to see
what's going on there.
While I answer to the question.
Kiss there, a bunch of questions here that are pretty good.
Weird.
So for some reason changing the order really mattered a lot there.
Why is that, is there something special about the first layer that I
don't even know about.
You must be that the sort isn't actually stable.
I don't know.
That's weird.
Anyway, that's fine.
Let me take some more questions here.
Okay, your maximum frame times about 2 to 3 milliseconds, without
vsync enabled.
But with it enabled, I see it stays at 60 ml s supposed to time, but
sometimes goes to 70 most, I guess.
Does that mean it will skip a frame?
Is that a problem with vsync?
No.
So that's, that's not really what's happening.
So, and in fact, I should make this very clear because this was
something that people were confused about before for a totally
different reason.
And so let me just kind of try to hammer it home
All right, so in our code, we have a call to swap buffers.
So what happens is everything?
Step 1, everything step to swap buffers right?
Step 3, everything.
Step four, swap buffers.
And so on.
Okay, so this is the game Loop, right?
The game Loop does all the stuff at call swap buffers and all the
stuff swap buffers, all the stuff write all the code in between the
swap buffers and swap buffers is the thing that tells opengl we're
done with the frame.
So go do all the stuff and and display it right.
And some people were under the misconception that this means wait for
that, it doesn't swap buffers.
Just means that we're done.
It doesn't mean that we stop.
So it can roll straight on through the swap buffers.
It'll, it's just the telling the driver, you can go kick off a frame.
So what actually happens is we plow through here, we call the swap
buffers call back, kicks off the graphics to let it know.
It can start rendering if it hasn't already which I probably actually
has started processing right?
But we keep going and then we get to the next swap buffers and we kick
that off too.
Right?
Because remember, when we don't have vsync enabled, we only take two
milliseconds to sink a frame.
Okay.
So we think a frame.
This is two milliseconds.
We think another frame into Ms.
We could even think a third frame potentially
Right?
And this Frame will not even have been shown on the screen yet.
Then what will happen is?
Some point depending on how the graphics card has chosen to set itself
up, right?
Whether it's a double.
Or triple buffered, right?
At some point, we'll go to a swap buffers and it's like I'm too.
I'm, I can't take any more stuff.
I'm too far behind now and that is when we will actually wait,
If that makes sense.
So as far as I know and I have not looked at this recently, so maybe
this is old and someone's going to tell me.
No, that doesn't do that anymore.
But as far as I know, swap buffers doesn't actually block your
process.
Or I should say the that thread.
It doesn't actually block your thread until the driver actually
decides.
It doesn't want any more info from you, the driver if it wanted to
could decide that it quadruple buffers, right?
And then it's four frames ahead all the time.
Our game is for frames ahead.
And, you know, the, the graphics card is it sort of chewing on all
those frames and displaying them right now.
The graphics card, probably could let you get very far ahead because
there's a lot of memory and
It can do a lot of stuff, right?
But the reason it doesn't is because you don't delete in C increases,
however, long you do this for right because every one of these frames
that took two milliseconds to compute.
Take, 16 milliseconds to display when you wait for the vsync, right?
So, the more frames we sink in the pipeline, the more latency there is
in the controller.
So, while we do want to be one frame ahead because the graphics card
has to have something to work on while we're working.
We want is some overlap there.
We don't want to be like 12 frames ahead because now all of a sudden
you can feel the lag.
And now that that action games not going to feel very good anymore,
right?
but so what you're seeing when we report the frame time has nothing to
do, it's literally unrelated that number
to waiting for a frame to be displayed.
What it is is it's waiting for the driver to tell us when it wants
more information.
and the reason it comes out to 60 milliseconds is because, hey, since
it's waiting till the vsync to display the next frame, the point where
it tells us when it wants more information, after it's gotten this far
ahead, as it wants to get
That point will therefore be very close to the frame time but they're
not.
They could they could be literally completely different if the driver
wanted them to be.
There's no real correlation between them other than the fact that a
well working driver is basing it off of that frame time.
So yeah,
Has nothing.
We won't learn in any danger of missing a frame because of that, that
makes sense.
He's object-oriented, programming bad in general, or for game purposes
and why it's bad in general.
And I've covered it many times Rohit and I believe you do a stir Stir
of jail extensions, then check if the end of the extension is no a
space or tab to see if it exists.
Yeah we can do that.
But I think what I'd rather do is just parse it and have just a little
hash table that tells us whether the extensions that we want or there
or not, right?
Soy sauce.
The kid is there any reason to make the swap out of a larger than one?
Yes.
And we will probably do it ourselves on handmade hero.
The reason is because let's suppose that we're on a machine and we
find that we are unable to hit the actual frame rate of the monitor,
right?
so we're doing a thing where we're like, okay,
You know, we wrote frame BC whatever and this each one of these is
like 60 milliseconds, 16 milliseconds or whatever.
But the machines really slow and we're not hitting it, right?
So we're not hitting these boundaries, we're coming in late, what we
can then do is down shift to 33 milliseconds per frame and set the
swap interval to to
so that we can run at 30 frames a second locked, if we can't run at
60,
Right.
Is there an asynchronous way to do vsync?
I mean a way to ask opengl if it has displayed the frame or how much
time you have to wait until the frame is going to be displayed, not
that I know of
There might be in like in very recent opengl like four point x, it
spot.
Maybe there's a
they're like there might be a
Offense of some kind you can set for that.
But I don't know, I've certainly never done that, but that doesn't
mean that there isn't an extension or something that does do it.
Easy odd, dito Ramirez.
How would you allow the game to run at a non 60 frames a second rate
and not speed up slow down the animation speed?
Well it's pretty simple straightforward right?
Our game already just runs off of a DT.
So this value right here, is just as long as when you run the as long
as when you call the game game update and render, as long as you pass
the correct value for that, for whatever your update rate, actually,
is then you're fine.
K, apologies.
If you explained this before or since rotation is stored in the upper
3x3, part of the
Matrix and scale is stored in the 0, 0, 1 1, 2 2 diagonal.
How do they play well together?
I mean, wouldn't change the rotation or scale?
Affect the other.
Let's hold off on that question for a second.
Let me see if there's anything related to what we're doing right now
first.
Quickly games, you mentioned 120 hertz.
How do you handle skipping every other vsync event?
Do you just detect the monetary face Rhett rate?
And if one trying hurt swap twice in a row, yeah, basically if we
detect the monitor, refresh rate is higher than 60 hertz.
What we can do is set swap interval to whatever that divisor is.
At least we can try.
Connor rents.
If vsync is disabled in Windows.
Will there be no vsync at all?
Correct.
If vsync is disabled in Windows, we will not get it and that's why I
say it's a request, not a guarantee.
The glove in the scene where Krampus is giving it to the kid.
Looks a bit strange with the thumb pointing downwards.
Okay, noted long billion?
Why does he sink cause input lag on some machines?
Because again, it means that there's a deeper buffering.
Like these think adds latency just period, right?
Because it's delaying when a friend is frame is displayed until the
point when it won't tear.
And so there's always going to be a little bit of latency
So it doesn't add much, but it can add some and especially if the
frame rate is low.
Look at the frame rates, only 34 frames a second or 15 frames a
second.
20 frames a second.
You end up with with a lot with some, some possibly noticeable time
being added in there.
What are the trade-offs to storing the textures on disk in the same
linear Colour space for Matt you were using you don't really want to
store Textures in a linear Colour space because you waste a lot of
bits.
The human eye doesn't perceive dark tones the same way it perceives
light tones.
Light tones, need less data than dark tones to represent properly.
So that's why we have srgb in the first place.
So in order to get better color quality for the same number of bits in
your textures, you
To store them nonlinearly and that's why we do this nonsense with
changing from the nonlinear space to the linear space to operate on
them.
And then putting them back at says so that we don't use unnecessary
amounts of data.
See Flixster.
Any update on when to implement sound effects?
Who knows whenever we decide?
That's a good idea, Garland.
A balloon.
What is the bottle full of that?
John post on Twitter?
I have no idea.
Nibbler, we're still fading from to the desktop.
Did you have to re-implement that?
Is it being Hardware?
Rendered is the
Here to stay.
So the reason that that's back is because when we switched opengl to
being to not be double buffered, and is said to be just background
glitter, whatever the same thing that fixed OBS allows Are Over the
Top window to still work.
So that's why that's working.
With wiggle swap interval, do we still have to do sleep at the end of
the frame?
Could you also comment on GL finish gel flush and how they're used?
Sure.
So wiggle, swap interval, like I said, doesn't actually guarantee us
the vsync, so we don't have to sleep at the end of the frame.
If wiggle swap interval is working, but if it's not working, we will
probably have to.
But yet it will do a sleep there for us effectively, so we don't have
to sleep if we will swap intervals, sleeping.
So, so that's a good thing Geo.
Finish until flush or not really relevant for us GL, finishing GL
flush.
Just tell the graphics card about particular times when you want stuff
to happen.
So, for example, if you want to force all rendering to finish, you can
call GL flush.
I believe, I don't remember, which is which they each one of them, is
a more stringent guarantee than the other and I don't remember which
one is the more stringent
I never call these functions.
Let's cgl flush.
Yeah.
So I guess what I would say is Gee L finish from Rich briefly reading
it GL.
Finish is the full completion one.
So basically GL finish says I want to wait until you finish all the
rendering that you have to do and don't come back to me until that's
true.
So that pipeline.
Where are saying, look, we kick off the renders and they're going
while we're doing stuff.
If you want to say no I want you to finish everything right now.
Please you could call GL finish.
We don't really want to do that.
So we don't call that
That's what that would be GL flush on the other hand is just a way of
saying.
Hey, if you're buffering anything right now, in anticipation of
kicking it off, I would like you to kick it off now, the don't wait
till it's done, but Kick It Off please.
So it's kind of like asking for like a buffer flush in like the C
runtime Library where you're saying, hey actually go flush this buffer
of stuff, I'm writing out to disk please, but it doesn't
Sara Lee guarantee that the operating system has finished writing it,
right?
It's just saying, hey, kick off the right.
Insofar, as we use x, swapped are negative 1 in the swap interval
call.
Hopefully, not
should we wait for swept over his weight exercise that returns to
fast?
Yes, that's what I was saying before.
Whereas like, we're still going to have to do
some work there.
Would it be better to minimize or maximize how much you do per frame?
Like, would it be better to make your program take any time that it
would be waiting for vsync and instead, focus it on performing, more
computations even potentially Computing, things ahead of time.
But that's what we are doing right?
That's exactly what what's what the swap buffers currently does.
Like I said, you come through to your swap buffers call and if if it
can keep buffering,
Up it will.
But if you've reached the end of the amount of buffering that the GP
is going to do, then you stop.
So you already are able to get quite far ahead right and but you don't
you just you gotta stop at some point otherwise your game runs off and
now your input lag is way too big, right?
So, you have to only buffer one or two frames.
You can't let it go too far.
Tiberian, how do you easily affect the vsync is active?
You just gotta check the monitor resync, refresh.
If you can and then see how long it takes and make sure there are
similar, right?
Okay, let's see here.
How do I vsync and prevent tearing with a dual monitor setup?
Is it any different than a single monitor setup?
Yeah, okay, so if you're, if you're on a dual monitor setup, you have
to do a thing called a swap swap chain, or a swap group.
Swap meet.
You got to do this stuff.
basically what you do is you say like, okay I'm going to like issue,
all the rendering calls, I need to each of these contexts, one for
each of the windows that I'm trying to draw and then depending on, you
know, all of those depending on assuming that you want them all to
update the same time, maybe you have, you know, if you have 12
monitors and you want six to be 1 times 6 to the other something but
assuming want them all at one time, they're all added something called
a swap group and then you say
okay, I need you to go ahead and update the
Group now, right?
And then that will flip them all at the same time.
All right, it is 6:30.
So
I think I will conclude.
Bloop.
All right.
I think that's everything.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coating with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on him here at organic comes with a source code,
which you can use to follow the series if you would.
Like, that's a handmade here at or argh, there's also links to the
forums where you can go to.
Ask question about the series.
There's our patreon page where you can support the video series and
there is our tweet bot which of course tweets the schedule.
You if you want to catch the series live in, if you do want to catch
the series Live, you
Catch it live tomorrow at 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time if I'm not too sick by then and that will be our
last stream of the week.
That's about it for now.
I will catch you guys tomorrow.
Hopefully, until then have fun programming and I'll see you on the
internet.
Take it easy.