Start recording.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on Twitch.
No engine.
No Library.
Just are only our wits to guide us really.
And, you know, sometimes that can be a problem because some days
you're just not smart enough, you're just not and you know what?
That's okay.
Because at the end of the day programming is a marathon, it's not a
Sprint and so you just have to keep at it and eventually you'll get
where you're going.
That's my motto.
Anyway,
And today we are totally keeping at it.
We're working on some Z, stuff that we've been working on for a couple
days.
And, of course, it wasn't really a problem of us not being smart
enough.
It was the problem of just us having a bunch of things that we wanted
to figure out.
And so we're kind of going through and figuring out how we want to
handle everything in terms of layers in the game.
And so we kind of opened up a bunch of things yesterday because
there's there's, we sort of have this little thing that when we can
walk up and down levels and kind of a little imaginary stairwell thing
and it kind of opened up a bunch of things that we need to
Take care off to get Z handling, totally solid in the game.
And that was really one of the big unknown pieces in terms of engine
architecture.
And it's not really a necessarily about the architecture per se
meaning it's not really about necessarily how the components that are
running the game fit together but it is sort of about this the
underlying language of the game, right?
Like how it treats Z and how the different components look at Z and
use, Z is something that we don't want to.
To leave in the air for very long, right?
We want to get that nailed down before we start writing any game code,
certainly because we don't want to be in this situation where we get
halfway through the game and realize our Z is totally wrong.
So we want to be able to sort of know that we've done a good
exploratory job and have a reasonably good opinion about how ours he's
going to work before we kind of push through that.
So before I get started, let me just remind everyone.
It is day 108.
That means if you have pre-ordered the game
Handmade here, dot org and you want to follow along at home at the
source code, exactly.
As I am doing it, you will need to unzip day 107 source code.
So go ahead and unzip that into a directory and that is all you would
need to follow along with what I'm doing.
Well and of course the free version of Visual Studio, A Community
Edition or whatever.
But let's go ahead and take a look at where we're at, right?
And let's talk about some of the things that we need to do to get us
to where we want to be.
So we set up.
Some interesting stuff here.
Basically, what we did is we said well, we're not going to draw any
ground, we're just going to draw the trees for now because that if the
ground were there, it would obscure the different levels and we
actually have several levels.
Now, stacked on top of each other and we drew these little.
We don't actually have a bitmap for stairwells yet, which is a little
bit of a mistake on our part.
But what you going to do?
So we drew these little yellow rectangles in there and we can use
them, we can actually use them to walk down.
Levels, right?
So I can I can keep going up to the top of the stairwell and then
walking down it and you can kind of see that as I do that we descend,
right?
And if I want to walk upwards we Ascend to the next level, right?
Like so.
And you can also see that we're doing some fading in and out.
There, you can see is the trees come in, they fade.
But what you'll notice in the thing that I kind of left off with
yesterday, which I think might be a good thing to fix today at the
start, is you'll notice that we're not like the
Actual Z motion of things is not correct.
Like if you if you've ever just looked at even in the real world,
you'll know that s things.
If things are moving towards you or moving away from you, they appear
to be moving faster as they get closer to you, not as they get further
away.
But as you can see, from the way it's working here, that's that's not
what's going on, right?
Things in the distance are actually moving faster towards us than
things in the front, and that's because we haven't done anything.
To try and do proper perspective to make our game.
Actually have that real 3D movement feel in Z and even though we're
not a 3D game, we are handling a bunch of Z as if we are a 3D game and
we just our art happens to be 2D.
And so what we want to do is we want to get the math right there so
that it will look as good as it can look because it won't affect our
performance really, to do the correct Z calculation.
So, if we go ahead and do all the optimization on our renderer to
handle all the stealing and stuff like we're planning to do, I
We already wrote the simple version, but when we do the optimized
version for doing all that work to support scaling and stuff, we want
to make sure we don't lose all of the goodness that we get from that
by having a stupid function, that calculates, the scaling at the head
end, which is the cheap part, right?
So what I want to do today is talk a little bit about how that works
and then we'll go ahead and try to set up something where we can
compute, what those values should be in a more correct way.
So let's take a look.
Let's go over to the Blackboard here and take a look at that.
I can kind of try to explain a little bit about how 3D transforms work
without going into too much detail on stuff that we don't care about
because we're 2D.
But while still kind of hoping to give you a full enough picture that
you understand how it works in general.
Okay.
Now, I'm going to draw both the traditional diagram, and a little
extension of the traditional diagram, just to set you up for Success.
Should you ever try to step past a 2-D game into a 3D game and want to
kind of understand what's going on?
So anyway, I, I want you to imagine, if you will, you're monitor,
right?
You've got, you've got a monitor, right?
And I'm going to draw this.
This is the screen here.
And you are back here somewhere, right?
And you are looking at the monitor, okay?
And if you know this is where you are.
This is your eye.
And you're you know there's your eyelashes lovely and you're looking
at the screen, right?
You can kind of imagine that what you want to have happen is you want
the screen to behave almost as if it were a window into a
three-dimensional world that were behind it, right?
And what we want to do is we want to draw things on this screen at the
locations where they would appear, right?
If they were to be flattened onto the screen based on where your I was
actually,
Really seeing them if they were out here, right?
So if I have, you know, some kind of a cube that's out here, right?
That I'm trying to draw.
Like so then you can imagine drawing a line out to each of the points
of the cube.
Like, so, right and seeing where that line intersects the monitor,
right?
And then if you drew the cube, with those points, that would give you
the perspective version of the cube, right?
Because if you think about it, no matter where we sort of take a plane
in the world, if we were to take all of that incoming light, right?
You can imagine this is light, that's coming.
Into your eye or something like that.
If we were to just capture all of the light that was passing through
that plane and found all of it that was headed for your eye.
That would give us.
Write that complete picture.
Okay.
And so if you think about looking how this looks from the side right
here is the monitor.
So I'm taking this, this piece here.
There's the monitor right here is the eyeball
And here's my Cube.
Alright, so here is that line that I'm drawing right down to the that
Iris and you can actually see here where it would intersect, right?
And what I want you to notice.
Is that these points?
This cube is totally aligned right with the horizontal and if we
wanted to project it straight across both this point.
And this point, let's say this is point a and this is point B.
These two points would actually be projected to the exact same place,
right?
They be projected to like there,
But if we were going to do this sort of perspective, projection, and
that, by the way is orthographic.
That's what they call an orthographic projection in orthographic.
Projection didn't mean to put an S on the end of that, an orthographic
projection is one where points project in straight, parallel lines
onto that.
The, the imaginary display surface there, right?
That were pretending is the monitor.
But if we actually use perspective lines, right, you can see that
Loops draw.
That very well really need some kind of a 3D imaging, like one of
those little construction programs, if we were to do these lines in
perspective so that they all converge at the I point, right?
Then, you'll notice that the same points that were at the same level,
which would have been projected to the same point.
If we were orthographic in perspective,
Right, which is what this kind of projection is.
In perspective, they actually appear sort of shrunk down, right?
You can, you can sort of imagine if I was to take like the other one
here, right?
The back part of the cube, even though it's exactly the same size.
As the front part that back part projects onto a much smaller plate, a
much Fuller area, right?
It's only that big, whereas the same size object under that big and so
what we get here is this is is you know, what they often call, you
know, foreshortening, right?
Or just perspective you see terms thrown around for it not necessarily
in technical sense, but in an artistic sense, even right?
But that's what's going on there, right?
The shrinking is because we are trying to project things as if we are
capturing the light that's heading to your eye.
Now it's not quite as simple as that.
I will briefly mention the more complex diagram that's actually a
little more accurate.
This is the simplistic one that we're going to use and that most books
use for three weeks waiting 3D.
So we'll stick with it so you can follow along with those cuts expire.
There's actually a slightly more complete explanation, which is that
in Optics when you're actually talking about capturing light, it
doesn't really work this way.
What actually happens, right?
Is you've got a lens assembly, right?
And I'll sort of idealized that lens assembly by drawing just a single
lens.
Right.
But you imagine like, a camera or your eye or something like that,
right?
What?
Actually happens and I apologize.
Effect, turn off your brain and don't listen.
To this right now, if you're afraid of being confused by stuff that
doesn't apply to today's lesson, because this is entirely optional
everything that I'm saying from from here, until when I tell you to
turn the brain back on, okay?
But for people who just want to know, this is how things actually
work.
So in the real world, it's not quite as simple as that.
What actually happens is, there are lenses either your eyeball or a
camera lens, something like that.
And light, that is coming in to the lens.
Like so,
Right, light that is coming into the lens, hits, the lens and gets
refracted, right?
Which is the term we use to describe what happens to light when it
passes through something, which does not absorb it.
But only changes its direction, right?
It gets refracted and focus down to a point, okay?
That point is called the focal point.
It is behind the lens somewhere and you can see, it's kind of similar
to this drawing.
We drew over here but what then happens is the light continues, right?
Because it's just focusing to a point and then continuing through
there's nothing to gather the light there.
And then in the back we actually have something that gathers it right.
Either?
It would be your retina right in if this was your eyeball, right?
Or it would be like the image plane or the film back in a camera.
Let's say, right.
The actual thing that you're trying to expose the light to write or
the sensor in a digital camera, okay?
And the reason that this diagram is relatively important to
understand.
If you want to understand more advanced imaging techniques, is that if
you look at what happens here it is.
Not the case that a point in the real world is only sending light in
one direction to a pixel on the screen, right?
What's actually happening.
A cone of light, that is the radius of the lens big at the lens and
which focuses down to a single point at the point where you're talking
about the, the light reflecting, right?
So photons are coming in here, right?
Photons are hitting some surface.
Let's imagine.
This is some surface here, whatever it is.
This is the wall photons are coming in from all directions.
Remember when we talked about lighting photons are coming in from all
directions, they're hitting this and they're bouncing out
Out.
Right.
All of the photons that bounce out within this, cone will all hit the
lens and we'll all project two points on back on this, on this image
plane, right?
And it's kind of hard to draw a single diagram, which actually
captures how that will work, because I can't show you.
It's a very multi-dimensional problem.
There's where the point is dependent determine sort of where it
projects.
To the film back and The Cone, right?
You imagine is not actually focusing quite to a point.
It's actually doing sort of this sort of a thing back here, right?
There's there's sort of this this this different sort of process
happening with all the light that happens.
So it's actually kind of confusing to think about exactly how this
actually works.
If I was to draw one, perhaps a little bit more accurately for an
image, it would look something.
if the supports that it would look something,
Probably raise the part back here as well.
Okay, here we go.
It would look something like okay I've got this back here.
This is my actual image right?
And at each point on the image, right?
I'm going to end up with all of the light that could have hit this
point, right?
That pass through this lens and the part that I'm trying to get to
which is really hard to draw this diagram, right?
This is probably why computer graphics books, don't go into this kind
of detail until you get to physically based rendering.
But basically, the point that I was trying to get to so far is that
what happens here, right?
Is that when this light passes out in to hit the lens right and it
gets refracted.
Well, it depends where this point is where it's going to actually
capture the light from, right.
Right.
And so you have to imagine, like, all of the
Is that are going to hit that point from the lens, all get projected
down and hit a specific point out in the real world.
Like so.
Okay, I try to draw this as accurate as I can.
I don't know if I did a very good job.
But so here is a point on the image plane here is a point in the world
and there is our wall, a mover wall up so it can hit it there.
Right?
And so what you can see is the actual light that's passing through the
lens here is actually much.
There's actually more
More light coming than just a single Ray that hits directly.
It's a whole family of rays that are in a cone, right?
And what this means is the bigger, the lens size, like the bigger, the
actual physical size of the lens is the more actual light from
surfaces.
It's capturing and actually The Wider, the angle of stuff coming off
of the surface is Right.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
So what happens in this process is you're not just talking
About single point projected single points.
First you have that cone right, which hopefully I've Illustrated here
to some degree and then you also have what's often called Boca or
depth of field.
Which is that you have to remember what would happen if there wasn't a
wall right here, where these things converge, right?
Suppose, the wall actually was back where I originally drew the wall,
right?
So here is my wall.
So the points all converge here.
Then what happens is?
They fan out again, right?
And so now, not only am I capturing light from a cone from a point,
right?
All of the photons passing through there that come out of here,
But the actual area in the world that is contributing light to that
point is not infinitesimal, its large, right?
And the further back the wall is from this point.
The more of those photons.
The bigger the area is that I would sort of be capturing and this is
called like the focus point, right?
This is this is actually where you are focusing, right?
That's the focus of the camera.
So anything that's right in here.
Will be nice and crisp but everything that's
Outside, or if I was to move it closer.
Again, look at that area.
It's taking a whole area and projecting it onto one point, right?
So everything that's nearby to this appears to be in Focus because all
of the points in the cone that are focused on the lens are actually
coming from a single point, but as you move away in either direction,
you get blurrier and that's where you get depth of field from right?
So there's one more part of this equation.
Okay.
Which is that how wide this is is actually not only determined by the
lens assembly.
It's also determined by something called the aperture and the aperture
is of synthetic device that has nothing to do with the lens.
It's just in there and what it does is.
It closes to a certain size.
Thus clipping off part of the raised so that they can't get through,
right?
This is what you set.
When you set something like an F, stop on your camera, okay?
And as you can see, if you were to set the aperture to a wider size,
you will get.
So if the f-stop is wider right?
Which corresponds to lower values of f, stop the way that they do
f-stop numbers.
I won't go into because that's if your
We're not doing any of this on the street.
Like I said, you can do not worry about it, but I just thought I'd
give you some insight into how physical rendering works if you're
actually doing say a ray Tracer or something.
I actually simulate some of this in the game that I'm doing in for my
day job.
But anyway, so if you set this f-stop to a lower number, it means it's
wider.
So there's more it's like it's a, it might let this whole cone in,
right?
But if you set it to a narrower setting, right?
Then it's going to be it's going to be higher f-stop number, right?
So for example if you have a lens that's got an F stop of to, you
know, set to 2, that's going to be very wide and taking a pretty large
coat.
If you set your camera's, f-stop to 14, it's going to be very narrow
and what you can see, if you imagine what happens there as this gets
narrower and narrower, the cone collapses down to something that is
very close to a line.
What happens?
Less
Light.
More depth of field, right?
Or I should say more things in Focus, right?
Because as you cut that down the apparent area, like imagine if I was
to cut out, right?
Like let's take just this area here, right?
So we have that Focus Point.
Here is the focus point and we've got all these lines passing through
it right.
Well, you can kind of see that if I was to allow, right?
If I'm to allow that whole cone through, then I'm talking about the
focus diverging very quickly out here, but if I was to in stay, only
be letting in ones that were very narrow cone.
You can see that.
I have a lot further to go before I widen out to the same amount,
right?
And so setting, that f-stop, number higher, reduces the amount of
light thereby.
Making it more difficult to capture, same nighttime imagery, but
giving you a wider Focus range so that you can have more
Things in focus at the same time, right?
So, I hope that makes some sense to you.
This is what's actually happening and what we're doing in the
simplification, which now you're going to turn your brain back on a
very shortly.
So, warm up here, get ready to turn your brain back on, it's time.
Okay.
So the simplification that we use when we're not trying to simulate
these effects.
Like if we don't care about polka, if we don't care about lens
aberration, which is stuff that happens because this is not a perfect
comical thing.
If we don't care about like
Just to give you some.
A of crazy stuff you can do.
If you're doing photorealistic rendering, you can simulate light
bounce inside the camera.
So, for example, there's camera walls here as this comes in.
Some of the stuff will get deflected up here.
But then that will bounce out and deflected, like, back onto the film
back eventually.
So really, really bright light sources can cause light bounce, which
will wash out the image.
There's all kinds of things like this.
In fact, you may have noticed.
I'll give you one more thing before you turn your brain back.
Kahn.
You may have noticed that your a see the these these these Bros out
there at the sporting events for like ESPN and stuff.
And they've got a camera that is like, f an absurd.
It looks like something like this, you know, and like it goes all the
way back and the cameras like this little thing, right?
And it's got this huge gigantic thing on it that's like a giant
shotgun thing, right?
So then at the end of that, there's like this huge hood on it.
I mean, this is like what the camera looks like, right?
It's a giant phallus.
It's a giant thing, right?
And what you'll notice is, there's two parts of that lens assembly,
right?
One of it is the lens assembly.
That's actually, just used for getting that really long.
It long range, which I won't talk about how the lens assembly works.
But you want a, you want a sort of a bigger lens assembly if you're
trying to shoot things that are far away, we'll ignore that part for
now.
But you'll notice there's this
Big hood on the front and it has nothing to do with the lens.
It's just a thing.
You like, screw onto the lens and you've seen it on cameras to even on
personal cameras like a dlsr, a DSLR camera, right?
That's, that's reasonable.
Something that kind of looks, you know, like this sort of a thing as
regular camera.
You see it.
You put on a thing, right?
That looks kind of like that.
It's like this little four-sided hat thing that goes on the camera,
right?
And you're like what you know, what is that thing?
Why is that on there?
And the
The answer is because again, light coming into the lens, will bounce
around in here and it will hit the film back.
It would all, we'll all the photons are coming.
Here are going to hit something and it gives or buy something.
And there's a hole in here where they can pass through bounce around
and hit.
Now.
For light, that's pretty weak, it doesn't matter because so few
photons will actually get through and hit this thing that you don't
care.
But when you're shooting in, say bright sunlight, which is when they
tell you to put this thing on, there are so many photons entering the
lens that if the sun was like up here and you have a
Ton of photons.
That would be coming in off angle.
They would bounce around in here and wash out your image.
You'd get collection on the film back.
So what they do is they put in a hood right here like that, right to
block out those errant ones and only capture light that's coming in
directional, from the way that the camera is facing right now.
You may ask, why is it shaped like this, right?
Why is it shaped in sort of this?
This, this way, where there's only like four,
Four pieces to it.
Whereas this one shaped like that, right?
And the answer to that is a little more confusing.
But it basically boils down to the shape of the sensor in the back.
You don't really need a spirit.
You don't need a cylindrical Hood because typically the actual film
back itself, cuts out some of the bounce because it's not the, you
know, the lens is circular, but the film back is rectangular, right?
And so you're setting up these, these sort of blockers right to to
block specifically where the film back is going to actually be
be right.
And so you need heavy blockers on the top and the bottom because
that's where it's lined up the circle, right?
Let me see if I can, I can't really say anything.
To useful here.
All right, so you have a circle, right?
And the circle looks something like this.
It's overlaid.
I'm not doing a very good idea, Java this, right?
I have a circle, that looks like this, right?
And then I have a welt.
It's probably more like this.
So I have a circle that looks like this, right?
You can see that right here.
Here here and here, right?
You actually don't have all of this extra lens stuff, right?
Capturing more photons, then should even be coming in where the actual
sensor can collect them, right?
We're not even looking at this part of the image.
Technically it should never can contribute, But the lens is a circle
and the film back is a
So you don't need, you need blockers on the top, the sides and the
bottom.
But right at the corners, you don't need as much because you don't
have as much of the lens contributing extra photons into the image as
you do here.
So, the actual shape of this Hood can be, you know, notched when they
have to do the longer hoods because you're trying to really narrow
down that Barrel because you've got a really big lens vac here, thats
collecting a ton of light, right?
Then they just do a circular head.
I think because it would just
it'd be stupid to try and match this in at all, but I don't really
know.
I'm not sure what their rationale is for not keeping this size.
I think it's just turns to it tends to just be easier to deal with
like this structurally.
But anyway, that's our little tour into photorealism again.
You don't have to know a single piece of this to do handmade hero.
We will do absolutely none of this really, but I just thought I'd give
you the background so that, you know, I only learned this way and it
was really annoying because I couldn't understand like all these
techniques until I learned
Other way.
And so I just wanted to give you a way to think about it and it also
makes your camera makes sense, right?
You can understand how your camera Works entirely just by knowing
getting familiar with this diagram, right?
Whereas this will tell you nothing about how your camera works, you
have no idea how the camera works, right?
So anyway, back to this.
So we understand how this works.
We're all good.
The approximation we want to use is one where we don't have any Focus
effects.
We're just going to pretend that everything's in Focus all the time.
So wherever something is we just trace it.
Back to a single pin hole Point basically.
And if you want to think of this as a camera instead of thinking of
this, as a monitor out here that we're figuring out where the points
are, you could almost think of the film back as being back here and
we're just figuring out where things on the film back actually.
Are the reason why it's a little bit weird to do that is because
obviously you can see what happens to the light here, is it flips
around when it gets back here.
So you actually produce a negative image on a camera.
And by the way, that's actually what happens cameras flip, the images
that they have or you might think of the film is being loaded up side.
Down and reversed or whatever, right?
A mirrored film.
If you will, that is actually what happens.
I guess, mirror?
It is the wrong term.
Just flip just completely flipped, right?
However, you want to however you want to do that.
I trapped use the word mirror because it, I don't know, it's hard to
explain, it's hard.
That means like negating one access which is not necessarily what I'm
trying to say.
I'm trying to say that.
It it totally inverts itself on both axes, right?
It negatives and negatives, right?
Okay.
Ignore that.
Ignore that again down, important.
So what we want to do, right?
Is we want to figure out how we can compute say where this thing
should be on the monitor or if we want to do film back where it is on
the film back, they're actually both the same equation for the most
part, so we should figure out how to do it.
How do we do that?
Well, this turns out to be a very easy diagram to construct and solve,
right.
It's very, very simple.
If we are back here and we'll say that this is our I, right?
So that's RI point, maybe
we will call that e, right?
And then out here, we know we've got some image plane that we're going
to intersect with and we'll use the forward method because again, I
think this is how it's normally discussed and can see G books.
So curious, you know, our monitor, right?
And so, what we'll do is, we'll just call this distance here, right
the distance from the eye to the monitor.
We'll just call that D for now, write the distance between those two.
And then we have out here, we actually have the point that we want to
project.
And so we're looking for, right?
Like this.
We're looking for
This point right here, P Prime.
Okay.
And now, as you can see, this is essentially a diagram that works no
matter in one axis at a time.
So we don't actually care which Acts were solving.
We could just, you know, say We'll solve for x or something, whichever
one we want to do, we're going to solve the same equation for every
axis X and Y, right?
So what do we actually need?
Well, we need to know how far this p is from E, right?
And that's pretty easy to figure out, right?
There's not much we would need to do there.
We know that we have, for example, a measurement, axis, here.
We know that we have, you know, whatever this axis we want to be.
Is and right now we're we've already said it Z, right?
We're looking right down the z-axis, although I guess Z is coming up.
So technically, Z goes this way, right?
But we know we've already sort of talk
About the fact that Z in our world goes up and goes up out of the
screen.
So we already know that this is the Z axis.
So really this distance here.
Right?
Is just whatever the Z coordinate is of this guy, right?
It's the cameras, z- his Z, right?
Because the cameras, he's going to be higher, right?
The eyes, I should say that.
I see, you know what, maybe I should call this C for camera cameras.
Easy peasy, right?
So, this distance here is camera, z- peasy, right?
And what you can see, if we construct this here, is we've actually got
similar
Angles here, right?
These are the same triangle but for the size right here is a right
triangle with the same angle here and the same angle here.
And here is another right.
Triangle with the same angle here, same angle here and what we know
from.
If you remember way back in your high school geometry or trig classes,
I don't even know.
I think it's probably geometry classes.
If we want, we can always construct a ratio of any sides of similar
triangles, right?
So if we know that this side of this triangle here is D and the side
of the bigger triangle is cz- peasy, right?
Then we know we have a ratio that that would map the other points.
We need P Prime and P, right?
Because we know that P Prime to P is going to be the same as that.
Devalue is to the
Z- p z, right?
That's, that's what we know about these triangles.
So, if we multiply out this ratio, right?
If we just solve this ratio, we would get P times d, right?
Are actually do it Vector style there D times P, right?
So, we have D times P, just cross-multiply equaling again.
Cross multiply here, c, z- p, pz p Prime.
Right.
And what you see here is, if P Prime is the thing we want to
No, then we just have to divide by this to get it, right?
So we'd have DP / c, z- p, z equals P Prime.
And that is the perspective projection equation in a nutshell, right
there?
That's all there is to it.
And what you can see right here, and you can understand, hopefully now
why we were doing it wrong.
If you remember when we just threw in that fudge value and I said, I
want to talk about it later.
It's because I wanted to show you all that stuff on the Whiteboard.
I didn't want to just throw in a correct solution and everyone be
like, what are we talking about?
if I actually go in here and
Let's see.
That was in get render entity basis.
You can see that we computed as e, fudge value here and we can
computed this easy.
Fudge value based on the Z coordinate so it seems like it's kind of
okay.
But then what did we do?
We multiply by it.
Right?
And as you can see, the equation for perspective, projection is not a
multiplication.
It's a division and that is why we're not having realistic Motion in
our Z.
Remember, take
A look at this, right?
You can see how that works.
It's like some kind of weird Stargate.
Right?
Which would be nice if what we were constructing was a Stargate and be
sure to remember that effect should you ever want to construct the
Stargate?
But if we actually want our game to look like it has some 3D
perspective going on it, that is not the way to do it.
So let's think about how we would actually do this, right?
We want to implement this equation right here.
Now, what do we know?
Well P Prime is the thing that we want to solve for, right?
And so again this equation Works in both X and Y.
So, you know, you can imagine PX D PX, right?
Right.
Or equivalently the exact same equation.
Works in y right?
Like so, so both equations exactly the same to solve for each of our
variables, right?
So, what do we want to do here, right?
We want to solve for p Prime.
Well, that's our excuse me, that's our result P, right?
That's the thing that we're trying to solve for, okay?
And I guess right here, it's entity.
Ground point is actually the thing that we're projecting.
And so, in fact, what is this even week?
We decided to stop doing this thing?
Well, I don't know, that's just the way it is.
So anything.
Ground point is the thing that we're projecting.
And you can see right here that this is the part where we
A projection.
We take the entity based e XY and we add the entity base offset X Y,
to essentially produce sort of the unprojected version of the point,
right?
So this is kind of like the raw X Y that we did here, right?
That's our row XY.
But then we just we multiplied it by this by this value.
Okay, now the problem with doing that multiplications, what we
actually want to do is a division.
And so this this right here this dpy we know what the pi the in the
pxr
That's our raw Y and X.
Right?
That's what this is.
In fact, I could, I could even call them that if you wanted, although
I guess row.
XY is fine for now.
That's our raw X and Y.
And what we want to do is we want to actually compute this equation.
So we need a d value here.
So instead of being Z fudge, which is actually based on the Z
distance, what we actually need here is whatever that distance is
essentially the, the focal length, right?
We need, we need to know.
Oops, we need to know D, right?
And remember, what D is, is this the length from the, it's a distance
from the camera to the monitor, right?
And so, that's what we need to know.
They're okay.
Again, in this has to be
In the actual space that we care about.
So one thing that's interesting here to is, I guess now that I think
about it.
How is this working?
Exactly.
We did m.
2 pixels first, I don't know if we really want to do that.
We probably want to do all of this in meters actually first, right?
And so if you take a look at what's Happening Here, what we want to do
is we want to start getting rid of this stuff.
I think we want to save it.
Till the end here.
So it's something more like that if that makes sense this sort of
thing, right?
So that we're actually doing that that m 2 pixels at the end so we can
do everything else in meters.
So here we go.
Let's go ahead and say we've got distance from camera to monitor,
write something like that or just distance to monitor, that sort of
thing.
And, you know, how far is the monitor way in reality, is probably a
totally fine thing to use.
I feel like it's probably what.
I don't know maybe about a third of a meter or something like that.
I'm not sure how far I am away.
I need to look a ruler here or something like that, but let's say
we've got that far to the monitor, right?
And then in our world,
We then need to know that sort of that Z distance and in order to
compute the Z distance, we know that the Z distance is how far away we
are, right this this entity based P.
So we need our distance to P or I should say, maybe Z distance to
monitor something like that.
I need to know the distance to the point in Z, right?
I need this c, z- p, z thing.
And in order to do that, well we know what the points Z is right.
But we only know it relative to the place we're looking at, right?
Because remember, we did all this centered around a camera location.
We're looking at which is not actually where the camera is.
So if you imagine here is sort of a, maybe I'll do it this way, if you
imagine Kira's the world we were talking about looking at this point,
but that
He's the cameras actually somewhere up here pointing down at it,
right?
So we also have another value, which is essentially how far away is
the camera from what it's looking at, right?
And so, we have another one, which is basically like distance above
ground or camera distance above ground, right?
And so, who knows how far the camera is above ground.
That is something we can tune to taste, but maybe it's, you know, I
don't know how big we want it to be.
It's, you know, 10 meters above the ground for now and we can
basically play with these
Has values.
These are purely arbitrary values.
Obviously for framing the shot and setting the, the lens type, right?
They don't matter at all, we can pick them to you, whatever.
Whatever looks good we know, we will still get something that behaves
similar to a camera and so that distance 2pz right is going to be
whatever the entity based based peas Z was right.
And remember, that's going to be
If that number is positive, right?
It's actually going to be closer to us because he comes up words, and
if it's negative, it's going away.
So we actually want to subtract the Z value from the distance to
monitor because as it gets - gets, I'm sorry from the camera distance
above ground because it actually, as it gets - it's getting further
away from us, right?
So we want to make this value.
Get larger.
That time.
So then we get our distance to PC.
We now have essentially everything that we need right to compute that
the equation.
Okay?
So let's go ahead and compute the equation.
Go back and scroll to it.
There it is.
So we want dpy, right?
And so we know what the p y p.
The p x py is, right?
We know that those are entity based the sorry.
We know that there they are.
Right there.
We know that they are raw X Y.
That's the, that's the actual value.
So we want our distance to the monitor.
Times that right?
And then we want to divide that by that sort of denominator and I'm
going to I'm going to call it denominator and that that will compute
our result, right?
So this is our new, what should I call this?
I guess we'll call this projected XY.
All right so there's projected X Y so I don't want to just do the
divided by the denominator because what we have to do here first is
verify that that denominator will actually be
Positive right we do or I shouldn't even say positive.
We want to make sure that it's not going to be a divide by zero,
right?
So we have to pick some cut off there so that when things get super
close to the camera, we will no longer draw them.
Otherwise, they would potentially be directly on the camera or
something.
That'd be like if you passed through the lens of the camera and got
back into the camera itself or something like that, right?
So what we need to do is compute that denominator.
The denominator again is the cameras, easy right?
-
The point Z and so that's what we've already computed here, right?
That distance 2pz total right.
That's the total distance up to it, so we've got that, right?
So all we need to do with our denominator is check to see whether
that's going to be, you know, big enough that we consider it far
enough away and that's that's what we normally call the near clipping
plane, right.
And if you've ever heard near clipping plane before, but the near clip
playing right is the thing that says?
Well, you know, if I take a look
Kathy's the similar triangles, right.
In fact, I'll just go up here to this, right?
At some point when something moves far enough back here that it would
actually be, you know, behind me, obviously, I don't want to render
it.
So that would be, you know, an ear clip playing of 0.
But if it was right on zero, I would have a divide by zero, so that's
not good either.
So I pick some arbitrary point out here just sort of say we're only,
we're only well-conditioned past this value, let's say 0.2 or
something.
So we're only going to consider things that are
At least that far away.
So we want to make sure that the distance to p z is greater than
whatever that in your clip plane is and then we can do our projected
XY.
Right?
Like so and what we'll do there is will just say well okay you know
we'll set the the kind of think of
What?
We just shouldn't draw the thing here.
So I think we probably need to say that.
It's clipped, like we're going to have to return something here.
That basically says don't draw this, right?
We need to do like, something like that if that makes sense.
And so, you know, we want to do something like like this, right?
I'll say, well, you know what I can do, I can just say it's nothing,
so there we go.
And so result, dot valid equals true, there we go.
And let's take a look here.
Oh yeah I'll just do.
We don't actually support a divide the moment.
So I'll do one over that.
There we go.
So our focal length, though.
I named it the wrong thing.
So there we go.
Sorry about that.
Got a little overzealous the naming.
So, there we go.
Focal length.
Comes in both places that correct.
That doesn't look right.
I think I while I was busy talking, I think I made a mistake there.
D should only show up once.
Right.
So what did we get here?
We got one over the distance times.
The focal length times the rod.
That's correct.
So, why was the focal length used before or used again focal?
Length x 0 because I started to type it in here.
Yeah, I don't know why I did that.
That was just me being being my typos self.
So there's our projected XY, we've got it and so we can go ahead.
And also, you know, I
We can do it that way.
It's a little cleaner.
I think that's basically all we need this scale value.
I guess would just be if we were going to say so that was actually to
project other points.
So if we were going to take something that was one unit long and
projected, that's what we would want to return return for a scale,
right?
Because we want to say how things are scaling with C.
So if we want to say how things are scaling with Z, I guess what we
would probably want to return.
I got to think about whether that's correct.
Normally what we do is we project all four points but I guess what we
can do instead of just project the unit distance
That's right.
Take one right?
And say, well, if we were going to project one at this same distance,
what would it?
Give us, right.
And so what I can do is say, well, let's do a three, let's do three
projections, make raw XY actually be sort of raw XYZ and actually do
it this way, right, pass in a 1 value there.
So now I see how one will scale, and that's the scale value.
You are projected X, Y actually has like a secret Z component.
That tells us how it scales, right?
And then to actually do this, obviously, I don't
That Z value in there when it's actually been used.
Okay, so now we assuredly have some things we've got to fix, but of
course, actually already, even though we're kind of super janky here,
you can actually see that the scaling, at least now does actually work
more correctly, but that's sort of a separate that sort of separate
issue.
So, first off, let me
Let me just set these values a little bit more here.
Looks like we're off center a little.
I don't understand why that would be but let me see.
It looks like we're just not centered but our transform is looking
actually correct but it just doesn't look like we're we're centered
quite yet.
Alright.
So let's double-check everything here because everything should be
based around the screen center which it is and because all of the
values that come in are just based around the screen center.
And so, when we're adding these
Heather, right.
Best just in fact, I'm going to go ahead and just take this out here.
You know, that was for our y displacement, I guess was where that was
happening.
So I don't know if we want to keep doing that wise to a could put this
in here for now to simplify things out a little bit.
Okay.
So we have our distance values.
We have our focal length.
We have our raw X Y.
We have our entity based peas and the offsets to those base peas, and
that all kind of looks
He's roughly correct to me.
I'm not sure why we seem to be scaling out of the wrong place because
I feel like all these values should have been properly centered around
the X and Y.
So, I'm not sure why we're getting.
You can see that we're kind of everything seems to actually be down
from where the camera is, and I don't understand why that is right?
Everything seems to be offset massively before the actual scale.
Only takes place before we do this, right?
It's as if everything is very sort of shifted and I'm not sure exactly
why that is might be something.
I'm forgetting about how we're passing in our values.
But anyway,
It looks like everything else about it is correct though.
So taking a look at this.
I want to kind of know if the entity based peas here.
These should all be centered around zero correct.
So let me see.
I want to make sure that that is actually true.
So when we push a bitmap on here, right?
M 2 pixels - so that's our problem, right?
We haven't quite gotten it down to the point where things are all
actually happening in.
M, right are offset is still happening in pixels here and that bitmap
alignment.
Hmm.
Mmm.
Well, you know, that's not a problem per se, I just don't know if I
want to leave that hanging around, right?
I just don't know if I like that.
It seems to me, you know, like I just wonder if that's just going to
keep causing problems because everything should maybe be done in m, 2
pixels, should maybe be done later on in the pipeline, right?
So what the reason not to do that, it would force us to store the
alignment until later and that doesn't sound fabulous.
So taking it into meters fixed actually does seem like the right idea.
The problem is all the rest of this stuff then has to be done in
pixels, right?
Which is actually fine.
It's just kind of crazy, right?
But okay so if you think about it, if the offset comes in as pixels,
right?
Then you know, now that would translate this into a pixel value,
And in theory, I guess since the focal length and the distance 2pz are
essentially going to divide out, I suppose it would still work even
just having them not be, you know, being an ear in meters per pixel.
So I guess technically, we could leave it that way.
I'm just not sure that's such a good idea but we can actually do that.
Now if that was the case and we were actually doing m 2 pixels, then
we need that the camera distance above ground again to also be in
meters to pixels as well.
Hmm.
Which is kind of crazy but let's make sure this is also camera
distance Above Ground - entity base peasy.
I lied, it's actually this quantity has to be and you can see this is
kind of messy and I don't love it, but you can kind of see already in
there.
We're starting to get it back to the right centering.
So yeah, okay.
So m 2 pixels.
This is, this is super chunky.
I
It's one of those things where I feel like it's so much nicer to
write, it just doing everything in meters and saving the bitmap allow
you to the end, but the same time, if we're going to try to go for
efficiency in the render, you probably want to smack all that stuff
down to begin with.
So I guess we should just keep going this way and then we'll try to
condense everything down into something that properly that that just
makes it.
So it's not too big of a deal that that's happening, right?
all right, so
I guess we would also need this focal length to be in meters to
pixels.
It's kind of crazy.
And yeah, and then I think we're getting there.
We are starting to get there.
I want to move the camera back a bit here.
So now you can sort of start to see that stuff is actually moving
properly though.
Like, for example, you can kind of see that.
As I move around here, the things in the background, sort of look like
they're more obeying, a proper perspective rule.
So we're very close.
Now, we just have to go through the math one more time.
Now that we actually have to deal with the the M fix this thing and
make sure that we have everything actually correct.
I'm also going to restart here because I don't remember what we went
down or up in terms of groups in terms of things here.
So there's the actual starting setup of it and I feel like we also
have a there's some kind of a weird
Here with them with the stairwell.
Wow.
So you can see how much radek that scaling is.
There we go.
Alright, so let's go ahead.
I want to see what happens.
Also, I just want to see what happens if I change this value.
Just playing around with it here.
Yeah, so so we just have a we just have a few more scale, things to
work out.
We basically we're basically got everything essentially correct.
We just got to go through and rework things out to make sure I'm your
toaster pixels or right.
But we're pretty much good to go now.
So I think we're going to be fine.
Like so yeah, are rectangles are currently the wrong size though?
I believe, because I think we need to actually make sure that we
properly handle their sizes.
I don't know that we're probably handling the size of them back in
the, in the the call that we were in the wreck.
Drawing call.
But yeah.
All right.
So let's work through this math.
One more time now, knowing that we have M to pixels to contend with.
So what's basically happening is this stuff is getting smacked down
into m 2 pixels when we actually make the push bitmap call, right?
So I got the push bitmap call.
We now Know The Enemy base is offset is in meters to pixels, right?
I should say isn't pixels.
So what that means is that when we call entity, when we take any basis
P, it's not in m 2 pixels.
So I guess I'm just going to say the first thing.
We'll do.
Let's change entity basis.
Basis P2 m, 2 pixels so that it's in m, 2 pixels.
We want the focal length in meters to pixels.
We want the camera to sits above ground and M are going to pixels.
Everything's going to be in pixels and so then we do this computation.
Now this computation is just done in pixels and that's fine.
The New York
Kipling is also in pixels, and that's
Fine.
Get rid of the Z, fudge value because that's gone now, right?
And, and then when we actually do this, any base, BX y, this offset X
Y is already in.
Pixels is the reason we had to do all this.
So we can actually do this math properly.
We then do our divide out with our raw x y, and our screen center.
All that goodness.
And I think that's about, right, I'm going to change this back to the
value.
We originally had it at all.
So so did I stop the game running?
I did stop the game from running and
So I think that's mostly all we need to do to make sure our scale is
correct.
And then we want to do is for how far above everything the camera
should be, which is again, kind of a, an arbitrary value.
I don't know what this should actually be able to think about what
that actually is.
Obviously, if we were to pull it down cameras, above ground, I wonder
what happens if we just set that to zero, that's interesting.
Kind of I'm interested to know what is happening here.
It seems like we're getting a lot more elongation then we should have,
right.
So I feel like there's still something.
Something odd going on there, right?
And I don't know exactly what it is because I feel like this is
correct.
The focal length should not really be too far off from that.
I would think, right?
I wonder if this is a non-linearity problem as well.
I'll see wife all that stuff's in pixels.
It should still just work.
I feel like this is should be scale-invariant right after.
Think about that little bit more.
The camera distance above ground 0.5.
So, really, this should be able to be higher though, right?
I mean, the camera, should be able to be a few meters, above the
ground, and still work properly.
So, that's a bit odd, right?
So, I want to leave that at that, and figure out what exactly is going
wrong because we've still got something a little bit weird, should not
be that small is I guess the way I would look at it, although the fact
that
Pixels is kind of weird.
It's kind of weird.
I feel like maybe there is a hidden scale thing that happens there,
but I don't know.
So anyway, the raw x y and a debased pxy were sent right?
And this is correct, right?
We've got the inverse of the distance, 2pz camera, distance above
ground and then as the Z values get more - it gets further away which
is exactly what we expect to see and the distance to it.
Always going to be roughly that which is what we expect.
So yeah.
I don't see I don't see what the problem is there and it really does
seem like the focal length wants to be set a lot higher but I just
don't understand why that would be right.
Like if we were to set this focal length higher, then everything looks
fine, right?
You know, the game looks as we intended,
It with it, with a, you know, the other focal length but I'm not sure.
I know.
Not sure.
I know why.
That would be
Normally, there's a step where you turn, you know, World units into
pixels and of course we've already are doing it in pixels.
So maybe I'm just maybe the focal length actually gets multiplied in
there in some way that I don't understand.
So I'm going to have to actually see about that.
Certainly
But you can basically see that by changing these two values, we can
get the effect we want.
So there's actually nothing practically wrong at the moment, with the
math.
Like it it works fine in terms of getting the effect that we want, and
the effect is correct, you can see that.
Now, it actually works properly right to give us the Parallax that we
wanted and we can use those two values to control.
Just how much of that we want.
But the thing is, I just don't think that's what the
Should be right.
And so I feel like what's happening is the fact that we're not doing
it in meters actually, introduces some kind of a nonlinear effect,
with the pixel values, that is why I have to make those values larger.
And so I have to think about, I want to know why that is it data, but
that's going to bother me.
So I suspect that we will probably even though technically we've done
what we need to do.
I feel like I really want to go find out why that is right.
But yeah, so everything seems to be working properly now and we can
get exactly the effect that we wanted.
It's just that I'm just not comfortable with how that worked out is,
all right?
Jump jump.
I can actually jump up into the sky.
Yeah.
So anyway I think that's probably all I want to do right now because I
don't know that I want to go.
I want people to be able to ask questions that are not necessarily
related to that.
So I guess I'll just say here to do these the values of 20 and 20
seemed wrong.
Did I mess something up here?
And you know, let me real quick.
Before we start the Q&A, let me just do the math.
One more time to make sure that I actually didn't screw it up because,
you know, like I said, I haven't actually I guess made a kill his
master on the stream yet, which is unusual.
This could be the first one, right?
It could be that I just did it totally wrong or something, right?
Which would not be unlike me that's what normally happens in my real
life.
Like it actually looks like I'm better at math on the stream than I
actually am because probably because I'm covering things that are
maybe that I you know know pretty well when I'm actually working out
new Mass stuff, it's atrocious.
Like I just it's a disaster Zone all the time, you know.
So anyway let's say this is the the monitor so cure is, you know that
I point
And here is p Prime.
I'm sorry, here is p, here is p Prime.
And so, we'll call this x.
We will call this distance D again, and we will call this this long
distance.
We will call that
Oh, I did do it wrong.
I totally did do it wrong, I drew the diagram wrong, if this is the
camera point, right?
Then this is just that's yeah, I mean, I guess I shouldn't say, I did
it wrong, but you didn't quite do it.
As I probably should have, right?
If this is the Z distance from we could just say this is the distance
from the camera right to here.
Yeah, it's going to come out to the same thing, so, never mind.
I guess I didn't do it wrong.
Well, I'm going to keep going anyway.
But anyway, if this is the, the Z coordinate, that is the total
distance, right?
Then I know that my ratio is just going to be PX 2.
Pz is equal to PX Prime 2D, right?
So multiplying that out its p zp x Prime.
Equals PX d, right?
And so solving for this, I want pxd over peasy.
Right?
If that seems Seems like it to me, right?
And so, yeah, so basically like that's what we're talking about here.
That's the entirety of solving that equation.
You don't see anything else going on there, really?
Yeah.
So, yeah, and if I take a look at what we're actually doing here,
right?
You've got 1 over distance 2pz which is what that is X focal length,
kind of relaxed.
So that's exactly right.
The distance to the pz is just, how are afar the cameras above the
ground level?
Or I should say Target perhaps is a better word.
Right.
- whatever that that base is z value is, right?
And that seems like that's correct because our Z value is going this
way.
So we want that to get more negative so that that I don't know.
That really just seems right.
Yeah.
All right.
Let's go to Q&A.
Let's see here.
Work.
Yeah.
Let's go to the Q&A.
Oops.
Is squinting analogous to closing a camera's aperture.
So I don't think so.
I think squinting is probably more similar to changing the focus and
putting on one of those Hood things changing cameras aperture is more
like your iris Contracting.
Like when you go out in the sun and your iris contracts that's like
the aperture I'm sorry that you're Irish your pupil you know the
little black dot it contracts.
That's that's like what that's doing?
That's that's Contracting.
The
Chart right.
Are you intending to multiply by x y z and not just the X Y as the
variable says yes.
So the reason we want to do all three is because we want to know what
one would project to as well so that we can use it as our scale value,
right?
So that's why I do the Z as well.
Just doing the exact same equation on all three variables.
So we're just getting all three at once.
That's all
Wasn't the room height 8 meters.
Really.
Did we set the room height to be eight meters?
If that's the case, that's just totally stupid and that maybe it you
you may have mailed it.
Let me see here.
Typical room.
Typical floor height.
No.
The floor height looks like it's about, right, right.
Because that's about a 10-foot floor which is about right.
Expect a ton of pre stream questions.
Oh, what happened?
Where we on the front page or something.
Wasn't the parameter already converted to pixels if so then I think
you are converting to meet converting meals for just twice.
I don't think so, because so entity based P has not been converted to
pixels, right?
So that's at any base.
B needs to be converted to pixels.
The thing that was converted to pixels was entity offset, right?
And that's why we can't do the things in meters because it was already
done in m 2 pixels.
We could have multiplied by the inverse here and then done everything
in M, right?
And then projected out right and that would have been fine.
In fact we can try that and see if it's the same.
I feel like it.
Well I mean I guess we kind of know that it would be the same so I
don't really need to do that but
if you wanted to use this code to make a full 3D games, such as a
first-person shooter, how much would you have to change to give the
player an adjustable fov option?
Well, so
We can actually cover that since this we kind of need to debug this.
So maybe Monday what we'll do is we'll cover that because really what
you're doing here is the focal length is essentially what tells you
what the fov is, right?
That's what that does.
And so really you can solve for what the focal length is trying to try
to give you what the idea is here.
So this is the value that we're using, right?
That's the value that we're using to control the projection, right?
And what fov is is it's this angle, right?
This angle, let me draw new diagram.
New diagram.
There we go.
So, let's say this is the top of the screen.
So that's this is how big the screen is, right?
So this is top of the screen, this is bottom of the screen.
Okay, and here's the eye.
Okay, so here we go.
When we're doing is projecting point.
So here is you know RP prime or whatever.
And pees out here somewhere, right?
What you're talking about when you talk about fov, right?
Fov means field of view.
And what that is is that's an angle, right?
So if I say I've got 90 degree fov, what I'm talking about is that the
maximum angle of a point that could be projected is going to be 40.
Five, right?
Because if it's 90, it's half this way, half that way.
They're talking about the total angle like between the top and the
bottom, right?
So that total angle that's your fov.
So what that tells you is well, if you just, if you've got this, you
know, how far away the screen is.
Right?
I'm sorry, you know how big the screen actually is right.
And so, if you want to know what this length is, all you need to know
to
To figure that out is to use this, this size, plus this angle.
And, you know, you have a right triangle, you can use the tangent
right to compute, what the D value would be for a particular fov.
So the answer is you actually don't do anything to this code to make
it support program will fov.
All you do is you stick a tangent computation onto the front to
basically compute D from knowing
Angle and and a height, right?
That's that's that's it.
So it's the same code, it's just
it's just
Computing it
So this says, expect a lot of preaching questions, but I don't really
see that many questions on there.
So, that's good.
How long do you think this is going to take my estimate was 6:00.
Which right?
Like so I feel like that's a fair estimate.
So right?
If 6:00 and you figure a work week is 40 hours or so right then I
figure if you divide this out,
So that we're just saying, how many, like I'm going to say, work
weeks, right?
How many workweeks do we have here, right?
It's roughly, like 15 or something, right?
So we're talking about like a 15.
Imagine if you were going to program 15 weeks of programming is
roughly.
What we're aiming to get the game done in which is actually incredibly
short, right?
It's incredibly incredibly short, it's much shorter than most people
take.
Been to make a game with an engine, but, you know, since we have to do
it, we do only an hour at night and this wood, or this is already two
years here, even an incredibly short game.
If we actually stream all of the programming, which is what we're
doing, just takes a really long time to get through nothing.
You can really do about that.
Sonic Fino, opengl no audio library.
Know anything house being a masochist coming along.
So it was all really simple, right?
I mean, we already have the unoptimized version of the render and we
have audio playing, so that turned out to be nothing.
I mean, we'll take a couple weeks, maybe.
So, you know, maybe something like, I want to say, like 24 hours or
something of time to optimize a renderer but
If that's what you call being a mask has, I mean literally like we've
only program for 100 hours right?
So far.
And a lot of that's explanation time.
So if you actually want to talk about how long it would actually take
me to write those things like redoing opengl is Trivial, it's like a
week's worth of work or something.
Right?
It's just a, it's a, no brainer and audio library.
Audio is so simple.
You can read an audio library in a day, right?
It's totally trivial.
We take a long time in the Stream because we tackle it.
Of random stuff that we that I kind of want to go.
That's like a trade-off based like handling Z.
Like, we could have just not handled Z and that would have saved
probably like, literally 50 hours of time or something, but, but yeah,
like, it really just doesn't take very long at all, because we do
explanations, and because we only do an hour, a night, it seems like
it takes a long time, but if you actually map that into how long it
would take you through just sat down and Cody, it's like nothing.
So yeah, I mean, how long did it take us to do a texture map triangle
1 hour and 40 minutes of it was explanation.
So it took 20 minutes to program at extra mapper.
That's how long it took us.
So masochist.
No, I mean if it's taking you longer than that to do the programming,
you should come watch the stream and not call people masochists
because you've got something to learn.
Hello, as a software developer, I understand the performance benefits
is C plus plus or important.
However, there are a lot of
PL based code at runtime tools coming out that streamline development
on, both the web and in games.
How do you feel about this departure from traditional software
development tools?
so,
I'm sorry, I'm not sure what repl stands for in this case.
Code at runtime tools.
Are you talking about things that just try to come like jetting?
What do you mean?
Tell me what you mean.
Our PPL code tools.
Read eval print Loop.
so, you're just talking about the fact that you can run code that you
type in,
Not sure, I understand here's what I will say.
so,
If you think that for some reason, C++ means that you can't
interactively, code.
Maybe you're new to the stream but here's the game running, right?
And here's my code, right?
If I wanted to do something like change the projection equation, I can
just do that and it updates in the game live, right?
So you don't need some crazy web language that runs super slowly and
makes all of
Our code lousy to get real-time coding, you just have to code the
code, you have to write the code properly to do that and see which I
think took us three hours of Total stream time to do so it's extremely
simple to do that and see it takes hardly any time at all and there's
like one or two things you can't do if you do that but they're things
specific.
See things you can't do once you do it that way.
If you want the incremental stuff to work, but for most for 90% of the
tweaks, you
Ooh, it's it just works.
Do you use iPhone?
If it's yes I would like to give you a copy of my game for iOS.
Thank you very much for the offer but no I do not have an iPhone.
Sorry.
Will this game have cinematic mode?
Well, it will have some cinematics.
It'll have cutscene you'll have an intro cutscene
Don't want to give too much away, but it will.
I don't see any more questions.
Are we done?
Is that it?
Kappa.
Everything just has a cap on the end of it.
Apparently,
And I feel like if Jonathan Blow wants to Flame about the iPhone
Jonathan Blow Ken flame about the iPhone.
I feel like he is well within his rights to do so because they're
pretty darn annoying devices.
Would the renderer be able to support something like zooming out for
one screen that is twice as large.
As normal sure, we can support any kind of zooming that we want if we
wanted to support smooth zooming down to really tiny sizes, like so
right now, I guess you can't really see it here.
But you could sort of you, sort of saw it before when we were doing
the test and we had this number a lot smaller.
So when we were down,
Here.
Let's say, oops.
That's not what I meant.
So when we were down here, right?
I don't know if you can see, maybe if I turn off those blue lines, you
could see it a little bit better.
Let me go in here and in turn off those, those boundary lines.
So I'm going to go ahead and just turn those off, right?
So if you turn off those boundary lines, I don't know if you can see
this because it's not I guess it's probably not who I don't want to
know what I just hit.
I hit something that Windows is thinking about.
Please don't do something, crazy Windows.
Know what?
What the hell was that
Why did it do that?
I don't want a media center.
Expiry, I don't even know what that was.
That is unacceptable.
Anyway, what I was trying to show you, is, if you take a look at at
this, when things are shrunk down, do you see how you get some like
kind of sparkly artists?
Like, it doesn't look smooth, right?
Like if you just look at the pixels in the in there, it kind of looks
a little sparkly and janky at the edges, right?
Whereas if I, if I go back to sort of the
Normal size you can you can sort of see there.
Isn't that right?
It's nice and smooth everywhere.
The reason is because once you scale down to a certain size, we're
only doing bilinear filtering which means once you scale below half
size.
So anything from half size down, third thighs, quarter size and so on
you'll get sparklies because you're no longer sampling, all of the
pixels that are involved, you know?
So I'm sampling all the colors that are involved.
And so, you get this week and talked about this a little bit and
that's where you need.
Mapping, which we didn't Implement because we don't actually ever need
it for the actual game.
And so it would just slow us down.
But if you wanted to scale things down, really smoothly to very tiny
sizes.
So, let's say, you go to something twice the size the screen down to
the size of the screen, down to half the
The screen.
So the total scaling size was like a quarter of its size, we would
want to implement Implement mipmapping for that but we don't really
have any need for that.
I don't think in the game and so that's not necessary.
So didn't have 73.
Lots of quick time.
Events too.
Yeah, I don't know about quick, time events.
Probably not quick, time events, but yet
We're about is the explanation of the reloading, the code while
running, it sounds like fun.
So that is if you go to the Forum site, right?
This is this thing here, if you go.
So, this is handmade hero dot-org.
If you go to the Forum site, you can actually go to this episode guide
thing, and it's got like a lot of stuff on there.
And this week, 5 fun with win32, basically shows you a bunch of stuff
and we've got
All kinds of fancy stuff in there.
I don't even read, haven't used this, because we're not working on
animation right now.
We've used it like once or twice.
I think, but we haven't used it too much.
But one of the things that we also did is we actually have looped Live
code editing, which is even cooler than Live code editing.
So, you know, if you do something like we're I, you know, I go down
the stairwell or something, right?
And then, I come over here and I don't know, go down it again, right.
Like, so,
I can just set that as like a loop, right?
And then it'll just play while.
I edit the game, right?
So I don't even have to go up there and do input, right?
It's just, yeah, it's pretty awesome.
Like, basically, like anyone who doesn't do this should do this, it's
way better than even developing and like other languages that are
supposed to be easier.
This like, you know, it's it gives you all the benefits of optimized
code, but you also have complete freedom to modify the code while
running and there's a cup.
Like I said,
You can't change structure layouts.
If you do it the way, we did it on stream because we did it in the
simplest way.
You can do it, you need more advanced stuff if you want to be able to
train structure, layouts on the fly, but that's not that often and all
you have to do is just restart, you know?
Just just on those and that's not a big deal.
So even the simple one that we did on the stream is pretty darn
powerful at the end of the day, you know?
So
What kind of game is this going to be?
And what will the point of it be?
It's just a, it's a, it's just a Zelda type game where you kind of
adventure around in a forest, and the emphasis is on programming.
So we're trying to make sure that it has lots of complex programming
things in it.
Meaning like multiple Z levels and scaling between them and walking
between them and, you know, all kinds of stuff and crazy.
Between stuff like a very complex, object systems and stuff like that.
We're focusing on that sort of thing, if that makes sense because we
want the programming to be sort of difficult to cover and stuff like
that.
And we write the renderer and all that sort of stuff, it's not running
opengl.
This is our own renderer that we wrote which we're not done yet.
That's what we're in the middle of doing.
When the game is finished, you expect the game to look as good as if
you made it in a commercial engine.
I actually expect the game to look way better than it looked, then it
would look in a commercial engine.
And the reason that I say that is because the graphics are basically
the same because we'll call opengl just like everyone else for our
Hardware acceleration path.
So it'll be basically the same but I feel like we'll just have a bunch
of stuff that, you know,
Game engines really are very lousy at nowadays like you know I when I
load up games like a game in unity or something, I'm often staring at
somebody's loading screen or the world, you know, has to pause when it
loads and it goes from level to level something that and we will not
have any of that stuff because we'll be doing our stuff properly.
And so you know, I I don't suspect that.
This this game will be just at parity with an engine.
I suspect it will actually better in a number of ways an engine and we
already are way better than any engine that I know of.
Right now in terms of scale because we actually support
extraordinarily, large worlds, or ready.
We already did the work to like handle that and so assuming that we
maintain that, I think will be pretty good as well.
I also suspect our object system will be much better than anyone
that's in available in commercial engines.
So, yeah.
So I don't intend this to be.
Like I said, this is not a toy project.
This should be significantly better than anything.
You can buy off the shelf.
The only thing we might not do is like go nuts on effects.
So, you know, a commercial engine might have had better effects like
special effects stuff because we probably won't spend time on some of
that stuff that be the only thing, but you know, who knows, maybe,
we'll even decide to do that at some point, but that, that wasn't
really, I don't think that's super interesting cuz that's just kind of
like, GPU sort of flailing.
Can I learn how to be a better programmer from this channel?
I hope so, that's the goal anyway, or at least a better game
programmer.
I don't really talk about any other kind of programming on the stream
because I'm a game programmer so I don't know if it would help
programming in general.
But
Hopefully it would it would be good for game programmers.
How are you planning any DLC for this game actually?
Kind of yes.
And the only reason for that is actually because since the entirety of
the game development is streamed.
We've talked about this a little bit in the past.
I've been trying to figure out how to still have their be surprises in
it that people don't know about.
And so one way that I was considering doing that was basically like
release, you know, we do all the work up to shipping the game so that
everyone, you know, could see that on stream, which is the goal, but
then, you know, maybe I do a DLC pack that is not
dreamed and so people can download that and and have surprises in
there for things that they didn't know we're in the game, right?
Until they find them.
So maybe but it's not a concrete plan, you know.
To use Windows Media Center a lot in your game development process.
Yes, that is why it's so good that Microsoft made a hotkey that I
don't even know what it was to get to Media Center.
Because what if you're right in the middle of coding and you really
need it to be like right now, you don't want to slow you down, right?
You don't want to like, it's like having slow compile times, right?
If it takes you a long time to open up Windows Media Center, that's
really gonna drag on your productivity.
So good job.
Microsoft getting that hot key in there because
Sure that if someone had to go to the start menu and pick Windows
Media Center, there would just be no way they'd ever get anything
done.
Manic the nobody.
Why does he move slower at higher Zoom?
So the reason is because we have not optimized our renderer yet and so
actually, although it is running sort of at, you know, I don't know 15
frames a second or something because holy cow computers are fast.
Once we're using actually an extraordinarily slow rectangle filling
routine because optimizing it is something that we want to start maybe
in a week or so and so
The closer you are to stuff the more pixels there filling on screen so
the slower, it runs.
Once we go ahead and optimize that this will all probably run, just
fine and you won't see any of that.
But until we actually do that work of doing the optimization, it will
it will run slowly.
When, when things are covering a lot of the screen because the cost, I
guess the thing, I'm not implicitly saying the cost is based on how
many pixels you draw.
And right now, we're probably 100 times slower or something.
Well, not 100 times slower.
We're probably like 20 times slower than we should be or something
heinous, like that would.
And so, every pixel takes 20 times longer to process than it should.
So if you have less pixels, it's drastically less time.
Hence bigger things slower, smaller, things quicker.
Will the game be fun?
Well, I don't know.
I'll try to make it fun but I'm not a game designer.
So
A promise that I can promise it will be well programmed but I can't
really promise.
It'll be fun.
Will you cover things like patching and downloading code from the
internet?
Probably not.
I don't think we're going to cover networking on the stream.
So we just, you know, we just let steam handle that I think is how we
would mostly be doing that.
So, looks like we are at the end.
Are you planning on implementing some kind of Shader support?
Oh man, you know, we've got it right.
You, we just, I mean, but you just write it in C, so, but we've, we
already did some fairly complex stuff which we haven't, we haven't
quite put to use yet because we wanted to go get all of our Z and
other assorted things straightened out first.
But basically yeah we where is it here?
Coordinate system.
Coordinate system where it is, we already did a bunch of Shader stuff
in preparation for lighting, right?
So you can kind of see that sphere.
There is is using reflection.
Some reflection stuff that we were testing with these reflection Maps,
right?
So yeah.
All right.
Well, this game have a collector's edition.
I want a plastic drag it in it for $150.
Ningen, does that mean carrot in Japanese anyway, I feel like for
$150, I don't know if that gets you a plastic Dragon.
It might get you a cloth map.
But if you want the plastic dragon that maybe only for the 250 dollar
pre-order that's through GameStop.
And but before you block at the 250 dollar price tag, remember you
will also get a special golden prosthetic, limb for your limbless
child in game that only people who do the 250 dollar pre-order get.
So it's not just the plastic dragon in the Collector's Edition in the
pre-order special.
It's also that that special in-game golden golden Prosthetics.
So you know, it's it's pretty hard to pass up.
Up, get those 250 dollar, fat cash, wads ready?
All right, I got to close down the stream now.
I gotta go, guys.
It's dinner time.
I'm kidding.
Of course about, there's not going to be a pre-order special.
I'm not that kind of a developer.
All right?
Let me close this down because it's doing its little looping there.
Let's close this down.
Thank you.
One, once again, for joining me for handmade hero, it's been a
pleasure coding with you, as it always is.
I hope to see you back here, Monday.
I believe it will also be 5:00 p.m.
on Twitch at seems to be a good time slot for us.
I think we're going to stay there.
It's easier for me to work into my work day, if we do it that way.
So that's when I tend to do it, as always, if you would like to follow
along at home, you can pre-order the game at any time and it comes
with a source code every night.
I update the source code after you finish your.
So if you want to play around the source code yourself,
if you can go ahead and do that, just go to handmade hero dot org and
hit that pre-order button and off you go.
If you want to support the video series, we also have a patreon page
which is much appreciated if you want to be a supporter.
That's awesome.
We also have a tweet but that tweets the schedule at you.
So if you want to know when the stream is going to be live, check that
out, it's pretty handy.
It'll tell you the schedule every weekend, tweets out the full
schedule for the week and then on weekdays, it gives you like kind of
a warning.
Like today's stream is going to be at such and such a time.
And then finally there's a forum site
Which is a great resource for trying to learn from the screen.
There's a forum you can ask questions.
There's also an annotated episode guide which you saw on today's
stream in fact me pointing out and also there's ports to like mac and
Linux and stuff which you know we're going to do on stream.
But if you want to follow along today on Mac and Linux before we get
to those ports, people in the community have already done them for you
so you can just kind of go look at that, which is kind of awesome.
So that's it.
Thanks everyone for joining me.
I hope to see you back here on Monday.
Have an excellent weekend and until then take it.
Easy.