Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream.
I believe we had site technical difficulties this morning.
I had to reboot the machine as I sometimes do, for whatever reason.
The OBS, like Arrow capture thing that we use to stream every couple
of weeks, it just goes black work, it doesn't show anything just but
just a black screen and then
I have to reboot the machine.
There's no other way to get it to come back for whatever reason.
I don't know if it's a problem with Windows is no longer, outputting
the arrow, compositor information anymore for some reason or if it's a
bug in.
Oh yes, I have no idea but we are okay now and I believe I've got the
day right day.
364 I had to reset my little dick after as I have to do there's day
363 so day 364 is correct.
So we are good to
To go now and we can go work on our program which is what we want to
do.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Here we are.
When I should probably also get our Blackboard back because obviously
since I rebooted everything got shut down, there we go.
Close that and open up handmade Raj.
There we go.
So where we left off last week is we had finished all of the 3D
pipeline stuff necessary to make it so that we're actually properly
rendering in 3D now, like with actual transforms and all that sort of
stuff.
So, you know, we can actually zoom and rotate our game around and that
sort of
F, which is nice.
So, this is what I wanted for being able to see things in debug mode,
and we can now proceed with putting in our Z buffer.
So, we've got a lot of options for this actually, you can see.
So right now, right?
We're not doing any sorting at all.
That's where this flashing is coming from.
These Sprites are literally right on top of each other.
It exactly the same depth as well.
So if I don't think even a z-buffer, if we turn it on right now would
would do anything for that.
That you can see what sort of happening is that hey whatever order, we
happen to submit them, that's how they get drawn.
So there's really no Rhyme or Reason to it.
For the most part.
Well, there is, but it's a very, like, unintentional sort of random
Rhyme or Reason you might say.
And yeah, that's that's the situation as it stands.
And so our goal, I can even I can walk the hero around in this weird
sort of flattened State.
It's rather amusing actually look at him go.
All right, so what we want to do here is we want to start doing the
thing that
He did all this 3D work to do in the first place which you switch to a
sorting scheme that actually uses the Z buffer, and doesn't have to go
through a individual object to object sort which is what we had
implemented and which I wasn't particularly happy about, okay?
So we need to be able to do that.
And if you take a look at what's going on here, you can kind of see
that right now.
Everything is just a flat Sprite on the Z, it has no nosy.
See depth at all, in terms of changes, right?
So if you look at everything, everything completely flat in Z.
So everything has its X Y position as it used to but it has nosy at
all.
It's just a it's everything is just a thin plane with nothing rising
up, out of it at all.
And so the first thing we're going to have to think about is how we
actually want to submit things so that they have a sensible version of
of sorting that will work with the depth buffer.
And so, let's just talk about that for a second because that's like
the next logical step.
We have to do to turn on the depth buffer.
Now obviously we can just turn on the death before.
The only thing we have to do, there is map, RZ range to something
useful.
Which you know obviously we have to do with our perspective.
Matrix has two members arranged something useful because our Z is,
will be used for the Z buffer or the depth buffer.
And turn it on.
But other than that, the rest of the Finesse in getting the game to
work properly, in terms of sorting is to figure out how we should send
down the, the Sprite information so that the Z buffer does what we
want it to do, right?
Because right now that would not happen right now, we're sending
everything down flattened on top of itself.
It's not going to do any good.
So what we will probably do I'm guessing is will go with kind of a
standard trick one that I've seen done before.
I don't know.
Who is the first person to think of this or use it in a shipping title
or anything.
But I've, you know, I've seen it done a lot and that is to say, well,
okay essentially we've got this flat plane here and that flat plane is
going to be fine for doing some things.
Like if I want to put ground chunks on here,
On tiles or whatever.
You know anything that's on the ground is going to be okay?
In terms of sorting because it's all just part of the ground at the
same height in Z and nothing confusing is happening.
And even if I wanted to put something kind of over the top of
something, I could just give it a slightly, higher Z value.
Just a little bit higher and then it would work properly, right?
I can use the Z values to sort of stack things up on top of each
other.
Just a little bit if I want to, and what I could.
Also, do if I need to is I could use the same Z.
Value for them.
And just send them down in in sorted order as well if I wanted to,
right?
Because typically these things wouldn't be moving up and down pass
each other.
So I would know that things that stack on top of each other.
How they should stack, right?
I could do that as well.
And just use a depth comparison function, that was like greater than
or equal to in Z for example.
Well, I guess in this case,
It'd be less than or equal to because the Z direction will be flipping
although we can really control that but that's beside the point.
Anyway, so if you think about what's going on there, it's like well
stuff on the ground isn't really the problem.
So the problem for us comes when we've got like these trees or the
hero or whatever who's sort of supposed to be standing upright, you
know?
And the problem, what's going on?
There is the things that are standing, upright have to exclude each
other properly when they stack, right?
So, you know, if I've got a tree and I was to draw it here, I could
make sure that it drew on top of the ground but then if someone was
standing behind it, how do I make sure that they appear behind the
tree or if they're standing in front of it that they appear in front
of the tree, right?
And so what people often will do is if we look at this site on if
Camera is looking down this way.
They'll sort of put the Sprites like this.
Right?
They'll sort of stack them so that they do go upwards in Z.
They just go upwards at the same angle as the camera comes down.
So they appear nice and flat onto the camera but they, you know, get
kind of taller as they go.
So that part actually may be harder for us because we're not going to
be very oblique with the artwork depending on the circumstances.
So having it face directly at the
Cameron may also not quite be enough because the the actual facing
direction for the camera, maybe something more like this.
In terms of what we're actually thinking of in terms of there may be
very little tilt there but the scheme still works because if you think
about it what we can do is still produce the Sprite that will look
roughly correct but that does have this shape even for a different
down.
Look, right.
And what I mean by that is you can imagine let's suppose that I'm
looking down like this.
And so in order for a Sprite to appear, it's correct size on this.
Green, it would have to be placed like that, right?
Well, it's free for me to do the same thing with the Sprite.
Meaning, if I come down, like, if I think about how this is getting
projected, right?
If I have my screen, this is not a very good diagram but if I
My screen here, right?
If I imagine the projection and say, well I want the Sprite to appear
as if it looked like that on the surface of the monitor.
If I want to I can extend this line further down, right?
And instead, send down that Sprite.
And that Sprite has the same appearance on the screen as this Sprite
does, right?
But this one Stacks, much more cleanly with someone who might be in
front of it.
What do I mean by that?
Well, imagine I have, you know, something that's coming through here.
And I want it to appear in front of this guy but I'm drawing him like
this, well, it'll appear behind incorrectly in that case.
Whereas if it looks like this, it will appear correctly.
Why is that?
Because this is a sort of the ground point of the Sprite.
Like if we think about what we see, when we look at the Sprite on the
screen here is the tree this part our brain because it is a tree even
though it's just a 2d flat thing.
Our
It immediately goes, oh this part is low to the ground.
This part is high to the ground, right?
That's what your brain is thinking, so matching the Sprite right so
that this part is actually low in Z.
And this part is actually high in Z leads to what the brain will
perceive as correct sorting results.
When something of mid-height comes through here, right?
And it's looking like this as well, it's tax properly against this
thing.
Whereas, if they were like this it wouldn't because the difference in
Z is simply not enough.
Capture the fact that the ground is down here, right?
So, what we want to do is probably output our Sprites, so that we do a
tracer down to the ground where the Sprite is sitting.
So, we have the ground point and we know we're here on the monitor
plane, right?
We probably want to do a tracer and then say, okay, we then want to go
up on a on a diagonal, that's at a particular slope and that slope
will have to select sort of to be something fairly eccentricity.
Trick like that something fairly, you know, at a high angle.
I guess what I'd say, this is probably going to be more than 90,
right?
We want that to basically be prescribed and say alright let's generate
a Sprite where we go up to this particular point so that we end up
with the correct width on the screen or I guess I should say the
correct height on the screen.
For the Sprite that we prescribe for the bitmap, right?
Because we've got an idea of H and W for the bitmap and we want the
screen sort of idea of height to be correct.
So the aspect ratio of the Sprite is maintained, but we want it to
slant upwards relatively dramatically there so that we get that better
sorting, right?
So that's what we kind of want to do here.
The, at least, I think that's what we want to do here.
It's hard to say, but I think that's probably the best option.
And so what we want to do is is make it so that, you know, from the
top down, our thing does look like okay.
There's some trees here, you know, and there's a hero or whatever.
And, you know, maybe there's a tree in front of the hero and stuff
like that, but from the side, right?
If we were to look side on these trees, actually look like that down
here.
Are, you know, and this tree looks like that here and the hero looks
like two Sprites one that's there and one that's there.
You know what I'm saying?
So we kind of want to do something like that because the the effect of
pushing those Sprites through the Z buffer will give us what we want.
And that's I think that's basically
That's the basic idea anyway.
Yeah.
So I think that's what we want.
I think that's going to be better than trying to use flat stock
things, flat stack things, I think would get us right back into the
problem, how do we sort these things?
So I think we want things to be slanted so that they will stack on
each other naturally and use the Z buffer, properly, to figure out who
is standing in front of whom.
Okay, so that's kind of what we need to do.
And hopefully now that you've seen that, you understand why I think
this is going to be important for us for debugging the ability to tilt
down like this because essentially we've got to create these sort of
three-dimensional.
Placards and without being able to bend the camera, we're not going to
have very much intuition for how we actually created them.
We're going to write some code and hope that it's right by an
inspection.
But, you know, without being able to actually play around with it and
see it, like, I can.
When I do this, we wouldn't really know that we'd gotten it right?
Or more importantly, when looks like we'd gotten it wrong, we wouldn't
have a lot of intuition as to why it was wrong.
It might look
Relatively correct in 2D.
But then when we spin it in, 3D we go, right?
Okay.
It's totally busted here, right?
So that's what I would say.
And so that's what I'm going to try and do here.
So let's start I guess by talking about
To turn on the z-buffer.
That's probably the first thing that we want to do and then we've
already talked way back at the beginning of this set.
If you want to go back and double-check what a z-buffer or depth
buffer is, so hopefully that's something that you have familiar.
If you don't, if you're not familiar with, I'm not going to re-explain
it.
Go check that one of those previous versions where I talk about it in
depth.
I think there's one episode particular where I go through it and talk
about how it works entirely.
So that's the one to check out baby.
It's about six six episodes goers
Eight Episodes go, I don't remember.
Was that the very beginning, so it probably will more than that
actually.
Anyway, so if I go into our opengl pipeline, I'm going to show you
roughly where this sort of thing comes into play.
So you can see our opengl renderer commands here.
And you can see us doing our you know, texture 2D scissor test blend
etcetera.
What we need to do here and I don't think we ever disabled it because
it's not on by default.
So you can see we're not we're not really ever.
Are doing anything to disable it.
It's something you have to turn on.
And so in here, I want to be able to do a thing where I say, GL enable
and what this is called I guess, in this case, let's see.
I don't care about that.
What I want is a better class, there we go.
When I'm enabling things such as texturing, I want to be able to
enable depth test right at GL and able GL depth.
Test is a thing that says
Is turned on the depth buffer and when I say turn on the depth buffer,
I actually mean testing against the depth buffer.
There's actually two separately controllable things you can do with
the depth buffer in the fixed function pipeline.
One is to control whether or not you are reading and testing from the
depth buffer.
The other one is to control whether or not you are writing to the
And so there's actually also another one called GL depth mask and I'll
show you this one.
And doxology L because it's not an enable call its own call.
And you can see here.
What happens is, it's sort of a separate enable kind of thing.
I don't know why these don't go through enable but basically GL depth,
mask is the equivalent of another function.
I don't think we ever talked about GL color mask where you can set the
red green blue and Alpha channels.
And what these do is they essentially allow us to control what we're
working with, right?
So if you imagine the default State we don't have to set these but the
default state looks like this I believe which is that every channel
gets written to depth.
Red green blue and Alpha are all the things we can write to except for
stencil which we haven't really done anything with.
But you can see that one has one down here as well.
We don't need that the moment.
So all the things that we're writing to would be enabled in this case.
Now, what's important to understand about this, and this is true in
the fixed function pipeline.
It's also true.
If you move to shaders, you have even more control there.
But what happens here is, you can see this allows me to control what
I'm actually writing to as a well as what I'm testing against.
So I can say whether or not I'm testing against the depth buffer for
occlusion, but I can also say whether I'm writing to it or whether I'm
running to color channels as well.
What that means is if I wanted to, I could write only to the depth
buffer on a pass if I wanted to, right.
And that's important too because it means you can build up depth
buffers without drawing any thing which sometimes becomes important.
So I'm just very common in rendering is called a depth prepass and so
you know, things like that are only possible because you can change
what you're writing to at any given time Hui.
Yours it's tired in here.
You can change what you're writing to an egg in time and decide not to
write Colors.
So you can just write depth.
If that's what you want.
And vice versa, you can choose not to write the depth buffer only read
from it, for example, and
Colors, Etc.
The but basically, if taken together this sets up the entire drawing
situation that we're working with.
Now there is one caveat here which like I can
look up at the frame buffer.
I don't know where we allocate frame.
Buffers probably right here Jill by for a bit so you can see what
happens here.
GL frame, buffer texture 2D, where we put a texture attachment into
one of these frame buffers.
One of the things that we're going to have to deal with and I'll just
put the to do in here to do create a depth buffer or this Frame
buffer.
one of the things that you have to do now, in addition, to enabling it
is, if you ever change the render Target because your default render
target comes from a different place and we'll talk about in a second,
but anytime you create a render Target like we were doing here that
render Target cannot use depth buffering, if it doesn't have a depth
buffer and you can see here that when we bound this Frame buffer, the
only thing that we gave it was a frame buffer texture which is
basically saying
A color to right into we Never Bound a depth buffer.
Now, binding a depth buffer is very easy to do so it's not a big deal
it's just a called looks exactly the same.
Looks like that.
But so you instead of saying that it goes into a color attachment, you
can say it goes into a depth attachment and then you can use death
buffering on that frame buffer.
But we have to actually generate a texture for it, which at the moment
we are not doing.
So that's really all that is and this this will be something we'll
have to deal with when we go and re-enable sort of like the room
stacking or stuff like that that we had wanted
Do so that's it for depth buffer is there's not a lot to it.
However, like I said we do need our default buffer to have depth
information in it and so there is one of the thing we have to do.
Because remember that and you remember we did this when we looked at
the srgb stuff, our original color and depth buffer and everything
else comes from opengl es Windows initialization.
Stuff in wiggle when we actually do our wiggle, set up for set, pixel
format, when you look in here, you can see that we've set up a bunch
of, you know, a trip stuff and all this sort of thing, right?
Where we go, like suggested, pixel, format intended pick, and we've
got double buffer and support opengl ARB, and all this sort of stuff
in here, pixel type rgba arm, and that sort of thing.
Right.
And what you can see here is like, for example, in both of our things,
we are no.
We're specifying whether we wanted a depth buffer or not, right?
And this is important.
So if we take a look back at some of this code that we had done, when
we did it without thinking, we would want to death buffer if I go to
pixel format descriptor here in Windows, where is it?
There it is.
You can see that there's a seed depth B.
Like a parameter for that very piece of information, right.
And so if C depth, B isn't set to something, we wouldn't be guaranteed
that we would get any kind of depth buffer at all right.
It could just not give us one and so it depends on what kind we want
here.
If we want a floating-point depth, buffer or not, or exactly what we
want, I don't know how greedy you can be in this case in terms of
backwards compatibility.
So you know,
One thing to first see that this might be to say 24.
And to say that the there'd be eight bits of stencil in there,
probably something like that.
And if you want to be greedy, you could say 32 and say one a full
floating Point depth buffer we probably don't need that.
So I think for backwards compatibility sake asking for a 24 bit depth,
buffer is probably the safest thing to do because it probably would
extend to most platforms that I know of that could.
Someone could reasonably be putting animate Hero on.
but that's only our path for failing the extended pick if
Makes sense.
So, you know, when we come back here to this guy, this one doesn't
really talk about those at.
All right?
It does that suggested pixel format index.
Extended pick thing through wiggle, choose paste or an herb.
I don't remember if you have to set something here.
In addition to pixel type ARB that says, whether I want a depth buffer
or not, so probably what we're going to have to do is take a look at
wiggle choose
Axel format or and see,
Where's the spec?
Hello specification.
All right, folks, there is a specification to this.
I don't care about any of these things.
I want the spec please, that'll do.
Here we go.
And so in this case yeah you can see.
So we're not specifying any of these, we're not specifying a red, B,
Green B, blue b or alphabets and we're not specifying, death fits.
I don't know if that's because we were smart or not, let's take a
look.
So, I don't know why we weren't specifying these.
I guess because we didn't care.
But we need to tell it that we at least want a depth buffer, and I
don't know if there's any particular way to fix that.
So these are minimums, so I guess that's fine because that way we
wouldn't prevent it from giving us a 16-bit color buffer if it had
one, right?
So that seems reasonable.
So I could do red green, blue, Alpha, and depth, and just specify
those and that seems good, right?
We're knocking out number 10 which is 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8.
Nine.
Yeah, so we're knocking that one out and ending the list there, so
that means we would need to sort of put these up here.
All right, so red bits are.
Will say eight, green.
Bits are it again.
Lubitz are
Alpha, it's Barb.
And get B.
So now we should be able to say knockout number 20, if we're not going
to specify that if it doesn't support srgb.
And in theory now we should be specifying in both cases.
The information we need to specify in order to get those buffers.
Now we do need these values so we need, you know,
Red B.
Green bits.
Lubitz.
Alphabets.
And depth bits.
And so now in theory we should have a functioning depth buffer, right?
In theory and by the fact that we're not seeing anything on the
screen, I believe that indicates that we did, in fact, turn it on.
Because remember our open our our projection Matrix is not actually
Loops that
Our projection Matrix is not actually doing anything with the Z.
So, yeah, you can see here, if I, if I leave it off, it it draws.
If I enable it, it doesn't draw.
Right?
So I believe that that is actually turning it on correctly and that we
do have one.
Now, a couple other things that we're gonna have to do.
So, first of all, we need a GL clear.
Because one of the things that would prevent us from
Seeing anything on the screen is the depth buffer.
Don't forget is an actual buffer that needs to be cleared, right?
It's actual information just like color information, it just stores.
The Z values of the things at the locations of every pixel, but right
now we're only cut clearing the color buffer bit and we need to clear
the depth buffer bit as well, or I shouldn't say we're only carrying
color buffer.
This color buffer bit says, clear the color buffer, the depth buffer
bit says, clear the depth buffer.
The B part just means it's a bit mask that I or together to tell clear
what to do.
And I can also much like Geo clear color.
I can also say what I want to
Clear that value to write clear depth.
There it is.
Oops.
Ah, web browser.
There we go.
So you can see here, clear depth, it gives a depth value here that
we're going to clear too.
And one is considered the farthest away.
So again, Z gets larger as you get away from the camera.
So if I wanted to, I could also say, hey, let's just specify this
explicitly that we're going to clear, two one.
So now we're saying clear to this RGB and a and also clear to this
depth when you go now, this will become important potentially later
because remember,
If we want to, we can do a number of things here.
I don't think will actually need to use this, but we can use that
depth clear to create slices through the image as well, right?
If everything Compares against the depth buffer, if we wanted to make
sure that we didn't draw anything past a certain point, we could clear
the depth buffer to that point and then nothing would compare in front
of it and we would never draw anything behind it.
So in effect this is a clipping plane in and of itself.
So in addition to
During the near and far clipping planes.
For example, we also have the ability to set a third kind of value,
not that we need it for anything, but you can with that,
Just for the record.
Alright, so now that we're playing the depth buffer, I would suspect.
Yeah, there we go.
Now that we're clearing the depth buffer.
We're getting a sort of Z tested drawing here but it's still
completely, not what we want for obvious reasons and I guess I'm a
little confused at what I'm seeing, to be honest.
This isn't exactly what I would have expected.
I'm not sure why we're getting
Those gray outlined areas.
Oh wait, no I dunno.
All right so I know exactly where those are in fact so and we can
actually fix those earlier rather than later.
So we might as well do it.
Now while they came up on the screen and I was had to think about what
they were.
So if you remember what happened and I'll draw this on the Blackboard
because this is particularly important to understand.
I suppose it's something that has a subtlety that were probably going
to have to deal with later in some way.
It with Alpha to coverage or something like this.
But so we have an issue.
Here.
Which is that, if you remember how our hero Sprite was made, this was
just we still have never updated to real art yet.
We're still just using mostly sand and stuff.
So what we did is we have a Sprite that was, you know, the ground
Shadow, you know?
And then we had another Sprite that was the hero.
Torso or whatever, right?
And then another one, that was the head and whatever.
Doesn't that right?
Well now that we're drawing with the z-buffer.
Remember this whole thing is getting set to a z value of whatever its
Z is into the depth buffer.
So the depth buffer is writing whatever the Z value is of this Sprite
into the depth buffer.
At that point, what that means is when this Sprite comes along and
tries to draw
Even though the ground Shadow was only this small thing down at the
bottom, this whole area got cleared out by the z-buffer, right?
So when this tries to draw, it's like, no, I'm at the same Z is this?
And there's already something there, I'm not going to draw right?
So there's two things we want to do to help with this situation
because it depends on the circumstance which one is going to make
sense.
There's actually three but we're going to leave one of them for later
because it's more of an advanced thing.
So what we want to do here is say like, oh, okay, well if that's what
we're going to do, we need to first of all probably stopped our
Sprites from filling the z-buffer.
If there isn't any actual color information there, if the alpha value
of the thing is 0, we shouldn't draw in and there's a thing for this
very, very purpose.
Which is g l Alpha, funk.
So what Jill Alpha function does is, it says, all right, in addition
to test against the z-buffer to determine whether I should draw.
I'm also going to test a against the incoming Alpha value.
So if the incoming Alpha value of my Sprite, doesn't meet a certain
threshold, for example, which I can use by setting up the equation
here,
I'm not going to draw it.
So what you can do is say alright I can set never less than equal less
than or equal to greater than not equal greater than equal to are
always right to specify how I would like to compare the alpha value.
Coming from my Sprite with this reference value that I Supply and if
the function does not succeed that I specified, if it's not say less
than the reference value it won't work right?
So you can see here at them to find.
If I set it to jail and never, then nothing will pass.
It's always discarded.
The fragment.
If I said, it's a GLS that it passes if the incoming Alpha value is
less than
Reference value, right?
So basically this would give me something that the smaller the alpha
value was.
The more likely it was going to pass but I don't want that.
What I want is greater than right.
I want to say or perhaps greater than or equal to, I want to pass in a
reference value here, that something low like 0.1 and say if the alpha
value is not greater than that, that assume that there's no Sprite at
this location and you shouldn't draw, right?
So, that's step one.
And I don't know what we want to set this to yet.
We're going to have to talk about that a little bit later.
Certainly it has to be you know, higher than zero but
I forgot one other thing.
Well, I think I know this one by heart, so I guess I don't have with
that.
But this much like the depth mask is controlled by a Boolean enable.
So when I set the function, I still need to turn it on right by
specifying GL and able g l Alpha test.
Once I've turned on Alpha test, then it will actually execute that
thing.
And now, you can see, we're starting to get a little bit better right
now.
You can see that where
Properly, sort of clipping those.
Things to their regions.
But you can see another problem or set of problems and these are all
problems.
We're going to have to deal with a little bit more carefully as we go.
So you can see here that if you look in sort of the the areas around
the tree, for example, or around this piece here, when it's actually
visible, you can see that by clipping it to 0.1.
We actually create two types of problems and this
Happen wherever we clip it to if we clip it to too high of a value,
you don't get any softness.
You don't get the softness that you would expect if we clip it to too
low of a value.
Then we get, you know, sort of a band area where we you know, where
were the alpha isn't really high enough to Warrant clipping but it's
still going to happen and you can see, oh wait that's not hot code
reloadable.
I should have made that reloadable.
But I didn't, you can see that.
Let's say we made it that it just has to be greater than 0, for
example.
Now you can really see where the problem is here, right?
And the reason that that problem exists is just because we don't at
the moment, have any clean way of making sure that the draw order is
proper in this case, right?
Because those Alpha values and this is an inherent problem with the
z-buffer.
It's the one problem I think that we're really going to have with it
that we have to be
Ever about how we're going to do it.
But what happens is, if you imagine before why, our Alpha blending
worked, if I have a tree, and then I have something behind the tree.
This whole area has Alpha values in it, right?
And those Alpha values are important, because they are telling me how
much of the tree to blend with whatever is behind the tree.
It's a way of getting sub-pixel information in there.
It's like, here's how much of the tree was in that one pixel or
something, right?
And so in that case, what that means is we have to know what's behind
it first before we can use, what's in front of it.
In this case that becomes a big problem because
As we don't know what order these things were drawn in the whole point
is we want to draw them in any old order, we don't want have to think
about it too much, right?
So it's highly likely that rather than this being drawn first, and
this being drawn, second this may be drawn first and this will be
drawn second in that case.
We're totally we're we there's nothing we can really do, we given this
the The Limited tools we have at the moment because when this tree
draws it will clear.
It will set the Z.
A buffer all along its entire line.
There, no matter what the alpha values were, as long as they were
above zero, it'll set them to basically being at its Z value.
This will come along and be at a deeper Z values, further away, it
won't draw anything in there.
So what we end up with is no blending
Right?
We get perfect blending.
If they happen to draw on the right order because the Z buffer will
correctly.
Determine that this tree was in front of whatever was behind it.
But if they happen to draw on the wrong order just happenstance, then
they still sort properly because the z-buffer takes care of the
Sorting, but we don't get any blending right.
And that's a problem.
so hopefully, you can see
Mmm?
Why that causes a nasty problem because again we don't know what the
sort of these things are until the z-buffer takes care of for us.
And so we don't have any way of really reproducing that blend that we
need to reproduce.
So that's going to be something that we're going to have to deal with
later.
It's important and and this problem only gets worse with shadows,
Shadows are supposed to be soft things.
That kind of have lots of low Alpha values and they're the worst,
right?
Because they're effectively a transparent object so you can see that.
We've got it.
We're going to have to think a bit and do some cleverness with our
rendering.
In order to get something that's a reasonable that that's reasonably
workable there.
And yeah, that's going to take some cleverness to avoid having to get
back into the business of sorting everything.
Again, which is exactly what we don't want to do.
And so we do need to
To bring some cleverness there.
When we when we when that we get to that point.
Now, the other thing we need to do here is we need to set up a very
similar to our Alpha function.
We need to talk about our debt function.
So let's take a look at that function as well.
It's basically the same kind of thing.
Whoop it up.
So you can see the GL death Funk here.
Now, you'll notice that unlike Alpha Funk, it doesn't take a reference
value.
Why?
Because that value is coming from the depth buffer, right?
In the alpha case, we're just setting a threshold in the depth case,
we're talking about how to compare against the death buffer, same set
of options here, we can have it so that it never passes, we can say
that it's got to be less than whatever the ink the store depth value
is, right?
And that's what we want.
In this case, if we wanted to draw things in
Order.
However what we really want is less than or equal to, right?
We want to be able to say, hey if the thing coming in happens to be
the same as what was already there.
Draw it because we're probably going to want to do things or we send
three things down, say that are meant to go on top of each other, all
the same Z value, and we want a good chance of that working.
So we probably want something like that.
And now you can see, we get back to sort of closer to what we had
originally because now that drawing order is getting respected, right?
And so that's a good thing as well.
So, there we go.
Now our Z buffer is functional.
We are drawing through it.
We're going to have to do some work regarding Alpha Testing, and we're
going to have to think about that.
Again, that's not really something that I've typically had to deal
with, when I've been working on game stuff because I'm usually used to
3D things more but this is a problem.
Even 3D things.
You end up with the transparency problem that we talked about.
We have to sort your transparent objects and stuff like that.
Obviously, for this game we want to get out of the starting.
We want to be able to throw a lot of things in here.
We're going to find some clever Solutions there, maybe use alpha
coverage, or things like that, but we'll try to figure out some good
Solutions using the horse power of the GPU, which were not really
utilizing in most other ways, right?
Because we're more simplistic 2-D game, you know, we're going to start
thinking about it and just figure out, okay, what's a good way that we
can utilize the power of the GPU to get us some nice blending here?
Without having to worry too much about sorting, right?
So anyway, that's where we're at.
And so now we just need to start start to work on how we're going to
stack those Sprites up because this flashing is still going to persist
until we actually have something stable to be sorted.
You can see when I kind of come through here the the problem that we
have there which is that we you know we really just don't have any way
for this.
Before you differentiate between us is all stacked on top of each
other and the draw determines when they draw.
You can also see
due to this right here, you can see
If you can see that as I rotate back and forth, you can see the trees
kind of slice in and out.
That is actually a classic case of z-fighting, right.
I've got two things stacked on top of each other.
That happened to be at the exact same z-values the whole way, but
because they are different actual triangles, right?
Because one of them is, you know, like for example, this is two
triangles here that make up a square and this is
Two triangles that are bigger, right?
That don't that don't coincide.
They're not identical iterating.
The Z values across those triangles leads to slightly different
results.
And so they no longer are exactly equal and you get depending on where
the iterators are.
You can see the banding in, how the, that iterate, those iterators
were iterating and where the Precision was for the transform.
You can see that happening with the z-fighting, right?
So we've got one more thing, we need to do.
I guess now that I think about it though.
The z-fighting remind me of this before we go any further with our Z
buffer, which is that we're not properly processing Z values to give
them good values for for the Z buffer.
Because remember our projection Matrix, we have that yet.
So we do want to do that and in fact that might improve that
z-fighting there a little bit but that's separate issue.
Because we don't really want that Z fighting in the first place,
right?
All right.
So let's see.
Where is our projection Matrix?
Here we go.
So here's what we're calling our perspective, projection.
And let's go ahead and grab that all the math.
So here we are.
So you can see here, here's our perspective projection.
And what's happening right now is whatever the Z value is that comes
in is the Z value that comes out.
This is kind of useless, right?
If you think about it, the reason it's kind of useless is because we
know that opengl wants the Z values that get produced from the depth
buffer to be in a certain range.
I think it's is I would have thought it would have been negative one
to one but it sounds like it's 0 to 1.
I don't know if that's
Kind of want the opengl spec here.
It's too bad.
Jocks dot DL doesn't have glue perspective.
Can't remember, I tried to grab a good one of these.
I don't remember which page had a good one.
Here it is.
So I don't remember what open Jill wants in terms of the depth values
but I assume it wants it - one two, one.
Yeah, so like I said, I thought it was negative 1 to 1 everywhere but
I wasn't sure.
And then so I guess it is, in fact, native whenever and then just when
it does the window, when it when it actually outputs those
coordinates, they become between 0 and 1.
After the fact, it sounds like because right?
If that wasn't the case,
There we go.
If that wasn't the case, then you wouldn't be clearing between zero
and one, right?
You'd be queer clearing between negative 1 and 1.
And so I think that, you know, they did the math as if you are on the
negative 1 to 1 Cube but you know in actuality they then turn around
after it comes out of that and sort of fudge it back into a different
range.
Right.
Okay.
So anyway, you can kind of see here, this this stuff is you can ignore
this stuff for the moment, but you can kind of see what has to be
happening here.
What they're doing is they're trying to map between the near and far
clipping planes.
They're trying to map that range into the negative 1 to 1 range and we
I think really could probably choose which way we mapped it, whether
it
- 121 where - one was, the near clipping plane and one was the far
clipping plane or the other way around, right?
We could do either or but
it would just all that would do would change how our depth values were
what we would set our depth function to write if we mapped it.
So that negative one to one, where one was the furthest thing away and
- one was the closest thing.
Then obviously we want to depth um, to be less than if we did it the
other way around, we want our deaf Funk to be greater than right, so
how we map our Z in the perspective Matrix would determine how we
would have to test against it.
So let's work out the math here, right?
so,
What we want to do here is set an earring far clipping plane.
These are basically going to be in that camera diagram that we've sort
of been drawing very often.
They're going to be.
If this is where I'm looking from, here's my little eye, looking at
the world, the world is out here, right?
There's going to be some place where I cannot see anything on this
side of it, right?
Nothing out here is visible anything on this side of this plane?
And there's also going
Something out in the distance.
That's the far clipping plane and nothing out here.
Nothing to this side of.
It can be seen and so it's creating sort of a boundary
That looks like this.
Only this region is visible, right?
So in addition to sort of the boundaries that the screen creates in
terms of the Left, Right?
Top and bottom boundaries, there's these near and far boundaries and
those boundaries clip things in z
Furthermore, they set up the range for our Z buffer, because these are
all the values Z from negative 1 to 1.
We'll only Encompass just this range
Right?
That's, that's the entirety of the range that it will encounter.
And so, what that means again, is that, you know, when we do our Z
buffer, the Precision,
Of the z-buffer.
How precise it can be with its computations, and comparisons is
entirely dependent upon how big this this area is, right?
However, we map this space, the Z buffer has only the same amount of
precision, no matter how big I make this.
It has to still cover the entire range with the same quantities in z.
Right.
So it doesn't have any ability to increase, you know, it can't just
arbitrarily invent more Precision.
Somehow, if I want to make something bigger, it means that I'm losing
Precision throughout this volume.
If I make the volume bigger, whereas if I make the volume smaller, I
get more precise because I can I have more distinct Z values per unit
of Z / distance in the world.
Basically,
All right, so what I want to do here is I want to be able to prescribe
the near and far clipping planes in terms of distances from the
camera.
And then I want to convert the incoming values so that they lie
between those two Z values.
Right now, what we know about the Z values that are coming in
obviously and you can see that here is that the Z values coming in are
Sort of going the wrong direction as well, right?
So the Z value is coming in are going this way.
They're coming out toward the camera.
But opengl wants to think of them going away from the camera is the
more natural way?
That it was thing about that's why we had to negate our W parameter,
right?
So in order to think the this through what we have to do is say, all
right.
We've got a near and far, clipping plane, our Z values are coming in,
they're coming in this way, but the near and far clipping planes are
going to probably just be described as distances from the camera.
So they're going to be positive, right?
So the near clip planes, you know, it 0.4, F or something in the far
clip planes like, you know, 100.0 f for something like this.
I don't know what will actually set them to write.
But what that means is, those are
Distances along the negative Z Direction.
Does that make sense?
So what we want to do here is say well, okay, you know, we've got
these two points here is my near, here's my far right?
And I've got my incoming Z, how do I map it?
So that this becomes negative 1 and this becomes 1 right?
Which is what I said I wanted.
Well, I know some equations, right?
I know some, some things that I want to have happen.
Right.
So essentially what I'm saying is I've got a function that I wanted to
find that a z-value kind of comes into, right?
And whatever my z-buffer value is comes out, right?
So this produces that z-buffer value that's supposed to be negative 1
to 1.
I know that if I put in like, whatever this whatever this function is
going to be, I know some things about it.
I know that if what I feed it is negative n, right?
So if I feed it, this value right here, this point in the world, I
know that I want that to be equal to negative 1, right?
That makes sense.
Furthermore,
I know that if I feed it, f,
I want that value to be one, right?
So I know, two distinct points that it has to satisfy which gives me a
lot to work with.
So now I just need to know what is the structure of this function
going to be?
Well, I know that as well actually, right?
Because I am completely constrained.
I have no ability to do anything other than what the perspective
Matrix allows me to do.
What that
It's like a look at the perspective Matrix and again remember the
prospective Matrix looks like this.
Actually going to put dots instead of excess.
We don't get confused thinking their actual X.
Okay.
We know that W is going to be 1 in this case.
So, if I look at what happens here, remember, I don't care what
happens to my x coordinate.
In this case, we're not talking about X.
These values all affect the x coordinate.
We don't care about them.
They're not involved same with these.
These are determining, the why we don't care about them.
They're not involved.
We already worked out what those are and they're done.
Right?
So we don't care about that anymore.
That's over.
Here we've got a line that deals with the Z, right?
And here we've got a line that deals with a W again W we've already
worked out and it's working fine for us.
We don't care.
So the Z
Is what we care about looking at the Z.
What are the values we can actually use?
Well, we can't use anything that's proportional to X or Y because that
has nothing to do with what we're trying to map here.
So those values also don't matter and we can't really use them.
So all we end up with.
Is these two parameters here?
We have a times Z Plus B, right?
And those are the two things we can feed into our Matrix there.
Right?
We can put two values in what that means is we know that the function
of this structure structure.
Sorry the structure of this function is f of Z equals AZ plus b,
right?
Because that's all I can do.
So now what do I have?
I have the structure of the function f of Z equals AZ plus b.
And I have the two points that I know have to be true.
Well if I combine these together this is a equation in two unknowns
plus two values for that equation.
That is exactly what I need.
Right at equation with two unknowns and two values, Elementary High
School math.
In fact, it's junior high school math.
Solve the equation, that's it.
So, here we go.
I know I have a z plus b, right?
And I want to plug in in this case negative n, let's say right, I will
do at first so I have a f plus b equals negative 1.
That's one equation.
And then the other equation I have was 14 - n.
That's - A N plus b equals 1, right?
Those are the two points that I've got.
Let's solve these equations 4A and 4B.
In this case, I have I'll solve this one first.
So I've got AF plus b equals negative 1.
I'm going to choose to solve in this case, for B, let's say, because
it's already isolated.
So, I'll do b equals -1 + AF, right?
Oops, - eh heh,
There we go.
I'm just moving the AF to the other side.
So now we have a term for be.
So now over here, I can go ahead and substitute that in to solve so I
have - A N - 1 - a f equals 1, right?
That's just substituting into this equation and then I can start to
pull out my values.
I've got negative a, which is what I want to solve for here, right?
I've got - A on both of these so that's n + f.
And then I can move my constant over to the other side and that's just
going to be plus 1.
So that's going to be a 2 over here so you can see how I did that.
And now I just need to solve this equation for a that's going to be a
equals 2 over.
And plus F.
And the - here, I also need to get rid of so that comes over their
side / - + + FS that comes over to their side, right?
So there's my value for a if I want to look at what that becomes when
I look at what it is.
For B, I can say b equals -1 -2 F / n + f.
And hey that's actually just already done for us.
We don't really have to do anything else there because we have yet the
complete equation.
So you know math
Is hard.
Let's go shopping.
This is exactly the kind of thing that I often make mistakes at when
I'm moving things around, I wish computers just did this for you, and
sometimes they do, you know, mathematics is not bad at it but it tends
to produce.
It doesn't produce things in a clean way.
A lot of times it's just annoying.
I still haven't found the like computer-assisted algebra product that
I really want in my life someday, I'll have to make it, but
This is the process by which we would produce these values.
So let's take a look.
If they make sense from what I said because we can do three things.
Now that, you know, we to test this one is I can put in negative 1 and
verify that I get an out.
I'm sorry.
One is I can put an n and verify that I get negative 1 out one is I
can put an f and verify the get one out and the other is I could put
in, you know,
0.5 and plus F and verify.
That the thing I get out is somewhere in between, right, that I should
be able to get something that Maps between those two, right?
All right, so let's take a look.
So let's assume that these are these, the simplest I can make them.
I'm not sure, let's see.
Yeah, it looks like yeah, I don't see much else.
I mean we could write it this way.
we could write it this way and then say, Okay - 2f
And plus F minus n plus f.
Over M plus F and this is just me.
You know.
Again if you remember sort of your Junior, High math, if I want to add
two fractions, I have to make them the same denominator first.
It's all I was doing there.
And so if you see what happens here, now I can combine the them on the
top and my B becomes -2, f - n - F / n + f.
And the reason I did that was just because if you look at what happens
there, I was looking at it, it looks like comes a little simpler
because now pun top, I've got multiple F's there.
I can just do - 3 f - n.
N+ F, right?
And off you go.
So I believe I did that correctly.
But again, this is the kind of math that I tend to mess up.
You can kind of see that it's a little bit strange and so I can make
both of these in terms of f if I want to just like that.
I can also make them in terms of the n + f, i don't know.
Have to think about, if there's any way to do that here, I don't.
I think so, but again, that's just sort of my math Badness.
But yeah, so - 3 F + n Over N plus f is what that looks like and it
just feels like I'm a sure I didn't make a mistake here.
Let's double-check.
So all right so what's our final equation AZ plus b, what would it
look like in this case?
I now know what A and B are.
So I'm basically saying like, Okay,
F of Z and here's my A and B.
So I've got negative 2N plus F this case.
And then I've got negative 3 F + n.
Here's my C - 3 F + n 4n + f like so.
So here's my values.
Let's go ahead and plug in into my Z.
Let's plug in N.
What do I get?
So in this case,
I get Negative 2z, right?
Yeah, - 2 Z /.
I'm sorry you have to n Over.
N plus F minus 3 f plus n Over.
N plus F.
And let's see if I can bind these F of n equals -2.
N minus 3 f - n.
And plus F.
Yeah, you can see.
I've got a sign bug.
I just I could feel it.
I feel like and I feel like I have a signed by but maybe not.
Maybe not.
Maybe I didn't.
So - 3 n minus 3, F / n + f.
Right?
And that's negative 3n + f /.
N + f.
Right.
And that's not what I wanted, right?
So I definitely have assigned bug because it should not have been
that.
All right, so let's take a look.
And again, like I said, you can plug this into something like a
mathematic and have it.
Do it for you for checking purposes, but plugging back in and checking
is usually pretty good.
Of course, I also don't know that I made a mistake in the actual
plugging in, that's the best part about not being someone who's very
good at doing computation math.
I have no idea why we still have to do this, or
Thing, but what can you do?
Anyway, - + + - + + B.
I want to make sure that that's actually correct.
So f of negative n.
Oh,
that's my problem.
I did two stupid things.
First of all, when I plugged in to check, I didn't put in negative n
but also when I did f, it was supposed to be - F
Right.
I messed it up.
I said that F was supposed to be - and I didn't make it negative.
So, this is incorrect, right?
Yeah, that's just wrong.
So my f of negative n was correct but my f of negative f was wrong.
That's why it didn't look right.
I was like this just doesn't look like it's coming out to be what I
would expected and that's why because I've set up my initial things
wrong.
So I did have a sign bug just not necessarily where I thought it was.
Alright, let's try that one more time.
So, f of negative n, we want that to be negative 1.
F of negative.
FS1, right?
That's what I actually want.
It's weird to have F in both places here.
We'll just ignore that pretend that never happened.
And let's give it one more go.
So in this case, again, we've got negative 1, we've got negative, n
should produce negative 1.
So that means that a times negative, n plus b is negative 1.
And similarly, Jimmy.
For plugging in negative f.
It's - AF B was one and I have those, right?
This time,
Look right, hopefully, it looks right off we go.
So now solving again, same process B, in this case equals negative 1
plus, ay, n again.
Just moving the an to the side.
And on this one, I got to plug in this be again.
So I have negative AF and then negative 1 plus.
Ay, n.
So you can see that that's very critical.
Plus a n there.
and- AF this time, whereas before,
Both were negative.
Right.
Yeah, so I think that's probably the only difference.
We'll find out in a second and then hopefully this will flow through
properly.
All right.
So then off we go.
We've got our - one coming over to the other side and we've got these
two terms combining, right?
So off we go, we end up with a n minus AF in this case, equals to
write that goes to their side.
That's a n- f equals 2 or a equals 2 over n minus f.
Right.
Plugging back in, we get for our B value negative one.
Here's our a value so that's 2 N Over.
N minus f.
Right.
And again, let's combine the terms there.
Just to see what happens.
We get a negative 1 over n.
Minus M, Coupe, sorry
Do - n- F Over N.
Minus f.
+ 2, n + - F that.
If we combine these two terms, we get
To n.
Minus n plus F right in this case because the - distributes here, all
over n minus F.
Then when we're done combining these we just get n plus F on the top.
Right to n.
Minus n is just n n+ f Over N.
Minus F, there's our B value, there's our a value.
And so our final equation for f of Z,
is 2 over n, minus F times Z, Plus n plus F over n- f
Okay, plugging in to check if I want to take a look at what my
function will be if I plug in negative n.
Let's see what I get.
I get negative 2 N Over N minus F, right?
Because I'm plugging in negative n to here.
+ n + f / n minus f.
When I combine these you can see what I get.
And I get n.
Well, I get minus n, right?
Because I got - to end here and I just got an end there.
So I get minus n plus f.
Equals n minus or over n minus F right?
Which
Do that correctly.
I did do this correctly.
Yes.
This is where it would be nice if the stream if I actually looked at
the stream because I'm sure the stream check could tell me.
So it's F minus n Over.
N minus F, I believe correctly.
If I'm not mistaken, I'm not sure.
That correctly.
I said, myosin + f.
Plug in negative N4 Z.
Very slow, math day here today if ever, there was one - 2.
N should.
Be on top.
Should be able to combine these because they're both Over N minus F.
Yes.
I feel like this is correct everywhere.
But you always do.
Right.
That all looks pretty clean.
Am I missing something?
This guy might still be wrong.
Let me just double-check in.
And times F Over N times F, which is still negative one, which is
correct.
So that's 2 N.
Minus n plus F over M minus F, which is correct and that's just n + f
Over N.
Minus F that looks right to me.
Looks right to me, however, we know that plugging in f of negative n
in this case should equal negative 1, but this doesn't look like it
worked out the way that I would have expected F, minus n Over.
N minus f.
That is correct.
So what I can do here is just say, well, okay?
Sorry I'm paranoid about this.
I wanna make sure it's correct thing.
That's all correct and this looks like it'll work out correctly.
So F, minus n Over, N minus F.
If I pull out a negative here and minus f is the same as F minus n.
If I pull out a negative, right?
So at that point, I end up with being able to cancel the terms.
In this case,
So that ends up being a 1 over negative 1, which of course is negative
1.
So good on that.
I got a little worried there because I didn't think that was that a no
just did look familiar to me but hey, it ended up being correct and
let's try.
Same exact equation.
But this time plugging in negative f just to make sure.
And so that's again, to this the C value here.
Now is negative f, so that's going to be negative, f and minus F + + +
f /.
N minus F, right?
And same thing going to do - 2f + n+.
F / m- f,
and now we say, well okay that's -2 F, that's going to be n, minus F
Over N minus F, which is 1,
So those are the two answers that we wanted.
That's a good thing and so I think we can go ahead and use this guy so
there's our equation.
And so then we know what to put in our Matrix.
We need to put in that and that and then we can start specifying near
and far clipping planes.
So in here in our perspective projection, we have RN + RF
At some point we may want to pass these in for right now.
I don't think we need to, we can just kind of be arbitrary with them
for the moment because we don't have anything we need to actually do
with them.
So we'll wait until someone actually needs to specify those before.
We think about how we might want them to be passed in or other things
like that, but we do know again.
What our what our value coming in here is, right?
Here's our a and our B.
Unfortunately already have our B & B, so let's do D and E.
In this case.
And so,
Our D value is 2 over n minus f.
And Ari value.
Is n+ f / m- f.
So that should do our mapping for us properly.
We hope and you can actually see already even though we don't really
have any way of testing this explicitly.
You can see how there's a lot finer grained z-fighting because now
we're mapping rz2 a real correct range, right?
We're taking a seen an actual reasonable slice through the scene and
mapping that to the full Precision of the z-buffer.
Or as opposed to before, when it was just, whatever the z-buffer
happened to be, which meant that it would get be getting clamped
between negative 1 and 1.
So only like the broadest Z values would actually be doing anything
inside where we were, so you can kind of see that that actually did
already give some effect too.
To our Sprites there, right?
So let's do we don't have much time left.
So let's just go want to do one more thing here.
Let's take a look at how our Sprites are being outputted here in the
render group and we have the sort of notion of upright Sprites but
we're not actually using it at the moment when we actually push stuff
on and I don't actually know if that's I don't think that's coming
through anywhere, I could be wrong about
Fat.
You can kind of see where setting this up, right transform, but we
don't use it anywhere, right?
But we do know when it's happening.
And so when we're in here, in our render group,
See here.
when we do a push bitmap call,
So when we're doing this, push bitmap call, you can actually imagine
what we could start to do.
Here, in addition to passing down, like, for example, our X and Y
axis, if we wanted to, we can set our X and Y axis, to be something
that is not flat, right?
We can have the X and y-axis be something that's like standing upright
more and start to take a look at how that would would progress, right?
So for example, one thing we could do is say like, you know, if
Object transform upright.
And this is not even remotely a good idea, but I'm just giving you
what the idea is.
We could add some height to the Sprite in the case where the object is
supposed to be an upright object, just so we can see the difference
between the two of them, right?
Oh wait.
Are the x axis or only V2s.
All right, that's fine.
so we need to do here say oh actually
these have to be fully 3D.
And then here we can just say oops.
There we go.
And now when we're actually using these
We can always just actually use the right.
Oh wait, I don't have to do that.
Alright, so now we're drawing these.
Hopefully you can see what I'm getting at here.
This is already starting to sort of do the thing that I was talking
about, right?
And you can imagine doing this fairly with with a relatively
exaggerated.
Height, something that's not at all, what we would actually want the
height to be, but you can start to see how this will work, right?
Looking kind of at how these go.
This is sort of the diagram that I was drawing before, right?
Everything is kind of slightly sort of slanted at an angle there.
And then, you know, when we're drawing these things, we're drawing
them in
In a way that allows the z-buffer to actually properly overlap things
and you can start to see how that will work.
Now you can also see just based on what you're looking at right now,
you can also see why we have to start taking the camera into account,
right?
Because we don't really want our games Sprites to look like sheared,
So when you take a look at what's Happening Here,
And I add that.
That one value in there.
I'm sharing the Sprite in a way that is not appropriate.
And furthermore, you know, like let's say I'm looking directly top
down on this thing like so, so suppose we were playing the game like
this.
You can see how it really changes the Sprite in a way that really
shears it and makes it to squatty, for example, down here or too,
tall, for example, down here.
But what we can do is if we take the cameras location into account,
when we're generating,
The Sprite information, we should be able to work around that, right?
We should be able to figure out a way to make that.
Do something more reasonable.
Okay.
And so, that's the next thing that we have to do.
We only have about 10 minutes left here, so I think maybe it would be
a bad time to start that, but hopefully I can sort of hint you can
sort of give you an idea of what I mean by that.
So if you just look at this guy who happens to be centered on,
if you imagine here, the y axis, again, getting that sort of Z slant
up to it.
What I could also do their say, well, what if we also elongate that,
right?
And I hopefully what you can see here is that for any given Sprite
that I wanted.
So for example, this right here, this is the one I was working on for
any given Sprite.
We can pick a modification to its axis that when you look at that
sprite from a particular camera position, like the one I'm in right
now, it appears as the correct, sprayed again, right?
And, similarly, I could even do that with one over here that appears
very bent, right?
All I would have
Have to do.
Is take that y axis and share it.
To see how that works.
Oops.
So now you can see that even something that's off to an angle right to
the camera and, you know, down in the corner.
It's completely perspective in out and all that stuff.
If I just had a way of computing, the axes that I was going to use.
So that they corrected for the camera Distortion to the viewer, it
appears that the stamp has just been stamped down like a regular
Sprite with no modification.
But in reality,
it's this heinously warped.
Really messed up tree like it's that one, right?
I mean, look at that thing.
But from here, you know, from the original Viewpoint, it looks
correct.
Right.
So what we can choose to do.
depending on how we need to end up making this work, we can choose to
do is just use every time we send out a Sprite use, it's the knowledge
of where the camera actually is to bend the Sprite to properly, align
with the screen in a way that makes it appear as if it's being stamped
out, even though it's actually bent in 3D which is all we really need
to have happen and that will get us back to proper rendering with Z
buffer, sorting and
The only thing that we're going to have to do on top of that in order
to really solve the problem is we're going to have to figure out a way
to deal with our blendable things, right?
Like our hour.
Basically, the edges of the Sprites like this sort of thing here.
That's the only thing that we're really going to have to deal with
separately because that is a real big pain in the butt but they'll be
other things we can do for stuff like Shadows.
You'll see when we take a look at those.
Hopefully, there's there's some things we can do with with stuff like
Shadows.
There's some tricks we can pull with that that don't force us to sort
in as complete a way through sorting before.
So we can do some simple tricks there that might potentially work.
And so we'll have to talk about those as separate issue.
All right, I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A and tomorrow.
We'll we'll work on that transform there.
I'll pull it out for now.
so, let's go ahead and Q a
Ratchet freak.
When adjusting the Sprite like that?
Don't you need to interpolate the texture coordinates in screen space
instead of clip?
Space the default.
Yes, we can.
We well I guess here's what I'd say.
We certainly have the option of doing.
So if we want to, you know, opengl when we switch to shaders, for
example, you can pick how they're interpolated even in
The fixed function pipeline.
If you needed to, you could do it.
If you want to, you just have to have a texture Matrix setup.
I think I don't think there's, I don't know if there's any other way
to do it.
Yeah, I'm not sure but in at least in shaders it's a trivial, it just
change.
All you have to do is change the Declaration of like one variable and
you can in interpolate screen space.
So we should have the opportunity to do that.
Just fine as well.
So that what is Alfred to coverage any good references on that?
So what Alfred a coverage does is and I don't even know like I'll
probably have to go do some reading myself to see if there's better
modern techniques because it's it's possible that that's not even
really what you would do these days.
If that's an old its old that's an old technique.
What out for the coverage does is it says well.
Alright, if you set up a multi sample buffer, so if you basically set
up anti-aliasing like the kind you normally do in 3D,
What you can do is say, oh, when you're actually drawing instead of
using the alpha Channel, as blending at the time, you can use the
alpha channel to say how many samples in the multi sample buffer, you
want it to fill.
So that basically does a anti uses the anti-aliasing capabilities of
the hardware.
Rather than using Alpha blending so that you don't have to worry about
the Order anymore.
It's a little less precise than Alpha blending but it's an interesting
option, right?
What an orthogonal projection Matrix be applicable for your game.
It might be but I don't think so.
We're going to have to see now that we've taken the step to 3D we have
the option to kind of play with that a little bit.
And I'm thinking we probably still want perspective.
Because again, I want things too.
I want multiple floors to work properly and I also want some other
things for probably that will see as we go.
Sherlock 93 is the negative n and negative f because opengl has the
camera on the negative Z axis.
Well, more specifically, the camera on the - the camera having
negative Z pointing away from us in X and Y is sort of what we want.
That's our math view of the world.
So really more specifically, the way to say it might be that the
reason we have to do the negative 8 and negative f is, is because
opengl wants to use the Divide, as a value that increases because it
that's how the peck
Spective divide has to actually work.
Right?
And so because they chose not to bake a negative into the divided.
The projection Matrix has to do that negation
Magic 63.
Why are using Legacy opengl?
We're using Legacy up in jail because I feel like that's the right
opengl for people to learn first in some sense because if you don't
know Legacy opengl yet, it's a lot harder to learn.
Non Legacy opengl so like Legacy.
Opengl lets you pretty much just not set up anything and just start
drawing right?
It's very easy to use non Legacy opengl
Nuts.
Right?
I mean you got to do all sorts of stuff, you have to teach people,
what a Shader is you have to write Shader main routines, you have to
declare variables, setup, vertex, and pixel shaders, and all this
stuff.
And so it's really just, at least as long as opengl as like as long as
Legacy opengl continues to be viable.
It's much easier to show people how to use that first and then show
them how to use Shader based opengl.
And since none of its low-level anyway, like all of it is completely
just telling drivers what to do, right?
We never get to really do anything.
Particularly low level.
There's I don't see any real reason to skip the the Legacy pipeline
because that also was exactly how you programmed say.
And I are xgl machine, it was 100% level of that point because it was
a map directly to the hardware, right?
See voucher, do you typically use an infinite far plane for increased
Precision, Sean McGrath mentioned it in his stream a while back.
So here's what I'd say.
I do often use an infinite far clipping plane in 3D stuff.
I wouldn't consider it appropriate for this because we know exactly
where our end bound is so I don't know that it's necessary for that
but I unless I'm missing something, I don't know why you would
characterize that as something that you use for increased precision.
It's not really increasing the Precision per se.
It's increasing the view distance.
If that makes sense, I guess I can see why you might consider it
increasing the Precision.
Because if you were talking about having to set the view plane out
that far in practice, then you lose a lot of precision up front where
you care about it.
So, I guess I can sort of see why that would be a way to say it, but
in our game, everything's fairly.
We don't have a large swath, it's pretty narrow.
So I don't know that we would bother using an infinite farplane here,
but I do use that often times myself in 3D stuff that's not like, not
in 2D.
That's children.
Would it be simpler to use orthogonal orthographic transforms for
upright objects?
Are you not simply undoing the perspective projection there?
So it would be simpler to use if we didn't care about mixing the two,
right?
But what I am suspecting is I want all of the perspective stuff and I
don't know that for sure.
But I'm I'm guessing that I really want all the prospective stuff.
So what I would rather do is just fuss.
With the Sprite coordinates for things that are standing upright so
that they get mapped properly rather than turn off perspective and
have to deal with orthographic.
That's my guess.
In fact, I'm pretty much certain of it.
Would it be possible to use a Shader to do the Z buffer rendering?
I guess I don't know what that means.
Per se, meaning I you may be asking question.
I don't know what question you're asking, I guess what I would say
first.
So you may need to clarify it but shaders can use the depth buffer.
Just like anything else.
So in a Shader you have the ability to do depth testing and whatever
else you want.
However,
you know, the shaders, the depth, the depth buffer is sort of handled
specially, you might say
So depending on what you're doing, certain things you might want to do
in the Shader, might be more or less costly depending on how fancy you
want to get what I mean by that is depth testing has a special place
in the Shader.
It's not generic it's not 100% generic while you can do 100% generic
depth, buffer testing by binding a texture that is the depth buffer
and operating on it separately.
There's a bunch of early out special condition stuff that the graphics
card can do when it snows.
It's talking about its main primary depth buffer and so in the Shader
in general you can
Do anything you want in terms of depth, testing and rejection and
whatever else.
But certain
if you use it, the way we are traditionally using it here, you may get
a speed win, whereas, if you do arbitrary sorts of stuff with it, in
terms of the complexity of how you use the information in the depth,
buffer versus what you're when you decide to kill or not kill a pixel.
you might incur speed penalties because it can't use things like early
Z outing on whole blocks and stuff like that and like other sorts of
compression Tech that it has
To what degree that matters is.
You know hand wavy and depends on the card and what you're doing and
all that other stuff but you know the general answer is shaders.
You can set up the render path so that you can do pretty much anything
you want.
In terms of calculating what you want to do with the depth buffer.
So the near and far planes are linearly mapped.
I've read somewhere, the mapping is not linear, in which case we do
not in which cases, we do not make them linear.
Yeah, I'm not sure.
I understand what you're saying there.
I guess let me throw some things out there for you.
Technically with a perspective projection Matrix or any other Matrix
nothing can be nonlinear, right?
And the reason we know that is because a matrix is a linear operation.
So there is no way with just the Matrix to do anything other than
linearly map between the near and far clipping planes that said
We don't only have a matrix, we have a matrix plus the synthetic / w
at the end, right?
So what that means is we can if we want to
Use the synthetic divide to do a nonlinear mapping of the near and far
clipping plane range.
But it can only be one that is still compatible with our Z divide.
So we can put the Z that we were using
Excuse me.
We can put the Z that we were using in our divided by w.
We can put that into the denominator
As we know that our Z value, will be divided by Z at the end, right?
and and yeah, in fact, now I think about it, do we forget that we may
have made an error here,
I'd think about that.
I'm glad you just brought that up, because I totally forgot that
Where's my protected?
So I actually totally forgot about this when we were making this, I
did the mapping from negative 1 to 1.
We did not.
Factor in the / Z.
However,
Right after this.
After this, this runs we have a synthetic / Z that happens here,
right?
Are our negative 1.
We'll put our Z actually into the denominator of these functions,
right?
Not say in this very well.
So, after we put these guys in here, right?
So we've got
So, after you put these guys in here, right?
We have AZ plus b here but we also have negative Z coming in here
which means that this actual quantity is going to be AZ plus b, / - Z
Right.
There's a / - Z that implicitly happens here and so technically we
should have accounted for the / - Z in our coefficients, right?
Because we need that - Z2
We need to still map between negative 1 and 1.
We want to have that mapping between negative one and one happen, even
after we divide by negative Z,
Bright.
And that's where the non-linearity comes in.
If that's if that makes sense.
So actually because we are doing that, if I if this came out to one,
so if we were doing an orthogonal Matrix, then it wouldn't be the case
but if it comes out to negative Z which is what we're doing it here,
then it will actually be nonlinear because that is going to go into
the denominator.
Later.
Right?
And we can force it out of the denominator by sticking Z in here
separately.
But yeah, because it's in there.
What we should have done is compensate are two terms by that value,
right?
So what we want to do is say well this whole thing sort of has to be
multiplied by Z as well.
Right, if that makes sense.
And so,
Yeah, and so what we might say here is like, Okay, so we've got our
see, we've got CZ plus d.
Let's say that we want that to equal.
Because we say we have c z over Z, we want that to equal our AZ plus
b, right?
And so you can kind of see what happens here.
If we end up with a CZ plus d and this case, we end up with these
coefficients being because we're going to multiply both sides by
negative.
See, we end up with a being negative, z a z, right?
And this is
- Z be right in these cases.
And so, looking at what the terms have to be, you can see that this is
not strictly possible because now, these are both in terms of negative
Z.
So we can't assign them to two variables one that doesn't have z in it
and one that does, right?
So that becomes quite tricky, actually,
However, I'm pretty sure.
Let me double-check.
So let's just see because again like this all depends on what opengl
wants it since it's not our code anymore, we just have to guess.
Where is the glue purse?
I can.
I never can get a good.
I so the only question I have and I don't actually know is just
Whether or not opengl expects that to be the case or not, right?
Like I just don't know whether it lets us do that divide first or not
or whether it wants to do that.
If it does that divide first before taking the value for the Z buffer
or not, I guess at the risk of being incredibly dry
The easiest way to usually figure this out is to actually look and see
what the spec says.
It just takes a while, so I'm sorry to do it on stream, but that's
usually the way.
that it's easiest for me to figure out what it is opengl does with the
values and when
I think I want the transforms.
Here's probably section.
Let's see, coordinate transforms.
I'm guessing that's probably where it is.
Let's see.
The viewport transformation is determined by the viewports width and
height in pixels, PX and py respectively and its Centre 0, x 0 y.
Also, in pixels, the vertices would have coordinates x,y and z are
given by XY w.
So z d is in fact, / w.
Right, you can see that here.
So pretty sure.
The factor an offset applied to ZD encoded by n and F are set using
the depth range.
That's fine to me.
Oh, and one that's are all arguments clamped.
Okay?
So there's that mapping 2021, that we suspected was there.
It's there, and it happens within this range.
Presumably that's normally negative 1 and 1.
So there we go.
But yes it is divided by that value.
So technically, right we're going to have to redo this guy because
technically what ends up happening here is if we take a look at this
equation again,
Actually have is we have AZ plus b over negative Z is what we actually
expect our F of Z to be, right?
In theory.
So if we actually want f of negative n to equal our negative 1, and
our f of negative f to equal 1, we actually need to do the math
assuming this.
Is the is the actual output value, right?
At least, I believe that's the case.
We don't have time to do that right now, but I guess
I guess that's what we will have to take a look at
No, no Sherlock.
That's a very good question.
I'm glad you said that because we would have made that mistake.
And it would have been a hard mistake to notice for a long time.
Like and I guess the other way to do it to here is we could also say
it slightly differently.
We could say.
So we plug in negative n, right?
We want to be negative 1, but we know that we're going to divide by
negative Z.
So actually, in this case, it's going to be negative 1 over negative
Z, right?
Which would be just Z.
And similarly, in this case, we have a negative f.
And so we know that this is going to be 1 over negative Z or just
negative Z, right?
So what we actually,
Like to have happen here is we want to have our AZ plus b.
In this case we want to do like - n we've got - a n + B.
We want that to equal Z
Which is our incoming value, right?
Which again, yeah, it's just going to make it harder for us to solve.
it's going to make it harder for us to do the math app but that's
that's really all it is in this case when we divide this guy
I see you end up with I guess you could also look at what this ends up
being, right.
In this case, we just end up with Z / - Z.
So this is really just - a right because that divides out and it's
negative B over Z.
So you could just divide by Z first and you end up with this as your
actual
equation that you're trying to solve.
That might be the easiest way to do it too.
So if we take the negative n case, for example, equaling negative 1
would get negative 1.
Equals negative a and the negative ends on the bottom so it's plus b
over n.
Right.
And similarly, if I want to do the negative f version, we'd end up
with 1 equals negative a
Plus b over f.
Right.
And so, then solving these guys, you know, swap the ace with the one
and you'd get one plus b Over.
N, is your term for a right?
Just swap.
Those two guys,
So each one becomes plus and then when we sub that in here we'd get 1
equals negative 1 plus b Over N plus b over F, right?
Because in this case that we just have to swap this in here otherwise
everything else stays the same and so there we end up with when we do
the subtraction in.
We get negative 1 negative B Over N plus b over F.
Like so
Excuse me and the negative, one comes out temporarily, let's say to
the side, let's put that over here so we get end up with a 2.
And then this we have to add together and so you can see the same
thing would happen here, we'd end up having to cross the terms in
order to make that work.
So we would end up with B over F minus B Over N.
We need to solve, I'm not saying we need to be able to combine these.
So we need to be able to multiply both by whichever one, it doesn't
have right.
We need to make these two denominators.
The same
So we need to put an end in here.
Is this would be the N FN and we need to put an F in here so we'd have
b f and f, right?
So then we're just left with b and minus F over FN like so.
And then we are able to solve for b, which is what we wanted, right?
Our B is going to be to f n Over.
N minus F, right?
That means our a value is
Computable.
Now it's on.
Tangible to us.
It's just going to be the bee comes up in here.
So we end up with a 2 f.
N Over N minus F.
But that's of course, the over goes down to the bottom, so it's
actually n n- f, if that makes sense.
And there's your, there's a value as well.
So then we have to me two different values for those, I don't know if
it's worth combining, these terms, it might be take a look so to fm+.
N n- f.
Over N minus F.
That's just if I turn this into an N minus F Over.
N, minus F, I don't know if that does anything for me at the moment, I
can't say that.
It looks like it does.
Yeah, I don't, I don't see anything in particular there.
So that and that look like the most condensed forms that I would
probably use.
But let's just double check again, like we normally we're before.
So if we rewrite this equation, so we've got F of Z equals AZ plus b.
/ - Z
These are the two guys were using here.
If I write that out longhand, I just get 1 + 2 f n over n and minus F
times Z plus 2.
F n Over.
N minus f.
All over negative Z, right?
And so if I want to simplify that equation out a little bit, I can
Jimmy
I guess ahead of time divide the negative Z out here and that would
just be too FN / z n- f
right - this,
Guess I could write that.
- 1 - 2 f.
N over n and minus f.
Right.
And hey you can sort of see that this probably checks out pretty well.
If we wanted to plug in Z equals negative, n 4r near clip plane.
So we've got the Z value right there, the negative n.
If we plugged it in,
Would give us.
- n and minus F that turns this whole term - which means these two
cancel.
And we just get minus 1, which is exactly what we want.
So the only question is does - F work and in that case we would get to
FN.
Actually this becomes a plus.
So 2 FN over F and minus F, minus 1, minus 2 f, n over n and minus F,
right?
That's what we've actually got.
And so in this case, if we actually want to combine all those terms,
it's sort of a nightmare because we've got an F and an n in on
separate sides of this, right?
And we have to figure out a way to get those guys together.
So we're going to have to multiply both sides.
By we're getting one of these two things would end up having to square
itself at first.
I believe so let's see if that actually works.
So if we have to introduce an end of this term, we'd end up with 2 F
and squared over F and minus F.
In fact, the whole thing can now be over that, right?
Sorry FN minus FN and minus F which is the one term minus 2, F squared
n.
Right.
That's what we're actually going to get here all over f, n, and minus
F.
And in this case, we're in reasonable shape here because the FN is
actually already isolated and will cancel in all of our terms.
So that's pretty easy.
If we do that cancellation, we just get to n- n- F, right?
I'm just cancelling this term here.
Minus 2 F Over.
N minus f.
if we look at what that becomes when, I simplify this this by pulling
out the to I get - and - F
and then I'm going to pull out the 2.
So plus 2 and minus f
/.
M- f.
Right, that's correct.
Yeah.
And these guys would cancel which would just give you negative 1 plus
2 which equals 1
So there we go.
I said I wasn't going to do it because we were out of time and then I
did it.
Anyway, what you going to do?
There we go.
So here we've got our a value being 1 plus 2 times f x n.
/.
N times n minus f.
Type that in, right?
And then here we've got 2 times, F times n Over.
N minus F, you can see there's common terms there as well, so you
don't actually.
It wouldn't actually have to compute all of those, and I think we've
got all those
And so that should be correct.
Now, not at all.
I did type that incorrectly, right?
It's 2 times F times n Over N times.
N minus f.
2 times F times n.
Over N.
Minus F being he.
I feel like that should be correct.
I will leave it for next time.
Because I don't want to try and find the.
I don't want to try and find the bug in that math right now.
Oh, and
No, I think I don't know.
I think I type that in.
Right?
So I must have typed in the math wrong or not typed in the bathroom.
I must I must have gotten the math wrong.
Okay, you can see we're working just fine.
But when we change to that c, mapping,
It is not correct.
All right, so anyway, I'm going to end it.
There we will pick up tomorrow and take a look at if we made a mistake
math wise, or if there's something, we were missing there.
Oh, you know what?
Wait a minute.
Tonight.
No, that should be good.
I don't know.
Well, we'll take a look at this again.
Figure out what the problem is here.
I like the old to zoom in and out on the math.
It's funny.
So we'll take a look at this again and we'll figure out what the
problem is.
Here, we'll do that tomorrow.
I would love to do it now but I really have to go so that'll be the
end of it.
So I apologize for leaving you hanging on that one, but since I don't
immediately know what the problem is, I feel like it could be an
arbitrarily long amount of time before I find it.
And, you know, I gotta end at some point.
So thank you very much for joining me for this episode of handmade
hero to a recording with you.
As always, if you would like to follow through as you always pre-order
the game on how many here at are going to come to the source code.
And also we have a form so you can go to.
If I ask questions a patreon account for 30 series is schedule, bot.
How do I know when we're going to be live and an episode guide for my
ketchup?
An old episodes will be back tomorrow, same time, 10:00 in order to
take a look at what we messed up in that Z calculation.
And then after we do that, we then we'll have to go make our Sprites
correct for the camera location properly.
So those are the two things we have to do, until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.