There we go.
Hello, everyone and welcome to day 34 of handmade hero the show where
we coded complete game from scratch using nothing, but our bear typing
fingers and you may ask, why are we doing this?
And a lot of people do ask a lot of times?
Why aren't you using this?
Why aren't you using that?
Why do you use this editor?
Why do use this language?
We don't use an engine and a lot of the the the answer to that.
Is actually kind of complicated and I suppose that I don't explain it
often enough.
So maybe I'm just going to take a couple minutes here just to say why
we do what we do on the stream and why I think it's important.
So, basically, the first thing I just want to point out to everyone
out there, and this has really nothing to do with my own personal
preference or anything like that.
The game industry runs on C and C++.
That is just the the truth of the situation.
And basically almost everything that you play was programmed in C and
C++ the engine for the game was written in C and C++.
And it is extraordinarily rare to find games where that is not true.
Doesn't mean you can't.
There are examples of games written in all sorts of languages out
there that you can find and that's always good.
But everything that, you know, about and everything that sets the bar
for gaming is C and C++.
If you go out and you buy the best selling game of Last Christmas, if
you buy Call of Duty or you buy, you know, Grand Theft Auto, they
weren't written in F sharp.
They weren't written in C.
Sharp.
They weren't written in Java.
They weren't written in Python.
They weren't written in PHP.
They weren't
In JavaScript, they weren't written HTML5.
They were written in C and C++.
So at the bottom of the sort of, basically, at the base layer of every
game, that is what is there.
And maybe someday that'll change, it's hard to say, but the truth of
the matter is C.
And C++ is what runs the game industry.
And so, if least for the time being, that is what people need to know
if they are programming games in their programming games, seriously at
a low level trying to do performance oriented programming, that is
What the game industry runs on now?
Doesn't mean you shouldn't go programming something else depending on
what your goals are, but it does mean that when I do teaching on this
stream to try and teach little game programming that is what we are
going to use, because that is the industry standard.
So that is just the the case.
Now, I happen to like, C and C++ as well, I like having control over
what I program.
And one of the reasons that I like C and C++ a lot is because I like
to basically be able to nitpick every little thing.
I'm very detail-oriented in that way and I like to be able to know
I know that after I go over my first pass of programming.
I always have that room to kind of go down there and drill down into
every little bit and have complete control.
I don't want the language doing anything for me.
I want to be able to do it all myself and that's just sort of a
philosophical thing and I don't want to force it on anyone else, but I
could just basically tell you that, that is the way I make games and
that is the way I enjoy making games.
I think there's something kind of just at a fundamental level really,
very much.
Fun about programming computer directly.
It's why I got into this business in the first place.
It's what still gets me excited about things.
When I'm actually programming.
I like being the person who is in control, right?
From the CPU, all the way up.
And in fact, to be honest with you.
Nothing aggravates me.
More of these days in the fact that the operating system is kind of,
in my way.
I really don't love it.
And it's one of the reasons that one of my personal goals to the
stream, is to eventually get us to the point where we're programming
on a Raspberry Pi because I would like,
To get the operating system completely out of the picture so that we
can start doing stuff at a really low level.
And, you know, maybe we can even try to do that on the PC sometime.
But the problem is the sort of the mess of devices and specifications
for how the devices work on the PC.
Makes it a lot harder to do something like that in a short time scale.
So anyway,
That is why we are using what we are using.
And one of the big things that I just want to say is like, you know,
if that is something that people, you know, aren't super interested
in, that's totally cool.
I don't want to be dogmatic about stuff.
I think everyone should use what they want to use to program.
But I would also say that there's something to be said, for the fact
that low-level programming does have really some pretty interesting
results.
And that we have made some pretty amazing things with it.
If you look back over the history of game programming,
In Assembly Language have given us some of the most formative gaming
experiences that have ever occurred, you know, things like doom and
Quake back in the old days, all the way up to the things that you play
today.
And I think there's just something kind of interesting about that and
I do think that it's worth learning.
I also think that the more, you know, about how to program a computer
at a low level, the more powerful you are even at the high level.
So when you do jump up and you start using someone's prefab engine
like Unity or unreal or something like this.
And when you do jump up there and you use something that's like a
higher level language.
You want to use to Sharp, you want to something like that, knowing
what it is that those languages have to do to provide the services to
that they provide such as garbage collection, or such as the animation
system in unity or any of these sorts of things does.
Kind of put you at a significant advantage to someone who has no idea
how those Services work.
Because if you've been there and you've implemented one of those
systems yourself someday, even if you choose, not to use it because
someone else provides a better system that you can license knowing how
it worked.
Allows you to use it in a much more intelligent way and avoid the kind
of pitfalls that often happen.
When people who don't know anything about these sorts of systems, or
how they work, try to implement relatively complicated games in
high-level languages are or engines going into those sorts of
problems, not knowing what the support engine and what the libraries
have to do in order to do the things.
You're asking them to makes it really hard for you to sort of make
good decisions about how you use them and how you structure the Cody.
Even at a high level, the truth is, we just haven't gotten to the
point yet where people can program games and not care about the
hardware.
Not know anything about it.
Maybe if your game is very, very simple.
That's true.
But it's your game gets more and more complicated and more taxing on
the system.
It really becomes important for you to know, sort of, at least, at a
basic level, how all these things work.
So personally, I just think it's a great idea for everyone to have the
experience.
Just once to kind of go through the complete pipeline of a game and
see how everything works.
From the bottom, all the way up to the top.
It's very, very empowering.
I think it's a great idea and it doesn't take that long to do an hour.
A night is all we're doing here and I think we make great.
Progress.
There's so much that you can learn in just that our or if you even go
off and do it on your own.
There's so much that you can learn in just a little bit of time.
And so I highly recommend that everyone seriously consider that even
if they are someone who thinks that, it's a waste of time to program C
and C++ or waste of time to write your own engine.
I'm not here to convince you otherwise but I am here to say there is a
lot to learn about how things work and the more, you know, about that,
the more empowering is and there's also a surprising amount of fun to
be had at the lower levels when you
To get pretty fast out with it and don't knock it.
There's something to be said for that, you know, back in the 70s in
the 80s, huddling over a personal computer and just figuring out how
to make it.
Do the basic stuff that it could do was just, it's a really rewarding
experience.
I think for a lot of people and I think we can have those kind of
experiences again.
So I think there's just a lot of positive stuff to say about the sort
of stuff that we're doing on handmade hero.
So I would encourage everyone to maybe not focus, so much on questions
about whose language is better or whatever.
Are you should be using or why you're not using an engine of those
sorts of things because really those questions, don't matter.
Very much when you are making a game, the big, the big picture and the
big questions often are a lot more important than those things.
And it's really about the craftsmanship, your knowledge of the
programming, your knowledge of how to use the hardware and your kind
of ability to to focus on what's important in a project that really
matters.
And so, I think we're doing a pretty good job of this on that on this
stream.
And I think we made some really great progress.
We haven't even made
Through one full work week yet.
It's day, 34 day, 40 will be the end of our first work week and we
have so much to show for it.
We have features that even professional engines.
Don't have looped livecode.
Anything is something.
You can't even buy today and we've already written it.
So, I think there's a lot of good stuff going on here and I would
encourage people really to just have fun with it and maybe don't worry
so much about a lot of those other things.
All right, that's my PSA for the day.
I am done talking at you.
It is time to do some programming because we're at a pretty fun part
of the product right now.
You asked me.
All right, so if you are following along at home with the source code
today is day 34.
So you want to unzip day 33 source code.
If you have pre-ordered the game on handmade hero dot-org, you will
have gotten a link in your email.
You can click on that link and it will have a zip file inside.
That zip file is one ZIP per day.
You just go ahead and you find a 33.0 you unzip that into directory
and you are exactly the same spot in the code base as I am right now.
And so you can follow along at home.
Exactly the same way that you see me do on the street.
Okay.
So if you remember, we had just started finished.
Virtualizing, our tilemap yesterday.
What we have basically done is we've turned of, we're sort of making a
scratch game.
Right now.
We're basically just sort of laying out what the sorts of things we
want.
Our game engine to do so that we can go right our game engine.
And one of the things I did just before the end was, I made it so that
every time the player now moved to a new tile, we move the camera.
Now that's not maybe so nice because I
People would probably prefer some smooth scrolling there.
So one thing that might be kind of fun to do would just be to go ahead
and add the smooth scrolling.
So why don't we just do that for now?
Because I feel like that's probably a pretty regional thing to do.
You know what the one thing I haven't checked recently.
By the way.
I haven't checked to see whether we have any, I wanted to double check
because we had added some things at the end of the win32 platform
layer stuff.
I want to do that control shift, escape to bring up the task manager
and just make sure we're not doing anything weird with our memory.
I want to make sure it always stays nice and constant.
It does so,
Was good.
Anyway, we'll be adding a lot of features that allow us to track our
debug stuff.
Probably not too, too long after we get sort of our render a chops up
a little bit.
But anyway, so what I'd like to do is just go ahead and make this
smooth scroll.
Now, if you remember how this worked, we basically were drawing the
tile map.
We're drawing the town map, by starting it whatever tile to player is
on.
And then we're just asking what the tiles are that are around him.
And we're drawing, that's all we're doing.
So instead of moving the player Sprite like we're doing now, it's all
relative.
Like Einstein said really all we have to do is we just have to move
the map and said
Out of the player and then we'd have smooth scrolling, right?
That's really all we have to do right now.
We're moving the player based on his offset.
But all we have to do, when we draw instead of drawing, the player
Sprite offset from the tile, we can just draw all the tiles offset and
the player stays in the middle, right?
Pretty darn simple.
But I feel like that would just be a funny thing to do.
Right now, people were asking about smooth scrolling and I just
thought it would be funny if we go ahead and do that for them.
So let's let's just take a look at how simple that would be.
Again.
We will not really be doing smooth scrolling in the game because I
don't
Super like that.
Feel of a game.
I like, walking from screen to screen.
But I just wanted to make sure everyone would be aware that.
The engine could support either one and we're not actually cutting any
Corners there.
It's just something that I don't think is particularly interesting.
So in here, we do our drawing with our Center X Center y, right?
And basically all of the tiles when we draw them are based off of that
Center X Center y.
So if we wanted to, we could just go ahead and add the players offset
in here.
So right now you can see the players off.
Set is being used to offset their position.
Right?
Right here.
We can just go ahead if we want to and make that offset the world's
physician the opposite direction, right?
So instead of adding that in here, I will just subtract it from from
where we're drawing the tiles.
And instead of subtracting this and here, I will add it to where we're
drawing the tiles, right?
And that would be a pretty straightforward way.
I believe to make that happen.
Hmm, I believe, you know, don't quote me on this but
So there you go.
That's smooth scrolling, right?
That's the way you would normally see it in a game where the player
was locked in the center and you scrolled around obviously, we could
put logic in there for the camera about when you would actually do
that scrolling, if we wanted to make it so that you only scrolled when
you hit the end.
But these are things.
Like I said, we're not really doing for this game.
So I just wanted to show how, how simple that was to conceptualize.
So at this point, we sort of have to start thinking about some other
things here.
First of all, we've never really tested.
Our virtual tile system or any of that stuff.
We've never tested a bunch of the things that we implemented
yesterday.
So one thing that we might want to do is start to think about making
like a much bigger world and making some way that we can actually sort
of zoom out and see, like a large part of the world or something like
this.
I'm not sure how we want to do that.
Exactly.
I'll have to think about it.
I also want to take a look at the two dudes in the code base right
now, just to see what they were, just to see where we're at on, on the
stuff that we have to figure out on the tile system.
All right, let's take a look.
So we've got player movement code, which will be doing a little bit
later.
We started using the tell side and M that to do is done.
Let's see, we've got to do some work on our floating Point math.
In here that's going to be a problem.
But that's about it for two dues.
Not a lot of to do is left in our town map system.
So that's pretty cool.
We did this switch that we said we were going to do and so now we can
just document this basically
Um, these are fixed Point Tile locations.
The top Nazi, the High bits are the tile chunk index, and the low bits
are the tile index in the chunk.
Right?
Just so we know what those are and then we kind of said, what we kind
of said.
We're we going to make these offsets from the center for tile.
I don't know.
It kind of feels like we should make them offsets from the center of a
tile because then there's really no bias.
We don't kind of have this sort of concept of an upper corner or, you
know, a left or right or anything like that.
There's just the center is always the center and it's the same whether
you flip upside down or not.
It's all the same.
And that sense, it seems kind of compelling to make it be the offset
of the offsets be from the center of the tile.
But at the same time, if the off sensor from the center of the tile,
I'm just trying to think about.
So then we would just do a rounding operation.
I supposed to figure out which tile we were in.
I don't know.
It's tough to say I guess maybe let's try making it from the center of
the tile.
Let's see what happens.
And then we'll basically say whether or not we like that one way or
the other.
So we basically have
we have a tile side, and
First, we could change that tile side and M to basically be a tile
radius in meters.
If you will and we can sort of start to think about it as being
measured this way.
So we basically have a center position and we've got, you know a
radius out to here and that radius is the same in all directions.
So that would basically be our, it would be half what we were doing
now.
I think we said that tiles were 1.4 meters and we were basically
saying something like okay, now if we divide that by two, they'd be
point seven meters in radius, right?
So that was one thing we could do.
Someone also suggested that they like the idea of having of a nice one
meter, a nice unit measure.
One thing we could think about doing is making the tiles V, 2 meters
long.
If the tiles are two meters long.
The radius would be 1 meter.
I don't know if that's a compelling thing.
Hard to hard to say.
But it is something to think about, that's another thing we could try.
So, I don't know.
I don't know.
I don't have a strong feeling today.
I'm not sure what the best stuff to do is here.
So I think maybe I will just go ahead.
I will just go ahead and say
Yeah, let's let's do it for the center.
I don't know.
I think this is the case where I just got to do an experiment here and
see whether I liked it better or not.
I don't really know.
And so if we have our economic collapse coordinates, basically, this
is the place where it's going to affect things.
This tile relative.
Exhale relative.
Why is going to take on a little bit of a different meaning if now
what we basically say is, okay.
This is the center.
So the time that we need to offset where our tile actually was is just
going to be about how far we are from that Center and when that
distance gets larger than the tile radio,
Then we will go ahead and update it.
So, let's take a look.
Here.
We saying the world is assumed to be to a real topology.
If you step off one and you come back on the other.
Oh, you know what?
Maybe I can think of a reason why you wouldn't want this.
Maybe I can, you know, what?
Can I?
No, no, I can't really, I don't think I can, I almost did.
I was thinking maybe that there is a reason not to do it.
So let's take a look.
I'm going to take a look at what happens when we do this.
Alright, so if we basically said, cure is where are our Center Point
is on the number line.
We're at the center of the tile, and that's right on a numeric
boundary or right?
That's zero.
And so then we have some number Crossing where basically, if we go
over that crossing right now, it would be
Be 1.4.
So be -1.4 is to be positive one point for when we do the Divide out
by 1.4., What we would get is essentially, we would normalize this
down to a negative 1, positive 1, right.
And here's our zero, and we've got, you know.
Our our Vector here, what we would then do I guess is instead of doing
the flooring we would just do around around in function, right?
Because we just want to know the closest whole number.
Because remember, we've got the, we're talking about the tile.
We've got an offset from the center of the tile, and now we want to
renormalize one of our coordinates.
If it was pointing outside the tile.
We basically just want to find out where the nearest whole number was
and then we're going to make it an offset from that.
That right.
So we're just talking about a rounding operation.
Now, we just need to basically do a rounding operation.
So, how do we want to do?
How do we do that rounding operation?
And the other question too?
Is the routing operation.
What that we would have to do.
We also have the question of how do we support that rounding operation
in float?
Because we're going to have to handle negative numbers.
Now.
I don't remember if we handle negative numbers in are rounding.
Probably not.
So, basically the way we were doing rounding before is we were
basically just adding point five and then truncating.
So basically we have the truncation, the truncation goes towards zero,
right?
Any on the circumstance?
And so basically we would have to change the direction that we added
in order to do the rounding when we get to 0.
We'd have to we'd have to make it flip, right?
Because what we were doing before for rounding, I don't know if you
remember when I said this.
Basically, for rounding, we had something where we would take, you
know, the point five, right?
And we wanted anyone who is in this part to round up and anyone who is
in this part to round down.
So what we did is we just added point five and then truncated
So that would push people in the upper quadrant over here and then the
truncation would knock them back down and people here would knock up
as well, but they would not pass the next whole number.
So they would come back down.
If we have negative numbers.
Unfortunately, I believe since the rounding Direction flips the I mean
the truncation direction.
Flips, we would technically want to be subtracting point five if we
wanted to round properly and so we can actually Implement that.
Again.
We have not actually written that in our in our intrinsics.
Right.
All we did was this which will only work for a positive numbers.
So we'd beat basically be in another circumstance where we have to
lean on math.h.
I believe we can use the round function.
There.
Let's see.
CRT round or I should say round F.
I believe, I don't actually remember if we, they actually have one of
these.
Let's take a look.
Although we could also just keep using floor and and do the bias on
floor as well.
So, let's see what we actually have.
Yeah, so there is a round F.
I don't know why it wasn't getting found.
So round f is is what we would be doing and so really.
Yeah, I think this basically ends up being exactly the same thing and
we're still, you know, this is our intrinsic stuff is basically going
to have to re-implement these functions.
Now, they will actually get in Trent we
See that when we turn on intrinsic and FP fast in our build line.
I don't know if you remember this, from one of the q&as if we turn on
020 ifp fast, we don't actually call the C runtime library for these.
I think in a lot of circumstances.
And so, technically we wouldn't probably have to re-implement these
ourselves.
The compiler would do them for us, but we might as well learn how to
implement them.
Anyway, So eventually we'll get around to that as well.
Alright, so I believe all we really
Want to do here is make sure that these things round properly, the
truncations there, sine and cosine.
So we are basically calling the C runtime library for these sorts of
things.
And this will be our to do to convert these to our own at some point
in the future.
Okay.
What are we complaining about?
We've have an extra parentheses.
There we go.
So, if I want to do that, and I don't know if anyone actually uses
that right now, okay, there are some people who use it for rent for
for the rectangle drawing routine.
So I'll double check to make sure that they still work properly, but I
believe that they do.
Let's go ahead and make sure that there's no weirdness there.
Yeah, everything's fine there.
So if I want to go ahead and make this change to do it on the center,
the center point.
Basically, all I'm going to need to do now is I'm going to have to
say, all right, we're going to take whatever that tile relative thing
is /.
The tile radius in meters.
Let's see here.
And so you can kind of see in some sense.
You can kind of see what I'm a little concerned about.
In fact, this was the thing that I sort of said in my head and maybe,
as I'm starting to implement it, I'm thinking that that maybe I was
right to be worried of it.
But basically, here's the part that I'm a little concerned about.
So the only thing that I'm wondering is if we do it from the center
point, if we do it from the center point, so this is the center point
of a tile, right?
And then I'm dividing by the radius.
Which is half the length.
Because this is the point at which it crosses over.
Well, no, I guess I can still just divide.
No, no, okay.
I'm thinking about it wrong.
I can still divide.
I don't need to divide by the radius.
I can still divide by the tile size the tile side in meters and do the
exact same math because the rounding is the thing that makes the
change right round.
Real 32 to in 32 is what will make the change for me.
Because basically what will happen is
Is if I go half the distance which is the radius, the rounding will
push me to the next center point.
So I really don't need to think about the radius at all.
I can really just use the towel cited M.
Again.
It's really just a question of how I do the snapping.
That's kind of nice how that worked out.
I don't know if you guys saw that.
Hopefully, that makes sense.
But basically, I was thinking I was gonna have to do something
different with like the fact that you only go halfway and then you
have to go a full one to get the next one.
But the rounding basically, I think takes care of that.
So I think if we do that rounding, I think we're all good.
Can't think of any particular reason why anything else changes here.
Does anything else change?
Pretty much just are assertions change.
We basically have to make sure that we're bounded on either side by
the radius now, which is this way like that, but I think that might be
all that changes.
I don't know.
So I'm going to say that.
So I think that just works, does it just work?
So I just divided by the tile side of meters around.
That gives me my offset.
I do the offset on their I subtract.
However many I went.
Which seems totally fine.
Yeah.
I don't know.
Gosh, that seems a lot to simple, doesn't it?
People.
I'm a little nervous about the fact that I'm forgetting something or
missing something but that seems pretty simple.
So if that was the entirety of the change,
Then a really, I think the only difference here would be how we draw.
The offset of the guy in terms of the fact that now that it's from the
center instead of from, you know, it's instead of from
excuse me.
Yeah, it's Center instead of from the corner.
So let's take a look at how we were drawing this here.
Center x minus World.
M, 2 pixels game State player Pete, our relative X+ r l column.
So, basically, the problem now, is when we're drawing, these were
drawing.
These, this is good.
The Min X in the Min y.
But now, this is technically the center X and the center.
Why if that makes sense?
Because we're basing it around the player and that, that relative
offset is the center.
A really?
All we need to do is we basically just need to take a little bit of a
of a step there and make this be, you know, I should probably pick a
different name for Center X.
This is actually screen center X would make a little more sense.
So that we know what we're talking about.
Here is the screen center, X screen center.
Why?
And so really, all I need to do is say well, okay, now we're Computing
the center because this tile relative X, Ty relative, why those are
the relative position?
It's of the guy from the center of a tile.
So if you want to draw the tile around them, we have to basically take
the center and subtract half the tile radius from that if that makes
sense.
So I will go ahead and do that.
Of course, we're passing them in Acts and the max is inverted now,
which I guess we don't, don't even really have to do that.
We could just go ahead and normalize these things as well.
Send y, minus 0.5 times World Towson inside and pixels like that.
And I think that is mostly all we would need to do.
I'm not sure again of just kind of slapping that down there.
I just, oh my goodness.
Well, that's no good.
What did I do?
Oh,
This, this doesn't need to be half at all.
Well, it could be we could just face it off the center.
That's what you would do for that.
But yeah, I don't know if you saw what happened.
There is.
I changed the the computation as if it was always going to base off
the center, but then I was still using the Min and the max not very
good.
They're all right.
So, let's see.
Seems pretty good.
That look good to you guys.
It looks good to me.
Looks like it's working to me seems to move the tile but he's on his
Active Child moves.
Every time we do that.
So yeah, that seems pretty good.
So maybe now would be a good time to start thinking about.
And I guess now that I think about it.
I'm going to have to maybe, maybe I'll have to have a key here.
Maybe the space bar or something like that or, you know, one of the
buttons.
I think to speed this guy up so I can walk around the world a little
faster.
He's pretty, he's pretty slow for debugging purposes.
I don't know if depending on how the game works out.
Maybe that won't be too slow for the game, but I probably want to have
a key that allows me to scoot around the world just a little faster.
So what I'm thinking about here is perhaps, we just have a little
thing.
Temporarily again.
The player movement code is really just not something I want to talk
about yet because we're going to talk about that a lot.
But what I could do
Basically say that there's a player speed and we'll go ahead and make
that player speed be based off one of those one of those key.
So, I know in gear, I basically said that those key down messages,
right?
We were processing, the key down messages and I think I added some
extra ones.
Right?
We've got, we've got the k space and that was the back button.
We've got well, we've got the different buttons here up left.
So maybe when I push up, I'll have them go really fast.
So, I'll just say whenever the up button is down.
Right, and I don't remember, that's action up.
I will just go ahead.
It's demeaning move that in there.
I will just go ahead and make the players feed.
Be quite a bit more than it was.
Right.
And so now when he moves around, if I want to he can he can go into
acceleration mode and that's fine.
You can see I don't know if you can see this too.
When we get to the player movement code.
I'm going to talk about this a lot, but you could already see now why
it's so important to do good player movement code because like you see
how we get stuck on things and stuff that just
Awful when games have this problem, a lot of times, especially if
they're not done by people, with a lot of experience.
They'll have these sorts of problems.
And so, one of the things that's kind of nice is when we do the player
movement, code, will be talking a lot about how to not have that kind
of stickiness, like you want to be able to aim for a door and just go
right through it.
So that'll be fun code to write when we get down there because there's
a lot of interesting things to talk about in there.
Anyway, so what I want to do now is I want to kind of get this world
situation, a little more straightened out.
Let's go ahead and say that we're going to do.
You know how much?
Larger world.
Let's try to put a much larger World in there now, so we can just
start a test the systems, make three things.
Everything's kosher and nothing weird is going on.
So what I want to do is I want to go in and say that instead of this
hand coded, tilemap like we had before let's start thinking about
making something that's going to be more procedural.
And so let's just go ahead and add some very basic things to our tile
map system.
I'm relatively happy at the moment with the way that we're sort of
doing the tile map thing.
So I think I might start to pull that out a little bit.
Into its own file.
I'm thinking that maybe it's a good time to start doing that.
I'm not 100% sure but I'm, you know, I'm leaning towards it.
So I think I might start doing that.
I'm going to make sort of a handmade tile maybe dot h, which will
start to contain this stuff.
And I'm going to go ahead and say that.
Now that I'm relatively happy with it that we're kind of have some
some of this stuff.
We'll kind of go in here and I'm going to
Pull this thing out to basically be, you know, I don't know what we're
going to call this yet.
Maybe we'll call this.
You know, our maybe this.
Well, you know what?
It's just this is the tile map.
This is the map, it's the whole map.
So maybe we'll just call that the tile map for now and that will have
all of our child chunks in it.
It'll have this stuff in here.
There we go.
It will kind of probably in fact all of this stuff that was in world
really this is going to be world.
World will have a tile map because the world will have other things in
it, right?
Because the world will have, you know, and it conducts this included
directly.
The world will have actual achieving.
The world will have actual things in it, like the entities and stuff
as well.
So it'll have the tile map, but it also have the rest of the stuff as
well.
Do I want that to be a pointer?
Maybe I do.
We'll go ahead and make that a pointer.
I'm not sure yet.
Okay.
So now that we have one of these, what I want to do is I want to move
the functions over out into here that we were using.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that we have a bunch of stuff like
the get tile value, and these sorts of things.
There's our draw, a rectangle call.
We're not going to touch that.
Get this out here.
So this will come in.
Oops.
That was the CPP file.
My bad.
Let's paste that into the H value.
Belongs.
So the CPP file will have those get Tau chunk calls in there and these
for now, I don't know.
I think those will probably stay in line for now.
Let's see re canonicalize position, get chunk position for that's
going to be that's something that's based on the town map.
Certainly the tile value and is controlled point.
Empty.
Those are certainly in there as well.
And then there's a question about the coordinates and who measured
manages those.
I'm not sure.
Actually, who that should be.
I really don't know.
Is this a world position?
Technically?
Or is this a tile map position?
It's kind of a tile map position when you think about it, because it's
based on the tile map structure.
So I don't know if that should go in there or not.
Again.
These are kind of questions that I don't know that we really need to
answer all that definitively, but I might go ahead and say that that's
a tile map position and that's going to be our final.
Name for that percent, you know, it's a position on the tile map.
Yeah, that seems kind of reasonable.
So maybe we'll call it that.
Those are Tha map positions and then we will go ahead and call this a
tile map position like that.
And I will go ahead and say in here.
Then we do we will put the canonicalize coordinates.
We will go ahead and put those in here.
Now we could also go ahead, you know that thing we could do is split
these out into their own file as well, which is basically coordinate
oriented.
But I don't know if that's necessary quite yet, so I'm going to go
ahead and just do that much for now.
And we will see what we want to do with that going forwards.
All right, so let's go ahead and make sure that those are all included
in here.
Make sure that that all works and then we will go ahead.
And why do I not have tile map?
That's in handmade .h.
That's the problem.
So, handmade .h, this stuff should be probably
probably how I want to do this.
See handmade that H has these things.
So I probably want one more h-file.
Handmade H is kind of our basic stuff if you will.
Well, you know, it doesn't really matter how I decide to do this for
now.
So I think, maybe what I'll do is I'll just do it this way.
We can deal with that, a little later on.
All right, so now tile basically World becomes tilemap.
So basically World becomes tilemap everywhere.
I guess.
Actually, I shouldn't say World becomes.
Tilemap everywhere.
So let's go ahead and make that happen.
There we go.
Let's do a nice little place there.
Oops, didn't mean to stick a y in there and then World becomes tilemap
that, there we go.
This redefinition tile chunk.
That's right.
This is pal chunk.
Not calm at this.
There we go.
And now, this stuff is actually stuff that gets allocated, or sorry,
that gets handled by.
Yeah, by our tile map.
So those will all be initialized.
Well, I guess I could still do it this way for now, but I want to
start moving things kind of over into a little bit more, proper space.
We'll see how that goes.
Sorry.
It's a little bit of dead time here, but I just got to kind of clean
things up.
When you make a change like this.
I guess World dot becomes.
Tilemap dot is a pretty safe changed.
Make everywhere.
So I will just make it.
There we go.
And now we've I thought we did world that we gonna have to miss that
guy.
World position becomes tilemap position as well.
We go to toot and now we've got a couple more of these guys.
So World becomes tile map.
Yeah.
Yep.
Here we go.
And that brought up a good point, which is, this is no longer is, is
tilemap point and oh, we are did that one as well?
All right, good.
So that should hopefully leave us exactly where we were and it did.
So, what I want to do now is I essentially want to have a way to start
writing to this tile map.
What I want to be able to do is basically set the tile type of any
place in the world.
I don't care if it's particularly slow.
I just want to be able to start reading the tile map.
Right?
So what I want to do is I want to do something that just starts making
Maps.
Basically.
I don't know exactly how we want to do this.
It's a kind of a good question.
And I'm not sure but basically what I guess I would say is at startup.
Now when we kind of come in here instead of having this thing and I
really want to do this thing at all.
We kind of had our 17 by 9 idea of how big a screen was.
So I'm just going to vaporize this goodbye.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm going to say, okay in our is
initialized, when we are not Alysha lized, we are going to go ahead
and do a little
World construction, I don't know how many screens will make.
It doesn't really matter, but I'll basically say something like, you
know, screen X or screen.
Y equals zero screen Y is less than that.
On our, let's say we make thirty two screens in that direction and
thirty two screens and X as well.
I don't know why not.
But basically, what we're going to do here is just going to generate
whatever random stuff we want to generate.
So we'll go ahead in there and then I'll say tile x equals zero tile
X.
Is less than whatever we said that.
Tell thing was I think we said it was 17.
In fact, I'll go ahead and basically make some kind of defined for
this here, which is that, you know, screen width is going to be 17 or
tiles per width is 17 and tiles per height is 9 because I think that's
what we said.
So we'll say tiles per width and we will go ahead and do those, and
we'll also go ahead and
Unit 32 tile, y equals x, y less than tiles per height, so I'm just
going to spam down some tiles here so that we can make a world.
And actually, I guess at the outset, I might as well just
Zeros everywhere, because, why not?
So let's just go ahead and say set tile value and will pass the tile
map.
Which we haven't decided, how we're going to get yet, and we'll pass
the ABS to accept.
I'll Y, and we'll say that, we're going to set it to 0, which means
that there's nothing in there.
Now, the app style X and the ABS tile y AB style.
X is just going to be equal to the screen x times.
However many there were a witness.
With right, plus, whatever, whatever.
We're actually on for a tile, right?
That's it.
That's, that's all we're doing here.
Right?
So that's the absolute tile index.
And then we're just going to go ahead and write some logic in here to
actually make something.
But at the moment, we can skip that.
So we're going to do this will spam that in there.
That'll be nice.
But we do have a problem, which is we don't really know where to get
our town map from.
And so we are actually going to go ahead and get our town.
Up from our game State now.
So we'll get rid of well, you know, what, we'll have the world I guess
or do.
We really need the world to be in the game State?
I don't know if we should have a secondary structure for it.
What the heck?
Let's go ahead and do that.
We'll just have a pointer to a world.
Will have the tile map for that world and we will have well, I guess
that's all we really need for now.
So we will basically say that we have a world which we will create
here.
So gamestate World equals some magic function.
Action that we're about to write which gives us a world.
We will then say that our world is that and we will use that world.
So our world tilemap, we will set the value and we need to do all of
this stuff.
Only once now, we were you doing it every update before we don't need
to do that anymore.
We can basically do that once when we create that tile map.
So basically, what we'll do here is we'll save the world, tilemap
equals, you know.
I guess what we can do is say that it's going to be the address to
something that we push.
We need this thing again up here.
I'm sort of skirting around something that we're about to write
because that'll be probably the bulk of the next 20.
Minutes is actually getting started on something that we haven't
written yet that we need for this.
But anyway, we'll then go ahead and write into this tile map.
Well, I guess I can quickly just do a thing, which says, town map, dot
equals, tilemap arrow.
That will go ahead and take care of all these guys.
Oops, didn't you do that?
And
Then.
All I should have to do now is actually go ahead and grab that towel
map out after we actually create it.
So Will basically do tilemap start AA map equals world's tile map.
Okay, so we just have to do our allocation stuff here, which we
haven't really made any system for doing any of that stuff yet.
So we're going to have to go do that and then we will go ahead and do
our set towel values.
Which will happen here.
And we might have to pass that a little bit more since that thing is
going to have to be able to, to push new pages and so on.
So we'll do that.
And then when we come out here, we will need to do exactly the same
things that we did in here.
We will need to take our game State structure and grab the tile map
and stuff out of there.
The world in the town map.
And so now tilemap dot becomes tilemap are oh there we go.
Going in there and
Let's see where we're at.
So we haven't implemented those.
The set tell value, we haven't implemented, but we will the re
canonicalize position that is no longer taking address of tilemap.
So address of tile map is just going to be tilemap because now that's
a pointer.
So it doesn't need to take its address anymore.
There we go.
And what else we got?
What else we got here?
Player left player with okay.
So the player with we
Moved into somewhere unenforced.
So these are actually still we haven't done anything with the player
yet.
So the player with could stay out there.
All right, so now we're down to just those do and the set towel value.
Now, what we can do, if we want to is, we kind of skirt this for a
second by actually just making it allocate ahead of time.
I don't know if I want it.
I'm gonna go big or go home.
I'm going to say, let's just start this.
If we don't finish by the end of the stream, it's not the end of the
world.
We're going to be getting into problems that are big enough that they
don't fit inside one stream anyway, and so that's not really the end
of the world.
And I can do the super, super, super, super simple, super simple thing
first, which is okay.
Here's the situation that we have found ourselves in now, which is ass
good situation, to be in because we need to do this eventually and now
is as good a time as any to get it started.
We have a world that we would like to start setting tilemap sin.
And that means we would like it to persist.
Now, if it's going to persist, it needs to be in our storage are
persistent storage.
For the, for the
Game, and so, what we want to do is we basically have this gigantic
chunk of memory that we've got for storing the game state in.
And what we want to do now is we want to start partitioning that
memory up into stuff that we can use.
Now, we already use a little bit of that game.
Memory, just the first few bites of it for our game State structure
because we did that just as a test, right?
We did that and we're still using it to store the player.
That's why the players position can persist across frames.
Now, what you may not have realized,
Sighs.
And what we were doing that whole time, is we work recreating that
tilemap.
Every frame the way we're doing it before.
Remember, it was all in game update and render.
So, when we came in the game update and render, it would just create
the tile map on the stack, create the whole world, right?
On the stack right there.
We don't want to do that anymore.
We actually want our world to be persistent.
So what we want to do is we want to start using some of this game
memory to store our tile map.
But of course, we don't actually know how much time that we actually
need to store because we don't know how many of those pages are
actually going to be filled.
We virtualized our town map.
And so we
Restore places in the world that actually have tiles in them, but we
don't know how many they're going to be.
So what we want to be able to do is basically use a little bit of our
B for the basic tilemap structure.
But then we want to allow the town map every time it needs to to
basically take a little more memory in a little more memory in a
little more memory from the pool in order to store those pages right
in order to store those pages.
So all we really need to do at the at the start right at the very
start.
We're not going to do anything too.
Complicated here.
All we need to really do it.
The start.
It's just have something that can get us.
Some
Emery in that permanent store.
So basically what we need to do is we need to basically say we've got
a struct here.
We've got a world.
What I want to do essentially is I want to I want to basically
You know, you know, have a thing.
That's like push memory.
I want to basically get some memory.
I want to I want to put some memory onto the stack or reserve some
memory, grab some memory.
However, you want to think about it and I want to basically, you know,
I guess I want to push a struct.
I want to push World on here, right?
So I want to get one of those and then I want to do that again.
I want to push the tile map, right?
I want to be able to get those so that we can use them.
Okay, hopefully that makes some sense.
So I want to get those two things.
And what I want to do furthermore is I want to be able to specify
Those things go.
So the world in the tile map.
I want to make sure that we know exactly where they're going.
So I'm going to say that I want to have sort of the concept of a
particular pool of particular place where this memory is coming from.
That allows me to sort of control a little bit more specifically where
the memory is used.
so,
I'm just gonna pretend I have one of those as well.
I'm basically going to say that there is some new thing.
I'm going to call it a memory Arena because you know, sometimes that's
a you know, it's an arena.
Its place for people to fight.
I guess.
I don't really know.
I'm going to say that I have this thing called a memory Arena, right?
That I'm going to be able to use to control these sorts of things.
Basically something that will allow me to say where I want this stuff
to be and I'll just say that we basically have
You know, the World Arena is the thing that the world uses for now, so
I'm just going to say that we have that and we'll see.
Like I said the way I like to code is to just kind of write the first
thing that comes to mind, see how it works and go up from there.
So I'm not going to even say what's in there yet.
I kind of have a guess because I've written a lot of these before.
But I'm just going to say, I want to be able to say at any given time
where things come from.
So, I'm going to say that these things come from that World Arena and
then they'll just get added on their right.
So given that the case I do need a way.
Way of initializing that World Arena.
I need to initialize that World Arena with some memory.
So I need to be able to say something like, you know, initialize
Arena.
I need to pass it.
The arena that fits in question fact, these should probably be
addresses, right?
Because they're modifying that Arena.
So I'm going to say I got that World Arena.
I need to initialize it and I want to tell it where to put gets
memory.
Right?
And the memory that I wanted is is on this permanent.
Where is I don't have anything else that's going on the permanent
storage at the moment.
So I should probably be able to initialize that with wherever we are
at the beginning of permanent storage.
So I might basically say, all right.
I don't know how big the the permit store is.
Let me go ahead and see, I believe we passed.
That least.
I hope we did on here somewhere.
Let's see.
Game memory permanent storage size.
So there it is.
Right.
So we've got the permanent storage size.
So I'm basically going to say, well, the permanent storage size of the
Arena, right choose me.
Permanent storage size - the part we used, right?
Which is the game State size of, did I make my own size of?
I don't think I did.
We'll just use this size of game state.
That is how big it is.
And the pointer to.
It is just going to be the memory that permanent storage wherever that
is.
It's going to be that plus that game State structure, right?
It's going to be I'm just basically saying we're not going to touch
Game State structure structures memory.
So we're going to point right after it.
Does that make sense?
So based?
I'm just going to say that I'm initialize that Arena miss a you can
use all the memory because we don't have any other Arenas yet.
So you can use all the memory that's in the whole thing.
But what I want you to do is I want you to use it at the part that
starts right after the game state, right?
And then when we do this push, I want you to get it.
The memory out of there, please.
That's what I would like you to do.
Right?
And so I all I really have to do now is I just have to implement
those.
I have to say, you know, I've got this initialized
Arena guy, so, I don't know.
That's, that's something that takes us Arena and initializes it.
So that takes this memory Arena that it's using.
Its takes a size.
So we don't have, do we have a science type yet?
I don't know if we do or not.
I hope we do but we don't we don't have one of those yet.
So what did we actually Define our memory to be?
We
To be you n64's.
That's probably not so necessary.
That seems like maybe that's a bad idea to make those be mandatorily.
You and sixty four rows.
We want to do that.
Do we not want to do that?
I'm a little torn, a little bit torn.
They're just a bit teats.
I want to know whether we should basically say that this is 64 bit and
64-bit and 32-bit and 32-bit seems like we probably should.
Would, you know, basically what I'm saying is, should we have
something that's essentially a size, T type, A type that like the one
that c defines which basically is going to be the size this necessary
for a memory to to record.
However, big memory could potentially be.
I don't actually know which one of those I actually want to do.
I don't know that.
I really need to deal with that right now because I don't know.
We're going to store anything that's above 4 GB inside, one Arena.
So many choices, let's go ahead and say that we do have that.
Let's say that we do have a size T and that size T type.
I don't know what we're.
I don't really have a good name for that one so we could just call it
sighs tea or something like this.
We could call it, you know, memory index.
Something like that.
Something that actually can be the size of memory.
I'm really not sure you call it an input pointer.
We call a lot of things.
I do things a little bit differently in my own code and I'm trying to
think about what's the best thing to do for the circumstances that
were in here and I'm thinking I'm thinking yeah, that I just kind of
want something like memory index or something like that.
I'm going to call it memory index for now.
Nothing else is going to use that so we can always come back to that
later and and and make it something else if we don't like it.
All right, so we're going to have a memory index.
That's the size and we
Can have a memory index that is the offset or rather.
That is the the location.
In fact, you know what, I guess this is just a pointer.
This is the pointer the storage area.
So this is the storage and and that is all that would really need.
So our Arena will have those two things.
It'll have the size.
It'll have the storage that will have the base pointer.
I guess we can call that and then we can just say what we have are
used amount and are used in.
Is going to be 0 at the start.
Let's say, because we haven't used anything inside the arena, and then
we have our push struct are pushed.
Direct is basically just going to be a function that returns some
memory like this and it is going to take that memory Arena like we
said, and it is going to take a size to push, basically, a size that
we want to push on there.
We're going to take the used size of the Arena.
We're going to increment it by the size.
So we're
basically using up a certain amount of the memory in there, and we're
going to make the result be wherever the Arena's base pointer would
have been at that point.
So, the base pointer plus, however, much was used before the call is
sort of the first free part of the Arena.
So that's where we'll return as our result.
And then we'll say, we use that much and then we'll turn the result.
And, of course, we would like to assert here.
We'd like to assert that the used amount.
Plus the size is less than the total size of the Arena if that makes
sense or equal to, we could go right up to the end if we had to.
And so then we'll do that push direct.
Now.
What we want to do here is we want to be able to say push a struct
that is this size.
So we're going to need a macro for that because basically what we want
to do is we want to say when you do a push struct and you give it a
type, you give it the arena and you give it a type.
We then call our push trucks function.
We do the
I asked here.
We do the type star to cast it to the right type whatever the person
asked for and we do the size of automatically for them.
So they get the right size back as well.
And there we go when we pass the arena, so that's all nice and good.
What are we complaining about saving?
Okay.
So now we actually need to put those things in our Arena.
I forgot to do that.
So we go in here and we say there's our Arena we have got our memory
index for the sighs.
There we go.
We've got our memory in.
Index or sorry.
Are you eight star for the base?
And then we have our memory index for the used portion that we go.
And let's see.
Let's see.
What did I do?
Oops?
Well know.
What was the what's what are we complaining about?
No, I was takes memory Arena.
Did I did I typo that or something somewhere?
I did.
That's what we memory index.
Not memory Arena.
So all we have to do.
Now is Implement that Sceptile value that's going to be over in our
tile file.
So we have to go ahead and Implement that you know what, I realized.
I forgot to put that my index card up course is a little late now, but
that probably means I've been typing behind my head a little bit.
I apologize for that.
One of these days.
I'm going to get around to writing the little thing that automatically
puts a window there.
I apologize for forgetting sometimes.
Really what I want to do is whenever my cursor goes there, moves my
head to a different side of the screen, that'd be future technology
right there people.
You know I'm saying, that'd be future technology.
All right.
So for now the world atomic bomb.
Go ahead and pass the that arena in here as well, the World Arena, but
later, we might sort of make it so that that's permanently sort of
stored in the town map.
So that doesn't have to.
But anyway, so I'm going to say that we have a memory Arena here.
We've got the arena.
We have our tile map that we are trying to set the value in.
We have our ABS tile X, our ABS tile Y, and then we have our tile
value, right?
So all we're really going to do here.
Is we're just going to try and do the exact same thing that get tile
value.
Does nothing different?
Right?
We're just gonna do exactly the same thing, get the tile chunk, but
the difference now is when that Tao Chunk, we want to be able to say,
if the top shock isn't there, we want to be able to create the tell
chunk.
Right?
We want to be able to say if the tile chunk comes back and actually is
there.
Well, that's fine.
We'll just go ahead and and set it but if it's not there then
Will be very sad and upset and lonely in our life.
And and and that would be bad.
So what we want to do is we basically want to make a way that we would
can create tile chunks whenever we go to set a value somewhere and
there is no tile chunk to store.
What should be there.
Right?
So we go ahead and here we say, if we do not get a tile chunk back.
Then we are going to we are going to go ahead and set that.
So get tile chunk.
If you remember gets the well, you know what, we could do.
This might be a little premature.
Now, I think about it.
Let's just go ahead and assert tile chunk for now and put it to do
there.
Because what I'd rather do not I think about is we're at the End of
the Street.
I'd rather spend more time talking about that tomorrow, even though
it's not really what we probably do eventually.
I yeah, I don't want quite do that yet.
So we're going to start the touch on everything to put to do on demand
tile, chunk creation.
But really, we're just going to take the tile chunk here and then
we're going.
To do that set that set.
We're going to do like a set towel value.
So we're going to do the exact thing here.
We're going to we're going to basically mirror the get towel value in
almost exactly the way that it works.
But instead we're going to call set to value and then back up to the
top where we've got our get, Tau value call, which retrieves the tile
value.
We're just going to do the exact same thing where we do where we do
the inverse operation instead of retrieving the value, we change the
value.
Here.
Yeah, so here we go.
And this also would be a set tile value on chunk, unchecked little
worried about maybe there's too many levels here.
I wonder if maybe we should just only have one of those but what do
you do?
Well, we can we can always eliminate functions in the future.
So there's our total value.
There we go.
And so all we do is just reverse the sense of this setting.
And there we go.
That and compiled.
So we need to pass the
Actual value here.
This is not return.
Anything make that take the value.
There we go.
And we don't need to return anything from you.
We are passing the World Arena by pointer now, and there we go.
So, now what will happen?
Of course, when we do this is we will crash immediately or at least.
That's what I think we'll do.
Because we don't actually have those chunks at all.
So, we immediately stop right here and say, oh, there are no touching.
So all I'm going to do is I'm just going to preallocate a ton of
Those tile chunks.
And then tomorrow we'll take a look at doing something a little bit
smarter.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to say, okay, we have our
tile map.
Let's go grab that.
We have our tile map.
I'm going to go ahead and say that our tile chunk X and our Tau chunk.
Why are very large, you know, they just got, we've got tons of them.
Let's say
Excuse me, and I guess at this point to it's unclear.
Why we actually even have to make this be a dynamic allocation.
But I guess we I guess we did.
So we'll have to sort of just live with that.
But what we can do here since these are 256 by 256 there even doesn't
have to be that many of them.
We could even just do that, many.
All I'm going to do here is just spin through here and allocate
everything.
I'm gonna go into the Q&A a little bit because I just want to kind of
finish up.
We're almost there and we can we can we're going to undo some of this
tomorrow, anyway, so it's no big deal.
All right.
So let's do, let's just do a quick quick Loop through.
Here, nothing particularly fancy.
I'm just going to Loop through all the ones that we have.
Like this.
Yeah, and I'm just going to go ahead and store into our tile map.
Basically wherever the tile chunks are, I'm going to do this the
standard thing that we had to access the tile chunks.
I'm going to do tell chunks why I'm sorry.
Tau chunk x times the Y plus the X and I'm going to go ahead and do a
push truck there to push one of the top shot.
So that we basically have a touch on in all of the locations that we
wanted to know why I'm going by the wrong stride.
There always go by y first and then X, so, yeah, so we'll go ahead and
push those on there.
We also need at this point.
Our tile chunks array.
Actually, that's not what that is.
It's supposed to be.
It's supposed to be the actual tiles that we want to do here.
Yeah.
So there we go.
We want to go ahead and yeah, so I you know what?
I might just stop here.
I might I might stop here just because
I also got to talk about push array.
Do I want to go about 5 or 10 minutes longer?
Let's keep going.
Sometimes.
Sometimes you just got to keep going.
All right, so I also want to do my, I want to do another one of these
guys here basically, so that I can push things on to my Arena.
I want to do the ability here to push an array of things.
You know what this isn't push structurally.
This is just push size, which is all it is.
So all I have to do here if I want to do an array of things.
I want to push an array of things.
I just have to introduce account parameter, right?
And then multiply the, the size that I was allocating by that count.
And then you can do the same thing for a push array.
All I want to do here is, I wanted to basically allocate this tile
array.
So I wanted to allocate you in 32s, and I have to allocate, however,
many, there are in each one of these things, which is chunk, Tim.
Right?
So I need chunk.
Tim times chunk Tim squared.
It's because it's, you know, it's a, it's a way, I think.
We said it was a 256 by 256 array for each of the chunk.
So I need to basically go in there and create that array.
And similarly.
I inside the tile map itself.
I also have to go into those tile chunks and I need to push an array
there of tile chunks and the number of tiles chunks.
That I have right is going to basically be.
I need to pass that World Arena their game State World Arena.
Probably pull that into a variable.
There we go.
So I'm going to basically take that those tile, chunk that top
Tanqueray, that used to be a static thing.
I'm going to allocate that as well.
And I'm just going to say well we know how many we have.
We have the tile chunk x times of Tau chunk count, why that's how many
there are total.
And so that's all we need.
At that.
And so that I think should allocate all of the tile map stuff for us
kind of Slam that in there really quickly.
And I apologize for that.
But we kind of hung out running out of time at stream.
So we'll have to go to a little more detail there.
Eventually, probably tomorrow or in the Q&A.
You never know.
Turns out the Q&A is, what is what is?
What are we complaining about here?
What are we complaining about?
Why, why are we complaining?
Why are we being a grumpy?
Little monkey?
I don't even know why these
He's our are in 32s.
To be honest with you.
No operator.
Found tile chunks.
So tile chunks.
This is the wrong thing.
It's actually dot tiles.
Here we go.
So I don't know if this will work at all.
Probably not.
Yeah, didn't think so.
What are we complaining about here?
The size of this thing to do?
How big is the size of this thing?
Let's take a look.
Okay, it's not useful sighs.
Let's make a.
What is Arena size.
Sighs is 0.
So we actually did use all of that is allocated a few, too many of
those looks like, that's a, that's a good reason to make those a
little bit smaller.
We'll have to think a little bit more about that in the future.
A lot of things to think about here.
Okay.
So, of course, this should actually always be finding a tile chunk.
I feel like, so, I'm not sure why that didn't find a towel trunk.
I got to make sure that I did everything right here.
Let's take a look.
So the tile chunks.
Again, sorry for just saying that, there's sometimes I get carried
away.
I promise I will talk a lot more in depth about this very, very
quickly.
But sometimes I get on a little bit of a tear and I just, you know, I
kind of had to go.
I kind of had to go for it.
And so, yeah.
Yeah, what can you do?
So when I make the tile chunks, here, I'm pushing this array.
Let's go ahead and stop in here.
Let's, let's
Win32 handmade new hammock.
So be, there we go.
All right.
So we come in.
Here we go ahead.
We initialize our Arena and our Arena has nothing in it.
Again.
All our arena is basically, all I'm doing here is I'm just saying, all
right.
I want a struct that basically tracks where I am in my memory storage
and every time that I want to allocate something, I'm just going to
put it wherever I was and move this thing down.
One.
That's all I'm doing, right?
It's really really
Trivial for now.
That's the only thing it's doing so memory allocation is just plus
feste.
That's our entire memory allocation screen as we just stick something
wherever our current top is and we just move it to down by however
much we pushed, right?
So that's all I'm doing here.
So I create one of those, right?
Here's my, my game state.
I create one of these these World Arenas.
I say that it's got all the permanent store in it - the part that we
use for our game State itself.
Give it the base pointer.
And then there's nothing used in it.
I then go ahead and push a world struck down there.
Oh, and you know what?
I actually forgot to do.
I've got to clear these guys as well.
So I want to, I want to go ahead and
Do it, big ol to do here to do Casey important?
Firstly, that clear 20 option.
You need to.
We need to
Do that as well.
All right.
So anyway, sorry, I've got talk about that a little bit.
Anyway, we going here, we create that, we push a struct on.
So now we've basically in our memory stack, we've pushed the world
right onto the top of the stack.
In fact, I'll draw it.
Explicitly, we come in here.
The game state is here.
Right?
Game state is.
Here are Rena's pointing here.
We push the world's the world onto their, right?
So the world's on there now,
and now we've got a world, right?
But our world isn't cleared to zero, which I said, I want it to be.
Oh, you know what?
It is though because our whole memory is cleared to 0, I remembered
respect that.
So no, we don't actually need to do that.
That's okay.
I take it all back.
I take it back people.
We do clear it all 20.
So that's fine.
All right, so we come in here, we get down here.
We get our world, our world, some code 0, it is we then go ahead and
push our town map on there.
We got our tile map.
Our tile map has nothing initialize, and that's fine.
So we have to go ahead and initialize it.
We set the chunk shift.
We set.
Mass, we set the dimension and then we go ahead and create our tile
chunks.
Oh, that's fantastic.
Well, that's our problem.
Right there.
We have initialized those yet.
Where did that go people?
Well done, Casey move that up there.
All right.
So we go ahead and set that, then we allocate.
So let's go ahead here.
Let's do do, doot, do do doot.
There we go.
We push that around there.
So now we've got our tile map and our tile chunks are just sitting
there but there's actually nothing I guess in them yet.
And that's fine.
So we go ahead through here and we spin through each of them and we
allocate tiles for them.
So now they all have tiles, right?
We go through each one of our tile chunks and we allocate towels.
So it's not as far as yet.
This is actually just a dense, tilemap a giant dense tilemap.
And so then we go ahead and initialize the rest of the tile map
parameters and then we start setting.
Tilemap parameters per screen here.
So we go into that.
Get tout that set tile value.
And then let's see.
Well, I guess now it works because I actually allocated a thing,
right?
So that's fine, we go through me, set them all and then our game is
running and we're in a giant empty world.
So, presumably if we wanted to, we could create a very large world.
Are just to end the day off, not too much overtime.
10 minutes overtime.
When we said the tile value here we could do something like, you know,
if tile x equals tile, why?
Right?
Tile x equals tile.
Why?
And tile y mod 2 or something that, you know, will just do that.
Then if that's true, then there's something there.
Otherwise, there's not just so we can see that we set things.
Oh, and of course, I happen to start out right in one of course, isn't
that always the way?
Let's go ahead and and change our starting parameter here.
I don't remember where the
You'd actually starts out.
I think he starts out 33.
So let's just make him start out at 13.
Alright, so there we go.
Now we've got some now, we've got like, I don't really want to call
this a world.
It's not a particularly compelling world.
That's true.
But at least some things are set and that's always good.
I suppose for lack of a better thing.
Alright, so there we go.
With that, and I feel like we should have been setting more screens.
This is supposed to be tiles for height here.
So, that's a bug as well.
I feel like we should have set more screens worth of that.
There we go.
So, there's our other things.
So new, we now kind of have a relatively big world that we can play
in, which is always fun.
But I kind of spend a lot of stuff out there.
So I apologize for that.
I just, that's, that's one of those habits that I probably should
break on the stream.
You don't want to just go, you know, code code wild.
I tried to explain everything while I was doing it, but I realized, I
probably introduced to many Concepts there.
So anyway, we're in pretty good shape here.
We've got all that stuff working.
Let me just briefly re say what it is that I did.
So previously, we were creating everything on the stack just in here
in game update and render.
And what I want to do is I wanted to move it all to the memory.
The actual permanent memory storage, right?
So I did that the way I did that is I made a really simple thing.
That's basically it's a Memory allocator.
It's just a very simple one and the way the memory allocator works is
it starts out with all the memory and it points to the bottom of it.
And then as soon as you allocate something it just uses whatever the
the next chunk of memory is and moves down to the bottom.
You can't even ever free anything in the scheme, right?
It just keeps using memory.
So I basically then just converted everything that we were declaring
on the stack.
I converted it to you.
Using the push array or push truck, which basically just pushes a size
on to that memory jump.
I went in and I pre-allocated everything because I didn't want to get
too far down the rabbit hole.
But basically what we're going to do tomorrow is will actually make
some real screens here.
So we'll actually make some.
Check the drawers.
Some screens with doors and stuff so that we can actually start
testing that a little bit.
But what I want to do and what I wanted to get to so hopefully we'll
get to it tomorrow.
Is this Sceptile value?
That will basically go ahead and allocate as necessary, the tile
chunks.
Now one thing that's also true, is we're using 256 by 256 child chunks
at the moment, but I do wonder and also, I suppose we should set this
chunked in value.
We can set this off of the
Chunk shift as well.
Right?
We could just do that because that's going to be 256, right?
That makes sense.
So anyway, we if we run this, you know, we've got our thing.
I wonder too.
If we could quickly test how our chunked system is working exactly by
going ahead and going in here and saying, okay.
What if we were to make really small chunks, right?
And I don't know what would happen if we did really small chunks.
So we do really small chunks and then we beef this number up a bit,
right?
I don't know if that's a good idea or not.
Yeah, I feel like the problem is we're going to I have to make it big
enough now after I make that so that these will be, I have there.
So few of them now that I have to make sure that we get enough of
them.
I didn't actually bothered to compute how many it would be.
Can we do this many?
I don't know how many we can do.
Yeah, of course, we can't do too many for the arena size.
Should probably think about how big that Aria sighs have to be.
So now our chunks are actually much smaller, right are chunks are now
only four by four.
I believe I say.
Oh no, we set the ship.
So there's 16 by 16 chunks, right?
And so now we're traveling across many of these chunks and I'm just
trying to make sure that our system was working fine.
So basically, we can change her to that page granularity to be
whatever we want it to be, and that's kind of nice.
So that's a good thing.
Here.
We are.
All around our world, very exciting.
All right.
So yeah, sorry to spend all that at you, but I really didn't do very
much.
All I did was just move things over to that permanent memory store.
We haven't actually talked about how we're storing these things yet.
We literally are just doing exactly all the same things that we were
doing before just now we're doing them in a way, that's actually
proper and permanently stored.
So it persists from frame to frame and if we were to change it on a
given frame, that would work.
So yeah.
So tomorrow we will do our sparse storage which
Be fine, and I think that we didn't actually put do we actually put a
to do in there for that on demand cha Chun Creations, that's good.
That'll be a primary to use for tomorrow, but that's about it.
Alright, so let's still we can still get in 50 minutes of Q&A.
That's not too bad here on day 34.
So I will go ahead and start the Q&A.
Sorry for taking up a little bit of that time and I hope that that
made some sense what I was doing there at the end.
I just wanted to kind of get us back to a running State.
I like ending the day on a running state.
So, sometimes I go a little bit too far and I have to quickly.
Do some stuff.
So I apologize for that.
Anyway, if you could please keep the questions to stuff we did on the
stream today or on a previous day.
That would be very helpful to stay on topic and please make sure you
put Q: in front of your questions so that I see them.
Let's see.
What have we got for questions.
Questions.
Questions questions.
Got to wait for the questions.
Of course, you guys don't hear this till after I have set it quite
some time ago.
Girl into bloom, hello.
Hello to you as well.
Can you explain the motivation behind controlling the page
granularity?
Yes, so let's talk about this a little bit.
Because this will be good setup for what we need to do tomorrow.
Okay.
So basically what we want to do, if you think about it is we have to
store a very potentially a world that has potentially very large.
Dimensions is what I would like to be able to do because I don't know
how big we want to make our game.
Exactly but you know, it might be pretty big.
So basically we have a possible.
Size of 4 billion by 4 billion tiles.
Okay, that is far too many tiles that we could possibly ever hope to
store.
Obviously for a billion times, for a billion is more than any
machines, memory has.
I mean, maybe you know, the NSA or somebody has something like that.
But for a billion times 4 billion is way too big of a memory for any
computer that anyone's going to run the game on.
So we certainly can't just allocate an array of four billion by four
billion tiles because no matter how big the towels worry.
Even thousand or 1 bit per tile, it still would be too big.
So what we need to do instead is we need to say, all right, obviously,
we can't make a world quite that big unless it was entirely procedural
and couldn't be modified.
So that when you walk to a world location, you really just got a
generated world right there and you couldn't modify it.
You would never modify it or save it or anything out because you know,
eventually that would run out of space.
So if that's the case, then what we're saying is, there's some subset.
Here, right?
Where the actual World exists.
So there's some subset where there actually are tiles.
And you know, I don't know.
You can imagine like a little thing, you know that kind of all these
like her tiles that are filled in or whatever, right and maybe they're
kind of eccentric so they don't lay, they don't densely cluster.
Always like there are dense clusters of them.
Like maybe there's a lot of them right here, but there's like winding
B, that kind of wind around and whatever.
And so now we have to do is figure out how to store this.
So, what we want to do is we want to have a way of storing it such
that we can kind of isolate the Region's right where there actually is
something going on and kind of box that out and store it but then not
ever store anything out in all these other regions, right?
And so we haven't actually talked about how we're going to do that
yet.
We have to start doing that and that'll be maybe what we start talking
about tomorrow after we finish our on-demand allocation stuff.
That's what maybe we'll talk about.
But basically what we already have to think.
And what we already wrote is the concept that we need some way of
creating small tile sets, you know, and this case like I think I left
it set at, you know, for by I'm sorry.
16 by 16.
Sixteen by sixteen tilesets that exists somewhere in the world that we
can basically use as our tile storage.
And and wherever there's tiles will store those 16 by 16 s around
where that is and when there aren't, we won't.
Now the question that the person was asking is how do you come up with
this?
Why are we storing them this way?
You know, how come we're storing them in chunks.
The reason for that is because basically we're going to have no
matter.
What is we're going to have some kind of an indexing scheme that
allows us to get at the tiles that are
Restored, right?
We're going to have a tile index.
You know, we've got a tile index, it's over here.
And we want to ask the question.
Is there anything stored there?
Now, if we were to actually store the tiles themselves in that table,
the table would be too big in order to be the table itself.
If we want to make it efficient, whatever the indexing scheme is, we
use for those tiles is going to incur way too much overhead because
there are so many tiles that are filled, we
Don't want to store sort of this infrastructure for querying them
directly because the infrastructure itself that we will build for the
sparse stuff would be too heavy weight in and of itself.
So what we'd rather do is have an infrastructure that just deals with
some aggregate amount of tiles, such a 16 by 16, 64 by 64.
Let's say something like that that we have to pick so that the
infrastructure can deal with far less of these, right?
Because let's say we do 64 by let's say what okay?
To put this in a little more explicit terms.
Let's
Say that the infrastructure.
Has a certain cost to storing how it's indexing.
These sparse tiles, right?
If I have to do 64 times 64, let's say right that's 4096 tiles in a
page.
Right.
That means that if that means that essentially, I can reduce my
infrastructure cost by 4096 times, just by using pages of that size,
right?
Because whatever, cost to do the indexing if I was doing them on
individual tiles, it cost me 4096, more infrastructure, cost, whatever
that have structure is then if I was doing it on these pages, so
basically the page granularity is about spining that trade-off where
the infrastructure where your
I feel fine enough that, you're not massively overstating where the
tiles are, right?
Like we could make it before thousand Isis by 4096, but then it's like
storing tons of stuff that doesn't need to store.
So, we want to be small enough that can capture the, the sort of shape
of the actual stuff for trying to store.
But we also want it to eliminate the to cut that total number of
things that are being tracked by the infrastructure down enough.
That the infrastructure itself doesn't become a problem.
And, you know, it's not out of the question that sometimes you even do
these things hierarchically.
You can imagine doing like 16 by 16 s, but then those 16 by 16 s are
in something that itself has 16 by 16.
There's there's different ways of doing it.
But since we haven't talked about how we're actually gonna do this for
our storage yet.
We don't actually know what that's going to look like.
We can't make a good trade off yet, but I know it's probably going to
be something like this.
So I just started us off by having a little tile sections because
we're going to want something along those lines.
Call Dragon.
I'm a little confused about the purpose of the memory Arena.
Would it be accurate to say?
It's for more temporary objects than we're storing in the game, State
directly know.
So basically here's what's going on.
So we need to store our game state.
Right?
And the, we need to store the whole game state, right?
We need it to be persistent.
We may even need to save it to disk in the case where the person stops
playing for a while, wants to come back to it.
We're kind of doing a roguelike Style game.
So we may never save it to disk in the sense that you can save and
load your game.
But if the user like needs to quit for a second, and come back to it
tomorrow night or whatever, when they're playing, we want to be able
to have them quit and they can just load back up where they were or
something, right?
So it may be need a persistent disk.
So basically this whole thing,
Right?
This game State, we need to store all of it.
And what is the game State entail?
Well, it's going to entail the world map that we generated, right?
It's going to entail.
All the entities that exist in the world.
It's going to have any attributes that they have, right, like our
things and it's going to have like score or gold or whatever, you
know, whatever the things are that the player has all that stuff.
This is all part of our game state.
So we need to store it all somewhere.
And so what we need to do is we need to have a place to store it.
Now, what you'll remember.
Is our game State structure, right?
Actually does contain all these things are game State structure
contains the world like it's a pointer to the world.
It's got the top position of the player.
The world has the tile map in it blah, blah, blah, right.
So all the memory arena, is it something that allows us to
conveniently, put more things on to the permanent storage?
Now, you didn't see it cost anything because the first thing we
allocate,
In the permanent storage doesn't require any work.
It's just the pointer to the firm and storage, whatever the base of
the Perma storages.
We stuck our game State there, that's free to do, but could you
imagine what would happen?
If all of these things I had to do the arithmetic for figuring out
where they were in the permanent storage.
That would be a huge pain, right?
This would have to be okay.
Take this and add however big it was and do it and then this thing
would have to figure out okay, where was the world?
Okay, put it after the World by however big the world was and then
this
I have to go and do a bubble bar.
Right?
So all the memory arena is the only thing that is doing for us.
Right now is basically saying automatically layout where all of our
stuff goes in memory.
So we don't have to do it manually.
So all it's doing is it's storing stuff in the permanent storage just
like the game state, but it's laying things out for us.
So we don't have to do it ourselves.
It's an automation for that, right?
Let's see.
Why not have smooth rolling and have the world generation.
Add edges.
We're scrolling stops acting as rooms or local tile Maps.
Yes, so that's that is essentially what we will be doing.
It.
Just I don't like Smooth scrolling.
So we won't really have any rooms that are bigger than can fit on the
screen.
Does that make sense?
So that is what we'll be doing.
Will have the world generation generate rooms, you know that, you know
kind of have a certain
Layout to them, right?
Like this sort of thing and then we'll just the camera will just
always be looking at one of them.
And when you walk off of one of them, you the camera is switched to be
looking at a different one.
That's that's what we're going to do, right?
Yeah.
I already have the oi compiler.
Flag set.
Do we already have the oi comparison like set?
Yeah, we do.
Hmm, so I wonder why, I guess.
Oh, you know what?
It's probably FP fast.
It's FP fast.
Probably that we didn't, you know what?
And we can probably just set that in our compiler.
Flags in general as well.
I suspect that would totally be fine because that's not really a
debugging issue for us, and we just don't want to call the C runtime
Library pretty much.
So let's take a look at what that does.
Assuming that we have FP fast set.
I feel like then
when we are in the tile, so, let's see.
Unreal 3 to 2 in 32, or is it you at 32?
I think that we actually used but either or let's go into the
disassembly here and just see if it did the right thing.
Yeah, so that's see that's great.
And that's what I like.
It's, you know, it's not.
Oh wait, no, no, never mind.
I just, I got too excited.
It's still calling around F lame-o.
Well, what do you do?
So anyway, yeah.
I was hoping that basically - ft fast and - oh I together.
I would do it, but maybe you actually, I guess.
Do you have to specify - 02 to get to get it to do?
Let's see.
Where is the place that does that give me?
Where is my tile?
I want my tile routine.
Get tile value.
There we go.
So let's go ahead and see it in line to that.
Didn't it?
Yeah, it's in line and it's aligning everything which I which is good.
I like inlining but I don't actually know ghost assembly.
I don't actually know what it decided to do for rounding.
Let's take a look here.
Did it ever call around?
F?
Get a chunk, and get Top Value.
I'm not seeing a call to it.
So that's although it doesn't.
Actually, now never mind.
Doesn't actually need to do that for Recon Eclipse coordinates.
That's going to be in the other one.
We only ever call that, we only ever call that back here.
So if you wanted to see whether to recalls round, if we've got to look
at here right there, right?
Basically, right.
We got to
What it does when it re canonicalize is.
So let's take a look and see be canonicalize position is going to go
ahead and do well.
PS Shuff PS Shuff Psy.
Is it what's shuffling out?
I guess I shouldn't be looking at this.
Now.
This is not really what we should be doing now, so it's still calls
round F.
So that's that's lame.
I wish it wouldn't do that.
Is I guess what?
I would say, but I guess we'll have to basically, like I said, we'll
have to write that ourselves.
What are you gonna do?
What are you going to do if the compiler whilst all around if it's
going to call around death?
Does using the memory Lee Arena?
Still allow you to Hot Load your code.
Yes.
In fact, that's the reason that we have things set up the way that we
do.
So if you notice the, you know, if we want to do stuff like are looped
Live code editing, I can totally do that.
So we come here and there we go.
You can see it's reloading properly just as it was before.
No big deal.
The reason for that is because that memory Arena again, you know,
don't be fooled.
Names of things just because I called it a memory Rina.
I called it that because that's sort of what I think of it as being.
But look at what it's doing, right?
You can answer this question for yourself.
The memory permanent storage.
Where did that come from?
Right?
You remember because we allocated it.
Right.
We allocated it with virtual a lock.
So what we did is we did our virtual Alec here.
The permanent storage came out of it.
The transient storage came out of it, right?
So we have that one memory block.
Now, that memory block remember is getting persisted by everything
that we do, right?
So everything that we do with the loop live coding, and all that stuff
is getting persisted all this whole block.
Now permanent storage, is the memory that we have here.
The arena only uses that memory in permanent storage.
It's only just all it's doing is giving you back things that are
inside the permanent storage and never call.
An allocation function or anything.
So, basically, what happens, there is all of the stuff that gets get
goes through the the the arena is always going to be persistable
because it's always going into that one memory block, right?
And so that's that's a, that's an easy way to think of it is like,
basically everything's going there.
So, so there.
Yeah, there's no issue with the persistence with that.
Will we be covering trigger?
Approximations msec.
Doesn't seem that right?
Yes.
We will have to implement our own sine and cosine because at least
last time I remember looking at it.
I don't think SSE has anything like that as he doesn't have signs of
cosines.
You have to do it with like serious Fashions and stuff.
So, we'll be doing this.
Will there be enough memory to store the entire sparse?
Tilemap, or, will you paging it in and out, in chunks?
I feel like, we'll just, we'll use enough memory for that.
I feel like, I don't know.
I mean, we'll have to see.
These are the kind of questions.
I can't answer off the bat because we haven't even really made the
game yet.
And once we make the game will start to feel, will have a feel for how
big we want the world to be.
And if it turns out that that answer is that it sometimes, you want to
set it to be huge.
Maybe we page things in and out.
It's not impossible paging in and out, would certainly work fine.
So,
Let's see.
Why not just allocate a large giant one-dimensional array.
Instead of the current tile.
Map tiles 2 dimensional array and refer to it by y times with plus X
format.
So.
Well, first of all, everything in memory obviously is one-dimensional,
but there is a question.
There is a sort of a
In there that does bear analysis, which is how you choose to break up
the world stride wise, right?
So, basically,
We could do one of two things for storing chunks.
We could store a long thin chunks like this or we could store
rectangular chunks like this, right?
And these would be the same size.
Right?
Let's say this was, you know, a 4x4, right?
So we can store something that's like this sort of thing where we
basically have four things for chunk.
Right, or we can store this sort of thing where we've got a 4 by 4,
right?
So we can have we can have a sixteen by one or a 4x4, right?
We could make those decisions.
And there's a difference between these two and the difference is when
we actually go to do sparseness.
Remember, we've got this whole world and we've got some stuff in it
that we want to represent.
And now, what we have to do is we
To accept some additional storage that we didn't actually want when we
go to fit these things to this thing, right?
So when we actually go to do this, we're going to have that problem
right now.
What we don't want to do is pick a shape for the sparseness that will
have negative connotations.
Like, when we want to store, you know, a thin thing of people are
walking up and down, when you don't want to be storing.
All of these extra, all of this extra stuff out here.
That would happen if we were storing with this long thing.
So, because we know we're having rectangular rooms and that sort of
stuff.
This is going to be a much
Better fit a rectangular or square piece is going to be a much better
fit to fit the data that we actually want, if that makes sense.
So that's why we're going with chunks that are that size.
Now.
There is a question, which is that if we have a canonical screen size
and that does end up being 16 by 9.
Don't we want to store them as 617 by nine chunks and the answer is
yes, we kind of do.
And so what we may decide to do is actually use 17 by nine chunks
eventually and and eat the extra.
Cost of doing the lookups because the lookups become a lot more
expensive when these aren't power of 2, right?
So, there's that.
You are losing a lot of pointers here.
How are you managing the memory regarding leaks and um, our etcetera.
Well, we
I'm not really sure.
I understand the question.
So.
I guess I'll kind of give a general.
Sir.
The way we're doing things, we just use a memory block.
So we don't have to.
We don't have any memory leaks like that.
Memory got gets Fleet Freed at the end.
There's no way we can leak the memory.
So there isn't.
I mean, this is something that I guess that I don't know, you kind of
just have to watch and see how I do it.
I guess as we go forwards but people often ask me this question.
They're like, how do you manage memory or how do you deal with
garbage?
Not having garbage collection All-Star.
Sup, there's no memory to manage in a game like games, typically just
they create their stuff and then they run.
There isn't any memory to manage.
It's usually just people sort of misunderstanding, the basic way that
you should probably program things.
I feel like when you have
Lots of memory getting allocated and stuff like this.
That has to get managed and freed in that way.
And so, if you'll notice, I've never allocated any memory that has to
get freed.
I've never done anything that requires tracking of pointers or
anything like that and that's intentional.
This whole game will be structured in a very clean way.
Such that, that sort of stuff, never happens.
So there won't ever be any leaks because there won't ever be any
allocations.
If that makes sense.
When we create the world, the world will get created as one in this in
this block.
And when
When you close that down and go to a new and it'll just jettison the
entire Block in as a whole and start a new block, right?
So you never have to worry about freeing forests of things which is
where you need garbage collection and stuff to help you.
If you are getting confused or whatever you don't you just don't ever
do those things.
And so yeah, this is why a lot of times I guess people find it weird,
but I don't think about memory management memory management is isn't
an issue.
How much memory
I'm using is always an issue, but that's because I always try to think
about think giving these just rain.
Like, I always try to think about let's keep everything inside like
64, Meg's or something like that.
And that's always something that you have to work on and think about,
because using how much memory you actually need is a problem, but
freeing it and managing ownership and that's our stuff is just.
You should never even think about that.
Or even have to think about that.
If you're thinking about that, you probably did something wrong in
your architecture and you should rethink it.
If that makes sense.
And so you'll just have to kind of trust me that that's true.
And you can see as I go that I always have a good solution for that at
all times and that I'm never in the situation where I'm like, oh and
then we have to free the thing and oh, but that points out the things
in those I've got for you to you never like, don't don't do that.
Just never ever write that code because it's basically like it's not
necessary and when you write it either you have to use a language that
has garbage collection because you can't manage it yourself because
it's too complicated or something.
And that incurs all these costs for the garbage collection and all
these other things that don't have to happen.
You're just wasting the user's time running all that stuff like the
garbage collector collector or if you're writing a language without
cover.
Listen, you're making a ton of more work for yourself.
Having to remember what's getting freed.
And what's not or using all these smart pointers to do all these
checks and those checks and corrects your cost and you're just
incurring all this extra cost.
All this extra work that the CPU does or that you're doing, mentally,
all that stuff that never needed to happen.
So just don't write that code, like, never write that code, write it
this way.
And then you never have to worry about it.
And I think that's deaf just generally a very good rule of thumb.
So, there you go.
Well, maybe Arena be aligning the assigned memory, depending on the
size of the first on the struct.
Well, eventually, when we care about alignment, actually, we will
probably be passing an alignment to the arena.
Because when we actually care about alignment, we will be caring about
the alignment on probably things like 16, but by boundaries or
something like that.
Don't forget to disable 02 again.
That's a good idea.
Thank you.
Thank you and X Sy.
Let's see X E6, ICS sign coasts, so it doesn't unfortunately that so
basically I mean it does but we're in x64 and you have to use the FPU
to do sign Coast.
So you really don't want to go that route.
You want to you and x64.
You really don't want to call sign coasts.
You want to do the the other way, if that makes sense like X.
Because x 86 had the, a, the
X87 FPU which had sinned coasts, but you never want to use that
anymore because it's way slower than the SSE registers and the SSE
path that's due to path.
So we're always going to be on the sse2 path, if that makes sense.
All right.
Let's see.
Why don't you use?
Look-up tables for sine and cosine.
You'll see when we get there.
It's very easy to do them in sse2.
What's not easy, but basically, you don't want to introduce memory to
solve something that a okay.
Well, let me just quickly say, the reason you don't use look-up tables
anymore for most math operations is because what's the most expensive
operation you can do on a computer.
Right now.
It's memory access memory.
This is like often times 100 times slower often times 100 times slower
than just doing an operation.
So if you can do and you know, 100 operations to do your sign, it's
probably faster than polluting, the cash with a sine cosine, table
that will now slow down memory access overall, because that's another
thing that causes cash to be evicted and can miss and so on.
So, look up tables.
It.
Unless the thing is crazy expensive.
I mean, it better be so expensive to compute.
It better be thousands of instructions.
There's something to compute do not do look up tables for operations
that aren't very very expensive and sine and cosine aren't that
expensive?
So you probably don't want to use look-up tables anymore.
I'm not a hardcore optimization guy.
So I don't want to say definitively.
Never use a lookup table for sine and cosine.
That's not my place to say.
I don't have that kind of authority on those sorts of matters.
Certainly, but what I would say is it's highly unlikely that we will
do that because it's usually the case that you're going to come up
with something.
That's not too many.
A SSE instructions to do it and then you're not using those precious
memory accesses, which you really want to be used for other things.
Let's see.
DJ.
Mr.
Regarding what you said about memory management, how can you say you
don't need to free up memory when you start spawning infinite numbers
of enemies?
Well, you'll just have to see what we do.
When we start sweating enemies.
I don't want to give away the surprise.
Why would you keep coming back to the twitch stream?
I guess I can give you a little hint which is that you can't have an
infinite number of enemies.
There isn't enough memory to store an infinite, number of them
enemies.
So I'm pretty sure you only have a limited number of enemies.
And if you only have a limited number of enemies, well, you should
have a pretty easy way of spawning, new ones when opens go away.
Let's see.
Enemy Mouse is memory access slower than mod.
Yes.
I mean memory access is slower than everything.
There's nothing slower than a memory access that I'm aware of like, I
don't think there's an instruction.
I don't know.
Someone correct me who's an Assembly Language guy if I'm wrong, but I
don't think there is a single.
I don't think there is any instruction you can execute.
That's a slow.
As the memory Access Memory access is the slowest operation.
The only time you can get operations.
The only time you can issue instructions that are slower than then,
things that gather data are, is it
Data is in the cache.
The Cache can be faster sometimes an instructions, but the but memory
know, if you're actually going to main memory, I don't think there's a
single instruction that you can execute no matter what random it
instruction it was but especially not sse2.
Sse3 instructions tend to be two clocks and I think memory accesses
can often be like 200 clocks.
So I literally think this 100 X is not off-base.
Like, I think I think you're talking about, like, two orders of
magnitude.
Attitude to decimal, or does the magnitude between between the average
SSE instruction?
And going to memory.
Why tiles, why are tiles used to reduce calculation or some other
reason what is the real benefit of tile mapping?
What will happen?
If we do not use it in a meme hero.
Well, basically I want to tell math because I felt like we needed some
basis for
World at the lowest level and there's really only two choices.
Sort of that we can do one, is like polygonal, right?
We could sort of Define our Region's, you know, our walls as polygons,
or we can define define them as tile maps, and I felt like, tile maps
have kind of a nicer understanding for the player.
Like, players could understand tiles a little easier.
They can do those kind of puzzles, where you have something that you
push around the Tom app easily and it you can actually make puzzles
that the players understand instead of just like random.
I just feel like polygonal things.
They turn into these random physics, bouncing around things, and
there's no concreteness to them.
And so we won't ever render things, the style Maps will always be
rendering, things more robustly and colliding with things and kind of
more interesting way then Thomas but the basic part of the world.
I just kind of felt like tile Maps was a good way to go and I felt
like it kind of Titus back to sort of the old school games as well in
a way that I thought was nice.
All right.
I think we are basically done.
with with
there are some few sections.
Well, let's see.
There's so few structures that can take the order of 100 Cycles on
has, well, okay, but x87 because the x87 is like really old school,
right?
Six hundred Cycles, like what FPU instructions?
Are we talking about?
Because I don't think the, if you're tired of the x87, FPU, that's
Legacy part and you don't ever even call that anymore.
So I wouldn't actually call that BJ.
Well anyway, we can talk about that on different dream.
Anyway, I think we are basically we are basically, you know, we're
already 15 minutes overtime.
So we've done a full QA even though I went over time.
So I'm going to call that the end of the stream for the day.
Thank you very much for joining me.
Everyone has been a pleasure programming.
You as always, I'm going to go ahead and close this down here.
There we go.
If you would like to follow along at home, you can pre-order the game
at handmade, here it up org and you will get your own copy of the
source code, which you can download every night.
I upload it.
After I finish programming every day.
So you can go ahead and follow along at home.
It's kind of cool way to be able to do that.
And that will also come with the our test sets that we use during
development as well.
So, and of course it comes,
With a copy of the game at the end, which should be pretty awesome as
well.
So definitely check that out.
If you're interested and the other thing is we have a patreon.
If you want Sports a video series, you can subscribe to our patreon as
well.
Now, if you're trying to learn from a series that news and forms
button, I just clicked on is a great place to go to.
It has all sorts of stuff for you.
It has a code discussion forum.
You can ask questions on, it's got coding resources.
So if you want to look at the people of done ports, to Mac and Linux
and so on, so if you're looking to run it on other platforms, that's a
great resource for you and an episode guys can use to catch up.
It's also got the schedule for the week that I post every Monday.
So if you are trying to follow the series closely, that is a great
place to go.
So, thank you everyone for joining me tomorrow.
We will be right back here at 10:00 a.m.
Too long from now.
Just just twelve short hours from now.
I will be back and we will do our little bit of are sparse allocation
stuff just to get that stuff working.
And then I don't know what we'll do after that because we probably
want to sort of close out the week so that we can start next week on
some, some fresh stuff.
But anyway, so please join me tomorrow at 10 a.m.
Pacific Standard time.
It would be great to see you here tomorrow on Twitch for more.
Handmade hero.
Thanks, everyone.
Have a good one.