Live.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream.
We kind of did some absolutely crazy stuff yesterday, which is kind of
on a whim.
I was like, I kind of wanted to be able to have the concept that I
would have compiled time constants that were actually changeable at
runtime.
And so we just did a little experiment to see if that would work.
And it turns out it worked quite easily.
So I think that what am I, you know,
One.
Good, good random trick deserves.
Another.
I think we should just go ahead and, and travel on down that road.
See where it takes us, really?
Because all I want to do now is see if I can make that into a slightly
slightly more General system, that allows me to kind of pull out all
the debug code that you've written.
So far is me.
And make it so that I can switch all of our debug code on.
And off really trivially runtime.
If I want to, without actually having to incur any overhead at all in
having compiled into the game.
Again, like I said, it's never something I never tried before, I just
thought it should be possible.
And so we tried it yesterday and it seemed to work quite well.
So I'm going to see if it's realistic to kind of make it go a little
further than that.
So let's see what seem to have the hiccups for some reason.
Which is kind of crazy.
But anyway,
we are here on day one ninety three.
So if you want to follow along at home and you've pre-order the game
on Hammer here at our org day 192 is the source code, you want to
start with so that you will be where I am at the moment if you want to
code along.
So here's what we did yesterday.
It was pretty cool.
What we did is we made it so that we could recompile things.
So this just is like a user interface action I can do which actually
causes the game to recompile with a different set of pound Defiance,
which totally changed.
Is the code for the game, and in this case it toggles, whether the
debug camera is on or off, right?
And so, what I want to do now is figure out, okay?
We know we now have an infrastructure that allows us to do that
change.
And so the question is, what is a way that we can very easily Loft
that into something where we can do that kind of code all over the
place for very little cost, right?
And so, I would assume that the easiest way to kind of
figure that out is to just go try to do it right to go.
Try to figure out like okay, where are these places that were having
these debug events occur?
Where I want to be able to toggle things on and off and how can I go
in there and make it easy for me to kind of change all that stuff into
easy to toggle stuff and that will also guide you know like I said we
want to go through and like make this interface a little more real
clean.
It up instead of just kind of this little test radial menu thing in
here that the overlapping words and it's ugly and doesn't really do
what we would want to do.
Are so it can kind of guide us too because we want to do a pass over
this to get more interface stuff in here.
And so when we have a bunch of things that we actually do care about
setting or toggling or that sort of thing, then I feel like that would
be a good point for us to kind of go you know figure out how this
interface is going to look right.
Okay, so what would we do here?
Let's let's go.
Let's go into the code and just see
What we could do here?
So we already have like, we have some code, that's already kind of
doing this sort of stuff.
We've got pushed wrecked outline, for example.
And so, let's just take a look at this one right here.
So if we were to take a look at that, this was the thing that would
show us where our ground tile, you know, where the, where the
boundaries were on our ground tiles.
So that's a good example of something that we probably would want to
be able to turn on and off, right?
And so if we follow the example of the thing that
Have at the moment, then what we would do you rate is, we'd come over
into this, handmade config thing, and we'd go ahead and say, oh, okay.
So there's another thing, which is like, you know, debug UI, I don't
know, wrecked ground, chunk outlines, write something like that.
And then in here, I would, I would put it in there.
You know what I mean?
And that would, again, tell me.
How that was working.
And so then we could easily toggle that on and off using the same
methodology.
So, I'm going to go ahead and keep doing that for some of these.
In fact, maybe I'll just look for a like, if zeros and see what's
going on here.
So, I don't think thats, that's probably not code we would super care
about.
But here, it's like a okay.
So here's another example.
So we also had a part of particle Fountain, right?
We had a particle fountain in here that was running, so that was, I
don't know what that was doing or why that was happening or wasn't
happening or
Her else.
So I feel like that is another thing that that we might want on.
Now, for some reason, I'm not seeing our particle Fountain.
I don't know if we turned it off, in some way.
That was more violent than that.
Lets see lets probably.
Okay.
And we're not rendering them either.
Is another thing?
It looks like know we are rendering them.
Here they are.
Yeah.
So I'm not sure what we did to to we never
Like we never actually get a bitmap from them for some reason, that's
kind of weird.
Or is that not what happened?
Hmm, let's take a look at why our particle system isn't running
anymore.
It's called, it's actually, we're getting a bit mats as guest best
match right there.
So we're running through the particle spawn index.
Were we're sort of making some of these things here.
We're creating them.
and that all,
Reasonable.
But I can't actually see.
Did we change something in here?
That would make that not work properly.
The push wrecked thing.
So this is I guess we could take a look at this as well to look at
those cell cell Dimensions so the particle effect is is happening.
It's working so but we're just not seeing ever.
So there's something janky about our push bitmap.
Call our push-fit map call is like not working at all for whatever
reason.
Now maybe that's because like the font or
Thing is not there or something, I'm not sure.
That could be one reason why?
The particle is not particle laying like if our font which I guess.
I don't actually know what we did with that font I guess we just said
get best mismatch from asset font.
Oh yeah this is just this is just old.
We need to actually load a particular font bitmap ID and right now
we're not doing that at all so that's that's why
So that's totally it.
So I guess what I'll do is I'll just go back to what we're doing
before.
I'll go back to the Head Fountain, right?
And that should, that should solve it.
So there's the head Fountain doing its Fountain thing, so that's good.
All right, so yeah, so if we look at this, you know, we could again
continue to kind of just, just going ahead and putting this out there.
Oh, so you know, that's another pretty interesting thing.
You see what just happened there since our system rewrites, this file.
I feel like I feel like we have to make sure we always respect, what's
been already added to it, right?
Because otherwise we're going to have the situation where it's going
to overwrite things that we add.
So another thing that we need to do, when we come in here, we want to
make sure that we don't have that, it's not going rogue, right?
And it's not over writing it.
I think there are some ways that we can do that pretty easily
actually.
And maybe that don't even require making that file at all.
But I'm just going to kind of go through the motions here so we can
I'm not going to jump.
To what I think the conclusion is especially because I don't actually
know what the necessarily right answer is.
I'm just hypothesizing.
So I'm going to continue going through the motions so I can kind of
see my for myself exactly how it goes out.
So I can do particle test, right?
I'll also do.
Debug you, I particle grid so we can see that.
and,
Just might seating here.
Let's see what else we got.
We've got rectangular outlines for our space.
Debug UI spaces.
You space Out Lines.
There's just a ton of code in here.
You can see it, right?
How much code there is in here, that was debug.
That's just turned off, you know, and you can kind of see if you
actually look at it all how much debug code there is.
And most of that debug code is was only accessible to us if we went
and found that if zero or whatever and it's kind of easy to forget all
of the debug code that we actually could use to find bugs, or do
whatever else.
I don't know if this code works at all anymore.
Presumably not right, but I'm not sure.
So let's see.
Draw rectangles?
Function does not take four arguments.
How many arguments does it take?
Might be the good, might be the thing to tell me.
It's like, it doesn't take for, but I'm not going to tell you how many
it takes.
I'm just gonna let you guess.
Why?
Not, it's fine.
So let's see.
Cliprect I and Brule even
In there.
Hmm.
So we don't have one that just passes the regular thing in so we have
clipped recti and bull even we never really use the even odd thing.
Did we we still have never done anything where we actually try to get
hyper threads on the, making sure they do the same even or odd of a
particular bitmap thing.
I wonder if we should probably remove that some point, I'm going to
make sure that that's on our little list here.
Right now, let's see.
Let's see, let's see.
That would be in here.
Get rid of even notion.
So yeah, we've got draw a rectangle.
I need to pass it kind of the whole rectangle, but I don't really
remember what this code super did.
But it looks like it's just going over the log height and the log
width and making a checkerboard.
So I assume that the rectangle to I for clipping right rectangle to
White clip wreck could be, you know, erect min, max of 0 0.
Log with W Hite, I'm assuming
Would be totally fine, and it would work.
Oops.
Although, I guess I could do it this way as well.
There we go.
So now we got the clip rect and then I guess we'll do true for evens
and false for odds as annoying as that is.
And then I don't actually know like I said if this code works anymore
because we kind of played with the renderer quite a bit and I would
not actually have expected it to to work so I think it is running.
You can see that it's going very slowly but I suspect that it's not
drawing to the right place on the screen or something because we
didn't I don't think we ever updated it.
To the projection code.
I'm talking about this stuff down here where we, where we do the push
coordinate system stuff.
I don't know that that's actually working.
So we'll leave that turned off for now.
And when we go back to do our lighting, will deal with that, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and grep for pound of 0 and see where else.
We see that.
Let's take a look.
That is 0.
Such that is a thing that allows us to see alternating chunks without
putting lines in between them right.
It's kind of interesting, Phil Gramm, shank with so that makes a
checkerboard pattern.
So if we wanted to I guess if we were talking about the config file,
we could do Define debug UI round chunk checkerboards.
That.
Do something like this.
And now we can actually see that that pattern as well.
So that could be useful.
So we've got that we go back to our grep.
Oops.
What else we got here?
This adds walls, this was for Rural gen, which I don't think I care
about.
So I'm going to ignore that for now.
This is well that's totally valid valued thing to do.
In fact, I don't actually know why.
We got rid of this, I guess, because we thought it was too slow before
because this was before it was fast enough, I'm not sure.
But I think that that's probably fine because it's pretty fast now.
So I feel like when we reload and I'll go ahead and see about that,
let me make sure that
The handmade config.
I want to make sure to save this.
In fact, you know what I'll do for the time being while we're doing
this.
Let me actually make sure that I take the handmade debug stuff and
make it not write out the handmade config.
So I'm going to undo that.
So okay.
Yeah.
Okay, so that's all good.
And the executable reloaded thing, I feel like if we do that with the
ground chunks, there's really no problem with doing that anymore.
If I just go like that, like they just come back, right?
So I feel like we won't have too much trouble with that with leaving
that on.
So I'll leave that on for now and maybe we can put I will add a debug
switch for it later.
If we if we find that we need it.
Although you know I guess the point of this is to have as many as
possible so that we think that through.
So maybe I'll just say okay there's a debug UI recompute round chunks
on XE change
Something like that.
All right.
Back to the grep.
there's if 0 again,
Enable us to test weird buffer sizes in the renderer.
That's not something that can actually be updated at that's in the
platform layer, isn't it?
No, I guess.
It's not
I guess it's not.
It's something that can just override it.
So I guess that's fine, too.
How to find debug UI test weird draw, buffer size.
and,
What else we got?
Entity type familiar, make spatial queries.
So I don't know why we don't do this anymore.
This is the thing that makes the familiar follow the hero but I don't
know why we turned it off to be honest with you.
Oops, what happened there?
mismatched if pair really
Please do tell me where is it?
I like how it doesn't want to tell me where the mismatch if pair is,
it's like, could you give me any more information or you just gonna
like
let that be a mystery.
I guess we'll just make that be mystery.
So what was the last one we did?
It was test weird draw by 4 size.
It's this one.
So if I set this back, does it actually fix it?
No.
So yeah this is great compiler.
Thanks for absolutely nothing.
Like there's like it literally gave me no information about what that
would be what I would need to know to fix this.
Do you really want me to go through absolutely every one of these to
make sure that they're actually closed?
Is that what you want me to do?
Because that seems
Well, I got lucky.
I found it the first time.
All right.
You could have just told me like this was the back, I guess.
Maybe it can't possibly know to think about that.
All right.
So that's also testing the word buffer size.
All right?
So let's keep going through up and if I guess I could also do it this
way.
I feel like there should be some way to, like, do white space properly
zero,
Oh, I know I can just Escape it.
See the grep, you see?
And hear how you have if zero there's a space there for some reason,
fine string interprets that as meaning find either of these two
strings, but I think if I escape it like that, it might actually do
the search for the string, but I don't actually know nope, that turns
out to not be the case.
So don't know how to get it to like, hey man, what you do?
You're fine, stir I actually want you to look
At the whole string.
You must be white.
What is the way?
Let's see.
Literally use of the Medicare direct.
So I feel like / should have worked for that.
You know what I mean?
But Wild Card any character is dot, so that would work.
Presumably or should have worked.
Maybe I'm using a s n, IL s and I use a search strings literally.
So if I'm using it, literally why can't it do it?
Why can't it do that?
But why can't it search for that?
That string that's pretty pathetic findstr.
Let's see.
You space every month stretching, lets you organize prefix with /c for
hello or there.
So I think I would I really probably want to do is put a put a c in
there.
See if that helps.
Didn't help at all.
You suppose there is a specific IC for civil fines, for a little,
their sisters for hello, or there and file finds her / Seco.
I got to put a colon
Okay, so it's the different type of search string.
All right, some I should have looked up a long time ago.
I've always just kind of hacked this as I don't know how to use fines
for not.
There we go.
Look at that.
Was that so hard?
That was not so hard.
See, debug UI familiar follows zero.
EXO.
This is the one that I said we're not.
Doing, don't think it works.
This is just some code that we aren't using anymore in the profiler.
This is something that shows our chart boundary which you haven't
really implemented yet so that's fine.
That is a relevant to everyone iaca marks.
Probably something that we want to do specifically as a separate
thing.
Turn this on to see we're in the map, your sampling.
So I guess this is good.
This is debug you.
I show lighting samples.
We would definitely want something like that almost for sure.
What else we got?
SSC clamping.
What is this?
That's the slowly.
We don't care about that function anymore.
We don't care about these at all.
What's this Bender?
Grouped output again.
Don't care about these do not care.
Don't care.
Let's see.
So this
this is interesting.
This is the camera followed behavior.
I'm not sure if we're really using if that path works anymore but
let's find out use room based camera.
There we go.
So I guess the reason we were doing it is because we don't really have
this information anymore or maybe who is the camera following entity.
And okay, so we have an index, we have, we do know which entity it is,
right?
It's just the entity that we're on at the moment.
So I would assume that that entity
Could have.
Poppy.
I soon x x.
Why?
Why, of course, the problem is the new camera almost certainly doesn't
have an ABS tile X.
So, that's a bit of a problem as well.
So I don't know that we well yeah, you might as well.
Just play with it a little bit, just to see if we can restore it to
functioning order.
It's been a long time since we touched me this code, but I feel like
we should be able to get the tile side in meters.
Right.
If that I guess, maybe that if that even exists anymore because we
don't really have the concept of typecasting
Giles ever.
So there isn't really any particular need for that to exist.
Ever.
And you can kind of see it's almost just ad hoc defined right in
there, right?
And that's the only person who cares about that.
So at some level we need to decide what this actual camera with was
that would have
Very little to do with tiles, but I'll just go ahead and assume that
for now, we'll just say, it's 9 meters by 5 meters and we'll look at
that in a second.
See what we actually want to do with it, but then the camera P.
Presumably, we just move the camera by twice, whatever that distance
is, or something like that.
So it would just be whatever the new camera p is right.
It has a world position and the world position should be able.
We should be
able to call offset on that.
Right?
Because in our world stuff, I remember we had ways of moving things
around like an offset by, right?
Where are you at?
Change the location raw Center chunk point.
We can map it to chunk.
Space get World chunk or in same chunk.
Is coming is valid no position.
So there should have been an offset on here not is canonical.
But something else that 0 subtract well, not subtract
Right.
So there should have been a thing and maybe the deal is that they got
moved out into something.
Else.
So I'm going to just go ahead and look, I feel like we should have had
one of those.
Already.
But maybe we just stopped doing that because we always map into this
image and then Mac back out and so it isn't necessary to do.
So I don't actually know
But we'll see.
So looks like map into chunks, space might be the thing.
So map into chunks space is what it is.
You give it a base position in an offset.
All right.
So that's fine.
That's no big deal.
Oops.
All right.
So where was I on that?
I need to find.
I'm, I'm lost.
I'm lost because we were sort of.
I forget where we were actually working on that particular function.
We were in the, we were in updating the camera, which should be down
here, right?
Yeah.
Here it is.
So we do you room based camera?
We're going to have to update the camera P.
So I think what we would probably say there is we just say, you know,
new camera p is going to be a map into chunks face of whatever the
old.
Poppy was and we know what the world is, right?
Oops, world is.
It's just whatever.
The game state says the world is
And the new camera p is the world position that we're talking about.
And so the offset for that is just going to be, you know, whatever
that distance is that we think rooms are wide.
So, here we go.
So yeah, if you're down - 5, then we want to just move you - 10 or
something like that, right?
Can hear.
This is weird - 18, so I don't actually know if that's right but I
just decided to do it anyway because why not?
This point we have so much debug code on.
It's kind of hard to tell what's going on, but let me see if I can
walk up into hey room here and see if it moves.
So the camera does not seem to ever be moving, which is a little
wonky.
Because I don't feel like that's that many meters.
Its entity p.
X is greater than
Yeah, because the same region centered about the camera.
I feel like that should do it.
Oh, I know, I never actually bothered to capture the result.
That's all it just I just need to save, right?
I just need to save
The result of that.
And then we should be good.
Okay.
Alright, so there we go so we can get room based camera.
Movement happening.
Pretty trivially as well.
Hey, look, The Familiar is following us around again.
Okay, so we can do you room with camera?
That's all good.
I'm going to do our grep again now that I actually know how to do it,
right?
So we'll come through here till we get to a new one that we have not
already looked at
Doot-doot-doot drawers.
Bounce Direction drawbitmap.
No no, no and no.
And so here we are.
Okay, so speculative Collide, that's just code that we never really
finished so that's can just stay there.
True.
Stb, to type is not our code that's Sean's code and we're not actually
using it at the moment.
That was just from the day when I showed how to use libraries.
So we don't care about the asset Builder, we don't care about what do
damage, so, that's everything.
So, that's all the debug stuff that was obviously in there.
I mean, there's probably other stuff that just didn't have, like,
necessarily a pound of 04 it or something like that, but this is a
pretty good list.
So, if you take a look at all these guys, we can come now kind of see
what we have.
And so, what I notice on here is so you'll notice I prefix them all
with debug you.
I and the reason that I did that is because I wanted it to be easy for
us to find them if we needed to find them.
Right?
So, I mean, you know, it's pretty trivial for me to grasp everything
and just say, hey, you know, show me where, all of those things are in
all of our, debug switches, are we now, you know, immediately know
where they occur in handmade hero certainly.
so,
a couple things we can do here.
First, of all, obviously, we want to know.
All of these, we want to know what all these values are.
So we could present them in a user interface, right?
And we then also need to be able to write them all out.
So if I go in and I'm just going to do the first very basic step of
this.
If I go into handmade debug right, we could imagine listing all of
these guys and having all of these guys be toggleable pretty easily
just by taking exactly what we already did.
You know, with our radial menu.
So,
So when we do right config or whatever it is config oops.
So if we were to do this and I'm going to go ahead and save these out,
these guys here into a little comment just so we don't lose them if we
mess up this code.
So when we write this out really, the problem is that all we were
doing was writing out this one guy, right?
And we need to write out all of these.
So a very trivial First Step that would make it work.
With all of the things that we just listed would be to make some kind
of a list that said, here are all of our debug variables.
This is like a debug variable that we have, okay, and we want to know
like a couple of things about it.
We want to know what its name is, so that we can write it out.
We want to know what its value is.
Right?
And at the moment we really don't need anything else because they're
all boolean's.
But you know, we'd probably want something eventually, right?
That was something like a type in here.
Like that.
So we could at least have in Kira something that says, you know, this
is the type and if later so we can add like integers and floats,
something like that.
And so then it would be relatively easy for us to Define all of these
guys.
In fact, so easy that we could actually just make a macro, I think,
which would be something like, you know, a pound of fine that was
debug variable listing or something.
And then name,
and then when we did debug variable,
And we make a debug variable list.
Like so it's pretty easy for us to just cut and paste these guys in
here.
Like this and then call like, you know, debug variable listing with
the name.
And what that can do is it can first string eyes the name.
So now we get that string and we'll also will hard-code that to a
Boolean for now, like I said, so there's the Boolean we have the name
and then we know the value is just actually the value of the variable.
So we just put the, we just actually use whatever the name is, that
should evaluate to whatever that was trying to whatever.
That that powder fine is actually set to at this time.
so then, all we have to do is convert this list into that, which is
I can use a macro for a pretty trivially that would just be search for
search.
For well, if I could actually type today that would help search for
pound Define right.
Change it to sadiebug variable listing parentheses search for space.
So whatever's, after the name do this comma and kill the rest.
And I think that's really all we need, right?
So now we've got them all kind of prettied up.
Up and ready to go.
So that point.
Now, if we want to write things out, we can actually write things out
in a list, write the kind of goes along
So if I want to kind of stream this guy out into the file in a more
coherent fashion, you can kind of imagine how I might do it.
Right?
I do something like this where that is where we're starting.
We go in a loop and we say, for, you know, debug variable index equals
zero, debug variable index equals start less than or a count of the
debug variable list.
For each one of those, we just go ahead and grab debug variable list.
Plus, we bug variable index.
And that's our debug variable.
So when we get one of those variables now we don't have to guess about
these things.
Instead of you do use debug camera.
I can just say whatever the vars value is is what we're going to print
out in the percent D and then I can also say that whatever its name is
actually comes from the name that's stored in there like that and now
we are could put them all out after I print it instead of doing Temp
and size of temp.
I can do instead.
It's a like size of temp - at and that at.
So I just I just kind of go through as I go and I just increment at to
kind of right through the string and then when I get to the very end
again all I have to do is say well the size that I'm going to write
out to the handmade config file is just going to be, however, big temp
was - however much however far I went
That's not right, sorry, it's just how ever much at is minus the base
of temp.
So any, what's between the start of the buffer and what's where I am
where I ended up, right?
So that should do it, I would think.
Oh, and that's a little sorry, that's brains little level today.
Obviously, we need to advance.
We need to start where we're temp, is Advanced by the size of its we
get to the end and then subtract add a way which that's how much room
we have left.
Left to right at any given time.
Okay, so cannot convert parameter or argument 32, size T argument 3?
Wait, shouldn't argument 3 be a string?
I'm Casey is confused by that a little bit, a little bit.
We know that this will not be big so we can cast to a 32-bit for
fixing that, but I don't understand why it would be 2y.
It's to size T's SN printf underscore s takes to size tease.
Does it really?
It doesn't anywhere else.
Right.
It just takes the pointer to the text buffer which I did right there.
Then the size.
Which is that does this just need to be cast to something else.
Cannot convert argument three from constant care, 22 to size t.
So, let's see, first our end is equal to 10 plus size of temp, right?
That should work.
Temp.
In this case is the base pointer.
So the end - at is how much space there should be remaining.
And that is what I would like to call this with.
So we're on Earth, it's getting the fact that that takes a care star
to size, teas.
And then a constant care star.
I don't know.
So, I would like to know why, in some places of our code seems to want
that in others, it doesn't.
It wants the buffer, which I gave it the size of the buffer.
Then it takes a count.
What is that count?
What does that count even for?
Have you been calling this wrong maximum to store Source location, the
size of storage location for output.
Interesting.
So, how did that not trigger here?
Because we don't pass it that here, right?
It's a little weird.
that we've never had to pass it before and all of a sudden wants to
know,
am I the only one who's kind of going crazy?
Maybe.
So here is another version of it, right?
In s n, printfs care, buffer size, size t, count concert care format.
And so, for some reason, it doesn't seem to have
That.
Right?
It only is it's only looking at these as options.
It's not considering this an option for whatever reason and I don't
actually know what that reason is.
At all.
If that makes any sense.
Totally perplexed by that.
Hmm, I guess it's because this is just a regular pointer maybe.
But what I can say is that we don't care because we could pass this
thing twice, and that would be fine.
Right, I don't know.
Well, let's go ahead and go into here and actually see what's going on
because I don't really care.
But this is one of the reasons, like I say, I never use libraries on
purpose, it's because I hate them and I never know why they make the
decisions that they do and things like that, or weird.
So, let's go ahead and here and step in
So here is temp our temp buffer.
And we are going to start writing to it.
So there we've written our first thing to it.
You can see we wrote the use debug camera which is correct.
Is the first one we Loop through?
Now, we write another one.
And, as you can see, we wrote that one in here now.
So now we've got wi ground, chuck out lines and presumably we can then
go all the way to the end.
It just look and see what it wrote out.
And it looks like it wrote out all of our thing, all of our variables.
So we can go ahead and let that right itself to a file.
So now, if we take a look here at the actual config file and reload,
it, it should look exactly the way it does now, and it does, so, no
change.
So, that's perfect.
That's what we want.
And so we're good to go.
So, now we actually are rewriting all of our config file variables
properly.
Which also means if we want to start toggling them, we can do that as
well.
So instead of doing menu items here, like, we were, what I could do is
say, instead of using menu items, let's use debug variables.
So in here we'll just say OK The Rake out to the debug variable list
is what we'll use instead of the menu items.
Something like that.
Makes makes good sense, right?
And then the carts Tara startx could just be from debug variable list
and grab the name.
Right.
Oops.
Variable list.
So that seems fair, right?
That seems like a that seems like a fair thing to do.
So now we'll have that many of them.
So if I ran it I should now have.
If I right click, I should have just a ton of these things, right?
I have a ton of these, these different things that we have in there
and whichever one, I click.
Now what I would like to do is make it.
So whichever one I click is the one that actually gets toggled.
And again that's also probably pretty darn
The for me to do, all I would have to do is when we look at the hot
menu index that comes back assuming that the hot menu index is less
than the array count of the debug variable list.
Meaning, it was like a valid pick or whatever.
All I would have to do is say, okay, if
if the the mouse button was released,
I know that the hot menu index got selected.
So the debug variable lists at that entry I want to set its value
equal want to toggle its value, right?
So that toggles, that value.
and now, when I rewrite it,
It will get Rewritten with the new value on it right again.
Really, really simple stuff here.
Nothing nothing kind of crazy that I'm doing is very very basic
So now our radial menu will actually be wired up.
Right at least in theory.
So if I click on debug use camera and it recompiles I should now get
back my regular camera which I did if I switch to using say what's the
the weird buffer size test, very buffer size the sky, I can go back to
full screen, right?
And so now I have the ability to literally change any of the variables
that I want to just buy like switching them directly that way, right?
If I'm tired of the room.
It's camera.
I can switch that and and so on, and then it'll do the recompile and
switch and again.
So now,
It's a little, it's not quite as nice as if the variables were
actually directly in the program, in the sense that it does have to do
the recompilation, but it's vastly more powerful because we can
actually insert things that are extremely costly and turn them on and
off.
And it's not a problem, because it doesn't, we don't have to put in
branches, that might affect our performance or anything else.
Like that doesn't actually have to happen.
We can also just recompile drastically different stuff.
We can switch out whole functions that were calling if we want to
I pretty much for free, right?
So anything that might affect the the whole structure of the program,
like an inline function, we could switch the witch in line which
version of an inline function, we were using and it would cost nothing
to do that, right?
Even in release mode, we would get the correct performance in both
cases, which is kind of awesome if you ask me.
And again, that's something I've ever done before.
And I'm not sure necessarily why I just never tried it.
So anyway yet you know, you can switch all these off.
But now, so now we kind of have a pretty I want.
I think maybe the particle Fountain is getting a little bit ridiculous
at this point.
I think, at least we want Turn Off the Grid because I can't see
anything.
Will that grids on there?
Right.
Alright, so now we're totally good to go.
And so now I would say that's like a pretty obviously nice thing to do
but there is a little bit of annoyance there, a very tiny like a very
tiny bit of annoyance there, I guess.
But a bit nonetheless which is that we have to I mean obviously we
want to clean up the UI because this is awful.
So we want to like I was planning on
I'm doing I see we want to push forward on the UI front but there is
one thing in here.
That's also probably I would say something to fit to think about which
is just the steps you have to go through to actually get into a
situation where something is wired up to the UI in that way, right?
And the answer there is that.
Every time I want to do this now I have to go add like if I wanted to
make a new one of these.
So I mean handmade that's either P or something like this.
And I want to make a new thing like something that just may be okay.
Like I don't know it it stops drawing familiars altogether or
something.
So they're just like a pound of 0 that happens in here.
What I want to be able to do is I want to be able to go debug you.
I like don't know, familiar, drawers or whatever.
Like that.
I'd like to be able to do that and just be done and I don't really
want to have to go in here and add the debug variable listening.
Necessarily right that seems like maybe it's kind of a little bit
annoying.
Now it's only a little bit annoying certainly.
So it's not like there's a huge deal there, but that is something that
might, you know, if I was going to go Whole Hog, I would probably make
something that just parses the file looking for these guys and updates
them here, right?
So, that I wouldn't have to do that manually.
It just be like you do it and it's done.
I feel like that might be going a little bit overboard.
Just a little, just a little.
so what I might do instead,
it's just make sure this is in a pretty obvious place, right?
So I might say, okay, maybe this goes like up here or something.
Somewhere where it's really easy to know where it is.
Something like that.
Yeah, maybe I'll even put it in a separate file.
So maybe these guys stay here but this kind of goes in a separate
file.
So there's handmade debug variables dot h and there it is.
Something like that.
And then in here, we just include it.
And that way, I guess that's really not too bad, right?
That's something that I'm okay with.
I'll just update that anytime we want to add something and offer.
Yeah, pretty straightforward.
So that's really all that I want to do there.
I'll just I have a few minutes left.
So while I'm I don't want to start on some new UI Elements, which is
really what we need to start doing.
Like, figure out how that screen is going to look.
So we can fix, you know, finish our radial menu and finish how so the
UI elements going to go.
So we want to play with that.
But well do in the meantime is let me just finish a couple little
things about the radial menu that we probably want to fix.
So if we take a look at the the driving, the debug menu here, then
what happens in the debug menu stuff is, there's no way right now,
there's two things that are kind of annoying.
There's no way right now not to select something because there's no
concept of like like an inner ring where it just never actually
triggers.
So what I'd like to do is make sure that the distance between so like
best distance squared or something.
What I'd like to do is say, I'm not going to use this result.
this right here where we set the hot menu index,
I'm not going to use that result.
I'm going to set it.
The hot menu index back to array count, debug variable list.
So the null value, I'm not going to use it unless the actual length
squared of the place where the mouse is - the place where the radial
menu is centered.
So the menu radius
If that length is less than some like the radius of the menu of the
menu radius or something.
Oops, I meant, sorry, I meant menu, I want the actual menu position.
Want me to pee
So if the user hasn't moved like out of the menu radius into clearly
into a Zone, then I don't want to count it, right?
Because that that would be bad.
So I I'm going to have that and then I'm also would like to indicate
whether these things are set or not might be nice.
So what we could do is say, you know, we've got the item color here
and we're setting it to white, but we could do something pretty
trivial and set it to like you know, gray or something, right?
We could just do that.
and so, since we know the debug variable,
We know all the information about it then given the fact that we know
the information about it like what its value is not just what its name
is.
Then not only can we get the text out of it?
We can also get what it's setting is right now.
So we can just use its value and see whether the value indicates what
the drawing, you know, whether the things should be highlighted or
not, right?
Oops, I should probably get rid of that.
Little example code, I added there, sorry about that.
That
Okay, let's try that again.
And take a look.
So now you can kind of see that the stuff is is you know, it looks
like I can't.
I've got it the wrong way around.
I've got the wrong way round.
Sorry I meant greater than the menu radius.
I wanted to make sure you move outside of it.
Not not that you can't move outside of it my bad.
Alright, so now, I think we're good.
Right now, you can kind of Select from the radial menu.
You can see what's on and what's off.
So if I don't want my ground chunks to recompute, for example, I just
turned them off and now they won't work computer anymore and that's
fine, right?
And the little familiar is following us around but maybe I don't want
the familiar to follow us around anymore.
So I just turn off familiar fellows hero and now he stays where he is.
Right.
And so again, I think we're all good.
I think everything is working the way that I would like it to work
now.
And now we can access our debug code again.
So we can like zoom out if you want to and that sort of thing.
The only thing I'm not happy about the only thing that doesn't fill me
with Glee so much is the fact that there's that, the compilation time
is a little slow right, that turnaround time.
And so, we can do a little bit about that, right?
Like, the asset processor, we don't need to compile, right?
So in the build-up batch file, we can speed up our build a little bit
by.
Can we both live with both with 1xe?
I don't even know what that means anymore.
We got to do that.
I do not even know.
So I could turn off the acid Builder, right?
And that compiles, a little bit faster and I could also turn off me.
Recompiling the win32 code, right?
So you know, if that was gone the compiles a little faster but that
doesn't actually change our refresh time.
I don't think but but not compiling the asset Builder you know, might
help.
So maybe that's something.
We should just leave off for now and see what that gets us for
compile-time turn around, so use you but camera that's pretty fast.
It's not as fast as I would like it, but it's not it's not too bad,
right?
So that's pretty good.
So I think that's where I'll leave it for today.
All right, let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
And yeah, if you have questions about what we did today, please feel
free to ask them, preface them with a Q&A:.
So I can see them and I will answer them, but I think we're basically
where we want to be now with this.
So now I think I can, I can go ahead and finish out, you know, or at
least make a more significant progress on what we want the UI to be.
Now we have an actual, some actual use cases that we can look at here.
I don't know, like one thing that we could do in addition, just as
another example, if we wanted to add another type in here and maybe
I'll just add it to do for.
This will be something to do tomorrow.
Is in our debug variables, I could put it to do, you know, add the
distance for the debug camera.
So we have a float example, right?
Or maybe like the parameterize, the fountain, I don't know.
Something like that.
Particle fountain.
Flutter falter.
I don't understand why a single if statement would be expensive, if we
do it at runtime, can you give an example?
Sure, I can give an example.
Let's take a look.
So let's let's, let's construct a concrete example.
And we actually, I guess we actually have the tools to do this to some
degree now as well.
So, here we are in our game.
And here is the game running.
And as you can see, we're running our software.
Under and it's pretty darn Zippy, right?
It's got a real nice frame rate.
Everything's going fine.
And you know what, I kind of need one thing.
I also probably want to do here is I'm going to need some way to.
I don't part of the grid.
I'm going to need some way to turn on the profiler as well right.
Oh, well I guess I don't because we actually have a thing up here.
You can see our frame times, they're down in like the, they're like
basically 60 frames a second.
Almost.
Just most of the time and this is in debug mode.
So it right.
Okay, so now let's go ahead and say that, you know, let's take a look
at our render here.
Here is handmade optimized, right?
Here's draw a rectangle quickly and supposed gear.
We want to do something where we've got a couple different code paths
for stuff.
Right, that have to happen.
So what we want to do is we want to say like okay when we do, when we
convert the texture from srgb to linear something like this, we want
to have a way of doing an, if on
That's going to come on in here, right?
So we're going to do this two different ways, right?
Something like that.
Of course, I guess.
Well you know what, I'll just do it this way.
I guess I just need some things in here.
So I'm going to need some sound of static variable up here that I'm
going to switch on, right?
Because it's debug code.
So I'm going to need a static.
Like do you know thing test 1
And so, let's go ahead and have things test one.
It's off.
So it won't do anything, which is the case we're interested in.
And then I'm just going to go ahead and put that in there, right?
so if thing test what happens, then we're going to recompute the
values of all of these things like so
There we go.
And then, I'm just going to sort of start to see what happens if I
insert that.
Now, the first thing you'll notice is our frame rates already dropped
considerably, right?
It used to be at 17 now, it's a 20.
Okay, so now I'm going to start adding some more of these in there.
Just to see what happens.
Right.
And I suspect, I don't actually know that they'll be that much of a
difference that happens if I don't actually involve some other
variables but you know will start will spam in another set for down
here, right?
So maybe like in here.
Or maybe when I do the load, like for up here when I do the fetches or
something like that, where we do Doucette EP is maybe what I'll do
here is I'll just do a second set of those and I'll test them off of a
different variable.
Do the thing.
Put it, I call it.
Don't remember.
Ping test 1.
Princess Leia.
All right.
So these are all branching off the same thing test.
Right.
And there we go.
So now let's make them Branch off one for each patch.
Like we would normally do.
So if we want to be able to turn these on and off right then, each one
of these is going to be a different thing test.
So we would have an array of these, something like this, where we have
thing test123, for that sort of thing, right?
So, here's the thing test to just three.
Thank us for just five to six.
Okay.
all right, so as far as I can tell
I guess that didn't actually do too much to hurt us.
I would have expected.
I mean it is a little bit but it's not as bad as I would have thought
I would have thought that adding more things to test on since it has
to do more checks.
Would have been a little bit bad, but I guess those particular ones
don't seem to actually have too much of effect on things I guess.
so that particular case, I would say,
Doesn't seem to be too bad.
I don't know that you'd want to do any tests in here, but if you're
going to do one test, it looks like you can do more as looking good.
Looks like, can maybe do as many as you want.
Once you're doing some, if that makes sense.
But maybe not, we'll see.
So that's thing one.
Okay, so
Let's take a look here, so if I then go and do something a little bit
more drastic so suppose that I wanted to do something like this.
Right.
Because again, like doing a test for one, if is not really the part
that is the most problematic, I would think.
So the part that we're interest me a little bit more is, let's say, we
have something fairly drastic like turning on ayaka or something like
that, right.
That we wanted to be able to do, I don't know that that's a
particularly good example because I suppose, you know, that's, that's
actually kind of just markers that are in the code.
So I guess we don't really care about that.
Maybe adding more timers in there, let's say.
Might be more of a thing or maybe using a different set, a different
function path.
I'm thinking would be something like I'm thinking more about, and
maybe I'm just being unrealistic about the time.
The number of times, I might care about this but, you know, I'm
thinking about something where it's like, okay something that's used
everywhere.
Like, I am doing something like the the subtract operator or something
for my, you know, for my multiplier.
And I want to do something really expensive in there, right?
So, I want to do an, if in there on a static, I feel like that's the
kind of thing that would, you know, that I would want this sort of
thing for.
So, if I had static, I got rid of it, I didn't say get rid of test at
night, but I didn't,
I feel like that is the sort of thing that I also would want it for.
So you know, I don't know what it would do in here.
Just some stuff.
Who knows what do we do?
But basically like things like that are more what I'm worried about
and I don't know like maybe they're unrealistic, maybe we'd never do
one that costs enough.
Maybe the branch predictions just always good enough and it wouldn't
really care.
You know, I don't know.
And so we can do is just wrap them around as long as we wrap them with
a regular, if we'll be safe,
I'm not sure I'd have to think about whether I can think of a concrete
case for these, but that was the thing that was more thinking about if
I want to insert something specifically into the code that could have
some kind of effect on it one way or the other that I'm worried about.
I now don't have to worry about it anymore.
So I don't have to worry about changing the performance criteria of
the code in the cases, where, you know, I in the cases where I'm
compiling debug stuff in
I know it's exactly the same code as what I'll ship, you know, except
for just the things that I turn on.
So, I don't know.
But it would be interesting to know.
It might be that, you know, if you don't ever want to touch the inner
loop of the pixel code or something with anything weird.
And you.
And like and you really can just have 0 as long as you have predicted
branches in here, the processor Just Hits it and it's fine.
Then it may be that there's no real, super good reason that you have
to be able to be able to do it at compile time.
But again, yeah, I'd like to test it.
I'd like to know and maybe as we go through on a major will be able to
find out.
Like, we'll see if we ever use things in a way that we could then go
oh wait, that might be interesting to see if that would have been a
problem.
In terms of changing how things were performing.
Oh, you know what?
I forgot to do though to that was the bad test.
I forgot to change to release mode.
So that was kind of stupid actually.
So in release mode where things are crazy, fast running
Let me, let me double check to see what happens in release mode.
If I do some of these tests again.
So it still doesn't look too bad.
It looks like it's okay.
With that, for the most part.
It does not look like it hurts.
It too much.
I mean, again, it may be hurts a little, but it doesn't hurt.
It doesn't hurt it.
Certainly to any degree, that, that you would probably be too paranoid
about it.
Like, it would have to be very specifically rare cases where you're
like, oh my God, I have to, you know, I'm really worried about about
what's happening.
However, you know.
So here's another thing, I would say though,
Even in that case.
So when you're working on performance stuff, they're like, what can we
think about this?
There'd be no way for us to test.
If mob, mask epi8 really worked with a toggle without this, though,
right?
Oh whoops, that didn't actually recompile.
All right, let me try that again.
I'm being too sloppy here.
God, I hate you Max's on do.
It's so stupid.
like, I just
Revert revert, the file.
Okay, there we go.
So all of those guys are in there.
Get rid of thing, test.
Recompile.
Okay.
Now.
You can see the frame rates, actually pretty variable there.
It's down, and kind of the noise.
So it's a little bit hard to really do a comparison.
We'd have to do something a little bit more if we wanted to do a fair
test we'd have to do something a little more straightforward Or
Meticulous.
I should say, right?
so now, if I remove these,
Yeah.
I mean I would say that that does look like it got about a millisecond
faster potentially but it's not a fair test.
I mean looking at a number that's fluctuating that wildly is not
really fair.
So, I don't know.
I don't know.
Let's try it again and see if that's repeatable.
Yeah, I mean it definitely feels like it does have a serious effect
there.
Now whether that has anything to do with the branches though, I don't
know.
Because one of the things about performance, it's that's annoying.
As like, your code alignment, actually affects it, right?
So, it could be that what I'm doing, actually, has nothing to do with,
with the with anything, other than it's just a different code,
alignment produces, a different speed.
So, again, you'd have to really meticulous to say, but I guess now
that I think about it, when you're compiling an Optimizer does, look
like the differences is actually there.
So so I guess I stand by my original statement.
I think you do kind of want this so that you know that when you're
working on perf stuff, you can still use all your debug things and
they work in a good way.
Why are we adding b32 comment in the config file.
So the answer the answer there is
That that was because I thought we would need that for information
purposes, but we don't actually, because since I decided it was okay
to keep it here.
We could just come out with that.
Markup can go in here later if we want to.
So it's totally fine for us to get rid of the, of the be 32 now and we
could always add it back in.
Obviously, if we end up, determining that that's important, right?
So yeah.
Can you toggle the debug options while looping?
Yeah.
You can.
I would think we make sure I'm all rebuilt here.
Okay.
I would think I can't think of any reason why they would be a problem
with that.
So if I wanted to do that, I just go like this.
Oh, so here's the thing though.
What we will have to do if we want to access debug features during
looping is we will have to make it so that the input for the mouse
passes through right which is actually pretty easy for us to do
because the mouse is separate.
But if you look
Right.
At what happens with the mouse.
You know, the mouse the new input Mouse stuff happens here, right?
That's all doing.
It's a little thing.
But then when we get down here, we do the input playback, it will romp
over it.
You know what I'm saying?
So what we would want to do there is we want to do something like
this, where we'd say, okay, you know, we want to let the mouse go
through so that debug editing is not recorded, its it happens,
At the time always it's not ever played back.
And so if you wanted to do that, we would have to do something like
this.
Where we said like game input temp, equals new input.
you know, new input Mouse buttons and if we have a copy struct, so but
Mouse x equals temp mousex
Y, z, z y.
And then yeah.
Here we would just copy that in.
I don't know if we have a copy.
We do.
So we do something like that.
For now I'll just actually do it.
I don't really want to deal with the copy situation.
I really wish she would just let you do it.
There's I do not understand.
No idea why they don't let you do that.
It's the dumbest thing that you can't just do it but of course,
usually can.
Okay, so if I go ahead and do this, oops,
And then fix the copy.
So this has to be, you know,
something like this.
For no darn reason.
So now I think that would allow us to pass the mouse through.
So, you know, this stuff.
Now in theory, oops,
This stuff here in theory.
And I should do as well.
Just until we actually do that you I I'd like to make that debug menu
a little bigger radius.
400.
You know what that also should be the square because we're taking the
length squared and we should compare it against the menus squared.
But that's that's for tomorrow.
So there's our actual UI stuff, right?
Okay, so if I go ahead and get the dude in here and set the looping
So now I'm looping and now I can get the UI happening on top, so I
think I should be able to do something like if I wanted to change the
ground checkerboards.
I think it just works and yeah, there it is.
So that's fine.
And I can do whatever else I want.
So I can, I can make the familiar follow the hero and there he goes,
right?
I can.
Change which way were drawn.
You know.
So yeah, so that all works.
You should add an optimization switch to the you.
I at some point, you know, that is a really, really good idea.
So that's such a good idea that I feel like we almost want to make it
kind of a little more formalized in the sense that like if we switch
to using the pragma on off method and we got that working, we could
actually have debug switches that turn on and off optimizations in
different parts of the code.
So when we need to debug something, we just turn off the optimization,
just on that piece.
Let's see.
Wouldn't - oh, to optimize the dead branches out?
Well, they're not dead though.
I assume I assume it didn't know that they were dead because they were
static variables.
So those variables could have been changed, right?
I suppose I should have made them volatile.
That would have been the way to make, make sure it knew it didn't do
that, I guess but
Engineer.
Oh, could you have an option to either recompile or simply toggle?
If it seems like most of the time you would use the regular.
If so the changes instantaneous but an extreme cases, you could
easily, just do the recompile option.
So I don't know how I would do that is the only problem.
So I think if you wanted to do that, I'm trying to think.
But I suspect that the only way you could do that is if you use some
kind of a notch, I can't think of how you would make it.
So you could switch between them like just free free switch.
Right.
Because so
You can trap a pound if inside another macro.
So you're pretty much stuck doing this.
And so you'd have to do something like this.
You have to double wrap everything.
You know.
Which seems super sucky.
So, I can't think of a fun way.
I can't think if the Seas macro processor was better, you could
totally do it, but it ain't right.
All right, I got to go.
We are over time.
All right, so, let's see here.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade here.
Oh, it's my pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along with handmade here at home, you
can always pre-order the game on handmade here at organ.
It comes to the source code which I upload every night after we're
done here so you can experiment with it and play around with it.
So if you like to do that, check out how many rat or grill.
So patreon page you can subscribe to if you want support the video
series and a forum site, we can you can go to ask questions.
And members Community answer them or I answer them sometimes to and
then we also have anti-deficit guide there and we finally have also a
tweet bot which tweets the schedule at used to if you want to hit the
stream life you can do that.
Now the next dream will actually be probably on Monday.
We're not having a stream tomorrow so it's going to be a long weekend
for a Sammy here.
I was concerned so I will see you guys again on Monday.
Hope to see you back here.
Probably it'll be five PM again pacific daylight time but check the
Tweet body.
If you want to schedule.
So until then have fun programming and I will see you guys on Monday.
Take it easy, everyone.