Hello, everybody, and welcome to handmade hero.
The sure we could have complete game live on stream.
I tell you what, there's not a lot of mystery as to what we're doing
today because yesterday we did a spatial partition for our sorting and
we didn't get a chance to use it for anything because we finished just
just when the bell rang.
So today on day, 3, 10, we are just going to go use it and so if you
want to follow along at home day, 309 is a source code to start with
that is the source code that I am starting with right now.
So if you would like to be
You know, if you would like to be in sync and I don't mean the bad boy
band.
You know, that was clearly, just a ripoff of the Backstreet Boys.
A fine group of upstanding gentlemen.
I mean in sync, as in synchronization anyway, point being here, we are
in the render code ladies and gentlemen, I don't mind telling you
The down at the very bottom hiding.
In plain sight, there is a sort entries call and right now we are
doing a build Sprite graph operation up here and you can see it and it
is doing the work of putting grids together for sorting purposes.
Its spatially partitioning all of the Sprites on the screen into a
grid but it doesn't actually do anything with it.
Then goes ahead and runs the old code because we didn't get a chance
yesterday to go and actually make this code use it.
So what we'd like to do today is make that code actually use it.
Unfortunately before we do that, there's probably one or two things we
should do as well, which is turning on viewing of the sort graphs, for
example, because right now, we would not really be able to see the
fruits.
The sweet, sweet fruits.
The sweet blossoming virginal, fruits of our
Our labor.
So if we just kind of pretend that this isn't happening for a minute
and go back to the win32 code, we should be able to turn on global
sort groups here.
I guess I could have used the UI for that, but anyway, turn it on
permanently.
So we can kind of see them all and we can kind of get an idea of
what's going on with them.
It's kind of hilarious.
How just not clipped, our Sprites are, it's going to be nice to
Which to enter asset pack and have properly clipped Sprites at some
point here because especially with the software under man, look at all
that overdraw that we were doing for no real reason.
Anyway, you can kind of see what's going on here.
You can see the sort of various lines indicating who is overlapping
who and all that sort of stuff.
And you can see that we're actually getting pretty
It's sorting with most of the stuff that we were expecting to and we
still have a few things that we haven't actually implemented yet in
terms of passing data, down to this in a reasonable way.
But for the most part it's pretty swell, you know, I could even rely
on this order to sort of handle these.
A little bit nasty things where I'm going in front of other Sprites,
and that sort of thing in addition to the ground tiles and all that
stuff.
So, it's kind of doing what we want.
I'm pretty happy with that because it's a bit of an
Charlie underspecified problem, the 2D sorting it out of it all.
Anyway, so now that we've got something that looks right.
Meaning.
Okay, we know, we can see what we are supposed to be getting when we
switch to the optimized version, we at least have some way before we
do any sort of visualization of the optimized version we will at least
have some way of seeing.
Is it doing anything at all?
Like is it is it even remotely close to what we had before?
Because we could have all sorts of bugs in our optimization pass
obviously.
So you can see here when we do build Sprite graph, we've got the
situation where we're going through each of these grids and We're
looping through all of the places that we need to insert now rather
than do this in a second pass.
I don't know that there's really any reason to do it in a second pass.
It seems to me like the easiest thing to do would be to actually just
Loop through all of the things in each grid when we do an insertion
and do the check then
As why?
Wait till later, we're already right there.
It just seems like the obvious time, right?
So yeah, so let's go ahead and try that.
Let's go ahead and say that here we are with our you know, we've got
our note index.
A that can stay exactly as it is but then in here instead of just
doing the simple sort of chained to the front operation which you know
obviously we know we're going to do maybe we can just before we do
that we can just or act, guess actually doesn't really matter.
But before we actually insert and before we actually do this insert
here,
Here, we'll just Loop through all of the sort grid entries in this
particular grid.
so this is going to be entry be and it's going to start out at the
grid location that were on
And then we're just going to Loop through each of the elements in
here.
Now, at this point we then have exactly what we need to do our
operation that we were doing before so we can just go in here and say
you know and in fact I can do a little thing that's like pound.
Define accelerated, Sprite, sort, one or whatever.
And then I could come in here and say, all right, you know, this
operation is the operation, we want to do.
If we're going to do accelerated, Sprite sort and then this operation
is the operation we're going to do if we aren't accelerated.
So here I can just say like if we're not trying to get, you know, for
for now
An accelerated sort, then do sort of this slow and squared version.
That doesn't try to do any sort of restriction.
So yeah.
So if we do accelerated Sprite sort, then we're going to come through
here and we're going to check each of these entries.
And in order to do that, I've already got sort Sprite bound a but I'm
going to have to get sort Sprite bound be from the entry itself.
And that should be pretty easy because I'm pretty sure what we did for
node index.
Be, I don't know why I left the entry point, run there.
There we go.
So node index be just comes out of whatever the entry is in the Grid.
At that point, I don't actually remember what we decided to store in
this grid.
And I also don't know why I didn't put it in the H file.
Whole reason I have an h-file, there's to put stuff like this in it.
All right, there we go.
Get rid of that, get rid of that.
Are it bracket?
All right, so, occupant index is all we need from there.
And then we can do exactly what we were doing before we can test for
the to in the two intersections of A and B.
We can then do the front back and we can, I don't know why I have
re-enable, the push still in here because the push has been re-enabled
for some time.
Ladies and gentleman.
This is why you never common code because those goes out of date.
Anyway, so now in theory, accelerated Sprites or can be set to 0 or 1.
It's now set to 1 and well, that's not a very good sign.
Now, is it
Not off to a good start.
So here we are in our
In our Loop.
That seems like we've got.
An odd sort of issue here.
It looks like we've created a linked list that just kind of Loops in
on itself on my right.
Let's take a look here.
Well, why do my eyes deceive me here?
This says that there's a there's a good one for you.
I hope it's not going to be that kind of night.
Ya gotta love it.
When you when you miss type that one.
All right.
Anyway,
Let's try that one more time.
Yeah.
If you never actually update the iterator unsurprisingly, you don't,
you don't get very good results.
All right, so you know what I'm seeing here.
Is it looks like we didn't make any obvious mistakes with the
Diversion, you know, it's, it's certainly not obviously wrong.
It doesn't mean it's right either.
Let's take a look here though at the profile.
So one of the things you'll notice about the profile, of course
there's a tremendous amount of opengl nonsense in the way but we're
already much faster than we were.
Right, so that's a good, a good start.
So let's go ahead and turn off the sort drawing and just take a look
at what we've got because it'd be nice to know how
How close we are to good or at this point.
All right, so there's the profile and so you can kind of see that
build spray graph is still a little bit.
Probably more, you know, expensive than we would like it still taking,
you know, fifty percent of the time, which is probably too much of the
time to say the least.
So it's not like, that's a great routine at this point, but it's
certainly getting better, right?
It's certainly better than it was.
And you know who knows?
We've got some things.
We
Play with as well to see what, what we want to do.
So you know, I don't want to belabor the issue certainly because like
I said, we don't have to worry about how long it takes to draw the
debug information.
But I do want to just just for like, you know, fun.
I do want to look at one more thing.
I would like to just go like okay, while we're in here and playing
around with it, let's go ahead and do
A test of, which part of this.
Or rather, let's do a quick test to see what the accelerated Sprite
sort does.
If we give it a bigger grid to work with.
So a grid with more cells, if that makes sense.
So if we were going to do that, we would say okay you know maybe maybe
instead of Sixteen by nine, let's double the count there and just do
32 by 18 at so that now there's more buckets to sort inside and so you
know, maybe that
Oops, maybe it doesn't help.
It's hard to say, it's certainly decreased the time, right?
So it looks like we were still having sort of a little bit of the N
squared Miss there.
And you know, who knows?
We could take that up even further.
If we wanted to, there should be a Breaking Point somewhere here and
the reason there's going to be or I shouldn't say is going to be the
reason I would anticipate a Breaking Point is because the act of
inserting things into cells, gets lower, the more that there are
right.
Right.
And so you can see that, you know, again that that maybe did get us a
little bit more there but it's not necessarily as drastic certainly,
as the initial one.
So, that's a lot better and it's enough better to that, you know, I
don't know that.
I would care too much about doing anything further.
This is not an optimized.
So we can also, you know, sort of count on the fact that when we're
talking about actually doing this hardcore, yo will get a lot better
performance.
So, you know, this is still compiling, all the debug stuff in.
And, you know, now you can see that our build Sprite graph is down way
below, even the time, it takes to wait for stuff to happen, right?
So I do Wonder to there if the case is well, you know, this is sort of
a little bit perf critical I want and, you know, a lot of the times
that clearing stuff, I think part of we pay a high cost in debug mode
for the clears.
It seems I don't really know.
It's a little weird.
but,
Since we do know.
Like sort of we've got these, these operations here, like that, we're
doing, that could be potentially a little bit costly.
I do wonder if we come in here and sort of clean this up a little,
like those push trucks are probably kind of much more expensive than
they should be in debug because a lot of stuff probably gets compiled
out in there.
I'm not sure exactly.
But yeah, you can, you can kind of see
It does get a little better, but I don't know.
Like, in general, there's a lot of business in here.
I'm a little bit tempted to push it a little bit further, you know,
I'm a little bit tempted to say, Hey, you know, maybe we should go
even further with that and, you know, try to make it a little bit
less.
Try to maybe reduce the number of things that are in here.
I mean, I'm looking at it and I'm like, no, not really sure.
I don't feel, you know, like the nice thing would be if we could sort
of build the topological sort as we go, but I don't really know how.
How plausible that is like.
In other words, there's a question of whether or not we really need
all of the chaining and or whether we need the second pass, you know.
But I'm not thinking of anything obvious, so I feel like maybe that's
enough for now.
I feel like, maybe that's enough.
So I'm going to leave that.
And we probably can.
A well, you know what, let's let's we can get rid of the the old
version here.
I'm just say, that's what we're going with for now.
And off we go.
Now, like I said before, we obviously have sort of a problem here that
we could choose to address or Not address.
I don't know whether we should or not and I alluded to it yesterday
and
You know, it's not going to cause us any practical problems unless we
need to actually break Cycles more logically than we're doing right
now.
You know, if we keep ignoring the fact that Cycles could be problems
in legitimate, things that we hand our sorting algorithm.
Right?
If we ignore that part, we don't then we don't have to worry but if
we're worried about having to detect cycles for something other than
just some debug checking.
Where we don't really care.
Then, we do have a problem of Cycles getting created by the fact that
we're adding things multiple times potentially, because since you
could place yourself in multiple grids, we sort of have this problem
where we don't necessarily know.
Whether we've already visited somebody on this run or if we've, you
know,
Well, let's put it this way.
I feel like it's probably Worth showing.
I don't know that if this were the real world, I would care about
this.
But since I can think of some fairly trivial ways that I would fix
this, maybe I should just go ahead and fix this so that you can see
what happens with the cycle determination.
So let's go ahead and turn this on.
And if you remember that, what we did is we made it.
So that Cycles, when Cycles happen, we change them to be bright, you
know, the sort groups get bright and I believe that previously, you
know, there were not so many cycles.
You can see there's like tons of Cycles all the time, that's almost
everything's bright and I think that basically what we're seeing there
is exactly what I just said.
It's the fact that since we now have multiple grids and I'll draw this
out for you.
Since we now have things in multiple grids.
Right?
If this is a, then a exists in each of these
That's just what's going to happen.
And so when B comes along and you know B is maybe this rectangle, then
what's going to happen to be is its first going to check for overlaps
in this cell and then it's going to check in overlaps in this cell.
And the reason that it's going to do that is because it spans both
cells.
And so in order to find all the people it might be
Lapping.
It has to check both otherwise, it might miss somebody who was only in
this cell, let's say, see right?
If it only checked in this cell, it wouldn't CC.
And then we wouldn't have the correct sort, we'd be missing some of
the overlaps.
So given that's the case.
The question is, what happens when we then go to link these up using
the comparisons?
Well, when be checks, and it sees a, in the list of cells, in the list
of Sprites in this cell and then later it, checks it and
sees it again in this, it doesn't know that it's a different a
It doesn't know that right it?
I'm sorry, it doesn't know that it's the same a, if as far as it
knows, it could be a different rectangle because it has no markings.
It doesn't keep track of what it visited.
And how would we even do that, right?
We have to like a hash table or something, where we put the index in
that we visited or something like this, it would be expensive just to
do.
And so the question is how can we avoid adding a second Edge in that
case?
Because the first time we're going to add the edge once we already add
an edge, we don't want to add an edge a second time just the same.
Hair.
Right.
So what are we going to do, right?
Well, what we need and we can go two ways with this, right?
There's a more theoretical way and that way is usually not so good in
practice if you're trying to do things quickly.
And that's just like, well, you know, we could have done our Edge
stuff as a tree or a hash table or something, right?
Where we just put edges into this storage structure and then we pull
them out later and it's not designed for quick to wrestle like a
little like linked list, right off the thing or array, or whatever.
And if that was the case, then when you said, hey, there's an edge
from B to a would go into that, you know, structure and it would
Collide, and go, I don't need to add that because I've already got it
or something, right?
So you could imagine doing a more versatile, more theoretical graph
structure but, you know, we're not really looking at that kind of a
thing here.
We're trying to make a little Tweaky fast.
A little thing that just runs in the back end of the renderer and we
don't necessarily want to go down that route because it doesn't seem
very fruitful.
So what we would like is some hacker thing.
That's just it right there in the data structures themselves in a very
like easy to poke at Fashion.
We would like some way of saying, hey let's not add another edge here
because we already added an edge right.
Okay.
So I think or at least I would suspect that this is not going to be
particularly difficult to solve.
And the reason that I say that is, if we take a look at what's going
on in in these data structures, here we have two passes, right?
We've got to pass that a Giselle ads.
Edges and then a pass that walk.
Those edges and so, you know, we've got recursive front to back here
and that's going to walk these things.
And then, you know, we've got this thing that actually adds them in.
And so when we're adding them in, we've got, you know, we've got node
index, a and we've got entry be here, and we're about to do a test to
say, do these two rectangles intersect.
Well, what we'd like to say is something more, like, if I have
Haven't already checked this rectangle and the rectangles intersect
then I will add that struct, right?
That's what we actually wanted to say button by the way.
Did I just remembered?
Yeah.
I just want to make sure I change back debug mode.
So we need some way of computing that if I haven't already checked
this rectangle.
Well what do I know about these rectangles right?
When I am doing insertions for node index a I know that the entire
time I'm doing insertions for a I'm going to be looking at people who
aren't a right.
I'm never going to look at myself because I haven't added myself to
the grid Square yet, right?
So all of these people are people that I haven't visited
It on the Node index a trip yet.
And so I just need a way of marking them to say, I have visited them
on the Note index a trip.
Right, that's all I really need.
When I then move to the next node index a, you know, the next setting
for note index a, I then need a way to say, okay, check, you know, I
want to know.
Now, if this pass-through has ever touched during these people,
So we have, you know, a pretty easy way, I think to, to make this
work, right?
We've got the Sprite Flags, we've got visited drawn debug box and
cycle, right?
Well, it wouldn't be particularly difficult for us to just move those
up, right?
We wouldn't even necessarily need any additional space, right?
I could just say, okay, you know, pretend that these are up in the, in
the high area.
So let's put them, you know, let's put them here or
Right.
So now with that leaves me with is the entire bottom part is free for
me to store stuff, right?
I've got 24 million or some odd.
I mean I don't even know.
So I've got I've got what is it 24 bits there.
I've got 24.
So I got 24 million Sprites worth of indices, I could shove into the
bottom B and if I needed more than that, well really I could go up
even another bit if I wanted to.
In fact, I don't even know why this is looks like this.
We could just do that, right?
If that makes sense.
And I don't know if enums technically can't be you 32s, I don't really
care.
We'll see if the compiler complains.
Oh C++ but point being so, you know, there's a massive amount of
space.
We've got there that were not using.
So what I could do is just say, okay, there's an index mask
And I could use that index mask, to mask off the bottom B and use them
as a generation count, where the generation count is just whatever the
note is that I'm on.
And so then when I go to check someone, I can easily tell what I've
checked in this round or not.
Because if the bottom of their Flags,
Right?
If the bottom of their Flags doesn't have.
My number, my note, index a.
And there, then, that means I have not checked this person yet.
so, what I can do here is say, like, okay, if I were to take the, the
entry, or sorts, right, bound be and if I were to take the flags in
that one and say and them with the Sprite index mask,
If that's not equal to my index, then I haven't touched it yet.
Right, anything else?
And it's not correct.
If I get in here and I find that I haven't touched it, then I could
just say well let's just go ahead and set the be Flags equal to it.
And by the way I don't really have to you know, I could assert just to
make sure
That it'll fit.
And that's just a little surfing to say, oh, you know, if the part
that I, you know, the mass that I'm using a story, this would actually
get rid of some any data in the node, indices.
Then that's obviously a bad thing.
In order to get there, we have to be way up in the, you know, in the
almost to the billions of Sprites and that would make this algorithm
runs so slowly that it wouldn't be 60 frames a second.
I can guarantee you that.
So now typically big deal there but we can also
We want to even though we did an assertion here, you know, we can, we
can also, I guess, assert that no one has tried to use any of those
flags since then, just in case this algorithm changes.
But we could say like oh assert that if I end, you know, it with the,
the not of it.
So I look at the parts that aren't indicated by the
Make sure that there's nothing in there.
So that would give me that sort of marker that I need.
And hopefully you guys kind of sauce.
Mm, love that texture download.
Hopefully that would give me all.
I really need to make my cycle detection.
Correct now because now we've done it and you can see it spazzing out,
right?
Exactly the same place as it used to when there actually is a cycle
when the guy goes through the thing.
So, hey, good job us, right?
So, I hope that made some reasonable sense.
I don't know, I guess I usually don't check the stream for questions
at the time so I guess if you have questions about what I just did
there, ask him at the end but hopefully it made reasonable sense.
Essentially what we're doing is we're just every pass through when
we're checking for, you know, a particular rectangle, particular
Sprite rectangle, against all the other rectangles in its areas.
We're just going, hey.
Every time we check someone tag them with our index, and if we see
that that index is there already.
Well, then we know we must have already processed it and if not, then
put the tag on.
So we'll know that we did.
And, you know, if the algorithm was completely unstructured and we
were testing anybody against anybody, randomly this sort of trick
wouldn't necessarily work because you would need to store for every
node which nodes had
I stood against it right.
It would it would have to actually store everyone who had tested
against it and check to see when we come through but because we know
we check one Sprite rectangle against everything in its area and then
move on to the next one and check everything in this area.
Then we only need one tag because all we need to know is did we do it
on this pass through because we're never going to come back and check
this rectangle as the primary rectangle.
Again.
Right.
So now we're in real good shape, I think.
And I'll go ahead and turn off the sort drawing one last time.
But, you know, I don't think there's really a whole lot else to do
with the sort at the moment, it seems like that's pretty stable and,
you know, Works real nice.
And you can even see that, you know, looking at the profile.
Just this is not scientific obviously but eyeballing it.
I think we were up around 20 to 22 24 milliseconds before not adding
those extra.
Edge's.
Right saved us some time in debug mode as well, because it's not
pushing on extra edges that doesn't have to do.
And in release mode, a lot of I think those Edge push has become
fairly cheap, right?
So,
Not like a real savings in the sense of the shipping version of the
game.
But, you know, I like to keep the debug version relatively fast
especially on handmade hero because we like to step through the debug
version so I can show you things into bugger and as you've seen the
debugger can't handle debugging release code hardly at all and so it's
very hard for me to do anything instructional, you know, if I don't
have the debug version running relatively fast.
So you know that was kind of a nice bonus, right?
That we got as
As part of making those, you know, not pushing on redundant edges that
we don't need we.
Now get this sort of bonus of, hey, even when we stress the system,
we, yeah.
We drop off a 60 hertz, but we don't not not very far right.
We still got of a pretty darn good speed profile.
Even Even in our in our janky assist State.
All right.
so,
I'm not sure what we should start on here.
I should probably save starting on anything to Major till the
beginning of the stream next time around.
So yeah I think maybe you know one thing that we do kind of need to do
maybe I can get this done in 30 minutes.
I'm not 110% positive but I've got 30 minutes.
One thing that we haven't really looked at yet.
Is we have not really looked at how we would go about making
suggestions to the Sorting algorithm if we wanted to.
And I'm not sure, I'll be honest.
I don't really know.
What the way is that we most want to do this.
Because there's a couple different things we could do.
So let me just give you a little bit of an example.
So let me label this here.
This was grid sorting
But anyway, let's move down here to manual.
Sort.
Override.
Now it may become clear to us after we do some work with the actual
game assets, a little further down the road that we don't really need
anything like this.
I don't really necessarily know, but I do certainly know that the
possibility exists that we will need to do some sort of manual,
sorting override.
And the example that I've already sort of used for this in a couple of
cases, right?
Is the hero Sprite.
So, you know, we've got this hero Sprite and in the future it
definitely looks a little more.
I mean you saw right what they looked like on the Molly rocket blog,
you know?
Definitely more top-down.
You can see here on this post as well, you can see what the hero kind
of looks like.
So Anna has definitely gone ahead and really solved a lot of our
perspective problems for us.
So that was kind of nice and it's going to be a lot easier to keep
that the art looking consistent with the new art than it was with this
art, which is really kind of not.
It doesn't it doesn't really work with the way we were doing.
The Sorting.
So it was very fake.
Whereas this is a lot more consistent and it has a lot more of a
consistent perspective, feel to it across the assets.
So given that, that's true.
You know, we may get out of jail, free a little bit more than we would
otherwise, because there's such a strong perspective to it now, but
In the case where we have something like that, you know.
Okay.
We've got the glove here or whatever the punching glove.
Well actually people's thumbs are on the inside, just in case you were
wondering.
It's not like that.
Maybe, I don't know and we've got the glove and then we've got the
head here, right?
Here's the nose, very important.
And maybe there's a hat because it was there was a steam sale.
So we've got this situation and we know, we've got hat, we've got
head, we've got body, and we've got glove, and we maybe know that.
Okay?
The glove is going to move all around the body and punch and stuff and
so that probably wants to be sorted normally and go behind things and
whatever.
But this pretty much always looks like this it pretty much always goes
had on top right then head and then body.
And is never going to go any other way.
Like you really can't ever do anything else until the head
disaggregates from the body.
Like if you get some magic spell, where you float away and they were
separate entities, maybe but while we're talking about one coherent
entity where the head and the body are together, I shouldn't say when
queer entity one coherent system when they're together and they're,
you know, in the brain it's working on head and body together.
It's not clear to me that we will always get reasonable results.
If we just let the Sorting do its thing now, maybe it would but maybe
I won't because if you think about what would happen here if these are
wise, frites then as one of as the head moves like back, it's going to
go behind the body and as the head moves forward, it's going to go in
front of the body, right?
And that's not really what we want to have happen.
So I don't know to what extent
and we're going to need to go in there and say, you know, this is
stacked in Z, these are actually
In Z, even though their wife's rights, right.
And we don't want them to necessarily not be why Sprites because we do
want that crazy, two and a half D nonsense, where the glove can go
behind it and in front of it, right?
So it's kind of a difficult problem.
And so the question here is, how do we want to deal with that sort of
manual sort override thing where we're saying?
Well, alright, you know, we don't really want these to be sorted using
our sort rule because we know our sort rule is a hack and any sort
rule that we come up with is going to be a hack and so we're going to
need some ways to work with that hack and make sure that it can
doesn't cause critical problems like we would have in this case, I
think,
Now one thing we could do is add more hacking this to the sort rule
meaning we could say, well, you know, we want a sort rule, that's a
little more generic.
So maybe we have this idea that there's Z planes of the, why Sprites
of a stagnant?
Yeah, I don't know that was a really nasty gray area and I'm not sure
that there's really all that much to be mined out of that.
You know, sorting these two and a half D things is a real pain in the
butt.
I guess is what it boils down to, and I don't know.
There are all that many good Solutions there.
So I would be more inclined to look for a way of saying when we know
how something has to be sorted for artistic purposes.
Can then we just specify that directly so that will always happen
properly, right?
So there's two ways we could do this.
And here are the two ways that I think we could do it one way.
Is we could say there are there are rule.
There are edges, right?
Edges, added
Manually.
So there's some way to like, shove down the render, you know, as the
render is going, the render queue is getting filled in addition to
putting sort Sprite bounds in there, which is what we're putting in
there.
Right now, we could also put in there.
Edges that we want to be mandatory like they don't have to overlap
there.
Just edges that already exists there, right?
So when we go to process, something and we're going to do an is in
front of operation on it or whatever.
There's another way that we could come to that conclusion rather than
having to test it.
We could just add an edge automatically.
Good says this is in front of this and don't process intersection
between these two things.
Right.
There's some difficulties with that.
Certainly one of them is easier said than done, right?
We want the book.
On that sort of thing to be fast.
And it's not clear exactly how adding the edges wouldn't be hard
avoiding, having the sort come through and re add more edges.
You didn't want is the hard part, so it's the, the suppression is the
harder part there, right?
But you know, are there ways around that probably?
Probably.
And it would also depend on how much of this you needed to do.
You know, if you only needed one Edge, one manually specified Edge per
Sprite.
One is in front of if you will / Sprite or something like that, it's a
lot easier than if it's many, you know, if it's like oh no we've got
to have 10 for some of them or something like this.
So, I don't know.
So, you know, that's
That's one way, another way of doing it is basically, having a way of
saying these Sprites get drawn as a group and don't sort them, right?
And that has some attractiveness to it.
The reason that's a little bit attractive is because we sort of know,
we probably want that anyway, and, you know, we could even you could,
you could imagine making this a fairly flexible system without too
much work where we could even keep sorting within the
Themselves if we wanted to.
So, you know, you could imagine, you've got a sort Sprite bound and it
says, this is a why bound.
And in it, you could stack some Z Sprites and say sort this first
then, you know, wherever it's going to get drawn, you draw, whatever
is inside it sorted by some other criteria
right?
And it's not out of the question that we could do that.
I don't know because we're using a grid acceleration scheme.
I don't know that there's really all that.
Apparently, I'm very tired.
Because we're using great acceleration scheme, it makes a little bit
trickier and the reason it makes little bit trickier as because we
kind of have this one acceleration structure, we kind of want to pass
everything through and we don't really want to have to deal with a lot
of fussing there, right?
So if we have to do sort of sub-regions of sorting, well, it wouldn't
be too bad if there's only a couple things in it, but you know what?
If we wanted to do it for like, say the debug thing where we're just
saying this is one layer that gets sorted separately, and then drawn
on top, or whatever else, right?
And the same thing is going to be true for, you know, for room layers.
And so to a certain extent, you know,
We're going to have to kind of deal with that that sort of coarse
grain multiple sorts.
And I just don't know if we want to start having lots of little sorts
happening in their ribs.
Oops.
Apparently, I can draw with the Eraser didn't know that.
So yeah.
Really, why you do is go take a nap?
Well, probably go to bed.
I don't know, I don't have a real strong opinion on this.
I think the thing we probably would want to do.
Is, you know?
Because I think it would be relatively simple if we just have the sort
Sprite bounds potentially have, you know, runs in them essentially
like, you know, if I pop over here to the sort Sprite band stuff, you
know, we've got this structure, it's a little fatty right now.
It's got a little bit too much in it, right?
There's no question about that but, you know, maybe someday we need to
kind of go in there and
And clean that up, make it a little smaller.
It's true that probably, you know, the Sprite Edge, this could have
been this could, instead of being pointers, these could be could be
indices, that would crunch things down a little bit, the rectangle to,
for screen areas, taking up a lot of space.
And, you know, some of that could possibly be harmonized with the with
the sort key.
I don't know.
There's just It's Tricky, right?
So I don't know.
So right now, it's a bit overweight, it's true but certainly with
respect to that part of it it wouldn't be a big deal.
Probably to say hey why don't we just add account
In addition to the offset.
Right, why don't we say?
Hey, we've got these offsets in there.
Maybe there's, you know, there's an additional piece of information
that's like a chain there or at the other thing, I guess that we could
do.
Right is, is actually chain things together.
So, you know, if you take a look at the render group entries
themselves,
You know, it's a union, right?
It was a union.
Where is Union?
Thought it was Union.
I guess everyone just puts the header in there.
I guess.
Interesting.
So I guess we didn't actually implement it that way.
Oh right, because I don't actually use it as a union.
I actually pack the things.
Wow, that's dedication.
Anyway, so point being, we've got these render group entries, right?
And it would be pretty easy for us to say, well either all of them if
we put in the header or some of them in the case of like, maybe we
only care about doing this with bitmaps because that's really the only
thing we tend to draw that we care about or whatever.
I'm not sure probably wouldn't matter because if we're going to put it
we might as well put it
Since most of our things are bitmaps, we might as well put it up in
the header because it's pretty much always going to be there any way
we could just say, here's another offset to go read after this offset.
And if that offset zero, then you're done but otherwise they're sort
of a chain of these things that you can follow to like draw more.
And so most of the time that wouldn't happen, but anytime that we did
have something where that thing was nonzero, you could draw a bunch of
things at the same sort level.
Right.
It seems like a pretty easy solution to do something like that.
So you just say like oh yeah there's you know next offset on here, you
know, and we could say, you know, if nonzero then jump here and render
and continue,
Rendering entries, so we could kind of just chain things through there
on the cases where we want things stacked in a particular way that
doesn't involve any kind of sorting, right?
So if we wanted to do that, let's see what would happen.
First of all, we would have to actually obey it.
So inside the renderer you can kind of see the way this works, right?
We have this sort of Entry thing happening here where we Loop through
the various entries that we have.
And the way we do that is we've got the sort entries and we pull them
out.
We index
We get the indices and once we pull out an index, we do the processing
on the header like this, right?
And so, we could say that we got the offset, you know, this way,
right?
So what we could do here is say, you know, let's go ahead and and try
see what it would be like to add chaining into this and it seems like
it wouldn't be particularly hard.
We could say, you know,
Let's call this header offset.
Let's say that we got it this way.
Right, I could then just say do what's in here, you know this whole
nice fancy schmancy nonsense that you're doing.
Go ahead and do that and do it well, header offset is not equal to 0.
Now, obviously, the first time through maybe head or offset can be
equal to 0 because the first one, but if we start chaining, we know
you can never chain back to the 0th one.
Let's say that's just not allowed for whatever reason.
I guess that would mean, we'd have to reserve the zero with element in
that case I suppose we don't even really need the do Loop.
We could just do it like this.
And let's take a look actually to make sure that that's the case.
Let me see what actually happens there with the offsets.
But I'm going to go ahead and add a thing that just a search that zero
because that way the loop looks a little cleaner to and we should
Reserve 0.
I like to reserve 0 most of the time just to make things cleaner
almost always.
So I'm going to add in a certain cure that the offset is never zero.
and,
Yeah, let's do a little bit more work here.
But anyway, inside the header will do next offset.
That's always equal to 0 as well.
So blah, blah, blah, such and so forth.
Everyone as happy and whatever people do things, and it's great.
So and I guess, you know, to be honest, we probably don't want to use
a for Loop here because we're going to pull out of the header after we
dereference it.
So I can't really be quite that slick.
So I have to do while the header offset is, you know,
Valid.
But once I know that the header offset is valid, at the end of it, I
could say, you know, after I get it.
Out, I can say header offset, people's header, next offset and then
I've got my daisy-chaining, so it's a pretty easy thing to do.
It's easy to add to both of our render dispatches because, you know,
they both basically work, you know, more or less the same way.
So if I want to, I can just have my daisy.
Chaining and I think eat it too.
So yeah, so now when I run in theory since everyone's going to push
down with the next offset of zero and Theory, there's no problem and
everything is good and it's all fine.
But as you can see, like we get situations here where, you know, we're
already like I was saying we have sort of artistic rules about the
sort that we want in forest and you can see we get situations like
that even though that's not ever really, probably going to happen the
actual game.
But you know, in the current state of the field, it can happen.
So you take
That in the sort order is messed up on the hero.
We know, the sort of our should never be that, and we want to kind of
just have a few regular.
We don't want to have to start fussing with Z values, and hacks, and
that sort of stuff if we can avoid it.
And so, let's see if we can make that work by using the offsets that
we just created.
All we need to do is make a way to actually access them now, because
now we're set up for day, two days of training through the system.
And I think we'll be good.
Okay, so inside render group, we have a way to push a render element
and a sort key at the same time.
But at the moment we don't have a way of pushing
Under element without pushing a sort key.
Right?
And we need some way of being able to push a render element without
pushing a sort key, if we don't, then there's no way to do that
daisy-chaining.
So if we take a look at what happened, right?
When we do our push render element here,
Where we at?
Well, I guess it's neither here, nor there.
I think, what I would say is probably when we're doing the push,
there's a couple different ways we could do this, but I think the way
that I would probably do it is, I would just say like, hey, you know,
we've kind of got this way of writing things in here for object,
Transformer, whatever.
Let's just say that.
In addition, that object transform that we're using also, maybe maybe
that would have the ability.
To record the last thing it pushed.
So if you wanted to push on to end of it you just could, I don't know.
We'll see, I guess.
I don't want to be premature at that.
Let's just see what happens.
So anyway inside push render element that pushes this this stuff on
here.
We also might want to have a version and I guess I could keep it in
line in the same sense but you know it doesn't have a screen area in a
sort key potentially
Hmm.
That.
Makes things a little trickier.
This means we do have a choice here.
I'm probably going to leave it at this for today.
And we'll tackle this tomorrow because this is kind of interesting.
We have a choice here and I'm not sure.
That we don't want to maybe say let's actually put that daisy-chaining
into the actual sort system.
And the reason I say that is well let's suppose that the hero looks
like this
If we only have one sort entry for him, then the hero ends up looking
like this even though these are the actual Sprite areas that are, that
are being used this area, which is not being occupied by the Sprite at
all.
And there could be quite a lot of that.
Potentially, depending on what the, what the layer Sprites look like,
you know, imagine I had some big fat thing, right?
With a teeny tiny head on it.
Something like you might see in Binding of Isaac, right?
Well, if we only have one sort key for it's going to have to be
Union of the rectangles.
Which means that all of this area is considered overlapping and will
get sorted by the sort system, it will it will take anything that was
under here and think it has to do sorting.
I don't know if that's a good idea or not.
I'm not sure.
Hm.
So yeah, so either, we Union them together or we store them separately
and thus the when it does the the checking inside the sort routines,
it will go and check all the rectangles sort of separately for these
Composites and it'll use the same sort key for them potentially, but
it wouldn't use the same screen area.
That's a tough one.
That is a tough one, my friends.
So, I don't know.
I got five minutes.
I'm going to play with this for a second.
So when we do a push render element on here,
you know, we've got the opportunity to do the command sort entry stuff
or not, right?
So we can decide not to do that.
I don't know.
If I want the debug tag thing to be there, I think it should probably
be here.
And that way, I'll put juice.
so, if you take a look at what, What's Happening Here we have the
opportunity to sort of
We have the opportunity to say, okay, you know, maybe we don't do
this.
And I don't know whether it would be a party Foul to sort of not
increment.
The push buffer element count.
I'm not really sure if anyone cares about the push but push buffer
element count.
Because really, at this point, the push buffer, element count.
I think is, is really only used for knowing how many things to sort,
and how many rectangles there might be.
In Toto.
In fact.
Why are we using the push by Four Element count?
Further.
Flip is that just a typo?
That feels a little typo to me.
Would you not say because cliprect count?
Is right there.
Yes.
it just feels like, you know,
It feels like the cliprect count is the thing you want to use.
If you want to know how many clip Rex there are, not the total number
of elements that just seems stupid.
I think that was a typo.
Anyway, so I think the only person who uses this is the sorting and so
maybe that should be renamed eventually as well.
Let's I'm going to mark that.
No Casey should push buffer, element cat.
Be renamed behind my head.
But yeah.
So I think what we could do here is say, you know, if we are planning
to you know, if it's a new element, we do this, otherwise we would
just need to merge the sort keys and the screen area with an existing
one, right?
So, you know, we've got
We've got all this stuff here.
Got a Sprite bound.
And rectangle to, for the screen area.
And so for the screen area, it's pretty trivial, you know, it's just
going to be like, screen area equals Union, screen area, screen area.
So there's going to be just some like, you know, existing like this.
Right?
And for the Sprite bound, since they happen to be min max has and
stuff, I think it's similar.
So I think existing, you know, bound and there's my my time.
My time is up, y, Min equals minimum, you know, existing Wyman.
Or something.
Yeah.
Again, I don't really know how we're going to store this.
Exactly.
But, you know, we take the minimum of that with the sort key one, I
would really wish that my little, let's move that up above my utility
so I can actually read it.
You know, it's really just going to be something like this.
So that would really be it I think.
And when we do that daisy-chaining on there, then you know, header,
next offset we have to have a way of doing like, you know, the
existing next offset equals whatever our offset was going to be.
So it's, you know, this the commands push buffer size.
And then, you know, we would need to
at the end of it here, make ourselves existing
That's it.
So yeah.
So know exactly how we want to do that but that's what we would do.
And I think that leaves us compiling and running properly for tomorrow
or overnight rather, so that's all good.
Alright people, let's go to the Q&A.
There's a queue a for you.
Let's take.
So we got two questions here.
Let me take them in order, thanks to the grid partitioning, do we now
have a convenient way of doing the graph sort in Cindy possibly
processing for grid squares for for Sprites within a square at once?
Or is it not quite that simple.
Well, you know what, I would say about that is your intuition is
correct that you could do things of this nature.
But we probably could have done that before, right?
We probably could have processed for rectangle checks at a time.
The reason that we won't probably do that is because like everything
else Cindy optimization ends up making code super brittle and strange,
right?
It's it's really not great like it's one of those things where see
certainly not
Your C++ and not really Assembly Language, either they just don't make
it convenient to code.
It's it's not a the languages aren't right for it.
And, you know, people have made sort of attempts to make sort of Auto
vectorizing stuff, but it's not really where it needs to be.
Because usually the problem with with vectorizing code is not the
code, it's the data, right?
And you need good ways of making the data look, correct.
And so, to give an example, in your what you're asking sort of is
like, can we leverage the grid for this?
Well, well, forget the grid.
Let's just say, we wanted to accelerate the one we were doing.
For we did the N squared test, right?
Will we have a giant array?
And we're going through the whole array testing.
If we bulk, bucketed those up into groups of four and stored for
rectangles as 4 x is 4 W.
4X minus 4X, Max's for Wyman's for why Max's, whatever right.
Then you could do bulk testing.
So in some sense it would actually be easier to do it there because in
the grid, now we have to as we as we're filling it in, we have to fill
in the grid, you know, in that way as well, which again, makes that
The grid, partition part, more expensive and the Grid's are less
likely to be full, right?
You know, a grid bucket might only have eight Sprites in it which is
too full buckets.
Oftentimes would have six and missed two, you know, or whatever.
That means that a huge amount of your processing is going to waste
their in the old way.
We had, you know, 2000 Sprites.
Well most of all of the buckets of, for our fill only.
It's like, it's like point 0, 1 percent, that's not full, right?
And so yeah.
So you know you could you send you guys it sure do we need to know
because it's way faster than we knew to be at the moment because when
we compile and release mode, we're at 60 frames a second.
So, you know, we certainly want to wait until we actually had a
problem before, we would go a cimetiere out.
And so I would say, you know, yes, you could do it.
No, I don't think it would be simple.
Not because there's anything complicated about the
Eating it but because it will make the code in the storage stuff, a
little twisted and easier to put bugs in.
And so that is unfortunately why it's usually not a good idea to
optimize Cindy all the time even though it'd be nice because it would
always be faster someday.
I hope we will have languages that make it easy to write the Sim
decode correctly and we might we're not there yet.
Okay.
The Mike DX with regards to the flags and the Order.
Checking, if you are anding the flags the ID to test.
If you have seen it before, what happens when another item does the
same check and Anne's it with the same changed unit.
Doesn't that make the result different to the check flags and masks
equal ID for the new item.
Did I miss something?
Or did you and the flags of the mass before you set the idea to clear
it first?
So I'm not sure I'm 100% clear on what you're asking.
I think I might know, but I might also not know.
Let me explain it.
Let me just walk through it once and then you can tell me whether this
answer the question or not.
Okay, so the code in question is right here.
The coding question is be flags and Sprite index mask, not equal to
know.
Did Nick say assert, nude index a, you know, and sporting spectacles,
no day.
A syrupy flags and nice x equals 0, B Flags, including site, that's
the entirety of what we can or the rectangle intersection because
obviously that's, you know, that's the check for the rectangles
overlapping, that's not relevant to the prevention code that we're
talking about here, okay?
So let's take these one by one.
Be flags and Sprite index Mass not
Go to node index.
A what is that actually doing?
Okay.
So let's pop back here.
Right?
So we have the flags.
I'm going to close that down.
There we go.
So we have the flags, we're and it with the mask.
And then we're doing not equal to note at, you know, not equal to a
that's what we're doing, right?
So what does this do?
Well what this does is, it gets rid of anything that might have been
in the flags field.
Now mind you, it's not strictly necessary and the reason that it's not
strictly necessary and you know, I can even put a note here.
It's not strictly necessary because really, we're never setting those
flags up above here.
So I was just being a little overly tidy and because an and is
extraordinarily cheap like extraordinarily.
So in the context of what we're doing here, I just did it for safety
sake, right?
But it's not strictly necessary.
We could have just said, be Flags, not equal to note in XA because
there's nothing in the upper two, two bits, four bits, the upper four
bits.
We reserved for Flags, they're all zero anyway.
So the and is Superfluous, right?
Because what this and does is it says well, alright.
What I had was a thing that was partitioned like this.
Here are the flags, the actual Flags, right?
And here's the index.
And so what I want to do is I just wanted the index.
This mask is one's all here and zeros all here.
So the and leaves me with just the index.
If there was anything in the flags, they are now gone.
so the flags field and The Mask basically, that's just getting rid of
the actual flags and leaving us with just
Index part.
And then we compare it against a to see if that's what it is, right?
So hopefully that's clear that all that and mask is doing is getting
rid of any flags on the upper part, which we know there aren't any at
the moment.
So, we don't even really need to do it.
Okay, so, next part and these assertions are just checking, we'll put
the assertion side.
These are just checking some assumptions, right?
So then we just do be Flags equals node index a right?
And you know what, I guess in this particular case, since I preserved
it here, you'd think I would have.
I think I even said I was going to and I didn't
Oh, and you know what?
Know, now that I think about it.
These assertions that we're doing.
I actually just asserted that they actually do equal zero.
So this is not necessary.
Never mind.
We don't even need the and right.
It's Superfluous because I asserted that we didn't do it yet.
So, rather than putting the and in and this is probably smarter, I'm
not sure why I didn't do it.
Why didn't just leave it out in the first place is just say that the
flags have to not be there because then that way we didn't write the
routine in a slower way because we might do something later we put in
a certain year that would catch it.
So someone up above a starts to try to use the flags.
It'll assert in here instead of that.
Just going wrong in them going.
I don't know why, right?
That makes sense.
Okay, so now hopefully this makes a little more sense to you since the
mask is even now gone.
Although I just explained what it was doing, you can ignore that
because we don't have to do it.
So we say be Flags is not equal to noting sex, a, so that means the
field inside the rectangle we're checking against is not set to our
field, right?
If we assume that it, it fails that check, right?
So you know, that we feels like it.
It's
Eve's in not finding it, right?
So it's the not equals.
It's saying the the node were checking that were on the pass through
when we go to check, should say it's more clearly.
Hey, who is the rectangle?
We are checking.
And B is the rectangle checking against if B does not have our index
in its flag field, then we will we will proceed right?
If it's it.
Has anyone else has that?
Means was from a previous iteration.
When we get in here, we say,
Okay.
Now we're going to set the facts field equal to note index a, right?
So now we have marked it that we're, it's we're visiting it on this
pass.
Now remember, all of our checks for index, a will happen in one Loop
So we will never check index again.
So, every other rectangle that we happen to touch, we will leave our
marker in them and we will not touch them again.
If we see that marker, when we move to the next index.
Well, now remember, we're checking for a quality with the index that
were on, right?
We're saying it has to be, not equal to that one.
Well, just because now there's a bunch of cruft in all of those flags
fields that are previous indices that we checked, right?
Yeah.
It doesn't matter because we're checking that something say, I did
just think.
However,
There is one problem with this.
That's kind of hilarious.
it's like,
I don't have a bug, I don't think, but it's only because it just so
happens to not be a bug, like, I wasn't smart enough to not have the
bug.
I wish I was smart enough to have thought of the fact that this isn't
a bug but I didn't actually.
And what that is is you'll notice this fails in one case and that is
the case when you're on the first index because all of the flags
Fields will be set to 0.
And so everyone that you check, you'll go oh I already checked it.
You know, I shouldn't check it again.
Hilariously there will never be anyone in the Grid on past zero
because you haven't added anybody yet, right?
So, it just so happens that the field that we picked the value that we
picked to represent the initial State and the time when that initial
state would have caused a bug, they perfectly line up.
And so there is no actual bugs.
That make sense sense.
A separate thing.
Good pass 6 will be ever Doing Network programming on hand?
We have on handmade hero.
No, I will not anyway.
Brian wag, I love how you said.
We don't want to solve this with hacks, for a particular sorting
condition.
Do you think the engine should cover most all boundary conditions or
is there room for boundary hacks in certain extreme circumstances?
Did I say that that may have been a misstatement or rather?
I may have not been trying to convey that.
I think what I was probably trying to say is a particular thing.
We Nest may not have wanted to hack for particular reason and I don't
know what kind of said that in but the
the concept of fake 2D sorting is all a hack, right?
Like really you need full 3D objects, you can't have Sprites and ever
produce real sorting.
And the reason for that is that like they just, you don't have the
information.
You actually need to do a correct sort, right?
I mean, take a very simple example.
You know, a Sprite that's supposed to represent a pyramid.
Right.
Well, if there's somebody standing right here, are they in front of or
behind the pyramid, right?
The answer is the only way you could have known that they're supposed
to be in front of the period pyramid there.
Is, if you had actual 3D depth information for this pyramid and depth
information for this and knew that it happened to be the case because
otherwise it should be behind, certainly, it should be behind if he
was here, right?
If you just slid him over, he's behind.
So the same two Sprites with the same rectangles overlapping in
basically the same way you wouldn't ever know how to sort them unless
you had actual 3D data.
And so the whole concept of Two and a Half, D sorting, in this case is
a complete hack.
And so we just have to do something that is reasonable and we sort of,
I guess gotten to that point now.
But by no means, would I ever say that it was some kind of a, you
know, beautiful pristine engine concept here II, don't think there is
one for to d.c.
two and a half D sorting.
I think there's just
Up with hacked rules that work for your particular circumstance and
then maybe doing a good job on the algorithm that implements those
rules.
Like I think we did, you know, we did a reasonable interpretation
there, it's not the best.
You know, we could spend weeks making way better ones, but it's
totally fine.
It doesn't run and squared because we partitioned it it's, you know,
only does the graph traversal, once it detects Cycles properly, it's,
you know, it's not a piece of crap, right?
And so I think you know that's maybe more what I was saying is there
some you know, we don't want to hack stuff, we don't have to hack.
If there is a good solution, maybe we should do it but the thing in
general is a hack.
And so your fault question do you think the engine should cover most
all boundary conditions or is there room for boundary hacks in certain
extreme circumstances?
The whole sort rule is a hack.
So you know that that is just I think unavoidable unfortunately
All right.
All right, so let's let's go ahead and close down.
Oh dear.
Cuz I didn't say something.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with the source,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and it
comes, it comes with the source code.
So you can play around with it, even as it is still in development.
You can and you know, do your own little tinkering, we also have a
forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions a patreon page, want support the video
series, a schedule bot.
Sweets the schedule at you, if you want to catch us live and an
episode guide, if you need to go find that very special old episode
you missed.
It's all there and thanks to me.
Blow the magical, God of annotation, it's even marked up with time
code, if you can believe that.
So that's about it.
I-i'll be back here tomorrow.
At 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
When I think we'll have to make that decision about what we want to
do.
Do with the sort of chain daisy chain sorting.
I don't know what the right answer is to that.
We don't have a lot of information, maybe we'll leave it like it is
right now and just implement the merging and we'll see if that causes
problems and if it is then we'll sort of moved out because it
obviously makes a sort cheaper to have less things in it so if you can
get away without it maybe the answer is get away without it.
But on the other hand when the hero stretches around it's going to be
bigger, I don't know.
The more I think about it, the more I'm thinking talking myself out of
it maybe we do.
We probably should actually put them on there.
Anyway, that's about it for today until tomorrow have fun programming
and I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.