Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream.
Yesterday.
We did some cleaning up of the way, we were dealing with our menus in
our debug system.
And today I think we want to kind of finish polishing the like
presentation of them and they use of them.
Potentially, I'm not 100% certain.
What I want to do today, I haven't really decided
But I would like to, you know, kind of put that stuff to rest and so I
want to at least go through and take a look and see if there's any
other little dangly things that are problematic.
So
Let's do that.
Do do, do do.
Oh, and today is day 269.
So if you want to follow along at home, you are going to want a 268
source code.
That is what I am starting with today.
So, here is where we're at on this.
So you can kind of see all of our stuff rendering and all of our debug
you, I kind of working the way that it does.
And so what I was sort of talking about work at, you know, the thing
that I was mentioning the other day was our
Rather yesterday was, I don't know exactly what we might want to do
with, you know, with some of this sort of stuff, right?
We have the ability to break things out at the moment, I don't know.
For some reason, we don't seem to be able to clone stuff that isn't a
group and I'm not super sure why that is true like we should be able
to grab one of these things and clone out.
I think I'm not 100% certain about some of that stuff.
Tough.
So, you know, like if we wanted to grab things from different places
and put them into something, I think that actually should have worked
or should be feasible if that makes sense.
But it doesn't appear to be so that might be something to look at as
well.
Anyway, most of the stuff that we wanted to have happen was happening
so you know we can we can sort of push a little bit harder on this
potentially.
Now, maybe clean up some of the way that this, these interactions
happen.
Like this stuff works pretty well at the moment, but like this little
Weird way that you drag things around is kind of a little odd and it's
also kind of annoying that this stuff is not collapsible in a more
complete way, like, it would probably be better.
If all of this stuff was tucked inside a, a big menu that could expand
and collapse.
Which by the way, it basically already is right, we just never exposed
it as something that could expand and collapse.
And so, maybe what we should do is is start with that because I would
like it so that when we're
running the game, you know, maybe we just get a line up here that's
like a
I can't spot but I don't want like tons of stuff here when we're not
actually looking at debug data so that might be a reasonable thing to
start with if that makes sense.
So let's take a look at at that.
Not sure how I want to really approach this but we'll find out.
So, here we go.
Loading our project in for a coder and building and then
Then I am going to go ahead and switch to the tea bag system.
And when we draw the main menu, you'll recall, or I hope you will
recall.
Oh, wait, it's not called that anymore.
What happens is?
We sort of have this idea that we can call one of these three things
and which, you know, those, the separate like movable pieces that we
had out there, we see, two tree and each one of those trees like
basically creates a layout and then draw some stuff.
And you can see that what we do here is we actually
Take a look this group and we don't call draw tree link on that we go
through its children.
And what I'm thinking is that probably, what all we would really need
to do is just stop doing that.
Iteration now that we unify.
Remember, yesterday, we unify the conservative groups and links now
that we've done that, I think we can literally just pass a group here
instead, and what we should get is we should get the root menu showing
up as an actual item, right?
Which is exactly what we want.
And then you can kind of see here that that root menu is now
collapsible in its entirety, which is more what I wanted.
So, when I want this thing to go away, right?
I can kind of do that more specifically and then, if I want something
in here to kind of be a separate menu, then I can also obviously make
that happen as well.
And and you know, we can place these in places if we want to leave
them up, that's fine.
But you know, we don't have to have a bunch of things running down the
side.
So I think that's strictly better just to begin with one thing that I
am a little bit concerned about is that this thing is not a sizable
like this.
This Frame metering bit here and so we may want to make that thing.
Be a sizable region that just starts out at this particular with and
so that can be, you know, controlled a little bit more specifically
and that'd be pretty easy to do as well.
Obviously, with the way.
That we've written the the UI system.
That would be pretty easy because we've got, we've got this Frame
slider here and there's the dimensions of it.
If we wanted it to have more specific viewing thing that would occur
with it.
Then all we would really have to do I think is take this part
actually.
You know what, we could use this part here is a little bit more
straightforward.
We're here.
Where is it?
There it is.
so, all we really have to do is say, well, okay, we've got
We've got a dimension thing here.
We don't probably need anything else.
So if we just want to dimension thing, we can grab out one of those
from this think it's called, what is it called?
An inline block?
Yeah.
If we want to grab out, one of these inline blocks, the inline blocks
have just a dim inside them.
So what we can do here is just say, like, okay, we've got the Inland
inline-block Tim.
So our Dimensions that were talking about
Are these?
And and then we can have that sort of do whatever it's going to do.
So we'll grab out one of those will say in the event that the thing is
uninitialized, which is this case here will keep the same thing we
were doing.
So it'll work the way that it used to but now it will
It'll be sizable and and you know the user can can play with how big
they want that frame control to be if they want to be smaller or
whatever, so let's see.
Now if I launch this and I mean there's really no reason not to make
things sizable, so it just seemed like the right thing to do so now,
if I launch this in theory, 08, forgot.
I have to actually say that.
The sizable thing, otherwise it won't ever become sizable.
Make elements sizable.
There we go.
So now that I have told it to that it's sizable we should get the
little stretchable stretchable nub and now we can you know, control
the size of this thing.
So if we want it to to be sort of
You know more diminutive if necessary.
Course it becomes hard to click on any of these but you know I mean
you still can it's just a lot harder when you shrink it down a bit and
so I don't know if we want to do something like if we if it shrinks
down to a certain size that will only draw the most recent couple
frames in here.
You know, or something like that.
There's obviously a bunch of things we could do if we wanted to make
that a little bit different but for now I think that's fine.
The other thing too is we really?
Yeah you know you don't really need to see
Quite that many frames of scroll back potentially to say the least.
But anyway,
po point being all of that looks fine now and and so all of this
appears to be working pretty reasonably.
Okay.
So another thing that I'd like to do actually while we're at that is
inside our profiler view here.
I would like to make these draw one level down again, which they
weren't doing before.
So I want to, I want to just play with that just for one second.
Again, in things like this for, I'm just kind of trying to finish
stuff up.
We can have to jump.
A bit because as I see things, I'm like, oh, maybe I'll go do this and
so it's, I don't have like a super concrete plan of.
I want this, this and this I'm just kind of seeing things like, oh, we
should clean that up.
We should touch this up, just just enough polish to make sure that
things are going to be nice and usable.
So let's say that we're here in draw a profile bars.
You can see it we do wrecked up.
Oops, we do wrecked outlines here.
It looks like for coder is very unhappy about the indentation.
I got to fix that one of these days, I have the power now to fix that
actually because I do have the four quarters source code but I haven't
dove into it yet.
It's not, it doesn't comply.
It requires Visual Studio 2015.
I think so.
I am, but I don't have installed on my dead machine so I could, I
could should probably do it on this machine, long story.
So push wrecked outline what I could do to start with just to clean up
that view a little bit is I would like to potentially do a push
wrecked and a push wreck outline separately because I think that might
look a little nicer.
So you know, if we drew a black border around things and then Drew
solid, rectangles around everything else.
I'm just thinking solid rectangles behind them.
I'm just thinking that might be nice.
Sure, I suppose I don't have to keep rebooting the game.
I could just leave it going here but
Here's the thread view now and you can see that the solid pieces are
just a little bit easier to view.
Obviously if we jump into something, that's got a little bit more to
it and we jump into say the game update procedures.
Here we should be able to see.
I think a little bit more like oh that hover gets clipped.
Interesting, we probably don't want the hover to get clipped Dewey.
Never thought about that.
But anyway, if we go ahead and pause here you can kind of see.
Here's us calling
All of the stuff inside this summer on which we should also.
We could also print out the one we're on.
I should make a list of these.
Here's, this calling entities overlap.
Yeah.
Anyway,
So point being that's a little bit nicer.
But what I wanted to do after that was restore one level of recursion
to how it was drawing.
And so what I wanted to do is say, okay, when we do draw, a profile
bars, I want to do like some kind of like depth remaining kind of a
thing.
And what I would do here is say like okay if the depth remaining is,
you know, still positive then,
I would like to continue drawing profile bars in like on top of this
one that kind of go go further and so that way when we call
Draw profile in originally and we call that drove drop profile bars
function.
We could say like oh you know draw it with a with an extra degree of
depth to it.
So so go one more pass where you were going and the reason I kind of
wanted that was just because I think it'd be it'd be nicer for fro
just the way that it works.
If we have the ability to go a level deeper, I suppose, the other
thing we would have to do is make them draw a little bit higher too.
so, we would need to do something like
Basic Z, right?
And we'd say, whatever the depth remaining was as that depth remaining
decreases.
But we would like the Z to get higher, right?
And so, you know, we would want to do something like okay, the base is
e is you know that or maybe 100 minus the depth remaining times 10.
Let's say, so just to give us like basically allocate some space in
the Sorting to make this go where we need it to go.
And then when we pass our Z values, here you can kind of see there's
the Z value here.
I don't know why we said,
Three here.
I think I've I was thinking that was the Z value, it's not the Z
value.
So anyway, I can say like here's the base is e and the wreck a last
line should be at the base Z you know maybe plus 1.
And then I'm hoping that'll kind of give me more of a like a good sort
there.
That makes sense.
So there's our thread View.
However, that does not seem to have worked at all.
Yeah, well that wasn't very good.
What is the problem here?
The note is the one that we're on so that's all fine.
We do a
Wait, what?
How does this work?
Yeah, we do do a root node, so that's all fine.
So when we draw these here, we are passing in a death, remaining the
depth.
So, as the death gets lesser, the Z values get higher, which is
exactly what we want.
If for some reason, I don't see any of these.
So I'm going to double check, just to make sure, but I'm going to get
rid of our solid fill and just to see if we draw anything at all.
So I know whether it's a bug, I want to know whether it's a bug in the
Z or or not.
So I can see those those there, right?
I can see the sub stuff.
They're already.
So like for example if I come in here you can see there's a bunch of
A stuff happening in here.
Here's an example.
Right, here's some more examples.
This is in begin Sim.
We can see all sorts of stuff happening in here, I guess.
Yeah.
So we're obviously drawing the rectangles, the Z is just not sorting
properly.
And so I have to figure out why I'm not getting.
What I would expect out of those.
He's part of it may be, I have to I should verify that we actually use
the Z when we do the sort keys.
So let me actually verify that we didn't nuke that, I'm assuming that
we didn't.
Yeah, so we still use the projected Z which is what we would expect.
So or rather the the
he's he
Original pee.
Yeah, so we okay.
So we only use the projected Z, we don't actually use the sort.
The the Z that's get passed in as part of the Sorting.
So in theory, you know, this would have to include taking into
account.
Whatever the original p is that we passed and then maybe that would do
what I thought.
Well, I guess I should re-enable the call that I'm talking about.
I want to test it.
Okay.
So, let's take a look.
Okay, so that was the problem with that guy, but now at least we can
sort of see what the difference is here.
Let's jump in.
And so that's just kind of a nice way to sort of see that, right?
That's a nice way to get a little bit of that information there.
Okay.
Oh God.
What have I done?
Stop, don't draw that anymore.
Here we go.
And so, I suppose the frames window probably would be better that way
as well.
Where is the frames window?
Here's draw frame bars.
And so in this case again, I'll just do
a push wrecked and leave it at that.
So, there's our frame bars, which now you can kind of see those a
little better as well, which is, which is nice and we can jump in on
those and all that good stuff.
And then it just it gets kind of, it gets kind of nasty if you try to
get in there and actually do once you've got that many of the frame
bars drawing but you know, that's just the way it goes sometimes.
And I suspect that I guess I don't really know what that mostly where
the time is actually being taken there.
But I suspect that's mostly because we're very inefficient at sinking
large numbers of things we're set up more for doing like like I said,
big sort of image Blitz.
And so if we wanted to make
that sort of thing run quickly, we'd have to first identify whether
there, you know,
We'd have to verify that it was just a case of our render sinking
being inefficient.
And then going from there.
But anyway, that looks pretty reasonable and so I'm okay with most of
that, that seems seems pretty fair to me, and yeah,
And the other thing that I guess might be nice is if this this view
would would probably be good if it could highlight, you know, the one
that we were on as well, would be pretty nice.
So in addition I feel like getting a wrecked outline here that sort of
banded the the, you know, the currently viewed frame or something like
that would probably be a big help to figure out where we were.
And so when were drawing this,
You can see the frame indices here.
What I'm going to say is, let's, let's go ahead and take a look.
Where is the frame?
We do have Min y Max.
Why, and where is our X and Y are.
Okay.
So here's our addicts and then the bar with, right?
And so if we wanted to hear, we could say, you know, if this Frame
index is the one that we were doing before.
So if this Frame index,
I mean, this is the one we're we're viewing.
If this Frame index equals the debug States viewing ordinal.
Then I'm going to draw it specially and so that's obviously, you know,
this is just the profile wrecked Min Y and the profile wrecked Max.
Why?
And in here, I'm going to probably just outline it like so.
And I want to make sure it's on top of everything.
And so I'm just going to say that it's going to be outlined in like a
yellow there.
And what I think I want to do here is I think I want to do an ad
radius to where I just expanded a little so that it so that it won't
overwrite so that the one that reviewing doesn't get overwritten at
all and it kind of just blocks out the other people.
That would be, I think the best way to go.
For as far as visibility is concerned.
All right, so as we kind of play now we can sort of see that guy
there.
You know what we all could also do?
I suppose is maybe this is a little bit better actually, even than
what I was thinking.
Maybe instead of that, we just do like more like, you know, if
if Raymond x equals debug State viewing frame ordinal,
Then maybe we make this have a highlight.
For now I don't know what we're going to do with that.
Exactly, we could also expose do it this way.
But what I'm thinking is like, so in here, we have the color we can
make the colored dimmer.
For example, like we could say like hi dim equals, you know, if the
Highlight is on its 1.0 otherwise it's it's you know, slightly dimmer
or I don't know, something like that.
And so I can just take that color and I can just darken it, right?
If we're not on the highlight.
And so, then you can kind of see when we pause, you can see that this
one's brighter, it's probably not enough brighter necessarily.
So we might want to make this be a little bit more obvious like that.
And then you can see the one specifically that we're on any given
time.
And then when we pause, you know, we can kind of go and you can see,
you can see that.
Activity there, right?
That seems.
Animal probably.
It would be nice if you could just click on here to set the frame as
well.
So it's kind of unclear to me that we actually needed these to be two
separate displays.
They probably could have been the same display, but again, I don't
really want to get any more bogged down in all the we could we could
do arbitrarily large numbers of awesome things.
I think at this point and hopefully you guys can kind of see how to do
them.
So, if you want to explore that, I'll let you know, other people.
Maybe take the lead on that.
So
I'll go focus on some other things but point being.
Now we can sort of see which one is the active frame in this profile
group as well.
So I think that's pretty good.
And the only thing that I'm concerned about now, is this thing gets
clipped because it gets drawn while we're inside the clipping mode.
I feel like those tooltips in general since we use them in Cumberland
places.
I think now would be a good time to maybe make that be a systemic
thing that's going on, so that we can
You know.
I guess I want to make that be like a utility that anyone can
participate in.
So basically any one of these, you know, when you Mouse over it can
just say here's my, like hover tip that I'm trying to display and it
doesn't have to be specific.
to like, you know,
It doesn't have to be something that's implemented per control, like
it is right now.
And so, the other thing that I might want to do is like this sort of
stuff information here, like this is some heads up information.
Like, how many frames?
How many milliseconds, the frame took.
I think that might be a nice thing to just print out up here.
So we might want to do also is have a way of changing what that route
printout is from from time to time as well.
And so what I'm going to do, let's take these in sort of serious here.
if I'm going to,
If I'm going to make those tooltips, these sort of more systemic then
what I need to do here is sort of have some way of getting out to I
guess the you probably put it in the UI system.
Something that's like you know internal void add tool tip or something
like this.
Not know why that's confused about indentation and the tooltips.
Are currently.
Where is that at this is debug.
Th the tooltip stuff is typically just done ad hoc like in draw
profile bars.
So it's basically just this stuff like you see here.
And so what I want to do is I want to basically take this stuff and
bring it back over here.
And so you're going to take the debug State and you're going to take
what the string is that you're trying to to print out.
And then we're going to make sure that this stuff just all works
fairly seamlessly.
So, okay, so that's that.
And this then becomes more like add tooltip.
And we just say, like, here's the two bucks date and here's the text
buffer, this stuff can go away and then Mouse Tech stack.
I think this this mouse Tech stack stuff actually wants to be set
probably at debug start up now.
So where we do like debug start
Inside.
Debug start is actually where we would make this happen, so that Mouse
text stack.
Why is actually going to be set here.
I also don't know what that did.
I also well okay I'm going to leave that like that for a second.
I also wanted to see text out at because text out at, I don't actually
know I guess that's actually in here.
I don't actually know what text out at does with its Z.
Right?
Cuz it does, it does a key that doesn't have any Z value and so when
it actually puts these things, when it actually sinks these things in
You can kind of see that it's actually, it has a z value here that we
could have been using for sorting this whole time, but that we aren't.
And it seems like we probably should, you know what I'm saying?
Yeah, so I think what we would like to do is we'd like to say that
hey, there's also probably a z value here and that c value.
By default doesn't actually affect anything, but if you want your
stuff sorted, you can have it.
That seems reasonable to me.
Okay, so let's see here.
This stuff.
I feel like that's something that probably should just be known.
I don't feel like the mouse key is something that should be all that
mysterious to anyone.
So I feel like that's probably something that's in the debug State.
We certainly know the last Mouse p&i, presumably, we would want to
know the mouse.
The tech stack X.
The text Doc, why?
I feel like that's just something we would want to know here.
So in general this would probably be more like hey there's a tech
stack.
Why in fact I think really this is just a mouse like text probably we
could actually just make this a mouse layout even to completely honest
with you in fact there's no reason not to do that.
So I feel like probably what we actually want to do is this
Right?
And we do it.
Begin and end layout.
And that way, you could even use like indentation, and you could even
put any anything you can put in the regular course of events.
You could put here, that seems like probably a better idea.
So I'm just going to go ahead and try that and see how that works.
Because that seems kind of reasonable to me.
Yeah.
So I'm going to get rid of these things, I'm going to say, there's a
mass text layout.
And then here, what I'm going to do is say, well, okay, the way that
we would be doing this
when like, I'm going to do one of these basic text elements
So what are these basic text elements?
I don't know.
So, with interactions if I don't want to actually include this in the
intro, in the set of things that can be interacted with if that makes
sense.
So I don't actually want to do the default interaction stuff and the
default interaction stuff is
It's probably somewhat avoidable.
Because since that's set on each individual element as we go, you
know, I should be able to say, I don't actually want that thing.
But I need to kind of untangle a little bit of this first, which is
probably good anyway, so yeah.
So I think that's good and this will also cause us to line ourselves
up properly so I think yeah, I think this is all good.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and again I'm going
to pretend we're just laying out a menu essentially at this point but
it's actually going to be the text that goes on the mouse.
So what I'm going to do is say okay that we're going to begin layout
We're going to use the mouse text layout here.
To store this.
We've got this begin layout and the begin layout needs to know some
information.
It's got to have the debug State itself.
It's got to know the mouse pee and it's going to the upper left
corner, which in this case is also the mass be right.
So we're going to do that.
And then in here, when I lay things out the add tool tip, I'm just
going to F0 out for a second and get the
To start compiling and then we'll focus on that.
Again, this doesn't have to do that anymore at all.
Mouse Tech stack.
Why?
Again, this is just going to be an ad tooltip call.
And finally, so the mouse p is not known here.
Apparently, we do know what it is.
I believe we just haven't actually gotten it yet.
So what I can do there is I can just defer this.
It doesn't actually have to be done here because until people actually
start drawing the trees, we're not going to care so we can actually
just initialize that right here.
Do our begin our begin layout.
And then do our end layout.
At the end.
So that should be fine.
I don't know what that's about.
That's because, yeah, we change the sizes of some things there so
that's not going to work.
All right, so now when we Mouse over things, we won't actually get any
tool tips on these guys because they've been removed.
We're still getting it on this which means that guy I guess didn't
actually use quite the same path I guess.
It must have been a simpler things but I'll take a look at the draw
frame slider here, the frame slider must have done so even print out
so we didn't detect it.
Yeah, it just does a text out at.
So since that
Use the mouse stack.
We didn't see it, but that's okay.
Now, we know where it is.
We'll just go ahead and make that one go through here as well.
So now everyone who was previously doing a tooltip, should be calling
through the same code path, and none of them should be showing up, of
course, especially not.
If the texture download fails, which does none of these should be
showing up anywhere, which is fine.
Right?
That's what we want.
Okay, so, now, what I have to do is I have to go through,
And make this ad tooltip, call actually print out the text as we
wanted it to which is pretty straightforward, really all that.
We're going to do here is every time we would have added a tooltip, we
just need to add something to that layout.
So we need to do, you know, like an element advancement and that sort
of stuff.
So in order to do that, I think what I want to do here is just do like
a begin and element kind of a situation.
We don't necessarily need to do them but it seems like we would
probably want to at least that's my feeling.
So I'm going to take a look at basic text element here.
I'm going to go ahead and grab this code out and I think that's
roughly what the tooltip code would do - a bunch of stuff.
So we're still going to get the text size will call this.
Text is that's what's called for looking at the text size.
We're going to feel figure out what we want this to look like.
We don't have it a border in this case,
We're just sort of printing out a line of bear text so I think that's
all we really need so we can get that we can then do our element
layout stuff.
And here we can do like this is a non interactable or non-interactive.
So we want to be able to say that something is not going to have any
interaction.
It shouldn't interact with the mouse at all.
It shouldn't be something that even tests against the mouse, we can
then output it.
Way, we were going to put it before and we don't really have the
concept of colors for these tooltip, things at the moment.
So we'll just put it there and we're not going to back.
We're not going to have backdrop stuff either.
So if I go ahead and do that that allows us to sort of just get our
tool tip, functionality back and working the way that we wanted it to
when we do at tooltip.
Again, we know the layout by default.
In that case, it's the
The mouse text layout that we saw in the debug state, so we don't have
to pass that in and I guess I we don't do reference either the
non-interactive part we haven't implemented yet the Border part.
We don't care about because we're not supporting borders in here or
rather, not wear else for them.
Nobody wants that.
And so then I can just go up and make this non-interactive bit and go
from there.
So, when we say default interaction,
Which is this code right here.
If we say non-interactive, I think what I need to do there is make the
ability to record.
The fact that this thing is not going to have any of the interaction
stuff happen.
So be like element, non-interactive equals true, it'd be something
like a flag field, which we don't really have the moment.
I don't know that we really need it because we can just make a Boolean
for now, but that's basically what we're talking about here.
So if we take a look at
At this where we're storing the stuff that's in the element.
What I want to do here is have something that's like you know be
finitude non-interactive when we push one of these on.
So like when we do a begin layout, we would not to do anything but we
would set it to True when we don't want things to be a
non-interactive.
The other thing I can do is I could default it to interactive like so,
which maybe makes a little more sense.
I don't know.
And set it to false.
We'll see what happens when I do the ifs in there and then that would
look like
Like this, right?
We just say like, okay
Where is that layout element?
Begin element rectangle.
Here it is.
We would just say, Oh, by default, everything is assumed to be
interactive.
And unless told otherwise, oops,
That won't happen is down here when we actually do stuff with the
interactions like we do in here element type isn't isn't a rectangle.
This is the testing right here.
I guess you know that I guess means that if we don't ever in
initialize the interaction it wouldn't interact.
So maybe I thought that would be well.
I guess now, I think about it if we just leave it uninitialized and we
wouldn't actually actually have to do anything.
Like if we just never say that there's interaction, that might be
sufficient.
So I guess I take it back.
We don't really need anything more.
I didn't realize it was, I thought it would just blocked it.
So there wouldn't be anything clickable there, but I guess that's not
what that does.
All right.
So, okay, so now we've got a few more things to do.
First of all, we need to make sure our Z for this layout is high
enough, which at the moment, right?
You can totally see that.
It's not.
So when we're doing our text out at here, we presumably want this to
be something particularly High.
I don't know what we want it to be exactly but
Wait, where is text out at?
Here we go.
And one of the things about this sorting is since it's very ad.
Hoc, we may want to make like an enum or not an enum, but like a
little Define that says, what our layers are so that we don't have to,
like, constantly fuss with them.
Okay?
So, now, what we want to do now that we've kind of got that stuff
straightened away and presumably the still works properly with the
double sorting.
Yeah.
Like, I just want to make sure that it could still add things on so
that's all good.
The other thing that I want to be able to do here,
Is I would like this to not clip.
Right?
So the reason that it is clipping is because at the moment we push on
a clip direct cliprect whenever we draw one of those windows and I
want to like sort of temporarily undo that clip rect.
So, when we push these on, I want no clipping.
And in order to do that, what I would need to do here is say, well,
oops.
Let's see, William button.
Add tooltip, it's not here to pee clip.
We just need to do this, right?
So this is this stuff has to happen, where we would sort of cycle
through the clip Rex really quickly.
So,
To do this.
It's really basically the same procedure we were doing before, we
would just say, oh hey, if you don't mind, I'd like you to use the
default clip rect
And then later on.
Will restore it.
Right.
And so then all we have to do is, is remember when we start up in our
debug start code, we just want to record what that default cliprect
was.
What I call it.
The reason I couldn't autocomplete it because I spelled it wrong the
first time default cliprect.
So that way, we always know what the default cliprect actually is and
can toggle back to it anytime we want to
and that's makes it easy for us to decide that any particular thing
can quickly be clipped to some other, some other thing.
So, we don't have the render group in here, but that's okay, because
that's part of the main debug state.
I'm just going to grab it.
I guess we did.
I just missed it.
There we go.
And so now I think we should be good to go with these guys.
So there we go.
It extends outside, like I wanted and that's all good.
So I think we're pretty set now.
Yeah.
oh,
but I might not restoring that properly.
What did I do?
Double check.
So I store the old clip.
Rect
I get out the index of what's currently the active clipping system.
I set the new one to whatever.
The default one was, I do my text operation and then I set
and then I set it back.
What did I do in correctly?
Let's find out.
Current clip rep.
Oops, that's not good typing.
All right, clip index equals
Yeah, so we did our push Rick bands.
Here we get this current clip rect and so we should be able to refer
to that.
Whatever we want.
Oh, I'm in the wrong function.
That would do it.
In case you were wondering.
I'm supposed that just says that.
No text will ever be clipped.
So big surprise.
It wasn't.
So actually, I want it in here is the place that I actually wanted to
change the clip rect and scroll out from behind my head.
So, actually, this is what I wanted to do, and so that's much better.
So what I'd like to do here is say, give me the render group, so we
can call it the way we were calling it and then I think that's about
it.
So now are clipping is restored to proper working order, and we're not
clipping in here when we don't want to be, which is also nice.
So that seems pretty nice.
Okay.
Yeah.
So I think we're almost done.
We've got about 10 minutes left if I'm not very much an error.
And what was I going to do here?
I need to think of what I actually was going to.
Oh right?
I wanted the route to print out arbitrary stuff so that we could have,
you know, some kind of a
And idea of what was going on, even when the debug system was in its
fully collapsed State and not drawing anything in particular.
So what I might want to do there is say the that piece of UI that's
like
Can't remember what we said, it was this, basically, this stuff here,
where would you, you know, viewing frame time.
And we sort of do this last frame.
Info stuff.
I think that what I want to do is maybe make this
This part here be fairly straightforward.
So I can say
Well.
I think you how I do this.
I think what I probably want is just this to be an arbitrary line.
So I think what I want to do is say, okay let's just pull that piece
just that piece out into a thing that's like, you know,
print frame info or something.
Well.
I'll be honest, you know, I think I'm just going to do it separate
because I don't know.
We're probably going to want them to be different.
So we'll leave that guy as he is and I'll just I'll grab this out.
And what I'm thinking here is that the route, you know, when we when
we add this thing, you can see that we add a variable link here and we
have its size is, is it for?
And it says route and that's what gets printed right?
But what I'd like to do instead is I'd like to make a buffer where
And print stuff in general.
So what I'd rather do now is say, okay, let's give it effectively a
fake pointer.
Let's just kind of mess with it, right?
Let's say, hey I know you think you've got a specific pointer here.
I'm here to tell you that sorry you're actually wrong.
I'm going to make its length zero for now, and I'm going to make its
pointer
Actually point to a block of memory, we can use for whatever we want.
So here is the debugger Arena.
Just go ahead and give me, you know, some chunk of memory.
That's what we're going to print out to that string, right?
It's not.
Is it not named length?
What's the or is it just actually you know what?
I think it's just
It just works this way, right?
Yeah.
So now if I did a Sprint, one of these sprintf sin here.
Where those guys are?
One of these guys.
So now if I was to do something in here,
oops.
we should be able to just printf into this thing with abandon
I think anyway does not take three arguments, it's just that
the thing where I have to cast this to something first,
Because I thought it does or maybe it needs one more.
Sighs t.i.
Okay.
What why do we have?
We have to get rid of that function.
Maybe what we're doing tomorrow is getting rid of the stupid uh
getting rid of that stupid C runtime Library nonsense.
It never pays through the C runtime Library.
It's always frustrating.
Anyway point being
For the time being since we're stuck with it, let's find out s and
printf.
We've had this problem multiple times with it.
So it does text size of text and then the formats string.
So, what if I said size of
Just debug stay here.
What if I just said that it work still does not does not take three
arguments.
So what is it?
It doesn't like
so what if I just do this?
So that works fine.
Right that works.
Now I want to say, hey, let's take name put that in there and now it
doesn't work.
So is named just something that I've forgotten that is not actually a
care star.
So name is a character.
It's right there.
So, what's the problem?
Why won't you print to that?
Explain yourself.
I have no idea.
I really don't.
All right.
What's going on here people?
Tell me what the problem is.
So we've got, which one are we doing?
We're doing SN printfs.
So, that's the care.
Star buffer, the size to size of buffer, the size, T the count.
And then the format.
That's not how we were calling it, which is interesting.
Okay, so and I remember this this sounds very familiar, sometimes we
had to pass it twice and sometimes only once apparently there must be
an overloaded function that differentiates between them.
Unbelievable.
All right.
Fantastic.
All right, so now we should actually have this thing.
Thanks so much.
Now, this is the most for the I just, this is why I hate using other
code.
It never makes any sense to me, and it's always like does not work the
way that I would think of that it should anyway per frame Arena, space
is what we put that in there.
So now if I want to print out anything that I want to print out, I can
write
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to say,
let's pick a number for this buffer and in fact, we can just store it
down in here we can even say like, you know, what's the the the route
info size and although let's be honest, it's going to be 32, there's a
route info size and a route info.
And so now we can just always use those.
So we can say in here
State Route info.
Debug State Route, info size debug state,
Route info size because you might as well pass it multiple times.
And this is some stuff.
Then we just set this thing.
Like so.
And now we have a printable buffer that we can just dump stuff into
any time that we want, which is what I wanted.
So that's it.
That's all I was trying to get to there and now I can just add this
code to essentially every time we do a
On start.
So probably somewhere around here.
I probably would actually say right about here.
Before we do anything else then I'll just go ahead and take that draw
frame bit that we were doing here.
So essentially this code and I'll just
I'll just have that happen right here.
And
Then we could tweak what we want this to be for now.
It would be the same thing as what was in the frame.
It was in the last frame info.
But
You know, we can we can take it after that.
So this is just now are essentially our menu which actually shows, you
know, some information we actually care about which is good.
And, and so now we can kind of make that a little bit clearer.
So first of all, we can get rid of this.
There we go.
And now we just kind of got a nice little bar up there, that lets us
know what's going down and yeah and so that should be pretty clear and
I think we're based out of time so that's fine.
That's a reasonable stopping point I think
Okay.
Time for some Q&A.
Omar, what is the purpose of the internal syntax?
It's just static.
It's a pound to find to static.
So,
You can see right here.
We just do like internal aesthetic.
The reason for that is because I like tool to grep for things like
where the global variables are.
And you can't actually do like or where local persistent variables are
and since static is overloaded to mean like a bunch of different
things, I just make my own so that I can keep track of them.
Cheaper Caleb.
I love how the compiler tells you.
There is a Paramus match.
Instead of telling you a list of actual params versus the ones you
typed, it could at least try to be helpful.
Is this an unsolved problem?
Whose science llvm.
Does it correctly?
If I remember correct, if I remember, right?
Like says here is what you passed.
Here's what I was trying to match and
And I you know it lists like all the options.
I don't know if msec does that ever.
I'm not sure.
I think it does that.
I think it will do that if you have the right number of parameters,
but not the right types.
It'll do it.
But not, if you have the wrong number of parameters, who knows?
Why
What were the abbreviations in the new menu header?
So right now, like I don't know what will print out in here but this
is how many milliseconds the last frame
Took essentially, like, how long did we spend from one's called a swap
buffers to the next called a swap buffers and since V sinks on right
now, will stall out at 16 milliseconds.
So we're not actually taking 16 milliseconds, which you can see in
here like, this is just a bunch of wait time, that's not actually
relevant to anybody.
But you know, like, you can see it in here that's all just time.
We're just waiting, not doing anything.
But that's
What we want to see, so we want to see that number always stay at 16
milliseconds.
If we're, if we're trying to hit 60 frames a second for 30 frames a
second, we want see that 33.
So then these are just some things that was like 52 events, 34 profile
nodes and eight.
What are those d d is what
It's how many data blocks?
Got sunk.
So those are kind of irrelevant.
Those are just like things like
For example.
One of these things which is a bunch of entity data, like whichever
one we highlight, like let's say, we highlight that one.
Colonel Dragon people have asked before what your thoughts are.
In functional languages in general, but I'm curious what your thoughts
are specifically on the constructs, they emphasize that other
languages don't for example, closures and partial application, IE Foo,
taking, X, Y, Z, being called, with Foo X Y returning.
A closure that take Z I like them.
I like most of the constructs of functional languages.
The thing that I don't usually like about functional languages is that
they're typically built to
Too far from being able to directly do stuff on Hardware, you know.
Like, you know, taking ml or something or things that are purely
functional, and if you use a more modern one like maybe, oh, camel or
something?
I don't really know actually to what extent do camel, has it, but more
modern ones that let you do everything that see can do, but that also
have those functional elements when you want them.
Can be very nice if that makes sense.
So I like most of those I which that C++ had more of that kind of a
thing in cleaner ways.
But, you know, it doesn't.
So I don't get much, I can't speak too much of that stuff in practical
sense because I've never spent enough time programming in a functional
language to go how important to me is like currying and stuff like
that.
But I like them all, they all seem like, useful tools that I would use
if they were implemented conveniently in C++, but they're all of them
are implemented if at all extremely inconveniently in C++ and they're
just not worth it.
But in a language where they were convenient and worked, well, they
would be cool.
Does the debug bit map viewer work?
Now, when you select an entity, I don't think we've ever actually
tried to fix that.
I'm not actually sure even what I think we may have commented out, but
if you want me to fix it, that's probably not particularly hard.
So
Let's see.
So this is probably the problem we need to make sure that it shows up
on top.
So yeah, let me see what's going on here.
There you go.
Not sure.
That's showing a bitmap ID, but I don't know if it's showing the
bitmap ID.
Are we actually outputting that?
I think.
What are we actually outputting there would be my other question.
That is in here, right?
yeah, so we're always out putting the Torso
Which is not helpful for obvious reasons.
So we would have to actually output this for real in order to do
anything useful there.
Now, probably the way we would want to do this is probably not the way
that we are doing it.
Probably what we would want to do is something where we actually go.
Like okay here
The Entity, debug ID thing, let's actually go When We're looping
through it, right?
And say like, okay, we're is the entity debug ID.
Yeah.
So we probably want to do like okay you know when we're here let's
actually check up at the head end so we'd say like okay you know,
here's what is debug ID is and if you know if the if we request one of
these things then we want to open a data block and push stuff out.
Now, in this case, I guess,
We don't actually want to use the debug data block automatic thing.
We actually want to do the like a begin and data block basically.
So we would want to do you know.
What are these?
So it doesn't have to be in the same script area so it would just be
Record.
Debug event.
Debug type open data block.
And then, oops.
Down the wrong one.
And this one would be.
And they block.
So so this would just be debug begin data.
Block, then we could print out, you know, whatever we wanted to print
out.
Throughout this entire process.
And then at the end, we would do.
We would do the end data block as necessary, right?
So we'd say where is it?
Is that the right place?
so be more like,
Here.
So yeah, something like that.
you know I'm saying, and
All of these things I guess, actually can stay exactly the same.
but now stuff like we had before,
Where we want to potentially print out different bitmaps, depending
on, what's going on?
Now, those can actually and I guess technically this probably wants to
be inside here.
See here.
Storage index.
What's the question?
Oh yeah.
So now what I need to do is basically like I want to print out this
one of these bitmaps and I want to be able to do it whenever we
actually do it.
So whenever we draw stuff, if we wanted to say what we were using for
drawing here, we could like when we do these push bitmaps or whatever.
So I don't know like you know let's say when we suggest it, when we do
a wall here you can see that we do get first bitmap from so bitmap ID.
You know.
This thing.
if I wanted to,
Make that be something that was known.
Now, it could be right.
And of course we're going to keep having.
We're going to have to restart eventually because as we move the debug
code around, it's going to it's going to stack up there, right?
But where's where's that at?
But in theory,
Like if we select a tree, we should get that.
How come that is not inside the debug block?
Oh right.
Because these don't have to be inside the debug block.
So I wonder, I don't know what I want to do so that's probably
something we should make a little cleaner to than right?
Because this is the first time we've really tried to do some more
fancy stuff with how we output stuff, it would be nice to say.
If you're not inside a debug lock, the debug value, just gets ignored
Right.
And actually, to be completely honest with you, I am not sure why that
isn't happening.
But for now what I could do is say, well, let's put it.
Let's put it in here.
But that's just a little cumbersome.
So it might be nice to figure out some way to not do that.
Okay.
so that
Is roughly how this would go.
And I'll have to see like, okay, so stairwells don't have a thing
familiar is do.
Right.
I hear a bitmap head.
And I'm not sure how useful this is because I don't think we would
normally really want to do this.
I like I'm not sure why we can't
Not sure.
Why.
Moving those around caught?
I should probably look into that.
Wow, what did I do?
Go away.
Okay, there we go.
Because I'm not sure why we wouldn't.
That shouldn't still work.
Across runs.
So that should probably look at what's going on there, but anyway,
so, there's that tree and
I look at the familiar.
I want to see what happens.
Can I select the familiar?
I guess.
I can't.
Because well, you know what I could do.
I can.
See here.
Where is the false hero?
There we go.
so, if I select the familiar,
Yeah.
So I guess what I could do here, I suppose one way to make this a
little simpler.
I just don't love the way.
Yeah, I don't love the way this is working.
I think we should maybe refactor this a little bit into something a
bit cleaner because, like, also that's going to create another debug
point because they're at different places in the code.
And so I feel like we want these to probably be by name,
You know what I mean?
Look, I feel like we actually want these instead to be like debug
value.
And then we would put here what we think the grid is for this thing
and like that would be
That would be used instead of the, the sort of weird currying bit.
So, for example, if I wanted to, I could say that, you know,
Maybe it keeps just the function name and then whatever my value name
is or something like that.
So like, you know, one way I could do it is say inside debug interface
.h, when, oops, when we do debug value and it does this sort of thing.
What I could do is say let's make one of these that's like
I don't know something like named debug value or debug.
Named value, something like that, and instead of using debug name
here, it would, it would just do instead of any of that would just do
like, you know, what's the function?
And then this value name,
You know.
Something like that.
So that way when they're creating their whatever their unique
signature is it's not going to move around when you recompile and it's
not going to be different based on which part of the code it's in.
So I can write to the same debug value in a couple different ways.
So there's the tree,
Turn The Familiar on, right?
There's the tree and there's the familiar course.
I'm so
Seeing the familiar head show up, which I'm not sure why.
It should be doing hero bitmaps head.
Why am I not?
Why am I still alive?
Still generating another 10 because I didn't call that a name debug
value because I'm pretty stupid.
So that's good.
That's what I actually wanted.
Let me see where this is actually debug event text.
Why are we getting?
That bug.
I'm curious to know because that shouldn't be happening.
I thought we fixed that possibility of having a the changeover go
wrong during Kool-Aid debug records.
Like I thought that was I thought that was handled in here where we
completed all the work and we did the reload after debug frame end so
that we should never have any events in the buffer that would be
problematic.
That's a little weird, right?
What are we drawing when we call debug draw element?
Where we getting this value from?
Hmm.
So this is in side one of our elements that we are drawing.
What kind of event is, it's just a random generic piece of data.
I guess is that even?
Is that even supposed to work?
Is that, let's see here, when we call debug event to text and we're
taking the events grid.
Is that the value that actually gets cloned or not?
When we store an event.
What actually happens to the grid.
so, when we do a get element from event,
That is where we do the push string.
But if you don't go through, get element from event.
Or the event itself because that's in the element.
so, I think this is just
An oversight, right?
Like this is not.
This is just not right because whenever we process an event we have to
translate it over when we do.
You know, when we make it into an element, we have to overwrite the
events.
We would have to overwrite the event squid or just never print out the
events grid and always use whatever the one is in the element, right?
So I'm not sure what we wanted to do there.
I'm not sure.
I mean, I guess technically, this is all fine.
To a certain extent, we just have to know that we don't print those
out and we were still printing them out for some reason.
So, for example, when we come in here and we're talking about this
event, we really need to be talking about printing that element.
So when we call event to text, we really need to be saying, what the
element is that we're printing in addition to the event, right?
We would need to pass that.
And I'm not sure.
So this was just, I'm not sure why that would just.
We never, we're never printing out many of those I guess.
So we never saw that happen.
But that's clearly wrong because you're not allowed to get that.
You're not allowed to access that, that's not valid at that point.
So I'm not sure why that was
Why that was ever happening?
But it was.
All right.
So, let's take a look here.
Let's have the
Tree there.
There's the the okay.
So now we can write to those reliably, which is fine.
That's all good.
but we'd have to make sure our selection stuff works a little bit more
solidly, I think, because right now, we're ignoring the selection, we
only use the highlighting
Which doesn't make much sense, but we're now back to back to.
Okay, there.
So yeah, inside the debug CPP code the for drawing the bitmap
Oops, map ID.
For drawing this stuff.
I think we also want in here, we do like a push wrecked on the backing
transform.
I think that's what we want to do.
For this guy as well.
So instead of no transform, I think that's supposed to be the backing
transform and
This all needs to be written to that layer, so that it's not getting
over written by people who are in the foreground.
And then, I think that's it.
Let's see here.
Yeah.
So, there we go.
Tuning basemen.
Are we going to make a bitmap of the memory that is used or unused?
And when we select a unit show, where it in the memory Arena, it is
I mean that would not be particularly hard to do, but I'm not sure
that there would be any reason to do it.
but you certainly could do it if you wanted to write, it's not
you know, it's not
it's not particularly well, I mean here.
So if you wanted to show
Arena's of some kind.
Right?
What you'd want to do is inside the debug interface, you'd want to be
able to say that.
One of the things that you were going to view was an arena, right?
So you'd want to have
On here that was like, debug type Arena.
You know what I mean?
And this would probably be just like, Arena occupancy, I guess, or
something like that.
And then when you go to draw, you know, where we have the same stuff
that we were drawing before, like frame bar graphs, and that kind of
stuff.
You'd have one in here that was like, here's the arena occupancy and I
gotta draw that, you know, and it would be pretty similar to this code
in here.
Probably I'm guessing.
What do you do?
You do real similar stuff.
You know, at this point I guess we don't have any buttons but you'd
probably have some there.
This would be like an arena
And Arena graph or something.
It stores, whatever the information is we need for that thing.
This stuff would be roughly the same.
Probably like
you know, basically the same thing, I don't know and
Rabe Boop's.
And then probably you do the exact same thing here where you just say
like, okay, I'm going to draw an arena.
I can probably draw in a couple different ways, we don't know what
those ways are yet, but I'll just make a switch statement here where
we can put them.
And so then we'd say like drawer Arena occupancy and then there'd be
the, you know, the exact same stuff that we were passing before.
So be real similar.
In this case, it's a little unclear.
Like what, how you get the arena.
So, I'm guessing probably the way that would work is in the debug
interface, when you pass the stuff in, this would you'd actually be
able to pass an arena pointer, right?
So, you know, the arena would actually go in here somewhere and it
would be a pointer to the arena.
So it would be Loops, it'd probably be
You know, I can just live there and you know I don't even remember
what we call Arenas these days just Arena.
It's called a memory Arena.
And so if you have a memory, read a pointer and blah, blah blah and
stuff and whatever.
Then you know, when you go through one of those, you can print it out
if there is one for it.
And so the Arena's are presumably stable over time, right?
They don't come and go.
So we probably don't need to make a lot of code that tries to figure
out where they are or what they are.
We can probably just say like when you draw the arena occupancy,
This is all the same, I guess.
I assume you do draw Arena occupancy, you know what we would do then
is we just say like okay we need to get that Arena pointer so we just
see, you know, we'd make sure that we could where's the root element.
We'd make sure that we'd say like okay, whatever one we're on right
now.
We hope that there is a stored event for it that we can look at if
that makes sense.
And and we would draw that, right?
So we'd say like, okay,
Inside this event.
Yeah, so inside this event, we have an arena so it'd be more like if
there was if we did find the event, then we have a memory Arena
That we can draw here and, you know, we can say like, you know,
there's going to be, I don't know.
A rectangle and the rectangle is going to be like this is the frame
rack, let's call it.
So this is going to be you know it's got the frame wrecked Min EX
And the frame Rex and why?
And the frame wrecked Max X and the frame wrecked.
Max Y, and, you know.
So okay.
There's like, oops.
I guess I don't know why I wouldn't just pass.
Pray, McMinn!
it's kind of stupid but anyway so you know maybe we start by just
saying, let's Draw, Something simple, so we'll say, okay, we've got
Like the used wrecked and the unused wrecked or something and so then
we've got like the two rectangles and we want to set the max X of this
one to the split point and the Minix of this one to the split point.
So we're kind of drawing two rectangles there and then you know we
draw
The two rectangles like so one of them is the used wrecked.
One of them is the unused wrecked.
Don't care about this stuff at all, and, you know, the used rectangle.
We draw in, you know, yellow or orange or something, I don't know.
And the use rectangle be drawn green because because we can,
Something like that.
Is this not a known thing?
Probably not.
Okay, so let's see.
The split point is not particularly complicated.
The split point is just a linear blend between the frame wrecked,
right?
And what do we call that?
We have that in our math Ops somewhere here.
Oops.
I always forget it.
Slurp.
There it is.
So we want to lurk between the frame.
Wrecked Min X, and the frame wrecked.
Max X.
And we want to do that based on the memory Arena.
This particular memory Arenas like used to unused if that makes sense.
So you know a memory Arenas, got a size and a used.
So we'd say like okay whatever you know.
Whatever and I'm using in our city for her.
Because maybe these would be really big values.
So, whatever this Arenas size is is the total amount that it could
take and I want to divide out how much we actually abuse so far in it
you know I'm saying?
And yeah, and I got to convert that back to a R32 eventually.
As well.
I suppose.
All right, so then we've got just some cleanup to do here.
And we got to make a storage for these in case we want everyone to
edit them.
So what I'll do here is I'm just going to copy these guys and make a
debug View.
Arena graph.
There is no quit the moment for it but you know, there could be
eventually.
So here's the arena graph.
Just have to add that in.
Like so and then we've got viewing Elements which is an Undeclared.
Identifier that's correct.
It is jumped me to there.
So viewing element is actually presumably just going to come from the
element that were actually on right now.
So this is probably just element, right?
So yeah, so now we have the ability to put one of those things in
there.
So maybe we start off by saying inside here, where we have, like,
where we put the profile, you know, I'm going to put debug data block
and inside here.
We'll just put one of these UI elements.
In the UI element is going to be debug Type R, Enoch b c and that's
the arena.
Or something and we've got two of these.
So actually, that needs to take a data member, right?
It's actually debug value.
Now that I think about it, it's actually a debug value here.
And these are the two Arenas that we have.
So,
I guess we actually want to come down here and make sure that
everything is initialized.
And then once it is, when we get down here then I might say here is
the memory after all initialization happens.
Oops.
And then I need to just output these two Arenas.
So we have the memory and I want to Output the translate Train Arena.
That's the transient Arena.
And I want to do the gamestate /.
Marina.
Or whatever it's called.
So, we've got a motor Arena and audio Arena.
And the transient Arena.
Right.
All right.
Oh, and by the way, this is what someone's talking about.
It does see how it shows you the possible matches or whatever so
that's all good.
Anyway so if I then go into debug interface and I add the ability to
print these out so something that actually knows what one of those is
good going here.
So there's a memory Arena.
We go value memory arena is not true.
It's not
Forgot my convention for all of this.
Here we go.
Cannot convert member Arena to memory in a star.
There's a reason for that.
It's because I didn't type it into star because I messed up.
So, actually, I want this to be that.
although, I don't know if that's actually going to work here, so
Hmm.
Yeah, that's unfortunate.
That basically means I need 20 most I need to use like Hungarian
tation because memory arena is going to have to take a pointer to it.
So it's basically like a memory Arena pointer if that makes sense,
which is kind of annoying because there's no, yeah, that's just the
again, the see Miss of it all being super annoying.
So not a huge deal but just kind of annoying because I have to do
typedef
Memory Arena, star memory Arena P.
Like I have to be able to do that.
Otherwise it's not going to know.
It can't do all of its automatic type stuff that we had to push
through the macrosystem because that's what we had to work with.
So yeah.
So, there should be one of those now.
Do you bug value set the event data?
And there should be a memory in a pea and I would think it should have
been able to find that.
Yet, I don't see it.
Ah, because it needs to take an address that is why and I did not take
an address.
So this should be here here and here.
There we go.
I don't know why.
There's a double Ampersand happening there.
Did I mess up something in debug value.
Let's double-check.
Where where would that be?
Value.
So, this needs to be wrapped.
And I think that's it.
So what requires an l-value.
Okay?
So it doesn't want that doesn't want to take the address of that,
which I can understand because
you're not really allowed to to take the address of the pointer in
that way.
Like we don't usually generally sinks pointers for this reason.
But
Yeah, I guess we could say.
This is not editable.
Oops.
We could just say leave it as is.
Although that's not going to work either because we do it.
We do dereference it up here.
So I'm not sure I'm really not sure of a good way to make that work.
I mean, I guess what I could do.
Since it's only one with one timer, we do it here.
I could do something where I say,
That.
And again, this stuff is all this is all just super annoying nonsense.
This is just because C++ gives a lousy language.
So it's not like this is actually anything that you would ordinarily
care about doing it.
Just when you try to actually do stuff that compiles out and stuff
like that, or that does automatic type determination, see either you
go into template land where nothing ever works correctly, because when
you get down to the last part of it, there's something you can't make
work.
Early or you go macros, which will eventually work properly, but are
super ugly anyway.
So let's see.
This is value memory Arena p.
And now we actually have the memory Rina.
So when we were drawing the arena occupancy, this is the default, I
guess, for one of these things.
and,
I guess we could even sort of take a cue from this bit right here and
say, like, okay,
Occupancy.
And if I run this now in theory, we should have like a memory thing
and it's got our Arenas in it which is fine.
And if I say that, I want to see the occupancy for something
We should be able to actually see what it is.
Now I probably should print out the name of these things because
otherwise we're not be able to see what's happening in any of them.
So there's that, obviously, but now we sort of have the basics of
drawing an arena and we could we're kind of way over time at this
point.
But this is, you know, the basics of how that would happen.
So, in a particular Arena,
Which honestly don't know that we even need to quite do it this way.
There's probably some other way things we could do up to think about
how we should do that.
Maybe we can do that tomorrow.
If this is something that interests people, but the debugger Arenas in
general, when we draw them,
I would like to be able to see what the name of that Arena was Hoops,
so where we were doing that.
Here we go.
So where we were doing that here, I might want to do like just a label
sort of a thing where we do.
Whatever the name of this guy is so the element.
Name starts at I think orser, is it get name?
if there was a get name or something like that,
Yeah, it's just get name.
So if you want to print out the name of this element, so we can tell
what it is.
We could do that in the same way that we were doing the other things
here.
And so if I take, for example, the Boolean button code, what I want to
do is make one of these.
That actually doesn't do anything, so there's no interaction, but it
can print out a label.
So it prints out the name.
There's no interaction here.
I don't know, do we have a null interaction?
No.
Do now and then we do the basic text element, I'm thinking more like,
yeah, there's none of that stuff and it's always white, like there's
no highlighting to it or anything.
So it's just
White all the time.
Yeah.
It's white all the time like Donald Trump's America.
Okay.
So label and an entire not found, that's because I didn't change the
name of this but I should have.
And now in theory like you can see which one of these are, there's the
motor Arena, there's the audio Arena, there's the transient Arena, and
so we would have to start doing now is like recording, what gets
allocated in those and actually laying them out, which we could do.
And maybe we'll do that tomorrow.
If that's something that people want to see, it's not
Hard.
Probably.
What we'll do is we would actually have the Arena's become their own
debug elements, then we just store the allocation events probably
inside them, I would suspect, but yeah.
There is a little bit of nuance to it because unlike other things,
these Arenas, they they have like stuff that gets pushed and popped.
So we would probably actually keep.
We wouldn't flush their stored event information over time, we would
probably keep it.
And so that would be a little bit.
A little bit different.
Thanks sense.
It's like there were no other questions during that time that I can
see.
Yeah.
All right.
Um so yeah, I'm going to close down for now because I want to have
some food.
I'm hungry so I'm going to stop for the day.
Thanks everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade.
He wrote some pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here at or it comes to the source code
so you can play around with it and learn from it.
We also have a forum so you can go to ask questions and that Forum
will be going down this weekend.
I mistakenly said it was going down last weekend, but I was then told
that
It was not last weekend.
It's this coming weekend.
This.
Weekend.
The handmade Network people are going to take it over on their server.
Because honestly, I don't like administering for him, so I'm happy to
have them go somewhere else, so that will be happening this weekend
and they'll be down for a while while that's happening.
But hopefully next week, they'll be up and back.
We have a patreon page transport the video series, it's always much
appreciated.
We also have a tweet bot, the tweets, the schedule at you.
Now, with Unix startup script magic.
So it actually will always come back up.
Even if the server gets rebooted and that's about it.
I'll be back here tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time.
Time for some more, handmade hero, fun.
And hope to see you here, until then have fun programming.
I'll see you guys on the it, take it easy.