Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero the show where we could
complete game live on stream, except for tonight.
And the reason for that is we have come to the point.
They don't happen that often on the stream, but we have come to the
point where we need to explain computer science.
Fundamental, and so, today is going to be one of those days where we
talked about at on the Whiteboard or Blackboard in this case.
And so we're not really doing it again program right now.
We are really just going to
Talking about that.
So, if you care about what order notation is or rather, if you don't
know if you care, that's really the more important part.
If you don't know if you care or don't like you haven't, you don't
have a real firm enough grass.
Want to know whether you care or not.
This is probably the place to because you will have that answer in
just a few short minutes.
So, let's go ahead and get started on that and I will, I will go over
here to the Blackboard day, too.
3231 order notation.
All right, my first, I want to start off with a really big caveat,
which is to say that people who do like, sort of the formal discipline
of computer science care about these sort of things a lot.
And in fact, order notation is just a very small scratch of the
surface of the sorts of theoretical Computing, things that they care
about.
I am not a theoretical computer scientist.
And so, all of the things that I'm going to say on this stream Are For
the Working programmer.
If you will, we are going to be talking about order notation from the
To have someone who's trying to make code run on a machine and cares
about its performance characteristics.
That is not all there is to this story.
And so a number of the things that I say are going to be very
simplified or they're not going to really go as far as you would want
to go if you actually care about theoretical computer science.
So what I would say is as we are going through this if you find
yourself curious about these sorts of things are feel like you're kind
of interested in it.
In general, you may be interested in can in theoretical computer.
ER science just as a discipline and I would encourage you to go read
more about it or watch some lectures online.
Maybe people have some recommendations they'll post on the handmade
hero forums that you could look for to learn more about it because it
is a really interesting field.
It's not one that necessarily has immediate ramifications for what we
do day to day all the time.
But sometimes it does.
And you know I wouldn't be talking about it if it didn't have
ramifications what we're working on right now in our code for example
but it's also just a theoretically interesting thing.
And so if you do find that
Please don't think that what I'm saying here tonight is really the
full picture.
It's not, it's just the basics to help you understand how to apply it
and how to use it.
The more richer more interesting parts of it are you know, well beyond
my computer science background certainly and they're best left to
someone who's a professional in that field.
So that caveat aside, let's talk about order notation.
You've seen it even on this stream.
We've mentioned it, briefly and I gave her door capsule overview of
it.
But I want to sort of get it out of the way.
Now, once and for all, and we're on sorting, which is kind of a
classic place for this thing would be covered.
So let's talk about that.
Now you've seen order a notation before, probably something like this.
Typically, it has a no a large 0 Capital that it's not a zero.
It is an oh, and it's got a parenthesis and then there's something in
the parentheses oftentimes involving an end.
Then it can involve other things too, but oftentimes will see
something like this and people will often say it to, they'll say, oh,
that's 0n, or they'll say, oh, and squared, right?
You'll hear them.
Say this out loud.
When they say, oh, and squared, they're talking about that, right?
So people will typically say the oh, and then they'll say, what's in
the parentheses and that is what they're talking about.
And we've talked about this on handmade here on, we've used the term
but we never covered in detail.
So what is it?
What is this notation?
Really me.
Why do we care?
Blah, blah blah, right?
Okay, what this is is it's an attempt to talk about how an algorithm
scales with the amount of work that you expect it to do.
So what we talk about when we talk about work is we typically talk
about like some kind of a unit and the unit is what's represented by
n.
And so for example, we're talking about sorting right now.
The number of individual elements that you expect to sort might be
like the single
The unit that we're talking about here, that refers to n.
So when we say, n in the content in sort of the context of order
notation, what we're saying is, how many units of work do you expect
us to do in the sort?
How many things do you expect to be sorted?
If you give me a list of 10 things to sort?
Then, in terms of order notation typically, that means that the N when
we say, N means that 10 right.
Okay.
Now, why do we say n?
Why don't we just say 10?
Well, the reason is because typically when we're talking about order
notation we want to know how something scales.
So we're inherently saying, we don't know, we don't want to say ahead
of time.
How many work units were doing?
We want your, or we want this branch of the math to tell us how our
algorithm performs across the whole range of possible workloads.
It could be assigned and so that's where the end comes from.
The end, comes from a saying, we're not going to say ahead of
Time.
How many work units we want to do.
We want you to tell us something about this algorithm so that we have
an idea of how it will perform?
As we scale up the amount of work,
Very, very basic.
Let's take it up to a slightly more complex level.
All right.
Now, if you were to just think about this from a non-computer science
standpoint from a non programming standpoint as just a naive person.
Perhaps looking at this problem you might say.
Something well like well I don't know what you mean by.
How does it scale, right?
Because in the real world typically, when we talk about specific
things, that a human might do scale, is always what you might call
linear most of the time.
Okay, what that means is that every time I ask you to do a certain
amount more work, it will take you a certain amount, more time, okay?
If I'm asking you to put stamps on envelopes.
Right then if it takes you one minute and don't ask me why to stamp
one envelope, right?
Then we would often expect it to take five minutes to Stamp five
envelopes.
That's just the kind of thing we're used to seeing as humans.
Now, it's not always true, there are things we could pick.
That wouldn't be true, right?
But I'm just trying to give you a little bit of a foothold into why it
may be not intuitive, some of the things we're talking about.
If you've never seen any of this before, if you have seen it before,
Probably into it by now but you get the idea.
Okay, so that is what we would call linear and the reason we would
call it linear, right is specifically because of this whole concept up
here if we were to write an equation that talked about or not an
equation, just an expression that talked about how long it took you to
do something.
Well this obviously is my n write.
The number of envelopes is the number of work units.
So I am talking about
n envelopes.
And if for example I made a slightly more complicated thing so it took
2 minutes per envelope so it took 10 minutes, 45 right.
Then you could easily just just if you've had any math at all,
instantly tell me how long it takes to do n envelopes, correct?
You would say it takes two minutes.
Times on N, right?
That is the time right?
And furthermore I might leave the units in there and say and envelopes
at 2 minutes per envelope.
The envelopes cancel and I just get to end minutes.
Right.
That is why we might say it is linear because the factor, right?
The, the exponent I should say, not the factor.
The exponent on our n is 1, right?
It's linear.
It looks when I graph it, like a line here is my, you know, number of
envelopes, here are my minutes and this goes up and I said it was too,
and so it's probably a little more like that, right?
But it's a line.
Okay.
Now, if all the things huge humans did that are typical like this.
If that was all that computers ever wanted to do, we probably never
would have developed order notation at all.
In fact, we probably wouldn't care and I wouldn't be suspending this
stream time explaining it to you.
But computers often do things that are much more complicated than what
humans are expected to do.
In fact, that's why we have
Peter's, if they didn't then why do we even have them?
Right.
And oftentimes, what happens is we will produce algorithms that are
not linear
So let's take an example of what that might be and I'll give you an
example of how it could happen even in the human world.
I am going to give you an envelopes like I did before.
And now what I want you to do.
Is I want you to go through and tell me if any of these two envelopes
are addressed to the same person.
Right.
I would like you to check to see if the address on any given envelope
matches the address on any other envelope.
And if it does, I want you to tell me.
Very simple, right?
Well, even if you're a human, you've got a problem, the most naive way
to do.
This might be to pick up one envelope and look at all the other
envelopes.
One at a time and see if they match if they don't.
You know, that that envelope is fine and you put it aside, you then
pick up the next one and you go through it.
How long would that take you?
Right.
Well, you can imagine if we could quantify the amount of time, it took
you to look at one at one address and the other artists and see if
they match.
Let's say it took something like five seconds to do that, so five
seconds per pair,
Then we would simply need to know how many of those do you have to do?
Well, you're going to take the first envelope, right?
And you're going to compare it to all the other envelopes.
That would be n of these comparisons, right?
So, that's n comparisons for the first envelope alone.
Then we would have to add to that, right?
We put that envelope aside, we don't need to look at anymore.
We pick up the next one and we'd have to look for through all of them.
So now, how many pairs are there again?
Well, you know, ahh.
We have one less pair so really, it would be something like n minus 1,
right?
And we keep going all the way down, right?
Until we got, you know, to just the till we got this all the way down
just to one, right?
There's got to be a minus 1.
N minus 2 and minus 3, m as far as fought until they got all the way
till this was n, right?
And so, if you look what happens as this kind of goes out and out and
out depending on how big it is.
What you can see here is that if we were to add up all of the ends,
right?
If I was to distribute here, I'd get n and this is the plus and minus
1 plus n minus 2.
I'm going to get as many ends because remember, I've got as many terms
here, I've got n minus one of these terms, right?
Because this till I get in all the way down to zero, I'm going to I
gotta keep going and so that means there will be n.
N terms.
Or N squared, right?
Which
That the number of envelope pairs, I have to look at is going to be
proportional to N squared.
Now, there's a subtraction in here, right?
I have n minus 1 times n as well.
That gets removed from there, but, you know, I'm sorry not and and
minus 1, I have n, minus 1, the constant that gets removed from their
right because these these constants get removed from their right, but
those don't actually subtracting a single end from an N squared, is
just going to give you
You, you know, N squared minus n or something like this, right?
It's going to only get, take away a very small amount.
And so typically, when we're working on the order, notation for
something, meaning, how long we expect something to happen?
Often times, you don't even really care about that part of it, if that
makes sense.
Right.
And so, usually this part is the only part we concentrate on now.
Why is that?
Why is that the only part that becomes pretty well.
First, let me just observe, this is the nonlinear part here, right?
The fact that we now have an exponent on this thing, that is not
One that means that this is nonlinear in the amount of work that we
have to do even for a human, right?
A human has to do this much work.
There's nothing special about it being a computer or otherwise.
So, somewhere around the proportion and squared is the amount of work
you might expect to do.
And so if it took five seconds, prepare your thinking of something
like 5 Seconds, right time?
Something like N squared if you want to be precise, maybe you do N
squared.
Minus n, minus 1, minus 1, or
Like that.
Maybe you try to make a little more accurate, but this is about as
accurate need to be for our purposes.
So even if you didn't have something, that was this clean, as long as
whatever.
The thing is that you created.
As long as you could clearly, see how many n terms there would be,
that would be enough for our purposes.
So anyway, so just ignore that for now because like I said, it's not
important, you'll see why in a second, but point being it be something
like 5 seconds on the order of N squared, right?
So B 5n squared seconds and that's how much work you would expect it
to be for us.
An envelope comparisons.
Now, why do we care about that?
Well, the reason we care about that is because you'd imagine what
graph shape.
This might be here was the graph shape of something that was linear
and as you can see as we add more work to do, we spend more time in
exactly that proportion.
Okay.
But if we had something that was N squared, that's going to look like
a parabola, right?
It's going to look like this.
And it gets to a point where it's extremely extremely steep the
difference in computing power or human power.
In this case human time you know this might be an hour but just add a
few more envelopes and all of a sudden you're at two hours, right?
Whereas before that same number of envelopes, added would only cost
you another five minutes or something.
Let's say, right?
So what that means is there's a very real
All difference.
These two tasks and the conceptual difference is that in the linear
case, I can always without even knowing how many envelopes were
talking about.
I can always tell you the exact amount of time extra you will need to
do a certain number more envelopes.
It's always the same want to do five more envelopes.
It's 10 more minutes with anything that is super linear, right?
It's not end to the first.
It send to the second and the third end of the 10th.
Heaven, help you.
No longer true.
Now, there is a Breaking Point in the algorithm.
There is a point where the curve gets so steep that even just adding a
single extra envelope would be so expensive that you could never hope
to do it.
Right.
That's the bummer of super linear algorithms.
Now, let's go back down here to what we're talking about with order
notation.
Hopefully, now you can start to see why we might care about the
concept of order notation because order notation is precisely the
thing that boils things down into how long we expect them to take as
they scale.
So when we say that something is 0 and we are talking about the linear
case.
When we say that something is O N squared we are talking about the
squared case, we are literally talking
About the things we just did in our simple examples.
So in Auto and algorithm can be expected to be scaled, very
gracefully.
As I add more things, I spend more time.
Exactly proportional to the number of things I added, and I can keep
doing that forever without ever expecting to hit a Breaking Point.
The time just keeps going up proportionally and off I go, right?
Very very predictable, very stable, very easy to deal with
it's nice.
As soon as I start talking about something that doesn't have that that
is super linear and then has something in that exponent bad news.
That's very bad news and the reason that it's bad news is because that
N squared means that there will be a breaking point, I don't know
where it is but somewhere there will be a breaking point where I will
no longer be able to add Computing resources or human Manpower
whatever it is that I'm feeding into this algorithm fire.
I will some point reach that point of the Curve.
Where the game is over, right?
And it's here and just adding even one more envelope just cause this
ridiculous amount of nastiness, right?
Whereas I was used to doing it here so I'm scaling I'm scaling I'm
scaling oh it's kind of working in an up forget it now it's like it's
just everything ground to a halt and I can never process any more
envelopes.
Right.
So that is the basic idea behind order notation.
It's to say, let's break an algorithm down into the fundamental size
of its input.
How many work units is it expected to do?
And then let's classify it based on how it will scale.
Now, you'll notice what I didn't include in the order notation is
something like this.
Five seconds here, right?
None of that stuff made it down here, why?
Because I don't care, right?
I just don't care.
I'm talking about how it scales.
Now, that doesn't mean that CS doesn't ever talk about this?
It does often times, it will say, well, there's a constant Factor,
right?
So when I say some things, Owen school.
Oh, and rather or O?
N squared, what?
I'm really talking about you.
Ali.
Is that it?
So some constant times n or o some constant and squared and they will
talk about that when they actually do their proofs and elevations,
they will often even compute what the sea is in some sort of you know,
if they're talking about some abstract machine they might even
included who knows right?
But the reason that we don't actually care about that very much when
we're talking about order notation is because order notation is about
how things scale and the constant doesn't affect
Scaling the constant just affects how bad the overall cost is right.
But it doesn't change where that Breaking Point really, is because the
breaking point is about the steepness of this curve or sorry.
The change I should say, in steepness of this curve over time.
And if I was to elongate, if I was to multiply this curve by some
constant, yes, the curve, you know, gets more like that or whatever,
but the general scaling,
You know, sort of look of the curve doesn't change.
It doesn't go like that.
For example, where the breaking point happens when it sooner.
It's just a gradual sort of stretching of the curve that that's keeps
its exact same shape.
Right.
So typically you know yes, does the constant Factor matter to people
when we're implementing?
Absolutely.
Because that constant Factor when we start to talk about algorithms is
how many instructions it takes to do each and
Raishin of this Loop or things like that, right?
So we do care about the constant Factor coming Plantation time but
when we want to talk about how something scales, we don't care what
the constant is.
We just want to know this because that's the answer to the scaling
question.
The performance question is more complicated that involves the
constant Factor but the scaling doesn't.
And so what you know is that if you have a no anything no matter what
the constant is, it's scales.
It may be really slow but it's never going to hit a point where it
becomes drastically more slow, right?
It's always going to be the same amount slow when I add new stuff and
squared not true.
Could be extraordinarily extraordinarily fast.
Very, very low constant but I can give you enough items until we're
adding one more to it would be a breaking point for you no matter how
fast the algorithm is.
And that's the important part to internalize about order notation.
It's telling you
How something?
Tails out to Infinity like as we add more and more and more units,
what will happen to this thing and the constant doesn't come into play
there.
The constant just is a thing that talks about the reality of a
specific implementation and how fast it will run for a given number of
units.
Yes.
But in terms of knowing whether it will scale not relevant.
Okay.
So how does this translate into code?
Well, it's very, very simple to understand how this translates into
code.
Actually, it's a for our Loop, basically, I mean, essentially you can
think of things as being that simple.
It's like okay I've got a for I Loop I'm going to say for I equals 0,
you know I is less than you know n plus plus I that is 0 n right?
I am going
Iterate over and items.
Done.
This is a know.
Anything.
It will scale.
Linearly everyone's happy.
What if I do this for J, equals 0.
J less than n + + J.
And now this is where my algorithm takes place.
Uh-oh, there's an end Loop.
This is an end Loop, right?
Every time I go through this loop, I have to go through all in items
again, suddenly we've Hit N squared, right?
And so really, it does directly translate conceptually in to coat.
It is not a purely theoretical thing.
It is all theory that you can use in a pure Theory sense, but it
actually is exactly translatable into code.
It's the loops in your code right?
Or some you could write it with tail, recursion.
There's nothing a recursive functions have this property, as well.
Like, how many times will, they were curse?
That's also could be an N, right?
But Basics Loops, how many nested Loops do you have one level of
nested Loop on2 levels of nested loops and squared, three levels and
Cubed and forth and so on and and so on, right?
All right, so that's that's the basics of order notation.
Okay, let me tell you a few other things about it.
Let me check my time.
I've got about a half an hour.
So let me tell you a little bit more about it so that you can have a
little bit of a foothold into it.
If you would like to go explore it, more on your own because like I
said, it's a very, very rich theoretical area that computer scientists
are working on all the time and you may find interesting to go read
about some of the stuff that they've done, okay?
So there's other things.
So let's talk about first that 0n.
What does it really talk about, right?
Well, this may be a very simplistic view of what it might look like in
the code, because maybe there's a break statement in here, right?
And that break statement is inside some, if, and that if
Vigorous sometimes that means that when I run this program I may not
actually execute N squared.
Loop iterations.
I may exclude only one I get in there and break immediately.
I may execute and I may execute all in squared, I don't know, right?
And so it's important to think about what we actually mean when we say
0 n 0, N squared, what the Big O notation actually refers to is worst
case.
Running time.
And I shouldn't really say that that's what the Big O stands for, what
I probably should say it again you really want to go read up about
this if you want to be very specific.
I don't get very pedantic about these things but if you want to you
you're going to want to go read everything, right?
But what I should say is when people throw around the term 0, N
squared.
Winnie average programmer says that to you, what they mean is the
worst-case running time of this algorithm is O N squared.
Oh, and whatever the oh is that they set, right?
So 0 N means worst-case running time.
That means in the case where this break gets hit as late as it
possibly could given all possible inputs.
This thing accepts
How long will it run?
Okay, it's N squared right?
That's the worst case.
Sometimes through it might be better, it might be better than having
squared.
So it doesn't mean when I say that something is 0, m squared, I don't
mean that it always takes a win squared.
I mean that it might.
And again the reason that we typically use that as the metric is
because we're talking about scaling, we want to know how this
algorithm scales, we don't care how it performs because that's a
different discipline.
We care about what we can guarantee.
How does it scale in the worst conditions?
Because that's what we want to know about.
That's what tells us how heavy this algorithm can handle, right?
The worst case.
That's what we're looking for.
They don't only look at those.
There's things that are like best-case running times, right?
There's things that are like average running time.
And this is typically called expected.
Ryan times meaning.
Well, the worst cases, O N squared, but we expect it will only be 0 n.
What does that mean?
Well might not be that appropriate for a game because maybe you will
hit that case, the bad end squared case.
But it might be just fine for an offline utility because most of the
time, it will run fine.
And as a little amusing side note, one of the things that typically
happens with these expected ones is there's a whole branch called
randomized.
rhythms, which
Designed exactly for this purpose, they don't care how bad the running
time of an algorithm is.
They only care what it's spected running time is the worst case is not
relevant to them because they employ random techniques to ensure that
if you ever did hit the worst case, you would just stop running.
It re randomize and run.
Again, when you won't,
There's a whole theoretical Branch devoted to just these they're
called randomized algorithms and it's it's a great thing to go read
about.
It's not that applicable to games necessarily but it is great to read
about it and it's a good thing to know.
So I would recommend taking a little detour to there.
If you're the kind of person who's curious about stuff, I would highly
recommend entertaining yourself for a little while by reading about
randomized algorithms because it's pretty funny.
And they're useful, like I said for offline tools, very, very useful,
all right?
So there's other things that they talk about and you will see these
sorts of things talked about.
And again, what they're talking about there is, well, there's the
worst case but then there's also other cases.
So we would like to know that as well.
And there are analyses that are done of algorithms, that try to
analyze what the expected running time of something, is because it may
be that certain algorithms are very good even
Go there and squared because you can almost never hit the N squared
case and so they do care about these other things, it's not just the
worst case.
That's the only thing a computer scientist might be analyzing.
Okay, so now let's talk about a little bit further Beyond this.
Now let's talk about something you may have seen which is p equals NP,
right?
This is something that you may have seen.
You may have heard stuff about it like, oh, that algorithms in P.
It's an NP and it's np-complete.
Right, you may have heard even the phrase np-hard, although often
times, I think most programmers have never heard that.
But point being, there's a lot of things there, okay?
What this refers to is actually order notation.
And so once, you know the 0 n 0, N squared, and so on this starts to
come into play, you can understand p and NP totally fine.
What they actually stand for is just polynomial.
And non polynomial.
So something that is polynomial time, right?
Means that I can write it with a polynomial.
I can write its 0n expression.
Whatever we want to call that it's Big O notation as you might hear it
said it's Big O notation.
You can write it with a polynomial and as you know a polynomial is
anything that looks like you know,
And to the something like n, N2 I'm going to use x here to refer.
To any constant, let's say or n to the C.
Plus, you know, ended it to the c 1 plus n to the c 2 plus n to the c
3.
Plus end the sea for however, many of these you want.
Right?
It's just a standard polynomial from math, right?
And you can put constants in front of it as well, whatever you want to
do, but it's always got to be n to the something, right?
That's that's just how that's just how polynomial is defined, right?
so, if you can write it as a polynomial, where the variable,
Is n, right?
That the not saying this.
Well this is my math terminologies to Limited.
If you can write the Big O, notation as a polynomial, where the
variable of the polynomial is n.
It is in, it is in P, right?
It is, it is AP algorithm.
It is a polynomial time algorithm polynomial time, because we expect
it to scale as a polynomial with the work input.
Now, you'll note that this could be an extremely heinous expression,
something that was like, end to the 12th.
He's still a polynomial time algorithm because I didn't use anything
besides a polynomial to represent its running time.
So even things that you would never ever ever be able to run for any
reason because they are absolutely ridiculous.
Like end to the 12th are still considered in p and I often use that
phrase.
I should explain it.
People say these p and NP.
I I kind of started explaining them without really saying
They stand for polynomial, not following you, they represent sets,
they represent classes of algorithms.
So, if I say that an algorithm
Wow, handwriting.
If I say that an algorithm is in P, it means that it is in the set P.
It is in the group, the class.
I'm sure there's a pedantic actual thing you want to say there, but I
know what it is.
It is it belongs to the class of algorithms that are polynomial time,
and that means I can write it 6 order notation with a polynomial.
Now, obviously NP is just the other
A round.
I can't do that.
I cannot write it.
So if an algorithm is in non-polynomial, it's an NP.
It means that it's order notation, looks something like this.
The expression, the end the variable that represents the work units.
It is actually in the exponent, right?
And at that point, I am in NP.
I can no longer say that this has polynomial time.
Now, obviously,
No, the difference is pretty drastic.
I don't know if like Wolfram Alpha can help us out here with a handy
little graph.
I don't actually can Google Glass graph, something graph, N squared +
2 to the n
Can it do that?
I don't know.
I don't know how to like get a good graph.
I want to I want to graph.
Let's try.
Wolfram Alpha will from alpha.
Let's see.
Will from Alfre how are you going to do knowledge engine?
Can you, please graph N squared + 2 to the N for me?
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Okay, I would like you to expand.
Please.
Can you expand the range for, for us here, on handmade hero and able
interactivity?
Oh, we're not subscribed to Pro.
How about over the range?
0 to 100.
There we are.
Did that actually work?
I think it did well.
I maybe made my point a little bit too much.
Let's try it down a little bit so you can actually see what happens.
There we are.
So here, if you actually look at the plot, you will notice that 2 to
the N is wickedly worse than N squared.
It makes N squared, which is already very bad for us.
Look like a line, it doesn't even look worrisome, right?
So, 2 to the N is vicious.
Be worse than N squared.
For those of you who, you know, don't have an intuition, maybe for how
those two things relate.
I just wanted to sort of give you a little bit of a perspective into
why we care.
So yes, p and p.
This is tractable, right?
This is like intractable right does not scale.
You know these things are just are horribly bad you know you try to
feed a hundred things to it and it will never run, right?
You can't even you know forget about it, right?
So even though this may look bad, it is nothing compared to this and
that is why we care about about what happens to these situations.
All right?
So what does this whole thing mean, why do we care about this sort of
stuff?
We do what's going on and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, right?
All right.
So what I said here this was a little bit of a perhaps like I suspect
maybe pseudonym.
I don't know if he still comes to the stream, the river but he
probably got extremely nervous when I wrote this, you know, pretend I
never wrote that.
I just kind of wanted to say you probably saw something like that.
Let's not talk about that for a moment.
Let's talk instead about something a little bit more specific and
understandable.
Okay.
so, you know, that P is
Something that's polynomial time.
And you know that n p is non polynomial time.
Right now, the tricky thing about this, and the reason that computer
scientists are always so worried about these sorts of things is that
we don't really know that much about how to classify algorithms, or I
should say problems, perhaps, into these two categories.
You would think that it would be extremely straightforward to say, oh,
I've got this particular problem.
I know that in order to solve it, I can always, you know, up there is
the that there.
The polynomial time algorithm.
That will solve it.
Or no, there isn't it.
It's it requires a non polynomial, time, algorithm, etc, etc.
Right?
Well, the reasons you hear things like is p equal to NP.
Your things like that said, is because we actually don't know yet how
to classify a very large number of, actually practical practical
programming problems.
So, for example, there's a couple different ones, there's like,
there's a thing called 3sat, or a circuit satisfiability, I guess,
right?
I guess.
I don't know if they just call, it's at.
I don't even know what they call them.
They haven't.
Specific names for them.
There's a number of problems that are very straightforward, like,
let's say that you have a circuit that just consists of not a nand
Gates or, you know, in fact, you know what, I'm just going to get what
the actual term is believe.
It's three set though, yeah.
Here you go.
So you have a set of problems like this, which when you read it, it
will sound incredibly simple.
Right?
It basically says that.
Let's see if they've got it here.
If you have, like I said, a ands and not and any number of inputs.
So any number of Anne's and Knots, and a number of inputs, they just
want to know whether or not if you can find a set of inputs that will
produce like true or something, right?
So, for example, again, I don't study this sort of stuff for a living,
so I
Advised that this part is not going to be the smoothest explanation
but you just imagine you have some expression that's like a and not b
and a and you know not c and d and I can just give you any number of
those things, right?
Well, the number of inputs.
A b and c d here, right?
Is for, right?
That would be the N the N equals four here, right?
And the question is, well, I want you to tell me if you were going to
be able to write some algorithm, that could tell me whether some these
inputs here are Boolean, right?
They can only be like true, false, true?
True, whatever.
if you were going to take this,
And say, tell me whether this expression can ever produce true.
You can set these to whatever you want.
Can it ever produce true naively?
You might say, oh, I could totally solve that in polynomial time, let
me just go do it.
But then what you would probably find when you tried to solve it is
that you couldn't.
And the reason for that is because each input can be set to true or
false.
That means that for each input.
That you have, you have two options, two times, two times, two times,
two,
Right.
Two options here.
Two options.
Here are two options here that my friends is 2 to the N for a non
polynomial time.
Right now, if we knew that the only way to solve this was by Brute
Force, we would know that the solution to this problem was in non
polynomial time.
It would be in NP because the only way to solve it would be to try all
to and possible input combinations and see if any of them produce true
but try as they might computer scientists have yet to
Figure out whether that's actually the case.
We can't prove yet.
Whether there exists, some more clever algorithm for processing.
A thing of this nature that doesn't take n p.
Now we probably know that it doesn't take you know, and squared time.
But remember, in order to be polynomial time you could write something
that takes end to the 256 time if you wanted to.
And you would still have succeeded in proving one of the long long,
long long, long standing mysteries of computer science which is, are
these sorts of problems in P or not?
Now.
When I say these sorts of problems.
What do I mean?
Well, I mean, np-complete problems, np-complete is a term.
You've probably heard it's almost always not understood properly and
that includes by me.
So, the explanation are about to give you is probably subtly wrong and
you're going to want to go ask a computer scientist to correct it.
But what we mean when we say that something is np-complete, is that it
Quote unquote, one of these problems.
And one of these problems is a problem, like this one where nobody has
been able to prove that it takes polynomial.
Time to solve, right?
No one's come up with any way to solve it, okay, but they have not
proved can't be so they haven't proved the opposite.
They haven't proved that you can't solve it in polynomial time and
they have proven that you can
A verify the answer.
So for example, if you were to give me right like true false, true
true, you're like that produces true.
I can verify that Impala.
Mealtime.
So this has a pea verifier usually, right?
It has the ability to verify the solution without also taking NP.
Again there's probably something suddenly wrong with that.
Like it's like oh it doesn't have to have the P verifier.
It's called np-complete Fufu frou-frou.
If it's like got the P verifier and not if it doesn't.
Like I said, go check the specifics.
I am just trying to give you a photo to this so that you can go
explore more about point being
NP, complete problems are ones that we don't know where they land.
No one has proven either but we do know that they can be verified in P
time, right?
So we can go here through here and actually say that the answer was
correct or not without needing MP time.
Now the number of problems that fall into this category are actually
fairly large, and people have done a tremendous amount of work proving
that they are all equivalent.
What that means is that all of the problems that are in NP complete.
And there are many, the Dean's List problem is another example.
I'll just wrap them up here so you can take a look at them.
Or not.
Is that?
All right.
Well, there's a problem called the Dean's List problem.
The, I don't know, there's a problem about trying to make sure that no
two people sleep sleep in the same room with other people that it in
as far as assigning rooms to people in a college but blah blah.
And it's like you have a list of exclusions and you have to come up
with, you know, picking people for who's to share the same room at a
college without ever violating a list of things.
That's a two people can't be paired with each other for some reason,
right?
There's a number of problems like that that are all very reasonable
that.
All sounds very logical that sound like the kind of things you want
computers to solve.
They have all been proven to be np-complete, which means you can
verify the answers in P time, but you cannot actually solve them in P
time yet.
But until someone proves that you can't, we don't actually know.
And that's one of the interesting things about this problem and why it
is such a thorn in the side of computer.
Scientists is because
I would like to know we would like to know definitively whether we're
just missing the big Point here and that all of these problems
actually can be solved in p time.
Or whether what seems to be true because no one's ever found a pea
algorithm for any of them.
It seems to be that they aren't, right?
And the nice thing about all of the proof work that they've done so
far is because they prove all of these problems are equivalent.
What it actually means is that if you found a p solution, a pee-pee
running time, algorithm for any of them, any of the things that I be
complete, you will have proved that all of them are solvable in P
time.
Because computer, scientists actually done the work of proving that
you can map one to the other.
The other, they're all in the same, they can all be solved.
By just translating them into like three sap for example.
So if you can solve any of them
You could solve all of them.
Now, typical gotcha.
And I've heard this on.
I've seen programmers post videos where they make this mistake, try
not to make it.
Like I said, this stuff is very complicated.
I've probably already made a mistake but just so try not to make
mistakes about this if you can, but it's complicated for non-computer
science people, it's true.
There is a gotcha.
Don't assume that something is np-complete just because it is hard for
example, the traveling salesman problem.
Right.
That is a problem.
Where I have some euclidean array of points.
Let's say, doesn't have to be a pretty and actually, just have to have
cost between them.
But so forget I said that traveling salesman's really just some set of
nodes in a graph and then I have some edges in that graph.
Write something that looks like that and each of the edges has a cost,
right?
I could even make all the cost of one doesn't even matter.
So let's say.
It doesn't even have a cost.
It just costs one to Traverse.
Let's say
Because I don't even think you need a cost, but either way, pretty
sure the problems are equivalent find the shortest path, that visits
all the nodes, right?
So again, it's just like a Salesman, a Salesman wants to go to each of
these places and they want to see them all once and they don't want to
like waste any time.
So they want the shortest possible route that will do them all.
That's the traveling salesman problem, it is not np-complete.
It is actually harder than that.
The reason for that is because there is no P verifier for it.
Right there is no way to actually verify the solution to the
Travelling salesman problem in anything other than also MP time,
right?
If I were to give you a solution and say hey I solve this out.
This particular traveling salesman problem for you.
Here you go, happy birthday.
You'd be like thanks.
But that does me.
Absolutely no good.
Because in order to verify it, I would have to go solve it myself
again using another MP complete algorithm, right?
Or sorry, not MP complete online using another MP algorithm.
Right.
And so it is not like these other problems because these problems you
can verify solutions to them.
You can verify in P time whether a particular
Allure set of inputs does or does not do the thing.
You said it should and things like the traveling salesman problem, do
not have that criteria.
Right?
And so, it's important to understand the difference between those
because there's essentially, I don't know what you want to call them,
a harder class of problems, but there's definitely a difference
between problems.
as you sort of go through there and I believe that that is typically
a, I think that's a hard, but this term is also almost always
Almost always also wrong.
So let's see if we can do it and p-card and see firmly at least as far
as her son's in P NP hard.
When every problem P can be reduced following term age 50 plus of any
a element get players to all the problems in P which is unlike some
other sort of hard non-polynomial blah blah blah.
Yeah.
Let's see, this is going to be too hard class files which are at least
as far as far as Point.
P problems that are empty hard.
Do not have elements of a indeed they may not even be decidable cause
problems that contains the hardest problems in NP.
Each MP problem has to be n p and p.
Easy.
Let's see, a equivalent.
You can see why this is is
Is annoying.
Let's see.
Polynomial.
I don't know why I'm checking this.
As I said that someone in math mathematician
Yeah.
Okay.
So any MP complete problem can be verified quickly in polynomial time.
So that part is correct.
I have not made a heinous misstep there and I believe the np-hard so I
don't really know, I guess I'm not I'm going to take this, I'm just
going to say again to avoid being one of the programmers who puts up
yet another stream with bad information.
Let's just say that we don't know what that is.
Let's just say we don't know.
Because I think that's safer.
But point being travelling, salesman problem is definitely different
than one of these.
And so what that means is there's a set of problems that are very,
very difficult but that may not necessarily be exactly the same as
these kind, right.
Because there are differences in the problems that don't necessarily
relate strictly to whether or not we know that, there's an NP, whether
there's a
Non polynomial time or polynomial.
Time solution for them.
Okay, so that's just yet another aspect of that.
This whole thing here with the different categories that looks like
this is a pretty extensive taxonomy here.
So like I said, if this is the sort of thing that interests you you
should definitely go read about it.
There's a lot of interesting things in there.
It's not the kind of thing that I spend much time doing and so that's
why I say I'm the wrong one.
To give you any more, right?
once you get past what I've just told you, that's the end of
My, that's the end of my understanding.
What's on this Blackboard here is all you get from me.
I don't study it.
I don't know.
But again, like I said, it's kind of interesting.
It's interesting.
Like, I even find this this part interesting.
That's like, oh, there's problems that we can actually verify very
easily and problems that we can't verify very easily, but both have
the same sort of like np- thing to them, and I don't know that.
Even just, that alone, those sorts of things, I find weird.
Thing.
So I could easily see spending time doing it.
Just not doesn't come up at all in what I do for work and so I've
never really had time to say.
I'm going to spend several months really getting interested in this
sort of stuff in and like playing around with it, but that's all the
basics, that's everything.
Okay.
So let's bring it back around.
Now, I've sort of given you a tour through stuff.
I don't know.
Right.
I told you stuff.
I dunno.
I've been to a tourist if I don't know.
So, if you are interested, you can go, you know, sort of do.
Some home study on this stuff and maybe get into it.
Maybe you can learn a lot more about than I do and teach me some stuff
but now let's bring it back down.
Finally, to our goal, which is sorting.
Okay.
So sorting, why do we care about this?
Why did I pick sorting?
As a time to bring up this order notation stuff.
Why are these related?
Well, sorting is kind of a classic example of why you might care
about.
Order notation because typically, sorting is the kind of thing where
if done poorly is N squared, right?
The reason for that is because it's inherently talking about taking a
series of things and putting them in order.
In order to put things in order, you have to compare them and whenever
you're comparing think two things inside the set, you end up with a
pair wise thing, kind of like the envelope problem.
I talked about the beginning of the stream, I'm looking at an item and
another item figuring out how
They are different and then making a decision, then taking another
pair and another pair and anytime there's a pair wise thing, you're
getting into an N squared situation.
So sorting is a very studied problem for this very reason.
And there are many algorithms, which attempt to do better than N
squared at sorting.
Because naively, you would expect it to be N squared.
And lo and behold,
If I go ahead and open up the one that I wrote in just a few minutes
the other day so I could show you how sorting works in the basic case.
What is the running time of our sort?
You will notice hopefully, based on everything.
I've told you, you can see right away.
It is itself and squared there is Count.
There is Count, minus 1, that is Count squared, minus count or 0n,
count.
Basically, the N equals count so N squared, let me
If I could say that a little bit better, right?
We have one Loop that goes to count.
One Loop, that goes to count.
- 1, right?
And so if I've got to run those two, that means I have to do count.
Iterations of count - one thing's or count squared.
Oops, count squared minus count, right?
And that means my order is that and like I said, I don't really care
about extras here.
I care about the scaling.
So I just care about really the highest exponent.
So I would just say and again, these are our n right.
I would just say it's O N squared.
Right.
It's really O.
N squared, minus n.
But I don't care about that because that doesn't affect the scaling at
all.
Right, so it's this right here.
And so, just like I predicted, if you don't do anything smart, you end
up with N squared, which means this won't scale.
If you want it to render a million items, you would be sitting here
all day waiting for the entries to get sorted.
Thankfully, we're not.
So we don't have to worry about it right at the present time, but that
is what would happen, okay?
And so what happens with sorting algorithms, right?
Oops.
Where's my, where's my actual nervous?
So what happens with sorting algorithms is people have tried to figure
out how to make sorting
Not the N squared.
And so, a lot of the algorithms that people tried to come up with,
right, they're just ways of figuring out, can we do something clever
and and not have to spend N squared time not have to compare elements
to other elements.
Now, that may sound impossible at first if you've never considered it.
But the reason why I could do that it's because let's say I wanted to
do something like
I don't know.
Let's say I wanted to sort.
To be honest, I guess I can't give you a really intuitive reason for
why you can do this.
So I may just have to kind of explain an algorithm and show why it
isn't.
I'm trying to think if there's any intuition you could apply that with
let you go oh I see how you would approach this.
If you've never seen one before,
Yeah, I can't really think of one.
So let's go ahead and do it this way.
Let's talk about how we were doing our sorting before and then I'll
show you some other ways we could do it, right?
So before we had a situation where we, you know, we sort of said, oh
well we've got you know, a CZ d q.
Right.
This is my input and I want it sorted.
So I want you to give it back to me a CD qz.
And in the naive case, if I'm just going to compare every element with
every other element, like I was doing in my bubble sort where I just
kind of ran, I just, you know, with bubble things up.
And in fact, I could make this actually hit that case, pretty
trivially by just doing it this way.
B, c, d, a right, and maybe I'll put a few more in there.
B, c, d, e, f, g, a, my bubble sort.
Because it can only move the a one place.
Every time will actually take.
It will take the whole n Cycles to do it.
So it'll do end times through n passes.
Right to move the a all the way up to the beginning so it actually
will run and squared.
So our current sort our bubble skirt will literally take O N squared
time even if we early outed.
So, even if we did this to do here, where we said stop, if the list is
already sorted so you don't keep going.
We could trivially feed it.
Something where the the
Front most element is, is all the way in the back and it would still,
it would take N squared.
Time to produce a b, c, d, e, f g, right?
But
We can do, potentially better than N squared were stripped case
running time by observing that if we were to partition these things
into smaller groups, often times, it's called divide and conquer is a
strategy.
There's also another one which is bottom up, which is called dynamic
programming, and these are various different strategies for algorithm
design, they're very important to nothing.
We really cover on handmade hero, but maybe eventually we'll get to
them when we have to do some more complicated things, but divide and
conquer.
Is basically a strategy for devising algorithms.
That says, well, if something is really hard to do, let's just keep
breaking it into smaller parts and see if breaking it into the smaller
parts allows us to do it in any faster time, right?
So here's one example, let's suppose and you know what?
I'm going to go ahead and add an H in here, too.
So I have an even number four now because it makes it a little easier
on myself.
Let's suppose I broke this in two pairs of two, right?
So first, what I did is I
Just segmented it like this.
Okay, and then I said, I just want you to sort the pairs of two.
How long would that take?
Well, I need to compare these two items.
Right?
So that would be one that would take one.
Right now, you compare these two items so that would take one.
I had to compare these two items so that would take one right?
And you compare these two items so that would take one.
Depending on how we want to count it.
Maybe we'd say that count too.
Because we had to visit both items doesn't matter.
Either way it's going to either be double or single the running time.
But either way however you want to count it will just say we'll say
it's one for now because we'll talk about we'll say that are
N is in the comparisons, right?
It's how many comparisons you needed to do?
Right.
Okay, so
that's how many comparisons I would have to do to do this, right?
And I'll, you know what?
It would help, if I started with the right list, I need one that's out
of order first, let's try that one more time.
Okay, so I check these two, that's one I check these two.
That's one I check these two.
That's one, I checked these two, that's why.
And, you know, if I reverse the order of these two because that they
were, you know, they were in the wrong order in the list.
So that was what I was these all say the same but this one changed,
right?
So I can do one pass essentially and get all my pears in order.
Make sense.
Now, if I wanted to, I could then combine any two pairs, right?
I can funnel these guys together because I now know that the pairs are
in sorted order.
So there is no chance that if this guy, right?
If I compare this guy and this guy there's no chance that this guy
could be anything other than in the same direction as this guy from
during the comparison.
Right.
I know what direction they go.
So what I can do is I can say well let's produce a list here, I know.
I only have to check these
You to figure out who comes first.
I don't need to check either of these because they can't possibly come
first, the person who's in their own, pair comes before them.
So if I check these two and I say, oh becomes first, I'll put be
there.
That's one comparison, right?
I then say, all right, move to the next guy.
Compare these two.
Okay.
See your D, which comes first and this case it happens to be see.
That's another one comparison.
Okay.
Then finally, I would move to here and I'd say which one comes first C
or E, right?
And that's again, one comparison.
And so then I end up with that, right?
Oops.
So I only needed to do three comparisons, whereas if I had done all
the pair's bdb ecdc, right?
I would have had to have done for comparisons.
Make sense.
So I shaved off one comparison just by taking advantage of the fact
that I know these are sorted do the same thing here, right?
F, g a h, right?
Let's do that one.
So I take this one is fr a first.
Well, a is first right now, I move to H is frh first.
Well f is first.
Now, I've got G.
RH G is first, and then, I am course H, right?
So, that was three comparisons.
Then to get for results, okay?
So now you can kind of see as I leave her up here, right?
I've done effectively something that's only on the order of n here
basically and something that's only on the order of n here as well.
I've never had to do a full pair wise thing.
Still let's take it further and you can see how much power more
powerful this gets when we have the bigger sets.
Let's go together.
Right.
How many comparisons for all of these?
Well, being a witch is first, a is first, right?
Now, let's go to the next one, b or F, which is first be is first,
right?
So that's one comparison, one comparison, right?
It's one comparison basically for everyone, I right essentially.
Yeah.
Okay, so be where am I at here?
I did be f is first F isn't first.
So we go down to see, right CRF it, see right?
So then I can advance ahead d d or F.
It's still d, right?
That I go to erf.
It's still e0, then I'm out.
So now I just know that I just do the rest of these, right?
So then I'm just G and H.
Because they're just in order to just copy them, right?
So hopefully you can see how few comparisons I've done.
I'm already at the end of the list sorted.
Now if I was to do this and squared right?
1 2 3 4 5 6 7, which those ABCDE oops, forgot my f abcdefgh, right?
This list.
If I was to do this the N squared way, that would have been eight
squared or 16 comparisons, right?
Makes sense in this case at most, I only have two ever compare.
The number of things that are in each of these lists the number of
times up that I, that I had to do these these steps, right?
So I have to do n steps potentially right or something on the order of
n, but I only had to do it three times, right?
So even though I gave it n inputs instead of N squared, I actually
just had
had, you know, and time I actually just had three times that
Makes sense.
So this is much much better than this would have been, right?
This is, this is, this is like, like much much better, and I guess I'm
using the order here, because it wasn't actually three times and it
was nowhere.
Close to that because we're actually counting the actual comparison.
So, you know, it was instead of n here.
It's like, how many did we do?
We did, like six here we did for here so 46.
We did we did basically like something like fourteen right now, it's a
little bit tough because it
That only looks like it, Beat it by 2, which is not that great.
But hopefully you can see as you would go up here, things would get a
lot better because every time I moved up I was only having to do this.
Name this, I was only having to do a number of comparisons that was
based on the number of things for those numbers of steps, and how many
numbers of steps.
What I actually have to do, well, if I start with the lowest level,
which is every to, right, then that's just going to be too, you know,
for it's going to double every time, right?
It's going to be 2 4, 8, 16 32, right?
As I go up through here, that's how many I was processing each time.
And what you can see there is that essentially just a power of two
that it increases.
So, whatever, n was, in this case, n was eight, we just have to take
essentially, the log route to, right?
We just want to say what, you know, two to the x equals whatever RN is
write or log.
Log 2 to the x equals log and right.
Make sense.
So I only need to take whatever the log 2 is of my input n.
And I would get how many of these steps in this case, it was three,
right?
What that means is the running time for this thing instead of being in
squared, which is what we had before.
If I was to use this method, I would end up with something where we
took the log of n, right?
And then it was, it was times n, right?
Because I still have to do something on the order of the number of
elements each pass.
To this thing that makes sense.
And that actually is a very common running time to see, which is
written like this n log n, it's called right, which is anytime you
have some kind of a binary, divide and conquer algorithm, where you're
doing, N Things on every pass, but you only need to do as many passes
as the power of to what you essentially done.
Is you've taken something that was, you know, 0 N squared.
I could write as 0 n.
X n.
Right?
What you've done is you've taken normally I was doing n passes fact, I
could even draw this out for you.
Normally what I'm doing is I'm doing this right?
I'm taking every possible combination of the ends and I'm doing all
those possible comparisons, right?
And instead, what I've done is, I've attacked one of those ends, one
of the loops, instead of one of the loops being going through the
entire n.
I've changed it to a log n.
So now I've taken something that was
N times n and I change it to end times log n, right?
And so, just to be more concrete about it, right?
You could imagine pulling this out into something that made a little
bit more, that was a, you know, sort of longer or had more, you know,
got up a little bit higher, right?
So A B C, D, E, F, G.
H I J, this is going to be small enough, okay?
L
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven
twelve and m0 P.
There we go.
So now I got 16, right 2, 4 6, 8, 10 12, 14 16 right now, in order to
our bubble sort, we know exactly what this would look like, in terms
of how many times we have to process this.
We'd have to process this many things and we have to process it and
times, right?
So we'd have 16 passes through the whole thing, right?
So we'd have you know, this
Our first path second path, the third path, fourth path, 6:15 past
8:07 path that the top, right?
That's how many operations you be doing, but in the way that I just
talked about.
Now, what we do is when we order each of these, we then move up to one
that has twice as many elements.
So the next phase is a b c, d e, f, g h.
I j k l and m 0 P, right?
And the next phase after this is, see if I can get it right underneath
the number there.
ABCDEFG H, I J K.
L M N O P.
Don't ask me why I wrote those in opposite order?
And the final step is abcdefghijklmnop.
And so what you can see is that in the log, n case with 16 inputs,
after just four steps of the, OM part of the algorithm.
I am done, right?
But if we had done the bubble sort, we would have had to go all the
way out to 16 that's over here, right?
That we'd still be running.
And so the eight case I kept it small so you can see how it was
working.
It doesn't show how much more powerful it is because I don't have
enough, but as soon as you get more, you can see right where as the
bubble sort would have had to run each of these times.
It would only have been a quarter of the way through its process by
the time, the, you know this, this one's already finished in terms of
the number of steps, right?
So that's why this is again, n log n.
It's because it does have to look at essentially, it has to do it.
Work proportional to the to the items, but it only has to do that work
log n times.
So if n is 16, well, obviously 2 to the 4th equals 16, right?
And so that log n is for, in this case, 16 times 4 whereas our O N
squared algorithm, right?
That is a 16 squared.
That is a really nasty amount of work.
That is 256, right?
Yeah, not wrong about that.
Am I to the 4th x to the fourth is to the 826, right?
So we've taken something that would have been 256 in the bubble sort
case.
And we've changed it to something.
Then this case is only going to be 64.
And that's a pretty darn good savings right in terms of the number of
work units.
And so hopefully that gives you some sort of insight into why we
Care about stuff like this, the nature of the algorithm and how it
processes.
The inputs can have a very real effect on how this works.
Now, this I believe is typically called a merge sort
actually has a name and it's called a merge sort because it does
exactly what its name sounds like it does.
It takes little pieces that it knows to be sorted and it merges them.
And then it merges them again and if you can't quite figure out
because it is a little confusing where the secret sauce comes from,
why is it able to do it so much more efficiently than the bubble sort?
Well, the reason is because it reuses comparisons, right?
It's basically saying, oh, hey guess what?
In this particular case, I know that since I've already compared these
two, if I compare one of these to one of these, I then imply something
about the other one in that pair.
Right.
And that actually, I know, I said this, we're kind of getting off on a
tangent here, but I'll just say,
That is actually the basis of dynamic programming, which is a whole
another discipline of programming, which I would also encourage you to
talk to look up if you were interested.
Anyway, point being that is called a merge sort and it's an example of
how we could knock down the worst-case running time of our bubble,
sort quite considerably just by doing something very, very simple.
Hopefully, you understood exactly how that would work.
It's incredibly incredibly basic.
Now I've only got four minutes left, so I think what I'll do is I'll
reserve a little bit of time for questions.
Hopefully, that was a reasonable introduction to how this sort of
stuff works and why you might care about it again, as it applies.
The Sorting the choice of algorithm and its complexity determines, how
when you add more elements, how much work you will actually have to
do.
And this, as you can see, even with just a small.
Number elements will probably be much faster than our bubble sort if
we decide to do it.
And that will be the subject of tomorrow's stream will be talking
about some of these, sorting algorithms and implementing one of our
choosing possibly merge sort because it's kind of clean and nice.
But we could also do quicksort, which is
Dirtier and a little less predictable.
But let's go ahead and go to the Q&A here so I can see if people have
questions.
Quarter Tron.
N p stands for non-deterministic polynomial, Plus
Some other minor problems.
Otherwise well done.
Okay good.
So we have a crude correction there.
No one will know.
If I, if I, if I just change that.
There we go.
You know what?
That's good.
And in fact that's something I should have remembered because that's
actually if you're actually in NP you would assume that that would
mean that you you absolutely knew for sure, right?
So non-deterministic is way better because, you know, that makes
sense.
If you say non-deterministic polynomial time, it's like, now, you
actually are saying, we don't know if the fact that we don't know is
right in the name, right?
That makes sense.
So yeah, so that's better.
So, the only question is, how do you say non polynomial?
If you can't say NP, what do you say?
Because if you, if MP meant non-deterministic polynomial, like how do
you actually say like, how do you say the thing that I was talking
about?
How do you say that, can you just not say it?
I mean, you can't abbreviate it.
Let's see for the records are Mark.
I made earlier about restaurants also isn't merge sort, n, log, n.
Yes, that's the one we're talking about down here.
This is merge sort and it is n log n, right?
Is it?
That's what we said right here.
Long brilliant.
So unit testing a function that computes a path for the traveling
salesman problem.
We require writing the algorithm twice.
The second one testing the first Yes actually unfortunately yes.
Unless you, unless you solve some open problems in computer science, I
mean, as far as I know, traveling salesman there is no polynomial,
verifier for it and so you can't test its results if that makes sense.
You would need to
Yeah, there's really nothing you can do as far as I know.
577, do you think computer science major is a good path to go?
I'm in it now I don't know.
It depends on what interests you right.
Like I said you know well as the fact that I got the NP term wrong
here and then I actually died suddenly so let me ask again just in
case, someone knows how do you actually say non polynomial is there.
No abbreviation for it.
like, if I actually want to talk about something that's non polynomial
time,
I don't want to say non-deterministic polynomial.
I want to say, non-polynomial.
Can you say anything?
Is there a name for it?
Like, can you say q p or something?
That means non polynomial time or, or is there just abbreviation NP?
And that's the only be a shit and you'd only means not a German spy.
So, if you want to say non polynomial time, you have to literally Say
Non polynomial time.
Insofar as says you say, exponential and okay, it sounds like Busy
Beaver.
Huge hmong and strophe.
Amar Bose saying not in P.
Alright, okay.
So, basically, let's let me rewrite this just for the benefit of
people who might watch this video later.
So here is how we say what I wanted to say, p, is polynomial time.
That doesn't change NP is non-deterministic.
Polynomial.
And that is what I explained here, which is saying that it has the P
verifier, I guess.
Well that just says we don't know.
I guess let's leave it at that.
That just says me, don't know if it's in here or not, right?
and then not in P, was actually the thing I was trying to say,
So when I said, NPI actually really meant this because I was trying to
explain the things that that don't have, you know, that are, like, 2
to the N or whatever, right?
For sure is 2 to the N.
So I guess that's all you can say you.
There is no abbreviation for this guy.
Maybe you could call him an imp
This algorithm is an imp.
I like that.
This is an imp e0.
Algorithm.
It is not in p.
All right, so that's for those of you who like me, don't know computer
science, very well that maybe if I can just get that drilled in, I
will stop using the wrong terms to refer to things because I've never
known what that was.
That's good to know.
So, not in P.
I can just say that and I won't say NP anymore.
When I mean, that something is is like, traveling salesman.
Although I guess we don't know, have we proven traveling through.
Let's ask, let's ask that.
Has anyone definitively proven that traveling salesman could not be in
P, or do we still?
Is that potentially np-hard?
Like is this as hard?
As n p, but not necessarily.
Limpy.
What do we know about traveling salesman?
That's the question.
Because right?
Just again, to sort of cement this down,
if nothing more for my own sake, we know the Travelling salesman
doesn't have a p or n p thing that we know of yet or sorry.
Np-complete.
We know that it doesn't have a polynomial time verifier.
And we know that doesn't have a polynomial time solution that we
found.
But we don't know necessarily what has been proven about it.
I'm pretty sure that they haven't proven it np-complete.
I'm
Sure that it is not np-complete.
I think it because it doesn't have like I said, I'm pretty sure no one
has found a pee verifier for it.
But I don't know if anyone's proven that it's not in P, maybe it still
is.
So do we know?
so people on the stream say np-complete, which means that it is in
fact, possible that if somebody were to figure out how to solve
np-complete problems
I MP time traveling salesman would also be solvable in that time.
Meaning, even though it doesn't have a p, verifier that we know of
Here's another question.
Have they proven?
Have they proven that?
It doesn't have a pee verifier.
I really want a computer scientist to just step in here and give us
the full explanation because I'd like to hear but unfortunately, we
don't have that.
Well, I'll let I'll let this go.
I'll let this go on to the thing.
So,
Somebody.
Somebody figure out whether the shortest path problem, I don't think
so.
I don't think so, because it sounds like what you guys are talking
about.
The stream is not what I was saying.
Was this fabric sells a problem?
Finding the shortest path is different than just finding a path of a
certain length, right?
Although, I guess technically you could transform those by then just
asking some up all the paths and then take one off and in order to
take them off.
Well,
That know that maybe that doesn't work.
I want someone so on the forums, if one of you computer science, folks
would be kind enough to do.
So I would love for someone to post some information about traveling
salesman, right?
Because I would like to know if we've ever figured out whether it has
a p verifier because I thought it didn't but maybe it actually does or
maybe it does now and it didn't before or something.
Thing.
So, I'd like to know about that.
That would be nice if someone could post about that, and I'll take a
look at it.
Maybe we'll talk about it tomorrow if someone does post.
All right, so anyway, this is all good.
Everyone's happy.
I'll go back to the Q&A.
Oh, I've created, I've created a problem.
I guess people don't know which traveling salesman problem.
We're talking about.
So there's more than one
interesting.
All right.
See if there's any other questions here.
It scares me that people on the stream, who, I think RCS people are
not even able to agree about the traveling salesman problem.
I feel like tomorrow should just be called
Ten minutes traveling, salesman problem.
Koreans have three wouldn't say that.
Something is nin P.
Implies that P is not equal to NP.
Did we win a 1 million dollar prize?
No, so again like I said this stuff is outside of my area of expertise
so I would hope
Refer to you to someplace, that's better to learn about it but the
reason that there's pee, you know, something is in p and not in P.
The reason that that's not the same as not deterministic polynomial,
time or whatever, the reason for that is because it's possible that
you could prove that there are things you cannot solve in polynomial
time.
Right?
Maybe you can prove that.
So you might be able to prove that an algorithm is not in p.
That's just for one specific problem, right?
So, you know, maybe it's like the, you know, we make up some problem.
We have the magical
Sorting food problem, you know, and we figure out that problem is so
hard that there's no way we can prove that.
It's definitely not solvable in polynomial time, right.
It's non-polynomial period, right?
I mean I guess I could do that.
Can't we just do that, right?
All the numbers.
You know, from 1 to 2 to the n.
And it's not very computer science ee, but there's no way to do that
in polynomial time.
You have to write them.
All you're done, right?
It's not really valid but imagine you have something that was that
blatant where you're just like, yep, there's no way you cuz the amount
of work that actually has to get done is the 2 to the N, right?
This doesn't really count because you might then say, well that actual
number there is and blah blah blah.
So so maybe that's maybe that's bad but if you could find something
that you
Actually prove there's no way you can do it in polynomial time.
That's that saying it's not in P.
The problem with the MP complete things saying MP complete I believe
is saying that we've sort of proven that.
It's in this set the non-deterministic.
I'm going to write this so I don't forget it again.
My brain is getting old because like it's not like I didn't know that
term but I guess I'm just getting too stupid anyway non-deterministic
polynomial time.
This is a class of problems that we couldn't prove that for we don't
know how to prove this this for it yet.
So it's not so much that P and not in P.
It's not so much that you can't ever classify algorithms into one of
these too often times you can.
But there's a whole set of algorithms in between that we don't know.
We just don't know.
The proofs are too hard or not possible, or who knows, right?
For some reason, nobody's been able to prove it yet.
And so that's why there's like room in between here for the
np-complete stuff.
And we just don't know.
So I don't think it's necessarily impossible to do this.
You could prove something was not in P, but for these things nobody
has ever done that they've never proven it in either direction.
They can't prove that it's in p and they can't prove that it's not,
it's just in limbo.
I think everyone sort of expects that eventually we will prove that
it's not in P but no one's done it yet.
Long Billy is suggesting that the game should include a traveling
salesman.
I agree.
Keeper Caleb.
Will we go into more complex?
Sort out of them's.
Like Radix sort also is the space requirement of merge sort, something
that needs to take into consideration for handmade hero.
So we have plenty of space, so I don't think it probably would be, as
for Radix sort.
I don't know.
We've got floating Point numbers, so I don't know that Radix sort is
going to be particularly useful to us.
Maybe it will be
But Radix sort is kind of a very special case, sort of A Sort.
It's not very general purpose because it implies some very specific
things about the inputs.
That is not so good.
It makes it hard to sort on things other than very specific numerical
things.
Quarter Tron says, since you didn't go to college, when did you first
get your shit in or at least start learning All About Big O?
I think it was because I had a book called introduction to algorithms
that was just about like, you know, like sorts and just joint set
forests, you know, all sorts of weird algorithm things and it talked
about it, a bunch.
So I was like, okay, like I see, right?
But as you can tell, like, right, you know, nobody makes this mistake
that I made up here, where I was like, tried to refer to non
polynomial time.
Saying it was NP, right.
Like nobody makes that nobody makes that mistake.
If you do a lot of computer science, you can tell.
I just don't I hardly do any of it.
I only know it just from the very basic, like the very basic
conceptual stuff like here, where you look at an algorithm that you
write, and you go what's its complexity, worst case complexity?
Because that's very easy, right?
That's the very practical, very simple part of the computer science,
but any of the other
Stuff.
I don't know and like the non-deterministic polynomial Time stuff.
I find it really interesting.
Like I would I'd be super entertained going and setting that I'm sure
but I've just never done it so I know almost nothing.
that's why I say like, I don't know anything about
Like even which problems are in there.
I remember like Dean's, listen 3sat.
But you know, there's dozens of other problems that they prove, you're
a complete and they do mappings between them and all the other stuff.
I don't know anything about them other than I think it's pretty cool.
Insofar says, I'm not sure we can prove something is not in P, unless
it is undecidable or we can prove p is not equal to NP.
So maybe that's true.
Again, like I said, I don't know.
My computer science knowledge is way too.
Connor rents.
By the way, eight squared.
Doesn't equal.
16, did I do that somewhere?
Nice.
No wonder.
This looked no wonder this looks not so not so good.
8 squared is 64 so that compared to whatever it was 14 is a lot
better, right?
so I guess we didn't have to do if my quick math had not been so bad,
I guess we didn't necessarily have to do all these
So, it's bad even.
It's gets bad really quick?
Doesn't it man?
And squared algorithms are just really dangerous.
That's really nasty.
For obvious reasons.
But anyway, thank you.
Connor 44.
Correcting that.
I'm really enjoy.
So I kind of like seriously guys, I really want someone to.
Can we start a forum for on this because like just the amount of
argument that's in the chat over whether or not, you can prove stuff
is in P, or not, is kind of entertaining.
I would love.
In fact, all we really need if there's a good explanation for the
summer, like you go to the Wikipedia and like it's just dense
nonsense, right?
Like you go to something like, np-complete and you get a lot of stuff
that's just really hard to actually follow, right?
we're like,
They have stuff that just not a very intuitive explanation of what is
actually going on, which may be fine.
If your primary goal is like mathy, right?
But if you're just trying to understand the basics of it, it'd be
really cool if I could Point people on the stream like tomorrow or
something.
When we actually go, right, the store stuff.
It'd be really cool if I could plant some into something that's like a
really good introduction.
We're it's just very clean, you know, explained if you aim at, you
know, explain the way I was sort of explain it here where it's just
very like, intuitive and simple.
But someone who knows the real deep parts of it.
So it's all correct.
And, and has all the right interrelations and there's no mistakes, you
know, like and and and it has the stuff like, can you prove things
like examples?
You know, is there?
Somebody who has like oh and here's an example of something that's not
in p.
Right.
It'd be really cool.
If, if there was a place that people could go for that, I would love
it.
And I feel like other people on handmade hero would like it to just so
that people who are curious about that can basically like go and get
the primer that just lets them know what this is all about without
having to actually learn it all first, right?
So yeah, because that would be really, really great.
It's something I've always wanted to because like I said I don't ever
have occasion to study this and it doesn't really affect me, but it's
intellectually.
Interesting.
And so I feel like there's a lot of people who would benefit from, who
are like Curious, who would benefit from having the really good
version, you know, an hour or two lecture even or whatever.
That's just like, here you go.
That would be pretty awesome if that makes sense.
Quarter Tron says I shall dig through my copy of computers and
intractability by Garey and Johnson tonight.
Well thank you very much.
Quarter Tron, the first sentence contains the word whimsical, so it's
looking good so far.
Okay.
Long Boolean has posted a link.
introduction to algorithms computational complexity by Eric Daman
I will watch this tonight and see what I think.
All right, so I think that's about it for today, yeah.
Anyway, just to wrap up after after all of that.
So all of that was, you know, like I said, just tons and tons of stuff
in there from computer science.
If you want to know more about that, I would definitely encourage you
to go take a look.
It is not something I ever do much of.
So, I would definitely encourage you to study it on your own or learn
more about it, if it interests you, if it doesn't interest you, that's
fine but
This stuff, you still got to know.
So the part that you have to know, you gotta know this basic stuff.
The stuff that I sort of worked through, you've got to know these
things.
You want to be able to tell the difference between these types of
algorithms, right?
You want to be able to know.
Did you write something that's 0n?
Did you write something that's so in square?
Did you write something it's n?
Log n, right?
And basically, like if you don't know the complexity of your
algorithms, when you write them, you won't know how your stuff scales
as you add more entities to your system, more triangles to your render
path, whatever it is that you're trying to handle workload wise.
This stuff to, you got to know.
So like p and p stuff like this.
You don't have to know that it's interesting.
You don't have to know this stuff.
You do you really got to know this it's not hard, right?
It's not nearly as hard.
It's like halting problems are np-complete or any of those things.
It's not nearly as hard as you know, that it's much, much simpler, but
you do have to be aware of it.
And so this is the stuff again, that will go over for a second time
tomorrow where we just actually Implement a few sorts look at what
they're running times are and just kind of hammer home.
The reason why you care about this.
So yeah, hopefully, maybe you're a little interested in this stuff and
maybe you'd like to look a little, take a little bit of look at it.
That will probably never come up again on.
Made hero, but this stuff absolutely will come up.
I've already mentioned it many times in the past, I will mention it
many times in the future, and you really do have to be solid on this
stuff because again, not that hard does not require really any
theoretical knowledge.
It's just a very simple, very basic concept of.
Can you figure out the maximum number of loop iterations?
Your things going to do and that's something every programmer should
be able to do.
It's not theoretical at all.
Actually, obviously it has a lot of applications in theory, but in
terms of
Using it day to day.
It's very practical and very very worth knowing because if you don't
you end up with a lot of surprises things that you weren't expecting
to hurt.
You can hurt you, a lot, as you try to scale up your game to handle
different sizes of Worlds or workloads.
So very, very important there.
And I hope that again, that's kind of a little bit more cemented.
Now tomorrow, we'll go back and just start focus on writing some
sorting code.
And we'll look at the
Lexa T of that sorting code first our bubble sort and then maybe we'll
write a merge sort.
Like the kind I demonstrate today and we'll talk a little more about
that to make sure that it's it's really solid in your head, that's
about it.
Let's sort of put and and here to that, let's close that down.
There we go.
Thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of episode of
handmade here.
It's in a pleasure, black boarding with you.
As always, and thank you to the folks on the stream who may be sort of
tried a little bit to answer our n p and p.
Ian's.
But I kind of am trying to assign them some homework for those of you
on the stream who are good at computer science, if you would be so
kind as to go and click on our little forums link here and maybe go to
the code discussion place.
If you could post some resources there, I know I would certainly love
to have a more solid walk through that.
I could a watch myself, but also, just point people to if the stuff
they saw in tonight's room, there is kind of like I would like to know
About some of the crazier aspects of what goes on out there and
computer science land.
Something that was a good introduction, not too difficult to get into
for people who aren't on that track necessarily.
That would be really awesome.
So if someone could do that, I would really appreciate it and I will
check it before 2:00 tomorrow stream and if there's anything good up
there, I will talk about it and point people towards it tomorrow.
Alright, that's about it.
I will see you guys back here tomorrow at five.
5 p.m.
Pacific Standard time for some sorting code.
If you want to always, make sure you can catch it, We-Vibe Scout.
The tweetbot is tweeting, it's little tweet out.
So, if you want to check to make sure you catch it live.
Just head there.
Otherwise, I will see you back here tomorrow at 5 p.m.
until then.
Take it easy.
Everyone have fun programming and have fun CS researching.