Okay, welcome everyone.
We are here.
We are narrowing in on the 20th day, run day 19 of handmade hero the
show where we code an entire professional quality game from scratch
using nothing.
No libraries.
No engine.
No, nothing.
So that we can learn about everything that goes into a modern game.
And basically the goal with this series is to show how everything
works.
So that everyone who works on games will basically have a richer
understanding of what's involved in the
Always have the ability, not only to understand what their engines, or
their libraries, or whatever is doing, but also to drop down there,
and fix problems, create their own new, libraries improve upon the
tech that we have and basically just give everyone the opportunity to
understand the full Pipeline and really be fully effective.
And never let you know there be limitations in their game development
because of the fact that something is opaque to them and they don't
have the knowledge necessary to kind of go in there and take charge of
something themselves.
I think it's been going great.
So far, I've been
Been overwhelmed by the response from everyone.
I think it's amazing and awesome.
And I can't thank everyone enough for making the series so exciting.
And so yeah, with with that I will simply say, let's get to what we're
doing today, which is finishing up the win32 platform layer today and
tomorrow.
I think we'll be the last days.
Probably that we'll be working on our win32 platform layer.
And today, what we want to do is kind of work on our audio sync
explained yesterday.
The start stuff that we need to do for it.
And today we're going to be trying to actually get some of that stuff
implemented and hopefully test it a little bit too, just so we can
have some
Evidence that our frame Loop is actually working properly before we
sort of push onwards.
Now, if you have pre-ordered, the the game on handmade hero dot-org,
you should have gotten a link in your email where to place where you
can download the source code.
If you download that zip file that's up there, the source code it
should have every day's source code in it so far.
And what you want to do is since today is day 19, if you want to
follow along at home, you just unzip days, 18 source, and that will
line you up perfectly to what we're about to do today.
So if you want to follow along,
With this video and code along at home.
Just you understand everything and try it out yourself.
You can do that by just unzipping day 18 source.
That is what I will be starting with right now.
All right.
So what I'd like to do today is I just like to go ahead and talk a
little bit.
I talked yesterday about that, the audio code.
I like to talk a little bit about what I'm going to try to do here
because obviously it's always a little confusing when we're talking
about some of these concepts of like audio sync and stuff because it's
really hard to see when
I draw the diagrams like I did yesterday.
It's kind of clear.
What's going on?
At least a little bit from the visuals.
But you know, when you look at code, there's an awful lot of code that
you write in the course of thing.
This is, you know, it's, I don't know, it's a thousand lines of code
and we've done a good job, keeping our platform layer, simple
certainly.
So thousand lines isn't that much?
But even even just getting to that point, you start to see.
There's a lot of stuff in here that's going on and it can be a little
confusing to tie everything back to sort of a diagram or tie-in,
through everything back to what we're trying to.
And so what I want to do is kind of walk through it a little bit here
and just talk about what's not happening now and what needs to happen
so that we can kind of maybe push towards where we want to be.
Again.
We're not making our final platform layer here.
So we don't have to get 100% of the bugs out.
We don't have to get 100% of the perf out.
But we're trying to set ourselves up so that it's a good prototyping
layer and we will are prototypes built on.
This layer will be roughly equivalent to what they will be.
When we have the full full Power Platform layer working.
So
Basically, what we know is we opened, we are going to open a sound
buffer and we talked about Sam buffers extensively early.
When we first implemented this feature.
If you haven't watched those videos, I highly recommend you do, it'll
kind of clarify to you.
What's going on with direct sound when we output the sound, but
basically what we're doing is we're out putting 48,000 samples every
second to the sound card and what a sample is, a sample is one value
for the left and one value for the right channel that basically say,
the amplitude at that one point in time.
So basically what we're doing,
Is we're taking 48,000 amplitude points.
And that is what's reconstructing the way that's coming out of the
speakers to First approximation.
There's a lot of stuff that happens to it on its way out from from you
know, the computer to the speakers, but you know to First
approximation.
That's basically what we're doing is we're trying to find that wave.
Now, for a number of reasons, I discussed earlier way back.
When we first started doing this.
It's not strictly possible to actually perfectly synchronize.
Those waves with what shows up on the screen.
And the reason for that is there can be delay.
That happens at all, different stages, all the way out to stuff that's
completely external to the computer.
For example, if you have a HDMI cable and even if we ensure that our
audio and video are synced perfectly going out of the HDMI cable, that
may go into a user's receiver where it gets split off into like,
Something that goes out to speakers.
And one thing that goes out to the TV for the video and those might be
delayed separately due to circuitry and all sorts of other stuff.
So, to a large extent.
Perfect sink is not achievable on Modern Hardware.
I wish it was.
It's not.
So what we're trying to do, is not really achieve perfect sync.
But what we are trying to do, is make sure that we don't do such a
poor job in our own outputting that basically, we create a really bad
sink problem.
Even before the harbor gets look, we don't want to exacerbate an
already bad situation.
By ourselves making it very laggy, lacks output of audio and video.
So what we're trying to do is ensure that as we output those samples,
we try to have some measure of control over when they are going out
and we hope that they are leaving, they're basically getting pushed
out of the computer.
We kind of want them to get pushed out across the time period that
corresponds to the frame that we wanted them to be heard with.
So if we want a certain set of sounds to be heard across the length of
a particular frame that we're out,
And we're trying to line it up so that they come out the computer at
that time.
So we have very, unfortunately, we have very limited ability to do
this.
On some platforms.
On some platforms, we have more but we have very limited ability and
some platforms on Windows Direct sound in particular, which is what
we're using.
Basically, what we have to do is the we have to use this thing called,
get current position.
And what get current position does, is it allows us to retrieve from
direct sound where directsound believes the audio to be playing at the
time.
So it's where it's sort of telling us.
This is where I think the audio is playing out.
Hardware at the moment and it returns a something called the play
cursor, which says what that is.
So what I'd like to do sort of at the beginning here is just I'm going
to go ahead and make a debug diagram just using win32.
As we debug the win32 platform layer here.
I'm going to make a little debug diagram that draws.
The play cursor for us, just so we can sort of get a feel for where it
actually is in our ruling sound buffer, if that makes sense.
So what I want to do here is basically right at the end, we're going
to do a thing.
Or this win32 display buffer and window sort of thing.
Basically.
What I'd like to do is start to think about exactly excuse me.
I'd like to start of try to get if you will exactly where Windows
says, that play cursor, is at the time when we're about to do our
blit, right?
So it's a little sloppy because our blind isn't instantaneous.
But you know, we're going to try here.
So based on what I'm going to do is I'm just going to do a little
thing here and say, you know, this is debug code so we can
I can probably do a thing here where we're doing.
Can't remember what our what our definition of was.
We had a definition for it here.
Build up bat.
We were going to use, canned made internal.
So with handmade internal we could go ahead here and do this this sort
of check.
So if this is if this is an internal build, I'm going to go ahead and
ask that that buffer for the play cursor, basically.
Right here, and I'm going to wrap this, just because this is internal
thing.
I'm gonna wrap it in some, in some braces here.
Just so these two things don't escape.
So it's just a little local thing that I'm going to do here, right?
Like this.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to ask it for where that play
cursor is, and then I'm going to store that value.
So that on the next time around when I draw the frame, I'm going to
actually draw where we thought the play cursor was relative to our
buffer at that time.
Right?
So basically what I'm going to do here is I'm going to say all right,
I'm gonna get that play cursor and then I'm going to have a thing that
I'll put kind of up here just just a variable.
It's not a global variable but it's going to sort of effectively
Global because it's in the scope here.
I'm basically going to say, alright, you know, once we actually get
this thing,
Going and we're going to start this.
I'm going to do a thing called debug last play cursor, and I'm just
going to remember, basically, we're that debug last play Chris or was
all the time.
So we're basically going to say we get to play cursor back.
I'm going to set.
Like that.
And we don't actually care if this call fails, right, honey.
That's just debug code.
So, you have to check anything, but we're just going to take a look at
where it was, you know, in the at the time when we're about to do our
page flip, basically.
And you know, what, we could do that.
I'll even a little bit, we could do that even a little bit more sort
of
Sort of accurately.
I think by doing it after the page flip is done.
So we'll do it here.
Right?
So that basically says, okay, after the after we've submitted all our
stuff, the GDI and we don't really know when GTI is going to display
it yet.
Later on.
We'll sort of have more of a bill to do that.
But I wanted to show you how to do this code, you know, just get this
code in there first.
And then later, when we have a lower latency page flip where we can
actually think about it, maybe a little bit more, we can sort of get
this tighter, but base.
I just want some semblance of a debug display something.
It tells us roughly where the audio was at the time when we tried to
do our page flip, but I just want to impress upon you that again,
we're not getting 100% accurate stuff out here.
Windows is taking that bitmap that we gave it and it's going to
possibly delay until the vertical, retrace to retrace to flip it.
So we're just trying to get, like within a 60th of a second or
something of the correct answer.
Just so we can see if we're totally off base when we start to do our
audio thinks we're trying to get just something.
So there we go.
I've got that debug last play cursor and then when
I'm going to do is right here.
When we do this with you to display buffer and window thing right
before that happens.
Basically, what I'm going to do is I'm going to insert another call
here.
That's that's going to call up in the case where we're in the internal
mode.
I'm going to call a win32 debug sink display or something like this,
right?
And that's basically going to pass that that Global back buffer and
it's going to pass.
Whatever the last play cursor was right that deep.
Last play cursor.
So that's that's all I'm going to do.
And then I'm going to draw that on the screen.
And I would like to also pass it.
The Sound buffer if possible, which let's see.
Just so it can understand sort of the length of the Sound by for how
big it.
Is, that sort of thing.
So, we have a thing here, win32 sound output.
So I'm going to go ahead and pass that as well.
So that's going to take this thing here, right?
So there we go, sound output and that's address there.
So I'm going to go up to
The code up here and just drop that in here is our internal debug
function here.
That's going to draw some stuff.
Hopefully, we hope that it's going to draw some stuff and that's going
to take this win.
3-2 sound output buffer.
First of all, and it's going to also take this off screen buffer.
And then it also has this this d word here that is whatever the the
last play cursor was.
So that's the that's where we thought the play cursor was and then all
I'm going to do nothing particular, interesting.
All I'm going to do is I'm going to pretend
That the width of the off-screen buffer, right?
Maps to our entire sound buffer, right?
And you know what?
I'd also like to pass?
If possible is I'd like to pass our Target hurts as well.
Where is that game update hurts.
There we go.
Well seconds per frame is probably better.
So let's pass that.
So I'm also going to take 2 seconds per frame there.
That's all I want really wanted.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to basically start by just
drawing a really simple, excuse me, a couple things in here.
I'm just going to draw basically.
Maybe some little rectangles that will sort of dmarc 8 where our
desired frame boundaries are if that makes any sense or so.
Sorry, rather where our page flips are and come to think of it.
I probably going to want to draw more of them than just the last one,
as well.
So in some sense, I think I may want to basically do something, where,
where we actually have more of them kind of here than just one.
So what I think I might do
is go ahead and say, all right, the debug last play cursor.
Actually, we keep some number of them, right?
We keep some relatively large number of play, cursors.
And let's say that.
We keep like, say the last.
Mmh, let's say, let's say if we're doing a 30 frames a second.
Let's say we keep the last dirty, right?
So basically, our game update hurts.
We'll keep that many of them.
If that makes sense.
Okay, so we're basically going to track that many and the way that I'm
going to do that is just say that there's an index into that array,
right?
And that index.
I'm just going to update over time so that we write in the last play
cursor based on on that piece of information.
So here we go.
Let's go ahead and do that.
I'm going to do that here and we'll expand this.
I think in a second here, I feel like probably but for now, right?
So we'll basically just do that will write in what the play cursor was
into the array.
And then
If we happen to get to the point where this is higher than the array
count, we're just going to wrap, so it's just going to be.
We're basically just going to be a circular buffer where we just keep
reading into it.
And when we get to the very end, we'll go back to the beginning.
That makes sense.
So so that's it.
Nothing particularly fancy there.
That's all we're doing.
Hopefully, that makes some sense, right?
Excuse me.
Why didn't that want to initialize for us?
So that better expected constant expression.
Oh, right.
Sorry this
This game update hurts here has to actually be something that can be a
constant expression so we can do that temporarily.
There we go.
All right.
And let's see what else we got when 3D based ink display.
That needs to take our other parameter there.
The S.
What was it actually called Target seconds per frame.
So I'm going to pass that as well.
And there we go.
See a screen buffer cannot part 1 to address of
What did I do?
Did I forget the pointer?
I did.
Yes.
There we go.
These are supposed to be pointers.
Not a Sands.
Okay.
So now we just have to do a thing.
We're actually going to pass this thing and how big it is.
So we just need to pass basically our, our last play cursor.
Array, that makes sense.
So we're going to pass the whole thing, see there.
And then we will just modify this to take that as a pointer.
Last play cursor, count.
So, there we go.
Alright, so that's just going to give us basically what we need to
draw.
And now what I need to do is I need
To step through that, I need to do play, Chris or index.
I need to step through that array and I need to draw each one of those
into the into the window basically as a little rectangle or something
so that we can actually see what what is going on, right tubing.
So basically, we've got this, this bitmap here.
We know that it is, we know that it is with wide, right?
So we know that this is how big it is and then we know that
Oh, that we've got essentially, our sound buffer is going to have a
thing that has this secondary buffer size, a /, B per sample.
That's how many sample indexes there are in the entire buffer.
Right?
And this this guy, well, I guess we don't actually care because he's
play, cursors are not actually the samples there in B.
So basically, we just need to use this right?
The secondary buffer size is the width.
We want to draw.
We want, we wish we had a buffer that was that big to draw into,
because that's the sort of
Rains that were talking about but we actually only have something
that's this big, which means that we essentially have to sort of map
that secondary buffer size range into the with that we have.
Right?
And so, basically what we're going to end up with is we're going to
end up with a division here, right?
We're going to have a coefficient which is basically going to say for
something that want that is actually mapped in the buffer size and we
want it to now be mapped in the width.
We're going to basically just make the ratio
That Maps those out.
And again if you remember I talked about dimensional analysis before,
this is exactly what what I'm doing here.
I'm basically going to multiply this coefficient by the input B count
that we get from the from the play cursor, right?
Those play cursors.
The play cursors are in our in Sample, buffer B, and this is sample
buffer B.
Whereas I want them in pixels and this is in pixels.
So I'm multiplying by pixels dividing by sample buffer B.
The sample buffer B units.
Cancel.
And I just get back, basically the units that I wanted, which is the
pixel so I can draw it.
So, that's all that's going on here.
We talked about how this worked previous dreams when we're talking
about dimensional analysis and ratios, but that's exactly what all
that's doing.
Right?
So what I want to do is I want to draw this.
So basically I can just say whatever the this the value of
Play cursor is in this particular circumstance rank.
Basically, all I'm going to do is do a floating-point multiply their
to get out.
Basically what the x value is.
And that is the x value for where that page flip basically occurred.
Now, what I want to do is I don't want it to go all the way to the end
of the buffer.
So what I might do is also say, okay, you know, there's a little bit
of pad here.
Let's say there's, you know, pad X, right.
So maybe we'll start 16 pixels from the left and and 16
Will's from the right.
Just so it's so we can actually see it.
So there's a little bit of a margin there.
So what I'm going to do is say that, I want it to map to actually
arranged that's not quite that, right.
I want to subtract that out of the range and then when I actually draw
this x value, I actually want it to be looking more like that.
Right?
Hopefully that makes some sense and really I guess I'm going to have
to make this being a jerk because these are plotted as integers.
So we'll do the multiplication first, but then we're going to have to
actually convert it back.
The reason I'm doing the multiplication here is because I don't want
to do the multiplication in.
In something Harry, I want to be able to store ratios and stuff like
that.
So I'm doing the multiplication in floats, and then I'm casting back
to integers when we need to draw.
So what I want to do here is I want to do a little debug draw a line,
basically to draw.
In fact, I don't even need to draw a line.
I can just draw a vertical, you know, like a hash basically which is
extremely simple to draw and I don't have to talk about how to do
something like, you know, a crazy like brushing ham line drawing or
something like this.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to pass that in.
I'm going to say the global back buffer and then I'm just going to
say, you know, basically
What?
I want that hash mark where I want the top and bottom of it to be.
So basically I'm going to say, you know, I don't know Global back
buffer.
I guess I'll just do top and bottom, something like that and then
we'll just say what those are top is going to be equal to something
bottom.
Is going to equal to something.
They will basically be the global black back buffer height.
You know, I don't know - pad why say?
And we'll make that be 64 or something.
Well, we just think it's important all the way around.
Going to be a very funny looking diagram because going to be so tall.
But hey, what do you do?
We can adjust that later.
I'm going to say that.
It's just going to be pad y here.
Oops.
That's why the top and - pad Y for the bottom.
So then I'm just going to have to write this function.
Right?
Which is a thing that draws a vertical line, which is extremely simple
to do.
Although, you know, whenever you're writing stuff at a low level like
this.
It's always error-prone.
So why you typically make a graphics Library, we don't quite have time
to do that yet.
That's
what we will be doing sort of next week and going forwards in our
game.
So that will just be able to call things like draw a line and they'll
just work.
But for the time being, it's pretty simple for us to just sort of hack
something together that will serve for our debugging purposes just
fine.
So, what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to step the why this
is going to be this world's slowest and worst way of doing this, but
I'm just going to basically step the line from the top to the bottom,
basically.
And then I will draw each pixel.
So really all I need to do here.
Is get a pointer to the memory that we want.
Which is basically going to be a cast of this here, the cast of the
memory for the bitmap, which we've allocated and we've drawn to this
before.
So you guys are all familiar with what I'm doing here.
But basically, this is the pixel that we're looking at, it's going to
be that back buffer, memory times.
We're basically to move over.
However, many bits per pixel.
It is right, which we already know exactly.
How many
It is, it's basically four bits per pixel.
You know, I don't know why we know, because it's in info.
That's why I believe the bitmap impose.
The thing that stores, the bits per pixel, right?
But anyway, I feel like we should have had bits per pixel out here and
I feel like we didn't feel like that got removed or something.
I'm just going to say, bytes per pixel here, I guess because we
already know what it is as well.
So it could pretty much be a pound of fine.
But anyway, I've been a move over the X X bytes per pixel, and that
puts me at the correct place, but I also have to put
Go down, y times, the pitch, right?
Because I have to go that far down from the top of the buffer.
So we just need to know what this actually is.
So I'm going to I'm going to actually say, let's go ahead and get that
back in there.
I don't know why that went away.
I'm sure we could go back on the stream.
Historically and find out why it went away.
Maybe someone recommended it.
Maybe I was stupid one of the other.
Both of them are very possible.
But then when we get to this particular pixel here, we're going to
write, excuse me.
We're going to write into it as a un 32, so we can actually, I guess I
can just cast you into it through there.
R.
So will basically do it like this.
You went 32 star, pixel will write to it and then we will add to it.
The pitch again.
Alright, so there we go.
That and when we write to the pixel, I don't know.
We're going to write in here.
We didn't act specify a color.
I suppose we should allow the person passing it into specify colors.
So there we go.
And then we will just have withdraw protocol guy, specify a color and
the color for now can just be that color and now we just got to do
that b 4, pixel, when fix the errors.
I don't actually know again.
I don't know why.
We got rid of bytes per pixel.
It feels kind of weird that we did.
Let's put it back in there, bytes per pixel and then when we are
setting up that pitch,
I would like to set up that bytes per pixel.
So what I'd like to do here is just say, alright, bytes per pixel is
here.
Let's just go ahead and get that in there so that we already know
because we've already got it to find here and let's just do that
Hoops.
Just to make sure everyone's using, it just seems like a better idea.
All right.
So why?
Oh, right.
It's top, not why it is.
There we go, and secondary buffer size is something that is passed in
the sound output.
So that
That actually needs to be referenced here.
Alright, so we just typed in a crap ton of code.
There's probably some problems in there, but hopefully you understand
what I'm doing, really?
All I'm doing is I'm stepping through a bunch of cursor positions that
we saved in a rolling buffer, and I'm trying to draw them out.
Basically, when I draw them out, I am going to have a to me.
I'm going to have a vertical line.
So all I did.
There was I just stepped my pixel pointer to the top.
I stepped it over by the X amount for each byte per pixel.
And then I stepped it down by the pitch.
However, many the top was then I just did as many rows as there were
between top and bottom.
And each time.
I wrote the color out to pick slime at and advanced by the pitch to
move down to the next row, really pretty basic nothing.
Interesting going on there at all.
Like I said, just kind of finicky because we don't have a graphics
library at this point because we haven't gotten to that.
Not yet.
It's always hard.
When you start from scratch.
You kind of got a jungle as you kind of go upwards but eventually and
it's not that long into it.
You kind of get to a point where you've got sort of a lot of Leverage
underneath you.
And then these sorts of things aren't an issue anymore because you've
got your line draw.
You've got your rectangle in your, you're totally good to go.
That's exactly what I thought would happen.
You always crash the first time because you forget something.
So, let's take a look here at what we're doing to do.
So.
What do what are we doing?
Wrong are back by from memory times the bytes per pixel we did cast to
a uh, so that's good art at value of 16 times the pitch and I don't
actually know what the pitch is.
The pitch may be negative.
In this particular case.
I'd like to take a look at that just to see global back buffer.
There we go.
Take a look at that.
The pitch is not, so we're moving forwards each time by that pitch.
You think so?
And then we've got a 70 for what is our Y at?
At this point.
It's at 123.
So we started off.
Okay, and then when we got to 123, we crashed which suggests that we
are advancing too far each time through or something, similar to this.
That's a little suspicious and I'm not sure why that would be the
case.
So let's take a good look here and see what's actually going on.
So the
double back buffer is memory pointer is here, right?
That's that's what that is and our pixel pointer.
So I'm just gonna I'm just going to take a look at what our pixel
pointer is subtracted from that.
I'm sorry.
Let's take Take This Global back buffer.
I want to see what the memory size is, if that assuming that, that was
a care star, so, we'll cast that and see, oops, unsigned care star.
Sorry.
Okay.
A star.
So that is the difference there.
So the pixel pointer.
That's that's not good at all.
That is not good at all.
What what did I do?
I did something totally crazy there.
This is one of those things where hey, it's just like, I probably
wasn't paying attention and people on stream, probably already have
it, but I'm not going to look over there again, because I would like
to figure out, I would like to go through the steps that I would
normally go through to figure it out.
Like I've said, many times on the stream.
I want to kind of show how to debug stuff.
And so, when I have a bug eyed,
Rather just kind of go through it slowly on my own even though people
who have kind of been watching and not talking the whole time probably
already can see what it is if they're professionals.
Okay.
So basically I know that I was going to draw in this code, right?
So let me step in here and and and just start going through it.
Basically, I've got the global back buffer memory pointer.
I know what that is.
And now I also know what my pixel pointer is.
You can basically see it here.
Here.
And it looks to me.
Oh, I'm just doing the subtraction backwards.
That's, that's, that's it.
So that wasn't actually right.
There we go.
So, if I do the subtraction here, now again, then I can actually see.
This is, how far in?
I stepped just from the, just from the beginning, right?
So, just that first step, when I did my pixel offset, right.
When I, when I tried to start from the beginning of the bitmap memory
and go a little bit further into it.
Basically, all I was doing was, I was going to add fist.
Which which should be.
Let's let's double-check the math here.
I was going to add this much to get us to the right row, right?
Which is 81 90 and I was going to add this much here for the X which
which should be the remainder, right?
Oops.
Inserted an errant token.
You're right.
And that looks right like it did the math right now.
50 120 per row.
Does that sound about right?
1280, x 4?
That is what that is and if we were going to do 16 of those.
Those right.
That is what we expect.
So that looks like the right number of bytes to step for the start in
my opinion, that looks correct to me.
That is what I would have expected to have happened.
Certainly.
So it looks like our
Our computation.
There is correct.
Then we come in here for ry-ry is going to start at 16.
It's going to step to 704 and basically what we're saying here is
we're going to write to this pixel location.
I want to you know, what I shouldn't have deleted that?
I want to keep this here for now so I can see what my offset is.
Let's see here Global set memory so that I can keep subtracting the
two of those and just see what their value is.
So there we go, any 194 and then I come through here and do my
Addition and I stepped a row.
So that is what I would expect to see happen.
So I'm gonna set a breakpoint here and just make sure that this
happens.
Okay, that's interesting.
So it actually succeeded the first time through.
So it looks like it may be a computation of our X that is wrong.
Perhaps, our X is actually off this this computation here when I kind
of hastily sketched in this thing here, it looks like that might
actually be wrong because it looks like as long as the x is low, which
it is at this point in time.
The thing seems to work which which would suggest that perhaps my ex
computation was incorrect.
So let's take a look when I actually get the crash.
Now, I'm gonna step directly to the crash.
What the actual X.
Is to see if that's yeah.
Okay.
What do you think that that is not a very good x value?
I'm kind of glad this is exactly what I hope to show on the stream.
I know, it seems weird to be happy about showing you not being a very
good programmer, but this is actually what I want to show in the
Stream is this sort of thing because this sort of thing happens to me
all the time.
I'm not a great programmer at just writing exact stuff, right?
The first time I always make mistakes and then I just
have to debug them and it's really not a big deal.
It's one of the reasons that you make libraries as well as two kind of
to bug them once and then have them.
And I'm a big advocate of that because I do make a lot of girls
mistakes.
But yes, I just want to show you.
So you saw how I found that, right?
Like that was pretty clear.
How I went about debugging that, I just looked at what the memory was
doing.
I just looked at the pointers and I was like, oh, okay.
I can see that.
It appears to be tracking the why properly.
So, and on a Nexus reasonable it seemed to work reasonably.
So, I'm like, I guess the only other parameter there is that the X,
the X must be out of bounds.
And then, when that kind of true clued, me into bother looking at
that.
Now, if I look at the X first originally, I would have seen that right
away, but I didn't do that.
So maybe that's also a good thing to remember, always check all your
parameters once just to see but, yeah, so that's pretty simple.
We found the bug there.
So it's just a bug in the X computation, which makes sense, because I
just kind of slammed that in there and didn't even think about it.
That was, that was not particularly particularly bright.
Certainly.
So let's think about this, a second.
What are we actually doing?
So basically what I wanted to do.
With my computation here, and we'll go ahead and build that and then
step in what I was trying to do.
This competition here was just map from the B that the play cursor had
basically out to the, the pixel width.
And so I was hoping that this would be a relatively straightforward
thing, but it looks like I made a mistake when I was doing that.
So what I'd like to do here is I want to just so we can debug this and
look at it a little clearer.
What I'd like to do is break the computation into two steps.
So here is going to be the two steps first.
I'm going to compute the, the X in Real 32, right?
And then I'm going to cast it and add the pad.
So that way, you can see the result of multiplying by our coefficient
and hopefully that will let it inspect it a little bit easier.
Furthermore.
I'm going to get this out into a local variable and this is basically
just me setting myself up for debugging success.
I'm basically just trying to get these values out there so that you
can see exactly what it is.
What is going on in the actual debugger?
Right?
So I just wanna make sure I compiled that there we go.
So, in here, we can see what we get now in the watch window, and I
can, I can kind of very easily, make sure that the various stuff that
happens is reasonable.
So, let's take a look there at our, that's a totally reasonable value.
And so is the x that results from it.
Our coefficient also seems reasonable.
So, let's see.
See.
Happens when we sort of go through these here.
Does it seem to do anything particularly odd?
Okay, that is really bizarre.
That looks like a totally.
Yeah, so that looks like a totally uninitialized value of some kind,
which makes me think that are clearing of the this buffer did not work
properly.
That is what I am thinking.
So I'm going to check that.
But what I want to do as well is also drop.
An assertion in here.
Because the other thing that we kind of know is supposed to be true is
that this play cursor is always supposed to be smaller than the
secondary buffer size.
That's just what we were expecting to be true.
Right?
You're never supposed to be able to get what is this signed unsigned,
Miss mismatch.
Secondary buffer size, I guess is an ENT.
Mmm.
So, that's actually supposed to be a d word, I assume, but I'm not
sure if we want to do it that way or not.
We can do it that way for now.
All right, so I'm assuming that a
Well now just fire and that assert will basically tell us that hey,
you're getting values that are totally out of range for what you were
supposed to be allowing in this particular function.
And I just want to put that assertion in there so that it's there and
we'll catch those bugs in the future.
Probably should have put one in there to begin with but was not
thinking.
Alright, so what that suggests to me is perhaps that this is
uninitialized properly are our buffer that I said was going to handle
like sort of the circular buffer there.
So that was this right here.
Here and I want to 0.
We do.
That's the problem.
It looks like when I was hastily typing that in when I modified it to
be game, update hurts.
I accidentally deleted, the thing.
I had.
So carefully included, you'll notice last night in John's language
demonstration.
He did the initialized by default, unless you ask for it, not to be
thing.
I would love that feature so much because most of the time I want
things cleared 20 and stuff like that.
Where you just you accidentally delete.
It is just makes you prone to errors.
You shouldn't have.
So there we go.
Alright, so we're totally set now for drawing.
That's obviously, drawing our stuff.
The way we wanted to draw.
Unfortunately.
We also have the problem of basically.
It looks like there's a little bit more than 30 of them is more than
actually fits.
So I'm going to maybe do a little less than that.
I'll do half that, just so it stays on the page.
So there we go.
Yeah, that looks about right.
So basically what we can see already from this is we do have problems
with our timing already.
You can kind of see just from what I'm looking at here.
You can see they're not equally spaced.
That actually reminds me of something I was thinking about last night
after we had finished the stream that I remember there was a thing
that we had done wrong that I forgot about.
Basically, what I was remembering was we did our and anyway will we
will go right back to the audio thing in a minute, but I this reminded
me of this and we should we should fix it while we're here since we're
doing the exactly this sort of stuff and this says not testing yet
probably bug.
Which is true, basically the timing stuff here.
I was doing a little thing here to sort of lock our frame rate where
we waited and we wait on the total frame time, which is a good idea.
However, what I noticed is we don't track that fret, we don't snap
that frame time.
Basically, this last counter thing.
We don't snap this at the right place.
What we want to do is immediately after we do sort of that, that lock
right, that time is actually when we
Want to get that encounter because that is actually the thing that we
are looking at.
For our total time.
It'll still it'll still count because you have to remember this is
basically just a watermark that we haven't insert somewhere in our
Loop.
And if we're waiting for our Target seconds per frame, we want to wait
on the entire time that it takes to do everything up to this point.
And then immediately after we want to snap, whatever that time was and
count the rest of the stuff towards the next frames time because
otherwise, we'll wait till the target time.
Then they'll be a bunch of time afterwards.
When we're doing stuff, like doing our sink display in our buffer and
all this sort of stuff.
So this really needed to get moved to here and we didn't do that and
we saw that, I remember, I said we need to look at that tomorrow.
We saw that in the fact that these numbers were wrong.
They were a little over 33 and that amount that was over was exactly
that time that was taken up in here because we were waiting till our
Target frame time, which was 33, then still doing some work without
count that would count inside.
Side that that frame Benchmark.
So I just wanted to fix that to get one bug out of the way because I
thought of it last night after you finish, I was like, well, we've got
one bug in there already.
So I wanted to fix that and see ya and so you can kind of see now as
well.
Yeah, that's fine.
And basically you can kind of see now that 33 is right on the money.
And that's what I wanted.
I wanted us to be locked at 33 frames a second and that's exactly what
I wanted.
Now this assert.
We've got an assert here that fires anytime we miss our frame rate.
And so that's, you know, what you would expect.
Switch to another guy.
So that this is this is kind of something that we're not going to be
able to, to do anything about certainly because when we do our sleep,
we the operating system, like I said before, when we do our sleep, if
we're not the running application, we're not getting priority.
We might sleep for a very long time.
So this is just an assertion in debug mode to tell us when we missed
our frame rate.
So, if we switch apps, it's going to happen because windows will just
see no particular reason to give us the resources.
We need to do is hit it.
So that's fine.
But now, we are basically running at 3333 Point 33.
And for frame exactly as far as we can tell from our wall clock time,
which is exactly what I wanted.
So we know that that Parts working properly, but when I look at our
sound, you can kind of see there's some weird kind of gapping, unless
we've got a bug in the way we're recording it.
And if you kind of see what's happening there, if I pause this this,
like, let's say I just tapped take a pause here, right?
I don't know if I can get, let's do it this way.
I'm going to go ahead and take this guy sort of over here.
So this way we can run the app and then
Stop the app in the middle if that makes sense.
I don't know if that'll actually how well that will actually work.
I kind of just need it to.
I'm going to do this.
I guess I'll just make it kind of tiny.
This is why people often have two monitors if they're doing a lot of
debugging work, okay?
No, that's not what I wanted.
So, what I want to do is just stop it so you can see it.
There we go.
So what you can see is going on here is we're getting nice.
Sort of equally spaced samples most of the time but then sometimes we
get kind of these nasty hiccups where it's totally not right at all.
You can kind of see that there were two lines in here and there were
two lines in here, two lines in here, no line there.
So we're not getting a very stable read on the audio pointer right
that that that when we're asking for where that is it.
Look like we're getting a very stable read from it.
Now.
I don't actually know at the moment why that is, it could be that this
sound card, just doesn't give us a very stable read back from the
frame buffer.
I honestly don't know.
But what I can say is, at least right now, we're getting back, a very
unstable, sort, of piece of information from it for that play cursor,
and I don't actually know exactly why that is so,
It's something to think about though.
So what we want to do here is start to sort of improve our situation.
What I want to do is kind of try to do something.
Let's try to think about this here.
I wonder if there's a way we can ask for slightly more accurate time,
or if that's the most accurate time.
We're going to get because if that's if you think about it, if that
actually isn't buggy, right?
If that is not buggy at all.
Excuse me.
Then we're kind of, in a little bit of trouble to try and get audio
sync.
I mean, if you think about how inaccurate it would have to be if
that's where it actually is.
But so let's just take a look at that a little bit, a little bit here,
just to see if we can increase that accuracy if we're doing something
stupid or you know, hopefully hopefully there's something we're
dismissing.
So when we call this get current position here, let's just take a look
at the documentation for that.
Direct sound get current position just to see if there's anything that
we could be doing when we create the buffer.
Like that to make it be a little bit more accurate.
I don't know if we can or not, but let's see.
Let us see what it says here.
The right cursor into this was safe to write blah, blah, blah.
We know all this that is not going to help us.
Let's take a look at the buffer creation stuff, just so we can kind of
see set frequency is not really going to help.
No, this looks particularly interesting, but we can take a look at
that some of these things like the caps and stuff and then I can also
take a look at this creates a buffer.
And so we can take a look at whether there's anything we can do inside
the buffer description to tell it that we kind of need some better
stuff.
So, let's see.
So we don't really know what position notify exactly as I Tsum that
was called back to maybe that might have some bearing on.
Let's see here.
She's new, be placed in direct sound.
Let's let's take a look at some of this stuff says because some of
this may be relevant.
So in direct sound DirectX, 12, Play cursor was significantly ahead of
the actual playing sound on emulated sound cards.
It was directly behind the right cursor.
Now, of course, is just the apples and get a more accurate play
position.
If this flag is not satisfied, the old behavior is preserved for
compatibility.
So so, you know, I'm just like I said, going out on a limb here.
Let's just try some of these things and see if we can get that guy to
be a little smoother and hope that it's just a little bit of something
we're doing wrong, that's causing that.
And then it doesn't have anything to do with the actual platform.
Which would be a lot harder for us to work around.
So I'm going to go ahead and set that in here.
I believe it is.
Well, I guess it's only on our secondary buffer that we care.
I'm not sure.
I'm not sure if that's true or not.
But I believe it is.
Let's see.
Let's see here.
It's recommended Bobby, if the but Bubba, Bubba blah, if this flag is
not satisfied, the old parachute note that the slag affects only
emulated sound cards effects on drivers present like cursors, accurate
for directs on all versions.
Well, this probably isn't an emulated sound card is the thing.
So that's not a good.
That's not a good sign for us.
But what you gonna do?
All right, we'll, we'll try it.
Anyway, just to see, is there anything else on here that might have a
bearing on it primary buffer?
No static.
No Focus.
No, no Global Focus.
None of this stuff.
None of this stuff looks particularly useful.
Yeah.
Well, we'll try, we'll just we'll try some things and see if we can
get any luck.
That definitely did not prove anything.
Let me also double-check that that's not the right cursor that we
don't have some kind of bug.
We're asking for them in the wrong order or something stupid like that
because that could certainly happen.
Just want to make sure, let's see here.
So back up a little bit to get current position.
It is the play cursor, first the right cursor, s so we're doing that
correctly and not
How much we can say about that set format?
The set format is not going to have anything for us and I think and
get caps.
Well, we can get a caps B.
And there is not a lot there.
We could see if it has this, but that's about it.
So, I don't know.
Not looking great for our hero.
What I will say is let's not despair just quite yet.
You know, it's sort of disparage, be it's sort of time to despair a
little bit to get up, get our despair on.
But what I'm going to do
Who is going to do a win32 Time, marker, or debug time marker?
I'm going to go ahead and put some in here.
That's got basically a play cursor cursor and a right cursor, right?
Like that.
And I am just going to go ahead and use that as what are our.
Is so our markers and our marker account.
And then I will just sort of change this here to that and so we can
get win32 debug time, marker.
This marker equals that.
So at that point, I can do play cursor that way and that will be easy
for us to get out and that's good.
That should just count.
There we go.
And then down in the other function here.
We have to basically do debug time markers and debug markers.
Now, you can see what I'm doing here, is really very straightforward.
I had something working where I was just recording one value and I
wanted to record more than one value.
So I just broke it into a struct.
Again.
This is this is that compression oriented programming sort of style
that I'm talking about.
We're just when you
You need something.
Just do the step that gives you what you need and the codes sort of
marches towards better over time.
Right?
It just gets a little cleaner.
A little better more flexible as you go and everything.
Hopefully works out for the best.
So these are going to be our debug time markers and that should be
roughly it.
So debug time marker index, debug time markers.
And we want this.
To just be that probably get done this with a search and replace a lot
easier.
But, you know, sometimes markers.
You just don't think about it.
And this guy needs to be changed up here.
There we go.
All right.
No conversion, you're right.
There is no conversion, but
You know what?
I can do went through to debug time marker, marker equals address of
that, so I can just snap the address of that.
And then what I'll actually do is I'll just go ahead and get it
directly into to this thing.
So there we go, Mark Guerrero play cursor, Marco error, right cursor,
and now I've got both of them.
So with both of them I can now also go ahead and draw them both if I
want to and see how those look.
As well, so I'm going to go ahead and do that.
I'll just lean on our vertical line draw again.
And so, basically, what I'll do here is just say, okay.
Let's go ahead and pull that out as well into just a little guy that
does this exact thing that and this will be winter to draw sound
buffer marker or something like this.
And that will take is substantively the exact same stuff like so it
will just take
Take the coefficient here that we had and it will just do exactly.
This stuff.
So this is where local functions would be really nice.
By the way, you know, features that sort of get added to the language,
over time stuff that you would want.
That is definitely one of them.
All.
Right.
So all we really need to do here is just pass this, the things that it
doesn't have, which is the Sea and the pad X, the top and the bottom.
So I will go ahead and call that and I'll call it on both.
Things.
So, all right, so bubble back, buffer sound.
I don't know why we're still calling This Global back buffer.
By the way, that's kind of absurd.
It should just be back buffer in here because it doesn't actually care
that's using the global one.
It's not Global anymore.
It's just using one that's passed in.
So we'll get that out there and we'll do this.
There we go.
Paddocks top and bottom like, so, there we go.
All right.
So that's all good.
Now, we just need to pass two different values to it, which is
basically going to be this thing right here.
So this is our value that we actually want to draw that's coming in
and I will just pass a different thing.
I'll pass the play cursor and maybe the color here and pass the right
cursor and a different color here.
Let's say something like that, you know, and this might be a good
time.
The turn off our gradient to say the least, but you know.
It's so pretty.
Sometimes it's hard to part with it.
Certainly.
So we'll do that and we'll get a color in here so we can do them to
the color.
So I'm just going to pass the right cursor and the play cursor, so I
can see the two of them as well.
So let's go ahead and fix that.
Buffer back buffer, and that should be it.
I should be seeing the red ones as well here.
Yeah.
It's just not looking, it's not looking good for Our Heroes.
It.
Yeah, yeah, I don't know.
That's that's not that's not what you want to see.
Certainly in your life.
I mean you can kind of see if I pause this guy at any particular point
in the execution here.
You can kind of see what's going on there.
There's just a really even though we've got some measure of
verification that we're always updating ourselves at basically the
right amount of time.
We're definitely getting just a really bad kind of read back from the
sound card here.
That's sort of
seems pretty unreliable to me.
I don't know.
Hopefully, maybe there's we're still doing something wrong, but you
can see why I'm just thinking getting any kind of tight audio sync
when you've got that much variability, is
Just not probably something that's going to be on the table if that
makes sense.
But what can you do?
Of course, we're not really calling it right at the moment.
So maybe maybe let's go and actually do the work of what we're going
to do today.
What?
I was hoping would be enough today, but you know, with that with
looking at how bad that is in terms of it's tough, It's unclear that
we're going to get anything in terms of sound sink, but maybe it's
just because we're calling it sloppily at the moment.
Maybe the fact that we're doing the lock in a bad.
Way is causing the hiccup.
I don't know, or maybe we've got something else stupid going on.
So, for now, I won't despair quite yet.
It was a little despairing to see it.
But, you know, maybe maybe, maybe we can under spare.
So what we want to do here is since we kind of know, roughly what our
frame sync is going to be.
In fact, we can sort of look back at the beginning here and we can see
what our what our frame situation looks like.
It's pretty consistent.
We always
Are actually getting that 33 frames a second that we want to pretty
much across the board when our app is not getting interrupted or
anything.
We're getting a pretty good read on that seems like.
So if that's always getting 33 milliseconds to frame round trip time,
then basically what we should be able to do at the very least is just
right 33.
We should be able to sort of like keep ourselves that far ahead in the
sound buffer and that should be sufficient for our purposes.
So basically,
When we go to actually write the sound out which is right here, when
we actually go to write the sound out, we should be able to just do it
by writing.
However, much ahead are actual frame time is and, and using that.
So basically,
Basically, what we want to do is we want to do something along the
lines of this.
So we kind of want to go here and say, all right, we're going to do
our game update and render and then we're going to go ahead and we're
going to write into the location that we think the sound will be at at
that time.
Well, yeah, there's a couple different ways we could do this about
this.
This is why I said it.
Going to be very hairy and complicated.
I think I said it originally.
We may have to eat up some Q&A time on this one because it's gonna be
pretty hairy.
All right.
So, the problem that we have is basically, we know we have to write
from the last position that we wrote to write because our Sound Stream
has to be continuous.
And so, basically, what we're doing here is we're sort of doing
exactly that we're passing the B to, right?
And we're passing the samples here.
So what we're trying to figure out here is how far ahead of the of the
current play cursor.
We
Should be writing.
So we're doing the play cursor, plus, whatever.
Our latency is.
Now.
We're expecting the play cursor, right?
From wherever it was.
We basically want to use the play cursor, plus 33 milliseconds.
We want to use the play cursor that we sampled back when we flipped
the previous frame and we want to add our frame latency into that
effectively, right?
So what we want to do is we want to we want to actually go and I guess
this is noooo.
This makes this not really debug anymore.
We actually want to go ahead and do this, this play cursor access.
We want to do that access.
Back here, right?
If that makes any sense.
So what we want to do is say, okay, let's go ahead and take that
sample.
At that time.
Will basically say all right, when we actually grab this, we're all.
So this is no longer.
No, no five minute warning.
No wait, this is selectable text.
Is that actually true?
No, no, it's doing.
I thought for a minute was like letting me select this?
Which is kind of hilarious.
It's actually talking about P Max.
Oh, that's fine.
Okay.
Anyway, so what I got to do here or what I'm going to do here is I'm
going to say when we do our flip, we're going to look at
Whatever the sound card said, it was at that time.
So we're already doing that.
So now this is no longer debug code.
Basically.
This is actually going to be real code.
So we're going to access that play cursor and the right cursor and
we're then going to record them for debugging purposes in debug build
so that we can draw them.
But we're actually going to always also have them as well, if that
makes sense.
So we're going to go ahead and say that there is a plate cursor and a
right cursor, the rod that's good.
I'm going to get them both here.
There we go.
And I will actually store them assuming that they worked will have to
handle it with the sound is valid thing here.
Otherwise, the sound is not valid here.
There we go.
And then I will simply set last play cursor, equal to play cursor.
And so we will actually have some understanding of where the play
cursor is.
Now, we're going to have to handle startup specially, do you word?
Quaker sir.
Yeah, to do Casey handles startup specially but then once we get
through here, went in our sound is valid, whereas our sound sound is
valid.
Our sound is valid also needs to be stored here as well.
Okay, so our startup is going to be totally messed up.
There's no question about that.
But I'm just trying to get the actual frame to frame update working
properly first.
So, when I come in here,
I no longer need to do this.
Basically.
All we need to do is ask whether the sound is valid or not.
And assuming the sound is valid, then we do the computation using the
play cursor that we already have.
So in here, instead of you.
Lakers are we will use last play cursor.
There will be note, cursor queried here and we'll do our computation
off of that.
Now, when we get that, we will then asked to write essentially,
however, far ahead, we want for our latency and that latency can be
the frame time.
Plus some, if we want to add additional buffer in there.
So whatever the latency sample count, actually comes out to be.
Let's take a look at how we're Computing that right now.
It looks like we're doing 15th of a second.
So, maybe what we'll do here is actually
Shorten that down for now to actually be one frames worth.
So that would be basically the samples per second divided by the frame
rate, it hurts.
And then if we wanted to move it back to to be two frames where a so
it's always writing an extra frame ahead.
We can do that for now by putting in the to write this.
We can put like frames of audio latency, something like that.
We can actually say that's a thing that we have, right?
So, we have that.
So let's take a look at that for a second here.
I think that's a little more sane.
Of course.
It's not really going to fix any of our problems that we had.
But I just wanted to get that in their first course.
The fact that I hear no sound right now is not a good sign, but
looking at looking at it.
It it does appear to be a little more stationary and stable Maybe.
Maybe I don't know about that.
Is that more stable.
Serve does look, more stable to me.
Those are not double.
Lines are just weird-- using stretch blitz.
So remember it's going to kind of stretch our Graphics a little bit.
So looks, that's looking better to me.
That is looking better.
I feel like, wouldn't you say?
I don't know.
Looks it looks a little more stable to me.
It's still a little variable more variable than I'd like, but that
looks more stable.
So maybe if we're very lucky, it was just the fact that
Locking the buffer kind of Wonka lie, that was causing it to be errant
and I'm really crossing my fingers that, that's what it is.
And not just the fact that the sound card is going to be really an
accurate on.
This machine wouldn't surprise me because it's one of those weird
Realtek embedded like five cent chips or whatever.
But hey, the reality is that's what's in a lot of computers.
So
You know, we got to work on that stuff.
We can't have some kind of gourmet sound card all the time.
That's not on the table.
All right, so sound is valid.
Let's take a look at what goes on with sound is valid.
Basically, we've got sound is valid being set to True when we can get
the play cursor and sounds valid equal to false when we can't.
So if that's equal to true, I'm not sure exactly why we were having a
problem.
Here.
We were using last play cursor to Target it.
Are we for some reason?
Not owee.
Yeah, that's good.
We drop that succeeded line.
You got to love that.
Succeeded always always comes and gets you.
I think it's succeeded.
Let me double check again.
I forgot what that?
What that
Was so, basically, that was get current position and return values.
Its dies.
Okay, so no, I guess.
I don't you succeeded.
I use DS.
Okay.
Yes.
There we go.
So that should turn our sound back on.
So, at least our sound is back on, never, we're still getting
scratchy.
So we're still got a bug.
Still, it looks a little gappy.
I don't know.
We still got a bug.
That you can hear that scratching this.
There's no real reason for it.
So we're doing something stupid.
I'm just not exactly sure what.
So, let's step through and see what's going on here because I kind of
did that a little bit.
Hastily.
It does say the Q&A begins now, but I think I'm going to go through
the Q&A time a little bit just so I can kind of finish debugging.
At least the step that we were on because I don't want to sort of lose
the mental state if you will of what the changes that we're trying to
make because it's nice to be able to make a single change and then
kind of like put it
Down and say, okay, we're basically done.
So I'm going to remove this to do because that is exactly what we're
doing here.
So assuming the sound is valid, we're going to take a look here and
look at where we were in The Sound output and we are going to map that
into our sound buffer.
We're going to say that and that's just where we're going to right to
right?
Then we're going to take wherever that last play cursor is.
So that's where ever.
We flipped the last frame.
We take a look at where that is.
We're going to advance.
However, many samples of latency we want.
We're going to advance their times of the bytes for sample.
And then we're going to basically say that is the location that we
want.
We're going to map that essentially into the buffer size as well.
So we're modding both these by the buffer size to make sure they both
stay in the buffer.
So assuming that the bite to lock is greater than the target cursor.
That assumes that it wrapped.
I guess, just assuming that it wrapped.
Then the B strep is right, is the whole sighs - whatever the B to lock
is.
So this this looks a little hairy to me.
Actually, let's Okay, so this is
We're just going to say we're going to check that next but I want to
take a look at that.
So, all right, so we'll get rid of this map is where actually
debugging that.
So we make the sound buffer.
We basically say how many samples we're going to write and that's
however much we computed in here.
So this guy is controlling everything.
This is basically compute.
How much sound too, right?
And we're okay, so we have that.
I would like to know.
Where does where does running sample index?
Where does that get updated?
So that gets updated in here.
So basically our our out, our fill sound buffer will advance that and
it's updating it correctly.
So that's good.
Okay, so we're going to lock that.
We're going to figure out what's going on there.
We'll look at that.
That's we're going to check.
More detail later.
So we call the game update and render and that actually gets our sound
output for the sample.
The number of samples that we thought we wanted which is basically
however, many bytes.
There are my /, the B for sample.
That's how many samples were going to write.
So that's fine.
And then we're going to check if the sound is valid.
Meaning if the last time we looked at the position that actually was
able to give it back to us.
We are going to go ahead and fill the sound buffer at that point with
whatever came back from the game.
We're then going to sleep.
Just gonna go ahead and wait and let it cut.
Let it catch up to where that should roughly have been.
And that's fine.
We're then going to go ahead and do seconds elapsed.
And then once we actually do the flip, we're going to look at where
the play cursor was.
So that doesn't look totally stupid to me.
There's nothing obviously dumb about it.
But of course, there's a lot of math in there and it does seem like
it's like a little finicky.
One thing we could do and maybe this is a good idea is to sort of
encapsulate, some more of this math.
We're doing a lot of this map by hand.
Here.
And there's a lot of possibilities for error like when stuff is in
samples versus in bites and stuff.
And it's kind of the onus is on you.
When you write each individual equation to do it, right?
So it could be that we should go ahead and capsulate that.
So what we have a handle that works the samples or something like
that, that we just use.
And we know that gets map down to B properly something like this, we
can think about that.
But for now, I want to take a look at this.
So basically, let's see what happens the first time through here.
We have some Target cursor, right?
The first time through your sound is going to be valid.
Anyway.
The next time through, we're going to have a location and we're going
to have a place of running sampling.
I set to zero.
So we're going to write we're going to do an invalid right the first
time through, which is why I said we have to handle startups,
especially because we're going to write for the getting a buffer to
where we should write.
But really what we should do, is only right from like the right cursor
up to there.
So, really, there's a thing that's like, if it's the first time, you
know, it should use the right cursor.
So like something like this to do if first time through, right, from
right Chris, or kind of a
Or just if it's the first time through in fact, you know, we can we -
let's do this.
So all you actually have to do is the running sample index.
The first time sound becomes valid.
Again.
Basically, we would say if the sound was, if sound was not valid,
right?
If the sound was not valid.
So we lost where we were playing somehow, which is would be on Startup
or at some other time when the buffer went haywire some weird thing
which probably should never happen.
But let's say it did then that running sample index where we need to
write.
It should just be the right cursor, right?
It should be the right cursor, like where we should write to, and we
just need to map that into samples.
So in order to do that, we just have to divide by the samples, the
bytes per sample, right?
That's that's really all we have to do.
So we're just going to do that.
And and so that actually at least we'll make it be the more correct in
theory on Startup.
I think we'll have to well again, we'll have to actually debug that.
So I think that's right.
On Startup now as well.
Let's go ahead and look there.
I take a take a look at that.
Special handle start up.
I said there it is, especially because now we're actually handling
that.
So we've got a bugs, but we are actually least trying so, okay.
What I'd like to do, I guess is take a quick look at what actually
happens when we come in here, but I want to check out this equation is
by inspection first, just so I can see what's wrong with it.
So anyway, okay, we've got our bite to lock, right?
And we've got our Target cursor.
So if the bite tool,
Locke is ahead of the target cursor.
Then that basically means I guess that we're wrapping.
So we're kind of going to have to write all the way around this, like
the buffer, if that makes sense.
So, our B to, right at that point are equal to, however, much we have
left in the buffer.
It seems right.
Plus however, far, we need to go to get to the Target cursor.
That seems correct.
Otherwise, so in the other case, if they were equal.
All, what would B to write bne base?
Right?
Would just be nothing and that seems right because if they're if
they're the same we wouldn't need to write anything.
And in the other case where the tart cursor is head of b 2 lakh.
We just need to go that far, right?
So that does seem that does seem about, right.
So, what I would like to do now, I guess is just take a look at what
happens the first time through and, you know, what we could do, as
well as we could do an output debug string here.
To kind of give us just a look at what's going on, just periodically,
right?
We could do a thing where we basically say.
Okay, let's go ahead here and just do a little
This way, let's just do a right.
That's just basically going to tell us where we wrote to where the
play cursor.
Was that sort of stuff.
So let's just do something like this, where we say, the play cursor,
whatever it was the bite to lock and the target cursor and the B to,
right?
So that just so we can have a little running log again, just a sanity
check and before and then the next
Be obviously 22 to actually go ahead and draw these out a little bit
better so we can see why exactly we're getting that skipping.
Because I'm going to, I can draw these, I could draw these rights in
as well.
So, B to, right?
Let's see here.
Target cursor, B to write B.
To lock go.
So now we'd also get a log of our audio so we can just take a look at
it here and kind of see what's going on.
So, looking at this, right?
This is actually kind of roughly what we would expect from a hardware
that wasn't reporting itself.
Very granular e, right?
Basically getting a bite to write value, that stays locked at some
very close values.
So they're either, it's either writing this much or it's writing this
much.
And so, that's exactly what we expect for something that updates at a,
you know, a non cycle gland granularity.
So that seems totally reasonable.
It also kind of tells us.
Wow, that the the granularity is not particularly good if that's
actually the case.
And we could actually see, I guess what?
The granularity was if
We wanted to one thing that we could do, which would be kind of fun.
I suppose is just to sit in a locked Loop and see how often that that
updates that would actually tell us, I guess, exactly.
Once we actually start things, once we actually start the direct sound
buffer, playing wherever that is lay.
There it is.
We could sit in the locked Loop right here and actually take a look at
that.
In fact, I may actually suggest that, that's actually what I want to
do.
So you can see what our granularity is just right off.
The bat.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
So basically right here, I'm going to go ahead and do a while loop
that basically just locks us up the app will never exit when I put
that this in here.
Basically, what I'm going to do is I'm just going to take a look at at
what that what that play cursor and what that right Chris or are
reporting as we go.
So basically I'm just going to do this call right right here in a lock
loop that will do nothing other than it.
And then I'm just going to print those out.
So I'm going to print out play cursor and right cursor as B.
So play cursor and right cursor.
And that'll let us see how often they even update at all, like what
the granularity is.
Yes.
Thank you for telling me that it is unreachable, code.
It certainly is unreachable code.
I'm well aware of that.
Fine.
Let's let's say while Global running equals.
Roo are you happy about that?
Because that make you happier.
Thank you.
All right.
So now oops, gotta have a carriage return in there.
So now we should be able to see as we go.
Did I miss a carriage return in the other one, too?
No, I didn't happen there.
So now, we should be able to see what the granularity here is here of
the sound cards reporting, right?
This will basically tell me how often it updates because you can see,
basically, it just reports the same thing over and over and over and
over again.
And when it does, go up goes up by a very specific value.
So, if I do this calculation, right, this is in B, remember
This is printing out in B.
So if I do this calculation, the sound card is giving me back that
position.
The previous position, it gave me back.
Was that one?
And that's 1920.
Well, 1920, first of all, we know we are running at four bytes per
sample, right?
That is our bytes per sample to 16 bit value.
So I divide that by 4.
Get back 480.
So 480 samples should roughly be so 480.
Samples is my value.
I'm going to write that down here.
So don't forget it.
480.
Samples is the granularity that I can hope to get back from this
thing.
And the number of samples per second is that is 48,000.
So assuming that we're updating at 30 frames a second that 480.
Should actually be three per frame.
So it should be enough for what we're trying to do to work.
That's above Nyquist.
Certainly, it feels like that.
Should be able to work.
I think about this so it's updating.
Unfortunately.
Sample granularity for each frame, right?
We have 30 frames a second.
So we have 1600 samples in a frame.
So 3200 samples is how many ahead we would be writing?
Is should we certainly shouldn't be getting Skips from that?
So we're Stephanie doing something wrong.
I'm just not exactly sure what it is.
But that's good to know.
I'm just going to drop a little comment in here next to this little
while loop that we just made.
So basically put an if 0 around it so it doesn't compile but then I'm
going to put a little thing in here that says note Casey this test the
audio update frequency the erasers here to play cursor, right?
Cursor update.
Frequency on the handmade hero machine.
It was for an 80 samples, right?
So, there you go.
So for any samples was our latency, alright, so moving them back to
where we were at for we're getting our nasty audio Skip and why are we
getting that?
So the play cursor was here, right?
Arbeit to write was quite a bit ahead of that.
And then the next time the play cursor was here.
I guess we should also probably be recording what the right cursor.
Was.
Maybe we're not far enough ahead of it.
That's a good question.
I guess.
I'll double-check.
That as well because we don't know how far ahead that right cursor
normally is.
Well, actually, you know what we did?
Because I just actually ran the thing that said that, but I'm going to
add that into our thing here.
So, last play cursor.
I'm going to put in the last right cursor as well, or actually, not
even the last one get current position.
I'll actually just go ahead and call that right before we do our
right.
And then print that out so we can essentially see exactly where we
ended up writing to.
So basically what I'm going to do.
Here.
Right is I'm just going to say okay get that.
Get that current position right there.
And this should probably, we should probably put internal build around
all of these.
Where is the build-up at here and made internal?
Yes, we're going to have to go through and put that around a bunch of
stuff.
But anyway, we're going to take a look at that and say, okay, give us
back the play cursor in the right cursor, right?
At this time.
We're going to ignore the play cursor for now, but then I'm actually
going to go ahead and do this print out down here.
So that what I can do is say, alright, when we feel that sound buffer.
Where did it actually think we were?
So this is the play cursor.
This was last play curse.
And then this is what the play cursor, and the right cursor are now,
right?
So that we can just see, did we did we actually just miss our timing
or something?
Are we writing are we not giving it enough Headroom that sort of
thing.
I'm just trying to figure out what our problem is with the skipping.
So I'm just trying to look at where we are writing in the buffer.
That makes sense.
So, let's take a quick look at that.
All right.
So the last play cursor was here by the time we query.
It's here.
So it has advanced one.
Once here is where the yeah, so that's well, that's the numbers, don't
lie.
Ladies and gentlemen, the numbers do not lie.
Basically the right cursor is just hella ahead of that play cursor.
So it looks like it looks like, we're pretty much going to have to
increase that audio latency.
It looks like the audio latency.
Isn't going to be enough.
That's unfortunate.
That's a lot of audio latency.
If you think about how far ahead that is.
Gosh, yeah, that's that's kind of crazy.
But that looks like that looks like the truth.
Is that, is that really right?
So so what's what is the Delta there?
What is the, what is the mandatory audio latency?
Basically the lowest audio latency would ever hope to get coming out
of this coming out of direct sound here.
What is it?
5920?
Holy cow.
Look at that.
Look at that value.
Oh, man.
All right.
Well, alright, that's so that's the number of samples, right?
And that's like several frames, right?
So how much of a second is that?
If I do the Divide paste?
That's oops.
Did that wrong?
Let me do that one.
More time.
We need, I need some better than this calculator for doing this stuff.
So that's the number of bytes so divided by 4.
That's the number of samples and so basically 1440 so 1440.
Wow, so it's actually gosh.
So it's actually asking for 30 frames a second ahead of latency just
to begin with, so I'm going to have to be even more than that.
Yikes, so I don't know.
I'm maybe I'm misreading these numbers.
Maybe it's just, you know, like I said, I'm it's always a bit of a
rush here when I'm doing stuff on a livestream.
So it's a little bit tough.
Me.
I will say that but that that looks to me.
Like, basically what's happening is, we need even more latency above
what we were already specifying.
I could be wrong about that.
So we'll just go a little Hog Wild here and see if that's true.
If I say four frames of audio latency, for example, what do I get?
Well, that's scary people.
That is scary.
Well, I'm glad we stuck with it because we know the piece of
information now that we needed to know which is that basically we are
talking about something that's going to force to write pretty far
ahead.
And we do have a very narrow range there.
Maybe we should look.
We should probably look at the right cursor.
First.
Look at how far ahead it is normally and adjust our latency to
compensate for that.
But yeah, there's not a lot more.
We're going to be able to do.
It looks like two frames of latency is just not quite enough to make
it work.
So we'll have to yeah, it's just not quite enough and it catches up to
us.
All right, well,
Not what I would have hoped for.
That's a lot of latency.
That's a lot of latency, but that's just, we're going to have to live
with for now.
Yeah, that's just quite a bit that it's basically mandating there.
I, I guess that'll be interesting thing when it comes time to kind of
tighten things up for ship.
Maybe we Implement X audio, and we see if we get lower latency out of
it.
Or we hope that we do anyway, I don't know.
But I would say that's about probably it for now.
We're almost out of time.
I would like to take 10 minutes of questions, if we can, so I don't
want to go any longer certainly, but we would probably have to still
tighten this up a little bit tomorrow, because I kind of slammed all
that in here.
And there's a bunch of loose ends like all these printouts.
The stuff.
So we're going to have to wrap all of that stuff up as well.
So we're not really done with what we want to do today.
We're pretty darn close though, but we're not quite done because what
I want to do here is actually draw where we're writing to so that we
can look a little bit more what's going on.
So I'm going to say to do draw where we're writing our sound because
that's where I'd hope to get to it.
Hope you get it to playing smoothly and drawing it out so we can see.
And so we'll have to do that tomorrow, which means we
might spill over into Monday or maybe we sneak in a secret week and
stream, you know, you can you can work over time once in a while.
So we'll see.
All right.
So with that stated, let's actually still do 10 minutes of questions.
If you could, please make sure that your question includes senior
ettore in it somewhere so that I will see it.
I have a little thing that looks for see meritorious so that it cuts
out talk between people and basically if you could please keep the
questions, two things we did tonight.
Or in a previous night.
Let's not talk about stuff.
We're going to do in the game later because we will do that when we
actually get there.
And we've obviously got tons of stuff that we've already done so far.
So, let's keep the questions to that.
All right.
Let's see.
Are you set up to use?
ASI sound drivers?
I'm not set up to do anything special on this machine.
It's as far as I know.
Anyway, at least I don't think so.
It's just a default install of a default sound card.
So, you know, I had hoped that you'd think that by the time you get to
Windows 7, right?
You would have mandated low audio latency to people and you'd have
like the pipe out to the card.
Would be good and whatever but you know,
It still requires all this special Finnick finesse, I guess to do that
sort of stuff and or maybe they don't support direct sound properly
anymore.
And so if we switch to X audio or something, it would, I don't know.
We'll find that out down the line.
But yeah, it's kind of sad.
It should just work right and there's no reason why this sort of thing
shouldn't just work, so it's kind of unfortunate.
Is your audio pointer code?
Calculating.
Independently of the variable?
Fixed visual frames per second.
Yes, essentially.
It is.
So basically, I have those two decoupled at the moment.
Basically, what's happening is the audio is just looking.
So the reason that I have to do that is because the audios clock is
not guaranteed to synchronize with the computers clock, right?
There's no reason why the audio output clock has to actually match the
wall clock.
They could diverge and if they diverge even
Little bit, then over time, that could lead to a big error that would
cause our audio to be running to the wrong place, right?
So what I need to do is I manage my own frame rate here.
Right?
I manage my own video frame rate.
And then what I do is I just look at where the sound output is when we
flip and I go.
Okay, that's where we were when we flipped.
So ideally, we want to write to a particular frame boundary.
We need to look and frames in the future.
And right to wear a frame, boundary will be in the future.
That is the earliest frame boundary we
Right to write that that is past the latency of those past, the audio
latency of the sound card.
Now, we could go a little further of this and right.
Just only however, much the audio latency of the soccer was and not
truncate to a frame boundary, but that would basically pass that
burden onto the game code to have to think about its audio output
being uncentered from a frame.
Should we do that?
Should we not do that?
I don't know.
I mean
I think you kind of want to optimize more for the well working
Hardware case where stuff goes out, the HDMI kind of are synchronized
and maybe, you know, penalize the 0s in some sense for being crappy
about that sink.
I don't know.
I'm disinclined to complicate the game code in the service of this but
you know, it's again it all depends on what your aim is if you want to
get that extra, you know, Ms or two of latency out because you're an
audio game like, for example, a beat matching game, you make different
trade-offs.
And so I'm certainly not going to say that one way is, right?
Or one way is wrong because that's totally not true.
But I think for this game, I'd say,
Let's keep it on frame boundaries and that's that.
What kind of what sort of problems can high audio latency introduce?
Well, they don't really introduce problems for say they just make the
experience feel a little less tight.
You know, ideally I'd like one frame of audio latency so that
basically the visuals are almost exactly in sync with the Audio.
I mean perfect in best of all possible worlds there.
Exactly.
Synced, right, but that's not, I guess realistic in this particular
case.
Now if we wanted to we could trade visual latency for audio.
See, right.
The way that we do that is we render frames and save them.
We'd buffer them up.
Right?
So, we'd render like three frames and we'd wait to flip the first
frame until we knew the audio had caught up, right?
And so, we'd always sort of be flipping behind where we knew the audio
was, but that would introduce control lag into the video.
And that seems like a really bad trade off.
So we don't want to do that.
Right?
So, we're kind of at a situation where we don't have any choice, but
to take the audio lag.
Because that's just what what's going to happen and what that means is
that you know, you push the button and ideally, you know, if you shoot
or something you want the shot sound to happen.
Exactly.
As you push the button and audio latency the higher.
The audio latency, the more lag there is between when you push that
button and when you hear the result, now people are actually very
forgiving about this sort of thing.
They sort of interpret things that's happening.
They interpret sounds is happening synchronized to events.
Even if they aren't.
So if they
See a shot and they hear a shot sound.
Even if they're very far apart, people actually think they're
happening at the same time.
So as long as your game doesn't rely on them, hearing the sound and
reacting immediately to it like a beat matching game.
Does your probably actually.
Okay, but even though the brain accounts for it, I still do feel and
you know, this is subjective certainly, but I still do feel that
narrowing, that audio latency does make it feel
Nicer to play, like taking some of that slop out.
Just, it feels more visceral.
When your brain is doing less of that correlation.
You kind of are sort of aware of it, when it gets above a certain
threshold.
Now, where is that threshold?
Your that threshold maybe like 100 milliseconds for a lot of people,
right?
Which we are well within.
But, you know, if that if that's at 30 milliseconds for most people,
let's say,
Then we are not even close.
We are going to sound a little laggy to them.
And so that's why it's just disappointing.
I was hoping that the hardware Windows to Hardware pipeline would have
been better.
There it is.
Could you use that Anonymous Union, struck trick to access the members
of bitmap info header structure more easily.
Not really, because there's nothing you can really do.
So.
So what the person was asking, was we basically have this and the
question was, if we want to reach in here and access something inside
the info.
Could I use the anonymous trick?
I did.
Hopefully, you remember here.
I use that Anonymous struct Rick out in here to basically push these
names up into
This struct even though they're kind of an interior structure and the
answer is not really.
Basically, in order to do that.
I would have to do something like this, right?
I would have to basically make this a descendant of it.
You can't insert to the best of my knowledge.
Anyway, you can't insert a struct anonymously into another struct in
standard C.
I think there's an extension that lets you do it, but I don't know how
well supported that extension is.
So, I'm sorry, I guess, I don't know of any way to do it.
No, but there might be, well, I should say, I am 100% positive.
There is an extension that can do it, but I don't know which compiler
support it.
Whether there is a standard way to do it that supported across many
compilers that I don't know.
Let's see.
How do you find the level sound libraries to work with, you choose
direct sound.
How did you make a meaningful choice of that over X body or something
else?
The reason is because it's the only thing that's that was that
supported, by default, besides wave out on XP.
As far as I know.
I can look and see whether there's another one that supported by
default on XP, but I wanted something again.
XP was our compatibility Target.
We ran out of
And everything worked just fine and I wanted to make sure that that
continues to be the case.
So I'm disinclined to switch to something else.
At least for the Prototype player.
What we will do perhaps in future ones is we will check to see if x.
Audio is there and try it.
Now.
I think one thing that I would point out is I suspect it would not
surprise me in the least to find that the latency is no better with X
audio.
So I know a lot of people are always excited about like oh, yeah.
It's on in the latency.
Is packages using direct sound, but they don't actually know because
they probably have never tested it on this particular card or
whatever.
And so a lot of times people get excited about something like you
should be using this API or you should be using that API, but that
doesn't actually come from experience and they're just kind of
speculating, right?
And so, what I would emphasize here is we don't actually even know if
that
Proof things, we will test later whether that will improve our audio
latency.
But it's entirely possible that this machine's audio latency just is
what that is and we're not going to get any better.
So we'll have to actually see in practice if that's the case.
So I wouldn't get too excited about X audio or wdm or any of the other
Technologies because it may be that they're all roughly the same
latency and it's the sound chip that is actually causing the latency
and it's driver is just latent right?
And that could very well be the case.
So I would hold off on that kind of speculation until we actually have
some data because otherwise it's just pure guesswork.
I think that some or another API will be better.
Let's see.
Let's see here.
I'm not seeing.
Any other questions?
That are about the audio stuff.
Let's see.
Okay.
Here's some, yeah, sorry.
Okay, miss this part right here.
I don't understand what this means.
Someone said the sound is looped.
Begin Loop is at end Loop.
Causing mega loop simply space the code and this will help.
I don't think I understand that.
So you may have to repost that direct sound docs say don't write
before right cursor.
Why are we safe?
Ignoring it suggestion.
Don't overlap play and right vertical lines, use half screen for each.
That is a good suggestion, by the way.
Well, we're not really, probably going to ignore the right cursor.
Like I said, we kind of, we will probably use it in the future.
But what you have to understand is the right cursor.
Actually isn't relevant to us.
The right cursor.
Is just something that says don't right before this.
Now.
What we actually care about is where the play cursor is, right?
And since the the play cursor on the right curse are actually
technically usually locked but they're not really it's under no
obligation to lock them.
So we want to do is look at the play cursor and say ideally what you
want to do is write this far in front of the play cursor, right?
So, all we really want to do with the right cursor, is just add a
little bit of code that says, make sure if for some reason, the right
cursor is actually further out than that by on average like will look
at where the right Chris, are how far apart the right?
Kristen plugins are, are on average.
However, far the right cursor, is a way if that is more than what our
expected latency writing is then change our expected late written,
latency writing to encapsulate that, but we don't actually want to use
the right cursor because the right curse is actually irrelevant.
Avant.
It's just something that says your latency better be more than this,
but it doesn't actually help us.
It doesn't actually give us information.
Where the sound is playing, which is what we actually care about for
synchronization, if that makes sense.
Do you think splitting related functionality like the sound into their
own files would make it easier to conceptualize and debug not really
impact in?
Probably make it worse.
The reason I say that is because if you take a look at what happens in
these Loops, they tend to get very interrelated very quickly.
So for example, we know that we need to take our our sound check.
We need our sound check to happen, right?
When the flip happens.
And so this is like, coupled code.
And if I was to pull all this out into other code, that wouldn't be
true anymore.
Now, if we want to put it in a separate file and make calls a bunch of
calls in here, then that's fine.
But I'm not sure that actually buys us very much.
It might actually make it harder to read because you have to guess
what that function is doing.
So, no, I don't think it would improve it very much, pulling it out,
into a separate file.
I think that would just make more work, but I'm not sure.
It's kind of personal preference.
So if you want to put it in a separate file, that's, you know, that's
how I see it up to you.
If we use the play cursor as offset.
Could we not overwrite previously written audio data?
Well again, maybe I need to draw a diagram because this seems to be
confusing people.
So I'm just going to go ahead and draw it one more time.
Just so we can kind of so that we can kind of get a feel for it.
Here.
I don't know what I'm going to use to draw it.
I guess I could use smooth draw again.
But I think I'm just going to go for the good old Microsoft Paint
painting tool of Champions.
So anyway.
Just to be 100% clear about what's happening here.
We're going to get something.
Well, okay, let's do our frame ticks again.
So here's our frame ticks.
These are happening at 30 frames a second.
Right?
So basically each one of these is going to be 33 milliseconds
approximately, right.
Thirty-three point three, three, three bar.
So what happens is we're going to query direct sound and it's going to
give us back something that looks like this.
It's going to give us back.
Something that says the play cursor is here and the right curse.
Is here, right?
And we now know that the difference between these actually itself is
like 33 milliseconds, if I remember correctly, right?
That's what we computed.
So, given that, this is true right to me.
What we want to know is we want to know where ever the play cursor is,
right?
We want to know where we can safely right to?
That's a frame.
You know, where what?
What frame boundary.
We can start writing our audio to where is that in our
How should I explain this?
Which of these frame boundaries?
Can we safely right to such that the right cursor, if you will won't
catch.
Up to there by the time we actually output it and we want to be as
close as possible to the fact that when we actually do the page.
Flip the play cursor will hit that when we do the play, the page flip.
Now what we've basically determined is that that's impossible because
our frame rate is actually roughly the same as our audio latency.
So we're basically in a really bad position where we can't pop.
It would just be cutting it too close to try and do it.
So we actually need three
Frames of latency to make this work.
And the reason for that, is that since these, this is about one frame
ahead.
Right?
The right.
Curse is about one frame ahead.
When we did our testing, what that means.
Is that wherever the play cursor is.
We know, we probably can't write.
We know, we definitely can't write to this because it's already behind
the play cursor and we know that we probably can't write to this.
Because given the granularity of how this is being updated.
We don't even know exactly the right cursor.
Could be anywhere really in practice.
We're in a lot of
But we don't actually know what's going on with a lot of these things
because they're moving as we go.
So really, we have to Target basically one frame ahead of the next
frame that it could be and that's where the 3 comes from.
So we're on this Frame, right?
We have to skip this one.
Probably unless we hit it dead on and so we gotta always write to this
one.
And that's where we come up with our computation.
So the answer is can we ignore the right cursor?
Know, we have to look at that Delta there and
Find out what it is and make sure that whatever our frame latency is.
It's above that value.
Right?
But we don't actually care where the right cursor is ever.
It.
Doesn't matter.
What we care is, how far it is from the play curse, or we care about
this Delta, right?
Because we're trying to synchronize with this.
We're not trying to synchronize with this, we don't care when the
right curse or hit, something we care when the play cursor hit.
And that's that's about it.
So really, it seems like this is stupid when I'm saying it and that's
because this audio card is so latent, but imagine what would happen if
this audio card was better.
Imagine what would happen if when we queried it looked more like this,
right?
So here's the difference, right?
So here's the play cursor.
Here's the right cursor.
And now you're saying, well, let's synchronize using that.
Well, that's stupid because what's going to happen is now you've just
introduced that much audio latency.
On your frame boundary because you're going to synchronize with when
this thing hits that thing and that's wrong because this is actually
the playback.
So on a good card you would be very much better off thinking with the
play cursor because it's going to be very low latency.
And that is the thing you're trying to sync with.
So, you're only checking this ought, your only checking this Delta
here to figure out what your safety margin is on a bad card.
Well, it's already totally late in anyway, so I actually don't mind
the fact that we're a little more latent like let's say we're you
know, we're a little
We're you know, an extra 10 milliseconds Layton when the thing was
already 33 milliseconds, latent isn't as big of a deal to me
necessarily.
Like I said, we could be a little more proactive about that and cut
that down so that we wouldn't have that by allowing the game to write
on non frame boundaries, but I don't know, I just don't know if I feel
like that's a good trade-off to make their, we'll have to see.
So that's that's currently what what I'm thinking.
It looks like it might be the case that just like you'd favor.
Direct sound over wave out in Windows XP.
You should favor Wasabi or wave out for Vista 7.
So we might need to back ends for Windows based on OS.
We wanna support both.
Yes, and that's why I said, what we'll probably do is, we'll look,
we'll test at some point, x audio or will test whatever the very
latest thing was on Windows 7 will see if the audio latency is any
better?
If it isn't then we'll be like, okay.
This is just a waste of time.
But if it is, then we'll
I have a thing that says if we were able to open X audio will use it
if it wasn't, we won't.
Wood, rendering at 60 frames a second.
Instead of 30 frames per second, help with this latency problem.
Not really.
It does cut down the extra frame latency by a little bit.
So the total latency would go from an extra 33 milliseconds to an
extra 16 milliseconds potentially on the rounding.
So whichever direction it rounds.
You're rounding to a different granularity.
So you helps a little bit, but that's only because I said that I
wanted to keep it frame synchronized for audio if we decided to
desynchronize it and allowed.
The app to basically be writing to some non frame centered location
which might be a better decision, you know, as I'm saying it more and
more.
I'm thinking maybe we should just allow that because it doesn't really
matter.
The game doesn't really have to know the game could think it was frame
synchronized.
And really, all it's doing is cutting down that latency a little bit.
So it's probably a better thing to do anyway, but at the moment we're
not actually doing that but yeah, so if we switch to that, then it
wouldn't change at all.
The frame rate would be irrelevant.
Could you change latency values based on technically sound card
settings?
Yes, and that is what we will do based on the right cursor.
So tomorrow, we'll take a look at that, right cursor, and the right
cursor.
Will determine our sound are some granularity basically.
Is it possible that OBS is affecting the audio latency?
That's a very good point.
Yes.
It is.
Very, very possible.
I had not thought of that, but you're totally right.
It could be that the fact that I'm broadcasting.
This is what's causing that that could very well be.
I had not thought of that.
It's very good point.
We'll have to run this with after the streams over after run it and
see to see if it's different.
Let's see here.
Alright, I think that's it.
So I'm going to set up some sidhu's for tomorrow just so we know
what's going on here.
So the first thing to say is maybe we should just go ahead and run non
frame locked.
So I'm going to say to do Casey.
Let's think about running non frame.
Quantized for audio latency.
First of all,
So maybe that's just a better idea.
And the other to do is just let's use that right cursor to compute
whatever the latency is.
So to do Casey, let's use the right cursor.
Delta from the play cursor to adjust the target audio latency.
So that will, that will kind of give us that information.
All right.
Okay.
Well, thank you very much, everyone for joining us.
We kind of did accomplish what I wanted to accomplish today.
We're just a little bit behind and so we'll have to push it into
tomorrow a little bit, which means we may spill over into Monday,
maybe 21 days of platform code.
Instead of 20, you know, who's counting software is always late.
That's the kind of the rule.
So if it has to be that way, it has to be that way, but thank you very
much for joining me.
As always, if you would like a copy of the source code to play around
with at home, along with the
Aries.
You can go to handmade hero dot org and pre-order it using this handy.
Dandy little button here.
You can also if you would like to get more information and discuss the
series with people, you can click on this news and forums button and
you can basically get all sorts of stuff here.
There's a schedule on the homepage so you can see what's going on.
There's an episode guide which basically has all the episodes with
extra annotation on them.
So you can learn from them more easily.
There's a coding resources page which has ports that people have done
among other things.
So for example,
If you want to run this on Mac OS X, there's code.
There's information about that.
There's a Linux as well.
There's a bunch of stuff on there.
There's a form, we can discuss stuff.
There's all kinds of things.
So, please take a minute to check that out.
If you have questions, or if you want to discuss stuff in the series.
It's a great resource for that.
I will be back here tomorrow, but it's a Friday.
So it'll be in the morning as we always do our Friday morning.
So it's 11 a.m.
Tomorrow Pacific Standard Time.
Hope to see those of you there who can make it.
If not,
Again, you could always check the video archived on YouTube to get
that, right?
It should be a pretty soon after it plays.
If not, you can always use twitch also has it immediately after it
airs.
So either one of those is your source of that.
Thanks everyone for joining me, and I will go test that audio latency
with OBS off.
So we can see if that really was one of the problems or not.
Okay.
Have a great Friday.
If I don't see you tomorrow or and a great weekend.
I suppose we'll be back Monday at 8 p.m.
PST.
SD.
If you can't make the Friday stream tomorrow at 11 a.m.
Thanks everyone, and I will see you later.