Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here.
Other show Rico to complete game live on stream in the pre stream.
Actually wanted to kind of carry something forward.
Someone was asking about, and it's kind of a good just thing to show.
So I think I'm gonna show it.
I'll just remind everyone weird a 2002 today I'm going to jump right
into it, so if you want to follow along at home, but the source code
and you pre-ordered the game unpack Day 2, 01 source, code and
directory.
And you'll be right where I am right now.
But what I want to talk about just real
before we get back to what we were doing is if you take a look here at
Visual Studio when we build our game, you know, if we right click on
something you'll notice that there's these go to definition go to
declaration things and they're they're always great out.
So we don't actually have the benefit of using those features at all,
you know, in this, in this in this project, right.
But normally, if you build a project and it has, what's called browse
info, you can actually use those.
And so what you can do as I have a I have another project here that we
can look at, right if you're just using this
And heard if you just you know used Visual Studio to create a project
using their project Wizard and that stuff it'll automatically be set
up for brows in phone all that stuff.
So if you're in a project that normally has all that stuff you can go
ahead and like right click on something and you can see that those
like go to definition go to declaration things are there because
eyebrows info has been built and it can load it and so what that
allows you to do and you know it's not I don't find it particularly
useful in my code but I do find it useful in the windows source code.
So for example like you know you
You want to know something you're in this like load accelerators or
whatever.
You're like programming with that.
And you're like, where is that?
You can go, you can right-click on it and go to go to definition and
it'll come back and say, like, oh, that was a pound of find in the
windows headers that like, was mapped to load accelerators.
Wo where's that, you know, go to definition.
Of course, that would be right above it.
But, you know, you can imagine somewhere else and there's the actual
function that's getting called, right?
And that's just a handy way if you're trying to explore around,
someone's code base, just have no idea what's going on.
It's kind of nice because Windows headers are just this huge nasty
mess.
And so being able to just kind of have the compiler automatically
output the data so that you can just browse right to the right place.
It's kind of nice.
Now, you can turn that on yourself.
I just don't know if Visual Studio will load it without a project
file, but you can turn turn that on yourself.
In fact, let me see if I can find it here.
So, in the compiler, I guess there's a
Switch for it.
I have.
Don't usually do it.
So I don't really remember.
But let's see browse info.
Anyone anyone for brows info browse info?
Can you build the browse info?
I don't know.
Let's see browse info brows and foe browser info.
Visual Studio command-line switch.
Build brows info.
Pretty clear right?
Let's see, let's see.
Create browser for Matrix of a browsing compiler creates an SBR file,
I know.
But how to do that.
Ok FR or FR which one of these is the one that we actually want here,
right?
I don't actually know if our creates an svr without information on
local variables.
FR, create such are with complete symbolic information.
So /fr is like the full monty, right?
That's like everything, so /fr and then the path name.
So if we wanted to write, we could try that and just
The if we can get it and I won't spend much time on it because like I
said, it don't really care.
But I just wanted to point out the fact for people who might be
interested in this, it's something that's probably worth knowing can
can happen.
So yeah, if if we just put a minus FR just in their General Flags, is
that going to be sufficient?
Probably like if I just do this, right?
Let's find out.
So yeah, I see them there.
They are SBR SBR, right?
So that looks like it did a reasonable job of outputting that.
And so, I think all we would then have to do is build that into browse
info, which is says, we need to do to run BSC.
Make to create the PSC file, which is used to sway, the browse
information, right?
So again I don't actually know how we would actually put the browser
for modify the browser version file or enable so.
Okay, so we can probably just point it to it directly.
All right, so what we need to do is we need to call BSC make and it
looks like I
Yes we would just pass all those files in so something like you know
the build directory called BSC.
Make start out SBR.
I'm hoping you can handle star.
I don't actually know if it can but we do like start at svr and see
what it makes.
Let's take a look.
So did we get one of these guys?
Did we get anything here?
I don't actually know if we did, yeah.
Yeah, no.
Doesn't look good to me.
I'm not seeing much in the way of stuff here.
People.
And why did all our svr files?
Turn 200.
There it is.
So it just deleted them all.
So, there it is.
Handmade fpse.
I guess I should start at the top instead of the bottom.
So handmade that BSE is now some brows info.
So, in theory and again, like I said, I don't know if this actually
will
Work because I don't really ever do it but in theory inside our
properties for our win32 handmade, maybe there's a way to get browse
information set up in here.
I don't actually see if though, Legacy SQL machine environment to Bear
connection touch argument executable.
I do not see it.
See if the solution has properties.
Start a project dependencies code analysis to look source files
configuration.
Yes, I don't actually see it in here.
So again maybe I'm missing it but my suspicion like I said at the
beginning, is that in order to actually have it?
Do the Brows?
I feel like you have to have an actual project here, right?
And you can be like I think I'd probably a dummy project or something,
but I think you have you can't just have a bear.
If that's what it looks like.
Because let's see what it says here in these docks property Pages.
Let's see, click the C++ folder?
Yeah.
So like that's not going to exist, right?
We we don't build anything in here so we don't have a C++ folder.
Now, we could, you know, probably cheese out and add just some dummy
thing in here to do it.
But yeah, that's that's what you'd have to do.
So, so yeah, so like I said, just something that's good to know if you
find
That you need it.
I never use that but I do keep actually literally just one thing
exactly like this around at all times, which is a win32 project that I
load up, just for looking stuff up in Windows.
Like, I will often do it just so I can do that and go right to the
actual definition for that thing.
Right.
Kind of weird but that's just, you know, that's just what I do.
So that's good.
And now I will go ahead back to what I was going to do just a regular
stuff.
So I'm going to take that out because like I said, I don't need it and
I don't really want the compiler to be doing any extra stuff.
I like to keep the compile times as fast as possible, so, I'm going to
delete the BSC and the svr there, and just go back to where we were
before and let that just lifts that just percolate.
Okay, so where we were at?
Yes,
Is we left everything in a running state, but only because we turned
off the debug code, right?
We the debug code is not actually there, it's just hanging out in a
bunch of ifdef, so if I was to go in here and turn handmade internal
back on so that we are actually compiling all the code, you can see
that.
I just got a ton of Errors to deal with right, and we were right in
the middle.
In fact I think I even left Jimmy
I think I even left.
Yeah, and XXX you are here, right?
What we're in the middle of doing
It's just trying a few different approaches to how we want to
structure our debug variable set up.
I feel like again, you know, I feel like people don't really like
spending time on doing the debug code.
They want to do other things and that's fine.
But that's not really my jam.
Like, I like to make sure that if there's something that I feel like
there's a productive thing that, you know, to look at code wise, I
feel like it's important to look at it, right?
And you have to remember that in general, patients is definitely a
virtue in programming and you know, we're only on day, what 202 here.
So that's like
Like an extraordinarily small number of hours.
That's that's like, literally like, what, 205 hours, something like
that?
I think we estimated is the total number of hours of programming, 205,
hours of programming is like, almost no programming at.
All right, 200?
Five hours of programming is less than 10 weeks of programming.
And so, you know, you, I've often spent ten weeks on a single problem.
So, no amount of fussing with these debug variables that we're going
to do on this stream, should even come close.
Tapping out any serious programmers patience level with it.
And it's really important thing to understand.
Like it's very important that you have to be like one of I guess we
had say it is a crucial quality of a good programmer is that they are
willing to spend time solving a problem.
And you know that often is going to take many many hours, right?
And so, if you're not going to spend time solving a problem, the only
reason for that is because
Cuz you had something else that was more pressing and you had to make
a hard decision, right?
So like you know, if you are forced with some kind of deadline that
you have to hit, then you are forced to make decisions about what to
spend time on and what to not write but we are not in that scenario,
right?
Like we do not have deadlines, this is an educational stream and so
it's very important to make sure that, you know, you spend time on
things enough time on things to see how they should work.
And to go through enough iterations, of how the code is structured, to
make sure that you end up.
On a good one and not just on whichever one you happen to do first or
something like that.
So yeah, it's really hard to overemphasize.
That basically nothing.
We do on handmade hero will ever be done to the point.
That would even be what I would consider a reasonable amount of time
to spend on it actually, just because we, you know, are constrained to
one our night and have a fairly Limited schedule.
So it's like, you know, anything that seems like maybe it's taking too
long.
In your opinion.
That's probably a bad sign.
Like you really want to make sure that you have a very, very
Very large amount of patience for restructuring code experimenting
with code and seeing how it goes.
Because if you don't then you know, you probably honestly, this is
probably not the kind of code for you, right?
Like you probably don't want to be doing low-level programming or
something.
If that's something that that you don't like to do, like
You probably want to be in a sort of a different field or something,
because most of what you do when you low-level programming is working
out things very much like this, right?
So, let's take a look at where we were at.
I was sort of looking at this debug stuff and I'm not exactly sure how
I want it to be structured.
But I know that I want to it to be able to support a few very specific
operations.
And so we were doing is we're kind of going through and doing a bit of
a transform here and you know,
Again, we kind of want to play around with this.
And see what sticks like, see what makes it easy to add debug
variables and that sort of stuff.
So I'd like to go ahead and finish this transformation of the code
kind of get it working.
And then I'd like to do some usage case stuff so that we can see like
exactly how we might want to use this in a few scenarios in the actual
code.
Because again, we haven't really spent much time, defining.
What we might do with the debug variables, we did some simple test
cases, which is, we basically took the debug stuff that we already.
She had in the code and made sure.
We could change all that to Paris, but they were very simplistic,
right?
Like they were just things that were like, Boolean toggles, because
that's really all we had had for debugging stuff so far.
So, what I'd like to do is then, you know, once I kind of get one of
this, this this one version working here.
If you go back to the actual code, maybe make something like an entity
viewer or something like this, like maybe make a debug thing that we
can use to view something non-trivial.
That plus the profile view I think would give us enough of a core like
sort of example that we would know that our debug system was was good
enough at that point, right?
If those things felt like they were being handled in a reasonable way,
that's my feeling I.
So let's go ahead and move forwards.
Oops, let's see here.
Let's go ahead and move forwards on that.
I'm just going to go ahead and let the compile errors.
Drive this situation again.
So again that one of the things that I don't love so far, here is
these
This sort of like VAR, I just haven't decided what the best way to
store these things are and I wanted them to be very flexible.
I wasn't sure about this with a debug variable-rate thing and I'm
still not really sure about it, right?
But I just don't know what the best thing to do there is and it could
be something like this, it could be and maybe this is something we
should do because all of our stuff is like sort of push-based for now.
Maybe we'll just do something like a debug variable link like this.
And we could do something like, you know, next.
So this is a doubly linked list as well.
In here.
Like that.
And then the debug variable arrays would just be sort of a sentinel
based thing, right?
Like this sort of thing.
So this would be like, you know, of our group or whatever that sort of
stuff.
And that just might be a little bit better than sort of thing I was
doing before.
Because again, this is all kind of like pointers Rat's Nest kind of
stuff anyway, that we're sort of doing.
Can add and remove things at any time and other stuff like that.
And so that might just be the easiest way to make sure that everything
stays pretty reasonable in there.
So I'll just leave it like that for now.
Okay, so we've got pretty much everything we want to find here.
So I'm just going to go ahead and make sure all that's implemented.
Let's see.
So if we are doing it the same way, we were doing it before,
when we do debug, add variable,
It just makes the variable when we do debug add variable the context.
What we want to do is say okay we add the variable using the you know,
debug at variable.
But then what we do is we also want to add if there is, you know, a
group active.
We want to add it to the group that was kind of our definition of how
this thing works, right?
And I think we probably also want to.
I'm feeling like we probably want this to be one more layer deep as
well.
So we probably actually want it to look like this, where we have debug
add variable.
And it's got the debug variable like group associated with it there,
you know, although even that I guess, you know, since we had a thing
before it we could just have debug add variable to group and then it
calls that one that seems fair as well.
So that would just be debug, add variable.
And that's just like, okay, we've got the debug State.
We've got the debug variable to add and we've got the debug variable
group.
And that would just be the thing that
That puts it on there, right?
So we've got debug variable link.
We're going to get one of those.
and then, we're just going to go ahead and say that the the
Link preview know like next same same old.
Same old stuff exactly the same way.
And in fact, you know, this sort of thing you can even macro eyes if
you want to go one step further, like I said before, you know, you
can't empathize it, if you want to, you can even make a macro of it if
you really want to like for example, you can see in here, we've got
sort of the previous.
Next thing happening.
Oops, I wanted him a debug
Linked lists are so trivial, you know, you can basically just say, all
right?
When you add something to it, this is exactly what happens, right?
We always know that that's what's going to happen.
So you can imagine saying oh we just want a macro for the way that you
do a linked list or something like that.
So we don't have to type of every time.
It's just going to look like that.
That's what it's going to look like.
So, if you always have next and pretty, if you can do something where
you just say like, oh, all right, whatever the Sentinel is.
Best right, whatever the element is.
You know.
And then this code is literally just always going to be exactly the
same.
There's there's not going to be any, you know, any particularly
nuanced difference at all to it, right?
And so you can pretty much just treat it like a wrote thing.
Something like that.
And so you can do a thing where you like, you know, in, you know,
doubly d-list insert or something like this and you can just say the
Sentinel and the element like that and then this would this would do
it.
Yeah, I'm saying.
So again pretty pretty straightforward, but if you want to just save a
little bit of thinking you can always just do that.
You can say like okay I you know I want to insert.
There's the link that I'm trying to insert, here's the group and I
know that that thing has a has that sort of our group thing in it off,
you go.
Yeah, I'm saying.
And so again that that is also something that we could use in place of
the, you know, of the other guy, this one right here.
So you can take a look at since we know exactly what this is doing.
If we wanted to call dealers insert, you could say like oh well the
Sentinel is this thing, right?
There's the Sentinel and the element is this thing.
So there you go.
Dealers insert inserted right done?
So again, if you hate templates and they always ruin your life or
anything like that and you don't have metaprogramming either and
you're in whatever situation you're like, but I don't want to type it
doubly linked list.
Every time you do have a third option and that's just one macro and
it'll just do it for you.
So that's always good.
If you if you're in the mood again just giving you just give me your
tricks.
Just giving you some things in case you haven't thought of them
already or use them already.
That's one way to do it.
All right, so there is our add variable to group.
It adds it to the group.
That's going to be an address because that's that's actually the
thing.
So then we've got debug add variable, in this case it's just going to
call the debug add variable to group thing in addition to adding the
variable, right?
So it's just going to be like context group and that's going to be VAR
like so on.
And we'll only do that you know, assuming that there actually was a
group for us to do it and then it's done.
Yeah, yeah.
We then have begin variable Group.
Which again is just going to add a variable that's of the
Of that group type, what did we call it?
VAR group, short-term memory of our group?
And I don't know what we call this one too because some of our group
as well.
Yeah.
But our group,
Oops.
Are ya?
Not too much to say about that, other than it is just exactly what it
needs to be.
So then we can do begin variable group that's going to add the
Cable that's going to initialize the group itself.
So we've got this VAR group and again you could do this this way if
you want it to.
Because again, this is exactly wrote and will always be the same for
pretty much any linked list, doubly linked list that you have, right?
The initialization for the Sentinel is going to be the exactly the
same.
It's just going to be that.
Ooh, that's don't want that.
There we go.
That's just going to be the Sentinel.
It's next pointer, has to equal the essential itself.
And similarly, that previous guy has to equal to sine plot itself as
well.
Right?
And you know, we could we can put remove in here as well.
We just haven't gotten there yet but we can put remove in there as
well.
And so, there you go.
That's that's the, the link list.
That's all good.
And so if we initialize the linked list, We Begin the variable group.
The only other thing we have to do after that is make sure we set that
as the active group, right?
So now we know.
And I guess like one of the kind of things that's a little bit
annoying.
Is, we don't really have at this point.
We don't really have a lot of visibility into whether we will still
want the whole like parent notion thing happening here, right?
So we have like debug views which would store at the information that
we need to store and then we have debug variables, which would have
the tree sort of stuff baked in them as well.
And the question here is, do we still want to store parent pointers
for variables?
And the answer of course here is that well groups are things, we make
you know, but they you know groups are things we make but inside a
group we could be pointing to Any Given variable, right?
And getting back to the previous one is largely because that variable
may be cloned in many views.
Getting back to the previous one is not a given.
So I think we want to mostly do stacks here.
When we're doing traversal because you know, or you know if you don't
want to do stacks and you can do a recursive function.
And let the compiler stack.
Do it for you.
Well, the program stack.
But in this case, I feel like we kind of want to do something where
we're going to do, you know, that kind of, that kind of push and pop
sort of thing.
So when we do the this,
When we do the debug begin variable group thing, we now have a problem
which is that when we do end variable group, we will not be able to do
this operation right.
But that's a really simple thing for us to fix because we can we can
just Leverage The compiler stack here.
All we really need in this case, right?
If you think it through is we just need when you end a variable group
to give back something that says what the parent was.
So if we bundle those together right you know this is just sort of
like a you know variable group Builder.
Or.
If you give back something that has the group itself but also its
parent group, right?
When it's being built, then we get around that problem.
Because now we say oh debug variable group Builder, right?
That result.
We're going to store whatever the context group was and I guess I let
you know how to do that.
That obviously first and then we can just say well and then the group
Is captured that way, you know I'm saying?
So now when we do begin variable group like these guys do here, we
just have to actually have it's a little bit more ownerís, right?
It's this kind of thing.
So that's one way we can do it, right?
And it's really six of one half-dozen of the other.
It depends in this circumstance like what you're trying to optimize
for, which one you would want to do in this particular case.
Since I was just trying to show how that works.
I can show you also the other way to do it, which, you know, might be
useful and that's to have some kind of a stack, right?
So you just have a group depth here and you'd have like a group stack
and the groups that would just be like, however, many deep you might.
Ago.
There's no way you're ever going to 64 deep.
When you're constructing these things.
So you know, whatever doesn't really matter there anything you want.
But point being, you've got the Group stock here and then what would
happen is all this time.
When you're doing these operations, you would look at whatever the the
group dip is.
You'd look at into the group stack for that, right?
So, I basically say something like normally, you know, we say contacts
for you instead.
Now, we'd say if the context group depth is greater than zero, meaning
there is
Something on that stack, right?
And you can actually even get rid of that by pushing it synthetic.
0 on, I'll show you that too, why not right?
That would look like this, you just be debugged variable, you know,
parent or something.
And you do context group, stack, context, group depth like this.
So you do something like this and when you have that, that gripped up
we'd just take whatever the
Previous one was, right?
So the group depth well, I guess now you know what you just take take
which one it is.
So if the group that is 0, we take the 0th entry if it's one so and so
on so forth and so on, right?
Then we would just do exactly what we're doing before.
We just say, you know, added to the parent like that.
It's just past the state there as well.
And that's all you have to do and that gets rid of this stuff if you
want.
So again, if you don't like that and you want to make it again
simpler, you can totally do it that way instead.
It's no big deal.
Okay, so then we inside something.
Like, we can variable group.
What we have to do there is say, okay, we're going to add a variable,
that's going to give us back the variable that we wanted.
And now we want that to be the new, you know, for most group, right?
That's that's the one we actually want everyone else to be added in
from now on.
And so what we do there is we say, okay, whatever the group Death is.
Well, first of all, I've searched that the group right is less than
the max size.
right to make sure we don't overflow but then what we do is we say,
alright, the group depth
Is going to go up by one and then we're going to write into whatever
that group area is.
What, you know us we are now the people on the top of the stack right
now there's a little bit of a nastiness here which is that we can't
because we're actually writing into whatever the next location
actually is this check is a little bit under, right?
It's Miss, it's off by one because it's checking to see whether group
Death is less than a recount but when we increment it cure it might
then be equal to a.r.
a count which is one past the end of the array.
So what we want to do,
Here is we want to back up by one, right?
And say, okay, we have to make sure that's where we were now, again,
that's just debug code, it's never going to get there.
But again, I always like to have a thing that just left me know, in
case I forget, and use this code somewhere else and it's like, oh,
oops my bad, right?
I don't want that to happen.
I want to be notified.
So anyway, the rest of this stuff can pretty much just work the way it
was.
We don't really have anything else, we would need to do to these guys,
but when we get to, the end variable group, what this needs to do, is,
first of all, it wants to assert that the group depth is greater than
0, right?
Oops, because if the group Death wasn't greater than 0, that means we
weren't inside a begin group, so that would be a bug.
But then once we know that we are, we just back the grouped up by one
and we're done.
Right?
So that's all we need to do.
But when we initialize that context, now we do need to make sure when
we use that, debug variable definition context,
This one, we do need to initialize that stack, right?
So instead of this thing happening here, what we actually need to do.
Is initialize it with no group and then we would probably do this
right at least.
I think that's what I do.
In fact, that's kind of odd.
I wasn't expecting that to be what I would see there but okay, so we
have group depth equal to 0 and I guess we tightly don't need to do
that because that's there.
But we would have the group stack first thing
Go to the null pointer, right?
So the base of the stack is nothing so you can always reference it and
you'll find that then we would begin that variable group of the root
and we would keep going from there again like I said I don't really
know why we have that Route 1 in there.
Can't say I get it I'm sure we had a reason.
For it.
So yeah, and the other thing I might do just so we can debug a little
bit of that is say that.
Well, after we add all these things and we do and variable group at
the end, I'm going to assert of the context Group stock depth, right?
Or group depth.
Is Britt is equal to 0 so we didn't leave a group open because I kind
of feel like maybe we did based on what I just saw there and there's
nothing wrong with doing that in our code, it would still work.
But I just feel like that's sloppy and I don't really want that to
happen.
So I'm going to go ahead and prevent it.
All right, so moving along, let's see where we're at now.
So use debug camera.
I don't even know what that's doing anymore.
Debug camera that I don't think it's doing anything.
So let's get rid of that.
Like so, and let's see here.
We've got debug variable tree a tree.
Okay, so now we're into the debug code side of things.
So I think our variable stuff is now relatively correct for the most
part and it's sort of doing.
It's a little it's doing its little thing that it does and that's all
fine.
Right.
And there's some cool things that we can start doing now as well that
I have thought of as we were typing that in, but we'll get to that in
a second.
So okay, let's go ahead and clean this stuff up.
If we're going to do an ad tree, then we would need to actually just
call this debug tree because that's what those are called now and so
if we allocate one of those that's all good and we set the parameters,
they are all basically the same so there's not really that much that
has to happen to that.
That's basically the same as it was for the most
Part.
So all we really need to know is we just need to know what the group
is that.
We're going to be doing it, that's a variable now, not this other
special type so that's all fine.
So then we have VAR groups here, which I guess are just you know, kind
of putting in some placeholder stuff there, bitmap display and of our
group.
This is debug variable to text.
So it's basically just a way of making sure that that we have shown
that.
We know that these things, you know, are not necessary to convert to
text is mostly what I guess, I would say about it.
We don't really there's some things.
I was thinking that we probably want to do here.
But we'll talk about those a little bit later anyway.
So that's all good.
Let's see what else we got.
So when we do right, handmade config.
Now when we do our walking, this means are walking would need Stacks,
right?
Because we no longer have parent pointers anymore.
And, like I said, this was a handy trick, but and it's good to know
how to do a traversal of a tree obviously.
So I'm glad we did it but because now a variable,
Can exist in multiple trees at the same time.
This no longer works because when the thing descends and then comes
back up, it doesn't know which which up to do.
Because there's many people who may have been its parent because it
exists in multiple trees.
So the only way to know is to remember how we got there, and that
implies a stack, right?
And again, just to sort of give you a very concrete idea of what I
mean by that.
So here's right.
Day 20 to Wawa, you know, if I've got something that looks like this.
And I'm trying to diverse it, you know, I go down here and I come back
up using this link.
I go down here, I come back up and I come down here, right?
The reason that works is because this tree
the reason that works with no stack is because this tree has pointers
going in both directions or it did, right?
It has the pointer down but as the pointer back up, right?
And when you have a pointer back up, that means that you can always
just climb up and do that, diversity, can always go up.
I'm done down here.
There's nothing left.
I'll come back up.
Will come down again up, I can come back up because I can always ride
that pointer back.
But if those pointers go away, right, then you can't do that anymore.
And so then you need to have
Stack so that it's kind of like, you know, when you're rappelling down
the side of a cliff you've got the Rope there, right?
So you can always return to higher places on that Cliff, right?
And the same thing is true here.
It's like threading, a rope through it.
So as we descend down right, we can always use the rope to kind of
come back up.
So we want to do is any path when we're on an element, we want to have
a stack that tells us what all the previous ones are.
And that's exactly what we did when we built it right.
That's exactly what this is.
And that's exactly what we're going to want to do Jimmy.
That's exactly what we're running going to want to do.
For iteration, right?
Okay.
So assuming that we're going to have a way of iterating through these
guys.
I don't really remember I know I had some reason I feel like I had
some reason that I've now long since forgotten of why I didn't make an
iterator for iterating over these guys.
And I think it was because there were some like different
Things that happen depending on the expansion like whether you went
down them or not and other things like this and so you know we didn't
really make an iterator type thing for it.
But at this point I know I'm going to at least want the stack part to
be kind of reusable in that sense.
And so I feel like you know, at the very least I will want something
like this.
So this would be like, debug variable
I don't really know debug very well stack, something like that and
there's just the depth and the debug variable.
Something like that.
And so when I come through here and do this stuff and again, like I
said, you know, if you want to you can do this with a recursive
function as well.
In fact, you know if you want I could show you that since you've seen
me do the stack think here we could also do this with the recursive
function.
It's pretty straightforward, right?
When you have something like right handmade config.
You just need to wrap these guys up like this, this stuff needs to be
wrapped up in some state that you pass down and then you just call a
function every time you want to do.
Send right.
So, so basically you know, the recursive function version of it.
just wraps these guys up this like struct right and made fig
and do I really have to do this?
I don't know.
I never like I don't love recursive functions.
You guys know what I would do here, right?
You put this in here you call right hand made config.
It just calls itself every time it wants to descend, and then when
it's done it returns, right and Pops back up.
So I'm I don't really, I never liked doing this.
So I'm not going to do this.
They stress me out sometimes.
All right?
So if you want to write the stock version, like I said, debug variable
stock.
We just have a thing here.
It's got the count.
It's got the stock and really, I suppose, in some sense, you could
even just write it in line.
First, I'm trying to think if I really would say that much from not
doing it but we've already got like the depth you know, so all we'd
have is something like this which is like what was the stack, right?
Something like this.
Okay.
And that's 64 levels.
Deep of a tree which I really don't think we want to be getting into
so it's not something I probably have to think about too hard.
So in here you know you've got this the stock situation I can just
initialize the depth of zero or something like that.
I mean initialise the first one is zero well I don't know if we really
need to do that probably not.
Probably all I really want to do is increment.
The stack death by one
And push on whoever the root of the tree is, right?
So that's going to be the route group and that route group, I guess
it's just a regular thing now.
So that's just going to be probably the route group itself if you
think about it is probably the thing that we would actually just push
on there because that's the variable that we want to actually process,
right?
I think I mean that seems right to me anyway.
So yeah.
So we
Start, you know, we would start with the root group.
Once you've got the root group on there, shooting,
We would just start with a while loop while the depth is greater than
zero.
So like while there's something on the stack we kind of do debug
variable VAR equals
Whatever the stack is.
Like this.
So basically take one thing off the stack and then we go ahead and use
it, right?
We do the should you know, should right thing.
All that sort of stuff.
We then go ahead and say like okay if it was a group this stuff we
don't need to do anymore.
That just goes away, right?
And this stuff is just okay if this was a group that we were
processing, you know?
Then we would want to
Take whatever it's children were.
And push them on, right?
We also want to do a for I Loop in some sense, right?
We want to we want to be able to do a walk of siblings as well.
So we've got those, we got those debug variable links.
So technically in cure while we're on the stack this would really
probably look like this.
So this would be this is really like the VAR group that we're talking
about here and then the for Loop is going to be over.
It's it's a lynx.
Be like, you know, whatever the link is.
Right.
So we've got the VAR group Next wall.
It's not equal to the our group, our group,
Sets it all, we just ride that list or wrong, right?
So just keep going, going going gone.
And then for each one of these, we now have a debug variable.
Which way?
Get out.
And that's the one that we process.
Now, here is the part that's a little tricky, right?
Is if we want to the
Natural order that the stock will give us these things is not a tree.
It's like it's like
And maybe we don't, I don't know, depends on how we want to do this,
right?
But the natural order of the stack is not going to be a tree if it's a
recursive function.
Then usually what happens is, it actually does view them in sort of a
depth first order.
So what will happen is, we started a node, right?
And that node has a sub tree, right?
It's got some people in it, so it's got doodoo or whatever.
Right.
So, it's got a pointer to here.
It's got a pointer to here and these guys have pointers, right?
Is actually essential in here.
So there's, you know, it's really that sort of thing more like you
might say, it looks like this.
You know I'm saying?
So as we're cruising along, here we go through these guys, the natural
order for a stack is to process all of these guys.
So it'll process a,b,c whatever.
And it'll push onto the stack.
Any of these guys who were groups.
So on the on the side, we've got our stack here, right?
And it goes like a oh is he is fact?
No he's not.
I mean see a group noise.
Not be.
Is he a group?
Oh yeah he is put them on the stack cuc group.
Oh yeah he has put them on the stack then go pop.
The
Back and get the next guy, which means that we've processed everyone
at this level of the tree.
Before we process, anyone who be down here, so it processes the tree,
right?
It processes the tree in breadth, first order, it does, it does whole
rows of the tree before it does anything on the lower level.
Now a recursive function would do the opposite way, it would do a
depth first because of recursive function goes oh start iterating is a
A group.
No.
Okay.
It's be a group if so iterate.
Be and it calls the function right there, right?
And that's because what's on the stack in the explicit stack version
is just the data.
But what's on the stack in the code version is code and data, right?
It's got the instruction pointer because it's the whole program stack.
So it pushes the whole eater that whole traversal State onto the
stack.
Essentially, you don't see it, but that's what's doing when you do a
recursive function, right?
It captures the whole state there then, does this iteration pops back
to finish this one, right?
Does that make sense?
So yeah, that's I mean, that's just, that's one sort of, kind of kind
of benefit.
to using the recursive function is that if we want to keep it,
Back based explicit step base for a rewrite, the stack, then you have
this kind of nasty thing where you you have to do the walk in breadth,
first order or you need to do something, that makes it sort of less
efficient if you will.
Like we'd have to think about how we were going to actually reverse
these guys in some way that makes it.
So they will automatically do like you know next we put them on the
stack when we need to remember to let come back to them and so that
They'll go in the right order or whatever else, right?
So having that, you know, thing in the stack is is actually kind of
nice.
Yeah, so if we still want to do it with our own stack and that's
something I didn't think about.
When I was doing it, I was like I'd rather do.
I tend to rather do stocks when I can but in this case it's not just a
question of visiting.
All the elements we actually do care, what order we visit them in
recursive function, kind of hasn't the nice side effect there.
Now it's possible that we could just actually do the stack version in
by augmenting it.
Right?
So if you imagine what that looks like that would
Be like debug variable debug variable iterator or something like this,
right?
And that would be, you know, there'd be a debug variable on here
that's like, whoever is the guy
We need to store what we would be doing, you know, with this Loop,
right?
So we need to store the Terminator condition which is like, you know,
whatever the Sentinel is, which is like the stop, you know, whatever.
Whichever the senseless to stop at I could just call it Sentinel.
We need to call.
We need to do like where we were variable, like, right link that we
were at.
And now, if I augment the stack, this is sort of like, storing that
instruction pointer.
It's like storing the state of the code right?
At that point and destruction point is wrong way to say it.
It's like storing the local variables of the function.
Right?
Is the better way to say it because that is the piece of
Information that we actually needed, you know what I'm saying.
So if we want to we can say like, all right.
So now what we've got is essentially a stack of these iterators
instead
When we push something onto that stack.
Right, it would look like this.
We'd say, okay, the link is going to be the root groups of our group.
Next, that's the first one we want to process, right?
And the thing to stop at there is going to be the route group of our
group.
So now we've got the full state that we needed.
So now when we do this, we just say oh, okay, go ahead and get me, you
know, that variable iterator
Whatever it is.
I pull that off of the stack.
I come in here and I say, all right.
Let's go through and see.
We got to start iterating over and I guess I'll just call that
iterator, right?
We say, like the iterator link, is where we're starting from.
We want to make sure that it does not equal, The Sentinel.
And then, we just kind of chain through there, right?
All of this stuff.
Stays exactly the same.
The only change now is if we get down to here and we see that it's a
group and we want to descend, then we need to store where we were,
right?
That when we pop back we will get to it, right?
So, if you think about it, what that means is that this guy right
here, this iterator.
We almost want to, like, always keep using him.
So instead of popping the stack like this, we actually just look at
what's on the stack, right?
And we actually keep whatever the guy was that's their right and we
use them directly.
So
we'd say something like okay, we want to make sure that the iterator
link is not equal to the iterator Sentinel, we want to advance the
iterator linked as we go.
Right?
Like so and then
We do that, right?
And so this is just saying like, Okay, you know, we've got these
iterators were advancing this iterator as far as we can go when we get
out of that of that advancement then we just say like, all right,
we're done.
So now we can finally pop that guy off the stack right but we leave
him on the stack as an iterator until he finishes iterating that row
of the tree.
Then what we do here is say, like, oh, okay,
And I get we're going to have to do this slightly a little bit, a
little bit differently because we need to be able to break out of this
lit, this particular list in two different places.
So really this this won't exactly be able to go there, right?
And you'll see why in a second.
But so assuming that it's a group that means we want to iterate that
group right now.
Right.
So we want to increase the depth, we want to advance the depth
pointer, you know by one.
So in here we would say like okay we've got sort of a new iterator
that we're going to push on.
Here.
That's going to be whatever the current one is.
We're going to fill it out.
Just like we did before, right?
And that's just going to be whatever this variable of our group.
Next and this variables are grouped was right?
Whatever that is we're going to push that guy on the stock so then we
just plus plus the depth and then the problem.
As you can see, here is now we're like well, okay, if
Iterating over that thing.
We would want to now restart this.
This iteration.
Right.
And so you naturally think like, okay we break out of here but then
it's like, okay, I've got this this.
Now I'm going to decrement my death.
It's like everything's messed up.
Well, the nice part is since we're still in here since we're still in
this Loop, what we can do and say said, is just say like, oh, well,
what we could do is just say whichever one were this, this pointer is
sort of pointed.
Some places stack, we could just move to the next one and use that
next one and have it to start going from wherever it is.
Right?
So,
We could do is just say, like, oh, just use it, ER, itself, right set,
bitter up to be the next one that we need, right?
And so we've moved at one down the stack and now off we go, right?
We don't have to do anything else.
This Loop just keeps going and then when we break out of here, you
know, will break one down and keep going with the with the iteration.
With the pop, the stack popping iteration.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully that makes some sense.
I think we might be able to unwind this one more, right?
We might be able to do this with only a single Loop because we
probably don't actually need these guys.
We just would need something that was like if it hits the Sentinel pop
up the depth.
But anyway, hopefully you get the idea.
So that's like I said, that's if you want to do manually instead of
using a recursive function etc, etc.
But you do you want to control that iteration order.
That's how you would do that.
All right.
So what was I about to do here, convert debug variable link to debug
variable star?
That's a good point.
These are supposed to be links.
And debug variable type group.
Let's just called of our group now.
That's fine.
And what else we got?
Debug drop menu to put variable tree, so this guy.
Yeah.
Is just draw main menu.
I think this guy is just going to be yet another iteration style.
So that's why I was saying like, it'd be nice to kind of pull this out
and have it so that you can iterate over it trivial, you know easily,
because you can see that we could.
Presumably just wrap this guy up into an iterator that does just this
Right?
And I just don't know whether because there's kind of the part about
every time you descend and stuff like that, the drawing code needs to
know that you did that.
So I'm not sure exactly how I want to abstract that out.
That's kind of an interesting question, I'm not sure but since we're
going to do this in two different places at the very least that does
motivate me to maybe do that kind of fight that collapse to see if I
can get it out to just be
Up there.
Which should be eminently doable, right?
So if we were to enter,
let's see here.
if we were to enter this,
With this, just set to being that initial guy, right?
Then,
Or I guess we could say.
I guess we could say, when we pull this thing off the stack,
we could simply check at that point.
We could say, is it equal to the Sentinel?
If it is, we want to subtract one from the depth, right?
If it is not
then what we would want to do is process it, which is what we're doing
here.
Yes, and then say once we've processed it, move it to its next one.
Does that make sense?
So basically while there is something on the stack, we will grab
whatever that is.
If it is something that we want that, if we're basing, this iterator
has reached the end of its iteration.
Then we will pop the stack.
If it has not, we will get whatever the next one was an advanced.
IT one?
Oops, that's supposed to be next.
That would've been a fun, infinite Loop right there.
We processed the variable, whatever the variable is
And then we check to see whether we should push a new guy on right.
And that seems pretty straightforward to me.
And we can sort of wrap this up pretty nicely.
I feel like if we want to write just by sort of doing like a
Bit, just a, just the Bears, just a little touched up, just a smidge,
just a smidge, the barest, smidge of wrapping, but maybe, I'll, maybe
I'll say that for Monday.
So, all right, so if I come down here and go ahead and, and jump to
the right place there, so, there we are.
And I am going to take this guy and use him as he is.
Right, so if we do this, this bit here, again, this variable Jimmy.
This variable tree stuff is just changing the name down to very just
just a regular tree.
Everything else I think is probably exactly the same.
So in here, then we're going to go ahead and do that reversal stuff.
So that kind of comes out here like this.
We then do.
I guess all of this stuff is is all the same.
That doesn't change at all.
And then at the end right?
We do this iteration.
There we go.
And yeah.
That's basically it.
Now we of course, have the problem of our look up stuff.
We haven't implemented yet either.
So we have to now start doing that.
We want to for any given variable.
We want to do something where when we're displaying it, we like I
said, how we have this concept of the debug view for it so anytime we
display a variable we want to get its debug View.
Which will have this sort of stuff, like, what the dimension is and
stuff, like we have this inline block and that sort of thing.
So any given variable has to have that information, so we're pretend
temporarily that we have that, right?
And in fact, I could do it this way where we just go like, oh, we've
got a view and it's set to nothing do.
You cash?
And I guess now I think about too I feel like we would have it so that
when it gets the view for this guy, it's going to need to know what
kind of view it actually has.
And I do think that since the debug view, well, we might even want
different debug view types for different things.
So I feel like it's actually might even be the kind of thing where we
want to do it.
/ one of these, where we say like you know, get debug view for and we
then pass that variable, right?
and in fact, I guess we could do it, you know for everybody and say it
got the debug view for this variable and it will get, you know,
whatever the appropriate debug view is for that variable, then it here
we always use whatever that that thing actually was
Yeah.
Something like that.
So yeah, I feel like that.
That makes sense.
There's something some cool things we could probably even do.
There's just so many possibilities in here.
It's kind of crazy.
Anyway.
So when we do this, this stuff,
I don't think there's really anything else in here that has to be
modified.
It's all pretty straightforward so far.
And so really in here, again, that's just going to be changing the
this to be a view thing because would be view, inline-block dimension.
Like so.
Oops.
But which one is it that?
Why?
Yeah.
Inline-block mention not the .y and let me just let the compile
errors.
Sort of tell us where to go from there.
It's not a member of debug view inline-block, probably just dim, huh?
Yeah.
So a few more here and then we'll wrap up for the day bitmap scale tip
of you and like back does not have an overloaded member operator
Arrow, you are correct, it doesn't.
Bitmap display, dim dot size.
So that's just again, correcting this in mind block.
Dim.
X.
What else we got?
This is just again.
That same thing you inline-block dim.
And let's see what we got for our group here.
Make a dummy.
One of these.
And this will crash us nicely.
Colonel.
There we go, variables are not implemented.
Yeah.
That is not how you spell variable.
The variable B employee would be displeased.
Alright, that'll crash anyway so don't really need a macro there for
that.
So that's fine.
Debug variable reference Undeclared.
That is quite true.
It quite certainly is and I think I'll just comment this guy out for
now because this is the guy who were going to change primarily this
was the this is the tearing off value stuff.
So that's the guy that we're actually going to.
Then once all this stuff is working go in and change to support kinds
of more expressive job.
Drag-and-drop, sorts of things
Barbie implement
with new system.
So then let's see what else we got for our group.
This again is going to have to get that debug view, debug view, view
equals get to bug view for this variable.
And we're just going to go ahead and assume that we get one of those
back.
Whatever.
This guy actually is, there we go, collapsible, that's what it is.
So we would say that the view collapsible
A collapsible.
There we go.
Equals not view collapsible.
That's is also wrong expanded always for now.
Okay, almost done actually.
So I might as well just finish up the last of these
Before we call it a day.
So this stuff profile Dimension.
I'm not going to bother with those for now.
So we'll just go ahead and get rid of that.
Will leave that doing its thing.
What else we got?
Assert context, group, Death, does, not have.
No, remember for you are correct.
That is a DOT.
And group context group.
It's not a member of debug variable definition context.
You are quite right about that as well.
I agree wholeheartedly.
But I feel like this should actually look like that.
Alright, and that's the end.
Of that.
Alright, so that was pretty good.
Again, we're working it into more shape.
Like I said, this is, this is something that takes a while because
these sorts of things want to go through a few different iterations
till you get them just.
So and so I want to keep polishing that down.
We got to kind of take a look again at the the structure.
There may be one more structural change that I want to make, we'll
see.
And that has to do with how we iterate over.
About variables.
And what I'm going to do is again like I said Monday will debunk this
get and get it working.
And then Tuesday, what I'll do is I want to try some test cases in
terms of how we expose debug variables because I have a feeling
there's some different things we want to do there and they will inform
the last change to the structural elements of it and then I think
we'll be in good shape to say like okay this is this is right now.
All right, so I'll go to the Q&A.
Mabel do that.
Awesome.
Sweet.
Yeah, if you have any questions about where we're at so far,
Go ahead and put Q colon front of them and I will try to answer those
questions.
The size.
It doesn't work.
We'll know.
It definitely doesn't work.
Right.
So this is going to return 0.
And this.
We'll get used right.
So until we Implement that it's definitely not going to work.
Now, if you want to just kind of see, like, okay, what happens if we
do something here?
You could try to make a one of these if you want to debug it without
implementing this thing, right?
You can do that.
and, and
But I assumed like I said there's going to be more problems, okay.
So first off I don't really want to do all this because like I wanted
to bug this on Monday stream.
I was correct in that, we didn't close the final variable group,
right?
And you see how that caught that.
Because remember I was like the route group gets open and then the
debugging group has opened that's to opens but then we only do one
close at the end.
Right?
And so I just wanted to
I knew that was not happening and I wanted it to stop Bobby.
Now, like I said, it doesn't actually matter because you know, there's
actually no nothing happens when you close a group in our system.
So you can leave as many of them dangling as you want, but I just feel
like hygienically.
It's good to know that in case you accidentally left.
One of these other ones open, it would warn you at compile time and
I mean again I don't have a I don't have a concrete reason for why.
There's really no real reason.
I just, you know, programmer meticulousness.
I guess something like that.
I'm not sure.
So yeah.
So anyway,
Putting that in will make it not crash.
But yeah, like I said, we got to debug the iteration and the adding
and stuff.
So we, you know, we just we're not really at a point yet where like I
want to do that Monday and see what's going on because I don't, you
know, we wrote a ton of code there and we haven't looked at it at all.
Dear boys.
17 earlier in the Stream.
You said, you once spent 10 weeks on a problem, what was that problem?
Well, I've spent more than 10 weeks on a single problem.
I don't know if I spent 10 weeks on the witnesses Collision detector,
but I probably did.
I'd have to like add it up because I did a lot of different things on
the witness and like only some of it was the Collision detector.
So I don't know if it's 10 weeks but it could easily have been 10
weeks.
And I strongly suspect that it was more than 10 weeks.
I'm just a collision detector.
I spent more than 10 weeks on Granny's curve, solver.
and,
Because, I mean, that was a totally new thing in those days, right?
Like nobody had really been doing any of that and in fact, the the,
you know, the
The Source material added drawn from the literature, nobody was doing
that thing.
I had to draw on the people who were had been doing curve solving for
2D shapes and use that for like sort of the basis of how to start
thinking about it and took for animation.
So that first curve solve, it took a while.
I've spent 10 weeks on.
Yeah I'm absent 10 weeks on tons of problems as I guess the way I
would say it.
Insofar as have you considered using intrusive linked lists like those
in Linux kernel use offset of so I almost always use intrusive Luke
linked lists if you can.
But you'll note in this case we can't.
Because in this case we have things appear in more than one list.
That's why I had to do this, right?
If things didn't have to appear in more than one list, we'd be back to
where we started, right.
That's the way we had it.
That was an intrusive.
Blessed, right?
But in this case, they have to be external because we have things are
going to show up in more than one list.
And that's when you can no longer use it, intrusive linked list.
Now, we have an intrusive linked list, right?
Which is the tree.
So we do have one that's an intrusive like this, right?
I just want food, how portable with a game engine be?
Could it be used to make other games?
Well, portability wise, it'll be very portable in the sense that we're
going to make sure it runs on multiple Platforms.
In fact, it already is like, people have already ported it to svl and
stuff like that but in terms of what you can use to make other games,
I mean, I guess what I'd say is, I don't care.
Meaning, it's not designed, it's not designed to be an engine that
supports lots of games.
It's just designed to be one game so I don't know.
I neither know, nor care, whether it would be usable in that sense
because that's outside sort of the goal of the project that makes
sense.
Cuba, Caleb curve.
Solver a curve, solver something.
Well, I mean, it's just a term that I use
It's curve fitting, really?
It's like a solver that takes a bunch of data that is not curves and
turns them into curves, right?
So, like takes a bunch of points and runs a curve through them or
something like that, right?
And so far as will we ever see the memory chunk?
Debug visualization.
Yeah we'll do that eventually for sure.
I don't really know how we will visualize it.
I can't promise the visualization be very good because memory is kind
of hard to visualize.
Unfortunately since there's lots of little things that so I might just
be like a line with little chunks on it, but, you know, we'll do that.
So looks like we're done.
Alrighty, it's closed down.
And IMAP u.s.
hover currently.
It's on mint.
Actually, I don't have time to install a new thing so I just don't put
it to sleep.
It's been running continuously since the last time we stream,
And so unfortunately, yeah, I will try to make another installation
sometime soon, but yeah.
Insofar as, by the way.
Like I mean, I don't I'm not familiar with the Linux kernel
implementation but intrusive linked lists cannot have items in more
than one list.
At the same time.
You can have more than one threading through that link like you can
have meaning
Right, so you can have a thing that's like, you know, here's my
element.
And here's the next and previous.
If this is what you're talking in terms of intrusive linked list,
right?
That can only be on one list list at a time period.
However, you can always add another one.
Right?
So if you added another set of variables then you can have it on two
different types of lists but not on two of the same type of list.
So whatever this list was if this is like you know the food list you
can only be ever be on one food list but there can be a bar list that
uses a different set of variables and it can be it could be on two of
those, right?
But once you fix this offset whatever that is you can only ever be on
one of that kind of
Whatever that kind was.
Right?
And that's that has nothing to do with your implementation.
That's just fact, that's just like category Theory or whatever, right?
You just, that's just the end of the story.
Can you give me a quick rundown again of how you're substituting the
stack for instances of the debug View?
How you're substituting the stack for instances of the debug view.
Can you ask that question on Monday?
Because I don't think I understand it to be
Honest.
And Martin Cohen.
So what do you use as a formatting language?
Usually, I typically don't do those sorts of things.
Just not something I normally do.
Yeah, I mean, usually I markup things semantically, so I might like
have markup in things that says, oh, this piece is like a, you know, a
proper noun.
You should, you know, map it that way or look up a link for something
that I do stuff like that.
But I rarely If Ever, I just haven't written programs that want to say
like make this next piece italic and it's not I don't, you know, I'm
not disparaging that or anything.
That's totally fine thing to do.
I just, I just don't
I just don't have occasion for it.
I have not had occasion for it.
Keep your cab.
Is this how you DUI and your other programs?
So yeah, I mean some of it is some of it isn't like I said I'm kind of
working out a specific way of doing UI.
I want to show how you arrived at a good UI structure.
So I'm doing something that's intentionally slightly different than,
you know.
The exact way I may have done it before.
I usually try to do that even when I'm doing it myself so I can see if
maybe there's some productive new things that you know I'll learn or
arrived at by try something different than what I've already done.
All right, I'ma call it.
I call it down.
By the way, thank you to everyone for helping me the other day, get my
hex chat to show the list of people.
It's pretty nice.
Now to have it say like 159 or whatever, instead of 0, which is what
it was saying, all the time before, it's nice to be able to see
everyone.
Again, even if it is kind of just a little list of names, it's nice to
see that there's other people instead of the weird thing where twitch
was not telling me anyone was here.
So, that's cool.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero to pause recording with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, with the source
code, you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org, it
comes to the source code and you can play around with it yourself and
experiment with it and learn from it.
And do, you know, other sorts of fun things?
We also have patreon page, you want to split the video series?
It's always much appreciated.
We also have a forum site where you can go to ask questions or view it
anti-deficit guide.
And finally, we have
A tweetbot.
The tweetbot will tweet the schedule at you, and it will tell you when
the life is going to happen.
So you gave when the lashes gonna happen, not tomorrow, I will not be
around during the stream time tomorrow, so I cannot stream but we'll
be back on Monday.
So check the treat pot for that schedule.
I'll try to update this weekend.
Thanks everyone for joining me, and I will see you guys on the
internet until then have fun programming.