And then a start recording.
There we go.
Welcome everyone to handmade hero.
We are here on day 23 which basically maps to 23 hours on stream and
we are closing in on the end of our work with the win32 platform
layer.
We finished substantively all the stuff we needed to do last week.
But this week we are basically spending a little extra time to do some
fun and pretty powerful stuff with it.
So the past two days, I showed how you could have your C code.
Code be dynamically reloading all the time so that basically, you
never have to close the game and reopen it while you are tuning.
You can just go ahead and update your code and it live updates
directly.
So like basically, just like everything you might want from a
scripting language.
You can just get straight ahead with C code, which is pretty awesome.
And we and we played around with that a bit and it's working really
well.
Now works on to the debugger and it reloads instantaneously, so I'm
pretty happy with how that turned out.
But today I wanted to show how to do something even cooler.
I've actually never seen done before.
I mean, I've done it before but I've never seen anyone talk about it
or mention it.
So I don't know if other people are doing it and I just have never
seen their write-ups or maybe they're doing it, and they just never
told anyone.
But I'm kind of excited about it because I don't think anyone's ever
actually presented it.
Maybe not.
We'll see, but it's pretty exciting.
I think because it's really cool feature that you can do very easily.
If you've architected things properly, it's actually very difficult to
do if you haven't, but since we've architected things properly,
Can be very easy for us to do, I suspect?
So with that in mind.
Welcome to handmade hero day 23, where we coded entire game from
scratch using no libraries and no engines or anything.
Just so we can see how absolutely everything works in entire game
stack, which I think is very educational and also very empowering
because it means you can always write anything you need to even if you
are using an engine or a library, you can drop right down in there and
fix stuff.
If you need to or write your own stuff, if the engine falls short, or
something isn't working.
Okay, and it just allows you to understand how engines are working and
it allows you to better sort of manage them from your side of things.
So even if you are using engines or libraries knowing how all this
stuff works under the hood, can be a very, very powerful tool when the
time comes.
So with that, in mind, if you have pre-ordered the game, you should
have gotten a link in your email where you can download a zip file
which has every single day source code in there.
So if you want to since we're on day 23, you can unzip day, 22 source
code.
And when you do that, you will be in the exact same place that I am
right now.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and jump right into it because we have
a lot to do today to get to the thing that I want to show you.
So let's get started.
Basically.
What I want to point out now is we have what we did.
It was a pretty darn cool.
We basically do have, you know, most of what I would want for
something, where you can do Live code anything, right?
I
On the game and we've basically shown this sort of simple.
We don't really have since we haven't been working on the game.
We've just been working on platform code and stuff like that and all
the sorts of things that we need to do to support the game on Windows.
We basically haven't had a chance to do much in the way of an actual
game.
But of course, we have demoed the fact that we can live change,
anything that we want, and it immediately updates pretty much
instantaneously upon change in the editor.
So that's pretty awesome, but
If you think about what happens in a game usually, you know, like
we've just got this kind of toy thing running over here, but pretty
soon, you know, over the next month or two.
We're going to be building actual game stuff.
And there's going to be a real game running in here and things won't
be so simple.
In terms of actually being able to see the results of code changes,
right?
Basically, what's going to happen is we're going to have user input
and they're going to be moving a character around and they're going to
do stuff, right?
And so I just want to quickly create a little very
Example of what that's going to be.
Like, just to point out where we're going to run into problems with
this Live code editing.
And to be fair.
It's not anything wrong.
With our live coding, our lab coding at this point, is as good or
better than mostly anything.
I see out there in in other stuff.
So are our live.
Coding is good right now, but I want to make it way better.
I want to make it so much better that it's going to be like you you
would not dream of using something else after you saw this, if that
makes sense, but in order to demo, why this is going to be cool.
I just need a little bit of something that uses some user input or
Thing so that we can kind of see what happens when you actually want
to tune something in a game.
So I'm going to go into here to our sort of stand in game code that we
did.
That's just sitting here waiting for us to start writing a game in it.
And what I'm going to do is inside you remember we have our game State
thing, where we start some say, I'm just going to add like a very
simple player ex-player.
Why just?
Just so we have like a location where we're pretending the player is
right?
And then I'm just going to flat out say, all right, when we come in
here and initialize that I'm
To pretend the player is somewhere.
I don't know where he's at 100.
100.
Let's say, right?
Just just something real basic like that.
So we, the player starts out at some random location on the screen.
Again, we're not thinking this through, it doesn't matter.
Is just a simple example.
And then what I'm going to do here is I'm going to do inside our our
code, for the keyboard handling, or the non analog handling.
Basically.
I'm just going to go ahead.
Well, you know what?
I'll just use that that stick average X and the stick average y.
So, I'm just going to go ahead and for any
controller, no matter what it is.
I'm just going to go ahead and take the player X and the player, why?
And I'm just going to add to them.
Whatever these stick values are like it just again, I don't even care.
What's going on here.
I'm just going to I'm just going to do that straight away.
And then when we do render weird gradient, I'm also going to have a
ridiculous function called render player.
It is like player in real big quotes here, which will basically just
be, excuse me.
Something that draws.
Anything whatever we can think of to the player location.
Now, of course, we already have some code in here and we'll be writing
our own rendering code very soon.
So we won't have to be so slapdash and sloppy about this but against
it, you know, one thing at a time, we got to go in order.
So basically we have this this win32 debug draw vertical thing, right,
which basically just kind of goes through here and does this does this
nonsense, right?
Basically, what it does is it, it'll draw one vertical line and we
were using it.
Draw these hash marks, right?
So what I'll do is, I'll just do something which basically, you know,
basically does that I'll just do something which which, which let's
see here.
Okay, there we go.
Something that basically just Loops through the X and Y.
In fact, you know what?
Now that I think about it, and if this would be easier, well, now
probably not.
So basically I'll just do something that Loops over some x's, right.
It'll start.
Let's say at the player X.
It'll go to the player x + 10 or something like this, and it'll add to
X.
So, just just the most basic thing.
You could possibly imagine.
And this thing will basically be top will be player, why?
And bottom will be player, y plus 10.
So just making a simple 10 by 10 rectangle.
And I'm going to go ahead and fill that stuff in.
Now this will full-on crash if we if the player moves outside the
window.
So this is this is the like absolute worst code.
You could possibly imagine
Okay, this is never code.
We would even dream of putting the app.
I'm literally just slapping in there because we haven't written a
render yet and I just need to put something on the screen.
So I need to basically pass in a player X and a player.
Why here?
And then let me take a look at actually what I don't actually remember
what these these calls are here.
So it's a buffer memory.
We're going to need buffer, bytes per pixel.
Although we actually don't even need that at this point because
I don't know if we're going to basically fix that value.
This is this is basically for here, but I can go ahead and add that to
our thing.
Since seems like it might be nice to just have it there for code that
could work.
Either way.
Let's go ahead and do that.
So I'm going to go in here where we, where we pass that buffer to the
game, and I'm going to go ahead and add that in there.
So this right here, buffer will be like the pixel, oops, pixel for
Pixel.
And then I'm going to take a look at compiling this.
All right, so the color for the player.
I don't know what color the players should be.
Maybe the player will just be a white rectangle.
For now.
The back buffer is just buffer at this point render player now needs
to get called by somebody.
So we go down here and we will just do it right here to render the
player.
Okay.
So basically just a quick, you know, five-minute thing here, where we
actually
Have something going.
So I don't know if this'll work.
I just kind of slapped it in there, but there is my player, see it,
right there.
And I do not actually know if I can move him.
Okay, I can.
So I have my game pad here and you can see that I can move my play
around.
Of course.
It's a little wonky because I've got the stick mapped wrong.
Let's go ahead and I didn't think about that.
The y direction of the stick-up is actually up is positive.
Of and down is negative.
So we're going to have to go ahead and reverse that there.
But yeah.
Hmm.
So I've got this little guy and I'm moving him around, right?
So basically just imagine that this and I should probably I should
probably turn off the gradient motion and and for God's sake, turn off
the sound wave, so maybe let's just say that game output sound from
now on.
Let's let's go ahead and and and pretend that we're we're just quiet.
We just, we just don't need all this, all this sound happening.
So let's go ahead and and, and basically do this here.
There we go.
So instead of computing that sine value, let's just to, let's just do
quiet because that's going to get really annoying.
All right.
So anyway, here is our little here.
Is our little guy who's moving around.
Why did that?
That was a little odd?
I feel like that's a little odd.
There's a bit of a
Framerate did I did I do something stupid there?
I don't know if I did.
You can see I don't know if you could see that.
But basically I was getting a weird kind of frame rate, hitch
happening there.
I don't actually know why it is.
I think that it's weird because our game still is running at 33
milliseconds per frame.
All right, so we'll have to take a look at that a little bit later.
Although, that may again.
Be sometimes OBS creates a lot of problems for framerate stuff.
So it's hard for me to always know whether it's something we'd look at
or not.
But basically, all I did is right.
I just made a little rectangle here that I can move.
On the screen that's it.
And so what I'd like to do is I'd like to be able to, I just, I just
needed something where I could show sort of what a game would normally
doing.
So I can show what's Difficult about about tuning code.
So let's say right that what I want to do now that I've got.
This is I want to implement a way that this dude can jump or something
like that.
Right?
I want to have it so that when you push the button the dude jumps and
so I'm going to go ahead and just Implement something.
Oh, they're like if action down, right.
We've got this action down thing happening.
So if action ended down, then we're also going to pretend that the
player, you know, jump here.
We're going to move.
We're going to discontinuously move him up the screen by 10 by 10
pixels or whatever for right now, right?
So, I've got my guy moving around, I hit the button and you can see
when the button goes down.
He jumps, right?
And he doesn't come back down or anything.
Right?
I'm just showing you kind of what the deal is.
So that's it.
Right?
Well, let's suppose now that we want to work on our code for the jump
so you can tell that the jump is ridiculous.
It's totally stupid.
In fact, all the player movement code is awful.
So what I would have to do if I was doing this live, right?
If I'm if I'm if I was tuning this code, even with our Live code
editing, here is the process that has to go through it.
All right.
Well, what happens with the jump?
Well, I push the jump button.
And he doesn't come back down.
So I guess I need to add like a timer or something in here or
something like this.
Right?
So I'm going to have a timer in the game State.
I don't know.
Something that's like, maybe a velocity, right?
So I've got a player velocity in y, or something like this.
And I'm going to set that to something and then I'm going to change it
over time or maybe I just have a timer.
So, like I just have a t.
Jump timer.
I don't know.
Something like that.
So then I come in here and I go.
All right, the T jump timer.
It's going to be, I don't know the game State.
When he jumps the T.
Jump timer is going to be equal to one second and then basically like,
you know, I don't know, we add the sign of the T.
Jump timer kind of thing like this.
I don't know what's going on and I do that.
And then every time we go through the frame, I subtract something from
the T, jump timer, you know, I don't know, something like this.
I don't even know for a passing the, the frames per second in hear
anything.
Like that, but you get the idea.
Like I'm going to, I'm going to have to do a bunch of coding in here.
Let's see here.
I've got to actually add that inside there.
So I'm just, I'm gonna have to do a bunch of weird coding in here to
make this jump code, actually do something.
So when I, when I'm actually doing it, I have to then make those
changes come back in here.
Push the button.
Okay, like that didn't do anything.
Right?
And of course, it makes sense that didn't do anything, because I'm not
multiplying this by anything.
So, I have to come back out here and I guess since we're doing the
live coding, I could leave it running.
I can leave this guy running and that's fine.
But when I come back in here, I have to do, like, okay, I edit it
right.
Recompile.
And now the code is live or whatever.
But, oh well, do we have a
Oh, I may have to actually make this guy.
I may have to actually prevent this guy from running out of bounds.
Like I said, this guy will write out of bounds whenever the the player
actually gets to the bottom of the screen.
So I may have to do an actual, an actual attempt here at preventing
this guy from actually writing out of bounds.
So, let's just do something really simple, which is if pixel, if the
pixel pointer is, is in bounds, it will do it.
Again.
This is absolutely.
Or add code.
I apologize for being so horrid on the stream, but I just want to.
I'm literally only doing this to prevent to show kind of why we want
the thing that I'm going to show you how to build.
Because if we had already written the game, then it would be very easy
to show or had some part of a game running, would be very easy to
show.
Why the thing that I want to do is interesting but without having any
of that, it's much easier.
All right.
Bye sorry.
It's much harder.
So I could need something if that makes sense.
All right.
So basically we have the buffer memory here.
I'm just going to add the full size of the buffer in there.
So the bytes per pixel times, the width plus the pitch, times the
height, so I'm just going to add in basically the
Tire size of the buffer?
Again.
Do not worry about this code at all.
I will be explaining renderers in detail when we get there, and I just
don't want to belabor the point at the moment because it doesn't
matter.
All right.
So anyway, here we go.
You can now see that my junk code.
Awesome.
As it is, isn't even waiting for the timer to be set, right?
Because it's just always working.
And basically what I had to do is make it so that when this thing goes
out of bounds, we don't crash because when it would go, you would be
writing out of memory when we go here, right?
So, all right, so I'm doing this.
So I do this thing and I'm like, oh, right.
The timer isn't is totally messed up.
It's not right at all, because it keeps going down.
So, I flip back here, whatever I go.
All right, you know, so we got to do this, this game T, jump thing.
But that should only be happening.
Basically, if T, jump is greater, you know, is greater than some
threshold value like, you know, so basically, what I want to do here
is say, if game State T, jump is greater than 0.
Then we will, do, you know this piece of code or whatever.
Otherwise we won't.
So, you know, will do that.
We will do something like this and there we go.
And there.
So I do that.
Okay.
I got an error there, got to convert this to it and done.
So I come back here.
And now at least, you know, it's a bit better, but I got to pick up
the controller again.
I got to get back to somewhere.
I want to test.
I got to push the button Loop and the jump goes downwards.
Right?
Not at all.
What I wanted.
Sign goes downwards.
Okay.
All right.
So, stop flip back here.
I got to go ahead and say, all right.
This should be going the other direction.
I run it again.
Come back here.
Pick the controller.
Back up.
Take my hand off the keyboard.
Do it right?
So you can see what I'm basically trying to say here.
There's this whole process where I have to keep going like like this
is a problem because I got to like, pick up the controller tests.
The thing I want, go back to the code change, the code come back here
and you can imagine if there was more State.
Like, if there is an enemy, what if I kill the enemy while now?
The enemy is gone.
And so that firing the missile.
And what if the missile only had, I only have one missile left.
Do I, add a cheeky to add more missiles?
There's all these kind of annoyances in there that make it not as
smooth as
As I would want it to be right.
So what I would like to do instead is make it so that this can
basically be like the way musicians edit stuff, right?
I basically want to create something that's sort of like a
Editor where I can just go ahead and say, okay.
I'm going to record something being done.
And then I want you to just keep doing that thing over and over again.
Exactly the way I did it.
As I tune the code for it.
Does that make sense?
So, you know, I just I want to make something that's essentially like
a loop editor, but for code.
So, how do I do that?
Well, it turns out like I said, if you architect everything, properly,
this ends up being actually extremely easy because think about how we
have set up our game.
There if we don't care about sound for now because we have a separate
set way that sound comes in.
But if all we're trying to tune is stuff besides the the literal sound
output code.
We only have one function that's called right?
It's called updated render.
We know it takes the memory, that's whatever the state of the game is.
We knew it takes whatever the input is on this Frame and then it just
takes wherever we want it to draw to write whatever we want it to
draw.
That's it.
so, if we wanted to,
We could certainly start doing something relatively straightforward
here by saying.
All right, what if we just record whatever this new input thing is, we
just remember whatever that is, right?
And then we feed it back.
Instead of actually producing the input before we pass the thing here.
We just actually see whatever the previous input thing was right.
We just record it.
And go seems pretty straightforward, right?
So if we want to, we could basically introduce something right that
captures this input because we know it's just a flat struck.
We made it very simple, right?
It's really trivial to capture.
It's just one of these, right?
So you could imagine having something that was like, you know, win32
recorded input, right?
You could imagine as constructing something, that looked like this,
right?
There's an input stream, write something like this and there's
Input count, right?
And it would basically say, all right, as we go, we just remember all
of the, the inputs that we had, we stuff them in here.
And then later, when we want to play it back.
We just go ahead and grab them out of here progressively, right?
Very, very, very simple.
There's really nothing weird going on about that at all.
Furthermore, if we wanted to, we already know how to do file I/O.
So if we want, we actually don't even really need to do to me.
We don't even really need to store it in memory, right?
We could just log it out to a drive and save it that way.
So, it was permanent right?
We could just read and write from a file.
So basically, there really wouldn't be very much to at least that
part, right?
So let's think about how we might implement this.
All I really need to do is sort of know whether I'm recording
something, right?
Maybe I'll have a variable here and, you know, I might want to record
multiple of these or something.
So, maybe I could just introduce a variable here called like recording
index or something.
And recording index will be equal to 0, right.
So, when we're running, we also have a recording index and that
recording index is equal to 0.
And similarly, if we were playing something back.
Maybe I'll have a playing index.
Look at input, according index in an input playing Index, right?
And basically, if these are equal to 0 then
We are not playing or recording but if they're equal to something else
then we're well think of it as like a slot.
Basically that things are in make some sense.
It seems pretty straightforward, right?
I don't think there's anything particularly odd about that.
So if we want to now, basically, what I can do is I can sort of
Well, I guess there is one, we do have a bit of a thing.
That's a little Annoying here, which is that we kind of have our
keyboard processing up here and we'd like to start using that keyboard
processing to affect some stuff.
So, it would kind of be nice if we had these things, sort of starting
to be centralized in something.
So, maybe, you know, I'd like to do something like this, which is
win32 state or something like this where I have something like that,
right?
And, and that has some of these sort of globally, sorts of things in
it.
So, I have win32 state.
And that's here.
And so I'm just going to go ahead and wrap those in a struct so that I
can pass them around.
Because, basically, what I want to do is I basically want to do is
make basically, I say basically a lot what I want to do is I want to
make it so that we can record things by just hitting a simple key.
So basically, I look to see if we have hit the L key.
Let's say for Loop, right?
And what we'll do is we'll say, we'll take a look, if maybe, if the
shift key was down.
I don't know if
Or what was the easiest thing to do?
There was the the ALT key was down.
So we'll go ahead and well, actually, we don't even need that.
I don't think we need that at all.
If you press the L key, that'll go into Loop mode.
Let's say.
And then if you push one of the number keys that will indicate what
slot you want to record in.
So will basically say will push L and then one will like start
recording input to slot 1 and then you push L again and it stops the
recording at that point, right?
So l 1 starts recording L stops it and
Then on if you hit one, it'll start replaying that slot.
Right?
So let's go ahead and do it that way for now.
I guess what I can do is just hard code it so we don't have to do the
one, two, three processing, because I can show you how to do that in a
second.
But so let's just say that if you hit the L key, then the win32 state
the the input recording Index, right?
Becomes one, if it already equal that.
So if the if it equals 1
Already or if it equals 0, it's that otherwise we stop, right?
Otherwise, we will real set it back to zero so base.
We're just making a toggle here.
We hit L.
We start recording, we hit L again.
We stopped recording.
And since we're testing here will switch right to playing back as
well.
Makes sense.
All right, pretty straightforward.
I think not much to to do there.
Alright.
So basically I've got these these playing indexes and, and that sort
of stuff move those into here.
And so, basically, we just replace those with with our own struck
there and we can start putting other stuff in there as well.
So, this will kind of be a nice holder for things that we want to be
accessed outside.
So I go ahead and do that.
And now all I really need is I need to
Look at those when we're about to use that input, right?
So right here, we have new input.
And what I want to do is I just want to say well, if the win32 state
right?
Has a input recording Index, right?
If it's on if recording is on, then I want to call something like
win32 record input like this.
And I want to record this input that just came in and if the win32
state is is playing back something, right?
Then what I want to do is, is playback the input, and so I'm going to
overwrite whatever new input was with whatever the input is.
Whatever.
I'm basically going to get.
She's me whatever that thing reads from the stream of previous inputs.
It's going to put it in there.
Very, very straightforward, right?
So we've got these two functions.
Really, really simple again.
Nothing fancy Happening Here.
Really?
All we have to do is Implement these very straightforward.
So I've got my win32 state.
I'll have to go change that to a pointer down there when I, and then
I've got my game input, that's coming in here.
So we've got those two things.
That's our record input.
Then I've got another one here that's going to play with the input
back in through a two-state this and input.
New input.
So there we go.
And all I need to do is I just need to either write in the record
function.
I need to write it to a file in the playback input.
I just need to read it from a file, right?
That's it.
So assuming that I have a file handle, which I could totally do,
right?
I'll have a file handle here, which is recording handle, and I'll have
a file handle here.
Oops, which is playback handle, and we'll have to actually open these
files with win32 at some
ain't, but I've got those and so I'll go, all right.
I've got this recording handle.
So basically all I need to do is just write this out and we already
saw how to do this.
Remember we have our right file.
In fact, we already wrote a thing that writes an entire file.
It was just this, right?
That's that's the entirety of it.
We just need the file handle.
So we need whatever fine.
Louis, we need the memory, which is the new input, right?
We need the memory size, which is just the size of that struct, that
new input struct.
And then we don't even really care about the B written, because if it
fails, it's just a bug code, we don't even care if it fails.
So just we're just going to try to write and hope that it writes,
right.
So that's it.
So that's all we really need to do to write it.
So we write that to the recording handle, right?
That's it.
And then the same is the exact same thing happens with the read file,
right?
Where is that guy?
It's the wrong function.
There we go.
So read file.
Same thing again.
So we basically have our B red.
We don't really need to look at it right now.
We will have to eventually when we want to get the looping stuff
working, but that's that's the second.
So win32 state.
Playback handle I think it's what I called it.
Yeah handle.
And so then we just need to do the exact same thing.
Here.
We pass the new input.
That's what we're writing.
We passed the size of the new new input and and we're done, right?
So this is literally all we actually need to do to record and Playback
the input, right?
That's going to happen.
And then we also have the case of when we actually first start
recording.
So we basically have to do, essentially something that goes back to
the
Getting of the recording or opens, you know, opens whatever this file
handle is, that sort of thing.
So we need something that's basically like begin recording input or
something like this.
Right?
And then we'll need something.
Also, that's like when 32 and recording and put write something like
that.
And these will basically just be the things that get these file
Handles in the first place.
So to begin recording input.
We're going to just go ahead and do a create file just like we did
before.
Do, you know to open the file handle with Windows say, hey, let's
let's get this back.
So there we go.
So we need to open our recording handle here.
We're going to go ahead and create file.
We want generic right play Bridges this time because we're actually
running to
File.
In fact, I should copy the create file that we did for the other one.
Because that's the one we actually want to make a file here.
So we have our file name for now.
We'll just be fuu dot handmade hero.
Let's say, I don't know.
That's probably a bad name.
Handmade recording, handmade input.
I don't know.
We're going to deal with that in a second obviously, so we got our
file name here.
I never can decide whether file name should be capitalized, inter Caps
or not and I use it interchangeably.
Encode it drives me nuts.
What's I wish I had a consistent way of doing it.
So basically we go ahead and do the recording handle.
We open that up.
That's pretty straightforward and we can even go ahead and say that
recording real past that input recording index here.
Right?
And we'll say went through to State input recording index.
It wasn't recording index will do the open, and then in here.
We'll do a close handle on that and then we're done.
That's all we need to do.
And so, basically, these guys will move up here to above, I'm putting
them above because we're going to call them in here.
And I don't want to bother having to forward, declare them things.
You wouldn't have to worry about.
If you're a programming in John, blows new language because you don't
have to worry about any of that stuff anymore.
So that's going to be pretty awesome and that happens.
But yeah, so when 3 to begin recording,
Hoarding, it's going to begin recording, input 1, and this will be R
in 32 and recording input.
And then it'll be winter to begin with input playback and will also be
one.
There we go.
So, yeah, so that's really all we need to do when we hit L.
If we were weren't recording something, we ask it to start.
Otherwise, we ask it to stop recording and then to start doing
playback.
And so
you know, we've got
we've got to do the equivalent of these two functions and
All right, again, it's playback.
That's another inter caps one.
Should it be playback or playback?
You know what I'm saying?
I don't know.
See and I've done it.
I've done it, two different ways.
That's just, it's maddening when I don't know how it should be.
I feel like there should be some kind of a style guide that tells you
where there are the word breaks in playback filename that sort of
thing.
And so these are actually wrong now because
Again, for closing the handle on the end of playback is fine.
But we do have a problem where our create file is the wrong kind of
pray for all that's creating a, right.
So we want to copy again.
The, the one that we used for reading the file, this one right here.
There we go.
And, and that should be fine because we're always going to open an
existing one for our playback handle.
So,
That's about it for those guys.
So if you think about what that's going to do, right?
When we hit that Elke, we should start just recording in our input to
this food out HTML HMI file.
Then when we stop that, we're going to start reading it again.
Now when we're actually doing the reading, the input in our, in our
like, in our playback phase where we're actually reading stuff.
We do want to know when this starts to fail because when it fails we
want to go back to the beginning if we're trying to Loop, right, so,
We would want to do here, is, we basically want to do a win32 and
input playback, and then win32 begin input playback, right?
So we just want to do whatever the win32 state.
Excuse me.
Hmm, whatever.
That that input playing index is we would basically want to store
that.
So this is our
Index.
We basically want to just pretend that we stopped even though we
really aren't stopping so that we closed down the handle and then we
can go ahead and and start again.
And we could do it a little more efficiently than that, if we wanted
to.
But I don't think we do because there's a bunch of stuff that has to
happen during begin that we'll see in a little bit.
So based.
I just want to set us up for Success.
They're basically by making this do it as if it ended and started
again.
Alright, so and there's my that file name and your caps, right?
It's crazy, right?
Right, it's awful.
All right.
So basically, we're almost done surprisingly for such an awesome
feature.
You're going to be shocked at how little work.
This thing is.
All right.
So we've got our win32 state coming in now.
We've got our record and Playback happening when those things start
and end playback input.
What is wrong with that?
Oh,
That is win32 playback input.
I guess.
New input is already a pointer.
That's the difference.
So there is a couple little things.
Again.
I slammed that in there real quick and just want to take a quick
second.
We do begin recording input.
This is supposed to be input.
Play back into playing Index, right?
I like, when people on the stream site, copy pasta, I've never really
heard.
People say that phrase.
It's kind of funny when you cut and paste some code and you're
supposed to be changing, it to be some different code, but you don't
It's kind of funny, anyway, so, I passing this in and put planes us
when I close these out.
When I do the end recording, I need to basically clear out those
handles as well.
Right?
So I need the input playing index to change to 0.
I need the input recording index to change to 0 when you when you end
like that.
And I think that's roughly everything that I wanted.
All right.
So let's take a look at what happens here.
When we do this, so I'm going to go ahead and just set a breakpoint
inside that that keyboard Handler basically just so we can see what
happens.
So, here we go.
I'm going to run the game.
I'm going to hit the L key to start recording.
We're going to take a look here at our win32 state structure, which
basically should be just completely cleared to 0, which it is again.
I always like, zero to be initialization.
So you just don't have to worry about initializing stuff.
You just cleared to 0 and you know, that it's good.
All right.
Right.
We step in we say, all right, Sam Rubin recording.
So we're going to go ahead and set the recording index to whatever
slot were recording into.
We're going to go ahead and try and create a file.
We created the file off, we go.
We pop out of here, blah blah, blah.
Nothing particularly interesting going on.
There we go, through our code and we get down to the point where we've
done all of our input processing.
We say, are we recording?
We are recording.
So we step in here.
We take a look at this right file.
It looks like we're writing to a valid handle.
We're right.
Out the input thing.
Everyone is happy.
We wrote six hundred.
Bytes.
Is that how big our input is for a frame?
We can check size of game input.
600.
B.
That's exactly what it should be.
Everyone's happy.
We come out of here.
We keep going and it's good.
All right.
So basically, this is writing off out that stuff to disk, right?
This is writing out out everything that I'm doing.
So if I hit l in theory, this should now change to ending the
Ting input, which it does close.
As the handle goes in here, goes to start playing it again, creates
that file and off we go.
So now we actually should in theory, be playing back whatever the user
input was for for all the frames.
Now.
I don't know if it's actually working and of course I had left my guy
sitting there for a while.
So we would have to actually wait for a bit to see if this guy moves
but I also want to take a look.
I really wanted to kind of look and see.
How that input code was actually working when it does the read back.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this in a test where I know that I'm
doing something when I hit that Elke.
So basically Elke.
Oh, stupid mistake.
And this may have cost us from having it.
Work.
The right.
The first time, I totally forgot to check whether the key is going
down or up.
I always forget that when I jump in here.
So basically, it was, it was triggering twice once for the down once
with up, which minute started and stopped recording immediately.
And that's not very much fun.
All right.
So basically, here we go.
Let's try this again.
I do the L key, I do the jump come back down.
I push the L cake.
Hey, look, we're playing.
A car input.
I don't know if it's actually working properly.
It doesn't look like it recorded the jump.
So I think we're still a little bit buggy, but at least it worked
slightly.
So let's go ahead and and, and take a look at what what I messed up
because I think we're almost almost there.
So, all right.
So when we, when we do our recording, we are supposed to be writing,
right, file.
We're supposed to be writing this every time with our winter to record
input.
put and then when we do our playback, we are oh,
What what what?
What did I type?
How did this happen?
What this is this is what happens when you explain stuff when you're
trying to do it.
You just your you become an awful.
Programmer.
Everyone II promise you.
I'm not as bad at programming as I appear to be on this stream.
Like if you actually look at the stream, everyone's going to not want
to hire me.
They're going to be like, you're the worst programmer.
Like, why would this?
How did this get in here?
This this is, this is this is totally wrong.
Yeah, okay.
So anyway, basically, what we did is afraid read file succeeded.
We then.
Started looping that doesn't make any sense.
Obviously.
We only want to start looping when the read file is finished.
I mean, that's kind of obvious, right?
And read file if I'm not mistaken returns a Bool, so it's going to be
true when it when it worked, right?
Yeah, if the function fails or is complete a single serve, a 0 and I
assume I don't actually know, but I've seen when it runs out of B, it
will return false.
Let's
SC.
I don't actually know.
I assume it will turn false when it can't read.
All the bytes that you asked for, but I don't actually know but what I
do know is we could check for B red.
So either way.
So what we basically want to do is say, okay, if it read properly
note.
This is there's still input or here.
We've hit the end.
Of the stream, go back to the beginning.
So that that was just fantastic.
I mean that is, you know, high quality craftsmanship.
Right there.
Don't let anyone tell you otherwise, so I'm going to go down here and
try that again.
So we hit the L key for looping, we come down here.
We hit that.
I'm gonna walk back down here and then I hit l.
Hey, look, we just wrote input recording in 10 minutes.
So, I mean, all right, I will point out that there was an entire
company devoted to doing nothing but input recording.
At one point they failed, it was called replay something.
I don't remember what it was.
But basically if you architecture code, right input recording and
Playback is literally like 10 minutes or 20 minutes of work.
You just watched me do it while explaining it actually and it took
only that amount of time so it takes even less if you're
Going to do that stuff.
Totally trivial.
So, the only question we have left is how do we Loop the state of the
game?
Right?
We got a loop, the state of the game as well, because there's all this
state that was set up at the beginning and we need that to be true.
Well, hey, guess what?
Yes, this is going to mean our files end up being particularly big.
That is true.
Right?
If you look in the data directory, our food out HDMI R.H., Mi4 the
input recording is pretty tiny right now, right?
But if we want to, if we want to just say, well,
We want the whole game, State saved.
Well, guess what?
People I again architected this because I had a bunch of stuff that I
knew would be good when we got there.
And this is one of them.
We virtual a lock, the entire memory for the game.
In one block that has a known Base address.
Right.
So if we want to restore the entire state of the game, to exactly what
it was at any point in time.
All we need to do is save or load that block.
That's it.
It's like two lines of code.
No serialization layer.
No, big long walking change of things trying to figure out.
It's the state and what's not the state?
No, nothing.
We know that if the game saw it, it was in here.
And we also know that even if the game put pointers in there, they'll
still be valid.
Because we load it always at the same Base address.
So we don't even have to care.
It doesn't matter of game.
Could do whatever it wants.
It does not matter what the game does.
As long as the game does it in here, it'll work, right.
So all I have to do.
Now is when we do this, this game memory structure.
Now just has to be Park.
Of this guy, right?
Of win32 state so that we can save and load it.
So basically if I just go in here and do something like this, so the
game memories in there now, right?
And then I say that, that the game memory is actually something off
the win32 state like this, right?
And and I could actually maybe I'll do it this way, just for a little
bit game memory.
Okay.
Alright, so basically what I'll do is I'll go here at through here and
just change this to a pointer.
Again.
Needless busy, work is C actually did the dot and pointer syntax
annoyingly.
Right?
So now that should be set up in there properly and there shouldn't be
any difference.
So if I run this, I should just get the same old game working the same
way that it was before.
No, no problems.
Right?
Just what we would expect and then what I can do is
Can go.
All right.
So now when we, when we begin or end recording, right?
Basically.
Now what I know because of the way that I did this thing.
I'm going to put that total size remember in here as well.
In fact, I guess to be fair.
I really didn't need to do the thing.
I just did with the game memory.
That was probably premature.
Let's let's back that up for a minute.
Let's just back that up for one second.
Because I realized that's actually I don't even really need to do
that.
That was just a wasted code edit.
That was just dumb, right?
I don't need to do that at all.
All I actually needed to do was make it so this one virtual Alec was
actually tracked.
So basically, this void star game, memory block, right this thing.
That just needs to do that, right?
I just need to remember where that was.
So basically, what will happen is these will be off the win32 state.
Now, the game memory block will be off the win32 block, that and and
same thing here win32 State total size.
So those two things will work that way, now, right, win32 State, total
size, and that now gives us what we need.
Eat in our win32 state structure to basically go up here and do
exactly what I wanted to do, which is, when we begin input playback
and begin recording, it will now actually just restore the state.
So, when I do the begin recording input, when we open this file
handle, I am immediately going to just do a full-on.
Last right.
This thing here.
Right.
File like that.
I'm just going to go ahead and do a full-on blast, right?
Of the entire game State.
Just everything that there is in one call, one simple basic call.
Now, there is one caveat to it, which is because Windows doesn't
actually allow 64-bit rights.
If total size is actually greater than a 32-bit.
So it's more than four gigs.
This won't work, will have to write a for Loop that, you know, Loops
over it.
So I'm going to put an assertion in here.
Just
So if we ever get to that point, remember to come fix this and put a
for Loop in there, but, that's just because Windows doesn't do that
for us.
So, we're going to assert that total size is basically less than this
value right here.
Just because we know we can't actually pass that f.
F f f, f f f f.
We know we can't pass a value.
Is that?
That's that big.
So, I'm going to assert that.
That's true.
I'm going to write out basically that entire size here, right?
I'm going to
Have another lease dummy, B, written things that we don't care about
because, again, this is total debug code.
No user will ever touch this code, or if they do, they're, they're on
their own, and then I will just pass the memory, right?
Game memory block.
There we go.
So that's it.
And the opposite is, is exactly true as well.
So we'll just go in here and do the read file.
So we basically have when we begin the input playback when it does
that file handle, we're going to again do the assertion.
But then we're just going to do a read file on the playback handle and
the game memory block total size stuff is all the same.
I believe and B red is here as well.
I think that's all the same conversion to d word, right?
Well,
Actually, I guess bytes to read equals.
This is probably the say Norway to do this.
We just cast it down and then verify that they are equal after the
cast, right?
So B to read.
Yeah.
And same with my sister right, lights to right.
We'll go ahead and grab that total size there.
D word.
and,
Cert that they're equals well.
Likes to write.
All right.
Let's see if that does anything.
Alright, so my guys down here.
I'm going to start them in the corner.
I'm going to hit the L key to start recording and let's see.
They're not know how long that's going to take as a bit of a pause
there.
And you do it.
This is a very slow hard drive as you might imagine.
And Hey, look.
That was it.
Of course, we didn't actually Loop properly.
So that's not good.
So we still have a bug.
Why didn't we Loop?
Way.
Does anyone know anyone already know why we didn't do it properly?
Because we should have looped properly but I don't actually think we
did it stopped.
When it got to the end which it should not have.
So I guess I still don't actually know if this ever happens because it
may be that it just returns 0 4, B, red.
So I'm going to go into that playback input and that's the that's the
only thing that didn't work.
So I'm just going to go in there and really quickly check it just to
see
See what's going on there?
I don't, I'm so bad at Visual Studio.
I never know how to just jump to a function.
You know what?
I'll just do it this way when 32 way back foot.
Here we go.
So, alright, win32 playback input.
I go in here and I want to know.
Do you ever get there?
Basically, that's what I want to know.
L.
No, so it's as I suspected it.
I think it even if it doesn't read any bites because it hits the end
of the file.
I think it just returns 0 and B red.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that what we really needed to check
with not that right.
We do the read file here, but we need to check instead is if B red
equals 0 then we try to do this.
Now we could do that.
Only if the read file succeed.
So we if the file handle like isn't valid, we don't do it.
So that might be better.
So basically, when we get to the end of the stream, if the B red is 0,
we've hit the end of the file, and we'll restart it.
So let me just see if that was the problem that we were having.
So L.
And then I will move us down to the corner due to do.
And then L again.
And we'll see if we've got our looped at it working now.
Yeah, so basically that's it.
We now have looped editing just working
I mean it's kind of when you actually see how simple it was to
implement.
It's kind of like, oh, duh.
Like how come we're not always doing that because now you can
literally do anything that you want like anything that involved that
whatever you want to do to tune that jump code from before I can just
do, right?
Because I can just go ahead and say, of course, I didn't actually, I
don't think I actually have a way to turn off the playback.
I got to go actually add some real controls to this, but basically,
now, if I wanted to not jump, I could do that in a much.
More interesting way, right?
I can go ahead and say all right.
Let me set this up.
Let me start the recording right?
I'll go ahead and do whatever the the motion is that I want to do.
So I'll go in here.
I'll do the jump and then I'll finish it and I'll Loop that, right.
So now it's looping, looping my jump and I can kind of go ahead and
say, all right.
So now let's let's
Had an edit the code for that jump, until I'm satisfied with how it
works.
So I go in here and I say, all right.
Where was that code for the jump?
Here's the code for the jump, right?
First of all, it should go up and down again.
So basically, the sine wave should at least go through a pie, period?
Right?
I would think so.
Basically, we want it to be like, I think I have a pie 32 to find, do
I not?
So I'll recompile that right and I think that should change the period
of my sine wave and Theory.
No, that did nothing.
Okay.
This is actually working.
Is it not like let's say, I want to change the height of the jump.
Let's find out that works properly.
There we go.
So I've got a smaller jump, so I just didn't do this, right?
So the T jump, it was doing pi32.
That should be one thing round.
It should go up and back down, again.
Shouldn't it?
Unless I'm mistaken.
So the T starts at 1, it gets subtracted down 20 in theory.
That should do it.
Well, let's, let's see what happens.
Who knows?
This is the whole point of this, I suppose it's some level.
Oh, I know why?
Because it's only adding right?
That's it's only adding the actual.
Right?
Right.
So you, we actually do need it to go through the full, the full state
of the 2 pi.
Oh, man.
This is the worst junk code that anyone's ever written in the history
of mankind.
I'm embarrassed to even, it's not even jump.
Co don't even know what you want to call it.
But they're at least now, I've got him doing the jump.
So that's
Good and maybe we will also say, okay.
Let's actually make this jump.
Go like that and I'll recompile that see how that's going.
So, there we go.
There's that jump again.
Little more reasonable.
Maybe I want the jump to take a little bit longer.
So if the T jump was more like four, maybe, I don't know if that's
actually going to do anything for me, but I'll try it.
There we go.
There's a longer jump, right?
I guess, at this point, since I basically finished everything.
I want to finish, I should probably try to actually write some junk
code.
That isn't absolutely awful.
I don't know if that's a good idea or not or if we should just go back
to we're doing.
I don't really want to talk about.
Jump coated.
Also, maybe the best thing to do is say, don't ever do anything like
this.
This is the worst.
This code is absolutely horrific.
Lie bad, you would never write a jump code that even involved any of
the things that I just did.
It was literally just what came out of my hands when I decided
To start typing.
So let's we'll wait will actually talk about how to implement these
things correctly later, but you really, really really don't ever want
to do.
When I just typed in please, this is horrible and awful.
Like we need a velocity and there's all this.
It just don't, please don't do this.
I'm sorry that I even brought it up.
It's awful.
But anyway, point being we now have exactly what I wanted s to have,
which is the ability to do looped edits on our game and
Really?
The only problem here is performance.
Basically, if we go look at, if we go, look at how big that file is.
You can see this this giant, honkin one gigabyte file, right?
So basically doing that memory blast can be slow.
This is a machine that has no SSD drive or anything like that.
So actually I suspect on a modern machine.
This would actually be almost instantaneous though because if you had
a fast, if you had like a Santa 3 or whatever, I don't even know what
they're up to.
These days the Sabbath three SSD drive.
I think this would just be instant.
But this basically allows you to do all of your code tuning with a
sequence that gets recorded and it keeps resetting the entire state of
the game properly at the beginning.
So you don't even have to pick up the controller.
You don't have to take your hands off the keyboard, right?
And there's other things we can do.
That will make this even cooler will continue on this tomorrow because
basically, there's still a little bit more we can do.
That's interesting.
For example, one thing that
Be totally crazy that we could probably do and I'll just throw this in
there for kicks.
Just to give you a little bit of a heads up because we're basically
done with our state recording stuff.
I mean, that's that's everything we needed.
What we can do, as well, is inside, when we actually create our
window, right?
When we create our window e^x.
I believe we can also do some really crazy stuff, right?
Which is we could create like a topmost window.
Oh, so if we do, like, I'll just show you what I mean real quick.
So if we create wind oex, right, when we, when we pass that we have,
this ability to specify these extended Styles and there's some of them
that are like, you know, that this is a top, most window I believe is
the thing you can do.
So this kind of a thing.
So we can pass a topmost window and we can pass a layered with.
There's a lick, a layered windowed flag.
I don't actually know where that is.
I'm context visual Paradigm of friend layered, layered.
I think this is, this is the one we want.
Yeah, so we can do wsx layered, or, of course, we can't do that with
own DC or class DC, which I think we were using, right?
We're reusing those.
Let's take a look own DC.
Yeah.
We were using on DC so we may want to remove that.
Yeah, she's forever because we're not sharing with anyone.
So that may be something that we
Actually want to do anymore because of that.
So yeah, I'll throw this in there.
But so if we do this, right, if we actually create a topmost window
that the layered window or maybe, I don't know if I'll specify that
quite yet.
But basically, if we create a topmost window at the very least, right?
Then I believe we can basically have the game window right?
Can sit on top of our editor as well.
So it can kind of be a little more unobtrusive, right?
So we can come in here, we can set the recording marker.
We can go ahead and do you know that stupid jump that I was doing or
whatever like that.
Stop it have that looping and we can just be playing that essentially
in here while we're doing our edits full screen, you know, like not
having to do anything so we can basically tune.
My absolutely ridiculously terrible.
Jump code that is awful right?
I can go ahead and do that and there, you know, we've done whatever it
is that we want to do, right?
Yeah, so you get the idea and then the other thing that we can do in
the thing that I was going to suggest.
Is we can also change this into.
We can tell windows that we want this thing.
This window to be translucent potentially.
And of course we can't do that with a CS own DC window.
So we don't we don't really need that CS own disa.
So what we'll do is we'll actually just go ahead and the time that we
need the device contacts will just get it right?
Because there's only one time I think that we actually need it, which
is here.
So, if I just go ahead and do that here and do, you know, actually get
it the way that you normally get it.
I think we should be fine in theory.
So if I do that, I believe that will be fine.
I don't actually know.
But let's see.
Well that didn't work.
So well.
Now our window doesn't show up at all.
I think we may have to do this.
There's like a layered window update call.
So what is it?
It's layered window win32 update.
I think there should be a way to just say.
Make you some more popular asset layered window attributes.
I don't know.
Like we're will have to deal with this tomorrow because I probably
won't be able to get it working just now.
So I made back this change out real quick before we go.
I just want to see if I could slam it in there.
But basically you can make a call to basic says please make my window
translucent, right?
And so what I could what I was going to say is well we can just make
once after we create our window, we could also go ahead and make
Window be translucent, right?
We can basically say okay.
Hey Windows, please make make this this window translucent.
So let's see.
Color ref should have transparency color all pixels to turn color if
we don't actually want one of those.
So we want lwa Alpha.
So we basically just tell it that our window has sort of an opacity
level, right?
And that's what we can do by specifying lwa Elfa.
We can specify an alpha level.
It's from 0 to 255.
I've I believe is the thing, the color key value and actually know
what they want us to do for that RGB macro.
This is just Windows nonsense here.
So basically, I think I don't know if this is actually true or not.
But I think we may be able to do something basically a simple as that
where we just can have a layered window.
That's just transparent.
Yeah.
So there you go.
So that's a transparent window, right?
So you can imagine right us having the game running and we can edit
the code and we can even have a window.
That's transparent.
Did I not fix all the bugs here?
That we fix this but apparently we didn't.
Break course are transparent window with we need to make it not
clickable.
So there's a bunch of things will have to do to actually make that go
but yeah, so what did I mess up here?
Did I mess up the computation of end of buffer B?
4 pixel?
Because we're writing, we're still writing out of bounds, which is not
0.
Fantastic.
Let's take a look here.
That was not a way that code should have been written.
Copy pastas people say although that wasn't copypasta.
That was just a quick edit.
So basically what I had wanted to do in that code that renders the
players I'd wanted to basically just say if the pixel pointer is still
within the buffer, then it's okay to write it.
Otherwise, it's not.
And so I was checking it here.
So this pitch pointer, I don't know why.
That that's even in there doesn't have to be in there but basically so
this is not actually correct at the moment.
So this is less than end of buffer.
I guess this is writing to it.
This is technically
Has to be the pixel plus 4 has to be less than or equal to the buffer.
I don't know if that actually is relevant but it could be off by that
much.
Is there anything else I'm missing in there.
So if the pixel pointer, if it's greater than the memory pointer and
less than so buffer memory.
Plus the B, our pixel times, the with the pitch sound.
Oh, that's not right.
Yeah, that's just wrong as well.
I don't know why I did that in there.
So this is basically, this is the entire size of the buffer.
It's the pitch which is how many to
Vance per row times the number of rows, so that's actually correct.
So that's that's more, that's more what we should have had.
So all I was going to say, is if we do that thing with the layered
window update.
Layered window or start set layered window attributes.
This set layered window attributes thing.
We can actually stuff in our app in our window handle thing or are
thing that handles window messages and this WM activate app thing is
something that windows will call us back on depending on whether or
not our window is active.
So basically we could make a thing where we said.
All right, when our app is active, right?
So if the app is active, the
/ am that comes in with that message says whether or not the window is
activated or deactivated.
So if it's true, we're going to be activated if it's false.
We're going to be deactivated.
And so this is like activating and deactivating a window, right?
Bring it to the foreground or moving it away.
And so I believe what we could do is just say like if the the W / am
equals true then we want to actually set ourselves to full Alpha.
Otherwise, we want to set ourselves to dim Alpha.
Right.
So we could do something like this.
And again, I'm just kind of slamming this in here at because we're out
of time on the stream.
So I don't want to go any further on this but I just wanted to show
you kind of what I've been thinking about we could do.
So we do this stuff.
We're doing some things, we play the game.
We do something right?
We're like, oh this isn't working.
Right?
So we go.
Let's set a loop Point, get to the state, we care about set the loop
point.
We go through, we do the action that we wanted to have happen again.
Hopefully that's much quicker on any modern machine.
And Now We're looping mode.
We can then alt-tab to our editor and the game still runs behind the
editor, totally translucently.
So we can still edit full screen and see all our code pretty easily,
but we can see what the game is doing in the background anyway, and
then we want to see it again.
We should be able to switch back to it and then it restores itself to
full color, right?
So a lot of work, we still have to
To clean this stuff up, but that was the end of the, the sort of
Excursion into crazy Windows.
Tricks thing again.
I know it.
Hopefully, that seems both very, very cool because I've literally
never seen anyone demo anything that had this feature before.
In fact, I'd even seen things like Brett, Victor had something that
people were sending around where he was.
Like, you should be able to just have the code doing what it does
while you edit it or something.
I don't know.
And I'm like, well you can do most of that already.
Like we can just do it.
We just did did it.
We just showed how to do it.
Right?
And you can imagine extending this technique very easily as well.
Like let's say we wanted to see the path that the guy took
Well, all we really have to do is start annotating our game a little
bit to write to a buffer that shows that those things and draw them
over time.
And then you basically got the ability to type Live code and see like
pads and stuff update as you are changing the Live code.
So I think like, yeah, hopefully you hopefully, this did look
particularly cool.
I think it will look really, really cool.
Once we're actually working on the game and can just tweak stuff
really tightly without ever having to have anything.
We don't have to have a scripting language.
Which we don't have to have any of that.
None of that work just works.
But also so you can see that if you architect stuff properly, it goes
from being something that you can't even conceive of spending the time
to do to being something that literally took an hour with explanation.
Right?
I mean, we architected our game, platform layer boundary properly.
And now this was free.
Like, it was literally, someone could do it on their lunch break and
have something that's much more powerful than the editing.
You actually get in.
A lot of tools that are supposed to be very powerful.
Because they have scripting languages are all this other stuff, but
actually, a lot of them don't even do this.
Right?
A lot of engines that you by don't even have this feature built-in,
and we already have this feature from day one, and it only took us an
hour.
So, basically that is the end of what I wanted to cover on this stream
as the end of our sort of fun with win32 stuff tomorrow.
And Friday we will be on will be at 11:00 a.m.
We'll be on holiday hours.
And basically what we'll be doing on those two days is clean up.
So we'll basically going through our code.
Code, going through all of.
Like notes, I haven't went through two things that need to be cleaned
up.
We'll make this a little cleaner.
How you interface with the looping system.
Will, you know, will will round off the edges and make sure everything
set for going into Monday when we start writing, our actual game
engine.
So I hope you have enjoyed the past three days.
I know I have I was really psyched to get this working.
I was like, this is gonna be so much fun and it was, so I'm pretty
happy with how this turned out.
And let's, let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
Please put Senior ettore in your question so I can see it.
And please stick to questions about stuff.
We've already done either today, or in a previous dream.
Let's not talk about future stuff because we're going to get there
eventually.
And off we go.
Okay, does win32 playback input need to return status and case the
fide real fail.
The file read fails and are reaches the end.
Since in case those cases, the function output data structures will be
staler and valid.
It's up to you basically depends on.
I mean probably you would want to do that eventually.
Just for why not sake, but this is only for our internal use.
So if it can't write to the file for some reason, you're going to know
because things are going to kind of mess up immediately.
But yeah, I mean when we have more of a logging system and stuff like
that, it be it'll be easier for us to just note those errors because
really the only thing you're going to do at that point is note the
error.
There's nothing you can do about it.
You know you your abuser was trying to play back some input and they
can't and so they really what they need to know.
Is that something failed to?
They can go see why their hard drives messed up or whatever.
So yeah, so I do have to remember to delete this file so that I don't
end up shipping of the HMI because we need to move.
The other thing that we need to do is we need to move that that file
into the build directory so that it's know, we know that it's a temp
file.
So I want to make sure we do that as well if I can put it to do in
there so that we don't forget to do that.
So went through to record Put let's say
To do these files.
Must go in a temporary build directory?
That's very important.
I will write that down on the notebook as well.
Path for hm.
My files.
Okay.
All right.
Will this break?
When you make changes to the game State structure?
So yet basically.
So if we wanted to do the full version of this, we would need to have
code and Tatian so that we know what our structures are and we can
backport them when we load, that is just a lot of extra work to do.
It's it's
A lot of extra work to do even in a language that has better
introspection features than c c is awful at introspection.
It's one of the places that it really sucks.
And so like that is one place that, like, I think other languages do a
much better job is because they support that sort of thing, and it's
absolutely awful that they've never added that stuff properly in so
long, but that that's a big problem.
So I don't want to actually go down that route because of the amount
of time.
It will take and all it means.
Means is that we will have to just restart the app a little more
frequently, which just doesn't seem like a bad trade-off for this
project.
But if you were doing this in the industrial strength since where you
wanted to make like a game engine that had this feature in, lots of
people are going to use it.
You would go ahead and do The annotation.
And that way when you make changes to your structs, it will still work
there, still things.
That won't work.
I mean, this feature is for tuning, it's not for doing all of your
development inside of a loop, right?
Because if you do that, you can't change the way in which things
Get initialized either like the super structures of things.
You might change.
How that's how things are organized entirely and nothing's ever going
to make that work live because it you'd have to write specialized
functions to do the mutation and the person would spend more time
writing those functions than they save by getting the tuning.
So you want to focus on just the tuning here.
But even with that we probably will be able to do some stuff where we
just leave padding at the ends of our struct.
So while we're developing and we can add things pretty
Easily, we just can't rearrange them.
It wouldn't be too hard to set up the render ghost or to use two
windows to play Loops of current code and previous version, would, it
would be cool to see how game States.
Diverge?
Yeah.
Well, so we've set ourselves up perfectly for doing what you just
said, because remember the other thing we can do is we can load
multiple game dlls and play them separately.
So we could actually load to game dlls and be playing them back at the
same time.
If we wanted to write, we could totally do that and it would be
absolutely no problem whatsoever.
So like where we do that load library, right?
This thing here, this winter you loghain code.
We could call that with multiple on multiple dll versions, so we could
totally look at to game State sets separately.
If you wanted to, I don't have a use case for that right now, but
we've totally set ourselves up to do all that stuff.
You could do anything you wanted with that.
Why didn't you use a switch for all the V codes stuff?
I don't know.
I just didn't.
We could but I usually I don't like to do switches inside of switches.
I find that gets a little confusing.
So I didn't what we probably should do is just move this guy out into
its own function entirely, which is process keyboard or something like
that.
But yeah, there's no real reason.
Since it's mostly zeros, do you think it'd be worth writing out the
game state in a sparse way using a simple rle or something?
Performance sufficient or perhaps that would make performance worse.
Can you talk a bit about the trade-offs that may exist there?
I think that basically just by an SSD drive by a fast SSD drive and
you will never care.
I think you can blast a gigabyte to an SSD drive in a split-second
anyway, so I assume that it's not a problem but I don't really know.
I would test it on a machine that isn't 8 years old or whatever.
This one is.
Now five years old.
I tested on a machine that wasn't five years old for us before
deciding to do any work there.
But yes, we could do tons of
Stuff.
You could also just for the time being well, I think we're, what are?
We're allocating.
GB.
Just don't allocate a gigabyte, a legate, much less.
But there's another thing that we can do to.
So one thing that's worth noting is I split this up into permanent and
transient storage and we haven't really talked about what that
entails, what we will probably be able to do in the future if we
really want to is actually just loop on the permanent storage and the
transit storage will reconstruct itself because that's how we'll be
architecting the game.
But there's trade-offs to that as well.
So you'll see when we get a little further on other things, you could
do there, but I suspect that if you just buy a fast SSD drive.
This is just not an issue.
So you should just because this is strictly code for development.
You shouldn't spend a lot of time trying to figure out how to make it
better, because I think it's probably sufficient and just buy some
Hardware that works.
Well,
What's on the schedule for next week?
Next week is basically going to be a educational sort of overview
week.
It's going to be me talking about game engine architectures.
What's what is in a game engine?
What are the parts of it?
What are the parts that we have to build?
And why how should they be sort of looked at and understanding them.
So we probably won't do very much actual code next week.
We may try to like load a bitmap and put it on the screen or
something, right, but we're not going to get much further than that
actually, because where it's going to be a lot of sort of educational.
Materials that kind of have to.
We have to go through.
Are you going to show how to create more debug tools like this?
Yes, they'll be at least one other major debug tool to there will be
at least, two more major, debug tools that will get created.
But I wanted to do this one for fun because I felt like we needed to
do something fun because we had done a bunch of hard work on win32.
That was basic just about managing win32 and, and all the stuff that
makes us do.
So I want to do something fun with win 3-2, but one thing that you
probably will notice is that we could probably make a bunch of this
stuff actually live.
One layer above the platform layer because most of the stuff that we
just did wasn't really platform-specific so I don't want to write too
many debug tools in the platform code.
You can probably actually leverage them across multiple platforms.
So basically, yeah, we won't be writing any more, debug tools until
we've got more of a superstructure and place it on the game side of
things, but then we'll be at least two more debug tools.
Go over.
Regarding savings game state for recording.
Won't we run into problems?
If we port to A system that doesn't allow us to specify a base
address.
Well.
I'm not sure what you mean because basically, we can just always
develop on whatever platform we want to write.
So our main criteria for, what is the platform that we want to develop
on shouldn't be ability to specify a base address.
Good to bugger fast, compilation tools, stable, non crashing system,
good graphics drivers, right?
Those are like the things we want out of a Dev.
So whatever we choose as our Dev platform.
That's what it should be.
When we ported to other platforms.
We're not going to be tuning, like we're not going to tune the game
code on some other platform.
We're just going to do working on the port.
Right?
So we shouldn't really even need gamestate recording on other
platforms, but the answer is yes, if you are on a platform that can
specify a base address that,
And this gets infinitely harder and but we don't ever need to do that.
So we don't really have to worry.
Any chance for high-level overview while cleaning up?
Yes, there will be a bunch of that Thursday and Friday.
I'll do some recap stuff as well.
How often do you look up code or study code like you have done today?
I didn't.
Did I study code today?
I don't know.
I'm not sure what that means.
Sorry.
I don't understand the question.
But if you want to more like elaborate on the question a bit, I could
do it.
Isn't a 2gig snapshot of your game.
Memory.
Crazy huge though.
2 is a 2 gigabyte.
Snapshot huge.
Well.
Let's answer that question.
Shall we?
Newegg.com.
Let's see.
Just how huge that is.
Let's see here.
Computer hard drives ssds.
Let's see if we wanted to put an SSD in our system.
And we wanted to spend a reasonable amount of money.
Let's say 100 to $200.
How much would it have on it?
The answer is, it would have.
Let's see, hundred thirty dollars seems pretty good 240 GB so you
could store 100 game States.
100 of them on your SSD drive.
So crazy, huge.
I don't know.
How many would we even be storing 45.
We're talking about a number.
So tiny that the hard drive laughs at you that you think that it's
crazy, huge.
Right?
Like they don't care at all and these are dirt cheap, right?
Like, you know, and they're getting bigger every day.
So and you can look at here.
You can see there yet some random specs on them.
I don't know what they're there.
But they're Max sequential read and write like is absolutely huge.
So, 400 megabytes per second means that it basically take like 45
seconds, right to do the right, depending on what it was.
So as long as you're okay with that, that's, that's the end of it.
And it's in the cache, the rest of the time.
Like, the other thing to remember, is I did that because I wanted to
do it to disk to disk, but we could do it to memory, and then it would
be largely in.
In taneous, right?
So if we wanted to we could just make this go to memory and then
lazily output it to disk which you know, honestly now that I say it
might be a thing that's worth doing just so we can have that speed and
show how to do it.
Maybe someday when we when we're doing a stream where we just want to
do something fun.
Maybe I'll do that.
So what I'll do here is I could say for example
To do AC lazily, right, the giant memory block and use a memory copy
instead.
So that way you just have more memory in your machine and just works.
So you could do that.
That would be one that would be one way to go.
Certainly.
Let's see.
I'm definitely Batman.
I think your sine wave is a tad.
Bit off on the land of the jump.
No, man.
That junk code is awesome.
You don't know what you're talking about.
That's the that's the awesome dumb code, man.
That feel that jump feel.
Let's see.
I'm thinking maybe less about the error and more about what happens at
the end of the stream.
And it Loops.
Doesn't that generate an extra repeated input event played back or am
I missing something?
I see what you're saying.
You may be correct about that.
So the I believe what the person is saying, is that when we do our
input playback, we need to possibly also still read the first.
Yeah, so,
So I think he is correct.
Basically.
Our new input struct here will still get passed to the game because we
tried to read to it, but the read failed.
So it's still whatever the input was.
Then we'd start the looping, but we never try to read it again.
So really what we want to do here is we still want to try to do one
read, right?
I think is what he was saying, and I think that's correct.
So what we probably want to do here is basically say, all right?
When we have to do that that
Loop when we do, when we begin the input playback, I think we want to
actually do the read again.
So after we read the game State and we then read the input again.
Good catch.
Yes, that's totally.
I think that's totally more correct, that way than it was before
because, otherwise before there's a, like, a leaky frame of
Basically, that's not correct.
Right.
So, let's see.
Excuse me.
Let's see if that's true.
Yes, it looks good.
So I think yeah, I think that's more correct.
That's a good catch.
Thank you for catching that.
Can you clarify a function pointers are part of that game State block,
maybe elaborate on what could ever cause it to fail or Miss aligned?
So that is a good point.
Basically, inside here.
if we ever store a pointer to say to a function, oh
Wait a second.
Wait a minute, though.
So I'm about to say something that was a limitation, but I don't know
if it actually was.
Let me see something here.
I want to, I want to find out if it actually is or not, because I'm
not entirely sure.
Is there a way to load a dll at a known Base address?
Yeah.
So there may even be something you could do to fix that as well.
I have to think about that.
Because then you'd have to be to make sure the Linker was padded out
an alert.
So forget that.
Sorry, Sidetrack.
So yeah, what you can't.
The only thing that you can't do is since the dll gets loaded and
unloaded when you make a change game State, playback will work fine
with function pointers, right?
So you could have pointers to functions in the game State and the game
State playback stuff.
We just did would work.
Absolutely fine.
What won't work fine, is if you store any pointers to functions.
That are not updated whenever you recompile and reload the dll because
the dll may get loaded a different Base address and the Linker May
output different layout for the executable.
So basically, when you are doing these techniques function pointers
are a bad idea like you do not want to have a bunch of function
pointers.
Thankfully we will I can't think of really anywhere, we'll be using
function pointers.
But yes.
If we do use function, pointers and that is a thing that would break
and we would have to try
I to work around that.
Somehow probably anywhere, we would use function pointers would be
relatively easy for us to work around.
But yeah, what would be nice is if we could tell the Linker to always
be incremental and never move functions unless it absolutely have to
and then if it did move, the function, leave a stub there.
And also to tell Windows to always load the library at a known Base
address that we tell it, which I don't know if you can do, if we could
do those two things.
This would literally be bulletproof.
Like you could use
You could just go ahead and do it.
And so that it's actually mostly limitation of those tools that will
that don't allow us to get 100% the
Should actually just work, but unfortunately, I think we can't.
The Linker just isn't written to do that.
If we had written our own Linker.
Again, the more stuff you write from scratch, the more powerful you
become because there is no reason we couldn't just make that work.
The Linker could totally support that and it would just work but
unfortunately, we don't have that luxury.
So
how can we make the playback work?
If we have no Base address?
You can't really you really need the Base address.
If you don't have a base address and for some reason you really still
wanted to try and do this.
You would have to make sure that all of your code did not use internal
pointers to itself, right?
It all would have to be based off of offsets, but you could do that.
Right?
And in fact, see could have supported this but didn't and it's a real
shame that it didn't, there's
You could have supported this really easily but it just makes it a
real hassle in see to work without that.
So offsets are the way that you would do that.
Instead of pointers.
You'd always use offsets from the base and then you'd always just keep
around the base pointer and just use offsets off of it.
So you can actually make all of that work as well.
It's just again, the languages aren't set up for it.
It's, it's one of those sad things that just it's why we need a new
see.
It's why we need John.
Blow to make his new language, and for it to be awesome, because then
we can just fix all these things.
And then,
Then, there'd be no stopping us.
Right?
Because all these things are totally possible on the computer.
It's just either the operating system or the language.
Not actually allowing the programmer to do their job.
So,
Wouldn't the address spaces of to game States Clash?
So, yes, and no, I mean, basically, the way that I would suggest doing
it, like, if you wanted to load to dlls and you wanted them both to
use the same base State, what you would have to do is you'd have to
basically map the memory in and out of the location.
So you'd map one memory in Run the game for one frame map it out map.
The other memory into location map, the other one out.
But I think you could do it.
So I don't think it's actually a problem.
If you want to have the two memory States in in place.
Simultaneously, your, you got problems, but the other thing that I
would say, is, you could, you could actually do it, much simpler by
just creating a subprocess.
So you could create sub processes, Each of, which had their own memory
space.
For example, and then you could run the two copies as sub processes of
you with using the same location in memory.
So you could do that as well.
All of those things would not be very difficult to do again.
I just don't know why you would.
I don't know why I would want to run the two states, the game like
that.
I haven't thought of a good use case for it.
But if you if you had a really good use case for it, we could make
that work.
That's a thing we could.
We could make work.
Would a memory mapped file that doesn't commit to just be faster to
read right from?
Yeah.
So the reason I didn't use a memory mapped file is because we need to
control when it gets written because we want to change it a bunch and
then go back to the previous state.
So
I don't know if Windows allows you to do like a strobing memory mapped
file where you can basically say, okay, right the state of the room at
file, make sure the state of the Marriott in file right now is
committed.
Okay.
Now don't do that anymore.
I don't know if it can do that.
So there's I don't know if memory mapped files can actually support
the use case we need because otherwise that would be nice because
Windows would know stuff about the changes and know what would need to
be recorded.
So, that would be nice again, if the operating system gave us more
direct control over the mmu.
Um, we would be able to make this technique way better than it is,
but, you know, we don't have that control.
So
I thought you were going to use the memory snapshot as a game save,
but you're using it like a Save State in an emulator.
Yes.
We are.
Basically, just saying, hey, this is good for emulators.
Right?
We might as well, if it works for an emulator.
It should work for actual game.
But yeah, we can use memory snapshots as save games as well.
But there may be reasons why we don't want to do that.
So we'll have to think about that when we get to it.
How easy do you think it is to rearrange an existing code base?
So that it supports the instant live coding future and what steps
would need to be taken to get there.
Do you just separate the platform layer and collect all the game
membrane allocations in one place?
Yeah.
I mean, basically what you need to do is make sure that the code is
architected roughly the way our code is architected now and as long as
you can do that.
You can do this.
But again, you can't use function pointers.
So there's there's issues there.
Like like so I don't know if you can even attempt what I'm doing in
C++, for example, because in C++ objects have vtable pointers in them.
So right off the bat, you're dead in the water because those vtable
pointers are pointing to the wrong place now, so maybe there's a way
to fix that.
I don't know.
I haven't thought about it because I don't use C++ has object systems
and stuff like that.
I don't I don't like anything about C++.
Is.
Three tables virtual public all that stuff is really bad.
In my opinion.
I strongly advise against ever using virtual functions.
They're almost always bad for a number of reasons.
And so if you're going that if you have a code that's really
object-oriented inheritance E.
I don't know how to work around those limitations.
I don't know how to fix the vtable pointers.
Maybe there's an easier way to do it, but I don't know what it is.
So you have to be coding in a way that doesn't have pointers to
functions.
Functions baked into your data.
Will there be a Christmas special?
There's a there's a broadcast on Christmas.
I don't know if it's special though.
Might just be a normal day.
How will replay work once you have startup Logic for the game?
How will it be skipped?
Will just work.
It just works.
Because remember, we're saving the memory state.
So, basically the startup code for the game, runs you play the game
for a while, you get up to some level.
Something is not tuned, right?
You hit the L key that saves the memory state right there.
So, everything that happened previously doesn't need to be replayed,
right?
It just, it knows the state.
So it just is replaying just that one part back.
So startup Logic for the game is not relevant.
It's already happened, and it's captured in the memory state that we
say.
Okay, so clarification on the earlier question.
How often do you look up code?
Like you have done today then?
How often do you study code code defined here as simple functions to
complex programs on your own not due to a job.
I guess nowadays.
I don't really study code at all.
I kind of feel like I'm mostly know how to code everything that I want
to code.
And so usually I feel like the next time I'll start studying code
again is when there's a better language than see that I can do a bunch
of stuff in that I couldn't do before and I need to start learning
again.
But usually it's don't study code that much.
What I will study sometimes is like algorithms and techniques that I
don't know.
So like, you know, if someone posts a thing that's like
You know, here's a new way of doing like, like binary search or
something and I'll go look at that because I don't know, like, there's
tons of algorithms.
I don't know and tons of ways of making more optimal stuff that I
don't know.
So I'll often look at people's code posts that are like, here's a new
technique that we learned but like code architecture stuff.
I kind of don't feel I usually I almost never see stuff on the web
where I think that the code architecture stuff was with stuff that I
would necessarily agree with, or if it is that it's stuff that I
already knew.
So,
Don't usually get any benefit of out of that these days.
So I tend to be mostly reading when I study code.
I'm what I'm looking at code.
I'm looking at, not the code.
I'm looking at the algorithm, right?
I'm looking at the, the math, the person did or whatever.
Because I, there's a ton of that stuff.
I don't know.
And there always will be, you can't learn it all.
So, I learned I learned that stuff pretty often if that makes sense.
But a lot of those becomes like when you've been programming in c, as
long as I have, you probably know most of the architecture options
that you have.
Have right?
And so, there isn't a lot that I can.
I rarely, if ever nowadays, see something that I didn't already know
in terms of code structure, but in terms of algorithms, there's always
something new.
There's 100 new algorithms to learn every year.
That might be cool and you're never going to learn all of them.
So that's, that's pretty good.
And also, you can look at like papers, like, you can read siggraph and
stuff and that's again, you're not like studying code.
You're learning new algorithms.
And those are usually just new stuff that gets you thinking in new
ways.
So,
Perhaps rebase image regarding loading dll at location.
Yeah.
I don't know, again.
It doesn't matter because the Linker is going to mess with us anyway,
so I think I don't know.
I think we're basically just dead in the water with function pointers.
We need the Linker to help us.
Maybe maybe if we turn on incremental Atwood, I don't know or edit
continue.
Maybe would, I don't know.
Let's see.
Let's see, Dynamic, bass.
No - fixed the Linker and it will load at ox40.
So anal, I don't know if that's true.
I'm pretty sure that with address space layout.
Randomization now for security.
I don't think you're actually ever allowed to force your dll to load a
specific location.
So you can check it out.
It's basically, this stuff aslr, right?
You can read about a SLR.
I pretty sure, Windows just doesn't let you load deal as a fixed
location anymore, but
I don't know if that's true.
Maybe you can maybe there's still ways because there used to be old
Flags where you could actually specify what the Base address of the
dll was, but I thought that nowadays that was harder to do that.
Maybe not.
So I don't know.
You can take a look and see if aslr messes with you or if it doesn't.
But either way and you can turn S aslr off on the whole system if you
want to.
But either way I don't think that's the biggest problem.
It's the Linker.
That's the biggest problem.
The function pointers are already going to move even if we load the
deal.
Ll at the same Base address when we change stuff.
And so I don't think we can really count on function pointers and I
don't think we really need them either.
How long does it take for you to get to a point where you can conceive
of a feature?
And with little effort, know exactly what you need to accomplish to
realize that feature.
For example, I have conceived of game State recording and Playback
before.
However, I've never been able to get to the point where everything was
set up in a way to make it easy to do one.
Small example of that is the fixed Base address for the memory block
without it.
It seems impossible, or at least way more difficult.
Most of programming seems to be having the experience to know how to
set yourself up to make your ideas easy to accomplish.
How long did it take you to get to this level of effectiveness?
Goodness, so I guess what I would say is probably a very long time,
probably at least 20 years of programming.
Of course, I was very young when I started so you might count those
years a little bit less because you're not really that smart and you
It was a lot of stuff when you were little.
So I don't know about that, but I would say, yeah, probably at least
20 years before you get to be the point where you're pretty fast at
that sort of stuff, but maybe other people will be faster.
I don't know, but it took me a long time as for realizing stuff with
little effort.
The other thing to remember is this actually is a very easy thing to
do what I just did.
It's basically like, Oh, I thought about it for a while, you know, and
I was like, okay, it's not, it's not too bad.
And in fact, I think the first time I did a system like this was
actually like
1996 at D6.
I did one that just blasted the state of memory out something and
reloaded it.
So that we could do physics to bugging and you could single step.
So what it did was it just outputted the state of the game every time
because we had, like this physics block that we could blast out.
So like I first did that actually way back.
I think I was like 19 at the time and had, you know, a lot less
program experience.
I first did this thing then and it turns out that you can do stuff
like that.
If you have stuff that doesn't have a bunch of pointers in it and all
those sorts of
Things.
And so it was kind of building on that and later.
I was like, oh, okay, I could do this as well with other stuff by just
having a fixed Base address or something like that and then pointers
would work too and blah blah blah.
So it's just kind of like stuff that builds on each other over time,
but this is actually relatively simple feature complex stuff, still
takes me a long time.
I will sometimes work a month on a code architecture thing because I
have an idea that I think something should be possible and I left a
refine it and refine it and refine it and refine.
In it and I make tons of mistakes.
So it depends on how hard the problem is.
And it depends on how new the territory is for you.
And so this happens to be a particularly easy thing because there
happens to be a very clean solution.
If you just do a few simple steps, those are much easier to arrive at
than other things which can be much more complicated and take a lot
longer and have a lot more.
Intricacy.
And so we will probably even see some things on this stream.
Later on.
We're working on the game where I have to go through several revisions
to get it, right.
and so so this happens to be particularly simple because there's a few
simple things you can do architectural that, make it so that it just
works, but
You know, that that was that was a lucky that this this I don't want
you to get the sense that I sit down and it goes that smoothly all the
time, right?
You will see things on the stream where we have to really work at it.
And that's, I think I probably, I don't know if there's programmers,
who get past that point to, but I suspect, I will probably die.
Someday, never, haven't gotten to the point where it doesn't.
Sometimes take me a month to solve a hard architecture problem.
Couldn't you create an offset pointer struct which overloads the unary
star operator?
Probably not going to try and touch that one.
My first question would be how would it know what the base pointer was
at that point.
I guess you said a
I don't know.
You could try setting a global.
For specifying, a dll base address.
Okay, and I was just watching again.
I don't think the deal of Base address.
Is that important?
Like I said, I mean it may be possible to do now even with a SLR.
There's maybe a switch that says, no really.
Even though you have a SLR.
I really need to be at the space address, but I'm not sure if you can,
I'm not sure if it doesn't just get overridden, but even so, I think
it's the Linker that with toward us.
Pseudonym 73, we did talk about iOS objects, but we haven't talked
about rendering subsystem objects yet.
Like Shader.
Texture handles, can't be part of the game State perhaps getting ahead
of ourselves.
But how do you plan to handle this?
Well, that is getting ahead.
So wait till we get there.
Where is Santa hat for Christmas next week?
If I can find one, that may very well happen.
Care to reiterate your candy reiterate.
The pertinent compiler options that allow this to work as it is or
those that will prevent.
I don't know that there are compiler options that prevent this.
I think I don't think these are compiler option.
Related things, enemy Mouse.
I may be wrong about that, but I don't think there's any compiler
option things that we need to that need to be set for this to work.
Let's see.
Have you got some good explanation on how your Arctic code is that in
the text?
You wrote about your work on the witness?
Yes, if you go to my blog the witness stuff does have some articles
about architecting code, but we'll be seeing quote How We Do code,
architecting on the stream.
Because there's several things in this game that I've never done
before.
Like I picked things.
Like I've never written a system that does blah and so I will be sort
of live, architecting it.
Like you'll see me sick.
You'll see me go through each step that I would go through to arrive
at a good architecture.
And so, you'll see me do like a bad version and fix it and do stuff
like will
Through that process where I'm not just saying, I know how to write
this and Bam.
It's right?
Or something.
Like that, won't be happening.
We'll be going through.
They'll at least be a couple places.
If not many places where I have to work through the architecture,
live, rather than knowing what the architecture should be
cross-platform code.
I kind of know what the architecture should, because I've written it
so many times, but definitely, like, when we get to things pieces of
the game, they'll be pieces that I have never written before on any
game or
or in any even in a test thing.
And so then you will, I'm doing that intentionally so that you'll be
able to see me.
Architect the code, how I write something.
I don't know how to write because I think that's probably one of the
most important things to learn.
The.
Someone was asking.
Unfortunately, a lot of simple things have been made Complicated by
what I was taught by the correct way of programming, which was
entirely based on a very myopic view of heavy object oriented Ascend,
lack of solid.
The level understanding, I have to spend a lot of time on learning,
what I was taught just to get to features which should be easy, but
we're made hard by the kind of programming.
I learned in school.
Have you had some are painful and learning process?
Yes, basically, like when I was first exposed to C++ kind of like when
people are first exposed to
In in like 95, let's say I started trying to program and what we're
good luck.
I read like Scott Meyers effective C++ and like, I read like, you know
those, I don't remember what all those books are.
But like the I don't remember what who the guys names are.
But the people I had a subscription to the C++ report, right?
And basically, it meant that I didn't write a single good piece of
code for probably five years, like, everything I wrote.
It was awful and it's because those techniques don't work there.
They're bad.
Like, you know, if you have a Scott Meyers book on your shelf, throw
it out its complete garbage and every last thing and it's a waste of
time.
And so I had exactly the same thing.
I went to work for rad eventually and it was kind of like detox
because like Jeff Roberts and John Miles were both, not that kind of
programmer and Jeff.
Particularly is a very low-level old-school programmer, and I kind of
Added thinking, why am I doing all these things?
Programming was so much better back.
When I only programmed in C and then C.
+ +, it's all been awful and nothing works.
It's slow and it's ugly.
And it takes forever to write stuff.
What's going on here?
And then I tried just not programming in C++ anymore.
I said, let me go back to see and I'll only start using a C++ feature.
If I find that it actually use, if I can prove that it was actually
helping me.
And what I found is basically overloaded functions and overloaded
operators, were the only two things that I ever wanted again.
Occasionally.
For Destructor, pairs for doing things like timing blocks, but that
was about it.
And so when I was writing granny, the 3D animation library for rad,
basically, that was when I kind of learned how to program again and so
yes, it's a very painful process.
I I don't know if I wish I could get the time back or if I'm glad that
I went through it.
So now I just know to never do those things and that they're actually
bad and I don't just have to speculate that.
They're bad programming practices.
I just know that they actually are and so
You know, yes, I've been there.
I totally been there and it was it was not fun.
All right.
Looks like we've gotten to the end of the questions.
Okay.
Let's see here.
I guess it is.
The end of the stream.
We have reached we have reached the end of day 23.
Thank you all for joining me.
I had a lot of fun implementing that
I thought it was going to be fun.
It was fun.
So I hope you have enjoyed it.
If you would like to play around with the code at home.
You can always pre-order on the handmade here at org website and you
can download the latest source code every night and play around with
it.
Do whatever you would like to do experiment, try new things and play
around with the stuff that we did.
And you'll also, of course, get a copy of the game when it's released
and all that other.
Good stuff.
If you have to catch up or ask questions.
Or anything else.
Video related, the news and forums link will go to a bunch of
resources that you can use including stuff.
Like a coding Resource page that has how to run handmade hero on stuff
like, Mac or Linux with people who've done ports.
There's, you want support the video series.
There's a patreon page for it.
There's the tweets, obviously for following the series schedule.
And there's also on the news and forums.
There's a schedule posted and of course does a YouTube video archive
that has the videos uploaded.
So I will be uploading these right after they finish.
I upload them so you can always get them right away from us.
Item, so, thank you so much for joining me.
Tomorrow will be at 11 a.m.
And so will Friday and it'll just be cleanup days getting a set for
next week.
So if you're around tomorrow morning, please join me for that.
If not, I hope to see you recorded.
And yeah, I'm looking forward to finishing it up our win32 stuff so
that we can basically move on to game stuff, which I think is gonna be
a lot of fun.
So thanks everyone for joining me and I will hopefully see you
tomorrow.