Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on Twitch with no libraries.
No engine.
No nothing really, just our own code.
And we are right in the middle of doing our sort of engine design
work.
We are designing our own engine here.
We kind of have some of the parts that we need specced out so far kind
of kind of pro tip in place, but we haven't really tackled some of the
entity stuff that we need to get sorted out before we start working on
things.
Like
The renderer the animation system.
And so what I want to do is today, I'm kind of going to go through and
start to play with entities a little bit.
We don't have anything specific in mind, but we just want to kind of
start playing with them and see what sorts of stuff we need in the
entities to make them work properly.
And to allow us to build world's the way that we want to build them
and just try to get a feel for what's going to be required because
that will kind of inform our design decisions.
As we go forward, and let us know what the engine actually needs to do
in terms of supporting the stuff that we're going to want.
And so we're just gonna start playing around that and we'll see where
it goes.
I suspect this will take us several days because we'll want to build
lots of different like, sort of example, test sort of things in here
and we kind of have to see how each of them plays out before we can
really start to make decisions about what we want the engine to do for
us because we just do one or two different types of enemies will
probably miss some things that are important to some other types of
entities that work different ways and that sort of stuff.
In addition kind of all wrapped up in this.
We also kind of have one other small decision to make, which is, if
everything is an entity or if there's going to be other things that
are not quite full status citizens, like that, aren't all the way
entities, and that sort of stuff, like, you know, do we want the
grasses and the rocks on the ground to be entities, or is it too
expensive to store those entities in?
Are we going to need some sort of intermediate representation for
those guys?
That's, that's halfway.
Sort of lesser than an entity if you will, so that's, we're going to
do today.
If you have pre-ordered, the game on handmade hero dot-org, using the
pre order button.
Then you should have gotten the link in your email, which has
basically a download page, that download page allows you to download
the source code and that source code consists of a series of zip
files.
What you want to do is you want to grab a day 58 zip file because here
on day 59, that's the source code that we are starting from.
So, grab 5058 zip file, unzip it to a directory and you'll be exactly
where I am.
Right now.
And where am I right now is always the first question of the day.
And where am I right now?
Is we had just finished our spatial partition for entities.
We had thrown some trees in there.
And of course, we are not actually sorting our entities yet.
So we get some sort of nonsensical results, which is like, obviously
intuitively this tree should occlude, you know, the player, but it
doesn't.
Similarly, like, there's places where the player looks like.
He should be included in show.
He should include a tree, but doesn't like right there.
right, and that's
You're rendering things.
So I'm not sure if I actually care about that too much, but we might
want to you might want to address that again as well.
Sometimes seeing, which is basically just a sort of our entities in
terms of what order they should be drawn in just to fix that.
So, I don't know.
That's kind of on the table is something that may happen.
When I get too annoyed with it.
We know what needs to be done.
It's not a big deal, but just when we do it, if it starts to make me
too grumpy than that's, you know, it's got a, it's got to be fixed
before I can go do things.
That might be more important to do at any given time.
Okay, so I guess some things just to start with just really some basic
stuff.
What I'd like to do is just start playing with dropping some more
entities in here.
Maybe, what I'll do trying to trying to think of what the what the
smartest way to approach it is, maybe what I'll do is like, write some
simple things like just put in another entity, another copy of the
player, for example, who just kind of follows the player around.
So, you know, when the player goes somewhere that other entity will
All the play around because that's going to be a reasonable amount of
code that may take a several days to do actually, to work out exactly
how we want to store stuff like that.
Because for example, we may find that we want to do like pathfinding
or something like we may want to we may want to do something like when
I come up around here, you know in the entity is over here.
We may want him to be smart enough to like find this opening in the
trees and walk through it as opposed to just like bumping into the
trees stupidly or something like this, right?
So that's a good example of that.
And similarly with that with that same code.
At the same time.
I'll probably bring up some kind of monster.
So something that like attacks the player for example, and maybe give
the player like a hit animation, like a, not a hit animation, but like
a hit key.
So you can swipe, you know, at the monster and we'll just try to get
something like that going.
So we'll have a, you know, the player, a familiar, a monster and the
ability for them to interact in some way and that'll kind of allow me
to start a start to see what I want in terms of systems that will
allow me to construct those things.
Not having to worry a super lot about what's going on right without
having to worry about, like, the integration effort or whatever that's
required in it.
So, let's think about this.
Let's think about how we want to do this.
Okay.
So I'm gonna go ahead and load up the editor here.
Like I said this, this this should be relatively complicated because
I'm imagining that we want something.
Once we start to actually want real features, like the things not to
be totally stupid.
It's going to get relatively complicated.
Okay.
So I guess what I'd like to do now is I'd like to say that, you know,
we're going to we're going to put down maybe a monster in that first
room.
Let's say, just as a test.
I'll put down, you know, the monster and the familiar.
We'll both go in that first room.
So what we could use, we could use the new camera position, right?
We could use that new camera position as a way of figuring out where
those guys should go.
And then I also obviously already have in here sort of.
We had a very simple concept of what an entity was.
Right?
We had Heroes and we had walls that's all we had so far, but I could
go ahead and in here and add an entity type.
That's just our test familiar.
Right?
And I could add another entity type.
That was like our test monster, right?
That would be pretty reasonable to do.
And now if I want to, I can go ahead and add as low entity types,
right?
I can go ahead and add those in using our add low density function.
So if I want to, I could make a function here that that adds one of
these guys.
So if I add a monster, right, I can go ahead and do that and the
monster, I guess we'll just continue that sort of the trend that we
have been doing where I take Tile locations, right?
And we add things at those Tile locations because that seems, you
know, as good at anything at this point when we start to get more into
like, how we want to build the world.
We may change that but for now, it seems totally fine.
So all I got to do here is I guess do exactly what I was doing.
Where I where I get out the entity stuff.
What I'm wondering here is if this can't be collapse a little bit like
I might as well just get the low energy directly after I do it.
Do any people typically use the entity index.
I guess they do sometimes.
Times.
They kinda need to know that.
I wonder if add low entity, though.
Should just return both.
I guess what I'm thinking is ADD low entity.
Maybe should just have a low entity, you know, something like this new
low entity, right?
Or something like that.
And it just has, I guess I could call it.
Add low entity result, will be more consistent naming with what we had
before and that'll just have whatever its index was its low index and
also its pointer.
So the
The Entity low, right?
Or maybe I'll just call that low so I could do something like that.
Maybe that makes a little bit more sense to me because then I can put
this in here and that way when you call this just a little more
convenient, right?
So the result right is going to start out, I guess.
Let's see here at the end of the index.
We're always asserting that it's actually valid.
So, to some degree, that's that's relatively straightforward.
I guess.
I could even do it down here.
So I could say the result Dot Low.
Whoa, equals entity low.
Right, and it's here.
Kind of feeling cramped with my typing.
There we go.
And then my result low index is going to be entity index like so.
So if I go ahead and return that instead, now all of these people who
get both things can just do it in one go and they don't have to
constantly be doing all this, this nonsense and so we can just do it
this way.
I suppose.
Oops, just do it this way where we do that and now we don't have to
call that anymore.
And this is
just entity.
Low.
This is entity dot low index, like so and that can go ahead and
return, you know, it could even return just this.
Although for now.
I guess I won't do that.
We'll see if anyone actually uses that in that way.
In fact, I guess I could check right now to see what they're doing.
Yeah, it doesn't look like they actually use it.
So for now we'll just leave it that way.
But it could be something easy to do is just pass this on, right?
Pass it on as we go and that sort of seems a little compelling.
Anyway.
So now if I'm going to do this instead,
Of doing these two things.
I'll just do this right here, right?
Like that.
And this will add an entity type monster and it'll add at that
location.
Now, I don't actually know what the entity monsters, height and width
should be, I guess I'll just use the same as we were using for the
player for now.
And they will collide for now too, because I feel like that just makes
sense.
And I guess, maybe, we'll start the trend, what the hell?
Let's go ahead and start the trend where we go ahead and, and return
The Entity.
As it was like that.
And this will be Adler entity result.
So that'll be Loops.
That will be just returning that and same thing with the wall.
That'll do it this way, and that'll return that entity here.
Oops.
And Trinity, whatever that is, and there we go with this.
Okay, so that'll go away and these will become dots.
So and let's take a look.
There's anything else we
Fix their lips gonna fix that.
Oops.
That's no good.
Yeah, and add player is just could just get low index directly off of
it.
And so that's done.
And this is all good now.
All right, so that's all good.
And we should go ahead and add one of our monsters now, because we
can.
So when we add this in, I guess what we would do is say, oh, I don't
know.
We know that this is where the camera is.
So, I guess what I'll say, I'll do something like camera tile X.
This
Camera shy.
like this, and
Camera tile Z.
There you go.
Camera tile X camera, Tau Y and Camera.
Tile Z like so and so that way if I want to do an ad monster, I can
just kind of put him somewhere near the camera, you know, plus
something, right?
I can just do it.
Like camera tile y plus 2, plus 2, or something like that, right?
Something relatively simple and that will I believe take one of those.
So that will add our monster to the world, I think.
This actually takes that.
There we go.
So if I run this, I feel like yeah, I get that now.
Okay.
I'm not sure though.
That seems a little bit busted.
I don't understand why that is what I expected him to be a tree
because that's the only other thing we draw right now.
So we have to go add the ability to draw monsters as different things.
But why did he only appear?
Oh, duh.
I know why again, set camera is.
Of course, the thing that actually
Does the work.
If you never call set camera, then low entities can't be brought in to
the set.
And I wonder if that's a good thing or a bad thing.
I don't really know.
We might have to to think about that a little bit.
Like when we add something do we need to then check to see if it's
inside the camera bounds to know.
Whether maybe at the time we added it.
It should be added into the system, right?
And I don't know that's that's like a pretty
that's a pretty difficult question to answer actually, so, you know,
maybe I'll go into add low entity and just say to do, do we need to
have a begin and Paradigm for adding entities so that they can be
brought into the hiset when they are added and are in the
Camera region, right?
So you understand what was happening there, right?
Basically, what happened is I was I do that one set camera call at the
end to sort of set things up and that's what brings everything into
the high entity set.
Until there is a player on the screen set camera will never be called
again because the camera hasn't moved and so until I hit the spacebar
and actually make a player that will start causing a camera to called
there is no reason why that guy will ever come on screen, right?
Right.
And so until I actually have the player.
That's the only thing that will bring him on.
So now that should be fixed because I believe I moved him below the
set camera, did I?
Yes, so now it should actually be there the whole time which it is.
So that's what we want.
But again, just something to be aware of not sure if we really care
too much about that.
It's easy to fix.
But I'm not sure what our, what our Paradigm.
Like I said.
It's going to be for that.
Exactly.
So, yeah, so that's about it.
Okay.
Moving on, I guess what I would say is we might as well try drawing
this as something a little more recognizable.
And so we kind of just have we don't have any sort of Rhyme or Reason
to how our drawing things.
And I don't necessarily know that we want to address that now because
I feel like we want to address that kind of more when we start working
with animation.
So what I might do is just the most basic thing here, which is switch
on the low entity type and then go ahead and check to see
What a?
We is is the type draw each one different.
So we've got any type.
Well that will be drawn the way that we were drawing it as this like
so and then the other thing we can do is go ahead and do an entity
type monstar and monstar will you know have something else?
I don't know that we care about the default case where if we don't
know what it is.
Normally I assert on something like
That but in this case, well in this case, maybe I'll assert on it as
well.
So we'll do it assertion here where we're just say invalid code path,
right?
So basically, if we get to here, we know that we forgot one of our
enemy types and I won't put in any type null as well.
So that will remind us of where accidentally looping over and drawing
the nullity.
But so now if we get to monstar, we need to draw something.
I think, what I'll probably do is maybe just draw, you know, like
Something like the Hero bitmap.
Let's do maybe just the Torso, right?
Like so, and we also had a familiar to be not entity type familiar,
right?
And the entity type familiar, I think we'll just draw just just maybe
the head.
Like so, so we'll go ahead and try that out.
And again, this code is just just totally garbage placeholder code.
So as long as it works at all, I'm totally fine with it.
We'll go ahead and do that there.
So that point we should be.
And in fact, I can pull this out for now because people are using it
in general, even though, obviously not everyone will look up into hero
bitmaps, just for our own convenience.
So that should give us a monstar.
That's yeah.
That's just a little looks like a little
It's just a little torso with no arms and legs.
Yeah, you know, what are you gonna do?
It's a monster.
And I suppose we could also put a shadow in there for that guy while
we're at it.
So maybe these these guys, both get shadows and we have our ad
monster.
So we'll also do an ad familiar and the ad familiar is a little bit
weird, because I'm not sure if the ad familiar should Collide, or if
the ABS familiar is kind of a
Floating thing, which doesn't really have to collide.
So maybe the familiar can just do whatever it wants for now, just for
now, eventually, maybe not.
I think we probably want the concept of flying versus on the ground.
And so that it would still collide with things that were full height,
but it could float over things like, you know, that we're whatever.
You know what I'm saying?
You know what?
I'm talking about standard gamey sorts of stuff, right?
You know what I mean?
So that to me looks relatively good with ADD familiar.
I don't think I really need.
Much else with it like so and so we can add the monster and we can add
the familiar and then we will have both of those on the screen at the
same time, which is always good.
And we'll put this one kind of in the in the opposite on the opposite
side and now they should both be there and there they are.
So now what we need to do is we need to we have controller logic in
there so that we can move ourselves around right.
And you can see I'm
Not colliding.
With this guy could be said as Collide to false, but I am colliding
with this guy because we said it's gliding.
True.
So that's good.
What I need to do is set up some kind of a notion of when these people
think about what they want to do, right?
Because we don't need to think about what the player does really?
Because we just use whatever the keyboard input or the joystick input
is and that allows us to just, you know, know exactly what we should
be, how we should be updating the player, but we now need some way of
taking.
Entities that are not the player and updating them, right?
So what we want to do is is put in that structure and then what will
do I guess is for are familiar, will kind of have a notion that maybe
the familiar follows anything nearby.
That's a player and if it maybe if it gets too far away, it stops
following or something like that.
I don't know if we want them to be permanently tagged to a particular
player or not, but we'll see.
And then the monstar will do.
Similarly, if it sees a hero nearby it will try to
Start attacking it.
Maybe it'll have a bro.
Give it a projectile or something.
I don't know exactly what it will do.
All right.
So let's go ahead and do that.
I guess we can leave the code running for now.
And so the way we would do that is we already have the concept in our
in our code here of looping, over the controllers, right?
And moving the player.
So then, what we would need is something where we actually go and loop
over the high level entities and for every high level entity.
We like update its position.
Right now, I don't know exactly what we want to do in terms of the
order of operations here.
It's a little confusing because what I could do is I could do the
update and the render for those high level entities in one pass
really.
And by the way, we can get rid of this entirely now, we don't even
have a Tom have to draw anymore so that can go away.
So when we update our high level entities and we've already got their
high and low State here.
I don't know, it might be fine to just go ahead and write.
Here, do that update.
Now, entity offset for frame.
I thought we stopped using that.
What does that even doing here?
That's just, yeah, that's just leftover code, right?
We're now doing that offset in the same.
The set camera call.
So if we go ahead and just say, like, let's start by just putting it
here because we already have one Loop over everyone, and we've already
pulled them in.
So now would be a good place to do it.
Let's say that we want to.
Yeah.
Say that we just want this to be our code, where we update the entity.
So, let's go ahead and update this entity.
Here will pass the high entity, and the low entity.
And I believe we already have a structure for this though.
Don't we?
We've got this essentially.
So what I'll do is I'll just say entity and that entity will have its
low index equal to whatever the low index was which is that the
entities low pointer will be below entity.
And the end of the high will be the high entity.
Like so, and then, we can just go ahead and update that, right?
So we're update that, we know what our DT is, right?
We pass it, the game world as well.
So we're going to update the entity there and we're going to update it
by this amount.
So that's the amount of time that has elapsed and that seems
reasonable.
Right.
So we'll start with that.
Seems Seems plausible.
So basically this just has to take an entity and it has two to
actually do its update.
Now, you know what though?
Thinking about this a little bit further,
I actually already am checking its type to to render it.
So if I wanted to, I could do this, I could collapse this dispatch in
sort of a more.
I could probably make this a little bit smarter already actually.
So maybe we'll go ahead and do that.
Let's take a look at what's going on here.
First of all, this
First of all, this junk code.
Jump code.
I don't know what to do with this jump code that we threw in there at
the in a Q&A one day.
This is this is not yeah, this is not particularly great.
So let's Loops.
Let's go ahead and see what's going on here.
So we've got player RGB.
Those are those are not even being used anymore at all.
We can get rid of those for.
Now we have with the ground point is of this particular entity.
That is not something that actually matters per entity.
That's the same computation for everybody.
So we could sort of consider that to be to be something that that's
that's trivial to compute.
That's kind of just transformed into that space.
We've got the Z is done.
Yeah.
The standard way, the Z was done and then this is really just
Computing for the rectangle, which is only drawn in like debug
scenarios, right?
Yeah.
So I think what I might do is start to pull this
Out into some more like slightly more logical thing.
So let's take a look here.
Hold on a second.
I want to clean this up a little bit before we go any further, let's
see, we're still doing everything right over here.
Yeah, so the first thing I want to do is say, well, I don't think this
jump code really
Long's here at all.
Obviously, I don't know why it's even here.
It's updating.
The equations of motion for this guy's Z, but really if it was going
to do that.
It should probably be in some kind of like, well, you know, I mean,
now that I think about it, I guess, if everyone's under the influence
of gravity, I suppose, that's fine.
This, this is actually.
All right.
I mean, everyone could have their deezy updated with gravity.
I mean, gravity applies to everybody.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, you know what?
I guess I changed my mind.
Well, we'll let it stay on there.
So we'll call this Shadow Alpha and we'll just go ahead and leave that
on there.
I mean, if it works, it works, you know, don't don't kill it.
So basically, this is just how we would update the Z for the guy.
After we already did his regular updating.
And I suppose that that could be baked into whatever equations of
motion update, we do.
So, maybe I could just have sort of a universal equations of motion
update happen in here, for anyone who actually wants it.
So I'd pull out the Collision detection stuff and that would kind of
come in here and then we just have that happen and the Z would be
rolled into it, seems reasonable.
Guess, I don't see a real.
Overwhelming reason why not to do it.
And so yeah, I guess we could actually do that and similarly I could
kind of make these things queue up a little bit.
I could say whatever you want to draw.
You just kind of say where those things were relative to you and then
we'll draw them.
Okay.
Alright, let's go with that.
So here's what I'm going to do.
I'm gonna collapse these two things down.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to say that we've got some kind of a
rendering concept here.
So I'm going to say that we've got something like, you know, something
like this.
I'm going to call it a a rendered piece or something, or an entity
piece, right?
I don't know.
Entity visible piece.
Don't have a good.
I have no.
What the name of this should be, but for right now, it doesn't really
matter.
And essentially what that's going to be is it's going to be a piece of
information that tells us exactly what I would draw.
Offset from some magical Point like the players Grounds location.
Right?
And so, what I'll do is I'll say here, is that bitmap here are the
offsets for it.
So this is like
A dxi, I guess I should say offset like this.
We really, really need to put in some three dimensional vectors.
It's getting long in the tooth and then we'll also say what the alpha
was for it.
So, you know, we got this Edge be visible piece and then I'll just
make a really simple little stack here which just says pieces, right?
And we'll say that, I don't know, things have eight pieces for now.
This is again, totally random.
No real concern for it, and we'll just say piece count, like so.
And then for each one of these guys,
As we go, in fact, I guess I could go one step further and say entity
visible case group like this and that will actually just be these.
There we go.
Oops, not quite.
Okay, and so for every one of those that we have empty visible Keys
group.
This is our peace grip.
When we come in here.
I will just change our drawbitmap calls to something that's
essentially add piece.
Right?
So we're going to add a piece and each one of these things will be a
tad piece call.
And then at the end, we'll just Loop over them, right?
Like so and we'll draw them.
Okay, and what this will let me do is this will let me kind of split
those out.
And so that the update call can kind of side where it wants its stuff.
And then at the end it kind of gets collapse down.
And so that way we only have one piece of logic for each entity that
both does the updating and the rendering, which I don't know.
Like I said, feels like a little bit better to me at the time, but
we'll see, it may end up being not what we want, and we'll rip it back
at.
So, let's see.
So we've got our piece group here and it's got a count.
I guess.
I shouldn't bother saying piece count.
Because we know that's what that is.
So, we've got our count and we can Loop over it for each one of the
pieces in it.
Sarah, I will grab that piece out like so Peace Index.
Yeah, and here's my piece group that, and in here I can now, say all
right, what were the things that I needed?
We've got the buffer.
We've got the, the bitmap that we need.
We know this is going to be.
Oops, not bitmap torso, just bitmap.
We know that we've got essentially wherever the thing was.
So we've got these things, right?
Whatever.
These are will.
Those after-the-fact down here.
Right.
And that will be our peace.
This is our offset X groups like so, this is our our peace offset.
Why?
Yeah, and it's also plus the piece offset Z like so.
And then in there, we need to bake in the offset by what the actual
ground.
Point is.
So this is the entity ground Point here, X and Y.
And we will go ahead and put those in there.
And again, these are some pretty good candidates for vectorizing.
Haven't really done it yet.
But really, we should probably switch to 3D that's on my list of
things to do.
When we do the animation system.
I think I'm kind of putting it off because we didn't really have to do
it, but that'll be sort of, sort of web that has to happen.
All right, and so, we also need a lineman on there, as well.
So these offsets, I guess the offsets.
It could just bake in the alignment now that I think about it,
actually.
So, so yeah, so why actually were, why were we placing?
So yeah, if I think about this a little bit more carefully, we kind of
have two things you want to collapse them.
Both down.
We have the alignment but the alignment can be collapsed down into the
offset.
If we replacing something, we don't need to have two different ways to
place it.
Right?
And so we've really got two competing things.
There's how you would want to move it relative to where you are.
And then there's like how the bitmap was aligned.
Separate from where you're sort of hot spotting it, right.
So I'm going to say, I'm just going to go ahead and say, let's take a
look at that drawbitmap call because all it's doing is subtracting
those numbers out.
Right?
So maybe what I want to do is just eliminate that concept now and say
that that's going to attract a little bit higher up.
Just you know, one level back basically just get rid of that and say
we're no longer doing that that happens at a slightly higher level to
drop bitmap and that
Way, when we pass it down, we've just passed it down those things
preordained.
So that seems a little smarter to me.
That seems to be a more logical thing for us to do.
Okay, and then obviously we have to do our peace Alpha as well.
All right.
So we've got our entity ground points there.
We've got the Z which is going to be however high.
He is going to is thing there and that's fine.
So that actually would go in here I guess as well that would be
concatenated on there.
Whatever we said was the entity Z, I guess something like this, right?
And the player left top and the entity with height are really for
debugging only, so, for right now, we don't actually need those, but
we might want to leave those in the
Because we want to start drawing rectangles here to show like as a
debug situation where somebody is maybe those come back into play.
So what we're going to do here is we're going to do a push piece.
Call.
Those of you who know me know, I like a good push, like a good push
call.
I'm a pusher.
It's true.
Don't let anyone tell you otherwise.
And so, these are just going to basically push pieces onto this little
piece piece stack, right?
It's kind of like a peace pipe, but it's a
Stock in this case and nobody is getting high.
So what we will do now is go ahead and make sure that we eliminate any
of the things that we had before that, we're not necessary.
So we really don't need.
So basically, this is just always zeros.
We don't have any offsets that we need to apply to our dude at all.
In this particular case, we only have the alignment and that should be
it, right?
Because we don't have different pieces like hands or floating parts
that attach everything was actually right at the origin.
And then we have the alignment from the bitmap, which we pass along,
and then we have the, the shadow Alpha.
Now, what we could do here to is really this should be an x y and a z.
So this should really be, you know, one of these, right?
So this should be one of those.
There we go.
And so on.
So these are the pieces that he would want.
Similarly, we come down here, we can get rid of this as well.
We'll put this down here with this guy that
So oops gotta get out from behind my head and so yeah, that's about
all I really wanted to do here.
This is again, just a 0 0 and 0 and then it takes the 4080.
Those could probably be wrapped up as V2 as well.
Now.
I think that would probably be reasonably, right.
So maybe we'll do that next.
Let's see to do alignments.
As V2, right?
In fact, I could go ahead and just do that directly.
Let's just go ahead and do that.
I'm going to go ahead and say, let's do that.
So, this will take a V2 4080 like that.
And these guys, I'll just have the hero bitmaps will just collapse
those down into a line, like, so, and that'll, that'll be that.
So, that all looks good.
He's group again like this.
this, and let's go ahead and
Put in the standard unused stuff.
Then we've got our hero bitmaps.
Oops.
That's no good here, a bit Maps a line.
And there's that shadow Alpha.
Okay.
So yeah again, nothing not really doing anything, particularly
interesting here just wrote transformation of the code so that it's
just a little bit easier for me to manage what's going on.
And these are all pushed piece calls push piece this piece which piece
Peace, peace, lovely.
And then these are just
probably should have done this with.
The macro was too lazy, too.
Lazy.
To think it through.
It's true.
I admit that.
That.
Okay.
So that's all the stuff that we need there.
But now, we need to go fix sort of our bitmap or loaded bitmap.
If you remember, I just said, I want to change the alignment to
actually being V2.
So we're going to go ahead and say that that's a V2.
Now, which means we'll have to actually fix the aligned here to be
looking like this.
Yeah, so that's that.
and,
Guess these are all the same, huh, so I could just do this.
Shadow Alpha is this value here?
Right?
Shadow Alpha and of course, that's a little confusing because that one
you really kind of want to know what it would actually be a little
later on.
So it's kind of like a deferred rendering thing that we're doing here.
So I'm not sure that may have been a little bit of mistake love to
think about how we want to want to kind of think that through.
Because after we do the update,
yeah, I mean, we could
It's so hard to say.
So you see what my dilemma is?
I'm thinking now that maybe I didn't really need to do that because
what I should possibly have done is just made a call that's like,
okay, update, my equations of motion and you just call it here,
instead of trying to make it so that you put the logic in here, and
then the stuff executes outside.
Did I make a mistake?
Is it possible that we just don't need this extra?
Because what I was doing was essentially deferring the rendering to
later so that we could do some stuff in between it.
But what I was really realizing as I could just put it in here
directly.
Well, I'll keep going down this path follows want to see, maybe it
does make some things a little easier later, we'll find out.
But for right now, I guess I should just finish what I did.
Because then, at least I'll be able to see if it was smart or if it
was stupid in a little more detail.
So I think I did just about everything except for push peace.
And so I just got to go Implement push piece and that's it, right?
So push piece is up here.
Either way, I'm glad we changed the V2s on the alignment so that's a
good thing either way but we just may not have needed to do this push
piece.
Bit that may have just been unnecessary.
So there's the group right here is the loaded bitmap.
There's a bit where we're going to use here is the offset.
Here's the offset Z and here is the alignment.
So what we're going to do now is we're going to, you know, again just
make sure that we've got room for this guy.
So we'll make sure that the group piece count
is less than the space that we have so that we're not going.
Overflow it and then we'll go ahead and stick it onto the end of that
guy.
Right?
And so here is our entity visible piece like so we can inline the sky
so it can kind of fold away.
So here's our piece.
And then we will.
I guess just fill these out.
It doesn't seem to be anything particularly tricky about that.
So there's our offset - the alignment again because we're folding
those into one variable.
So there's our offset Z and then our Alpha is our Alpha.
Which we still need to put on as a default parameter since only some
people pass it.
Oh, I guess we don't really need to return anything.
Let's just avoid and that's it.
So, let's see.
That's just
Count.
I guess.
I really wanted to call it peace count.
So maybe if I really wanted to call it.
Peace count so badly.
I was right the first time when I called it.
Peace Camp.
So let's go ahead and just change it in the other place.
Let's see.
Cannot convert argument one.
Yes, that's because it's not pointing to the buffer anymore.
There we go.
And there is our piece count said we're going to do and then we also
have, let's see here, 32 Peace Index.
And it's less than P.
Scooped up piece count.
What are you saying?
Peace?
Potential.
See a local variable?
Oh, right, and we need to obviously set this guy's piece count at
startup to be 0.
Thank you compiler.
That was handy.
Oops.
What did I didn't?
I didn't remember.
I saw the game running and we changed the layout of things there.
That was not my intention, but I forgot.
All right.
So let's see here.
Piece count is eight.
How is that possible?
What did I owe?
You know why I put that in the wrong place, meant to put it here each
time.
So basically it's every entity just has its own like the, assert
caught that they're all right.
So now we're doing the exact same thing.
We were doing nothing special, but we've now got it into those that
sort of bucketed form.
And so, now, what I can do is I can start to pull this apart a little
bit more more cleanly here.
So what I could do is start updating these guys actually in here.
Now walls,
Don't need any update.
Familiars do need an update.
So there'd be an update familiar call right like this and monster.
So we'll have an update monster call, where I'll go ahead and call out
to something that does a bunch of logic for those guys.
And again, that'll just take the entity that we prepared and the game
State and I guess it also probably wants that DT, huh.
So we'll call that and we'll have our update monster calls well, and
then we can actually started putting some code that those guys use.
Now, this code right here, really?
He wants to get executed later, right?
And that's why I saying that, the shadow Alpha is a bit of a problem
because the shadow Alpha really wants to be computed.
After we figure out what the actual Z is.
And so that was a little bit of a mistake.
That was the thing that I was starting to think that maybe this was
wrong because really what we should be doing is making utility
function that computes these things and then you still do the draw
call.
I don't really know.
It's a good question.
And one that I'm not super prepared to answer.
What we can do for now is compute our shadow Alpha incorrectly.
So what I could do is say, oh, okay, you know, what will do is will
will will make that.
Be something that happens up here, right?
So I'll just do like to do this is incorrect.
Should be computed after update or something like that and we'll kind
of think about that.
But again, this is exactly why I'm doing this now is because I kind of
want to see where and why various things should be happening.
All right.
So if we want to make these functions, now is just sort of some test
functions that we can do.
What I could do again is just make it so that it moves like towards
the closest player or something like this, just
The real simple just to see what happens and and, and we'll go from
there.
Right?
So here's our update, familiar call.
Here's our update monster call.
So we should still come compile.
Presumably, looks like I got a don't have DT anymore.
Whereas my TT.
There it is.
So I've got put that up at the top.
Here we go.
And now our things are getting updated, but they just don't have any
update logic of Interest, right?
And so, you know, let's give them some update logic of Interest.
Let's let's go ahead and say that we want to try and find that
familiar.
And this is the part.
We want to try and find a hero.
That's nearby.
This is the part that I was saying kind of wants to to have a spatial
partition for our high entities, instead of our low entities at this
point, because if this guy's in the Hyatt do set, then when we got to
go Loop over, we'd have to Loop over all of our high entities with
just seems like it's entering into a bad N squared kind of
And right.
And so this is the other place that I was saying.
We kind of want a spatial partition for our Heidi's as well, but we'll
see.
We'll see for now.
So we're going to do go ahead and do the N squared route.
We're going to say, let's Loop over all the high entities in the game
State looking for somebody who is a hero, right?
So what we're going to do is say, all right.
I've got some test entity here.
However, these star test entity or I guess I should say test.
Hi, Andy, what's the?
We should have a way and I don't know if we actually do, right?
Get high entity.
We kind of need the opposite thing here, which is the thing that
chases.
Yeah.
So like this this function is lousy, right?
Because that what that
He does is that brings a guy into the high entity set?
So it's really a force, low-to-high kind of a thing.
That makes sense.
This is really the wrong name.
This is really get high empty as really Force entity into high or
something like that.
Right?
That makes sense.
I don't know if that makes any sense, but you see what I'm saying?
Right?
It's like forcing a low entity into the hiset, which is not the same
thing.
Whereas here what we might want to do is it would be nice if
If we had an easy way of saying to like get both, right or and I guess
what I could do is I could say, all right.
Entity test entity equals, you know.
Entity entity from high index like this.
There we go.
That seems like a reasonable way to say it any from high index and
then I go ahead and say that, and that gets me back both because since
I know it's a high, I know I'll get back.
Both entities always because there's always the low as well.
Alright, so if I'm doing that then I can go ahead and test here I can
say if the test entity type right?
Is a hero type.
This.
If the tennis enemy low type is a hero type, then I know that I want
to follow it, I guess I want to take a look.
So maybe I'll look for whichever ones closest so I'll say you know,
closest he wrote D or something like this, and I'll have right closest
hero.
And so what I'll do is I'll say the closest hero distance is going to
be equal to some Maximum search radius that I don't want to look
outside of right.
And so maybe, you know, I am looking in a 10 meter radius or
Like this.
So if somebody goes if it's outside of 10 meters I don't look anymore
something like that, right?
So that's the maximum radius, you know.
Ten meter maximum search or something like that.
So we go through here and we say I want to be able to compute the
distance between these two.
Of course that's very easy for us to do and I guess we will say is
close to 0 D.
Let's do it squared as well because that way we don't have to do
square roots in here which you know, are Superfluous to a test.
Because obviously which whatever value would be lowest squared is also
the same as being the lowest value if it was square rooted so we don't
actually care either way.
We just want the
Just one, we don't need to know what the actual length is.
So that will allow us to do a length squared.
Remember if you remember from our vectors.
We've got our length squared here.
I can always compute the length, square root of the distance between
any two entities.
I can just take the two entities positions and
Track them, right?
So I can basically say the test entity, p- my entity P.
That's the distance between us, right?
And so, if I take a look at the distance between us, that will give me
the, the test, the test, D'squared the test distance squared, and now,
I can say if the closest distance squared is actually greater than
that, meaning that whatever I've found so far is further away than
this.
This becomes the new best one, right?
And so closest hero becomes the test entity.
So that just grabs, whatever that closest one is of that particular
type.
And then, if I had one, right, if closest hero, you know, entity
indexes are actually is something there.
I could just say, if the high, if it's got a high pointer, then what I
want to do is I just want to move towards it, right.
I just want to move towards it.
So it seems logical to me and I guess I don't actually know but it
seems logical to me that what we should probably do is at that point.
We could just recycle I guess I should implement this function as
well.
Just recycle our function for moving the player to move the familiar
because it should probably move with the exact same rules.
I would think right seems pretty straightforward.
Relatively uncontroversial.
So, what I need to do here though is I need to be able to do this
entity high-index thing.
So let's get a result here.
So, and I've got my hi Milo and my index.
So this is the what do we actually call this to be caught low index.
I forget it is called low index, low index.
All right.
And so what we need to do here is, I need to get the high end of the
first, because that's actually what we have, the index Force.
This is high entity's, and that's going to be plus the high entity
index.
I should probably also assert that the high into the index is actually
in the range of the high of these groups.
Hi, just ease it down.
So that we know that we're not out of there and I guess I could also
assert that high empty index or you know, what?
I could even just check I guess I should say if someone asks for the
zero, they should just get back to zero.
So if they you know, they don't have to double-check.
All right, so the lowest
Next is that I'm going to be whatever the high says.
The low index was, right and the low is going to be just the same
exact look up, the low entities, plus the low empty Index.
Right?
And so that gets back the full Suite, just the way we wanted to
before.
So, and again, it's a little wonky.
I don't love how much of this extra addressing that there have to be
doing.
I don't know that it's actually too expensive.
It's unfortunate that we have to do it.
And so, it might be interesting to start thinking about other things
we could do there.
If it turns out to be a problem for us.
Right, again, we'll have to see.
Okay, five minute warning, we are being warned.
That's okay.
Five-minute warning, seems totally fair.
Like I said, this is relatively complicated stuff that we're going to
start doing here.
So now that we have a move player call.
I think what we probably want to do is change this into a move entity
call, right?
Because there's nothing particularly player e.r.
Bout.
It, the only thing that was player.
I was the thing where it moves it, if it hits the stairs, but I guess
that would probably be something that actually happens for everyone.
I would guess not sure.
But so I feel like this is probably something that we could use for
everybody.
I don't see any real reason why we can't.
So I feel like we could just go ahead and make this a new vanity call
and so we can go ahead and move the entity in exactly this way.
So, all right, so we can pass the game State.
We can pass the entity and we can pass whatever we want.
Our dd p to B, right?
And that's something that we'll have to compute, but that's basically
what we'll do.
And then we also have to go ahead and change the old call to be move
entity.
Okay?
so,
Let's see, that's game State and the DDP here.
What I want to do is I want to move him in the direction of the hero.
So what that would be is the closest hero, right?
I'd want to take wherever the closest hero was and subtract my
position, which gets me a vector that basically points at the hero.
And then I just want to normalize that and factor in some kind of
speed, right?
So what I want to do is I want to change this to be a
You know, a vector of length 1, which we talked about how to do that
already.
We just have to divide by its length, and I guess I already have the
length.
We have the closest hero D Squared here.
Right?
So what I need to do is I need to square root that right?
In order to get the, the actual length back.
And then I would just go ahead and and invert it, right.
So there's my 1 over X.
This is 1 over length.
Like so,
And I'll just multiply that right here.
And so that gets me my DDP right at unit length.
So what I actually need in addition to the unit length is, I need the
speed here, right?
So I need some notion of the m/s.
Traveled by biscaia m/s2.
I guess, whatever is whatever his acceleration is, right.
I guess I could say acceleration that.
I need a notion of that.
I don't know what his acceleration should be.
B, I don't know accelerations very easily but yeah, but hey look at
that.
He follows me around.
Let's make him a little slower.
He's
Zippy right.
Now.
Let's kind of tone that down a little bit.
Let's make him sluggish.
Seems a little bit better.
I don't know.
He still that seems what's my acceleration.
I feel like we maybe have a bug here.
Is that right?
What did I do?
Did I do something wrong?
There's the length.
I want it to be.
Here is the length.
It was so we're basically multiplying by that ratio.
Here's the DDP doing one over length times.
The distance between them closest to your oh hi p.
Ttip, what did I do?
What did I do?
Shouldn't he be much?
Shouldn't he be much more sluggish?
Much more sluggish than that, maybe not.
So let's find out what the acceleration of the hero is, first of all,
just to know what I think.
So DDP is 10.
Duh, duh.
She's he has exactly the speed of the hero because this player speed
was baked into this function.
So that's, that's why yeah, that's that's the problem people.
That's the problem right there.
So, yeah.
So basically what I need to do is remove that.
So let's go ahead and say to do, you know, pull speed out of move
entity.
And we'll just say he moves half the speed of the hero because now
basically everything's in terms of hero speed, which is not useful.
So now he should get far away from the player and then eventually
catch up like so and and so that's fine and everyone's fine with that.
But what should also happen is, if I move their egos, if I move far
enough away, he should stop right?
And there he does.
So the other thing that we need to do is he should always be moved, so
that his equations of motion still handle, so it doesn't stop right
away like that.
I don't know why I was close the app.
So what we want to do too is we want to have this.
This DDP just be nothing at first.
And then it can, if there wasn't someone to follow at least two, then
he'll still Glide.
So, you know, he'll Glide to a stop right instead of instead of
stopping abruptly.
Right?
So, when I get out of range, he just kind of take should taper off a
little bit, and instead of stopping totally abruptly.
I think that's working.
Can't quite tell.
I probably should have some slower equations of motion to see if he
does or he doesn't.
And so, this was also the pathfinding problem.
You can see I can
Him trapped here, right?
And now he can't get to me.
And so that was kind of thing.
I was saying, is like, we're probably gonna want start adding some
more advanced features so that, so that the, the monsters and the, the
familiars are smart enough to navigate obstacles on their own because
otherwise it's going to be pretty stupid.
I would think.
Alright.
So got some work to do is to do tomorrow, but for now, I think that's
totally fine for today's progress.
And so, let's go ahead and go to the Q&A since it's cute.
And a time, if you could, please prefix your questions with q:, that
would be extremely helpful.
Oh, right, the Z.
All right.
So that's another to do.
We have to do, it's going here and push piece.
Call to do Z on Alpha.
Yes, please prefix your questions with q: and if you could keep the
things we've done today stream or on previous streams.
If you want to talk about off-topic stuff, that's totally fine.
But do it on the pre stream.
So come about 15 minutes before we start and that's where we talk
about random topics like stuff that doesn't have anything.
Do it the code.
We actually wrote.
Yeah.
Let's take a look.
I see, no questions.
Every wonder One understood everything.
That is how I choose to interpret that.
Why monstar and not monster well, so I believe I actually did call him
monster, but I feel like monstar is a little more is like better.
Like, you know, like I feel like monstar would be a better name for
this guy.
So I would be because it sounds more.
You know, it's like a monstar monstar, right, right.
Like that.
Like it's very you can even see the
Already, I think you can see that.
It's way more sort of menacing look at it there.
Look at that, right?
It's pretty menacing.
If someone rewrites your code using a loop and it runs faster, what
would you do?
Well, what code you're talking about object-oriented versus non
object-oriented?
Has very little to do with like the speed.
It's more about like the facility of development, but
Like, I'm not sure what you're talking about.
I guess would be how I would phrase that.
Why do you want to be able to outrun?
Your familiar doesn't having to stop for him to catch up, get
annoying.
I just wanted to make sure that that was working.
I just wanted to see if there was a search radius thing that would
happen there because eventually that might be a problem.
We will play around with that a little bit, but this is not game
design, right?
We are not designing this game right here.
We are implementing features to see how they would work in the engine.
And so I wanted to have the concept that as he gets further away.
He can't find you.
And then when you get closer, he finds you.
Then and we might play around with that a little bit.
I also feel like we should test because I don't know.
You should be able to like pull I hate the fact that you get started
right on top of the guy.
I got to have a way that we separate people.
When you launch a new character, like it finds us some space for them
but was going to say is try to figure out how I could.
How could I do that?
I guess what I would do is if you do add player, I guess what I would
do is I would say when you add player, you are actually at the camera
P, plus some offset.
I don't know.
World position, I don't know.
I'm not going to deal with it now.
But point being, it would be nice to be able to add multiple Heroes,
and I have no overlap on top of each other.
Could you make the head bob up and down while following the player?
Yes, of course.
That would be pretty easy to do.
Basically what you would need is you just need some notion of what it
means to bob up and down, but basically you know, in your entity,
right?
You'd have something that was like a T-Bob or something like this.
There's a couple different ways you could do this, right?
But when you add the familiar in there, right with set, the entity,
well, I guess it is that a lot of math to get taken care of, when it
Maps into the hi.
So, what you would do is when you actually go to render it the bobbing
head.
I mean, when you update the head, you would then set the Z offset for
the head to, to be.
Which one is the head?
This is the head to be like a sine wave you know on that Bob which I
don't actually know if we implemented yet but it would have to be, you
know, something that was basically going to be be done in that space.
So you basically say all right I've got some function that Bob's up
and down like a sine wave.
You know, something that goes like this and I've got some concept of
the entities bobbing rate and if entity T-Bob is greater than
You know, the full circle.
So then we'll just go ahead and and reset it.
That, of course, I don't know if these get initialized when the when
the high actually does this.
Oops.
Hi.
I don't know if we actually have a sine function.
I guess we do.
So that's good.
So in theory we should now be able to make him bob up and down.
I think.
Now I don't know if this is in pixel space.
This should have been in leaders, but I think we actually left it in
pixel space, but they're e Now Bob's up and down.
And you probably wanted to bob up and down a little faster than that.
So, maybe you want something more like this.
Well, that might be a little bit too much, right?
Let's try that again.
Is that, is that what you're looking for, I guess.
But yeah, so really all you do there is you just take the Z coordinate
and you throw it into some periodic function, like a sine wave and
you've got a bobbing head, right, which is pretty, which is pretty
straightforward.
There's not a whole lot else to do and if I got far enough away so
that he wouldn't be following me.
He'd still just kind of sit there and bob up and down until you know,
you get closer and then he starts to chase you again.
Can't you write pong real fast?
So I can see how to start.
I could I suppose but I don't think I'm going to sorry I'm not super
interested in writing pong.
Monstar would be confused with monstar a pointer to a mon that's true.
But thankfully, we don't have any moms in the game.
Are we going to eventually use a component based entity system?
So I feel like there should be an auto ban on the phrase
component-based entity system, just because what does it even mean,
right?
Like, what does component-based entity system mean obviously entities
are made up of things and so the phrase component-based entity system,
could mean like such a wide variety of things.
I don't know.
I wish that no one had ever.
Vented that term because it's so nonspecific.
So, I guess what I would say to the question of, are we going to
eventually use a component based on a system instead of using an enum
of entity types?
If not why, that depends very much on how the game code shakes out,
right?
We will probably have some notion of composable entity pieces, but we
may still have the concept of entity types that are used for other
purposes.
Purposes, right?
And so how that exactly breaks down, it's entirely a issue of
compression, right?
So it's entirely about seeing where the, where the right trade-offs
are to be made and it has nothing to do with like, should you use
system X or system?
Why?
All systems are entity component based systems, basically.
Like, I don't even really understand why people make that distinction.
Normally it seems very arbitrary to me, I guess is what I'd say.
Would you think about doing some proportional?
Integral derivative control for familiar as to follow?
Yeah, if we wanted to make them kind of Glide to a stop nearer to
You.
And I mean, one thing too is that the familiar doesn't stop when he
reaches close to.
You be kind of bumps into you.
He lets the Collision system stopped him at some point.
Right?
Well, not the Collision system, I guess.
But yeah, no, he lets the Collision system.
I guess.
It stopped him because he collides with us, but we don't collide with
him right now.
It's kind of a little wonky.
But that's just how it's written, right?
And so yeah, a proportional derivative controller or something similar
where he Glides to a stop near.
Us would probably be better but that's not super relevant to us right
now because that's more of a feel thing.
That's not probably something that affects the way that engine is
architected.
I wouldn't suspect but maybe it would be so we'll have to see
I have a bad feeling about that switch on entity type.
Do you think it will probably go away as we get closer to the final
architecture?
Switches are very good.
I would highly recommend not having a bad feeling about them.
What I would say is that probably what will happen is, we'll become
something that's not switching strictly on any type.
It's switching on like entities will probably be made up of multiple
parts that get switched on, which is, hopefully satisfies.
The people who like the phrase component-based entity system because
then they will be able to concretely identify the fact that there are
components.
But the switch statement will almost certainly remain.
It just might not be on an entity type per se.
We Collision be an XY, only thing, or would you take into account Z as
in jumping over another entity?
I think we will, probably I think we will probably have to handle Z
specially because of the nature of 2D games.
You can't usually treat Z entirely like a separate coordinate because
oftentimes there are special concessions.
You have to make to make things work out because of the fact that it's
a weird, like orthographic perspective and Z is more conceptual than
actually physical.
So we will certainly take Z into account, but how exactly we take it
into account, is it might not just it's probably not just going to be
well, that's awesome.
I like with that was just happening there, but it probably will be
something that's like a little more.
Little more.
I don't want to say hacky because there's nothing you can really do
about it.
But it's going to be something that's a little more fit twiki.
Right?
It's like it's stuff that we just have to make that makes the game
work eat because we can't do it as if it's real 3D since we don't have
full geometry for everything, right?
I have a feeling, I have a feeling you're low.
In fees will be quite big if they have a, i and stuff, won't this be a
problem for the huge World.
Maybe it would have made sense.
If you had kept the tile data in chunk.
So you can
Some entities just when needed.
Well that is what we're doing.
Right?
The low-end of these will have to store all of the data that gets
remembered right and there's no way we can really get around that.
We have to store that data, but we only have to store that data.
So the low enemies can be as small as we want them to be as small as
we can get away with basically for the day of testing persist and high
entities store all the rest of it, right?
But there's really nothing we else we can do.
Do if this data we have to store, we have to store it, right?
Although I guess we could try to do compression on the fly.
But I doubt that the entities will ever.
Be big enough to require that you probably just still just use the
memory for it, right?
The performance boost off the low high Shuffle.
When will we start seeing this come into play?
It actually already is.
So, for example, we would have gone N squared if we only had one, any
type already on a huge number of entities to give you an example of
that for like here right here.
All of our familiars would have to Loop over all of the entities every
time, right?
But now they're only looping over the hyades which is much much
smaller, right?
So if you look here, right,
It would have been looping over this many.
And now, it's looping over, only this many already, and these will be
partitioned, probably further.
So it'll be even smaller.
So we already are getting a performance boost.
Could we spawn a ton of these floating head things?
I guess.
I mean, it seems like we could, I guess why not would be the, why
wouldn't we be able to?
I guess would be the question.
We still don't have a random number generator, unfortunately, so I
guess we'd have to just do something like this, but I don't know.
Now.
Yeah, familiar index, equals zero, familiar index less than 20 plus
plus familiar.
Index.
Is this what we're talking about?
Familiar offset X.
Like so.
Offset X.
So I guess if I do a mod 5, I actually need a mod 10 minus 5 because I
want some to be on the other side of you as well.
So, all right, so there we go.
And I guess that should spawn a bunch of these.
Theory.
Boo, that find a bug.
What happened here?
What did we do?
Somebody got unhappy when we did that?
Change into the location.
For entity low key.
So it started in.
Yeah that's a good point.
So there is one other thing we have to do here.
So this is a case where we could divide by zero, right?
Because we haven't really played around with this much at all the
closest distance to the hero could be zero.
If the code like it shouldn't ever happen because the familiar
shouldn't be able to get right on top of the hero.
But in this case, I spawned them right on top of him.
So we probably should go ahead and check just to make sure that, you
know, it's not.
Right.
Let's make sure that the closest
Distance is a little, it's something.
Right, and that should that should presume they fixed that if that
actually was what it was, although it seems like that was not what it
was are in same chunk.
A offset.
Is not canonical.
So move entity.
Yes, this is the same problem.
But you want to make sure I did actually do this.
Right, right.
And close this here.
Do you squared is greater than zero?
Yeah, we've got to GDP.
Okay.
So let's find out what the problem is here and also move entity.
when we're fine with the DDP,
Can the DDP ever be 0?
Here we ever do DDP length and do anything with that.
If it's greater than one, we do it now so we don't have any problems
there.
So let's take a look at why we're getting this problem.
First of all, let me make sure that I actually have it easy way to
reproduce the problem.
So I'm wondering let's find out.
Let me just find out.
And familiar index.
Why?
Me just find out if it is because I'm spawning him on top of the hero.
No, okay good.
So it's just something random.
So what actually is the problem that we are having with multiple
familiars.
I have no idea.
If I only had one of them.
Can I get it to reproduce?
Yes.
So all I need to do now, I guess it's checked that one time when it
does move familiar the first time through and that will cause my
problem.
So I suppose that's probably
Good.
A Telex + familiar offset.
Right.
That's the problem I suppose.
Oh, no, it wasn't problem.
Never mind.
Alright, so now I can go in and find out what's actually wrong.
I didn't really want to do this in the middle of the Q&A.
But I guess I will have to since I really don't want to leave a bug in
there if we've got one.
So in this means, presumably the first time we call update familiar,
it will have the bug, I would assume.
So, let's go ahead and find out why.
So,
Not actually moving DDP is set to 0 so we're not actually asking it to
update our familiar at all.
Let's take a look at where the familiar actually is.
The familiar is.
Well, that's where it is.
Let's take a look and see what if that's actually considered
canonical.
So our world should have what it's chunks.
Ida m is and so that's the chunk sided M.
So that actually is not canonical.
So it looks like it just got created.
It looks
like we just have a bug and I guess now that I think about it, we even
put it to do in there, right?
I guess we just have a bug in our, in our tile conversion.
The the function that was like the gets the, the, the chunk position
from top position.
This guy.
I think what we probably want to do is do is canonical here because I
suspect that's just that's what our bug is, right?
um, and
oops.
And so we're not actually producing valid coordinates when we do the
style mapping, if that makes sense.
And does that take an address of what does it take is canonical?
World, V2 offset.
Oh, so I guess I owe right.
I don't actually have to pass the whole thing.
That's sufficient for saying it's a canonical, right?
So hopefully, that'll fire right away.
Yes.
So it's basically the fact that this thing doesn't actually compute
canonical coordinates properly, which I had to do there about this and
we kind of think about it.
So let's think about it.
What we need to do is we need to align our tiles on chunk boundaries.
So if I say that, I've got an AB style X, and I subtract from it.
However, many tiles per chunk.
We actually went.
Yes.
So I think what we've got is a problem of of just how the alignment is
being computed here, right?
Again, sorry about this having to do this right in the middle of the
Q&A, but I don't really want to leave a bug in the code.
It makes me grumpy.
So we basically we've got something where we have tiles, right?
And then we want to introduce.
Juice this concept of a tile chunk.
And and then we want to be able to pass in to this system.
A tile index.
Such that we can then compute.
What?
It's chunk relative offset is right.
And so, I guess what I need to do is this is Computing it without this
would never produce negative values, right?
This is Computing it as if the chunks were centered here and then it's
going to compute what the tile.
Index actually was, but that's not what we need to do.
We need to do is I guess, do that same math, but then say okay after
we do that, we need to figure out where the center of that chunk was,
and then go back towards the tile.
So so thinking it through
If our tiles for chunk is 16, that means that we want to go half the
tiles in.
We want to basically subtract half of this right away.
So it wouldn't be ABS tile X, right?
It would be AB style, x- tiles per chunk over to, right?
We'd want to we'd want to basically center around the center of the
Tau chunk.
I think that's right.
Again, we should think this through a little bit better, but I'm just
Trying to fix this so we can continue on with the Q&A.
If that makes sense.
So, let me see if that if that solves our problem.
Yeah, so that was that was that problem?
Yeah.
Okay.
And so then it looks like I broke the familiar though with our
I check their update familiar, which I'm not really sure why.
This I feel like distance squared should often be higher than that,
but I guess it wasn't.
Is that is that too aggressive of a check?
Or am I missing something obvious?
Like, why is that neutering the direction there?
What did I miss?
Because, if I remember correctly are familiars, were working just
fine.
When we were doing this, oops, when we were doing this, doing it this
way, but
Then it wasn't working.
So I'm very confused.
I'm very confused right now.
I feel like I've missed something.
I've done one of those like typos that I do on the stream and I'm
like, what is going on?
And then it's like, oh, duh, you forgot to do, whatever it was.
So this should have a check in it.
But when I actually added this check, I found that there was that it
almost it never would actually execute.
So I want to find out why that's actually happening, because that
doesn't really make any sense to me, right?
Oh, axe.
Oh, dear.
Accidentally deleted.
I must have hit Ctrl K on that line somehow.
Wow, how did that happen?
Well, that would explain it.
Yikes, that's that's awful man.
The Perils of editing on stream.
All right, well
Easy fix.
There we go.
All right.
So now if we want to actually generate more of them, we should be able
to now that we fixed the problem with spawning them in a lot of
different places.
We should be able to add them in larger quantities.
I don't know how many you were thinking you actually wanted.
We could see.
So we still not quite right.
So our chunk Prison from tile.
Still isn't quite right.
So, let's see why it's not right.
Let's take a look at that.
Result negative 7 negative.
What did I do wrong here?
So tiles per chunk?
Is 16.
Yeah, we will be actually look that up at 16.
So let's see.
ABS tile X.
We're taking that and we're dividing with how strong can get 0.
So, if we subtracting tiles for chunk out of that, we would have, you
know, three minus eight, right, which would be negative 5.
Why does that not seem reasonable?
Right - the chunk X tiles for chunk.
X World tile side in meters.
So what does that why tiles per chunk?
That seems totally fair.
Does it?
Not what is the, what is the issue there?
So let's actually walk through this math.
So I have my abs tile X is 3.
So, what does my result chunk x is 0.
So that should have that feels like.
That should be canonical to me.
So, what did it end up being?
So?
Tell side in meters, which is what?
Tile side and M is 1.9 chunk side, and M should be too tight.
So 16 times that.
Right.
So basically, we should have this.
Time 16.
Oops.
Times 16, which is what it is.
And so, if I come up with negative 5 negative 5 times the tile sided
M, should in no way have given me.
Okay.
So, that's what that gave me.
And so, then the, why is the only one that I guess.
That's wrong.
AB style.
Why?
Is the one that yet that appear.
As long as the ABS tile Y is negative 1.
and so, that's
That's causing a problem.
Because why, exactly?
So, our chunk, why.
Is still 0 which is fine.
Our ABS tile y minus 8 is going to be negative 9.
Oh, okay.
Right?
Because this is a floor since I did it.
I see what's happening.
So since this is essentially doing, this is doing the calculation to
find out where you would have been if it's negative.
We actually can't.
It.
We are trying to find the floor of that.
We're trying to find we would it should have been in the next chunk
over in that case.
So this is not really correct.
Unfortunately, right.
Yeah, this is not really correct.
Because if the number is negative than right.
I don't know if this this makes sense.
So what's going on here?
This is not really something I want to do in the Q and A.
This is unfortunate.
But what you gonna do, things come up when they come up.
So we have our chunks here.
Right, and there's actually I guess this is.
There's a lot more of these gridlines I'm drawing, but it would still
work no matter how many we had.
So what we're doing is we're representing the chunks by saying, we've
got the center and then we've got an offset to wherever the entity is,
right.
And then we've got this situation where if we wanted to find out where
something was, right?
Let's say that the something is here.
We need to First find out which chunk it's in and then we need
Find out what it's offset is.
Well when the offset is this side of the corner, the math.
I wrote work just fine.
Right, but when it's on this side of the corner, it's going to
truncate towards here.
So it's going to pick this chunk.
When it does the Divide to see which one it's in.
It's going to pick this truck chunk instead of what should have done,
which is picked the other chunk.
Right?
And so what I want to do is I want to have something that's going to
correctly, bucket this into the chunk.
That's
Behind it, right?
And so that it works on either side of the 0.
So that's kind of annoying, right?
But that's that's where we're at.
That is why that is not working.
And so I'm not sure what the, fastest way to fix that is, I guess the
fastest way to fix it.
Mmm-hmm.
What is the fastest way to fix it?
I guess, the fastest way to fix it is probably to say.
Well, let's just do it in full load.
I guess.
Well, then, I don't know if that introduces a Precision problem.
Mmm-hmm.
Because it's a little.
Yeah, it's a little tricky.
I'm not sure how to how I'm not sure how to do.
Quickly, this is something that I'm not particularly good at these
kinds of discrete math, you kinds of things either.
So this is exactly the kind of thing that if you need it done in 50
seconds, which is what we would like to have happen here.
I'm exactly the wrong guy for that.
So unfortunately, I don't know that I'm going to come up with the
correct solution is probably something, actually relatively simple, if
you just look at it the right way, but of course, I'm not actually
sure what that would be.
So let me think about this for one more second.
See if I come up with something.
NG relatively useful, so if I was to do it, if I was to leave it the
way that it was being done before, right?
Then I know that that does.
At least give me what the offset is now, right?
So what I could do is I could look to see I suppose I could look to
see if it's negative and then if it is just bump it up by one, right?
That actually would be really easy to do.
It seems pretty cheesy, and I don't really know if that works
correctly.
But right?
Like if I did, if I did ABS tile X,
yeah, I mean if I did ABS Thai Lex,
Less than zero results.
Chunk X plus plus like in theory that works.
I guess.
I don't know that seems really janky.
So this is definitely not good.
But yeah, you do.
Think this through on the real stream and actually work out the math.
So I don't know if that'll actually work here, that may be awful as
well.
But we'll see what happens.
All right.
So which familiar are we adding here?
We adding the same one.
AB style.
X is 3.
Ab star Y is negative 10.
So, okay.
So, oh, I went the wrong way.
Duh.
It's - it's the previous chunk.
Not the next jump.
In that case.
So there we go.
Alright.
So that's adding the same.
I must have had a typo in there.
I feel like familiar offsets.
Yes, I did.
There we go.
So now we've got our more familiar is that was way too much work to
add a bunch of familiars.
Bunch of them are stranded outside the map as well.
I guess I can't put them that far.
So the Y offset has to be less but the X offset could be more I guess.
So then we've got kind of a spread so there are some familiars.
I don't know that this is necessarily such a good idea.
But there they are.
There's a lot of them and they kind of all will collapse like Daleks
into a point, right?
Because they're all chasing the same guy.
So I feel like
That's maybe a little less interesting than it could be.
I suppose, what I could do is force them to actually Collide, right?
So I could change the entity to collide when we, when we add the
familiars right now.
We're saying that they don't collide with each other.
What I could do is say that they actually do and that might make that
a little more interesting.
So that when you run it, you know, they can't quite Bunch up because
they all hit each other if that makes sense.
So, they'll be less Bunchy.
And there they go.
And of course, that makes a crowd that I can't get through.
Like I can't push a familiar yet.
So that's a problem.
But yeah, we'll see.
How old is he work?
Exactly?
I don't know.
That's are saying.
We'll have to see what the game wants from Z.
I think, really mostly what I want to do is just, you know, allow you
to kind of float over things if you're flying or those sorts of stuff.
But yeah, I mean like you brought up with something like looking
through a hole in the ground to the low lower Z level work, that might
be interesting, so it might be something to try.
I'm not sure we'll have to see what we want to do.
Z and 2D games is always kind of janky.
So, we just kind of have to play it by ear and say, what do we want
out of our Z and then go write the code to handle it.
That's, that's one of the nice things about doing everything.
If you were actually doing a full 3D game is, you know, a lot of
things, get more complicated, but one thing it's less complicated,
which is you don't have to fake this sort of stuff, right?
Will there be a flock system for all the floating heads following the
hero?
Probably?
Not at the moment, maybe down the line.
What kind of path finding will be implanted for hyades?
And how will they differ from far away?
Low entities, and we'll low-energy NPC's that are always on the Move
really far away, always resolve.
It would be interesting to come across a very live world, full of
History.
Dead bodies, Etc.
Due to constant a updating, but would that be feasible?
I don't know, but we could try it.
Basically.
What we have to do for pathfinding for the low, entities is something
that's very structural and
We'll have to see how we can if we can treat our world in a convenient
way that allows that to be possible.
For Hire, these we can do fairly good pathfinding, but for low in
these yet, it's going to be interesting.
How easy would it be to chain?
Multiple Bob, Lee heads to follow each other.
Well, really easy, right?
Because since they're just looking for something to follow, you could
just have them use any hero or any familiar, right?
So if you, if you go look at update familiar, you could have it.
Be basically, like, if High into the index is not equal to my entity
High Index, right?
So it's not me.
First of all, and it's it's test entity type is either a hero or it's
a familiar then, you know, it'll follow it.
You know, it work, I think right?
So, you know, they all kind of followed each other there and and part
of the problem is now they're all kind of just locked up and I can
never be closer than that, you know, they are already as close as they
were going to be.
So what I'd have to do is introduce something that says like, oh, you
know, if it was a hero then you know, it gets preferential treatment
or something like this, you know, I don't really know.
No, I could say something like Heroes.
Get a bias on them.
So for example, something like, if test entity low, type equals entity
type hero like that, in that case, we biased the test distance squared
to be like, you know, half of what it was or some just something.
I'm just totally making this up.
I don't know why.
Close the app, but so that the hero can always pull one away, right?
The problem is he wouldn't be able to pull two of them away.
So, yeah, it's just, it's just not that useful.
Like I we'd probably need to make some logic that tried to well, you
know what I mean?
We could we could do something even more ridiculous, which is that,
like, you inherit a follow number or something, right?
Like you could say something like, you know, the high
Entity has something that's like how you know hero distance or
something that's set on it and heroes always have that hero distance
set to zero or something like this but a familiar will have it set to
whatever it's following plus 1 or something like this.
You know, I'm not going to try to invent.
I'm not going to try to do that right now though.
So, yeah, so that's we'd have to do something like that for now.
I think I'll stick with just having it.
Follow the hero.
And I think maybe we probably shouldn't have quite as many as we have.
So I'm going to go ahead and just keep that to 14 now because this
seems like a saner that was what I was trying to do.
And I think we maybe had a little too much going on there.
We're not ready for that yet.
Camera, 2 y, plus offset y, not offset X in add familiar call.
Or is there a typo in there?
Add familiar familiar?
Oh, you mean down here?
Oh, that's the one I already corrected.
Yeah, okay.
So, let's see.
That's very glad to hear that you deem classes to be basically
garbage.
I spent too much time in c-sharp trying to learn object enter.
Jugglery between them.
Oh, well, yes they are but that's yes, not really question.
But but yes about the Chancellor's could each of our check if the hero
has a familiar already and if it does then try to follow the familiar
instead guess but it needs to propagate out.
So it just needs to increment like a counter and always take the
highest.
Counter level.
If that makes sense, we could do it.
I just didn't work.
We're already out of time.
So I just want it's we base this, make an integer and we increment it.
For each guy.
We could do it on the next dream.
It wouldn't be too bad.
All right, I think we've come to the end of the questions.
Thankfully took up a bunch of time there.
All right, so we're a little late today, but that's okay.
Better late than never, we had something come up in the middle of the
Q&A.
That was good, that we fix it.
Anyway, although we didn't really fix it.
We still have a to do there.
We got actually think this through because that's pretty lame.
Presumably.
Thanks.
This is not really a function we do at other than at startup time, but
still I just like to figure out how we should actually think about
tiles and all that other stuff.
So anyway, ignoring all of that, go ahead and close that down and wrap
things up.
Okay, so
no clothes clothes.
There we go.
Thank you everyone for joining me for another edition of handmade
hero.
It has been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to continue our little entity trip here
of making entities and making them do interesting things, which we're
going to have to do.
Like I said, take several days to kind of just make crazy stuff
happened with them.
You will want to come back tomorrow at 9 a.m.
Pacific Standard time when I will be right here, doing some more of
exactly
That hope to see you here.
I realized this morning.
You'll be some breakfast coating.
So maybe you can't make it but maybe some folks from Europe, can it's
a different time sometimes a little bit better for them.
So anyway, I hope to see you here.
But if not have a fabulous Friday.
Anyway, if you would like to follow along with the source code, you
can always pre-order the game and it comes with the source code, which
you can download and play around with yourself.
You can do that here on handmade hero dot-org.
If you want to support the video series, you could subscribe to our
patreon, which we have with this little handy link.
Here.
If you want to follow the brand new totally amazing.
No one can believe how unbelievably awesome it is.
Hand made her a tweet bot, which tells you what the schedule is every
day.
And what the whole schedule for the week is at the beginning of the
week.
Ladies and gentleman, I wrote this by hand.
Okay, I wrote it.
But now I didn't really I use like lip curl or something.
I think so.
I didn't really write it by hand, but but I wrote it.
Using web Technologies, which is one of those things that I don't
really do very often.
So it was a little nerve-racking but it worked.
So, anyway, if you want to follow that, you can do.
Here, and that's an easy way to get schedule.
Finally.
If you would like to check out older episodes or learn how to Port the
serious to Mac or Linux or ask questions on our forums news and forums
is the place to do it.
Please check that out.
It's got a lot of good resources in it, and you can post on the
forums.
There are two to ask questions if you've got questions outside the
stream, so thank you everyone and I hope to see you tomorrow morning.
If not have a fabulous weekend.