There we go.
Alright.
Hello everyone.
And welcome to day 24 of handmade hero, the show where we create a
complete game from scratch using no libraries and no engine, just our
own, our own cunning and wit it is basically, it is a team effort here
at handmade hero dot-org.
It is, it is me, plus the twitch chat and so far.
We've I think done a really good job.
We've made some pretty cool stuff.
We have a win32 prototyping layer that we built it.
Pretty awesome things already such as Live code editing and the
ability to set like Loops in the game that you can live code it and
watch the changes as you go.
We did that earlier this week.
It was pretty awesome.
So I am excited for where we're at.
We are at the point now in the process where we are going to wrap up
the win32 platform layer.
So that basically will just be doing light modifications to it for the
next few months.
Where, you know, if we need something, will go in and deal with it,
but for the most part, we want to move on to working on.
The game.
So we want to kind of wrap up the winter to platform layer for now,
and not have to really think about it anymore.
So what I'm going to be doing today.
Is I am going to try to sort of go through the win32 platform layer
and clean up some stuff that we kind of have left that we haven't
finished or that we haven't really like kind of massaged into the into
the right format or whatever, that sort of thing.
Just kind of go through like spend some time dealing with your dues,
that sort of stuff in preparation for tomorrow, when we'll kind of
button everything up and do a little recap, just so everyone can kind
of get a second.
Look at all the stuff that we've
Done and how it's architected and how it works.
Just for kind of to cement in the sort of the the overall design of
everything and how it kind of came together.
Now that it's done.
So if you have pre-ordered, the game on handmade hero dot-org, using
the handy dandy pre-order button, then you should have gotten an email
and the email has a link that allows you to download a zip file
inside, which is another set of zip files.
For every day of handmade hero.
We are on day, 24, which means if you want to follow,
Follow along with your source code, you unzip day 23, which is
yesterday.
And that is the state of the source code that I am starting with right
now.
So I will go ahead and open that up and then we will start to get to
all the stuff that we kind of need to clean up.
So I have in my notebook here, some things that I've written down,
which are basically, like little bugs or things that probably could
have been better, that we just didn't want to stop and do at the time,
but that
Keep out of the afterwards, or somebody wrote in or post on the Forum
said, hey, you should take a look at this or you forgot to do this.
I just tried to buffer those up, and we can kind of go through them
all at once.
So, first things first, basically, we still have an audio bug.
It's not really I guess it's a bug, is the wrong word.
For it.
We did some work to make our audio better and then we didn't actually
use it.
So I'll show you what I mean by that in a second here.
I'll just going to turn the audio back on.
We turned it off yesterday.
So it wouldn't be so annoying.
But basically, if I run this here, you can kind of see that we have a
when we're when we're looking at the the audio here.
We had kind of a display that was showing us some stuff and I don't
know if I can pause this in an easier way.
Can I
I do.
There we go.
That's the easiest way to pause right now.
Oh, I made a piki.
That's right.
We made a pause key.
So basically what we did is we drew some bars here and the Bars were
sort of telling us some various things about where we were outputting
audio and all sorts of other stuff like that.
But basically the weird thing about it was that we were expecting our
prediction algorithm to give us something where this yellow bar would
always fall in between this white and this pink bar, right?
The White and the pink bar.
We're basically like the, we're basically showing us where the right
cursor and the play cursor and stuff was going to be during our page
flip.
And the yellow was where we were predicting it would be and we felt
like we should always have a prediction that was kind of in between
where it actually turned out to be.
And the next basically the pink bar.
Sorry.
This, this is the the play cursor.
This is the right cursor.
During the flip.
This pink bar was basically the error.
That we could expect to have in where the play cursor was.
So the play cursor would be somewhere in here and we wanted to make
sure that basically we were predicting that it would be somewhere in
between there.
But I believe.
Yeah, like right there, for example, various times.
It would not actually line up properly.
I guess it didn't.
It's kind of hard.
There we go.
It was kind of hard to make it happen.
But there you go.
There's an example where you can see it was outside of their and so we
were doing some work to try and get that Tighter and basically what
had happened.
As we had uh, we had talked with kind of gone through on that day, a
whole bunch of stuff that we thought we should do in order to try to
sort of get our sound as synchronous as possible and to make it so
that would work with low latency sound cards.
This is not a low latency sound card.
But if we had one, or if we later Implement, some lower latency
output, something that's not dirt.
Direct sound for example, and we could get better sound latency.
We wanted our system to kind of be structured properly to make that
work.
And so what we did is
We computed a thing that was called expected B until flip, which was
basically the amount of bytes in the sound buffer that we expected to
be consumed by the audio card in between when we were doing the
computation.
And when we like right here in the code, basically, and when we
actually expect the video to flip to the next frame, because that's
when we want our next frame of sound to start as well.
We want those two things to coincide.
So we
She did the work previously.
We were using expected sound bytes per frame and we were using it to
basically compute where in the sound buffer.
We thought the video flip would happen and we were using that and then
we can computed this better value.
That was not using these type of sound bites for frame.
It was basically subtracting out the part of the frame that had
already been computed, the amount of time that it already elapsed up
to the point of the computation, but then, we never actually use this
value.
We never replaced this with that.
So that's actually what we
Affected it.
What we were trying to do and we never actually did that.
And so I just want to go in and make fix that bug.
We did we did the work of doing the computation, but then we never
actually tried using it and so I just want to go through and actually
see if we could try using it and to see if that makes it any more
likely to be accurate, but it looks like it's a little behind now.
Actually is mostly the only difference.
So I don't know that that actually improved.
Our accuracy at all.
Now it's hard to tell because again, the information we're getting
back from direct sound is very inaccurate.
So we don't really know if maybe this is a more accurate thing.
I will say that it tends to be much closer to where the play cursor is
at least most of the time but I don't know.
I would necessarily say that's much of an improvement to me seems like
either we still have some bugs in there.
Are some things that we could do more efficiently or this is the
Best.
We're going to get on Direct sound because it's not particularly
accurate, one way or the other, so, I don't know.
So I don't know if I think that's actually better or not.
So, so, we'll see.
And I think in general, I would say we've probably spent enough time
trying to get the sound sync.
Well, we will probably come back and revisit this stuff when we want
to ship things.
But since our sound is playing fine for the purposes of developing the
game so far.
I think we can mostly call that fine for now, but I didn't want to get
rid of
So, we'd actually be using the values that we computed.
So, fortunately, that didn't seem to really help all that much.
That doesn't seem to be a very good Improvement.
But at least now, we're actually doing what we said.
We were going to do which is better than that not.
So people who look at the code in the future will not be like wait a
minute.
That is not what they said.
They were doing it all.
Alright.
So the next thing I want to take a look at is basically
So, there was supposedly, some, some stuff where we weren't checking
for succeeded properly like this sort of stuff here.
Supposedly.
There was some stuff that were, this wasn't quite right.
I'm not sure if that's actually true or not.
But let's see.
Well, I don't know.
Someone was saying, basically, that we were checking these
differently.
I think maybe they were just trying to say that we didn't need to do
this anymore.
Cuz we were doing these output debug strings, but I don't know this
looks this, this actually looks roughly correct to me.
I don't know.
I feel like this looks roughly like what it should look like.
So I'm going to call that one.
Not actually something that we need to clean up again.
I'm just going to go through the things that people were mentioning
and that looks that looks pretty good to me.
Yeah, in fact, if anything we probably want to pull out these guys
eventually so when we print out our Diagnostics will probably want to
save what the error code is in these so that we can print them out
since we don't have a logging system yet.
There's not much we can do about that.
But that does seem like something we probably would want to do
eventually.
So, yeah, I'm going to, I'm going to call that something we're not
going to.
We are not going to address at the moment, so good.
That's another one down.
Let's take a look here, get rid of that.
And then similarly on that front.
Someone was saying that we really didn't need to do these.
Not equal to s or equal to S anymore.
She's me.
So, let's see.
What are we actually doing with was down Elke.
Was down.
It does.
Yeah, I would agree.
So I would agree that we don't need to turn these into actual Bulls
anymore.
So that's, that's true.
We could probably simplify this by just saying.
Okay, this this evaluates to a to a non-zero value, if it is, correct,
and so we could just do that.
There isn't there?
Isn't anything happening there.
Well, no, you know what?
That's
Not true.
So, you know why that has to be there is because we're doing a
comparison between was down, in, is down.
And so, basically, because these two values are going to be separate
types of bit Fields, you know, if you think about it, if was down is
going to be true.
If we didn't do this comparison with zero, which forces see to produce
a unique zero or one value.
We would either have the 30th beset or you have no bit set.
So the true.
You would be the 30th.
B would be set is down on the other hand if it were set to true or
false, that's going to be whether or not the 31st bit with set.
And so, we can't really compare the two of those.
That's that's not going to work.
So we needed to do this, to turn them, to turn those two into real
values.
So that's not that's not an unnecessary check, that's actually
necessary and I can I can mark that up here.
I can basically, say note since we are comparing was down to is down.
We must convert, we must use equals equals and not equals to convert
these bit tests to actual 0 or 1 values.
Now, there's other things we could do.
We could, we could rewrite these Expressions to be simpler.
We could, for example, shift this down by 30 and then and it with one.
And then they would line up in the same place.
But I don't know.
I mean, that's totally optimization types of stuff that doesn't need
to happen.
So I think I would rather just leave it the way that it was written
and not spend time.
Do you know, kind of rattling on things like that?
We will care about those sorts of things when they're in Loops that
cost us a lot of time and we just don't care about them in other, in
other cases.
So, okay.
Let's take a look at what else?
We've got here.
We have a definite bug.
I think.
Well, I mean, I don't even know if we want to call it a bug, but it's
definitely.
Worse than it should be.
But that way, if you remember when we were doing our controller stuff
here, we had a thing where the game, the game input was wanted a flag
that kind of said, whether a controller was analog or not.
And that's pretty easy for controllers that are always one of the
other because you just set that set it and it's fine.
But for gamepads, there's a sort of a complex issue, which is that the
GamePad maybe being used as an analog controller or it may be being
used as a digital.
Controller.
Because if you start using the d-pad, right, if you start using the
d-pad, then you have this problem, where you want to switch it from
being considered an analog input to, it being considered a digital and
then if you go back to using the stick, you want to convert it back to
say, use it as an analog.
so,
what we want to do is we want to try and make a determination at any
given time.
That's the most accurate we can to say whether or not the GamePad is
currently being treated by the player as an analog or a digital thing.
So that the game knows which one they're using.
And so what we did in to do in here is we set the is analog to equal
to true or false based on whether the user was using the d-pad or the
stick at any given time, but if they were
Using neither, then it would always just default to whatever happens
to be set in the controller structure before now, since we have two
controllers structures and we ping-pong back and forth between them.
That means that it would actually be the value that was set the frame
before the previous frame.
What we would rather do is say that the new controller every time.
We're about to make a new determination new controller.
Let's set it to whatever old controller was.
Right, whatever.
The very previous frame was instead of skipping a frame.
Let's use whatever it was on the last frame so that the user doesn't
do anything.
Instead of defaulting to whatever the previous previous frame is, Will
default to what the previous frame is.
I don't know if that makes very good sense.
But you know, I could this could be our excuse to try out.
I don't know how you pronounce.
This could eat.
The maybe I don't know, krita.
I'm not sure how you pronounce it.
I'm not sure what nationality is Creator.
So I'm not sure how to pronounce it.
But if we were to try opening up creating here to see if it if it's
Our drawing problem, which I don't know.
If it does.
We will, we will see what happens.
Make it large, make it larger.
Is it working?
Well, I can't see the cursor so I can't say that.
That's particularly useful.
The cursor is hidden.
It would appear.
I'm not sure why I will have to maybe work on those settings a little
bit.
But otherwise, the drawing is quite nice.
So that's this is much closer to something, we can work with.
So, let's see here.
How do I make?
How do I pick a brush?
Is that a brush?
What is this?
What is that?
That's the text tool?
I don't want to text tool.
Is that a brush?
Oh dear.
I don't know what that is.
Something around here should be a brush.
I would think but I'm not sure what.
Okay, someone tell me how to use this program.
I guess I can just click on one of these.
No, maybe not, no, no tools edit.
Well.
I can maybe practice using this.
It certainly seems like it's pretty useful.
So and it if I can just make the gradient paint paint with brushes.
Well, I would like to paint with brushes.
I thought I clicked on that though and it didn't seem to work.
Can't paint on a vector layer.
Oh man.
Now I've really done it.
Let's get rid of all these guys.
Yeah.
So for some reason I can't seem to see my cursor.
So we almost we kind of snatching defeat from the jaws of Victory
here, like right?
We almost had something that would have worked on stream.
So we'll have to play with that a little bit more and see if we can
get that to do what we want because it's pretty close.
So I'll play around with that.
Maybe I don't want to waste too much time on the stream on it.
So I'm going to skip it for now, but that's pretty cool.
We might be able to use that in the drawings.
A lot better than mspaint.
That's for sure.
Anyway.
So basically what we have here is we have a thing where we've got
basically a 0 and a 1 version, in an array.
We've got two states for the controller.
Right?
So we have the controller in two different buffers basically for
holding the controller state, right?
And what we're doing is at any given time.
We have a pointer to the new one and a pointer to the old one, right?
During the frame.
We treat them this way.
Then, at the end of the frame, we swap which ones.
Which so, we basically say, okay, now it's no longer new and old.
Now.
It is old and new, right?
So we basically are just swapping the pointers.
We basically just do a little, a little swap right at the end of the
frame.
So the old one becomes the new one, and the new one, because the old
one, right?
So what that means is, if you look over time, right?
Well, what happens?
So if
We draw our famous Arrow of time.
I'm here.
Right?
This is time going forwards, and we look at our famous frame ticks
that we always draw in here, right?
Then if you actually look at where things are pointing in terms of old
and new, right, you sort of have something that goes like this, you
have old, if this is slot 0, if this is R 0 with 0 controller, and
this is not shouldn't say slot 0 code.
Or if this is our zero input State, and this is our one input State,
we have old and new here and then the next frame.
We swap it so that they're opposite and this flame, we swap it so that
they're opposite than this flame.
We swap it.
So they're opposite, right?
So we're constantly ping-pong you back and forth and that corresponds
right in here to this structure, right?
We've got, we've got to game inputs that were talking about two blocks
that represent the input State and inside each of those like inside.
Each of these inputs, right is a bunch of controllers.
We said there's five controllers or something like that.
Controller States inside an input, but we have to whole game and put
States and we have
We start by pointing to 0 is new and old is one and every frame at the
end of the frame.
When we get down to the very end after we've done everything.
We just swap them, right?
We do this little swap.
So the old becomes the new in the new becomes the old.
So all I was trying to say was well basically is analog Get Set.
Let's say in here, so we're here we set is analog.
So we start off let's say this is our is analog State.
It's zero and zero, right?
Then in this Frame, we find.
That they're using the analog stick.
So now we set a new, we set it to one.
But of course, old is still whatever it was before, so it's zero in
the next frame, right?
And the very next frame these carryover, right?
So one is here and 0 is here because they carry over.
We've swapped the pointers but we haven't swap the buffers.
We just swapped who's pointing to who.
So the old one is now set to is analog, which is which is correct the
in the previous frame which is what old means it was analog, but the
new one is not yet set to analog because it has whatever the value was
in the in the previous buffer on the previous frame.
So what we'd like to do at the start is just copy this in here so that
If if on the previous frame it was analog.
We're going to assume on the new frame.
It's also analog until we hear otherwise, right?
And so that's all I did with this with this line up here that I was
trying to base.
Correct.
That error is basically say, alright, whatever it was in the last
frame.
Let's assume that's what it is on this Frame and then if we hear
otherwise, we'll just go ahead and overwrite that but if we don't hear
otherwise, we'll use what as far as we're concerned is the most recent
information we have and so that seems like a clear Improvement.
Meant to me, someone wrote in on the forums that we admit that and
that's a good point.
All right.
So, let's see here.
Time for some more, almond milk.
All right.
So one thing I want to do.
Is that I think that for our prototyping purposes I had used stretch.
I'd use stretch deai bits here.
And what I think I want to do is because we're trying to learn how to
do rendering and stuff like that.
I don't think we want to scale our image at all.
I think for our purposes while we're doing prototyping.
I think we want to always see 121 pixels to pixels.
So what I think I want to do is say that we're always going to blit
the buffer width and the buffer height.
Ways no matter what the size of the window is.
So basically, like we're always doesn't matter how we draw this,
right?
We doesn't matter what you do.
We're always gonna just do however, big.
It should be for one-to-one, pixels.
We're just going to do that.
Right?
And we'll let the scale, the scale can go down if it wants to.
Oops.
I forgot.
We added that crazy feature.
It's just the weirdest feature will have to look at that today.
See if we can clean that up a bit.
Will let the it's scale.
If we need to like make it smaller, whatever we can leave the sizing
in there for now, but I'm just going to make it so that it's locked
and it won't ever do the scaling.
So that way we can see exactly 121 pixels.
What we're actually doing, right?
So that's what we're going to do there.
I'm hearing some audio clicking which I wonder if we introduced a bug
somewhere.
Its audio is always so annoying to try and get it all exactly correct.
Yeah, either you either you get little weird problems or you you or
you have high latency or it's just annoying.
Anyway, let's keep going here with the with the various things.
So I wanted to turn that off and so we did turn that off and I
probably will say let's just get rid of this for now.
Let's not play with stretch mode.
Not doing that stuff.
We'll save that for when we actually do our shipping stuff.
And so I'm just going to put a note in here and say for prototyping
purposes.
We're going to always blit 121 pixels, to make sure we don't introduce
artifacts with stretching.
While we are learning to code.
The renderer.
There we go.
Okay, so I think that's just a better idea.
Pretty much pretty much all around.
All right, so choose me.
Let's see what else we got here.
Oh, so some things in our build up at file.
So someone pointed out that we can do things a lot easier.
I like I said, I don't know batch file programming very well at all.
I know almost none of the things the commands you can use in Windows
batch files.
What they were saying is we could just put a random number in here.
They basically said that instead of doing all the date craziness,
since we don't actually care about that.
They were saying, we could just do percent random and percent random
just insert.
Is a?
Number which for our purposes is fine.
Because all we really wanted to know is all we really wanted to do is
make sure that we could generate ones that didn't conflict name wise.
And so that's totally fine and way easier and easier for people to
read and cleaner, and it's not confusing what's going on.
So I like that suggestion.
I think that's a better idea.
Another thing that I wanted to say was that when we, when we set the
compiler switch to make sure that we were using, that we were
statically linking with the c runtime Library.
Since we're currently only doing debug.
Builds at the moment.
That should probably be a d.
And what the D does is it says, use the debug version of the runtime
library.
And that way, we know that we have like extra checking and stuff,
which we may want.
Right?
And so I think that's just better.
It's a very simple thing, nothing particular interesting there.
But but something to something to do, just to make sure we're getting
all the checking that we can that make sense.
All right.
So, let's see what else we've got here.
So for our looping, we had a couple of things that we need to take
care of.
One of the things that we haven't done with our looping system.
Is we have not actually made it so that it writes those HMI files to a
reasonable location, right?
If you remember we had these HMI file things and we never really we
didn't really make them right to the build directory.
Like we want to we want we don't want to run into our data directory
because that's not a that's just not a good place for them because
those will get zipped up and we do
Our source distribution and stuff like that.
And that's just bad.
So we need them to be in some kind of temporary directory.
Basically, that's not gonna have that problem.
And so I think what I'll do here is maybe I'll just try to take a look
at how we were doing that before.
If you remember inside our wind main, we actually were to think we
were actually doing some stuff with that for the dll stuff.
Right?
We already did this sort of scan thing and we came up with a way of
saying, alright, let's build file names.
That are in the same directory as our executable.
So what I'd like to do.
Is make kind of pull that out and make that into something a little
more, a little easier to use in general.
Right?
So what I'd like to do is do something like all right, maybe we take
that win32 state structure that we have here that we started to use
right where we just put things and maybe we can put something in
there.
That's just going to be that stem.
So we could put something like like this information here that we had.
We could put that in here.
So the XE file name when we get that.
When we started up we can put that in there and we can also put in the
one past / B so we can put that in.
So this is basically like the one path / / in the exe file name last
XZ, file name.
/.
We could just store those.
And then anytime we want to,
We can generate a new one of these path.
Things, one of these, you know.
One of these past that's in the same directors are dll.
And so I'm just going to do that win32 state file name.
I'm gonna guess I'll call that count.
So, I'm going to go ahead and just say that we're going to Define
this.
This Max path thing out here because I'm not super comfortable with
that.
And we may want to revisit it later.
So I'm just going to basically say that everything has to be this
instead of Max path so that I kind of have a better handle on what's
going on with it.
And then,
I'm going to do is I'm just going to say let's pull out this code into
something that operates in the with the win32 state.
So I will say here, internal void process.
Let's say win32.
Get XZ, file name or something like this?
And that will take our win32 state structure.
And that doesn't actually need any parameters because it is it is able
to get the module file name, just straight from itself.
So basically what we'll do is we'll say that this is going to be off
of this now.
So we're going to say that the XE file name when we get it.
It's going to go straight into
When 32 State structure, we will then make our last one pass / /, that
will actually be off the state structure as well.
So now, these things are preserved, right?
And then when we do that, we can make a utility here that will just
generate these names for us and we'll be good.
So, for example, we can do something where we can say, let's grab this
in here.
So, there we go.
We can now do something where we'll say.
Went through to build XZ path, file name or something like this.
I don't know what we'll call it.
That seems reasonable enough.
I guess you pass in that state structure, and then you pass the file
name in and that will that will replace this thing here.
I think we also probably want to pass the site.
Well, we could, we could assume that that's always passing in an
actual null-terminated string.
So maybe we'll do that as
Well, so we'll take care of that.
And will basically say that all we really need is a dest count and a
dest and so that way we can just go ahead and get rid of all this.
So then we basically pass in that desk count and we pass in the desk
as well.
That's going to go in there.
We can now convert this to using our state structure, right?
So that's sexy, file name and that
at and this is actually file name as well.
And then this will simply be
The file name and the will say the string length of the file name and
we don't have a function for computing a string length yet, but it's
pretty easy for us to write one.
We know that basically if you remember all the way back from way way
back when, if you remember all the way back to the time when we were
in the intro to see course, we know that the way that these strings
are stored.
Is there just bytes in memory and then the last bite is a 0.
So
We know if we start from wherever the first the pointer to the string
is and we just look until we find a zero.
If we count, how many times we had to go.
How many bytes for we had to go.
That would be how long the string is.
It's just counting how many characters there are, we know each
character's 8, b, 1 B, since we know this isn't Unicode.
It's just an see if it's Unicode.
You got a little bit more to deal with because you can have multi by
characters, but ignoring that for now we can do a pretty simple thing,
but it's just the string length.
And in our case, we don't even we really just care about how many
characters are in it.
We don't even care what the number of logical characters is.
So even if this was Unicode, this is still probably what we'd want.
Anyway, so we basically have a string that comes in here and we have a
length that we're going to do.
So we're just going to get, get, get that length.
All we have to basically do is say, while, you know, while the string
star string is going to dereference the pointer to the string.
It's going to get whatever the character is.
We're looking for a null.
So basically we can do something.
That's really just that.
Right.
We can basically say that if the, if the character that's pointing to
Star string, right?
If star string is not zero, we increment count and keep going.
And if it is 0, we stop and don't increment.
And then we also have the plus plus here to basically say after you
check it increment the pointer to the string as you go, right?
So that's that's you know, what, let me, let me go.
Ahead and step through that too.
So you can actually see how it works.
We'll take a look at that in a second here and I can kind of explain
it a little bit in a little bit more detail.
All right.
So what do we have to do?
Here?
We need to fix that pointer.
There we go.
And again which places where that was true.
Then we have to come down here and right.
So now we basically have a utility function for doing this, that makes
sense.
So we should be able to basically make
This all of these guys should be able to work with that.
So now if we just have this place that we want it, we should be able
to pass that state structure.
We should be able to pass the destination, where we want the thing to
go, and then we just pass, whatever the file name, stem is like that,
and we can get rid of all of this extra code.
So that's kind of nice, right?
Get rid of some code.
They're always good to get rid of code, if you can, and this one will
be the handmade.
made temp Dot dll, and it
Going into this guy like that.
So, get rid of those and then we just need to actually call this guy
go and that should just about hoop and the why did that everything
turned green for a moment.
And that is just about it.
We now need to grab that win32 state structure and get it, so that
it's actually in a useful position.
I don't know when we want to actually
The the order of operations here.
I'm not sure when we want these various things to occur.
You know, we could think about how we want these to be lined up.
I don't know, you know, it feels like maybe, maybe we just want this
to happen right away.
I don't know, hard to say.
But anyway, 32 State and 32 state in 32 states.
And in theory, we now should be running.
Let's go ahead and step through that because I wanted to talk about
that a little bit more.
So this is again just doing the code exactly like it was before.
Or and doing that same scan that we already looked at.
So, that's basically, all it's doing is it's putting it in here.
Now, instead of before, you can see it, pulls out the stem just like
we wanted to.
So that all works exactly the same as you used to.
But now in here, we've got a new thing which is that string, length
thing.
Oh, and you know what?
There's I left that - one in there, but we don't need it anymore.
So I left that - one in there.
If you remember this used to be a size of, right?
And so it used to be taking an array and ask what the sides of it was.
Now the array will include that know.
Because you have to remember, there's always a little null in here.
This is zero.
Not the not the letter zero but the actual, and actual 0 B at the end
of it.
So when you ask for the size of a string, you will, if you do size of
a constant string in the code, you're going to end up getting one more
character than the actual number of characters in it.
Because that last character is that null?
And so we were subtracting one from those two to get rid of that.
But our thing here doesn't count that null Terminator.
Our string length doesn't count it.
So basically, we don't ever need that anymore.
We don't need to do that.
Make that subtraction, right?
So, let me jump right to this again, and go into that string length.
So let's take a look at the string length.
We initialize our count, 20, right?
So there, there it is, getting initialized to 0 and then we have the
oops.
Don't mean type in there.
While typing here.
Then we have our string and you can see that it's
I'm 10 11 12, characters long.
So we start and we look at that first character, which is an H.
It's not zero, so we increment count by one and we so you see we've
eaten the H.
And then we're just going to keep eating the characters eating the
characters, eating the characters, using the characters with Microsoft
Visual Studio is incredibly slow, watch window update, not able to
keep up with us.
You can see, we get to 12 like that.
And then we have now there's there's just a 0 B there.
You can see that like the bite is playing.
Actually just 0.
And so this will Now fail and we pop down and return that 12 count,
which is what we wanted.
So, let's see if the cat strings.
Worked probably should.
Yep.
Casting work just fine.
And so now we should be back to square one only.
Now, we have a convenient function for doing that so we can do it
anytime we want to.
So now that that's true.
We should be able to go ahead and move this guy up into just a sort of
General utility place here.
Let's take a look.
I don't know exactly where we want to put.
That probably just put it right right at the top here.
So there we go.
And then when we do our hiim nonsense down here, where was that?
That was like, .h I am or knows dot handmade input HMI, that's what it
was.
So what we want to do here is we want these
I has to be written out to something reasonable something in that
directory.
And so, what we want to do, I believe, is just do a, something, like,
win32, get input file location or something like that.
Seems reasonable and that'll just take a slot index.
Whatever that index thing is, right?
And the win32 state.
So, there's the winter to State structure, which again has the stuff
in it.
That we need, just information that we need to do our job.
So we're going to call.
All that, that to that not necessary.
So this is going to do that.
That build again will sort of go ahead and say that the the food odd
HDMI, I don't know.
That Foo is the best name.
So maybe we'll say like Loop edit or something like that.
I don't know, something like that seem reasonable.
I know what you guys think of loop edit dot h, of H of my.
So will basically say that that's, that's what that is.
I don't know if we want to actually do the slot index.
Yet because we don't actually support slot index.
So I'm just going to assert that slot index equals one.
For now later.
We'll actually dynamically build the file name and maybe stick the
slot and mix in there.
I don't know.
But we don't actually have even a way to test that yet.
So I'm going to avoid doing that for now.
And then we'll just pass that Destin this.
So there's our desk out, there's our desks.
That's all done.
And and that is pretty much all we need to do.
So now when we have the file name, this guy can be done this way.
It is
Is again not a great way to do this.
I'm just doing cuz we don't care about this code very much.
I don't want to think about strings or anything at this point.
So we're not doing anything clever.
We're doing just things very basic and very uninteresting.
There's better ways we could do some of the stuff we wanted to take a
day or two and talk about strings and do a nice string implementation.
Eventually we may get there but I don't anticipate us doing a whole
lot with strings in this app anyway, so I'm not even sure that that's
really all that productive anyway, so we're just going to go ahead and
do this.
Skal here win32 get input file location.
We will pass the recording index.
So, that in the future, when we do actually,
And make that maybe work.
If we decide to make it work for for more slots, we can.
And it's passing through properly.
We'll go ahead and take that out of there.
So that's going to be the file name now.
Compile that.
Oops.
What did I do wrong?
Oh, right.
It's true waiting for you to State.
I decided not to call it win32 state but there's some places where it
is still called that.
So let's just get rid of that because there's really no reason keep
saying that there aren't multiple.
All states in these things.
So it seems like it should just be called State.
I could call it win32 State everywhere suppose that the other option,
but it just seems like a necessary typing, so I don't know.
All right, so we did the file name and one of them looks like it
worked properly.
So let's go ahead and do the file name and the other one as well and
now they're both calling.
The other thing that I like about this is they're both calling
through.
There's that mean not ever having a consistent capitalization for.
Oh man, basically now, they're both going through the same function to
get the the name as well, which I like, because that way I know that
the names match up before there was a separate string in each of them
and that's not so good.
Right?
So this way, they're both calling the same function to get the names
of recording files.
So hopefully they'll line up.
So basically that's that's really all that is to it.
Let me test.
I did a bunch of changes there.
Let me test to make sure
that we actually,
See here that we actually have.
There's definitely some audio clicking.
So I think I definitely broke something.
We'll have to see about that.
See.
Yeah.
All right, so that looks like it's all good.
Although I don't know if we have
What's going on here?
GE.
I can't get, I need to get to my code, but I can't.
Damn you.
This is the problem with the top-level window stuff.
What was the actual as though?
The assertion was here, a certain new state ended down not equal to is
down, huh?
That I would not have been expecting basically that says that there
was a time when the keyboard input state was not, well, I could
actually see that being true once in a while, when because we don't
actually handle things, like switching apps, switching the app and
then.
Yeah.
All right, I could actually see that being true once in a while.
That's something we have to talk about when we get to the more
industrial strength input handling.
So I'm not going to.
I don't think we needed to worry about that quite just yet.
But yeah.
All right.
So what what was I about to do there?
I was checking the oh, the filename thing worked properly.
I'm going to get rid of that on top layered nonsense because I think
that's going to cause us some problems.
So I'm going to get rid of that until we actually until we actually
decide to spend some time on that.
So we don't keep having this problem.
Where our window is is being mean.
All right.
There we go.
Much better.
Okay.
So took care of that.
So in theory, let's take a look here.
That should be the end of the path for those guys.
So someone pointed it out.
I was looking for this on the stream, but I never found it while we
were on the stream when we were trying to get the date of files.
I was looking for a way to do it without a handle and I couldn't quite
find one, but
Someone pointed out you can get it with this one.
Get file attributes X, I guess so it looks like yeah looks like okay.
So it looks like there it is.
So it looks like we can use get file attributes X to get it without a
handle.
I'm not sure.
Get file attributes doesn't do it.
So only excess so what basically person wrote in and said is this
The function, you are looking for because I don't know if you remember
me trying to find it and I couldn't find it.
I was like, I thought there was one you could use without a handle,
but I never found it.
Well, this is it.
So, if we go to where we were getting that get last right time instead
of having to do this fine.
First find clothes thing we can basically say, okay, let's not do that
anymore.
That's, that's not necessary.
Let's just use, let's just use this guy.
Get file, attribute CX will pass the file.
Just like we were before and of course, it's inconsistently
capitalized because I always for some reason cannot seem to figure out
how to do that and then we'll pass whatever this thing wants.
So it wants a class of attribute to receive the parameter can be one
of the following values and it looks like get file X.
Info standard is the value.
It's a very odd value to pass, but that's it.
So I'll pass get file X info standard and then it wants me to pass one
of these.
These guys, as the as the file information out / am.
So basically, I have to declare one of those to hold it.
This is the data, then I will pass the address of it, and it should
fill it out for me.
It should return a Bool.
It looks like for whether it found it or not.
And then if it did, I will basically say that whatever that said.
The last right, time is what I will do.
Oops, that's a mistake.
And if there and so that should give us the same results but in a much
smoother way, we don't have to actually deal with an operating system
handle.
So hopefully that will that will let us do it much smoother.
So, let's see if that actually works.
If I go over here and make my emacs tinier.
If I go do the standard code edit that we've been doing to test our
hot reloading.
Let's just check to see if it still is nice and snappy.
Happy, sure is beautiful.
Alright, so yeah, that's just a better way of doing what we were
doing.
It's just a finding the right Windows call, can sometimes take a
while, but oftentimes there is like a better call for doing various
things and that's definitely better.
So we can get rid of this one.
We won't need that one anymore.
There we go.
All right, so that should be all there is to that.
We're getting through a lot of stuff here.
Let's see.
What else we got?
What else is on the, on the hopper?
All right.
So this is one that is kind of interesting to try a pair of Onsen
wrote this in.
Actually.
He's a person.
I actually know personally.
He used to work at rad game tools.
I believe he is that Oculus now.
But basically, he was suggesting to try something, which I think is
pretty interesting and it may work.
I don't know.
I don't think I've ever tried this before but basically what he was
saying was that and I may be putting words in his mouth there because
he tweeted it to me.
So it course with 140 characters.
Sometimes it's hard to know.
But basically when we when we go to write out our, our recording when
we do our work,
Hurting and we want to blast out that huge memory buffer like a lot of
its zeros if it hasn't been used yet.
And so one of the things that he was pointing out is you might be able
to use when NTFS is sparse file information to make that right faster
in the cases for free basically in the cases where there isn't that
much stuff in it.
Now, I don't think this will help us at all in the case when we
actually have the full running game.
So it's maybe kind of
A hollow victory in some sense, but for the time being, it may help us
because yeah, it may help us make the right faster in cases where we
don't have where we don't have stuff.
It actually filling the memory buffer.
So basically device IO controls, the thing that sort of tells Windows
additional information about handles and how you want them to work.
So we have a handle to a file here that we created and we can give it
some information about how we
expect rights to happen to that file.
And so the thing that we want to do is this device IO control call.
We want to
That after this and the thing that we want to look at is this thing.
It's a bit weird.
It's called fctl set.
Oops.
What was it set sparse?
I think sets parse this guy.
So, oh they've already filled out the whole thing for me that's even
easier.
So okay.
That's basically what we that is the call that we want to do.
And so what this does,
Is it says that a particular file is allowed to be stored or that
windows can look to see if large ranges of the file are 0.
And if they don't need to be stored, then they just won't be stored.
So since we know that almost all of our memory is 0 right now, it
might be that that helps Windows do this operation a lot more quickly,
right?
So basically, all we'd be doing here is just calling this device IO
control purely as a hint to Windows, basically.
Hey, we've got this handle, right?
We want to set it to sparse.
I don't know what the input buffer part is.
Let's see.
A pointer to the sparsely.
So the parameter is optional, if it's null.
So we don't we don't care about that.
We're not going to set that at all.
And the in buffer size will also be 0.
The output buffer will be 0, that will be 0 B returned that can be
known as well.
Right?
Let's see if we're just null.
Help B, return cannot be null.
Even when operates returns.
No output.
Okay.
So we do have two best.
We do have to pass it a d word here.
That's ignored.
Of course.
Because why wouldn't you do that?
So there's our ignored value, basically.
So the all we're doing is just telling it.
Hey, you can store this file sparsely.
If you want to you don't have to record all of those long zero runs,
so just, you know, be advised.
So I don't know if that'll actually help or not, but it did seem like
a pretty smart thing to try.
So I did want to try it.
So, let's see.
That does not seem to be any faster to me.
Yeah, so it doesn't actually seem.
To improve the performance at all.
Now, I may not have done it quite right.
I think I did but I'm not entirely.
Sure.
Let's double-check.
So let's see.
Here.
We get the recording.
Can do we create a generic right?
For the file?
We set the thing too, sparse.
Yeah, so that doesn't actually appear to help.
Hmm.
Does not appear to help to me.
So I'm going to say we don't actually do that.
It would have been nice if it did but I don't think it actually does.
So I'm going to go ahead and pull that.
All right too bad.
That might have been fun.
But what can you do?
Let's see.
What else I got here?
I got some of the things, some of these things.
Maybe we'll say for tomorrow, multiple translations units.
Okay, so somebody was asking some people have importing handmade here
obviously to other platforms and they were just asking basically for
something.
If we could do to make their lives a little easier.
Basically, what it is is there's these sub functions, right?
And the stub functions are in the header file.
And so what ends up happening, is they the stub functions being in the
header means that.
If they have multiple translations,
In units that all include the header file, then the thing gets defined
multiple times.
Right.
So there's a couple things we could do here.
We could make sure that these things are only defined once if we
wanted to.
And you know, that's one way to go.
The other thing we could do is just guard, the calls to them.
And so, what I think what I might do is just guard, the calls to them
entirely.
So, just get rid of the stubs.
The only reason the stubs were there.
Was to make it so that you could use this function calls, even if
there was an even if it was invalid.
But really all we have to do is just say that it's always going to be
0.
So we could, we could always just say that it's zero.
And then anywhere that we're going to call update and render.
Again, just clearing this 20, anywhere that we're going to call update
and render will just check.
We'll just check the sea and we just won't call it if it's, if it's
null, right?
That's, that's
We're going to do and that just seems to me to be a little more saying
we know there's, there's not going to be hardly any functions in here.
And there's only two time they're going to be called and so few places
will just say that you have to check for null.
So basically what we'll just Define.
Well, we will basically Define that excuse me, we will basically
Define this game code thing to say, you know, what note.
Either of the callbacks can be null, right?
You must check before calling.
And so, that's just, that's just a rule that we've made.
And that way people don't have to worry about that, that symbol being
multiplied, defined.
So that way, there's nothing in this header file.
That's a function that's being defined other than an inline, right,
other than these in lines, which inline functions, you can declare
multiple times because they just, they can be anywhere since they're
not declaring it and they're not actually making new function.
They're just basically a macro, you know, kind of thing that gets
inserted in code.
So that seems totally fine.
And that
It'll help some people out here, doing some porting work, and who
don't want to deal with with having to only have one one file in the
platform layer.
Like we are.
Okay.
So I think that maybe most of the stuff we're going to do today and
then we'll save the rest of the stuff for tomorrow.
Oh, well, I will say that there's a virtual Alec thing that I thought
might be good to do just for fun, which is that to release.
Some pressure on the the on the translation lookaside buffer
potentially something we haven't gotten to yet.
But one of the things that we could do is in our giant virtual lock
that we do down here.
This guy.
Where is he?
Oops virtual?
It's almost there.
There we go.
So in this is this guy where we do our giant virtual Alec, it might be
nice to allow the operating system to use large pages.
And so the way that this works is just me.
I believe.
Yeah, so there's this guy here, large Pages.
What large pages are, is when you do this mapping, when we're talking
about virtual membrane, right?
We've got our application.
Space is laid out in these pages, right?
We've got, we've got page size and that page size.
I think I was talking about before is usually for K.
So it's 4096.
Bytes.
And basically what has to happen is
Inside the processor, right?
Because remember, in fact, let's just do you know what, since this is
the Q&A?
Let's just we're since we're starting with you, and I let me, let me
just do a diagram here that explains this what's going to happen
because it's something that's useful to know.
So let's just use the first part of the Q&A for that.
So, okay.
Let's go over this one more time.
Here is physical memory, right?
So this is physical.
Ram if the actual RAM on your computer, so I don't know how much
you've got.
Let's say, it's a pretty good machine.
It's 16 GB, right?
So basically they're 16 gigs of physical memory in the machine.
It is actually laid out in order.
It goes from B 0 to B 16 gigs, right?
And it's all there.
Now in our process.
We have process virtual memory and that virtual memory is
Some other thing, it has no relationship really to this physical RAM,
right?
So we see, you know, B, 0 is, that's wow.
That's a great Arrow.
We see B 0 is here and I don't know we allocate we you know, who knows
how much we have.
But, but we're looking at memory, just kind of going up and this can
go all the way up.
I believe to 8 terabytes in 64-bit windows, for the app.
And then I think there's another 8 terabytes for the system.
I don't actually remember.
Member.
So I don't know if that's true.
But basically there's 8 terabytes.
This is again, the worst diagrams today is try that again.
8 terabytes for us and 8 terabytes for the system.
So that's like a 16 terabyte thing.
I think it looks something like that, but I don't actually know the.
I think this might be there might be a bunch of space in between here.
I'm not sure exactly what this looks like, but point being this is
some totally other space.
This is no bearing on.
Physical RAM.
We met
It's something and say oh, you know in a fact we did when we did our
virtual Alec right?
We asked for it to be at at this Base address right in the Base
address.
Was that two terabytes.
So we actually said oh, okay.
The Base address is somewhere like right here at two terabytes.
Well 2 terabytes.
There's only 16 gigabytes in the Machine 2.
Terabytes is way off the end of physical memory if you think about
where it actually is located.
So this is a purely
Fictional address that we've created and so our game exists in one
gigabyte of memory right here or whatever.
It's a little more than that because we have 64, Meg's of perm store
or whatever.
But like we said at the to 2 terabyte range, we're going to use the
number 2 terabytes and every all the bytes in between there and and
one gig from, there are going to be part of our game.
Those numbers have to correspond to Something in here when the
processor is actually doing work, right?
So the CPU is
In here, running our game.
It's going to see a number that looks like two terabytes.
So 2 terabyte number.
The number 2, terabytes, whatever.
It is.
Some number.
It's actually some big number.
That's like, complicated and long, right?
Two terabytes with some fractional part or whatever.
Right?
So some crazy long byte address.
And in fact, I can even make this more concrete, right?
Let's go in and just see one of the numbers I can give you an example
of exactly what it is.
Inside our game.
Let's see here.
Let's take a look.
So we go into our, our game call which I need to put some comments in
here soon.
So I can find my way around.
I keep getting lost in my own code because I haven't made any markers
in it.
What's going on?
Why can I set a breakpoint recompile?
Run?
There we go.
Ok.
So inside here, here's game update and render, right?
So let's just take a look at what the pointer to like.
Say the player, X, where is player X being stored in memory?
Right?
Well, there's the number and you can see, there's that two terabyte or
whatever and there's the like, fractional part of it, that the offset
from there, right?
So, that's the
Or if you actually look at what this equals in in a decimal, right?
Let me try and cast that to a decimal.
I don't know if it'll actually do it or not does not appear to
actually do it.
Why won't you convert it?
There it is.
So I guess I don't know my way around the visual studio Watchman, do
comment, comma syntax, very well.
But if you put a comma after something, and then you do these codes,
you can use in Visual Studio, that will turn it into different number
types.
Select up, be is binary.
That's a new one that we that didn't used to work the works.
Now D is decimal.
So you can see this is actually the number this.
A number of the processor actually sees when we go to reference player
X, the processor sees this number, right?
So that number is coming into the CPU here, right?
It's the, the CPU is seeing this, that crazy number.
We just said now that number doesn't exist that that location in
physical.
RAM does not exist.
There aren't two terabytes of memory, even in the machine.
Let alone, two terabytes plus whatever that was, you know, plus some
where we were looking at it would
Be way way off the end of physical memory.
So what has to happen is the CPU, has to translate that address into
wherever the memory is actually being stored in physical RAM, which
the operating system manages.
It basically pulls in parts of the memory that we asked for and keeps
them in.
Physical RAM as necessary, and it can do stuff like swap them out to
disk if it needs to write.
There's a paging file, right?
It can swap pieces out to disk if it runs out of physical RAM storing
stuff.
It can move it out to disk.
And in fact, you can see it move it out to disk if you actually look.
I think it can see it here.
Let's see if I can see it here.
So yeah, you can see on the C drive.
There.
It is right there page file dot sis.
So if I do pagefile this and do a doron that well, alright, so it
won't let me do it because it's some operating system protected file
nonsense, I guess but
I can see it there that page failed out.
Sis is actually where it's writing the stuff that gets swapped out.
So in this process, what has to happen is there has to be a way for
the CPU to translate those addresses.
It has to do work to support virtual memory, virtual memory isn't
free.
The CPU has to actually dedicate circuitry for doing this process.
So how does it translate that number?
Well, the way that it does that is in chunks.
Basically.
Each 4K page right for so 4096.
Bytes worth of memory.
Each.
4K page basically is mapped individually between virtual memory and
physical memory.
Such that there is a page table.
Which literally says stuff like, you know, okay, you know, you can
imagine something like, there's the physical address and the virtual
address, right, and they're mapped in like a table.
So we basically.
Oh, physical address, you know, 16 or something maps to Virtual
address, you know, 2048 or whatever, right?
It's basically just a thing that says, the 4K based at this address.
Well, they don't these would all be on 4K boundaries obviously.
So those are stupid examples.
But like the physical at two times 4096 and the virtual at 10.
X 4096 are the same page.
We have mapped this location to this location.
Right?
And what you have to appreciate is that this mapping isn't free.
It has to actually be stored and it has to actually be managed.
So the CPU has a bunch of stuff in it to try and make this faster and
one of the things that it has something called a tlb or translation
lookaside buffer and basically what that is is something
designed to translate addresses quickly by having a small number of
these mappings directly on the CPU, that can be looked up extremely
quickly.
It's basically like a cash for address translation, right?
And you can look this up if you want more information.
I'm not a CPU guy.
So I'm not the guy to give you the explanation on that, but you can
look for this translation lookaside buffer.
You can look for this on like Wikipedia and it can sort of
Tell you, right?
So it's cash for virtual addresses, like a saying and it can kind of
explain to you a little bit more about exactly how it works.
But the part that I'm trying to get to that, I thought was interesting
to kind of dive into here.
And the reason I want to talk about it was because if you think about
what happens, the number of entries in this table, the number of
entries in the number of total entries of translation that have to
happen in the operating system.
Right?
Is based on how big this number is, if each thing is 4K,
Then there's going to be a certain number of entries.
If everything was instead, 16k right?
Then there would be four times less entries because for the same
amount of memory to be mapped, each mapping stores four times the
amount of addresses, essentially, right?
Because you're mapping it in 16k blocks, which means that for a
translation lookaside buffer on the CPU.
If the pages are 4K, there's going to be a lot more entries in here
than if they were larger.
And so what I believe is that I believe you can switch to you.
Two megabyte, which is massively larger than for.
Okay, I believe you can switch to using 2, MB sizes for the
translation lookaside buffer.
I don't actually know if that's true.
But I think that's something like that is basically true.
And if you tell virtual a life, that you're okay, using large pages on
some operating systems on some versions of Windows.
I think it can actually switch your process to using 2.
MB Pages.
Which takes a lot of pressure off of that tlb.
And so, since we're allocating one,
Chunk, it may be that we can get a lot of benefit there and take
pressure off of the CPU by doing that.
So it's just something that I wanted to mention.
And so I think it's probably worth as passing that flag in the case
that we're not on Windows XP to just say, hey, you know, let's let's
go ahead and and use those large pages.
So what I want to do is I just want to go ahead and pass that.
That's about it.
I believe that's on, that's on the the mem commitment.
Curve, whatever side of.
So it's right in here we do that and I'm just going to put to do in
there to do.
Like do we need to not pass that in empty?
Will that mess up in t?
So do we need to not pass member large pages on Windows XP?
Or will it be fine?
Right, that's about it.
So I just wanted to try that because I think that may help us in the
future basically, avoid the situation where we have a lot of tlb
pressure.
That's just another thing that
Make life harder for the processor when it's trying to run our code.
So I just going to see if that works.
All right, so that doesn't work.
I assume there is a problem with allocating the mem large pages that
way.
I don't actually know what it is.
But I'm going to take a sari to eat up.
Q&A time.
We can go a little long but I just wanted to try that because I'd like
I've never used it before but I feel like it's something that we could
do.
So I'm going to see if there's anything particular that we have to do.
To use are two sorts lock memory, privileged privileged by calling
just tokens.
So we didn't do that.
We'd have to do that retrieve, the minimal large paid size.
Include member large pages.
So we'd also have to do a little bit extra.
It looks like here we have to actually call adjust token privileges to
basically say, hey, we're going to be a large page app.
Alright, so maybe I'll have to leave this as a to do for later, on in
things because that does actually sound.
Like I was hoping we could just say, hey, please let us use large
pages, but doesn't look that way.
So, let's see, use mem large pages and call adjust token.
Privileges.
When not on Windows XP, so that's something that I'd like to do in the
future because the translation lookaside buffer actually can cause you
to slow down because basically anytime you miss that translation,
lookaside buffer and you're accessing and a dress that needs to get
translated and you have to pull new entries into the tlb.
That's another source of processor slow down, right?
And so since we don't really care too much about how that memory is
page because we're trying to run in all of our game and memory.
At once I feel like there.
Isn't probably much of a downside to using the large Pages.
Maybe that's not true.
But I would least like to have it in our app.
So we could do some testing and like, turn it on and off and see if it
made a difference in any way.
And it might be that we find that it doesn't matter about it since we
can do it at thought, it might be nice to try.
All right, so I think that's about it and we are now into the Q&A.
So hopefully everyone knows the drill by now, if you could include
Include senior ettore in your question.
So I will see it.
That would be very helpful.
And please keep your questions to things we did on this stream or in a
previous stream, but not stuff that we're going to do a future streams
just because we will get there when we get there.
All right.
Let's see if we got any questions.
Course, I got to wait for the, gotta wait for the twitch lag'.
I got to wait for things to catch up here.
We got through quite a lot of stuff today.
I was pretty good.
That was pretty good.
A couple more things will have to do tomorrow, but we're in pretty
good shape.
Any questions any questions?
Any question.
Come on Twitch like ketchup.
Do do, do, do, do do.
Can we go over really fast overview of the game recording and Playback
code?
Sure, there's almost no code, though, but we can certainly go over it.
Very briefly.
There's basically nothing to it.
So, here are the parts that make it work.
Very simply again.
This is all, just because if you pick your architecture, right certain
things become very easy, I happen to pick the architecture.
So that this is very easy.
If you don't do the these architectural choices, then it becomes very
hard.
And that's just, that's the nature of architecture.
Architecture is about making choices that make the things you want to
do easy at the expense of other things, becoming
But those other things you try to pick such that there are things, you
don't care about, if that makes sense.
So, the first thing that we did, that makes it easy.
Is we made game controller input.
Be a structure.
That's easy to record.
Right?
So basically, the entire input to our game is in here.
And we made that that decision makes it trivial to record game input.
So basically what we and to play it back.
So basically the first thing that we did that made things easy for us
is we now know that in order to record or play back in, put the only
thing we have to do is before we call game update and render.
Which is the only place that can actually do any work to change the
state of the game.
All it does is take that input structure.
That's it.
That's the only thing it knows about.
That's the only thing that can affect how the game runs.
So,
As a result.
All we have to do is before we call that update.
If we wanted to record.
We just record the input that we're going to pass it by writing that
out to a file.
Just the whole block, this just destruct flat to a file.
Bam into the file, just like it is in memory, and if we wanted to play
back, we just do the opposite.
We blast, we pull it right out of the file.
We just romp it right over the input.
We were going to pass.
So instead of passing at the actual input that the user, did we pass
it?
Whatever we read from the file.
That was the other.
The input that we were recording.
It on some previous run through.
So that's Thing One and that's totally trivial.
It's just reading and writing a struct from a file.
That's it, right.
So, the only other thing that we needed to be able to do after we had
that working, right?
Is we just needed a way to reset the game state.
So that basically, we could record the input.
We just play it back by reading from a file.
That was fine.
But we don't have a way to do is reset the state of the game.
Well, again, architecture wise we made smart decisions.
So the way that our game works is it just gets past a block of memory
and it's assumed that the game is supposed to just run entirely inside
that block a memory.
So
All we have to do to save and load the state of the game is just save
that block of memory.
Now, we know what the block of memory is because we allocated it right
here.
This is the block of memory and because we told virtual a lock to
always put that block of memory at the same Base address in memory.
It means that any pointers inside that block of memory that point into
other parts of the locker memory will still just work because it's
always there.
Always going to be the exact same locations, no matter when you run
the game because it's always allocating memory at the same Base
address.
So what it turned into
You was in order to restore save and restore the game State.
The only thing that you have to do is just blast that memory block out
to a file.
So literally all we do when we first open the file to write it.
So, let's see.
Begin recording input to write it.
All we do is just write out that memory block the whole thing, blam.
And then we want to play it back.
We just read it back in right over the memory block, just romp It,
Whatever the memory block is right now.
We just read in the old one blam.
It's on top of it, and there, you
Go.
This is exactly like someone mentioned this in the forums and they're
totally right.
It's exactly like what an emulator does in like when you can save the
state in like a skin, like a NES emulator or something.
It just takes the memory of the machine and it dumps it out to disk.
Well, what we've done is we sort of created almost like a virtual
machine that are game runs in and so we can do just like what an
emulator does.
Our engine sort of works almost like an emulator where you can just
write out the block of memory and it's fine.
So that's it.
It's really simple.
And again, it's all about architecture.
If you build your architecture, smart stuff, that seems like it's very
complicated actually, is really totally trivial and, and you get a lot
of stuff for free.
When you're saving game State snapshot, how big is the file?
The file will be however, much memory you gave the game to work in.
So we allocated a GB, + 64 Meg's, so the file will be a GB.
+ 64 Meg's
That makes sense.
And I should double-check the work.
We did.
Today worked actually.
So in handmade.
These should be in the bill directory.
Now those, those yet Loop edit HMI, so you can see there.
It's a gig plus 16 Meg's, which is what we expected.
What is that?
That doesn't look good?
Fuu dot txt food up bar and to I think those were that was for when we
did that mistaken pipe, right?
Was that was from when we were messing around on the street before I
let me make sure those those guys don't get recreated.
But, yeah, that was funny that after their close that down.
yeah, so
yeah, so we're all good.
Okay.
Can you check if the string length needs a win 3-2 prefix?
Or is this game code?
Yeah, I don't want to put a prefix on that because we'll probably move
that into game code eventually.
That's not a win32 specific function.
How many lines of code is the finished game estimated to be?
I don't know.
I've no idea.
Yeah, I don't usually look at lines of code very much.
So, I don't know.
I've no idea how many it'll be, we'll see you when we get there.
Someone can run clock on it.
Maybe use to random in your batch file to get a more unique file name.
It doesn't matter.
Like if they Collide, we don't care.
It just means that the build will fail that one time.
You had all Dem.
But I mean, yeah, it's not that's that's just not going to be a
problem.
I don't think.
Having just finished my first University course in C++.
I found myself really enjoying coding, but not really sure where to
continue learning on my own any advice on where I could go or what to
do to pick up a bit more coding or knowledge experience.
Not really.
I mean basically this stream is is my answer to what I think maybe
people should doing.
I'm trying to go over the sorts of things.
I think people should learn how to do.
So, that's really this stream is the best answer I have because I
didn't think there was necessarily a lot of information out there.
So I
You know, that's what I'm trying to do with the stream.
So, I don't know, I'm sure there are other good things out there to
do, but I'm not super familiar with them.
So I'm not sure I can necessarily recommend anything in particular.
What is a good example of well-written game code?
For example, everyone talks about Doom code?
I don't know.
I haven't looked at the Doom code.
I'm not, I'm not sure, there's not that many Game Source Code things
out there.
I mean, Carmack was a very good programmer.
So I suspect that doom and Quake are probably very well programmed
things, but I don't know.
I haven't looked at them myself, so I couldn't say,
Assuming you want to record exactly what happens in the game.
How would the looping handle, random values, say enemy bullets that
are fired at random angles.
Well, the answer is there's no such thing as random values.
So actually what we already did will record quote unquote, random.
Enemy bullets just fine.
The reason for that is because the way Randomness actually is
generated in code is it's actually pseudo-random.
So they're basically mathematical
Chuckle functions that generate numbers that appear.
To be random but they're not actually random.
And so as long as you save the memory state of the thing of all the
stuff you're using to generate your random numbers, which we would by
default be doing because we're saving all the state from the game,
then all of the random stuff will happen exactly the same.
And in fact, you'll see that happen because we will have plenty of
random stuff in the game.
If we dump memory to disk in a large-scale application, wouldn't that?
Cause more than one gig footprint for every state?
I'm not sure what that means.
Obviously, whatever the size is of the memory that you're dumping is
the size of the footprint, so,
Yeah, I'm not, I do not sure.
I understand the question.
However, much memory it takes to store.
The state is how big the state is on disk.
All right, I mean you could compress it if you wanted to save space
for some reason.
But again, this is for the looped edit feature.
So we don't care.
We're only going to have a couple of those files at any given time at
most.
So we don't care how big they are.
They could be 10 gigabytes.
We wouldn't care.
Really.
It just doesn't matter.
The only thing we really care about is
We want them to load relatively fast so which I think they will do on
an SSD, but we could try to do things to speed that up a little bit
potentially, but that's really the only reason we care about the size.
We don't care about the space at all.
I don't get the stuff for you, declare a variable without initializing
it and then you use the address to it in a function call.
Is that a dummy thing?
Or what is it used for?
So I'm not sure exactly what you're referring to.
But maybe are you talking about stuff like like this?
Is this what you mean?
Assuming?
This is what you mean.
Then basically, what this is is this is reserving, space on the stack.
For essentially, use by some other function.
We are going to reserve something this big, however, big this struct
is we are going to call get file, attribute CX, and pass it.
The address of it so it can then right into that memory.
That's on the stack in our stack frame, right?
What it needs to write in there.
And so that we can access it.
So basically the reason that it's not initialized is because we don't
care what its values are.
We just care that space was reserved for it because this
Function is actually going to do the right.
It's going to actually create the values and you can see that happen.
Like what, you can just step in and watch that happen.
Right?
What's the name of this function?
Get last right time?
So if we wanted to actually watch that happen, you can see it.
So we come in here and basically at this point in the code we have
reserved.
So size of data, right?
We reserved 36 bytes at this address, which is on the stack, which is
on our stack frame.
We've reserved 36 bytes of our stack that we are now passing the
address to get file attributes to X.
You can see that it's just garbage right now, but then when we
actually call that function, it fills all of it in on our stack, with
the values.
So, so that's how that works.
Hopefully, that answered the question.
I'm not sure.
I knew exactly what, which question you were asking, but hopefully
that is roughly.
Roughly.
The question also is the breakpoints window.
Why do I need my breakpoints window, get that break points with
malaria?
Let's get those.
Okay.
You can make the recording instantaneous using copy on write Pages.
Yes.
Oh, I was trying to think about how to do that.
I was wondering about that.
And I wasn't 100% sure how to still always have the same Base address
when doing that.
Does that make sense?
so,
Yeah, I mean, I think basically the way to do it is you do a memory
map?
You do the memory mapped file of the memory from the current location
to attempt location, right?
And then you let the game Run, then we need to restore it.
You just mem map back, right?
And I think that works.
I don't know.
I haven't tried it yet.
I didn't want to do it that way at first, because I wasn't actually
sure if it was gonna work, but I agree that that may work.
I just have never tried it.
So I can't promise you that it would but I think that it might it
doesn't help you with storing it to disk really as much.
But, you know.
With the sparse file for flags have dropped.
.H of my file size by how much?
Bye.
Well, it probably would drop the H of my file size and probably drop
it by however many 0 Pages there were in it.
But again, it wouldn't drop it at all later when we're totally feeling
the memory.
So it's not really a meaningful optimization later on.
It was just a fun thing to see if it would work in our current state
where most of the memory is 0.
Still got him says, I'm still not sure we're using the windows API to
get memory instead of the standard Library.
Why are we making windows calls?
If we were supposed to be doing everything from scratch, are the
windows functions were using optimized for use for use Windows?
Outperforming the standard Library?
I do not understand the question.
I guess, what, I would try to say is, we need to get memory from the
operating system.
There is no.
Such thing as writing something from scratch.
If you still want to write on Windows, we would have to like
re-implement the operating system to get any lower level.
So when I say from scratch, I just mean that runs on Windows, right?
On Raspberry Pi, we will be able to do our own memory mapping.
And so that will be more from scratch than this.
But as long as we're running on Windows, we have to ask windows for
the memory.
It's the only thing that controls the memory table.
We have no ability to
Me to do anything else.
We could write a device driver or something and try to do it that way.
But like assuming that you want to be a gain that person can run
without being administrator, without escalating to administrator every
time they run it or whatever, or installing a device driver on their
machine to run it.
Yeah, I so, I don't really understand the question.
Sorry.
As the game grows, how are you going to partition the game member
between systems to keep the record and playback feature working.
We shouldn't have to do the record and playback feature just works
because everything happens inside the game memory.
So it doesn't matter how we partition it.
It'll still work.
You did the partitioning of the memory for the game is not related to
whether the record and playback feature works or not.
Would it make sense to Temporary less than the size of game em, we
don't use it the moment.
Anyway, well, not really because like we're going to be using it so
lessening it temporarily doesn't really help us much.
I mean if we were tuning something early on and wanted to speed up
that, right, but I think we could speed up the right that right in
other ways as well like using the copy on write Pages or other stuff
like that that was mentioned.
So if we really found that was annoying us a ton we could speed that
up.
Are you happy with the timing FPS results?
I found an old article on RD SE for more accurate timing.
So rdst.
Our dtsc is for profiling not timing.
You cannot use our dtsc for timing using our DC SC for timing is very
bad.
So you need to use Query performance counter for timing.
Meaning, the thing that actually measures, how long the game Loop
takes for synchronization with like the audio and stuff.
And
For like trying to hit 60, hertz for 30 Hertz, or whatever.
That has to be query performance counter because our dtsc doesn't tell
you, well clock time, our dtsc we do call and we so we have that in
here, right?
But that's only for profiling and so until we start actually profiling
code.
We will not be using the results of our dtsc because that is not, you
never want to use the results of our dtsc for timing.
Unless it's you want to use it for profiling.
So they're ambiguous words.
You never want to use it for synchronization.
You only want to use it for profiling and we haven't done any
profiling yet.
When would the Mac code start?
I am following with Windows in a VM and is really slow.
We won't do Mac until we ship.
So it'll be a very long time.
But if you want Mac earlier, keep in mind that if you click on, if you
go to handmade hero dot org and you click on news and forums, keep in
mind that in the coding resources section.
There's already two options for Mac.
There's the Mac OS, X, native port.
And there's also the sdl port that's originally for Linux, but you can
use it on Mac.
So you
I have two options for Mac right now.
If you don't want to run into VM, so I would highly recommend checking
those out because there's people who are keeping those up-to-date and
all that.
Is there any negative effects of making the page size bigger?
So I don't really know.
I would say that possibly.
Yes, because having, you know, increasing the granularity like that.
To from like 4K to 2 Meg or something.
You do run the risk of sort of fragmentation of the tlb.
So if you think about like what happens here, right?
If I've got something where, you know, I've got memory and who knows
how like here's the translation lookaside buffer.
Right?
And the translation lookaside buffer has some number of entries in it.
Let's say it's got four.
Hopefully, it's got more than that.
But right, let's say it's got four entries in the tlb.
And
Four entries can each point, 22 megabytes, right?
So they can either, they can either point to 4K or they can point to
two megabytes or something like that.
Right?
Well, I would guess I'm trying to think about if this is true or not.
Well, now, you know what?
You know, the more I think about it.
No, I guess, you know what?
To tell you the truth.
I was going to draw something out that I was going to say, like, well,
maybe this is a problem, but you know what?
I don't know.
I can't I can't think of anything for our particular circumstance.
Where would be a problem?
But again, I'm not a CPU guy.
So I think probably I'm not qualified to answer that question is what
I would say, so all I wanted to do with the larger Pages was be able
to be able to turn them on and off.
So we could run our game with large Pages run our game without the
large pages and see if it
Impact on performance down the line, you know, later on when we're
doing Performance Tuning.
I kind of want to be able to do that.
But I do not know practically.
If there'd be downsides, are upsides.
Let's see.
How do you calculate the size of a struct?
Do you mean besides just doing size of?
I mean, the easiest way to calculate the size of struct is just to ask
what it is, right?
You just ask the compiler, we do.
The time we just call size of right, I did it right here.
So size of is the thing that says, how big a struct is and technically
that's the only way to know how big a struct is because I think
technically the compiler is allowed to pad things in ways that maybe
aren't completely defined.
I don't know if that's actually true.
It may be that they're always completely defined and you could always
compute it entirely yourself but basically size of is the thing that
tells you how big is the struct is but all it's doing what size of
does if you're just cook, if you're just curious of like, how big is a
struct
All it's doing is it's going through the members of the struct and
looking how big they are.
Right?
It's just going.
Okay.
This is a pointer on 64-bit a pointer is 8, bytes long.
So that's eight.
This is an integer.
That's 32 bits.
So it's four bytes long.
So 4444.
So it's this is 888.
So that's going to be 24, right?
But that's how big it would need.
If it was packed optimally, you then have to account for.
The fact that the compiler aligns things on boundaries that are equal
to the size of the thing being aligned.
So for example, if I was to move this memory pointer, which is 8,
bytes long
If I move this 8 B thing below the integer, which is only four bytes.
It would insert 4 bytes of padding before it to make sure that the
memory this part is, is a is a line.
This 8 B thing is aligned on an 8 byte boundary.
So there is a little bit of Finnick Enos that you have to be aware of
but basically that's it.
Can you add line numbers to those of us following along at home?
Have an easier time?
So we tried to do that.
We put line numbers in the de bugger.
We couldn't really put line numbers in emacs because they were really
pretty ugly and they were a little bit buggy.
So I don't know about that.
Basically the problem was we can we can maybe try it again and see if
people object-- but basically
Basically, if we if you think is it line number?
No, it's not that it's like lyneham or whatever.
I don't know how to get this guy to let's let's see here.
So here was the problem with line numbers is that inside inside the
dot e, Max file, there's a linum thing.
So this guy, right?
So basically what we did is we tried turning it on and it looks it
looks like
Codes and 32, it looks like that.
And they were kind of really ugly, and bright and weird, and whatever.
So, anyway, and they also had this weird, this, this like a bug with
there was this weird bug with that line down the middle.
You can see it like it erases.
It's like go up.
It's really it's just all messed up.
And so I don't know if I really like.
That's all glitchy and weird and it just seemed kind of bad.
So
I was not super happy about that.
And I don't know if that's something that can be fixed or not.
I'm not even sure why that line is there at all in the first place.
But if someone wants to do the work on the dot, exe file, to get these
line numbers, first of all, to be like a darker color, like this, the
same as the comments, let's say.
And then to fix that line that goes down the middle.
If someone wants to do that, then I would turn them on because I'd be
fine with that.
But I as they are, they're really
kind of bad and ugly and they're very distracting.
So I don't think I would be inclined to use them if we can't fix that
problem, but if we can then that's that's that would work.
So yeah.
Okay, I believe some people think that the game state is saved every
time with the input, whereas it is only saved the beginning of the
recording and then modified through input playback.
That is correct.
So, we only save this.
The one gigabyte only gets saved when we start from, then on, we just
play back.
What the input was.
I mean, let the game recreate it, state from that.
So, it doesn't create a gigabyte, every frame.
It just creates a gigabyte, once that's it.
Do you think the recording technique will run into problems if we have
multiple threads using the game State?
Well, it depends how you do those multiple threads.
So basically I don't think we will run into problems with it.
The way I am going to do the threading in the game.
But if you didn't do it the way, I'm going to do it then yes, you very
well could but you also have the option of sort of having your
threading system have two modes.
You can certainly do a mode that safe for recording and one that's
not.
And so when you're doing tuning, you could use the one that's safe
recording.
And when it's not not right.
So you could work around it that way, as well.
If virtual Alec does not guarantee contiguous memory.
Could this pose a hindrance to cash optimizations virtual Alec does
guarantee contiguous memory, so I'm not sure what that means.
So I'll say, two things about that question.
So first of all, the first thing to remember, is no virtual a lock.
Only operates on pages anyway, and cache lines are smaller than a
page.
So, for example, 4096 bytes is the smallest page size that virtual
Alec will even allocate in a chunk at once.
And I'm pretty sure that virtual Alec always aligns to 64k boundaries.
Anyway, so basically you're talking about things that are massively
larger than a cache line anyway.
So, so I'm not sure the question.
I'm not sure.
I understand really where that question is coming from, but also
virtual Alec does guarantee contiguous memory.
So so I even so it is all going to be contiguous.
And remember it's contiguous in our virtual address space.
It's not continuous in contiguous in physical memory.
But again, that doesn't affect the cash at all because the cash is
actually always going to be some some subdivision of the virtual
memory paging sighs anyway, so it doesn't really matter.
It's never going to be discontinuous across a cache line boundary that
makes
Where can I get earlier versions of the code?
The link only gives me the latest version?
No, the link gives you all the versions, so that when you download in
the link where you download the source code, it's a zip file that has
every day's Source in it.
So you should be able to just open up the zip file and see all the
days every single day is in there.
Really should be if it's not, please let me know.
All right.
Looks like that is the end of questions.
So that is good.
Perfect, all right, everyone will thank you very much for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero.
We have one more day of cleanup that we're going to do tomorrow and
then next week.
We will be starting on our game engine, which should be pretty
exciting.
I'm looking forward to it.
Definitely.
I'd like to have some prettier stuff up on the screen than our
gradient.
Not that our gradient is an awesome, but it would be nice to have some
real art made by a real artist on the screen.
So that's going to be pretty exciting.
I think as always
If you would like to follow along at home with the source code, you
can pre-order the game and it comes with the source code.
You can download it every night after I upload after we finish here.
I upload it so you can get immediate access to it.
And if you would like to basically discuss the the series or get more
resources, you can go to this news and forums site.
And basically it's got all kinds of things.
Got an episode guide for watching past episodes, along with some nice
time, annotations that allow you to
Jump Around the videos.
There's a coating Resource page, which has ports you can use, and also
some some helpful guides.
There's the discussion, which is the forums.
You can kind of go on here and post questions and talk with other
people.
So I highly recommend checking out this site.
If you're into the series and just want more resources and a place to
talk about it.
It's pretty handy.
So thank you very much, everyone for joining me.
We will be back tomorrow at the same time.
11:00 a.m.
We'll be back tomorrow for a little more clean up before coming back
on Monday.
At our regular time 8:00 p.m.
So thank you very much for and I will hope.
Hopefully see you tomorrow.