Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
We are in the middle of doing our Sprite sorting.
We, you know, it's getting better.
Certainly we, you know, we did the work to put in some graph sorting
but we haven't quite gotten to the point where it's, you know, 100%
what we want.
We can certainly do a lot better than what we're doing.
Now, we've got some kind of
Is room for improvement where the sorts not working properly.
And we also just slammed in a cycle, checking piece of code at the end
of last yesterday, stream, but I didn't actually have a chance to
debug it.
So we don't even know if it works or what it's doing.
We have no idea.
Like I literally just type it in there with like we ran the program.
It didn't crash or anything.
I mean it wasn't like completely bogus or anything, but it certainly,
And we don't even really know if it's, if it's were even step through
it or anything.
So today is day 30 8 load up day, 307 source code.
If you want to follow along with me, that is where we are at today.
And I will go ahead and load handmade proj and you can see where we
left things in that is if I can type Ms.
Dev correctly into the console window you can see where we left things
here.
We kind of had, I put a second room on top there.
One thing I would potentially like to do is draw
It alleges around those boxes inside opengl.
I didn't want our sort to get have those in there.
So we didn't have to worry about it at the moment, but it's hard to
see things of the same color stacked on top of each other.
So one thing we could do if we wanted to at least temporarily and we
can get rid of this later is it would be nice to outline just by
default those solid, rectangles temporarily and that's really easy for
us to do because in the opengl renderer, when we come through here,
when we see that, we have a rectangle, right?
Right?
We can do a rectangle vertices because you remember, we have the
opengl, oops, that's not gonna do anything for us.
Remember, we have up here, the opengl line vertices call, right?
And we can go ahead and pass the rectangle to that.
And that'll I put those vertices.
So if I want to, I can do a line.
That kind of goes around it and I can do that in whatever color.
I don't know.
Black seems fine for now.
So, oops.
That's a good type.
Oh yeah.
So in theory, well, in theory, I would have been able to draw a line
there.
What did I do?
Open jewelry.
Tangle texture is disabled.
We set the color to 0001.
We're drawing lines were passing the line vertices down that should
have been okay, right?
Render entry rectangle.
I feel like that should have been fine entry, dim, and entry P.
What are we?
That should outline that correctly.
Am I wrong about that?
Oh,
No, because we do GL.
Begin triangles inside are open.
Jill rectangle.
So this would have begin and end for triangles.
This is our g, l began, and then pair for lines.
So I feel like that should have been fine.
Certainly, if it works down here I would have thought because this is
how we draw all of our bounds in the other case as well.
So I would have thought that would have been fine but I'm not seeing
any of those show up and I'm not exactly sure.
Why, because they should we don't have a z-buffer turned off like
that.
So, if I draw them in this order, meaning, you know, I draw the
rectangle first, and then I draw the lines, there shouldn't be any,
you know, depth, sorting or anything like that.
So I should always see the line show up and we kind of know that it
does that it
that it does do that because for example, before we were doing this
Right?
And we can see all of our, you know, because this is our debug overlay
that would show us our different sorting groups, right?
And we can see that all of our line drawing works just fine there.
So I'm not exactly sure why we're not able to see our lines drawn in
this case, whereas we are able to see our lines drawn in the other
case because the only thing that's different that I know of is that
you know, texture 2D gets disabled once down here and then off you go,
but texture 2D is disabled inside the
Go drawing as well.
So I should think that we would be able to do the line vertices here
when we do the Jill begin GL, a for Lions, just inside of it, right?
That seems like that should be fine.
But at the same time, I don't see it happening.
So, that's a little bit odd.
I've been remember we have GL 1 + GL.
One, minus cos Alpha.
So, as long as the source self is one, we can draw black or should be
able to draw black.
So the fact that
At this is a all zeros as long as this is one that should still draw
black in there.
I mean, I guess I can double-check to make sure that I'm not doing
something stupid in that case, but I wouldn't assume so yeah.
But again, so I'm expecting to see those lines and not seeing those
lines and I'm not sure why not.
So, the first thing I would want to do here is I want to know whether
there's something wrong with you know, which part of this is wrong.
Basically, I would like to know if my
Realign vertices or like what, you know, maybe what I'm passing it is
wrong, or something like this.
I should double-check what opengl rectangle is doing it, doesn't it
just draws these directly so, you know, you can see that there's
nothing particularly weird in there.
So, in theory, if I just passed the Min and the max P that I was
passing up here, it should draw to see whether that's the case.
I just want to see whether there's anything obviously, stupid going on
here.
Like, if I just draw a line, you know, that
It's kind of an obvious diagonal line, do I see it?
You know, does that show up anywhere?
Right?
And so, you know, there's my line and immediately, it seems like
something is amiss because I specifically set the color right to 0001
and yet, it's not doing that color at all.
So, I must be doing something relatively stupid, right and I'm not
sure exactly what that is.
Suppose, it could be a texture thing, but I doubt it.
So, in here, we set the color ahead of time and then we draw the
lines.
Exactly the same as we're doing it here.
So I'm trying to think if there's some other thing that I'm not doing
that, I should be doing, but I don't think so.
Like, it feels like that should be okay.
But yeah, if we're drawing with GL color I don't see why that would be
a problem.
At all.
Let's double-check.
Yeah, so I wonder I'm interested to know, does this have to be inside
the beginning?
A, it's been a long time since I use the fixed function pipeline.
All right, so I guess maybe the this is not a sticky color.
And so technically maybe this has to be in here, you know I'm saying
to you.
So, all right, I guess that's a thing.
Remembered about the fixed function pipeline?
I don't actually know if that's true.
It obviously is true on this driver, but I guess it looks like if
you're not inside a beginning, a, you can't change the color.
It's not sticky outside, which seems plausible.
I don't know.
Again, those you don't really use those when you move when you're not
in the fixed function pipeline.
So if we outline those, there we can kind of see that we've got some
interesting situations happening, right?
And so what I'm seeing is I guess, somewhat consistent, with what I
might expect to see, given our sort, and some of the problems that we
might have with that sort.
And it does mean, I probably want to revisit our sort criteria
But when you can kind of see if you just look cursorily at this is it
does kind of look to me.
Like Z Sprites are at least sort incorrectly amongst themselves,
right?
So you can see that we've got
The room above us here.
Those little plates that we drew, those are sorting correctly, and if
I come up here, right, you can see those moving as I go.
And now, I'm on that sort of that top room, right?
And I don't see a lot of errors in those sorts.
However, as soon as the why Sprites are introduced here, right?
You do see you can see those kind of bugs happening as we introduce
why Sprites that overlap the Z Sprite.
It's which suggests to me that you know are sort algorithm may
actually be fine and we might just have a bug in the store comparison,
right?
So you know that's just what I'm thinking.
That's where my head's at going into it just to kind of give you a
little perspective of just the feeling that I've got on it.
Now I don't want to dive into that just yet and the reason is because
I want to get our cycle check working we don't know if our cycle check
us working right now and that's just a piece of information that I
want to have, right?
I would like to
Know if we have a proper cycle detection.
And one way I could do that is create a case where I know it has a
cycle and then watch to see if it works.
But before we do any of that, I'm just going to look at the code
because we kind of slammed it in there.
I don't really know if it's right, I don't even know if my algorithm
was right.
I just kind of did it really quickly at the end of the stream and I
kind of want to see what's going on.
So if you remember correctly, what we did here is we said okay you
know we're going to Loop over all of the bounds that we have, right?
Every everything that we saw
Sorted on.
And everything that we sorted on if it had a Sprite cycle, right?
So if that was set in the flags, then we're going to draw it, but
otherwise, we're not going to drive.
So right now we're not drawing anything, you know, if I look at this,
we're not we're not drawing any of those debug lines, right?
The only thing we're drawing is the actual I mean.
Yeah, these are debug plates where the floor would, because we didn't.
We don't have an art pack for it yet.
But it's not part of the sort debugging, right?
And so the question is well you know, did the Sprite cycle just never
get set because there weren't any Cycles or did the Sprite cycle?
Never Get Set because we don't we didn't write the algorithm, right,
right.
We don't know.
We could have bugs.
It could be there could be a theoretical error in what I did and so we
have to now go and see whether I've done it correctly.
I try to make an answer, you know, try to ascertain, whether it's
whether it's proper.
So the way that I did that, if you remember is we have this notion of,
you know, the walking the Sprite graph, and you can see that when we
do walk, the Sprite graph.
What we do is we say, well, every time we start looking at a node, we
set the hit cycle to false.
So there's basically a, it's not Global in terms of.
It's not a global variable but it's Global to
An individual.
So we've got this.
This thing that will be passed to all of the recursive calling here
and it will be set to true if we ever hit a cycle.
So we start that false and then we do our recursive from
Is it supposed to be called from to back?
I think it's supposed to be called recursive front to back.
Isn't it?
But wouldn't do we just have a complete typo that we never noticed?
Am I Wrong?
How come nobody has mentioned this the entire time, right?
It's recursive front to back.
Isn't it?
I'm just going to say that it was supposed to be recursive front to
back and you guys can correct me later.
If it turns out that I had a good reason for that, but I don't think
so.
That just looks like a typo.
All right, so anyway, we go into recursive front to back on a
particular node and we check to see whether or not we've ever visited
that node before.
If we have visited that note before, we don't, we don't enter the if,
right?
So we start off by just saying, well, if we've already visited this
guy, we don't need to visit him again.
Well, and so, there you go.
And so that's a bug.
Right there, right?
So because we will set the visited flag, we will never actually do the
walk cycle chuck, if that makes sense.
So, this was kind of a typo, what we want to do is this, right?
We want to say, okay, if there was a cycle set on the guy, we're going
to look at then, we've hit a cycle for sure.
Now, even if we said, we already visited him that we don't want to
not,
not do that.
Check.
Because the whole point is, of course his, if we find a cycle, of
course, he's visited, will be, chat will be set.
That's the whole point of a cycle is that we've already visited and
that's what that would mean.
Right?
So we need to set that outside.
Then we can check to see whether or not it's been visited.
If it hasn't been visited we can come in here and or in the the visit
in the the the cycle.
Go through all the edges and recursively call and then on the walk
out, we can remove the cycle if it turns out that
We haven't hit one on the way down.
All right, so we definitely had a bug.
And that's fine.
And so, okay, so now what we can see, as we sort of come through here,
is that we definitely did have some Cycles right like that saying
every time something lights up on the screen.
It's basically saying that we did have a cycle of some kind, you know
I'm saying?
And it's a little weird to have them but I guess it's just when you
overlap enough stuff.
I mean either we've got a bug which you know is always possible,
Right?
With something of this complexity.
just started working with, we could easily have a book but either we
have a bug
Or there's just, you know, very unusual times when we when this or
sort of starts to happen but, you know, you can kind of see that
things get pulled into the cycle.
Very dramatically there.
As like all of those things are getting pulled into the cycle and yet
it's kind of crazy because like here, nothing is in a cycle.
Apparently, unless we've got a bug but here,
Right in the middle.
There there is.
It seems unlikely.
That that would be true.
I feel like that just indicates.
We probably have another bug.
I mean, I don't know obviously until we look at into a little bit
further but it seems a little unlikely that that I could get into, you
know, there is a cycle and there is not a cycle, you know, is that
really realistic and maybe it is?
I don't know, maybe you have to overlap the bottom row before the
You know, something that overlaps the trees and if you're not, then
you can't and you know that's you know, it's not impossible that that
would be true.
It's just I feel like you know, what are the chances?
It seems like it's probably more likely to be a bug than than that
that's actually the truth.
But anyway, at least now we've got that, that particular bug out of
the way.
And yeah.
So there we go.
Now.
What I would like to start off by doing is I would like to start off
by going back to a simpler version of what's on the screen.
Because if you remember, we sort of have two rooms stacked on top of
each other because we were just kind of playing with the sorts.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to go back to the simpler case
where when I when I add standard room I'm just going to add one room.
So there's only one actual, excuse me.
There's only one actual room in this game, and I want to see what
happens with Cycles in this case.
Okay.
So in this case, when we only have one room, we are getting no Cycles.
Okay, there we go.
So this is where it thinks there was a cycle right in between those
two.
Is there any place I can stand and get a cycle or is it only as IHOP?
That's unfortunate.
It would be nice if I could.
Well, you know what though?
Of course it's a little bit difficult to do.
Oh that's interesting.
So as my little rectangle is capable of creating these sort of Cycles
as well, apparently
Bizarre.
Yeah, that just that seems
A buggy to me.
I'm going to have to go ahead and say that.
I don't think it's particularly likely that the cycle check is
operating properly, but you know, who knows.
Famous last words, right?
So, what I was going to say is we can I don't remember simulation.
Yeah, simulation time step I can kind of bring that down a bit.
All right.
So now I'll move in extreme slow motion.
And we should be able to see when that.
Yes, you can kind of see that when that happens there.
And it's really odd.
You know, I just I just hopefully you can see why I'm a little
incredulous about why that in particular would be.
Somehow the important part like that creates a cycle and everything
else wasn't creating a cycle.
It's a big cycle to, right?
I suppose I could pause as well.
Right.
We've got a pause.
I don't really remember how it works.
It might just be pee.
That is less than useful people.
That is less than useful.
We don't draw while we're paused.
Are you kidding me?
Who wrote this game?
Yeah, that's not great.
Anyway, point being we probably want a better pause in that, you know,
I mean, let's face it.
That does seem likely, I feel like when we pause, we would just draw
the old.
Like, if we had a clue nowadays, we just draw the old render list from
the previous time through.
That would be smart.
Of course, we're not apparently smart, but that's okay.
But yeah, so point being, when I jump over here and it's only on the
transition jump, it looks like that cycle extends through everybody,
right?
That that cycle extends to to like, every last
Part of the screen, it goes all the way around and that's just really,
that's just really bizarre.
So let's take a look here.
I'm going to go ahead, I kind of want to get a little bit better feel
before I start to do some debugging on this.
I'm just trying to get a little bit better, feel for what I believe is
actually happening.
Not sure.
I'm drawing.
The best things.
For this yet.
Like I'm not sure whether I should be drawing something different than
what I'm drawing at the moment.
You know, maybe maybe not if I could think of some better things to
draw I would but I'm not sure I had a I know what to draw yet.
So I'm going to try doing something here where I draw the cycle
colors.
A little bit more aggressively.
In fact, you know what I might do is say I'm going to draw very light
groups and then I'm going to increase their Alpha dramatically when
there is a cycle.
So I can kind of see a little bit better.
I don't know if that'll work or not.
Oh, and you know what?
We're in premultiplied Alpha mode.
So we're going to have to do
At the end of this, we're going to have to do.
We're going to have to be multiplied in order to get that to work out,
obviously.
All right.
So that's a little confusing, right?
Because according to that, there's the according to that, there's a
cycle on the outside there, or at least it seems that way.
Let me, let me double-check
Right, I mean that looks like that, saying there's no cycle on the
interior.
Right.
You can kind of see that this is all faint and that's all faint at the
moment.
Ah, okay, so it's my little.
Yeah, it's my little entity selection thing that's making that happen.
Okay?
So, according to this, we've got a bunch of sort groups, none of those
sort groups are actually doing anything at the moment, they're all
like well-behaved, right?
And then in theory, I hop up on here and I get a I got a splat
that just blinks just me.
Except occasionally like the one right here, blinks everybody.
Right.
That's what I'm seeing.
Hmm.
You know.
I have a.
Question.
That just kind of popped into my head.
Regarding how we're doing the Sorting in the first place.
And it occurred to me.
That with the actual Sprites.
Like, you know what I'm talking about?
Like these guys here.
I'm kind of wondering.
Separate from the Sorting stuff that were working on now.
If we treat everything as a z Sprite, does it just work?
Do you know what I'm asking?
Like, we've been doing all of this work because we're sort of,
thinking of like, well, there's two kinds of Sprites, there's upright
Sprites and there's, you know, Flats rights.
But is that really true with the actual person?
Correct?
Correct perspective, art.
Like, if we just said that there's like a couple levels of Z, there's
the ground Z, then there's the Z of the body and then there's the Z of
the head and they're just slices this way and all Sprites are stacked,
there's never a Sprite
That is actually considered to be why?
Does that just work?
I would admit to feeling very stupid.
if that did just work, because
Then we've essentially built a bunch of stuff that we don't need at
all.
Just because we didn't quite understand.
What the trick was for wood, could be right.
I don't think so.
I think we still have the problem because even if there's only even if
you're like this, you're still going to have the why stacking problem.
I think.
To D's is I don't like 2D.
That's all I have to say.
I never think in 2D very well.
I think it's just too much of 3D programming.
I never have a good intuition for it.
Like I'm sure probably what I just said, isn't true.
Like it's probably like, nope.
If you had Z's, it wouldn't work.
Like you can't just sort by Z sort.
By why?
Because I thought we went over that like, we have that in there and
that didn't seem to work, right?
But now it's kind of like well, I don't really
Know what the case was.
I probably should have taken more careful notes on that and didn't
like well here's why we don't think that would work.
Right.
But sometimes I wonder whether that was based on the fact that I was
sort of thinking of it or looking at the screen and thinking there is
a more dramatic sort of perspective than there.
Actually will be in practice if that makes sense.
But anyway,
That's neither here nor there.
Okay, so let let me just put that aside temporarily.
Oh, there we go.
There's a nice place.
So it looks like
Unfortunately, that's that's all that's that's only if I have my mouse
cursor over it never mind.
I thought I was going to get a nice place where I could stand and have
a cycle but I guess not.
So one thing I could do and I might do is just make it so that when we
detect a cycle, I could stop and pause on that.
So we could actually debug and look and see if we believe there
actually is a cycle in this case because I don't actually know if
there is or not.
Now it's possible its
Is sort of somewhat plausible to me looking at at the besides the fact
that the ring around the screen is flashing.
It is somewhat plausible to me that we could get during the hopping
here, weird things happening because right now, we're kind of we're
probably penetrating through the ground like having the, why Sprite
sticking through the Z Sprite or something like this?
In a way, that doesn't make a lot of sense.
And so I could see that being the case.
But it's that I don't really understand that.
Flash there.
I don't understand why we're getting that ring.
You know how that's getting pulled in is a little bit of a mystery to
me.
And that's the only reason that I'm at the moment.
A little concerned and thinking that we have a bug or something.
I'm also wondering about those.
It seems like these this thing creates Cycles.
Everywhere it goes, right?
Like I go on here, you know, here is a place where the guy standing.
I put the thing under there and now the group definitely has a cycle.
Now that might just be because those guys are all overlapping
themselves and that's probably true.
Like, you know, if I do this
Like if you look at what that actually is, it's four rectangles that
actually overlap each other, right?
A little bit on the corners, so, you know, yeah.
Okay.
That probably is enough to create a cycle.
So, so, maybe that that makes some sense.
I could probably take care of that without too much trouble, right?
Oops.
I didn't mean to close that.
Going to close this.
I could probably stop that from happening.
by when we actually do our render pushing here,
when we push wrecked outline, for some reason, we do sort of a
thickness of weird,
This thing here and it seems like we should be able to make that not
happen.
Exactly.
So we do our offset and we do we do our push back there, we've got our
thickness as our Dimension and so that thickness is is going to come
out from the center.
So if we wanted to displace the rectangle to the side properly, you
know, all we should, I would think have to do is put the thickness
inside.
Our offset, right?
So if we just said like, you know, I want to go, you know, half
thickness away and I guess
Actually what I want to do is be a little more concerned about that.
So if we take a look at what's actually happening here, so these are
the top and bottom ones.
And so if I want these to be completely non intersecting, I need to
draw this today.
I need to draw.
So it looks like that, right?
And so when I'm drawing the top and the bottom, I want to start inside
a little bit, right?
I want to start halfway.
And now of course, if you look where this is actually a subtracted
term, I'm going to change it to a positive term just so we can see it
a little more clearly here.
There we go.
And so in this case, like we're going from that - 10:30 why deposit
have to NY.
And we're going to bump over half the thickness so that our top and
our bottom should be slid into little and I just want to double-check
to see to make sure I did that.
Right because you're you know, just trying to remember and you can see
now we've got well, it's kind of hard to see.
Actually, unfortunately, so many lines, which you can see, hopefully
there that it's bumped over correctly for the top, okay, and the bomb.
So then what we want to do,
Is not draw all the way over either, right?
So the dimension of this thing, we actually want it to be - the
thickness because we're we don't want you know, we want our thing to
not overlap when we when we draw to the edge, right?
So we don't want it to be the full width.
And so now we should get it so that it's oh,
Although this is the centered rectangle, right?
So what we would want to do in that case is
Right.
I was thinking actually put the corner in there since this is a
centered rectangle.
I actually don't have to do the adjustment.
I just have to make sure that we don't make it go that way.
that with it'll, if the fact that it's centered will automatically
make it,
Keep its boundary.
All right,
so that's all good.
And now I just have to extend the other ones out so that they will
cover.
The part that we're not drawing.
So instead of just Dimension why we need to do to mention y, plus
thickness but that's all we should actually have to do and then I
could restore the way that this was working before.
If I wanted to run, I can do this because it turns out of don't
actually need to do what I was doing.
All right.
So now we've got it so that we're actually drawing that so that
they're not overlapping.
The only problem is when we do overlapping we're probably doing an
overlapping check that accounts.
If you have you know things that end start and end on the same line.
And so, what I want to do here is go over to our sort and I want to
see in rectangles intersect
Actually, I guess it's in here.
There's an overlap, what is it?
That's rectangles intersect.
So I want to look at rectangles intersect and I want to see yes you
can see that we are using strictly inclusive intersection all the way
around and for sorting I think we want to allow our rectangles to a
but and not consider them intersecting for this case, right?
So what I actually want here is I do want, I guess I should say make
one of these rectangles intersect intersect open or something like
this like open interval.
So in this case, where we have less than or equal to S before I want
to make it so that we we have one of those sides be open.
So we can say, you know, if the max in X is less than the minindex,
not not if it's equal to
Two.
Well, we draw this out for you.
Okay so currently what are we doing in our existing rectangles
intersect routine, right?
We're checking to see whether the max is less than the Min.
So you know here is a
And what we're trying to say is, well, okay, is the maximum of be less
than the minimum of a right?
So you know, if
if here was be
We're trying to see whether my Max X is less than or equal to this
one.
and it looks like what we decided to do, probably, because it's the
guess is the
Thing to do is we decided to check to see whether it wasn't
intersecting and then if it wasn't intersecting will not, we'll figure
out whether it was intersecting.
And if it's not we will not that to get the result for whether it is
intersecting, right?
So let's check whether the min
Whether the Min is greater than equal to the Max and consider that
non-intersecting, I guess.
So what's interesting to me about that is in that case, rectangles
that are right next to each other, in theory, shouldn't
Should not actually have had a problem.
Now, it could just be that we don't have the floating point, it could
just be the floating Point math.
For those rectangles since they're being computed as Center
difference, rectangles, it could be that they're just overlapping just
a little bit, right?
And if that's the case, then you know, that's why this is doing it.
But this is a non-inclusive one.
It actually, if two things are right on the edge, it actually doesn't
consider them intersecting.
So it actually already is doing what I wanted.
Do I think which means that if we wanted these to not be intersecting,
we would have to make it so that they were just a little bit.
There was like a, at least an epsilon's worth of some kind.
To prevent them from intersecting.
You know, it would be something where we would, let me just make sure
that this actually works.
So, I do we don't have some other bug here.
It could be that that it actually is okay, and it's something else
that's happening, but no, there you go.
So, if I just give it a little bit of an Epsilon, you can see that.
Now, when I move it, it doesn't create a cycle.
So it does look like the thing that was creating the cycle.
Was just the fact that having those outlines basically creating a loop
around with themselves, is enough to make a cycle.
And now,
Are no Cycles when I do that.
And so that's all good.
And since that's only a debugging thing that we use that for any way,
it seems to me.
Like, that's fine to leave it like that.
And, and off, we go.
All right, but that still brings us back to the other question, which
is, why are we getting a cycle in some of these other situations?
And, you know, I guess, I guess when I look at what's happening on the
screen, it does seem at least a little bit coherent in the sense,
that, if you look at moving sort of back-and-forth here, right?
As I am, when I, when I am down here,
I am not part of the group that's in those top trees, but when I get
up here, I am, right?
So, it actually does think of that as being part, and I guess I'm not
sure like, I'm trying, I'm trying to see what is making me part of
that.
I guess it's the heads.
No, it's the Torso Sprite.
I'm guessing it's the Torso, Sprite.
But it's really kind of hard to.
See ya, I guess the Tarsus, right?
And again, it's really confusing to the eye because right now we don't
have Sprites that have tight bounds around them.
So that you know those those Sprites are huge.
We also aren't taking into account access scaling, which we should
probably do right about now.
Anyway,
But anyway, so the question is, why are we actually getting a cycle
there?
It does seem like I have maybe a little more confidence in our cycle,
a grow them at the moment because so far, everything I've looked at
now.
So this is holding up to scrutiny.
Like does actually make some sense, I'll be honest, that's a little
weird.
I guess that's just cause it's kind of still faint.
You can't see it.
I guess it's just changing color so that's okay.
Yeah.
So I would like to have a little more Assurance of why we're getting
that and I'm guessing that that's just because the Sprite is
interpenetrating, the stairs at that point, which creates the cycle
but I'm not 100% sure.
You know, I'm saying to you.
So yeah, so the question now is, you know,
couple things.
One I'm relatively happy with this because at least at the moment,
this is sort of doing what I wanted to do because don't forget, we're
actually not we're probably not going to throw multiple rooms at the
Sprites order because they're going to be sorted into separate drawing
planes.
Anyway, I suspect right because we've got, we've got some work to do
there.
It just in terms of how we want to fade them in and out, and that sort
of thing.
So, you know, I'm not too worried about that actually.
But what concerns me slightly more is just there's a couple things
with the Sprite sorting that doesn't seem to make good sense to me.
Like, for example, if you look at what's going on now the fact that
the head is sorting in front of this tile here doesn't make perfect
intuitive sense to me.
Hmm.
Because I feel like it should be behind it.
And to be honest, I feel like the head should actually be be behind
all of these guys and maybe I'm wrong about that.
Maybe we have our Z value.
Set in a really wonky way, but you know why?
The hero would be in front of those stairs?
I'm not 100% sure.
And so I would like to take a look at that because that just looks
that looks like an error.
Because I didn't think the head was that high up that
It was actually floating at a level, that would be above those stairs.
Now, this isn't actually a problem we'll have in practice because
we're not using the X Y displacement in practice.
And so part of the problem I suppose here is we should actually move
those things now.
So that they're not having that scaling happen, they're not having
that X by saying those should all be right in line with their existing
locations at the
Should be Z elevated.
I mean why elevated or moved up the screen but not to the side.
So yeah, I guess that when I'm not sure I'll but some other things
that I would note, it does seem hard to get this to do the wrong thing
with the Y Sprites together and that's pretty great you know?
I'm happy about that.
Certainly
Like nothing seems to be happening to weird here, and that's good.
But the thing that does concern me a little bit.
Is like, for example, it looks like y Sprites sort above Z Sprites, no
matter what like these these Sprites should be huge.
Like, these things should be out in the stratosphere and yet they
don't seem to be right, like, this should be, this should be above any
Sprite.
Like there shouldn't be a way for it to sort and
In some other way and yet somehow it's not, I don't understand that.
So I don't understand why the debunk is that way.
Furthermore, why is the debug text even just two lines of debug text
itself, right?
The drop shadow is sorting behind the actual text.
And so, I feel like there's something wrong with our Z.
Sorting you just in general, right?
Like like if you even forget the part about the, why Sprites and
The Z Sprites interacting in an odd way.
Even if we just look at the Z Sprites by themselves, it appears that
we've got some kind of weird sorting issue and I don't know exactly
what it is.
And it's especially odd, just because thinking about what we're
seeing, when I turn on an additional room, those Z Sprites all do seem
to sort above other Z Sprites, so it doesn't seem to always be the
case that these rights are sorted in correctly.
Only most of the time or I don't know.
So that's really, really odd.
So what I would like to do here and I don't know how feasible this is,
but I do have 15 minutes left so I feel like it can't be too
infeasible is if I go and turn off like everything, right?
So you know if I'm if I'm like here, right?
The only thing on the screen is the text.
That's it.
So if I were to change that to something that only Drew one letter, I
should have only two like totals rights on the screen, and I should be
able to step through the routine pretty clearly and see if I believe
what's happening makes any sense.
Or if there's some kind of obvious bug in there that doesn't write,
and what are we?
What do we drawn up there?
Let me strike and search for it.
16 milliseconds.
Epd
So I think it's this line that we're talking about here.
So if I just were to temporarily make it and
Set it to H4 handmade hero.
Then at this point in theory, there's just one thing being drawn.
So let's let's see what we can see.
Like I said, I'm at this point.
I just want to kind of look for something that will guide me towards
how I want to proceed in the debugging process because they don't have
a solid idea yet of exactly how I want to pursue to pursue it, right?
But creating simple test cases.
Seems like a good plan.
So let's take a look at what happens here at sort entries.
Here we are running.
Now, we've only got the H.
So what we should see is that there should be two things, we got
three.
So let's see what those three actually are.
What is the problem?
Why ain't you showing me my stuff's?
All right, so you're telling me I got three things.
That's what you claim.
I don't actually know what those three things are, but hopefully we
will find out.
So it looks like we've got well, you know what, I could also see what
well, you know, I guess we don't really need to.
Let's see what they actually, what we do with the drawing here.
So we're going to start out by sorting A and B against each other.
Well actually seeing, if they intersect, I should say,
So let's take a look.
We've Got A and B I guess we knew that they were input node 0 and and
one there.
But let's do it this way.
We're looking at a and b and here we've got the oh,
you know what?
I just remembered I wonder if that's because that information is going
through the sort bias path and the sort bias path.
Maybe doesn't do anything.
Anymore.
Seems pretty likely.
Yeah, I bet that's exactly what happened.
I bet that's exactly what happened.
So, what we probably need to do here is go, okay.
Inside render group, we're not using the sort of bias anymore, are we?
Nope.
No, we're not.
So when we actually do our, our rendering here, like our push wrecked,
and that sort of stuff.
When we do, our get Bound for, we're going to need to use that.
That sort bias, right?
We do get Bound for our Z.
Max probably should have
that added into it, right?
Let's see.
Okay, so now we at least have the things that we're using sort bias.
Now, those are at least
Restored in theory.
Let's see if that's true.
If we open it up a little bit,
Okay, so that's all nice and clean now.
Huh, it's funny to look at the sort groups.
So much stuff.
The poor build Sprite graph.
I tell you computer.
Sure are fast though.
It's kind of amazing when you write algorithms, then computers just
crank through hundreds of millions of, you know, permutations of
something like that.
So it does look fairly true at the moment that our Z Sprites are
sorting against each other correctly.
Now, when there are only Z Sprites because that's what we're looking
at here and now our sort is not messed up, right?
So, that's a good thing to some degree.
I do wonder about the alignment of some of these guys looking at their
bounding rectangles looks a little wrong.
That might be because we're not doing some of the scaling stuff
properly yet but
all right, so
At least that's one thing down.
We still have another thing though.
Which is that when we come in here and we've got y Sprites in the mix,
well, it doesn't work, right?
So those why Sprites are still sorting above the Z Sprites, despite
the fact that the Z Sprites are supposed to be like hugely
Serve and that might be an aspect of our sort rule, but that may mean
that are sort rule needs to get improved, right?
So let's take a look at what our sort rule actually is because it's
been a while since we did that.
And let's just see if maybe this doesn't make as much sense as we
thought it would.
So, in this case, we know that the both Z Sprites case works at least
amongst, you know, in its of itself, right?
So it works for its own purposes.
In the case where we're doing something else, we've got our a includes
b or B includes a.
And basically what we're saying there is we're going to sort by the Z
value of these two things.
If they are included, right?
But if they're not included, then we're going to sort by the Y.
So presumably what we're seeing here is that neither a nor B includes
the other.
And so we sort by the Y and of course, if
Sort those two by the why.
Well, it doesn't matter how much Z there is on one of these people.
It's, you know, which are Whoever has the earlier position in y is
going to win.
That's, that's obviously, common sense.
so, I think
It is actually just our sort rule that is the problem at this point
because we don't it doesn't look like the algorithm is failing to
actually enforce the sort rule.
It looks like the sort rule itself is just a little bit bogus and so
you know,
Considering this.
I guess the, what we were sort of talking about here is
Well, there's a couple things.
First of all, we wrote this rule before taking into account.
The fact that we knew that they overlapped in screen space.
So we know that they overlap the two things that were checking overlap
in screen space already which means I'm not super sure what the a
includes B&B includes a really is meant to do here because and
furthermore I'm not sure how that's ever
Failing.
Are we just setting the y-min and y-max to be just wrong?
Because that's probably the case.
But if you look at that, the a includes BB includes a nonsense.
Really, I'm not sure.
I guess the idea is that the Z Sprites themselves
Have a lineman in the Y Max.
But the wise Sprites don't have a Wyman in a WiMAX there at a single
y, right?
So in theory, yes.
So I guess in theory that does mean that it's eminently possible.
And probably the case we're getting now that I think about it.
It's okay because I mean or knots, okay?
But it wasn't illogical because if we have a z Sprite and I guess I
always am,
Challenged at how to draw these out because we're talking about a sort
of pseudo 3D thing.
But if I have a z Sprite,
And I have a wife Sprite that's sanding on that sea Sprite, then it's
eminently possible that if we looked at it from the top down, you
could have a situation like this, right where this is where the why
Sprite is actually standing it extends up to here, which does make
them overlap in screen space.
But if you look at it from the side, wouldn't look like this.
It would look like this.
Which is to say that they don't actually it's not inclusive in that
case.
Right.
So I think what that means is that we
We don't necessarily have a bug.
Pretty much anywhere at this point.
This is exactly what we would expect to happen and it would be correct
for the single room stuff that we want to do.
We don't have the concept in a single room that something can be on
top of something else Z wise in that way, right?
Because even in this case over here, where it looks like we do, we
would never actually have that case because this thing would be
Where's my mouse cursor?
This thing would have to be right here.
Right?
So I don't know.
We may actually be at the point where if we just started slicing these
into layers, right?
Where we had a layer for each room level, right?
And then we had a layer for the debug information, and we could, by
the way, turn off sorting because we don't need sorting on that,
right?
Or we could use the other sorting.
We may actually be in.
Okay, shape here.
I don't know.
We may not actually have any immediate bugs at the moment now, that
doesn't mean we're going to find any as we add more stuff, but it does
seem like it's looking positive.
Just let's say I do miss, I miss our snake and floaty head people.
So I kind of feel like they maybe want to come back in.
Because we turned them off oversimplifying things but I feel like
maybe now might be might be a good time.
In a world.
Where there's a snake and some monsters and a familiar who pisses
everyone off by following them around.
I don't know, man.
Starting to look kind of good starting to be good.
I mean Chris, I have an ulterior motive here to get all of this stuff
working because Anna's art pack is looking so darn cool.
That I really want to put it in the game.
She made like this dungeon area and there's a whole bunch of Orphans
now for the orphanage and it's just it's cool.
So that's going to be fun.
All right.
All right, let's go to the Q&A for now because I think we may be sort
of getting to the point where the sort is actually pretty reasonable.
And I think maybe we want to go do the layer stuff now and then see
with the layers.
Plus the Sorting are we at the point where we're kind of comfortable
put moving forwards on things?
We do have to do some optimization.
We don't think we want to leave that N squared in there even though
it's running plenty fast at the moment.
I just that that's not going to be great.
So we probably want to do something to kind of level level eyes that
But yeah.
In sohbat.
Yes, the Torso spray a casing does draw on top of the head Sprite, but
that's expected.
So what we have to do now that we actually have a coherent sorting
plan is well, there's two things we have to do and I probably will
wait till after the art pack to do them.
But the first thing is we have to have actual real Sprite bounds for
the Torso in that stuff.
So that has happened.
But the other thing we have to do is I think we
want to just add rules for sorting this because right now, the only
way that's working is by tweaking,
Z values.
They're all actually, it's completely Bogus the way that spread is
constructed.
They're all actually the same place Sprite wise.
So it's just like, oh, you know, here's the, the, this bright and
there's another Sprite right on top of it.
That looks like that and another spray it right on top of it, that
looks like that and they're all in exactly the same place what we
would rather do right is we want those to actually just be Sprites
that look like this because then I think they would all sort properly
all the time but
Even if they don't.
We don't really want to deal with this anyway because this is a
semantic.
Like we don't actually want the head to move.
How should I say this?
If this is the body and the head is moving around, on top of it, we
want the head to always be above the body.
So we probably want a rule that just says, that's always true, if that
makes sense.
So I don't even know that we want to let make the sort actually have
to deal with that in the first place.
This Collision work between stairs and hero.
Right now.
Collision is turned off for basically any, there are no Collision.
Well, you know what?
We just drove her.
There are no Collision, there's no Collision anything on on the
round tiles.
Where, where are you?
So do you see those blue?
You see the blue rectangle there?
Blue, rectangles are Collision right now.
And you can see that there's blue rectangles All Around The Ring of
trees, right?
But yeah, but that's, that's all there is at the moment.
The don't ask me why that's drawing where it's drawing.
That seems kind of weird.
I think we may have a that code.
Maybe a little bit stale at this point, unfortunately.
Oh, I see it's because it's actually hovering up above, it's actually
higher.
Yeah, this is going to be nice to get all this is easy stuff cleaned
up.
Now, we can go back in there and once we finish the layer section
where we were right in the middle of doing the layer stuff, and we
decided we needed the Sorting to work properly.
So we did that.
But yeah.
So the only thing that currently can Collide is the trees and the
hero.
That's one thing that has a nickel.
Geometry and that's probably going to stay kind of like that.
Just remember, we're mostly going to be using the sort of square
occupation stuff to prevent you from moving.
So the way that I keep the head from going through things will
probably be moral.
I don't know if that'll really be Collision based as opposed to just
you can't move the head towards something where there it's not open
like you can't move past the halfway point if you couldn't hop, there
is probably how we'll do it.
I do.
Don't so Collision.
I think may end up being something that's more about
Like like, projectiles hitting you or things like that and less about
movement because the movement is des kind of discrete now.
Now, you know, and I but I don't know it's hard to say
Do you anticipate similar, if not identical graph, sorting would be
used for any other game purpose other than Sprite sort?
I mean, maybe some World Jen stuff.
Could maybe use it?
I probably not identical.
Honestly you know could be cut and paste this and then change it
around a bit and make it into something.
Probably, will we be pulling it out as a reusable component?
I am guessing that probably nothing will use it quite this way, but I
suspect that world generation will do some graph-based stuff, just not
this.
Let's see.
Let's look at on, have any other specific questions?
So I'll take some of the nonsti questions.
What language is this?
This is a C++ and we use mostly C the C subset of C plus plus we don't
use a whole lot of actual C++.
So it's a it's kind of a, it's an old.
It's kind of old school in that sense.
This style of programming is not 100% old school.
It's a bit new school in a couple of ways.
And obviously we, you know, we use the resources of the machine.
We're not trying to make like a fork.
A demo kind of old school sort of thing.
Well, of course, 4K demos.
Now, use the GPU and stuff like that, so, that's separate, I guess.
But, you know what I mean.
So, you know, it's a hybrid of old-school, new-school, kind of
programming, but it's definitely kind of old-school.
Language-wise, we're not using an
Interpreter or Garbage Collection or any of those sorts of things.
so,
What are a few pieces of advice you would give to a new programmer?
Yeah, I would say that what Rome said program program program
practices key.
I would say that programming a lot is really what it's about and
there's lots of ways to get better but you know, the Corwin is to
always be programming.
And, you know, always ask how something works, why something works the
way it does, you know, dig in, learn how things actually work.
Don't just try to get things working.
Try to figure out why they're working and you know program, you know,
if you start out in a language like basic or you know, JavaScript or
something, that's very high level.
And you don't necessarily know what's going on, you know, which is
where everyone starts.
I mean, most people don't start programming in c.
I don't think, you know, challenge yourself to move past that into
more low-level languages, learn some learn, some C programming
eventually, learn some Assembly Language programming, you know, like
Learn about how the computer actually works.
And how programming actually works.
Not just, oh, I put these libraries together and something happened,
you know, because regardless of what you actually do, when you go to
make, you know, when you, when you go to work, the education process,
I think has helped immensely by always digging in and saying, what
should I, you know, what should I be doing here?
I should be.
I should be trying to figure out how stuff is working.
at a core level in not just being satisfied, when something seems to
kind of work, and then I move on, you know,
And I'd also say, oh, he's never stopped asking yourself.
How you could have written code better or what?
What are the reasons why the code?
You just wrote wasn't as good as it could be or what are the reasons,
why the code you wrote had to be written that way in this language,
you know, ask yourself, is there a better way the language could have
done that?
You know, be aware of those things and try to push yourself for words
and so it's really just a lot of practice and always having that
mindset of like, asking why
I figure out why things work and always trying to push yourself for
words instead of just being satisfied that you kind of got something
working or whatever, you know, never let that be enough.
Always try to keep pushing yourself to learn more and
And be more and more knowledgeable about how things are actually
happening.
What is your time estimate?
Or sorry, what is your estimate time?
It will take you to finish a maid here.
And how is it different from your original estimate?
My original estimate was like, 600 days, which I accidentally said
would take two years, but that's obviously not true.
Because it's 600 days is more way, more than two years actually,
because we only do five days a week, right?
And we take some time off.
So, you know, it's probably more like three years or something like
this to actually do the 600.
But my original estimate was saying like, 600 days.
Unfortunately, I don't have any idea if that's accurate or not.
I mean it's just a complete Ball Park.
I have no reason for suspecting that I just thought that might be
roughly correct.
And, you know, I don't know.
I don't know how long things will take.
I also don't know how, you know, we have some control over what the
scope of the game is, you know, the game engine programming, I think
is winding down.
We don't have a lot more stuff that we need to do.
So I think that will easily get finished with in the 600 day window.
The question is, how much time is the game programming?
Like just program implementing game features, right?
You know, is that 100 days, 200 days?
300 days, 400 Days, 500 Days, who knows?
And so if that turns out to be 300, 300, 300, 200 to 300 days,
then I think we would probably finish around my estimate.
Maybe will be 50 days over a hundred days over, if it turns out that
that's wildly off, that's to take way more than 300 days.
And of course, days is weird.
We mean ours, right?
Because we do an hour a day, but so hours.
So 6:00 was the estimate.
You know, how close we do that?
I have no idea.
Once we have more of the game up and running.
You know, maybe 100 days from now.
Let's say when we kind of have a game probably, because we're at the
point where, you know, you can hop around and do stuff, and the engine
does all the things it needs to do and you could start making the game
part of the game.
Now, if you wanted to, there's a couple more things I would like to do
first but, you know, once we decide, yeah, we're done with that and
now we're just pretty much implementing like monster types and World
Jen whatever.
I think then we'll have a more realistic.
Estimate, right.
Will be like how long do we think you know, to get enough content to
this game?
That we think it's reasonable because I would like to do some
expansion packs the game and stuff like that as well.
So I don't I don't need everything to be in the first version of it,
right.
I would like to do kind of a thing where you know the game ships on
steam or whatever and
Or whenever we sort of say, like, here's an actual playable version
that we want people to play.
I would probably want to then ship, you know, add-ons to it.
They wouldn't necessarily be paid add-ons.
But just I would like it to have some some of that sort of.
Oh I played the game for a while and then oh cool.
There's an update that like added some stuff, you know.
I'd like to have that happen as well.
So we have some flexibility in like deciding what needs to be in
there.
But obviously like we want the game to be fun and interesting in its
initial shipment.
So there's a you can't just arbitrarily say like well whatever we have
it 600 days, that's what ships we would want to make sure there's at
least enough in there too.
To make it engaging game.
And, you know, there's a certain I think minimum set of elements and
minimum number of sort of different monsters, different area types or
whatever to make that happen.
Room says, off topic at the start of the show.
You said that every game, programmer, use the dev setup similar to
what we use debug with Visual Studio, but code with a different
editor.
Why?
I don't know why.
All I know is that Visual Studio is really the only debugger for
Windows that works at all.
I mean, there's really just not many options out there.
I wish there were more, you know, I really wish there was and maybe,
you know, some people in the handmade development community,
I've been working on some debugger stuff and so maybe someday we'll
get it to bugger.
We can use and so we don't have to use Visual Studio more and that
would be great.
But for the moment, it's really the only viable de vulgar for game
style code.
It's the only one you would really use there really isn't anything
else that's, that's better in a measurable way than it for that sort
of thing.
But you know it's editor is not necessarily everyone's cup of tea.
There's a number of reasons why you might not want to use the editor
and visual studio.
And so some people do use the editor visual studio, and that's fine.
And then other people use an external editor,
And the reason for that is just because the editor in Visual Studio
isn't clearly the most useful editor that you can currently get, you
know, there's plenty of people who would argue all day and night long
about we know you got a program in VI or you got to use emacs or you
got to use sublime or you got to use Source Insider, I don't know.
And so everyone has their preference on that and there is no clear
consensus that it's the easiest thing to use for debugging.
I'm sorry, there is no clear consensus.
That it's the best Editor to use.
There is a pretty clear consensus that there aren't really any
available at debugger options that are better at the moment.
So I think that's largely what it comes from.
If there were more good to buggers out there, I think that it wouldn't
look like this very long.
I don't think most people are all that happy with the visual studio
debugger.
I just don't think they have a lot of options.
I know I certainly don't like it.
If there was a better better to better out there.
I'd switch in a heartbeat but there just isn't
Philadelphia, are you enjoying this project as a programming challenge
or are your efforts, mainly put into the teaching part of it?
The latter really?
Not not because I don't think there's plenty of things you could find
that are challenging about making a 2-D game because really it's only
the 2D part that's you know any different from a 3D game.
It's only the graphical part.
Like the there's plenty of all the game code and all that stuff.
You could still do.
And you know, you could our pipeline stuff is there's plenty of places
you could look for to do interesting programming work regardless of
whether games 2D or 3D, certainly
But at only an hour and night I kind of have to stick to things.
I mostly am not going to push myself really hard on.
And the reason for that is that if I'm pushing myself really hard on
something,
It's, I can't, I can't talk through it, really.
I need a lot of, like, concentrated mental energy to, like, focus on
the problem.
And so just I don't think it would be feasible for me to solve a very
hard challenging programming problem on the stream.
Like something as simple as a 2d sorting stuff takes a while on the
stream and it's hard for me to work through much harder, probably,
than it would have been if I just had to do it by myself when I'm
regularly programming, right?
And so, you know, that's it, just
I have to be scoped in a, in that way, but I like programming in
general, I don't have to be challenged to enjoy programming.
So, so, you know, just because I don't feel like handmade Heroes going
to evolve a lot of challenging things per se.
Like, in that sense, I still enjoy programming it.
And similarly, like there are things in it that I haven't done before
and I've done things in different ways.
He's on handmade hero than I've done before so it's so it's still
interesting in exploratory sense as well.
All right, let's see.
I think we got one more question here.
What do you think about unit testing and test driven development?
We get this question so often.
It's the weirdest thing I guess unit testing and test driven
development must be like this fad that everyone is into these days or
something.
I'll say the same answer I said every time every programming
methodology is a trade-off and it's based on trade-offs.
And so the answer to whether unit testing and test driven development,
are a good idea, has nothing to do with whether you're using C++, it
has nothing to do whether your games or web.
It has nothing to do with any of that.
It is simply whether or not you think the time it takes you to make
the tests.
Is more or less than you?
Think it would take you.
To debug the code without the tests.
Right?
And so there's it's like every other programming methodology, you're
trying to get your trying to ship a product of a certain quality with
a certain feature set in the shortest amount of time that you can
write.
Nobody wants to take more time than necessary to produce whatever
they're producing, right?
And so when you look at something like test-driven development, you
have to ask yourself if I was to make a test for this thing.
How many bugs could I find with it?
Like, how easy is it to make a test?
That could find the bugs for this?
How long will it take me to make the test?
And how long would it be for me to find or know like, like would I
even know the bugs were there without this test?
And if I would then how long would it take me to find them without the
test, right?
That's what you need to be thinking about in your head because if the
answer is that the test will not take very long to write.
And we'll probably find bugs.
That would be hard to find any other way.
Sounds like a very good idea, right?
If the answer is, well, the only thing is we can really test are not
actually, the kinds of bugs were all that worried about, then it
becomes not such a good idea because now you're just wasting time
making test.
Making yourself feel like you wrote better code, but you really
haven't, you haven't really gone after the bugs that are going to
cause you the problems, right?
And so what this means when you, you know, when you sort of
extrapolate it,
Is that depending on exactly what you happen to be writing, whether
this is a good idea is going to be very different, right?
If you have code that can be tested, very specifically, like, we know
what the inputs and outputs to this should be.
Then that may be a really good case for test-driven development, but
one of the reasons why in games, there's only certain things we can we
can apply tester and go into that makes sense.
Our because a lot of the stuff is like ethereal user-based stuff.
It's like some particles were supposed to spawn out of this guy.
When he got punched in, they were supposed to look like blood, did
they?
Well you're not going to write a unit test for that, right?
The monster isn't attacking me.
As often as I thought he should you're not going to already you test
for that either, right?
And so one of the reasons why you will, you know, and like I said, it
doesn't matter what kind of code you're writing.
The mindset should always be the same but one of the reasons why you
won't see on average as much unit testing in a game, environment is
because a lot of the outputs from game code aren't inherently testable
yet.
You know, and so that's really what it ends up being.
Whereas sometimes, you know, maybe you see it more in the web world
and maybe, you know, it doesn't mean that game people are stupid or
whatever.
We are stupider that someone's making a bad decision.
Like I said, the mindset should always be the same but what you may
find is like, well, okay in the web World, we've got a lot of things
that are like, take some text in and spit some text out, and we have
an exact idea of what those things should be.
Well, that's something where maybe it's like, okay, you know, we could
unit test that it probably wouldn't take too long to build.
That's an easy thing to run regression tests.
Annika, that makes some sense, right?
So there you go and to give you a little more perspective on that,
like I do write unit tests for things sometimes.
And for example, when I worked at Red game tools I had a unit test or
that I made for my, for granny, for the 3D character animation
package.
And the, you know, what are the reasons for that is again that
equation?
So show is on your head.
Am I getting bang for the buck here, right?
Am I?
Is this a good idea?
Am I going to save time and energy by doing a thing?
And the answer is, well,
Okay, maybe this code that I'm writing.
Wouldn't actually benefit from unit testing.
If all I was doing is using it in my game, but in that situation, I
was writing code, that's used in thousands of games, right?
And so at that point, I'm not there running at the, you know, person
who's using this technology, I'm not there helping them, you know,
debug it on their machine.
I'm not there, I'm not in a situation to make that trade-off really.
As soon as this code goes out the door, I can't find anymore but
They have to find the bugs and send them back to me.
And so at that point because that's a much more costly debugging
process.
All of a sudden now it's like things I might never have written a new
test before suddenly it becomes very beneficial to write a unit test
because now I am saving time, I'm saving them time, I'm saving myself
time having to remotely find these bugs, right?
And so that equation should always be in your head where you're going,
am I making a good development decision, for whatever the Horizon is.
That I can see for what I'm working on, and it's always going to be a
trade-off there, where you have to make a good decision and if you
ever get locked into things, like I always write unit tests or I never
write unit tests or whatever.
You're almost certainly doing it wrong because the answer is almost
always more flexible than that and I have a hard time.
I strongly suspect that there is no discipline where unit testing is
always the debugging.
Answer
That's always the right choice.
You know.
And so, you know, that I think is the Fairly complete answer to that
question.
Should probably excerpt that.
So, I can just point somebody at it.
Every time they ask that question because that's the answer doesn't
change.
And I would also add that.
This is not specific to unit testing.
You could take what I just said, you really, that's the mindset to
everything, right?
And any development practice you use, I've talked about const before
this way, right?
Like I don't, well, it's not even feel.
I know, concept doesn't find any bugs for me, right?
It's like maybe finds a bug, you know, it could find a bug once in
every six months or something at best.
It never finds about for me.
My data coding.
I think we've had maybe two in all of handmade hero that maybe would
have been found by const.
And they took me a second to find, like I found them like immediately.
Right?
So I just know that when I program I generally don't get any value out
of constant so I know that I just shouldn't use it.
It's just, it's a waste of time if I put that in my code, right?
But, you know, not everyone codes the way I code.
So there may be people out there who always make cos mistakes.
Did that not?
Because they're bad programmer, because you see me make mistakes all
the time, right?
Every stream, I'm making mistakes.
It's about what kind of mistakes you make, right?
And so if
Look at some other programmer.
Maybe that's the mistake.
They always make.
There's a bunch of mistakes that I make that they don't make right.
But then that mistake, they make all the time.
And so, at that point again, it's that equations in your head for me,
cos is a waste of time.
I would just, I'm literally just wasting my time ever typing it in.
But for somebody else, it might be a great time-saver.
It might be that that catches bugs to them every day.
Right?
And so, you can't even say from one programmer to the other what you
should be doing because it dry
Changes and similarly, let's say I'm working with someone who has that
problem.
Well now it might make sense for me to put cost of my code because
when they have to use you know, if it's parts of the code that I think
they're going to use that I'm writing I got to be aware of that.
And be like okay this guy always messes up con stuff.
I should put constant here because it's going to save us all some time
because now he's not going to make those mistakes or whatever, right?
And so literally everything in programming that usually people get
very dogmatic about really it's usually more
About trade-offs, it's usually more about you know what is the
holistic situation that you're dealing with and realistically is doing
this particular thing that I'm about to do going to save time?
Holistically or am I just wasting the time to do it because it won't
actually help.
Right?
Answer that.
That's it.
Really
And in a room, I disagree on the, when working in a team that will use
your code, you need constant thing.
I don't actually think that's true.
I agree that when you're working on teams because remember, like,
working on granny was like working with the largest team in the world,
right.
Everyone had to use this Library.
It was like, you know,
When I was, there was hundreds of people and now it's thousands
people.
And what we did in that one is we just made it so that it worked both
ways.
So, it was always accepted constants in, but always allowed non
constants out.
So, it was basically like no matter whether you are cons programmer or
non constant over, you would work.
And the way that I usually approach those situations is I design the
API defensively if
I believe that the team is not going to be able to do it or there or
whatever and with Granny that's the way we did it.
Like it was very like it was a very defensively designed API in the
places where we thought it needed to be and but not in places where we
didn't contest is a very weak thing, right?
Like Costas, just saying that a piece of data can't be managed.
It's really doesn't help that much.
So if you're really worried about what how people are using something,
you kind of got to
Abbi.
You gotta go further than that, and think about how to shape the API.
So that it, it doesn't lead to mistakes, you know?
And so, so I don't really think Constance all that great pretty much
ever, to be honest with you.
But like I said, you know, everyone's should make their own trade off
there, but, you know, I'd be I'd be, I'd be cautious of believing that
there's
that there's
all that much you can do with const that you couldn't have just done
by making the API clearer, you know.
But yeah, if you're in a situation where the team is like going in and
mucking with all your code and you don't have clean delineation of
who's working on what then maybe, you know, hey, Constance something.
I still think you're in for a world of hurt.
I mean, if you don't trust someone to not get con strong, they're
going to get a lot wrong when they go, you know, like I'd be worried
about that person touching my code in general but you know what you
going to do.
And so I agree they're, you know, probably better than nothing but you
know, I think probably that point I'm a little more.
I'm a little bit worried in general.
And yes, trying to graph, actually just mentioned.
I also programmed 100% cons correct for about five years and
You know, I think it did literally nothing for me other than waste of
time.
All right, let's go ahead and
close it on out.
Okay.
Where am I hammer Hero at.
There it is.
Everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade here.
It's our pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the series at home,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and it
comes with the source code.
So you can follow along and play around.
Do your own experiments at home?
We also have a website you go to ask questions a patreon page, you can
use if you want to support our video series, a schedule bot, the
tweets is cut you, if you want to catch us live, you can subscribe to
that on Twitter and then we
Also have a an episode guide.
If you want to go catch up on stuff, that happened in the past on
handmade hero, that's about it.
I'll be back tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time, until then have fun program, everyone.
And I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.