Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we could have complete game live on stream, you know,
we had a pretty depressing discussion in the free stream.
I'm not going to lie to you.
So this is kind of going to be, like, probably the most depressing
programming stream that we've had your own handmade hero.
I feel like we should all just accept that and, and, and try to wallow
in it as much as possible today is is day 219.
one of the saddest numbers to 19, of course, was was the
I believe it was Gauss who said that it was the number that
encapsulates.
The sadness, all of human suffering and he was right.
Because, of course, he's gross and I don't know anything.
The cows was ever wrong about and so if you would like to follow along
with the Despair and tragedy of today's stream, you should unpack day,
218 source code into a directory, you should
Fertilize that directory with human tears and then you should see what
grows from it and it will probably be black roses that crumble and
Blow Away With The Wind that said, let's jump into it here we are in
the middle of the the debug system, of course, a system, which is
meant for catching problems.
So the whole point of the existence of this system is because
Was humans are so fallible and always do everything wrong.
So we're pretty much just programming right now, with the expectation,
that everything is bad and we need a system to prevent it from being
so horrible.
So, let's go ahead and and look at where we're at.
If you remember, we did our memory management stuff yesterday.
So we now can store essentially unlimited debug information as it
streams in.
And what happens is, when we run out of memory to store it, you can
basically say
How much memory you want to use for that process when we run out, it
will just recycle old memory and throwaway, sort of information that
is the oldest.
And so, that's pretty great in the same way that anything can really
be great, which is to say that it is, but a fleeting edifice that will
crumble on the force of time.
And eventually will be nothing but a corroded statue face peeking up
above the Sands its body.
destroyed in crumbling covered beneath the
desert heaves.
So like I said, that's the debug system.
So what we need to do now is start to pull everything back together.
You know, kind of like a sad child of a divorced family who just wants
some normalcy.
Again, we're just going to try and pull the pieces of our debug system
that we had made all separately.
Sort of as we were trying to figure out how we wanted it to work.
Probably, you know, sort of like an awkward teenager who is unpopular
at school and just is trying to figure out, you know, how to be
themselves and will anyone ever love them?
We're going to go ahead and try to pull this together.
Now that we have a coherent idea of how things should be stored.
So the first thing that I'd like to restore is our hierarchy, of
course, we're going to have things in a hierarchy.
Because it's easier to access things in a hierarchy, humans are used
to accessing a hierarchy but also because we really don't have any
other choice because humankind has evolved to keep things in a
hierarchy where the majority of the people are at the bottom and are
oppressed by the elements of the hierarchy that are higher up.
So let's go ahead and do that.
We have all of these events stored.
And so what we need to do now is just build some user interface
elements on top of them that will place them into this hierarchy in a
rigid caste system that does not allow them any upward Mobility
whatsoever.
Unless the user who is all powerful should reach in and Dane it to be
so and transfer them around.
So, what we want to do here is we want to say that the first time that
we see an event type right?
Because remember now we've
Events coming in from locations in the code and those, you know, like
like very brief little beacons of light in a vast Sea Of Darkness need
to sort of get coalesced into streams based on where they came from,
right.
It's kind of like, it's basically like racism.
We don't consider them individually in any way.
We are cruel and superficial and we just take it and
We say, you came from this place.
We are going to put you here, no matter what you want it to be, no
matter who you are on the inside.
We just, we just plain don't care because our souls are devoid of
compassion.
So when we get one of those events, we are putting them into these
places that we call debug elements.
So that the events kind of pile up that are all coming from that one
place.
so, what we want to do there is we want to say the first time that we
create one
Elements.
If that element had hierarchical information in it, we would like to
organize it into the hierarchy, right?
That's what we would like to do.
So I'm going to go ahead and try to make that happen.
We will probably fail because like all human endeavor, it's destined
for failure.
Shakespeare's tragedies were the true ones.
The comedies were mere fantasy.
That we could never hope to Aspire, sorry to, which we can never hope
to Aspire.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that, you know, we have these trees
obviously, and we sort of had the concept that these these trees have
those, those groups and all that sort of thing in there.
What I'm going to do is I'm just going to say that.
Let's let's make this root tree bit here.
I don't know that we actually needed to be a tree.
I'm going to go back to the concept of the route group there.
I don't think there was any real reason we needed to stop calling it
that we can just say that there's a group and
That group is there because it's not really a tree per se.
It is just a group that we build and then if a tree wishes to view
that group, it can, if it doesn't want to, it does not have to.
So let's take a look.
At that process right here for the moment.
So, we have that route group and I'm just going to create it
synthetically, like we were doing before.
I'm going to go ahead and start re-enabling those things that can
create the hierarchy.
Right?
And and so we've got you know basically everything we need here.
We just need to sort of rejuvenate it.
We need to make it sort of conform to our new system.
We need to be Pro crusties and say it doesn't really matter how these
functions may have wanted to be
What they aspire to or what their dreams are, we will place them on
the bed and saw off their limbs until they fit.
So, here is ADD variable to group and create variable group, right?
Create variable group is fairly straightforward.
I don't see any reason why create variable group, can't simply work,
the way that it was working before.
Again, a variable group, doesn't really have much in, it doesn't
really have anything other than sort of a linked list.
So I feel like that's just fine, right?
It's just this and that should be fine.
So create variable group, probably doesn't really need to be changed
in any particular way, again, these are
Static stationary things so we can go ahead and allocate them in this
way right now.
In the future.
I do think and I suppose we kind of want to start doing this as well.
I do want these to kind of be free list based so I almost want to
start making these guys freely space but I think I'm going to push
that off for just a little bit.
And in fact, we probably could push it off forever, to be honest
because we can just, you know, the amount of of interacting that the
users going to do.
With building debug States isn't really that much, you could, you
could even just leak the memory, it doesn't matter because the debug
system.
But you know, for completeness later, we may want to actually make it
properly, recycle things as it goes.
Yeah.
Like just like pretty much all of the humans on planet Earth like they
don't really care about recycling till they absolutely have to.
And they'd rather just have everything pile up in a landfill until the
Earth is completely destroyed and Barren.
So let's take a look here and variable to group.
I'm just going to
To look at how this was working.
So it looks like what we did here was we have the event stuff in that
got added.
And I think really the only change we have to make here is that now,
instead of thinking of things as having events that get added really,
what we're doing is we're adding elements.
So it's really going to be like add element to group, right?
And we're going to pass that element in.
And the element is going to be the thing that we actually set.
Like, so,
Everything else I think is pretty much the same.
There really isn't anything else that needs to happen there?
I don't think so that should be fine.
Now what I don't know is I'm not seeing anywhere here and I'm assuming
it's because we haven't implemented it yet in this in our last pass
through things.
But I'm not seeing anything here that deals with how one of these
groups could have children.
And I think, you know, this is just kind of one of those things where
it's Barren, it cannot sire a child.
Probably the only thing that it wanted was to be a parent, really?
But it was either born infertile or its mate was.
And despite what they might have wished, they will never.
Have a family, they will just have to live out their life with that
emptiness and and despair.
So let's take a look at what I would have to do to make that happen as
well.
Because here with create variable group and you can see that what it
does is it creates a variable group that does not have a parent.
It does not have children, right?
There is no.
Yeah, right?
It is essentially, it is both an orphan and and baron, it is both of
those things.
So, very
A difficult life.
Rather tragic.
Actually, if you think about it it is it is sort of both the Alpha and
the Omega and that sense it neither has a past nor Future.
IT exists only for a brief moment.
And then all trace of existence is gone and it's life is meaningless.
So let's let's see if there's something that we can do about that
because when we create a variable group, we're going to want to be
able to create a variable group underneath that variable group.
That's how we get a hierarchy, right?
We need to have children in the variable groups in order to make that
happen.
So when we create a variable group, I'm thinking that maybe we would
want to pass something in like, you know, do you have a parent who
You were expecting to be a part of, right?
Like are you, are you expecting to be a part of it?
Frank.
And so I'm just looking at how this would have gone inside, debug
variable group, we've got this tplot variable like this essential,
right?
It kind of comes through and you add these in here and if we just look
to see whether there's a group that needs to have children.
So when we do add element to group,
It's going to do this stuff here.
As you can see.
Go ahead and dive in there.
It's going to go do this stuff here, but we probably also want the
ability to do ad group to group, right?
We presumably want the ability to do ad group to group like so, so we
can go ahead and get
All that in here.
So this would be the same thing.
We'd add a link, we would insert the link, but in this time, we
wouldn't insert it into the 08.
And we would insert it into the group, Sentinel whatever group were
going, we then would set the link up.
But this time we would, we would do the opposite of what we're doing
here.
We would set the children to be children here.
So this is I guess I should say.
Group.
And then we would really not need to do any of that stuff.
That's this is all meaningless.
In fact, it started as well.
So that's all that is.
I'm trying to think whether this is the, is this, did we already vet
this structure properly?
The fact that there's a pointer this is this is sort of like a, you
know, it can either have a group or it can have a set of elements.
I mean, or can have an element that seems reasonable
But I would point out something here.
That strikes me as a little bit odd, which is that if you have a debug
variable group and there's a children pointer, I don't see any place
you can where you get, you know the name, right?
So you know, we've got these
We've got these hierarchies now if we wanted to but there is no way to
know what it was.
So I feel like this here, you know, I feel like you'd normally have
some kind of a name that this group would have and I suppose it's just
goes to show you how you know dehumanizing we really are when we just
don't even care what as far as we're concerned you just have an
address we just have a number you're nothing but a number in a system
and
We don't care about you, we don't care about your individuality as far
as we're concerned.
You're just here to serve the purpose for which you were created and
there is no, there's no real soul to you, we are uninterested in that.
So let's take a look.
Here.
So we've got this is this would be parent, I suppose.
So, let's take a look here.
So parents Sentinel and here, I think probably we would want to do
parent as well.
Just to be clear about what's happening there.
That seems reasonable to me.
Go ahead and compile that so that all compiles relatively well.
And, and I think that's mostly everything.
We would need at least to start adding things and creating groups now.
Unfortunately, like I said, we still need one more piece.
Piece of the puzzle which is that we need ways of figuring out where
in the hierarchy things should go.
And so we need to do that part as well, which we will do in a second,
but for the moment,
I create variable, I think it's something that we don't ever need
because we're always just going to be adding elements at the moment.
So I feel like that's and it's all code.
That kind of irrelevant for what we were used to be doing as far as I
can tell as well.
I don't see really any part of that that needs to stay.
So I'm just going to get rid of that as well.
We have free variable group, that's not implemented yet and that's
fine.
We can leave that there and and still leave it as not.
Wanted, should we ever free one of these?
You know, we'll get that and we'll go do it.
And I think this is both not relevant anymore.
And so really, the only thing that we need to deal with now is this
and it's still actually the sort of the the correct thing to do this
correct call we just never implement it, right?
Because we were sort of busy with other things.
So that's really the part that will have to do to finally make things
work.
Let me double check your
You're what we were doing by just sort of doing the same thing we were
doing before and having a temporary sort of thing.
Like that and then we'll focus on implementing this guy.
It won't be particularly hard.
It just took be a bit of typing.
Okay.
So that's what we've got so far.
And so, what I want to do now is I just want to actually start calling
these guys in the appropriate places.
So, you know, we've got when we create our debug State at the
beginning, right?
We've got our sort of initialized tips, that's spelled wrong.
And so in here, when we initialize everything, we're going to want to
do, you know what this is interesting?
We still want any of this stuff.
I don't know if you still wind stuff, but at the outset, obviously,
we're going to want to do something where we take that route group,
And we actually create a variable group there, right?
And if I go in to create variable group and I look at it, pretty much
all I need to do is pass that debug State, and that'll go.
So now I've got a route group and that's ready to go.
So, now I should be able to
This up and I should be able to add things hierarchically into this
group and be good to go, right?
So let's take a look at Co ladybug records.
And if we look at store events, I think that's where all the magic
would happen when we go to store an event.
When we hope.
Sorry, not story, bang.
It's actually get element from event right here.
When we go to get an element from an event, you can see that when we
get to a time when we see an event for the first time that comes from
something, we didn't understand, you can see us kind of getting it
here where we're like, oh right, we didn't know where this was from.
We need to create one and put it in the hash table.
That's the time when we now want to do the hierarchical look up.
Now, the thing that I don't really know here,
Is we sort of introduced the system that was based on underscores for
finding these.
Not all of our stuff necessarily follows that the moment and we kind
of have that block pain thing.
So what I'm going to do for now because I'm just going to say let's
just treat everything the same way and we'll see what happens and then
we'll kind of go through and think about it a little bit more as we
start to integrate the other parts in.
So what happens here is we're in a situation where we
Received an event.
We know that are that are
Our code has this block named thing and we know at least at the moment
that block name was what we want to use to file it.
Now we might remove it and which case we'll just always use grid to
file to do a filing.
But then we would also have to think about how we want to do grids to
actually create the hierarchy.
So
we definitely have some thinking to do.
And I think there's probably some stuff we need to do that, you know,
to fix a few things that are that probably want to be fixed as we get
this going and specifically that would be that while our debug value
what we call them are well our debug variables, all have those little
names when we gave them like, you know, ground chunks underscore
checkerboard or whatever.
Well, those make sense, the other things like, where we were dumping
debug data, we probably want that all to use the same unified concept,
but it won't be and just, you know, again.
So, you know, kind of what I'm thinking about and we're on the same
page, you're not like, what's he saying?
You remember, we have like this stuff here where we can say, like
begin data block and you can see this thing and then we sort of push
out all these values, right?
So, what I'm saying is that these
Youse are all coming from locations in the code that are bracketed by
this data.
Block thing, we probably want them filed under a data block.
That's created in this in this thing, right?
That's probably how we would want them to go.
You I wise and so we're probably going to have to once we get this
working, do a little bit more in terms of just like thinking about how
we want to produce the hierarchical structure of these things.
In order to make it do what we actually wanted to do.
So I'm just going to start by doing the basic version but I think
we're going to want to level it up a little bit to get the really
good.
Sweet action.
Don't know why.
We would be getting sweet action on a day.
That's all about depression and failure.
But sometimes there is a brief, you know, a slight ray of sunshine
peeks through the clouds before being squashed and choked by the
swirling Darkness.
So let's let's go ahead and take a look at that when I go here and
find a result for the first time when that's not there anymore.
What I want to do is I want to do is that get harp goal, you know, get
whatever that, whatever that was.
Yeah, it's group for hierarchical name, that's what I want to do.
So I want to to place the sky in the hierarchy.
So what I want to do is say all right, so I want to find its parent
group.
And I'm going to do that by passing that name in which is the block
name, that's going to.
Give me the group that I feel like this guy should be at to, which
this guy should be added sorry, tranquilo tongue twister there and so
then all I'm going to do at that point is I'm just going to add it,
right?
I'm just going to say.
All right, I've got the element.
So now I'm going to add that element in like so I guess I don't
actually need to store
Swing for any particular reason, I'm going to add that into the where
the palate parent group is and that's it, right?
And that's really all I wanted to do if that's not a result event.
That's really all I wanted to do, right?
And I'm going to go ahead and again, Force the drawing of this thing
which I believe groups like we were doing before us.
So we can see what we're creating as we as we create it.
So we can start to get our little hierarchical placement thing working
properly.
Of course, I don't remember where any of that code is but you know,
sometimes you just don't remember.
Running the code is
Deal.
So let's take a look.
I believe it's.
Here we go.
It's right in here.
So when we're doing this tree group here, again, what I can do is just
do the same thing that I was doing before where I could just say, like
you know what,
Do we ever create?
The tree.
Can't we just create a tree down here and make that tree.
Always point to our route group?
That seems like the easiest way to get started.
So it's not.
It doesn't have to be hacky.
We kept hacking it in there, but there's really no need for that.
Where's the tree?
Yeah, here we go.
Perfect.
So now I believe oh that was not what I was expecting.
It looks like there's things in our hierarchy that we don't know how
to draw, which I suppose is understandable, because now we're adding
just about everything in there, but we want to be able to handle that.
So we should probably go ahead and make sure it says and we started a
whole half-hour late today, so this five-minute warning is completely
meaningless.
Just like
Existence, so let's see.
Here we have debug event to text.
We're passing this event.
I don't want locals, I want my watch window.
So let's take a look at what the event actually is.
Here it is.
We've got a type of 6.
So let's take a look at what that event type means.
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 so that's just a marked debug value.
And so we can easily again make make make a our system handle that.
And we probably just should there's no sense in not doing it.
So here we have debug event to text which I believe is where we were.
We were flailing before.
I'm just going to go ahead and make this print that out anyway.
And in fact I feel like what we could
You as well is just do something like this where we actually just do
you know?
That which I see which I feel like is totally reasonable.
And what we would pass there is just that block name
You know I'm saying.
So I'm just going to let that go for now and we'll see, we'll see what
we get.
So, let's continue on here.
I don't actually know, I'm kind of surprised that all that stuff
worked just without us, actually doing anything.
That's kind of amusing.
You know, sometimes in, even in the depths of Despair, some little
tiny thing goes your way.
And the important thing to remember is not to let that go to your
head.
Things are still absolutely.
As bad as you thought they were and a minor Victory is no reason to
change your highly pessimistic outlook on the inevitability of human
suffering.
So,
Let's take a look here at what we've actually.
One thing that's a little bit strange to me, is I realize, I'm not
actually seeing any of our debug variables, and I don't know why, I'm
not seeing any of our debug variables, if I would have expected to see
some of our debug variables, but I guess I am not internalizing
correctly, how those things flow through the system because I'm seeing
all of our debug data showing up, but not our debug variables, which
is a little bit off right now that maybe because we don't print them
out.
Like I don't know if we
Them intentionally or something like this, that's certainly possible.
But I want to be able to see them so I want to go ahead and see why
we're not getting those first before I do anything else.
So, here is debug event to text.
Well, here's debug dropping menu.
So here we go.
When we switch on the IDS, it looks like it tries to print out just
about everything besides the bitmap ID and the counter thread list.
So in theory, I think that anything that was there
Should presumably be handled through the system.
So, I feel like that means that we must not be adding them at all, if
that makes sense.
And I'm not sure why we wouldn't be adding them, because it feels like
are pretty much everything should be added, right?
When we do Co ladybug records, pretty much everything that's in the
debug stream.
I feel like should be getting processed right here, right?
And so it seems to me that all of those debug values should also.
So be happening that way.
Now, let's take a look.
So I feel that's, yeah, I don't know why.
I don't know why that wouldn't be happening.
So there's begin block, end block, copa-data block, close data block,
I don't know, I don't know why.
We wouldn't be getting that.
So I think I might want to take a look at that because event type Mark
debug value.
That is.
And we even know that that was coming through because we even cat a
request to print one out, right?
In fact, that's this one.
Is it not?
So we know that at least, one, debug value is getting hit, but for
some reason, it has no block name.
So things things are a little wonky, right?
Things are a little bit strange.
So, I'm going to take a look at what's coming through, Mark, debug
value.
I think that's what I want to do.
You know?
I mean, again, like what I want to do is just cry, I want to just weep
openly.
I want to break down in tears.
I want to
Just give up and let the Horrors.
The world.
Continue unabated but instead what I'm going to do is set a breakpoint
on Mark debug value.
So let's take a look at which ones we're getting here.
We are getting.
So the block name is set to 0 so I guess I must just not set the block
names for some reason but we're getting code handmade, debug interface
of H2, 93.
So that's
That's a bummer right, I think because that's not what we actually
would probably want to have happen.
And so I think I know I think I can see exactly what's going on here
and that's, that's a bummer.
So what's happening is because we call debug initialized value here,
everything
Is going to come from the same location, the code is going to come
right here.
So I think with that implies is that we would somehow have to make
everything happen in a macro there or at the very least, we have to
have
You know, we have to have this this part right here.
We have would have to have it generate a different grid.
Now, what we could do is use the name for the grid.
Right, that would work this.
Would presumably work.
Oops.
At least that's my that's my assertion.
I don't actually know but that's my assertion and hey it does and you
can kind of see that happening there but what that also means is that
we probably want to store the block name in this event as well.
There we go.
Wait a minute but I just did a vent grid equals grid.
What is the grid that's getting past their?
Oh so that was just a straight up that was just we had already thought
of that and we just kind of failed.
So all right.
That's actually not so bad.
So here is a slightly more reasonable version of this.
Although I'm not sure.
I also see exactly why this is looking the way it is, but at least
we're getting more of the variables that we thought we were going to
get.
Now.
Like I said, the unhandled thing there.
What's going on there?
I want to see what is happening.
Why are we getting
Stuff before the unhandled, right?
You can kind of see here that we're getting a bunch of information
before the unhandled and I guess that's because we're actually
printing out
We must be doing the add name here where we're printing out, whatever
the name is of this guy, right?
The event block name.
We're printing out here so I guess that's why we're seeing two of
them.
But anyway, we can deal with that a little bit later.
So, this actually.
Now, when we look at it, you can kind of see that we now at least know
that we're getting the data that we expect to be getting here is all
our debug variables.
And so now what we want to do is organize these into a hierarchy,
right?
and,
In order to do this, what we want to do again is like dissect that
name that comes in and use the underscore to tell us how the hierarchy
should be self-assembling, right?
That was what we decided to do.
For those of you who don't remember what we decided was 0, because we
want these things to sort of work and compile out and do those sorts
of things.
We had stuff, like, debug, if simulation you space at lines, we just
built the hierarchy into the name.
So underscore is essentially.
Like a slash almost that like says that you know, simulation is the
group it's under and used space outlines is the you know is the actual
value.
That's what that is right?
So now we just need some way of actually parsing that and you know
doing the right thing.
In order to do that, we can just go to our get group for harp go name
instead of always returning the route group.
We now just need to actually look at the name and return a group that
is actually correct, right?
So let's do that.
The first thing we want to do is we want to take a look at this name
and we want to, I think scan the name for that underscore, right?
So we probably want to do something like
First underscore equals 0 and then we want to do you know something
like car stars and equals name scan is valid plus plus can so just run
through the string like so?
And then I think what we want to do is say all right.
excuse me, if the the value
Is the underscore?
I'm going to set first underscore to scan and then I'm going to break,
right?
So we're just running through the screen, the string and finding the
first underscore that we see there.
And once we have that first underscore, we sort of know, we sort of
have a bracketed region that is the the substring if you will.
That's the first sort of hierarchical group under under which we
should place this guy.
so, what we want to do here is say, well,
The first underscore actually was valid, then we know there is a
hierarchical Miss to this thing.
If it's not then there's nothing there's no more hierarchy to do.
So we would just want to insert the thing into whatever its parent
was.
So I think we want to do something like this.
And so we would want to say, like okay, debug variable group result,
just equals whatever the parent is, the thing passed in, right?
And then what we'd want to do is say if there is a first underscore,
we keep going, otherwise we just return the result because if we
didn't find underscore we don't need to do any more work
hierarchically.
If we found that underscore, then what we want to do.
Say okay, we now need to see whether or not a group already exists
for, you know, underneath this parent that I can file the sky in and
if it doesn't, I need to create one.
So I need to do something like, get or create group with name or
something like this, right?
And that's just going to be okay.
I know it's going to be first underscore - name, that's how long the
group name is.
Is, I know it's under this parent.
And I know it starts here so I'm just passing them, the substring and
saying I need you to give me that group, right?
That that you found when I get that group this is like the subgroup
that we should be filed under.
Then I'm just going to say like okay the result I can just call myself
again, right?
I can recur ass down here and say like you know what?
Now let's just take the next part of the name.
So first underscore R plus 1, take that next part of the name and keep
going.
Right.
Just just keep going.
And that should do everything I needed to do.
So as long as I can do this operation.
Oops.
As long as I can do this operation somehow.
I should be fine.
The only kicker is that I don't have a null terminated name anymore.
I have a name that has a particular length to it, right?
Which is generally how I prefer to do strings anyway, but it's not how
we generally do swings on handmade hero because we don't really do
that much with strings.
So, it's not that big a deal.
But anyway, what we want to do here is we just want to search through
the parent to see whether or not we can find something that has the
same name.
So I just all I need to do here is I just need to Loop through that
that sort of list.
And remember, get group for heart girl, named is not a performance
critical function in any way.
So we don't really have to worry too much about
The only happens sort of when debug things are first coming in.
And then once the hierarchy set up, it never does this anymore because
it's only actually activates, what it sees, a new debug location, come
through that, it's never seen before.
That's the only time this stuff even gets called.
So even in the kind of the debug system, it's not even performance
critical.
Never mind the fact that the whole thing is also in the debug system.
So it's super doesn't matter at all which is kind of nice because it
means we don't have to do anything fancy or be too concerned about
what happens.
He's here.
So what we want to do is we want to Loop over these debug links.
Right?
And that's going to go by taking whatever that parent is, we're going
to do to me.
We've got a parent group, we want to take the Sentinel and we want to
look at its next pointer, right?
We're going to go until we hit the essential again and we're just
going to change.
So all we want to do is say, if the name matches on these guys, then
we found it.
And we're good.
Pretty straightforward there.
Otherwise we have to create a new one.
So we don't really know what this quite is yet.
We'll deal with that in one second.
But again, we do know what happens here.
If we don't have one of these, then we just need to create one, right?
So we need to create our little group here.
And then we also want to add ad group to group.
So again, pretty straightforward there, but the problem is we don't
have any way of doing this and you'll notice like, I sort of foretold
this like a grim prophecy where the world ends and everyone dies.
I said this day would come and like all prophecies that foretell the
end times.
Of course, it comes true right?
On schedule.
And debug variable group does not currently have a name.
It needs one because without a name, we can never create a hierarchy
and we can't even we couldn't even display one if we did have it,
right?
We just have a bunch of pluses that we expand that don't actually have
names.
That's hardly very useful.
So I think we want to say here that
Going to do that.
So now that we have a way of storing those names in there and using
them.
So what I'd like to do is say that when we call create variable group,
we passed the name length in the name and it stores it.
And then, that way, we can now also do a string compare to see whether
the names match
And other things of this nature.
So the first thing we want to do is say, does the link is the link a
group thing and if it is does it match.
So we would want to say length strings are equal or something like
this and we would want to pass.
Okay, link children named length, link, children name and name, length
name.
Like so.
That's pretty much all we would need to do there.
We would need to do and create variable group.
We would want to do something like this where we just have name length
and name.
And so when we initialize one of these we give it a name.
And off you go.
So strings are equal.
We haven't written yet.
Create variable group.
Identifiers are not found.
That's probably because we need this to be in a slightly different
place.
So we need all these guys.
It's guys need to move.
Doot doot, doot do do doot up here except
And this is a, you 32 trust me.
My strings will never be more than 4 million characters long.
If they are more than 4 million characters long, I think we would have
a hard time displaying them on the screen, I can tell you that, so
let's see, get group for hierarchical.
Okay, so the first time we call get group for hierarchical name,
obviously, it's a recursive function now so we need to start it off
with the route group.
So it knows that it's kind of, at the base of the hierarchy.
So, that's easy enough.
And and then, of course, this one.
Well, you know, what I could call it root
I wanted to.
That's about it.
Okay, so I think all we need to do now is Implement a strings are
equal?
I don't remember where strings are equal was we wrote one for just the
regular string compare but I don't remember where I put it, okay, we
put it right here.
So what I need to do is I need to make a string compare that that uses
lengths, instead of null termination.
And so that's just like,
This sort of a thing.
And just we can even make it so that this can compare strings that
happen to be as long as can fit in memory.
There's not a particular reason not to do it, so we easily could do
it.
We might as well.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to say that the result
is probably going to be equal to.
Well I guess a equals B is a fine.
Is a reasonable enough thing to set it.
I'm not sure why we did that way originally but
I think what?
She want to do is say if a length equals B length, then we know that
we actually, you know, have something to work with here, otherwise the
result is false.
So I think probably that's what I would start with.
I'd say the lengths have to be equal, so if that is true, then we can
continue.
Right?
So assuming those links are equal, we can do something like this.
Okay, where we say all right?
Index, equals zero, index is less than a length and we know that the
lengths are equal if we're in this at all, right.
I mean, I'm basically saying, hey, if the lengths are equal, then
obviously, the strings aren't equal because they're different lengths.
So duh?
Right then I'm saying, all right, Loop over the a length because since
they're equal now a length or be lengths, are the same value, we don't
have to care.
So we Loop over both of them, right?
And I guess what I would say is,
Are we would just go result assume true.
And if anything doesn't match, we set to false and break.
All right, so what I do here is say if a index is not equal to B and
X, then we're done.
Okay, so that's roughly where we're at now.
This is not quite going to work for us at the moment.
If I am correct because what, we debug drug main menu, we don't
actually have any way at the moment of drawing, like the actual group
headers, right?
I mean, we didn't really do that and this code is kind of
All weird and wonky but so you can see we're kind of coming through
here.
We're looping over things and we say like okay when we get to one of
these things, we say debug variable and here is the link, we say
dipping a get event from link, but it might have been a group, right?
It might have been a group, so you can see that it's doing if link
children kind of a thing here, right?
So if event is not a particularly
that's,
I don't really know what we want to do about that because we want sort
of the ability to do either or right.
So I think probably what we want to do is say something more like
up front, we want to say like you know, if the link has children
Then we're going to process it in a hierarchical way, right?
And I think since both of these use we could use the link like so I
think we could just do this.
well, I guess we can always just
Man.
Makes sense.
Right?
So if we are going to do the one, you know, if it's a if it's a group
we handle it and if it's not a group, we don't kind of a thing.
We do the other path.
So yeah.
So if I want to do that, I'm trying to think about what I would need
to do here.
It looks, I think I can just go ahead and do basically this exact same
path for now.
Just to get us, get into a place where we can do stuff.
So let me
Do that effectively, right?
We don't want to do debug event to text.
In fact, when we do debug text out,
it would be nice if debugs text out, let me just see how debug text
that worked.
I'm interested to know it would have been nice if we had made it so
that we could have passed in length, strings, right?
It would have been nice if we could just pass the length of a string
and have that do it because, you know, when it actually outputs text,
there's no reason this couldn't be a, an index Loop here as well,
right?
So, that's a little bit unfortunate to say the least, but that's okay.
I'll get over it.
This can be crappy for now since we're kind of in the middle of other
things, I don't really mind.
So I'll just say all right link children named length is less than R.
I can't text.
Which it's always going to be but just want to make sure that we're
sort of asserting on our crappy code.
And then what I want to do is I want to just kind of copy into that
text buffer.
So I'm just going to I'm going to literally just do this.
Where I take the name length and I copy into that text buffer.
Whatever the name was.
And I should probably say plus one because I need space for the null
Terminator as well.
And that does this whole situation and I don't actually know, I feel
like we had code for doing groups before but I don't really remember
what we ended up doing with it so I'm not sure.
So for the moment, like where's the thing?
I guess.
Like, where's the thing that tracks?
The depth is the depth is here, so I guess that's fine.
I don't know though.
We may have to go remember how this code worked so that we can
actually restore our processing.
Of it.
Yeah.
And I guess that at the moment can be can be gone.
So, item color, I don't really know what that was doing before.
So it's an is hot sort of a thing, okay?
So that's all good.
I'm actually do it this way.
I feel like we have this code before but we must have kind of gotten
rid of it at some point.
All right, so actually amusingly that work.
The first time, which this is supposed to be a stream about deep
depression.
And so I'm not really sure how to take that other than to be extremely
depressed about the fact that it worked the first time.
But you can kind of see.
Now, we've got our
Our Harkey simulation.
And put simulation over there.
We have ai familiar.
It did two levels.
They're like, just like it should have done render a camera, do the
same thing so, that, that totally self-assembled exactly the way that
we would have wanted it to.
So, that's actually exactly what we wanted.
So, yeah.
Okay, so we now, just want to kind of go in there.
Presumably and actually do something where we will allow you to
Expand and collapse in which we already had sore.
Just restoring our old code that we had working for that matter,
right?
That's really all we need to do to get that happening.
So I'll go ahead and I'll go ahead and do that.
How much time do we have left?
Let's dream.
Only about 7 minutes but that might be enough time to make that
happen.
We'll see.
Okay.
So yeah again I think that this code could be sand to be cleaned up a
little bit.
That's certainly true but we can do that next week that's all good and
let's see here.
So what the problem is that we eliminated the place where group
expansion and collapsing is stored.
I believe.
Oh no, we didn't.
We still have it in debug you.
That's where that is.
So really all we have to do is reinstate that code where we don't
actually know if we accidentally deleted it all or what happened to
it.
Here we go.
So here it's got the expanded stuff happening there so so yeah, we're
pretty close looks like and and here is yeah.
So so I think, I think really all we need to do is this
and say, you know, the iteration,
Is going to be based on The View.
Right, and we will do that.
Push if necessary, write this code is to janky the way that this
iterates over things.
I don't, I don't really like, to be completely honest with you and
yeah, because like it's got link here.
It processes, linked it then, does Interlink equals everything.
Yeah.
I don't like the way we wrote this stack thing, I feel like they're
it's too obtuse.
It'd be nice to make this more straightforward and cleaner in a way
that was more legible less likely to be messed up.
But anyway, so we got the expanded always thing or whatever.
This is happening here we now are checking on that.
So what we need to do is just get that view.
So we need to do it like this right where we can just say like okay
grab the view for this thing and and I think that's all we really
need.
Right.
And so, once we know that, we can also create an interaction for it.
Which I guess, I'm not sure what default interaction did originally.
But what we want to do here is we want to create an interaction that's
going to allow things to expand and collapse, right?
So we just want an interaction for this guy that would do like,
toggle, collapse or whatever.
Do we have one of those?
I feel like we must have because one point it was working debug
interaction.
I just saw the code for it as well.
Knob toggle value drag value to every size select but I just saw there
there just was and expand.
Always right?
I mean it's right there so it was toggle value I guess is what we
called it.
Some kind of generic thing.
Yeah.
yeah, typical
typically generic, you know it's just like the way life wants
everything to sort of be slotted into some homogeneous selfless like
sort of being selfless but sort of
It's just the unbearable sameness of it all, you know.
So let's take a look and see what that does here.
Who is calling 0, VAR, link interaction?
This is not actually a this is not actually a viral ink.
It is.
Something else but of course, I don't know if we have an interaction,
that's four groups, we may have to create one, right?
Because of our link interaction,
Let's see, get event from link.
And Dubai, right?
So if it's calling debug variable link, although what it should do is
just I feel like it should sort of detect that, right?
Because it can so item interaction event.
I feel like, yeah.
I feel like that's not.
I feel like it should be able to detect that.
So let me I want to look and see how that get traction stuff, worked
in toggle value.
Right?
So here's toggle value when we create this guy.
We take a look at what the event is.
It was an open data block.
We did this right.
So that suggests that all these those open data blocks, were going to
be things that were being cynical after but that's not really what we
want, right?
That's not what we want at all.
We want there to be a way to yeah.
So, so this is really what we want, we want debug interaction, you
know, expand or toggle expansion.
And I don't think we want this at all.
Right.
We want that.
That makes sense.
I think that's what we want.
And so since that's the case, it really only needs this sort of a
thing here.
So really what we could do instead of our aggression we can just do
this sort of stuff directly, right?
We can just call this directly.
So instead of a violent interaction, it's really just a regular
interaction.
Debug ID interaction like so.
And we've got the the link that's made from the tree there.
There we go.
We need to name the sky.
So that we can have him.
And then we also need to actually pass that, so, toggle expansion.
So.
So let's see how that looks.
Don't know why those are all highlighting.
But now we're working properly.
So that's all good.
And so why is the item color item interaction tree link?
Why are they all?
Why is that item interaction always considered?
Hot.
That's a little bit strange.
Because this should be specific to the tree link here, right?
And correct me if I'm wrong.
But it's a different link every time.
Where is that guy?
Debug ID from link.
Where is debug ID from link?
I don't actually know.
divide ID from
think.
And I think that does mean we're out of time as well.
But I'm going to take a little longer, let's see.
That looks correct.
So I'm not sure, I'm not sure why.
It thinks that we are in why thinks they're all hot there?
That's, that's a bit.
It's a bit obtuse to me and I'm not sure why everything else work just
fine.
So I'd like to know
What it and in fact you can see we shouldn't we should probably do,
like, debug i d like this.
Because this is the same thing.
Right.
So I don't really know.
I don't know why that's doing that.
That is a bit surprising to me.
And so, all I really know is that, for whatever reason, the
interaction is always coming back as hot and that should be checking,
I would think to see whether or not the hot interaction and our
interaction of the same.
And I guess it's checking type.
In generic.
What are the type in generic?
But it's not actually checking the ID.
Did we do that on purpose?
Why does it not check the ID?
Shouldn't this also say, debug IDs are equal.
That just seems like probably I mean your but IDs are equal.
I feel like that must have just been an oversight because we've gone
through so many iterations of the code that we just didn't quite do
that because that makes no sense, right?
Like the interaction has an ID on it, those IDs have to be equal in
order for it to be the same interaction so it shouldn't ever be
considered hot unless that was true, right?
in other words, this
this should have to be.
Like that.
I would assume.
And big surprise that works.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A because I think
that's all good.
Now, I'm pretty happy with where that's at.
Yeah.
All right, we're getting pretty close on this debug stuff.
I'm feeling pretty good about it.
I mean, what I mean, I'm very depressed about it.
And it's awful and everyone should give up now.
And with that, I'm going to go to the free stream.
D7 Samurai was this the depression oriented programming approach?
I keep hearing about yes, very important.
You need to read the book depression oriented programming or
something.
M1 elu pass string.
Length together with pointer to string data in several places.
Do you think it would be better to create a string?
Struck that holds length and a data point.
You know, it hasn't really been something that I've felt like we were
that was cumbersome currently so no but I do do that.
Sometimes it just hasn't gotten to the point where I really thought
that that was necessary.
So while I wouldn't say, don't do that.
I also in this case, don't really feel like it's super necessary to do
that make sense.
If it's to radiate, you've talked a lot about about layers lately.
Have you taken a look at Swift?
At all thoughts, I have not taken up the Swift it all but I thought
Swift was like an interpreted language or something new, which case I
doubly don't want anything to do with it.
Elvin, how do you come up with that literacy stuff?
That was awesome literacy.
You mean like being able to being able to read
I'm not sure, I understand what you mean by literacy stuff, but I'm
happy to tell you how I came up with it.
If you tell me what that meant
program gamer, I don't get anything.
Okay.
Well,
That is a problem.
But don't despair.
You could go back to the beginning of handmade here and start there,
perhaps.
Union fan, do you think that the bug in debug interactions are equal,
would have been caught by compiler generated comparison operator as in
C++
First of all, I didn't know that C++ generated comparison operators.
When did they add that?
Because it didn't used to.
What, what are you talking about?
Did they add a feature recently?
Where you can tell it to automatically generate one?
Or what because it didn't, it did that didn't used to be a feature as
for whether it was something that would have helped us.
No, because it probably can't generate automatic code for the union,
so we probably couldn't have used it.
It would be too dumb.
Grug.
I will handmade Euro to be written in Jay.
I don't know that.
I'm going to make a handmade hero too, but
Elvin.
I meant literature talks, sorry.
Oh yeah, I don't know.
That's that's just like
I am good at making up parody sounding literary phrases so I can kind
of do them while I'm doing something else.
It's not too bad.
I mean, they don't, they're not great obviously, but they could be
good enough.
I feel like part of that's just like, it's just mimic rewrites.
Like, if you hear enough of those silly, kind of things you can, you
can generate them.
it's sort of like doing an impersonation of a celebrity, write your
impersonating, a philosophy student,
The geek pirate.
Who is your favorite figure in the Computing?
World Dead, or Alive.
Mine's Claude, Shannon?
It's not a bad one.
I don't know.
I Like Cows but he's not really Computing.
He's more math.
How about handmade browser and J?
I, I don't I think if you were going to start with that, you just
rewrite the web and like the actual like substrate.
I wouldn't Implement a browser because the prop half, not even half
90% of the problem.
With the web with web browsers, is not the browser.
It's the spec.
Luigi, off-topic.
But how old were you in?
Sort of coding.
I was seven.
A pulsing Mage, do you think that Intel kidding?
The process size limit will make video game falter, or will they
survive?
I think they'll survive just fine.
To be honest, I don't.
In the video game industry is really predicated on on Hardware
improvements these days.
I mean, I think that's almost just almost self-evident by the fact
that like a lot of the biggest franchises aren't even very good look
like, I mean, if you look at the latest Call of Duty, it doesn't even
look very good.
Like it actually looks kind of old tech-wise.
And then nobody seems to care.
Casey you are as old as me.
Are you also planning to retire from working as soon as possible?
No, I like working and and in fact II, don't know really what I do
with myself.
If I stop working, what I really want is not stopped working.
What I want is to have a better environment in which to work.
I want to have like a
an environment where the rest of the people who work on Computing,
actually care about it being good and saying,
Like I want to live in a world where nobody would ever say something.
Like I think the answer to this problem is to take a high-level
language and compile it to a lower level language and then compile
that to JavaScript which we've set up as a template in a specific way
so that the browser can read it and know that it was generated by that
process and then compile that into native code and then run it.
I want to live in a world where that's just obviously,
You know, that you need to just stop erase everything on, everyone's
hard drive at your company and start over instead of going.
Like, I think that's a good idea.
Let's go, let's go forward.
What do you think about test-driven Development?
I've answered that question.
So many times, I'm going to have to skip it, sorry.
But we've answered that like many many, many times.
Actually play games yourself.
If so what?
Yes, I haven't had much time to lately but you can actually watch
effect.
If you go to my twitch chat, my personal twist Channel, senior ettore,
you can even see like old recordings, I think on there there's of me
like playing some games and stuff.
Why should I keep on going in this harsh?
Cold reality when I get lost on episode 005 of ham in here.
Oh why why indeed, right?
And you know, the because existence is meaningless and we are separate
points in a void that can never feel any connection, you know.
Ever sort of, like transcend, our human limits of sort of our Earthly
trappings.
Why indeed, why?
Why even watch handmade here at all?
And the answer I think is that we just have to have faith.
That the variable is watching down is looking down on us from the
great memory.
And that if we all just like work hard and try to be good, people that
eventually the variable will let us into the great memory and we will
live in peace and happiness with all of our other.
Are discretize values.
Active binary, would you prefer to you, I and C code or use something
like HTML or something else?
I always prefer C code or rather more specifically meta program C code
but definitely not HTML.
Engineer.
Oh if you could be given complete control over Microsoft or apple,
which one would you choose and what would be your number one priority?
If I was given complete control over either of them, I wouldn't care
which one you gave me and my first priority would be restoring.
The, the old concept that an operating system, is an open platform for
running code and its primary goal, is to make a stable environment for
people to run programs on.
That's what I would do.
Which by the way, neither of those companies ever does or cares about
in any way.
As far as I can tell.
Brett Hudson mind giving a shout-out about your appearance on the
Indie Radio podcast tomorrow.
Sure,
you know what, I'll be honest with you.
I don't really know much about the Indie Radio podcast.
They asked me if I wanted to be on the show and I said yes because I
like both the concept of podcasts and the concept of Indie Miss.
I went and listened to the podcast as well and it seemed like a cool
podcast but I know nothing other than the fact that I will be on it
and it was like, I don't know how you search for it, but
It was like, it kind of looked like that, like you have parentheses
around it.
So, yes, I know nothing about it.
I know.
Absolutely nothing.
I do not know who bread Hudson is, for example, I am like the most
ignorant person about any of this but you can go to this site in
d,function.com and find out more about it.
That's how I found out more about it.
It's also very pretty like it's a nice.
We design site, but this radio button,
Here, I know this is where I went, that's all I know.
So I listened to some of the back of the I don't know how you listen
to it live.
It looks like there's just some kind of flash thing here.
Maybe.
So tomorrow you could come here.
I believe it's at 12 p.m.
if I'm not.
It's at noon, I think.
But I don't know when the live when happens.
I assume it happens.
Then I like I said a little I literally nothing about it.
Other than I said, I'd love to be on the show and I will be on the
show.
That is all.
I know I am.
I'm as in the dark as anyone else.
So, so maybe Brett Hudson.
I can tell you more about it.
But I'll be posting a link on my Twitter to it after it's done anyway
so you can listen to it after the fact.
So does that I will know for sure.
Mitch 77 xkc.
The question was not entirely meant to be funny.
Can you imagine to still code games and stuff when you were like 60?
Yeah, I mean, I would like to continue working on technology projects
when until I'm 60.
The question will not be.
Whether I want to the question will be whether or not I'm good enough
to because at some point, your brain is just too old to do anything
useful.
But you know, maybe if I do enough good stuff while I'm still capable
of it.
You know, someone will let me be sort of like, just a random, you
know, old sort of good luck charm at their game company or something.
And that would be fine with me too.
Like they wouldn't even have to pay me, right?
Because hopefully, I'm retired.
I have enough money by then to like live or whatever.
I'd be happy to just kind of like go in and like participate a little
bit or whatever, you know.
K.
Sometimes I compare myself with other repairs, get depressed because
I'm far away from their level.
I know I shouldn't be comparing because they grew up in different
environments and I know for sure I can reach their level if I apply
myself and learn quick.
But sometimes it just gets to me and I feel bad about it.
Have you ever felt that way?
Any tips on how to overcome it?
um,
I guess I don't know if I've ever felt that way.
I don't think so, I don't think I've ever felt that way.
I guess what I would say is,
There's obviously any particular thing.
Some of it is nature and some of its nurture, right?
And
You got whatever genetics you got in terms of your ability to
understand code and to be a good coder and whatever.
Like, it's whatever was up.
There is up there, right?
And so that part is fixed and you can't change.
So the part that you can effect is how hard you work at it, right?
And so I would say that the majority of the you know, of the
Of what you want to do, is just make sure that you program a lot
everyday and if you do that, you know, that you will at least reach
your own potential, right?
And I don't really know what to say about it.
Other than that, there's no sense in getting depressed about it either
way.
I know we this was The Depression stream so I should be saying
something like in character and depressing, but in actuality I don't
want to say anything depressing about that because I feel like really
what you want to do is approach it in that way.
You want to basically go like look I got whatever I got in terms of
natural talent for this and the rest of what determines how much
interesting stuff I'll do in my program, career is just how hard I
worked at it because
Yourself on an absolute scale.
Someone else like someone else may have been born with a better
programming brain than you.
Right?
That's just the truth.
It could be possible, Right?
But who cares?
It doesn't matter.
There's there's not some ranking of programmers.
That's like your tits.
There's no Olympics for programming.
And even if there were is, it wouldn't matter, right?
Your ranking.
Among where you are in programming is, is not really relevant what
you're able to accomplish in your career, is what's relevant and, and
on a more personal level whether you enjoy, it is what's relevant,
right?
Those are the two things, you know, whether whether you get
satisfaction,
And whether or not you accomplished something interesting, that's
what's actually matters and the chances that you're not smart enough
to do programming.
That matters is pretty low.
I think, you know if you're able to follow anything on handmade here
are you're probably at a point, you know?
And I seen you ask a lot of questions you're obviously thinking about
this stuff a lot.
So
I feel like the chances that you don't have enough gray matter in
there to make it work is low.
And so what's much more likely is not working hard enough at it?
And not doing enough to try and, you know, not not writing enough code
and so then you never actually, you know, do much.
And it's worth noting that most programmers will never really do
anything particularly interesting, right?
Because they just don't work that hard to let go in and like read
Facebook all day and their or they're like, you know, I
You know, twiddled some PHP code and imported some Library so that
like Facebook's like GIF resizer could resize.
Like, you know, an animated cat or something, right?
Like, you know, a lot of people just aren't picking interesting
projects.
They're not dedicating themselves to them.
They're spending a lot of time in the, at the ping-pong table, or
whatever else, right?
And so, just being diligent and picking interesting projects to try.
And actually, you know, up,
applying yourself to try and solve an interesting problem is already
putting
Of ahead of, like, most of the people who call themselves programmers,
most of people who call themselves programmers, are just trying to
figure out how to get like a high-paying web job or something, you
know, like, they just want to, like, do that.
And so, you know, you don't have to be.
Even the world's smartest programmer in the world, you just have to
apply yourself and I think you're in good shape there.
That's what I think, anyway, but I don't know.
I mean, I have no idea.
I can't tell you that it took me a long time to be a good.
Programmer, for whatever that means, like, for me to consider myself a
good programmer.
You know, when I started programming, when I was seven, you know,
those, I know what was going on and like, I had to call my dad in when
I had bugs because I know, like, how to fix them and, you know, it
takes a long time.
So, the other thing I guess I would say is, don't be discouraged if
you've only been programming for a few years and you're not great at
it yet.
Well, neither was anybody else?
you know, I don't know anybody who like just sat down and like, you
know, six months in was a great programmer, I don't
I don't think that's possible.
I think programming is very much a linguistic kind of endeavor and
much.
Like there's nobody who picked up and speaks fluent Japanese, within
six months.
You don't speak fluency in six months.
It's a long process.
And it, and when you're talking about getting to the level of fluency
to create something you're talking about, like, you're talking about
learning a language, and then writing a novel, right?
And if you were to think about how long it would take you to, like,
pick up a language, you don't know.
And then write a great book in that language.
It's a fantastic number of years, right?
I mean that's just a long time and so I think you shouldn't also you
should.
You should make sure you don't have unrealistic expectations about
your ability to program.
And for how long you've spent on it and so on.
So,
Cast 05.
Do you think Japanese?
Not adopting?
The oop Paradigm is because they are smarter or simply because of not
being interested.
In changing to new languages.
I don't, I'm sorry.
I was unaware that the Japanese didn't adopt loop, I have no idea.
I literally have no idea about that.
I both have never heard of it and don't know that I could say anything
about it.
Even if I had
JP to pseudocode or question.
How would one go about learning Assembly Language and are compilers
linkers written in that?
So pretty much Assembly Language is not really
I think that a lot of people programming anymore these days in terms
of the whole code, you know, in the old days when I was a kid,
Certainly like if we talk about the Commodore 64, let's say or the
Apple to it was very common for someone to write like a whole thing in
Assembly Language.
That was that was not.
That would have been a shock.
If you were like I wrote this commercials before a game in Assembly
Language, no one would be like, oh my God, what that's weird.
Nowadays, if you said I wrote this whole game in Assembly Language,
people be like what are you talking about?
Nobody does that.
So you know, Assembly Language.
Nowadays is more something that's that's done.
In small chunks for only the most important part of your code.
And so yeah, compilers linkers know.
There are almost never written in assembly language.
Typically, what happens is you take an existing compiler, an existing
operating system, in existing compiler, you write the new operating
system, new compiler, whatever it is on that system and you like crush
your like cross-compiling, right?
Or building a compiler with another compiler, until it gets to the
point.
Where can self host,
So, you know, if you're interested in learning Assembly Language, I've
said this before.
Use the debugger.
The best way to learn Assembly Language, is to look at what the
debugger generates.
Because then you can just say, okay, I put some code in here, go to
disassembly and now you can see what what it did, right?
So that's the easiest way to learn it.
I think in addition to obviously like reading people's tutorials
online, which will be, you know, a way to get you started but to just
see what happens, you know, anything that you could write in C, you
can immediately
The in the debugger, what it generated for assembly.
So, it's pretty easy for you to go.
I don't know how I would Implement X.
Well, just look at how the second power, does it?
That's a way to kind of learn pretty quickly?
Something you don't know.
Let me see.
Would you ever think about using C sharp or python?
No, I don't like interpreted languages.
Also, garbage collection is totally unacceptable for me, I hate
garbage collection as well.
Yuan fan.
How do you approach getting an overview of a large code base?
Like, clang of the Linux kernel.
I'm the wrong one to ask.
I'm the wrong one.
Ask I am not good at that, kind of code.
That's like a mic.
Certain question.
You got it yet.
Ask Mike certain.
He's the he's the one that does that stuff.
I, you know, if someone told me you got to fix a bug in clang or
something, I'd be like, I forget it.
Like I don't even want to know, don't want to know.
Don't want to look at it.
All right, are we done in Garland abloom?
It's not a long stream.
It's a normal time, right?
Because we started a half-hour late.
So that's just go until seven.
All right, folks, that's about it.
That's about it.
My friends.
I'm going to wind it down, thanks everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game here on handmade here at dot org and it comes with
a source code.
So if you want to follow along at home, it's an easy way to do it and
it's for your fun and enjoyment, your maximum fun and enjoyment.
We also have Forum site which you can go to if you want to ask
questions about series.
Or you can also take a look at our anted episode guide which is done
by some of the people who are on the chat.
If you're on their mid blow for example is like the point man.
These days for it even has a patreon page which I think I finally got
them to link to I say in forever and you got to put the patreon page
on the episode guide but it wasn't there.
Yeah.
Now it's there needs to be bigger.
God you guys got to make you spend all the time on the episode guide
and the what the place where people can pay you for it.
It's this little tiny never going to see that.
You put it over here or right here or something patreons, contribute
to the contribute, you know, help make episode guide possible button.
Right.
But anyway, point being
There's a patreon page for me, blow where he actually accepts
donations for all the work.
He does on the handmade hero annotations which he does a lot of work.
Like if you look on here you can see like all this stuff.
Like for example, here is yesterday's, you can see that he puts in all
these time markers and stuff so you can just jump directly to things.
You can say like oh okay you know I want to know exactly where you
know this quote was or here's where we did this particular thing.
Or here's where we did this, you know, here's where push sides with
dealkylation, got removed or whatever, so, it's pretty great.
When you're trying to learn from a series, you can jump around and
it's just, it's just a way better than using the royal YouTube.
Anyway, so that's about it.
If you want to follow the series, obviously you need to know when it's
on.
So we also have a tweetbot.
You can go that button right there, it tweets.
When the series is live, which will be next week.
Probably won't have one Friday of next week's.
I'm guessing because
Was, is that oh wait, no, no.
It'll be a full week next week.
So I think next week is Thanksgiving, but I probably will.
To a stream on Thanksgiving.
So I think next week I'll be a full week after week after.
That's right before handmade cons, we might miss a day somewhere
there, but otherwise should be 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time straight through next week.
But if you're unsure about it, check out the tweetbot.
It will tell you.
That's about it for now.
Please enjoy your weekend, have some good coding.
Despite the fact this was intentionally, our depression stream.
I think, you know, now, the depression streams over you should at
least be able to enjoy your weekend.
That's something.
I will try to enjoy mine as well.
Until Monday.
Take it easy everyone and I'll see you on the internet.