Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade.
Here are the show.
We could a complete game live on stream.
No engines, no libraries.
We are attempting to show the complete development of a game here
right down to the very last little pixel.
And we just finished up a bunch of major work.
We were doing on Wednesday and so yesterday, I decided we might as
well just do something kind of fun and Whimsical.
So what I thought I'd do is I'd show how to make particle system.
So yesterday we made a particle system and I guess
Should say before I go any further.
If you pre-ordered the game on handmade here at org and you want to
follow along at home with this episode today is day 156.
So you should go ahead and take day, 155 source code, unzip it into a
directory and that's what I'm going to be starting with here.
Just so you've got kind of you know, the same state as I have the
same.
The same codes is with a z and so what we did was you know really I
just showed kind of the very basic
Of how to make a particle system and you can see that because it's the
Sprite that we happen to have lying around.
We, you know, we did used ahead and and I think people sort of ended
up kind of liking the head particle and you know, so it's kind of
stuck there.
I was going to say let's make a little sphere particle to put in there
but people seem to like the head so I don't know, maybe the head has
to stay in there but point being you have this little particle system
here.
And so what I wanted to do today was just finish up kind of talking
about part.
Call systems and some things.
Maybe showing a few more things that you might want to do with them
and just kind of again, this is kind of a two-day sort of intro to
particle systems and then we'll wrap it up and Monday will start
undoing our asset system memory management stuff.
So okay, so you know, hopefully everyone understood roughly, what was
going on there, you know, particle system is a pretty basic idea,
right?
We that's no good.
A particle system is basically just a lot of little low-cost entities
to simulate, right?
The
Buying a particle system is you're going to throw a lot of sort of
cheap things at the problem?
Instead of having like an entity, you know, whole entity, which in a
game can be very complex and have a lot of simulation logic and and
very and can take on a lot of different roles.
We're going to make a lot of small cheap uniform fast, you know stuff
and throw them at the problem to sort of do this simulation for things
that any of these don't stimulate particularly well like, you know,
Mists and liquids and gases, and that sort of stuff like we talked
about.
And, and so,
You know, that's what we wrote and there's some things that I thought
I wanted to sort of show you to extend sort of what we did yesterday.
Just again as sort of getting your feet with particle systems for
people who haven't really ever done any particle System Program before
which maybe some folks out there.
So, what I wanted to say is, you know, I wanted to take our particle
here and do a couple more things with it and a couple more of the
traditional things that you might do with it.
And so some of them are
The first thing I want to do is say, let's add a an actual
acceleration to the particle.
Right.
So that when the particles are spawned, we will have a little bit more
information about what they're going to do physically, right?
And so in order to do that, you can see that as we spawn these things,
right?
I could then say well, you know what, let's make particles subject to
gravity, so you know they're going to fall down, they're going to fall
down at some rate and that rate, let's say is going
To be, you know, negative 9.8 meters per second squared, right?
So our acceleration is going to be the standard acceleration of
gravity.
And then what I want to do is I want to come in here and say that the
the particles when we update the position like we did here.
We are also going to update that velocity right by adding it in.
Now, what we can do when we do the update, the velocity we can just do
the sort of standard two-step thing, where we update the velocity and
then,
The position, which is not quite accurate, right?
If we were worried about saving every extra, like little tiny cycle.
Maybe we would do something like that, but we really don't have to do
that.
Instead, what we can do is the full equations of motion, like we
talked about 1/2, a teaspoon, where'd assume you guys remember this
from, we talked about it to account for the complete effect, over the
entire time, step of that, you know, of that acceleration, right.
So I'm just going to go ahead and type that
It out.
And if you don't know what I'm talking about, then that would be, it
would be a good time to go back and watch the episode on equations of
motion.
So that, you know why I'm adding, you know, 0.5 f.
Times the time step squared times, the times the acceleration into the
position.
And so that's a little bit more of an of an accurate integration.
But again, it would work regardless of which one you were doing.
And again, since particles are supposed to be sort of fast cheap acts
in a lot of ways, really, any way that you want to update it, that
accounts for acceleration in some reasonable physical.
Fashion is probably going to be fine, right?
So, let's take a look at what happens if I run that now?
Kind of see those guys falling down, right?
Kind of like a sort of a waterfall effect sort of thing.
And so, in order to counteract the effects of gravity, we probably
want to start them with a stronger upward Force, right?
So, you know, if we were going to and I'll use again, I'll lean on the
live coding system that we did here to help us understand what's going
on.
You know, when we create that, that sort of DP, that sort of velocity
Vector, what we can do now is just kind of beef up our upward motion.
Ian Wright.
So instead of just between .71 I can, I can really just kind of Jack
that up by adding a little multiplier on the front that just gives
them more of an upward thing.
And now you can kind of see how we've got more of a fountain effect
going, right?
And I want to talk a little bit more about the
Effect because I feel like it's important maybe at this point just
when we're talking about it Loosely and again, since these are kind of
fun days, I want to kind of bring in, you know, we're just kind of
playing around the partisans, getting you interested in them.
I want to bring up a couple things about particle systems that you may
not know, even if you've done Parsons before, or you may not be
familiar with, if you're not like a physics, some guy or whatever,
right?
So I'm going to point out some things there, but before I go into
that, I just take our little Fountain here and say, you know, one of
the things that's not very good about our Fountain is, is
When these things hit the floor, right?
When these things you know, collide with the floor they should
probably bounce right?
And as you know Collision detection is pretty difficult, you know they
we spent some time on it, we solve more stuff, we have to do our
conjectures kind of rudimentary and not really great and so we have
some things.
I said when we want to go do our final pass on that.
We have some more things to do so you know do we can really afford to
do any kinds of fancy Collision detection on our protocols.
And the answer is maybe not so much, but just because we can't do
real.
Good Collision detection are particles, remember particles are about
doing something fast and cheap, that allows us to create some
interesting phenomena and we can do some things that would allow that
to happen.
So, for example, one thing that would be pretty trivial for us to do
is just to check to see if we cross below sort of a ground line.
And if we do just Just Bounce ourselves back up, right?
And so, it would be pretty easy to do something like, you know, if
particle P or even, you know, I could even do it in clothes for
Michael.
I'd just say whatever the particles I guess, it was, why is our thing
here?
Absolute value particle.
P that y, so I could say, just don't let that don't let the y-value.
Go - right and you can kind of see how it now.
Does this sort of It, kind of has a nasty nasty vibrating effect for a
reason, which I'll talk about in a second.
But you can kind of see how we can start to put in a fairly cheap
effect, right?
That will make it so that our particles will kind of land on something
that we really don't want them to.
Have that kind of nasty bouncing effect so it's a couple different
ways we can do that.
With that bouncing effect is coming from.
If I may go to the Whiteboard or Blackboard I should say, for a
moment, just to kind of draw it out.
So you kind of have an idea of what it's going on there.
So what happens when I when I have this bounce situation is the
particle is coming down, right?
And you have to remember, everything is happening in.
It's nothing really happens on a curve in our Graphics of everything
always happens in discrete steps, right?
So,
It's like here and then it moves to here on the next frame and then it
moves to here on the next frame.
And then it moves to like here on the next frame or whatever.
Right?
And if the ground is here, if I'm going to negate its position.
So I'm going to take this mountain, flip it back up, right?
You know, that's going to like oscillate this guy very quickly because
it's going to come here and then grabbed his going to pull them back
down again and he's going to come here and guys can pull back down
again and so on, right?
So what I'd rather do is something a little bit more, like what we
were doing before where I say, okay, if he goes
It let's just set him a be projecting back to the point of contact and
maybe just negate his velocity.
So instead he'll bounce and kind of go up, right?
Because remember we did that when we sort of did our stuff there.
So I'm going to do instead is say if the particle p y right is is less
than zero.
Then I'm going to make the particle p y equal to 0
And I'm going to make the particle DP y equal.
Its -.
So I'm just going to flip the direction.
I'm going to, I'm going to bounce it off that that surface right.
And there you can see.
Now I get kind of a more natural bounce, right?
And, and of course, the other thing I can do is if I wanted to now
that I've taken care of that, velocity problem, and it won't go back
and immediately, I could choose to try and keep some of that momentum
there by doing something like that as well.
Right?
So now, I can keep that that negation.
That was like,
The absolute value of thing we did before.
Right?
So now we've got those bouncing heads, but you'll notice what happens
is they bounce as high as they fell, right?
And that's actually the physically correct thing to happen.
If you bounce, if you let something go and it bounces off the floor,
its natural physical thing to do, would be to bounce as high as you
dropped it, right?
That's actually what should happen if you were just looking at the
strict equations of motion for the bounce, but the reality is there's
a couple different things.
There's dragged through the air.
Right.
So
There's Mo, there's energy being lost their and so that will count for
a little bit.
But what really account for the majority of why something doesn't
bounce as high as when you originally Drew at that, the height when he
was dropped, it is actually the impact with the thing that it's
hitting.
So if I drop a ball on the floor, the reason it doesn't bounce as high
as from where I dropped.
It is actually because the there's energy that goes into deforming the
ball and to some very small extent, usually the floor slightly those.
Those atoms as they
Each other, you know, as they kind of Squish together, there's energy
that's lost in that actual collision and the energy that's lost in the
Collision comes directly out of the energy.
That was the kinetic energy of the ball, that was bouncing, right?
And so, any real ball bouncing, any real floor, will always lose some
amount and that's there's a coefficient what they do to approximate as
they have a thing called a coefficient of restitution, right?
Which is basically just a thing that says
Let's have a number.
The tells us what percentage of the energy we retain after the bounce.
So we just say, yeah, we're not going to simulate atoms like smashing
into each other and losing energy in that and all whatever it is going
to say.
You know what, this thing, loses half of its velocity when it bounces
or something like that, right?
Because we figured it out and that's what it does in the material
science just says, okay, right.
And all we have to do is just add in that coefficient of restitution
and then we will get a much more natural bounce happening, right?
And you can kind of see those guys bouncing out kind of more
The way that you would expect like with a, like we said, a fountain or
something like that.
I'm gonna kick up the initial kick a little bit.
They're also just so we can have a higher sort of Bounce to it, okay?
That may have been admit that that may have been excessive.
I'm going to I'm going to calm that down a little bit, so there you
go.
Right now, we're kind of throwing those guys out a little bit more.
And I feel like maybe the bounce is even still a little bit much,
even, even even with a half.
So I'm going to take it down even even a little further.
So, there's something that feels a little bit more like, you know, a
fountain of something.
Spewing out like it is, right?
And and you know, I'm reasonably happy with that.
And as you can see that's that's not a particularly onerous piece of
code to, right?
That's pretty trivial.
And we could even do this for some limited.
Like if we had a very limited cleavage Collision geometry that we were
working with something very simple, we could we could probably do
something with that.
So it wouldn't be too complicated to have a couple things that happen,
right with these guys.
And so that's, you know, that's kind of, like, the basic thing with,
like, just starting to add a little bit of stuff into the into the
particles there.
Now, what I wanted to talk about, in terms of the, what happens with
the fountain here, there's actually some other things.
I don't really know, you know, if we want to actually try this today,
maybe we should, maybe we shouldn't
It's such a hard decision.
You know, what do you go for and what do you not go for, right?
I want to I wanted to kind of time to talk about lagrangian versus or
Larry and simulation and just kind of how they differ in what they
mean.
And I don't know if we're going to be able to get through it in a
daze, the only thing.
So I'm not sure if I should start talking about if I should save it
for some other time when we're going to have a longer period discuss
it, but what the heck it cut, you know, if comes up, it comes up.
So let's just talk about it because I was on my mind.
So what I kind of wanted to point out is like, so let's say we wanted
this fountain.
To you know to look a little bit more like a fountain and one of the
things that happens with a fountain of stuff right?
Is that the upward velocity there is not so variable, right?
The actual upward velocity and a fountain is in like a month or the
spread the horizontal spread is much narrower, right.
It's a much narrower thing that's happening there and so really, you
know, for a fountain we're talking about something that's really not
going to have that kind of lateral spread to it.
It's a very
Nozzle, right?
Like you can see that shooting straight up and that's you know what,
we've got there is a much more accurate depiction of a fountain on the
way up, right?
But if you notice what, if you take a look at what that looks like and
you think about what a fountain actually looks like, right?
Well, our simulation right now.
Looks like something that just kind of comes up here and then comes
back down, right?
So it kind of creates like a little narrow cylinder, right.
But if you've ever seen a fountain, a fountain has a very distinctive
look.
Any kind of a spray like that as a very distinctive.
Look, when it's got a reversal in its path.
And what happens is, it comes up, right?
And this part is still roughly the same, but it actually then kind of
comes out like this kind of a thing, right?
So it's kind of as an arrow thing coming up here and then it comes out
like this and for
seems kind of like a more of a mushroom on the way down.
So the thing is coming down, right?
Are very different from the things that we're going up, right?
They don't kind of has this this different character to it.
And if you think about why that actually is, that is because these
things are not infinitely.
Compressible typically, what we're simulating, right?
They cannot hold an arbitrary amount of themselves in a given area
without a consequence.
And what I mean by that is imagine that you have a glass of water,
right?
The typical substance we might make to think about how Fountain looks
would be say water, right?
So if we have a glass of water, it's a fair bet to say
That if the glass was filled up to here, right?
Let's say your glass is half empty, right?
Versus your glasses is full.
However, you want to picture it.
What we know about water, even from our daily, you know, observations
of it.
You can understand this very directly because you've seen it all the
time.
The amount of water that is in a glass is directly reflected by how
much volume it takes up, right?
You do not have to ask how squished down the water was in your glass,
to figure out how much water you have, you know, that you have exactly
as much as the volume that you have.
There is no density.
E2 water other than the one density that water has, right?
And that is because it is an incompressible fluid, right?
You cannot just squish it into an area like you might be able to do
with a solid that had air in it.
That could come packed down and become more dense and stay that way.
Water will not do that, right?
Water wants to expand to its natural density.
It is an incompressible fluid in that sense, right?
And so when happens with our Fountain is on the way up, when we start
shooting the fountain, everything is kosher because the water has an
upward velocity, that allows it to get out of its way at roughly the
same rate as new water is.
Coming in.
So the water on the way up is pretty happy but as gravity takes its
toll, the water on the top is going slower and slower and slower until
it stops right.
Eventually that the water that first water that got shot out is going
to slow.
And at the apex of the fountain at the part where it's going to change
direction, it's basically motionless.
Right?
And so what happens is you've just got this huge amount of water
that's
Getting into this zone right here, that's going to try and come back
down, but when it starts to try to come back down, there's more water
there.
There's water that was on its way up that it is trying to occupy the
same volume.
And so it's going to happen is as the water kind of comes up in and
tries to, you know, think negotiate with its other water molecules for
how are we going to occupy this space and maintain like a uniform
density?
It starts to push, right, it starts to have outward force.
That is pushing.
Water out of the way new water that's coming in, wants to push other
water out of the way.
What if it's falling down wants to push other water out of the way,
right?
So all of those interacts to the molecules is causing an expansion of
the water volume at that point because you're shoving new water into
it.
And the old water is got nowhere to go.
It's got its got to leave, right?
It can't just stay there.
And and to be clear, it's not like new water and old water, are
pushing each other out, or it's more like there's just a collection of
water.
And as we put more of the
Water molecules in it doesn't matter whether the new ones are the old
ones or whatever are getting pushed out.
Some water molecules are going to get pushed out because we can only
have so many in a certain space, right?
And so if we were doing that in zero gravity somehow, you know, you'd
expect the expansion to be uniform, but obviously the whole reason,
this is even happening is because we have gravity, which is slowing
the water down.
And so what happens is you don't see much in the way of water shooting
out these directions, because any water that got pushed upward is
still under the force of gravity and will very soon, find its own path
downward, that does not involve hitting any other water, right?
And so what you end up with is that very characteristic Fountain shape
Of water that comes up and then kind of get splatted outward, you
know, in that way.
Because outward trajectories will never get pushed anymore.
They'll just kind of be able to naturally fall, right?
And so, if you think about our problem that we have, if we were wanted
to capture this, well we could write some kind of special purpose code
to do this, right?
We could, if we just wanted a fountain and we just only want to
simulate that you could imagine having some kind of a force that kicks
in.
We just say the there's like a, just, a dispersal thing up here,
right?
That pushes it out and that would be one way that we could fake the
fountain thing, right?
So, let's write that fake one right now.
For I tell you a little bit more about sort of lagrangian, Euler stuff
so that you could kind of see where I'm going with it.
So let's just write that one because you know, it kind of turned into
a little bit of a talky stream.
All right.
So if we wanted to write that one, what would we do?
Well let's just say that we have at that Apex there.
We've got some kind of a thing that's going to push our water
molecules out, right?
So we're going to have a thing that's going to push them out.
So what I want to do is say something like and again I kept saying I'm
just writing a super cheesy thing here doing the thing that is the
effects artists.
Way of getting this done, meaning we're not trying to do physical
simulation, really?
We're just trying to make something looks like a fountain.
So what I'm going to say is if the velocity of the particle has gone -
so it starts its went up and then now it's on its way back down.
I want to make something that just makes those guys kind of poof
outward, right?
I just want them to poof outward a little bit, right?
That's all we're going to do.
So all I'm going to do there is if they're on a downward trajectory,
I'm going to end and maybe you know will also check to see and you
know they are there within some reasonable bounds.
So you know and Y is greater than some magical constant that we come
up with right and these are going to be these are going to be too kind
of locate where the dispersal thing is going to happen, right?
What we're going to do is we're going to say that whatever their x
velocity was.
It's we are going to maybe magnify or you know what, we'll add a
little bit of acceleration to their acceleration based on what the
Yeah.
Bait will add a little bit to their acceleration based on whatever the
they're they're sort of displacement was an ex.
I mean however, far they were from the center line, will add a little
bit of that back in, right?
Least, that's the roof.
There we go.
I'm kind of wanting to be able to type this in and physics notation,
which doesn't really work.
All right, so let's try that and see if we can get something a little
more sensible there, right?
I actually want to make sure that I do this in a strictly, it's a
vector equation.
So, I got to make that keep happening there.
But all right,
so, let's see, I've got a bunch of stuff that I'm going to have to
tune now.
I don't really know what these values are actually going to be.
So let's see that one, we know.
So this one's really the only one we have to figure out.
I'm not really sure which one it should be and I also don't really
know how much the magnitude of this Force should be.
So it's really just again just kind of super tweaking, these things to
see what they might want to be.
So it looks like
It looks like for some reason that steak having more of an effect down
at the bottom which I don't super understand why that is I guess
probably because by the time it gets down there or something like
that.
Let me see if I can restrict that effect to a little bit higher and
then maybe make it a little bit bigger.
I wish I knew how high those things were actually going of course is
the thing but I don't.
All right so I'm going to make that Force huge.
There we go.
And so I feel like my py here is wrong.
Wrong.
I feel like it should only be operating at the top but it's clearly
operating at the bottom.
So what did I mess up about that?
Assuming that the velocity is negative and P Y is greater than
One.
So its height above the ground should be greater than 1, right?
Is it that just needs to be much higher or something I guess.
It does look like that was the case, right?
So, I don't know.
Are we now at the point where it can't be added at all?
It does appear, that way.
Yeah.
So, not particularly good, although I could also make it.
So we've just hacking the velocity directly
Again, this is all just just randomly stupid hack.
Sorts of things.
Nothing.
I'm doing, literally nothing smart here.
Let's try it that way.
so, maybe 10 x that
Know why?
I feel like I should be seeing more maybe I'm not thinking about this
quite correctly but that is often the case with hacks when you're just
trying to figure something out.
It's often not particularly smart what you're doing so it can be kind
of there we go.
So now we're getting a little bit more of that, but it's not really,
it's not really what I want.
So I actually maybe want to make it so it's more like this, right?
So it happens on the way up a little bit more there.
Let's see.
You know, I could make it sort of only when the Apex happens.
So you know what I could do?
It's more like this.
I could just do it in a balanced of Y, so, but the bounds of velocity.
So, basically, we do something like, you know, if it's in between that
Narrow band.
So it's relatively slow.
You know what I'm saying?
Then we will do, you know, this, this sort of displacement based on
its Exposition or whatever you want to do, just.
So in that, very narrow band, right?
And I don't know if that maybe would make it a little bit better.
Yeah.
So of course at the bottom, that's a problem.
Oh, right?
Because at the bottom, it will also have that velocity Man packs are
hard.
This is why this is why it's difficult to hack things.
And I often try to just do them the right way because man, trying to
come up with little things like this, that do the sorts of stuff that
you want is not always, is not always easy.
It ends up being like, you know, this kind of War of Attrition where
you let go and then maybe I can hack this on the thing.
On top of it.
So it tends to be a little bit nicer to just do the right thing.
So that's looking a little bit more looking a little bit better but
only a little bit, right?
Like it's not still not quite there yet, right?
But it's, but it's getting a little better, right?
It's getting a little better.
So let's see.
Maybe maybe a little more.
So if it's in between
In these two.
So it's relatively low velocity.
So if it's less than three up, I'm going to make it so that it, maybe
we'll let it do a little bit more there.
Right.
So that's looking a little bit better.
And you can sort of start to see that a little bit.
I think another one of the problems is that it's just hard to, it's
just hard to take the sort of that narrow band and spread it out
enough.
So you almost need to add some entropy into them at the top there in
order to get it to happen but you know you know how it is.
Alright.
So if I were to then say narrow this down even a little bit more.
So let's say that the upward velocity is hardly jittered in any real
way.
So
Upward velocity is like very straightforward, right?
And then we've kind of got, you know, maybe even a narrow stream.
So it's a very stable stream kind of going upwards, right?
And then we go ahead and kind of Jack that that spreading effect up
there, right?
Let's see, that's starting to that's actually starting to look a
little bit better, right?
But it's just kind of a little disquieting.
I don't know, I don't know if maybe the if acceleration would, it
would be calmer or
Her as well.
Yeah.
I don't know, I'm not sad, I'm not very happy with this.
It's not doing it for me.
I don't know if that's just because I want to do the right thing or if
it's just because I'm not doing a particularly good job at hacking it
today, right?
The point being either.
This is a good demonstration of why you should care about the thing.
I'm about to talk about next.
Or maybe if you're good at hacking stuff, maybe if you're better at
like hacking stuff than I am, you won't have a problem and you'll just
come up with something that you know, that that's that's reasonable
right?
So yeah.
So let me tell you a little bit about what I was going to say in terms
of how you actually want to solve these problems, typically
If you can, if you can afford it and sometimes you can't afford it and
then you're back to doing what I was just doing where you're like,
well, set aside a couple hours and figure out how you're going to hack
something to, you know, make it work, right?
So let's talk about this for a second.
So why are we having the problem that we're having, right?
With the original simulation, which was relatively phase the correct.
It's a bunch of particles that are being simulated by Newton's, you
know standard love of Newtonian motion, right?
Newtonian Dynamics.
So why are we having this problem?
Well, the reason we're having this problem is because all of the
particles are just separate entities right there, not at all being
considered.
So, what we actually,
We would do, right?
Is when we have this upward stream of particles.
And we start having a collection of particles that are sort of
occupying, the space, and these ones are coming down, and these are
coming up and we now have a high density of particles of the space,
right?
If we actually sat there and said, oh, for every particle, when we're
going to simulate the particle, let's go collect all of the other
particles that are in the nearby region.
See how many there are.
And if there are too many, we will consider that there to be a force
that repels this particle away from these other ones.
Right.
You can imagine this happening, right?
So we could do that, right?
But it would just be incredibly expensive because it means.
Now, we have these big queries to do for each individual particle,
right?
Well, it turns out that physical simulation on computers like physics,
simulation, right?
The actual not the kind that we do in games where we're trying to
approximate things for visual effects, but I mean like real physical
simulation for like engineering and stuff.
Actually, considers two ways of stimulating things to like broad
categories of simulating things because of this very problem, and they
are called, or larian.
Methods.
And lagrangian methods.
And they're kind of, they're very separated in some sense.
They're kind of a very different and what we are doing right now is
What's called the lagrangian method and what distinguishes, a
lagrangian method is, when you have the information about what you are
simulating,
Is actually the thing that moves through the configuration space,
right?
So we are talking about a real, you know, our simulation space is like
this XYZ thing, right?
And of course, we have this weird.
Why is up thing at the moment because that's how our renderer is built
temporarily.
So we have this sort of situation where we've got a three dimensional
space and we have some information about this.
The thing we're simulating and what we've chosen to do is encapsulate,
the information about the simulation space into these particles and
the particles themselves which are the things that hold the
information and are the and are the even more than just hold the
information.
They are the locations at which we do our simulation, right?
We think about I'm now stimulating at this point and I'm going to move
it to this new point, right?
Those simulation points are actually moving through the space.
They are actually there.
The actual quantities of simulation are themselves, evolving through
the space, right?
And there's another way that you could choose to think about this
problem, right?
Another way we could choose to go, this problem is in what's called an
oral Aryan, or as an oral or larian method thinking about it in terms,
Alms of things that are stationary.
So instead of this, we could think of it differently.
We could think of it as a discretize grid, right?
In space.
Like so where our Fountain starts here and it is producing particles
of a velocity that are upwards.
But instead of considering them as particles what we instead, consider
them as what we can said, consider them to be is just a density, right
there is just a density and velocity at this location.
So if I was to spawn five particles, let's say and I was, you know,
their average upward velocity was going to be something like, you
know,
Two meters per second, right?
Then this cell of the grid would simply store five and two, right?
And two meters per second, write five particles 2 meters per second.
And instead of ever even having particles at all, we would just have
this storage of the grid and the storage would be fixed.
It would be how everybody it is.
I 1 2 3 4 5 6, 1 2 3 4 5 right it would be a six.
By five array that stores that quantity per grid cell.
And what we would do every frame is we would simulate each grid cell
forward in time but they would not move instead.
What they would do is they would broadcast
Their quantities throughout the simulation.
And there's a lot of different ways you can do this obviously.
And this is a whole branch of simulation.
But basically what would happen is there would be equations that we
would solve or send, you know, simulation steps.
We would take depending on how we want to write it, that would take
the values in all the cell's and try to determine what the next set
of.
What the, what the future time values of those cells would be for our
next time step, right?
So one thing we might say is well if there's a lot of particles, if
the density is high and the velocity is upward here then we should
have you know, our equations should add.
Particles to this cell, right?
I mean, that's what would happen, right?
And if that became true, then later, this one would get more, right?
And this each cell would kind of add density.
Basically two neighboring cells by virtue of the fact that it sees
that the velocity should go forward, right?
And there's many ways of solving this weirdly enough, there's a boil
Aryan is, you might as well not even call stuff I Larry and because
we're those guys name on so much stuff.
I mean for that matter, I guess so does l'orange that half the time
you say the word doesn't even matter.
It's like although which of the twenty or other things we talking
about.
But in the specific case of talking about physical simulation, if you
said or Larry and Method versus lagrangian method, the person would
probably know what you were talking about, right?
They'd be like okay I see you're moving like particles through Spirit,
moving simulation through space or you've got to fix simulation grid
and you're moving quantities through the grid right?
And so, the reason I bring this up is because you can see how the
lagrangian method falls down be at certain things, which are about
density, right?
Lagrangian methods are very bad at handling density, because density
is about how much stuff exists per unit volume.
And the lagrangian method doesn't even have a notion of volume volume
has to be imposed on top of a lagrangian method.
So when you're
Going to go do a lagrangian method that has to take account of
volumetric forces.
You're constantly at a disadvantage.
Doesn't mean you can't do it, right?
It just means you're at a disadvantage and soy larian methods.
Have the opposite problem.
They have the opposite strength and the opposite problems basically.
They're, they're complementary schemes.
What happens in an oil, Aryan method is things that have to do with
volume are very, very easy, right?
Because we've already said that everything exists in these nice little
bounds.
So if we
Talk about the fact that if things get too dense they repel.
Well, that's really simple.
We just go, what's the density in this area?
If it's high, it needs to try and spread its density out.
So basically it's like look at two cells if the density gradient, you
know, if this one is higher than this one then it means it should flow
this way.
If the density here is higher than here it means it should flow that
way right?
It's really simple.
And even without even showing you how to do it you can imagine in your
head having a 2d array and going you know even the totally crap hacked
version of that.
It's like just looking at the
Cells.
Which ones greater or smaller.
And just moving some density from one to the other, right?
I mean, you, you can even imagine doing that.
That's not exactly how you'd want to do it, but you can imagine it.
Okay.
So why do I bring this up?
Well I bring this up because if you add these two guys together and
have them make a little love.
Child flipper baby.
Right.
You get you know these kind of mixed methods.
Which can try to combine the two schemes, right?
And so, how would that work?
You know, how would we use that?
And of course we've got, I don't know, 20 minutes left.
So the answer of how it would work is like I said, I probably will run
out of time before I could actually Implement one because there's a
bunch of stuff we have to do there or whatever, but the point being
If you imagine how these things would, would combine together, you can
start to see how we might be able to use both scheme simultaneously to
produce an interesting effect, right?
So, let's suppose that, instead of using the or larian method for
everything, we use the lagrangian method like we're using now, but we
use the alerian method as an intermediate to try and get some of these
volumetric effects happening, right?
So, for example, if we were to do something like I have a lagrangian
method, the lagrangian method is shooting these particles up, right?
And now I want to know if somewhere.
Kind of bout.
I want to sort of introduce like some forces based on where they Bunch
up.
So when these things started start bunching up, I can poop, I can put
them out, right?
I can, I can make them start to disperse.
Well, what I could do is say, okay, I've got the particle system as we
have it now.
But first, before I do the simulation on the particle system or maybe
after depending how I want to interview the steps.
I am going to take a grid, right?
And I'm going to sum up
The quantities.
I might be using in an oil Aryan situation from the lagrangian, right?
So the lagrangian frame is here, the or Larry and frame is here.
The lagrangian frame says, here's all my points.
So what I'm going to do is just compute the density, so, the density
is like, really high here, right?
I'm just going to add for every grid cell.
I'm just going to add an account, the particles, every particle that's
are going to add it in, right?
You know, so I've got like 20 here and there's a 2 here.
2 here, 3 here, 2 here, 1 here, something like that.
Right, I'm going to do that.
And then what I'm going to do is, I'm going to do some kind of an
update step on the grid to see which cells are high density.
I could even decide if I was super cheese ball.
I don't even have to do that.
I could just just do the sum.
And then what I could do is say, well, when I go to do my simulation,
now my
Step, which is going to update these guys and move these guys
somewhere, right?
Instead of just updating the particle in isolation using the
techniques we just did, which are the kind of lagrangian way to
simulate it forwards in time, moving the point through, I'm going to
do an oral Aryan style, look up and say what's the the stationary
density at this point and if that density is high, I will, you know,
introduce a velocity that moves
Of things from high-density to low densities.
So for example, maybe what I'll do is I'll take this cell and I'll
subtract the density of this cell from it.
And based on the gradient, I will add in a velocity this way or
acceleration this way.
I'll do the same thing here, I'll do the same thing.
Here to produce a final comment, like composite velocity or
acceleration that I add in as like an oil, Aryan term to my lagrangian
update, right?
And so that way, I can sort of do something where I
Do allow my particles to be considered as density.
Groups being a kind of relatively clean way.
That doesn't really hack it, right?
It doesn't really force it to be about a fountain.
We could do anything we want here, where we have, you know, particles
spraying around and where they happen to, you know, where the spray
happens to concentrate.
They will you notice verse from there or whatever, right?
So, you can kind of see how you can start to construct a more
physically accurate, part of the system, out of this without really,
having to do N squared Loops.
Because that's the real problem in the
Ron G and right.
The real problem lagrangian is if I have to consider other particles,
what I could talk about one particle that ends up in a row N squared
land.
Right?
We have n particles and if each one of those n particles has to think
about all the other end particles that's n times n.
And that's a very bad run time for a particle Loop because n is going
to be high, right?
If we want four thousand particles, well, now we've got four thousand
times, four thousand things to consider, and that's no good.
Instead of what we'd rather do is say we've got four thousand
particles, right, and we've got
You know, some fixed number of 64 grid squares.
So now we know that we're four thousand times 64.
And we don't even if we drive this number up, this number gets no
worse, right?
We can have eight thousand particles.
This number still gets no worse, right?
Instead of the N squared minus where as we drive, the particle count
high, you know, this this becomes a disaster because it's 8,000 times
eight thousand or whatever, right?
So hopefully that makes some sense.
What does that look like in practice like I said, it's almost it's
completely unlikely that I'll be able to do anything remotely
resembling a mixed method.
Integration scheme here questions, education to my mix method physical
for stimulation but you know what would it look like?
Well it would look like something like this particle cell.
Right?
And in the particle cell, we just have something like density for now.
Density.
And you know what?
We probably have a velocity, right?
And and maybe I guess we'd have velocity times density, actually,
would be what we'd have, write something like that.
So, you know, as it comes in, we would get that sort of, we could
normalize the velocity out.
So something like this, right?
And what we would say is when we have our particle system, we would
then have our protocol cell, right?
And our protocol cell would be, you know, a two-dimensional array that
again, tries to capture this thing.
Who knows what it is?
It's 16 by 16.
Let's say I'm not sure and then we would go in and do exactly what I
just said on the Blackboard which I could.
I said it's just a lot of code so you know.
Can we do it in a day in 50 minutes and a long day?
Probably not.
But you know, it's something like that.
So so we have something where we'd do, you know?
I don't know.
You know, X is zero.
X is less than 16 + 16 x, right?
Uther y equals 0 Y is less than
15 and this is really, you know, define particle, seldom something
like that so that we don't have to have a magic constant strewn
everywhere.
We can change easily, something like that, you know, we do this,
right?
And maybe I'll do it quick this way.
We do this, and we say particle cells.
Write YX.
We're going to clear it.
Clear it out, right?
We just want to be zeroed first, although I guess now, I think about
we wouldn't have to do that in the
We could just say 0, right?
We could just we could just zero that because they're all going to be
at you know, we know that there's no special values that have to that
it has to be initialized to.
So we could just say, you know what, go ahead 0 the whole thing,
right?
So we can do that.
And then what we want to do here is we would want to be able to do
that summation like I said, right?
So we want to figure out where all the particles are at the moment and
then we want to add that kind of force in instead, right?
So we know it's all 0 now.
So we're going to do in here is we're going to run through the
particles once taking their locations and putting them in, right?
So it's a little bit again.
You do, you don't pay N squared, but you do pay like a second pass for
example, because you've got to compute that grid first
What we could do.
There's yet another way we could do it which is you compute the Grid
on the previous pass.
So we can actually get rid of this and have a one frame lag in the
past.
There's there's all these other things we can do, but I don't want to
get too complicated.
I don't want to throw too much down just yet.
So let's just do it in separate pass first.
Right?
So what I would do here is I just need to know which cell I'm in,
right?
I just need to know for the game state for whatever the particle cells
are I just want to know which of these cells, I'm actually going to
land in.
So I'm going to say
Cell cell equals, you know, whatever this cell is.
And we'll figure out how to compute that wire next in a second.
So when I have that sell, what I'm going to do is I'm going to take
again, we've got the density, they're going to take the density and
I'm going to add our, whatever our density is to it.
And for now we'll just say that the density of every particle is one
but we could have particles that are like more or less dense.
And then I'm going to say the velocity times density is just going to
be equal to whatever our particles velocity.
It was going to be right times, whatever are particles.
Density was right.
So we're basically summing up those two things.
And what that means is that now
When we go to look at the cell, we know what the average velocity was
weighted by density in that area, right?
Because we can go ahead and divide.
We could take the density and divide out the velocity times the
density to find out what the average velocity was.
Right.
That makes sense.
So yeah so we could do something crazy like that and this would give
us a cell to sample from if only we knew the Y and X right?
But that's pretty easy.
We've done stuff like this a bunch of times before, right?
You've seen us take things that were not on grids and stick them into
grids, right?
And so all we really need to know is where the the base of the grid it
like how to basically map our coordinate space onto the grid.
So I'm just going to take
Arbitrary thing and say you know, okay the base of the grid is is
going to be at like you know maybe - 50 or something, right?
You know.
Here's where our fountains sprays things out of right.
So maybe it's negative 50 or something like that.
And this is going to go out to, you know, or I shouldn't say negative
5 because it was 16 or something, right?
So it's negative 80, or - the the span / to, right?
So it's out there somewhere and then this is going to go to 80 and
then this up here would be, you know, 8 comma 16 and this would be
negative 8 comma 16, right?
And so all we really have to do is take the position of the particle,
right?
And turn.
Turn it into an integer and stuck.
It s of the grid, that'd be fine, right?
Because again, we're just, we're not trying to do anything,
particularly fancy hear it, you know, nothing nothing, particularly
weird, just something basic.
So, what I want to do is I want to do a round.
So I can just kind of see or actually, I guess I want to a truncate to
put it into a cell it's probably a little more reasonable.
So we have those that we've done multiple times.
We've got our truncate so all this truncated right?
Well the particle
Well, it sucks to be P, right?
Particle.
Dot X and the particle .y.
Now each particle.
Its position is pretty much the exact thing we want.
Only, it's offset by a little bit because remember our grid, our grid
doesn't start at 8:00 as far as the particles are concerned.
It actually starts over here.
So all we really need to do is just first compute.
What the P would be if we subtracted the origin of the grid, right?
So we have the grid origin here and that's a really easy thing for us
to figure out, right?
Because like I said, only the x is really different.
Everything else is the same.
We've got.
whatever this particle seldom here is, we just need to go ahead and
say, okay, yeah, the particle sell dim
We're just going to do - half of that.
So we're so that way it's kind of centered around X.
So that's our good origin.
This will do all the summing and the only thing that we really have to
do now is make sure that we clamp these guys to something reasonable,
right?
So if x is less than 0, it equals 0, right?
If x is greater than that particle seldom, right?
We need to to truncate that down.
Like so right and the same thing would be true for y.
So now we know we're always in.
We're always in the cell.
And we could also, after we do this scale, this guy.
So if we wanted to scale the grid, we could do that too which is, you
know, it's pretty easy.
So, again, if we were doing this for reals, we think about more about
how the grid has to get overlaid and all these are the sorts of
things.
But for now, that seems pretty reasonable.
And that should sum up, that should like get our grid going just fine,
right?
Of course, we can't, that's going to change the data layout, so I got
to rerun the program, right?
And so now, we're actually Computing those grid values and, and that's
all fine.
We probably need to draw.
Owe them a little bit.
In order to kind of see what's going on.
But you know what, that even even that is not particularly difficult,
right?
We could we could pretty easily just do a push wrecked here where we
actually draw out what our grid looks like right.
And so what I could do is say, okay, I'm going to do a quick spin just
for our own like edification, right?
So we can see it.
I'm gonna do a quick spin over this grid right over the grid just so
we can kind of see you know what we're even.
In here.
So I'll do that.
I'll go ahead and say that will spin over the grid.
Right.
And yeah, and as we do that, I'm going to go ahead and pull out that
particle cell and then I'm going to draw a rectangle that's is that's
going to be centered, our I guess is going to show us the grid
location and is going to maybe be colored based on the density, let's
say of what's there again.
I got about 10 minutes left on the clock.
So I'll just or I don't even know if I think it's something like, 10
minutes, 78 minutes, something like that.
So I will go to about 60.
It.
So if I want to do that, right, I know that it's again, just x + y,
nothing particularly fancy there but it's offset by that grid origin,
right?
And so whatever the grid origin is we need to add that in, okay?
And the other thing that we need to do is recognize that this
dimension thing here.
We know that we're drawing something that's like that, but the problem
is, I believe this was centered the way that we draw our Rex, right?
We really need to like lock down the red or sometime soon in.
Document it so that we know how our stuff works.
So we don't have to keep looking at some point.
That's, that's yeah, that's a good idea to do.
Let's say, so anyway, but if we push wrecked here, I just want to see
which one we do.
So there's the offset and the dim.
So it looks like scale times gym, so it's actually going to be up in
the actual code.
It looks like we're it.
Does that displacement?
So there's rectangle entropy entropy plus dim.
So no, it's actually corner.
It's actually corner and, and wit, and with tight.
So that's that should actually be it, right?
That should actually be the thing.
What is this complaining about just these guys?
We have that.
All right, now we go.
All right, so if I go ahead and make this happen, there we go.
No use running conversion from.
What are you talking about?
This is just a B2, is the problem.
There we go.
All right.
And so what I can also do here is I can make the density proportional
to you know I can make I can make a alpha value here, right?
Which is going to be like, clamp 0 to 1, whatever the density of this
thing is and maybe we say that it's like, you know,
No, it's a tenth of the particle count.
Being like that, right?
So we're just going to want to just kind of get brighter based on how
many particles are in that cell or something.
Just so we can see if this is working at all, right?
So let's go ahead and okay, that great is way too big.
First of all, I guess that makes sense because each grid cells and M.
So let's start by by calming that down a bit.
So we'll let's introduce a grid scale, right?
And the grid scale should maybe be you know 0.2 or something.
Something a little bit more coherent there.
Right.
And so what I want to do now is I want to say that we got the grid
scale times that, you know, just to kind of shrink things down
properly.
And so that does mean.
Also that these values have to be multiplied by the grid scale as
well, right?
When we're drawing it.
And similarly, this would also be multiplied by the grid scale rights
because we're sort of shrinking everything down a little bit, right?
Okay, that is not right.
And the reason is because this of course, also needs to be scaled by
the grid scale.
If that makes sense, because it's going to be too far away right now,
it's being moved as if there was no grid scale.
So the the actual origin has to be computed knowing that that's how
far it's actually going to go per step as well, right?
Alright, so there we go so that's looking roughly, right?
But are we're not getting the right density, calculation there at all
as far as I can tell.
So let's feel, let's figure out what's happening there.
Why is that?
Why is that not working properly density cell density, plus equals
sell that?
Why is that bad?
Looks reasonable.
And yet it is apparently not reasonable.
Yeah, I don't know.
I'm going to also I'm going to do
this instead just to make sure that I don't have any weird things
happening with Alpha.
Yeah, that's just totally wrong.
Well, that's okay.
Let's step in.
Got a few minutes left, you never know, this could still work.
You never know.
If you could get something in before the end of the stream, always
kind of tricky.
All right, so let's scoot on back here, too.
Where is that?
Particle fun.
It is right here.
Alright so let's come in here.
And let's see.
What we tend to get for X and Y values.
Okay, well that's not helpful.
What is going on there?
oh,
Okay yeah, wow.
So obviously the idea here right is to scale you we want to map things
into the space of the grid.
So what I did here was I actually made the problem worse, right?
I multiply by the grid scale, which will shrink the values.
I want to make the values larger so that they move into more grid
right spaces, right?
If our grid, you know, if here is our X, you know, here's our origin
right here, 0 0, and I've got a particle, right?
And it's
You know, it's going to the value like .7, you know, point three or
something, right?
If I want the grid to be smaller.
So the grid is like point to on a side or something.
If I want to know what grid Square, This falls into the last thing I
want to do is make this value smaller.
This value needs to be bigger because it needs to fall into three,
right?
So, I'm really supposed to be using one over the grid square, right?
I'm trying to figure out where it actually Maps.
We've done this before on the stream, multiple times.
I just yeah.
Italy space, right?
So I actually need to know the inverse of the grid scale so that I can
map it that properly.
And that's actually what I, what I actually wanted their right.
So that was just being stupid.
So let's try that one more time.
Okay, so now you can see a little bit better.
What's going on?
Of course, our heads are offset, which doesn't help.
So we should probably use something that's actually centered, but it's
kind of cool, right?
You can kind of see that.
Now we kind of know what the density is everywhere.
And if I go ahead and make it draw after the fact, we can see it a
little more clearly.
Oops.
Right?
So there you go and so you can kind of see where the densities are.
You can kind of see where they where they're sort of adding up.
And so if we wanted to now, we could sort of have things that make
them dispersed based on those densities.
Yeah, so it's a little bit confusing to watch because as you're seeing
it, you're seeing kind of not the true answer because this is the this
is what the densities are without the fact that when they get to the
top, they would start to disperse.
So this part is going to be brighter than it should be because
everything falls.
Straight back down onto it, right?
Which is not actually correct.
But yeah, there you go.
So,
That is the start of a scheme, but we don't really have time to do
anything anymore.
Fancy with that, right?
Because of well, because of the
Lateness of the hour, shall we say?
But what we would do is we would do the exact same thing in here,
right?
We would, we would probably we would pull this code out into something
common, right?
But then we would do you know exactly the same thing here, where we
grab out whatever the cell is for this guy.
And now we can use the cell cells information to do some whatever we
want to do, right?
And so, for example, even if we just were to take this thing here we
could instead of doing
The if statement like we were doing it before now we could actually
just add something proportional if we wanted to do this thing
proportional, we just add in the term here for whatever the density
was in that cell.
So the poofing Factor could now just be based on the cell density.
Right.
And off you go and hey that actually does roughly, what we actually
wanted it to do.
Of course, we're adding a little bit too much force there to say the
least, but at least,
East.
Now we do have something.
That's kind of dispersing those guys a little bit better.
So we have one of the things that we need to do which is that uh no.
We don't actually cap are like particles that have have gone to
nothing.
Don't actually are still counting for everything.
So we might want to do to just temporarily is say that the particles
Alpha since that's our kind of Life Time factor is is what the density
actually would be there, right?
So now, you don't
Have those ones that are kind of fading out don't actually count for
for any kind of, you know, for any kind of a density Factor, right?
So, yeah, so if we wanted to play around with that a bit, now we could
actually try playing around with some forces there.
Of course, it's a little bit confusing because we don't have, since we
haven't done work on the grid which is the important step of the rural
area in part.
We don't know what direction to shoot particles.
We don't know how to move particles in any particular way.
So it's kind of bogus and this is never going to produce anything,
particularly interesting, but point being, you can see that we're kind
of getting a start to it, where we can sort of start to get it, where
things are kind of, you know, moving away from from where they should
move away from.
But of course, we also have things where they'll yeah, you can see
them kind of bouncing off the things there and and part of that is
just what happens when you get to the edge of the grid.
Now I could expand the grid out a little bit, just to, you know, sort
of prolong the bad or keep the Badness a little bit, a little bit less
problematic.
Again because we're still because we're not solving what the density
says, you should do because we need to look at like neighboring cells.
It's just going to keep accelerating guys, right?
Anywhere there's density, it'll accelerate away from 0 which is just
not particularly useful useful, right?
It's not a particularly useful Force.
So again, so we're still not quite to the point where we don't have to
hack it.
I mean, we could hack a little bit more of it, which is just to say,
you know, if the cell density, you know, has to be higher than a
particular value or something like this too.
Before that happens or something like this and that would calm things
down a little bit, but it's still not going to be, you know, it's not
going to be good enough, right?
It's not going to be good enough.
It's still, it's still not going to give us the effect that we want,
but it's starting to get there.
In fact, you can already kind of see, even just from this.
You can kind of see how it's how it's already starting to disperse at
the top more, right?
Where that density starts to build up.
But again, there's a bunch of stuff we would need to do in order to
make this more correct and they are operations on the grid.
First of all, that would look to see because if first of all, you
would look at the velocities and the velocities if things were already
going to move out of the cell, right, you would not feel the need to
disperse them if they were already moving into a place where there
would be room for them.
Right?
And second of lie for density, you would only move things from places
of higher density to lower density.
Whereas, right now we're not looking at that at all.
Right, so yeah, so again totally bogus, but you know, what do you do?
I suppose the thing we could do even just quickly now, I think about
it that that wouldn't actually be too hard to do is we could do the
sort of like next door neighbor's.
Sort of a look look up in the grid which is where we do.
You know something, where we where we keep these guys a little bit
more truncated.
So we say something like, you know, you got to be you got to be inside
the grid by 1 square.
So there's a, you know, there's always an apron right or whatever.
And then what we'll do is we'll actually check the neighbors, right?
So what we do is when we look up the cell, right?
We've got a couple here cells here.
We've got a cell, you know, that's to the left, right?
Right.
Write something like this.
And we would just basically have all the different all the different
cells.
So we'd have y plus 1 which is the up.
When we have y -1 we have y plus 1 which is right cell and and then we
have our Center cell, right?
And then we would literally just go through and instead of any of this
nonsense here, right?
We would do something like, you know, cell like this version.
we would initialise it to zero and then we would say something like,
okay, the cell center density.
Going from the left cell.
Going from our cell to the left, so what's the density gradient?
Right?
And we're going to add to the dispersion, some quantity, you know,
some proportion of that, right?
Which is, you know, whatever our whatever, our coefficient of
dispersion or whatever is here, the debt, whatever the density
difference is, We'll add a force in that direction, right?
So if the density in the left,
Well, I guess I should really do it the other way around.
If the density coming from the left sell to us, right?
If we are higher than what we want to do is add a force that pushes us
towards that cell, right?
And we would literally just do this for each of those differences.
Right.
Or maybe down up would be the correct order there to keep parody.
But right, does this make some sense?
I'm literally just checking the neighbors to see.
What the what the density gradient is between the two and then I'm
just adding a force that moves things from a direction of low density
to one of high density and I don't know what that's going to do again.
It's like don't really you know this is this is very ad hoc.
So all I need to do now is just kind of move that coefficient up a bit
and see, you know, if that if that yields anything beneficial for us
/, it's just kind of always the time.
So I'll crank it up a bit.
And we'll see.
All right, that's not very much.
Oh, it would help if I ever added the dispersion into anything hahaha.
Awesome.
Yeah.
Let's try that again.
So yeah.
Our particle acceleration, that's pretty funny.
So, our acceleration is going to be whatever.
The constant acceleration is for the thing.
Plus our dispersion, right man?
That was stupid.
All right, you know, sometimes we're stupid.
Sometimes I'm very stupid.
I've been known to be extremely stupid.
So there you go.
Now we've got our dispersion going on and it moves things between
ourselves.
Based on that density, right?
And so you can see that that actually works very it's very
well-behaved now and does sort of sort of what we want but it's still
not quite the right Fountain shape.
And the reason that it's not quite the right Fountain shape is because
we don't account for that velocity movement of the fluid, right?
We don't account for the fact that the velocity was already upward so
these particles were already going to vacate the cell that they were
in.
We don't have to move them out of the way because
Is there going to a new location already?
So we need to kind of think a little bit more about that, but you can
already see it starting to take shape slowly, right?
And so, we're getting somewhere.
As always, I'm saying we're getting somewhere.
Alright, so I hope you enjoyed that brief introduction to to physical
simulation or Larry and lagrangian methods.
It's a bit of a butcher job because we had to do it in one day.
But what you gonna do it was kind of interesting.
I had fun with it to be honest.
It was kind of fun to just suddenly do compositor Larry and lagrangian
simulation of a fountain today but it's overdue for the Q&A, it is
overdue.
So let's go ahead and go ahead and
Now I threw out a ton of stuff at you.
So hopefully you've got some questions because I did.
I covered it very sparsely and so I hope that you will
We'll ask them questions so I can go ahead and clarify that.
Now we got a good 50 minutes left here.
And a see said, I suppose adding some friction to DPX might help.
I agree with that, especially on that bounce.
In fact, if you wanted to add that friction, it'd be pretty easy.
There's a we're not really simulating the kind of contact area very
well or anything like that, but on the bounce, we certainly could do
it.
You could say that the coefficient of restitution was actually going
to be on the entire velocity, right?
And so, instead of doing it this way, we could do something more like
this, which might, which well, actually, typically you've
To right.
There's there's there's actually usually two of those, right?
So, you know, maybe the coefficient of friction is something different
or something lower, right?
But you do it, I guess like this.
Yeah.
And that would be some friction to just slow that lateral motion down.
Right.
Oh, whoops.
That I didn't mean - there we go.
So that would be something that kind of dozens that lateral.
You know, that lateral thing they're on impact, but there's a reasons
why that's, oh, I should make that much weaker.
There's reasons why that that's not exactly the best thing.
But for particle system, it's probably fine, right?
If that makes sense.
Try reducing the size of the individual cells so you wanted to make
more cells or something.
Is that what you mean?
Like you just want, you just want to see what happens if we have a
higher resolution data.
I mean, one of the things that we haven't done like this is very ad
hoc, right?
And so one of the problems is we haven't the volume.
I'll run this and then I'll say what I was going to say.
Right.
So oh wait, I got change that grits to go down a bit.
Where is my grid scale?
Where am I grid scale?
There it is.
So I'll say, I'll say something about about that in a second here.
Right.
So there you go.
That's with a denser grid.
So let me say one thing about that briefly though.
So if you were actually doing this like like if we actually sat down
we're like okay we're going to make a full-on lagrangian or larian
particle system for high and made hero that's going to be like a real
thing that we use a lot and we care about it, right?
there's a problem with the way I did this ad hoc the hosta is you
can't just add a force that's like what's the difference between
Through cells.
Okay, there's the difference, add the force.
The reason is because you haven't taken into account the volume of the
cell because the volume of the cell and the distance, like between
cells, right?
Would change how big that for should be.
If you don't want to look at the the Delta between two cells this way.
And then a Delta between two cells that are this size and add the same
amount of force for the for the density gradient, right?
Because it would take more force to move.
Things from this area to this area than it would to move them from
this area to this area.
So your you want, you need terms in there that account for the size of
the cell, right?
So, so I guess the way I would say is right now, the way we've written
it, it's not would have to be tuned for a particular cell size,
whereas you could write it in a way, that, although, it wouldn't be
completely oblivious to the cell size because it's the resolution, the
cells has real effects on the simulation, obviously, it would at least
not require the constants.
Retuned, when you changed it.
Back of the head would make it better protocol than side of the head.
That's probably true.
If you want something even freakier, we could do something way
freakier than this actually though.
and that would be instead of doing first asset from
we do get random bitmap from and then we would need to pass the sea
and handmade asset.
Get random groups, random bitmap from.
Where is it?
Get random pick, Matt.
From so be assets type ID series.
Game state facts.
To that.
Why did not oh, oops.
That was a mistake.
okay, so if I go down here and where we are actually asking to, you
know, get
we're we're actually gas going to get the bitmap, but I could do is
say get random bitmap from
game state.
Affects entropy.
and that way we just have random heads and they'd be flickering all
In crazy, right?
So yeah if you want some like crazy shit that's that's that Loop.
Then third swear if you want some crazy stuff, that's what it would
be.
And and you can also add variety the particles to like if you wanted
to write, you could do something where that this bitmap ID, so the
bitmap ID would actually be on the particle.
Frank.
And if you did it that way, then what you do is when you actually
spawn the particle.
The thing would get picked at that time.
So the bitmap ID for the particle will get picked when it actually
when it happened and then the bitmap ID would be something that was
stored with the particle.
Again this is all about again making trade-offs of like how complex do
you want the particle system to be how expensive is it versus how
versatile are any individual things.
And so then you got kind of the, the various like, you know,
Particle.
All the different heads in there.
And student in 73.
I see that you said if you're going to alter the grid scale you
probably need to scale DC by a to I'm assuming you type that before I
said the explanation of that.
Yes like I believe you work in these kind of a field in general.
So you know probably better than I do exactly that thing.
Which is that yeah like
If you actually want to do this right?
You have to work out the forces based on the actual meaning of the
grid cells.
And so the dimension of the grid cell is a critical component of the
scale so that you don't have to like change things like DC, right?
Did you ever add a way to tell the music to shut off or to just
disable it?
I just disabled it.
What happens if the particles respond between two cells?
Will that cause and effect?
Where everything will just not bounce off each other anymore.
I'm not sure what that means.
There's really no way to put a particle in between two cells.
It's going to fall into one cell or the other because yeah.
So I'm not sure what that means.
Sorry.
On API design.
You recently emphasized right?
The usage code first and then the implementation later,
Compression oriented programming is about writing code first and then
compressing it pulling coated two functions where necessary allowing
the API to evolve out of that process.
They seem like two contradictory methods are they how do you decide
when you're using one or the other?
So, no, I don't actually think of them as contradictory at all
actually.
Which is weird.
I know.
what they actually are is
if I sit down at the computer,
And my goal is to reduce the amount of duplication in the code that I
have.
So, I'm looking at a thing and I'm like, I have to reduce the
duplication of this thing, right?
Then I already have all the information that I need to do that job,
compression, or interpreters tells me.
Here's what I need to do, right?
So the always write the usage code.
First thing
the way that it would be contradictory would be if you said you should
do that.
Then meaning I sit down and I have all of the working stuff that I
need like my code is doing what I wanted to do and then I sat down and
wrote, you know, the usage code for it first or something like this,
right?
I said well okay I was going to write a bunch of usage code and then
try to reverse map that onto the thing.
That's not usually how I think about it.
The way that I think about it is if I don't have anything yet meaning,
I don't know what it is that I'm supposed to be writing.
I have no idea, right?
Or I could make up ideas, but I haven't yet, right?
That's when, when right, the usage code, first is the thing to do so.
In other words, what we did on the
I like the, I think it wasn't like I had a bunch of code working.
That was loading in the Assets, in the streaming way or whatever,
right already.
And I was just saying, okay, what I need to do is make this reusable,
we just didn't have an API, we didn't have any, we didn't have or
sorry, any code that was doing it, right?
And so when I say it was right to use this code first, I mean it's
okay.
So now I need to do is I need I need a thing that does this whatever
it is and I don't have one
So rather than going and starting to formalize, something like go in
writing an API without having any idea what the thing, you know, who's
going to be calling it?
I prefer to do the opposite which is to like go at the usage code.
That is the thing that I wanted to have and then I'll go implement it,
right.
So I really see them as not actually being contradictory because
they're actually not doing the same thing.
this not like you could get I don't think of it as being possible to
get to a point in the program where you could where you could do
either one, you can only either do one or the other and it's based on
What you have in front of you, right?
And so if you don't have anything, you write the usage code first.
If you do have stuff, then you do the compression reprogramming.
And another way this there's top-down versus bottom-up.
Programming is another way to think about that, right?
Like that.
Those are phrases that are used a lot in the olders in older school
literature, right?
Where it's like you just have to, you have to go the direction.
From stuff that you have to stuff that you don't have.
And if the stuff that you have, is that the bottom, you need to go
upward.
If the stuff that you have is at the top, you need to go downward.
And so compression oriented programming is saying you have a bunch of
bottom stuff you're trying to fix.
That's compression do compression.
Look at it go.
How do we pull out pieces that do the thing that do the same stuff
here, right?
If instead what you have is an idea of how things are supposed to
happen but you don't have anything to make them happen.
Then you need to go downward and that's like when I say right, this is
code first, right?
So, I don't know if that maybe that didn't explain it very well, but
that's the way I usually tend to think about it.
It's like there's an empty spot.
Avoid of information.
And if that void of information is more specific than the code you
have.
Right now, then you are writing the usage code first if that void of
information is less specific than the code you have right now, your
compression compression, or any programming, right?
We another there's like there was Snuffleupagus.
But then, I don't know what the with the other way it, what the other
direction would be.
Would it be possible to split the food competition across two frames?
Like use the first frame to accumulate velocity momentum changes and
the second one to resolve them.
Yes and I think I mentioned that when I said it before, I was like we
could I'm going to split this in two passes, but we don't have to, we
don't.
Yeah, we can we can make that a little bit.
We can make that not, you know, not do that by using two of the size
of the cells, right?
One from the last frame, the rest sample from and one from the new
frame, but sometimes that actually is a lose because you because now
you have more memory and so, your cache performance can be worse,
right?
So you don't typically want to do that stuff, unless you really know,
that's a good idea.
Does the size of the grid relative to the to each particle of matter,
much?
Yes it does.
And that's what that's one of the problems with these kinds of systems
to be sure.
Is you know all computational physics stuff is kind of ad hoc in that
way.
Where it's like yep.
It's like we're just making approximations that and so it
I think that it is sensitive to it.
If the cells are 22, large the simulation won't be accurate enough and
you won't be able to capture some of the phenomena you need.
If the cells are too small then you will never accumulate enough
particles into them to actually have them do anything, right.
Say you're deciding whether to bounce the particles off.
Based on the density.
Now then if the particles respond between two cells, wouldn't the
density?
Be halved and not bounce off anymore?
Oh, I see what you're saying.
You're just saying if the width of the particle stream is wider or as
moved and the answer is, yeah, the again the VIS these schemes are not
awesome, right?
There are things you can do to help mitigate that.
For example, you can give particles actual area and add the, you know,
add to all four.
So the way that you can solve that or not solve it, but mitigate it is
to do the bilinear thing again.
So, if a particle is here you add its density to these four centers
based on its proximity to each of them, right?
And that gets you out of the business of the in-between to sell
spawning problem, that you're talking about where you got some
particles in here and some particles in here and now you're trying to
talk about the density there, right?
So, there are some things you can do to help mitigate that.
But again, discretize all methods that involve discretizing things to
a grid, have a lot of problems like that.
And so you just have to be, you just have to be okay with knowing that
the goal here is to / to produce some kind of effect.
And if you can produce it with a district ization, it's okay.
But is it going to be perfect?
No.
It's going to be very far from perfect.
Let's see with simulated annealing work for this issue.
What?
What issue?
I'm not sure what the issue was.
Doesn't writing, usage code.
First imply, Simplicity in API calls, well, yet, try.
I mean, it it that's one of the metrics that you would be trying for.
Doesn't this box you in when trying to create persistent things on the
stack?
I don't see why those are even related.
All complex initializations for persistent.
Have to be done somewhere.
That is true.
If done on the stack how do you persist complex data structs without
using static?
Well, if you're persisting it, you wouldn't put it on this stack.
If by the stack, you mean the program stack, you would put it on.
It's appropriate lifetime stack, right?
Like, we've been doing and handmade hero.
so, I'm not sure, I understand those questions, really
Bring Cruise.
Our current simulation is in pixel space.
No, it's in meters.
Our pre-rendered effects viable.
Wow.
In handmade hero there, probably aren't something I would want to do
because it's is about programming.
And so we want to do things that are programmer e.
And so, I would say, most of the time, what we want to do is do our
effects dynamically, right?
Because this is more learning that way, like, we learned a bunch of
stuff today, even just hacking around with this and like, you know,
are you ready to go an off and write your own physical simulation
code?
No, because we only just kind of brushed against it in a very, very
quick and dirty way.
but,
you know, you can see that that doing effects like this.
When we say, let's let's make, let's figure out how to program them
rather than having an artist make them or something, and then just
didn't display them back.
You learn a lot of programming that way.
So I think that's pretty important, and that's kind of where what I
would like to stick to on the stream as much as possible, Right?
So there's our lovely fountain.
It's kind of cool.
Actually.
I feel like I'm liking it.
I feel like our d alpha is maybe a little high though.
I feel like our d alpha maybe wants to be smaller.
So we can kind of see it.
It's just kind of fun to see it pile up a little more, right.
Do you see how it's doing some pretty cool stuff there?
Like the water isn't getting near the nozzle because the nozzle is
very high density down here, right?
It's just kind of fun, like, even already.
Like that's what's cool about about, leveling up your physics
simulations a little bit, not that.
We've really done much of a physical sensation are.
We've done the simplest dumbest possible thing right.
But that's already so much cooler than the hack we were doing.
Because now it's actually starting to capture some of the phenomenon
that you might want, which is the water staying away from other water,
right?
And dispersing itself out in that way.
And so, you know, it's just, it's cool.
All right, so we're over time for about 8 minutes overtime, so I'm
going to call it.
I'm going to call it a day.
That is that's kind of cool.
That is just fun.
I mean, you know, you got to admit that a spewing head fountain, that
that sprays heads into the air is, is pretty cool.
At some level, I wonder what would happen?
This is always what you get.
If I decrease the spawn rate a little bit too.
I'm interested to know what would happen.
There looks roughly the same but you kind of get a little more.
It's like less force on the nozzle.
So it gets a little more.
It's kind of throws up.
It throws them up a little bit more as they kind of get into spurts.
That will ya got its physics?
Stuff is just cool, it's just cool.
And so there are you know if I spray it out more at a time again,
haven't given them any more upward velocity.
I've just I've just increased basically the hose the, the pressure on
the hose.
This is fun, right?
I mean that's just fun is nothing.
There's nothing better than the crazy physics stuff like that, it's
just amusing, right?
That's great.
So I think, you know, what else?
It would be nice to do at some point, too.
I mean, it's, we're we're not only supposed to be working on particle
systems right now.
So maybe we'll revisit this in a while, but we'll also want to do a
thing so that, you know, they could kind of be more stationary.
It's kind of fun.
I wonder if we should just do like on next week as particle systems
week.
Probably not probably not do those later.
All right.
Okay.
I'm going to close everything down.
Particle systems who doesn't love particle systems.
Alright, so here we go.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, I hope you enjoyed our brief foray into particle systems
and the discount, in your interest peaked in such things which we will
maybe talk a little bit more on later on in the project when we want
to focus on effects for a bit, but until then if you would like to
play around with the product source code or any of the other source
code, if you preorder the game on handmade here at or get does come
with the source code so you can check that out and download it every
night after I'm done, I upload new zip file so you can always have the
latest
Also, we have a forum site, if you'd like to come ask questions, or if
you want to download ports to Mac and Linux that community members
have done, they post them.
There there's also an antidepressant guide maintained by the
community.
That's pretty cool.
We have a patreon page, you can subscribe to if you want support the
video series and we have a tweet.
Art, which treats the schedule at you.
So if you want to catch the series live you can do that.
And speaking of catching it live, we will probably be back here
Monday, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time next week, but just to be sure do check that
tweet Bacchus.
Sometimes we have to do other schedule things depending on my schedule
for the week, just to make sure we can all fit in.
So that's about it.
I hope you will have a particle filled weekend and have fun coding.
I will see you on Monday.
Take it easy, everyone.