Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on stream.
We are back this week with some camera code probably today, I don't
know because we kind of started the camera code last week and I have
some more things I would like to do it this week.
There's some restructuring.
I wanted to do to it.
There was also like a sort of discontinuity bug that I want to fix and
then we can just improve generally the quality of it, but there's a
bunch of other things.
I was thinking of that, I kind of wanted to get to, as well, so I
don't know today.
To today's episode might be a little bit of a potpourri, you know,
that fabulous smell that that you're, you know, grandmother's bathroom
smells of because she has that weird floral or stuff, you know, kind
of above the toilet.
It's that kind of episode kind of like above your grandma's toilet.
Let's go ahead and and jump in here.
I'll talk about a couple things I want to do today is day 379.
So if you're following along at home,
You want to follow along with Dave, start with de 378 source, code,
that's source code.
I'm starting with here.
I will point out we did have and I probably want to do this first.
If it is the case, just because someone took the time to write it in,
someone was pointing out because we haven't gone and looked yet at
re-enabling sort of the cliprect stuff.
I briefly touched on it in the Q&A last time because someone asked
about it, but I had never looked at myself.
Snoring tortoise wrote in and said, hey, I think it's just a question
of like, passing some parameters wrong.
You changed some stuff and you haven't updated the way that the calls
work.
And so, I figure if since I know that people, I don't actually know
why they were asking about running the profile again, but I know that
they were asking for it.
And so since other people are apparently using that at the moment, I
feel like we might as well real and re-enable it for them.
If this is actually the only bug in there because hey, I can go fix
this bug, really trivially.
And then the people who want to do, the profiler can use it.
So in advance of us actually getting to the debug system and
looking at it in more detail.
So if we go ahead and take a look at what that mail was talking about,
you can see that when I build this here, we have loops, if I spell
Microsoft developer Studios command line tool, name correctly, that,
when I run this, if I wanted to go to the profiler, you can see that
although things are drawing in the debug view.
You can see that there's like, this weird
Your of the profile rectangle I'm of the profilers clip rectangle,
where it's not really showing the things right.
It's like the you know the rectangle is this sort of darkened region
here but then we've got this like listing, that's getting half clipped
you know what's going on?
And the reason there is we never really updated the cliprect code to
be correct once we updated ourselves to the 3D pipeline.
Now, what the male is talking about though is that they were saying
well,
I know that there's actually anything wrong.
Now that you updated that because in the Q&A, I went and fixed the
projection code to do a reverse projection for the clip Rex, but they
were basically saying that, hey, I don't know that there's anything
actually wrong with that.
I think you're just, you're passing the rectangle information wrong
now because it's offset and dimension here, and it's rectangle here
and blah, blah blah.
So, if I may read the mail, you can see what they said.
I believe the issue with the clipping on the profile.
Is due to the get Center rectangle.
Being passed from rectangle to, I get cliprect into rectangle, to I
get cliprect.
This is an issue because the latter function assumes, the data past is
min-max without modification to simple, approaches to fix.
This are either to change get Center rectangle to rectangle, Min or
change the calculation of Min corner and Max Corner in in the, in the
resulting code.
So you can see these two here and you can see how these are being
done.
It is correct that
Exactly saying the offset in the dimension.
This is being interpreted as a corner and that probably was just
because I read it when we were doing here, and I just wanted to do
that or something like this, probably didn't think too much about
because then we just did it the Q&A last time.
And then you can see here, when we do get cliprect this rectangle, to
that's being specified, here, you can see that it's turning that
rectangle into a center point in a dimension.
So probably the easiest thing to do in this case would be to
pass a minute Max because since that's what's already getting done
here.
It seems like maybe that's the best thing to do.
I don't really know.
It depends on how we imagine these functions to be used, but here we
go.
Let's just try it this way instead.
Oops, so if we do rectangle Min here, then this offset will now be the
minimum Corner as expected.
And the dimension will just go out from that and we'll see how that
works.
Okay.
So I've made that change and I believe that corresponds to suggestion
one, right?
This would have been to change the other routine.
So addition to be change the other routine and hey look they are
totally on on point or on fleek as we might say that is exactly the
problem and it looks like we still have some other issues.
We might want to dress like you can see our tool tip still doesn't
work properly that.
I don't think it's anything to do is clip.
Rex, I believe that is just because our draw order is not in any
particular, least smart State at the moment.
So we have some issues here to do with that.
So what I might suggest is since snoring tortoise went through the
trouble of writing in to tell us how to fix this it seems like maybe
the least we can do assuming that he cares about it or she cares about
it at all is just to go ahead and change those drawers.
So for example,
In here.
We have some debug text.
Think it's called Tech stop there.
I think that's the one.
So I think most of our text is going through Tech stop I'm not 100%
sure about that but you can see that the only to push bitmap calls in
here are right there.
And in here you can see that there's only one and it's for drawing an
actual bitmap.
So I think pretty much 100% of the text flows through this line and
what you can see about this line is that this line actually does APUSH
bitmap.
Of two lines of text, one of which is the drop shadow and one of which
is the actual white text on top and we're actually drawing these at
the same Z value.
Because we got rid of the Shadow transform, text transform stuff doing
anything in particular.
And I don't think I really want to think about that too hard
necessarily.
But I think what we probably could do is just say if we want this
working again, then when we set that shadow transform, instead of
default flat transform, all we really have to do is offset these by a
little bit of Z, and I think that that just fixes the problem.
You know, don't quote me on this.
I don't really know, but I think it's probably true.
So again, I don't really know what order these are supposed to go.
And I'm gonna have to think about that a little bit.
Backing Shadow UI text tooltip, seems likely I don't know but so you
could imagine it's just a signing these literally unit increments in Z
like so and those would just sort of get closer to the camera as we
went.
Similarly, if we wanted to make these be things that went further
away, we could do something like this in Stead.
Now I don't know what we set up for the Z range is the only thing for
clip.
You know, our our orthographic transform.
I if I remember correctly we didn't really do much with near and far
clipping planes.
So what we did is we just hard coded them here too.
- hundred hundred, which means that basically anything that we want to
put in here will be fine as long as it doesn't overflow.
That value, I think.
So let's just try this first because the z-buffer should in theory
sort these things for us.
Would be my assumption.
So now we can see just looking at this it looks like they're sorted
properly now and that's good.
It looks like our tool tip is still a little bit busted so we may have
to look at that one but the text itself appears correct and so maybe
we can just go in there and take a look at the tool tips because that
seems to be the only thing that is now incorrect, right?
All the rest of this stuff looks like, it's working pretty good.
We can pick properly in here and look at our various d.
Frames, we can size this window.
We can even hover and get a tool tip, but we just don't see the
tooltip, right?
So I
No, will have to take a little bit of a gander over here at what's
going on, because I don't know what's going on in this code anymore,
was a long time since we touched it.
So, what I'd like to do is take a look at say, for example, the
profiler just so I can remember what we were even doing with Z in
there.
Whether we were setting Z.
I just I'm literally looking at the code here to just re-familiarize
myself a little bit with what this code was doing.
So what you can see here is there is a base Z value and we're actually
Actually using Z as a sort.
This was what I was suspicious of here.
So what that means is z value wise, we are actually doing a bunch of
stuff with the Z value to do sorting and so it does suggest to me that
what we probably need to do.
In this case is give ourselves plenty of room here.
And in order to do that, we will need because we're using Z inside of
individual elements to do sorting.
And so that seems like an important thing if that makes sense.
So what we want to do from there out and again, if this is 100 minus
10,
The depth rating thing.
We're going to need a lot of range.
So what we can do in this case is again, just if we just give
ourselves a large window of the near and far, clipping plane, we
should be okay to use those for sorting values like we were using, I
suspect.
So I just want to double check to make sure that doesn't ruin any of
the stuff that we were doing.
It doesn't look like it does.
And so, that's a good thing.
And now we've got more room in the Z range for any given individual
element because we were using those, as it turns out,
So now what you can see when you when I'm sort of hovering over, these
is that the tooltip itself now appears to be working correctly as far
as sorting on top of these things.
So the only real problem with our tool tip is that the texture, the
tooltip appears to be drawing underneath the tooltip itself.
And the reason we're not seeing that as a result is, the Z will kill
it.
So, what you have to remember and sometimes when you see these
results, especially if you haven't program Graphics very much in the
past, you can Stacey things that seem kind of confusing because they
don't conform to any sort of real world.
That you would expect to see.
And so let me just take a brief moment since we're seeing one of them
now to just try and articulate what's going on here.
You can see as I move over here for the tooltip.
you can see that the rectangle for the tooltip is drawing, and I don't
know if you can see this on the video as well because maybe the
compression artifacts are too bad but hopefully if you're maximizing
your at 1080p, full stream Source, whatever
Hopefully, you will see this, you can see what's behind the tooltip,
right?
So here might be the best example.
I'll get it for you.
If I grab a tool tip there, you can even see the level moving around
behind it or like the blue bar of the cube behind it.
So what you can tell from this is that we are seeing what is behind
the tool tip.
So the tooltip is drawing in a modulated blend mode and it's
darkening, whatever was in the frame buffer prior to
Being drawn.
Okay, so now if you were thinking of this strictly, as a real-world
analog where I'm holding up, say a translucent or transparent in this
case, transparent piece of cellophane or something, that just happens
to be dark.
So it cuts down the light of a little bit but otherwise you can see
through it.
What you would expect to see here.
If the texts were drawing behind it for the tooltip is you expect to
see a darkened version of the text.
And in fact, you can see a dark inversion of the other text behind it.
Was drawn as part of the profile window.
You just can't see a darkened version of this text, right?
And so, it's important to ask ourselves here is, does that imply that
the text is either being clipped or not drawn at all?
And the answer is no in our case that doesn't actually apply that and
the reason that it doesn't imply that is because, remember, we are
using a z-buffer.
That means that every time a pixel is drawn, it's going to test to see
whether the Z value of what is already in the frame buffer at that
location is higher or lower than the individual object.
That's you know,
That is higher or lower than the thing that we're drawing now, right?
And furthermore we have a multi sample buffer on and the multi sample
buffer will look to see whether or not individual samples.
Are we're also using Alpharetta coverage and what that means is our
Alpha 2 coverage will be making it.
So that eight steps, I think that's how many we got on.
This machine is eight levels of eight samples per pixel.
Alpha 2 coverage will be randomly setting those
date samples.
Well pseudorandomly setting, those eight samples.
How many of it will cover for any given pixel is based on the opacity
of the thing being drawn.
So given that all of those things are in play, what we don't actually
know in.
Any given circumstance is exactly what if we don't know what order
things are being drawn in, right?
If the Z value of one thing is underneath the Z value of another.
It depends on the order in which those things get drawn, whether or
not
We will see them show through or not.
Now, in this case we have to think through it very carefully because
it does seem to suggest that they probably we should see something
showing through.
And the reason that we probably should see something showing through
is because, whatever the opacity of this thing is, we know that it
hasn't fallen below, the eight samples per pixel threshold.
Because when we move it over something that we can see like this begin
World change, right?
It's obviously not so opaque that it covers all eight samples.
If it did cover, all eight samples, we would not see anything behind
it at.
All right.
It would just look black but since we can see something besides behind
it, that means at least one of those.
Eight multi samples is not getting covered, right?
Okay.
So what we would expect to see them in this case is even if we were to
draw the thing afterwards, which I'm assuming must be happening here,
right?
Or sorry.
Even if we were to draw the thing beforehand and then draw thing on
top of it we would be expecting to see that thing show up dimly below
it right but here's another option of what can happen in this case.
If the XIV, if we were to draw these, in the other order, right?
So let's say we were drawing these two things in the opposite order,
so we're going to draw well, even at that case, I don't think it would
happen.
Yeah, strike.
What I was about to say, but another thing that can happen here,
right?
That's what I point that out is the Z.
Buffer also will kill anything.
We're trying to draw that is below something that we already Drew.
So, in the case that we had accidentally, let's say set the text to
draw behind the tooltip bar, which I don't think it'd be possible
because presumably wouldn't have shown up in our previous rendering.
But let's say we did that, we could expect to see nothing there.
And the reason we can expect
I think there is that even though the open up the version of the
tooltip backdrop is not opaque, right?
And we and it what it's going to show is when it you know, kind of
goes over something, it's going to dim it.
The things that it will dim have to be things that have already been
drawn.
They have to be earlier in the draw order because opengl is not
sorting anything for us.
It's just using a z-buffer to resolve the depth.
What that means is that when the text comes, if the texts were to have
a z-value lower than the rectangle, all of the pixels for the text
would get rejected because they would always think they were behind
it.
So not only would they not draw on top of it, but they actually
wouldn't draw at all because it has laid down a solid rectangle of
That is higher than the text and that appears to be what we're seeing
here.
But we could also just be seeing a clipping problem, right where the
text is getting clipped.
The reason I think that it's not as easy, sorting problem is again, it
doesn't seem like the tooltip would have worked in our previous
render, which was sorting if the Z value is less, but who knows?
I just wanted to point, all that stuff out about how it's a little
confusing there because because the Z buffer is a comparison and a
rejection, not a sort.
You can get situations where it appears like something should be
drawing, one way or another, and it's, in fact, drawing an either way,
right?
So you might think that you would always see either the text dimly
behind the
Tangle or the text in front of the rectangle, but not just no text at
all.
If you were in fact, drawing it properly with no clipping.
That is actually deceptively.
Not the case because there's plenty of ways with the z-buffer, that,
that could actually occur, right?
That's the only part.
I wanted to get out there again.
Crazy Graphics bugs, just something to be aware of.
So, anyway, let's take a look at the tool tip situation.
I think that's in here if I remember was down at the bottom.
Yes, it is.
So let's go ahead and take a look at what's going on there.
In fact, we move it over here, so my head's not ever going to be in
the way and let's take a look, what's going on here.
So you can see here that we're passing the tooltip transform as the
place.
We want to draw this text, we're drawing some stuff here but I don't
really know.
It's a bit of a little bit weird.
We've got a hard-coded, that's probably the problem.
We've got a hard-coded value for the text here, which doesn't seem
particularly bright.
Can't say that sounds smart.
And so probably all that we're seeing here.
Literally what we're seeing here is the clipping like I was saying
before.
Like I said, it's suggestive clipping turns out.
It was slipping, it's not clipping in the clip rectangle sense, which
makes sense why it didn't get fixed when we fix the clipping
rectangle.
What's actually happening here is, it's clipping outside of the Z
range so you can see that this is being given 11 110,000 in Z, but we
only allow in our in our transform, if you go back to the math
functions, we only allow 10,000 as the maximum value.
And so what ends up happening is it's past the far clipping plane and
just gets clipped, it gets clipped in Z, not an X and Y but in Z and
so that's really our only problem here.
And I wonder why we had to do this in the first place.
I don't really know why I'm not sure why we couldn't just use the tool
to transform itself.
Probably has something to do with the way we're sorting before or
maybe this was just an expedient way to do it.
It's the debug system so hey nobody probably cared, especially not me.
But at this point, we do care because we want it to work again in our
system because we'd like to see our tool tips.
Now, what's interesting is the text out at
Here, I'm not really sure why.
It doesn't take one of these transforms.
I would like to take a look and see how we were calling that most of
the time, just, to find out why it's it's not just taking a transform
as normal.
I'm not sure why that would be but let's take a look.
So, here's text out at and you can see that all it does is called Tech
Stop and it uses a Nazi here.
The p is just a regular P value, and when we come through here, it's
going to call push him out.
It's going to have to pass.
I'll Transform of some kind and it looks like, okay, so you can see it
does Shadow, transform, text transform.
This is kind of a nut.
So, way to do this, if you think about it, what's really happening
here is that these two transforms are assuming that the transforms are
just you know automatically going to be
In some plain of Texans Aegis sorts within that.
That doesn't seem particularly bright.
It's at that doesn't seem like a particularly smart thing to do.
I also don't really know where the actual Z value here.
Is getting applied.
You can see the @z, let's take a look here.
So there's it's getting put into that bitmap offset, right?
There's that at Z so we're effectively taking the transform in the
text transform and just using those as baselines and then we're at
using this at Z, to sort of rebase where the things are.
Again, I think that was probably something we had to
To do because we were trying to, you know, use our old wacky, two and
a half D system, that doesn't seem to be particularly smart to me.
I'm not even sure why we would have to play.
For the for the Shadow and the regular text before.
It doesn't really make a whole lot of sense.
Honestly.
So I kind of feel like this whole system wants to be simplified.
Now that it can be, I'm going to take a quick Gander.
I just want to know.
If I take a look at all the places, we call text out at.
I'm just curious as to how they're used.
So you can see here.
We've got a basic text element 1 and in the basic text element 1.
I guess we don't really pass in a z of any kind.
So when we're just doing basic text elements, it looks like we're you
know, we're sort of just not really doing any kind of text element
stuff.
There we got the one in the tooltip, which is busted as we know and we
know why it's broken.
Now we have this
Here.
This is the string that kind of just shows up at the top of the screen
is like a permanent reminder of what our frame rate and memory
Footprints and things like this?
It's all that does we then have a text out at
That were using right here to sort of show us.
Hey, okay, you know, here's the the tree that we, you know, that we
view all our stuff in in, this is the case of a group.
This is like, if there's a group, it'll draw, the, like, name of the
group, but I don't think that's basically it, right?
This.
I don't know what this is.
This is old radial menu stuff, which we don't use anymore, so that's
just not a concern.
It's not even the same function.
So there's not a lot of
This is getting called.
So it wouldn't really be out of the question to just start having it
past a z value.
That was sensible and get us out of the business of this Shadow
transform, text transform stuff, which doesn't really make a whole lot
of sense to me because I feel like we should always inherit this z a
little bit more explicitly.
So I would kind of be interested in doing that again.
I want to see in basic text element.
The only problem there is four basic text element.
I don't really know if the people have been leaning on this fact.
That they can get Z values.
You know in a convenient way here.
I,
Because none of these, all of these things, kind of just assumed a
sort of basic Zenus.
And I don't really know.
Here's where, for example, we make those like Boolean buttons, right?
And so I think everyone just assumes that the Z is just a flat thing
and it doesn't really stack on top of itself at all.
I don't really know how smart that is, you know?
Maybe it is.
Maybe it isn't.
It seems to me like, it might be problematic in a few ways, but at the
same time, maybe it's not, I don't really know.
I guess what I would say is we can just fix the tooltips or we can fix
this a little bit more, maybe, what I'll do is just fix a tooltips and
hey, if
Becomes a problem.
Then we just don't look at it further, but you can kind of see why
that's just a little bit weird and probably not what we really wanted
to do.
So in here, if we said like, oh okay, we just want the tooltips to be
on top of everything else.
That's all we were trying to do here.
What I could say is well, alright, when we initialize these things
Shadow transform
You know, we've got here is all of our stuff.
So if we want the Z value for these things, to sort of counteract, the
sort of normal Shadow transform that we're seeing here, what we would
need to do is like boost them over by 4,000, might we'd have to like,
push them up right into the closer range.
What I might say is, hey,
Eventually, it's probably the right thing.
To go ahead and make the flow through the debug system sensibly, but
for now we just don't care.
And then, I think we should now have our tooltips back or rather the
tooltip text back.
Obviously the tooltip, rectangles back.
So there's that tooltip text working again and you can look at the
frames here and so on, I don't know that there's anything else
particularly that we did with tooltips.
I think it was just mostly for hover in the profiler.
I don't know if there was any other thing that it did.
So anyway, this is seems to be working relatively well, now I think we
can drill in here.
And that works.
Okay to do.
It was there a there wasn't a back button.
I remember.
That was because it was hard to implement to know which was back.
I guess I don't really remember there's something nasty about going
backwards.
I remember that.
But anyway, you can you can see that we're pretty good to go here.
We can we can look at you know anything we want now and it looks like
everything's back and working.
Okay.
And the profiler, what are what is all this thing World mode?
Some locations, enfant location?
Sim region.
Handmade particles.
You know, it really bums me out that we don't get the function names
anymore, all because llvm and clang, or dumb or I should say GCC
And the C plus plus back, I suppose, because they kind of ratified the
dumb that dumb decision.
It really bums me out.
That's the only reason we don't have the function names here is
because C++ is spec didn't provide access to a constant like a string
an actual string literal for the function name.
They only provide access to a variable name which we couldn't
concatenate on and that was just the worst anyway.
but had trouble drawing, whatever that is
Go back to Route.
Here we go.
So anyway we don't know the function names anymore which is a bummer.
I wonder if we could like cheat and have an, if deaf in there that
makes us get the function names on Windows because I really like
having the function names.
I don't like having to go.
Okay, what's this?
You know what's that win32?
Handmade sevp line 24:02 right?
It's like, okay, well let's see, win32 here made that CPP.
Go to 24:02, okay?
It's the game update block or whatever, right?
Well, I suppose that one is less bad because that one at least we
could was a string constant one, handmade debug 1981.
All rights debug end, right?
So, I want that to just say, debug n, you know, and that's what it
used to do, before we had to fix it for
Try not to get too upset about people who do C++ stuff literally
making the wrong decision in every possible circumstance they ever
can, which is kind of like some kind of unbroken streak.
It's like some kids like the longest unbroken streak of bad decisions
that that we've had in history.
It's probably like u.s.
foreign policy followed by the C++ standards committee.
All right.
So let's see what if we were to go to that.
Just real
Way and take a look.
So actually do like interface .h, the reason that that's happening
now.
If I remember correctly, it's like when we build the, you know, these
debug names, we do this this sort of nonsense here, right?
File line, counter name
Like that and I guess we don't stick D in there like the because that
is sometimes underscore underscore function.
Right?
And so, you know what we could do here, I think if we wanted to is we
could do something like if you know handmade win32.
The think we have that I could do something.
I think we're, that actually works, right?
So on handmade win32, we
That on the end.
I don't know if that'll work, I'm going to see if it does, maybe it
does, maybe it doesn't.
There we go.
So, so that way, we can have those on win32, right?
And it will always show them
Yeah.
now, I suppose, the other thing is, maybe we were still getting that
information through a secondary source because I guess one thing
that's interesting is here are the time to Regions
and if I don't do that, so if I don't have win32 and so the build
right,
Set in here.
So that way you know people who are compiling, other platforms won't
have to worry if I do force it to the other way.
I guess the thing I'm not sure about is how is the what is the profile
do in that situation?
How is the profile getting this information?
How is it getting the function name here?
You know I'm saying that must be stored in an additional location
because in here it like doesn't know that now,
But in here it does so I guess like we still we worked around this
problem and then I guess we didn't forward it forward when we had
because we only worked around it for platform portability and it was
after we'd already finished everything.
So I guess it has to do with the fact that the name gets stored here.
So, that's it.
So we still do store the name here, we just don't concatenate it on,
right?
So in theory, I should be able to get that piece of information back
in the debug layer where we do the tooltip, I think.
So, for example, on here where we've got tooltip,
Like this where we do element quid in theory.
If I did element name, I would get that back.
So maybe I don't have to be too grumpy about this because maybe we
already solved the problem for all intents and purposes.
And I can save my extreme hostility for the C++ people.
For one of the other many Myriad times where it was, like, not
something you could work around.
Let's go ahead and just try it this way.
That battle I guess I can just leave it back to the original way.
It was like so, so maybe what I can do here is say Yeah in this case
let's let's print out the element name as well.
Which I don't actually know exactly what that is.
So in this case, I'm going to have to look
It is just a character.
So I'll just say like,
That.
And we'll see if that now, which one did I just update?
Their, I don't even remember which function as in profile bars, so I
believe I go to profile gear and then I'm in here.
So there we go.
So then we can get it back right by just like sticking that.
Additional bar piece on there and then similarly, I should be able to
do that in the other case, where you had the tool tip again right
here.
Because we already did the work to work around this, so that's good.
That.
We'll work on Linux as well, which is nice too for people who want to
be able to use this.
So, let's see.
Looking at this here on the frames one.
There we go.
You can see debug Haitian frame display a game update, perfect here.
We've got them too.
And I think those are the only places we had it.
This was, this was just to say, which frame index it was just to Aid
in debugging there, and the clocks here didn't ever print one out, it
was already on the on the screen.
So this one was just one that says, here's how many cycles.
It was cumulative, right?
I'm sorry here's how many cycles it was per call.
Like that number divided by the call count and then what the
cumulative percentage was.
So you can kind of see like, okay, cumulative up to its 90% right here
is where it ends.
You know, what's kind of interesting about looking at.
This is update and render entities takes a lot of time now, which is
kind of cool now that our profilers back and working.
We can see the 30% of the time is spent there, which is pretty
interesting actually, right?
I'm not sure why.
And it would be interesting to know why.
It would be interesting to take a look at what was costing that time
in a little more detail.
And in fact, why don't we go ahead and do that?
So we're not compiling in debug mode.
I'm sorry, we are compiling a debug mode, right?
So that's fine.
And I'm going to go ahead and go to update and render entities.
Let's take a look at that call.
Here it is.
You can see the time function
Bit here and we go through each of the end of these individually.
We do the Boost code here which we don't really need to do anymore,
but still kind of happening.
We have the physics part here.
We've got the render part here, and then we've got the debug pick
entity part here.
And so, what might be nice at this point is to do a little, you know,
sort of
Begin block, instrumentation and just kind of take a look at where.
Exactly, we're getting that time.
Getting where?
That time is getting sucked away, right?
So let's see.
We know that we're going to process active entities so let's let's
just do some quick instrumentation here.
So there's the begin block.
End block.
And there's all that stuff.
Do do, do do.
And inside there, we actually.
Have during the render, we've got this debug as well.
So I'm just going to go ahead and give those a little prefixes because
hey, those are there.
We don't know that they're entity based at the moment, if we just saw
them show up on the profile and weren't sure what we had been doing at
that time, we'd be like, what physics?
What?
So at least now we can see that there are specific to this
All right, so this should give us a little bit more granularity there
in terms of the profiling, so we can kind of see what's going on.
Hmm.
That's weird.
Did I miss a closing block?
Begin block and block begin block.
And block begin block.
Yes, I did.
There we go.
Try that one more time.
So it looks like here what we can kind of see is that none of these
things, they're all kind of down in the noise so it's really only the
entity render call that is doing anything particularly substantial.
So we kind of know exactly where our situation is.
And if we take a look here, you can kind of see, you know, debug end
is not something that we're indeed acylation are things that are
processing like tons of entries and doing a bunch of stuff, and we
don't care so much about those,
But these two right here, we do kind of care about because we want to
make sure that nothing particularly nefarious going on in there.
Opengl renderer commands.
He is also a little bit suspicious at that point.
I'm not sure we may want to take a look at at what's going on in there
because that should be made relative Vision.
I don't know.
It depends on whether the GL texture changes and stuff like that are
taking too much time.
And who knows what?
Not in terms of the actual rendering, but I just mean in terms of
going through the driver and doing the handle translation stuff like
that.
But let's take a look because for only 510 calls is taking a 60
thousand Cycles to do these.
And so it just seems like well, you know, I'd like
To know that that was appropriate because I don't know that it
necessarily was right.
So some things that are interesting in here.
You can see that we're creating some vectors.
And doing matches on them.
I don't know if get bets match bitmap from, that's a very slow and an
optimized and pretty stupid call.
Really.
So I'd be interested to know how much time that was taking and then we
look on here.
We've kind of got some other fairly straightforward stuff.
I think just pushing on nothing, particularly interesting going on
there.
Just, you know, pushing volume, Atlas like that.
So who knows how much time those
Take, I would like to know about that get best best match bitmap from
I'm assuming that it's not really taking too much of a problem.
Because okay, so there it is it's already been removed, that's already
a Time function and is not too because I would say like I feel like
that function will have to optimize eventually but we just don't have
very many Assets in the system right now.
And so since we don't have very many assets, we wouldn't expect it to
take long to iterate through them.
Right.
Let me pause this for a second so you can see right here.
There's the function, and it's not taking any time.
So we're really talking about this entity render here.
We don't really know,
The more specific elements of that are so we probably need to
investigate even further to see what is this low point?
So since we know that in here, let's see, we're going to go through
here.
Get best fit bitmap from push Cube, push bitmap.
I guess we know we sort of have some of these, I'm going to get rid of
these ifs, don't know.
We don't really need them at the moment.
We're not doing that one.
So we really only have two here, I'm going to go ahead and just and
see if I can isolate this a little bit further.
So let's go ahead and do you know
Render pieces.
Under hip points.
Render volume.
And now I've kind of got this, like marked up pretty explicitly, so we
should be able to see if there's if it's an even spread or what.
So now if I pause we can see render volume takes quite a lot of time,
but render pieces also does, so both of those are pretty slow
actually.
So what I'd like to do is take a look in there because those are just
both basic render calls.
I'd like to kind of know what's going on in there.
That's making them so slow.
So if we go to get best, I'm sorry if we know that that's not taking
any time.
We know that this is probably not take any time because it's literally
just dereferencing some values.
Push Cube and push bitmap are are really our only sort of suspicious
and entities here and I suspect you know it could just be the case
that because unoptimized these are going to go through
Tons of calls and lots of cop unnecessary copies and stuff like that.
It could just be that.
That's just too much, right?
But I want to make sure that's the case before I say.
So for sure,
And if there isn't something else going on, that's that's you know.
More suspicious, if that makes sense.
So let's take a look at what's going on there.
Just looking through here.
I mean, I can sort of see
I mean, there really isn't much to say about these functions.
They're just pretty much writing stuff out extremely straightforward.
So I don't know that there's all that much to say.
It may just be that there's just too many function calls in here.
Of course, don't get in line and when you're not in release mode and
if I look here at, you know, get current quads for example,
I mean the again, just nothing happening.
So I'm pretty sure all of these things are basically harmless.
I'm going to verify that by switching to 0-2.
So that once those are in lined, I want to see what happens.
So again, pushes that way up in the top there, but render pieces is
still pretty substantial at 10%, I'm not really sure.
45 hunt for that eight thousand Cycles is an appropriate number of
Cycles just for pushing some floats around but again it's a little bit
hard to tell.
Without further analysis of it.
So, if I take a look at here,
And again, all I'm doing is sort of looking to see if there's anything
particularly unusual about what we're doing.
I might want to take a, just a quick Gander in in optimized mode.
Mind you of what the compiler has actually generated here just to give
myself a little bit of a just a little bit of insight into like what
actually is going on in here.
So if we step into render pieces for example and I'm going to go to
the disassembly here, you know here's the code for push Cube and you
You can see here that we're going to skip over this.
See here.
And look at see if we're going to make any calls.
This is actually the call to push bitmap.
So that's going to look at the asset there.
That's going to go.
So I got to let this run so we can load some assets.
It's going to skip bloat assets on the that's going to skip Red Ring.
A bunch on the
Frame because it hasn't had anything loaded yet.
Alright, so let's go in now.
So we can see one of the calls.
Here's the call to get asset, it will succeed this time.
And now I'm going to look at that call to push bitmap.
So here it is.
Right.
I'm stepping in to push bitmap here and we can sort of see us testing
what's going on.
Here's the check against the bitmap width and height to make sure that
there is a bitmap to push.
We probably don't really need that anymore.
But you know, we probably could just let it go.
But here we are calling get bitmap Tim and that looks like it was not
inlined.
Right?
So it's actually calling out to get bitmapped in now.
That's a little weird.
And I'll be honest, I wouldn't have expected quite so much work to be
done here.
This could probably be done a lot better.
You can just see there's just a lot of lot of fussing.
Just a lot of fussing.
It did in line, get render entity basis P which again is very, very
straightforward.
I believe now, because we basically got it.
It's just this, we got it so much.
In fact, I don't know if object transform is even worth it anymore.
Like it kind of feels like this.
Maybe wants to go away entirely and object, transform should just be
banished but you know it did in line that but that's literally just a
trivial
Trivial operation.
But you look at, there's just a lot here and to be honest, I'm not
really sure.
That just some multiplies and some tracks would account for all of
this.
You know, let's let's do a little experiment here, shall we?
I'm just, you know, I'm kind of interested in, you know, since we're
we happen to be in the middle of it.
I'm just going to go ahead and and see.
So you know, here's get bitmap Tim right there it is.
And well it actually goes to here.
I'm going to I'm going to just cut and paste that and I'm going to cut
and paste it into the scratch buffer.
So you can see get bitmap, Tim here.
And here's all the instructions for it and maybe that was a reasonable
number instructions and maybe it wasn't.
What I want to do here is I'm going to go to get bitmap, Tim now.
Which is this code here and all I'm going to do is, I'm just going to
rewrite it without using any C++, right?
I'm just going to use straight.
See and that's all I'm going to do and I want to make sure that it
isn't.
There isn't anything funny going on here?
So, if we take a look at what's going to get produced for size, it's
a, you know, size is a V2, right?
In fact, I'll just I'll just go ahead and do it this way.
So, we can generate either version.
And so if I reproduce this second to say, well, alright the exercise
is going to be the height times the bitmap with the over-height,
right?
That's just a multiply and the size in y is going to be the regular
height.
That's that's all we were trying to do here, right?
The alignment you can see here is the hadamard product of the aligned
percentage and the size times the C line again, that is just a 2d
equation, right?
And so the highwomen,
Murmured product is just multiplying these two things.
So really all that's happening here is, is this, right?
You're just that's I mean, there's nothing.
That's all that's happening.
The Z is getting copied, directly, the X and the Y again are doing a
very straightforward equation.
like so, and
That's, that's really all we're talking about here.
And then get render entity basis.
P is is really just
This.
Oops.
So it's just adding the two together.
And so just adding the two together is, is really trivial, right?
It's this.
And so, all I want to do there is just do them explicitly.
And so, that's what this function looks like without C++, right?
So, without operator, overloading of any kind, this is the actual set
of operations, that's occurring.
Don't know why.
I just did that.
So that's everything.
So I'm going to compile this.
What did I do wrong there?
Is object transform sorry.
There we go.
So that's really all there is to it, and we'll have another transfer.
We there'd be another sort of thing I could do there that I'll do in a
second but I'm going to go ahead and and do this again.
And I just want to see if if it really was correct to assume that that
Stuff bitmap can.
Okay.
So that's very interesting already.
You notice I couldn't set a breakpoint there and what that suggests to
me is that now it has been in lined and previously it had not been in
lined and that's a very interesting thing, right?
So here we go.
So let's take a look here where the here's that call to push bitmap,
same call and and here we go right?
Here's push bitmap and what you can see
Oh God.
What you can see is that the exact same set of SSA operations,
Now, produces inline code, which hadn't been in line before.
Probably because it couldn't.
know that the
Well, no.
I mean it can't be an aliasing issue because we're still leaving
everything in the structs and we didn't pull anything out to a
temporary variable.
I have no idea.
I I guess I don't know why the compiler didn't know that those two
sequences were the same but hey guess what?
Now, there isn't a function call to that function.
I wish I could say that that was surprising, but it didn't surprise
me.
And you know, that it didn't surprise me because that's why I took the
step of writing it out explicitly.
Not fabulous.
So if I now pause, you can see that render pieces is still quite a bit
of time, so it's not like we, you know, did some major amazing
optimization on it yet but it's a little troubling right to see that.
Literally, I took the exact same piece of code did nothing to it and
just the same SS.
A single static assignment.
We haven't talked about animator, I guess I shouldn't be using that
term yet.
But the same set of mathematical operations in one case, is understood
to be in line of bull.
In the other case it isn't and I literally didn't do anything other
than just expand this out in the same way that you would expand that
out if you were to include those functions there.
So that's not great.
Just to be clear that is not great.
That is what we would call a not great thing.
But let's continue to investigate further.
All right?
So we can't even compare Apples to Apples because the other one wasn't
getting in line to.
Now, this one is so we don't even know.
How much of a difference that one made in terms of assembly?
But I think it also probably resulted in less assembly code just in
general.
And again that's because I think it was doing more operations than I
felt.
Like it should have been doing in that situation.
Let's go to the disassembly here and just look
So, it looks like it starts about here.
And ends about here.
So I don't know how much better that is.
Here's that original version.
I don't know how to,
Yes, I can come in here and just put it at the end.
Here is the new version.
So it's definitely simpler a lot.
I don't know if it kind of elided, some of those observations, I'm not
being particularly meticulous, meticulous here at looking at it.
But you can see at least that, you know, I mean this was very long
before, right?
All I really do think this was doing more than necessary and I feel
like now it's down to sort of more like the number of operations I
would expect, but again, I'm not being meticulous there, so I don't,
it could have just stuck some of the Ops further.
And so it's a little bit hard to say, right?
Alright, so looking at here, so that's one call.
And now at least we're getting that call in line which I wanted, let's
take a look at the push quad call.
I just want to know if that's getting in line as well or not.
That here.
Where are we at here?
So we are in push bitmap, which is where we want to be.
However, it's pretty hard to isolate, where it actually spread this
code out too.
Unfortunately.
But I guess that's good enough for now.
Okay, so in the push quad call.
It looks like this has been properly in lined as well.
Aha.
So I'm going to take a look at this.
Saucy gentleman right here.
because I'll be honest, he does not look particularly
good to me.
In fact, what I might do is I might actually step back for a second.
Figure out what's going on here.
so somehow,
and I am not sure how
our rounding function is actually something that is not getting
inlined.
And so our color, I'm assuming this is due to the color conversion.
Oops, I don't know what just happened, hit some weird, hot cue there.
Let's go ahead and jump to the non optimized version of this code.
Since we know that round f is getting called, I don't really need the
Deep the other version right now.
So let's go to the disassembly here and see what's happening with that
with respect to that.
So it should be in the call to our GBA Pac for it by 8.
So, let's jump in there and you can see us calling round.
And so, here's an actual call to round.
Oh boy.
Oh my goodness.
So this is just an epic disaster, right?
So all we're trying to do is round a number to an integer to pack a
color.
So this is just, this is just real bad.
I mean, look at this, we're going to actually eat this function call
going to do all this work.
We're going to eat another function.
Call to f d and I don't even know where that is in the source code.
Oh God just
My Lord, no.
All right, so that's just that's real really bad.
Like that is really, really, really bad.
When we're pushing Sprites on to a list of things that is just awful
and let's just go ahead and get rid of that right now.
So I'm going to go find that round F function and excise it from this
code base immediately, because that is a really bad, very bad
situation.
That is not good.
And is that
Add the Badness of it is exemplified by its being bad, and we don't
want that.
So, you saw how much code there was there.
It was multiple function calls, it was a call into round, F, multiple
calls into F DN.
T, there is a whole bunch of boilerplate.
It couldn't be inlined.
This is really bad.
Surround F needs to go.
Fortunately, for us, we were smart at the beginning of our code base
and didn't call Round F.
We called round real 322.
You in 32.
So we have an even easier job for ourselves because we knew we were
going to have to replace.
This is some day and that day is today.
So the question is, if we just want to do a rounding function, so we
want to take a floating point value and rally to an integer.
How do we do that?
Well,
Fortunately, for us back when we originally did this, we didn't know
anything about 70.
We know something about Cindy now.
So we know about the Intel and trims, this guide.
Oh, by the way, thank you snoring tortoise
I forgot to close our bug there after we fixed it.
So, what we can do is we all know about the Intel intrinsics guide,
right?
And where is my?
There it is.
We know all know about the entire entry this guy which gives us access
to those nice intrinsics that we've been using and what happens to be
the case.
And again, remember we are on sse2 is what we decided our platform
was.
So we can go up to these sausage element right here, but we can use
any of the other ones.
It turns out that all of that work that was being done there with the
craziness that you saw.
We don't really need any of that work.
That's the C runtime libraries around F function.
We don't
Use that because it will you just saw what it was going to do.
We want something that, you know, we can be done much more quickly.
How much more quickly can we do this?
Well, it turns out that there's actually
a an actual function in SSE, a processor instruction for rounding.
So it should really be one instruction to do what was current
previously, taking hundreds of instructions and function calls and
everything.
There, it should just be able to call Just One of these and so we
should be able to round a, we should be able to round a floating point
value with with just, you know, going straight away.
So,
Let's take a look at that in a second here.
I believe I can't remember the names of these here.
Let me see if we if there's any way I can isolate them.
It's like convert PS.
We used it on the in fact you know what?
It's right here, right?
CVT TPS is.
I believe the one that does truncation the extra T without the extra T
I believe it doesn't do truncation does rounding right.
So let's see here, it's convert PS epi32.
Convert packed single Precision.
Three fluorine has in a 2-pack, 32 Miniatures, and store the results
in test and I believe it will just use whatever the mode is of the
chip at that time, which will be rounding if we haven't set it to
anything else.
So this is all we really need to call now, we don't need to do packed
singles because we're only converting one, but I don't know if they
have a convert s sf32.
Do they?
They do.
So.
That's also in SC2 and that's fine.
So if we want to do a convert SS in this case let's see what this does
convert the lower single-precision floating-point element into a
32-bit integer and store the result in death so convert sssi 32 should
be what we want and it should just preserve provide the integer that
we are looking for, right?
So, what we should be able to do here, I would hope is to just say,
okay, really, all we wanted was mmm convert SS SI 32, mmm, set, 1, PS.
Real 32.
And so that's I think and I guess set 1ss is really what we want.
Set SS.
All we really want to do is say, hey, take this float and round it
please.
That would be nice of you.
And presumably we can do this in either case, I don't actually know if
there's a way to do this in a way that doesn't involve casting because
I don't think they provide any version that that would do it that way.
We just have to take the rounding one way or the other.
Let's see ya.
So we're just going to have to do it that way but I think that's all
we need.
So if we do that in theory we should be good.
I don't actually know that's verify that our game is not all broken,
but it doesn't appear to be broken.
So now we've at least gotten rid of those calls, let's take a quick
look here to and see if that helps at all.
It's getting better.
Still not great, it's getting better.
So, let's take a look now and see if we've gotten rid of that.
Oh, that was good.
Get I said that and I was comparing the non-optimized version.
Now, let's see how our optimized version is, now that we've gotten
that that call of round F out of there.
Ha ha ha.
All right now you will notice that it has basically gotten slammed
down from what I think started at nine percent of the time down two
point eight, seven percent of the time.
So I was right.
I was like I was going to say removing that that call like, multiple
for calls to round outside of the inner part of that,
Should have done a lot more in it did so they're okay.
So
I'll say a couple things about that because I think it's a really good
illustration of a bunch of things that we've said many times I've had
made hero and they come up occasionally.
So number one
How important is that profiling, right?
We were very quickly, able to zero in on what the problem was and know
what was going wrong, right?
So having a profiler always running, it's just great for awareness,
right?
Number two,
Being able to read the assembly, right?
The only way I started to know what could be going on there is because
I looked at the actual Assembly Language code.
Now I'm not a great Assembly Language program, I don't write very many
things in Assembly Language ever.
Most of the time I just use intrinsics which you know, is not very
good, right?
It's a pretty, it's a poor man's assembly.
It's not as good nearly as running things in assembly, but I can read
it well enough to just to just get a basic idea of what the processor
is doing.
And know when things are too.
Totally wrong.
Which in that case they were, we saw it fail to inline a function
because of use of C++ features a very common thing that you have to be
aware of and you need to pull back on those features when it's
happening.
And then we saw using the C runtime library to do around not
acceptable.
Because even though the C runtime library is built into the compiler,
in the compiler, knows all about it.
It's still doing a really stupid thing.
They're probably because of some requirements in the spec.
Now there's ways we probably could have forced it to do something less
stupid there.
So for example, there are flags, you can pass the compiler that say
stuff like don't try to be all that accurate with floating Point
numbers.
And sometimes those will help make calls like round F, not have that
problem, but in our case, we don't want to do that.
What I'd much rather do is thing I said before, which is get rid of as
many C runtime Library calls.
We can because if we implemented them then we know they're not doing
anything too stupid.
And if they are do something stupid, we at least know what it is.
We know our own
Pity, we don't know the compiler stupidity and we don't know the C
runtime Library stupidity, but we probably do know, is that it?
It knows no bounds.
They can be as stupid in some cases, as you could possibly imagine.
In this case, that's one of them because again, not because the people
who wrote it, we're necessarily doing something dumb, but because they
have to follow something, that may be very stupid from our
perspective, but that was the requirement for what they were doing.
So happiness upon all happiness is now just from that minor
investigation, what you will note is that we have dramatically reduced
the degree to which, any of those things was affecting our frame rate
at all now, right?
I think you can see that.
Now, we're up in in just the platform layer in the debug layer are the
only things taking any time.
So let's pop back to debug
Mode.
And now see where we're at.
For our
Bug builds time usage, just to get a feel for it.
So now we can see that render pieces and render volume still do take a
little bit more time than I think, we would probably like.
So let's just push a little deeper into those and see if there's
anything we could do to make them in debug mode.
Go, faster.
Even though we don't care about that for shipping the game, it'd just
be nice to know what was happening there.
All right, so let's take a look.
Probably just too many function calls, like a death by 1000 function
calls, but you know, let's take a look inside.
Say, push volume is our worst offender at the moment.
Of course, for some reason, I can't find it.
It is pushed volume.
Is it not render volume?
Sorry render volume.
Nope.
Surrender volume is exclusively calling push volume outline and so,
push volume outline.
It kind of makes sense.
Why that's our worst case.
It's doing a lot of these line segments, doodads, and those line
segments doodads, obviously, do a lot of nasty stuff, right?
You can see in here we've got these like length things happening and
all kinds of stuff like that.
It's not great and blah, blah blah.
Let's take a look at push line segment 0 and in this got two of these
packs here going down.
And so, that's going to do a bunch of calls to round real 32.
But fortunately, at least we removed the really bad stuff from there
and in release mode, it'll be quite efficient, probably, so let's take
a jump, a little Gander, a little look-see, a little, you know, a
little bit of a, just take a little bit of a gloved finger in here and
just kind of feel around and see what we can palpate.
What I'm going to do here is just I'm going to skip over these because
I think they're probably as good as they're going to get again in
release mode.
I think they would
Now down to very clean at the moment, although they could still be
made cleaner.
Certainly, in fact, I could show you some stuff about that pretty
easily.
Anyway, we're doing some of these things here, the inner, and so on
functions.
Again, that's just going to be basic math.
That's okay.
Still calling down through.
Again, these are just basic math Ops, let's take a look into that
length.
I'm just interested in what's going on there because that, you know,
length does have a square root involved.
So let's see what's happening here.
There's our call to length squared again, that should just be math.
Nothing weird there.
And an inner product again, nothing where they're just basic math Ops.
So way to any function calls but those should all go away and release
mode and based on the profile looks like mostly they were
But once we get out of here, then we're going to call square, root
square.
Root is calling this, which I don't even want to hit f11 right now I
I'm hitting it and I'm sort of looking to the side.
This is again C.
Runtime Library.
Oh, so we don't have that, I guess we don't have their Square routine
in here, so that's fine.
We look at the assembly.
So let's see what we do.
Okay, so mind you square, root is one instruction on next 64.
Here's what the C runtime library is doing again, probably because it
has to handle.
All kinds of weird cases, we skipped over this handle error case, so
that's good.
And and then hey, at the end of it, we finally issue squirt SS to
actually do the square root.
So at least, it does the one
Square root, which is nice.
That's not that owners.
I didn't I squirmy my I didn't need to square them too much, although,
I mean, yeah.
Come on, you know, that's way too many for a square root that should
be one instruction.
So let's replace that one, too.
Just because we can, but at the moment you know, not not as egregious
as I feared, sometimes those you step into a square root and you're
just like, oh God, the, you know, the horror the humanity of it all,
you know, and you're just like, you're just terrified.
So I'm just going to scan through here to see if anything else
particularly now.
He is happening.
I don't suspect it is.
Again, I think this is just a case of like death by a thousand calls
that would all be inlined in a normal circumstance.
And look like they are from our other from our release mode profile.
So not too concerning.
See here.
Nothing else happening down here.
Not too much.
So I'm going to go ahead and just and just fix that while we can't
while we have the opportunity to do that as well.
So let's see here.
Is it in intrinsics squirt?
Deaf
So there it is.
So we've got, we've got our squirt F here.
And I just want to change this to something that's a little more sane,
like I said, so I'll fix it to our new naming scheme as well.
So, we know we've touched it recently.
So, all I really need to do here again is just lean on the fact that
we have a square root instruction already.
Here it is, it's m/s squared PS.
It was in sse2, which means basically all processors today.
Have it so you can go ahead and just call this directly.
It's going to do exactly what we want.
So let's just do it.
So again that's M square and I'm going to use SS in this case because
we don't need to do all of them.
There really isn't much of a difference between squirt.
PS and square SS.
However, in some cases and you can see here for example, in some cases
there are either
Slight performance differences or power differences like the chip can
use less power if it doesn't have to do all the lanes or whatever
there are reasons, why you may want to pay attention.
So even though it doesn't really matter whether we do all of them or
just one of them in most cases it till if you happen to know that
you're only doing one lane instead of four lanes or multiple Lanes,
you might as well, right?
It just makes sense to not ask the processor to do things, you know,
it doesn't have to do.
Okay, did I do that wrong?
What did I do wrong?
Set SS, right?
And I'm squirt SS.
Takes it in 128.
Oh duh.
this obviously I have to actually extract this floating point value
now, I don't know if there's no God
I don't know what happened there.
I accidentally hit like some debug key or something.
Can I extract it?
Yeah, so unfortunately, I have to store it with a pointer, I don't
know.
I don't remember if there's an intrinsic for just give me the value.
I don't think there is but there might be
Let's see if store so store doesn't have it.
What is the category?
Does it say which category is?
These are in
It doesn't say which category they're in because what I basically want
is like the 14 convert SS.
I want one that just Returns the floating point value, and I don't
know what category that's considered to be in.
It's not considered to be in storing.
It might be considered to be in round like a, if they've got rounding
on here,
Convert.
There we go.
So, convert our cast might be the right ways to look at it.
And let's just see, does anything ever return a float?
Here we go.
So, think this is all we want.
Copy the lower stem position to a to death.
Yes, so that's that's what I actually want convert sf32, so I'll call
that here.
And then we now have a square root that in theory should just work
right.
And it does look like it does.
I don't see any obvious problems there.
Let's take a look at the profile again.
So
Yeah, again, render volume not not good.
In this case still very, very slow, right render pieces continues to
get better but render volume unfortunately does not.
So, not much I can do about that, unfortunately.
But anyway, wanted to get rid of that as well.
So I don't really know what we can do with render volume.
again, because the optimized version seems to work relatively well,
I don't know how much time I want to spend on it, but let me just
verify that that is true.
Yeah, you know, these are just so low on the totem pole at this point.
And then basically, our whole game takes almost no time, right?
Our game is just this down here.
And so really, the only thing we're still even responsible.
For those taking time is the opengl renderer commands where we are
outputting those render commands.
I'm not sure why that's taking so much time and we should probably
look at that as well.
It could be, you know, because of calls to the driver.
It could be something we're doing stupid either way something we
probably want to look at eventually but that's just yeah.
So I don't know.
We could try to optimize that further.
I might just
I guess we don't really care in this case.
And we should just let it go.
In the meantime, opengl renderer commands is causing us trouble even
in debug mode which is unfortunate and yeah, that render volume just
takes a ton of time and it would be nice in debug mode if we could
speed it up at all.
I guess the other thing we could do is just render less volumes.
Because the other thing about that is we don't really need those on
except when we're doing active de bugging.
So what I could do is just not do those, right?
And so you know have a switch for rendering those
Turning them on and off so that we didn't have them open you know, up
when we didn't actually need them to be up.
That's certainly one thing we could do.
But in the meantime, let me also take a quick look at that open jails
because it turned out to be sort of a little bit of a performance
check day, we might as well just go ahead and look at that as well.
So if we were to look at the opengl render commands function, which is
here, you know, this is what we're actually dealing with and we don't
really have any idea what our performance profile is in this
particular case.
Like we don't know how many times through this Loop.
We're going.
We don't know, you know how much we're stalling behind any of these
particular calls.
We really just don't know anything about it.
All we know is that we time to the whole thing and we're getting that
result.
Now, I don't remember where that timing actually occurs.
We'll have to see.
So let me, let me take a look at where what we're, what we're actually
timing in there.
Opengl renderer commands,
That's this function, but where is the timer?
Are we timing it outside?
Okay, so we're tiny it outside and here you can see the swap buffers
call getting timed and the opengl renderer commands getting timed.
If I wanted to in here, I could definitely do some more targeted
profiling, just to see, you know, which of these things was doing
anything, you know, something like this.
You know what I would expect to see is I would expect to see the, you
know, let the, the quads is where everything's happening.
So, you know, I would expect to see the Lion's Share of the time spent
in there.
If I don't, I'm going to be, particularly surprised, not that that's
unusual.
But yeah.
So you can see here.
Five calls to the text 5.
Executions of the textured quads block is taking basically,
All of that time now granted.
You can imagine that the time spent in here actually is changing when
I'm opening closing this, the reason for that is because that's
actually a call that has to draw the debug system, and the debug
system gets tons, you know, there's a lot more quads that get end up
getting put in here.
When the debug system is open and what we can see, is every time we
call through here, there's a certain amount of Preamble, and then
there's the actual Loop itself.
And what I would assume is that because the Preamble is only getting
executed five times.
Again, I would be pretty surprised to find that the time was being
spent anywhere other than the quad loop, right.
I would expect this Loop specifically because it's executing on every
quad to be the one that takes all the time and I would expect the rest
of this stuff to be irrelevant.
So I'm guessing that if I just time just that one portion.
It should take all the time and everybody else is
Take any right?
And that seems to be the case because now opengl renderer commands is
doubt down to 4% of the time and opengl quad loop is at 22.
That still seems a little high like it doesn't really make
Whole lot of sense to me.
Why all of this stuff is taking that much time.
This only happens one time because most of time we have all the frame
buffer.
So we're talking about just this and some of this like boilerplate
stuff here like binding, the frame buffers and stuff is really taking
that much time to only do that a few times.
It's a little odd, right?
But 20% of the time is spent in here and that to me does make more
sense.
I'm assuming that the problem is behind the driver because this Loop
It is not really doing very much but I don't know that that's the
case.
And so what I'd like to do is verify that the driver is the thing
taking the time before I assume that it's not and furthermore it would
seem like maybe that's suspicion isn't really valid because if it was
then why does it get faster potentially in release mode or maybe it's
not getting any faster and Lisa and everything else is just like let's
in fact we could we could figure that out.
So here it is in debug mode.
And there's the cycle count, right?
It's like, let's see.
One, two, three.
One, two, three 20.
So it's like 23 million Cycles, right?
So, let's see if it's still 23 million Cycles.
Now,
So it is so what I can basically determine from that is that pretty
much there's probably nothing we're going to be able to do about that.
While we're still in the old school setting textures lots of times
because basically the driver is just thrashing around hating life
really badly because of this whole situation here, right?
And that's unfortunate, but that's just the case, right?
So what we would have to do if we wanted to fix, this is we would have
to make it so that the textures again were being handled in a more
thoughtful way so that they were, you know, in a texture array or
something similar.
And the reason we're not doing that right now is our textures are all
sorts of unusual sizes.
So it's not a simple matter to just throw them into a texture array.
It's not that simple.
Because texture array elements have to all be the same size and it's
unclear exactly.
Lee, how we would do that, right?
We'd have to go to something fancier like a texture tiling scheme.
For a bigger size textures or who knows what right?
So there's a lot of issues at stake there or at play there and it's
not a simple matter to
To resolve that.
But at least now we do know that that is what's called taking the time
which is what we want to see.
And so at least we know it's isolated by in something that we already
know we would want to fix for performance and if there isn't like some
other weird like we were copying something, we shouldn't have been
copying tons of times or stuff like that.
Would be causing that slow down, right?
So I think that's about it, I don't know that there's anything else we
can really track down, performance-wise here that we care about, but
at least now we know what the deal is, right?
And it would be nice.
Again, if we could make that dispatch quicker because if we could make
that dispatch quicker, we would be much happier.
The other thing I suppose we could do is we could check to see if the
textures were the same.
Like if they were the white texture for example, because a bunch of
Quads are going through that white texture and they, you know, are not
going to have that problem where they would have to change text every
time.
But again, that doesn't seem particularly relevant because most things
in the game will be textured.
So it's really just an optimisation for things that don't matter.
So, I would say or in, you know, but maybe in debug mode, they would
because, hey, you know, there's like, it's drawn these cubes and
stuff.
And there's lots of those, you know, so you'd save a bunch of time
there, but that's really about it, like,
That's the only thing I could think of that would really have that
case.
So you know, we could do something like that again.
I don't know if we should if we want to do something like that just to
see if it would help in the debug case, it's really pretty
straightforward Loop wise.
All we're going to do here is say, okay, so you know, we've hoops
We've got a bitmap and every time we see that bitmap, maybe I'll say
here.
Well, you know what?
I can't even do that.
Really?
Because again, we have this problem of wanting to draw quads and so we
can't really even fix that part of it because we have to do our vertex
indices.
You know, we can avoid calling bind texture multiple times and I guess
we could just try that but that's the only thing we can really do.
So, what we can do here is we load the bitmap up and what we could say
is if bitmap is not equal to last bitmap then buying the texture.
Otherwise
I want and you know, is this going to help?
Probably not.
But you know, might as well check it out.
So all that does is in the case where the bitmap doesn't vary, it's
not going to call it and you can see that it did help a little maybe
tiny bit, but really no, it didn't.
So I don't expect that to be.
I didn't expect that to be anything special and it wasn't.
I think the fact that we call Jill drawer raised so many times is
probably just the problem, right?
And the fact that we change the texture probably doesn't help but the
Driver probably was already doing something like this so it probably
already did that aggregation, if that makes sense.
And so when we do that aggregation, it doesn't help.
If that makes sense.
So I'm guessing that that's just a meaningless optimization that we
don't need to preserve right.
And I'll just verify that hold on, one second.
So, here's this calling it every time in debug mode.
So, yeah, well, you know it is it's not nothing.
For whatever reason us doing that manually, I guess the driver does
enough work behind that bind texture call to even detect whether or
not the texture is the same that it does actually flatten it a bit.
It's it's not really that great but it's you know it's something and
again we could get rid of this deal drawers if we had a way of drawing
quads instead of triangle strips that would be something that we would
do here.
Unfortunately, we
Can't really do that with introducing and without introducing a
geometry Shader that would produce triangle that would produce quad
into index groups for us and we don't really have that infrastructure
in place.
We could go at it.
It's not hard.
But I just don't know if that's worth it at this point.
But yeah what we what we would end up doing here again is the same
sort of situation.
If the bitmap were not the same, right?
Is instead of actually issuing the GL drawer, it's called we would
sort of stack them up.
So we would we would do something like how many indices or right?
How many you know what's our driver, it count and then what we would
do every time is when we did the switch, we would say, oh okay.
You know, every time we do the switch, we need to bind
Or we need to do the draw arrays with the number of vertices that we
have.
And in each time we come through here, we need to increment the number
of vertices we have by 4, right?
So in other words, the first time through we would pick out the
bitmap.
We'd see and, you know, I'd probably want to put a check here.
That was like, if drover count is greater than zero, then we do the GL
draw raise otherwise, we don't, then we do the by texture and we set
the driver count to 0, right?
And we can do the vine texture, right before the call to
We could do it this way by calling last bitmap, right?
And off we go.
So we could be a see if it map cycle lasts but math then you know if
the driver caps higher than 0 buying the texture and draw the arrays,
then do less with my pickles bitmap and off you go.
Every time we end up with four or more vertices and then at the end we
would need to do one more.
Just you know, basically clear it out.
So to say okay if the vert count is greater than zero at the end,
right?
Which would almost certainly is going to be unless we didn't have
anything anything in the loop at all.
Then we have to do the last bit map bind and the driver count.
Right now, the vertex index that we're on in this case is not going to
be accurate.
It's going to have to be the old.
Vertex index that we would have started with.
So we also kind of need to track how far back.
We have to go in some sense but we kind of know what that is.
Right.
So we know we're stopping on this one in fact you know up smarter way
to do this actually now that I think about it, it's probably a lot
cleaner is just to say like first vert,
Right.
And then what we would do is every time we draw, we would say, like,
first, vert equals vert index,
And so then all we would say is well, you know, you always draw.
Oops.
This we can still leave it this way.
This last one is a little more complicated, but as we go here, we're
going through the vertex vertex Industries, the driver account is
basically just wherever we are in the index dream - wherever we are.
When we started is the number to draw if that's greater than 0, then
we just draw it, you know, starting from first vert and we draw as
many as there are, right?
As many as we have to go to catch up.
We then store where we are right now.
Is the new first vert, we don't have this at all and
Or and we just keep going from there at the end.
We would do the same thing, right?
And we just need to know what that vert into index is.
So we need to have that be an actual like more like a while loop now,
right.
That's going to work like this so that vert index actually equals what
it should equal at the end.
Right?
But that's it.
And and then you know, it's it's going to be doing that drawing now.
There's a problem.
Oops.
Well, two problems here.
First of all.
These both have to be the same thing or rather, I could just do this.
So it won't show the first time.
The problem here is that we will get garbage now and the reason that
we get garbage again is because of that quad situation, right?
We don't have a way of generating quad.
So we're generating triangle strips, which means that the end will
always connect every Sprite to every other Sprite
As we go, right?
But interestingly enough, you can see that that really dropped
dramatically the number.
The amount of time spent in the quad loop, right here we are.
It's been flattened down.
It's about twice as fast as it was when doing those calls.
And again that's because just eliminating the number of times we asked
the driver to draw things by drawing things in batches right now.
I'm going to just back out all of that because again,
I don't really think that's particularly useful, it's not, you know,
There we go.
It's not really anything that I it's not really the appropriate
optimization.
I think the appropriate division is to figure out how we might use
texture raised here to avoid that overhead.
And again, the problem there is just that, that has a bunch of asset
implications that are really kind of nasty.
Basically, what that means is that, you know, if you want to use a
texture array there you get into a situation where you have to make
all of your textures fit into a particular size.
So,
Basically you know you have to pick a size like 1024 by 1024 and you
have to pack all of your Sprites such that they fit inside that
texture.
And if you have multiple of them that you know, are relatively small,
you would need to make sure that they fit, you know, maybe pack them
into a single one as like a texture Atlas or something because you
don't want to waste the space.
Since the memory is at a premium.
You have all of these issues you got to address.
Once you go to texture raised.
That are kind of nasty but that is what you would want to do to make
that Loop actually run in a reasonable fashion and the biggest problem
that we would have right now with that is the cutscene art because the
cutscene art is large and we would basically need to tile it, right?
We would have to break it into some tiles in order to draw it.
You know, the way that we're drawing it at the moment and so yeah.
I really just don't know if we want to deal with anything like that.
What we could do I suppose it's something like all of the in-game
Sprites we could put in a texture array and the cutscene art we could
leave outside the texture, right?
Because the cutscene is a very special case scenario and like the
cutscene
If we flip over to it here is not ever going to be in the performance
critical part of things because it's all it's doing, is just rendering
some basic stuff.
Wait, oh, and you know what?
We have never updated our cutscenes to work with the new 3D system
either have, we that's probably something we should do.
Maybe that's something I'll do right now.
So, you know, maybe we could just do something different for them, I'm
not sure it's hard to say.
So I don't really know what we want to do there, right?
I don't really know what we want to do there.
It's a good question but we definitely had the circumstance where it's
like, okay, like
You know, could we just slam all of our in game art into a texture
Ray?
And presumably, they would fit
Without too much, too much hubbub, I don't know.
Let me take a look here.
So, if we had a 1024, by 1024 texture because there's nothing, no
in-game Sprites, probably bigger than that times.
Four is what four megabytes of textures.
So, you know, if you assume half a gigabyte on the graphics card is a
reasonable minimum, minimum platform.
So then you're talking about what 128
Of those.
Right, that's just not very many Sprites.
So at the very least would probably have to say that all Sprites were
512 by 512, right.
And I mean, we could turn on dxt texture compression and get four more
times in there.
But so then at that point, you know we would get 512 Sprites images in
the cache at once.
Right.
And
It's not very many.
but, you know,
Maybe it's enough.
I mean it is a cash after all.
512 Unique Images on the screen.
And I know so 256 by 256, if we if we crammed everything into there,
With no texture compression.
Yeah that's 262.
So you know if we did say, well we've got 512, let's say we've got
512, oops.
1024 x 1024.
So we have 512 Megs to work with.
On the graphics card.
And we want to divide that by 2 to 6 by 2.
This by 4/4 Sprites.
2048 Sprites is a lot better in terms of how many different Sprite
images we could have in memory at once, but the resolution is not
great like 256 by 226 Sprites.
Isn't huge.
But you know, we could do it.
If we were in the mood to do it, we could do it.
So maybe we should be in the mood to do it and maybe we should do that
because hey that would get us into a much better place.
Performance-wise.
I don't know.
I really don't have a strong opinion about that.
Maybe we could take a poll.
What I can say is that regardless reasonably productive use of our
time at the moment.
I would be too.
Would be to go ahead and fix the cutscenes because I mean you were
going to want those to work either way, right?
So let's just go ahead and fix our cutscenes and here's how we, you
know, we're doing the cutscenes can see we've got sort of them.
Coated in here is just wear what layers we want and the layers as you
can see that they're already like pre-sorted, right?
So the farthest away thing comes first and then the closest thing
comes at, as the last one.
So they're, they're capable of being drawn in order is basically the
only important part about that and you can see here, I guess it never
draws the first layer index looks like for some reason.
Sure why that is seeing their accounts.
And it looks
That's a very interesting Loop.
It looks like we were previously drawing these in the other order.
I guess, just to match the layer tags in the bitmap matcher, but
that's just kind of a week if you think you could put, plus 1 here.
But either way, it doesn't matter.
You can see us drawing them here.
We are drawing them in order.
And so, as we draw these, and we push the bitmaps on, we should get
the transform Z.
Here - camera offset.
See being computed.
That peasy.
As far as I know,
I don't super get why we aren't seeing.
Let me take a look here.
Ah, so these look like they're coated.
In a, in a I guess I don't know how we've set up the camera.
But if you take a look at how we set up our Z values, though we did do
it, so as they were coded, how far away from the camera they are,
right?
So
That Z value there is really not what we would normally think of, as a
z value, because Z goes up in our game.
And so, when we set the camera transform here, you know, we we've got
the Z values going the wrong way, round in terms of distance from the
camera, I'm not sure how that was working.
Originally, it seems a little weird.
Did we account for that somehow?
Because you can see here, like, this is supposed to be the
The way, but in our game Z comes towards the camera.
So setting this to 300, doesn't really make any sense.
It's supposed to be 300 - 300 right but I don't see anywhere where
this is getting negated.
So it's a little bit weird what's happening here I'm not sure how to
interpret that or not sure I remember because long time ago we did
this why we weren't taking steps to rectify?
I have that, right?
It's just really strange.
So I also don't know what the camera offset Z stuff is for
So looking at this here, you can see like intro shot.
You can see here, our camera information, I believe is what's being
coded there?
So you can see here, we've got layered seen.
So these are those things, right?
There's the
Let's see how we got here.
Intro layers index.
So we start with the asset ID, which is
Is this one?
Then we have the shot index.
Then we have the layer count.
Then we have the layer pointer.
Then the next thing is the duration, which is this.
So 20 seconds, right?
Or whatever.
We then have in here, we've got
Where the camera is supposed to start.
And then we have here where the camera is supposed to end, right?
And there's also a fade value but only one person uses that which is
the first one.
So, if we take a look at what's happening, here are the camera
starting at 10:00 and it's going to 54 a zoom in.
And again, that's like, correct, if you're trying to zoom in zero
going to
Or also corrects you're going to -1.5 those are all proper Zoom values
in the distant, space of the game.
So what I don't understand is how these values.
Oh I see those are actually like
used for some other purpose.
These are the actual z-values I guess because those properly lineup
negatively, right?
So what are these values here?
That's more what I'm interested in.
So that's the height value, is all that is, okay?
So these are still, I was just taking some time to get back familiar
with how these are encoded, that's actually fine.
So what I really want to know there is is if these are being drawn
properly from Back to Front, I don't really understand what I'm
looking at.
I guess the problem is probably Alpha to coverage in this.
Case, let me find out though.
You know what I should do?
First is, let's not start into game mode.
So if I go to
Handmade CPP.
I'm pretty sure we can just turn this off and we will start with the
title sequence like the game would in reality.
So like looking at this you can kind of see I don't super understand
what I'm seeing here.
This this is confusing to me.
The reason it's confusing to me is I have this whole portion of this
image here, the alpha for this part of the image should be zero, which
means I should be seeing through it.
It should even
With Alfred to coverage, it should just not be affecting, what's
underneath it in that way, if there was anything being drawn
underneath it at all, but even if there wasn't, it should still work,
right?
And so, what I don't understand is it seems like the Z buffer is
getting set there in a way.
That doesn't make a lot of sense to me or something.
Weird is happening.
And I really just do not understand it.
So one thing is, I don't know what the Z clipping rectangle.
Range is here, but it could be that the Z.
Clipping range is too aggressive for where these are.
So you know, 300 what's are near for our clip plane, right?
So if I go here to perspective projection, well there's your answer,
right?
So our near clipping plane is at Point 1.
Nobody is in danger of violating that but 100 is certainly going to
clip out a bunch of these sausage gentleman here, I guess, 200 175.
E100 not going to work.
Can't see if there's anybody else here who wouldn't work.
Most of the other ones should be in line, so that would really only
Swinging a couple of these ones, right?
That we have
But that's definitely the case.
And so one of the things we might want to think about in here is
starting to say, well, what maybe we want to be able to specify the
near and far clip planes,
In some kind of a more reasonable fashion.
So let's let's go ahead and take a look at what we would do there.
So inside render group, when we have set camera, transform what we
could do is just tack those onto the end.
And then when we call perspective projection, we can just pass the
near clipping plane, the farthest plan and we call orthographic.
We could pass the neighborhood plan.
And the far clipping plane.
And then when we go to handmade math, we could just do
like so-and-so in same thing here.
Now that's parameterised.
And so we're going to want to do this in two places.
So in the debug system, when we do set camera transform, this is now
going to want to specify these two.
So it's going to want to specify those put planes like so so that we
have that nice big region that we were expecting.
And everybody else will be fine.
What is this complaining about?
What is it that that position that has to get set?
Their tell me, please.
I assume it is the position.
Let me find out for sure.
Yeah, camera p.
So now we should be fine for this as well, just want to make sure that
all the Z still works.
There it does.
So now in the cutscene case we can specify near and far clipping plane
that are more amenable for what we're trying to do.
We don't actually want to change any of these.
We want all these to be the same for the moment.
But the near and far clipping plane in this case, you know, we want to
be more generous for the cutscenes because that's just how we encoded
them.
And now we can take a look and see if we get any more reasonable in
this here.
Although I don't really see us getting any more reasonable.
And it's so and you know again the dimming weird dimming effect,
We get here is not explainable by clip planes, no matter what.
So that's also kind of a separate issue that I don't really know.
Oh, you know what?
That's our distance-based fog.
Right.
Are distance-based, fog.
We don't have a way to turn off.
Right here, we are.
When you do perspective projection, we're set this fog distance as
well.
So we also need that.
We should probably have a better way of passing these parameters.
Cuz there's just too many of them at this point, right?
and maybe at this point I'll just do ab32 that's like fog equals true
or maybe equals false
And so that way I could come in here and say, all right, well, you
know, if they ask me for fog then turn on fog, if they didn't ask me
for fog, then don't turn on fog, right?
And then inside World mode when it did the one person who actually
wants it
I thought it was here set camera transform.
There it is.
I so
I think that would also get us out of the business of doing this
switch, which is kind of nice.
So, what we could do is say like alright, it's always negative camera
Z in the case we wanted fog and just when you you know you near
clipping plane far, clipping plane false right near clipping plane
far, clipping plane through that.
What we can do here is say, well, let's encode the near and far
clipping planes.
Here.
And off you go.
So in shit in theory that should give us now, the ability to turn off
the fog in this case, although I guess that.
No, I think about it.
That's not important because we will get a default value of false
there.
And so now at least we're in a much better scenario where we're
looking at the cutscene and we can only see all the pieces of it and
nothing's getting clipped now, which is also nice because we have a
proper, a proper near and far clipping plane.
So that's also good.
And presumably all this stuff is still working as well and yeah it
does it does seem to be so that's good.
So now really our only real problem now is that our depth of field has
changed quite a bit with the, with the way that the projection is
working here.
So our camera, like our fov and stuff, all seems wrong, I don't really
know why that happened.
I'd be lying if I said, I really had any idea what was going on there
that seems going to be wrong because the near clipping plane and we'll
have to take a look.
Take a look at what's going on there.
A little bit later, but all the rest of the scene should be fine.
So, what we need to do is kind of restore that focal length, I guess.
And I'm not 100% sure, like I said how that got undone, I really don't
know.
So yeah.
Yeah, I really I just don't really know what the circumstances were
here.
In terms of how this was previously, what stuff in the old sort of
transfer system.
What it was actually trying to do.
So I'm just going to fuss with it a little bit here and just figure
out what maybe it was trying to do.
So we can get a little bit more involved in that now.
So I don't know what this is, we don't even need this anymore.
If you look at camera fram's, it's not even a thing.
It just focal length is focal length, so we can just set focal length.
Something here, you know, whatever it ends up being at the moment.
It's up to 0.25.
And so that's fine that just get set down here and nothing happens,
but I am interested to know what will happen if we change that focal
length,
We're we sort of thinking there was a different focal lengths so
suppose I change that focal length before.
For example, you can see we get closer in and perhaps perhaps a little
bit closer to what we were expecting.
Originally, here's a closer focal length and again, that's even closer
to the image that we were originally expecting to have which is a much
closer.
Inversion this one again, looking pretty good here.
I think maybe mostly what we had had happened before as we did it with
a focal length.
That
Is more akin to this.
And so now that's what we're looking at.
I don't really know.
You know, I also don't know when we were supposed to stop.
How long has it been since I've been streaming?
But I start at 11:30.
I was supposed to stop like 20 minutes ago, wasn't I?
I don't even know.
Yeah.
With okay.
So streams over technically and I'm still going.
I don't know what happened.
I apologize.
That I just got carried away.
Anyway, point being the focal length.
Setting might be the only real thing we need to fix their in terms of
getting the the scale.
Right?
I'm just not 100% sure.
So again looking at that that's a little bit too low in terms of where
we were supposed to be zoom in Wise.
Let me go ahead and just try a couple more values to see if any
particular value.
Looks like what we had tuned it to before, in terms of how we had
wanted those scenes to appear.
It honestly looks like something.
Very
Those 28 is probably what we actually used in terms of where we wanted
those cutscenes to be.
It's a little bit hard to tell but it seems correct.
We still have to fix the
window sizing there.
That's so it kind of seems like for the most part this is is more
correct.
And so really the only problem that we have at the moment
So you know, I guess you might say there's two things, we probably
want to fix one.
These cutscenes would look a lot better if we did not use Alpha to
coverage.
So if we just had a way of turning Alpha to coverage off at this
point,
That would be helpful.
And the other thing is we have everything hitting the near clipping
plane.
I believe in this in this particular scene.
So all of these are a little bit off where Santa Claus get went, I
don't know, it might be that his Z is set wrong, but I'm not sure
let's take a look.
Don't know which scene that actually is.
So there's that.
But
Let's see here.
So we've got your Sky wall and icicles here entry.
So
I believe it's this.
Because Krampus is next, right?
I believe it's this one.
And these both have the exact same Z, so that does seem like maybe
that's a problem, but maybe they're just in the wrong order.
Oh wait.
No, these are the same Flags.
So there
These should be sorting properly.
I don't know.
What's going on there?
I don't know why we're not seeing
I don't know why we're not seeing those those values.
Let's let's just take a quick look because
I'm already over time and who cares?
No one cares.
Hmm.
Need a quick way to set this to like large values, right?
We use it enough.
I don't think it's a waste of time test and better UI in there.
I can't pause, can I?
Hmm.
That just pauses the profiler,
Of course.
We don't really have a global pause working around so many things.
We should probably go fix in there.
Anyway, the problems of only having a few hours every week.
All right.
So yeah, I don't really know what's going on with that particular one.
It's a little weird to me that, that's a problem because it looks
harmless enough.
And so, you would think.
That it would be fine unless it has something more to do with these X
offsets here.
So the fact that this is marked a transient just means that it will
only show up between these two x values, right?
So there's nothing particularly weird there and we know that that
system is still working because if you take a look at the scene
immediately subsequent to it, you can see that that one also relies on
a bunch of transients and it's fine.
So I'm not really sure what's going on there.
I don't know why it would be having that problem.
Now, what I would like to do is I'd like to make this be the first
scene.
So I think what I can do there is just say like, oh well, you know,
let's just force it to be first.
Right?
And so at least then what I could do is I could go into cutscene and
see what's happening, right?
So, let's see how many layers of thinks there are.
Where are we?
There we go.
So we've got layer and X1, and we got layer count of five.
Here we come through here.
We're looking at this layer.
So, here's the transient.
Active is zero.
And active is one.
So we do know that we draw
one of the transient layers which is exactly what we expect.
We'd always expect to draw at least one of the transient layers, we
get the bitmap match back.
It's a real bitmap.
As far as we know, we go ahead and
Prepare the transform as we normally would and here is that transform.
Here's the offset P.
It's in a reasonable location, right?
-3.7,
And again, it's really only the x value that's at all unusual there.
And I'm going to assuming that's correct.
We don't really know, but I don't know why.
That would be at all bizarre right in theory, that should just work.
I guess, one thing I don't know is are these being rendered is upright
or not?
I would like to find that out.
Let's make sure they're not being rendered as upright Sprites because
that would potentially create this problem due to the Z offset.
So, they're not being rendered as upright, which is good.
However,
When we coming to push quad.
after packing, all of these things in here,
Yeah, all of the W values are properly zero.
It looks like
No, they are not.
Okay, so that is also a problem, right?
Because these are supposed to be flat, they're not supposed to be up.
Right?
When we bind these, this Z bias in here, the Z bias is only supposed
to be for upright Sprites.
So this has been a bug like the entire time.
We just haven't had any non upright Sprites, so probably what was
happening there and this is exactly what I thought might be happening.
Which is why when it's funny that it actually was true because it was
really just a hunch is since this bit
App starts lower down, it's Z bias will be increasing as it goes
upward and Santa Claus starts right here.
It the Z bias in an upright Sprite in, the Shader was enough to make
it Z value be higher than Santa Claus by the time Santa Claus started.
Because remember even though Santa Claus starts in front, his height
is is going to his Z bias, is going to start increasing only at a
certain point on the screen where he begins.
So it looks like the problem there is just in render group.
We never properly, handled Flats rights, the Z bias should only be
happening here.
If the Sprite is not a right that stands upright, it should have a z
biases, zero and and not of any other sort of like, stand up value.
Okay, so now our Santa Claus is back.
Everyone is happy.
And now I will go to the Q&A because I'm not going to try and fix the
near clipping plane thing yet.
So let's go to the Q&A.
So handmade he robot is really dead for real, right?
Just use asked, what will be our way forward to reduce GL drawer?
A calls will be looking to texture.
Atlas is Mega Texas or invent our own way, is it better to separate
cutscene rendering because it's so different.
The answer is, we don't know that we need a Way Forward yet.
In other words, like we don't actually have any performance problems
with this yet.
We only were looking at that as being a source of time that mattered
because our debug frame rate was not 60 frames a second but our nandi.
Our release mode frame rate is 60 frames a second so we actually don't
have a problem to solve yet, right?
And so before I would look at anything more complicated there, we have
to actually end up with a frame rate problem.
We have to solve which we don't currently have two,
Kylo asks, are we forced to use Cindy registers to use those
intrinsics for?
Are there some ways to do that without those like inline assembly or
something else?
So I guess what I would say is I'm not 100% sure if the question, if I
understand the question,
So I'll just start with a bit of background and you can stop me if
this is not answering the question.
On the original x86 architecture.
It did not have floating Point operations.
So you only had integer operations as far as manipulating numbers are
concerned.
They then added a CO Processing Unit called the x87, which had
floating Point operations for the first time, and those floating Point
operations were done.
Using a special set of registers to hold floating Point values.
So, when you wanted operate on floating Point values, you had to put
them into those registers.
And when you wanted to transfer, you know, if you want to round the
back to integer, something you had to move them out of those registers
using instructions for doing.
Exactly that.
So anytime you operated on floating Point values, you were going to
use the x87 stack, you put them in there you operate on the remove
them back, right?
Now, there's Opera you don't have to necessarily load them into
regular processor.
Registers first, you can load directly onto the x87 stack and you can
store directly out of the x87 stack to memory as well.
So it's just another set of registers but they were the registers for
operating on a floating Point unit, on a floating Point values.
When Cindy instructions were added to the X6 x86 architecture.
A separate set of registers were added for wide floating Point
operations, right?
The xmm registers and those registers are separate from the x87
registers.
So now, when you did floating Point operations, you had a choice of
putting things into one of two registers.
One register set was the x87 stack that you would use.
If you were trying to use x87 floating Point instructions and the
other one where the registers for Cindy instructions that you would
use for executing floating points.
But again in no way, were you ever doing?
Open operations in the main set of registers, because the
general-purpose registers don't have the capability of doing floating
Point operations at all.
once they move to the x64 architecture, they got rid of the x87
coprocessor concept altogether because again, it hadn't been a
Roster for quite some time.
It was simply just the old instruction set that the coprocessor used
to use had been sort of welded in and now just was used on the trip.
Always
They got rid of that and only have the same D registers, so single
Priscilla, like, single floating Point operations are now still done
on the vector floating Point Unit because the only floating Point
registers that are on the chip are wide floating Point registers,
there is no x87 stack anymore or x87 instructions as far as mainstream
x64 processor.
Use is
Concerned.
So,
The reason I don't quite understand.
The premise of the question is when you say, are we forced to use
Cindy in registers to use as intrinsics?
Or are there some ways to do it without those, what I would say is?
Well, what do you mean do it without those?
There's only one set of registers on the processor for doing things
like square roots or any kind of floating Point operations at all.
Just even adding two floating Point values together.
There's only one set of registers for those and that are the xmm
registers, right?
So I'm just not sure what you would even be trying to avoid.
If you're doing floating-point, you're using those registers, they are
the registers you want to use.
There is no reason you would want to avoid their use.
That is all there.
Therefore, and they are the only thing that that is used that that is
used for floating Point operations in that way.
Desi is.
Have you seen em USL standard Library?
It has very good code.
Quality Square.
F on x86.
64 is one instruction on it.
It's for Linux.
But parts of it are very profitable.
No, I have it.
Mus l.
I can take a look.
Oops.
So, here we are.
Well, that doesn't really seem to be like source code to the x86 64
version.
Oh, are these directories?
Hmm.
I don't know where to go to get the actual code.
I don't know where the code is, unfortunately, so I can't really look.
Okay, here we go.
So I don't know where the floating-point stuff would be, for example.
Math.
Wow, they use 1 C function per function.
That's
that's some some aggressive.
Work there.
So that's not an optimized version.
So how do I look at like the optimized that's like a sea version?
I don't know if maybe there's yeah.
Not sure how to get.
The like the specialized one.
Maybe it's also in there but under something like
there it is.
Yeah.
Let's check out a tan too.
What?
What is what is this?
How that's not those don't exist anymore, do they?
Can you call fva Tan from x64?
I mean, I guess you could
but if you did,
Your operating system has to be restoring.
The old x86 stack, which I don't think it does on Windows does it?
Maybe it does.
Yeah, I don't know about this man.
This does not look good.
That is not, that is not probably a good way to do an F.
Be a tan on a generals.
I don't know about this dude.
I'm not getting a good feeling about this, you know I'm saying?
do you know whether the squirt function in math that H uses processor
instructions or calculates results via some software algorithm
I don't think I understand the question.
I mean, a software, algorithm would still use processor instructions,
right?
Do you just mean does it use Squirt PS and we showed that on today's
stream, it does eventually call call underscore.
Mmm, underscore a squirt underscore SS.
It does eventually do that in the C runtime Library so it just does a
bunch of preambles first, right?
It does a bunch of checks to see first whether it needs to be in a
special case probably for like in fernan or something.
I don't know what it's checking for actually - one maybe your negative
numbers and maybe the sea spec requires certain things to happen on
negative numbers.
I don't know but it was doing a bunch of Preamble but then eventually
did get down to actually just calling
This word instruction, which I never remember what it's actually
called.
The intrinsics called one thing, but the actual instruction on the
chip,
Intel, gives it a different name, squared SS.
So, squirt, assess is what the processor did.
In fact, call.
So the C runtime library is, in fact, using it.
It just only uses it after doing a bunch of unnecessary work for our
purposes, which I believe we're for checking for how for error
conditions.
And yeah, if you go back in today's stream and watch where I stepped
in to squirt squared F, we saw it call Squirt SS.
So it is actually calling that in the C runtime Library.
It just does a bunch of unnecessary Preamble probably to conform to
spec error, reporting standards or something.
All right, let's go ahead and close it down.
Thank you everybody for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
It comes to the source code so you can play around with it.
We also form site.
You go to ask question a patreon.
Age.
You can go to transport the video series schedule bot that tweet the
schedule.
You so, you know, when we're going to be live and an episode guide so
you can go back and look at any previous episodes we did and it has
all kinds of great annotations and stuff.
So it's easy to find things that's about it for today.
I'll be back tomorrow for another episode where we will probably just
go back to doing the camera stuff since the day, we kind of had a
little bit of a diversion fixing some things, but it's nice to fix
things.
That's about it.
Thank you for joining me until tomorrow have fun programming and I'll
see
we won on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.