Alright, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The, this is the stream where we code a complete game live here on
Twitch.
Here's the thing, I believe, yesterday, I was just about to finish
cleaning up some code and I didn't really get a chance to do it.
So we're just going to dive right back into that we were sort of
cleaning up our debug layer so that we can call it done and kind of
put the stamp of approval on it for use in the game.
And so I got some things that
Want to do to make that happen and so we're going to finish doing
those.
If you are trying to follow along at home today is day 250.
Not quite at day, 255 yet.
Obviously when we get to date 55 we're going to wrap or back around
today zero because we only have a bike counter.
Just kidding.
That's not actually true but it would be funny if it was anyway day
250 you want to unpack day 249 source code if you're following along
with the source code at home because that's what I'm going to start
with today.
So if you're trying to follow the stream on your own,
Start there.
So let's take a look at where we ended up, if you remember correctly.
At the end of last night's dream, I turned off the debug system
because I didn't want to leave the checked-in code in a broken say,
for any money.
So, right now we're not actually seeing any debug output on the screen
at all.
We're just seeing the regular game startup, as it normally would with
the cutscene sequence and all that sort of stuff, right?
So what we want to do now is we want to go ahead and get back to that
sort of debugging.
Well, wasn't debugging it.
Actually just us.
Oh, you don't need the max anymore.
I always forget.
It's like force of habit.
We need to get back to getting our stuff compiling because we changed
around how the macros were going to work on on our debug layer.
And so we need to like finish that.
So here we go.
Let's load up our project and let's build.
There we go.
And so if I load our build that bat file, it was this part right here.
Here right hand made internal.
That's our debug switch and you can see that I've switched it off.
If I switch it back to on, we will go back to getting.
I assumed or not.
I figured we would have got compiler errors on that but I guess not.
There we go.
I don't know what happened there.
That was weird.
All right, I won't ask anyway when I when I compile now we're back to
getting compile errors.
And so what we have to do now is we have to go through and fix the
compile errors, that we got from changing the way that we do our debug
output.
And I believe what we decided to do here was we updated how debug data
block works and that's in debug interface, you can kind of see, debug
data block
Right?
Here is one of these things.
All it actually typically gets past is the name, whatever the name of
the data block is actually supposed to be and, and that's all
That's all it is.
So I don't know.
Like I said, we sort of got rid of the concept of having a debug ID
beyond that.
It's just that one name pointer that gets used.
So I don't know, maybe that'll be a bad decision.
I don't think it particularly will be.
I think it's probably going to be okay.
But what that means is that this point we can sort of get rid of this
concept here in it's entirely and the end of The Entity debug ID which
we had up here, was previously just being used for this debug hit
stuff, which is basically what let's
If you say whether or not you were going to request that thing and
that can stay in, right?
So the thing that actually works for that, that totally is fine.
And if we wanted to, we could associate this data block with that
entity, debug ID in the future by having some way of specifying that
as a value.
Like we could, if we wanted to include this in here,
I need you back ID for coder, has its expansion for.
Some reason, doesn't pick things that are nearby to the cursor yet.
So it's kind of hard to use the auto expand.
It doesn't work like it used to in emacs.
I tend to it tends to be pretty tough.
I'm not sure how it actually decides that.
But anyway, so that's why I kind of got cycle through that.
But anyway, we could do something like that in the future.
So, I'll just say, you know, do we want this?
And I don't know if we'll have much of a reason to use that or not.
You know, it's our prerogative if we want to, I don't know.
So anyway, like that's that's how that works.
And what's the problem here?
This is supposed to be a string.
So this is like simulation entity, kind of switch to the / for passing
text.
In case I want underscores, I figured I should pick something that
isn't a valid identifier name.
So yeah.
And now we got to fix the debug system because we removed some of
these things like name event block name for now.
I think what we want to do here is just let this be the grid for now,
but in the future we're going to parse that get out and actually do
some stuff with it.
So we'll leave that for now.
Open data block, I don't know that we actually want any of this here.
I think I might just say that that's not going to get printed out at
all because we decided to stop putting those anyway and they're
handled kind of differently in the external code anyway.
And so I think we're just going to leave that like that here.
I'll put that grid again if we need to and
In case for debugging purposes, I think that should basically be it.
So let's see.
So we've got that.
Now, we've got get group for her.
Cool name.
If we are to pass the, the block name in here, I mean, sorry, we're
for past the the Grid in there, we'll have to do some work inside
there to sort of first find the the end of it.
Right.
Because the way that we're building these now is a little bit
different, right?
We've got handmade.
Debug interface is, is building, these potentially using the debug
name thing.
And speaking of that, is there a
Do we know why we didn't do the debug name here?
I feel like that's a screw-up.
Like I feel like we want this to really be that, right?
Because what's the what?
Why wouldn't we do that, right?
It only gives us more information and the name is preserved when it's
passed through, so we can still parse it out.
So I think we're pretty much always going to want to do that.
If I'm not mistaken, all names that come through the system, I think
we would probably want to First, do a debug name on them so that we
just have that information about where it came from.
So I would say, almost all of these are probably that way, right?
When we do any of these things because record debug event, I don't
think will automatically do it right record.
Debug event doesn't try to do anything automatic, it just takes it
directly as it is.
You can kind of see that.
So I think in all these cases, what we really want to do is we want to
make sure that we're always passing that debug name because that's the
thing that will wrap whatever we say.
Into a string that's got the additional information.
So I think that's what we want.
We can obviously always bail on that if we if it turns out that I'm
doing something stupid and that's not a good idea, but that feels to
me like the right thing because that way, we're essentially packing
all of the important information into one pointer, it just has a
string that's just got all of that in it and that way the debugging
system at its Leisure later can just kind of grew up extract that as
necessary, which seems reasonable to me.
Yeah, we're going to have a little bit of work to do obviously later
on where we have to kind of deal with these strings.
That's going to be a separate issue but anyway, so alright.
That seems fine to me.
Let's see what we've got here.
Block name
So this matching block named stuff is just going to match the grid,
that's pretty straightforward, right?
What else we got here?
Block name?
Yeah, I don't I don't know that.
I don't know that there's really a lot of cases where we can't just
swap block name, you know, we're we can't just swap block name with
with that code and then later we just got to kind of parse it out and
make it into something more reasonable.
So anyway, time date we're now in the to time block
So we got to go ahead and fix our time to lock stuff.
So here is time block.
Not sure what the complaint is there.
It looks like our unwrapping macro is not working properly.
It looks like it's not welding.
Maybe the way that it should because this is a, this is the first time
that we've got two time blocks, I guess.
Or is that just the first time?
Like what does it say?
Time block underscore so it's not actually welding a number on there.
So that just looks like a macro bug, it's not welding this number,
right?
So why isn't it welding that number?
Well, if we say time block name, it looks like it's not welding the
number because we accidentally eliminated that which is stupid.
So, that's not a good idea.
So let's not do that and then we should be fine.
Okay, so missing clothes before, identify our pixel fill again.
This is probably just a problem with them.
With the macro.
So pixel Phil is going to come out right here.
Where is debug name function and debug name name?
That needs to be a string.
Am I right about that?
So yeah, let's take a look at that particular guy wears it.
There we go.
So I think the only problem here is that that's supposed to be a
string and it wasn't a string other than that.
I think we're fine ignored time, block.
I don't know what an ignored time.
Block was supposed to be, so I guess these are not really so ignored
if I may, so that's fine.
I mean, there's nothing wrong with that.
All right.
So ignored time block pixel, Phil just needs to again, be
Like this.
See what else we got here.
These guys don't need to be there anymore.
And debug data block, platform.
/ controls.
You know, I don't know why that happens.
Also, there's a weird photo thing where it loses.
The compilation directory, periodically.
I got to see what I'm doing wrong there, because that must be
something I'm doing since I'm the one, who stores the compilation
directory.
So, I must have a bug in my fur coat or config, but I don't actually
know what the bug is.
I got to look into it because I'm actually the person who stores that
and it gets, I must like accidentally hit a key that overwrites it,
that I bound to something, I don't know.
It's weird.
I
Something up anyway.
So let's see, executable refresh.
So this is begin block.
Now again I think this is just going to be a situation where this is
actually a word now where we don't have to.
Yes it's so that's really there's not particularly much.
Wait, why does end block need a name?
That doesn't really make any sense.
Does it do they match by name?
Is that how we did that?
Because I assume that they
Like what's, what is the idea behind that does anyone know?
in fact, end block is not supposed to even have to take an
Anymore.
Yeah, I don't know what the point of that is I'm just going to delete
that and then we'll see if that actually matters because the blocks
have to open and close symmetrically.
It's not like you could open one block, close a different block and
then close that block.
I don't think we allow that or at least if we do, I think it's fine to
disallow it because I don't really feel like putting that in there,
you know?
So yeah.
So let's let's, let's go ahead and
And I get rid of that because I don't even know what the point of that
is.
It should just always close the surrounding block.
And I suppose, what we could do is we could make this be a begin block
and block.
We could just use timed block for this pair and have it passed the
string twice.
If we wanted to do that, you could do that.
I don't know that we care that much about it.
We'll see.
All right.
Oh wait, I need that.
Why am I doing that?
I just said, I just said, I didn't want that or that
go.
And let's see.
Okay, so now I don't actually know if where we should probably have,
we didn't really go finish the debug layer to change it to support the
things that we did.
So we are kind of not quite there yet but we're already, you know,
working to a certain degree as you can kind of see we have like we
have some stuff doing some stuff.
The problem is that right now.
Doing is this taking every debug event and like I said, since we're
not parsing this extra information that it that we get and stripping
it off before, we do any of our other debug work, we just end up in
this circumstance where we got all kinds of garbage in here because
each one of our dear this is like there's going to be one of these for
every line of debug code because hey our grid is working good news.
It's got the file line, encounter and all that stuff.
So it means that we have a unique source for every last piece of
debugging.
Ugh code in our game but that's not how we want to actually display
it.
So basically we need to do now is just ping back over to the debug
code and when these goods come in, we want to parse them out so that
we grab the file line and counter information from them, which is all
good.
but,
we want to strip that part off and save it and then just
Is that that other part, which is sort of the like that the real name
that we gave it, parse that, and use that to construct the debug
hierarchy as necessary.
So that's what we need to switch over to doing now.
I think, I mean, don't quote me on this, but I think we're at the
point where we, where the macros are a little saner.
So, anyway, we, I'm pretty sure we also tested.
This will have to test this again.
As you know, this is the this is the debug space remaining.
And so when this gets down to zero is when debug information starts
getting recycled after we're done with all this.
Since we've made so many changes, we should set the total debugger
Mina down to a really small size like you know 1K or something so that
we can watch it recycle a lot and make sure that we don't have a bug
in there because obviously, even though we tested it a while back,
we're not really testing it now because until that number gets to
zero, no,
Recycling is happening.
So until that number gets a 0, we have no idea what's actually
happening in the recycling recycling might be totally broken because
it's never getting run, right?
And so that's also just something to something to note when if until
this number read zero, we have not tested the recycling in sort of the
new stuff.
All right, so, let's take a look at where we're at, in the debug
system.
So I need to take a moment to reefer miliar eyes myself, with sort of
what we had here, because we've pulled some things out, and sort of
reorganize things a little bit.
And so, I kind of want to make sure that we're, you know, we don't
have too much of a stijl remains at the outset here.
I kind of want to trim away, potentially a little bit of that as
necessary and we'll see how we go.
So,
Going to start at the beginning and just take a quick look at how we
ended up in terms of our structures here.
You can see that the debug state is pretty pretty giant here yet at
the risk of stating the obvious.
So, we've got a lot of stuff in here.
We have the high priority queue.
And I believe, the only reason we have that at all is because this
needs to be able to display font information and other bitmap debug
data.
So it needs to be able to talk to the asset system and load stuff.
So I suspect that's why that's there.
But again since I'm just refill your muscles I'm going to I'm just
going to make sure that I actually know that that's true for for
reals.
So
So I'm going to go and search this file and just say, okay, where is
high priority queue actually used.
it's like the answer is no, where
So let's take a brief look and see if we even need that anymore, we
might not.
Looks like we don't.
So if the hike priority queue is not need anymore.
I'm just going to vape it because yes since we're talking to the asset
system I'm assuming that that's yeah you know what that was it was for
when we actually called the renderer in here probably but we don't
anymore we just build the command q and let it deal with it later.
So I think it's probably fine because the render group is going to
have access to that I mean at least I assume.
So anyway, let's go back to what we're looking at here.
So we've got our Rena's
You're going to nationalize that stuff's fine.
Our render groups are fonts which we need.
We don't really need the compiler anymore because we don't ever run
the compiler from the debugger anymore so that actually could go away
and we could if we wanted to pull that stuff out of the platform layer
and just say, we don't do that anymore because since we don't actually
need it for anything.
As far as I know we could just we could just Vape that maybe we should
And we can leave it in the platform layer for now.
You know, we can say that.
That's, that's going to stay in the platform layer for now.
Just in case, we want to turn it back on.
We won't delete the important part of the code, but you know, might as
well get rid of that for now.
So we've got menus and selections and that sort of stuff.
And then we've got our hash tables here for elements and information
about elements of the root groups and the trees.
That's what I want to take a little bit more of look at first.
First, I'm going to just go through here and just
Check this stuff out scope to record.
I believe that was a thing we were using for profiling.
I'm going to get rid of that temporarily and C because I wanted to
know.
Is that just that that actually is part of the collation work?
I'll leave that in there temporarily.
But that probably we want to reassess as well as we do the profiling
as we do a profile view.
All right.
So oldest frame, most recent frame and collation frame.
I don't really remember very much about these frames to be honest with
you.
So I'm going to take a look at that.
Struck debug frame, just to see what's here.
So yeah.
So these are just in Max reasons for frame.
Is that even a thing?
Do we even do any of this stuff anymore?
To what extent do we use these?
I'm interested to know.
So let's take a look.
Let's look at collation frame.
Is that even being used anywhere?
There it is.
So when we do this we create a frame and we're collating that frame
and then I guess we're done with that frame.
We push it on that set of frames, so that's fine.
Don't really know what we do.
I guess that's just kind of sitting there waiting for us to put more
information in it because if you take a look at it right, there's
nothing really in here, it's just, it's pretty minimal.
Formation.
It's just when the frame began and ended how much time elapsed between
those two and then some information that you might have used if you
were displaying like other stuff.
So I feel like, yeah, that's not super important.
Hmm.
Interesting.
Anyway, not doesn't matter.
So anyway, yeah, so we got the frame information there.
We've got this stuff which is really only used during collation.
We could probably pull this out into a separate thing.
So it was clear that was only two user in question, but this is how we
sort of build up our collation stuff.
And then we've got sort of our free lists here, just for some memory
management purposes, but that's about it.
So, alright, that all seems fine for now.
Why
Shouldn't looking at it in a little more detail here.
Is this element the element tree view, all that stuff?
Because I kind of don't really know much about how this is supposed to
work, right?
And we went through a couple different revisions of it and so we kind
of never quite settled it down into exactly what we wanted.
For, sure.
And we're closer to understanding what we want now.
So now I think would be a good time to massage that down just kind of
Polish it out and make sure that it's working in a reasonable fashion.
So, we have four things here, in addition to debug events, debug
events are the things that go into the buffers that we actually look
at that actually capture some important piece of data, but then we've
got four more things.
We've got a debug elements, a debug view, a debug variable group and a
debug tree, and I feel like that's just too much stuff.
My, my, my hunch is that
You know, I wanted to do explorations to see how much stuff we could
do and maybe we want to cut a feature or two, that we don't super care
about necessarily and make a nice try to get that feature in a
different way so that we don't have to worry about some of the things.
So, for example, one of the things that I was playing around with was
the ability to tear off, I don't know if you remember this like you
could tear off a variable and and view it.
I don't know if we still have, I don't know if we actually still have
that.
At all, but I think you could like, right, right.
Tear off something.
I don't really remember how it worked.
It was some weird thing that you could do.
Yeah, I have no idea but we had some weird thing a while back we could
tear off things and place them and I don't think we really need that.
I think that was an interesting thing to look at but it was probably
just not that necessary.
Because what I was thinking and I don't know why I didn't think of
this before.
But what I was thinking is if you want to build you know easier access
things, we don't really need that to be.
We don't really need that to be.
So dynamic.
Right?
We can still just have one debug view tree and then we can just have
different like trees that it could view that we just set which one it
is in the program and be done with it.
We don't need the ability to really like dynamically customize those
at runtime or do anything else to ridiculous there.
So I'm not sure that we really need to do it that way, but either way,
you know, we may want to keep the concept around anyway because we
probably do want multiple views into the data.
We can like have optimized use for different types of debugging like
when we're trying to bug memory, we can set it up for one way and when
we're trying to debug you know performance we set it up a different
way or who knows what, right?
So let's just try to drill into these a little bit.
So I'm just going to go take a look at what each of those is and what
it's supposed to do.
So you can see the debug view is here.
And debug views are just all a debug view is and this is something
that I don't think really needs to be edited much.
All a debug view is is a way to give some information that attaches to
a piece of debugging state that says like how to view it, right?
Because what's happening is we've got these debug events than they're
sort of coming in.
These events are like coming in through the system.
We're recording them.
All right?
And we wanted some way of saying oh when I'm looking at one of these I
want to attach some information to it.
That'll let me know what to do when I debug.
And so they were set up so that we could sort of look at them up in by
debug idea or whatever.
And that would give us the information that we needed to know about
what should be happening in that case.
And the reason that we did that by hash was so that we could have it
be sparse and
Sleepy like if you interacted with something, then we'll remember it.
But if you've never interacted with it, then we don't really need to
remember it.
So that way, we could view things like giant list of things without
having to really worry too much about them, right?
So I don't know how necessary that is, but there's nothing wrong with
that system.
Seems totally fine.
So, I don't know that we need to do anything too, much more
complicated with it.
We can just leave that as it is at the moment.
So, let's move on here.
So we have debug start event.
Debug stored event is how we take information out of our debug buffers
and keep it around permanently.
Those are the things that we're sort of filling up that, that
Per frame Arena storage as it kind of goes up.
That's what storing it is.
This thing, this debug start event our debug element,
A debug element is a sort of the header that says this is a particular
source of debug information in the program.
And it's got some number of stored events that have happened to it
over time and
Are stored here.
So, this right here is basically a linked list of all of the events
that occurred from this particular element, right?
Then we have this, which is a hierarchical way of viewing, the sort of
the data, right?
Can link this up to children and then finally have debug trees and
debug trees are just the one of those sort of like the notion that we
would start.
At some variable Group, which is the higher cool thing and display it
somewhere on the screen, right?
So honestly as much as I'd like to say that, it's a little
overwrought.
Honestly, I think we've represented actually, each thing we do really
need to have in here.
Like none of those are particularly redundant.
You could collapse some of them down onto each other if you wanted to
lose a feature like for example, we could collapse the concept of a
debug View.
We could just collapse that into the debug variable link itself that
probably would work fine.
But if we did that, then different debug trees would not be able to
have different states.
So for example, if we had to debug trees that both included somewhere
in them, a particular collapsible group.
When we expanded the group, it would be expanded in both.
So you can see why, you know, you might not want to do that reduction
because you definitely lose a feature.
So I'm not sure that
These are actually completely redundant so it seems fine to me that we
actually have them so really all.
I think we need to focus on for the time being in order to get things
to a state that's useful to us at the moment is that the debug
element, the debug elements that we're building.
These grids are now those full names that have a bunch of information
in them.
And I think what we probably want to do is parcel out that information
into something that's actually going to be.
It's going to be more human usable, right?
So you saw how it was going there.
We want just that last part to be constructing like the hierarchy for
us.
We want to parse out the file name and the line number in a different
way or whatever.
So what we could do is say that when we encounter a debug event, we
will create a debug element that sort of has that information in it.
So we'll have you know the file name that it came from you know the
function name that it came from perhaps and the the
The line number in that file, right?
We can have that information and then we can have its actual name.
All of that stuff.
We can actually have sort of known, right?
All of that stuff seems totally totally doable so when we get to one
we parse it out and we put it in that format that way our debug
elements actually kind of had that information blown out and people
can use the one, they actually want to use, right?
So let's just start there.
Because I know that I want to do that, so we might as well do that.
All right.
So when we're doing this and we're looking to see if we can match
instead of matching these grids, we don't want to do that anymore.
Anyway, that's just not a good idea, right?
In fact, when we, when I'm looking at this, what we probably want to
do is just take it a little slower actually, hash the string value,
right?
Because if we want this to work across hot loading, we have to be able
to allow the
Winds to change pointer, right?
We can't count on the Grid's, always being the same pointer because
across hot loads of the game code, all of those pointers are going to
change those strengths while not necessarily all of them, but some of
them probably are going to change possibly all of them but certainly
some of them are going to change.
So what we want to do here is we want to have some way of actually
hashing the stably, I think so.
I think what we want to do here is do a string hash, right?
So we always do exactly what I said.
We always always need to do, right.
And you remember this, we need to do this right here.
Better hash function
You always put it to do in front of your hashtags as better hash
function.
Then you write a really bad hash function and then you ship it.
That is how everything always happens.
It's a requirement.
If you're going to be a professional programmer, you need to know how
to do this because, you know, you, hey, you put it to do there.
So, the fact that you'd use an awful, hash function, you're absolved
of all guilt, right?
I mean what's the problem?
So, here's my scan function, I'm going to take a look at the grid as
it comes in so that the event has that grid that's that's coming in.
I'm going to look through the the string here and I'm going to start
with a hash value of 0, I'm going to go ahead and you know what we
could do.
And I don't even I don't, I'm loathe to eat and do this because I'm
teaching you the wrong thing I suppose.
But if we were to type in good string hash, right?
We could take a look to see if there's any particularly good hash
functions here.
Hey look, it's University of Washington, which is, you know, actually
pretty good for CS right.
You can see here, they've got a whole slide presentation on it.
Making string fast.
Use Horner's rule.
This doesn't look I'm not I'm not so confident in that hash functions
for Strings.
Let's see here, let's see here what have we got for hash functions for
Strings.
Because we could take a look and see if there were good hashes for
Here we go.
So, here is an example of a string hash, right?
Not
Particularly good looking.
Maybe it is.
I don't know but you can kind of see what what tends to happen with
these guys.
You do some math Ops on the thing as you go and that supposedly gives
you a better string hashing.
I don't know, I'm not gonna do it.
I don't know anything about hashing.
If that's number Theory and I'm zero, knowledge of number Theory so we
are just going to use the world's worst hash value for Strings which
is to just use the the sum of the values and we'll just let the chat
people on the chat.
They'll be somebody who's more into number 3 and chat.
Maybe pseudonym 73 will know and then he can say maybe multiply the
values by this, as you mix them together and then it'll be better and
then we can go back to it.
But I don't really want to do that now because I don't know.
So anyway, so once we get a reasonable hash value and we pretend that
somebody else did that for us.
Obviously, we do the same thing that we always do.
It's trivial to get an index from that.
We just say.
Alright, let's go ahead and MOB that value so that we know that we're
inside the array and then we can search through here to see if we get
any matches for that string.
Now, when we take a look at that string, we are no longer going to be
able to just check these two.
We have to actually do a string compare but we can
do a string compare on some of the other values.
Probably a little more easily if that makes sense.
Although well,
No little turn here.
So if we just do one string compare than that makes it a little bit
quicker, I suppose than having to do multiple of them, I don't know.
But what I was thinking of doing and maybe this is a bad idea.
Is I was thinking of saying like oh okay, maybe I what I actually want
here is debug element source.
And debug element Source has that in it, right?
And that way, what I can do is I can just say, like, oh, okay, when
you actually send me one of these things, for whatever it is that the
debug event.
I'm actually gonna, I'm going to actually assume that after we do the
hash of the quid.
We're going to store it in here, but then we're going to want to parse
it out, right?
So we're going to want to do the parse of this, debug element Source
into its separate pieces.
So that we actually can compare them, which we
Not have otherwise been able to do, right?
So that makes it a little bit trickier.
The that's why I say it's a little bit, it's a little bit iffy.
I also don't know we don't actually get the function name do we.
We only that sometimes past so it's really just this is all we have,
right?
So maybe what I actually would need to do again.
Just trying to think through how this is actually going to work out.
Maybe I do still want to keep the grid there and then I would want to
do something like say well,
You know we've got the grid and then what we do with the grid
afterwards is we just parse it, maybe we keep sort of like a pointer
into it that we can use like something like you know.
Val name, count caressed.
Our file name, something like this, right?
And
Since we know that we have to sort of extract it and then like this,
so we'd still just keep one buffer and then we just keep pointers into
it to sort of say where those things work.
I don't know if that's a great idea or not.
But that's what I'm, that's what I'm thinking.
So anyway this way if we did the reason we do that way is because then
if we keep the grid then I can at least just do like strings are equal
to each other and then I can say like if the goods are equal to each
other as strings, then this is the one
If not, then it's not.
And so then here we would go and we would get that information out,
right?
And so if we get to me,
if we get to the point where we need to allocate a new one, then what
I would want to do is I'd want to use sort of the debug memory to
store these grids.
Like, before we weren't storing the Grid's, we weren't sort of pushing
them, onto our, debug memory.
And that to me is like a bad idea.
Because like I said during reload, you know, we would crash
occasionally there, we would be using it because the debug system was
not safe across hot loading.
So if we try to Hot Load, we could crash device.
I mean I don't want to do that.
I want the final table system to be able
To work across reload.
So that when you're doing hot reloading, you can use the debug system.
I mean, we want those two sets of work together.
So, what I want to be able to do here is I want to be able to push
that string onto some permanent storage and you know, inside handmade
debug dot h, we have an arena for permanent storage that we can use
because we've got the perfume, we also got the debugger Reno one and
so what I was hoping is that we could say well the debug State
debugger Arena, you know can we just push that string on there?
So this way now we would always use that result grid instead and now
we can sort of do that parsing out that I was talking about before.
So we have we have the next in hash part that all that all that stuff
is going to be exactly the same that that's all just that this is all
exactly the same.
The only difference now is we're going to be passing event name
through here and that's going to be what's used for the hierarchical
name stuff.
And so
All we have to do to get this working properly is due the parse of the
name so that we can extract the that sort of additional info that we
need for like the file name in the line number in that stuff.
So we just want to make this stuff work now.
So the first thing we have is we have the file name.
We want to get the file name by just scanning through the string to
find where we actually.
Our that open parentheses close parentheses.
So we would just start with our scan again.
We in fact you know what, we could do.
We could also just do it right here.
So while we're in the middle of hashing, we're all.
We already going through the string.
Once we could just do do it right here.
We could say that like well we know the file name pointer in fact, I
don't even know why we bothered with the filename for enter the file
name.
Pointer is just the quid pointer, right?
This is
Right?
Those are the same thing so they're just used in whatever case you
just would use the file named count.
So really all we're solving here is the file name count, if that makes
sense.
And don't ask me why this isn't it?
Because I don't know.
So anyway, so the filename can't we just need to start at zero and
then we just got to go till we see that open parenthesis there and the
closed parenthesis.
So we know that we've got those parentheticals and what we could do,
Know if you had a file name that had a parenthesis in it.
This would work.
We don't.
So we'd have to care about that.
But just so, you know, this isn't a going to be like a robust parse of
this thing and and so we could just look for the first parentheses and
say that's the end of the file name and that's totally fine.
Now, in order to do that, we just say, if you know, that's what we
see.
then filename, count equals scan - the beginning,
That's how big it is, right, really, really straightforward.
And I suppose this could also be as well.
Just be named starts at right?
That's pretty simple.
So anyway, we've got we've got the file name count.
That's how long that's going to be.
We've got the name starts at and the way we know where the name starts
at is the name starts after the file name.
It's got the parentheses going to dots go.
Number two, I got: right.
So when we see that:,
And where's our debug name here?
Debug dot h, or excitation state interface, so here it is.
We should just make this be the optimal thing for parsing, now that I
think about it.
So probably what we would actually want is just this
So all we have to do is just say like okay each one of these bars
tells us that particular piece of information, right?
so,
every time we hit a bar in this Loop, we know that we've got a
different one.
So first thing will be, it'll be the file name, count.
The next time we hit a bar, it'll be the Y number, right?
and then, the last time that we hit the bar,
Actually I guess technically this is the file name, count and the line
number.
The next time we hit it, we don't care the next time.
And the next time the last time we hit it, that's the file name.
Right?
So I think that's what we actually want the line number.
We actually have to parse out, right?
So that's actually one of these.
It's, it's like that.
And again, at some point when we replace the C runtime Library, we're
going to have to replace this guy.
So not a hard one to replace, so I would don't really feel bad about
calling that it's not going to be a lot of work for us to replace an
A2.
Ia2 is pretty easy.
We don't have to parse a floating-point number even so it's especially
easy.
Here.
So, that's okay.
So, that's not a big deal.
Anytime we call something from the C runtime library, right?
If we presumably at the end of the series, want to actually get rid of
it entirely,
Just for fun.
Anything we call we kind of want to know when I think we call a couple
things, a couple math functions, printf, et toi, and so those if we
want to get rid of them it's just good to know if you're calling
something particularly crazy and weird but we're not.
So atoi is pretty easy.
All right, so and
it's the same thing we call in our
Parser to write, I don't know, doesn't matter point being, it's not a
bad function, it's pretty easy to implement.
So I don't, I don't think we're adding any kind of unnecessary burden
on our cells for that.
So anyway when we do the scan, what we all we really need to know is
like this is the I guess the pipe count.
So the first time we hit one second time, we hit one and third time,
we hit one, right?
And right now we don't care about the counter value.
There's really nothing for us to do with it and so if we have all that
information, now when we actually get down here, we should be able to
just fill out the struct pretty trivially.
So we can just go ahead and say, oh, okay, let's see here.
I've got h.
So filename, count equals results line number equals and result in
starts at so filename.
Count we already
Line number.
We've got and name starts at.
We have, I believe
Right?
So, yeah.
And we could also make a little thing here, that's just like
Get name, debug element element.
And that could just be, hey, if you want to get that and I could do
this week, There's no actual need for that Union.
Obviously, that way, there's basically just a way to get those without
you having to actually remember that.
That's what that work is.
We can just say like, oh yeah, yeah, the result of this guy is going
to be the element grid plus name starts at
Right.
And that will return this and this is get file name that can just
return the grid directly
Although it's technically a counted string.
So, you know, you kind of got to say something like, I don't know if
we even have that concept of counter string.
So we do here in deep here, in debug variable group, we've got that
concept right here.
So probably what we would want to do, I would think is make that a
little bit more of a First-Class citizen, right?
So we probably want to do something like saying,
Stretchy, bowstring, and that would be like name length or length and
contents something like this and or value and so that way, you know,
when you get one of these you could just get, you know, the file name
as a debug string and it would return it to that way.
So you just say like oh you know, the result of this is just the
It's filename count and the elements value.
Sorry, the element WID is the value, and then that's it.
So that seems reasonable to me.
And then this guy from the debug variable group, obviously, that could
also eventually become a debug string after we, you know, if once we
care
So yeah, debug source that went away.
Name starts at that is supposed to be off the element pointer
obviously.
And what's the confusion here?
That is not supposed to be there, not supposed to be there at all.
All right, so let's see.
This is obviously just going to be assumed that these can never be
whoop.
There we go.
That these can never be that long so we're just going to cast them
down.
That's fine.
No.
Wait, how is our atoi?
Not found because it's in, right?
I mean, isn't it in here?
Maybe I'm missing something.
Not really remember where that is.
There we go.
I really wish my five-minute warning window would go away.
I can't see anything.
Hello.
Try that one more time.
so, same thing here,
Obviously since these are 64-bit pointers after we do subtraction on
them, they want to say 64 a bit but we don't really want them to.
So, push string needs to take the address of the Arena.
That's all fine.
And then this right here actually needs to take get name
Other result.
All right, so I don't know if this will work well have to step through
it and see first, I'm just going to run it so I can see what the
output of it is and then we'll go from there, all right?
So interestingly enough it looks like part of the person is working.
So I guess that's a good sign to some degree anyway and
And so really, I guess if I just use get name when I'm printing these
out.
Yeah, it's kind of interesting.
I think this is going to be good soon.
I'm thinking by tomorrow, this will start to look kind of nice, I'm
looking forward to that.
All right, so anyway, we when we're printing the grid we really don't
ever want to print the grid anymore.
Like, we're printing the grid and a bunch of places and that's just a
bad idea, right?
So we kind of want that to stop happening entirely.
And so, for example, here, we don't want that ever.
We want to do instead of this, we want to do get name.
On the, on the element.
In fact.
Why is this?
What is this doing?
so, when we do a debug event to text,
I guess when we remap I'm going to.
So I got to look story event.
How does story event work?
So here we go.
We go into story event.
We take the frame index, remember the frame index?
We copy the event over so that's just wrong.
That is?
That is also a problem, right?
Because that means that, that Gwynedd value.
That grid value is going to get copied and it's going to be wrong.
I don't know what this is here for.
Exactly.
But all the rest of these aren't pointers and that's important, right?
These two are.
And we may have to deal with them separately, but this right here is
not going to be safe.
And so what we actually want when we when we do this is we want the
resulting element.
Sorry event to actually use the grid from the element because that's
been cloned.
And so now that will be safe across reloads because it's not going to
point to a string.
Table.
That's in a dll that might go away, right?
So that's yeah.
That's a, obviously, a good thing.
You know, I kind of thought about just now something that's kind of
interesting, I suppose.
One thing you could do with hot reloading now on 64 bit System.
Since you have kind of infinite memory in some sense, as long as
you're not touching it, you're not infinite memory but a lot
You could just load the dlls.
And never free them.
So you just load a dll in and it's got the script string table and you
load another dll in and it's got another string table, but the old
string table still valid.
Right.
And then if you wanted to, you wouldn't have to ever worry about
copying the strings.
It's not that big of a deal because you still can't do this stuff that
you would have wanted to do, which is compared like to string pointers
for equivalents and know that they were pointing the same string.
Because that doesn't work anymore anyway, but it's kind of
interesting.
I never thought about that.
If you wanted to keep data around from previous runs for some reason,
you just can just don't free the library because you can load 12
copies of the game code, right?
You load 50 100 copies of
You can roll as many as you want.
It don't matter, right?
So that's kind of nice.
But anyway, so, weak restorative have a problem here, which is when
we're doing this, debug print, the event, the event printing.
We don't actually have the element, which is where our stuff has been
parsed.
And so really, when we do debug event to text, I kind of feel like in
here we want to supply the element pointer if possible, right?
So you
want to do like, you know,
Optional element or something like that.
So that you wouldn't have to keep parsing the debug name all the time
for no reason.
Right now it's not a big deal to parse that all the time.
We could just always parse to the last pipe and print that out.
It's not like that's that costly or super problematic but it does just
kind of strike me as being not that particularly important.
Oh
or we could just store it pre advanced.
That's interesting.
So what we could do to is when we do store event, we
To say, like I forget that like let's do this.
Now, they would always just be the name.
Right when we print them out.
So, that's interesting.
That's, that's pretty interesting to me.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and and take that one step
further.
So those slashes, there, any time we were talking about underscores
before we're talking about slashes.
Now, obviously, got to remember to change my for CO2.
Config, I forgot to change it.
Gotta change it, I'll do that tonight.
So yeah, what I want to do here is, I want to go ahead and say, all
right, that since we're talking about started last time, just score,
that's really going to be called started last / now, you know I'm
saying, and so start at last /, it's going to look for that.
This guy.
Yeah, and the other thing we're going to want to do is now when we're
parsing for that, which we're doing, we actually want this thing to be
this get group Parc, guell name, whatever nonsense here.
We actually want that to be this.
So I'm going to call this first separator, right?
So that we don't have to pin it down to an underscore.
There we go.
Separator.
First separator.
Versed, separator.
Okay.
So now I think we're getting closer, still not quite there yet because
it's a little confusing as to why these look like they do.
So we're not quite and and these are like printing out weirdly right
so we got we got more work to do obviously but we're at least in
better shape.
So I think we're in good shape for tomorrow to kind of get displays
into a better place.
We can also start filling in the profile stuff and think about how we
want to do these like these things.
So
Let's go ahead and let's go ahead and call it for now.
So I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A.
And leave it at that.
This is like hatch competition.
I'm 9 plus can so do we know if that's a good idea?
I mean, obviously you want to do something other than something the
values, but I just don't know.
How did you, how do we know that 65 599 is a good idea.
I guess you've got a source there.
Let's see what it says.
Look at pseudonym 73's.
I trust his math skills is all.
So what he's suggesting is anding out the high for bits.
And then X touring with them shifted down, knotting them.
Well, that's a crazy little, that is a crazy.
Hash,
Is there a reasoning behind?
The sash?
Is there a reasoning is their reasoning behind?
What why we would pick this hash?
and fnv hash,
And then someone else's is suggesting this, the 655 91.
So let's take a look at what that one is comprehensive collection of
hash functions.
Oh, hey, look KN.
Our first edition, had the sum them all up.
That's so great.
That it goes all the way back there.
I just kind of six five five six five, five, nine nine was picked out
of thin air, while experimenting with different constants and turns
out to be prime.
This is one of the algorithms used in Berkeley DB and elsewhere.
Beard.
I feel like somebody should have.
A more sort of stringent proof of why this is good.
I'm not look back at the chat.
Hmm.
So I guess what I would say is time 6599 is really easy to do.
So I feel like if we were always going to do you know to do better
hash, right?
So if we were like to do Casey better hash function and you're going
to type this in any way.
Oh wait, that's not, that's a different.
I'd say we have that comment, it's so good.
So if we have to do better hash function and the only thing that we're
going to do here is do this add.
It seems pretty straightforward to actually do the six.
Five five, nine, nine one.
Right.
So
That seems trivial to remember, right?
6599, if that's all it takes to get us, you know, I don't want to say
significantly better hash function but perhaps significantly better
hash function that seems worth typing in, right.
I mean
That seems are typing it.
Now what students are going through is saying is that using the 1/4
symbols, and elf might be a good idea because we have common strings
with numbers at the end, and at that, be a similar case.
And so, it may be that the one that pseudonym 73 was suggesting might
actually be the better one for this case here, but it looked like it
was a little harder to remember, potentially, if that makes sense.
So, I don't know about that part.
like, it'd be kind of hard to remember that L function, if you were
just going to type something in
You know.
So what do you think pseudonyms anything you think that this one is
good enough?
Like, how would you feel if we just went with a 65 599?
What do you think it's going to be okay?
I mean, either way, it's probably okay.
But, you know,
All right, so we'll just leave that in there.
And we'll call that good.
Looks like no questions today.
It's all quiet.
Kenny's room.
Do you have a stream schedule?
Yes.
Actually if you want to know the stream schedule, there's a couple
different ways you can get it, but the easiest way, I've been, there's
one way is this button tells you the countdown to the to the next one
on handmade here at dot org.
So that's helpful.
The other one is, there's the tweetbot.
So if you follow this tweetbot, handmade hero on Twitter.
Then, basically, it just tweets the schedule all the time.
So you can always know when it is at the beginning of the week, at
tweet, something that looks
Like this.
So you can just look and see what the whole week schedule is going to
be and then everyday.
It tells you the time in the morning that that's that the stream will
be.
And then an hour beforehand, it'll ping with the link in case you want
that.
It also afterwards will will ping out the YouTube video in case you
missed the live stream.
So, it's pretty handy.
Students 33 actually, could you humor me and look at the assembly for
that hash function, the six, five five, nine, nine one.
I'm curious to know how well, it compiles it but an integer multiplied
is not going to be that extension.
Extensive is it expensive?
Is it?
What's the, what's the clock cycle on an Eye mole?
These days, maybe it's still is I don't know.
Actually, you know what I could do?
That would probably faster than trying to look it up there.
But yes, I will definitely humor you in a second.
I just kind of want to satisfy my own curiosity here first.
I mean that's like,
That's like no-cost, pseudonym 73.
Is I mean right?
So why what?
I'm curious to know what you're concerned about is actually.
What now I'm curious.
I'm curious about your curiosity but yes, we'll do it twice obviously
the this version has optimizations off.
So that's not going to be very interesting to probably but we'll do
that first.
And then I'll switch off patients on.
Because that's what you're actually going to want to look at.
I would assume, so if we go into him a debug, and we take a look at
655 Hoops 99.
Oops.
Yes, thank you.
Thank you, goodbye.
And we set a break point on that line and run it.
What's the problem?
There we go.
So if we run that guy and take a look at what it did with no
optimizations,
What did it do?
It's just issues the Imo.
So, read issues the IMO.
It does the ad and then it's done.
So that's what you would expect.
I would think I don't know how expensive the IMO is.
To be honest with you, I just don't remember how well it's not.
I don't remember, I just haven't looked recently, how expensive and I
mul actually is but I have trouble believing, it's particularly
expensive.
If if the mole epi32 is a throughput one instruction, then maybe
you've got a little bit of an overhang.
What was the latency on that five worst case, and you have five Cycles
isn't the best but at the same time it ain't horrible, right?
So
there's there's that if I go ahead and allow the optimization stuff to
kick in so we haven't done that in a while but
It's, if I go to handmade platform that itch, where do we turn off the
optimizer?
I don't remember.
Because we do what we do.
Do it right.
or did we not so have we never
Let's see.
64-bit build Hammer.
Dot CPP.
I've been through two, handmade.
Yes, so we we change the optimization, right?
So that we always
we always build with optimizations on, right?
Huh.
So, what did, what did we, what did we do here?
I'm super confused.
Did we just never?
We never went and back and did that, but we did switch the code
together.
All right, to be continued on that one.
But for right now let's go ahead and build with optimizations on and
see what happens here.
Okay, same basic difference.
I would say didn't really do anything else looks like it's just
Still issuing and I'm alone.
Dad.
Kb3.
What is I'm o?
Integer multiplied.
Yes, it is.
I'm all.
Is just a standard in x86 instruction, which got carried forward to x
64, which is what we're using here.
It's just the standard instruction for multiplying two integer values
together.
So basically, what happens is you put, which registers you actually
wanted to multiply
In this case, because we're multiplying by multiplying by a constant,
there's actually a special form, this kind of gets pretty off-topic.
But so Intel instructions set is
so, it's kind of a
It's kind of an interesting instruction set.
So the way the into Intel instruction set works is it's not like say
powerpc or something where every instruction is a fixed size.
Like, you know, how we do sometimes on stream?
Like, we'll do like a struct and we'll just have a union and all the
different things are in the union.
So every, even though there's multiple types of things, everyone is
the same size.
So, just it's however, the biggest one is, however, big.
The biggest one is, That's How big each of our things is.
And then we just,
A union in there, that's like the different size, whatever.
Well, some instructions that are instruction sets are like that.
So for example, powerpc was like that where every instruction was the
same size.
So when you looked at it instruction you knew that it was exactly the
size and all of the instructions have to fit in whatever that was, you
couldn't answer that was longer.
Until is not like that.
The way into the instructions work, is it's encoded as a variable
number of bytes.
And so, different bit patterns in each bite, tell you whether to read
the next bite.
So, for example, you can see
See here that this this mob ex and SX instruction is actually encoded
as 3 B, it's encoded as ofbe 03 but the I'm all is actually encoded as
a lot more bites.
It's 69 f f 3 F 0, 0 0, 1 0 0, right.
So it's totally different.
Now you may ask?
Why is this the case?
The answer is because of the way that it got extended over time if you
want to do backwards looking and try to be generous to it.
You would say that it's because you want to have the ability to have
some instructions.
Be longer than others, so that you don't waste time spending.
A lot of B encoding, a lot of instructions.
So it's kind of like a Huffman tree encoding of instructions, right?
And you could see that being a very smart way to encode instruction
streams for processors.
If you don't know what a Huffman tree is is basically a way of it's a
it's a compression technique.
You can go take a look at it but point being Intel's, architecture
editors, destruction coding is sort of like that, but it's not a
particularly well-designed Huffman tree.
Because instead of having all the instructions,
As you ever might want known ahead of time and then perfectly
balancing the Huffman tree to be set up for the frequency of a given
instruction translating to how many bytes it takes to encode.
It it's actually more like every time they went to extend something
that became another sort of level down the Huffman tree or whatever,
and so it's actually not that.
Well, designed for compressing necessarily, whatever.
What are you gonna do?
That's Legacy.
That's just how it goes.
So the long and short, that, that's a very long.
Roundabout way of saying, well what ends up happening is that you can
encode, some pretty fancy ridiculous instructions.
So one of the things you can encode for example is an I'm all where
you're going to say that you want to multiply the contents of EDI by
some constant that is included in the instruction.
So you didn't have to load a constant into register first.
And then say, I'm all this fresh vaginally, the instruction itself.
These bites right here are actually encoding the actual
In itself, the actual constant itself, right?
So the, the 100 3 F, that's actually this part right here, right of
that.
I'm oh, so the I'm always like, oh, I'm all this register.
And then here's a constant that we just stuck right in the
instruction.
And we're going to multiply, right?
And so that's just something you can do.
When you've got a crazy variable length instruction set architecture.
Like Intel's is, you can just go Hog Wild.
So, a lot of times when you look at
Documentation for an Intel instruction.
It looks very different from the documentation for say, a powerpc
instruction because like a simpler more straightforward non-variable,
instruction size architecture.
Typically, has instructions that are very simple.
It's like, here's the multiply the first parameter is the register 2
multiplied, by the second parameter is the register to multiply two.
And it stores it in that in that second one, the
Result it over right, sit there that with result or something, right?
Something like that is what you would see documented in like the power
PC or something like that, usually, right?
But if you look at, I'm all on an Intel architecture.
It's nothing like that.
What?
I'm a looks like on an Intel architecture is like, ah well
Here are the eight thousand ways you might want to run an Eye mole.
So let me tell you about them, right?
And you can see that here if I pull it up here,
Are all of the things that it might be right.
So it's like, oh, did you want?
Like, you know, this times an immediate that you want this times?
Memory, did you want this one?
Like each one of these is actually two different ones that's like,
register or memory 16.
Like, oh, there's all kinds of stuff.
Like it's just, it's a festival, right?
So the Intel instruction sets are very like crazy, configurable in
that way and like everything.
Is like all these prefix codes, or they're like, oh, well, if you set
the high bit of that, then it means that that you'll read the next
bite and use that to determine whether or not it's going to be an
immediate.
And if it is, then it's the first part is the seven bits of the
immediate that combined with the blah and blah blah blah.
And and that's honestly that's how the instructions that works.
It's a crazy instruction set to work with if you're writing a
compiler, because the outputting the instructions is just this funny
like crazy bit of code, that is so much more complicated.
Then what it would look like in like a powerpc or something.
Okay, let's see here.
Yeah.
Extracting pixels, dude.
You inspire me to write a handmade Windows?
Debugger?
Are you serious?
Because if you are seriously doing that, is there any way that you
could make it be callable as like, a dll?
So, that, like, you know, we could integrate into for coder or
something, because that would be awesome.
I would love or Windows debugger that wasn't Visual Studio.
Mojo Bojo.
Why did you put the Delta time of each frame into the input struct?
That seemed a bit strange to me while looking through the source code
today?
Well, I guess I'm not sure.
I understand your question is the question, why do we need to pass the
Delta time per frame to the game?
Or is the question?
Why was it passed in that structure?
Which, which of those two questions?
Do you actually want to know the answer to?
Qbert.
Caleb, why are the half b of the hex value.
100 3F reversed in the instruction.
I can understand the B being reversed, but the half b.
Let me see what you're trying to say.
I don't think they are.
These are B.
Not half B, right?
And so this is the 3F, right?
This is the zero zero.
This is the 01 now you can't see the 01 there but there it is.
Right?
And remember that's not super unusual because Intel's little endian,
right?
And what
Means is that in memory the 3F comes first.
It actually goes in the bottom of the register.
The 00 comes next.
It goes next 01 goes it comes next, right?
If it was big ending to be the other way around so it's not that
unusual for Intel to encode it this way in memory because it is a
little endian architecture.
So that's how it would be encoded in memory regularly like for reals,
right?
And I suspect that this might be a full 32-bit immediate because that
is probably part of the I'm oh, let me take a look.
Look.
Uh-huh.
Sure enough.
Check it out.
So basically what it's doing here is this is a full 32-bit immediate
and it's just happens.
So it's actually storing this value in there, right?
That's what it's actually storing.
And so it's just it's like 3 F 0, 0 0.
1 0 0.
That's what, it's, that's what it is.
So so it's like, here's the I'm all 69 f f.
That's the instructions.
That's the like I want to do and I'm all with an immediate and you can
see here that we're probably doing, let's let's take a little bit.
Let's look at the instruction operating coding here, right?
So operands one operand to Upper in 3M for here,
upper and 3 is that immediate 32 operator operand to is one of these
like register memory and and this one is a register
So I'm assuming that in our world that we may be in the one operand
from because it's just EDI.
But this was an echo to that used by the most traction source operand
is multiplied by the value.
In the ill X RX pressure to perform with this.
From a destination operand is multiplied by The Source operand, the
same summer has jumper must register in the source.
Operand is an immediate value.
A jumper stretch for or remember location.
The intermediate product is truncated stored.
So do they have the encoding?
I don't know.
That they do, we probably just the general encoding.
Let's see here.
Did you sign multiply opcode.
F 6/5 here.
So I don't actually remember the encoding.
The, I don't remember the decryption that way to decode how that is,
but I'm assuming that that actually has EDI encoded in it, that makes
sense.
Quarter on and you want until the ship a unifying ISO for all gpus.
Yeah I mean look ma'am.
Just because it's ugly.
Doesn't mean it doesn't work, right?
Like
every year these
You still run all the code.
That was compiled for them.
Right, like code, I compiled 10 years ago, if I run it today.
The only way it doesn't work, is if Windows screwed up the apis which
they often do, right?
But the exit before just works.
So as crazy as that sounds and I admit this is a wacky instruction
encoding.
You know what it does.
The thing I want it provides an extremely reliable way to build a
piece of code and run it forever.
It's like it's exactly.
I want so yes I would love if intel would just be like here is the iso
for gpus because if they committed to that and treated it like xxt as
just part of x64 from now on what an amazing world that would usher in
there be like no more compatibility problems at all.
They just be gone overnight, right?
And I would trade almost any amount of graphics performance for that
because man, the times when I'm sitting around going, we don't have
enough graphics performance compared to the time to sit around going.
I wish.
Of the stuff, we ran it all and didn't crash, you know?
It's just it's no contest nowadays.
Okay, so let's see here, extracting pixels.
I'll keep that in mind.
Please do if.
Yeah, if you have any interest in like making, if you're going to do
the work of making the debugging stuff, which is a bunch of work to
like parse pdb files or not, really parse them, but read them with the
apis or whatever.
And then you know, set the brake set breakpoints and get register
information out.
If you're going to do that work.
If you could expose that as a dll that people could call,
Or you know, whatever that would be kind of amazing because then
people could build tools on top of it and that would be awesome.
Mojo Jojo.
Why was it passed in that structure?
It was specifically looking for the Delta time variable and that was
the last, I supposed to be.
So, the reason that I passed the clock as part of input is because, if
you think about what the clock is, its input, right?
Like basically, like you can think of the things that are coming from
the outside.
I've got, you know what?
I'm tapping on the keyboard, what I'm clicking on the mouse and that
time is passing.
So when I need to, like hand, the game stuff,
And be like, here's all the information.
You need to know what happened.
Since last time you did something.
The time is, just like all of those things, right?
It's the interval of time that has elapsed between the two and then
like, these are the key presses that elapsed between the two of these
are the mouse clicks of that.
So I consider that to basically input other way to look at.
It would be, what are the things that you would have to record in
order to play back a user's session, right?
And again, same thing, I need the keyboard input, the mouse input,
The time, right.
So basically, like it is essentially an input device.
The wall clock is an input device and so that's why I tend to think of
them as the same.
Mojo budget to add on since each player has their own input struct.
It seems to me like passing it through each one, was going to be the
same for each player.
Seems redundant.
That's not.
We don't do that.
That's not how it works at all.
So if you go and look at handmade platform.sh, where that stuff is
defined here,
You can see in game input that you only pass the DT once and then
like, for however, many controllers, there are, is a separate set of
inputs.
So that we don't do that.
There are not separate inputs per person.
So so yeah.
So there you go.
All right, I'm gonna go ahead and close this.
Here, I should do that.
Now that I think about it, probably shouldn't quite cozy yet cuz we
shouldn't leave the probably leave it compiling, you know, to, because
I'll forget and be wondering why our debugging is all squirrelly and
then be like, oh, that's why.
So, let's go ahead and save that off and leave it like that so
building, right?
Yeah.
Alright, let's close this down.
Alright everyone, thank you for joining me for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along the series, you can
always pre-order the game on handmade here at org and it comes to the
source code so you can play around with it.
So if you want to learn from the string, that's a great way to do that
and you can do that right here on having a dork.
We also have a forum site, you can go to the Forum site to find out
more about the series ask questions and and have Martin's Mosaic.
Oh I don't really know how to pronounce his last name.
Answer them because somehow
Seems to know the answer to everything so before I even see your
question, he'll probably answer it with a better answer that I would
give an anyway.
We have a patreon page where you can split the video series and other
hand made projects.
We also have a tweet bot that I mentioned earlier on the stream during
the Q&A.
When someone asked that tells you what the schedule is it speaking to
schedule?
I will be back here for the last few of the week.
Friday Stream, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
Hope to see you here for that when we can do a little work prettying
up our debug display, that's about it, hope to see you.
You guys here tomorrow till then have fun programming and I'll see you
guys on the internet.
Take it easy everyone.