Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we code a complete game live on stream.
We are just going to continue what we were doing yesterday where we
were implementing printf, just to kind of show how to do it and to
remove dependency on the C runtime Library.
So that we can be more portable more easily, portable etc, etc.
So
Without further Ado today is day 328.
We are going to dive on in so you will want to use if you're trying to
follow along at home day, 327 source code, that is what I'm using
right here and you can kind of see where we left off yesterday.
Basically we parse everything in the printf.
Now we may have some bugs in there but we definitely implemented sort
of a scanner for all of it but you can kind of see in here that we
don't actually obey a lot of the print apps.
So right now
Kind of, you know, we do % s but, you know, things like %, D your %,
F, we just look at and discard.
So, we now need to go Implement some of those percent operators that
we don't currently do % f is the hard one as I mentioned.
So we'll leave that one for the very last that'll probably have to be
after we come back, but the other ones are easier to do and we should
be able to make more Headway on those, in short order since there's
nothing particularly bizarre about them.
All right, so let's see what we've got here.
We have a number of functions essentially that we want or I guess to
say output types that we want to handle and some of them are well, a
lot of them are very closely related, right?
So, you know, d, i uo x + + p.
And C are all basically just integer print out I guess.
Well, C is
I think C is actually print out the actual character.
So C is actually a ASCII print out so that one's actually much easier
but all the other ones are kind of like integer print out.
And then the other remaining ones, the A gef.
And so on, those are the floating-point printouts.
So we should be able to write one routine since we don't care about
this being particularly fast or anything.
We should be able to take.
At least, in theory a routine that can print out a use 64 like one,
unsigned, integer value, that 64 bits long.
We should be able to take that and use that to print out.
Basically all of our non floating Point values, right?
Because if we can print out a 64-bit value, well we could just use
that to print out a 32-bit value.
Just by leaving zeros in the upper bit, right, and we can use it to a
16-1 by just again
Zero.
So a 64-bit value could print out a 32-bit value, a 16-bit value and
an 8-bit value just fine.
And furthermore if we want to print out a signed value, instead of an
unsigned value well we can just call the unsigned print out routine
and just first check to see if the value is negative, if it is
sticking - in there and then call the routine with the negated value,
right?
So we also shouldn't really have any trouble printing out signed
values with the unsigned routine.
And so, really what?
I think we need to do here is just right.
That one routine that can print out of you 64.
And then from there, we should be able to leverage all the rest of the
information.
Pretty trivially.
Now, the other thing that we know is we could print the 64-bit value,
essentially out into a temporary buffer if we wanted to and then do
some reassembly that's actually probably what we want to do here
because
Regardless of how we actually print this out, we then have a bunch of
stuff we need to do.
That might involve sort of fancy footwork.
Like for example, if we want to pad something with zeros but we don't
actually know yet how long it is, that might be very difficult.
So we might want to print to a temporary buffer first because we know
that a 64-bit value can only print to a certain number of individual
values right to me,
Since we know that a 64-bit value can only take so many characters,
it's easy to have a little temper on the stack that we just fill with
those values and then we can go after we fill it with those values and
and figure out, okay, how long was it and what do we need to do with
it to sort of straighten it out and so on and so forth, right?
Okay, so let's go ahead and start this process.
And I'm just going to kind of sketch out roughly what I want to do
here.
So in the case of D or I what I want to do first is say, like, you
know, if the value is less than zero, then I want to negate the value,
right?
And I want to print out a sign.
So I want to do like an out care to attempt essentially.
And you know we've got this sort of out care thing, right?
Where did that guy go?
Well, I thought we did.
I don't care, there he is.
So we've got this out care thing, right?
And so I could make one of these little format desk.
Guys, out of a temp buffer, essentially and just print to the temp
buffer and then use, you know, do reassembly essentially after the
fact, right?
So here I could do something like okay, care, you know, temper,
whatever and I don't know how long that should be yet, but we'll just
leave it like that for the moment.
And then we can say like
Account temp and 10th.
Like so,
I can then come in here and say all right, you know if if the values -
I can
Laughs, I can output a - I assume out care.
I don't remember how we actually wrote out care, you just takes a
single care.
I can output the - if I need to and then I can negate the value now.
I might want to do that a little bit differently in a second and
you'll kind of see why as I go through it because I don't know if
there's a clever way to if there's like a interesting way to do what
I'm about to do, but I don't think there is so I actually probably
We don't want this to happen quite this way, but we'll see.
In other words, what I probably want to do is something a little more
like this.
You know.
Probably want to do this.
I'm just guessing where I do was -, and if it was negative, I negated
So after that, I just want to be able to process the value.
So I just want to be able to say something like, you know, you 64 to a
ski or something like this.
And what I want to do here because remember I need to be able to print
out this in a couple different ways.
I don't really remember what all the ways are, we can look at the
format list, but at the very least, you know, that we want to be able
to print out.
As in both decimal and hexadecimal now, decimal is base 10 and uses
the digits 0 through 9, right?
But hexadecimal is Basics teen and uses the digits 0 through 9 as well
as a through F.
So we essentially have two different character tables that we kind of
want to do here.
So you can imagine, you know, having like heck scares and decimal
cares or something like this.
You know, and sort of having like a lookup table where we
We would have each of the digits that are involved in the process and
trying to make a routine that's generic.
So that, you know, we can choose which ones we want to use and maybe
like,
Because this was a stupid little minor spec thing because you're
supposed to be able to choose uppercase and lowercase.
Heck, we could support that pretty easily by just having two different
tables.
We don't even have to really change the code at all, if we're already
supporting it.
So what I'd like to do is do a, you 64 to a ski where, you know, I
pass it to you 64 that I want to do.
I pass it.
This should not be desk.
There should be temp, dest.
I pass it like you know please right into this thing.
Here is the value I want.
And you know here's the the
String of characters that I want you to use, and obviously, I'm going
to need to tell it how long that is because yeah, otherwise, it
wouldn't know.
Now, in this case, I would have to do re count minus 1 because the
null Terminator is included there.
I'm just going to tell it it's 10 because we know that it's 10.
It's a, you know, it's decimal.
Obviously it has to be ten characters, right?
So that's neither here nor there.
And so then in theory, you know what, I'm hoping and you know, we'll
see if this pans out is that I can do basically the same thing here,
right?
So I can get for putting out you.
I could use that for.
Oh, I don't remember if that's octal.
Unsigned octal.
So for octal, it's you know, actually still the same character is
there's just less of them, right?
So for octal I could just say we'll only use the first eight
characters, right?
And if this magic routine works, okay, then you know in theory it'll
just work and that'll be fine.
So yeah, so then we can do your 64 to ASCII four hexadecimal.
This is lower hex Cara's because the small X and this would be upper
hex cares.
Don't ask me why that 27.
Somebody had their finger one to the left.
Let me try to type the value.
So, you know, that's that's what we're talking about, right?
And I don't know about the pointer value thing, but I'm pretty sure
the pointer value.
B is exactly the same as everything else.
I you know I'm pretty sure that it's just going to print it out in
hexadecimal I think so.
I think it's just that and I don't know whether it's uppercase or
lowercase to be completely honest with you.
So you know I'd have to look that up.
Looks like it's lower case.
So, I guess we'll just use lower hex.
So I think in theory all we have to do is actually implement this
function now and then we could start having actual some print out
there.
So let's take a look at what that would entail.
And of course we've got some problems with how we're going to do the
Precision formatting and all that sort of stuff.
But so in this particular case, what do we, what's the name of this
guy here?
It's a format desk.
There we go.
So we know we've got a use 64 of that's our value.
We know that we've got another thing, which is basically the base,
whatever the, the number system base is, and then we've kind of got
like our array of digits, right?
So, what I want to do here and maybe I'll switch the other windows to
my head.
Doesn't get in the way.
So so in you 64 to ASCII, what is this complaint?
For my testing from
Sorry about that.
I'm going to pass that address.
dad address do
One more room down here to this one?
More of them down here.
There we go.
Okay.
Can I convert voice art?
That is true.
So what I really want you to do is pretend it's a use 64.
The problem with this is, I don't really know what size that should
be.
So we kind of need this to be a um M because if we were compiling a
32-bit, we want to be a 32-bit value.
So I kind of want to cast it to that, that makes sense.
Alright, so let's go back up here.
You 64 to ask a, what I want to do now is I have a value.
I want to convert that value into digits and, you know, I need to be
able to sort of do that in any arbitrary base, right?
Well, that's not really that hard to do, right?
Because I could I could easily peel off the numbers kind of one at a
time by just dividing by the base repeatedly, right?
you know, if I want to know,
This is pretty straightforward but I'll draw it out anyway just in
case it's unclear.
So you know if I'm here on day 3, 28 and we're talking about printf
If I have a number of like 123 and I want to know what the digits
individual digits are of it.
Right?
Well, I know, I can take this value, you know, if this is, if this is
my value.
I know if I take the the value modulo, whatever my base is, right.
And I say my, in this case, my base is base 10.
If I take the modulus with the base, I'm going to get the remainder,
right?
I'm going to get whatever the remainder is when I divide this thing.
By that value and you can look at this value and know.
Well, if I was going to look at what the remainder of be, if I divide
it by 10, well, it's going to be three, right?
It's going to be that first digit.
So I can always tell what the first digit is by just doing the modular
with the base.
And that gives me, you know, my first digit
So the question is, well, how do I get the next digit right?
And the answer there is, well, if I need to advance to the next digit,
I can just actually divide the number by whatever the
Base was right.
If I divide 123 by 10, then I'll kill this digit off and move one
over, right?
So V divided by base, like moves one digit down.
Right.
And this is integer division which means there is no fractional part.
It just kills the three entirely and slides everything over, right.
So really all I have to do is like, do my modulus and then divide
right do my modulus divided modulus divided and I can peel off the
digits one by one.
Now, there is one inherent problem with this and this is why I said,
you know, temp buffer has its bonuses as well, obviously.
And that is that if you think about what order we're going to get the
digits in, we're going to get them from the smallest digit to the
largest, right?
So, if I do this process repeatedly, I'm going to get three, two, one.
But that's not the number.
I
To print the number.
I wanted to print was 1 2 3 and so, you know, for our purposes to keep
things simple, we can still use this procedure will just flip the
digits at the end when we actually go to Output them, right?
So that's why I said the temp buffer is also handy because it means
you don't have to think very hard about the output routine because you
can just do the dumbest possible way of getting the digits.
And then you can just flip them after the fact, you know, you could
try to be more clever than that.
But you know, like I said it in cases like this, where it's only for
debugging, it's probably not in your best interest to sit around
spending a lot of time, thinking about the fastest way to print out
integers.
Although, you know, if you are in the mood for, you know, something
sort of like a small constraint exercise to do, it's probably
something.
think about
floating Point certainly is
so anyway, what we can do here is just say, well,
If the base, I'm sorry if the value equals 0 then we know we really
don't have anything to do, right?
Then we know we're just basically doing whatever the 0th digit is.
And that's it, there's nothing else to do but otherwise we probably
want to do a while loop.
And I guess, you know, what I could do to is just make this
Something like this.
So we'll get in there.
And we'll just say, okay while the value is not equal to 0 do it but
we want to go through it once because even if it is 0 we want to point
out one digit, right so.
All right so we're going to do exactly what I said.
We're just going to have a thing which says okay the digit that we
want to print right like the digit for this time is just whatever the
digits are.
I suppose I can just do this directly.
Well let's let's write it out.
Long form.
So, we'll say, digit index equals value mod base.
Like so.
The digit is equal to whatever one that is.
Output it like so.
So you can see there, we just do the mod, we look up in the table,
which one that is.
And then we have put it then we just need to advance to the next
digit.
So we say, okay,
Whatever the value was.
It's now going to be divided by the base.
Now obviously, you can't pass a base of 0, but we know we're never
going to pass the base of 0.
So that's fine.
And of course, you can print out a value in base.
0 least not that I know of maybe, there's a clever math.
Way to do that, whatever that means, I don't know what it means.
So that would essentially be our printout, right?
That would give us our characters, but again, it gives us the
characters in reverse order.
So now, the caller does have the responsibility of actually doing
something with that.
That makes sense, right?
So our attempt test here has an array count, oops, situation set up.
Where, yeah, we kind of need to come through here now at the end and
do.
Thing with it.
So assuming that it was filled, right?
We could say you know if temp test at is not equal to Temp, then we
know we've got something to sort of fill out here and
I guess we could also say is, you know, if this thing was - then we
want to include that that negative sign, right?
We want to put in that negative sign.
So into the temp desk, we want to put the negative in the if it was in
fact - right.
So now we've got the value with the positive or negative sign in there
and it's ready to go.
So then all we have to do is say well okay.
If we're you know, if we're in a situation where we actually printed
something out, we can actually just probably print these out in
reverse order, we could just say like okay
Back up one and print out whatever you've got.
so that's just like takes our temps buffer and like puts it out,
So yeah, we're going to step through that because that's just the kind
of a ton of weird code but you know, there it is and you can sort of
see.
Now we're actually starting to get some of these things Printing and
you know, they might even be right, who knows?
We going to have to go test it because you know, we don't actually
know what these values were supposed to be for all.
We know they're not those values, they certainly seem reasonable like,
it gets it's conceivable that those could be correct values.
and yeah, like I said, now we can
Out all kinds of integers that we might conceivably want.
And so that's a good thing as well.
I don't think there's really anything else to say.
They're looks all good.
Nobody's crashing or having a problem so that's all fine.
So yeah.
So that's that.
Okay.
Now like I was saying before we'll put it to do here.
Well I guess implementing right backs actually, instead of putting it
to do I - let's do it.
The definition for right back is we're supposed to take however many
characters we've used so far and let it know.
So we're supposed to just take whatever they gave us and say, well,
okay, whatever the temp test actually is at were and wherever it
started.
So it started, you know, here at at Dustin it.
So, if we just take a look at the difference between where we are now
and where we started, that's the value that that tab just wants.
Back and of course we've got to truncate that to an integer because
the printf spec doesn't allow you to write back 64-bit values even
though our printf supports more than 4 gigabytes string sizes fancy
that you be wouldn't be able to actually write any of that back.
Because it two gigabytes, the it runs out of space.
So, anyway, we have the pointer value as well.
All these things are pretty easy that this one I guess, with the
With the c value that's going to want to go into the temp test as
well.
Like so,
Yeah, so all of those go into temp test and this is actually supposed
to be regular Des not temp test.
I think.
That all is, what should happen now?
I guess.
I don't know for Strings, I guess, I don't know if strings are
supposed to follow.
Yeah, I guess they're supposed to follow.
Sort of those other rules the like, with rules and stuff.
So this is definitely to do obey, Precision, Etc.
Precision, perhaps not but with definitely like dot star or whichever
one that is with this Precision or with I don't remember there is a
meaning for those Precision in a string.
I think it actually a base.
Both I think Precision is string is how long you treat the string to
be.
So instead of looking for the null Terminator, you cap it to that long
potentially even if there isn't an alternator encountered by then, and
then width is sort of like how wide it prints out.
So we do need to obey both of those and so that will be something that
we have to do.
For the rest of these guys, who print out into the temporary
destination, we should be able to kind of roll some of that in.
So for starters, let's take a look at some of these other things here.
So, positive sign is is blank.
What were the other one for sign and positive sign is blank?
Are those sort of contravening values?
We see what those actually mean.
If no signs written a blank space inside before the value forces to
proceed, the result with a plaza / - but following negative numbers,
okay?
So we should be able to obey those actually now in our + or - there's
only one person currently because we're not looking at floats yet,
there's only one person currently.
Who does that right?
And so, what this does here is it says well if it's negative if we're
going to force the sign then we would output it even if it wasn't - so
I guess actually that the right places that is probably an else
Clause.
So if we're going to force the sign put a plus in there, if you
weren't going to put a negative in there, right?
Otherwise
And I guess this goes in here, otherwise print the - in the forest
sign case.
In the fourth, sign case, I guess, I don't know which one of these
takes precedence, but I'm guessing that it looks something like this.
It's just a wild wild guess.
But basically saying okay, you know if this thing was - print the - if
it wasn't - and you wanted me to always print a sign, I'll print a
plus if you didn't always want me to print a sign but you told me that
I have to leave a blank when it's positive, then I'll print that.
Now, if you specify both for sign and policies, think I don't know
that, that's the right precedence.
Like maybe you wanted to be blank and not a plus if you specify both
of them, but it seems like kind of an error to specify both of them.
A so I don't really know like what's the most, you know, maybe I'll
say assert not positive.
Sign is blank, note not a problem here, but probably shouldn't happen.
You specify?
Something like that.
Just to the programmer knows like how you've got sort of conflicting
things in there, seems reasonable.
I don't know what the printf spec says about whether you can have both
of them or not, but it's almost certainly a bug if you had them both,
I would think because you wanted one or the other because they can't
both be in effect unless I'm missing something.
so yeah, so that's all we really need to do there and we can pull this
out into a routine once floating-point needs this
To do make this a common routine once floating point is available.
So, yeah, the rest of these guys just do what they do, they don't have
a sign.
So it doesn't matter.
And these guys are float, which we don't handle yet.
So then we're pretty much just down to the out care stuff here and
let's take a look at what we have to handle.
So we've got pad with zeros.
Left justify annotate, if not zero, I think.
Is is what is that?
I don't even know.
Use with 0 x or X of the fire is the value is proceeded with 0 x or 0
x respectively for value is different than zero.
Okay?
So basically, that's just saying we're going to put something in there
if it's not zero, what a strange.
What a strange thing?
I don't even know if we should bother supporting that, but I mean, I
guess it's not that hard to
I don't know.
So it's 0 x + x.
It's these 0, x and x.
And it says that it's going to be like an 0 and 0 x or an o x in that
case.
So, it's really just like, well
You know, if annotate if not zero and value is not equal to 0 then we
want to Output the thing, right?
And in the case of this, I guess it's just oh,
In the case of this, it's 0x.
And in the case of this, it's oh, capital X.
I guess.
Now the problem is these are going to be in opposite order.
So technically I guess it's like that.
I don't know.
That's just, I guess that's just well.
There you go.
I have no idea, but that's
What the specs seems to indicate we should do, so we did it.
Well, star value out care dust.
Plus.
The most inelegant possible way to do this.
But there you go.
So anyway, that's I think all that has to do with that and so really
we just need pad with zeros and left justify.
So I think those are the only ones we actually care about.
so,
We've got with, we've got Precision, we've got left justify.
We've got Padma zeros, that's what we need to support now.
I don't actually know what Precision means for integer.
Some look it up.
Precision specify the maximum over digits to be written if the value
written is shorter than this number.
The result is padded with leading zeros.
The value is not truncated.
Even if the result is longer a position of zero means that no
character for the value 0.
Now it seems
Shouldn't it be padded with spaces?
I guess not.
It's padded with spaces.
If the width is bigger.
Man.
Okay.
So I guess you always get zeros in the case of the Precision but you
don't always get zeros in the case of the with
Welcome to it boys.
Yeah.
All right.
Let's come down here and take a look at what's going to happen.
So here is our printout routine and you can kind of see that this is
going to have to be extended because there's two things we don't know
the or rather that we can't count on.
First of all, we don't know whether or not we want to print out all of
these characters because it may be that the Precision that's specified
is not big enough for all of them.
Furthermore, we don't know if the width is big enough for all of them.
So we may need to sort of like print less of them if that makes sense.
But we also don't know whether or not we may need to print more,
right?
Because it's possible that somebody has specified a with or a
Precision that is larger than the actual number that we got, in which
case we've got to start adding numbers to it to make that happen.
Now there's a couple things I
I'm not really sure about.
I don't really know where the zeros go.
So I guess we will have to do one sort of
I guess.
We might have to do something a little bit more clever here where we
do like a prefix or something if that makes sense and you know temp
prefix or something like that.
Because we may need to insert padding like in between.
you know, in between the
Sign or the like 0 or 0 x, and the actual value.
So I think we may need to do something where we say like oh yeah, you
know, we don't actually insert that.
Because it's got to be sort of taken into account separately.
And we'll sort of deal with it later.
On the plus side that does mean, we probably don't need to keep it in
reverse order because we can just out put it in four words order or
something.
All right, so there we go.
So we've got some temp prefix stuff in there, I kind of just call that
prefix.
and so, when we get down here and we're going to do our print out, we
can also sort of do a 4
Strobe.
We fixed our pre-split.
Spree at care.
Dest 3.
so, in theory,
That will.
Do what we needed to do, but we still haven't taken care of the things
we actually needed to take care of.
Oh,
I got to make sure my prefix starts out with something.
I could print in the case where there isn't one.
All right.
So yeah.
Now we have to start working on actually obeying those widths.
I think that these guys, for example, probably all should have had
with and currently aren't having with.
So, I'm not really sure but we can always insert some people who need
to have them so that we can make certain that we're supporting them
properly as a test.
I don't know that there's really a whole lot of
other stuff here that's printing out numbers.
So yeah, let's go ahead and start to work on this.
So here is the stuff that we care about less justify and pad with
zeros.
and then, we sort of got
With specified in Precision specified.
So these are sort of all the things that we need to take into account
right now.
I don't actually want to define a these here, at they're already
defined up top.
I just want to, you know, kind of see what they all are.
Like so.
Okay, so the first thing that I guess I want to try to do is figure
out how to get this thing to be the right size.
So I feel like the way to do that is just to say, well I'm going to
have to print out a certain number of things.
So like I'm printing these things out like so.
So what I could do here is say, well, you know, there's going to be a
use with.
There's going to be a number of characters that I'm going to print out
and I'm going to set that equal to the width itself.
But if I have not specified a with
Then I guess I'll just use the Precision, well, I guess not the
Precision but the Precision, plus the prefix.
That makes sense.
So yeah, so if I haven't one set one, I'll just set it to the
Precision.
Plus the length, whatever the string length is of the prefix, right?
Because I'm going to print out the entire thing.
if you didn't tell me something else,
Right.
So then I have a used with the variable that I could legitimately use
and then we have to deal with the Precision situation and so in that
case, I could say the same thing.
Let's actually use a variable called use Precision here.
So I'll say use Precision equals the Precision.
But in the case where you haven't told me of precision, so if you
didn't say what the Precision was then I'll just use however long.
The thing is, you actually told me you wanted right?
I shouldn't say that.
However, long the thing actually, was that that it generated
naturally, right?
And so you can kind of see the the approach I'm taking here.
I'm trying to boil down a lot of variables into one.
Sort of simplistic way that I can actually do a single print out of
the character is taking into account all these sort of relatively
complex dudes.
So I'm going to leave left Justified for a minute.
Powers Heroes and see.
We'll get to those in a second.
I'm going to see whether I can get this working.
Relatively cleanly, I now have a Precision value and a width value,
And so what I want to know now?
Right is what is the difference between the Precision and the width
right?
Because if the Precision is different than the width or or rather if
the Precision is less than the width that I can actually use then I'm
going to need to Pat it but if it's not then I don't write.
And so that's actually relatively important for me to know and so on.
So I'm kind of trying to boil this down
Some like easy check.
So as I print a long, I can do the right thing.
All right, so what I kind of want to do here is I probably want to do
A bit of a fake out since I already have a way to clip.
Well, you know, maybe I don't actually want to do that.
I'm not sure exactly what I want to do here.
It's a tough call.
But here's the thing.
So when we start to print out, we know we're going to print the
prefix.
Always, I think I assume the prefix takes profit precedence.
So I think, what I want to do is I want to start printing and I want
to say like print the prefix so long as there is with remaining.
Right?
And so every time we print out a piece of the prefix, I'm going to
decrement the amount of with we have left.
If we run out of width, I'm going to stop printing the prefix.
Right.
Does that make sense?
So that seemed and it just eats away at the width that we have, right?
Then what I want to do is now I'm left with only the part that has
nothing to do with the with right.
So now I have to print the stuff that has to do with the Precision and
what I want to say is, well however, much with I have left if the
Precision is bigger than that, then obviously I'm going to need to
sort of shorten it right?
So I think, at this point, I want to say, if use Precision is greater
than use, with then, use Precision equals the use with, right?
So I'm going to get down to just the use precision and then I can say,
well I've got to have some Precision left and I have to still have
something to print
Assuming that I do, then I can just sort of do this, you know, exactly
as you would expect.
okay, so I think that properly would handle all those cases, but I'm
not actually
Doing any padding it.
So I think this would handle the case where we were too small, but we
haven't handled the case, where were two large, right.
So, what I need to do here is say well, okay, in the case, where the
width I still have Precision left or I still have with left, I need to
do some operations here, right?
And so what I can do as well is say, well, I know I'm going to print
out, I'll just do it.
The long for my, you know, at the end of this, I know I've got to use
within a use precision and they might both be greater than 0.
So, the first thing I want to do is pad for the Precision
And then the next thing I want to do is pad for the width, right?
Something like this.
So as I go for the Precision, I'm supposed to pad with zeros, right?
And when I pad for the with, I'm so stupid with spaces, and those are
things that in theory, could be modified by the pad with zeros or left
Justified I'm sorry the pad with zeros part so we may have to fuss
with that slightly in a second.
In fact, I guess we could literally just do this.
Cuz this is what that is, right.
I think.
We would just have the zeros, but I guess the pad was zeros has to
happen at the front.
Now, I think about it.
So I guess I have to check up here and do the pad here, right?
So I have to say like if you specification is greater than used with
then the user is going to get clipped but on the other hand if used
with is greater than use Precision, I need to do the pad actually
here.
So this is actually this while the use with is greater than the use
Precision.
I got a pad.
I think that's actually correct.
Right.
So that's basically saying like, okay, we've got a clamp, those two
down.
But then, if I have with that's left over, I've got a 60's in here to
kind of make sure that I, you know, fill everything up to the point
where I'm actually going to print it out.
Right.
Furthermore, I think this needs to be done up above because the pre
well,
Yeah, it does.
Furthermore, I think it needs to be done even higher because, right,
it should be part of the prefix thing here, right?
I should pad before I put the prefix on, I would assume
so, I think
I think what I need to do is say, well, as long as the you
Choose with.
Is greater than what I'm actually going to want to print at the end of
the day.
Then I need to kind of Pat it up front.
That seems right to me.
Then I do all my printing out of the prefix so now I should get to the
point where I'm ready to go.
I then have to clamp the Precision in case it was going to be too big,
I then use all that up, but at the end of this, I still may have more
room.
I still may have Precision left over that, I would need to pad.
And so that's going to be the same thing I think.
So,
I need to have.
The exact same kind of loop where I just kind of decrement the
Precision going forwards.
By padding with zeros.
All right.
Kind of heinous, but there you go.
So I think that actually does mean though that left justify probably
isn't too hard to implement.
I think all we need to do to implement left justify at that point and
say well, okay, we've got a use with specifier here that's going to
pad with the zeros on the front end but we could say you know, that's
only if we're not left justifying, we're right justifying.
If we do want to left justify.
Well we could just do this at the end after everything else is done,
right?
The only difference there is we have to make sure we actually track
the with everywhere just in case, but that doesn't seem too hard to
do, you know, whatever, right.
So here we could say, if we are left justifying, then we just need to
say, well there is still used with the new pad, with whatever the
padding is that you're going to use if that makes sense.
And I'm not sure what would happen in the pad with zeros case.
I think you have to be patting with blanks and that case because it's
you're going to pad with zeros.
It doesn't seem like there's any way to ever do that so I would
probably say that left justify
I would I would probably say that left justify.
had was zeros left Justified because false,
Cert left justify.
Nope, not a problem.
But no way to do it, I guess.
All right, so let's see what we've got.
You 32 here.
Well, I guess there's really no reason to do that.
I could just make these all be umms.
Signed unsigned mismatch between, oh well, I know that that's not that
fine.
Do we have a signed memory value?
Yeah, so that's just a lot of ridiculously finicky code so I'm not
particularly expecting any of it to work.
We're going to have to step through it all and actually verify that it
works at all and you can kind of see that like well we didn't
completely fail like we're now getting columnar output here in a
number of cases.
So some of our stuff is working, but you can also see that like we've
got a little bit of a problem here with our percentages.
I'm not sure.
There were those floating Point numbers.
So maybe we didn't mess anything obviously up.
Because I think those are supposed to be floating Point numbers.
Why we're getting
Anything?
Well, I guess that would just work.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I guess, you know what?
Honestly, I guess we don't necessarily know that we did anything wrong
because we, we don't have any obvious errors yet.
I mean, that probably it's unlikely that we implemented, all of that
correctly, like that just seems not, particularly likely, let's be
honest.
So, you know, I wouldn't hold hold out hope for that, but that is kind
of cool.
Like, hey, look, everything just kind of worked first time out.
Give ourselves a little pat on the proverbial.
go back, but
Like I said before, even though that stuff kind of works, we still are
left with the problem of being able to plan out print out the floating
Point values which we do not have the ability to do at the moment.
So that's really the one that's going to be sort of a in if you want
but we're out of time.
So you know that's pretty much it before vacation I suppose and that
Is that I guess the Intrepid among you?
I could just say, you know, homework assignment people you gotta
figure out how to print out.
Any point value.
Go read that paper.
And see if you can add it.
You could try.
Let me see here.
About.
It's there.
It was there.
Is this?
It?
This is not it.
Maybe it was it 2016 or was it 2015?
This is the actual one.
Okay.
so if you are so inclined,
You could go read this paper and implement it, I will be away for a
while so you certainly would have time to put it in there and I seem
to recall not being particularly lengthy in terms of code, you know?
I mean is there's that and this but they give you basically the
pseudocode for it.
I have not looked at it myself, but you could look at some of these
Can see I don't know that they're going to be particularly onerous to
implement even if you don't totally understand them in all of the math
behind it, like I said, I haven't really looked at it myself yet so I
can't tell you how difficult that's going to be, but that is certainly
something that you could do for homework.
In the meantime, I've still got a couple minutes left.
I just wanted to take a brief look here in that.
string output, if that makes sense and just to see
As I spill watered-down limeade, all over myself, which is always a
good start, just to see how we're going to actually do that.
Now, one thing I should probably do is say, well, this whole thing
should probably only execute if we actually want to print out the
temper because the string has to do its own thing.
So I think we want to sort of do this
Just to make sure that we're only actually doing that stuff in the
case where we actually care about it, right?
So I think,
All of these values besides the floating-point ones are now sort of
doing probably roughly maybe what they need to do.
So the only one that we really have a problem with I think is the S
value and so that was going to print out the string and it seems like
in order to obey the Precision and the width in this case wouldn't be
particularly difficult.
All we really need to do is sort of handle stuff, similar to how we
handle the below.
Unfortunately, we kind of need to do
Placate it probably.
You know what?
No, I guess we really don't.
So I guess what we could do here is say, well let's just set the
pointer for this stuff to our string.
Right?
I think I can just do that.
So I could say well the temp pointer is going to be the string that we
got the temp dest.
How does this guy work?
Oops.
Right?
Because we just need to read from it.
So I could just say the size of the string is going to be the string
length of whatever the string is, so just priests can it.
Yeah, it's slow but hey, we're just trying to make a compact version
of this thing and we don't care how fast it runs for the most part.
It's only debug code so I could say the temp pointer is the string.
The the temp test size, the string like Tempest at is the string there
and then I think that just works.
The only thing that I think we want to do is make sure we never read
off the end of the string.
In case they were trying to use the Precision specifier to prevent us
from Reading off the end of a string that doesn't have an alternator
on it.
so, what I might say is, well if used Precision is is on
Should say, Precision specified.
If Precision specified is lon, then we need to only look as many as
there are actual Precision things, right?
So I would want to do something like tempteth size equals 0, you know,
care start at or scan equals string starsk.
And plus plus can plus plus temp to size.
So, we'll look at, you know, increment as we go
To kind of find find location there.
This is going to be kind of heinous if we actually want to do this
though, because we would have to reverse the
Order.
So I guess that's a little easier said than done but oh well.
All right, so if we come to hear me say like, okay, what's the
position that specified?
Then we have to sort of scan through to see whether or not we've hit
it.
And what I'll do here is just say, well, as long as the temp test
size, is less than the Precision, then we keep incrementing.
Right?
So that we will never look past the end of the string, which because I
know that you're not supposed to do that.
I'm because I use that in printf all the time to print out strings.
Don't have an alternative at the end so we don't want to go hunting
for a null Terminator in the case where we know that we've hit beyond
the length of the string that we could possibly print out.
right now that would just work sort of
except for the fact that now because we print out things in reverse
order, all our strings will be backwards.
So like for example that's not what I would have expected.
What's going on there?
Tim just size equals string.
Length string.
Oh
of course, I have to
move it past there.
Yes, you can kind of see the pup.
It doesn't look good.
Sorry to go over time but I just kind of wanted to put in this guy
flick the asshole thing, Precision specified, tempt us to size equals
0 to plus size will string length of the string.
The at is going to be pointing sort of off the end of it there, right?
Because that should be right at the end so it should be
I mean, it should be.
The string pointer plus however, far we said we were going to go.
Yeah.
That seems right to me.
Am I missing something there?
I was missing something there.
That needs to get Advanced every time we read, one of those
characters, so that was a mistake.
All right, back to our story.
So yeah, like I was saying the problem here is that anytime we print
out a string, we're going to print it out backwards because that's the
way we're reading from our our temp test, right?
So I don't know how we want to solve that problem.
You can kind of see here.
We've got the, the loop that actually reads from it.
Is this one right here.
So what we could do if we wanted to is just have two Loops here
whether or not we want to reverse, so we could do something like, if
reverse.
We do it one way.
Otherwise we do it a different way, right?
In either case, they're going to be essentially the same, but in one
case, we'd go from the beginning forwards.
Another place would go backwards, right?
So in this case, we'd do
That.
So yeah.
Ladies and gentlemen, printf previous custody.
Anyway, we've assumed that we'd reverse because all of our numbers
print out in reverse order and that's fine.
But when we get to the string, we don't want to reverse same without
care.
So in here.
We'd say reverse is false course, that's only one characters, whereas,
so, it doesn't matter whether we reverse it or not but point being
either of those two would not be reversible.
So now I think we actually be obeying that even in the case of
strings.
So that now you could clip the strings and left justify your strings
or do whatever else you want?
I don't actually know.
Let's find out if that works.
I mean
Who knows?
Let me go over to the debug thing and see where we do like rcy
printout, right?
Let's get a different one here.
What is this straw profile bars?
It's not really what I want to do a profile in.
I think drop drop top clocks list, that's the guy.
So here's our top clocks list and you can see it printing out the S
here.
I don't actually know like let's just play with this and see what
happens.
So left justify is what again, I don't even remember.
Crazy printf left justify is - so what that is.
So let's just throw that in there and see what it does.
Because who knows?
I have no idea.
That in no way left justify 08.
But string is by default left justify.
Right?
So it would be numbers that would be different if we left Justified
them.
So it would be like that would left justify the number if we implement
it properly, which we probably didn't.
Let's be honest.
There you go.
Well, hey.
All right.
That was surprising.
I wasn't expecting it to work.
Get it worked.
That's good.
I guess.
So, for a string, if I actually set the width, then I should be able
to see left justifying or not, I guess.
So let's say I set it here to like 40 or something, because who knows.
Then I should see all these guys.
Flip over to the right side.
No, yeah.
So that all worked fine.
I am kind of shocked that this is all working.
What's a bit odd?
But whatever.
All right, so that all worked.
Let's try it with that.
But with a Precision specifier now
Wow, all right, well, good stream to go out on I guess.
Cuz all that stuff, just sort of worked.
How about padded with zeros and left justify doesn't do anything with
that, right?
So we should assert, yeah, just good.
So, all right, there you go.
Let's go to the Q&A.
Any questions?
Let's see.
I posted my question twice on pre-screen, but both times it wasn't
addressed.
I experienced a bit of lag back then, so I checked on archive.
What's up?
And it wasn't their.
Am I doing something wrong?
I don't remember seeing a question by you in today's pre stream,
What was the question?
Sometimes, I don't address questions if I don't want to obviously, but
I don't recall seeing question by you that I didn't want to address.
A few questions.
A few people in twitch chat are asking about what level of math.
Do you think is required to Be an Effective programmer?
Well, I think that depends a lot on what kind of programming you want
to do, right?
Because, you know, programming there's a lot of different things that
happen in programming, right?
So, you know, if I'm working primarily on like high, concurrency data
movement, stuff,
then the sort of slice of math that I have to know is probably not
that huge, possibly, not really very much at all, depending on whether
I'm working on theoretical aspects of it or not, you know,
However, I'm a game engine programmer.
The math is just dumped on you everywhere, right?
There's math.
There's so much math involving game engine programming, you can almost
not know too much.
I've never learned a piece of math and not been like, oh, I could
probably apply that to something.
I do game engine, programming wise, right?
so, you know, I think that's
The thing that you really got to ask yourself, is what kind of
programming do, I actually want to do?
And how good at it, do I want to be?
And the combination of those two answers is going to tell you how much
math you need to know.
Certainly for going to be a game engine programmer.
You know, a lot of math, there's just that's just the case.
But if you're not going to be game intrapreneur going to be some other
kind of programmer, then the amount of math, you need to know, could
very pretty dramatically.
And so, you kind of need to know that the domain and the necessities
of the domain before you can really
You know.
Answer that.
Okay, so I understand that you're replacing all the string header
functions.
Are you not worried about optimization for these new functions you
plan to write correct?
I am not worried about optimizing these functions because we never
actually do anything with strings in, in handmade hero.
Actually, that's user-facing.
It's pretty much all debug stuff and the amount of string Printing and
stuff.
We do is so limited that it just doesn't matter, right?
It's not like the rasterizer or stuff where we were,
Kind of it's like a really heavy very important.
Path item that we wanted to like, you know, try to do some work on.
I'm just trying to learn how to code.
I'm following strew strips book, and he insists on teaching using
math.
All the good Beginner Books tend to assume math knowledge.
Yeah, I don't know too much about that to be honest because I don't
know.
What are the good Beginner Books these days?
I mean I would sort of State the obvious
Cavalier snubbing and say that.
I would never learn programming from strip because he's not a good
programmer, right?
Like you should try to learn programming for people who program well
so there's that.
But that said, yeah, I don't know that much about what are good
beginner materials right now.
I've kind of said in the past that I would like to do a beginner
stream at some point that like kind of teaches introductory
introductory programming but I haven't done such a thing and obviously
the programming we do on handmade hero is
To be introductory for people learning game programming but not
introductory for people are in programming.
I kind of assume that you already know what a pointer is.
For example, you know, in episode 1.
So for people who don't know what a pointer is that really not going
to going to help right if that makes sense.
So I guess that's what I would say is.
I apologize for not knowing what the answer that, but you have to
remember, I learned to program 30 years ago so you know the
introductory materials that are available today are nothing like the
introductory materials that were around when I was learning and so I
don't actually have any familiarity with them or I'm also not really
in a position to really judge them and me what you'd want is someone
who recently, some people who learn to program who have tried some,
the various ones and maybe have
More of an opinion of you know what works for them.
And what was what was, you know, easy to get kind of get into and what
gave some good grounding on the concepts and that sort of stuff.
So yeah.
Sorry, I don't have a better answer than that.
But I do kind of see it as a something that should be addressed in the
future.
I'm not necessarily convinced that there even are good beginner
materials right now, at least not ones for people who want to be
serious like
Programmers to understand like CPUs and computer architecture and that
sort of stuff as opposed to people who want to be like, you know, I
don't know.
I just program in PHP or something right.
There may be very good materials for that but that's not what we do in
games.
And so it's
You know, it's not really relevant to the kinds of programmers that I
you know trying to sort of reach with him a hero for example.
So I do think better beginner materials, probably are necessary and
they may not really exist at the time and I apologize for that.
But one step at a time.
So let's see here, nearest 909, I guess I know what the problem is
from the port, where you say?
I posted my question twice on pre-screen, both time, it wasn't
addressed down to the part where you say, and again, just let me know
if you see it.
Those are the only two things that came across going to Twitch chat.
So it's not whatever.
You're posting is not coming across, I don't know why, but it is not
actually showing up.
So that is probably a very good answer as to why you were having
trouble.
Getting me to see the question.
Yeah, they're in the twitch chat as opposed to maybe the IRC chat,
there's an IRC.
There's a handmade here IRC, you can use on handmade Network on the
twitch chat.
They may have all kinds of weird stuff like that, bans long messages
or messages, that include links to things that they don't like, or who
knows what in sohbat.
Is the only moderator of the Channel that I know of, and, and it
usually says, if it does anything, so,
It's probably something native to Twitch.
I would encourage you to maybe break it up into multiple pieces, so
maybe like, cut and paste, just one sentence at a time and see if you
can paste it in that way.
If not, then there's a another easy solution to which is you could
just make a paste bin somewhere like an like gist like a guest or
something and then just post the link to it and then I could just go
to the link and view it.
Okay, so, I saw one.
Now, it says, Hey, in one here, I'm graduating and it will be time to
find a job.
All, I always wanted was to work in game mystery, but I have no work
experience or projects that I am proud of to show as my portfolio.
I guess you were leading programmer in your projects and you were
responsible for making decisions who to hire.
And then I'm guessing there's going to be more to the question in a
second, although I can sort of assume that it's going to be asking
about that process of how candidates are screened and so on.
so, I've kind of answered this a couple times in the past, but it's
Long time, since I've answered it.
So I'll kind of just quickly recap rehash that territory.
Assuming I know what you're going to answer.
I wasn't sure what you're going to ask.
So three things, first one is actually, I have never been involved in
any entry level hires.
That's just never something that I ever was in a position to do.
I've been involved in, you know, Pro level hires like hires for engine
team people with
and that sort of stuff.
So, I actually don't have any experience on the sort of hiring manager
side for a, you know, person fresh out of school.
Okay, I have literally, no experience that I've never been involved in
that.
I have no idea how that goes.
So say that do the rest questions.
Come in, how you see people like me incision?
Should I take whichever offers a programmer?
I could find, which might not even be connected with games or
Maybe try to make the best game I can do in a year and save enough.
Money enjoying an internship without salary.
I didn't see any studio with paid one in my region.
What's your opinion?
Yeah, so that's the first thing I say to.
When I got into the game industry, it was very different than it is
now.
So I also unfortunately don't have much experience to share about how
to get your first job because my experience was a time when the
industry is completely different than when it was now completely
completely completely different.
And how I got into this tree, pretty much has no bearing on how anyone
else could get into the industry especially not today.
So unfortunately, that's case.
And the third thing I will say is I did pose this question to Mike
actin who is the head of the tech director of Insomniac people do like
Ratchet and Clank and you know Sunset Overdrive and they're doing new
Spider-Man game and so on so big, Triple A company
But very serious about Little program.
And his answer is archived in the handmade Con 2015 video series.
So if you want to go check that out.
No, that's somebody's repost of it.
Where is it?
Should be a playlist.
I had to put these up in a way that's easier to find.
Oh well, that's the one I was looking for anyway.
So here's the mic actin interview and I don't remember exactly where
he talks about this.
But in this interview, I asked him this question because I always get
this question on stream and he is someone who is involved in hiring
sort of a broader range of people.
Whereas I never really was, I was only involved in hiring like very,
very high-end individual contributor.
Kinds of people
So you could check out that video for some of his answers.
But I don't think he specifically addresses sort of the latter part of
your question, which is what should you do in terms of whether you
should make a project or try to take a job or those sorts of things.
And I would say that that's kind of depends on how good of a
programmer.
You are at this point, probably, you know, if you can do something
impressive that you can post on the web, it doesn't really have to be.
Be a game and it depends on what kind of program you're talking about.
If you're talking about, you know, just Unity scripting or something,
then I have no idea, right?
That's not the kind of programming I do.
It's not the kind of programming that I have an experience with
whatever, but if you're talking about game engine programming, then
you know, you don't have to make a game.
You just have to do something that you can post online, that
demonstrates that you have a core technical skills.
Like the kinds of things we do on handmade hero, just showing that you
can do that.
So for example, you could do
Were you like, you know, take something like, you know, Implement your
own software rasterizer or interactive Ray Tracer or something like
this.
You know, take a small project and just do a good job on it and so
that you can point to it.
And say here is what I did.
Right?
And you know that is pretty valuable, right?
It shows people that you can do something and and and that you can do
something relatively complicated.
Now, the question is, can you do that right?
Because
Maybe you're not at a point yet where you can do that and that's okay,
right?
Like not, you know, a couple of years in the program depending how
long you been doing it?
You're not going to just be like mr.
Knows how to do everything or whatever.
And so at that point, you kind of have this situation where yet, if
you're not a good enough programmer yet to really stand out, do take
whatever job you can get.
If there's, you know anything you can learn from it, right?
You know, if you can go work at a company.
And there's probably a good programmer there, or at least a
programmer, who's going to be at least better than you and that's when
you could learn from and then you can get good enough to start
standing out a little bit more and getting a job somewhere where maybe
you want to get a job more.
So so yeah you do need to kind of assess like where you are and how
realistic it is that you're going to be someone good enough to want to
like stand out in a pack and get a particular job or whether you're
someone who's like you're not there yet and there's nothing wrong with
That right?
I certainly can say, from experience that I've made really pretty
dramatic increases, in ability, in various aspects of programming
based on having worked with other people and sort of having that
experience of seeing how other people program and stuff like that.
It's one of the reasons I'm doing handmade hero.
So people just have a you know if they don't have the ability to go
work at a game company right now, they can watch How I program and you
just get a programmer, right?
And similarly the same.
For a lot of other people who are streaming their right?
Look, you can go watch John Barrett stream and you can watch John Blow
stream and you know, that's a great place to kind of do that right.
Watch how they code and learn from that that's that's really good and
if you can get a job doing that every day somewhere, I mean, yeah,
you're probably not going to be fortunate enough to land a job or your
program with someone as good as John rochon.
But you know, you can still work with a more experienced programmer
and maybe learn some things.
Hopefully, in the process now.
If you can't write, like, maybe the only job options, you have are
places where the programmers are just awful, right?
It's like you can only get a job at a place that's like it's staffed
entirely by Darkness trip and Scott Myers or something, right?
Like those are the only two programmers there.
So the only thing you're going to learn is how to type a bunch of
texts that doesn't do anything into a computer and have it run slowly,
right?
That's the only thing you're ever gonna learn.
But hey there's a lot of constant, it everywhere, so that's good.
Then yeah, I don't know what to do.
I really don't write.
If you don't have the opportunity of going to work with anyone who you
can learn from, then maybe it is best to just try to go like hey okay.
Try to watch streams online, if people who are good programmers, like
the aforementioned try to get to the point where you can do something,
where you might be able to get the attention of somebody who is, you
know, any any company that might have some people out at that you
could learn from and then just keep trying to get a job at one of
those and I guess I don't know that there's really anything else you
can really do at that point.
You know, it's tough.
It's definitely a
Tough industry to break into.
So you know the the more you can do to stand out in at the better
certainly and that is one of the reasons why I would say try to be
diligent if you can and make something interesting.
It doesn't have to be big.
It just has to show that you get this stuff right?
You know it's not uncommon to get people who are like
Interviewing for entry-level jobs who don't know like what the values
in a matrix mean, like they couldn't, you know, maybe couldn't even
tell me what, like, what's the First Column of a transfer Matrix like
explain it?
You know what I mean?
What does it mean?
What's the first row of a transfer matrix mean, you know, stuff like
that?
It's not uncommon to get people who come out of college and don't know
these things.
So on the one hand, it's also kind of nice in the sense that there's
just not a lot of good.
People out there at the end of the day, a lot of people are just
really bad at programming, a lot of programmers, most programmers, are
bad, and most people don't know a lot about a lot of the things you
might want to know for game programming.
So one of the nice things is it's not the bars, not actually that
high.
The problem is, there is a bar, right?
Because there's plenty of chat, there's plenty of people who just
like, I know how to program Java from college and I'm applying and so,
if you're just one of those people, you don't have anything Civics and
out, it is difficult, but it's kind of a crapshoot at that point.
And, you know, I do you do, but like I said, I think the good news is,
you know, you you don't have to make some amazing huge thing to
impress.
Somebody you just have to pick something and show that you can focus
on it that you're curious.
About it.
You took it apart.
You understood it, and you did something cool there.
You know, that's enough, right?
and,
You know, I mean like I'll give you a simple example and don't, you
know, take this for too much I guess because like I said, I'm not
involved in entry-level hiring.
So my opinion is not that meaningful here.
It would be better if there was, you know, someone from Electronic
Arts or somebody something, who had more experience with that, who
could say, you know, here's how we hire.
But
How do I get think?
I retweeted it.
Okay, so I'm just going to use this as an example, just a simple
example.
So here is a tweet that somebody tweeted at me.
They said moving towards an interactive path.
Tracer I find I'm using handmade Heroes 2D rendering code time and
time again and they just have a screenshot.
Here's the code, some code on the screen and they did a nice little
sphere raytracer.
I can see that they've got, you know, glossy Reflections.
They've got, you know, depth of field looks like.
So they even have the some kind of rudimentary lens
Old perhaps happening there, you know, like right and so on and then
they've got, you know, some code, I can see other got to do here for
linear Colour space, so they're thinking about the colors.
We see right?
That alone tells me a bunch about this person, right?
I can look at some of their code right now.
I can see that they've got something running.
I can see that they kind of understand so many things, I'm like this
person would already be more on my radar as an
Entry-level hiring manager, then some random resume that came across
right.
It's like, so that's, you know,
You should have something like that.
Probably, it certainly can't hurt and you know,
Think about it doing a programming stream.
Might also be a good idea, like when you're good enough to start
programming streaming, maybe, you know, have a stream or two, I can
look at and say, you know, is this person?
Let me see how they, how their code looks and how they go about their
coding process, you know, maybe that gives them until I don't know.
But just, you know, throwing that out there.
It's like if you can show that you do stuff and that it's stuff,
that's non-trivial.
That's really good.
And that helps
Kind of put you a little bit more on the radar of people who are going
to be doing hiring than, you know, somebody who just sends in a piece
of paper that says, I'm looking for a job.
And their sponsors.
Thank you for the in depth explanation.
I have one more question since you're going on a break.
Can you trash out hoop just a bit so we don't get confused in the
time.
You're not there and stick to beloved compression or any programming.
No, I think I've already trashed Loop enough.
I mean everybody knows that I hate it and, you know, either they think
it's good or think it's bad.
And at the end of the day, I I don't care how other people program as
long as I don't have to work with them right.
You know as long as I don't have to work with a person who goes up
nuts.
I don't care, right?
They can go up up.
Their stuff.
Unfortunately, it does mean sometimes.
Like, I have to use software written by oop stuff that's just awful.
But, you know,
Poop alone doesn't make software bad.
You know it's you can make really bad software any you know just
No matter what methodologies you follow, you can make lousy software,
right?
It's there's so many decisions that are more than just what your
fundamental methodology is its but one ingredient in making good piece
of software to have a good methodology.
So it's not like it's oh you just avoid upin you make it soft like
know.
So you know, there's that.
But anyway I'm going to go ahead and wrap it up here because it is
time.
It is over time to wrap it up, obviously.
So
I'm gonna call it.
I'm going to call it for a while, actually.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you wanted following series at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here.
A.org comes the source code so you can play around with it yourself.
We also have Forum site.
If you want to ask questions, you can go there.
We got a patreon page.
You want to support the video series, a schedule bot the tweets, the
schedule you.
If you would like to know when, we're going to be live and an episode
guide, that you can use to catch up on past episodes,
Assad's.
I am going to be away for.
Little while.
So it's going to be a few weeks before I return to handmade hero.
I hope that you will find some good programming to occupy you in the
meantime.
I am sure that some of the usual suspects will be doing streams,
probably, both, Sean's.
I'm guessing.
I'm assuming Sean Barrett and Sean McGrath will both be streaming.
I don't know.
Who else would be streaming?
Maybe John Blow do another language stream but I'm sure they'll be
some streams to keep you busy.
In the meantime, there's
Always the past episodes.
If there's some that you've missed, you can go do that or pick a
little bit of programming to do on your own.
That is always the best way to practice.
Anyway, maybe you can go implement, the floating-point, print out for
our print F-14 or do anything else.
You might like to do in advance of us actually doing it on handmade
hero, you know, The To Do List as well as I do.
You could go pick something and beat me to it.
Well, I'm on break.
So that's about it.
I'll be back here in a few weeks.
Keep an eye on the Tweet bot.
If you want to know, when we are going to be back, I will tweet a few
times when the series is returning.
So you won't miss it until then everyone have a good time programming
the next few weeks and I will see you on the internet's.
Yeah, you can always tweet it me on Twitter or anything else.
In the meantime.
So, that's it.
Have a good break, everyone.
And I'll see you when I return.