Start recording.
Alright, hello everyone.
And thank you for joining me for another episode of handmade hero the
show where we code complete game live from scratch on Twitch.
No engine.
No library is just us.
And right now, we're in the process of sort of working through our to
do list.
We made it to do list on Friday, where we kind of said, like, wait a
minute.
We're kind of gotten relatively far here on stuff that we want to spec
out.
We're trying to basically build out our entire engine superstructure.
If
Well, so that everything kind of fits together nicely and we still
have a lot of work to do on any individual piece of it.
There's a, there's a bunch of stuff that we haven't done in terms of
the actual components but we're just trying to make sure.
We know how everything fits together and so on Friday, we made a to-do
list that was basically like let's think about all the things that we
would need to do before we're done.
And so now at least we're in a position where you can just kind of go
take a quick look when we when we come to a stopping point on any
particular thing that we're working on, we can go take a peek at that
and go.
What are the things that we still have to do?
Let's pick a good one to do next.
And go do it and so that'll be pretty handy allowing us to not.
Forget basically to do something often times what I will do.
When I'm programming, not on the stream, just my regular day,
programming is actually keep a notebook next to me.
And I've actually heard multiple people do this and it wasn't like we
got together and talked about it and all decided to do it.
I've actually heard multiple people do exactly the same thing.
Independently completely never having talked to them or them having
talk to each other and it just turned out to be a
People do.
On the notebook we write out the things that we still want to remember
to do as a list on the notebook next to us when were programming and
then every so often when the page gets full we go to a new page and we
copy the list down again filtering it with by removing stuff that we
no longer want to do or the isn't applicable that we finished or
whatever.
And for some reason this because this is very popular.
I don't know why it's much more popular than using like
Actual like to do manager or something.
There's something about the act of writing it and copying it.
That is somehow important.
That nobody knows why, but that's what happens.
So we have the next best thing.
We have an actual to-do list that I can display on the screen since we
need that since you would be able to see my notebook.
If it's sitting here,
that's what we're going to do today is we're going to go start
tackling that before I start.
This is day 71 so if you are trying to follow along at home what you
want and you've pre-order the game on handmade here to org what you
want to do is download Day 70 source code.
Well you download all the source code together but you want to unpack
Day 70 source code and that's what we're starting with today if you
want to follow along.
So, let's go ahead and open up that to-do list because we basically
put a bunch of stuff there and there's also a
Briefing.
Maybe I'll do this right at the start here before we do that.
There was a to do like a bug that someone noticed on the forums that I
want to mark down.
The actual code where it actually happened.
So in our familiar, guess that's over here.
So we have not yet moved our enemy code out.
So we're still actually doing our entity updates in here.
I said, I want to move them to ham identity dot see if you we haven't
quite done that yet.
Anyway, one of the things that we did not do, is we kind of we're
playing around with, with doing this before
Somebody had said, what if we made familiar as follow other familiars,
and we had kind of hacked that together, and one of the things we did
was change the test distance squared to basically, wait Heroes as if
they were closer than familiar is just to try and make it so that
familiars would follow Heroes when Heroes were close by in doing so,
we never actually went and updated the code to still store, whatever
the actual distance was and so as a result this code is under shoot,
it's moving things closer than they should be because of this.
Location by 0.75 that we kind of had act in there at the time.
So what I'd like to do is since we remove that sort of play code that
we were doing, I'd like to remove this and make it back the way that
it used to be.
And so that way, now there that won't be in there.
So it's just a little cleanup.
We had sort of introduce them code when we were playing around at the
end of a stream and we didn't quite restore it to proper working order
when we had stopped.
And so, now, the familiar at least should be presumably at the the
distance that we thought it should be, which is not
We a big change, but but, you know, it's better to have it that way in
case we end up using some of that code in the final stuff, we don't
want to then have to figure out why we have a bug anyway.
So, let's go ahead and grab our handmade dot h here, where we have our
to-do list, and you can kind of see that we have it broken down here,
and I was kind of saying that like, well, we're we've only got five
more days of programming.
Excuse me, it's getting on allergy season here in Seattle.
So I may still be sniffly for a while even though I'm not really sick
anymore.
All right.
So we sort of said so we only have five days before we go on break.
People were asking for a break so I can catch up before we go on break
for a week.
Let's focus on things that we have that have been sort of accruing
that we'd like to just kind of finish up instead of getting into
something new, like some of these new things that we were
brainstorming on Friday that need to get done before we actually start
production work on the game.
And so what I was thinking there was, you know,
Maybe let's say the Collision detection for now, let's do something.
Since it's Monday, start something a little bit more straightforward.
Let's clean up our use of Z A little bit.
Let's just take a quick look at that, go through the code, once clean
up, the places where we weren't using Vector threes, where we could
have been, and maybe just kind of like, get that a little bit more
tightened up so that we don't constantly have different things in
there for Z versus
Nazi.
And so I think the place that I want to start with this was we had
this notion of a world difference and really a world difference.
Doesn't need to exist at all, because all it was is just a vector3
where we have the distance in all three.
But when we originally wrote it, we didn't have a vector3.
So we were still, well, we didn't have any vectors at all and then we
had only a vector to so it move it to this.
So I'm just going to go ahead and get rid of that class entirely and
then I'm just going to go fix, all the places that were actually using
it.
To just use Vector threes directly from now on.
Right?
And so that's kind of handy because now what we can do is we can
actually just sort of unify a lot of this code I think to make it so
that we don't have to worry about that anymore.
So this still gets out the tile difference.
The the D, the the detail XY there and what we can do is we can roll
this.
This computation in there as well because basically that's all the
same like so,
And then when we do our chunk side M we don't really know yet, how big
our Z chunks are going to be.
So maybe I spoke a little too soon.
There may be, I don't quite want to do that because I'm not sure what
we want to do with that.
Maybe that's the first thing I kind of have to think through a little
bit more carefully.
Basically our chunks are probably not going to be symmetric in Z.
So when we multiply this, we probably do want to actually say, okay,
you know, let's go ahead and make sure that
That our, our, our code handles that that asymmetry.
So I'm going to go into the place where we store in our trunk side in
meters and also do our a chunk height in meters.
Basically, if you will or maybe we want to call it depth in meters,
maybe a little bit better.
I'm not sure what we want to call it.
Exactly.
It's kind of ambiguous because usually think of width and height but
then you think of height in the world as being high.
So I don't actually know.
You know what the, what the
Best way to think of that is, but we can think of it that way.
The other thing I could do here is actually change about chunk side
and M to be something that was actually just a vector.
In fact, maybe that's a fun thing to do.
We could do like something like, you know, III chunk dim in M,
something like that, right?
And then it's basically has the dimension.
Each X, Y and Z, and then we can make them be whatever we want, right?
And that would be interesting here, because then I can unify these
right then.
Can pull these in like this.
And then what I do here is, I just bust out what I was talking about,
before you remember, I talked about the hadamard product, right?
I don't know if we ever actually end up implemented, the hadamard
product we're going to want to because it's useful, especially for
working with colors.
So I'm going to do that, go ahead and do that.
Hadamard product.
And I can say that we have the chunk demand meters and I multiply that
by that D Tau X Y Z now.
So, this is a full one now, right?
And then what I can do is I can add essentially
My this will be good.
This is going to get us a lot of little tricks in there and this is
just our result can just be right here.
I'll show you the other trick that I was going to hurt.
Not trick but like thing I want to add to our to our math Library.
So they had my product here.
So basically this this tells us what our chunk difference was now, and
we get to do that sort of all at once, so that we can, we can kind of
do it without having to split it up into multiple access anymore.
And then we have an offset here and that offset really should be
three-dimensional as well.
And so, I think, what we want to do is sort of move to making that
just be a three-dimensional offset.
So, we'll let that compiler out for now and we'll go ahead and move
that to it.
Mention offset soon as well.
And then we can get rid of this because this actually, this works.
Now that hadamard product.
I don't know if.
If you guys remember I talked about it a bit.
I don't think we implemented one we didn't.
And so we implemented our DOT product, I believe right here.
There it is.
We planted our DOT product or the inner product and so I'm just going
to go ahead and also Implement while we're at it the hadamard product
for both V2, S and B 3.
So that's basically just
Taking in these guys here and I had a mod product.
Although, the name is fancy, it's just component wise multiplication.
So basically multiply the X by the X and you stick it in X, you
multiply the Y by the why you stick it, and why in many ways, it's
exactly the same as the inner product.
Except for the fact you don't some the terms.
So you notice here we do x times X and Y times Y, and we sum the terms
for the hadamard product.
We leave the terms separate as they were right?
And so that result is basically exactly the same as here, but instead
we just actually
We keep the two terms separate and put them into their respective
positions.
I don't know why that type 2 plus, they're lazy shift key, right?
So that is all that's happening with the hadamard product.
And similarly, we can do it for the V3.
I don't know.
Did we ever do our inner product or anything for the V3?
We haven't really done anything for our V3.
Have our V3 is basically just sitting there like we implemented.
Literally like nothing for our v3s.
I don't even know what we were using it for.
That's kind of crazy.
We
Absolutely nothing.
Which is kind of bizarre.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, so I'm going to go ahead and do this now.
A lot of people don't like to do this and that's totally fine.
I'm not going to yell at anyone for this sort of thing.
Basically, like what I do almost invariably is I do not go get
template happy here and start making template because I find it's just
more trouble than it's worth.
We're Sarah Mayer such as well as compile time where it's everything
and it
So easy really to just go through and change it once.
Yes, you may need to make some stupid mistakes.
Yes, there, maybe there's a little extra typing involved.
Oops, I want to go ahead and do a replace just in this region I don't
deny that and so if you do want to go to template template
I'm totally, you know, totally fine with that but I just have found
that typically because it's so rare that you do stuff here.
Typically you make this math file once and then you're done with it
forever, you know, you'll debug it once and then that's it.
I just find the introducing that kind of nastiness you just doesn't
pay off.
It does it isn't worth the hassle because you'll be left with those
nasty additional compile times an additional
Error, message, ugliness and all these extra things you'll be left
with after you've debugged it.
And whereas in this case, once you do that to bugging, once you're in
kind of nice, beautiful land.
That doesn't have any more problems.
So anyway, I'm just going to go through here really quickly and build
out our Vector threes as well.
And again, this is just literally doing what your template would have
done.
So if you do want to do this with a template, knock yourself out, all
you're going to have to do is basically, you know, if you don't know
how to program templates, then you probably don't want.
But assuming you do know how to program templates, this should be, you
know, trivial thing to template on your, just going to template on the
number of dimensions and you would have to stop using the dot x dot.
Why you'd have to stop using that and start using the E syntax that we
had, because you're only going to know numbers and you'd have to put
four Loops in here as well and all that garbage.
You have to do all that but you know, if you want templates you've got
to do it, right?
So so that's what you would do here, okay?
And so like I said, there might be some copy and paste as I might be
some nastiness there.
They're what, what is?
I don't need that?
I don't know.
Why was square square kind of got stuck in there that was not
appropriate.
Square should really be up here.
Kind of in a section where we have our our you know scalar operator is
kind of kind of breaking this up roughly into like scalar operators,
right?
For operations, I should say.
And these are the two operations.
All right, that we did there and then here's our B 3 operations.
Right.
And so then again multiplication Operator by a scalar again is just a
scalar times, the 3 components, set it back into, you know, piecewise.
And then again this is just an operator that that's used for the other
syntax.
Then there's the x equals, which again, same thing.
Just just end up there all going to call this thing.
You Nora, - right just flipping each of the things X y&z.
That's how vectors work.
You do it to each component, plus same thing.
Do it to each component, right?
So, we just added the Z plus equals just calling that guy.
Up again, subtraction basically doing the same thing as the addition
was and then we get to our hadamard product or had a more product news
into doozy.
Now our inner product needs to do Zine again, just adds another term
on to the end and then our length squared and our length are
essentially the same calls because they just leverage the fact that
operator, I'm sorry a function or call overloading.
We'll just call the right thing here and so that's all I wanted to do
there.
So then we get our hadamard product.
Which means we can multiply out this by the scale of our chunkin, all
Dimensions.
So we're just taking the chunk dissed.
The chunk distance between those two positions and multiplying It Out
by however, much that would be.
So we get our meters back.
These are now going to be the threes, right?
So this is going to be I'll be 3 now, like so.
I feel like this to do is, is less useful than it was any more tests
to be able to figure out where they are or other, which wrong so well
I guess not.
So it still remains to be seen
I wonder this maybe something.
We can actually get rid of now, which is kind of humorous.
Gosh.
I hate to break up the flow here, but I just want to point it out.
I think we may have architected ourselves into a position where we
could actually do the thing that we said we might want to do in a to
do.
If we could figure out how to do it, The Puzzler may have unpleasant
itself.
And the reason I say that is because now we no longer operate on
entities, without bringing them into the same region.
And in order to have brought them into the same region, we iterated
over the
Now, chunks, which means we don't need to know what tile chunk and
entities in anymore.
Using its World position, right?
So we would no longer have to store that we might still use it, to
figure out.
We still need a chunk XYZ thing.
That's basically, just lets us know which World Chunk.
We would put this guy in.
So we still need to compute, x, y and Z's, but we wouldn't need to
store them anymore.
So, I think The Puzzler, the answer to this Puzzler may actually be
the same
Region solved the puzzle.
So I'm going to go ahead and just say that, maybe we're going to stick
that.
Solve The Puzzler from World position because we may have accidentally
by doing a bunch of other architecture.
Work that needed to get done.
We may have backed into a solution to this problem that was puzzling
us before, which is pretty awesome.
That would be pretty awesome.
Okay, so there's our rope system is going to generate more compiler
errors and work through them here.
So now when we do is canonical our world side in chunk side in meters,
we need to now know, basically, which dimension this actually was when
we do is canonical.
So you can see when someone calls this canonical, they're basically
going to have to know which which one that was now that's the only
place I believe on those couple.
There's two other places that call it, okay?
So basically
What's going to happen here is the is canonical needs to know what the
chunk side in meters.
Actually is we could do that in two ways but since world is only
really used to access it.
I'm thinking maybe what we do is we just pass that.
So we do chunk side in meters or redo chunk dim like that and we
replace this with with chunk Tim like so,
And then when those guys used to pass the world instead of what
they're doing is now they're passing chunk demand M.
This thing right here right there, passing chunk demand meters and
they're going to pass the X for the X and they're going to pass the
wife or the Y.
Right.
And so you know pretty simple code modification there.
Yeah, works that out in that.
And so now for canonical I suppose what we should also do is start
adding the Z in there because now we're going to want to start
validating our Z's.
Well, jumped him and M like so we'll so we'll go ahead and do that.
Choose me.
And then, we're just going to keep on going, right?
We're just going to keep on pushing through that that'll do actually.
That does it right there.
We don't actually have to do anymore there.
Some skill at the compile errors guide is here not a member of V to
you are right sir?
That's because now we're taking v3s.
All right.
And so when we initialize the world we need to actually go ahead and
set that up.
We need to set up that chunk side and M to basically be something
reasonable.
Now, I don't think we want
I don't think we want to use this value for Z because I think Z is
going to want to be smaller than that.
I feel like RZ slices are only going to be like kind of one tile deep.
So, you know, if our tiles are square, then I would say that our kind
of our chunk side for Z is actually just just going to be that tile
side, right?
So it's just, it's just going to be one tile high.
And when they Stack Up,
Because we're not storing 16 by 16.
Like we were, I feel like that's probably how we want to slice it.
Again, we don't have tiles anymore per se.
So this is really a meaningless measure.
We could just stick a number of meters in here.
The tiles per chunk is not useful.
It's not a meat, it's not really a useful metric.
It's mostly just something.
We're kind of still using to guide our construction, but we could
totally pull that out eventually and it won't matter but either way, I
think that's roughly what we want to do there.
Now, let me just take a quick look.
I want to make sure that we're not missing something here.
This stuff get World chunk.
Doesn't really care about those offsets, but I just want to make sure
these guys aren't doing anything weird.
It looks like they're all pretty good with the way that they're
working.
So
I think that's fine.
I think that's that's probably just fine.
So what we now would move on to is that we canonicalize stuff.
I did I do here chunk side and M is not a member of world.
It's chunked in meters.
It's try that again.
Yeah.
So let's do that and tile side and M I guess is also something we
probably want to get rid of eventually but you know it's kind of their
it's a Vestige will remain is not harming us so we'll leave it for
now.
All right, so when we actually do our, okay?
So this is actually pretty interesting as well.
I'll just kind of show you another thing that I usually often do here
and it's Now's the Time to do it for sure.
So what you can see here is when I have this offset that I'm
producing, we could be doing this entirely in bulk if we wanted to, I
guess.
Now, you know what never mind.
I won't bother doing that.
I was going to show something else, but it's just, it would just get
us off topic, really doesn't matter.
But point, being our world chunk side and M.
Now, what we actually, again, want to do is, we would now want to pass
that that chunk Tim along the axis that we're talking about.
And so, we're just going to just going to pull out just that chunk,
Tim that we're doing, and that kind of lines up nicely with how we
modified is canonical.
So that the data just flows right through exactly as it should and
that's a good thing and so that will do the re canonicalize for us.
But now everywhere that calls that re canonicalize is going to have to
use all three.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
And now we're going to have to pass that proper that proper chunked
in, in meters for each of our Dimensions.
Like, so there's our why, there's our Z, right?
And so, there we go.
Now, this is now, mapping into chunks face is going to want to take a
three dimensional offset now, because again, we're sending everything,
the three dimensions.
So, we want to allow people to pass in offsets and Z that will get
reconnect lies back correctly because that's how the same region is
going to map those things back together.
They're so we want to make sure that's correct.
Let me go back there.
We kind of got out of that quickly because I guess there were no more
Powers but I want to make sure yes you can kind of see I don't know
what's going on here.
So we're taking a chunk position from tile position.
That's basically a thing that's supposed to produce these for us.
This was.
Yeah, so we want to do here is we want to kind of be able to produce a
V3 out of this because we don't have yeah, we want to be able to
produce a world position.
Out of that.
So really what we want to do here is we would want to set that result.
So I'm just going to do this are we don't really need to do this, I'm
going to show it.
So I think what we should say is basically the plane where the actual
like people are standing on is generally going to be Z equals zero for
a given.
Like that's the basis point, right?
So I think that's better than having it be the - bottom of, you know,
- half tile side and M.
And the reason I think that is because we don't
Want to have you oscillate?
Very close to the bottom of the thing.
We'd rather you have you be sort of well within the Z bounds of a tile
when you're standing on the ground, right?
So I'm going to leave.
Oops, I'm going to leave that at zero for this.
although,
I guess we still want to do this in case we set tile side and M, to be
something.
You know, I'm saying to you.
Hmm.
Hmm, hmm.
I say
So, you know, technically like I saying that, you know, setting it to
0, we know that that would work because we know what the tile side,
what, what are our tiles per chunk?
Is?
We know, our tiles for chunk, is always going to be one, right?
So we essentially know what this works out to be, but in case we
decide to change that later, it does seem like
Would kind of want to change that?
Yeah, like we kind of want to change that.
Now, here's a question for you and I guess I don't know why we weren't
doing it this way to get in with I wonder why we're not just using map
into chunks Pace with a mapping Center of 02 always produce this.
It seems kind of weird, right?
So, I'm not really sure why we're doing it this way.
So, I'm wondering if maybe we shouldn't Force everything to go through
here anyway, am I totally off base there?
I guess, because when things get larger, maybe that wouldn't be a good
idea, potentially.
You'd rather do the Divide first.
But is that really a concern?
I don't know, because we're doing the math here, either way.
So it kind of seems to me.
It kind of seems to me like for now.
Anyway you would want to just go ahead and do that directly, so I
think I'm just going to go ahead and do that, right?
I mean that seems logical enough right?
You would just say okay we've got the tile side and M I'm just going
to go ahead and take these and multiply them out, right?
So I'm just going to go ahead and say that basically got a V3 which is
my offset, right?
And the offsets going to be, you know, whatever that that AB style X
is X.
The it's really just going to be, you know what?
It's just going to be this.
It's going to be that hadamard product, right of the chunk demand m.
Let's talk to me, m.
It's going to be that hadamard product of the chunk demand m.
Times, whatever, the the ab style X AB style.
Why and abs tiles e are right.
And that seems that seems pretty pretty easy.
To to, you know, come by here, we met, we're gonna probably wanna do
something different when we do world-building, anyway, and that's the
only thing this was used for, so kind of feels to me.
Like that's a little bit better for now, and, and we can that way we
can worry about alignment and all that other stuff in a totally
separate pass.
So I don't I think this just seems like we should just get that's all
just goodbye.
Like why is that even there?
It's just no good.
And so what I'd say is, we'll set our base posed to be all zeros,
right?
And then we will go ahead and say whatever our world position result
is is just going to be map into chunks, Pace will pass, the world will
pass that base position and then we'll pass the offset that we just
computed and they said we'll just leverage this routine that way we
know that it's over.
Everything's going through this routine.
Now eventually that may be problematic
I like because of precision when we get way out there.
But like I said, I think we're going to switch to a different thing
for building world's anyway, we haven't done World building yet, so
when we do World, building, will probably have a smartest game anyway.
Probably something more like some regions that like we move around to
do stuff.
Okay, so that seems fine to me.
Our subtraction looks like it's pretty much already worked out so
that's all good.
Yeah, that's going to give us a few three results after we do that
detail.
Where did that stuff centered?
Chunk point you even call that anymore and don't even know if we call
that anymore.
But hey, it's looks fine.
So we'll leave it.
Change in C position location raw.
That doesn't really use the offset anywhere.
So I'm pretty sure that's probably fine and then changing the location
regular?
Yeah, I think those are probably mostly fine.
So let's go ahead and put the code that uses it.
Now, this is just going to be a V3 like, so getting our Sim Space P.
I don't know why our Sim Space P was a V2.
I guess we just kind of carried that through for now.
I guess I'll go ahead and
And well, you know what?
So be a good time to do this to one thing that I like to do.
Just go nuts with the anonymous unions which I love Anonymous unions.
They're the best.
So we basically have a struct that has an x y and it, right?
And now we have a V3.
And so what I'd like to do with this V3 is I'd like to be able to just
say I want the XY coordinates out of it, right?
That's what I'd like to be able to do there.
I'd like to upgrade this routine to use the 3s, but I want to do that
in a second pass.
So I don't change too many things at once.
So what I can do, right, is I can make another struct here, right?
That actually has just that the X Y in it.
Right, something that looks, you know, something that looked like
this, I guess.
anything if I have a an XY like so on, and
You know, just a pad on here, something like this.
Right.
I may know it's a little weird, but you could imagine something like
this.
Where, this way I can grab the XY by just typing X Y.
I'm not sure if that makes sense.
I know it's a little confusing but hopefully that you can kind of see
if I just stack enough of these things up on here.
I can actually grab out the XY by just typing x y, and it's in the
same place as the X and the Y, which makes it work, right?
So, yeah, I don't know.
Can do something like that.
You can also do something like this if you were so inclined, something
that looks like that if you want to be able to go out the y z.
So I don't know.
It's just kind of interesting thing.
I don't know if that makes any sense, but it just kind of fun.
And then you can see that code compiled properly where I did that XY.
It's just kind of a fun little trick.
So I kind of like to do that and and works on all the compilers I use.
So I'm pretty happy with it.
Okay, so my map into chunks face.
Now one problem with my map and a trunk space is we are now going to
have to start thinking about Z in terms of when we do that, Min Corner
Max Corner stuff.
Now, right now.
We don't really have a concept of a three-dimensional rectangle.
I don't know if we need one or not but does kind of seem to some
degree like really we don't I don't know how much we really want
rectangle.
2's at all, it may be that we mostly just want rectangle threes.
But again I'm not gonna I'm Not Really Gonna fuss with that too much
just yet.
I'm going to go ahead and make v3's out of these guys.
And so one thing that you can kind of do
We can go ahead and in our handmade math where we have these V3
Constructors, we can also make them and they're not, I don't mean see
what's left of our sites mean thing, that make something that makes
something else.
Obviously, these are not actual Constructors, so we can pass a, an
ex-wife, or the first ones, and do it like this.
Oops.
So that we can sort of easily easily construct, a vector, 3 by
extension, which is kind of nice, right?
So there you go.
We'll just extend those guys out.
Out for now.
And same thing in here.
Our entity class that we have here.
And again, I use the words class and Constructor here.
Obviously, we don't have a classic instructor but you and I'm talking
about.
I don't really mean implementation.
I mean, conceptually something to think about it is typically called
The Entity class.
And so, you know, imagine I had typed that if you're someone who likes
classes, the actual classes better.
So anyway in our same entity, we
Have.
Jimmy.
A p which is only two dimensional and then we restoring our disease
here.
And so what I'd like to do is just go ahead and update our all of our
stuff to just go in three dimensions.
Right.
Which actually shouldn't be too hard.
Even that sounds like a pretty big change.
It shouldn't be too.
Big of a deal.
I don't know that the chunk Z.
I'm not even sure why that chunk Z is still there to be honest with
you.
I'm not sure what we're doing with it, we're sort of using the
Trunk Z for some reason, we're just directly setting it which isn't
doesn't super make a whole lot of sense and we're not using the one
out of here anyway.
So I'm just going to I'm just going to delete that because I don't
actually know why that's there or what's going on with that.
Alright.
So we have our invalid PR invalid P needs to get boosted up a little
bit as well.
Like so into a V3.
Oops that and then we're going to have to actually take Vector 3.
He's when we, when we set things, again, just pushing the compiler
errors forward to like bring me through the code in a front that will
allow me to change the things that need to get changed, right?
That makes sense.
So we're all good, the result here.
Now again, we can now make this change that we didn't make before.
Now, our results is just that it just the direct result of the
subtraction.
This Sim space p is the same thing.
In the words calling, there is not going to return us a video.
Three.
So off we go with that and our ad entity is going to have to be
upgraded to take one as well.
So that is taking a V3 now.
Like so let's take a look in here again.
Same thing, just change that up.
And most of these are just passing through.
So I don't suspect, there'd be a whole lot there.
So we do our is in rectangle check?
Yeah.
I mean I'm kind of thinking that we pretty much always want.
That isn't a
Let's check to go ahead and be on a rectangle, three.
So I'm sort of thinking to this, let's just go ahead and do that now
right, let's just go ahead and do that so that we don't have to deal
with it later.
We'll just say that we're going to actually have rectangle 3 as well.
And I don't even know if we really need rectangle 20s anymore, but you
know, what do you do?
So let's see where our rectangle to use, they should have been in here
somewhere.
There they are.
So those guys going to be rectangle, threes, and then I'll just go
into our math again and build those out.
So here is our rectangle to OKC, rectangle to and I'm going to go
ahead and move the sky up as well, because we kind of have our our
definitions up at the top here.
All right, Andrea.
All that is exact same code just with the v3s, right?
And so it's exactly the same stuff here.
And again,
All the same things I said before, applies, if you'd like to use
templates here, be my guest.
I don't tend to prefer that approach but obviously you know, it all
depends on what your experience is and what your priorities are in
terms of what you're doing, whether that will work out better for you.
So be advised, it wouldn't be hard to template eyes and I think it
should be pretty obvious.
Why basically, the code is, is pretty straightforward, right?
So, anyway, you know this, I wonder why this isn't just taking also
A vector here, right?
Seems like this would just be that.
And then, you know, then you're just doing this, which seems a lot
smarter not sure.
Why in type that in first time, you know, like, I can't think of a
reason not to, but you do add radius to, I kind of feel like you would
just do that, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and say, that's what we'll do.
That just seems seems a little smarter so we'll just go ahead and
we'll we'll do our safety margin, their safety margin in Z is tough to
figure out exactly what that would be so I don't know.
I'm going to say update, safety margin.
Z cuz I don't know.
That's, that's going to be the same at the end of the day.
But we'll see.
Alright, so off we go again.
Just dupes just trying to
Correct, some of these things here.
So let's see.
No operator found which takes right in my V3.
Okay, so basically we are now taking in which a three-dimensional
acceleration.
Hopefully, let's push that through.
And so all of these guys have to be three-dimensional as well.
And that also means that.
Now what we were doing before with gravity, if we want, always to have
gravity, then really all
Have to do is just add into our acceleration.
The fact that we always have gravity.
So basically that negative 9.8 is going to just add in to whatever the
acceleration was that we actually give our entity and then that, you
know, will we no longer have to do this computation separately because
you can see it.
It's happening right here automatically for us, right?
So it's just, it's totally, it's totally set.
So what we
Do want to do however, is we sort of had this cheesiness here where we
were sort of doing the ground collision with with z, and we're going
to leave that in for now.
But eventually, what we probably want to do is start getting a little
more hardcore about Z.
That's what this passage is about.
So,
Ashley will do something smarter here with z and actually see like
what maybe we should land on or something like that.
Just get a little bit fancier there.
And again, we don't need to update the velocity because now our
velocity is properly tracked along with everything else.
Now, I don't remember.
Did we already get rid of DZ?
I think we did, right?
Yeah.
So we got rid of d z, so that's all now nice and kosher.
So we just get rid of that.
And then after we do our Collision detection, right?
We also want to do the sort of cheesy ground Ridiculousness like so,
so that's after we've accepted the update.
Step we would basically say our whatever our position is.
We don't want to let it go below zero.
But again, that's something that we gotta.
I supposed to do in there to do, this has to become real tight
handling.
Ground Collision Etc.
Yeah, and we'll see what happens with that.
All right, so let's see.
Got our desired position here.
That's going to have to go up to a V3 as well.
Our well normal will have to be a V3 as well.
Basically, everything in our Collision routine is going to have to be
upgraded to a V3.
So we might as well go ahead and do that.
Now, we were doing diameter of the enemy because it has a width and a
height.
We don't actually know of it, actually having a depth yet.
Which makes things a little complicated.
Unfortunately, but we can sort of start to imagine what that would be
right.
Our diameter depth is just going to probably be you know for now like
a tile height it's worth or something, right?
So would be something like what we were talking about in here before
handmade world's out of H?
You know the something like in here maybe we have a tile depth in
meters, or something like this.
I don't know what we want to call that, but maybe we'll just go ahead
and say,
That we've got that and then that way because we don't really know
what it is yet that way at least we'll see where it's being used.
And so that way in the tile Dim, when we set that tile dim in meters,
we can also set this tile depth in meters.
And since we know that these are all essentially, all the same, we're
just going to leave it like that.
So,
We can sort of think about that a little bit more later.
So when we do our diameter D, now we know that our Min and Max Corners
are going to expand by that as well now.
So we've got that diameter D.
And really, I feel like this should just be a V3 called diameter,
which seems a little bit more logical, right?
This is just doing two times this.
Is that what what was this supposed to be?
Oh, I see what we were doing here.
Yeah, so we were
Okay, so this was this was the Armand Cascade.
So really diameter is a little bit weird.
It's this is really the Mankowski diameter, right?
That's really what we should call this.
And so that's like adding the depths of these together.
And so really this should probably be two times.
This eventually we should have probably to do, you know, entities have
height, you know.
Probably who knows and so, you know, there we go.
So now I'm going to go ahead and do that.
Makowski diameter here and just use that.
So there we are.
We can put that in there and we'll compute it that way and then when
we do our relative positioning, we can go ahead and do that.
Now, all of this should still work.
Basically, we're doing the Collision detection in two dimensions.
That's fine for now we don't need to upgrade that for any particular
reason.
And then our normals are all still exactly the same.
They just, again, end up having enough, no, no Z component, they just
stay in that in the plane, right?
And then, everything else is still work.
I think, I don't think there's anything else in particular that we
need to worry too much about their Hoops, those supposed to be threes
now, like so.
Like so, our world difference again, these are now going to be pretty,
pretty basic stuff.
I don't know if get camera space p is even called anymore.
To be honest with you.
Let's find out camera space.
P&R us-based P.
Was that used anywhere.
It is not so you know what?
That can just disappear and let's see begins Sim.
What is begin?
Tsum doing?
Let's see here.
That is passing the camera bounds which now needs to be a rectangle 3.
So that's going to be we're going to use a Center Dim again we're
going to go ahead and do tile side in meters and we're just going to
say that.
It's fans 14 now again because we don't really know although I could
do it I can do it this way.
So it's a little clearer that is just going to do one.
So we could do real to be to tile span Z like so.
And yes, I am totally picking those numbers randomly.
So let's see here.
There we go.
V2 again, I really like typing V2.
When really I should be typing Bakery.
And okay, so this is just our entities position .z.
Now because we're old the Z into it and our DDP is now going to have
to be not, not based on Z anymore.
So our DDP here, if the con Heroes DZ oops we do the line accidentally
there.
Then I want to actually make that DZ change so that I can just make I
can just put that what I was putting in.
As a request.
Their I can actually put in
in as a request on the the acceleration now because we don't have to
keep it as a
Then you can go get passed through directly.
Unfortunately, I overwrite it here.
Oh, well, so actually that's even easier.
I guess, what I can do is just go up where I actually write can con
hero, and when Conn hero does it, we can just say, okay, you know,
let's put that DDP.
Let's put that onto the Z component of that, right?
That seems to make sense.
I don't really know why it's a
Plus equals there.
Oh
Wait, because that because that's we're actually setting the velocity.
Sorry that was a that was me having a quick sort of brain as it does a
bit of a brain farts.
True.
We're actually cold setting, the velocity.
That's not getting rolled into the acceleration at all.
We're actually cold saying the velocity.
So that's actually a deep E.Z.
That's just straight up getting an additional jump to it.
So all right, we'll leave it.
Go doing it that way for now.
Because that's fine.
And again, jumping jumping, just something that we're keeping in there
for fun for now.
So it's not really a huge deal either way.
So our con hero DDP technically.
We're not even going to allow that to really accelerate in the Z
Direction at the moment anyway.
So we'll just go ahead and leave it.
Like so oops, the three and let's see here, no operator found.
Which takes left hand side, May, Kennedy, spatial.
What's wrong with it going to be spatial?
Did we not update that make the key?
Spatial, is that an entity that h
Make entities spatial is taking a 2 V 3 S.
So it's calm here, OD sword.
So con hero d sword also is only allowed to throw in the plane.
So we'll just not bothers propagating that changeup word, okay?
So old P I'm assuming doesn't get used anymore because we fixed that.
Yes, that's just a vestigial remain anyway, so that should be fine.
RZ is now our P.C.
So that's fine too.
Our worlds difference again, we're just
Getting V3 is for those things now.
So if we want to actually get that out, it's just gift out, x y.
And now we have a program that compiles, yay.
Of course, we made a ton of changes, so it probably won't work, but we
have gotten to compile, and that when you're making a big change, like
this is the first step to success.
Alright, so as you can see, we have absolutely nothing here.
Which is not at all what we wanted.
Of course, there is a problem already that I kind of knew that we
would have when we did that change.
And so I want to just go ahead before we start to bugging, which may
have to wait till tomorrow.
Obviously, because we're just about out of time, we got about 30
minutes left and I started about 10.
Wait, what I wanted to do, was, when we actually do our rectangle
inclusion test, right?
I wanted to point out that we kind of have this problem where we have
to think about where stuff is actually centered and whether or not it
gets included in that centered rectangular bounds.
So yeah, like basically what I wanted to do is just make sure that
we're actually getting our bounce set up properly.
So before
Why bother debugging things I want to actually, make sure that I kind
of fix that and basically what I wanted to make sure I fix this.
You know, when we are doing this checking, right?
We've we were doing before we were doing this checking where we would
take a chunk in the world, right?
And you know these these chunks were sort of on a grid and we would
gather all the entities that were in that Chunk.
We wouldn't care about where they were in Z.
We just used their abs tile Z or something like this to grab them out.
And so what I want to make sure we're doing now is if you look at this
sort of side on right, so if this is our top view,
And we want to look at our side view, right?
Basically, we've got this sort of thing where the ground I want the
ground to pass through the middle of our, our query region.
And I want things to be placed on this midline.
And the reason that I want to be that way and I want to go make sure
we're doing it that way, instead of this way, where it's like that is,
I don't want floating Point wise us, to be always really near to being
moved into the trunk below us, right.
I want the
The plane where everything happens to be squarely in the middle of our
gather region.
And so that the next like stare place, you would stand would be up
here in another chunk, right?
And so that when you walk, you'd walk like upstairs or something like
this, you would transition like the halfway point in the stairs from
being in one chunk to another, and you'd never be standing on anything
in here.
Anyway, just to keeps you away from that boundary so that you don't
end up basically, having to constantly check two things for Collision,
Section in vacillate between them and all that sort of stuff.
So I just wanted to make sure we were actually doing that.
Properly.
So I'm going to go ahead and take our remaining 10 minutes to just go
do that.
And then we'll probably saved a bugging RZ stuff for tomorrow.
Although it looks like we sort of we're working.
We just probably have some problems with our gather to work out.
So we'll go ahead and do that, but it looks like we weren't too far
too.
Terribly far from working, hopefully fingers crossed.
So yeah.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead and check when we add
entities first and also then when we
Pull them out.
Just that the what the actual values are that we're actually using for
that.
That's that's really all I wanted to make sure we do.
So.
Okay so we have our chunk poster from tile position.
and then we add
Sing our tile location.
So let's Okay, let me just go ahead.
I'll do it actually in the ad wall column will take a look at it in
there.
So here we go.
We're doing chunk position from top position.
We're passing all zeros here.
And so what I want to see come out of this, I just want to see what we
end up giving it as its location and that is exactly what I had hoped
to see, right.
I wanted basically our XY and Z 2, all be 0 because that zero is right
since its measured from the center, or should be that Z is right in in
the middle, right?
And you have negative half tile dim and positive half tile.
Jim,
To go in either direction.
Right?
So, that's what I wanted to see.
That's all good.
And hopefully, like, if I check a few more of these, we can kind of
see those work properly.
Let's take a look here.
Yeah, that doesn't look right to me.
All right.
Well, I guess I said I wasn't going to debug it but I, you know how I
am.
When I see something happening wrong, I kind of have to go look at it.
So what
Happened there.
I would like to know because we have our AB style, ABS tie lab style.
We should be seeing some multiplication happen.
There AB style, ABS table style.
Did I mess up our implementation of the hadamard product or something
like that?
Macbeth.
Let's see here.
So, we have our a, you have our B.
So if we do our multiplication, what do we end up with?
Make sure we produce a valid value there.
So that looks like what I would have expected to see.
So that's good.
We come out of there and now we're going to do mapping the chunk
space, right?
So that's fine.
Oh well, this actually might be fine.
I may have, I may have overreacted that makes because we are aligned
on our tile boundaries because that's how we
Placing our trees should never be offset from the tub tile boundaries.
So okay.
Sorry, I may have overreacted, let's double-check
So we go ahead and do that ad.
We're going to canonicalize canonicalize clockwise.
That's the correct answer.
Out comes the results and our word position result is 7.
Okay.
So we refined nevermind, nevermind.
I was looking at the wrong thing.
It's all good, it's all good.
So, yeah.
So that looks fine.
How come we can't see?
Where is our P?
There it is.
There's the nine.
So that's what we would expect to see.
All right.
So it looks actually totally fine.
That's all good.
So I'm just going to go ahead and check.
Now, the other thing that I want to check like I said, when we do our
Sim region grab over here.
In begin Sim, come on.
Begin Sam.
There we are.
I want to make sure that we're grabbing
From sort of the bounds that I expect, right?
That the bounds are something reasonable.
So those bounds are going to be in our Sim region updatable bounds or
just a guess, just bounds.
So, taking a look at those.
Let's take a look at what the Min and Max are.
So we're - 36 never 19 -1.7 36:19 1.7.
So that looks
right on the money to me, that looks totally good.
Although I would say,
The span looks larger than it should be, but I guess that's because
our, we have our safety region margin that we added.
So that's that, now, that's about, right?
So, let's go ahead and check a look at our Min and Max chunk, right?
So we have our moon jump P, Max chunk P like so you take a look at
what those give us.
We're going from 6 3 - 1 to 10 51.
That doesn't seem right to me at all.
I don't like the that value for men to be completely honest with you.
I don't understand, I don't understand what I just witnessed their I'm
going to have to set that through how much time I got.
I got five more minutes.
Because if these are negatives, I feel like the tile index should have
been - because the time to seize our signed now, so that's kind of a
little weird.
So let me see what's going on here.
Okay, that's fine.
Okay.
Because that's relative to the camera and our camera is not starting
out at 0 0, all right.
Totally fine.
I'm happy with it.
I'm totally fine with that, totally fine with that.
So then we're going to grab out are chunks.
We're going to come through here and now I guess the other thing we
could see is do we actually ever grab an entity or don't we?
So it looks like our problem is our checking for entities is never
actually returning us any.
Any entities is that?
Because we're failing on our chunks, it is because we're failing on
the chunks.
So if you notice here, when I'm adding I'm never even getting in
22 these checks here.
So we're basically never our world chunks are never actually seeming
to include the entities even though we were supposedly adding them.
So I guess the thing that we would have to debug and I don't know if
we want to start this.
Now I'll take a quick look at it but I think this will basically way.
Tomorrow really what we need to do is find out when I did my
modifications to handmade world.
What did I break in terms of how we're storing things into chunk
positions, right?
How we're basically putting them in, it seems to be a little bit
broken unless I'm in less, I'm missing something obvious.
So basically
for some reason, our map into chunks face is busted in some way.
Something like this or there's some other thing that I'm not thinking
of that we haven't updated yet that we need to update and didn't but
we handle all yeah we always we always were, z4r 4r indices so it
should be something relatively straightforward.
I would think but I'm not obviously positive that yet.
So I'm going to go ahead and stop for now.
Because I don't want to get too deep into the bugging because it'll
just eat through the whole Q&A.
So we'll stop for now and we'll pick it back up tomorrow, which I
don't think will probably take us that long to debug because, you
know, it's not that complicated.
All right, so I'm gonna go ahead and start the Q&A dude, like so and
if you could go ahead and prefix your questions with Q: so I can see
them and also try to keep them in stuff, we've done today stream or on
a previous dream.
If you like to ask off-topic questions, we can do that.
Basically in the in the priest dream come about 15 minutes early to
any scheduled start time and we do off-topic questions then so.
All right.
Let's see.
Have you considered using macros that, take a name and operator to
paste in simple Vector functions?
I don't love using macros because they can be kind of unwieldy to make
longer functions, and they're kind of, they're just, they're very
cumbersome.
And really, that's not because macros are bad.
It's because C makes me and C++ the same make macros bad like macros
should be good and I would use them a lot if they were better.
If see actually allowed proper macro processing if you like using
macros and want to get more into that than what I would probably
recommend you actually do is not use see.
Macros use a macro preprocessor you know something that's designed to
do those better more interesting macro Transformations, might actually
be better for you because sees sees macros are pretty weak.
They've got a little bit better now, they can support varargs and
stuff but they're pretty bad.
As macro language is go-sees is real bad and C++ really didn't fix it.
What kind of onlooker drinking?
I'm drinking water right now, actually.
No, I'm in milk tonight.
You have any suggestions on how to keep up with your five episodes a
week.
When me, and my friend have only started watching your videos from the
beginning.
Last week, I would say, don't try to keep up, watch at your own pace.
That's why I put them all on YouTube, and people maintain the episode
guide to and all that stuff.
I would say don't try to rush.
There's no reason why you have to keep up with me, take it at your own
pace, and if you do keep up, you do.
If you don't, you don't, it's not an issue, right?
The important thing is to learn.
The only point of the stream is for to make it easier to learn how to
do a bunch of these game things.
And so I would just kind of say don't stress about that at all, you
can always ask questions on the forums so you don't have to worry
about like, being able to ask questions in the Q&A.
So I'd say, it's take your time, it's about learning, it's about being
comfortable, the material and catching up, doesn't really help in any
particular way, right?
So you don't have to catch up if it takes you
you know a very long time to go through all the episodes as long as
you learn from them that's really the only that's really the only
thing that matters I think
Why did 1.0 F instead of 1.0?
So you don't really need to anymore.
It used to be that compilers were too dumb to accept 1.0, they would
only accept 1.0 F.
And the reason for that is because they thought 1.0 was a double.
And 1.0 is afloat.
And so every time you typed 1.0, it would say it would, it would
complain, it would say, conversion from double to float, possible loss
of precision.
And so really what?
You're seeing there when I habitually type like 1.0 F.
That's where that comes from most compilers.
Nowadays are smart enough to know that it's one play know.
It could be a double or a float.
So just see if you can convert it to a float properly without losing
any precision and then you're fine right.
Most compilers today don't have that problem.
So really when you see me doing that F, it's because I was, you know,
basically, when I grew up, compilers were too dumb to understand that,
so, you had to always put an F, otherwise, you got warnings,
Have you considered writing tests?
So tests are again very test test very.
So in order to justify spending time on tests, you have to verify that
the amount of time you spend on test will be less than the amount of
time you spend in debugging, right?
At any stage in the process, like, where we are now.
Because right now, we're not considering shipping this code.
We're doing a engine architecture work and so,
if you write a test,
You'd be better.
Be damn sure that the time you spend writing and debugging the test
and getting the test working properly is less than the time.
It would have taken you to debug the code without the test because if
it's not, you just made a mistake, right?
You wasted time the time when test become a more reasonable more,
justifiable thing to write is when you actually have code, you're
planning on shipping.
Or because then you can think of the test as even if it takes longer
to write the test a test about the code.
The test is helping to validate that the code doesn't have bugs in it
before I ship it, right?
It's part of your Q&A at that point and then a test can be more
justifiable in terms of the time it takes to write it, right?
The other time you could do it is if you feel like you're you're
having a lot of trouble debugging something because then you can see
that you're spending that debugging time now, it might be time to it,
be better to switch that time over into running a test because the
test will pay off more.
Then the debugging time, right?
And so thinking of it, strictly in terms of I should write tests for
my code is not a good way to code.
In my opinion that leads to a lot of wasted time and wasted effort.
What you want to do is include tests in your thought, process about
how to write code efficiently and then make the decision as you go all
the time.
I don't think this code is going to take us very long to the bug.
I think it'll take us like five minutes or something or 10 minutes on
the next screen, maybe it won't, but I don't think it will take
Very long.
And so starting to write a bunch of tests here, I think would just be
a waste of time when we actually go to lock down something.
Like when we do the renderer we start locking that down stuff.
That's when you'll probably see me start to write some tests because I
want to be sure and also because for certain things I know that I can
write tests that will help me develop and debug, the thing that I'm
working on now, unfortunately for games testing is very difficult,
because there's a lot of things in games that really can't have unit
tests.
For them.
So the tests are very complicated intend to be randomized, more
because you couldn't possibly exhaustively test.
So testing has in general, less utility in game programming than in
other disciplines in other disciplines.
Sometimes when you're talking about text transformation like web
programming you can often times isolate things and write more specific
test that do cover a lot more of your usage cases.
So you can get more out of tests and other disciplines.
Sometimes in game design is a little bit hard, but we will have places
where we can use them in you.
See me use them.
Now however is not one of those times.
Can you explain what your Z really means?
If it's for separating levels should tall walls be able to poke into
upper Z layers.
So really what I'm sort of doing here.
Is I'm just kind of building out what's almost a 3D game engine.
If you think about it and just letting us regress back to 2D for
things that we find our more.
Be so, what Z actually means in this engine right now, like we're
basically treating Z as if it was almost.
This is almost a 3D engine at this point, right?
So our Z doesn't have special meaning anymore, we've kind of gotten to
a place where Z can just be handled and so that probably won't
continue to be the case will probably have places where we want to
treat Z very specifically because it is a 2-D game and that means
we'll have to make some some sort of semantic, z mean,
Things and places as opposed to making the Z real.
But for right now, Z means is it's a third coordinate period.
So you could do anything you wanted, you could have things that span
multiple Z, you can have entities that that span two floors.
So you could fight the top of the monster and go down a floor and
flight the bottom of monster.
Which come to think about it.
I don't know why.
No, one's ever done that before.
That sounds awesome.
Don't put that in reminders file.
So we're basically not cheating yet on Z so so, yeah.
And so,
Once we start cheating on Z at some point it will be because we have
things we want to do there but I put I'm going to put that in the
thing.
Monster that you fight on two floors at once.
Whatever you want to call that going up and down stairs to fight the
bottom or the top.
Yeah.
I've never seen that in a 2-D game.
I don't think so.
Yeah, what's going on here?
Oh no, there we go.
Okay.
All right.
How do you tab between things so quickly?
I am just using alt be
Which brings up a little buffer.
If that what you're talking about in emacs, I can do like alt shift b
or alt be.
So alt shift B allows me to bring up something in the separate window
so I can just type like handmade entity or something, right?
And bring it up, alt be switches in the same buffer, so I can be like
math and got the math thing.
So, that's all I'm.
That's all I'm doing.
It's pretty quick.
When you get the hang of it, if you use Visual Studio, you can
actually do the same sort of thing in Visual Studio.
I can't remember what it's called, but there's
There's a function that's like switch to buffer and you can bind it to
a key.
And if you're if you're slow at moving around files and visual studio,
I would highly recommend going looking that up and binding it to a key
or just using whatever the key.
I think it's bound to a key by default, but if it's not then bind it
and that's that helps you get around a lot quicker.
How good of a computer do I need to smoothly?
Code coding doesn't require.
Any kind of computer, you can smoothly code with, like, my computer at
work is probably four years old at this point, and I could comfortably
code on one that was eight years old, probably just fine.
In fact, this one that were using handmade hero, it was a crazy beefy
machine for Hardware development.
So at the time it was kind of ridiculous lie, Advanced.
But it's pretty old too.
I think it's four years old.
At this point, probably more.
So really coding is not the thing.
That's the problem.
The thing that you need to worry about is what kind of game you're
developing.
If you're developing some kind of crazy game that does a ton of 3D
that's really stresses the GPU or even if it's too,
D but has tons of overdraw or stuff like this.
Then what you have to ask yourself is how good of a computer do I need
to handle the development of this because until I optimize it a lot or
if I'm targeting high-end machines for the day, then I can't obviously
develop on a machine that couldn't even play my game because I
couldn't run the game to test it and I can't optimize the game
properly.
If I'm not running on the sort of machine that I expect and user to
have.
So really the coding part, it doesn't matter.
You can program on anything just like an editor and a compiler.
Don't take a lot of
CPU.
So it's really more about about what the game is going to need.
So
I love you.
Will you marry me?
Well, I'm already married and fortunately in Washington state.
You're only allowed to marry one person.
So, you know what you going to do?
When they bring polygamy back, you know how smooth?
Is it transitioning?
A knowledge of python into C++.
So, I would say that if you can just learn to work with memory, more
directly, you're gonna have to learn to work with pointers and memory
a little bit more integrally and like get them a little bit more than
with python but otherwise I mean, you know, code is code and so it's
really the memory part and thinking about where things live and how
you operate on them.
More directly is most of what would be different.
So, yeah, but I can't say beyond that, I haven't written much python
code.
I've only written a little bit so hard for me to say,
Have you thought more on how the Z axis will look when finally
implemented?
I haven't quite yet.
So I looked at the people were posting and I appreciate that, we're
posting videos on the forums because I was out talking about it and I
haven't thought about my I didn't like the isometric looking ones that
much or was like tilted and there was a lot of Z motion.
I think I kind of want to focus more on a flat
World of this, not a lot of Z motion and the Z motion happens when you
go down into things or up out of things.
And anyway, it's kind of I mean I don't know we'll have to play around
with it a little, I don't have a good basically.
What I want the Z2 mostly do is that but, you know, when I think about
things like fighting a monster on the top and the bottom and you kind
of want to see into something below you a little.
So we'll see.
We're going to we're going to have to play with it.
I didn't see anything where I was like yes obviously this game.
Just did it right or anything, you know?
So so I don't know.
Let's see.
When you work on a game, do you work on one project or do they contact
you from multiple projects?
It depends that's entirely.
Contextual most people tend to work on a single project at a time
though.
Do you think about data locality all the time to reduce cache, misses
No, not really.
So the answer is, I probably think about data locality a little less
than I should because data locality wasn't a big deal.
When I started programming, like, my first 20 years of programming
data locality was not a big deal and it's only in like the past 10
years or so that it's been growing into a more and more dominant
thing.
And so I
This point really tend to think about data locality more when I'm
optimizing things, then what I'm just coding them and in some sense
that's good because you don't want to spend a lot of mental energy
thinking about optimization stuff when you're just trying to figure
out what the architecture for things should be but part of figuring
out the architecture is making sure you don't make decisions which
make it impossible for you to do good optimizations later.
And so I should think about locality more than I do.
It's really the answer.
But I've never been a super hardcore optimization guy.
So you know, like I don't tend to focus.
I don't tend to be the person who focuses on making the absolute
fastest, possible thing.
I try to make my code be pretty darn fast but it's not as fast as like
some of my friends at rad.
For example, who are all about the speed
And so, you know, at some level, I'm just not, I'm not the, I'm not
the like super crazy Optimizer guy.
I'm below that and so in some sense that's it's not that unusual that
I'm not like always thinking about those things.
And answer the other question.
I've been programming for 31 years now.
Am I done working for real made?
All your money and this is just for fun, philanthropic reasons.
No, I am.
I have to go to work.
Day and I do worry about making money.
I am, I am not independently wealthy.
How do you determine what gathers in a chunk with the Z axis?
Do you grab entities from all six sides of the chunk?
Well, it's not really 6 size of the chunk, it's a volume, right?
And so what we're doing and this is the part that we have to debug
tomorrow because we broke something.
Right?
What we were doing before is we were basically saying, okay let's
gather everything from a-z slice in the world, right?
Because remember before we were sort of dividing up the world, right?
We have this notion that the
World was sort of in slices, right?
And then inside those slices, they were little 16 by 16 tile chunks,
sort of, and then we got rid of the concept of tiles.
So really it's mostly just like, you know.
However, I do remember how wide a tile was on the side.
But, you know, it's something like, you know, 20 meter by 20 meter
chunk at this point or something.
So it's, you know, it's just a chunk.
And basically what we were doing is we were storing all of our world
in those chunks and we only had a sparse storage for them.
And then what we would do is we'd go through the chunks that
overlapped a camera region and we grab them out and process them.
And then stick them back.
Right?
And so now what we're doing is we're extending that to basically think
of these things, instead of a slices to be actual like they're not
actually cubes because they're they're they're sort of square on one
side.
But there's stuff out there, they're not as tall as they are wide and
you know with them height and Z they're not as tall.
So, I believe the term would be right.
Rectangular prism.
also, often called an axis aligned
bounding box, even though these things are not the same, this one
doesn't have to be access aligned, it just has to be some kind of a
thing that has all right angles, right?
But an excellent bounding box is a special case of one of these, where
we know that these things can't be freely rotated in here, they have
to actually line up with the x y&z axis, right?
There, axis aligned chunks and so it acts as a line bounding box.
Really.
We have actually about us also called an AA BB
Axis aligned bounding box.
You'll see that term pretty often and so really what we're doing is
we're trying this isn't just something that pulls out.
Whatever's inside, that axis line bounding box.
Anything that overlaps it we pull out
So that's what we're doing currently.
And right now we actually, you know, and I should put it to do in.
We actually are doing something not quite right, which we could pretty
trivially start doing right now.
So we might as well just start doing it, right?
Which is that when we pull things in, when we do is in rectangle,
right?
We've got sort of these two calls
Is it rectangle is in rectangle really what we want to do is to do and
you know what?
I'll do.
I'll put it in our Master to do so I remembered it.
Do it.
See in here minkowski it'll do that pretty easily I guess we did that
clean up things.
We're just a buggy Matt now, so that's gone.
So we have our Mankowski, we want to do Mankowski inclusion test for a
Sim region, begin updatable bounds.
And so basically what I was going to say is what we're not doing right
now is our entities.
When we do tests on the entities, we're not actually seeing if we're
treating them as points.
So when we do our inclusion test, oops I zoomed out there.
Didn't I when we do our inclusion tests I actually am just doing a
point test and saying is this point inside the volume that we're
pulling in?
Yes.
Know what I really should be doing is saying okay entities have volume
themselves so
Let's do the exact same Mankowski.
Some we were doing for vision to action.
Let's expand that gather region by the dimensions of the entity then
test the point to see if it's included or something similar dude.
So, basically actually test for volumes overlapping instead of just a
point being inside it, so we should probably do that because it's
pretty free for us to do.
So we might as well.
Let's see.
I recently, watched John blows talk on a tempting deep work and became
curious.
Do you do anything similar from a psychological perspective by ego,
dancing like John does or do you have some other relaxing rewarding
activity that helps to spawn, creative thought or gain elusive
insights into problems?
You are struggling to solve
So no, I guess, I don't.
But you have to remember, John is, I mean, he is a programmer, but
he's a game designer probably first nowadays and like programming.
I don't know if John would be doing those things for programming,
like, I don't know if John feels like he needs to go dancing to think
through a problem in his new language compiler, right?
That's a good question to ask him actually.
So I don't know if he does that but he may be talking about that more
for doing game design which has a lot less rigor to it, right?
It's a lot more, there's a lot more creativity and loose constraints
and things that are harder to Think Through logically.
And so I don't know if he would say that he does those same things.
He was talking about in that lecture for programming only but I don't
know because I actually never seen that.
Lecture, I know what you're talking about roughly about never seen
that particular lecture.
So I guess I'd say you'd have to ask John to be more specific about
that but no I don't and I also don't know how to dance very well so
that doesn't help.
So we're almost done here.
Let me see.
Do you think rk4?
Integration is overkill for a 2-D game like handmade hero.
So, I answered this question before.
I will answer it briefly again, but I would say, maybe try to go back
and find my previous answer.
Rk4 is not something I would ever use in a game.
Under any circumstances rk4 is a numerical integration technique.
First of all, we had we don't have anything to numerically integrate
yet.
So there are k for we wouldn't have any use for rk4, I assume your
form.
The runge-kutta integration fourth order, or whatever, but, or
whatever the force transfer, I don't remember how they number them.
I assume you're referring to a runge-kutta flavor, runge-kutta is not
a good integrator for games.
I would not suggest using around cut off or anything.
If you're numerically integrating things, I would strongly recommend
using something like backwards, Euler or something, that was more
conservative, and that doesn't add energy to the system.
Our case.
4S unless I'm misremembering are very bad and they have all kinds of
energy explosion criteria and you just hate life.
If you're running through in rk4 integrator and unless things have
changed significantly, I don't recall the the high in physics people
in games to ever think that rk4 was a good idea, but I could be wrong
about that.
So rk4 II.
I don't think that has anything to do with her.
It's Overkill, or not, for Duty game.
I would say stay far away from rk4.
Unless you really know that it's a good idea because I've been
programmed physics in a long time.
Last night program physics was 1998, maybe let's say, I mean serious
physics like three-dimensional rotating rigid body physics was
literally 1998, so a lot has changed since then.
But at that time we were using around Kutta methods, and they were
awful, and it was right at that time where people were figuring out,
you don't ever want to use those kind of methods.
You want to use methods that remove energy from the system, virile a
schemes backwards, Euler stuff like that, that remove energy from the
systems instead of ones to add energy because the last you want things
in your game to calm down, you don't want them to excite and rk4 is an
exciting, you know, integrators.
That add energy to excite things and they cause those physics
explosions, where stuff, just goes crazy, and, and the game goes nuts,
right?
And you really don't want that.
Let's see.
Last few questions here.
Give this anything?
Like an answer that's related to the programming.
Let's see.
Okay, I will take two more of these that I see here.
Maybe I'll take three.
All right.
So we'll do these in order here.
So, someone asked why am I using assertions in non test code?
So I guess
I want to take that question because I feel like that suggests that
maybe you are thinking about assertions in an unusual way because what
assertions are for is assertions are specifically for non test code.
The whole design of assertions is to put them in your non test code.
So the way that assertions work is when you compile normally you leave
them in and then when you want to do performance testing or release
the
They disappear, right?
You can just compile them out.
So they're zero cost to you when you're actually doing performance
work and they only actually cost you when you're doing your debugging
work which is when you want them to do the work.
So the idea behind assertion is to put them everywhere.
You have some condition you think is always going to be true.
And I don't always do that so I can put in a lot more assertions,
like, for example right here, we know that that ref can't be 0, right?
So I can put that in there.
The reason that I don't is because that's literally a waste of typing.
We know that that if ref was passed in as 0, the first thing that's
going to happen is this codes going to fault immediately because it
going to try and reference off of the zero to load this pointer out.
So the assertion didn't do anything that code will already Fail Hard
immediately.
But what you do want to do is you want to put in a search engines that
will try to make your code Fail Hard at that point whenever you have
something that would not have caused a null pointer.
It's because that would stop you heart.
What you need is to, you're trying to create hard stops where none
existed before.
So for example, in this case, If This Were a zero, this this storage
index.
No problem.
When the storage index gets passed through this code would just work
but that be very bad because that meant someone was trying to add an
entity with a storage X of 0, which we know is not allowed.
Zero means no entity, so that assertion here is to catch that much
earlier in the debugging process.
It makes it.
So it's loud.
It fails right there.
R.
Otherwise, what will happen is that in any gets added as entity 0,
then somewhere down the line.
We go, wait, why do we have an entity 0 Y?
Is this, this is actually getting someone is looking it up and he's
finding it as to what's going on, right?
And then we got to work all the way backwards and get all the way back
to this part where it failed.
And so the goal of assertions is specifically to put them in code,
that is not test code, is to put it in your release code, your actual
real code that you're trying to make.
You're trying to assert the things that you think should always be
true.
And then again, what you do is at the end you just compile them out,
right?
We inside handmade platform that H.
We have this assertion macro, right?
We've got handmade slow.
All we have to do is pound a fine handmade slow to be 0 and all the
assertions disappear poof, they're not even there anymore, right?
So it costs us nothing to put in those assertions.
They are completely free when we actually go to do our optimization
work.
So I would greatly
courage you to put a certain in your actual code.
It's not just for test code, it's for all your code and it's for
making things fail, quickly, and immediately upon any circumstance
that seems out of the ordinary in shouldn't happen because that's
going to cut down on the debugging time.
If anything, I am using less assertions here than I probably would
normally.
And part of that is I have a hard time when I'm explaining code and
writing it.
It's harder for me to keep my mental state proper for coding.
If anything, the code that
See me right on the stream has less assertions.
That it would, when I would normally be writing it because it takes
extra mental energy for me to think about what should be asserted.
So I'd highly recommend certainly don't use less asserts that I'm
using.
I'm a decent programmer.
I don't make a huge number of stupid mistakes so it's not the case
that I have to put in these assertions because I'm just really bad or
anything like that.
I am reasonably good at coding and I
still always want those searches there and they always catch errors
Because unless you're way way better than I am, trust me, you will
make mistakes of the kind that these assertions will catch quickly and
they'll save you a ton of time and I'm the guy who says don't bother
typing const, right?
So I would not tell you, to put something in your code by rote or
anything like that.
I, I trim out all of those things that I think don't catch my errors.
The kind of errors that I make because I make errors all the time.
You see me, make them on the
And I make them that's not just on the stream.
I make them in real life all the time.
My code doesn't work the first time.
I'm not mr.
Like everything comes out perfect and so I don't type the things in
that I don't find Sammy time.
I don't type private, don't type cos I don't find.
They help me right?
But assert it absolutely does every day, maybe not every day.
But you know, every week let's say I have bugs that get caught every
week by assertions that I may not even have seen till much later.
And that could have been very hard to track down.
So assert good, I would highly recommend keeping it in your code, not
just test code.
So let's see here.
And then the last question, what about having two regions one outer
and one inner included?
He's that move into the inner and exclude entities, that move out of
the outer.
So there's a margin that allows some moving without ping-ponging,
right across a hard in outline, so we already have that.
I don't know, if you remember what we have is the updatable zone and
the non updatable Zone.
And so we have that area in the outside where we basically allow
people to move out into it, but we don't allow anything in it to move.
It's not quite for the purpose you're talking about, but the idea
behind the non ping pong is whatever the region is, you're still going
to have this.
It's really an optimization.
If that makes sense is to make it so that you can have tighter bounds
on the number of entities that are in your
set or that you have to check to see if they're in the set.
And so really what I was doing there was I just wanted the alignment
so that we don't have to pull in.
We don't have a check another tile chunk so it really didn't have
anything to do with the bounds we were using.
It was more just about centering it so that we do the minimal amount
of work to get the same volume and if that makes sense because it
wouldn't matter.
The ping-pong is going to affect us, it's fight.
We'd it doesn't bother us.
It was more just to make sure that we didn't have to check that extra
region.
And to be clear it's not always
Roppongi either entities have a size so we just don't want them to
straddle that boundary.
We want to center it and now we have less tile chunks to check.
So that's that's really it, right?
So I think that's about it.
Hopefully we covered enough of the questions there.
There were a lot of them but yeah.
So hopefully we covered all that there.
So I'm going to go ahead and and call it here.
And tomorrow, we will pick up.
We'll finish that to bugging process, just to clean up, all the
changes that we made and make sure everything's working, okay, enough
with our V3 change and then what we'll do is we'll just finish these
guys up and so this will be some more cleanup tomorrow.
Just working through that Z and we might be able to finish the off
tomorrow but maybe
Not will have to will see, it may take another day because we've got
this nastiness here, which is it's kind of like, we don't really know
what we want to do.
And when we don't know that implies playing around in testing in that
test, take a little more time, but we should be able to make pretty
good progress.
So hopefully I will see you tomorrow for that.
That's at 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time, same time plate, same place.
Hope to see you all here again then.
Until then, if you would like to follow along at home,
You can always do so by pre-ordering the game at handmade hero
dot-org.
If you go ahead and pre-order the game, it comes with a full source
code.
So you can download the source code play around at home.
Just like I'm doing.
And of course, all of the videos are archived both on YouTube and at
our news and Forum site, we have an episode guide.
That's pretty cool that you can go through.
And so, if you want to go back and see how everything was made,
absolutely every line of code, I explained on this stream, just like I
did tonight and so if you want to check that out, you can always do
that.
We also have a patreon if you want to support the video series, it's
very much appreciated.
You can check that out again.
He made here at Orange, got all the links for it.
Finally, if you're trying to catch the stream regularly and you want
to know what it is, we've got a tweetbot, the tweets, the schedule
that you and that's a good place to go to sort of just keep up to date
on when the, when the streams are.
If you're having trouble catching of course, you can always subscribe
on, not subscribe, follow on Twitch and that emails you when I start
but that doesn't really help you tell like when it's going to be so
the treat box pretty handy for that.
That's about it.
Thank you for joining me and I hope to see you all tomorrow.
So, thanks everyone.