Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero show.
We could a complete game live on stream.
We did a bunch of work last weekend.
Hmm.
Well, I guess last Saturday Sunday?
I don't know if we do any work on Saturday for it, but we did a bunch
of work.
Last Sunday to enable multi sample anti-aliasing which was made a
little bit, artificially, more difficult than it.
Possibly had to be because it looks like maybe there's some problem
with the opengl drivers on this machine that don't let us set srgb
rendering.
For a multi sample, render Target, even though you are supposed to be
able to set multi sample anti-aliasing, and srgb on on the same render
Target even on AMD Hardware supposedly.
So we're not really sure what's up with that, but this is a very old
machine so maybe that's part of the problem.
But at the very least what I can tell you is that this is pretty much
why PC development is always so much of a pain in the butt.
It's because the hardware is so variable in the drivers are so
unreliable that you typically end up in situations where you can't
just count on stuff, that's documented to work to actually work.
That's not typically the way things go.
And it's a bit of a bummer.
One of the reasons that people like console development,
Fact is just because the platform does a better job of actually saying
what it can do and doing it when it is asked.
That said we still have to deal with the PC obviously and it's a good
platform for everything else.
It's certainly a nicer platform to deal with because it's open at
least as long as Microsoft continues to let it be.
And so you know, it's one of those things that you got to take the
good and the bad together in some sense.
And, and just deal with the fact that the driver situation and dealing
with Graphics GPU access on these platforms is really unsatisfying.
Anyway, let's go ahead and go to the code here.
Today is day Three, Sixty eight.
And so if you want to follow along at home day, 367 is the code start
with.
We have on handmade opengl here.
We have already done actually I gotta open that project file as well,
so we have all our code loaded.
We can build.
There we go.
We have running now.
Something that in theory creates the render targets and also renders
to the render targets, but as you can see, by this black screen, we
never
Any graphics, the reason for that is we have not actually put in any
calls to actually get the the buffers that we render out to the
screen.
So if you recall how this Loop is working in the opengl renderer, what
happens is that the beginning
Goes through and allocates render buffers for.
About Kate's textures for all of the frame buffers.
We think we might need now in our case currently because there aren't
any rooms stacked on top of each other or anything like that and we
don't really have any other reason for it at the moment we don't have
more than one so we're only going to presumably in any given frame.
When we're looking at the contents of the command list were only going
to see this.
Max render Target index being equal to 1 and
So the first time through, we're going to create one of these buffers
and that's all we're going to ever use.
Now what we can see here is that we've changed this from what it used
to be two calling GL, text image to Dee's what it used to call.
We're now calling GL text image, 2D multi sample and you can see here,
we've had to pass GL r g b A8 instead of the potentially srgb version
and the reason for that is again, because this
Card for whatever reason, does not seem to be allowing us to actually
pass srgb.
Now, one thing that I do want to address real quickly just before we
get any further into it is, if we go to the GitHub Martin's has
helpfully posted for us, a really great bug report work, you found
something that we were trying to find, I was looking for it in the
documentation and we couldn't find it the other just last week when
we're doing this.
This and he found it for us.
If I go here to the handmade CPP project and I go to the issues issues
list.
It's right in here, you can see where we've got this, this stuff here.
Oops.
And you can see him talking about Geo, Mac samples -1, and he said
that Wiki where we looked it up was wrong.
And he looked it up in the spec, which we had been trying to find it
failed to find.
And so what it says here
The real max, let's amplify for textures.
Can be achieved by creating GL Max color texture samples.
GMX a vestment for render buffer objects from our frame buffer
extension.
That's what he put in there now, I'm not 100% sure about this.
The only reason that I'm not sure about this is, I don't think that
that I feel like that's the actual number of Samplers, you can read
from
In a texture, right?
Meaning, not an texture in that.
So in a texture, in a pixel Shader, basically, the fragment Shader,
which we haven't written yet, I'm pretty sure Jill Max color texture
samples is how many samples you can take of Textures in a Shader.
So if you want to take, you know, 32 samples from, you know, Textures
in a Shader that this would say, whether you could do that or not.
And whether if this
number is high enough, then you can.
And if it's too low, then you can't write.
And I'm pretty sure that's, that's what that does.
So I don't
That's actually the correct one.
Furthermore our, our texture multi sample is again, I'm just not sure
about it because that's specifically talking about grabbing it from a
texture.
Now, I guess that's what I was thinking, but Martin's is almost
always, right?
So that's the so I guess that's what I would say.
So what I assume then is happening here is maybe what we're talking
about is that GL Max color texture samples.
Is actually talking about how many if you're creating a texture, how
many samples the texture could have?
Like, meaning.
If a, if you're creating a render buffer object, there's a certain
number of multi sampling certain multi, sampling level.
You can do there and if you're creating a texture object, there's a
different level of multi sample, you can do there, right?
I don't know.
So again, because of the fact that Martin's is almost always, right?
That makes me believe that we should probably take a look at these
here, at the very least, just so we can see what's going on and try to
figure out what the actual rationale is there.
Exactly, maybe take a look at that.
Maybe take a look at that extension as well because the extensions
usually where things are explained in the best way.
So if I go ahead and open up the the core our header, I'm going to
grab that Max color texture samples,
and if I go up here and just paste that in,
We should now be able to get that value.
I got to set a breakpoint though.
So they're both equal to 8.
In this case, which makes me think that Martin's is in fact, right?
Because the number of colors samples, you could take in the Shader
would definitely be more than that.
I would think.
So I think Martin's is definitely correct on this, and we should
change it.
Like I said, Martin's is pretty much spot-on, so when he sends
something in, you'd you'd better pay attention, that's been my
experience anyway, so let's go ahead and get rid of this.
Oops, I don't need to get rid of that.
Let's get rid of this and use that value.
Now, this is not going to help us, unfortunately, it's because they
were both set to the same value, that that's obviously has nothing to
do.
And
Tested a bunch of values.
Anyway, does nothing to do with the problem that we really have here
of these services.
Not having the correct draw format, they should be srgb and they're
not.
So that's a bit of an issue, but what are you gonna do, anyway, what
we need to do now?
To finish this up is at some point?
Remember these are all rendering to textures.
Now at some point at the end, we need to actually Target the real
frame buffer and we need to Target that frame buffer.
Because the only way we can actually present something to the the
actual user in opengl is to at some point draw into frame buffer, zero
frame buffer.
Zero is the one that's the actual backing store for the window that
will.
Actually get displayed when we call swap buffers and so in order to
have our stuff displayed through swap buffers, we have to make sure
that we draw to it eventually.
Now, when we want to draw to it, you can see here, I've saved the GL
viewport call, which will set up the same viewport to the main buffer
that we had wanted before.
And that's again, in case the resolution, we get needs to be
letterboxed for our game or anything else like that.
And then we've got a GL B, frame by Furcal here at that's the last
thing we need to do GL.
B flame buffer is is, I guess not quite what we?
It's a little misleading.
I guess is what I would say.
The reason that we have to call GL blitt frame buffer, even though
we're talking about taking a texture and put into the screen, is
because as far as I could tell from the documentation and opengl the
way to do a multi sample resolved,
Is to call GL but frame buffer even if it's in a texture.
So you bind your multi sample texture to a frame buffer, you do the
blitz flame buffer from that synthetic frame buffer to frame back from
zero and that does the resolved.
Now what do I mean when I say resolved well resolve is just the term
that I don't know why it's a term that's used for.
It's the term that they came up with when they were first talking
about this where if you have a buffer that's a multi sample buffer
like I described last weekend if you want to
Take that set of multi samples and produce actual colors from them.
You have to like average them together or do some kind of a filter on
them to produce final pixel values that you can show on the screen.
Because remember multi sample means more than one sample per pixel.
In our case, we can't display more than one sample per pixel.
The monitor has to display a pixel in each pixel its pixel to pixel,
right?
It doesn't have the option of showing more than one color sample in a
given pixel.
So we have to smoosh those.
Our samples down to produce a single output color sample for every
pixel and we need the graphics card to do that.
We can't write a for I Loop to do it, right.
Because we're on the CPU here.
So if the tell the graphics card to do it, either by uploading it,
some code or calling something that already knows how to do in this
case.
It already does know how to do it, so we need to sort of tell it to do
that thing.
GL blood frame, buffer.
Looks like the way to do it and let's go ahead and take a look at
Doc's.
Touchy land.
See what that GL plis flame buffer call.
Looks like here is the earliest version of it.
You can see it here.
It's got sort of a source, a source rectangle, and a desk rectangle,
which is something we're obviously very familiar with.
Here we go.
Here we are.
And these rectangles, as far as I know if they're an integer
coordinates, that would suggest that this is bypassing the viewport
potentially, which might mean that this is not a relevant call.
I don't know, hopefully it'll say in the spec, otherwise we'll have to
look it up somewhere.
So let's take a look.
Otherwise we've got sort of a mask, we only need to use the GL color,
buffer, bit in this case, we don't need the depth buffer or the sense
of buffer to copy because we've already done any work, we were going
to do with those, we will have done them in the, in the renderer
proper up above this call.
So we just need the the color buffer bit.
And then, finally, the filter specifies the interpolation, if the
image is stretched, in this case, I assume we want.
Nearest.
Right?
Because we do want it to sort of do some averaging here, I'm sorry.
Linear because we do want to some averaging it.
Now what I don't know is what exactly happens here with with multi
sample, so I'm going to just double check to see if we can
if we can get a little bit more information about that here,
there we go.
This is, of course, the unreliable Wiki but here it is.
So you can see here, right here is where they do the resolved and so
I'm assuming that is yeah that that's that's what we want there.
And it doesn't really say anything other than doing this, but will
automatically resolve the FBO.
So it looks like, that's pretty much all.
We would need to do since we don't need to micro program it at the
moment.
So in theory, if we're right, that will just work.
So that's fine right now.
What we
To do here obviously is we need to make sure that we can actually bind
both frame buffers.
And you can see in here where we've done this bind before, let's take
a look here in mind, frame buffer.
You can see here, we've got Global frame buffer handles Target index.
What we want to do is bind that zero with frame buffer.
And we are suppose, we also want to make sure that we actually have
any frame buffers at all.
If nobody did anything.
If Max render Target index is is 0.
I suppose, then we wouldn't want to do anything.
Here we go.
And so when we go ahead and find the frame buffer, we're going to have
to bind these two frame buffers.
Here we need the global frame, buffer handle zero.
That's the one we want to read from this is when we want to write to.
And so when we actually go ahead and do that, you can see we need to
specify each one into a slot.
That GL, blind frame, buffer will understand, right?
So we want the GL draw frame buffer, to be free.
40 and we want the read frame buffer to be our Global frame buffer
handle.
So we want to read from this one and we want to draw to this one,
right?
That's our goal here.
So then we come through here and we do our GL viewport, we set up the
viewport and then we do the blitt and all I really need to know.
Now is what coordinates these are in now for the source, it should be
fairly straightforward because it's just going to be 0 0.
We know that these are entitled.
By early always created exactly the same size so we know you can see
here.
Where's are not fair.
Here we go.
You can see when we create them here, we always do them the same get
with get height of the draw region, right?
So we know that that's going to be if that's going to look like this
for the source, no matter what.
Because the source never has a shrunk viewport to it.
It never has anything weird going on at the moment.
If it does later, we'll have to change that.
But then we've got this destination when here and the question is just
Does the destination one follow this?
Is it, you know is it the draw region style stuff here that we need to
do is or
Is it is it relative to the viewport in which case we should pass the
exact same things to it?
And that's all I really need to know.
So, let's see.
Let's see the extra drawer by for Izzard.
Me, it's going in offset, the lower bounds of the wrecked, our
inclusive, the oppressor exclusive.
So it's not really telling me here.
I'm afraid.
So I guess I don't know what to do about that.
Exactly.
Because I need this to specify.
What it wants those coordinates in.
Maybe.
If I'm lucky.
It will specify.
So let's take a look.
Here is the original one from Nvidia.
It looks like
And let's see.
Transfers, a rectangle fixed values from one region of the read favor
of to others the driver.
But wise or just goes with the pics.
Of course around these buffers or capri pants.
First rectangle Bound by the locations.
This is about the lower bounds inclusive because transfer advisor
your, the read the actual region.
This is exact same text.
So I guess I'm just going to assume that the viewport is not in there
but I really just don't know, it's not being straightforward about
whether or not it would be in window coordinates or view coordinates
or what so I don't know.
So I'm going to assume that it's this and it looks like these are not
These are not in width height terms with width width and height terms.
So, what I really want here is, you know, when I'm doing this, the
drawer region,
Max X in the drawer region.
Max.
Why are actually what we're looking for here?
And then finally, it looks like we've got to get all of these together
from the opengl core ARB list and query them, right?
So let's go ahead and get that core arm header
and we need,
Those two.
So we now need to put these into wiggle.
Our calls to get the stuff from wiggle can see here.
That we've got the other frame buffer calls.
So I'll just go ahead and stick it on there.
Oops.
That's missing the back half.
There we go.
And so I'll go ahead and make this GL blitt frame buffer, there's the
coat, the call Signature.
When you type def for it.
And then we just need the global variable.
So, in order to get this, now we have to go actually ask for it,
right?
At this point, we pretty much need all these.
So what we really can change this into it.
Some point is just something that actually just requires this and
won't start the game without it.
Because pretty much there's not going to be a way to run open gel on
this without multi-sample since we've decided that that's basically a
requirement.
So, if you want to use cards from more than a decade ago, you can't
with handmade hero unless someone wants to write a different render, a
back-end, which
Good.
But we're not going to support that natively.
So at that point it looks like we're pretty good to go, we compile.
All right.
Now whether or not anything works or not, we don't know.
Oops.
So we got to kind of go over here and take a look.
Make sure actually calling this
What's going on here?
Oh,
Wait a minute, Max frame.
Buffer texture.
The that was kind of dumb.
We always have zero is actually a valid one, and so that's actually
not necessary at all.
That's going to prevent that code from Ever Getting called, which is
not what we want.
So actually, this is just always okay because there always is a zero
with one in every case and we actually want the zero of 1, all right?
oh my
well, it looks like that worked better than I thought it was going to
work and presumably.
We now just need to create some depth buffers to attach to our
textures.
That's that's great.
I was not expecting that to just work.
But it looks like it just did.
All right.
So now all we have to do is re-enable, our z-buffer, I mean, our Z
buffer is enabled, but it doesn't actually do anything.
Why doesn't do anything?
Well, it doesn't do anything because we have no, actual
Depth, buffer attached.
So this is the thing.
Again, you have to remember what we're doing here when we create these
textures, right?
We're creating textures that we're going to render into and those
textures have to act just like a frame buffer would when the graphics
card or I should say when wiggle automatically sets up a back buffer
for us when we asked to open the opengl window, it's going to have the
stuff we ask for so it's going to have a depth buffer it's going to
have a stencil buffer it's going to have a color buffer whatever
right?
All those things will actually be there.
We, if we want to use those buffers ourselves, we need to set them up
ourselves when we render to a texture.
So we've set up a color buffer, that's what we're doing with this call
but we have not created a depth buffer.
So we do need to create a depth buffer and attach it.
So you can see that happening here, you can see that we've got this
Frame buffer texture 2D call and you can see that it goes.
Okay, Jill frame, buffer GL color attachment zero.
What we need to do is create a depth attachment.
Just to create a texture that will hold the Z buffer, right?
The depth buffer to go along with our color buffer.
So, right now, our Z buffer is essentially disabled because when we
set the render Target to be targeting our texture, it no longer has a
depth buffer attached.
So depth is not used.
So, again, slot, in this case, we will need to sort of redo the same
logic appear effectively.
So we'll need to bind, you know, I need to do a thing like this here.
I guess in order to do that,
Because I believe it has to be bound.
Wait a minute.
So I guess it doesn't have to be bound.
So we don't need to do that.
I guess, I guess we can just say death texture handle here, right?
And be done with it.
I don't know, I don't remember what this last parameter here is, let
me just double check what it is.
So, that is GL.
It's the level.
So that's just the map level.
We're drawing to which in this case again is 0.
We are not using it maps in the rendering here at all so that all
looks reasonable as far as I can tell.
So all we need to do is create one of these depth texture handles.
So, what I might do is say, let's create GL text handle glue in here,
let's just do Tech sandal to and then we'll just say let's jet.
Of us, two of these Tech sandals.
Then we'll bind the first one.
This doesn't need to be here.
Will bind the first one?
We will create what we wanted to create here with it, and then will
bind the second one?
and the second one,
We just have to again do creation of a depth buffer that has the same
layout, basically as our color buffer that can you know, match up with
it, right?
So pretty much this should all be the same except we need to pass a
different value for what it's actually storing.
Okay, so here's that function and everything else should basically be
the same.
But again this internal format here needs to be something different.
So the internal format is going to be and unfortunately, this doesn't
list them.
It looks like so probably will just have to go to jail, text, image 2D
and get them or I don't know where it might list them in here.
Let's see.
No.
So can I search for your GPA?
Ma'am.
Well,
I believe that we can just use because I happen to know that there is
a depth format, we just need to find out what its identifier was.
I just need you to tell me the identifier for the depth.
Let's see here, opengl internal texture format list.
So this is sort of what we're looking for, but not quite.
Here we go.
Depth component, 16, 24, 32 and 32 F.
So
at this point, we kind of have
a decision to make what kind of debt buffering.
Want to do, do we want a 32 bit depth, buffer to on a 16 bit depth
buffer?
Obviously a 16 bit depth buffer and a 32 bit depth, buffer differ, in
that a 32-bit, death pepper has more Precision, right?
And so if we use a 32 bit depth, buffer, we will have less z-fighting
in cases, where we might have z-fighting, which might be nice.
On the other hand, it would be twice as large twice as large means
half as fast.
Usually, because it means that the graphics card has to use more
memory bandwidth fetching the depth components.
And the, if they are twice as big
Then it will be twice as slow doing that, right?
It just takes more memory now if you're not memory bound that won't
make a difference but if you are maybe it does.
I don't know which of the two to pick up front.
Fortunately, it's pretty easy to switch between so I guess let's start
with the easier one, which is 32 F, because that's a better one.
It's going to be the highest quality one and the easiest to use and
then will regress down to depth component.
16, if we find that it's a speed win to do.
So at some point for us that we care about
So let's try that and let's take it to do in there that says to do
check if going with a 16-bit depth buffer would be faster.
Because our game doesn't have long draw distances.
So we can, you know, it should we don't have long draw distances,
right?
We should be able to, I would think get what we need out of a 16 bit
depth buffer.
So, you know, we'll see.
So if we create one of these multi sample doodads here for the depth
buffer,
Then we can bind both our texture handles here.
1 and 2 to get both the color and the depth set up for this Frame
buffer at which point we should be able to render into it with the
z-buffer.
Again, I believe that's all we would really have to do.
Let's take a look here, that should be address of texture handles.
Global frame.
Buffer textures, that wants to be text handle zero.
Not that it matters.
And so we really just need the depth attachment and depth component
from core arp.
Those are those depth components right there.
And then we need Geo depth attachment.
And that should be everything.
Now, because we're switching to using our own textures for rendering
here exclusively and that's looking pretty good, right?
That's exactly what we wanted to see.
Now, we've got a depth buffer and we've got multi sample anti-aliasing
there and you can also see that a number of other things are working
properly.
Now, you can notice we get in, we've that Alpha to coverage has solved
the problem that
I was suggesting it would solve, which is to say that it is correctly.
Kind of doing this this edging.
We're now we're no longer getting those Edge artifacts.
We still do have the problem with things laying laying down to Flat,
which we need to solve, like I said, by potentially just messing with
it in the Shader as opposed to doing it geometry wise, which I think
might just be more computation work than it's worth.
But otherwise, we have the render working exactly.
Like we want it to
Except well except for tooth two things.
So one is we are colors are wrong, right?
Because we, since we couldn't specify a srgb, like we wanted to
remember this problem over here.
So
We jump down there.
So remember this this problem, right?
Opengl default internal texture format, remember that
Needs to be on.
And at the moment, we can't seem to get that to work, right?
We get a GL error.
Third shell set error.
How do I clear it?
I just want to confirm that nothing renders cuz I'm assuming that that
error also means that nothing renders
If I get it, will it automatically clear it?
Yeah.
So I guess all I really need to do here.
Is step over these.
So, they're sitting next statement.
Sending statement.
Yeah, so you can just see
This is interesting.
New frame.
Buffer, count equals commands Max rendered.
This is busted.
So new frame buffer.
Count equals commands.
Max better texture.
Max render Target is plus 1 and
We are going up to and including that one, which is not correct.
In fact, I don't know why.
Yeah, I don't know why we're doing it that way at all.
The new count.
Yeah, this is just this is just nonsense.
So we're creating one more render buffer than we need.
Because that Loop is incorrect, right?
This should just say that.
And furthermore, we could just do it like this.
And then it's just using the Direct Value directly with seems better
to me.
All right, let's try that one more time.
Again, I'm going to skip over these assertions here and I just want to
confirm that.
We don't render because we shouldn't, but I want to make sure
Yeah, so as far as we know on this card, we are not able to set.
Srgb rendering on texture, it just doesn't work.
So we're going to need to figure out what to do about that.
Not the least of, which because I don't think that's true of pretty
much any graphics card in existence at today.
That anyone still using, you should pretty much always be able to do
that as far as I know.
So it's really kind of strange that we can't.
You know, 88 times over sampled multi sample anti-aliasing and, and,
you know, render targets and all this stuff and srgb is not supported
is weird.
So I'm not sure what's going on with that, but we can do a little bit
more clean up here even though we're getting most of the way through
the render setup stuff, we need to do
I am so stuffy it's allergy season here.
I was as far as I know, I'm just constantly blowing my nose.
Is disgusting.
Anyway, so what we need to do now is we need to actually clean up some
stuff from the win32 side that we didn't really actually need so
If you take a look at how this is working here, where we've got the
depth B ARB stuff happening, the death, B arm stuff, doesn't actually
need to happen anymore.
The red green blue, Alpha depth bit stuff.
Just doesn't really need to be there.
We used to be using it but we don't really need it.
The reason that we don't need it is because now the depth of B is not
used the frame buffer is deficits are not used.
We are only using
Depth buffer, from our actual from the textures that we create, that's
the only time we're using them.
So we're drawing exclusively detectors, those textures have Z buffers,
you know, we create z-buffer textures for the frame buffers that we're
using that are our texture frame buffers.
So we don't actually need to have the frame buffer itself have that
depth B.
So this is just a waste now and we can go ahead and get rid of it.
So I believe we can actually go back.
to the way we have this originally now, where we just sort of
Do this.
and now, we've got
This is just five again.
In addition to that, the other thing that I think we should be able to
do is srgb capable frame.
Buffers should now not be necessary either.
Because since we're not drawing directly to the frame buffer, I think
we could probably delete this code to write this is probably not
necessary.
If that makes sense.
Because if you think about what's happening, the srgb rendering is can
all happen in the texture.
Once we have the textures completely done, we in theory wouldn't need
to do that anymore.
Now, I'm going to leave it in there because it may be that the multi
sample resolve is still best done in linear space and maybe this will
force that to be true.
I don't know.
So I guess that might be premature and we'll just leave that in there
for now, but we do not need a depth buffer.
Like I said and you can see that the depth buffering is still working
just fine.
The reason for that is because we're using a depth buffer we made as a
texture and bound.
So that's all good.
Now, no real worries here, and the only things we need to worry about
now are again.
We've got to make a
We've got to go ahead and put some some work into looting a Shader so
that we can modify the Z values properly and we have to figure out how
we want to do that.
But then the other thing that we need to do is we need to fix our
Alpha shading on our Alpha tinting I guess you could say.
So let me talk a little bit about that.
Now the reason we did the multi sample was specifically so we could
get the edges of Sprites to work properly.
And you can see, they are now working properly, and that's good.
We don't get any of that weird fringing anymore.
We don't get the weird depth mismatch stuff anymore.
So that's all good.
And so, in fact, the only thing we need to do really, to finish our
Sprite rendering is to have the those tweaked Z values in order to
make sure that things work properly there.
But
As you can kind of see, I don't know.
It might be that the video quality is not good enough.
When it's streamed to really see this.
I can see it on my machine, you may not be able to see it on yours and
I apologize for that.
But if you ran the game at home, you'd see it.
The fade levels of these Sprites that used to fade out.
Smoothly are now fading out in like jerk in a jerky motion.
In color space, they're still moving around the screen, just
financially, but there's this kind of stair-steppy kind of Fade Out
effect.
And what's that coming from?
Well, that's coming from the fact that we have told the game now that
all the alpha that's being used, is Alpha 2 coverage, right?
So that means that the only thing that's going to happen.
If we set a Sprites Alpha value lower, is this going to fill less
samples in the multi sample?
Buffer since the multi sample buffer only has eight samples that
Means that no matter how much range our Alpha has, we will only ever
see 8 steps worth from Full opaque to translucent.
Sorry transparent fully transparent.
So, not good, right?
That is not what we want.
We want the alpha coming from our texture.
To have that be the case.
We don't want the alpha.
Coming as from our tent for that to be the case.
So that is definitely an issue but I'm not sure if it's an issue we
can address in the fixed function pipeline or not.
That's a really good question and I am not sure I really don't know.
It might be.
Oh,
while we're at it, we should probably check our cutscenes.
Hm.
All right, so our cutscenes.
Have a couple problems one.
Looks like we change the projection.
Sort of blow up values a little bit in a way that we're going to have
to fix but otherwise it looks okay, besides the srgb problem, right?
You can see that all the colors are too dark and that's obviously just
because the srgb rendering isn't enabled and we don't really know how
to enable it on this machine.
We need to figure out why that's happening.
I'm not sure why that's happening because in theory, it should just be
It should just be working when we specify that value.
So again, not really sure what's going on there, but you know what you
gonna do.
So we'll take a look at that a little bit later, but
What I was saying before is, we need to take a look at what we can do
with those Alpha values and, and, and we'll see what's going on.
So, what's what's actually happening in this opengl pipeline?
Now, with the way think we've got things, let's just take a quick
second to review, because we've done a lot of work here to set up our
rendering.
And we've got some fairly complicated stuff happening in there.
So let's just recap, I mean, certainly not complicated compared to a
modern full.
3D rendering system, which does even more ridiculous Shenanigans.
But in terms of handmade hero where we have always done software
ending and now we're just doing, we're starting to do more Hardware
rendering stuff.
It's probably a little bit unfamiliar to a lot of people, so, let's
just quickly recap what's going on here.
So remember, we've got a screen buffer, right?
This is our back buffer here.
We have our back buffer and this back buffer at the moment is just
color.
It's just our G.
It's just an srgb.
A 8 Bit And I'm going to put question mark here because we're not even
specifying that.
So who knows how many bits it is.
The operation is actually free to pick any depth at once.
So as an srgb, a 8-bit frame buffer, that's our back bumper.
We never draw to this directly ever.
We used to now, we don't.
So we got an output stuff to this.
Where does it come from?
Where it comes?
From a texture.
That we created.
Right.
It's an srgb.
8-bit texture.
That's how we create it and it's at the moment 8x.
Say now we, we allow in the code, anything up to 16 x Ms.
A on this particular card if that's so maybe what I should say is some
amount msaa.
What that means is in this texture, right?
If I was to take a single Pixel in the same place on both of these
actually, this one has one sample.
And this one has in our case eight, right?
So what that means is during the blip frame buffer call
Right?
GL, B frame buffer.
These eight samples in this texture are getting smushed down to one
sample in the output.
So that's the aunt that anti-aliasing, step right?
So this is a frame buffer texture, we're using here.
Furthermore, stacked with that.
These are sort of together in use is a 32-bit float.
Depth buffer.
and it also,
Has that msaa?
Right.
Now this does never get split to a back buffer.
Anything it's strictly used essentially as a temporary buffer during
rendering to do depth sorting right?
It's per pixel or per sample, in this case except sorting
Now when we actually render, we are rendering to these buffers.
So we render to these, right, here's our render.
Render to these that only at the end, does the jail but flame before,
take the data out of the color buffer, this gets thrown away.
No one cares about what it is.
We take, whatever we render to there and we put it to the screen doing
that 821 down sampling, that produces the sort of smooth anti-aliased
values as a result.
Okay, so here's our render step.
What is our render?
Step doing well, what our render step is doing is our render step is
taking
Our Sprite textures.
And up, Sprite texture has a particular pixel value, it's one sample,
right?
And I guess more, more accurately since we have bilinear filtering on,
really what's happening?
Is this taking four samples?
Smashing those down to one, right?
So it produces one sample by averaging these together with certain
rule with a bilinear filter, right?
We end up with one sample from our texture, so we have one Sprite
sample.
we're left with and then we also have a you know, color
Right?
So both of these have Alpha values in them, there's an alpha here and
there's an alpha here and those two alpha values.
We actually want to different things to happen with these two alpha
values and that's the confusing part of this, right?
So, what we want to have happen is Alpha from this.
Right?
We would want to, well, I guess not, wait a minute.
Let me not say that quite right.
Let me not say that quite yet.
I just realized that actually, if we want things to fade out, they
would have to be drawn in a fading pass anyway so that's probably dumb
that I'm even talking about this.
It's good that I did this diagram because it's good to have any way
but now I think about it there's really no way we could deal with that
in any other way for the fading out Miss of it.
Yeah, never mind, I take it all back.
So
If we take a look at what's happening here, we've got these two alpha
values.
They have to combine together and I was going to say we want to use
wonder if the other the only way we can really use a more transparent
to get more transparent steps, there is to draw transparent object in
a separate pass.
That doesn't rely on the multi sampling.
So at the moment, I don't know that we have really any other thing we
can do better than that.
Which yeah, in this case, I think we just have to
Live with that.
So I believe that's all correct.
So we've got the Sprite sample.
We've got the color.
We combine those two and we produce the rendered pixels that go and
operate on our depth buffer and our famous right now.
So that's all good.
I think we're all good.
So I think the only thing we have left to do is really to cheat those
Z values, so that the Z values that were using in the z-buffer are
going to be exaggerated.
Now, I'm not sure if we can do that without a Shader or not.
I think about it.
It may be possible to do so.
But I doubt it.
So we'll take a look, I think.
That we could do certain things with it.
But not others.
so,
let's take a look at the moment.
Let's say here's our camera.
It's looking down to seeing this way.
Here's to like stair-step pieces of ground.
And here's a tree.
For obvious reasons, we want the tree to be camera facing because we
want it to show up properly, right?
We want it to show up.
Such that it appears to be a rectangular Sprite aligned with the
screen.
So, here's the plane.
That it's going to be him right now.
Our problem is that we want it to really look more like this.
And the reason that we want to look more like that is because we want
it to occlude things behind it as if it were standing up kind of
rather straight, right?
And it's always a kind of a bit of a you know, a it's definitely
trickery because we don't have 3D geometry, we're making up some
Fanciful.
Three geometry that we hope will do sort of what a Sprite, what a
Sprites image implies, it would do if it was in 3D, right?
But we don't actually have full 3d geometry, which is what we would
need to always produce a correct seen.
So we're just guessing here but we know that we can do something a lot
better than that.
So you want it to appear as if it's doing this, which means the
fundamentally speaking, what we want to do is adjust the Z values for
the Z buffer, so that the things in here as we go, the Z values are
actually, even though this is the XY is reproducing, the Z values are
actually
We produced as if we were on this plane.
Right.
That's what we actually want to do.
And so, all we really need for this purpose, is essentially a z bias
value that's associated with these vertex positions as they come in.
And like I said, in a Shader, this would be very easy to do, which is
why I would think we should do it that way rather than try to do a
bunch of weird math trickery that we don't really need to do.
So what?
I would propose is say like okay you know we've got an XYZ that we're
passing down for each of these points.
Let's just also pass down a z bias value, and the Z bias value is just
something that when you're actually producing the depth component of
this thing.
Let's actually make sure that depth component is offset by whatever
the Z bias value should be right?
So we can just set that Z bias value there to be whatever we want.
And therefore, pretend that the thing is standing up like this, even
though it's not, right, and then we still get all the same rest of the
stuff exactly what we want with, you know, with perspective and
everything sits in the scene properly.
But we just need this
We'd essentially send down for coordinates instead of three for every
vertex, which is no big deal.
We're not going to be vertex throughput Bound.
In this game.
I assure you at least not on any modern card.
So that seems very nice and then all we do is in our computation of
where these vertices are.
We do exactly the same transform we're doing now.
Where we just do p, Prime equals, you know, AP this is that sort of
composite Matrix that we've been making.
We do exactly this but at the end at this P Prime, after it's done all
were saying is that that P Prime Z coordinate, right?
Is going to have that Z bias.
Per vertex added in.
So the only difference between this and what we're doing is that we'll
have a pervert x z offset.
So you could think of you know, when we've got our matrices here,
Right?
And we sort of have if you if you look at what's in here, you know,
we've got our x-axis here.
And here's the translation.
Right?
This is how we were doing object placement, right?
We have the x axis Y, axis, Z axis, and then the translation was in
here.
And the problem with this, is that this is fixed for everybody who for
all the vertices that go through the system.
When we set one of these camera transforms up,
This Matrix, which we multiplied by the projection Matrix to get our
final Matrix, only has one Z offset.
Right?
The the Z offset value is only going to be applied, is going to be
applied to all vertices uniformly.
So I can't offset.
These vertices differently from these vertices.
There's no way to do so, right?
So all I'm saying,
We just need something which is doing effectively the same thing.
It just incrementing a z value.
What just like the Matrix is doing after the fact.
We've got that.
We just don't have a way to do it per vertex and so that's all I
really want.
And like I said, the easiest way to do that would be with shaders.
Unfortunately, that's a pretty huge step.
We have to take because now we have to have those shaders and we have
to, you know, implement the Shader loading code and all that sort of
stuff.
So I'm guessing what I should probably do because we've got an hour
left, is just show how to get that process started.
And then next weekend, we'll just be
Shader weekend where we go through, how they work and how to write
them, because that's sort of a topic that will require me to do a lot
of explanation that we don't have time to do today.
So let's just go ahead and do some preparation work for that as we go
and we'll go from there.
So, if I say first of all, know that I'm going to need to send down an
additional coordinate, in addition, to what, I'm already sending down
for things.
Like these bitmaps that are coming through.
Then I know that I need to upgrade in my render entry bitmap.
This this p-value here, and these X Y axes and that sort of stuff.
This stuff now needs to be extended a little bit, right?
And you know it depends on how we want to do it but you know for the
for the moment we could just use a single Z bias value that's going to
go in there and later we could sort of look
It making that a little bit more General.
But, you know, essentially we only really need one for the moment and
that's the bias if we went into handmade opengl, right?
You can imagine this here where we're doing.
There's our cubes when we're doing our bit maps you can see here.
We sort of got our vertex 3fv stuff happening.
Instead what you could imagine is, all right.
The lower triangle upper triangle system that we're doing here where
we're starting with menu, V and Min.
Y here we would say that it's actually going to be a V4 in all cases.
Right.
And when we produce this V4,
We're always going to start with a V 3.
But we're going to include the Ziva bias or not.
Depending on which one it is.
So in Max why we would include the Z bias.
But in men wise, we wouldn't.
And again, that's just to create that exact shape that I was just
talking about.
Right.
And so there's our Z bias.
And this just allows us to send v4s down, right?
And those v4s are going to have that see bias in there.
Now, the problem with this is that this will immediately cause or
should cause kind of disastrous results and you can see why that's an
uninitialized value obviously, but that's not really the reason why
it's going to be a disaster.
The reason it's going to be a disaster is because right now without
the shaders,
This GL Vertex, 4 V is actually setting the W coordinate of the
vectors that are going to get transformed right now.
We know that it's a z bias value.
We know this not supposed to be the W coordinate that's used in the
vector transform.
But opengl doesn't know that yet because we haven't loaded a Shader,
that tells it how to operate on incoming vertex values.
So it just sees a value.
That's the fourth value of the vertex that goes up.
Oh, it's trying to tell me how to set the W coordinate.
I should set the W coordinate and multiply that through the Matrix.
That's exactly not what we want to do here.
So that is an expected, erroneous Behavior, that'll won't get fixed
until the shaders are written.
So now in our push bitmap call,
When we, when we do push bitmap and we're setting that entry p-value
here.
We want that to be set to that Z bias to be set here.
And at the moment, we can just set it to 0 0, and then that'll be
fine, right?
Because that will restore.
Sort of, you know, some functionality to
Guess that won't know.
I think about it.
The Z value.
The the W coordinate has to be one in these cases so I guess there
really is no way for me to restore this Behavior.
Now that I think about it, we can restore the value of behavior for
two of the points.
Her right.
But not the other one which kind of produces a rather amusing effect.
I suppose as everybody gets sort of sucked out into infinity and
beyond their yeah.
So I can't reproduce.
That I guess at the moment.
So we'll have to actually just do something reasonably Ur.
So Okay, so for our push bitmap, call the Z bias in this case is going
to be proportional to the height, right?
So I'm just going to say for now, it's going to be some value
proportional to the height.
We don't know what that value is going to be yet.
But you know, we'll have to tune that based on how much we want our
Sprites to sort of be upstanding, that's what we need.
And that's all we need.
That's the complete modification that would have to happen in order
for our Sprites to properly.
Now be set up for the Shader to actually work with them.
Again, unfortunately we don't have a Shader yet, so that's the next
part that we would have to tackle.
Now, in order to tackle that we're going to have to load a bunch of
stuff in here and do a bunch of ridiculous Shenanigans, because the
Shader stuff.
With gpus, you just have to appreciate the fact that they were sort of
designed by committee and designed over a long period of time
incrementally, where no one really knew what they were going to be
doing at the end.
The Shader stuff is incredibly incredibly ugly.
It Doesn't Matter What GPU API you use.
You can use DirectX 11, or 12, or Vulcan, or metal, or opengl or
Of the other alphabet soup of ways of talking with them.
Shaders are always just this really, really broken half abstraction of
stuff and it's it's just ugly.
So you just kind of have to grit and grit your teeth and Empower
through.
There's nothing I can say other than it's a mess, it's why I didn't
really want to do them on handmade hero.
But because we
Guided to try to go a little further down the 3D path and actually get
z-buffering in the game.
I'm afraid that I have to show you how to do this.
And so, here we go.
So I won't talk about the the Shader stuff in particular today or how
it works, because that will be saved for next weekend.
So, again, all I'm doing is trying to do some groundwork here, so that
we won't have as much busy work to do next weekend.
So, basically, all I want to do is get our opengl
Platform layer to the point where it can execute Shader code rather
than executing the fixed function pipeline, that's all we want to do.
So, in order to do this, we need to start thinking in terms of
programs and here on Doc's that GL wherever that was, let's see here.
Here on Doc's dot DL.
We need to start learning about things like bind program and let's
see, compile Shader these sorts of things.
Alright.
So and Link and all that other good stuff.
So let's do these up here.
You're going to need to yell uniform.
and,
I'm not sure what else we're going to need, I have to remember as we
go, but
I guess, is it text?
There's one more till Shader Source, that's what I'm looking for.
All right.
Okay.
So let's start by talking about how opengl does this stuff, and again,
I'm going to skip the Shader part because that's a good thing to kind
of cover as a unit.
So we'll cover how to actually, write one next weekend.
I'm just trying to get the opengl code in place to actually load them,
right?
So the first thing that we need to be able to do if we're going to
create shaders in opengl is we need to be able to specify the Shader
code to opengl now.
Opengl unlike its
Sort of some of the other like DirectX.
For example, it doesn't deal in terms of an assembly language for
shaders.
Instead, it deals in terms of actual just straight source code.
Now, it doesn't have to deal with source code because you can also do
things like ask it to compile a program down to Binary and save the
binary, which you can then re feed it later.
But you always have to be able to fall back to Source because
compiling a binary.
The the binary code will be specific to the
GPU you compile it on.
So, on a particular machine, if you know if Shader compilation, if you
want to get that out of your pipeline because maybe you have thousands
of shaders and you want them all pre-compiled or who knows what on any
particular install on a particular GPU, you can ask opengl to take
Shader source, code, compile it to Binary and then use the binary
from.
Now on, you can do that at the GPU and Driver, don't change.
But you always have to be able to fall back to the Shader source code
because if you can't go back to your source code anytime,
There's a new GPU or a new driver update that might need to recompile
it needs the source code again.
So the fundamental the primary way that shaders are shipped in opengl
is as Source.
Not as an intermediate language in DirectX, that's not the case.
Typically shaders are compiled down to a sort of Assembly Language
like thing.
It's not actually the Assembly Language for the card, it's an
intermediate Assembly Language and then that intermediate something
language does get compiled by the card into binary.
You later.
Then there's also a thing called SPI RV, which is that right?
Fit program, intermediate.
Representation V.
Yeah, I don't know what the v stands for 15.
I don't know.
So there is another thing called strv that Vulcan uses which is sort
of the opengl version of an intermediate representation, that's more
like an assembly language.
That is an Assembly Language might be the wrong term there, but it's
you know, it's an intermediate rep, not the source code that is also I
believe getting back ported to opengl now so that you can use it in
opengl.
Well, as Vulcan as Intermediate Language.
So,
There's a whole mess of that sort of stuff happening, but as far as
we're concerned because we don't have to worry too much about most of
that, since we are only going to have a very small number of shaders,
it's not really an issue for us.
We are always going to be dealing with just text.
That is the actual see, like code that shaders used to describe what
they want to do in source.
So the first thing we need to be able to do is take that source and
turn it into some actual usable Shader in open that opengl can use and
GL shaders.
Source is the called that does that.
So if I want to do that in opengl, I need I'm just going to start by
making a little scratch space here where we can put this stuff in.
Maybe I'll put it up here in the top.
We got Oak.
Get impo, get screen.
Space or set screen space.
Why is that still here?
Nobody knows.
All right, that's always good.
Jill bind frame buffer.
All right, anyway, so what we need to do here is we need to have
something that's actually going to compile these shaders, right?
And so, what I need to do is I need to have
Something that's going to call GL shaders Source.
Like you can see here and it's going to have to pass and things.
One is the Shader right?
And it's the handle of the Shader object which whose source code is to
be replaced.
And so much like textures, there's this this notion of sort of handles
and you can see here that I'm going to need to make one of those in
order to do this.
So there's a corresponding called GL, create Shader.
And you can see there's the Glu in there, which is the Shader, and I'm
going to call this vertex Shader.
No caller ID.
When we create a Shader, we say what type we want.
In this case, I want to jail vertex Shader.
I'm going to specify this Shader source code.
Here.
And what you can see, there's kind of an odd way that this is
specified, but you'll understand in a second.
Why?
So the GL shaders Source?
What it does is, it says, okay.
Here is a not a string that says the source code, but a series of
strings.
So there's actually an array of strings with a length of each one.
And that says, for each, that that says, for each of those strings,
take the strings.
Concatenate, all these together and process them like one big source
file.
Right?
And what's that for?
Well, it's basically, for include right, it basically, it's a cheap
way to do includes without you having to do it yourself.
So, in here, I can say, okay,
We've got serious source code, maybe I want to things.
And so what I want here is my vertex Shader array and maybe I could do
this, you know, array count vertex, Shader code,
It's shooter code and four digit code length.
So here is an example of how this would be called, and then we just
need something to fill it.
And so you can see we got a GL care, which is vertex Shader code and I
have to provide pointers here, right?
And then I've got GL in t, which is vertex Shader code lengths.
And then here, what I want to do is take
These guys, right?
And do a string length on them.
I need to know how long they are.
Okay, at least I assume so I don't know if you can pass.
Z is 0 here, you might be able to each of the link that we may
continue the length of the corresponding string.
The null characters archives or a value less than zero to indicate
that the string is null terminated.
So we could just specify - ones here as well.
looks like,
And so, in that case two, we could just do this.
This is going to be the same everywhere.
And we can just pad this out.
So even if we did more source code or something, right?
We'd be fine.
Okay, so now we have a way of creating Shader source code feeding it
down for the vertex Shader and I want to create two shaders.
I want a Vertex Shader and I want a fragment Shader, those correspond
to how we transform vertices and how we shade pixels, how we like
compute the color of pixels.
And like I said, I'll explain all this next week in terms of when we
actually want to write some shaders.
So for the moment, we won't have to worry too much about
That but off, we go here.
With our fragment Shader code in a Vertex Shader code, right?
So now what I want to do is I want to make this function.
Right.
What I want to do is I want to have a way to create programs that
opengl is going to use to do our Graphics pipeline processing and we
need to be able to specify how to deal with vertices.
That's a Vertex Shader part it how to deal with pixels.
That's a fragment Shader part.
and so here, I'm just going to say like, you know, opengl
A great program.
I'm going to say that.
Whoever wants to create one of these programs.
It will probably return something in a second here like like one of
these IDs.
So it's probably going to return, you know, Jewel, you enter,
whatever.
When it creates a program, I want to be able to pass a couple things.
First of all, I want one care star that is going to be my vertex
Shader code.
I want my fragment Shader.
Right.
And then I also want to share it header.
Let's say.
Like that, then what I'm going to do is going to put the header code
in here.
The vertex code.
The header code and the fragment code, right?
And so you can see what I'm doing here is.
I'm just using the fact that we can pass multiple strings to allow
whoever's creating the program to pass some shared code that will be
used by both and then the code, the specifics to the vertex Shader and
the code.
This is there to the fragment Shader, right?
And again that's just using the fact that opengl is nice and allows us
to pass an array of strings to prevent me from having to concatenate
these things together, right?
So I'm just kind of
Using that feature.
That's really all I'm doing.
So when I once I've done this and I've done my Shader Source, I now
have Shader IDs that have whatever code we passed in here compiled and
ready to go.
Well, not really compiled parsed and ready to go.
And so now, the question is, how do I actually bring them together
into a Shader?
Well, the answer is I do a GL, compiled Shader on the actual
individual Shader portions and then I
I have to link them together as a program in order to sort of bind the
vertex and fragment shaders together.
So I have to call GL.
Compile Shader this again does nothing other than tell it.
Ok, now you can kind of finalize this code that I sent down, so we'll
go fragment Shader ID.
Vertex Shader ID.
Right.
And then what we need to do is do that GLD program.
But as you can see, there's some steps missing here, we don't have a
program and we haven't told it how to associate these with the
program, right?
So now we need to go to a few of the other parts in here.
First of all, we need to do create program as you can see, that's
exactly the same as the.
It's exactly analogous to creating a Shader.
So here's Jill crate program.
And again, we don't need any parameters because a program is the whole
pipeline.
It's
Shaders come together to make a full pipeline.
So we don't need to tell it anything.
It's just a program and it has whatever it will have.
And then what we need to do is use this function called GL attached,
Shader to say, what the shaders are that constitute this pipeline.
So we say, GL attached,
Shader, we give it the program in the Shader.
So there's the program ID.
There's the fragment Shader ID.
Program, ID vertex, Shader ID.
Okay, so you can now see the full sort of sweep of creating a program
that opengl is going to use.
We assume like we're going to learn next weekend like I said how this
code actually works.
So we're just assuming that in here is some valid code.
We have some shared code that everyone's going to want to look at.
We have some vertex code that's going to be only for the vertex,
transform part of things.
So fragment code, that's only for the pixel part.
What we do is we create some just a buffer of negative ones because
we're not specify any links explicitly.
We're going to use null termination.
So that's just a just there for that.
We're going to create a Vertex Shader, so opengl understands there is
a vertex Shader.
We want to talk about.
We're going to pass down that code, the header code, the vertex code,
say here's the source code for it.
We're going to compile it and maybe we should compile it like this.
Right.
We're going to compile it.
We're going to fragment one same thing, compile that.
And then we're going to go ahead and make a program, which binds those
two shaders together and Link that program.
That is all we really need to do to create a functioning program and
opengl.
Then we can just spend all day filling in strings here that do
different things, right?
Just write arbitrary code.
They can be executed on the GPU.
So we need all of that stuff.
So we're going to have to go, grab all of those functions and get
them, right?
Because these are all functions that need to be bound via wiggle.
Get proc address just like everything else.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Let's go ahead up here.
And we have to go to core our band, get all of our stuff.
So we need Jill, create Shader.
Why are there six entries for this because creature bright?
Okay, so we need all these.
We need create program, we need compile Shader,
attach Shader.
I guess we need all of these actually.
all right, so we've got
Type desk.
Now,
and so here you can see
I don't know that we actually need find out of trouble location yet,
so I'm not going to put anything that we haven't actually called.
We are going to need some stuff for binding.
Attributes will see what that's like later but you can see here we've
got tabs, compiled, create, and those are all the ones we needed from
here, but we need link.
Right.
And we need Shader source.
Now I can't tell which one get shooter Source.
There we go.
We don't want get Shooters source and we're going to need Lincoln use
obviously as well.
So let's go ahead and get those
There we go.
okay, so I think we are now
Pretty good to go in terms of.
The basic stuff we need to get our compiling working.
There is one more thing we're going to need.
I think in a second here but we'll see.
All right.
It's not what I meant to do it all.
There we go.
Sorry zoned out there for a second, too much mindless text
manipulation.
Yeah.
so,
Looking at that you can see that we're starting to get a lot of things
here that we have to query.
And so, you know,
Obviously, in my own code, I have some automated stuff that kind of
generates these sorts of binding things for me.
And so it's kind of a pain in the butt when you're doing it manually,
you can also use there are like libraries like glue or whatever that
will do the querying for you if you want to.
But as you get into sort of trying to use extended opengl because it's
a little bit balkanized at this point, you kind of have to deal with
either using a library or doing this stuff yourself, unfortunately.
That's just how that goes.
Okay.
Actually, that was not what I wanted.
I think about it.
I actually want to retain this piece of information.
Because yeah, this is just kind of mindless and there's really no
point to it if that makes sense.
You can easily automate it.
Something that just parses those header files in generates, one of
these things
There we go.
But writing something like that on handmade here is not particularly
good use of time, because by the time we finished it, we could have
done them by hand, probably it shorter, right?
So depends whether you're trying to solve the problem long-term or
whether you only need a little bit.
So here is
The appropriate wiggle.
Get proc address stuff.
To get us all of the functions that we need to compile a program.
And fortunately, there's not that many more functions we actually need
because once we can compile programs, most of the the new stuff that
you need for shaders comes in the Shader which is just text your
passing to opengl and doesn't require any get proc address or anything
like that because you're just sticking the code in the Shader and off
it goes.
So that's pretty good, right?
What we do need to do, however, what is the problem?
Into sumed D, does not support, what missing types as far into sumed.
Where is the missing types of Safar?
Do not know GL sighs.
I perhaps we find out.
I don't know if it knows.
Jill, size, I or not, we just find out.
That's the problem.
So what don't you know?
Do you know g?
L care?
You know, Jill.
and,
How do you not know, Jill, Shader source.
What is the problem here?
I'm not sure what it's actually complaining about.
It would be really nice if this gave me a column for the error.
So I knew what it was actually complaining about to say the least.
missing comma before star, of course there isn't
Let me get rid of these constant here so I can see.
What it's actually talking about.
So you have G Ln, T GL care, GL sighs.
I and Glu in all of which I feel like should be valid
Gee L care.
So it doesn't know.
G.
L care.
That I would not have expected but I guess it doesn't.
Well.
That's pretty easy to rectify.
All right, you learn something new every day.
Okay?
So let's take a look here at GL stuff that we need here.
Create Shader is apparently not found why not create Shader 0 because
I called it create Shader.
Create Shader, sounds good because games always have crates in them.
So I feel like you do need a crate Shader.
Right?
That seems reasonable.
All right.
So we've got everything we just need the
Oops, we just need the pound.
Defiance for what a vertex, in a fragment Shader are, and then we're
done.
That's that's all we should need.
So let's see those in there.
So now we can compile code and of course that's not going to change
anything.
We still have our crazy W, coordinate being wrong there.
So now we just need to go into the opengl.
And actually give it some code to compile, right?
If I wanted to create a program I could now that would be pretty easy
to do.
So let's create some of these you know while we're at it here is our
opengl info here.
I'm not sure how we were setting up like our opengl default texture
stuff.
I'm not your fault internal, here you go.
So the way that we're doing this opengl default, internal texture
format thing.
It's sort of suggests to me that we maybe need to have a sort of
Global's for opengl so that they're a little bit more contained
because opengl default text internal format here and reserved blit
texture.
Those things I feel like now it's kind of at the point where we want
this stuff to be sort of bundled together, if that makes sense.
I feel like this stuff should just kind of come into, like, you know,
and opengl .h basically, as are we even including an open Gilded Age?
I guess, we don't yet.
But some kind of an opengl today, chair.
You go see where I want to make that.
and what I'll do here is just say, okay, here's an open Jill, that H
and this thing will have
an opengl levels.
Piece of information or I guess opengl.
We could just call it up in jail, just the stuff we need for opengl,
right?
And in here, I can stuff these guys.
And then I'll say, Global variable opengl opengl.
Something like that and I should it be open underscore.
Go.
Not really no.
Maybe.
and so,
I think that'll give me everything that I want here.
And then, every time we were using something like that, I'm going to
go ahead and put this way so you can kind of just see that those are
bundled together and I don't have them strewn all over the place, not
sure what's go below and what's not or anything like that, right?
Okay.
So now that we've got that taken care of all, I really need to do is
go into the opengl in it, call and try creating some shaders and we
can sort of start to work with that and get ourselves in position to
do it next next week.
Here we go.
So this open Jill and it should really be down kind of at the bottom.
We can start to move things into that Global as well which will be
nice.
So here's our opengl in it and we can pretend that the end of this
year, for example, that maybe we want to create some programs and
maybe we say that opengl we've got, you know, two programs or I guess
we probably just have
in this case,
For all of our rendering, we probably would have the default.
I mean, I guess what, maybe we'll just call it for now our Z bias
program,
Maybe basic Z bias.
And when we call up in jail, create program, what we need is the
header code, the vertex code in the fragment code, right?
And in this case, we can sort of just be kind of absurd here, if we
want to the header code.
Oops.
Unfortunately C++ only recently supported hear Doc's.
It would be really nice if they did but since they don't, you kind of
have to do it this way until you get to a version of a compiler that
actually supports here docs, which only the latest ones do.
But for now, we can sort of say, here's header code, right?
And we can do
Vertex code.
and fragment code,
Similarly, right.
So basically, this is a way to do.
Header code.
Vertex code.
Fragment code.
And actually have it all.
As far as I know work properly, we can sort of go in and take a look
at that.
Now
So now we have the ability to create a program.
We know how to pass the text down to it, right?
And so if I come down through here,
Hmm.
Ah, so when we do our in it, we haven't yet finished all of this
stuff.
I guess I misunderstood what we were doing in our in it there, so are
in it.
I'm not sure why is our in it happening before we query.
That seems really strange.
I think that's because of the way that opened you'll get info used to
be happening.
But I think that's not probably how we want it.
I would think what we probably want is opengl get info modern context
and then probably what we want to do is do this stuff here and then
come down and do this, right?
And the reserved lit texture stuff.
Should probably happen here and so on and so forth, right?
If we're looking if we're looking at what sort of going on here, so I
feel like we probably want something more like that.
and then,
you know, the opengl info would be getting passed down here like so,
Now, in the opengl info.
Where is that struct?
Is that appear?
Yeah, the opengl infrastructure.
I'm going to grab out, put it up here.
You can see that that already has the modern context piece of
information in it which means that it wouldn't have to pass it here.
And the frame buffer is supports srgb part of it as well, is also
something that it would presumably know.
Not sure exactly how that one should work.
So I'm going to go ahead and get rid of that.
And we should be good to go.
All right.
so, I think
I think now those would be initialized when we get to them and we
should be in good shape you can see here that we've gotten through
that compilation phase.
Okay.
And so now what we need to do we still got a little bit of time.
I still got about 15 minutes left.
So if we take a look at what we need to do, now we're just at the
point where we we can call, we can pass code down here whatever we
want, but if there was a problem, like when we call
Opengl cray program.
One of the things that we're going to find is we don't actually know
whether the compilation succeeds or fails yet, right?
We haven't checked any errors in here and furthermore if something did
fail, we're going to need to know what failed, right?
We're going to need to get have to get some kind of information back
from opengl.
That'll tell us how to debug, you know, like what's going on.
We're passing it.
Source code.
We could have a typo in the source code, we
You know, be calling something wrong and the compiler might fail.
We need to get errors back so that we're in a position to debug the
shaders as well.
And so it, there is ways we can get that information as well, and I
believe it's the program.
Info log in the Shader info log calls are the two places that that
happens if I remember properly.
So let's take a look at those.
You can see here.
What happens is it returns?
basically a text buffer, you give it a sort of a chunk of memory and
then it will fill out that chunk of memory with a with a
Textual description of what went wrong in the compilation.
If something went wrong in the compilation now, I don't actually know
I can't remember.
I might have to look up.
I don't quite remember what the best way is to.
Okay, here it is like there and I knew there was a way to validate the
program to make sure that it works.
And here we go.
So GL validate program.
So from after we call GL validate program, we can call get program
with arguments program and GL, validate status, and that will tell us
whether or not the validation occurred.
So what we want to do,
Here is we want to call that, right?
We want to call the jail validate program.
And it takes that program handle and then we want to call GL get
program.
Here's that we just now need to say, we want to know what the validate
status is of the program.
And that's the program than the the params is just the requested
object, so we just need a geoint.
Assume it's false on Startup.
Here's our program ID.
So this will tell us whether or not the program validated.
And so what we want to know now is if it didn't validate right then we
can call these other functions, right?
Not that one.
Oops.
Program, info log.
So the only thing that I'm not sure I remember is for the shaders.
I don't know if you can validate a Shader, I don't know how, you know,
whether or not the shaders validated individually.
Probably there is no point because shaders, you wouldn't really know
if they're valid.
I mean, you might know that they're obviously invalid but you don't
really know if they're fully valid till they all come together.
Anyway.
So I suspect what we want to do.
It's called get program.
Info, log in the case, for the program,
Got messed up, but we probably also need to get the Shader info log
and we probably need to do that in the cases.
Yeah.
In the case where we're not validated because I don't know that where
it will necessarily report the errors, right?
So what we want to do here is we want to create some way that we can
sort of get this information out.
So we're just
A Shader validation failed.
And then we'll just say, all right, we've got a Vertex error.
And then we'll just go ahead and get the logs for everything.
So for the Shader info logs, we need to press our vertex Shader ID.
And our fragment Shader ID.
And we're not going to bother with the length.
So there's that g l sighs.
I
And we're going to ignore that.
So, for the program itself,
Where's my program info log?
There it is.
Zack, same.
And so now in theory we should be able to get Hoops.
I did my internal caps on size of there.
So now we should be able to anytime opengl says that there was a
failure in validating the program that we passed it.
We should be able to get some air buffers back.
That'll tell us what happened.
Right?
And so again this is just an exercise in busywork now is to just cut
and paste those from the core arm.
Get program.
Info log.
Go.
Cedar info log.
Validates program.
And I think that's all the new things we're calling, right?
Get program.
So now that I think about it, we which one do we want here?
Get program IV for validate status
I assume it's yes.
So we want get program.
An integer Vector of integers.
So give me that one and I think we've got them all.
There we go.
Oops.
and,
Text busy work.
Okay, so that's all of the new ones here, just for new functions.
Those are get stuck at the bottom here.
There we go.
and,
I will actually carry them.
all right, so
we've got you'll get programming for log.
Shooter and full log.
Holiday Program.
Get program for.
So I think that should be all the functions we had.
Valid it satisfy, you'll have to copy, not sure that needs to be
there.
I meant to call that ignored.
And that is the wrong spelling for that.
So I think we're all good and then all I need is the GL validate
status.
And I assume that will be sufficient.
Okay.
So a lot of busy work there, but in theory, everything is now, okay.
So let's take a look vertex errors, fragment errors program airs,
So here's our compilation.
You can see that the vertex Shader was to compile it to run on
Hardware.
Fragment Shader was successfully compiled to run on Hardware.
and then here's our program errors really, shade has failed to link
Is fitting not all shares have valid object code?
So not particularly useful information in this case, of course, we
didn't actually feed it real code, right?
It's just some comments.
So everything compiled.
Okay.
But none of them have actual content.
So when it goes to link it's like hey I don't know what I should
actually do here, right.
But other than that,
It's all reasonable shape, right?
So we only have a couple of other things that we need to start talking
about, but otherwise we're pretty much good to go.
We will have to do is a GL, use program call and then we'll have to be
able to bind attributes to those as well.
So we have a little bit of work that we will have to do in in a, in a
moment.
But otherwise, we're pretty much done.
And so I'll go ahead and go to the Q&A and next week.
That we can talk about shaders and what they do so we can actually
write some Shader code and then we'll be able to finish that up and
actually start calling through the Shader.
Cam died, really.
Oh wow.
I've never seen that happen before.
Oh, the camera.
Did not die.
It looks like open OBS.
OBS is ability to composite the camera died.
Oh no, it was just it was set on the wrong looks like it was set on
monitor instead of programming for some reason.
All right, so nothing, nothing was actually wrong.
They're just somehow that got set to monitor.
So it's just the kid for some of the opengl function type test.
You have the win API entry point and others, don't I thought it was
necessary to have it or else you get runtime errors when calling those
functions or at least I did.
So actually, you never really need it in 64-bit code.
Where are those guys?
Those guys are over here.
I should probably keep it in there just to be nice but it's really not
necessary in 32-bit code because 32-bit code only has one calling
convention.
So, if you remember back in handmade here, when we talked about
calling conventions, essentially, if you're linking to a dll in 32-bit
code, you need to make sure you specify the calling convention.
we don't actually have to do that in 64-bit code, but if we ever
wanted to compile 32-bit code, we would have to
Really not necessary.
Otherwise I guess it's how I would say it.
So if you had problems with it, probably the reason you did was
because you're probably compiling 32-bit code.
We my guess.
The size that instead of Z bias, why not make the Sprite card, stand
up at a steeper angle and make them trapezoidal to under the
protective foreshortening.
So if you remember correctly, I did the math for that on a previous
dreaming that is what I was going to do but then I realized why would
we spend the time doing the math for that when we could just change
the Z value in a Vertex Shader?
Basically we would be spending way more math time.
We would be doing way more operations per Sprite, then we needed to do
for know.
Reason because all the only reason we'd be solving for the correct,
trapezoid in that case, is to change the Z value.
So, it seems like a really bad use of compute power there.
And so I decided to just go ahead and have shaders that just you feed
a difference e value because that's all we really need.
And then there's no extra computation being done.
So it's much more efficient.
Binbin L.
When you started writing the place placeholder Shader code.
You mentioned something about C++?
Something docks that are not yet fully implemented.
What is this feature?
Exactly.
So I honestly don't know who coined this term.
It's weird and I apologize.
It's just it's the term that's used.
And yeah I got nothing.
I do not know why it's called this.
I guess it's because hey the document is here, I don't know.
But anyway, a here document is what they call it a here.
Doc
is when you've got source code for some language and then you want to
stick a bunch of source code for another language or something that is
not in that language in between right.
And so what it is is it's a way of saying hey I'm going to start a
bunch of text here.
This text is not supposed to be parsed by you.
So don't do your standard pricing on it, just read it all and accept
it as some data that you're going to use later.
And so C plus plus, sort of, has a little bit of of a here, Doc, in a
way originally, right?
It grabbed, are we doing that?
So C++ sort of has a little bit of a constant over here.
Doc, which is a string, right?
An Ask easy string is sort of like it, but it's not really complete
here.
Doc, and the reason is because all sorts of parsing still happens in
here, right?
That happens parsing for that happens.
Quote happens, I can't have a new line, right?
And so the degree to, which a language.
It's here doc says sort of more about the degree to which you can
embed other document structure other sort of data in there that and to
what extent you can turn the parser off.
So in the future C++ may be able to properly support here docks
because it's in the spec and like llvm supports it.
I think maybe visual Studios supports it in 20.
I don't know if it's present wife.
Jean.
But at some point, all the C compilers you care about will be
supporting this because it's in the spec now.
But at the moment, like I think I'm on 2013, I believe, for this
stream, we use the community edition of 2013.
That's what we started with.
And that everyone had its, I don't believe has it, so we can't use it.
Let's see.
Two.
Do you think the Google's angle library that translates opengl to
DirectX calls would solve the srgb problem on your graphics card?
It might.
I do not know it might be, but it depends on whether this card
properly, supports srgb, rendering to msaa in DirectX.
I don't it might be that this, for whatever reason, the driver just
kind of busted and won't work.
I don't know.
Why are you downsizing 8 pixels into one using a blit and not using
32-bit math and rendering six back into two with a subtract to
finalize, 8 to pass out of 8-bit back to render allows Alpha on off
values and color, value attached, AC instead of color value where
Alpha belongs in blit.
I'm not sure.
I understand what you're asking.
We're not downsizing eight pixels.
We're just we're using multi sample.
Which is to say that the the there's eight samples per pixel taken to
allow us to do order independent Alfred edges.
If that makes sense.
Insofar says you can pass.
Null has the length for a GL shaders source and it treats all the
strings is null terminated.
I was hoping that would be the case, but it didn't say that in the
docks, if that's the case.
Then we can get rid of this, which would be nice.
Because there's no point to it.
I just didn't see anything in the in the docks that said that, that
would be okay.
So I assumed it wasn't.
Okay.
Whoops.
All right.
Just double-check that, that works.
Frosty ninja.
Can't we just adjust, can't we just adjust gamma in the shaders?
We could but it's typically faster not to do that because the hardware
has built-in look-up tables for it usually or at least.
That was my understanding in various places.
Now that may not be true anymore, I don't know.
And we could but in general we should be allowing the gravis card to
use whatever its fastest method is rather than micro coding it
essentially for in the Shader
So, I'd like to find out why it's not working, because every other
card that I know of our situation, I know of it would work.
For us.
You said regarding checking Shader status.
I believe the best practice is checking GL compiled status after
compiling a Shader and then Geo link status after linking a program
that might be true.
Although, I guess, I don't know what the difference in a lot of these
would necessarily be.
I'm not sure what the pros and cons of any particular one is, I'm not
sure why there are so many ways that it happens to be completely
honest.
But
Are you eventually go into new Shader code into the asset packs are
going to keep it in line, probably always in line because we want to
be signed that modifies with the code, not with the asset packs, the
asset packs are for assets, obviously, and they get updated very
infrequently.
Where a Shader is?
We want to have a fast turnaround time on
This Isaac, will there still be problems if a tree is in front of a
tall block, if the Sprite still technically intersects the tile above,
there might be.
But even if there were.
So I would rather handle that in the vertex Shader on the GPU, rather
than handling on the CPU side, right?
Because again, I can do stuff in there that I couldn't do otherwise.
However, I don't know that there's anything you could really do.
I mean, essentially, it doesn't matter, right?
Like no matter what you do with those fright cards,
There's no point if they have to show up as a card, then there's no
difference between multiple changing the Z bias and creating a
trapezoid, they're both exactly the same, right?
Because the only difference is what the screen space z value is, so
it's always better to do it.
I think the Z bias way there's never a case.
We're doing a trapezoid would give you anything other than less
computation.
I mean, sorry more computation resources being spent to do it.
A slim sir?
Will you implement Shader hot loading?
I think we could probably I think if we just move
I think if we basically just move the thing that gets the shaders, if
we move that into our reloadable code section, which we could pretty
easily do then, I think we would just have it for free.
Right.
Right now, it wouldn't work because the program only gets compiled at
in it time.
So we have to have a thing that tells it to recompile the program.
But that's about all we would need because we already have the hot
code reloading.
So in theory it would work.
Looks like no more Q Cullen's.
Anyways.
Hot loading seems safest with use of bind attribute location, correct?
So as not to have to Chase locations all over the place.
Yeah, I guess that's a good point.
I mean, I guess so, probably what we should do is move the opengl code
into the reloadable section.
That's probably what we should be doing.
Saenz says, last time I was here.
You talked about the in 32x types.
What are your thoughts on type space versus cash utilization?
Usually, that's just an as you know as the case is present themselves,
kind of a situation.
So basically like I tend not to think too hard about optimization
issues until I actually have something to optimize.
Right?
So I don't tend to think about how
Big a type is unless I fear that it is a cash going to be a cash
problem like it's unless I'm thinking it's in a place where I think
it's really likely, the cash effects are going to be a problem.
I'm like planning for that or where I think that you know there's some
other reason for the types size to be relevant like loading off of
disk or marshalling of the network that sort of thing.
But in general I don't tend to think about the
The size of types in terms of their impact on the cash.
Unless I actually am thinking about optimizing something at that point
because otherwise I feel like it's just wasted thought, really?
Because if you haven't actually measured what your
Doing and you haven't actually decided, you're optimizing it, then
you're really just guessing and fussing around, you know, and it seems
like kind of unproductive to do that until you actually know what
you're doing.
Wretched freak.
If you recreate the program and hot reloading, you should probably
free the old shaders and program.
I don't think there's any reason to do.
So I mean, obviously, if you cared about this being something that an
end user was going to have to do, you would, because in that case you
could, you know, if they kept reloading reloading really eroding, they
might run out of handles or something.
But doesn't really matter for our purposes.
We can just leave those old programs around right.
They don't they don't harm us by being by just sitting around.
Okay.
Are the program's cleared automatically when the game exits.
Yeah, all of your GPU resources that you've acquired if you crash or
if you exit cleanly or any other thing that happens.
Everything is is purged, all your textures, all your programs,
everything unless there's a bug in the driver or in Windows, they are
all going to go away.
Let's see.
Do you have any plans about temporal anti-aliasing?
Not really, it's not something I've really worked with so I don't have
much to say about it and then last question I assume that you don't
give much thought to how hot data is.
I remember a talk by Andre that you could get a few percent speed up?
From organizing the data according to hotness.
Yeah.
Again, like I said, I feel like when you're creating architectures and
working on getting code to the point where it does what you want it to
do, typically I'm not thinking about any optimization issues at all
except for making sure that I'm not doing something.
I believe, we'll make it fundamentally impossible or very difficult
for me to optimize sections of the code later.
So if I to the extent that I ever think about stuff like how cash
things are cash aligned or how things are organized, due to how hot
they will be, you know, on average, I'm only going to think about
those things in passing when doing the main work on the code.
And then only when I'm starting to optimize a particular section
because I believe it to be performance-critical.
Am I going to actually try to measure and organize and optimize for
any of
Those things.
You really shouldn't be thinking about those all the time because you
probably can't get it right without actually being actually working on
it, right?
Like most of the time on Modern Hardware optimization is very tricky.
And oftentimes counterintuitive, it's not like the old days where it
was very straightforward and easy to understand.
So if you think that you can make improvements to your programs
performance by randomly doing stuff as you're writing code, when
you're not even testing it for optimization,
Looking at performance counters or you're not in the actual situation
that it will actually be in production and so on and so forth.
Typically, you're probably, not really doing anything all that great,
like probably mostly what you're doing.
There are going to be things that are, you know, could be as likely to
hurt as help because you just don't know.
You're not really, you're not really measuring the results and you're
not really knowing that what you're doing is correcting a problem, or
improving a situation, right?
Hubby reissue.
Unless there's a bug in the driver in Windows.
Yeah, there are never any bugs in those.
Yeah, that's why I said that, obviously.
So that's why I said that when I said, you know, unless there's a
bugger driver or in Windows, everything gets perched, chances are
sometimes there might be bugs in Windows or win32, which would result
in things windows or the driver, which result in things not getting
Purge properly.
But again, that's not a reason to delete the Shader code because
there's just as likely to be a bug in that,
At right?
Meaning, you know, if there's bugs in the driver in terms of purging
stuff out, then they're just could be bugs and you have no idea where
they are and you're not working around them in any more likely fashion
by freeing stuff or not.
Right.
For all, you know, the bug might be in the free call.
Where is if you call the free call it accidentally does something that
makes it not get purged when the game exits, right?
So, you know,
Bugs are bugs.
There's nothing you can do.
That will make it like, you know, better in that case.
We eventually be doing such a Passover handmade here.
I probably not because I don't think we're going to have performance
concerns of that form.
If we do, then we would but probably we won't
Should you add a, a probably backslash.
And I think twitch filtered out.
Should you add it back soon?
At the end of each line with the format?
You are using, Wouldn't It Be parsed by the opengl as a long comment
as it is now?
Yes.
So what we're going to have to do, there's two reasons to do that.
Service talking about here.
So yes, as we add code to here, we will have to do this as we go.
Once there's more lines in here.
Technically you don't have to at anything that's not a comment.
Like so you could also just do this
Right.
And it will parse fine but the reason to add is not because of the
comments, the reason to add the backslash ends.
The reason for the backslash ends is actually that the error reporting
will be better because when it reports an area will tell you the line
it's on it won't necessarily tell you the column, it's on.
So if all you have is a line number, you really want to insert line
breaks all over the place so that you can tell where it's complaining.
That makes sense.
Starchy pancakes.
Hey Casey I got a job as a gameplay programmer wouldn't have happened
without the stream not in a million years, dude!
That's awesome!
I'm so happy to hear that.
Congratulations.
I hope that it starts a really good career for you.
If game, programming is what you're into, I hope you enjoy it and you
continue to find it interesting.
That's great.
Well, that's a great one to end on.
I'm very happy to hear that starts with pancakes.
That's great, make a good game.
I don't know very much about gameplay programming myself, you'll
probably know more about it than me, pretty soon.
I only ever do the engine code and you know, I I always would defer to
John Blow on how you write gameplay code because I have no idea.
He's the expert on that stuff because I feel like, I feel like if you
write gameplay code, you kind of have to be a bit of a designer.
You know, maybe I mean you'll know I guess as you start doing it,
you'll see.
But I feel
Like I feel like I'm not super qualified to write gameplay code,
because I just don't necessarily know the right stuff to do for the
game design, kind of pieces of it, you know?
And so if you're a gameplay programmer, if you're if you're doing
gameplay programming, you'll probably learn that stuff.
You'll be ahead of me pretty soon because you'll probably learn a lot
more about the design.
How the design Works in there and
And that's kind of interesting part.
That's that's really what makes gameplay code.
You know, different from engine code is that gameplay code is very
much about enabling design.
Whereas game engine code is is more about technical requirements that
are easier to articulate.
You know, it's easier to say what you need in engine code and it's
more difficult to say what you need in gameplay code because gameplay
code is sort of fungible and has this design
I meant where you're exploring things that don't really necessarily
know how to verbalize potentially, what's supposed to happen.
But you know that it's supposed to happen, right?
And so it's kind of a it has a softer element to it.
That I feel like you kind of need experience, you need the you need to
have done gay programming in a real game scenario to really feel it.
So that's going to be cool because you're going to get that experience
and and you'll probably learn a lot from that.
I would suspect expect and probably learn a lot of things that I don't
know.
So anyway,
Best of luck to you.
All right, folks with that, we wish start your pancakes.
Well, that's pretty exciting.
I'm going to go ahead and wrap the rest of the stream up.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for handmade here.
That's going to pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the series at home,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org.
It comes with the source code, and if you want to play around with it,
that's an easy way to do it.
If you want to ask questions, we have a forum site.
If you want to support our video,
Series, we do have a patreon page as well.
We've got a schedule a bot that tweets the schedule and let you know,
we're going to be live and we have a past episode guide if you want to
catch up with all the episodes.
That's it for this week.
Next week, we'll be back.
When will write some Shader code?
Hopefully that won't be too much of a yak shave because all we really
want to do is some very simple stuff in there.
But until then have fun programming and we will see on the internet.
Take
It easy everybody.