Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream and we are doing a
little bit of debug code clean up at the moment.
I'm going to go ahead and jump right into it because I don't actually
know precisely what we want to clip that.
I mean for sure I think we want to try and finish up some of the way
we were getting the debug Harkin place but I think we also want to
start in on getting our profile view working cleanly.
So we got a bunch of stuff
To do.
So I'm going to go ahead and hop in on that if you are one of the
people who's flying along at home.
But the source code today is day 251.
So do today to 50s source code and start with that.
That is where I am starting with today.
So, let's go ahead and open open things up here and see where we're
at.
So, let's see here is our handmade prj, and we have built it.
Load the debugger and run it.
And
At some point, I think we should probably pop back over the opengl
thing, and remove some of that context face and stuff, because man,
it's so long.
It takes so long to start up now, it's just really frustrating.
But anyway, I think we were sort of almost finished with the debug
hierarchy stuff here and you can kind of see that we have a space for
our debug profile here as well.
But there's nothing in it.
So obviously, you know, that's something we would want to deal with as
well, but none of
Is that is neither here nor there is this.
This actually it's like a solid shaded window.
It looks like it's like a has a darkening behind it.
That's interesting.
Anyway, but first we got to finish sort of this stuff up where we want
to be able to edit these things and have these things come out in the
right places and we're mostly there but not quite.
So you can kind of see that like we started down here and we're not
quite there yet.
You can see that the path gets read properly but then the name of the
actual item is not correct.
at the moment and also we have not yet enabled, the ability to edit
these which we would also like to do
So, I don't know if we'll get to doing the profile today so but I
definitely would like to try and get it to the point where we can edit
these things.
So I think there's probably a little coded involved in there, that
might take a little while.
So that's what I'd like to try and get done today and then next week,
we can just finish up.
I think that that gives us most of what we want for our debug output.
Next week, we can try doing a couple things like putting some
profiling stuff in there.
Unless we happen, this happens here really quickly right now.
And then we can start on the profile today either way.
But that's where we're at.
So, let's take a look here at
What we need to do to make that happen.
Let's pop over to for coder here.
So right now it looks like our main problem is that when we're out
putting
These debug events we're obviously printing a name, that isn't what we
want the name to be.
And so we can see here that we've got this event quid is what we're
starting with for the name and there's the start at lash lash thing
which says, like go to, you find the last lash and you know maybe
we're sending that, maybe we're not.
But the point is in order to actually figure out how to display all
the stuff we need to sort of.
Now have some idea.
Of how this hierarchy is being built, exactly.
We sort of work through some of that, but we got to make it actually
be totally correct.
Now in order to have to have the display that we want, so looking
through how it's currently getting built.
Oops, I got to get my area looking through.
How it's currently being built.
If you remember correctly, the way that it sort of happens, at the
moment is debug blocks themselves.
Sort of get get
Moved into the hierarchy as actual unit as actual elements and then,
whenever the debug those debug blocks get output, they output the
events inside them.
In fact, this is the actual routine right here.
You can see when we come to a data block gets printed out right here.
Like so now it seems to me like this is the thing that I don't really
know and just kind of thinking it through.
The only reason we wouldn't do it is
Is because we want to display multiple data blocks that are all the
same kind of data block, but it doesn't make a whole lot of sense to
me, why we actually even need to have data blocks stored in the
hierarchy as separate printable things like this.
Other than the one reason that when we go to draw events like this
here, you can kind of see that if we were, to have multiple data
blocks of the same kind, that would actually work.
Okay, at the moment.
Whereas, if
We made them all in the hierarchy wouldn't necessarily work correctly
so it depends on how we want to approach that.
I don't know necessarily how we want to approach that but we could
sort of simplify this down by saying that data blocks always kind of
get expanded into the hierarchy at the time when we see them, they get
slots in the hierarchy directly rather than just having the data block
itself, have a slot in hierarchy and then the thing get printed out on
demand which is what's actually happening right now, right?
So thinking that through is mainly the part that I was talking about.
Now you can see that when we're printing out these names, you can see
us doing the debug draw event business happening here.
And when we call debug draw event for each of those things, for some
reason, we're getting a weird name for each of them, and that's the
part that I kind of wanted to look at a little bit, and I know we've
got the store event here, and I want to take a look at that.
So, inside store event when we produce the actual
I will name you can kind of see here, we push the we
Take the name that we want to call the element and we put that into
the grid.
Now the thing about this get name that happens here is that that's
going to give us the whole name including the slashes, right?
And so that's actually, you know, when we look back here, it actually
makes some sense to me why we're seeing if opengl over starts up, why
we're seeing, you know, render a / camera as a name of the element,
that makes some sense.
It doesn't make a whole lot of sense, is why the final thing after the
slash does not appear to be there, right?
That part much more confusing because if we take a look and I guess,
maybe we'll go back here and let me just make sure.
I understand what we were trying back.
When we originally created the debug value stack that we were printing
in the first place.
You can kind of see here.
We've got the data block render camera and then inside here we've got
each of these debug values.
Those debug values should have been
Like ridiculous stuff.
Like we should have seen Global renderer camera use debug should
actually have been what showed up under under there.
So, you know, that's what I'm expecting to see under there and that's
not even remotely what we actually are seeing under there.
It looks instead, you know what it, what it actually looks like.
In this case is it looks like the debug values themselves are
inheriting, just the debug blocks actual name, right?
So
So, this is the name of the debug block that's getting inserted there,
but we don't actually want that at all, like, we don't want the name
of the debug block.
There.
We want this name there and I'll quickly verify that we're actually
passing the right thing down.
Because, obviously, if we're passing the wrong thing, that would be y.
But presumably, we're passing the right thing in just parsing it wrong
because that's, it would seem to be the most consistent with the
behavior of seeing.
So you can see here,
Here's debug value and you can see record, debug event.
And we get the debug name here and then we do the set event, right?
This, debug name with the, with the pound value, that should give us a
debug value.
That actually has the name, Global renderer camera, use debug, that's
getting passed down there.
And so now I want to go back and look at handmade debug to see why
we're not getting that as the actual name.
Like,
Why are we not seeing that name?
Because we shouldn't even be able to get the other name.
So, it's a little confusing to me, right?
So that's what I'm doing right now.
So anyway, so here we are in draw me menu, right?
This is how we're normally drawing stuff.
And when we drove one of these elements, we come through here and
we're calling debug drug event, which I should go verify that.
That's actually what we're calling each time like that.
We're actually going through this path that I think we are.
And it's not something else that's happening, but if that if we assume
that that's the case, then what we're going to
End up here is in debug draw event.
We're going to have the story.
That we saved.
And that's the thing that we're going to come through here to actually
write out.
So you can see here.
Here's debug event to text, we're passing this event here right there
and you can see that that's stored event.
We're getting just whatever the event was off of it, which is, you
know, just the the most recent one for it, presumably.
That's sort of ends the most recent one and we're just getting the
event of that to print it out and so when we go to print out that
event, I feel like what we should be getting is we should be getting
that name, right?
We should be getting the name there so you know, that's what I'm
assuming.
So there is AD name and when we do add a name that just we grab the
grid out, right?
That's what we looked at before.
We grab the quit out of the event and we stick that onto the end,
right?
I mean, there's the username.
And we stick that on there and then we may or may not add a colon
depending on which one we're printing out, right?
And that's it.
So I'm not sure as I think I'm going to step through in the debugger,
I'm not sure why we're getting such a strange result from from these
guys and I don't know if there's something else weird happening.
That's like, that's not the code path or following or if there's some
other thing that I'm missing, that's, you know, that's going to
elucidate it.
But point being at the
Moment, that's why I'm a little confused.
So let's go ahead and take a look.
At what happens when we actually go to Loop through this?
This expect this data block.
So I'm just going to take a look at what these events actually look
like so I can see.
And so here is the the grid so that's actually I mean basically the
problem is Upstream, right?
Because we're already getting render / camera here and we should never
see that like that should just never be seen ever.
So, at this stage.
So somebody when they're actually storing the events,
Is doing something dumb and that's somebody's obviously me because I'm
the only person who touched this code to the best of my knowledge but
point being one part of the code is doing something dumb.
So I want to take a look at what's actually happening here.
When we store those events to see if I can ascertain, what the actual
problem is
So, first, I'm going to look at Sea, try to pick a vent that's
reasonable.
So, let's take a look.
So that's this is totally fine.
Global render, a test weird buffer size.
That's totally fine.
I think, because that's, you know, if we go back over to handmade dot
CPP, you can see that.
That's this one right here.
So, we should be able to see why that one isn't getting labeled with
its own name.
So, let's take a look.
If you step into store event, here we are.
and I guess,
I guess actually we can't step in now.
Now that I think about it, because what actually happens is,
That's already been parsed.
It's been parsed up here with get element from event.
Right, that's actually what's happening, is it gets called up through
here.
And so that's probably the actual problem.
Right.
Yeah, so in get element from event it's going to pass that event down,
right?
And then that's going to do this funny business here.
It's going to take a look.
At this squid, it's going to use the current event grid whatever it
is.
It's going to store that, then it's going to use whatever it parses
out, right?
If that makes sense.
So it's going to do all that and it's going to do the add element to
group which we don't really want it to do, right?
And so this gets back to the thing about these.
These events are not actually stored in there but they still go
through this path for no real reason.
So this is why I say, I wonder if these things need to actually be
parsed more properly because if they're going through one of these
open to one of these open data blocks, we actually.
Yeah.
This this just actually needs to be probably a little more clean.
Let's let's actually pull that out.
So it's easier to debug as well because we're going to have to deal
with it anyway eventually.
So I'm going to go ahead and do get element from event.
I'm going to actually just go ahead and
That out of here entirely and then I'm going to compile and then I'm
going to go see where that's actually used and I'm going to make that
happen on demand a little more, right?
So like this
And that way, when we come down here and we're going to do the storage
element thing at least at this point, now I can have it.
Do the parsing in a place where we can watch, which is, which is
better, right?
And
And I guess what we want to do here is actually say like okay if we
were going to store it in some place.
Yeah.
If we were going to store it somewhere, we should just use that which
normally we would otherwise, you know, fall through to this.
So that's a little bit more.
That's a little bit more saying, I think whoops, that's not right.
All right, and that kind of elucidates why we were having the problem.
So what will happen here is we'll just use this element to store it.
It'll get this.
These events will get stored under that storage element and it will
never actually get its name parsed, right?
That's the actual problem that's happening there.
This event, never actually gets processed in the appropriate way.
So that's actually, I think.
Why we're having this problem?
Or at least it's a big portion of it.
Right?
So when we actually do that parsing and we come through here to look
at this particular element, we still need to be able to do, you know
this operation, we still want to be able to strip out that, that whole
sort of rest of the part of the name.
And so we, you know, we would want to search for, we would want to do
this.
Find last pipe kind of a thing.
And we would want to start the name there.
So I'm going to hack that in for the moment.
But then I think, what this what I kind of think I want to do again to
sort of start simplifying things to continue simplifying.
Things more is, I feel like we just want everything to go into that
hierarchy, so that we don't have this constant problem of, you know,
These things go into Data blocks.
These things don't I'd rather just have it.
So that the data block is just a way of grouping things together.
If that makes sense because I feel like again this is a case of like
yeah there is some reason why we might want to do it this way but are
we really ever going to use that functionality and if we're never
going to use that functionality, then are we just making lives harder
for ourselves?
Every time you want to debug stuff by having it so crazy, right?
Because the debug system, we might want to pop in periodically to add
something.
If you're trying to bug a problem and we want to add something, we
don't want it to be like a huge disaster in here all the time.
I mean, yes, it's only debug code.
We don't have to worry if it's shippable or not because it's not going
to run on end users machines.
But we don't want to leave a huge liability for our own selves in case
we need to use it.
Right?
So that's that's kind of where I'm you know why I'm thinking about
that way.
So yeah, so if we were going to do this then what we would want
Say it's like, oh, okay.
So the event right?
That we actually go to store.
We need that event to actually skip the pipe part.
So we would want to hear do something kind of like let's see for you
know, I don't know.
Event would
and if star Skin equals pipe,
Event grid equals scandals one, something like that.
So I don't actually think that's quite the entirety of it there yet,
but at least now, the event itself is actually moving past the grid
that it was on, so that will actually have it be stored correctly.
So for example, when we come down here to the storage event,
There's that event.
And now it should just be the name, which it is.
So that's at least a good start.
Okay.
So that's thing one and now thing too is when we're grabbing these out
we must not be grabbing the event out of the right place, somehow we
must be grabbing the wrong, actual the wrong, actual piece of
information, when we Loop over the, the open data block.
So here, where we do, our open data block, where we do start with the
the last open data, block and scan across
It we must for whatever reason.
Never not be getting the right.
Events out of here, let me see store.
In fact, you know what happens it's actually store event, that's
causing our problem and right, isn't it?
Because if we take a look at that event, it's probably over writing
the grid.
Yeah, you can see it happening right there.
Right?
So that's the problem, that's the actual problem.
It's taking that element name and we're storing it under this other
element, right?
And it's it's sort of forcing it in there which is not what we
actually wanted.
You know I'm saying.
So that's that's pretty much it right there.
Yeah.
So in fact,
This doesn't quite fix the problem because then we still have the
problem with the other with the the tree elements being wrong.
But that's actually that's actually what was happening, right?
So okay so yeah so basically like you know I just think that that's
still a little bit too janky in my opinion, so I'm I don't know that.
I don't think we want to keep those open data blocks in there.
I think we want to just get rid of the open data blocks and just use
the open data blocks.
I mean still put them in the Stream but we just don't need to store
them, right?
And so I think what we would want to do is leave the store event
happening the way that it's happening.
Now we're always storing under an element and then we can sort of
restore the way that this process worked to something a little more
sane as necessary.
And so for example the way we would do that right as we would say
everybody gets an element so this nonsense never happens anymore.
We always allow the the element to go into its actual place in the
hierarchy.
Like so, right.
But what we need to do is have a way of well I probably shouldn't I
guess.
S.
Where's my?
There we go.
So I still want this code.
in the sense that I still want to know that I'm in an open data block
because I want that data blocks element to be
Parent, right?
But I don't want to do anything else.
I just want to basically use whatever it was as my initial parent,
that's it.
So it's going to be more like debug element initial parents or like
parents like that.
And then we're going to say like okay if it's the first open data
block, then the parent is whatever that data blocks element was in the
tree.
And otherwise it's going to remain zero.
then when we do,
Well, I guess I got a copy that here site, deleted it for no reason.
Then when we actually store the sky, what we need to do is call get
element from event and now we want to be able to pass that parent in
and so you can kind of see up here in get element from event, right?
Where we call down through here.
And we say, oh, you know, if we didn't find one, we've got to make
this this element, right?
And then we do add element to group and we, you know, we do that get
high.
Group from name and we're passing the route group here.
What we want to do instead is we want to be able to actually use the
group of that previous debug element that previous parent, right?
And so, it'd be like this, right?
We'd say get element from from event and we would have liked you bud
variable group here and this is the parent group.
like so and so when we're actually inserting this, this thing in here
we would just say like oh this is the parent and
I guess we would probably also say like okay if you don't specify one
you know if there's no parent then we'll just default to inserting it
into that route group.
Like so now the problem with that is just that I don't actually know
where to get that route group out of here, right?
Because gross, I do remember, but if we take a look at the, this thing
here, where we get this first open data, block, I'm assuming that we
have a way.
If I go to debug, uh, I'm assuming that there's some way their of
Let's see where the open data by.
I'm assuming that there's some information about what the group
actually is.
So yeah, like right here that group right there, that's what I
actually want.
So, rather than storing the element, I don't care about the element.
I actually just want that and this is actually going to be a debug.
Oops, debug variable group.
Like so.
So that seems like probably more what we want to do.
Okay.
Alright, so of course Apparently that is not
Working at all.
Probably because if we look here, we don't actually ever update that
right
So, we probably just need that to be updated here and that's probably
it, I would assume, right?
Let's take a look.
So inside.
Dubai government.
Here's debug element.
So we've got our debug element, which we are and we got our open.
What happens during allocate debug block
Yes.
So we never set that group at all, right?
And we would want to set that group when we do get element from event
and we get this back, we need to record what that group actually was,
is the problem.
And at the moment, we're not doing that, right?
And we would, we need to find that out.
So when we do get element from event,
Our problem is that we're losing that piece of state.
So we come down here and when we actually do this, get group for
hierarchical name and then we do add element to group.
When we're adding the, when we're adding that debug Block, it's
getting added as a regular element, which is, you know, not what we
actually want.
And in fact now that I think about it, I suppose we don't really ever
want to add the debug block as a first.
Class citizen anyway.
So I suppose it's really just going to be this when we when we do
that.
So for open debug block, I almost think I guess we don't ever actually
do any of this right?
We don't insert it at all we strictly do that right?
And so when we call you know, when we like I guess we just don't even
do.
This right?
We literally just do the part where we get the name out of the sky,
right, which would require us to have that parsing.
Pulled out a little bit but that's really not a problem.
So when we call, when we do open data block, we would get whatever
that harco.
Go, that hierarchical group name was and then we would call open it.
Open the debug block, and I guess that open debug block.
It never would actually have an element
Here.
Right there would actually be no element because we wouldn't ever add
the element to the tree.
Because there's nothing to add.
And so it would just be 0, right?
Then inside the open debug block, when we could create an element.
If we wanted to, we just don't really have any need to.
So, inside the the debug block there, we would just say, like, oh,
okay, the group for this, debug block is whatever that group was that
we that we insert in here, which I guess we have to actually do, like,
an ad,
Ad group.
Let's see, get her goal.
Is it get group?
For, there it is.
So we're just going to do, get a create group with name.
Right.
Don't know what's going on there.
All right, so that's we know what the parent is.
This is the actual name that we're going to use and that we know as
well.
So that's pretty easy, as I guess.
This is the size of the name so it's more like that, right?
And so all we need to do here is when we actually parse we actually
need that bit of name, parsing that pulls out the information.
We need that sort of to be
A standalone unit which is pretty trivial, right?
It's just going to be something like that.
So okay so here is named length here is name or whatever.
Well actually I'll just go ahead and pull that stuff out so that is
right here.
And what we need is all of this, right?
And in fact, we could even keep the hash value in there as well.
Because why not, right?
So we need something like this.
Debug parse name parce que bed parse name.
And in here we would just pass whatever the the name was
And then we would run this thing on it.
Like so.
So pretty, pretty straightforward.
Yeah.
So we just say, all right.
There's the results.
And now, when we do the scan,
instead, we're always going to
Right into the result pipe count.
We don't need to store because that's only used in here so that can
stay everything else can happen in here.
Like so.
So now when we do this little, this little doodad, we can just say
like okay we've got a debug parse name and that's going to be equal to
debug parse name of the event grid.
Now we've got that person a man anywhere in here that used to need to
use that.
It can just use parse name, dot whatever the thing was and that's all
good, right.
And I think that's all we really need for that.
Let's see, that's got to be great again and again, there we go.
Hash value.
Of course, is now in parsed name.
And okay, so now we're down here.
So now we can do the same thing.
And so the event.
Glad that we get here.
We can parse and now we know everything that we needed to know about
it.
We could also pull this out which we might want to do but that's
separate issue.
And so here we can just say, you know, whatever the name was we can.
And in fact we could actually just include
It right in there.
So let's do that.
Right.
So here we've got
name length and name and people can just ignore them if they don't
want them and then we can just say like at the end of this.
Okay so you know the result that name length
And the result that name, the result that name is obviously just
wherever the grid started.
plus name starts at
And then the name length is just going to be whatever the total length
of the string was right?
So scan, obviously ends the string.
In fact.
I guess I got to pull that out here, right?
Scan ends the string at this point, it's sitting at the end.
So if we were to take scan - quid
That's the total length.
So that subtracted away and we subtract away where the name starts at
gives us however long the name was so that's, you know, that's that.
Obviously, we got to tell it that we're never going to have strings
that are over 4 billion characters, long, always good to double check.
And then we just have to finish up this thing.
So all right, get group, the parent here.
It's going to be the debug State Route group
Actually, that's not true.
Now that I think about it.
Because aren't these things supposed to Nest?
So technically, it's actually this
Right.
So I think we actually want to do something more like this.
You know I'm saying because that way we'd say oh debug State Route
group, that's the default parent group.
And I think we want them both to go in there, right?
So we would want this to go into default parent group and we would
want this to do the same, right?
I mean, that's
right.
Let's see here.
Fault.
Element store event, Element.
No, no, no.
I don't want to store anything there.
Don't store do not store.
Does not store.
Do not store.
All right.
So now everything should be getting stored in the hierarchy.
Of course, I may have messed something up and in fact, I specifically,
did I mess something up as it turns out, we're just getting called
from
Wait, what are you doing?
Calling call from here?
Okay, that's storing the clothes data block.
Why are you starting the closed beta block?
Nobody asked you to do that either.
Of course, I want to know why it doesn't work, but I don't actually
want you to do that for the record.
You take a look at the elements elements is null which would be why so
I don't know what's wrong with that first open data block is here.
Oh, because we don't store that.
Yeah, right.
We actually remove that.
That's totally valid.
It's gone now so that can't happen.
So that's fine, don't care.
That goes away.
Opengl.
All right, so getting there.
Almost there.
But you notice we have a weirdness here with this whole situation and
I actually
Thank God that made that may actually be a data bug.
Now that I think about it, actually.
That may actually be us being stupid.
So in here, this is not right.
I mean that's that's why that happened.
And
Yeah.
Where's the other ones platform?
So that's in win32 and made us weak a platform controls or forms /
controls.
So that's
Well, that should work.
So that's a, that's a screw up.
So we should go fix that.
But render cameras is right now.
Okay, so let's go ahead and flip back here.
And we should now be at the point where we only have the ones that
don't expand out like they should, right?
And let's go ahead and double check here to this part works.
where we can actually look at the simulation entity and we can
Although why we can't view bitmaps in here?
I don't know.
So take a look at that too.
It's kind of nice to be able to view debug stuff, right?
Like there's our, there's our velocity.
Right X.
There's the last reason why.
All right.
Facing Direction.
There's me, jumping.
Don't know why jump is still enabled this game.
It's not supposed to let you jump.
Probably should remove that.
We'll get to that soon.
I guess we'll start to engage play coding pretty soon, so I'll get to
go through and clean all that code at.
All?
Right, so that's good.
But again, not pleased with this.
This is not working properly.
So when we do our name parsing here and we do get group for
hierarchical name.
I don't understand why it's not creating two links down, Whites
Whites, not W.
Expanding
so, that's
That's a little weird.
I guess the reason is because, when we do that, get group for our code
name, we don't then remove the slashes, right?
From this thing.
So, that actually is probably why now that I think about it.
we would need to go find the last / in the name at that point, and
move the pointer forward to it, but just to double-check
That's not quite correct right now.
It is correct.
That's correct.
All right so when we do get group for hierarchical name, what I think
I actually want to do here is is just make a slight modification to
that function.
So if I go up to get group for hierarchical name and we look at how
that's working, where is that?
Group 4.
so if I mean, get group for hierarchical name, what I want to do here
is say like, okay, instead of saying, if for a separator, I want to
kind of always do this, actually,
If that makes sense.
So I want to do something where I say like oh okay,
It's really that.
I want to always create that all the way down the tree.
I just don't want to continue going hierarchically if there were no
more separators.
And so this can be if for a separator or create entire tree or
something or create terminal, right?
And then so when we call this, we can just say, oh, create terminal.
And then, that way.
It's easier for us to do.
So yeah, so when we do this and we're creating an element, normally we
don't want to do that but when we're creating one of these guys, we do
want to do that.
And then we don't really do a parent group anymore, it's not a parent
group, it's actually the group.
I believe and so then when we set the group, we don't actually do
that.
Right.
So then we just let that function do what it's doing and then it'll
automatically strip off that / for us, I believe, or we could crash
the program because well it's not, I guess we're not Crossing room.
We could get an assertion, which would be always fine.
Everyone loves an assertion.
So what happened there?
Oops.
Go back.
So, yeah, when we create the debug block here,
Going to rearrange this code a little bit when I create the debug
block.
That poops.
That presumably should.
I've changed anything.
So I believe the only thing that we're looking at here is really going
to be that change.
I made to get group for hierarchical name.
And so for that,
why?
wonder what's happening there when we get a create the first separator
- name,
so that's the problem right there.
Right?
The length computation is going to be wrong.
So what we want to do there is essentially say Okay, first operator is
0 when we come out of here.
So really what we want to do is say when we come in here, if we don't
have, if the first separator was not set, it's just going to point to
the beginning of the string.
Right.
Because that way, we would create the full name at that point, or I
should say the end of the string, right?
So it's basically like scan is going to be for a separator and if that
makes any sense like this,
There we go.
What?
All right, so I admit that, that was not that was not brilliant.
That was not great.
Because of course since we also use that to do the recursive, check
you know.
Yeah that's going to go on forever, right?
Just straight on forever.
So I think we actually want this.
Probably makes more sense.
So in the case, where we do have a first separator, then we can just
use the name length that we were using before.
But in the case, where we don't,
then we can use the name length that we were Computing, the other way.
So that's just the same exact thing.
But it's the whole screen.
Not quite.
Subgroup is still getting wickets returned here.
Results.
Let's get.
This should actually be result here as well.
We want to take whichever result like if we created a group, we want
that to be the result.
Right?
That's what we actually wanted because we always need to return
something.
Otherwise the group won't have anything in it.
So, I think we're good.
That looks like everything that I wanted.
Right.
Everybody's there.
And so now I don't really remember.
I mean, that's obviously all working properly, but I don't really
remember why we don't have editing for these guys because I thought we
did have anything for those guys at least at one point.
So I'm not sure why those debug values aren't getting edited in are
not able to be edited, if that makes sense.
I also think that now are open debug block stuff can get ganked.
Here, so let's just get rid of that.
Where's that at?
No, no, don't do it.
No.
I can't, I didn't want to stop programming right now.
Can't you see mr.
Five-minute warning that I'm right in the middle of something.
What is wrong with you?
So yes, so this stuff can go away and here in
This code I think can just get get Vaped right back and just go away.
Goodbye.
I think that's all there is to it.
So that's good.
So now it's also take a look, why can we not edit these things?
So when we come through here and we create one of these guys, right?
We say, default interaction
for this thing, but
We're not actually getting any interaction and so I don't know why
like, is there a reason why Otto modify variable is not actually doing
anything for this type?
I mean it should be a be 32, right?
So it should be setting it to toggle value.
I would think
but,
Is apparently not the case.
You know, I'm saying.
So for some reason,
Auto modify variable is refusing to modify these variables.
Is that?
Why is that I asked you?
What is the problem here is ab32.
I believe these things are be 32s.
But maybe they're not.
Right?
It could just be coming through as a youth s32 because that's what it
be.
That's what it would crack, the type to
Let me take a quick look.
Oh wait, I'm in the right file already.
So when we do debug set event value, you can see here, yeah, it's
never going to set it because it doesn't know that it's a Boolean,
right?
It doesn't know that it's a Boolean.
So what we really need here is a way to clue it in because it's not a
real type, right?
Because C++ is awesome and always does everything wrong.
So what we have to do is we have to tell it manually that we wanted
this.
Thing to be.
A Boolean, right?
That's what we actually needed to do.
So if we do it, if we do it like this, where we say, like okay,
Set the value to be the value and set the debug type to be ab32.
Then I think we would actually get it set to the proper value.
Right?
I think.
And so now if I went in here to handmade dot CPP and said, oh, like
this is a Bool, right?
I could, I could just say, debug pool or debug be 32.
Undies.
And I would be debug.
What is the problem?
Oh, because this is actually value be through to.
That's the problem.
And that's not what that is not to be 32.
All right, so that presumably would do something resembling anything.
So let's see if that made those values editable already.
That's like use debug camera, was one of them.
For example, let's see, camera.
No, no, that is one.
so it's showing up as ab32 now, but
Can't click on it so.
So what's the deal?
They're like, what's going on?
I want to, I want to know.
Mr.
Debugger, I want to know why we can't do that because that's like, I
guess our next thing is to go through that system and start cleaning
that up a little bit as well, but I feel like that should have gone to
a toggle value.
Maybe we disabled toggle values but like
Interaction toggle value.
There it is.
That set the hot interaction to a toggle value so I just watched it
happen.
Right.
So what's the deal?
Hmm, not really sure.
So I'm assuming
Well, I guess I know why it wouldn't actually toggle.
I just don't know why it wouldn't highlight.
The reason it wouldn't actually toggle is because we don't have any
way to re pick up those changes.
So for example, if we go back in here,
In to debug be 32 or into Book value.
Either.
Or when we go set this stuff up, we don't actually try at this point
to go get any new, any changes to that particular value, right?
So we don't try.
We have, we make no attempt at picking up a change.
That might have occurred with that value.
So, what we would need to do here in this particular case, is we
need to say like, oh, okay, if there is a changed value, like we need
to do something here where we do like if you know,
Well, I guess just be like this.
maybe something like this where we'd say, like, okay this thing
If you wanted to overwrite it go ahead and overwrite it now, right?
And it would go pick up that change as necessary and and right over
the value with a new value.
If there was an edit that had been pending.
So you know when we do that edit it has to edit the value in the
element and then it has to sort of store that value back.
I don't want to try and do that right now because I don't think that's
well that's not going to be very helpful.
In like five minutes or whatever.
I got left.
So we'll do that next week, but that's
That's why we don't get edits but I feel like we still, there's also a
problem because it should be highlighting that line.
And since it's not highlighting that line, I think we may be also our
IDs are.
It's because
Maybe are we haven't done the debug ID stuff properly for these things
yet either.
So I guess we still have a fair ways to go on like cleaning this up
entirely, because we have to clean all of that stuff up because none
of its really correct at this point.
And so we're only just getting the hierarchy and shape, but we don't
actually have the other part in shape yet.
So, yeah, but I think that's what we actually would want to do.
So I'm going to save that for next week and that'll be, that'll be
that.
Oops, what did I do?
I don't know what's going on here.
So yeah.
But I think that's mostly all.
We actually need to do is just do that and then we would be good to
go.
That's my suspicion.
And this of course, has to pass the event as well.
So it basically just looked like that and same would be true up here.
But I guess I probably should insert those in the middle of the macro.
Unadvisable.
That would be good.
All right.
Let's let's go to Pune.
Do you know 27 1988 Wednesday, you talked about Microsoft's Xbox
process to detect, which vertex was close to another to form quads
tries faces.
I definitely didn't say that you have the math behind that, or maybe a
link about it.
I tried looking for it since then without any success.
So,
You try to say this may be a little clearer.
So what I was talking about is the fact that when you pass down
meshes, right?
This is
Imagine like a patch.
Looks like this.
So these are all triangles.
Okay, so nobody is the Xbox.
Originally I said, there's nothing about detecting vertices or
anything like that.
What I was saying is that when I say, when I'm saying locality, what
I'm talking about is actually, like, in a cash like like meaning the
actual memory, the actual Slots of something, it has nothing to do
with where the vertices are in space, right?
So just so we're clear on that.
So if we have a mesh here are the vertices and here are the triangles
of my mesh.
Okay?
Now I need to send this down to the graphics card, right?
If I were to send this down as simply a list of actual vertex data,
right?
So the positions of the vertex data, right?
Then I'm going to send if even if I try stripped it.
So try strip is when you just stand like this, this this this, this,
this, this, this, this, this this this, right?
And it draws it.
Draws the quads automatically so you don't even have to specify the
triangles.
It just kind of constructs them as a strip if I was going to send that
right?
And I sent P0 P1 P2 P3 P4 P5 if I send that down as a list I'm going
to send this right.
And these are actual vertex data, so this is actually going to be, you
know, 24 bytes, right, or 32 bytes or something, right?
These are Big.
It's not one integer or 116 B.
Not one 16-bit value.
That's an index into something.
It's actually all the data, but that's fine.
It can still share because since we told it it's a triangle strip, it
knows that the pattern we're sending, is this, then this, then this,
then this, then this, then this so it knows it can reuse the vertices.
To draw two triangles that share two vertices each.
And every time we add a new vertex, we draw a triangle.
So we're essentially, every time we write one Wright, we start out
with two, we don't draw anything yet, we started to.
But then every time after the first two were drawing a new triangle
every time because it always knows how to use two previous vertices
from this stream to draw the new triangle.
So we do p 2 and an immediately knows that it can draw this triangle
because it knows P0 and P1.
We draw P3.
And now it knows, it can draw this triangle because no stories.
Use p.
0 p 2.
Right.
Then we draw this guy P4 up here and it knows it can redraw this we
drop P5 down here and we know it can draw this, right.
Of course, now that I realize, the way I wrote this P0 P1 P2.
It's actually going to be this way.
Sorry about that.
I drew that upside down.
Yeah, if you're try strip was in this order, then you would not that
would not be correct.
So pay no attention to that.
Pretend that didn't happen.
Let's try that one more time, paying attention.
So, if you are specifying them in this order, P0 P1, right?
Then p 2 would be here.
P 3 would be here.
It would draw that triangle first, right?
And then it would draw this triangle, but it always reuse has two
triangles from the previous one.
So then here again, when I'm to draw P4 here, it still now, again,
knows how to draw a whole triangle with only one vertex.
so, the way to think about this, to way to think about Trey strips,
Is that every new vertex draws a triangle.
So you are pretty much except for those first two, if you can just
keep the stream going, you have maximal amounts of triangles two
vertices if that makes sense, right?
Because every time you specify a Vertex, you draw a new triangle.
Hopefully that makes some sense, but
There's a catch.
and the catch is that if you were going to start touching previous
vertices that are not the last two that you looked at
If you're only sending down vertex data, there is no way to share
these anymore.
So for example, suppose I were to draw my trash trip like this.
Right, here's my try strip.
So I come in here, I draw this, this, this that right?
So I did like, okay draw this, then this, then this then that so it's
going to draw that triangle first then this triangle, right?
So make sense.
So this this this this right?
And now I try to turn this corner, right?
So I've drawn, you know this I draw this
It's now or something.
So, I draw their write, something like this.
I guess I can't quite draw.
Their I got to draw here.
Write something like this and then I try to draw like out here to
start going this way, right?
If I want to sorry I'm not driving.
Very good pattern to show this.
There's a pattern I figured out a long time ago that actually does
this and I want to see if I can free figured out again.
I've never actually seen anyone talk about this pattern before so I
might as well try to figure it out again.
I think it's like this.
So it's here to here.
Here to here.
Right here to here.
So, now, the next thing that gets drawn, it's got to turn the corner
and I don't remember how you do it.
It's this way.
The next one that you draw.
Is going to draw across the diagonal.
So,
Maybe you go out further that way.
So you go like this, don't really remember.
Right.
Then you're gonna hear hear that won't help you.
So it's got to be the other way around.
Sorry, just give me a second.
Just give me a second.
So you draw here to here, right?
And so, that's that way.
Then you draw here to here.
So that's that way.
and so, then you would draw
I cannot figure out what this actually was.
Maybe you do it throughout the other direction.
so, if I go down, if I'm there to there, and I do here to here,
Right.
So it's there, there there.
So it's that way.
Right.
And then I do these two again.
So would be that way, I guess actually want to put this guy a little
bit for the ring.
So it's that way.
and then the last guy,
maybe it's like that, is this correct, right.
And so this guy would be here here, here and there.
That is going to connect to this one.
So you need that one to be on the interior somehow.
I don't know how I did this.
It was the weirdest pattern ever and it was super hard to remember as
you can see.
So here here,
what's the next one?
Is it?
This is going to drive me insane if I can't remember it.
And the insofar as the interesting thing about this one is there were
no degenerate triangles.
It's a way to draw a patch.
That looks roughly like this.
End.
It looks roughly like that and that doesn't actually ever require a
restart.
It's just a full, try strip and it touches itself, maximal maximally
so to speak.
I think I used the default ordering of a try strip.
So I know that it would have been the way that they normally would
have encoded it and so ABCDEF.
So it was going upward for starters.
So it's doing like a b c d.
E.
F.
G.
H.
Yeah, that's it.
That's it right there.
I J K L, that's it.
So, you see how that works?
So, you do ABC that draws this.
Then you do D, which draws that the new Dewey, which draws this.
Then you draw F, which draws that right?
Then you draw G, which draws this, then you do H, which draws that,
then you drew, I, which draws this
Then you draw J which draws that K, which draws this L.
Which draws that
Yeah, again, never seen anyone mention this before on the Xbox.
I worked it out on the original Xbox because it was the way you could
make a perfect patch that would get maximum throughput through the
vertex cash without ever having to restart the try strip.
So you never lost an index.
If that makes sense.
All right point.
Being that was an extremely lengthy way to get to this part right
here, which is what I was trying to say.
So if you look at the series of vertices that come down here, it's you
know, a b, c, d, e, f g, h.
I now I as you can see is an exact same place a z.
So if I was sending these as vertex data,
I'm going to have to go through Andre shade to do the whole transfer
and pipeline everything on two identical vertices V and I right.
And that's stupid because they're in the exact same place their
coincident.
So
I really wanted to do is tell the graphics card.
Hey, all you need to do is use where you previously computer that
vertex to be.
So the reason that you send down index buffers, what I was trying to
talk about the other day is because if you're actually sending these
down as indices instead of the actual vertex data, then this stream
looks like zero, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, four, and
the card can see that the indices are both for it can have a little
cash that it looks into when
It's he's for, do I have vertex for already transformed?
Yes, use it right now, the size, this is called the Primitive
assembly.
Cash.
This is the one that that does the try strip part.
So the fact that I do 012 and that does a triangle, then three also
does a triangle.
That's called hitting the Primitive assembly cache and that's the
thing.
That's does the like store the last two vertices that I used and it
moves things around in that in that little tiny cache of just like
three vertices or whatever?
That's the oh, so this is like three vertices long.
It's super tiny.
It's only for assembling the actual Primitives, right.
Triceps.
This part is the vertex transform cash.
Oops.
And this is the thing which basically says, oh, I'm going to store.
I'm going to remember some number of vertices tagged with whatever
their index was so like, oh, I know that vertex 16 or whatever, right?
I have that, you know, I have what it was transformed as so if I see
index 16, I'm just going to pull it out of the cash, right?
So that is how like the Xbox Hardware used to work.
Does that make sense?
And so, the reason I was mentioning that was I was saying like,
I was using the excellent example of how indices versus vertex data
will affect how the hardware actually performs on your stream.
It's not equivalent, even if you take bandwidth out of the equation,
if you, if you're not even talking about the fact that the indices end
up being a smaller way, indices plus only unique vertices like unique
vertices plus indices as opposed to just duplicating the vertices
anytime you use them again.
It actually turns out to be more efficient in a number of ways,
potentially depending on how the hardware works.
And so, just what I wanted to kind of get across with that is that,
like, hey, if you actually care about maximum throughput on some of
these things, you have to actually know what the GPU is going to do.
You can't just, you know, assume something about it, because there may
be all sorts of caches in there or optimizations that are happening
and if you don't understand that, you're not going to pick the right
format for your data, right?
If you don't care about Max's you but you don't care about any of
this, right?
And so like with something like handmade hero we just don't have
The any Vertex throughput or transform needs at all?
Right.
That's just not an issue at all.
We don't even have anything wherever probably going to do with vertex.
Shaders will probably do some things, the fragment shaders, but we
have no need for for any heavyweight verdicts operations, right now,
and possibly ever, so this sort of stuff doesn't matter at all for
handmade hero.
But somebody in the Q&A, ask the question about this.
And so I was trying to be clear in the answer.
So hopefully that makes some sense.
And so Diner.
27 1988 had a follow-up question there which is how does it know which
triangles to draw?
So this is a part that we didn't talk about in handmade here because
again it's not relevant but basically what happens is there's this
notion of like I said, primitive assembly.
Primitive obviously, meaning.
The individual Primitives like the triangle or quad or point or
whatever is the unit that's actually been rasterize assembly.
Meaning how do I pull together the vertex data that I need to actually
do that?
So in this primitive assembly what happens is when you go to draw your
mesh you tell it what kind you're drawing and we actually did this in
handmade hero.
It's just we didn't really talk about it much because it's not
relevant in handmade hero.
So what happened in handmade hero?
It's not here GL in hand weight hero.
There we go, in handmade hero.
We said Jill, begin GL triangles, right, that is an example of
setting.
What type of primitive assembly you are trying to do, okay?
And I'll talk about that in one second.
So primitive assembly is like how does the vertex stream sort of
indicate what try what Primitives should actually occur, right?
And there's a couple different kinds for triangles.
One is actually just triangles.
That's the kind we use on handmade hero.
One is try strips.
And one is try fans.
Okay.
And what these are is these are rules for interpreting the vertices
that come in as to how they will appear in the output.
So with triangles, the rule is that vertices are taken three at a time
to for try to form triangles period.
So if I send down vertex and in fact, let me just make an example of
this so that you can actually see it.
Okay, so let's say that, I'm going to send down the following
vertices.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
Okay, that's what we're sending down.
If I was to say triangles, if that's what I set, the Primitive
assembly to, it's going to take these three at a time.
So this list,
it's going to take these three and form a triangle and these three and
form a triangle.
So what I will get in the output is I will get this.
Right.
And I will get this.
That is what I will see.
So there's no mystery.
There's no knowing magically how it's going to do.
It literally is just looking at the indices in the way that you told
it.
You said triangles.
That means vertices taken three, two time.
Okay.
That's triangles.
Try strips.
Has a different rule.
Try strips is start with the first to write.
And then the third one, implies the first triangle almost exactly the
way that you would imagine.
It would, if you're just drawing triangles.
Right?
So I draw one, two, three, then the rule is for every vertex
thereafter, right?
We're actually including this one.
When I draw this vertex, what I want you to do is I want you to
permute the previous vertices.
You were using such that you throw away what the oldest one.
Right?
So I get rid of one.
That's gone now so it's like a sliding.
Imagine a sliding window, it started here.
So I'm going to move the sliding window down, right?
I've two and three and then I'm going to add the next new vertex in.
Okay?
So now I'm going to draw one that's between two, three and four,
right?
Then the next one I do.
I slide the window down again and now I'm going to do one that's
three, four, and five, right?
So instead of just taking a three at a time, I'm now just using every
possible set of three I'm just moving down by one each time.
So instead of only using three unique vertices three more unique
vertices three more unique,
Is I'm reusing every vertex in every, you know, three times, right?
The next one is try fan or I should say, the last one is try fan.
And what that is is almost the same only that uses a sliding window of
to, and never gets rid of the original.
So what that does is it starts with one and it says I'm going to just
keep one in the entire time.
And then I'm using a sliding window of to that slides downward, right?
One at a time.
So I'm going to draw a triangle that's one, two and three.
So it draws this triangle.
Then I'm use a triangle that's 1, 3 & 4.
So it draws this triangle right?
One that we've
never drawn before.
Then I'm going to use one that draws, one, four and five, right?
And that's going to be this triangle.
This giant triangle here then I'm going to use 156 right which is this
long triangle here and you might ask what on Earth?
Is that mess good for well?
Exactly what it sounds like if I wanted to draw something that looks
like a circle.
Let's say,
I could send down.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven,
twelve, thirteen fourteen, right?
Then it would just go.
Oh one, two, three, one three four one four, five, one five, six one
six, seven, one seven groups, 1781 eight, nine one, nine, 10 11, 10 11
10, 11 12, 13 21, 12 13, 13 14
114 to write.
Well, I'd have to send two again so I'd have to send this one one more
time if I want to close it.
Right.
So that's what triangle fans are 4 and you can see why it's called
triangle things like a fan of triangles a fan out around a point.
Not particularly commonly used, try strips are very commonly used so
that's that's what that is if that makes any sense.
All right, so I lost the Q Collins here.
I don't know where we are.
I don't know where we're at.
I should have paused my scroll.
I don't know.
I don't remember where I was in school.
Let's see if there's any more questions here.
You mention shortly to make a handmade sort of quicker which is slow
now because of what it would cost to do, how would I would think we
need to load textures first before showing here.
No, so texture load is not what slowing us down because our textures
are loaded on demand.
So it's actually showing us.
That is just creating the opengl context.
It's just amd's initialization routine.
It's that slow.
But we're creating to context right now.
14 texture download in one knot and one were actually three to four,
texture downloading and one regular.
And since I think we've basically determined that the
Context doesn't help you because the it doesn't actually help on
Nvidia cards as they had suggested.
It would we can get rid of those and just create one context, which
should make us roughly three times faster.
So that's all.
I was just saying, like, we go back there.
Get rid of those contexts and then we'd be three times faster.
Will still be a little slow because they just take a really long time
to create that context.
I wish they didn't NVIDIA drivers, don't have that problem.
A video drivers, start immediately but Andy's take forever for
whatever reason.
For people who do 3D meshes, it seems there's a rule or at least for
blender that, using anything else than quads, for topology produces
rendering artifacts.
So it has to be avoided is this because when rendering and game
everything gets split again into triangles.
Ignore the question of what I'm asking is to make sense.
Yeah.
So what what you're asking is a little bit of a it's a very deep
question that actually
Has absolutely nothing to do with rendering at all.
It has to do with what it has to do with topology, and the way in
which I'm not even sure how to begin answering this question.
It has to do with topology.
And the way in which essentially like two dimensional, manifolds wrap
around three to three dimensional objects and if you want to do stuff
that has to do with like Smooth curves, like subdivision surfaces or
smooth, mappings like texture mappings.
Then what happens if you don't have quads
Is you end up with unavoidable singularities are unavoidable artifacts
that are like, mathematically unavoidable, like, there's nothing you
can really do about them, and it really has nothing to do with
rendering the card.
Can that like the graphics card just needs things.
Broken up into triangles with, with, with information at the edges at
the vertices of the triangles and it can render anything that's of
that form.
But when you start to want to do
More advanced things with them.
The need to have things be locally planar.
And non collapsing is actually very important for a number of other
mathematical reasons and so you know,
That's something we'd go into probably in a lot of depth at this were
about 3D printing, but we're not going to get anywhere close to that
on hammy here because it's so not even remotely relevant to to what
we're doing that.
Make sense.
Ginger bill with opengl context creation, which B is the slow B.
Is it set pixel format?
As it may be visual studio 2013?
That is the problem in Visual Studio 2015.
This is not 2015 is not a slow, it could.
So
It could be that weird thing that they do where Visual Studio tracks,
the memory allocations.
And that's a good point.
Ginger Bill, actually, because we have not disabled that and we
haven't disabled that because we don't go through any of that stuff.
So if we disabled that Heap thing, it might make a difference.
Let's find out.
So if we run, you can see us taking a huge amount of time in here,
right?
And all of that's in the context creation.
It's in wiggle, create context, not in set pixel format.
um,
So, if we were to disable the debug Heap and I don't know if you can
do that in here, but we can do it external to here anyway, let's find
out.
How do I disable the debug game?
That may be the problem.
It may be that their drivers just doing hundreds of thousands of
allocations.
Wouldn't surprise me and that those are all getting slowed down
because they're going to the debug keep.
So, let's find out Visual Studio.
Thank you for mentioning that you do.
I never would have thought of that, but I just realized.
Yeah, we've never disabled the debug.
Keep on this machine, I normally do disable the debug keep.
I don't think I ever did hear disabled debug keep.
And if that was the case, then that would help a lot.
Where is, where is it?
No, no.
Here we go.
Let's see.
It is in advanced system settings, environment, variables, and then we
can set underscore.
No debug, keep equals 1.
Okay, let's give that a shot.
So actually let's let's give it a shot for for realsies.
Go ahead and put it in here into misc shelled up at.
And let's go ahead and spray it upset that
so set.
No, debug keep people's one and save that.
So there we go, close that out.
Close this out, close that out and see what happens if we go back in.
So, all right, so no, debug keep equals 1, which is what we want.
We launched, Ms, Dev which will inherit our environment variables here
and we run
Well, it's probably a little faster.
It's definitely faster but it's not as fast as I might have liked.
Let's try, let's see what happens if we start without debugging.
So that's going to be in.
Where is that was run?
I just want run.
Do we have a run here somewhere?
People project just run?
Hello.
Is it like shifter 5?
Used to be this is not anymore.
There must be some way to start without debugging there.
Always was in the past I guess I never really do that anymore but
there it is right there.
Control F5.
Alright let's try control F5.
I think that's as fast as it's going to get, unfortunately.
That's still kind of slow but like I said, we can get real, we can get
rid of that.
We can get rid of the extra context, frisson that may help, right?
but I think that may have helped a little because it
Much.
I feel like it was.
I feel like it was much lower than that before.
I feel like that did give us a little bit of a boost.
Soy sauce.
The kid is the fixed function g l stuff, still viable.
I want to do a grid Shader but the examples I'm finding are for Jill.
Sl3, I'm using glsl one on a Raspberry Pi.
Yeah, glsl one's pretty old.
And the fixed function g l stuff.
Is you really wouldn't like even we probably won't end up using that
in handmade hero.
I mean, we might still use GL vertex because we don't really probably
need anything there but yeah.
Oh, that wasn't a question.
Okay, nevermind, I'm sorry, right.
So yeah, just in case it was wondering what that was Visual Studio.
Has this debug Heap stuff that it enables and what happens is, if the
code that's running under the under the original Studio, has a bunch
of
Has a lots and lots and lots and lots and lots and lots of calls and
Malik which you know C++ happy code tends to do.
Yeah.
It's it ends up.
Slowing it down tremendously so I tried turning that off but it looks
like the am decode still pretty slow either way.
Now like I said, I think we'll still be able to do something about
that by not creating those extra debug contexts, so we can try that
and see but you just
No, like our startup time was, they'll a lot faster before, so before
we switch to the opengl context creation, so I'd like to get some of
that back.
Alright, that's about it.
Pretty day going to close down.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along the series at home, you
can always pure to the game on handmade here at a torque and it comes
to the source code.
So you can follow along at home.
We also have a forum site, you can go to to ask questions, we have a
patreon page, you can go to if you'd like to put the video series and
we have a tweet but you can look at if you would like to know what the
schedule is.
And speaking of the schedule, we are going to be back here next week.
I don't know what the
Jewel for the week will be but that tweet but is the right place to go
to find out until then.
I guess what I would say is if you're looking for more handmade hero,
handmade handmade after dark, which is f Yukon on the tweet on the
streams, sort of Chat Show, which has people from handmade hero will
be live tomorrow at 5 p.m.
eastern time, which is going to be 2 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time.
Tomorrow and I will be on the show as well as he and coronal Dragon,
and also stream Zack who I don't know, it was on the stream today but
sometimes he is.
So if you would like to see that you can check out handmade after
dark, it looks like in sohbat is tweeting that link for you as well?
And so I'll be there tomorrow.
Hope to see you guys there.
Until then take it.
Easy.
Have fun programming and
I will see you guys on the internet.