Okay, this is the Q&A for the first day of coding on handmade hero.
And what I would like you guys to do, if you can is put at seem your
ettore in any questions that you have so that I can see them clearly
on the IRC because there's a lot of you know chat that goes on there
and I want to be able to see basically what's going on.
I want to be able to see the the direct questions so I can answer
them.
All right.
Let's start with rice.
Oh, senior Tory.
Can you show how you added the handmade hero directly to the path?
You went a bit fast during the mainstream.
Absolutely, I can.
So let's go back into.
If you remember the place that I decided to do.
That was inside handmade misc.
There is a thing called shell dot bat inside shell dot bat.
Basically, it's this line right here.
So what this line does and I agree.
This is a little confusing and part of the reason.
I'm actually going to be going a little slower than I went tonight.
In the in future episodes because honestly, I didn't want to spend a
huge amount of time in all of this drudge work.
I just kind of laugh.
So here's how you do it, you know, off you go because once we went
done with it, we're done with it.
So yeah, I didn't believe her some of these points.
But basically, the way that it works is, if you are out here in the
command prompt and you hit set, just the word set and hit return, you
will get all of the environment variables that are set, and those are
variables that are local to this shell.
That basically anything can use.
So for example, here is one called winter.
It's winter equals c: windows.
And what happens is, if I type in percent the name, winter that
variable right.
And then another percent so I can close it by percents.
It will substitute in the value of that environment variable in place
of this, of this, what I typed here, right?
So when I hit return, it actually ders, whatever Windsor is right?
It does that dirt, okay.
So path.
If I wanted to reference what the current setting of path is that's
just percent path percent.
Now in the path, each individual thing to search for is separated by a
semicolon, right?
So there's this semicolon this right, semicolon this?
So what I did is I just say use the the the other version of set right
cassette with nothing lists everything, but set with a variable name
actually sets it.
So for example, for example, set handmade demo equals.
W:.
And handmade demo code or something, right?
If I do set now you will notice that handmade demo is actually a
variable that's actually set and that'll just be that'll live for the
lifetime of this shell window.
Anyone who wants to now in fact, Echo Prince things out so I could do
that.
For example, there it is, right.
There is my handmade demo.
So if I hit percent path up here, that means insert the value of path
as it stands right now.
So all
It hear what I just said, set path.
The variable equal to itself, but put before it right our thing.
So basically put us before everyone else.
That's all I did.
So that line right?
There is all you need to do to change the path.
It's pretty simple.
Okay, let's see here.
Where are we?
Why is my RC wigging out here?
It's going crazy.
Because I started with rice house.
Where did he go?
There we go.
Okay.
Sorry.
Sorry about that.
I do crazy.
I don't know.
Perhaps it.
Do.
Yo, Chrissy, do all windows programs written in C.
C++.
Use win?
Main does the witness have the same starter code yet?
Everything basically starts at win main.
So the witness doesn't, we're the code for the witness, the platform
code for the witness, and the platform code for handmade.
Here are very different.
Actually, the witness is much more sprawling with its proper platform
code.
I will be showing you, basically, the way to
Things in a much more lockdown fashion and that just comes from me
having shipped a lot of cross-platform code for a lot of years.
I guess I should cross platform for my very first thing that I did
professionally was cross-platform.
So I keep things like lockdown hard and the witness is not locked down
hard.
It's a little more typical.
I would say actually of Ginkgo basis where it's not, so locked down
hard.
So we will be doing a much more rigid barrier between the operating
system and the game whereas the witness is much more fluid.
Let's see using GCC a compiled without having to specify user through
D2.
Lib.
What is the difference here?
Between Microsoft compiler and GCC?
I don't know because I don't compile what you see on Windows, but I
would suspect that GCC basically has a different import library of
scheme.
Now, one thing that you should understand is that well, you know, what
should I break out?
Depends know.
We're going to save this.
We're going to save this for tomorrow basically, but so I'll say part
of it, but I'm going to
The rest of it, tomorrow, we'll see the rest of it.
But basically, what you're doing, when you're linking with these
libraries is you're not actually grabbing real code for the most part.
Normally.
What a library is a library of code that actually links into your
executable.
That's what a lib normally is.
But these are special lives.
These are import lives.
And what an import lib is is it's basically just a jump table in some
sense.
It's basically just a bunch of Stubbs such that when you actually get
loaded by the operating system, those stub calls will actually get
replaced with where the actual jump to the real code.
Or the operating system that gets mapped, you know, into your memory
space GCC, which I'm assuming you mean Ming went and being WS.
G CC, on on Windows may have a different convention for how it does
the import live.
So
You just already have them all and you may just linked with all of
them all the time or something.
I don't know.
I'd have to go look for GCC at GCC.
But what actually happens at the end is always the same, which is that
when Windows loads, it has basically a dynamic link patching system
that goes to your executable and patches, the places that it needs to
to point into itself.
So the calls work,
Let's see.
Do do what type of milk you're drinking almond milk.
How do you write a render?
That is Harbor accelerated?
We will be getting to that way.
Way way later.
We're actually going to be writing our own renderer first instead of
writing a her accelerated one.
So that people can see how to do every last piece of the thing.
Can we get your Dottie Max and you always code without line numbers?
Yes.
I always go without line numbers and the .m x value is included in the
source.
So if you download Source, you get the D-Max with it.
This is the most important question.
Let's see.
Will there be a sushi bar?
Samurai Easter egg and handmade hero.
Maybe we'll see if we use Visual Studio.
Do we need to tell the Linker?
Every Library will be using like you did?
Or is this?
Because of the different IDE?
If you are inside Visual Studio?
You?
I don't know which one's it specifies for you automatically.
It probably specifies, some for you automatically, but actually, yes,
you do.
There.
Actually is If You're Building inside there when you're in the project
settings, there actually is a
I don't know if I can show that easily.
Maybe I can in the old Visual Studio.
Let's see.
Can we do anything here now, we can't so this it's I'm sorry.
I can't really show you very effectively because we don't have an
actual project loaded here that will have those settings.
But basically inside the settings there's a Linker setting and it has
like additional Libs.
In there and you have to put the additional lives in there, so I don't
suspect you'll have to put user 32 because I suspect that's one of the
ones they probably add by default for you, but you may have to add
some like if you used windsock.
Like, if you use the sockets Library, you may have to put one's like
that for example.
Is there a reason you do not recommend using the developer command
prompt shortcuts from the start menu?
Which set up all the pasta for you and still let you run batch files.
Not particularly.
I just wanted to show you how to do it yourself.
He's talking about inside here.
If you go to, where is that?
Where is visual studio?
2013?
Is it in?
Why is it 2012?
Okay.
Well, who knows?
Inside here?
There's usually a thing.
Lets you actually, you know what?
I can't even find it though.
I guess would be the first reason.
Well, point being inside.
You should have had when you installed it.
There should have been some way for you to actually get to essentially
a
A launcher that will sort of make a shell for you to use with Visual
Studio, but I wanted to show you how to do that stuff yourself.
So you can make it again handmade hero.
Everything's handmade.
We're going to do everything from scratch.
That's just how it goes.
So if you want to, you can look for that one.
There's nothing wrong with that one.
I just want people to know what it was actually doing so you could
see.
How much experience do I have writing?
Audio processing code?
Not a whole lot.
I guess I just wrote you, I prosecuted you mean effects and filters
and stuff.
Not too much.
Let's see what you make a video about setting up a program environment
on Mac Linux, as well.
Yes, eventually, we will be doing that as well.
And I will basically show you how to setup emacs on those with a
command shell, that builds the game just like I do here.
Well, be a 2d or 3D game.
It will be a 2-D game.
Because I want to basically focus on how to do all of the I want to
focus on the code and not the math, 3D brings in a lot of a lot of
math.
It also brings in a lot of pipeline stuff.
That is not.
That is often.
Very transient.
That isn't going to last very long.
It's going to be different every year and so I was hoping with 2D
because there are a lot of great 2D games out there.
In fact, all my favorite games right now happened to be 2D.
I was hoping by going
2D I could focus on stuff.
That was more Timeless stuff, that will be good and that you want to
know forever instead of stuff that you'll only want to know like this
year.
Let's see to our streams know, we're only doing one, our streams plus,
and a half hour of question and answers, because it seemed like people
were not gonna be able to handle two hours.
What style of game are?
You making an approximate ETA on release?
The style of game will be announced probably next week when we sort of
get to there once we actually get to it.
I'll talk more about it.
But the ETA on release is completely unknown because as you may
imagine I have never tried to code something completely live before.
So I have no way of ball packing a time.
I feel like the fact I have to explain everything as I go is obviously
going to mean that it's going to take a lot longer than it normally
woods, and I don't know how to predict that.
Will the game be windows-only are with the Kobe from Mac as well?
The code will be for all platforms.
Yeah, we'll do a Mac, will do a Linux will do a Raspberry Pi.
So almost all the game code will be platform-independent, but then the
other parts will be platform dependent and I will show you how to make
one for each of them.
Let's see, will you do extended livestream exceptions such as delving
into a topic?
You're so interested in talking about in a, to talk about it.
Even after last year's already an hour long.
It's probably inevitable.
I mean, I'll try to keep that sort of thing to a minimum and I'll try
to keep the streams to basically be stuff.
That's educational things that you will want to know.
And if there's something that I feel that we should really talk about.
I'd put it in there.
But yeah, we might have some times where we just do kind of tangents
and stuff as important.
Can you show the command-line parameters that you set in the shortcut?
Yes, I
Han.
So, the command parameter parameter settings shortcut, they are here
and I will make them larger.
For you as well.
There's gotta be a way to make that bigger.
So let's see.
A Liberation mono 11, okay.
So this is what I did in the Shell.
I basically did / K which says start with this and then I did she'll
dot bat which is our shell that we wanted the thing that we wrote
together and that just basically means execute this on start up when
you start up.
So hopefully that's, that's really clear and you can see that there.
I can also if you guys want I can copy this into sort of a notes file
so that you'll have it when you get the source tree so I could do
that.
Let's put that in Shell dot bat.
So in Shell dot bat.
I'm just making a comment here.
It says.
To run this at startup use this as your shortcut Target.
And there we go, so they're okay.
Let's see.
What is your favorite Linux distribution?
And why is it Fedora little bit of leading question?
I don't have a favorite Linux distribution.
I just run whatever actually runs I'm running Ubuntu on this laptop.
That is to my left here that I'm reading the chat on and that is
because it's the only one that would install on it.
Actually none of the other ones worked.
At the time, that was my only choice.
Will I will I be able to follow you just using visual studio 2013
communication?
Yes.
I mean, Emax is just for editing code.
That's it.
And I am using visual studio Community Edition 2013.
That's what this is.
So you will literally if you just edit your code in there, instead of
an e Max, you are good to go.
There.
You won't be any different.
It's just text text.
This text.
Will you be pregnant in for alternative controllers like Xbox
controllers or arcade sticks?
Yes, we will.
At least do anything.
That is X inputs.
Corded.
So like Xbox game pads because they will probably be the thing we want
to use for this game anyway.
Should it not be /zi, instead of Dash, zi in build dot bat?
So, that's an interesting question.
So you notice, I put Dash t.i., The reason I put Dash t.i.
Is because I am a eunuch, see style person in dash, is how you
normally specify command line option.
In Unix Windows.
You often specify them that way in the compiler, it reads both, so you
can use either one that you want.
They guess, there are making basic concession to people who are used
to other platforms.
So you can use a slash.
Or a.
Either one works.
Will the game have multiplayer?
So there's two answers to that question.
Actually, it is a yes and no answer in some sense.
Yes, it will support multiplayer.
Meaning that I will show you how to write the code to make it so that
local multiplayer works.
I don't necessarily want to do networked multiplayer.
And the reason for that is because I don't know if we'll have time to
really do that.
So if we were going to do networked multiplayer, we'd actually do that
as sort of like after the game is out.
We'd add that as like a new string that was like, here's how to do the
networking or something.
But local
A player will definitely support.
The reason I say no to multiplayer is because I don't know if the game
design will support multiplayer.
So you will be able to play it with multiple players at the same time,
but we may disable that when we ship it.
If the design doesn't actually support it.
Does that make sense?
Because this is not really about game design.
This is about game programming.
So I'm going to show you the programming, for sure.
The design.
I don't know.
That may not happen.
Can you please remove the return, parentheses zero?
No, I cannot.
I like it there.
When can we get some details on the actual game?
Not until probably we're out of Windows and have a little bit of the
rendering up and going because I want to focus on the platform stuff
now.
And when we actually do start doing the game, I want that to be kind
of a fun thing that we get to do after we worked through the windows
part of things.
Why don't you just compile directly in Visual Studio?
Because I don't like.
It's editor is the is the entirety of the reason I prefer to edit in
emacs.
And I also find that if you, if you learn to edit in Visual Studio,
you end up with a problem.
When you want to go program on Linux or you want to go program on Mac,
which is that Visual Studio isn't on those platforms.
Emacs.
On the other hand is the same everywhere.
So I can use the same editor, on all the platforms, which I really
like because it means that I am super fast everywhere.
I go.
I don't have to downshift because now
QT Creator.
And it doesn't work quite the same as Visual Studio or whatever.
I like having the same editor on all the platforms.
So, one of the big things I look for in a text editor, is that it has
to run everywhere Linux Mac windows at least.
And if it doesn't, then I'm probably not interested.
Let's see.
How does it feel that?
You got more than 700 simultaneous viewers on the stream.
That is stunning.
I had no idea.
I was not watching the numbers but that's amazing.
I don't know how I feel about that.
That is crazy.
I guess the main way I feel about that is I wish that we didn't have
to do the first stream as a bunch of drugs, work to get the build
working.
That's probably honestly how I feel about it.
Tomorrow stream.
I think will be a lot more fun because we'll be doing, you know, hey,
we got a window up and running.
Okay, we're drawing to the window.
That's kind of more fun.
Right?
But hey, what can you do?
The main thing I'm trying to be in this series is honest.
I'm doing absolutely everything exactly the way I actually do it.
There's no lies in this stream.
So I got to do what I got to do the first day when I sit down in a
machine, and I don't have anything installed, and I don't have
anything set up.
I got to put kanui Max on it.
I got to put Visual Studio on it.
I did those beforehand because, I mean, you have to do like, reboot
some stuff too, like install Visual Studio off and stuff like that.
So, I did those beforehand.
So they wouldn't interrupt the stream, but I had to go do the actual
setup code.
And you know, is it that useful to people probably not it's
interesting perhaps for them to see how I do it.
But yeah, I mean, it's none of it's really necessary for you to do.
You can set up your development environment.
Anyway that you want.
And I encourage you to experiment with other ways to find the way that
you like best.
But this is how I always set it up and that's what I got to do when I
start a new project.
So, but now that it's done, don't have to worry about it again.
So that's at least a good sign, you know, it's quick and it can be set
up in an hour or so.
That's also good to.
If we were to go the route where we have used like ninja too.
Things that seem a can also, we'd probably still be fussing with make
files at this point because it would probably take two hours to step
the build.
So that is another good thing about using.
Just a simple build up that system is once you have build up at going,
your kind of, you know, you can quickly get building on any machine in
a very short amount of time.
How did you go from the XE built-in command line to using a visual
debugger?
So, that's a good question and I did show how it was done, but I
didn't make a big deal of it.
So I'm going to make a big deal of it now.
And also, by the way, when you close Visual Studio the first time, you
open it on an executable.
It makes basically a phantom project a.s Ln for it.
And when you exit, it's going to ask you.
If you want to save it.
You do want to save it because that'll save all your set up your
settings for your debugging.
So you do want to save that and it'll ask you.
I'm going to put it in the build directory, was going to leave it in
there and then, you know, we're a division studio.
So the way that I did it.
Now, if you remember I said, I said about that thing dead end, right?
And Deb M, it launches, the debugger, you know, launches it launches,
the, the IDE for us.
So if you want to, to bug an executable, you can type Deb em, and then
the name of the executable, you are trying to debug.
So I was trying to debug W build win32 handmade.
Boom, right.
So that is all you have to do to get into debugging is just just that
one line.
That's it.
And Devin is in the path.
If you've run that VCRs, all thing that we did to set up.
If CL is there, Dem should work as well because that VCR sets up the
path to both of them.
So anyway, this will do it.
But once you've done that, you can actually go into tools options and
there's a startup.
In here and environment their startup.
And there's at startup load last loaded solution.
You can set it to that.
I don't think it's set to that by default, but you can set it to that.
If you set it to that, then you never even have to do it ever again.
You can
Type Dev em and it'll come up and already.
It'll just be with the thing and you can just hit f11 to step in,
right?
Or F5 to run, right?
Or any of that stuff, f9c big points.
It's just it's good to go.
So you don't have to really do any setup.
You just Dem the executable off you go.
What GDP front-end do you use on Linux QT Creator, but I really don't
like it.
Let's see.
What else we got?
What did you work on while working on Bink video?
I well, I developed pink.
The second version of Bink.
Bink to the one that's available.
Now that is used in games.
Now.
I was basically just a second programmer for Jeff on it for the first
year and a half.
I guess.
I did all of the like, I guess all of the assembly code.
I think I did.
All of the assembly code for the initial version, which was basically,
which wasn't so much about optimization.
I mean, there was optimization and stuff that we did, but it was
mostly about getting stuff fast enough and being flexible with just
changes.
So Jeff would be like, we need to do this stuff to it.
And I would re I had a bunch of stuff that I made that would like
generate assembly and do things.
So space about facilitating him as he sort of tuned to the
compression.
And I also developed filters for him.
So I the filters that are used in there, I did, but after
I was a consult on that project.
After I signed off on it, Fabien giessen came on.
He's an excellent programmer.
And he's the guy who does that stuff now.
And he really came in and like, he's a guy who did the like, the, you
know, tighten down the ratchet.
He really came in and did all the, the going through every line and
optimizing everything like really well for every platform.
So, pink tutus platform.
Our positions are probably pretty awesome right now because Fabien
he's real good and it was in a good State, you know when we did.
The when Jeff and I did the first one but I think after Fabien got
done with it.
I strongly suspect that it is, it is pretty pretty incredible right
now, but, you know, that's just, that's just me.
Let's see.
As far as sound files Go.
Are we going to be handwriting dot wav and MP3 loading functions.
We're going to handwrite dot wave and I haven't decided yet how we're
going to talk about compression.
We are going to hand, write everything.
So we're not going to use a library.
So if we do do something with compression, we're going to have to
write it ourselves.
The very least will be handwriting.
Wha've but that's very very simple.
You'll be shocked how easy it is to handwrite wave, but when we go to
actually shift the game, you're probably going to want compression.
And so we will do something there, but I haven't decided what it is
yet.
That's a long, long ways away because that's like ship Time stuff.
So you don't have to worry about that any time soon.
We'll look at the chat for viewer answers while you work.
I'm sorry.
I don't know what that means.
Please consider five our streams.
I can't.
No one will be able to follow it.
I'm sorry, we got to do an hour a night.
I know it's painful.
But you know, I think you'll be surprised at how fast it goes.
Like I said, I think we'll have some pretty graphics on the screen
before Christmas and and that's pretty good.
Like, you'll be surprised how little work it is.
Now.
It's going to be a long time to we have a good game because there's a
lot of code that goes into a good game, but just getting something up
and running, you know, the Drudge work we did today is some of the
most drudgery represent to do.
Windows is going to go pretty fast.
I think and we'll have a nice little thing up and running where we
can, you know, move some Sprites around.
And then from there we'll be able to start really coding the game and
it will be good.
So five our streams aren't really that necessary.
Yes, we could blast through a lot more of it, a lot more quickly, but
it would be a lot harder for people to follow and the whole point of
this thing is for people to follow it.
So I really want to try and keep it to an hour and mainstream night.
It's a Q&A is get long.
The Q&A is get long.
That's fine.
But I want the mainstream to at least stay an hour's worth of coding
on the game every night, if you can follow that.
That you can follow the series.
Let's see.
Is there a design?
Document opinion, on design docs?
No.
We are going to do what is basically designed driven by awesome.
And awesome.
In this case will be what we think will be the most interesting thing
to code.
So we are basically going to spend most of our time sitting around
going.
Okay.
We finished that feature.
What would be the most interesting thing to try and code in this code
base now.
And if that's that everything needs to be lit on fire and the fire
needs to catch on things.
We're going to implement that if that's that we need to have like
secrets that are hidden throughout things.
And we're going to implement that if that's what we need a is that
chase you across multiple screens and try to block your progress or
things that we're going to code that.
So the game is going to all be about coming up, something, awesome.
Every time you finish an old thing and implementing that and we will
try to tune it so that it's a good game at the end of it.
But the goal for the design is going to be to get everything in there.
That's cool that is interesting to code.
So we're really going to focus on having lots of really intricate
gameplay things.
So that we can keep kind of pushing more and more stuff in that game
core and so that we can see how to keep it alive and keep it from
crushing under its own weight.
Right, which is a big problem that people have when they code things.
So we're going to we're going to really focus on that kind of like how
to add features how to keep things, Nimble, how to write stuff that
interacts well, with the other aspects of the design, that's really
going to be the focus.
So yeah, that's basically what we're going to do.
Let's see to do.
Are we able to open source?
Our own implementations?
Might need some lights in Clarendon this.
I would prefer it if you didn't until I release the code into the
public domain.
So basically I would like it if you keep your own implementations.
Oh, well, I guess that depends what you mean by that if you literally
re-implemented the whole thing like using your own code and weren't
just copying this code.
I would maybe that would be fine.
Either way.
Basically, what I say is, email me when you want to do that, like,
email me first and ask me because I would like the game to remain a
commercial game for two years at from, from from ship.
I would like that to be true.
So basically, what I would say is, email me, if you need to do
something before, then, if you really need to tell you before, then.
We've using fixed point or floating point for audio representation in
the game.
Floating point.
The spec is the reason the language works.
I don't know who said that.
I think they're laughing at it.
But yes, I don't care about this back at all.
I only care about what compilers do.
The spec is not relevant because the spec is only as relevant as what
compilers actually follow.
And so, I pretty much try to do what compilers actually do in a
compilers.
Do it, then I do it.
And yeah, that's, that's about all I have to say about that.
Let's see, when we move past Windows stuff.
We've returned to developing on Linux.
Are you going to stay on Windows for the bulk of the show?
I will probably stay on Windows for the bulk of the show, because it's
debugger is much better than any of the ones on Linux.
Visual Studio is a much much better debugger than any of the ones on
Linux.
If one of the newer debugger projects happens, to come to fruition and
is running on Linux, during the stream.
Maybe we'll switch over there.
But until Linux has a really good debugger.
I wouldn't use that as the primary platform.
I'm for demoing where we go through and we step through things.
Will you be making generic 2D animation system for rotating scaling,
2D Sprites over time along with an external editor for these
animations?
We will not use an external and editor website, will not write.
An external editor will probably use an existing editor like spriter
or something, but we will write a 2d animation system.
How long after the stream each day, is it going to take for the vid to
be uploaded?
YouTube?
It's the videos uploaded immediately.
But YouTube takes a long time to produce the various compressions of
it.
So it usually takes several hours before video fit before YouTube
actually has like the 1080p stream up.
For example, sometimes it takes many many hours for that.
But twitch instantly archives it.
So you can go on twitch under past broadcast and see them right away,
but those like disappear after a little while.
So the YouTube
Basically the backing archive because the twitch only archives for
like two weeks or something.
Let's see.
Do you have everything planned already or you coming up with ideas on
a daily basis?
I don't have everything planned.
I have you know, I have a relatively full game planned but that's just
because I wanted to have something planned.
It's very flexible.
And like I said, we'll be trying to go driven more by what's going to
be interesting to code.
And so I have a design that is what we'll start with, but we'll be
free to kind of mutated as we go and add interesting things as we go.
Why don't I run?
Windows 8, 8 .1, I would turn that around and say why would you run
Windows 8.1?
There is nothing.
That Windows 7 is not doing for me that Windows 8 does for me.
So doesn't seem particularly useful.
OBS seems not to render some of the pop-ups that show in Visual
Studio.
Yeah, I'm worried about that.
And what I would like to do is I think because the serious is seems to
be very popular already.
I think what I'm going to do is try to order like some kind of
external capture card so I can just capture the Monitor and I don't
have to worry about OBS, missing stuff.
Because yeah, it came up like tooltips, don't show up either.
Apparently that at least, that was something that was said in the live
stream.
So so I worry about that.
Let's see how much emphasis on math and physics for the 2D game.
Well, I'm not going to try.
I'm going to try not to make it too terribly math heavy because it's
more about code that about math but there is a fair bit of math that
has to happen for the code to work.
So there's going to be, you know, you're going to get a pretty good
workout of your of your high school trigonometry at the very least and
you'll learn some, some linear algebra by osmosis, but we're talking
really simple.
Linear algebra here like vectors.
We're not talking about a singular value decomposition.
Position.
I recently looked at the Doom, 3 source code, and also at the ID style
guide, you have some guidelines for variable names and stuff.
No, I think you should name variables.
Whatever it is, that makes you the most comfortable reading them.
The advice earlier was, you should look at the stream more frequently,
or even better, get an intern to do it.
I don't have an intern.
But yes, that would be fun.
I'm afraid I can't because I have to concentrate on what I'm teaching,
but I tried to basically say hold everything for the
You a?
And if something, you know, I realize that people are trying to sort
of give me advice and stuff in the middle of string, but that's just,
that's just the price of doing business.
When we do get, if we do get an intern in here, maybe but I don't know
about that.
Oh, do I know if I got the quality?
Seems friendly?
Yes, I guess I did get quality settings to Twitch twitch upgraded us,
because I guess, because of all of you really, I'm sure it was because
the stream was popular.
So you made that happen.
Twitch.
Now, apparently has quality settings on this stream.
Not many people.
Get that.
I guess.
You have to be more popular or something.
I don't know what.
It is, but so it's awesome.
I'm super psyched.
They did that.
So thank you to all of you for making this dream popular, because I'm
sure if we didn't have hundreds of viewers, they would not have done
that.
Any chance you could stream earlier.
It's 5 a.m.
Here in Europe.
No, unfortunately not.
I have to pick a time and that time is going to be problematic for
people, either.
People are going to be at work, or it's going to be too late or
they're going to be asleep, etc.
Etc.
So we're doing 8 p.m.
PST.
That's just the way it is and I apologize.
I put all the videos up right away.
So hopefully it's easy to keep up even if you're in a different time
zone, but and like I said, they're on Twitch immediately.
So you can you can keep up that way as well.
But I am going to try to do basically Fridays.
I will do the stream at a different.
Time or something?
We'll try to pick up.
Best time.
That overlaps the least with a p.m.
PST, basically.
So that people who are in different time zones that are not fortunate
that, don't, fortunately coincide with a p.m.
PST can basically, at least get on one livestream a week, that that's
what that's the compromise that I kind of worked out in my head.
I hope that's okay with people.
You have an actual repo for the project know you will just basically
get a zip file.
If you get the source that has a zip file in it for every day.
So you can just go grab a day you want.
And if you would like to make a repo for your own personal use, you
can just use whatever source code control system, you want and just
unzip the contents over your existing directory and check it in.
So you can basically just trivially automate.
The process of having your own repo in any source code control system,
you want.
Which better Linux debugger programs?
Are you looking forward to?
Well, there's one called like Pro dbg.
I don't know if it's going to come to fruition or not.
But there's that and rad and valve or are partnering to do one.
And I don't know, you know, which of those will come to fruition or
how they'll go or any of that stuff.
But if one of them does and it's good then, you know,
Then that's good Windows 7, doesn't support avx2.
Well, you know most people probably aren't running avx2.
So I don't know that we should use that in our renderer.
But you know, yeah, it's true.
We could we could we can consider that, I don't know.
Is, are you sure there's not some way to get that to work though?
I don't know.
Point being will cross those bridges when we come to it, but at that
would probably be a week reason to upgrade to Windows 8 will send I'll
be the only method down to the D-League.
Any chance of some type of repo, sorry, only I just answered that one.
When a scripting language, we use in the game.
No window capture doesn't capture the right click menu by default,
monitor capture, should capture everything, but I am using monitor
capture, and it doesn't seem too.
I'll see if I can tweak the settings, but it doesn't seem to did.
I consider doing a Kickstarter for this series?
I did not.
And the reason was twofold one.
I had no idea.
This many people would be interested in it.
So what I thought was going to have to happen was I was gonna have to
do the stream for six months, end up with a cool game.
At that point.
That was like, you know, still a ways away from being done, but it was
obviously cool.
And then people go.
Oh, there's this cool game.
I played it and oh, by the way, the whole development was captured so
I can go watch.
To it and learn how it was done.
And that would be how people would get into it.
I didn't realize that people would be so excited about doing it from
the start.
So there was that.
So I was like, I don't know what I'm gonna Kickstart My okay.
Let me kick start this project that you don't even know the game and
I'm going to tell you you want to watch it being made like I don't
know and and I'm all into low level game development.
I want to teach you all these crazy things and everyone's gonna be
like, I just want to make a game in unity, like or whatever, right?
So, you know, I
I didn't know.
So I didn't do a Kickstarter for that reason, but the second reason
was also I just kind of wanted to do this as a project and I felt
really strongly about it.
In fact, so strongly that I did it expecting that.
No one would watch it for six months.
And because I felt so strongly about it.
I didn't really want to do a Kickstarter because I felt like that
would be somewhat disingenuous.
A Kickstarter to me kind of says that I want money due to this project
and and if I don't get the money then I can't do the project or
something.
But the truth is I was going to do this project, whether I got money
or not.
It's like I will pay for it out of pocket off.
Find a way, you know, I'll consult or do whatever.
I'll make money to support it if I need to.
But like, I'm going to do this project.
So I felt they would kind of be disingenuous to have a Kickstarter
because it's like I I this product is going to get made and I don't,
you know, expect you to fund it because I'm going to fund it.
The fact that people have been so supportive of it and have been
pre-ordering the source.
A lot of people say just to support the project like they're not even
saying that they want to appear to be in there.
Like I'm just doing, this is Brother products.
Great idea.
Has been amazing.
Like that's so incredibly cool.
It's basically like I got
Kickstarter, you know, backing essentially because people were so
generous and that's amazing.
And honestly just a fact that people did that to makes me so excited
about the stream because I feel like I feel like it's going to go so
well.
Now I feel like we're going to get to these milestones and like every
week we're going to have something cool to show and everyone in the
Stream is going to be pumped about it because it's like we spent five.
We only spent five hours on the stream.
We've got this cool thing going, and we spend another five hours.
I've got this new cool thing in, and every week.
There's going to be a new cool thing.
That everyone was part of and everyone saw every last thing I did.
I think that's going to be awesome.
And so I'm so excited that all these people are excited about it and
are watching and and want to support it.
It's just awesome.
I'm really psyched.
Quality seems worse today than yesterday.
Is that?
Because we have more Watchers.
I don't know.
Maybe I need to upgrade my internet connection.
Let me know if the quality degrades over time so we can to do
something.
I'd like to suggest an almond milk power for the game.
Alright that's going in the notes.
There will be a nominal power up in the game period almonds.
Milk powder up done.
Excellent, excellent suggestion.
You could set up a poll to run for the week.
Letting viewers vote on the best time to stream on Fridays.
We could do that.
That is not a bad idea.
I will write that down as well.
I don't know if I want to do that because the problem too, is that, I
mean, I work during the day and so I might have to keep it to a
regular schedule because I have to kind of schedule my work week to
make it work, but I'll think about that.
What do you think about learning math concepts by reading Wikipedia?
I think it's horrible.
I don't know why it's so bad.
Wikipedia is a fantastic resource.
And I love that site.
But any time I try to go there to read math.
It's like the most dense super antiseptic math.
And like, I can't even really learn from their like, I think you have
to already know the math to understand the math on Wikipedia.
You have to basically a real math person.
So, yeah, I wouldn't try to learn math from there.
I'd try to find good books on the particular thing.
You're trying to read trying to learn because Wikipedia is hard, it's
hard.
Let's see.
Is there a significant difference between the normal C code and an API
that we interface with dedicated graphics cards?
I'm sorry.
I don't super understand that starchy pancakes.
Can you be more explicit?
We are all excited that you're doing this in C.
So am I I love see.
There will be a little C++.
We're going to compile as dot CPS.
So they'll be a little C++.
We will probably use operator overloading and function overloading.
I also use declare anywhere but that's in c99 as well.
I believe.
So that's not really C++ anymore.
Used to be used to be that see doesn't allow you to declare things
other than at the start of a block.
Let's see.
Would you be planning to get the kickstarter?
As you're done with this half way?
I'm sorry.
I'm not sure what that means.
Ed's one show.
Let's see.
Orlando Bloom, I definitely purchase Justice brother product, but
there's a frowny face.
Oh.
I'm sorry.
I didn't want you to frown about that.
I hope you will smile.
Oh, I see you damn iPhone keyboard.
You say?
Okay, so maybe that wasn't supposed to be a frowny face.
That was supposed to be something else.
Okay.
Hopefully you're happy about pre-ordering.
I guess you actually word.
That's cool.
Let's see, just planting the seed super hand man.
Here of the 3D math and physics.
T-sql.
Ha ha.
Yes, you know, I'm sure that when we get to the end of this, if some
reason people have watched a year or two of streams every night and
somehow, what they
After that, they're like, you know, what we need is another two years
of streams.
You know, what I'll be used to it.
So I'm totally fine with that and we can do 3D handmade hero after we
do handmade hero because yeah, I mean honestly, that'd be the right
time to do it because you need to learn all the if you can't write a
great 2-D game.
If you can't read a great to decode base, forget, right in a great 3D
code base because 3D has a ton more math than a ton, more moving Parts
in it, right?
So the right way to do it.
Anyway is Right a great 2-D game, then write a great 3D game for sure.
And so even if we were going to tackle 3D, we would do it this way.
Anyway, we just say we're going to do a 2d first and they're going
through because you gotta learn the 2D before you learn the 3D.
You've got it because 3D is just a super set basically, so
Could you consider dropping the framerate a bit?
I don't know if we need 60.
I don't set the frame rate, do I?
I will I will look into that frame rate.
Setting, if I set it.
I would be happy to drop it to 30 because yes, we don't need 60.
Let's see.
While we're at it.
Let's have a risk.
Love power up.
Ha, ha ha, at the risk of giving too much away.
Well, you know what?
I'm not going to give too much away.
I'm just gonna skip that question for now.
Can you recommend some good books tutorials know?
Unfortunately, that is why I even did that intro to see stream as the
test dream was like, I don't even know where to point people.
To learn, see the original K.
In our book.
The C programming language is probably the right place to learn it.
But like, I made the intro stream because I was like, you know, what?
If people don't know any see at all, you know, they only know, like
JavaScript or Java or something, or python.
I'm like, I don't know what to tell them to use for a prerequisite.
I'm going to be on the stream going.
Well, if you don't know what a pointer.
Is then go read.
So I did that intro to see stream just so you could kind of see stuff,
pun intended, you know, that you can kind of go watch the under the
sea stream and kind of get see, as opposed to the whatever programming
language are used to, you know, whatever it is that you know, how to
make C sharp or whatever.
And you can just kind of see me go through the basics of it, the
really, really Basics to kind of bring you up to speed on that.
So hopefully, that helps but, you know, if I, if people send in good
references, I can try to post them later, if their turn
Zhou to the good ones.
When you did that struct instead of class was because you're calling
the file CPP instead of c key term 87.
I'm not sure I understand what that means.
Just to be clear.
I mean, this is the off topic a little bit but it only take a few
seconds and I planned on doing a long queue a tonight because I
figured people would have a lot of questions on the very first Dream.
Even though we're not, even though all we did was set the bit of our
favorite people would just get the question presses out of the way.
So struct
If you define something as basically lets me put some stuff together
that I want to allocate together in memory base.
They want to talk about together in memory.
If I say struct Foo, that just says, I need, you know, covered this
the interest rate, but that's the space that says I'm going to create
a new type.
That is basically a composite of other types, right?
And they're laid out sequentially in memory X, then y, then Z, but I
guess the person is asking what's the difference between the class and
the struct?
And why do you type one of the other?
Well, the answer is largely.
It's just
Just whatever.
Your convention is in C and C++ class.
Well, actually, there is no class in C.
But in C++.
There is no difference between Class instruct.
The only difference is whether things default to being private or
public.
So, there's these access control specifiers, which we will never be
using in this stream called public and private.
And they basically have to do with who can access the variables.
You will never see us, do one in this in the Stream.
So, it's not really relevant to this.
But basically, the difference is in,
Struct everything defaults to public.
So, struct is a is essentially this write struct Foo is the same as
class food public and by inversely, I guess I should say struct
through private is the same as class through.
But there's no other differences.
Really.
That's really the only main difference between the two things.
You can freely switch between them.
They're not actually different in practice.
The compiler, does the exact same thing with them.
So it's really just whether it defaults to
To public or defaults to private.
That's it, since I want everything to be public.
I always type struct.
If you wanted everything to be private.
You should type class.
That's it.
That's all.
I guess what I'm wondering is how the implementation of running code
would change and taking advantage of dedicated graphics as opposed to
using the GP.
The CPU will will get there.
But basically what we do is we write the renderer in such a way that
all the stuff we want to leverage with.
The GPU is underneath a certain API barrier and so we can later just
Vector.
Those API calls over to the GPU instead of to the CPU.
Basically.
That's all we're going to do.
It's pretty straightforward.
Actually, you'll see.
Guitar m87 making structure.
So yes, you can make instructors instructs.
There's no difference between a class of a struct.
Just trust me on that one.
They're exactly the same.
It's just whether defaults to public or private girl and of Bloom.
I'm happy about pre-ordering.
Definitely even if the games that crappy, this is going to be awesome
to watch.
Thank you.
Okay.
Good.
It's want to make sure.
There were no frowny faces.
Earlier, you told us you're not playing to make the kick starter since
you don't like the idea of getting crowd funded by something that you
can't show and work as you go.
So why not when you're halfway through and show you don't get the
kickstarter started.
Okay.
Well, I don't think I need the kickstarter.
I like I said, it's got that pre-order button.
Lots of people, you know, did the pre-ordering?
I mean, you know, I'm not greedy.
I don't need a Kickstarter as well.
If you want to support the project you can click on that and that is
great support for me.
So I don't think I need a kick starter in a
Listen to it because I think especially also as the game gets cooler
and cooler, people will just want to preorder the game who aren't even
watching the series or something.
So, you know, I don't know.
I'm hopeful that we can just fund it through that basically, and that
will be a reasonable reasonable source of funding for me, doing the
project and me paying the artist to do art, for the project, and
Licensing, the music.
And so on, if it turns out that I'm broke and I can't then sure.
You know, I'll go to Kickstarter and ask for money, but, you know,
until then.
I'd like to just go with the pre-orders and see if that works.
Are you plan to have descriptive names for the YouTube archived
videos?
Yes.
Well, names, maybe not.
I try to put some things in the description, but I'm going to separate
them into playlists basically, because like, for example, this one
might be named because it's just how to set up the build on Windows,
but then we might take four or five days to do the windows code.
So, I might make a playlist called, like making the windows code,
right?
And whether each of those things will be named.
I'm not sure, but I'll try.
Looks like it was already 30 FPS someone earlier was complaining that
it was 60 FPS.
Sorry.
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
So we are already 30fps.
So there's nothing I can do.
Sorry.
We're already 30 FPS.
That's as low as it probably going to go.
Since you're in the mood to deny saying spoils, what's up with the
handmade hero icon on the twitch page, tell me elaborate more.
What do you mean?
What's up with it girl?
And oh, Bloom.
I learned a lot from the intro streams, even though I programmed in
CSS for several years and halfway made a game using opengl and all
that is awesome.
I'm really glad to hear that.
That is cool because that's exactly the stuff.
I want to bring to a stream.
I want you to see stuff in this dream that you don't see anywhere
else.
I want it to be all the kind of minutiae like professional Game Dev
stuff that people gloss over.
And more importantly, I also want to show the mistakes, capturing them
steaks is really important to me.
I want you to see me mess up and to see how I recover from those
mess-ups because that's one of the biggest things that gets left out
of a lot of teaching materials is they just show you the finished
thing.
They're like, here's how I think you should write blah, but they
didn't show you the steps that got you there, you know.
So if I just show up and say, hey, here's this cool game.
It's got all these cool features in it.
And here's how to write it.
Well, that's not that interesting because you didn't see all the
iterations.
I had to go through to get that code to that point and that's a huge
part of game development.
No, professional game developer sits down and writes the right code
for their game.
The first time ever never happens.
The only time that could happen is if you wrote the exact same game
before.
So what I really want to show on this stream is me trying things.
So, okay.
We want to implement fire.
Here's how we get to let it fire the first time, but then
Didn't work as well.
Because of this.
It was a little messy.
I didn't work with this system.
So we changed the way we did fire and we went through several
iterations and eventually, you know, down the line.
We've got a really cool system for handling fire, something, right.
That's the kind of thing that I really want to show in the Stream
because I think that's the part that really like kind of levels you up
into a better.
Developer is knowing how to do those iterations.
Right.
And recovering from your failures.
It's like it's way more important to be able to recover from a failed
architecture attempt.
Then it is to get the architecture attempts, right the first time
because nobody
ever gets to that point.
Usually nobody ever gets to the point where they're doing The
Architects.
All right?
The first time and even if they were that probably means they're not
really doing that good architecture.
Because usually every time I write new stuff, I come up with better
things every time because I learned from the last time and so it's
always good to just keep iterating.
Keep be thinking rethinking how you're going to do things.
Okay, are you going to be ditching pound include Windows, .h?
Maybe I don't want to give away too many Secrets there.
Anybody to 23, how often do you need to hit the debugger?
Do you rely on a lot for your coding style all the time?
I just run in it so every time I run the program, I alt Tab and I
write it into the debugger.
How often I actually debug depends on how intricate the code is, and
how many bugs I got basically,
Yeah.
I noticed this new scope to the for Loop in some of the code that ran
by.
Why do you Scope the for Loop?
The way you do that is in one of the intro stream qas, if you would
like to look at it.
That's your ettore for syntax.
I'm going to try not to use that.
Actually on the stream.
It's Antiquated and it's something that only I ever did.
It's an anachronism that was for handling, GCC and msv.
See cross compatibility back in 1996.
Microtransactions are all the rage need to add a couple of those.
I totally agree.
I would never actually Implement a game with real microtransactions to
because I think they are a really bad way to treat your players, but I
would certainly put in joke microtransactions so we can certainly,
think about that.
Let's see with the game.
F.2d lighting.
Yes, it will.
Can you do the whole game with test-driven development?
No, because games are not really very amenable to test driven
development.
Some things we will be able to drive by tests.
But most things we won't because they involve user input.
And user input is very difficult to do in a test driven way.
You can do fuzz testing, you can do randomized, input testing and
those are good ideas, but unit testing is very hard in those
circumstances.
Choo choo!
Will there be an option to pre-order for a friend as a gift?
I don't know.
I will ask send owl, they do the order processing and I am not.
I mean, I'm not a web guy.
So I don't know how to do half that stuff.
So I'll ask them and we'll see, are there differences between C
structs and C++ trucks?
Yes.
There are C++ trucks.
Can do everything that C++ can do in a class because like I said,
they're the same so we can have member functions.
It can have public-private declarations.
It can have overloaded.
Stuff do anything it wants?
In see, none of that stuff exists so you can't do those things.
There's no public and private and see, I don't think unless they add
it in c99, there used to be so C++ trucks are have a lot more stuff
you can do in them than than C structs.
We won't really be using any of them, but you can if you if you just
want crazy stuff.
When does the street behind you turn green?
Yeah, I need a green screen.
That's true.
We should just hung a green screen up there so I can appear like, I'm
in some crazy, tropical locale.
You're working with artists already.
But what about sound effects and music.
Are you going to leave sound alone for long time?
No sound will come in right away.
I will record it on my little pocket recorder for sounds for stand-in
until we have the game, you know, closer to finished.
And we want to ask for final sounds and music.
I already license.
So musical go in right away as well.
As soon as we have sound playing, will have music playing.
Let's see.
If you have this much viewers on a regular basis, you'll soon, have a
subscribe button partnership with twitch which will give you some cash
to.
I don't know anything about that.
I don't understand any of this streaming stuff.
I only just set it up because it seemed like what people could use.
And I really want to be able to
Live.
I thought that would be a cool thing to be able to do so, I don't know
anything about twitch subscriptions.
Since you said, you aren't a game designer, how do you plan to design
a good game from this?
Well, basically I'm not, you know, I'm not ignorant of how to design
games.
Like, I know, I talk to my friends who are excellent game designers
all the time.
I understand the things they're talking about.
I understand the basic mechanics of game design.
So I will be able to design a traditional game, just fine.
Like, I'm sure I can handle a game that is not avant-garde, right?
So I'm not going to
And make a game.
That is like, oh, it's the emotional Journey.
If someone is told Through The Eyes of their pet goldfish, who got
cancer recently and had to go to a thing, but it's really a dream
sequence.
And at the end you realize something about, you know, your sexuality
or something like those are like super Advanced game, designing sorts
of things that people are doing nowadays where they're like trying to
talk about like basically doing more.
Or high-concept stuff in games.
And I don't have the skill set at all to do any of that stuff.
Like, I'm not good at it, and I don't really know how to do that sort
of stuff.
So, if you want me to design like a game, that's different from
traditionally.
How games have worked.
That's really not something that I'm going to be able to do.
Right?
So I'm intentionally staying away from that.
Our design will be very, very traditional.
It will be a game where, you know, you go off on an adventure where
there are monsters who try to stop you.
You know, you adventure around and find cool things that is, you know,
the extent of the high concept for this game.
So it will be more like, you know, you were playing an old-school
console game with the old little paddles, where there weren't like
cutscenes trying to tell like a story to you or things like that.
So so that's basically what I mean by the game design.
So I am not a professional game designer and I don't want to take on
the responsibility of trying to show how to make a new great game
design that no one's ever done.
Before because I just don't have the qualifications for that.
I would love to see someone do that stream.
I am very interested in new types of games.
I like it.
When people like, I really liked, you know, saying like I like to
start Steed starseed Pilgrim.
A lot.
It was pretty cool.
And, you know, I really like kind of wacky games and stuff like that,
that are that do interesting things.
So, I would love if people made streams where they talking design
because I could learn from that, but I can't do that.
That like I don't have the capability that.
So,
let's see.
You probably already answered this, but why start from scratch versus
using an engine?
Why reinvent the wheel?
It's a good question and the answer is twofold.
One is
Because I think it's important for game developers who are going to be
serious, programmers to learn everything about how a game works.
And if you start with an engine, then it it basically changes.
What you're learning from the fundamental truth of how to implement a
game to someone else's version of that.
They have basically gone from what the actual game code actually does.
And put a big old giant layer in between you and that.
So now, what you're really learning is that
Engine you haven't learned how to make games, you've learned how to
make games in unity, right?
And if Unity were to disappear, for example, you would no longer know
how to make a game at all.
I'm not exaggerating this.
That's just the truth.
And so while there's nothing wrong with making games in engines,
because that may be the most efficient way for you to make the thing
that you want to make.
I don't think you can have a complete game development education as a
programmer without learning how everything works, right down to the
core principles that have been.
True for the past several decades.
That's how a CPU runs a game.
And so I think those are essential to learn and I wanted to show them.
So if people want to use engines, that's totally fine, but that is the
opposite of what I'm trying to show here.
I want to show how all that stuff works.
And I want to give people the ability to make their own engine stuff
as necessary as well, because even if you go use an engine like unreal
or something, to make a game knowing how all of it.
It works underneath.
Makes you so much more powerful even in that engine because now, it
means you don't just have to look at the Docks and guess how the thing
kind of doing it.
You know, how the Thing Really Works and so you can go.
Oh, I know there must be a way for unreal to do x y z because I know
that's how the CPU works.
And I know it can do it.
So let me go find how to do that or white my own plug-in that can do
that for me.
And now you're so much more powerful.
You don't have to be like hamstrung by the things that they allowed
you to do.
In that sort of layer, right?
So it's empowering.
It's educational.
That's all good.
But the second thing I wanted to point out is saying reinvent, the
wheel is a very misleading statement.
And it always bothers me a little bit.
When people say things like, why reinvent the wheel and the reason is
because the wheel is an amazing invention.
It is almost perfect or even possibly perfect for what it does.
When you look at a wheel, it is the thing that perfectly turns,
Dynamic friction into static friction for moving objects, right?
It's something that is so elegant and beautiful.
That, if you ask me, why you would want to
That I would say, of course.
You don't want to reinvent the wheel.
The wheel is amazing.
It is worked for thousands of years.
It has been unchanged for thousands of years.
The concept is the same today as it was when they first made a wheel,
probably, right.
It does exactly the same stuff physically.
Nothing, we have developed in the past 30 years of game development is
a wheel.
We do not have a single wheel if you think Unity is a wheel or you
think unreal is a wheel that is just it's just plain short-sighted.
Like I'm sorry, but that's the truth.
In the future.
We will have so much more powerful tools for game development.
That they will make the engines we use today.
Look like a joke.
People will laugh at the things that we did to make games today.
And the reason that I point that out is not to diss on those things
because they are the best engines we have today.
So yes, if you need to use an engine you want to use some of these
things, right?
But I want to point out the fact that if we want to get to a real
wheel that when you really do say to me, why would you reinvent the
wheel?
I would say, you shouldn't use the wheel if we want to get to that
wheel.
We need people making new things that attempt to be a wheel and you
can't do that.
If all, you know, how to do is program stuff in unreal or Unity
because that's all you get.
That's the
Square wheel, right?
That's kind of clunking around.
And if all you're ever gonna do is build cars on top of that.
They're going to be lousy, right?
Unless you're driving on a road that looks like this.
So basically what I want to inspire to as part of the series, if I
can, as I want people to look at this and go, hey, wait a minute,
low-level game.
Programming is not that hard.
I saw him do it.
I saw how he did it and I'm starting to understand this, I could go do
this and if they get into it and get excited about it, then they may
be the people who make
make those next engines that allow a whole new wave of game
development to happen.
Just like Unity allowed.
So many more people to make games who didn't have that knowledge,
who's going to be making those things of the future, right?
And so that's why I think Lil program is so important is because we
need lots of people with those, with those talents and those skills to
get us to the point where it really is silly to be working on anymore,
but we are so far from there.
Me.
Let's see.
Stream is going to happen every weekday at the same time.
It can you name a subreddit?
Can you name the subreddit as the official Community Hub are set up?
An official Forum?
I so if you have a good idea of how to do an official Forum, you are
welcome to email me.
I was trying to figure out how maybe that should happen, but I
couldn't figure out a good place.
I could maybe pay to host it or something where it wouldn't just get
all spammed up.
I've had bad experiences with forums where they take a lot of
Maintenance work and spammers start registering on them and stuff like
that.
And so, if there really is a way to set up a reliable Forum that
people can use that.
Don't get all spammy.
Please email me.
You can use the the button on the on the handmade.
He rode up or website and email me because I would be interested in
setting up before arm eventually.
Yes.
Let's see to all the people who are saying, thank you and saying that
they learned more in their University.
Thank you.
Thank you for turning it tuning in teaching is very important to me.
I love doing it.
I love explaining things.
It's a lot of fun and the fact that people are are listening to it and
getting something from, it makes it so much more rewarding for me.
Like I really can't.
Thank you enough.
So thank you very much for tuning in.
I really appreciate it.
You do not need to thank me.
I am having a blast and just the knowledge that people are starting to
see this stuff and get into, it is everything that I wanted to have
happen.
So like this you are making this series as a success before it has
even gotten off the ground and and for that, I am so grateful.
So, yes, thank you.
Thank you very much to all of you.
Let's see.
Do do do, do do.
Can you explain your choice to mix and C++?
Why not code with just see or pure C++.
I'm not sure.
What pure C++ is, since C++ is just see with stuff added on top of it.
So there's really no such thing as pure C++.
Obviously there is such a thing as pure C, which is just C or C 99
without any of the C++ editions.
The reason that I didn't want to do that is because there are some
features of C++ that I like such as operator overloading.
Math and function, overloading.
I like those too.
I use them fairly frequently and I don't see a really good reason not
to use them especially because, if one were writing a compiler to
compile handmade hero, they don't take much effort to support.
So if you were trying to write a compiler from scratch, that can
compile handmade hero, which is a project that I would love to do it
in the future and maybe that'll be some kind of separate stream as
well.
Or you know, who knows?
Maybe, I'll tie into what John's doing.
For example, if
Those of you who have been keeping up with Jonathan blows making a new
language, which is super awesome.
You know, basically, I didn't feel like those features would be
additional think if I started using like templates and stuff like
that.
Those start to add a lot of complexity to your language.
And so there are, you know, you could see why if you really wanted to
use those, you might say.
Oh, maybe I won't use those because it will keep it simpler.
But overloaded operators are overloaded functions are really easy to
implement in a language if you've already implemented the basics of
see that you need to compile it, so I didn't see any reason to
To gopura see because I'm not sure what the benefit would be all C
compilers or C++ compilers at this point.
So it's you know, llvm which is what we'll be using on the other
platforms.
You know, it's way better than visual studio.
So visual studios are our Baseline for C++ compliance and it's way
more than what we need.
So I figured just compiling and CPP was better in general because it
meant that we could use some of those extra features without actually
incurring any complexity for people who want to play with the source
code later in a way that would require require them to be able to
parse it.
In handle Advanced features.
Are you a tool that converts almond milk into code on the stream?
I am I don't actually I actually convert Almond Roca two streams.
Normally during the day.
I do drink almond milk out of these same bottles like this, but I
drink it much less frequently.
The reason I do it here is to keep my voice from going.
It just helps me not get laryngitis on the stream, basically.
Is there a Game Dev company that you really admire?
In other words being how you think makes great games the right way.
If not, do you have at least a favorite game?
I don't know.
I mean, you know, I haven't worked at many game companies.
Really.
I mean, I worked at rad for a long time.
That's a game tools company.
I'd like rad.
I mean, they're good company.
That's why I worked for them for so long.
So they're a good company, but for game companies, I don't know.
I'm not really a position to say.
I have to go work at a lot of different.
Bunnies and really judge their prosthesis, I guess.
But also the other thing is
developing games.
The right way is just developing games that ship reliably and aren't
buggy and are performing.
Well, you know, I mean, I mean the proof is always in the pudding.
So anyone has been out any companies without their in a shipping
games, reliably is doing something right.
And that's an important thing to keep in mind, you know, a lot of
people get hung up on sort of demagoguery and like what's the right
way to do this and the right way to do that.
Well, the right way is the way that gets things done efficiently.
It's on time as possible, you know in a way
To keeps people's morale up, you know, if you can if you can get that
to work, then you're doing something right?
And so I'm not really in a position to say one way or the other and
especially since I tend to do my own projects, a lot of the time, I
don't know a lot about working with large teams or that sort of stuff,
because that's a whole another complexity, right there.
There's a lot of communication things that have to happen there and
stuff that has nothing to do with the code.
So yeah, so I would say I don't really have much of an answer for you.
I apologize.
Let's see.
I think we're getting to the end of the questions.
From your point of view.
Where do you think most of your viewers come from?
I have no idea.
I suspect that that
Some of the retweets that I got helped a lot like Jonathan Blow
retreated me and a lot of you know, game developers follow him.
Obviously some buddy from like somebody with like 300,000 followers.
Retweeted me.
They were someone who was, like an author, something who I didn't
know, but retweeted me apparently like some kind of O'Reilly
newsletter, had it Hacker News had it.
So I feel like maybe just people were getting the message out because
I guess they, they like,
You know, they were excited about the concept.
We're like getting the word out, and I guess that just cast a wide
enough net, that a lot of people decided to come check out the series.
I don't know anything more than that.
I one of the things that I'm intentionally not doing.
He's, I try very hard, not to look at how many people have
pre-ordered, I try very hard.
Not to look at any statistics.
I don't even collect statistics on the website of any kind.
No analytics.
I don't even keep a weblog.
And the reason for that is because I just want to do this stream
because I'm
Excited about doing the code and teaching it.
And I feel like if I start trying to think about like am I reaching an
audience and how do I get more viewers and all stuff than that's like,
It turns it into some kind of bad social media thing for me and I
don't want to do that.
So yeah, so I can't give a very good answer because I really don't
know.
And basically I just see what I see on the Twitter stream and that's
all I really know.
And I don't really want to go find out because I'm afraid that it'll
start to ruin it a little bit for me.
If I try to start thinking about this as trying to be some kind of Web
2.0, popularity thing instead of just doing it because it's, you know,
awesome to code.
And I want to share that with people.
I'm trying, I really want to keep that genuineness as much and as long
as possible, and part of that kind of, unfortunately, means I'm going
to remain fairly ignorant about, even who is watching, let alone how
they found out about it.
Sdl versus S FML.
I do not know what that means.
Is that simple, directmedia layer.
I like that.
Matt Cornell has beep.
The mega timer.
This is a very long Q&A session.
They often won't be that long way since this was the first Dream.
I want to do an extra long one.
So you're right.
It is Mega timer.
Let's see.
Looks like we are basically done.
I'm at the end of the twitch questions, of course, there's a lag but
at some point I got to call it.
So it's 10:30.
We've gone like a full hour of QA basically a little more than an hour
even so thank you so much for staying for the Q&A.
I really hope that even though today's was not the most exciting part
certainly of this series that you are excited enough to come.
Tomorrow and see us get our window up in our rendering started, which
is what we will be doing tomorrow.
So if you, if you are in the mood for some more, handmade hero, 8 p.m.
PST, tomorrow, I will be right here, casting.
We usually start between 15 and 30 minutes early.
We don't actually do any of the stream of that time, but I, you know,
usually have the stream up and you know, I'll talk to people on the
chat.
So if you just want to chat or something will be there and we kind of
Let people sort of filter in at that point.
So if you want to come a little early you can catch that.
Otherwise, I will see you at 8:00 p.m.
Tomorrow.
Thank you so much for everyone for tuning in and and have a great rest
of your evening.