Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could a complete game live on stream in the pre stream,
QA.
Somebody asked the question just now about whether or not a function
call was slower than I'm sorry, whether or not calling a function via
a pointer with slower than just a regular function call.
And I was trying to explain what the difference was between these two
things.
And then I was like, you know what, it's time to start the stream
anyway so why don't I just show you the difference between those two?
You things and then you don't have to speculate on it, right?
You can, you can have a little bit more intuition, the sort of Pat
answer is that, it shouldn't, it shouldn't be appreciably slower.
Depending on the circumstances, it depends really on what you're
doing.
It can be or it cannot be depending on the circumstances.
But I'll sort of try to give you a little bit of a background on that.
It's not really my area of expertise I haven't studied it recently, so
there is that but all right so let me open up.
I think do we use this one of these things buildable
One of our whole test Solutions we use for searching.
Let's see.
So this is just the project we use for searching stuff, okay?
So let's say that we wanted to take a look at what was going on here.
So I'm just going to make one of our favorite things here and info and
in fact I guess you know I'll make it avoid no rest at the moment and
we'll just say that it passes an integer in here and here is our Foo
and then I'll call it down here with with Foo five, right?
And so if we want to I should be able to just go to the
Disassembly here, and give you sort of a quick look at what's
happening.
So what you can see Happening Here, Right is.
Here's the code for Foo up here.
Here's the actual Assembly, Language instructions for Foo.
And what you'll notice, of course, is we're compiling a debug mode, so
there's no optimizations going on.
So it's literally doing the stupidest possible thing right?
But Foo doesn't do anything, right?
There's nothing going on in Foo.
So what you're seeing here is you're just seeing like the code for
like, you know, getting the stack frame set up and that kind of stuff.
And then returning, right?
So it's not doing anything other than just, the basic, really simple
stuff that has to happen as boilerplate for functions in debug mode
and in optimization mode, you know, a lot of that stuff, might go
away, but we care about, of course, is the call site.
And you can see here at the call site, that it's very, very simple.
If I want to call this function, you will note.
What happens is, I do a push of 5 that 5 is the 5 that I'm trying to
pass.
So that puts that on the stack and then
then we have here, the actual call to Foo.
And what you will notice about this call to Foo is that it knows.
As you can see in the disassembly itself, just from
This this this sort of encoding here, you'll notice that it knows the
address that it's jumping to and to be honest, my my B decoding skills
are not particularly great.
I am not an Assembly Language programmer, so you know, I don't know,
the x64 instruction set really well or anything like that.
But what I assume is happening here is that this is using an encoding
for call that
Does some kind of instruction pointer relative, addressing any way,
but point being, what I can tell you is it didn't have to go load the
value to jump to, right?
You can see that just the instruction for the call in these bites as
encoded where it needs to get to.
And I just don't know, I think it probably is encoded as a relative
offset from the call site or something like this, right?
And if you went and looked up the x64 instruction and coding, it would
explain to you how to decrypt what this means.
Such that you know, how did they get oh f
E12 for eh or whatever, right?
Because you can see that it's not really, it's not directly in the B.
And again, like I said, I've got probably two encoded.
What we could do is take a look.
You know, this is the hexadecimal value.
That's that's where we're jumping to.
What I could do is say well, what is that relative to the instruction
here?
Oh thanks.
That's good.
Thanks, visual studio for deleting that.
I certainly didn't want that number that I put there.
So if I do 0 x 0, x, and I take a look at the hex here, so let's see
if ff8.
You can kind of see, that could very well be f.
F f f f 8.
And I would have expected for for but maybe this is encoded.
So I would suspect just looking at the Delta between the jump Target
And the address, I would suspect that what we're looking at here is
some kind of relative encoding.
That's my guess.
Doesn't matter.
Not relevant to the discussion.
Really, but point being you can see how this works.
So this is the entirety of what the processor actually had to do.
Now where this information is coming from, is a place called The
i-cash, okay?
What the I cash is is and, and again, take this with a grain of salt,
this is not my area of expertise, so processors, get rid of all the
time and what I say is, like a cursory
Nation of what's happening.
The actual nitty-gritty of a modern processor is incredibly
complicated.
So there's layers and layers and layers underneath what I'm saying
that are, you know if you really want to know and really get it good.
You're going to have to know more than I do about how and a modern x64
is Chip works as a lot of my sort of way.
I think about process is a bit dated at this point.
But anyway, much like we talked about how the we have a cache for data
where every time you access something, it's got to be pulled into the
cash and so you want things to stay low.
Cash in bubble block.
The processor has a number of things that are going on like that for
the instruction stream as well.
So is the thing called an eye cash and the I cash is something that
that caches the instruction streams, right?
And so much like data, you know, this, this information here, that's
what the process is executing.
Well, that's essentially data to write it stuff that has to get loaded
out of memory.
Our program is a thing sitting in memory.
So just like data occupies space in the cache.
Well, there's a cash for that for that code because that
has to be read in as well.
And, furthermore, there's often times something called a trace cache
as well, which is to say that.
One of the things that's true about modern microprocessors, is that
the instruction stream that we give it these bites here that you see
these, these bites that include the push, five, the call.
That's not actually what the processor executes.
The processor actually takes those instructions and usually kind of
breaks them up into smaller logical units called micro operations.
And those micro operations are what it actually executes.
So sometimes the processor also has a thing where in addition to
caching actual instruction streams as we write them, it may also have
a micro app cache which caches the decoding of those instructions into
the Micro Ops that they actually that it actually executes and, you
know, a processor, you can imagine processor.
Architecture can do all sorts of things there, it might only have a
micro app cache, it
I only have an eye cash, it might have both you know, who knows.
And like I said, I'm not an expert on the x64 architecture so I have
no idea.
I don't pretend to know that stuff, I don't keep up with it, but point
being something like that is going to go on there.
So you've got this kind of cash.
So what needs to happen is when the processor sees this information,
for the first time is going to get pulled into a cash.
It's going to get decoded into Micro Ops possibly cash there.
Those Micro Ops have to be executed and the result of the micro app
execution is what's going to happen.
Now, what you can see here,
Is this entire sequence is entirely fitting in the I cash, right?
There's no, I don't mean fitting like it fits size wise.
I mean, it all comes from there.
It doesn't need to go to the data cache to get any information.
There's no data coming here.
The push 5 is encoded entirely there, because the constant value, so
that's entirely inside that the instruction stream in the i-cash, the
call with the location entirely encoded there.
And so, what that means is, all it has to do.
Do is just look at the instructions in order and execute them in
order.
Another crucial thing about this is it means that the processor modern
processors for the most part, most of the ones that you'll encounter
certainly, x64 outside of larabee and stuff like that, where you're
talking about the main desktop chip, they are out-of-order processors.
What that means is that it will be looking ahead in the instruction
stream and doing all sorts of things.
So it doesn't just sit there and go do the push first.
Then,
The call then do the ad, then do the mob, then do the push.
It doesn't do that, right?
What it does is it looks at a window instructions, and if it thinks,
it could execute an instruction, it will.
And furthermore, when it tries to execute instruction, it's not only
going to execute instructions that it knows.
It can execute.
It may also try to execute instructions that it only thinks it might
be able to execute.
For example, let's say that you have an if statement, right?
You have an if statement and inside the, if statement are some things
that will only happen if the
If statement is true, well, the processor May employ a branch
predictor which is a thing that tries to guess, which way you're going
to go on that if statement, do you think it's going to go through, or
do you think it's gonna go false, right?
It may employ one of those and then it may start looking at, whichever
branch of thinks is more likely and speculatively executing those
instructions, right?
So there's there's even this whole other state of things where if the
processor can can concretely predict which instructions you will be
executing, it can get
More performance than if it doesn't know what instructions is going to
be executing and that can be true across a call.
You can easily imagine processor architectures where, when you hit a
call site like this, if it knows what it's calling into it, can go
start to get those instructions before we ever get to the call.
And if you take a look at this instruction stream here, you'll notice
there are no jumps in it.
Push mob sub push, push push leap of mauve rep Bob, affects our mob
push call and the
call has a known address in it, right?
So it's critical to understand about that.
Is that a processor?
If it was so inclined way back here, when it started executing this,
push the out of order.
Window could have easily read this call and gone.
Oh, I should start fetching instructions from this location because I
know when I get down to here, I'm going to need them, okay?
It did not have to know the result of any of these instructions in
order to start fetching that and be right there was no chance that
Could have been wrong.
Unless there was an exception or something, right?
Like a, you know, divide by zero or right to a illegal memory
location.
That was the only thing that was going to stop it because all the rest
of these things were deterministic and don't require an aren't
required to know.
We're gonna jump.
Okay?
So that's what happens when you normally call a function?
But now, let's take a look at what happens if I call a function and I
needed to get that function pointer from somewhere, okay?
So let's suppose, I introduce a global variable here.
Like so.
Okay.
So here is the function pointer concept, right?
Or I should say function signature
Here's the function signature.
And what I want to do is say, all right, I'm going to get a pointer to
one of these things.
Three-pointer right.
And I'm going to point that at the foo function.
So then in here in, you know, here's my call to Foo.
I'm going to also do a call to food pointer and I'm going to pass Five
to that as well.
Okay, so now I'm going to run down to there.
And go back to the disassembly and it wants you to take a look at what
these two things are, are both doing.
All right?
So yeah, okay.
I suppose this is probably a little bit different because of the
static variable.
This is going to be a little harder to read.
I let me do one that's going to be a little easier for you because
that's like everybody's segment to pull up static.
It'll be easier if we do it this way.
so, let's pretend instead that I have another function here and I
pass,
One in, right.
Of course, I guess.
Oops, I still need my Foo in order to have a function to pass.
So here's my bar.
Okay.
So now what I'm going to do is I'm going to call that bar function and
I'm going to call that with my Foo function.
I just think this will make it a little easier to see.
Okay, so remember, this is what it looked like to call the function
normally and now I'm going to go into bar and see what it looks like
to call the other one.
All right.
Okay, because this is a little easier to see.
So here we go.
This is obviously just again the boilerplate and then here we push the
five on the stock like we're going to before.
But now, what you'll notice is, we actually have this situation where
the foo that the site that we're going to call, right is actually Foo
the local variable, right?
And that local variable is sitting at this location, right?
And do I
Of see here.
Yeah, yeah.
And so what has to happen first is it has to load, whatever is at that
address before it can actually jump, right?
So you'll notice it doesn't know like before, right?
When you looked at it, it had just encoded right in it.
Here's the hard coded address, there's no more information here when
we get to the call, I have to look at what's at that location.
And then I could jump, right?
So, what the processor ends up having to do, is it has to know what
this value was ahead of time, right?
And maybe it does or maybe it doesn't.
And that's the crucial part about this situation.
So,
At least this is the part that I think is crucial.
If I was more of an expert on x64.
I could tell you.
So what you can imagine Happening Here is
Do you want to know if it's going to be less efficient or more?
If you know if it's gonna be less efficient than calling the
hard-coded function, the answer is usually going to be how hard is it
for the processor to guess what this value is going to be in time to
get here right in time when it actually gets here?
So in this case, the answer is probably it's going to be just fine
because this information comes in it doesn't get modified anywhere,
there's no chance, it could be
Long.
And so it's going to go ahead and just know that it could go start
fetching instructions to that address.
There's nothing.
It doesn't seem like there be anything crazy going on there, right?
But let's say you were talking about a different circumstance.
Like for example you were just talking about Ray tracers, right?
In re tracers, if I was just doing some intersection work here, I may
not know and there might be a bunch of ifs and branches.
That are determining what the actual resulting pointer is to the final
object that I hit.
And if immediately after that intersection determination, I then try
to immediately call whatever that function pointer was, well, that
could create some problems for the processor.
It could create some kind of stalls there, I don't know.
Like I said, you have to contest it, but it could be that it's just
not enough time for the processor to have gone and loaded the code
needed to call, or to have the out of order window.
Fetch enough out of it to start pulling instructions, right?
And so that can be a problem, right?
That can be an issue.
So like everything else when you're asking questions about is it more
efficient?
Is it less efficient?
The answer these days is almost always.
It depends.
And in this
This case, I think it's definitely an.
It depends.
Sometimes calling through a function pointer will be no more expensive
in practice.
Then not calling through a function pointer right then just a regular
function call.
There are certainly plenty of times when you would never see the
difference on a profile between those two things.
They will be equivalent, right?
But I think it's certainly plausible depending on your situation that
you could construct cases in several reasonable scenarios like where
you weren't doing anything crazy.
You were just trying to use them in a reasonable way.
You could I think create cases where you would see problems with that,
and it might not be the best way to go, right?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
Okay.
Also, if you wanted to see, I think I can switch this thing over to
release build.
Oh you know what?
So this is interesting.
I just noticed I was wondering I'm like why is it pushing five right?
You remember with push five?
I was like I thought about time I like it doesn't want to talk - I'm
not gonna be around like why is it pushing 5?
Because on x64 typically the first parameter if it fits in a
registered goes in a register and what I realized is the reason is
because it's not compiling x64, it's compiling win32.
So it's compiling 30.
A bit code.
Let's, let's change that.
Shall we?
First, let's go back to debug build, and let's make a new one of
these.
And let's do an x 64 build instead.
Because that was bugging me.
I'm like, why is it pushing 5?
It should have just moved 52 eax or something, right?
E CX.
There you go.
So that's what I would have expected, right?
Yeah.
X is for return or something.
Yeah, so ECX I guess is where the first parameter goes.
So yeah, that's what I would have expected.
And that's that makes a lot more sense.
Okay, so then if I go ahead and switch this to release build, you can
see what it would do differently because it's going to be a lot
differently at the call side.
Anyway, well, okay, so it looks like it completely optimized these out
because they don't do anything, right?
So I'd have to do something like
Some of that.
There we go.
All right.
So now that I've forced these to compile in, let's go to the
disassembly here.
Yeah and hopefully, can I look at a new this?
So yeah.
I mean the optimizer I get a, I would have to create a more hard to
discern case for it.
There, you can see that the optimizer was did a great job, right?
It looked at the evaluation of bar looked at the fact that it's
Is calling Foo five, took that and in lined it into just, you know,
straight up calling the printf, right?
So, yeah, you can see it.
Call the printf right here.
So yeah, like that's that's style.
Anyway.
Enough about that.
Hopefully, that gave you a little bit of a, an idea of the difference
between calling through a
Should pointer and calling just regular.
I would point out that C++, in particular does a really, really stupid
thing which is that C++ because it was designed so long ago.
It does this really, really dumb?
In fact I can I can show you.
It's like the worst thing ever.
C++ is just real real dumb and it probably made sense at the time
because the thing that they were most concerned about was space, but
it's real bad.
In modern times the way that they handle virtual functions.
So what happens in C++ is if you make a class I guess we don't need a
class we can just call it a struct.
I don't want to Sully the name of struct which is a good thing though
with a virtual function.
So we'll call it a struct class like, you know, and you make a class
or
Thing, right?
And so I'm going to add a virtual function here so I say like okay
there's a virtual function and the virtual function is actually the
food.
So now there's a virtual Foo and it takes one of those, you know and I
mean I don't know what it does.
It does some kind of a virtual thing that's like, you know, the printf
or whatever.
Right?
And so when you have one of these guys and you want to do that, and in
fact I could do this.
so there's a virtual function with Foo and you know, if I want to
write then I can do one of these things that for some reason, he
thought was a good idea and, you know, there is our inheritance and
now I can go ahead and say, like okay, yeah, maybe like get it prints
out a different thing in this case,
Write something like that.
So if someone gave me a screw strip, it would print out a strip.
If someone gave me AB yarn over, put out of yarn but in both cases it
prints out the % d.
Right, that's it.
So if I have one of these, you can sort of see like I go.
All right, here's a, here's a strip and
if I call Foo on that,
I'm going to turn off the optimizer temporarily.
I could show you how these things are implemented and they're real
bad, they're much worse than what they're much much worse than the
case that we just sort of went over, if that makes sense.
Oops.
Got those lovely Publix.
so,
Here we are creating our strew strip and then we're going to try and
call one of these guys, right?
And so, let's take a look at what has to happen when we try to do our
call.
Okay?
So what you'll see happening here which is kind of crazy, although, in
this case I think it just determined.
It knew what the call was, did it actually know that or not?
It looks like it actually knew that.
So I'm a, I'm a
I may have to operate it one more so it doesn't so that the compiler
doesn't know exactly which one it's calling.
Let me go ahead and do that.
so, let's say that we take of yarn in here,
And off of the Barna, I want to call the food.
So this function doesn't know which one it's going to get, right?
And so I have a whatever, and then I'm going to call my my function.
Up in here.
Okay, so now you can see the Epic disaster that C++ playing out for
you in Assembly Language.
So here is what appears to be as simple and operation as the one we
had previously, right?
It's just calling a function through a pointer sort of, right?
It's the same idea what's in directed, but the problem is, what ends
up happening is the way in which these are encoded is
Ee in directed, right?
So basically, there is a virtual function table which has the pointers
that it needs to call.
So it first needs to load whatever that virtual function table is and
then it needs to load whatever the function is out of the table,
right?
So you can see it's got a call off of a pointer that it had to load,
right twice.
Right.
Here at did the load and here it does the call off the load, right?
And so that's just a huge.
It's just this huge W directed thing.
That the processor has to struggle with all the time because it never
knows where it's calling off, too.
And that double load means that you're always having to pull these
unrelated things out of the cache.
Those virtual function tables, right?
Always have to be like pulled into look, be looked up into even though
they have nothing to do with the memory that
You were already accessing.
Right?
So a lot of times it's just real real bad to hit these double in
directions because if a processor happens to be set up to hit them
really well, which a lot of times like Intel chips actually will
because hey they're used to dealing with crappy, C++ code or whatever.
But you know heaven forbid you do you hit one of these on a processor?
That's not so set up for that.
Like for example the you know Xbox 360 or something like this,
something that didn't want to have to do these kinds of things that
didn't have a lot of ways of masking, those double in directions by
doing other stuff or whatever and it's real bad, right?
So that's what happens every time you do a virtual function call and
C++ it's it's worse.
It's worse than both.
The other cases we looked at and it's just not the way that you
usually want your program to work.
You're paying a huge cost there for oftentimes.
No.
You know, you could have implemented it a different way than a virtual
function and you would not have had to have that speed hit, right?
So yeah, not not great.
I never use Virtual functions for this reason.
I
Must always want to be able to have control to do something different,
if I need to, because the problem with going down, this route is,
there's nothing you can do to fix it, right?
There's no way you can tell the compiler.
Oh, hey, I really want you to implement this a different way, because
it's too slow with a double direction.
For this piece of code, there's nothing you can do.
Whereas if you implement it yourself, you can change the way that
those dispatchers are happening.
If you're, if you end up in a situation where it's important, right?
So you know, that's why I never use them.
But if your are the kind of person who wants to use Virtual functions,
you want to be real careful that you never use Virtual functions in
places that you think you might have to optimize heavily because
there's nothing you can do about it, it's just going to be slow,
right?
So, you know,
A word of caution.
All right.
We have blown through a tremendous amount of time answering this
question but hopefully we entered it.
We answered it sufficiently, if that makes sense.
And yeah, there you go.
I don't know if that answered the question, but hopefully it did and
now we can move on.
Okay, so I don't know if I'll have time to do anything.
We ate up a lot of time, but I'll
I just wanted all I wanted to do today was just take a look at
animating, the the, those sort of little, little jumpy pads.
A little jumpy poo.
So what we did though, that's not the right project.
What we did yesterday is I made these little jump pads here, right?
So I could jump onto the pad and then it would spring me down to the,
to a square below, right?
But right now all we did is just have those pads setup but we don't
actually do anything with them.
The first thing I'd like to do is see if I can just get teleportation
working.
So that basically like any time you jump on one of those pads
We'll move whatever jumped there to some other location that specified
by the pad, right?
I just want to do that too.
To see if we can make that work relatively well.
So, in order to do that, what I, what I believe happens here is just
that inside handmade entity, right?
There's there is simulation code.
For various entities.
And so what I want to do is say well, okay.
So you know as we go through these entities, if we look and see that
somebody is sitting on any that does have this particular piece of
behavior, then we might want to do something about it, right?
So for example, what we could do is if we go to here we go, stim
region.
If we take a look at the occupying, the people who
Doing occupation.
What we can do is say, well alright there's two ways we could do this,
we could do it, forward-looking your backward-looking, I don't know
which one I want to do.
So I'm just going to pick one random kind of a haven't thought
particularly much about what should happen.
But what I'm going to do here is, I don't know that any flag active
should really be.
I don't know if that should be a bait here or not, it's a good
question.
I don't really know exactly what's going on here per se, but what I
want to do is say, all right, if this entity
Is one that has Loops the magical boost, right?
So if I've got Auto boost to and the auto boost to is valid, right?
So if I say,
and I think we decided that ought that
The right way to check for these things.
I always wanted to say is valid but I think
What we decided is to just call get reversible, right?
So basically if we say, you know,
if this thing has an auto boost to then what I want to do is say if
the someone was standing on me, then boost him.
Right?
Whoever it was.
So when we say, get reversible for the auto boost to, I then want to
see like for anybody who's standing on one of my traversable is
whatever they are, right?
If there's an occupier on that reversible, I want to like move.
Whoever it was I want them to go, right?
And if I remember correctly, the way that this stuff works is, we have
already like a routine that handles that sort of like trade-off that
that sort of movement.
And I think it's in here.
I don't again, it's been a while since we've done this stuff and I
have it, paged out in my brain right now but I remember we have a
transaction.
Yeah, here it is, right?
So if there is an occupier, I feel like I could do something here.
Where we
Said you know try to do a transactional occupy of whoever this this
person is.
So I think it's just like, Oh Yeah, from where were this dude was
To wherever our thing.
Our boost to is
I'm just saying if anyone standing on anything in ours, will try to do
a transactional occupy and if we can, we'll move them to the Boost
too.
Right.
Cannot convert.
Argument 32 traversable reference.
Oh,
So I guess I didn't need I was assuming I'd need to save that but I
guess I don't.
So, you know, something like that kind of just like randomly
suggesting that.
Yeah, so there you go.
So you can kind of see that it hopped my body down there, right now.
The problem with that obviously, is that right now?
We have no code that mu the to move the head, to where the body has to
go, which will have to do, but that's really all I wanted to see
happen, right?
I just wanted to see anyone who hit that one, get teleported down
there, which they do, which
Great.
Those guys did too which is funny.
But anyway that's that's all there is to it.
I wonder if the snake would do that too.
Kind of curious what happens.
If the snake goes up there, go up there mr.
Snake.
Come on.
Oh come on.
You went right by it dude.
All right, get over there.
I'm going to block your path.
Go down there, go, there we go.
Ha ha ha.
So for people who are asking whether the snake would work, it clearly
does.
So that's great.
So that just got rid of our snake there it went okay so that's all
fine and good and really what we need to do
At this point is just make something that will force the body to move,
though.
The head to move down with the body which right now we don't do.
And so like I said, that's a bit of a problem.
It's a problem in a number of ways, not just this one and the reason
for that is if we go over here right?
When we you know, we should not be able to do that.
Right, that's not supposed to happen.
What we're doing here.
That's just ridiculous.
You're only supposed to move, the the head about that far and what's
supposed to happen is?
If the head is too far from the body, it's supposed to get sucked back
to the body, right?
It's not supposed to ever actually be able to go any further than it
could go.
Half the, you know, half a square, unless the body will actually
follow.
So if you're moving in a straight line is fine because the body will
always hop after you, but we want to stop you from being able to do
that.
Whenever the circumstances would be otherwise, right?
So, yeah, so that's what we want to do there.
That's pretty funny.
So that's what we want to do.
There, we need something that will Spring the head down.
Now, it's interesting as our our head does spring back in X Y.
So I guess is our head.
Currently not springing.
I guess it doesn't spring to the body.
I guess the it just Springs back to whatever the closest traversable
is, maybe I guess.
We need to do some work on our player movement code to say the least.
But, you know, that will come with time.
That will certainly be the most complicated piece of the entity
movement code.
I'm sure because, you know, you got to really tune it and it's hasn't
been tuned at all yet, right?
It's pretty crappy.
But anyway, so I think this is the code here that does it the right?
Like, here's the re-centering stuff that sort of happens.
Right, you can kind of see what's going on here with the closest here
is the spring to the, to the closest and so on.
And yeah, it does look like
that closest pee.
Is the closest reversible to the Head?
So, I think really all we would have to do here is say well, okay, you
know, try to go to the next one, like we were doing before, but
afterwards, you know, we probably want to, to when we do this closest
to pee, when we do, get some space reversible, we don't really want to
use this one.
What we would rather use is whichever one, the body is occupying,
right?
So, what we probably want to do is something more like,
Get some space traversable you, nobody out.
Pine here, something like that.
Probably.
So we always suck back to the bodies one, not the heads one, right?
If that makes sense.
So you know, if I go over to this guy and let go now at least I'm
sucking back.
And so now the only bug in our thing is that we let it go too far but
it can't stop there.
And so now in theory I should suck down when the body goes down and I
did.
So that's what I, that's exactly what I wanted to have happen.
Are right?
So that's perfect.
So now our little teleport pads are working.
Like I said, we I don't really want them to teleport pads so I would
like to go ahead and make it so there's a little jump animation there
but there we go.
That's exactly what I had wanted to do.
And we do have about 15 minutes left.
So even though we had a bunch of stuff we did today, we should be able
to, oh wow.
That was crazy.
The snake jumping down there.
How did it jump back though?
I don't know how it did that.
That's probably a bug somewhere or who knows?
We have some pretty crazy code in there right now for some of these
things.
So I guess it doesn't surprise me but that was kind of wild.
Yeah.
How would they get back up Theory?
I don't wouldn't think they'd be able to do that but yeah, so that
works almost exactly like I wanted.
So that's good.
So really all I want to do now is when I hop onto this thing instead
of immediately teleporting my body down there.
What I want to do is make the body actually go through one of the
standard hops, right?
So when I do that, and we do the, you know, this sort of thing.
This transactional occupy, the problem here is I don't really know
what that, what that entity does to move itself, right?
So, you know, I mean, I can do something like this.
And maybe that would be sufficient.
I don't know.
It would certainly work for the hero but you know, if somebody wasn't
a hopper then it wouldn't work.
Presumably.
Yeah also hey, guess what we just moved the occupier off of there so
that ain't going to work.
That's what we want to do, is this?
So grab the occupier out and then we can do whatever we want with them
and we don't have to worry about the pointer going away.
Go.
so, I think in theory,
That should hop other.
Didn't look like adopt?
oh,
that reminds me.
We need this as well.
So hopefully you can see their wives saying, we're going to need to
sort of upgrade something a little bit before we can make that a
reasonable piece of code.
Although it still seems like I'm not getting a hop there.
I'm not sure why.
Right.
It's kind of a little busted.
Can I I need a better way to slow time down here.
first thing there is
So now we're running extremely slowly, right?
So I can see exactly what happens when I hop on this thing, right?
Like that, that was all messed up, right?
I think probably because it happened before the person ever actually
landed.
So it takes the occupational part of that and and goes from there.
So really like, you know, we're going to need sort of a little bit of
a
And upgraded logic here because right now like this is what happens.
We need to sort of take when it goes to the planted mode and do it
then, right?
And we can do that.
Pretty trivially, right?
We can say like, you know,
But this isn't going to work generally speaking.
Right.
This isn't going to be a particularly good way of handling this.
We need to sort of upgrade that logic, right?
But that at least allows them to jump and then jump again.
And so now you can kind of see that working there still a little bit
of a, of a problem with it which is that the head starts animating
faster than the body does, which is not great.
And furthermore, The Hop isn't really set up quite so well to do that
Ark.
So we'd probably need to upgrade that code a little bit, but we're
starting to get to the point where it's doing the right thing.
Thing, right?
Let's slow it down a little bit more.
Right?
So they're it hits.
And now it jumps down to the floor and you
It actually does the jump.
The problem is, it's not a very satisfying jump because the arc up is
not enough for that big jump down.
So, we probably just need a little bit better controller code there,
but otherwise it's reasonable, right?
It's not too bad.
I'm going to kind of slowly hop over here.
So you can see, we really want a bigger Arc there.
And the other thing is we want that head to animate a little bit
differently, right?
Okay.
But yeah, kind of getting a little bit ahead of ourselves here because
that's really entity code specific sort of stuff that we want there.
So really we kind of I think are done for the most part here with this
stuff.
So I think we kind of want to do.
We want to put this down somewhere later, right.
You know this is going to be sort of like a
We really want to do that a little bit later on.
It's not really something we care about at the moment.
So looking at this stuff here when we're doing our Z stuff, I feel
like now we're pretty much good to go because I feel like flying
things could go over low walls very easily.
Now we kind of have the concept of all that stuff.
Worked out pretty pretty well because we can still do 3D Collision
detection.
So if we update the Collision detection, as we're supposed to do here,
we shouldn't have any trouble using boxes that are sort of floating in
mid-air,
If we want to, we didn't do anything that would prevent that from
happening.
We have our different layers working properly and our coordinate
systems are fine.
I think I don't know that we need any special texture coordinate
systems is not sure we're going to use those very much.
So I think we can kind of say that most of this stuff is pretty much
done.
So I think we can kind of go kind of go start looking at at this
bundle of stuff here.
This is basically like
Graphics upgrade.
so,
Let's take a look here.
Collision detection.
I don't know.
We're going to kind of have to look at this because these are mostly,
probably not so relevant anymore.
Now that we have grid-based movement, requirements, for Collision
detection, it's more going to be about floating entities, what they
need to do, and about like projectile Collision sorts of stuff.
So, I don't know what we want to do with that.
We'll have to look at that a little bit more and AI storage.
We haven't really, we don't have
A lot to do with that stuff yet.
I don't know when we're really going to want that.
Yeah.
So I think we're mostly living up here and particle.
Systems is probably something we do want to get to fairly soon.
Let's take a look at some of our situation here.
I'm going to take this Notch down a little bit.
I'll just have two screens for the moment.
So we can still kind of zip around here.
All right, you see?
See how people were able to get up like that?
I don't understand what the hell they were doing that.
Is that because there's some kind of a warp here that I left in
Or something.
I don't understand how it did that.
I want to know what it was doing because it was pretty cool.
I just don't know how to do it.
It's like the snakes have a magic way of going upstairs that I don't
have, which is weird.
All right, so I think what we want to do is we want to start taking a
look at putting some particle systems in here, because we're going to
need those for effects and stuff like that.
They're pretty important for an action game because they kind of sell
it, you know, seeing lots of things kind of Sparkle around and spray
around and do fun stuff.
Is it tends to be pretty important for an action game, you know?
So we kind of want some of that in there and it's just going to be a
way for us to accentuate the various things that we need to
accentuate.
Yes brights, do it.
It feels kind of good to hop around here as we tune that it will
certainly get better and we put in the new art it'll be way better.
But you know when we hit somebody you know like we're going to have a
glove in here and we're going to swipe with the glove, you know, it'd
be nice.
If you could leave a particle Trail, it'd be nice.
If, when you hit something, you got some particle Splash that sort of
stuff.
So in terms of making, you know, selling the feel of an action game, I
think particle systems are going to be pretty important.
So I would like to put some in there and I think that's what we kind
of want to do next.
I won't get started on that because we're almost at the end here and I
think we're pretty much done with all the other things that I want to
do.
So I'll save the explanation for tomorrow and will end a little bit
early.
I think that should basically do it.
So yeah.
So let's go to cue a little bit early and then tomorrow I guess you'll
have to tomorrow.
So next week, we'll just be particle systems week and we'll do all
sorts of particle system stuff.
Will upgrade the renderer to have particle batches so that they're not
Slow.
And then we will
We'll just sort of get them nicely integrated, so they're easy to use
and do a couple that will be reasonable, right?
All right, so any questions?
About where we're at at the moment.
Sean McGrath asks, my three-year-old would like to know, why is he
angry regarding the hero?
Well, keep in mind that the hero now looks quite a bit different.
So this is the old art.
The new art.
That we are almost a good point for putting in looks like that.
Does your three-year-old think that that still looks angry?
That's what the hero looks like.
Now from it's got the proper top-down perspective and an has kind of
got that nice.
She always puts a lot of good personality in the face so I don't know
if that looks angry still or
This Isaac, I think the snakes choose their next jump destination
while still on the Upper Floor, okay?
So after they get boosted down they can jump back up again.
Okay?
Okay.
Yeah, that makes good sense.
Because yeah, the brain, the brain doesn't know that the snake got
teleported down, so it could have already picked a destination to jump
to.
That does make sense.
So if you look at Kirby, the American version always has an angry face
and the Japanese version is always smiling.
Well, so maybe we should have two kinds for internationalisation will
have like a frowny face for America or an angry face of America.
Uplink coder.
What happens if someone blocks the place someone gets boosted down to
then you can't boost down?
That's one of the nice things about the way we did it, right?
Which is
This transactional occupy makes it so that you can't have two people
occupying a space, right?
So it just won't move the person down.
Can we talk again about Euro time stream?
We could talk about Euro timestream.
I just don't know what Euro timestream means.
So it's worth noting that, you know, we still when we do kind of our
final past, we still will have to deal with the fact that when you
move down, your kind of just continuously going between the coordinate
systems, so we still will need to have some way that that works
probably.
But I think we should be okay because you don't, you know, you won't
be going.
We'll be able to kind of hack it.
I think.
Seems at times for Europe like you did at the start of the project.
So actually at the start of the project we were always 8 p.m.
it was only in the middle of the project that we did five PM streams
but streams times are just based on my schedule.
I can't I don't have the up really the flexibility to worry about who
is up when for them.
So they they are when they are and sometimes depending on what my
schedules are, they will be your friendly and other times they won't.
But I don't
Do not set the schedule based on what is convenient for people to
watch.
I said it based on when I can do it and you know, that becomes useful
for some people and not useful for others, that makes sense.
Our more General software questions.
Okay.
Yeah.
If they're I usually just answer questions that are about what we're
doing first, but if we don't have any more questions about that then I
don't want mind.
Ones that are broader.
Loan billion, not being boosted down with glue, the player in that
there is an enemy there.
Will that affect gameplay much.
So I guess what I would say is I'm not sure how we're going to
implement these just yet.
It may be that the place that you land when you boost down is the same
place that you would step on to boost up.
So, it may be that there's never a way to actually stand on one of
them.
Anyway,
Really right?
You would both have to kind of get on them at the same time and
prevent each other from boosting or something, if that makes sense.
Sort of okubo any reason why you don't just let the hero jump down and
only use jump pads for moving up levels.
I kind of wanted to make it specific when you could move up or down so
I don't want Holes in the Floor to be things you can jump down.
I just want them to things.
You can see down and then only when there's actually a sort of pad.
Would it let you do that?
We could also think about making it be more of an elevator e looking
thing but I don't think so.
I think I just wanted to kind of boost you and
team its key.
In case you care my problem with McCaskey sounds before is that when
you drew it, the way it was drawn, my brain assumed, you meant the
origin of the shapes and not the origin of the graph.
Well, it's true in either case, right?
The origin of the shape is what you're talking about, basically,
right?
Because that shape is relatives, World relative, if you're talking
about trying to do two things colliding in the same space, but the
Makowski some doesn't is talking about just the
Of the shapes, which could be either way, right?
It's whatever you define it to be.
The point is just that when you do the minkowski sum, you're talking
about the actual values of the points, which means that where you
chose to consider the origin when you define the shapes matters.
Demetri Spanos told me about time, reversible debuggers and it sounds
kind of bunkers.
How would you implement it without making a huge strain on the run
time?
I don't really know how you implement them.
If you didn't have to worry about operating system stuff, then you
know, you would implement it, it's pretty trivial.
All you do is
like pages and then periodically you wake up, save the contents of all
the pages that have nut have been men protected
that have triggered, right?
And then record the instruction pointer and that just gives you
checkpoints and then you can always jump back to any one of those
checkpoints and that's really easy to do.
The thing that's much harder to do is like, let's say you call F right
to write to a file or something like that.
If your debugger is supposed to be good enough to undo the F, right,
that's real tough, real real tough.
So, I don't know if time reversible debuggers.
If there are any time reversible debuggers that can do that, I don't
know.
but if you think about what happens with programs that do not involve
calls to the operating system that can alter permanent on disk stuff,
then it's pretty easy.
If you don't then what you have to do is start intercepting all of the
system level stuff so that you can do essentially the same thing I
just said but with any resources in the system, right?
So if they write to file Pages, you have to remember which file page
has changed and be able to back those up as well.
But just doing time, reversible debugging on Sony that doesn't call.
The operating system is actually trivial.
All you do is just periodically, suspend the task.
Look at all the pages that have been touched right out their contents.
Right.
Well, it's actually not quite that you men.
Protect all the pages that every time that a page is touched, you
right out.
Its contents.
And then let the thing resume, then periodically, you go back, men,
protect all the pages that have been touched, right?
And start the process over again and that just gives you check points
in time where you can restore exactly what the memory say that the
machine was, it's actually almost the same thing we do in handmade
hero where we do that sort of loop live coding.
basically that it's just we didn't use the win32 calls that let you do
the men protect we could have but I just didn't
Thoughts on VR, I don't care for it.
It's not my cup of tea.
I like the regular old stuff so I don't know.
I understand why certain people get excited about it because it's
definitely a different experience and it's the kind of experience
that's fun to have once.
Like, it's everyone should try it sometime at a trade show, right?
It's not the kind of experience I ever want to have again.
Like, I've never wanted
To go back and do V re.
And it was just like, yep.
It was fine and now I'm done.
It doesn't engage me the way computers in general do.
So I haven't really had
The kind of enthusiasm for them that other people have.
I think as the technology becomes easier to transition in and out of
then it might make sense that I would occasionally use it more.
So, for example, I would probably enjoy having VR, like, if I wanted
to play a space Sim so I could like, look around the cockpit, you know
would be fun.
Like, I've always wanted to have more of a dog fighting experience
where, you know, I can quickly look behind me and see, you know, if
there's a spaceship behind me, right?
And V are starting to do that.
Pretty good.
And so I think that if it didn't take so much set up, and so much junk
on my desk and all this other stuff to have that happen.
I think I could see, like, oh, I'm gonna go play a game of the elite,
or whatever, or, you know, in my dream world X Ring, the original
X-Wing, let's say, and I can if I just like quick, grab the thing, and
stick it on my head and that's it.
And I just start playing and it wasn't like this big.
Oh, you got to make sure your base stations were configured and
Here is your wand and whatever and like, oh the Oculus cameras like
got knocked over or what, you know, all that crap.
So, you know, I I feel like that's kind of the barrier for me using it
occasionally.
I definitely don't like VR enough at the moment to deal with all of
the hassles, but I think if they, you know, and they will write.
I mean, you know, that, you know, that this is the kind of things
they're working on, right?
They want to make it really easy as that barrier to getting into VR,
goes down.
As the headsets get lighter and it's cheaper to buy them and you don't
have any set up and blah blah blah.
If they can get that down enough then it becomes something that I
would use occasionally when I'm playing a game that I think really
benefits from that.
Right.
But I just when I do VR stuff, I'm like it's kind of a neat novelty
but it's just not something that I am excited.
Enough about to want to deal with any of the earlier adopters stuff.
And so I think like probably the vast majority of game players out
there.
I'm like, yeah, you know, we'll see you in five years.
Let's let's see what it is, and maybe I'll go, you know, look at one
then but I'm just not
I'm just not sufficiently motivated at by the current crop of tech to
really bother with it, right?
I looked for calls to the OS to give me the page size, the page size,
and I couldn't find it.
Well, the page size is always 4K at the moment because turning on
large pages, is
Like impossible in Windows.
They really don't want you to do it for some reason, so you basically
can't ship an app that's large page where I mean you can.
But it's really hard.
I think you have to be like administrator to do it even, it's really
weird.
They just, I don't know why it's windows.
It's a disaster nowadays, right?
It's just an epic fail.
So, you know, the page sizes aren't particularly problematic in that
sense.
But,
I don't know, maybe you're talking about how big a particular
allocation range was,
But anyway, if you want to know what the what the default page size is
get system info or one of those gets us the metrics.
I don't think it's get system, info.
You can call and they'll tell you the page size.
I meant the allocated pages.
Okay, so your talk well I guess I don't know why you're talking about.
Are you talking about like I have
I guess I don't know what I'm right.
Sorry.
Are you talking about?
I have a pointer into a region and I just want to know like in that
region.
What was the page that like like how big was the virtual Alec call
that caused this page to be reserved kind of a thing?
If you had a chance to look at the rust, programming language.
No, I don't I don't do anything with rust.
Is the penalty for polymorphic calls in not intensive sections of
codes worth the trade-off of usage.
Benefits.
Also, do you think you could beat John Carmack in a fight?
You seem buff.
Let me answer the second question first, which is that I seriously
doubt that our degrees of relative buffness would determine who would
win in a fight.
Like, I just don't feel like if John Carmack and I were fighting that
the determining Factor would be like, who's stronger, right?
That that doesn't seem like the primary thing, right?
It's probably who like throws the better punches or whose murmur do
verbal.
Like, you know, for example, John Blow studied kung fu for a long
time, right?
And so, you know, if if you factor in like that, fighting
Variance would mean a lot, you know probably John would be able to be
a much more effective fighter regardless of whether he was as strong
as say I was.
Because most of the things that are going to matter there are
Not just how strong he is at this moment.
It's going to be like reflexes and stuff like that, right?
So since I know absolutely nothing about John carmack's fighting
skills, I would say, who knows.
But why would John Carmack and I be fighting in the first place would
be another question altogether since.
I would assume that me and John Carmack would be friendly.
If we were talking in person by we have talked in person before and
certainly a fight did not break out.
So it seems like
that would not be necessary.
And certainly I have a tremendous amount of respect for me as well so
I would I would prefer not to get in a fight with him if I could avoid
it.
So, as for the polymorphic calls in an intensive sections of codes
worth being worth a trade-off, I would say that if you're talking
about not intensive sections of code, then you've kind of already
answered the question.
Like, if you can verify that the places where the polymorphic calls
are happening, are not going to occupy a significant amount of your
time budget, then obviously you don't have to care.
So if you find that you're getting some benefits from it,
Then you should be fine, right?
The important thing is this that you determine that that's actually
true, right?
The important thing is you determine that.
This is not going to be a half heavily trafficked area that's going to
cause you problems, right?
And you should be able to know based on how many of these calls do you
anticipate happening, right?
Are you talking about 10 calls at frame?
100 calls a frame, a thousand calls a frame ten thousand calls a frame
like right?
If the answer is 10 times a frame, then it really isn't going to ever
matter, right?
There's just no way that's going to probably add up to something
that's going to be relevant.
If the answer is like 100,000 times a frame, well, that's starting to
sound pretty darn concerning, right?
So you kind of got to think through where you are in that Spectrum.
How long do you think until a new low-level capable language?
Will be produced to surpass C++.
I would say that I don't anticipate that anyone in the game industry
would be starting a, they're starting engine programming in C++ 10
years from now.
So I would say, 20 26, their C++ will be a dead language in the game
industry other than Legacy code.
That's, that's my prediction.
I think there are enough people now working on successors, who are
serious about it?
That I think the train has left the station.
I think we all know the C++ is a terrible language, that doesn't suit
our needs and it is not being designed or maintained by people.
Who are producing quality work for the specification.
And so I think it's dead.
I think it is waiting to die, so I think, as a programming language of
the game industry, I think C plus plus will be gone within within a
decade.
And obviously, they'll still be stuff like, you know, oh, maybe the
whole Unreal Engine still written in C plus plus.
So there's, you know, it hasn't been totally replaced by 2026 or
something, so they're still like Legacy maintenance stuff like that.
Going on, that will obviously continue for quite some time.
You know just like COBOL is still being used in banking some place or
whatever, right?
So it will take a long time for C++ to completely die out as something
that is still used in the game industry, but fundamentally C++ has
Ever been a good language.
It's always been lousy and I think it always kind of just was only
clawing along because C is a was a good language and has a lot of good
things going for it at the time and I think we've all come to that
realization now most of us know this and and I think serious
programmers in the game is tree all kind of know that this is true and
so we're we're I think in that mindset.
And I think outside of the game industry, everybody already knows this
just like we do and they've just since they don't have the same kind
of performance constraints and they don't have the same kind of crust
pallet come across platform performance.
Constraints that we do they have just moved to languages that are less
capable of doing some of that low level stuff because they don't have
to worry about it.
So you know they could they can use Ruby if they want to write and a
game programmer will probably never use Ruby for a serious engine.
But you know we I think now also appreciate that we need to move on
and it's just a question of us getting a language that's suitable for
games.
Much like a web programmer programming or back-end programming has,
has made that determination has tried to move to things like go like C
sharp or even Java or whatever.
You know people have moved away from C++ to all sorts of other
languages whether they're good or not.
And so
I think in games it's just a question of us.
Working out that successors language or set of languages but I think
we know we need to do it and it's unsustainable.
It is not a sustainable language for game development.
It's costing us every day.
It's costing every programming team programmer, Team every day.
And, you know, it needs to go and I think it will go.
And, you know, like maybe John blows language will do it, but if it
doesn't, I think there's other initiatives, you know, I think there's
other things happening.
I think also probably,
I know there's been other people inspired by John to do their own
languages, so it's getting started right?
Like the process getting started, but it's just going to take a while
until we get up to the point where we can.
Where we have something viable, that's got a solid tool chain and that
we can start using.
But yeah, I mean, I can tell you for a fact that I will not be
programming in C++ by 2026.
I'm hoping that within about three years will be off of C++ at Molly.
I'm hoping but you know, who knows that's aspirational.
And yeah I don't think D like d and go in these sort of languages.
They're just you know a lot of them don't even have as good as tough
as John already has in J.
I write like, I'm just I'm not impressed with a lot of these other
languages, they just don't seem very good.
And you're like, if you're gonna go through the trouble of replacing
see,
With a new language, it should be baller, right?
It should be a really good language and like these other languages are
just not that good, you know, they're, they're pretty minor
improvements over C or C++ and like, we should at this point have an
epically better language, right?
And like the kind of stuff that John shows where it's like, hey, you
can run anything you could run, run time, you can run a compile time
that should just be like, if your language can't run,
Invaders during compilation.
Why does it even exist?
It's obvious to me that you should be able to do anything.
You can do at runtime, you should have been able to do a compile time
that's just an that is a, it's me and obvious thing that a language
should be able to do if you can't do that.
Like I don't even want to hear about it, right?
Like don't even send me a language that can't do that because it
already just demonstrates to me that you're not thinking this problem
through.
So I have high hopes for j.i.
because, you know, it seems to be doing a lot of things, right?
Like that.
I don't know if it will succeed or not.
You know, who knows how good it is when we actually start to try and
use it or whatever, but I think like it's an example of something that
is clearly going the right direction and I think we'll have more of
those as well.
And one of these I think we'll be able to stick and we'll be able to
move past C++ and
And off you go, right?
so,
And yeah, Miller plexus.
A lot of things worth noting are made in C++.
But again you know a lot of that.
A lot of that's just because it's the only viable low-level
programming language, right?
You know, people just don't have options for some reason every time
people make these like, you know, I don't even understand like when
they made go, they made it like, you know, almost you have to use a
garbage collector and stuff.
I don't know why you would do that, right?
Like why would you make a new language that you had to use garbage
bags for doesn't make any sense, but you know, that is just this
recurring theme that for some reason.
When people make new languages, they don't consider c-level
specificity as like a bare minimum.
In my mind, see,
Is actually too high.
Like, in my mind, the level of specificity should basically be
Assembly Language.
Like, you should basically be able to program essentially Assembly
Language at the base level of your language, right?
And then you should be able to scale up from that as arbitrarily far
as you want to go.
But the concept that people introduce languages now, which can't even
do sea.
Level specificity for what you want.
The machine to do, is so strange to me, I
I don't understand why you would do it because there's no cost to it,
right?
It's not like you can't introduce high level features because you have
low-level features.
Like that's not how language design works right.
Language design is scalable like you can have low level constructs and
build higher level contracts on top of them if you're doing your
design cleanly, right?
And so unfortunately everyone always makes these were decisions like
you know, will make Ruby or whatever well it can
Do any of the low-level stuff or whatever, right?
You can't be as specific as see about what you want machine to do.
It's like that seems like it just carves off a huge set of things.
You never going to write an operating system in this language.
You're never going to write a high performance web server in this
language.
You're never going to write a game in this language, you never going
to write mission-critical you know, space code or whatever, right.
But
I don't think that's necessary to have a high level programming
language.
It just means that you need to think about the low level and establish
that cleanly as part of your overall design.
And I wish people would do that because when we're programming games,
I mean, you see a lot of the code I write, right?
There's tons of like intricate weird high level code going on and you
want better constructs than C++.
In fact, you could make more efficient code.
Then what I write on handmade hero, a lot of times, if you had more
efficient, high level constructs that you could work with, right?
So you want all those high-level contract.
In programming, you don't want to throw those away just because you
know, you have a bunch of pieces of code that do need to be
performance critical and do need to have that specificity, right?
So you just need people to start taking seriously the concept that you
need that Spectrum, you just need language designers to start
thinking.
Okay, at the base level I want to completely specify the Assembly
Language for this code.
I want to be able to go all the way down to 100 percent explicit,
right?
Right?
And I want to scale up from there to get less and less and less
explicit.
So, the programmer basically has a Continuum of explicitness.
So that when they want to nitpick and say, no, this is exactly the
sequence of instructions.
I want on this platform at this time, do it this way.
And then, as they slice away at it, they can remove remove remove,
remove until they get to a part where it's much more high level and is
not specifying anything.
Specific like what instructions to use or anything like that.
And is operating at a much more abstract level.
When the programmer doesn't care how it's done, right?
And you want that range, and I think that's the thing that's really
missing.
I think you have the opportunity right now.
To pick languages at a number of places on that spectrum and get
locked in, right?
So, you can pick C C++ and get locked in at a very low level of
abstractness, right?
Because even if you throw
So all the templates all that stuff on it C++ still can't even barely
do any metaprogramming worth anything right?
Or you can pick something super crazy like, you know, you could go up
to something like, you know, a weird list.
Be sort of language or an MRI Haskell, or who knows what and have all
kinds of crazy stuff happening.
Right?
But forget it if you want to try and do some really specific like
low-level stuff at that point, right?
And so you kind of have this weird thing where you can pick places on
the Spectrum and get locked into that place.
But I think the language we really want
Games and perhaps WHY games is so challenging?
As a language design space is we need the Spectrum.
We need to be able to do those high-level weird, you know, ml style
constructs if we want them.
But then we also need to make sure that we don't have to use them when
they're inappropriate, right?
It's cute.
Do you think the fundamental issue with programming languages is not
giving access to memory and treating them?
First class.
No, although that is a symptom.
What I think is that you pretty much know today.
You can look at x64 and you can look at arm right?
You can see the instruction sets, you know what the CPU does?
Fundamentally speaking, you need to appreciate the fact that the
programmers job is to construct Assembly Language.
That is what they are doing right now.
Huge classes of programmers like to pretend.
They're not or don't care or something, right?
And that's where we get slow code, you know, that's where we get code.
That takes too long to execute and annoys me and it's, you know, I'm
sitting around waiting for my Gmail to refresh for some reason and
it's taking, you know, three seconds.
No, I have a 1 millisecond ping time to the server, right?
So, who knows what's going on out there, right?
But if you actually care about program computer, what you care about
is the Assembly Language that comes out the other end.
So what you need to do is you need to give the programmer access to
that Assembly Language, and control over what it outputs.
And that includes all the things just say, like treating memory.
As a first test citizen pointers, you can try to pretend the pointers
don't exist but guess what?
Your program.
Is using them everywhere.
That is how a CPU works.
There is no way for it to not use pointers so pretending they don't
exist, is just dumb.
It's not a constructive way to do things.
You need to acknowledge that they exist.
Give you access to everything the CPU can do.
Right?
And then you need to layer on top of that until you get up to high
level constructs that don't need to think about memory as a first
class citizen that don't need to think about instructions as
first-class citizens that don't need to.
Think about multi-threading as first-class citizens that are just
abstract ways of stating needs to be done, you need that Continuum
because that Continuum is what allows you to when you need to optimize
drop.
On to the appropriate level.
Most languages designed today have hard floor limits that are nowhere
near specifying the Assembly Language.
They're not even close, right?
Some of them are so far away from that, that it takes like literally
thousands of Assembly Language, instructions, just to issue the most
granular version of their programming language and that's not
acceptable, right?
The class mammographic plus actually cursed me out last week because
Malik is too complicated to use in large programs, it's nuts.
How Ardent people are about believing obviously wrong things.
Yep, it is.
I totally agree.
It's a sad world out there.
and the software shows it right, the software is real bad and that's
because
People don't take these things seriously anymore, they try to make
their lives as easy as possible and they don't care.
Fundamentally what comes out the other side unfortunately, right?
And so if it means that users are waiting five seconds for result.
That should have taken 1 millisecond, right?
They fundamentally don't care because they finished their job quicker.
Like they didn't have to do as much programming or whatever, right?
And and
Just not good but that's fundamentally what people look at.
And like a lot of times you'll see that you will see huge lectures on
best practices or something like this.
And there is not a single mention of the performance implications of
the things are talking about.
All they talk about is whether it's saved them time or it reduced.
How many bugs there were or it was the time to Market got smaller
whatever.
Right.
So the things they're looking at are just fundamentally, not
performance and honestly, I don't really think you can get away with
that anywhere.
I think the only reason that people get away
With that in the web world is because they don't have competition,
right?
Fundamentally speaking.
If someone was shipping an email server right now that had one
millisecond response time all the time, everyone would use it.
Like that would be the end of any other anyone else's email because it
feels awesome to use things that are that fast, right?
It feels fantastic and people feel the difference, right?
But the truth is no one in that space is serving anything like that.
You can't go get the high performance equivalent to Twitter.
You can't go get the high performance equivalent to Facebook.
You can't go get the high performance equivalent to gmail.
You can't go get the high performance equivalent to Google Maps.
They don't exist.
Right.
And so until people actually are shipping competition in that space,
right?
It's it'll skate.
The reason it doesn't work in the game Space is because you do have
competition.
Nobody wants to play a one frames per second game when they can play a
30 frame per second game.
And nobody wants to play a 30 frames per second game, when they can
play a 60 frames per second game, in fact, there are streamers now, I
think it.
TotalBiscuit who said he won't even stream 30 frames per second games
anymore, something like this.
I don't know if that's really true, but someone was saying something
that's right.
So in the game Space, you see all of this pressure for performance to
matter and hence we can't go use, you know, Ruby or Pearl or something
like this because throwing away, even if it was great which I don't
even necessarily think those languages are all that great.
But even if they were, we can't afford to give up the opportunities to
optimize.
That we need right but that doesn't mean we don't want high-level
languages, we do.
I don't want to have to keep writing the kinds of codes.
I write on handmade hero.
I don't want to have to build linked list myself, but the stupid part
of it is, is it C plus plus, it features are so bad.
That usually, I end up being happier, writing a linked list myself
every time than trying to use templates because they're terrible,
right?
And so you get into these situations where it's just like yeah, you're
damned if you do damned if you don't.
And so, hopefully what we'll be able to get to now that we're getting
serious about this sort of thing is that we'll be able to start
getting a spectrum based language in here.
Whether it's j.i.
or something else that allows
Allows us to have the low-level specificity when we want it and scale
up to not having it when we don't, right?
so,
Trans women.
This sounds like a good argument for requiring software, engineering
students to ship a game as one of the requirements for Education maybe
or just have a hard cap on their performance of something, right?
So let him write something web related but say it's got to respond in
one millisecond.
It gets one millisecond turnaround time, right?
So you got to respond within the Ping or whatever to Ms?
Let's say.
You know, so they can't just they can't they can't even use PHP,
right?
Because I think the PHP is like, minimum, turnaround time is probably
worse than that.
Maybe not.
But you know what I mean, right?
Catch over.
I do think it's worth moving from to see posotion c99.
I don't see 99 would be fine for me.
I don't really care, but other people see some stuff that they like
and see bus so, you know, your mileage may vary.
Picking the lesser of two evils here.
What's your advice between good new emacs and MCS?
I don't know what MCS is and I don't use going to be Max anymore.
I use for coder and it is what I would recommend for an editor.
If guy doesn't work out, will you have to take it into your own hands
to make a language?
I already sort of do like, at Molly.
We have our own custom stuff.
And like I said, I'm hoping that within three years will be entirely
on the custom stuff, and we won't be using C++ at all anymore, but I,
it's kind of a phased thing because we have to shift games the
meantime, and so I can't afford to just dedicate my time entirely to
doing that if we have a windfall where one of our games makes a ton of
money or something, then, you know, I might
Right.
But yeah, we will we will either be off of our stuff because we moved
on to jii or something equivalent or we will just be entirely on our
own stuff, one of the other, but we definitely will not be on C plus
plus ten years from now.
I can tell you that I'm hoping three years but you know, everything
always
It's longer than you wish it would.
So, you know,
I wouldn't count on it, I'm not counting on it.
Unfortunately, I wish I could, is there a practical way to use C in
place of web languages like JavaScript and HTML?
Is it possible to give them competition on the web?
Yeah, so like I said, I did this actually recently and it's kind of
awesome, right?
I don't know if you've ever seen how long it takes normally to
subscribe to like a mailing list or something on the web, it's this
big long process that takes multiple seconds or something where you're
like waiting in.
There's look usually a little spinning thing or whatever.
But I wrote Our
Revealing the server and see, and that's how long it takes.
Right?
It's like instant, you push the button.
It's like, boom, you're done and
I think it took me two days to write the email server for a list.
And it's hilarious, like the thing, we replaced, which Ismail jet
mail.
Jet took many seconds to like do it and it was buggy.
It didn't work.
Like that's why we replacing the first place as it was like, the code
was so bad that they messed up the subscriptions for things.
It was pretty hilarious.
So yeah.
And I like I said I think you know if we wanted to I think we could
just annihilate male jet like if that's if that's what we thought we
want to do it.
Molly rocket was like, I'm sure we could take out MailChimp and mail
Jet and everybody else because I mean, I could probably run a single
server that would probably be as efficient.
It's like their entire AWS Farm or whatever the heck they're doing
because it's mailing list is so simple.
It's trivially parallelizable.
It's like
Almost no back-end processing time, right?
So yeah.
I feel like a lot of this stuff is just Amateur hour and if you were
really serious, you could go totally.
Just, you know, you could just go into some space like that and you
could just totally own it because all your stuff would just
would just annihilate.
What's in there currently?
When I started University, we started learning.
Oh, and Java.
Do you think that this is part of the problem?
I'm pretty sure if we'd started learning about Hardware than assembly
then see, I would have had better programming earlier.
Yeah.
I guess what I would say is,
I think you have to learn a very simple programming language first.
Like, you know, I the first thing that I learned was basic, right?
Which doesn't have object-oriented it at all, either, but it certainly
doesn't have, like Assembly Language.
You stuff in it either, right?
So I think, you know, to bootstrap, your first language needs to be
whatever is simple and allows you to get some traction and it
encourages you to learn logo even
Anything but yes I think that starting with object orientation is just
bad because it's kind of a throwaway thing that I don't really think
is useful and so I think yeah, once you're ready to start taking the
leap into more serious program, I think Hardware assembly.
See very good things to learn because you start to learn like how code
actually works on a computer and then build up your higher level
language class with there.
So you can see what you are losing and make sure you don't lose
important things.
When you choose a higher level language, construct for the problem at
hand,
So Risco, how high is getting rid of Windows that H and standard
libraries on your to-do list?
Are you talking about on handmade hero or at work?
So you still need to convert to HTML, JavaScript etcetera.
But you do, your main development.
See
No, it's a back.
End is completely written in C.
The hilarious part is is I didn't even do any performance operation in
fact, the server isn't even compiled with optimizations on.
And it runs as a cgi-bin, it's not even memory resident so it has to
load the executable.
And it's still like 10:00 10:00.
I don't know how many times a thousand times faster than the male jet
one.
I don't know what the fuck people do.
Who I sure am not supposed to swear.
We're still technically on stream.
I don't know what people do when they write these things.
I have no idea because that is not even an optimized program, it's
completely unoptimized program.
I could make it 10 times, 100 times probably faster.
Then what it is right now.
Probably even more than that, but it's so much faster than everything
else.
I didn't even try, I was just like, oh my God.
So risk.
Oh yes, getting rid of sterile, Arizona, Windows a Chanel, okay?
I don't know that we'll ever bother getting rid of Windows .h on
handmade hero because I don't there's I don't know that I ever said
that I would do that for sure and it's not super necessary.
Getting rid of the standard libraries.
We only use about five functions from there right now.
So it's not very high in the list at all.
It's just a trig functions that need to be replaced, sine cosine, and,
and round, and seal.
That's about it.
So someday
Take a break and just do a few math routines, but that's the only one
that's all we need.
Is the master teens.
We don't use anything else, so so
I don't consider that particular high priority because like I said, we
don't really hard.
We basically don't use anything right now.
We're almost standard library free, but eventually we will have to
write the Cindy versions of those math routines and then we can pull
the stick then we can pull the library's completely
What do you think about the new coffee Lake processor announcement?
Seems like Intel is losing it.
I have not heard about that.
Should I be terrify?
Do you think tdd is efficient for a learning tool?
I don't know.
It's got some benefits, I'm not sure.
What is your opinion?
High level features that are predicated on the unobservable, T of
various low-level details?
Well, you know, again like I said, I think as long as they're
optional, it's not so bad.
So, I know Crown, how is it even possible to remove windows, that H?
I thought that was the lowest possible Choice without writing a noise
yourself.
Yes.
Well, so when you talk about Ruby winners, a nature not talking about
removing Windows, obviously, if you're running on Windows, you have to
call windows.
So yes, there is no way to get any lower than what we're at right now,
but you don't actually have to include Windows of H.
What you can do is just take the windows functions, you actually call
and you can just copy your, the ones you want into your own.
All and then be done and then you don't have as much.
It doesn't take as much compile time because doesn't have to include
all those ridiculous Windows headers.
It only has the few that you actually need.
So, yes, there's no way, you know, if you're running on Windows, you
have to call windows.
So you won't get rid of that, but you can avoid including their header
files because all you need is the function.
Signatures,
Have you done any JavaScript programming?
Yes.
In fact, I've done a bunch of JavaScript programming.
I don't like it, but I've done it.
Policymakers, you know, so it was 10, nanometer for low Performance
Machine and 14 nanometer for high-end, but more cores.
Hmm.
oh wait, so you're saying that the process
the, the process is,
A smaller.
It's a die shrink for the low perf but not for the hype perf.
I guess I'm not sure.
I'll have to look at it.
Shawn I know has his own file for just the windows function
prototypes.
He uses I've tried this and see and it worked practically flawlessly.
But I've had a problem.
Getting it to work in CBP.
Do anything about that?
Help me or should try the form.
Well, I've never had a problem with it and I compiled in CPP on at
work and I don't use any headers of any kind and I've never had a
problem with that.
I just use have my own prototypes.
Don't forget, need to put an extra in see around them.
Right, you need extern quote, see quote and then a bracket, and then
you can go, right?
So don't forget that.
Have you considered getting a team together and maybe making new
language doing it the right way?
Well, you know, I like I said I don't really know it's not necessarily
my area of expertise and I don't really know that I'm going to have to
you know, like for we don't know what's going to happen with Jay.
I maybe it's great and just works.
And then why would I bother right?
Like, you know,
We don't know that that that the successor to see much less isn't
already here, right?
So, so we
I have a ton of stuff to do obviously, right?
And so,
Until I have a little bit more freedom to explore stuff like that.
I certainly am not going to rush into try and be the person who does
that when there's already capable people trying some things that area.
And so, I'd rather see if they succeed first.
Because if they succeed, then, then we're done, right?
I mean, I don't need to be involved in that.
I am currently writing the renderer for my own engine, and I don't
know if I should future-proof it by writing it in, Vulcan are sick
with opengl 4.3.
Do you have any opinions on the importance of multi-threading for
rendering?
Yeah, I guess what I would say is multi-threading is incredibly
important for rendering but if you want to you can just write in
opengl 4.5 and be done with it.
Opengl 4.5 has lots of multi-threading effects because better
multi-threading the Vulcan if you want in terms of, if you use
extensions for example, Envy command list,
Is fantastic for multi-threading.
So you have some options, the problem, the thing that I'm worried
about is that I would say.
Opengl 4.5 is much better than Vulcan in most ways.
Opengl 4.5 with extensions, is much better at the problem is, I don't
know how well it will be supported if vendors decide that Vulcan is
the way to go.
And that's where they put all their time, then we're just screwed,
right?
And there's nothing we can do about it.
We're going to all have to write Vulcan, even though it's not
particularly well-designed API, opengl 4.5 is a lot closer to a good
design, a pi, it's still not great.
But it's better than Vulcan, but I don't know how well supported it
will be.
And it still has the old Legacy context crap, that that is not good,
and I don't know if they'll be willing to get rid of that.
So it's really too bad.
What?
I wish they would have done is not done Vulcan.
I wish they would have taken opengl 4.5 removed, a ton of the stuff,
that's not a zdo and removed context.
Completely
That opengl 5 because I think that would have been great.
I think they would have a real good API instead.
Now we got this ridiculous Vulcan thing, sitting around.
I have no idea why it's even there.
It's not useful.
I don't I I wish Vulcan would just go away.
Honestly I don't think it's good.
I think it's just a bad API.
I don't really have anything else to say.
Other than that, I think opengl 4.5 is way closer to a good API.
I just think I think you could just get rid of a lot of stuff from it.
It and make a few targeted additions, and I think you'd be, you'd have
a really great high performance API, that does everything the falcon
can do.
But without all of the really bad sort of artifact, you stuff
Lexis remove context for opengl.
What do you mean?
What I mean, is you want opengl to be effectively stateless for the
most part.
And right now, it's very stateful.
You have this concept that you've you make contacts current and then
there's all this state that's stored on the context.
And that's just not constructive.
Like, you don't really want that.
What you want to be able to do is just build up things in memory.
And then you really just want kind of one call, which is like execute
this memory, right?
And they've got a lot of that in opengl 4.5.
Plus
Tensions now.
So for example, you could just build up MV command lists, execute them
and there's no real estate associated with them and so really you just
build up your memories sets and you batch them in off you go, right?
And that's what you want because the closer you get to that the more
you get away from threading restrictions, which is what you want
opengl right now.
Because of the make contacts thing is really, really tough to
multi-thread properly and it just
Needs to go away, right?
It just needs to go away.
There's no need for it anymore.
They've replaced almost all of the things that you need to context for
with better systems.
But there's just a few cases in terms of like which display you're
targeting and how you ever just call through it that just require you
to still use them and that's like a really big problem, right?
So we just got to get rid of that.
So I'd say opengl 5.0 should have, it should be that right?
It should be no more context.
There's no
After that, there's just one call to call us execute memory.
The memory has an own format where you write in the things you want to
do and that's the API, right?
It would be baller.
So, you know, that would be my wish is that and then we can get rid of
Vulcan and never have to hear about it again because it's just a giant
monstrosity that I think distracts and takes implementation time away
from the other targets.
Interesting that you and John Blow disagree about the usefulness of a
zdo.
a CDO is like, absolutely
% critical and and it not not because the performance actually
performance is one reason that a CDO is is interesting, but the real
reason is, is robustness, right.
The real reason is robustness, and you just don't get that without a
video when you define a large driver surface, right?
It becomes much more difficult.
Cult to a for the programmer to know whether they're using that
drivers surface effectively and in a bug free Manner and also it
becomes very, very difficult for the driver to implement what it needs
to implement in order to execute things efficiently, right?
And so typically what you'll see happen, often times is you'll see.
Even in a scenario where you have a large driver service, what ends up
happening is the driver, buffer is a ton of stuff so it can figure out
what you're actually doing and then executes it, right?
So what we want to do is move away from that to a system where you're
just prepping the memory.
It has all the commands you need to do you dump that off to the card
and to the driver and it goes, right?
Because not only does that let you be completely thread thread.
It is highly thread.
As you want, you no longer have any thread issues, you'll ever have
any words, think problems and all that stuff.
You just go and prep everything you want and when you're ready to prep
you kick off and then all you need is notifications of when those
kickoffs are complete so that you can reclaim the memory.
That's all you need to do right?
And it's very, very clean.
It's extremely efficient really, really important.
And so I see the azd z ZD o design is being crucial.
It doesn't go as far as I want it to yet but it's getting there and
You know, I think it's a very good thing.
And we both agreed that we should just have a stable I say and not
even bother putting a GPS or an API, you are.
Absolutely.
And that's one of the reasons that I think a CTO is so constructive as
we go towards more and more easy to do, that becomes an icy, right?
If you literally have zero driver overhead, meaning that I just make a
call and that thing sends men coming down to the card to execute that
effectively has now been a data format that is a stabilizer, right?
So easy to do is is basically a step to stable.
I say, right?
Because the more driver overhead, you have, the less specified.
What is happening on the card?
The less specified it is.
What is actually happening on the card by definition, right?
Because the driver is doing more stuff.
Do you think dx12 is going to be a big improvement over 11?
I don't know.
I don't program DirectX really hardly at all.
so,
all right, this has been a very long queue a so I'm done.
I'm spent.
I need a drink.
Or as Microsoft would say, I need lots of dranks.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and it comes with source
code so you can play around with it at home.
And follow along the series.
We also have forms that you can go to.
If you want to ask questions of patreon page, you can go to.
If you would like to support our video series, a schedule bot that
will tell you when we are alive and an episode guide.
If you would like to catch up on old stuff, that is the last stream
for the week.
I will be
A off, as you can see, nothing scheduled.
I will be off till next week, but we will be back working on particle
systems next week that is about it.
Until then have fun programming, folks, I will see you on the
internet.
Take it easy, everyone.