Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just us in our typing fingers, right now, we are in the middle of
doing fonts, actually.
Been a long time coming.
A lot of people have asked over going to be fonts, and we are doing
fonts.
We've got fonts on the screen actually they look just fine but there's
some things that we have not finished yet that we need to finish and
really the biggest one is called kerning which we discussed a little
bit earlier and today is pretty much going to be all about kerning so
that we can get our fonts horizontal spacing looking nicer than it
looks right now.
If you would like to follow along at home, and you preorder the game
on handmade hero dot-org, today is day.
17 T.
So please unpack day 169 source code into a directory.
That is the source code that I will be starting with today and it is
the source code that you will want to start with so that you can
follow along at home.
I'll go ahead and bring this up.
Let me get my emacs window.
So if you take a look at where we left things on Friday, we had just
finished getting our Baseline stuff working so that our
It's are nicely lined up on the screen.
You can kind of see that everything lines up very nicely along that
Baseline.
Like we would want it to typographically speaking but we do not have a
bunch of other things.
We might like to have working with our fonts.
Namely our horizontal spacing is now just based on the bitmap we don't
have any information about how letters should go together like this.
See for example looks too far from the I compared to how the you is
set up stuff like that.
Like you'd want to be a little bit closer saying with this T.
And this you for example, a lot of places where you
I have two pieces extending right?
It's setting them up the way that they should be based on the bitmap
with.
But really, the way typographers do it, is they, let things could have
come into each other's space, right?
They let them kind of interpenetrate a little when you have, when the
two things don't line up, right?
When you have a thing like this, where two things line up, then it's
fine to, like, sort of line them up with a bitmap with.
But when you have things where the, like furthest extent to the left
of one character, and the further extend to the right of another
character, don't line up, you typically want to sort of push them a
little closer together, it just
Looks and reads a little bit nicer.
So we want to do that.
We want to fix that, for sure.
And then there's also a few other sort of leftover text metrics.
We'd also like to have such as the line spacing, you can look and see
our this p.
And this L right.
When you have a descender and an Ascender, you can kind of see how we
don't leave the right amount of space, that's because all we did for
this test routine was just arbitrarily pick some amount of pixels to
advance to put the next font to put the next line in and what we'd
really rather.
Other do is read that information out of the pond itself, so that we
know how much line spacing they're supposed to be and so that it works
with any font.
So we'd like to do all those things and so let's get started.
On that.
So first things first, let's take a look at that font routine.
Let's take a look at how we were drawing that font, right?
We have that debug text line and if you take a look at what happened
in here, it was all very straightforward.
We added some fun things in here like people wanted like being able to
switch for the colors of the lines and stuff like that.
But if you take a look at the actual meat of a code, this stuff is
just for changing colors and scales and stuff by using embedded code
and weird stuff like that really.
The only part of this code that matters at all, is just this right
here, right?
It's just the, the code in this Loop in.
Well, in this part of the loop, where we go ahead and say, find
whatever the font is that fine.
Whatever.
The like, the character Cliff is that we're trying to draw.
Go ahead and figure out how big it is and where it should be and draw
it, right?
That's that's
That's the entirety of like what we actually have to do and we've
already sort of mentioned, the fact that, you know, one thing that
we'd like to do is get the line spacing.
Be correct.
The line spacing would just be replacing this ad hoc line here where
we just got a random 1.2 times 80 like, you know, whatever that is,
right?
Get rid of that, and replace it with some actual real value that we
know is the line spacing.
So that's one thing that we would want to do
And that's pretty easy.
That's just one value.
But the more complicated thing is we want this part right here where
we actually have the the @x advance, right?
This card in value where we advance the horizontal spacing.
What we'd like to do is actually have something there that advances,
the spacing differently.
Depending on the pair of characters rather than just on one character.
We talked about this before when I did introduction of fonts, it's
called kerning.
And what kerning is, is it setting different advancements depending on
a pair of characters instead of just a constant advancement or an
advancement per character, right?
Because right now we're actually advancing a different amount per
character, potentially, right?
If a character is with is smaller we advance by less.
So we're actually sort of doing a proportionally spaced font at this
point, right?
And in fact you could see this if I was to switch which font we were
using and let me just go ahead and do that.
Just
To underscore what the difference between a proportional spacing and a
kerned spacing are because they're actually not necessarily the same
thing.
I mean, the terminology is a little fuzzy there so it's unclear what
you're really referring to, but I just want to underscore that there's
two different ways you could think of it, right?
So let's say we're here in the asset processor and we switch back to
Ariel.
So instead of using courrier, new, which is a less, it's sort of more
of a fixed width.
Supposed to be more of a fixed-width font.
Let's say we go ahead and do
That.
That sort of proportional font as the font that we're going to have in
the game, right?
So now when we run, we're going to have Ariel in
At okay.
And what you can see very clearly.
When you look at this is we are, we are totally already supporting a
proportional font because the distance that we advance for every
character is drastically, different, the distance.
The spacing on this T is much different than the spacing on this.
You write this U advances much wider than this.
T Advance is much narrower.
Right, so we are already supporting proportionally spaced fonts.
What we're not supporting is kerning and what
Learning is is moving a sort of a font designer tweaked amount because
like the classic case right here?
There's two is a very obvious one, right?
You can see right in the space of this T, what a font designer would
do is it would it would reduce these two gaps here dramatically,
right?
So even though right now it's perfectly flush like this.
Oh the first character of this 0 starts right?
Where this one left sleeves off and the first character this T
starting the first pixel.
This T starts right where this Laster, the P leaves off.
So we're
Obeying a proportional fault rule there but we're not obeying is the
fact that when there are different shapes of letters sometimes you
want the spacing to be more or less because it looks better.
It has nothing to do with how big the character is.
That's not what it's about.
It's about how the different pieces of those character glyphs line up
with each other.
And so, it's about the pair of characters.
If this right here was another uppercase t, we wouldn't want them to
be closer together.
So it's about the fact that it's a lowercase p and an uppercase t and
it's that pairwise.
Size spacing, that's the important part, okay.
So, that's what we're talking about.
So, how do we do that, right?
Well, like I said, when we were talking about kerning originally, it's
really not a big deal.
People were asking whether I was going to support proportional fonts
and all this sort of thing, I get this impression that some people
think that's a big deal.
It's not a big deal.
As you already saw getting a proportional spaced font is Trivial.
It just means instead of incrementing edx by a constant value.
Instead you at increment it by a value that changes per bitmap that we
did.
So we're already got.
It was trivial, right?
It is a is a literally one line change in the code, right?
You're just adding in instead of making this a constant somewhere,
you're just making it based on the, with the character case.
Very, very, very straightforward.
That's the only difference between a fixed-width font and a
proportional font.
That's all right.
Now, in order to take that up to kerning, which is one level above
again, very, very straightforward.
We are not going to change this routine pretty much at all.
We're going to do exactly the same thing that we did in doing the only
Difference.
Is that amount that we advance now has to be based on both the current
character and the previous character?
Right?
So what we want to do here is we want to store, you know, we've got
these code points.
Right.
What we want to do is we want to store the previous code point, right?
We want to have here and I notion of what the previous
Code point was, Will initialize it to zero saying no code point.
And then we coming here every time we output, one of these characters,
what we will do is we will save whatever that code point was.
We will remember, right, whatever that code Point actually was.
Okay, so we'll keep that previous code point.
So then, what we would know is, we know, both the current code point
and the previous code point, right?
And we could even do this a little bit more sort of opaquely here.
We could do something.
Where we want to, you know, sort of formalize, this notion of a code
point, a little bit, just just to make things easier on ourselves
later if we want to support International languages and things like
this, right?
So, I'm just going to go ahead and pull that out and called out the
code Point here.
Really, very simple.
So, if I pull that out there, so now we've got the code point and
we've got the previous code Point.
Like, so let's go ahead and compile this right.
Right, there we go.
It's code point.
I thought I had that hero.
Just my capitalization there.
There we go.
So if I do it like that, now you can see, nothing has changed, right?
Same exact routine nothing's different.
The only difference now is I've set myself up for actually getting
what I need, which is that?
This thing right here, right?
Which is the kerning amount is going to be something that we look up
now, right?
It's going to be something different.
We're not going to save this anymore.
This care dim thing.
Is not going to be used, right?
We're going to get rid of that and what we're going to do instead and
you know, we could even do something a little bit fancier.
If we wanted to hear, we could do something like this where we say,
Okay are kerning right?
Or are our Advanced x equals something.
Well, which we don't know what it is yet and we'll do our Advanced X
there.
And that way, if we want to, we could always go back to to setting it
up to use proportional.
So you can switch between the two modes.
Just so you can see the difference between them, which might be a
little bit interesting.
I think, right?
All right, so we've set ourselves up like this, right?
And again, if I just do this, we're back to the same, right?
I haven't changed routine at all.
I'm just some kind of, like, fussing with it.
I'm just like moving it into a slightly different position than it was
in originally.
Right.
So now if I want to I can I can comment that out and say we're not
going.
Advanced sex.
That way anymore.
We're going to do instead is set Advanced effects based on some kind
of kerning, right?
What I want to do now is I want to be able to ask for the kerning.
The proper amount of kerning for sort of these two, these two code
points that I have.
I want to say, like, get, you know, horizontal advance for pair or
something, right?
And I want to say, I want to know what the horizontal Advanced is
between the code point that I'm on, right?
And the
Point that came before it.
Makes sense, right?
And furthermore, I think what I'd like to do, I mean, you know, now
that I think about this, I kind of want to phrase this in the reverse
way I think, because when we start out, you wouldn't want to advance
at all which we could handle by just saying that.
Well, when the code Point, whatever, the code point zero is we'll just
have no advancement or something like that.
But the interesting thing is that when I actually do this, the
advancement I would want to pre Advanced, right?
I'd want to pre Advanced it like that which makes it a little
Order to keep the older method here.
You know what I mean?
Because I want Advanced between the previous and the current like so.
So, yeah.
Hard to say right?
What I could do instead, if I wanted to is I could do something where
I look at the next code point, right?
And then do that, but if I do that, then it becomes harder for people
who want to do this kind of nonsense where you parse things out of the
string and use them.
So I don't know, I guess maybe I just give this up and say, you know
what's not going to happen?
Sorry my friend.
And what we will actually do is always, do are advancing previous that
you know at the head end right?
Basically
And so that seems like a little bit better to me.
That seems like a little bit more what I want.
And so I'm going to do it like that and then when we compile, you
know, all of our code will just work at this point.
The only thing is we just don't know what that actual value is going
to be.
Now obviously, in order to get the horizontal Advanced, we going to
need some different things.
First of all, I'm going to have to scale by whatever it is.
I'm scaling everything else by, right?
Because we're all all of the fonts that are stored in some space,
like, whatever the dimensions and the font are and all that.
Stuff in pixels, whatever.
We're scaling that by however much we want to scale the font, right?
So we're going to store our kerning in that same space obviously that
just makes sense.
So in the in the asset file, all the current information should be
stored in the same way as any other number in the van system.
That's just, you know, just the same way to do it.
So when we do this we're going to need one other piece of information
which is which actual font we're talking about.
And this is sort of gets into the final piece which is sort of, like I
said, sort of it is moving
Asset system up a notch, like adding the notion of having these
different fonts so that we can more quickly access this the data that
we need to access in them, right?
So what I would like to do is I'd like to have some way of having
because you'll notice I have this thing here where it says this is too
slow for text at the moment I'd like to have some way of sort of
having a centralized piece of font information because I'm going to
have to have this kerning information.
We know that I would like to have something faster for looking up the
glyphs than going.
Going through the whole matching system.
Every time we want to render a character, that seems like a bad idea
and furthermore, I'd like to have some place to store that
information, like the line height which we just don't have the
Right?
And so those are a bunch of things that that's what I would like to
start having.
So what I think I really want to do, right?
It's I want to be able to get a font and actual concept of a font back
from my asset system, right.
I want to have something where I can do you know asset or you know,
font something like this.
And it's a first-class citizen out here in, you know, in the the whole
asset thing.
We're in here.
We just have these and they're not going to be demand loaded.
The bitmaps will be demand loaded but we can actually just have them
you know as a separate adjunct thing that gets loaded as part of the
giant block load, right?
We could totally do it that way and there's really nothing
particularly stopping us from doing that as far as like and think of
and so what I'd like to do, yeah, like I said, it's just go ahead and
start expanding that out.
So in here, you know we would have
In like, in addition to the asset counts in the asset types, we would
also have something here.
That would just be you know our font right?
And you know what?
Now that I think about it, we could actually use the acid system to do
matching where we just put in what we've kind of the characteristics
of a font that we want and out would come.
And so maybe we even want to go that far.
Like maybe we want to to make that happen as well.
I don't know if that makes a lot of sense, it may it may not but it's
something that we can consider
And if we did go that route, then things would be a little bit weird
because it does mean that we would have stuff like our fonts would
have to actually be tracked as part of the as part of the loading and
all that sort of stuff which, you know, I just don't know how
important that is.
I don't know.
I do not know what I think about that.
I'm okay with it.
Maybe let's just go down that route and we'll see what happens.
And that way fonts can be as big as they want and they won't get
loaded unless they're actually being used seems okay.
The downside of it is it means that that any code that needs to work
with the font can't necessarily.
Yeah.
See this is the part.
I don't like any code that's going to do operations on the front.
Like seeing like laying out where the characters have to go, can't
actually run until the font is actually paged in, right?
I don't know how I feel about that.
On the other hand, if we have lots of different fonts, if we have
different fonts for different languages or stuff like that,
could get a little hairy right?
Having all of those things always loaded, like always having to load
the kerning tables for every language font does seem a little bit
annoying.
It's Tricky, right?
I mean it's a little bit tricky.
I feel like
I'm gonna go for it, I'm going for it, you know, it's sometimes you
can't make a decision.
Sometimes there's no way to make an informed decision so you just go
for it.
So I'm going to say that we have some kind of a loaded font thing
here.
I'm just going to say we've got that and then what we do is we say
okay, you know, we've got this loaded font, we want to get our font
and that's the only thing that gets type matched, right?
That's the only thing that we actually do sort of have the the match
Vector for, right?
And so, what we do here is we say okay we want to go ahead and get our
font back so we'd have.
Yeah.
In fact this this stuff up here would now actually be exactly for for
that.
So the will have the match factor in the weight Vector.
We'd say go ahead and get us the best font.
So I guess we'd say something like you know font ID.
Oh okay.
I see how this is going.
This is might not be so bad.
Guess that get Matt best match font right?
Put it like all this bitmap from soda pop from right we passed that
asset system.
We say that we want an asset fonts which is exactly what we do want,
in fact,
And then we pass our vectors and right now we don't really have
anything to pick from.
I suppose.
We'll have like a debug thought sort of concept or I don't know
something like this.
Hard to say.
So anyway, we do our guests, get our best match font or and what not.
And then down in here, we would have we would get rid of this this
notion.
So it would just be our code point would be something relatively
direct right and we would assume that we could actually get our font
out as well.
So what we do here is we'd say something like get font, right?
Because we have, you know, these sort of query routines where you do
get sound, get so on right.
So,
Have a loaded fonts and we'd call get font.
We would pass the assets for that.
Look, so
And we'd also need our generation ID for that guy as well.
So I think that just be our render groups generation ID, right.
Like so, so when we get the font we would pass it For Thought ID.
That would either get us back a font or wouldn't depending on whether
it's loaded.
So assuming that it actually is loaded, if the font is loaded then we
can proceed with doing what we would like to do.
If not, then obviously we can't.
This feels like this should be
Yes, that's all good.
So I thought that looks fine to me.
I think I can live with that.
I think I'm okay with that.
And so again, what I'm going to do here is just say what I want this
thing to do, I'm just going to say I'm going to pass you a font and
some code points, you're going to tell me what the horizontal
advancement is.
I'm just going to assume that we can make that happen.
We are you know, sort of we are bright and capable programmers who
will make that occur.
And so we've got a code Point here, we were previously putting in a
match vector and having get bitmap info.
Pull that out.
What I'd rather do is say that we've got that bitmap ID now is going
to come from a direct look up inside the font so we do get bitmap for
glyph right?
And we would pass it.
The code Point, write something like this.
There's some extra stuff in there.
That I would like to sort of look at a little bit later as well, but
point being so, what I'd like to do is get that bit back there and
then assuming that we get the back that bitmap ID from from the thing,
we can then get the info and continue, right?
So we've kind of just stubbed out we've, you know, again, I'm
following the right, the usage code.
First methodology here, I'm just trying to make it so that everything
makes reasonable sense.
Don't actually remember where we were defining the
I d like sound ID and so on.
I have no idea where those are actually defined to be honest with you.
This is the problem of maintaining, well, working in three code bases
at once, I guess I do our game at Molly, the witness and this one, I
start to forget, where everything is anyway.
So I'd like to do struck sound ID and I remember how to make this
actually find those as a group, doesn't it some kind of weird thing
where it
consider it considers them multiple things.
Oh, you know what?
I can probably just backslash the space is that work?
Can't do this.
There we go.
So if I want to get my struct sound ID,
Here they are, handmade file formats.
So what I'd like is I'd like to sound idea, I'd like to go to be a
font idea, right?
But a similar, that also can be retrieved, right?
And, so now, assuming that I do this, I can get all of this other
stuff that I want starting to be stubbed out.
And so, in handmade asset .h, I can start to sort of make these actual
routines.
They should be relatively straightforward, right?
So, if I'm calling get sound, for example, I should be able to call
instead.
The same thing on a font right?
I should be able to say get font pass it a font ID and the generation
ID and then when I get that asset back, I'm just going to only look at
the font part of it, instead of the sound part of it.
And that's really all there is to it right then.
Inside that loaded, font will just assume are all the things that we
actually want which we're going to go over figuring out.
What those are in a second here.
And they're just going to be based on these routines now while I'm at
it because I'm being greedy I might as well.
Write also say that we can go ahead and get that line advancement as
well, right?
Get the thought comes back, okay, I should be able to do something
where I just say.
Okay,
What's the line, Advanced?
Right?
So I just say get line advance for this font and as long as I multiply
it by the font scale, there we go.
Now font scale Cara scale that stuff looks about right.
So I'm satisfied that I think so now if we compile this you can see
we've essentially got four different sort of things we want the font
to be able to answer.
So I'm going to go ahead
Ed and sort of stub, those out here and start to see what I actually
need.
What will I need in terms of data to answer these questions, right?
What if I'm, if I'm going to answer these questions for the
application, that's what I what I want to see, right?
And again, this is just following that, right?
The use of church first, push down kind of measurement, methodology,
kind of a top-down methodology that I'm taking here because I know
what I want.
I don't necessarily know what I need to do to implement it.
So I'm coming from the
I know, and going towards the thing, I don't know, which is always the
best way to work.
If you're, if you're relatively certain that your code on one side is
correct.
It's pretty easy to kind of just push downward from there, right?
So, if I come through here and start implementing these guys, so I can
start to see what they're going to look like, right.
Like so.
Right.
and so assuming that these take loaded fonts,
So someone's already done.
The lookup.
Excuse me.
Oh, this guy is a little bit different, isn't he?
So this guy is going to be slightly different, so I'm going to move
that guy potentially up into a different point.
But anyway, these guys, we know
Exactly how what they're taking, and what they're going to return
here.
So, for the moment, I'll just go ahead and say, oh, yeah, the
horizontal advancement is just 10 pixels, I don't know, right?
And the line and, or 50, let's say 80 pixels will say, we, I think we
had randomly 80 in there for a bunch of stuff.
I think we had one point to F times 80 in there.
She said random values that are totally garbage for now, and then this
get best best match font from that.
We need to
Go put up with the asset system, probably the other asset system
calls.
We also have got this guy, which I've some reason to the copy in here.
Let's go ahead and put him in there.
So there we go.
We've got the loaded font and code Point like so and so we could even
sort of stub these out a little bit by.
We can we can even make these use the old thing that they were using
for, right.
You can imagine us doing something absurd in here, but yeah, I don't
know that.
I
I just really want to do that, but we could do something like, you
know what, we're just going to take font ID.
I don't even know, loaded font.
Don't don't try this at home, kids.
Do not try this at home.
We could do something like this.
I know it looks ridiculous.
We could do something like this at the moment and just actually have
this thing.
Still do the exact look up, just so we can make sure the code is
slotted in properly.
Not really, that important.
I'm not super worried about this but just to show that we could just
to make sure we've got the stuff we need.
So for getting the bitmap ID for the glyph here, I don't know if we're
really going to
Need the assets or not?
We're probably not, so I don't know, but I guess we should probably
have it one way or the other.
In case it does need to do look up in something.
That might be a good idea.
So I think maybe I will add that to the call just looking at it it's
like yeah I could see maybe we want the assets and their that seems
fair.
So if we do do the get bit best match bitmap from and I'll do the
match Vector e tag code.
A point.
What was the name of that?
File formats, Unicode code point.
So close right.
All right.
So if we do our weight vector and our match Vector, the match back,
we've got a match that code point.
And then we could still do this exact same thing, right?
And now I think our code is compiling or close to compiling, okay?
Probably should actually make that be something reasonable asset, ID
asset ID, and then we've got font Vector.
So this is an asset Vector match.
Can't wait.
Right.
Okay.
Get best match asset from asset type ID that is what I actually, yeah.
Initializing.
Oh, you can trust me, you can
It's all good and that returns a font ID.
Yeah.
Huh.
All right, never mind.
So we could have just a dress, all the trouble here and done.
That never mind.
There we go.
So yeah, and so then all we really have to do now is we just have to
make it so that the other function is stubbed as well.
So in our, in our in line here, where you actually get the font
We would have to sort of cheat at that.
We have to do something like this.
Where we say loaded?
Star results.
So now we're still working right?
In a kind of crazy way.
And as you can see, we're always advancing by the exact same size
everywhere, right?
Because we're just hard coded with that returns, but we're still wired
up properly.
So, all we really need to do now, to get things working, is to
actually go Implement these routines.
And we know that once we implement, the routines will be in good
shape, right?
We know that everything is kind of getting return properly and that
we're all set.
So let's go ahead and pull these things out, one by one.
So let the get font actually call through to get the font.
And then, let's start to implement these guys here, right?
So get best match bitmap from just does this.
So I'm going to call the exact same thing for the font because really
these are just very simple Funk functions that just kind of all they
do is make it so that you have to pass the right type to the asset ID
thing, which is really pretty basic.
So this should be totally fine.
We're just passing exactly all the stuff all the way through.
And so really, we don't, you know, we don't really need
Think fancier than just that that straightforward thing.
So, I'm just going to stick that there and that's all good.
Matt Decker, and weight vector.
And so that's all taken care of.
And now we're going to have to start actually going and editing the
asset file format to include these things that we actually want,
right?
So in here,
Let's pretend we actually have.
What we want.
I'm going to the simple version first and then we're going to do a
slightly more complicated version after that, but all I'm going to do
here is I'm going to say, okay,
We've got handmade hero asset, .h up in that loaded font.
I'm going to assume that I have a code Point count and a code Point
Min, something like this.
And that we basically have some kind of a range of code points, right?
In fact, at the beginning, you know what?
Let's not even do that at the beginning.
Let's just say we've got a code Point count, because that'll be fine
for for a ski.
When we start trying to think about, you know, do we want to handle?
Kanji or something, right?
Maybe not such a good idea.
But at the moment, we can just say, okay, we've got a code Point
count.
And then, we've got a bitmap ID for the code points, right?
So the bitmap ideas were just all in that code Point table, right?
So that's fine.
We then have an addition, we need the horizontal advance.
Right?
So we need horizontal advance and that's going to be a two-dimensional
table, right?
It's going to look up on two different things.
But that's relatively easy to do as well.
And then we also need a line advance and that's just one thing, right?
So we need something that looks like that.
That's what we need in our actual loaded font.
And so then if we were actually going to use that, it's pretty
trivial, right?
We just say, the result is the font line advance.
Pretty straightforward.
In this case, it's slightly more difficult to D array, look up, but
still totally trivial.
We're just going to look up into the horizontal Advanced and the way
that we would look up into that.
Horizontal Advance is we would just say, okay, we've got however many
code points.
There are right our previous code Point.
Let's say x the code Point count, plus the code Point standard 2D
array referencing, right?
We all know how to do this by now, we've done it a million times.
X.
So, we're just taking a two dimensional index.
One for the pre of code point, which is in this case and one for the
code Point standard, 2D array X array indexing we go ahead and return.
That simple, 2D array index, and done.
And then, in here what we have now is, we've already got a code Point
array.
So now we can just go ahead in here and say the font.
Has the code points in it.
So, whatever the code point is we just look it up directly and now
it's not that kind of annoying.
Remember I said it was really going to be slow before.
Now we're not running some kind of a search Match we just look up
directly what's a bitmap ID?
We get it back, we're done, right?
So that's way, that's way better.
Okay.
So now one of the things that's true about this is we probably want to
clamp these guys, right?
We probably don't want to be doing stuff, that's out of range for for
what we have.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to introduce the concept here where
I'm just going to say, well, there's like a desired code point that
I'm asking for and then there's the code point that I'm actually going
to get, right?
And normally it's going to be the desired code point, but only, if the
desired code points actually in range.
So if the desired code point is less than the code Point count for the
font,
Then I'm cool with it, right?
Otherwise we're just going to give you back the zero bitmap because
you're trying to draw a glyph, we don't have right.
And maybe the 0th code points always going to be mapped a bitmap 0.
So that you don't try anything right?
Who knows?
Point being, I want to clamp that right and serious.
Similarly, I'd like to do that here and you can kind of see that those
are going to be very similar.
So what I'd rather do is just have a thing that's like get clamped
code point.
Something like this so that I can pass these two things into it and
get back a result.
Right.
And so with that is
Do is that's going to do this exact clamp that we just did.
Excuse me, like so.
And so that allows me to just say, okay, I know now that I can just
always do this, these clamp things.
So anything that comes in I can clamp and then use, right?
Very, very straightforward.
And same thing.
Here we have code point is going to be equal to get clamped code,
Point desired, pre-code point.
Code point is going to be equal to get clamped code point I, guess
week.
Yeah, well, desired code point.
So
And that way again, the lookup will always succeed in, oh, he's work,
okay, even if we're getting out of range request, which is tireli like
Leon van.
So I don't want to have that.
Be a crash in area.
I'd rather have that be handled gracefully because it's the kind of
thing that might be happening in.
It's okay.
All right, so that's all I really wanted to have happen there.
I need to pass the font.
And now I do.
And that's about all there is to it, right?
Very straightforward.
That is literally all the code we actually need at runtime, right?
Because what I've essentially done is said, you know what, I just want
all of this information to be tabulated.
So that I can just straight-up look, you know, look it up and I don't
have to worry later about, you know, calculating things or figuring
things out.
I want it all.
Just be there as a quick index.
So once I get that font handle back, that's the only slow query.
The only slow query is give me the loaded font, everything else is
like a direct table lookup and doesn't have to go through anything
fancy because that you know, if we have lots of characters on the
screen, we don't want to constantly be doing all these queries to find
that we want to know.
Where is the character, here it is, right?
So now, although it's very easy to write that code because we base, so
we want everything tabulated.
We now have to actually go and build those tables right?
Which is, you know, that's work right there, right?
But hey,
Let's go ahead and do that.
It won't be that hard.
The first thing that we're probably going to need to do, and we'll go
ahead and do that in handmade file formats.
The first thing that we want to do is we need to introduce the the
fact that there's a difference between a font and the font glyph,
right?
Because our font glyphs are going to be different, are going to be
different range of bitmap IDs that are fonts, which are now actual
citizens, right?
So we kind of have two different things.
Now, do we really need
Need a font glyph asset type range, probably not but we might as well
just have one in there and then font itself of course is going to be
specific to the actual you know.
I want information.
Okay, so if we do that, yeah, again we're never really going to use
this to look anything up because we're going to be looking up the
fonts indirectly through the tables by just kind of thought it would
be nice to have it marked in the file so that it's clear what is a
font glyph?
And what isn't right?
so,
Now, we have to store these things, right?
And we know exactly what we need to store.
We know, we need to store this information so far and maybe some more
stuff, you know, we might want to store a couple other things with it
but that's that's basically what we're dealing with here, right?
That's what we want.
That's what we want to do.
You want to have?
So if we go ahead and look into this loaded font, we're going to want
to sort of augment what we're storing here.
So that when a font is stored, as an asset, it's in the file.
As something intelligent, right?
So we've had h a bitmap, we've got h a sound.
We now need an ha font, which has some of this additional information
in it, right?
And we started 20 minutes late today, so I'm definitely going to take
the extra time on the clock because this is all pretty wrote code.
That's obviously, as you seem very simple to write.
So we might as well kind of push through it and get as much of it done
as we can.
So that we're, you know, in the best possible position for tomorrow.
All right, so I've got my h a font.
I know that I need this information, right?
I know this is what I need.
But if you take a look at what happens here, obviously I've got two
different arrays and and so on.
So I can just basically say well okay, normally like a bitmap and
things like that.
They've got sort of the data-offset thing where they go and load their
data.
That's a late loaded thing, what I could do is just say for us, it's
not late loaded for fonts, it's loaded immediately at the time.
When you kind of open I could do that or I guess I guess, you know,
now that I think about it we said that it wouldn't
So I guess we're going to have that the actually in the data, the data
section, right?
So basically, all we're going to put here is what the code Point count
is, and what the line Advance is I guess, because those are the two
values that we actually could just store that aren't large.
And then we're just going to assume that our data offsets going to
point to array of bitmap IDs and then a 2d array of horizontal
advancements, right?
So I guess we could say data is right.
Code Point count.
And
Like so.
Right, and I'll mention this because people often ask me this
question.
On the stream.
I'll just mention it.
I'm going to try and start mentioning it more often now because people
have been asking, you know,
A lot of times.
I talked about how a lot of stuff like C++ has is bad and Javas bad
and all the sorts of stuff like don't do them and that's all true but
that's not the same thing as saying that C is good.
Okay and so I just want to point out.
For example, this sort of thing is stuff that should totally be
automatically generated and in a better language it would be and the
problem is in order to get those functionalities out of other
languages.
You have to take on a bunch of stuff you don't want.
Write C++ C, sharp Java that are, they don't make it easy to do what
you actually want to do.
They force you to incur all this baggage and that's what I don't like.
Right?
So the way that I typically handle these kinds of problems.
If I wasn't doing a game like handmade here, where the goal is to kind
of teach the ground up programming is the fundamentals, right?
The way that I typically handle these is, these are meta generated, so
I will typically do generation that generates file formats, so that it
can automatically do stuff like, oh, how many raised did you want?
Okay, we'll pack them together that sort of stuff, right?
Very, very simple.
It's trivial to do, right?
You just write a program that generates C code, right?
But it's kind of a level above.
And it's not something that I want to show on handmade hero because
everyone should do this first, you should do one game this way first,
because if you don't know how to do it, this you'll never know how to
write the meta code, right?
That's the big thing.
And so you got to do it once this way, but once you've done it once,
this way, you will see for yourself, how you like to arrange these
things.
And then you'll be able to pull out those common things into a meta
generated version if you so choose.
Now on handmade here, we're not going to have a lot of it.
So you would my argument would almost be that you wouldn't bother on
handmade hero anyway because the amount of time it would take you to
go do the Generation stuff is probably going to be longer than the
amount of time you would save.
But if you're taking the longer view, like I'm going to build an
engine.
I'm going to be lots of games with it.
Blah blah blah blah.
Then it becomes clear that it's easier to invest in that time because
now you have more flexibility and you can do many games and so on and
so forth, right?
So it's always about trade
US stories about making the right judgment call about what's the right
thing to build and what are the trade-offs and so on.
But I do want to point it out that, you know.
Yeah.
Do I always write all this stuff by hand?
No, I've got a lot of techniques for making sure that I don't have to
write it by hand, but the key part is the way that I choose to handle
that is not by going to a crappy language like Java where I then take
on all this baggage in my code is slow and lousy, I don't have to do
that, right?
I can still get all the benefits of c and I just fixed the parts that
are actually broken, which is the fact that I don't want to have to
write stuff like this, every time we're now I have to manually search.
Figure out how my array is packed in the file, right?
And so that's kind of the important thing to understand is that, yes,
he has tons of limitations, unfortunately, the higher-level Learners
don't fix them, they just exchanged them for other problems.
And so if you really want to get past that point, I recommend look,
you know you know, be a Jedi, build your own lightsaber, don't go
taken this sort of like, you know, targeting computer approach the
stuff, it doesn't work.
You're never going to get it into the exhaust for it that way.
Anyway, so moving on,
In that brief digression.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and say that the data
for these guys is this, you know, and I could go ahead and augment
these guys here as well.
To just make a quick note about what the data is.
So in this case data is channels, zero Channel count
Sample count.
Right, that's the way we chose to store that.
So it's kind of saying this is what goes in the data and same with h
bitmap.
We know what that is.
That's a you 32 of the pixels with Jim zero.
And in one, right?
So that's just me kind of making a note.
That's like, hey, yeah.
If this was a good programming language, that was like, super modern
and amazing.
I would have been able to met a program this so I can just say that.
And then the file format works or something.
It's not, but it's still a trustee language.
So I'm going to go write it myself the way I want it written and it
will let me do that, and that's awesome.
But I do want to make note of for people who are trying to read it,
that's what you're actually seeing, right.
Okay.
So let's go.
Ed and go over to the actual implementation of this stuff, right?
First thing I want to do is I want to figure out how I'm going to
actually load that stuff right.
Because if you look here, when we do load asset work directly, we kind
of have a problem there, which is that when we do that load asset
work, we, you know, oh well, you know, I don't have a problem.
We just set the pointers ahead of time, that's how we always did
stuff.
So, that should be fine.
So, yeah, so this will actually work the same.
So, if we, if we take a look at load bitmap, it's pretty much should
be the same as load sound and that should all be totally fine, right?
So we should be able to go ahead and grab like one,
You guys here and then we should be able to sort of do our own version
of this for loading fonts, which won't presumably be particularly
difficult.
We could come in here, we do our standard atomic exchange and add and
one thing that's a little bit annoying.
I will point out is I feel like this little bit of boilerplate here is
a little risky to do Casey, merge this boilerplate.
Because it's a delicate little Atomic thing.
I feel like we wanted that collapsed so that if we change it in one
place, we don't try to, you know, actually forget to change it for
each of the loading calls.
You know what I mean?
There's still a little, there's a little more.
There's too much shared code happening here.
That's not actually being shared and that makes me a little bit
nervous.
And so that's something that I would like to address in the future if
we have a chance to do.
So it's not the end of the world, but it, you know, it would make me
feel more comfortable if we did.
So anyway,
Moving on.
So if I have my load font call here, basically everything is the same.
The only difference is going to be that when I actually do the sort of
pointer sus stuff remapping here, I obviously.
Too well.
Set up the pointers in that loaded font, right?
So in here, if I had my loaded fonts, like so then I know that I have
to set again, I'm just I'm sort of just total totally on Rails here,
right?
I'm just following the footprint that I already laid down for myself.
Very, very very straightforward, right?
So let's go ahead and do this.
And you know what I mean?
Now that I look at this, right?
There's even, we can even, we can even make this even simpler, write
the code Point.
Count is really the only thing that we really need the line.
Advanced doesn't really even have to be there.
Honestly, I mean, we could, we could simplify that by having a font
header, I don't know that we need to do that.
So, you know, maybe we don't bother but and really, those could get
it.
Come out of the HOH, a font and probably should
That's how we've kind of been doing it.
So really, it's more.
We want just that almost
So I you know, it's a little bit it's a little bit tricky so I'm going
to go full pull I'm just I'm voting for full pull here and so if we if
we take a look at what that implies it basically I'm saying that the
AHA font would have something additional to head which is just like an
h a font info or something like that, right?
Or font header, something like that.
That it would have on the front and that HHH fonts font header would
actually have, it would actually be a sort of a data piece for that
font, right?
So it would have the line advance.
It would have, maybe the, like, the Baseline, the ascenders, the
dissenters we could have to, do you know, anything else we want?
Right.
And so I feel like that's a better thing to do almost in this because
the only piece of information we actually need for a font is the code
Point count.
That's it.
We don't need anything else.
Everything else can just be loaded?
And so what I'd like to do is sort of change that up a bit.
I'd like to go ahead and say that we have that font header and maybe
it's the info.
I don't know.
Fought info front header man.
It's difficult to really say.
Like the chain, for example, the chain value.
Do we want to do is hear you now I'm torn.
I'm really torn, right?
I'm going to all right.
Fine.
I'll stick with convention so far.
We haven't been doing that.
We could just put the fire in there.
We won't do that.
We're going to leave it this way so that's fine.
What that means though, to is the loaded font to keeping with
convention would only have these two
Senate because you would call get font info to get the h a font back
and that's already got your stuff in it so we'll change that up to
work a little bit slightly differently, right?
But anyway so inside the font itself, we would have the HHH h.h.
a font here like so so we'd have the font info and then what we would
do is we're going to set up the loaded font code points.
And the horizontal Advanced right?
And these are going to be really, really simple, right?
All that's going to happen.
Here is the data immediately after the header, right?
Like, like is going to be where the first table is, right?
You can kind of see the way we were doing it here, right?
The memory for the bitmap is just, whatever is immediately after the
header.
So that's the same thing going to do here, when this stuff gets loaded
in
It's going to get loaded into that memory slot.
So we're just going to go ahead and say all right the code points are
the first thing after the header and then the horizontal advances the
first thing after the code points, right?
And the code points size, really in order to do that is it's again
really, really basic.
We know that the code points are going to be the size of a bitmap ID.
So we know that there that that big and we know how many code points
there are because we
That in the info which we always have.
That's why I saying that's the only thing that we need is because we
need to know how many, right.
How many we have so we know how to unpack those arrays.
That's it, right?
That's all there is so yeah there's really nothing else to it.
Really, really straightforward, really really straightforward.
And you can see how common all this code is.
So I really feel like we need to merge, this merge, all this
boilerplate, same between lewd, that map, loads sound and load font
because now it's just that internal ifs that that little core that
changes.
And so we can do it, we can do a better job for sure.
Okay, continuing on, we need to do our science computation here.
And I don't actually know, looks like it looks like really all we need
to do is remember what that size the size of the data actually is.
So we really just need to compute this stuff out.
Pretty straightforward sighs section is relevant.
So I'm going to get rid of this notion altogether.
I'm just going to say here that we've got size data and size total and
then we'll just use those because that's kind of antiquated thing that
struct we kind of got rid of it, right?
And so the size data we know how big that's going to be right I guess
and this is the place where I should have just done code.
Points sighs because I can now just go.
Okay, code Point size.
Was that?
So then I know the size of the data is going to be the code Point
size, plus the size of the horizontal advance,
And that's going to be the total size of my font, right?
So we've got horizontal Advanced sighs.
That's just going to be the size of an R32 times.
The code Point count squared, right?
Because it's a 2d look up.
So that's it.
That's all there is and then the rest of this routine will just load
the font and everybody wins everyone wins as it turns out.
But we've got a lot more work to do and we're running out of time.
We only have about six minutes left, so I'm going to go ahead and make
sure things are compiling here, at least.
And then we will have to sort of, maybe quickly fix a few things to
leave ourselves in a semi running State.
We won't be able to leave ourselves completely running state today
because we've made too many changes but
Okay, rarely, can you get all your changes in an hour?
It's surprising.
How many times we are actually able to do that on handmade hero but
you know that's not the norm.
Normally big changes it take a while.
All right, so yeah, looking good so far.
I don't see any problems.
And so now we have to do again, these are going to be when we do get
clamped code point and stuff like that, when we're passing the loaded
font, we actually need the the font info here for those which is a
slightly different thing.
Again, what that means is that these guys kind of all need in
addition.
The ahha font, right?
They need, they need that.
It may not be Savory.
You know it's a little ugly but that's just how it goes sometimes,
right?
You got to pass both things.
That's okay.
Not really a problem and we could always copy and if you want to but
I'm going to leave it this way for now, because why not?
That's the way other things were working in.
I'm fine with that for now.
So let's see get bitmap for Cliff.
That's going to need both as well.
H a font info like so and yeah.
This one doesn't actually need the loaded font at all the moment it
just needs the info so that means we got to push those changes.
Back up one level and the compiler will do that for us automatically
right?
Will be here and what that means is we're going to want that font
info.
So we're going to want to h a font info, get font info.
And again, that's just going to be a really straightforward call to
get that van info.
And now when we
Come through here.
We're actually passing both of these right?
Same thing here.
And this guy only needs one.
Right?
And I guess for good measure, I'll have that guy take both just to
give us the option a little bit later on of not, you know, so we
don't, you know, everyone not have that.
And think they can get a line of ants will make that happen anyway.
So then we need to get font info.
That's again pretty straightforward.
We already have the get good mapinfo stuff, right?
Okay, map info and so we just
Either get font info, that's going to sort of mirror those guys so
that produces that ha font that we wanted.
There's get font info and there we go.
All done.
Oh good.
So now if we actually try to run, we're just going to explode because
we totally change the asset file layout like stuff's going to go nuts,
right?
Or not.
How does?
Every time, every time I say stuff's going to break, it doesn't break
every time suppose I should be happy.
What can you do?
It didn't break.
All right.
Well, I don't know to say about that.
We've got about two minutes left.
I'm going to go ahead and switch over to the test asset processor.
So if we're in the test as a processor here, you can imagine sort of
what we're going to have to do differently when we come through and do
our fonts, right?
We're going to kind of have to restructure this a little bit and I
guess I won't start that, that'll be.
What will start on tomorrow is will do that.
So you know what?
I'm not going to talk about.
We'll talk about all the stuff that we have to do to fix that.
Tomorrow.
So, all right.
We're going to leave things.
Leave things, broken.
And we'll fix them starting tomorrow.
We'll go to the Q&A and yeah.
So if you have questions about what we coded, please go ahead and send
them to me with q: in front of them, and we should be good to go.
Did you run the asset Builder?
No, we don't really want to run the acid Builder.
That's only going to make things worse because we haven't updated it
yet.
Right.
So that would probably put us in a bad situation, right?
I'm guessing now.
It's okay.
I was a little surprised at that but yeah.
We we don't store those font tables yet so we have to go, right?
The font tables and then we'll be done.
So tomorrow we'll write the van tables out and then we're
we might we might be done with well.
You know what, we probably want to spend a day or two on supporting
more languages on
For even if it's just rudimentary.
Just so we know that we've got a story about how we could translate
the game into Chinese or something, right?
I mean the artist on the game is Chinese we should at the very least
support Chinese, right?
Kubrick Caleb missed part of the stream.
Can you give context on?
Why you want the metaprogramming thing?
Sure.
It's just that, you know, if you think about the asset processor, it's
very there's a bunch of sort of finicky stuff that it's doing and we
have to do it on low on save and download, right?
So if you come down here and you look at, like, all of this stuff
where it's like, doing sort of these different right outs of where
things are right, then, what happens is in handmade?
Lassiter CPP.
You've got to do all these sort of fancy reads to pull them out in the
right order.
That's all it's all wrote, like there's nothing it the computer
doesn't need help for me to do these things.
It could just solve that automatically right in the same way.
It's just think of it.
Think of it the same way.
You think of what this is doing?
When I say struck HHH, HHH a sound I don't ever have to actually do
that, right?
I could just manually myself have a giant array of you 32s and know
that, like they go Sam.
Check out channel count, chain sample, count Channel, count chains,
and manually, address into the right one to get the sample count,
right?
I could have done that, but that's just a lot more work.
It's a lot more error-prone.
So having the C compiler, know that, I dip declaring a layout of
things that I can then.
Use my name is very handy.
What you wanted to do is also let you do that for variable sized data,
but it doesn't right, and they started to make a little bit of forward
progress into that in recent versions of the spec, but it's still
garbage.
um,
And so it's just like, whatever.
So that's typically where you go matter program.
You're just like, okay, fine.
You don't want to give me a language that works.
I'll make my own right.
And you can get really far, you can do a lot in terms of augmenting,
see to help you make these things trivial without having to take on
all the baggage of a higher level language.
That does a lot of things wrong, you know, like, you know, like a
python or something, where it's like, forget it, right?
But where you could potentially get this thing very easily.
How would you make the font tables more sparse?
So you don't need to stork earnings repairs.
That probably won't get drawn like ww-well if you want to store a
sparse table, you have a lot of ways of doing it, but probably what I
do is I would just store it as you know, tube to Binary trees,
effectively, you know.
Maybe I'm well.
It'd be kind of slow to look up into.
I don't know I mean I wouldn't is the answer which is why I didn't
because if you think about it most you know the hardest language we're
going to do is maybe it's something like Chinese which doesn't really
do kerning
and we can probably short-circuit.
So most things that have kerning pretty much all things that have
kerning have really low.
Letter counts, you know, you're talking about something like 80 glyphs
or something.
And so a 6400 entry kerning table at four bytes of peace is 25k
So like anything you introduced in there is going to be a pretty bad
idea, I think, right?
That's like L1 cache size, let alone, L2 cache size is how tiny that
is.
And you can compress it.
If you wanted to, you could make it.
So, instead of starting a float, you stored, 16 bits would be plenty,
right?
Can you close people that follow development of handmade here on the
stream?
How will you protect us from spoilers?
Unfortunately, I won't.
You're going to get spoilered.
I think where we landed on that.
Is I'm going to stream the whole development, right up to the point
where we ship it.
Like the day it goes like out of Early Access or whatever.
The thing is on Steam when we hit the like, this is now officially
version one I will stream and then I think where we landed was Alvin
probably do a DLC.
Or something like that, that you can add to handmade hero that will
not be streamed live.
So no one will know what's in that.
We may do something like that but in terms of the main game I want it
the whole thing stream live.
That's the point of the project so you're going to get spoilered.
OMG a giant rock says you use code Point count less than code point,
but will this not fail?
If the first code point is,
Not 0 or will, we need to include the ASCII control Carriage to make
control Point, can't work.
So
Just to be clear.
What we will be doing eventually is I think I mentioned this, when I
almost typed in the Min code Point thing, but I don't want to do that
yet.
What will eventually do is store different?
A few ranges of code points.
So
A will be addressing a bit of a sliding window thing, but the more
important thing to realize is that when we deal with this stuff in
here, we're eventually going to translate this into a compact code
point.
Case if that makes sense.
So we don't want our lookups to be based on Unicode which has tens of
thousands of characters in it.
Right what we want to do is base it on the number of glyphs actually
in the font.
So we're going to do when we do the language stuff.
We're going to do an additional layer that compacts things down asking
is already totally compact for the most part.
You know, we could store just a couple extra clips of the beginning
and be fine, but so I wouldn't think too hard about that part yet
because we're just not at the point when that stuff is going to take
place.
A pet dragon or a pet rad Dragon?
A Petra Dragon, I don't know.
Will you have stream later on various meta programming?
Tricks, some useful.
And if you tips and tricks for developers, I don't know.
Like I said, I'm committed to doing handmade hero but it's a huge
commitment, right?
I'll be streaming this thing for, like, 2 years, or more.
Actually, probably more because I think I said, 600 days of coding and
we code only five days a week on here.
Or is it 6:00 of coding?
And we code one hour a day, five days a week, which means it'll
actually be more than two years.
It'll be like two and a half years or something because we don't
stream on Sundays.
Saturdays and Sundays.
Which Chinese dialect are you thinking of supporting well to be clear?
I was thinking of just supporting all languages but we just ship with
whatever dialect yangshin speaks or something as an example.
Just so we know we were actually supporting another language properly
but then we just make it so that you know, I mean, since handmade here
is going to be open source, right?
Like I said, within two years of its shipping everything will be open
sourced, right?
That means other people can ship language packs.
And furthermore actually people could ship language packs right away
because your allow you you know we parse process although the asset
files in the directory at startup.
So people could just make their own translations and put them in
there, probably right.
And so so people can Port it to languages.
It doesn't matter what I ship will be trying to make it so that people
who want to translate the game to some other language, that's not
supported in the official build can just do it without having to,
like, talk to us about it.
That would be mine.
I hope.
Each junkie 64.
How big do you think the game will be in the end?
It will be so huge.
That no computer can possibly hold it.
What if a computer tries to run the game?
It will complete collapse into a black hole.
Ostrava scav lad.
How about right-to-left languages?
I'm not averse to it, I mean supporting right-to-left languages as
For trivial, it's so trivial that I don't even know if the routine
changes, the only thing that we have to change is the starting
alignment, right?
The only thing that changes in the entire code that you've seen so far
Is.
This right here instead of left edges right Edge, that's it.
That's the only thing all the rest of our code does not assume a
direction, right?
Because keep in mind, all of the glyphs have an anchor point.
So that Anchor Point could simply be in the bottom right corner,
instead of the bottom left corner and then the kerning table, says,
how far to advance it would just have negative numbers in it.
Done.
Right?
So the only thing that would have to change is our centering code.
That's about it and that wouldn't be very hard for us to do.
So we could we could do that if people really wanted to
Hey, look at that.
We are done with questions, right?
As the stream is over.
How is it possible?
How are we that perfect.
And that's you guys.
That's not me.
That's all you.
You ended the questions, right?
As the stream ended.
That is some data, some next-level stuff you guys just did, right?
That's insane.
How do you even do it?
In case anyone is wondering who has the best audience on Twitch, I
obviously do because they nailed that ending and that's not easy
considering the lag, right?
It's crazy.
That's crazy.
All right.
Let's wind it down.
Let's wind it down, folks.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, we got about halfway through the stuff we want to do with,
with updating our fonts to use creating tables and also have other
good stuff.
And I think we'll be able to pretty much get that working tomorrow,
because we did all the specking of it.
We just have to write the asset like flow through, which can be a
little finicky at times, but I don't think it should be too hard.
So I think by the end of tomorrow, we should be in pretty good shape,
on our fonts, pretty good shape.
And like I said, from there, I think we might
Not want to move on immediately.
I think we might do a little more work just to make sure that we have
a plausible story and a plausible story in place for how we support
multiple languages.
So that were not kind of caught totally by surprise later when we
decide we want to point it to another language and go, oh my God,
we've like baked in all these assumptions that don't work.
When you change to tie or would you change to Hebrew or something?
Who knows, right?
All right.
So that's about it.
I hope you'll join me tomorrow, for the conclusion of this coding.
It'll be same place.
Same time, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time, right?
On Twitch until then if you want to play around the source code you
can always get it by pre-ordering the game on handmade hero dot org
and you can go ahead and download the source code every night after I
finish working on it and play around with it yourself.
Similarly, if you would like to support the video series, you can
always support us on patreon, it's always very much appreciated.
We also have a forum site, you can go to where you can ask questions
and get community contributions like anti.
Oh so guide and forced to Mac and Linux good stuff like that and we
have a tweet bot that tweets the schedule at you.
You, I also got most of the GitHub stuff working, I believe, crossing
my fingers, I need to do some testing here and I got to figure out a
little bit in terms of their API.
Like making sure I'm actually handling errors like rate limiting and
stuff correctly because their API is really janky.
So I'm working on that and so I hope to have an announcement sometime
soon that we are in some kind of official beta testing where people
besides me are actually playing with it and seeing if it's working.
In terms of getting authorization, but so stay tuned for that.
Maybe later this week, maybe next week, but I'm pretty hopeful that
we're getting there.
It's been a bit of a grind, but it, but it's getting there.
So stay tuned for that until then.
I will see you guys on the internet, have fun coating.
Take it easy, everyone.