Alright.
Hello everyone, and welcome to another special handmade hero
presentation much like yesterday.
No program.
Today, it's actually interview and one of the things that I wanted to
do it, handmade conned was get all the people at rad, who work on
compression to give us kind of an explanation of how they think about
it.
And sort of like for people such as myself, who don't know, a whole
lot about the field to try to get like an expert's point of view on it
and sort of
Set your mind straight if you want to sort of understand compression
things or start getting more into compression and Charles was the only
person at rad who we didn't get to talk to him a con and he graciously
agreed to come on the show for an interview.
Hopefully, we'll be able to record this.
Okay, with, with the webcam setup, we're kind of amateur at recording
a live interview here.
So we do the best.
We can.
Charles thanks so much for joining me, my pleasure.
I want to start out by just kind of asking you sir.
Of the same questions that I asked Fabien and Jeff a handmade con
because I kind of wanted to know your take on it.
But before we do you want to maybe get people who don't know a little
bit of background because you know, I think a lot of folks probably
don't don't know where the people at Brad came from or how they got
there.
So great.
So I started in software on data compression long, long ago, probably
20 years ago and I worked in data compression for
Years before I transitioned into the games industry, how did you get
started on compression?
Why did you end up doing that as like the first thing just as a hobby?
Kind of, oh no, I started even in like high school.
When I had started coding, I started playing around with the data
compression really.
Is the way most people get into data conversion, I'd say, okay is just
kind of out of curiosity and playing in their free time.
All right.
And I found it fascinating so I started playing with it more and more
until it turned into.
Two jobs that I started taking gun.
And I wound up working at eclipse for Dave, Stafford were removed the
Genesis 3D engine.
He actually hired me to do data compression there.
Really?
Yeah.
Okay.
Because the idea at Eclipse was to do 3D on the web.
Oh right okay so I was doing the like transmission side of that
compressing the content you know because at the time we were a lot of
people were still on modems, right?
Right and bandwidth was important.
So
So how long I mean I guess I didn't think about that but we still
don't really have 3D on the web today even as a practical reality of
it sort of exist how so it's been it's been like 15 years or something
of what a 20 years of people like maybe sort of going to be doing 3D
on the web is a major thing.
It's like not quite right, you know, right at the time it was kind of
too soon in the sense that yeah, lots of computers could barely.
Run 3D and like the web barely worked.
Yeah.
People were more concerned about like, hey, can we just have a web
that works?
Yes, opposed to.
Let's have 3D on it.
Okay.
So you worked at eclipse and then somehow you end up it rad, like what
happened in between, right?
So from Eclipse, I kind of got interested in the 3D engine aspect of
it, okay?
Started working more and more and the like the 3D rendering pipeline.
And transition into doing that as my job got it.
So I moved over to games and worked in games for 10-15 years or
something like that.
Okay, eventually sort of quit games and move to rad as you know, a way
of working near the game industry but not in evidence the periphery
just like just on that that crust.
Yes.
Not having to get too deep into the actual reality of it, right?
Okay.
So I guess let me ask
The couple compression questions here that we're sort of like the ones
that I asked to hand make on so I'm curious like since you've worked
on compression for extremely long time and just have a lot of
experience with it.
I'm curious.
How do you tend to think about compression like the just as a whole,
if that makes sense?
Like what do you think about it in terms of is like, how do you
visualize compressors?
Or like just in terms of your mental space?
Sorry that's a broad question, we'll start there.
And then if you're like I
I don't understand what you mean.
I'll be more certain.
I don't want to pre pre bias the answer, at all, if I can avoid it,
it's great.
It's a very broad question.
And I mean, the answer is kind of tricky, because compressors,
Our can all be very different or they can they can look very different
in the way that they work.
They're always trying to achieve the same goal but the end result can.
The way the algorithm Works might not look at all like what they're
actually doing.
So kind of generally the way I think about compressors is
I am always trying to think about the very theoretical aspect of how
they're working, okay, in terms of like what are they actually
expressing about the data?
Okay?
Like what are they trying to model?
Okay.
And then there's there's kind of the algorithm or how you express that
in the machine code and that can not necessarily look very much like
Theoretical side.
But I'm always trying to keep those in mind as I'm working through
things.
What do you mean by the theoretical mod are like?
Can you give an example of what you mean by that?
Well, so all let's talk about compression in general.
Yes, yes.
So the cooler
Best way to think about compression is always in terms of the model
coder Paradigm, okay.
Which is you, you have an entropy decoder on the back end, okay?
And you have a model of the data, okay?
So the model is trying to predict the data, okay, normally we work, in
terms of streaming models, which I predict, either a bite at a time or
a bit at a time or something like that, okay, though, there are more
General models.
Okay, so the model is trying to assign
Probabilities to your data.
Okay, basically watch, which data thinks is extremely likely to
happen, broken, which data is rare?
Okay.
And then you entropy decoder, assigns bit lengths based on those
probabilities.
Okay, which is just minus log.
2 p is the correct bit length.
Okay.
For a given probability.
Can you expand on that?
A little since you, since you brought it up, already, do you want to?
And you can draw if you want to?
I don't know if you want to, but can you expand on that for people who
don't will immediately know what that means?
When you say,
Are you want to pause and go back to later?
What?
I don't like.
I don't want to teach old glass of data compression as it's too
complicated.
Yeah.
But if you have certain probabilities, yes, you can assign certain
code lengths, okay?
The code lengths are constrained by decodability.
There's something called the Kraft inequality, okay?
Which is a constraint on the code lengths.
Okay.
You can't just say every word gets a code length of 0, okay?
Hey, you have in
Compression, but it's not decodable.
Okay, great.
I see.
So if you have, if your input is a bit, it can either be 0 or 1.
You could have a code length of one for each of them.
Yes, that's decodable.
And that's no compression essentially that's a copy, right?
Okay.
That's both B.
Both values of the bitter equally likely.
Yes.
Or you can have code lengths that are logged to pee and log2 1 - p
okay for any PE.
Okay, that's also decodable.
Okay.
Code lengths below that are going to be non decodable below.
What?
Log to peed log2 1, minus P for any P.
That makes a curve of the to code lengths.
Okay.
And anything.
That's anything that's in that space shorter.
Okay, is non decodable.
Anything longer is wasting B?
Some inefficient entropy encoder.
I'm not sure.
I mean I vaguely understand that but I'm not sure.
I totally understand that.
So just to be clear when you're talking about code lengths, right?
And in this case, I guess we're talking about potentially fractional,
bit lengths, in the sense.
Yeah.
So so the, I mean, the optimal entropy coder would be fractional and
infinite Precision Fit, perfect Precision, right?
So one of the things you have to deal with is when you go to a
practical,
Her.
Yeah, which is obviously not infinite Precision, right?
It has to buy us into this slightly wasteful space, right?
And so you want to minimize that bias, okay?
How far you go into the wasting code space?
And so, I think, if I can restate what you're saying about the log P?
Part of things.
So what you were saying there was that, like, okay, so if I have
fractional B, I could say that I'm going to assign you know, point to
bits.
20 and point two bits to 1 which would give me this nice compression
because now it only takes .4 B / B.
But what you're saying is that can't actually exist because of that
theorem, right?
We have proven that, that's not possible.
It still has to sum up to the one bit value at the end, right?
Is that a fair statement restatement of what you're saying?
Correct, it doesn't sum up to one bit.
Exactly.
Okay, they don't add up.
They don't add up to two bits.
okay, in order to be the what happens is when you when you save on
one, you actually gain more on the other
If you look at what log p and log 1 minus P do, okay?
So like if you want to save, if you go to half a bit on one.
Yeah, other one goes to two beds.
Okay, right, sorry.
So yeah, I shouldn't say sum up to 1 that it because it's in the log
space.
It's going to be not bad but right out of the log space.
If it's enough to one might be a way to say it.
I don't know how.
Yeah.
I know what the right way to say that is to each code length.
Yes.
That sums to to okay.
Okay.
Alright, that'll okay that all makes sense.
Now I'm on board, okay, so back to the original statement of how you
think about it, you were saying that you think of it as model and
coders.
So you basically, which I think does kind of echo.
Although, I don't know that anyone broke it down exactly that way but
it did sound of sound.
Like what people had said in terms of when fobbing Jeff were talking
about it.
Yeah so basically the model part of things is basically saying I'm
trying to figure out what I expect to happen in this.
This stream as I'm seeing it.
And the encoder part is saying, well, based on what that, you know,
front end, sort of gas about.
What I expect to see is I'm going to assign B to what it sort of told
me.
I needed to assign, I guess that makes or if you want to say that.
I mean so the model is you have some assumptions or some knowledge
about the data and you're trying to reduce the amount of bits that you
have to actually send based on.
That knowledge like if I know that you're going to be speaking English
to me.
Yeah.
Then I know a huge amount about what letters you're going to be using,
right?
Even before you say anything, right?
And the way that you express that knowledge precisely in a way that
saves B is through this model coder mechanism, got
If so, so what I'm thinking about theoretically is, what is, what is
the model of the data that I want to create like, what do I expect
this data to be like, and how do I express that?
Or if I have a compressor that is not obviously, like a model, like an
lz77 type compressor, or okay, there's a whole lot of other kind of
heuristic compressors.
They don't obviously appear to be
pressed as a model, okay?
Some you know, some compressors are more obviously expressed this way,
okay?
Whereas, others don't appear to be this way, and when you say lz77, as
an example of one, that isn't expressed this way, you mean because,
hey, it's just sort of saying I refer into the stuff in the Stream but
I don't really beyond that.
Have a lot of opinion about what I expect to be seeing.
I just expect me seeing things I have seen before, that's about it.
Great.
So for some compressors like PPM or
The Pact context mixing compressors.
These compressors are very obviously making probabilities for what
they expect the next thing to be.
Okay and then coding based on that.
Okay, so you very clearly see here's a model and here's a coder got it
and the way you get more compression is to make the model, fit the
data better, got it.
So that is like one kind of whole realm of data compression where
people are just working on.
Working on making better models and I say you make better models, you
get more compression and those models are entirely based on the data.
So it's like hey for every type of data.
We might be looking at any given time.
We have to create model specific to that because the more specific it
is to the data, the better compression were going to get out of here.
Is the more you know about the data the more you can specialize your
model to it and the more compression you'll get.
All right.
So I guess like one thing I might ask which
The question that I had maybe it's a little too early in the Stream
for it but since it's already seems to come up, one question that I
had as someone who's not a compression expert, was the split between
prediction and entropy encoding is somewhat.
It's not obvious at least to me based on not knowing very much.
Why?
That is, how things split out because even with from just a cursory
understanding of
Ian.
I totally see where you're coming from with that, that model entropy
split because most things I've ever seen also discuss it that way,
right?
It's like, oh, here's jpeg or here's pkzip or hears any of these
things.
It's like that is what they look like.
They've got this one part that's designed to sort of like pre-process
the stream into these pieces that then gets fed into the entropy
encoder.
And that's what you write out as a stream, but it's not obvious to me
why that is, if that makes sense.
Like, are there deeper reasons at this point as to?
Why it's
Natural for that to be the way that things have stood out.
Is it a
Our goal thing that's the reason that they stood out that way and
maybe in the future they won't is it just because we're not good
enough compression yet and later will realize that was dumb.
Like can you give some perspective on that as in terms of what the Y
as opposed to just the fact that it is because it definitely does seem
to be.
Well it's just a powerful and useful way to look at the problem.
Okay.
I mean it for one thing, you could consider the alternative right?
Which is
You there's they're sort of the theoretical best possible.
Compressor is to enumerate all possible data streams of all possible
lengths, okay?
And either assign a probability to each one, okay?
Or assigned an output code stream okay to each one.
Okay.
So you're you know, you're making this huge enumeration of all
possible data, okay?
Where there's like every picture we ever want to send
Exactly.
Is going to be in this summer, right?
Okay.
So if you think about this, what this data looks like, there's a
massive amount of it.
99% of it.
Okay, is garbage like random bits, okay, which you would never expect
to occur, okay?
As like an image or text file or something like that, okay?
Like there's you know, right?
And then this small part of it is organized data, okay?
so, it turns out that organized data is,
You know, a very small amount of all possible data.
Okay, should I?
This sun is getting oppressive so this it's going to did I close it
up?
Shorter lengths, to the organize data that you expect to be seeing on
a regular basis, okay?
And longer code lengths, to the random data.
Yes.
Anytime you're doing a data compression, you're always, if you're
compressing some data, you're expanding other data.
Yeah.
So your it's not like you or just getting stuff for free, you're
choosing this data.
I want to expand this data.
I want to shrink got it.
So if you could do this that then theoretically you are working with
out.
The specific entropy code, or you can do, you know, you can do very
fine since you're on our file system, we're only have B accuracy.
You can have B accuracy lengths of your output, and you can do as good
as possible compression without ever getting into anything like
arithmetic coding or funny stuff with fractional bits.
And this would basically just be a case.
Of well, would you?
I mean, so if you actually have this case.
So I have, you know, the, you know, 17 trillion images that were ever
going to send or whatever and I go through and I enumerate them all
and I say we want to be able to send all of these.
I guess what you're saying is you now just have one number that can
represent between 0 and 17 trillion and you just have that number that
tells you which image you had and that's the entirety of the
compressor.
Her go.
I don't have to actually have well, and the number would be different
lengths for each of the images based on the probably the image think
is more likely.
So I would still have to get into arithmetic.
Encoding, in some sense, wouldn't I or this point?
They're just different bike lengths of okay.
Okay.
The first couple of bets are the length of the thing.
All right so you can do that without any incremental coating or
whatever.
So part of the reason why we don't
That is because we want to be able to process little by little.
I don't want to have to have a giant table of everything, right.
We don't have to wait until we see all the data to be able to Output
anything got it so a lot of the work has been about how to do things
incrementally which is where things like arithmetic coding.
Come from.
Okay.
It's just the ability to what you're trying to do is create a kind of
an expression of a multi symbol.
All probability estimation but to do it one at a time.
Okay.
You mean one at a time being, as the symbols come in, you're changing
your estimates of their probability.
Or what do you mean by one at a time?
Maybe I can draw sure.
Go nuts.
Just should be live.
So what you're trying to do is
You have some multi symbol sequence and you want to give a code length
to it?
Based on the various codes in it.
But you don't want to have to deal with lots of things at a time like
that.
You want to be able to do it incrementally.
So you express the probability of the whole sequence.
As you know, the probability of four characters is the probability of
one, given the previous three times, the probability of the previous
3,
And then, you can go ahead and place this in the same way.
Are those in reverse order?
Yeah, okay, I'm doing confusingly reverse order, okay?
Because that's going to say like, I'm cutting my stream.
Backward, you cutting your name backwards?
Yeah, all right.
Wait, is that because you guys do do streams backwards now with Rands
is here right at all?
This like if you hold down the spacebar, you can scroll around to if
you want to try to put a probability of D down here and right, and
fair enough.
So, you know, this is just a way of expressing instead of
Is make sure that yeah, it did work, you know?
I mean like so like you may think of word estimation like the if
you're doing text, the important thing is the probability of the word
occurring, right?
But you don't want to have to wait.
You want to have to buffer up, lots of things before you run through
your model and kind of you want to go one at a time.
So we have a probability of T first and then probability of H with t
following and then probably go.
E, th proceeding got it, I kind of thing.
So the arithmetic coder then allows you to Output from each step of
the coating and accumulate into a streaming output, instead of having
to wait until you see the full probability to create the correct code
length.
And even if you, but even if you didn't, you'd still need some like,
arithmetic encoding, assuming that you wanted, those code likes to be
fractional, right?
I mean, because, you know, we need some strategy to what I'm trying to
get at is that
If you buffered up until you got to the end of your file, you don't
need fractional code, lengths, really?
Because you're outputting B in the end.
You only need fractional, code lengths, because you're doing a
character at a time.
And you want, you don't want to be flushing to B after each character
because that would be an enormous weight waist.
But when you get to the end of your file, you are flushing to B.
So if you're if you were just creating code lengths, at the end of
your file, you don't need fractional wings.
Okay.
So I don't think I understand that then because I mean let me just
sort of say how I was thinking about it and you can tell me why this
is wrong.
So my understanding was that.
Okay, so if I'm going to Output a bunch of stuff I've got, you know,
all these symbols that I want to stuff, you know, and I want I'm
trying to tell you the order these symbols came in.
So even if I assume that I already know, like, let's assume that I
looked at the entire piece of data, I don't know, maybe it's small,
its 32k or something.
So I look at the entire thing I count up.
However, I choose to partition this into symbols, I partitioned it.
I count up the occurrence of all of those symbols and now I know a
specific frequency for each symbol but
Frequency is fractional, right?
So it's like if there were 2,000 symbols and this one appeared like
three times it's three over.
Two thousand is the, you know, the frequency, right?
So at that point, when I want to go to Output these things out, I
thought that the idea behind the arithmetic compressor was simply that
well I probably don't want to use say, 3 bits to represent this
symbol.
I want to use three point two bits to represent this symbol because
that's the closest to the frequency that I could get.
Ergo.
It doesn't matter if I'm flushing to b or not.
I still want to pack these things as tightly as possible to make the
smallest Stream.
So I still want something like an arithmetic encoders so that I can
always have fractional B in terms of the length of encoding.
A
Simple.
Is that an incorrect way of thinking about the problem?
It's true.
If you're encoding one symbol, okay.
But that's what I'm talking about is the difference between
incremental, coding versus but even if I'm encoding a whole thing,
don't I still have to encode the symbols one, by one in terms of
telling the other side, what to produce?
No, you don't have, you never have to code things, one by one.
You have lots of choices.
Okay.
So tell me more about that then just, you know, again to solve it for
people who are not familiar with this sort of stuff or not.
For example, consider that you have data that only has orders you
Correlation of order 0 statistics.
Okay, by that.
What I mean is that you have two symbols 0 and 1, okay?
And they have some different probabilities not based on the where they
are in the Stream it's just always the same probability everywhere
right?
So order 0 means there's no it doesn't correspond to whether the
previous symbol is actually a 0 or 1 or not.
It's just each time you see a new symbol it has no relation to what
you've seen.
In the past, got it.
But there's a different probability of a big zero or one God can so
anytime you have data.
So first, I'll say that.
One of the goals of data compression sometimes is to transform your
data into order zero data Isis.
If you have order zero data, then we know how to compress it
perfectly, right?
Because now, you don't need Markov chains and all these other sorts of
things that are trying to look at.
Where we are in the Stream and stuff.
You're basically saying, hey, if you can transform it into this, it
gets much simpler way.
So one of the ways of approaching data compression is to try to find a
d correlating transform so that you get into order zero data, then we
have solutions for it, okay?
So if you're trying to compress order zero data, got it.
If you want to go bit by bit,
Then you almost certainly want an arithmetic code or an A and S coder
or something like that.
Got it has to be able to do fractional B because right, doing, you
know, integer numbers of bits when you only have 0 and 1 as input.
Right?
Not very useful right?
Yes.
But if you don't want to do one at a time, okay, there are lots of
solutions.
Okay, so yeah, tell me, give me a little.
I mean, I was just at it's a brief things like kind of have it in my
head space of, like, wait, what's there?
So one of the possibilities is
Of coating.
Okay, what you do is you send first either the you take some block,
okay?
You send the number of zeros or the number of 1s, okay?
And then you know that you're just trying to send an arrangement of
where those ones are zeros far.
Okay?
Since it's order, zero, there's no bias for them to be rights
particular place, right?
So now this is just a common, a Torx problem,
you you you know it's a choose
There are three ones and I have to put them in eight buckets, right?
There's you know,
However, many I see is you can put them and now you just you just have
to send which one is of that, okay?
So you count, how many ways there are, and you send it a number that
is which one of them is it from one of those icy?
And so you you initially chose, oh, a block length to do this in, I
see as that block, length, gets larger, you get closer and closer to
the entropy becomes a perfect coder.
Interesting.
So that is a way.
So in theory, if you wanted to, you could have just done the entire
block this way.
And then you wouldn't have need arithmetic and you have compressed it
down to roughly the fractional bit way that the arithmetic would have
done it.
Wait, I see.
Okay, similarly you can do Huffman coding on, you know you take eight
or 16 of your bits at a time.
I say you do Huffman coding on it and you're getting again closer,
depending how big that block is you get closer and closer, you're
wasting at most a bit on average.
It's less than half a bit icy.
And then, as that block, gets bigger, you're wasting loss.
I see.
Okay, thank you.
That was actually very.
There's also.
Okay, optimal ways to do run length coding.
If really, if one of the probabilities is biased, okay?
You know if one of them is
Zero tax, you typically have, you know, lots of 0 B than a one bit.
Okay?
So one bits are sparse bring this file.
So in in the case that one bits are sparse.
Yeah, you can code run lengths with
I believe column coding is the best way to do it.
Okay, this is what Golem coding like the little girl with the ring in
the ring is that we're talking about here.
I could be wrong about that but okay one of the like classic a
precious coder classic variable-length integer codes is optimal for
run length coding okay for for bias cases.
Okay.
And again that's an entropy decoder.
Okay though it doesn't, it doesn't necessarily look like an entropy
encoder.
Okay.
Well, so popping back out of that then.
So back to the question of model versus entropy encoding.
So I was kind of saying, is there anything else you want to say about,
why it tends to break down that way?
Like I guess I'd also be interested in since you're pretty theoretical
compression kind of person to.
I would guess I'd be interested to know, like,
Is that you support that break down?
Or is that break down fairly practical?
Dude?
You know what?
I'm sort of getting out there.
Like, it's like, does the theory suggests that in general coder should
be split this way?
Or is it more just like in practice?
It turns out to be better to slip this way for a number of reasons.
Sort of thing.
It's
so I'd say that it's a way of understanding the problem in.
It clear way where you don't get yourself in trouble because you okay,
if you're using a valid entropy coder.
Yeah, you know you're always making decodable bit streams, right?
So you aren't you know you're trying to make a perpetual motion
machine, right?
Right ways a hazard.
Yes.
And it gives you something clear to work on which is the model.
So it's just like
We have an entropy encoder which is well understood.
And all we have to do is make the model fit the data better, okay?
And it's something that you can go and iterate on and, you know, it's
just a way of expressing the problem in a way that's easy to
understand and analyze.
Is opposed to, you know, the more heuristic data compressors.
It's hard to tell.
It's hard to analyze them.
Mathematically.
What are the more heuristic like what he is there?
An example, if people want to look up a compressor that would fall
into the category of harder to analyze, what kind of compressor might
that be
Well, a lot of the classic ones, so like that's a good question.
Okay.
Most of the ones that are obvious like lz77 have been analyzed in a
semester later, okay, that we understand them as models now, okay,
they don't, they didn't appear originally to be models.
Okay?
But now we know they are, okay.
Things like block sorting, there are still
Their difficulties in.
How we understand these as models.
I said in a practical sense and I guess, would I be correct in saying?
It sounds like, I mean, just from again, from hearing about it or for
the limited amount that I know about it.
It seems to be sort of that entropy encoding seems to be much better
solved.
In terms of like, hey, in term, we can give you a particular
definition of a problem.
And then we can give you an interview coder that like exactly solves
that problem.
Whereas data modeling feels a little bit less like that so far, like
it's more.
It feels like it's a little more wild Westy in the sense that, you
know, I get is part of the reason you break that up is because hey,
entropy coding is very well solved to, you know, for certain specified
problems.
So you can just take that part out of your equation and be focusing on
the part, that's maybe less solved.
Is that a reasonable way to phrase it?
Or is that not really true?
Yeah.
Okay.
That's a good way to phrase it.
I mean, it's so entropy coding, we thought that we knew all the
entropy coders and Elaine has appeared out of nowhere top.
Why is it since since you guys did some of the pioneering work on this
in terms of shipping, ANS encoders
Talk a little bit about that, because that was an interesting
inflection point.
I suppose, for people who don't know about ANS encoders, who aren't
familiar with that give can give a little back when I like, what
happened there, because this was an odd, an odd story and subset.
Yeah, very, very odd story.
Yeah.
So this guy jarek Duda become years ago, four or five years ago.
Okay,
Wrote a paper about asymmetric numeral systems and like, lattice and
coding.
Okay?
And it's so, a lot of people noticed it, okay?
Like, I noticed it and commented, hey, this looks interesting.
How did you find this paper?
You were like,
I mean cuz it's like not very many people, that's really knew about
it.
I'm listening, I don't recall but I'm guessing it on someone else's.
Blog or something was like, Hey I noticed there's nobody really
understood it.
I didn't understand it okay because it's the original paper was
written in a very abstract mathematical obtuse way.
Okay?
Nobody really saw how that the Practical implementation of that would
look, okay, so people kind of read the paper and we're like, all
right?
That looks kind of interesting.
Not sure.
I get why or how we would use it.
But hey, so
Let me back up a tiny bit.
Sure on entropy coding like with arithmetic coding.
It's very easy to understand how to write a bad Earth metal coder or
one.
That doesn't work very like, okay.
That the that, the implementation is terrible, okay, slow, or the most
obvious way to write it requires.
Buffering up the entire data with infinite Precision or their
arithmetic, right?
So there's the tricky bit about arithmetic.
Coders is
How do you translate it into an implementation?
How do you make it incremental?
You know, huh?
Like how does it work with with finite precision and that kind of step
is a little bit?
It's not, there's not a formula necessarily for how to make your
arithmetic odor.
Okay.
There have been many over the years, there are a lot of different ways
to do it.
Yes and there continue to be Innovations in that.
Okay, as we have found slightly different ways of expressing the
operation.
So ans originally looked like, a new way of expressing the algorithmic
operation of entropy coding.
Okay, which if that's all it was, it's not very
Staying and since the okay.
So basically like at first it was kind of like, oh, hey, someone did
some theoretical work here but it's not immediately clear that this
would change, how we would actually type code into a computer or it
you know, it was a different mathematical way of expressing entropy
entropy coding, but it wasn't obvious that if we type that into a
computer, it would be efficient at, all right, which is what we're
interested in, right?
Got it.
We already have entropy.
Ders, that get us as close to the entropy as we want, right?
That is not the issue, right?
It's a question of how efficient can it be a problem?
Being, that efficient arithmetic coders are difficult.
Yes, there's issues.
Right?
Huffman is much faster than arithmetic in those days, right?
Like meaning you, you typically had a significant speed difference.
I remember, especially at some point, there was sort of like, oh, it
was kind of a divided per symbol or
Then they were like, kind of table driven methods for arithmetic or
whatever but they were much more complicated than the Huffman kind,
which could just go direct and be very fast.
Apparently, this is going very cursory knowledge, my advice.
Remember the sat/rad at the time when I was there that was seem to be
kind of the case.
So yeah.
So like doing faster that coding is a whole huge field.
Yeah there's tons of approaches.
Got it table based approaches.
You can go binary and
Yeah.
So but they all have drawbacks, you know.
It's not like
So the interesting thing about ANS was, you know, some years later
young Colette started looking into implementing his own.
I believe that he kind of had the idea on his own, okay?
It turned out to be an ANS implementation, oh, really?
And the implementation was interesting.
He was not aware of an S at the time, we'd have that
Okay, so nobody knows.
All right.
But my understanding is that he was fooling around with ideas on his
own, he had some problems with his ideas and read the ANS paper and
realized that it was the same.
Basic idea isn't like this paper solves his problems that it's the
same idea and it actually has the answer, okay?
So, his implementation of ANS showed that it was quite interesting.
Okay?
And then, we started looking into it more like, yeah, that's actually
is very interesting.
Okay, because when you express ANS in terms of machine operations,
they turn out to be quite appealing.
I see.
Okay.
And this is just an artifact of how the ANS math works out.
Is that when it maps on to actual instructions, it maps on better.
Yeah, in arithmetic, right?
It's actually it's very similar to Earth Metal Coating.
Okay?
There's a something I touch on and my blog, a tiny bit.
I didn't really go into it in a great way, but ANS is, is very similar
to The Backwards arithmetic.
Coders are trashed the original way of doing arithmetic coding, okay?
That's why ANS streams are process backwards.
Got it and why you wrote on the Blackboard backwards, protect my
right?
Yeah.
So ans is a lifo, coder.
Got it and it the way it.
It's
loading up the probability in this way for a multi, simple sequence
and the way it flushes out
Incrementally in order to stay in finite Precision.
Yeah, it's kind of backwards from the way arithmetic.
Coders, do it.
Okay.
It flushes out the bottom bits instead of the top B.
Okay?
And that kind of winds up being the magic of what makes it so
interesting really okay.
So the fact that it flushes out bits from the other side of the value
turns out to be that important in authoring the compressor that you
can get.
Oh I guess I should say decompressor since that's usually what you
care about I suppose as decompression speed at least for rad style
stuff.
Yeah that one aspect of it turns out
About important.
Interesting.
Why is there a way you can explain why without too much detail?
Or is it really like no?
You gotta understand the whole thing or is there sort of like vague
why you can give?
Because at first blush, you wouldn't think right?
If you just ask someone like, oh hey, yeah.
You know, you had this thing and it was flushing out bottom B before,
and now it's pushing out top bits, I don't know that they would
immediately go like, Ah, that's that's clearly going to give me so
many more options than I had before, right?
And maybe that's
I mean the key thing is that it allows you to know your
renormalization interval.
Its I mean, so the way we talk about doing this is renormalization and
in arithmetic coding because that's fifo and you're you're sort of
zooming in as you go.
That Zoom factor is a variable, okay, which is what leads to you
having to do a divide, okay?
Whereas with ANS you're building up from the back, okay?
And you're dropping bits out of the bottom, okay?
Which allows you to get to a fixed
Kind of code word size and stay there.
Hmm, you so you don't have to do the Divide interesting.
Okay.
So in arithmetic, the window is narrowing over time and in rands it
isn't the the intervals.
Yeah.
one way to think about rants is that your
you're building up a large integer, okay?
And the entropy coding comes from the fact that if the integer is
shorter, you send fewer bits.
Okay?
So you're actually, you're building up this integer X, okay?
And you wind up sending log 2 of x b.
Okay, that's what grants does, okay?
So in reims the more probable symbols make X grow less.
I love this probable symbols make it grow more.
I see so you know as you're adding more probable symbols your integer
is growing small amounts actually whenever you add a less probable
symbol, it takes a bigger step, got it.
So if you didn't do any streaming out, you would just be building up
this large integer.
You get to the end.
You see.
It's log 2x B, and you send it, got it and that is in ANS coder with
got it.
No flushing.
Okay,
What the Practical streaming ones do is build X up to 32 bits or
something and then flush out bottom B at 8 or 16 or something.
Yeah like this and then start adding more bits in.
Yeah.
I see ends.
This is probably too detailed to ask, but I'm just going to ask it
anyway.
Then you can just say like ignore it for now, if you're building up an
integer, you're actually building it up in bit order though.
So, meaning, you're not adding to the, you're not incrementing the
integer, this giant inter, you're not really incrementing it, you're
actually concatenating B on to it.
Meaning, you know, the low order, bits of the integer right away.
Then how are you flushing?
Does that make sense?
Is that a dumb question?
Okay.
All right.
The I mean so that is the key to the ANS streaming.
Okay?
So when you do streaming ANS, you don't make the same final number
that you would if you didn't stream, okay?
And the only reason it works is because I mean, so you're right.
You are actually like multiplying this integer up and adding to it.
That's it.
So that's what it sounded like you were saying, but on a b, should
change all these things.
But the way the streaming scheme works and it is when you hit the
streaming threshold, you just output them anyway because you assume
look, the decompressor doesn't need the bits of the final integer.
It just needs the bits of where I was.
At this point in the final integer.
So as long as I give it that it knows where I it was and it's just
going to do the same thing to get to that final integer that I was
doing that kind of exactly.
So that is the key - streaming is
The encoder decoder have to be in lockstep in the sense that they have
to stream in in the exact same spot.
Okay.
And that's actually something that we
There's some careful analysis that has to be done to make sure that
the encoder and decoder can do so well.
They have to
Right.
They, I mean they have to have enough information to know to do so in
the same place I say, without sending more bits, you don't want to
send another bit that says like, hey buddy, do your recognition now.
I see.
So you have to ensure that you can tell from the code word value
itself.
I see when to do that.
Got it and up the decoder will be able to replicate what the end but
they did.
Exactly.
And as out to be a specific condition,
Which is interesting that's part of the theory of learning.
ANS is exactly how that ends up being chosen or done great.
It becomes a constraint actually on the on the way you do it on the
way you build your code, word table.
So one other I guess question while we're on that subject is that was
actually that's a new thing.
But kind of an interesting difference between ANS and arithmetic is
that with most arithmetic schemes.
What you're trying to do is approximate this imaginary infinite.
Precision thing that you would get you know, if you did arithmetic
coding on the whole file and never flush it out.
Yes.
Eventually you get some fractional thing.
You have with output that got it perfectly.
Yes, and the streaming methods are just trying to approximate that got
it.
And they generally don't put a constraint on how the decoder, does it
streaming, okay, the decoder could stream in b, or B, so it doesn't
matter who it is.
You time got it.
So that's a kind of that's a big difference to a NS which turns out to
make a big difference in how you can implement it.
And if I could ask one more question, I guess they're just sort of
perspective question.
What is the because I assume that it's related to all that if it's not
too hard to give a little bit of insight into, why do?
Because I've actually seen a mess compressor before.
Why does the encoder and the decoder run opposite each other?
In Direction, meaning in an ANS coder.
Unlike and when I seen arithmetic, typically, the way that they're
implemented these days is you put the, like you said, it's fifo both
ways.
It's like, I put in a bit stream, into the encoder it outputs that bit
stream in order just smaller and then in the decoder, in comes the
same bit stream and it comes out in order now decompressed, but ANS
goes the other way around.
I take a bit stream.
And if I put it in an order and then decompress it, I'd get the
flipped version of it.
And so, when I see a NS encoders, they typically have the encoder run
backwards through the stream.
So that when the decoder decodes, it it comes out in the
Order, where does that flipping come from?
Is there an easy way to sort of think about how that is happening?
Or does that require understanding ANS really deeply to have any idea?
What comes from this streaming mechanism?
We can use the space if you hold down the spacebar, you can just drag
and pan around
I mean, so if I'm trying to send my ABCD stream
The way NS works is you get your first symbol and this goes into your
accumulator.
Okay.
Then I get my next symbol and I you know, X does something is scaled
up and then I add on something, okay?
And then let's say it's time to flush out.
Okay, so I drop some bits out of X.
Okay, they go out to the Stream.
I'm down here.
Now, X is reduced, and when that has happened, my new X has lost
information about C and D.
Okay, I can no longer decode C and D.
Okay.
So then I put be in and I do the same thing.
It's scale to up and add something in and maybe ice cream out again.
And now I can't decode be anymore.
Then I put a in 2x, I scale it up and add something at this point from
my ex.
I can only decode a
therefore, I have to go backwards with how the decoder went, okay?
Because I've streamed out the information from the end of the file
already, you know, in my in my file are low bits of X that I had
before.
So what probably that one.
So if I'm going to decode
To decode.
So I put the final value of x in my stream.
So, did you code?
I need to take from the Stream.
and I can output a
because of that information was the only thing that was in the final
value of x.
And then I need to input some more bits.
So after I decode a, my ex changes.
And I'm going backwards.
Now, I need to stream in my ex changes again.
Now, I have enough information to help would be
And go backwards and I stream in again.
And I have enough information to Output C and D.
Well, I guess looking at that diagram, it certainly makes sense, but I
guess I might turn the question around and go shouldn't that have been
the case for all interpreting coders that were arithmetic, like
because with an arithmetic encoder, I would have thought the same
would be true.
I'm putting these symbols in and presumably when I flush.
I'm going to lose information about the earliest symbol that I encoded
it.
But why are they different in that?
Well, that's what I was trying to hint that in terms of flushing from
the top, or the bottom.
And it's that difference which bits get flushed, right?
I see.
So, if you're enter peeing, if your entropy encoder flushes bits from
the top, it can be in order, both directions but if it flashes from
the bottom, it's going to have to run reverse.
So the that be a fair statement.
Yeah we'll just do a classic arithmetic code or real quick.
So you see the difference?
So classic way of thinking about arithmetic, coders is, you have your
number stream.
It's so hard to write on this thing.
Sorry, 0 & 1.
I'm not used to it.
You can hold it like a, like a pen pen.
Just you can.
Yeah, yeah.
So your your you have your thing between 0 and 1 you have probability
intervals for let's do binary.
So you have a simple 0 and a simple one with different probabilities.
The intervals.
As you code each one, you shrink your full range to that interval.
So you started from zero to one and you shrink to this range, okay?
So we drink to that range and then now we're subdividing with in here
as if this was your to 10K, the renormalization step.
I see.
So then we say we coded 0 B.
Now we're shrinking to this range.
And you keep going this gets smaller and smaller which is why you need
infinite Precision, gotcha.
And eventually, if you could do all your bits in your file, you wind
up with an infinite Precision number, you know, somewhere out here.
Gotcha.
That is you know, very finely specified.
And this is sort of the, the, the anecdotal version is the like, hey,
you can encode all the data in in the world on like a metal bar, just
By picking the right distance along the metal bar and making a mark
like precisely there.
As long as you didn't need.
More than molecular Precision, you could encode, you know the Library
of Congress or something.
Sure.
This is that process, right?
You subdividing, ranges, yeah.
So in order to specify the spinal number
If you didn't know the length of the file, you would have to specify
it with infinite number infinite Precision, okay?
Okay?
Gotcha.
Which obviously you don't want to do right?
Since you do know the file, you know, where, you know, the length of
the file, you know, closest possible to sides of, you know, the
bracket of anywhere in between here and here would give me this file
because everything else is past the end of the file, right?
Got it.
Exactly.
So you
No, the two Clauses neighbors.
So you only have to specify enough bits of precision to differentiate
your final stream from to that level of detail, right?
Got it that winds up giving you the length of your code.
Got it.
And the way to do this incrementally streaming is as soon as you let's
see, my mid area.
My 0.5 is here.
My initial probabilities were not in the middle.
So as soon as your coded word,
Goes to either your whole interval has to go to either side of this
bit then you know that so let's call it this point.
I high goes or Milo goes over point five.
I know that my first bit in this final sequence will be one.
That means I can output a 1 B immediately.
Okay.
And it will never change, no matter what I code in the future.
All right.
So now I see, I've output my one bit and then I can renormalize onto
this interval and grow this up to 01.
I get it now and you do that over and over.
So at this point, I could also output 0.
Another 0 a few times actually, okay.
I see.
Actually outputting the same bits as you would for infinite infinite
Precision, but you can do them yes.
From the top down.
Once, you know that you will be within that.
Interval got it and we're ignoring the middle under flow zone for this
discussion.
Okay?
Yeah, yes, yeah.
One of the Practical issues that you have to deal with, okay, so let
me ask one more question on that.
Is this too many questions?
How you doing?
Sorry.
Okay, good, good.
Let me ask one more question there because something interesting that
I kind of wanted to ask about along those lines.
So because based on what we talked about before with ANS encoder like
you were saying it's not necessary to actually output the bits of the
number that we're actually building.
So that large integer, that is the integer.
That's actually how we are encoding.
The stream theoretically is not what we actually output.
That number is being built, but the thing we output is actually an
intermediate.
A portion of the intermediate
Value that we were using to construct that number.
So it's like a step in the summation up to that number or
multiplication of their whatever.
The ANS fundamental equation is or whatever.
Why do I have to flush out of the bottom then?
Because if all I'm trying to do is tell the decoder, clue about what
the state was, what makes the low bits of my interim solution, so much
more interesting to flush than the high B, is that to minutiae to go
into, or is there an easy way to sort of mention?
How why?
That turns out to be the important.
There's an easy way.
Talk about that.
So your goal with ANS is to get the growth of your number X correctly,
okay?
So because the size of X is, you know, what gives you log 2 of X,
right?
You the length of your stream, which is what we wanted.
So your goal of your entropy code or is to make that length, be what
it should be theoretically right?
You know it should match the probability model.
Okay.
To be used is close to an optimal entry coder as possible.
Got it.
So the goal with a NS is to make the growth of X as close to that as
possible, right?
And the growth of X in this case means for the symbol table, every
symbol was supposed to be assigned, a very specific way in which X
would grow.
And we want to be as close as possible to that growth in order to hit
our Target.
Any error in that growth and our encoder gets worse.
Wait, yeah.
So when you stream,
Mount of X you're making the final value of x slightly wrong.
Okay, you want to do that in a way that minimizes the damage 0x grow,
and of course, the lower bits are the least relevant rate.
Exactly got it.
And so that turns out to be a factor in how precise your coder is.
Got it.
So free like four-speed frequently, we want to do B wise
renormalization, or b y streaming, which means we're putting out eight
bits at a time.
Got it.
And the more bits you strain out of there.
The more you are screwing up, the value of x.
We got it, we got it.
And, in some cases, we've even looked at doing word word at a time
output, which increases an even bigger cost, 16 bits of time rate is,
I believe Fabien posted a reference implementation of ANS.
That was 16 bits of time?
In fact, that obviously, was not trying to be optimal in any way,
speed or space, but it was just kind of like, here's how I do it.
I think his wits
16, if I remember correctly into the 16th at a time when yeah.
And because, you know, your your value of x at that point is bigger
than 2 to 24.
It's the, it mean, you can Define your interval in different ways.
Yeah.
Typically we choose it to be between, you know, X is between to the 24
into the 32, okay?
And then you output 8 at the bottom.
Whether it's got plus 0, or plus, 255, added onto to the 24 turns out.
It's not a very large amount of the value God.
I so it doesn't cost you very much in terms of your coding efficiency,
got it.
Whereas, if you streamed out the high B, you're essentially destroying
the most important part of the data that time.
So, it would be like an awful encoder at this point, right?
That's very interesting.
Okay.
All right.
So
Did you do anything else you want to say about that for?
I asked, a sort of a separate stream of questions here, that all seem
pretty good to me from it with me in my head.
But yeah, it's good.
I have a question about sort of some of the things that was underlying
a lot of stuff.
We talked about that.
I don't think I really know necessarily why has asked about that.
So in my experience when I've used compression and this is more of as
a user of compression, not as somebody who actually knows anything
about it.
And is like implementing it incremental is rarely something.
I actually
Care about in any practical sense.
Meaning, you know, from the perspective of say game, like gaming
working on.
Now, the way that the assets system is structured is everything's
broken up into streamable chunks that I am only loading to manage
paging and stuff like that.
Anyway, so, both the encoder and the decoder always know, they're
working with some fairly small 256k at a time pieces, or something
like this.
So why is incremental so important?
Is it more about the getting compression localized?
Or is it like why do we even care about?
Like a lot of things are saying like incremental incremental, why
aren't compressor is generally written?
Just to assume that they get to see the whole stream and work from
there.
Am I missing something about that or do just something you want to say
about that?
Because that in my perspective, while I can understand why certain
live like, you know, this this streaming that we're doing here, maybe
you might
It was a long stream and you need to be incredibly whatever else.
But in practice, for gains streaming, in that sense, it's almost never
necessary and the usage of the encoder.
And the decoder could always have all the data if they wanted to.
It's really just not that big for the sizes that we tend to care
about.
Can you talk a little bit about that?
Just to maybe put it in perspective.
Yeah, there's a lot of issues there.
So one thing is, for entropy coders.
The reason that we look at incremental is partly because of the finite
Precision issue.
That you 32-bit words or whatever to work in, can't do that many
symbols and their got it with Precision so you have to do one at a
time so you have to have a streaming way of doing that.
So mostly that's to keep the computation time down because if you kept
allowing it to grow and grow you would have to do like a big mum sort
of thing where we're doing multiplication on, you know, 4,096-bit
integers and Beyond and stuff.
In terms of compressors in general, I would say, historically people
were very interested in incremental because they actually did
incremental compressors, okay, like back in the Shannon Bell Labs
days, right.
Okay, people actually wanted to be able to flush one bite at a time,
right?
Over a very slow channel, right?
Because they just had much
More severe, practical constraints that we do now.
Whatever?
I mean if you're doing a telegraph, yes, you actually.
Yes, you don't want to have a thousand symbols before you get
anything.
Got it.
Yeah, that's much less of a concern.
Now, like almost everybody is working on at least some kind of packet.
Yeah.
So there are I would say that people have moved towards looking into
block-wise compressors that
Don't work incrementally, got it or things like hierarchical grammars
and block sorting and things like that, that fundamentally our whole
file only.
Okay, so they just they start out with the assumptions.
Like look, we're just assuming we get to see everything and the point
of this compressor is to look at all the data first and make some
decisions.
Yeah, most compressors are still incremental
partly it's a practicality issue that
I mean, so there's a lot of factors there, like, even if you could do
whole file compression, you usually don't want to because you want
adaptability.
You want your compressor to be able to change as it goes through.
Yes.
So, even if you had a whole file compressor which imagine for the
moment, yes, say you have a blocks order or something like that, okay?
In order for that to be optimal.
You would want to find regions of the vial to cut.
Right.
Said that give you better compression by not doing whole file?
Yes, because real data is very changeable, you don't want to just make
a model for a whole file and apply it across the whole file, right?
So, by doing a streaming compressor, even if you don't care
necessarily about the streaming capability of it, it allows you to
make it, learn over time, and offer, get over time.
It's important, right?
So, basically, like, in some sense, the streaming is a relatively
efficient way to have localized statistics for your statistical model.
It's like it's, yeah, it's sort of only,
You had a narrow section of the file.
And since we assume that typically things in the file, tend to appear
close together, if they're similar, or something like this being
circumstances where that's true, this will do well because it won't be
trying to use statistics from very early in the file to compress
things late in the file when they are no longer applicable or things
like that, great.
I think it's also a good way to limit memory.
Use.
You know, if you only have four megabytes to put your model in
Project, you don't want to make a 4, MB memory for the model of the
whole file.
Cuz that is not very much Precision for the whole file got it.
You rather have a
MB model of a small region in scan that over, so that you actually
have kind of more bites of model memory per bite that you're trying to
work on, got it.
All right, two more things I wanted to ask if that's cool.
So I wanted to ask a question from theoretical perspective and kind of
touched on to it.
So the modern noodle compressors are not streaming back and mermaid,
and so on.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
Okay.
You want to talk a little bit about that?
I didn't know that.
So they are block based in a sense.
You give them your like, here's the chunk.
Yeah, they work on blocks.
Okay?
And part of that is just taking advantage of the efficiency of not
having to be streaming that you can kind of work on chunks of the
time.
Yeah.
Instead of having to necessarily do do one by one output okay and that
is for what purpose is that to achieve better compression or is that
for better efficiency like what was the speed?
It's forced.
Speed.
Okay.
Because that way, you can know, hey, this is how much I'm working on,
and I can look at it and make decisions about what would be the,
fastest, way, for the compressor operate here, or something like that
or Aids, it's about being able to reorganize how the output Loop works
because kindly, okay, the output Loop meaning just to be compressors.
Yeah, okay, so I mean the simplest way to think about it would be like
Say you're outputting, you're trying to Output some data and you have
a bit that tells you whether to Output an A or B.
Yes, if you're going streaming, you have to go through each bite of
your output and check that bit and go.
Okay, either I'll put an A or B got it.
So instead we're trying to reorganize so that we can do like let's
output a bunch of A's ahead and then we output a bunch of bees ahead.
Okay.
Oh oh.
Oh okay.
I think I see what you're saying here.
So basically you're saying it doesn't even necessarily right in order
so meaning it may go right in a six bytes away and then ready to be in
between.
Yeah.
Is that a correct statement of what you just said?
That's what I thought you just said but I wasn't sure.
I hope I'm not going to go into the details very much.
Okay.
All right, if we should probably move on but just mentioning this fair
enough.
Okay, so ignoring proprietary high-tech compression, let me ask this
Acrostic is because they did not involve anything you do specific.
Yeah.
So I sort of along the lines of what I asked earlier and this is
again, sort of more my curiosity about the subject matter from not
having ever had the time to sit down and really understand it myself.
I have like a bunch of
Like this is what I would look into if I had time to like try to build
up this knowledge so I try and try to cheat by asking you these
questions.
Yes.
So
when you look at something like an arithmetic encoder or maybe a
Huffman encoder and you look at something like l z,
So, one of the interesting things about these from the cursory
inspection is like an LZ.
Encoder is a fairly old encoder, right?
I mean, it's like 40 years old.
At this point, roughly right.
Lz77 was 1977 or something and it's like 2016 2017 now, right again.
So we're literally like 40 years away from the invention of thing.
Yet, the typical compressors that are used to compress.
Generic data are still these kinds.
Pressors like, you know, LZ n a, which is the most commonly used
high-compression variant, that I know of me as, um, a sari L DNA is
yours.
So lzma is still using variance on those algorithms from what I
understand.
She's right.
So I kind of had like a two-part question there.
The first question is
Is there some specific reason why we haven't moved past those
compressors?
Are they at a sweet spot in terms of being able to compress generic
data?
That is simply impossible to get by in any practical sense?
Meaning like in order to like make significant improvements on them,
you're going to end up in a position where you're doing a incredibly
large amount of work to get very little practical returning.
Like did they hit a curve particularly?
Well,
Or is it more the case of like we just don't know yet, we haven't been
able to make theoretical improvements here, that sort of thing.
That's my first kind of question about those, you know, Huffman
arithmetic LZ which seemed to kind of be in this.
Like we still use them today they're still the best whatever in terms
of like.
So, that's the first question and I have a second question which I'll
wait till after four, but those, that that's kind of the first one.
It's my second one is related.
I mean, the answer is just another good algorithm.
I mean, we still use good algorithms of all kinds.
Yeah we still use a star and okay whatever.
You know, we still use quicksort, okay?
Like when there's a good algorithm, that happens to be kind of a sweet
spot of implementation.
Yeah you're going to keep using it.
Okay and you modify it slightly over time, okay?
But you don't go to something else.
Unless there's a major discovery which could be I mean inventing, new
data compression, algorithms.
It is not like a science that you go and chip away at and they just
get better, don't panic.
You can always get more compression by throwing more work at it you
know by making the model better.
But refining there's you know,
You look at anything like lzma, there are every single spot where it
does coating.
You say, I could compress this better, okay?
But it would take more CPU work.
I see or more memory or something.
So then it's question of, is it worth it to throw that at that?
And in the answer, in that case, is almost always know, I guess, so
does.
It depends what what trade-off you want, man?
What your goal is, but there's no like magic.
So what happens with data compression is there's kind of obvious
vectors to work on things.
There's like you can you can take any existing algorithm and throw
other existing algorithms on it, you know, they compose
Very easily.
Okay?
So you can toss PP M into l z, okay, you know, you can you can take
something that does Huffman coding and replace it with her athletic
coating, right?
Okay.
So you can always modify these algorithms, you're not really
inventing, anything new but you're kind of bolting together a new
machine right out of the parts and you can trade off your speed versus
compression ratio that way.
Gotcha, but you aren't making a big step into
You know, unexplored territory.
Yes of efficiency got it.
So like is there a big step that would give us more compression at
most of the times, really?
Yeah.
We don't know.
Okay.
Like we haven't found it yet.
Are kind of maybe there is.
Maybe there isn't.
All right?
I mean it feels like there isn't.
There's nothing for me is because we should have seen it by now, every
well.
Okay.
But maybe you know, that's like with ANS came out of nowhere block,
sorting came out of nowhere.
When he's when these things do appear, they tend to be like, wow
unexpected, right?
Okay.
Because if it was something expected, someone would happen 40 already
rate because people are looking at this all the time,
Tends to be something weird that comes out of nowhere and I go.
Well, so maybe there, I mean, it doesn't seem like there's that much
fat left in it.
I mean, if you think about what you can express in terms of machine
instructions, yeah that makes it data compressor.
Yeah, it's hard to imagine where it is okay but you know who knows.
Yeah.
And the other factor is that as the hardware changes
The algorithms that work well on the hardware can change as well.
Right.
So the things that we're doing now are different design choices than
we would if we were making 20 years ago, just because the hardware is
different.
I suppose.
It's also true that in general.
The trade-offs are constantly changing in terms of what you even want
in terms of compression.
Because you know, nowadays there's a whole Suite of things that you
might not even care about.
I mean, you know, it used to be that compressing, your
CD collection to MP3 was like a really important thing that allowed
you to have that CD collection digitized at all.
Nowadays you really just don't care about 10x smaller CDs for your
like whatever, like I can store the whole thing uncompressed and don't
care so it's definitely true that.
Like what you're, you know, nowadays bandwidth is probably the more
important thing that people are trying to compress for things like
this and so you're looking at you know, more of those use cases.
So I suppose like what you actually want your compression to do and
why probably moves as well, which would change, totally what the
relevant thing is, right?
You know, the big thing that's happening.
I mean there's a lot of
Obviously like 4K video and things like that is a huge issue for
compression.
Yes.
The other big thing is the speed of disks with like nvram disks, and
yes, right, right.
It's like massively changed, so this idea of like using compression to
speed up.
I owe ya changed?
Yes, romantically.
Yes, because of that, except on consoles still, that's me.
Yes, someday someday we won't care about that anymore because we're
not quite there yet.
Okay, so last question that I had this is kind of a bit of a minutiae
question but it's still one of those ones that I feel like I'm just
curious about in the, like, I just don't have enough theoretical
understanding of a lot of the stuff to answer myself.
So from a Layman's perspective when you look at something like LZ,
Hoffman or something, like a sir, l z arithmetic as a way that people
would prevent a compressor.
One of the things that's kind of confusing about why it works the way
it does, is that it sort of seems like, for lack of a better term.
There's an arbitrary decision about what is a symbol?
Versus what is not a symbol.
And what I mean by that, is, if you take a look at like literature or
something like that, that talks about say arithmetic encoding.
It makes very simple understandable sense.
When you read it, it's like, let's suppose, we have this alphabet of
things, we're trying to encode, we don't care what they are.
You can make up whatever you want.
You can say how many symbols you want them, what they are.
And all we really care about is that you can assign a probability to
each one, and then that, that probability is accurate.
And then we make the
Ascertainment of Monaco turn off you go, that's a pretty easy thing to
understand.
When you extend the system out to something like an LZ encoder with an
arithmetic back end,
All of a sudden there's this sort of idea that like well, okay, so
what a symbol is in this case is the output of the things that the LZ
compressor cares about which means, you know, we've got symbols of the
form.
Say, there's a look back distance that I need some way of expressing
that.
So the symbols could be offsets of things.
I've got another thing which is symbols, which are I have to encode
literals, so in some sense I have symbols that would be the actual
symbols.
I would have talked about, if I just have the arithmetic encoder,
those are still involved there and so on, right?
And what's a little bit difficult?
And this is my question.
What's a little bit difficult to wrap one's head around.
I feel like is
It seems like these sorts of things are treating that very fast and
loose in some sense, it's not obvious to me why the theory doesn't
wrap the whole thing up in a more coherent way where you can talk
about symbols or maybe a better way to State, it would be an LZ system
is a system that has the ability to talk about symbols by using
previous symbols that you seemed to construct them.
But in arithmetic, encoder cannot do
Such a thing.
Why do we not have can encoders that talk about both of those things.
Theoretically, as the same operation, does that?
And I wish I could phrase the question better, but the question in and
of itself is about not really understanding how these two things
really fundamentally differ and why it's feels a little bit under
baked, in terms of the way that it's expressed, when these two things
come together.
And since they're always together in implementation, I
I would have expected maybe a more complete way of looking at it.
Does any of that make sense for you?
Just like I have no idea what you're asking.
Well, not not sure.
I know what you're asking, but okay, I'll say a few things related to
that, okay, so the extra symbols, that tells you you're adding are
totally hacky heuristic.
It's like, there's no rigorous Theory to it.
And there's a lot of possibilities.
There are different LZ, coders, add different things.
Okay, like, traditionally you, are you add a match, which is an offset
in a length.
Yes, modern LZ, coders.
Add other things there.
Okay.
You know.
So there's like, single literal matches, right?
There's Delta literals.
There's instead of offsets you might send rap, offsets things like
that.
Yeah, I do remember LZ.
Um, a had a number of special cases like this is a literal match.
I'd say, this is a match that has the same size as a pretty like, they
have like, weird things of like, we found this to be efficient.
So we write these everything.
It's, it's sort of you think of it as just like a toolbox yet.
Like, these are different ways of sending characters.
Yes.
You can kind of, add whatever you want there.
Yes, so like, broadly has some new weird things that it's added.
Do you say broadly or broccoli?
Broadly.
Okay.
So the Google I was hoping you said broccoli because I wanted there to
be a compressor going properly, but okay webp lost Liz has a similar
thing where I was like codebook, like, okay, trying to send pixels
losslessly but it can send pixels as like local palette selections
like that.
So it just has different modes there.
So, like you always have a literal as a fallback, yes, in case your
other
Don't you have to be able to send all their own, right?
But then you have these other codebook things.
They're just ways of grabbing characters and part of your LZ design
is, what do I add in there?
That is helpful.
Yes, and to some extent.
That's part of your modeling of different data will have different
types of things that are helpful there, okay?
Like whether your data is binary and has structured repeat patterns or
different.
Things like that.
So l z, in that sense is an over complete.
Alphabet for expressing data, right?
Because everything you send could be expressed, many different ways.
Using the LZ rate that you have it's what you've made your alphabet to
Big essentially, right?
Yes.
Your original B and B are minimal.
And then now you're using an alphabet.
That's like yes it's got lots of overlap of lots of these simple sound
the same thing, right?
Which is a very strange thing in data compression because
That's doing that.
Is wasteful, right?
You're getting bigger as you get smaller which is a little
counterintuitive I know, right?
Yeah.
So like in traditional voters in the model coder setup you don't do
that kind of thing because it is wasteful, okay?
And in the theoretical analysis, you generally would not do that, want
us?
It it's just something that's practical.
Yeah,
And it turns out that the waste from that is not that bad.
There are interesting ways to look at getting rid of that waste have
been done and some Elves.
He's like,
For example, if a match that starts with the letter a is available,
then you know that the literal a should never be used that makes
perfect sense which means that you could in your code or sepsis, which
is saving you some space in your entropy go during I think.
So, every if you look at all your strings that you have,
You can get one.
It's not quite precise but things like that, right?
No, I get what you're saying, but yeah, like it.
You could you can instead of allowing the over complete alphabet, you
can say instead that once I have the ability to express something in
one way, I will eliminate the other ways I could have expressed it to
reduce the over completeness of relevant and maybe that's good, maybe
that's bad.
But, you know, I could so most
practical coders that we use these days are over complete.
Kind of interesting to me like all the video codecs are way way over
complete.
Yeah, in fact I remember this both both from pink to and also from
like ever looking at like mpeg-4 spec it's just it's I mean you can
encode the image as a hobby and he was saying, if you look at the
specs there's just billions and billions and billions of ways to
include even the same little tiny part of
An image.
So it turns out that being over complete and having an encoder that
spends a lot of time, considering the different choices is an
interesting design point, that seems to be the one that works it.
Yeah, it lets you basically use an encoder time to find a good bit
stream.
Right, that of kind of baking it into the bitstream, inherently, yes.
Which would cost you decoder time.
Got it.
So, you have kind of these.
Lots of different ways to encode data, all of which are efficient to
decode.
And then you're putting the work on the encoder search time to
consider all those ways.
That's pretty interesting.
So, in some sense you could think of it, as we've kind of got, if we
imagine, there's a uniform constant, that's like how much compression
plus time there is, we can choose to, like, move that time around and
get more compression by, like, sort of putting the time into the
compressor versus into the decompressor.
We can still get the same compression by just moving all the time,
over to the compressor and leaving the decompressor efficient.
Even though, you know, in some sense you could have gone the other way
I suppose maybe.
Although I guess I don't know if we know of ways to go the other way
but maybe it's possibly good.
It's very good.
Yeah it's something that we haven't really looked at sometimes.
Very rarely you don't want that spot case is often.
Yeah it's it's something I've seen also in terms of just entropy
coding that you have kind of two classic choices that you can do.
Adaptive entropy coding with a model the changes over time.
Yes with arithmetic coding or rants or something like this or you can
do something like Hoffman or tance Tas coating.
Okay.
That uses static models and sense the code lengths.
So is TA NS technically.
What it is called if the RNs an RA NS is incredible version, T.
And S is the static version.
Well, or
Is it not?
Yes I'm sort of.
Okay, so ta + S stands for table based in us.
Okay, our ANS tents for range
Eunice.
Okay, which is by analogy to the range arithmetic.
Odor, got it.
And that is adaptive.
Those are both, just special cases of ANS and Jericho.
Okay.
So there are adaptive ens coders that are not rants coders.
I think, for example, in our static, there's a static version of
France, for example, got so tense is not the only static and US.
Those are just two particular ways to do it.
Got it.
So if you are doing static,
Attic entropy coding, you can spend time in the end coder, to find the
kind of similar regions of the file and cut it up, and separate
statistics for each one segment, so that can take a lot of encoder
search time.
It's a hard problem, right?
But the decoder is still fast because it already has a static data
that decoder.
Yeah, and that turns out to be very close in size.
To doing adaptive coating.
I see.
So you get almost a perfect way of taking
You know, an Adaptive coding your encoder and decoder or both
expensive, right?
Because the decoder has to be mimicking, the Adaptive work that really
encoder was doing and there's no way to get around that great
additional load, they have to be adapting in lockstep.
They have to always see the same model, right?
So by going to this static with encoder searching, yes, the decoder is
now cheap in the encoder is very expensive and wait so you're saying
even if in that
Case you're talking about literally, I'm sending statistics.
So I have to send a little block of turning 46, bytes or something.
For each.
One of these chunks to preload the statistics.
I mean, I don't know what exactly, but even given that, I had to send
that block, it's still close in size to the kind where I didn't have
to send anything, and I was just doing adaptive, correct.
That's what it can even be better in some cases, because, right?
Because depending on whether the Adaptive could get up to the correct
adapt adaptation because the B string
might not lend itself to that, I guess, right?
I mean, the the worst case is when the data is switching back and
forth rapidly, right?
Like if you have data that's like text in an image and then test and
then an image, right?
The static can actually find those transitions pretty easily, right?
Whereas the Adaptive has to adapt on every transition and if those, if
the if the size of each section isn't long enough, yet at application
may not get there by the time it has to go back to the next one.
And so on just I mean,
It depends the problem with the adapt.
The good thing about the static for that case, is that the
sophistication of your modeling is just in the end good or time,
right?
Whereas, with the Adaptive, if you're trying to make it smart enough
to realize, like, oh, here's a really sharp transition of Statistics.
I have to forget all my stuff quickly, the decoder has to do that same
backtrack, Nico.
Actually the same kind of analysis, so you aren't usually putting that
level of sophistication into your adaptive model to be able to detect
flush points.
That makes sense.
All right, so let me just close with.
Let me just see if I can ask one more time about that.
Just that the whole thing because I, I'm almost there, but I'm not
sure I'm quite there.
The answer may be that that we don't have any good explanation for
these sorts of things.
But so still on the, on the concept of the LZ, versus the arithmetic
side of things.
I think originally early on in the discussion, you said that l z is
understood as a modeling system.
Now and maybe originally it wasn't thought of that way or wasn't
immediately obvious that, that's how it should be looked at, right?
Wait.
So can you maybe just give a little bit more insight into that?
I guess, because I think that may also be part of the thing that I was
hung up on before.
Because again, it's just a little confusing to think about the way.
Something like arithmetic use symbols where you're talking about a
situation where you actually know what the symbols are versus
something like LZ where you, it seems to have this ability to create
its own symbols in that sense, right?
Meaning it's looking back into the stream of things that it's received
so far.
And it's saying what I'm trying to Output next is this portion of what
I've already seen, right?
And again, the part that just it's hard for me to wrap my brain around
is something like arithmetic thinks about things in terms of symbols
but seems to have no awareness of the fact that that sort of thing
could exist.
The idea that things I've already sent are in effect potentially
usable as symbols, right?
It doesn't have this notion.
It just has a notion of an alphabet that we've predetermined or
something like this, right?
Well, arithmetic is just an entropy encoder, right?
And so I'm just kind of curious about that dichotomy a little
like,
I guess another way to say it might be
Is there a is there really no thing.
Definition of something in between and entropy encoder and a modeling
system?
That is the thing that still has a symbol table, but it on a set of
symbols that it's thinking about that.
Those symbols are more dynamic.
Sorry, this is such a poorly phrased question, but like, okay, maybe,
let's just let me just say it in the most laymen way possible and you
can see if you can make anything of it.
There seems to be a world of difference to me so between like jpg,
like I'm going to DCT transform this thing into a set of numbers.
And then I'm going to think of that as my model.
So my model is I take my input set idct at first, that's a step.
That feels a particular way that doesn't feel like in its core.
It's thinking about symbols per se.
It's feels like a totally separate kind of an operation.
It's like a modeling, transform operation.
LZ while obviously not quite so specific and symbol.
And as something like an arithmetic or Huffman encoder, it still feels
very much.
Like it's thinking of things in terms of symbols.
In that way.
It feels a lot less like a DCT and a lot more like an arithmetic
encoder to me.
When I think about it,
Yet it is not that or something.
Does that have any more of it?
Like, do you see why?
I think of those those things that I'm having trouble policing LZ as a
thing in that way.
And maybe it's just like, yeah, that's the way it is.
Yeah, okay.
So I mean there's just
There's theoretical question.
Yeah, and then there's just algorithms that work, okay?
It's just a way of working with the data and expressing things, okay?
And so, a couple of points, all right, one is that
You can always see how a compressor corresponds to a model just by
looking at the number of bits that it outputs.
Okay?
So if I run my lz77 up to a certain point in the file, okay?
Then I can try adding on each of the next 256 possible characters.
Yes.
Give it that character to encode and see how many bits it outputs for
each one.
Okay.
That bit count, if I go to, to the length on each one is a probability
for, yes.
Possible.
Following symbol got it, which is a way of turning any compressor into
a model.
I understand.
So you can take the most heuristic hacky compressor in the world and
always figure out what model is this actually corresponding to.
I see.
So at any, instantaneous, point in a
I can look at the probability that y.
Sorry, I can look at the amount of bits that this thing will output
for any of the possible things that could come next.
And in a sense I have basically said okay, that is the probabilistic
model of this thing.
Now, it is not order.
Zero in the case of LZ, it depends entirely on all the stuff that came
before it, but at any instantaneous point, I can still just look at
the order zero right here, in some sense.
And get that at least unwinding the rest of it may be impossible to.
Is it some crazy turing machine, who knows what the, you know what
it's doing?
But just instantaneously I can look at it that way.
Great.
Yeah, that's the probability of, what is the next character, given?
All the previous characters?
Yes, right.
So, every compressor is a model in that sense tells he's got a way of
getting to that output links.
Okay, that makes a lot of sense.
Okay?
The other thing is that so the you can think of the extra symbols.
As ways of kind of getting to the arithmetic coder.
I can see this clearly but so like say you have a model that is just
predicting its most likely guess.
For the next symbol.
Okay.
Like it makes one guess and then it if it's right, it outputs a 0 bit,
okay?
If it's wrong, it outputs a 1 bit.
In fact what the character actually was got it right tonight, that's
got it.
So what we've actually done there is added and then another simple.
Okay that'd so we have our literal we've added the yes/no bit more
accurate inaccurate that
We're outputting 04, right?
And one, and then eight more bits, right?
If we're wrong.
You can think of this as a combined, alphabet.
This, this is the symbols 0 to 255 that are literals.
This is symbol 256.
Okay, and I'm giving this a 1 B code and these all get a 9 bit code,
got it.
So this is my like super simple LZ.
Okay.
And I've added a symbol to my alphabet to specify hey my guess is
right.
Okay.
So all LZ is is doing more of this, okay?
I'm more complicated set of possible adding more special symbols okay,
giving them special codes.
Okay.
And
That's that's what heuristic compressors General to are doing.
And the reason why you don't
Why nlz compressor.
Itself isn't concerned about how to encode things, in the correct
number of bits is because fundamentally speaking, at least so far,
nobody has figured out any particular reason why the way you would do
that.
Would differ from
Just arithmetic, Ali, encoding.
The actual things that the LZ is doing right, because in some sense,
you can think of an arithmetic.
Encoder is a thing that's trying to figure out.
Well, not trying to figure out.
If it's a machine for correctly, outputting the minimal number of bits
to encode.
This set of symbols that is trying to input, right?
The LZ encoder is not concerned with doing that.
It's not concerned with trying to get the optimum number of bits.
It's just trying to produce a series of
as of match versus not match and it wants to reduce the middle number
of bits.
With that in mind, but it's not trying to get down to fractional or
anything like that.
So you might say the reason why it's not concerned with that is
because the way that we have chosen to try to approach that is just,
it seems like bolting an arithmetic encoder onto the back of it is as
efficient as trying to figure out a way to integrate that directly
into the LZ scheme.
Because like in a fanciful world, right?
And again, from Layman's perspective, you could imagine an LZ encoder
that itself was working on fractional B.
I don't know what that exactly means but like the concept that I have
to copy out of a 8 bit at a time, bitstream doesn't really have to
happen like an LZ encoder.
Could a similar thing to know seeking encoder could maybe be done
imagining working on an infinite fraction grabbing parts of the
Fraction out, which means that now it's fractional B in terms of the
input, I'm making this up, but you see what I mean, right?
Yeah.
I mean, so we usually work on B just out of practicality, right?
There's no inherent theoretical reason why we have to write and like
the careful people in the literature will do their arithmetic coding
in terms of Base B, right?
Right is arbitrate arbitrate.
Yeah.
But it, you know, as a programmer reading it rice.
Think that's two right, right, right, right.
I'm not doing yeah.
Like ternary right?
Like arithmetic.
Ok, so that's all possible.
Yeah, there are more General things, so let me in terms of l z,
You could at each step of your coating.
Look at like in the LZ aspect of it.
Yes.
Before we get to the entropy coding, yes, we could.
Look at like, hey, some of my heuristic code.
Words are not even possible in this location where I am.
Yes, so let me exclude them from my code words, like maybe early on in
the file.
You don't have much dictionary, right?
So there's lots of things that aren't possible, like, Laura offsets
aren't
Right.
Maybe you haven't even seen all the literals.
Yes a lot.
You know you can't possibly match them and forget that.
So you could be doing more at that step in the LZ, right?
And people have tried it there.
Ben
There's lots of variants along there, there's things like L ZF g l zp
p more recently.
There's Cannon Konya and Kennen Conrad's were country which is kind of
an interesting thing in this direction.
Okay.
For the most part spending CPU work there is not a good trade-off,
okay?
That they're just better places to park CPU work.
Okay so I mean to some extent
The answer there is.
Compression is always an issue of design of where your where you
putting your CPU work, got it and you know, there's always options.
You know, there's no shortage of ways, we can increase the amount of
CPU work.
I can always do some more modeling.
Yeah.
There's always you know,
So one of the there's like like all the redundancies and the over
completeness of the LC you could model and eliminate if you wanted to
spend the CPU work on it.
Yes.
But it takes work.
Yes, there's correlations all over the place and LZ that we know are
there and we could model and take out.
Okay, like the previous character, for example, predicts a lot about
what the current sequence, what the current symbol is going to be or
whether it's a
Okay, and the previous occurrence of the same match.
Like once I send my offset,
I know, I can go back to that spot in the file because I've sent the
offsets the decoder.
Could do the same thing, right?
I can look around that offset at the data there.
It's probably very similar to where I am now.
Okay, so I could be using that information, but I'm not to predict
things about my local neighborhood.
I say, but I'm not other than, you know, obviously you're copying the
match but even outside of the match region, there will be similarity
stuff that you might want to know.
Yeah.
So, there's lots of opportunities and it's just like, what can you
express?
Well, that is efficient enough because this beats, we want to run out.
Now, we don't have a lot of time.
I'm still doing much of anything.
Got it, you know, are in the decoder and the encoder you can afford to
be slow, I suppose it was certainly, that's the, I mean,
The design point that we work at a Trad usually is slower and coders.
That's that's what the odors and we only get like one to ten clocks
per symbol in the decoder.
Gotcha.
So you can't do very much they're right?
All right, so in addition to that, so like if you look at LZ,
There's lots of points where you can see that we're wasting that's
okay.
And it's just a question of, how do we get them without spending too
much time?
You're also, there's also, of course, like, another level of things
you're missing that LC don't model.
Well.
Okay.
So there's a whole other issue of like, what other compression is
available in this file, right?
Right.
I'm never going to get with LZ, right?
Let the preconditioning sorts of stuff like different thing from
symbols or things like this.
It people have added to LZ I guess in.
Like I think lzma has some things like this of this nature, right?
Where it'll Delta symbols from me?
Other things like that before encoding or stuff like this, which is
not technically in the LZ scheme.
I think great great.
Yeah.
All right.
Well I think that's everything.
Thank you so much for explaining all of that.
That's been very very very helpful and hopefully we've got it looks
like everything.
Looks like everything went well enough, people seem to have been able
to have heard us even even though we have our happy little webcam.
So thank you so much Charles that's been awesome.
I will post this along with the handmade con one server and can get
the complete package and yeah I guess also at some point people
probably should
Take a look at your blog.
There's a lot of compression stuff on there.
Should I include the shock tube the URL with this video, potentially,
or do you just use, like, no block?
The blog is secret.
Don't come to it.
Yeah, we can include the URL, right, I'll put it on the bottom.
Thanks so much for being here.
I will go ahead and I will close down the stream.