Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could a complete game live on stream yesterday.
We did some cleanup work and actually found some interesting.
Profiler things in terms of some places in the code, we're spending
more time than we should have thanks to calling round F, instead of
our own sort of code for rounding things which we have now fixed,
which is nice.
I thought of something else while we were kind of on that sort of
clean up kick, I thought of something else.
I kind of wanted to do before we get any further.
Are especially because we sort of start working on that camera code.
And really, when I look at like what sort of stuff we'll be doing
next, I don't know that.
There's very much left to do other than sort of move into sort of
regular game development mode.
At this point.
There's always other things we can do but you know, we're kind of out
of really particularly meaningful things to do with that.
More of a complete game running.
And so, one of the things that I want to do before we started on
anything serious, in terms of tuning,
Is fixed how we do our clocking because we kind of never really went
back and did anything intelligent there.
And I would like to sort of do a little bit more with that.
And so today, I'd like to go drop back into that code and just fix a
couple things I think are problematic with it and hopefully, it'll be
pretty obvious what I'm talking about as we get started here.
So I'm gonna go ahead and jump right into that it's day 380 here.
So, if you want to follow along with today's source code 3-day 379 is
the source code to start with.
I'm going to go ahead and open up the project in trustee for coder.
See here, I found out also that I have not been building for a coder
with optimizations do to build thing that was happening.
So actually the for coder that we, you have been seeing on stream this
whole time is the one that's built without optimizations on.
So, apologies to Alan for that, although it's still plenty fast for
what we need to do.
Obviously Building without optimizations, makes it much slower.
But anyway, let's go ahead and, and take a look at where we're at.
So what I wanted to point out here is?
Oh, right?
I forgot.
We also fixed the cutscenes.
I should probably put that back the way it was.
Let's go ahead and fix that.
There we go.
so,
Let's recompile here, we fixed the cutscenes at the end of the last
dream as well.
So the thing that I wanted to talk about today is just that we've got
all this stuff working here and you know most of our most of our stuff
is okay at this point and if we look at the profile you know we did a
pretty good job of making sure that at least in release mode stuff is
is pretty.
No.
But you can see here our profile in in release mode is basically the
only thing that we're doing because, you know, the debug code is not
important that turns off completely at runtime.
So really the only things that we're doing here.
Wait a minute, is this even in release mode?
I take it back.
I think that's actually debug mode that's debug mode.
Switch over to release mode there.
For what I was trying to say.
So when we start the game in release mode, we take a look at the
profile.
We can see here that basically our top four functions, are all exactly
what we would hope.
Right.
So here is our game, which takes no time, right?
It's literally meaningless.
It's it's it's the case that 95% of the time or I guess I should say.
I don't know if cumulative this point, how we did it, but I guess over
90% of the time is spent up here.
And all of the rest of our game is is inconsequential, which is
fantastic news.
The top part here,
Swap buffers is just waiting right for the GPU to wait for the
vertical blank.
You know, or if it had to drawing by, don't think we're handing enough
drawing stuff for that.
So basically that's just extra time that we're waiting for the frame
to the monitor debug collation and debug and those are not even
relevant because they turn off in the shipping version of the game.
So the only thing that we really have at the moment that's costly.
Opengl renderer commands and pretty much all of the time.
In opengl renderer commands is being spent in the driver.
And so basically if we want to optimize the game, we know that there's
really only one thing we would have to start doing and that is
minimizing the number of draw calls by packing textures either into
textures raise or a texture Atlas.
So we're looking really good here on our profile.
Like it feels like we have absolutely nothing to worry about.
And again this is on a machine, that's 10 years old.
At this point, I'm sorry, seven years old at this point.
So on a seven-year-old machine, that's what it looks like.
I think we're in fantastic shape.
We've done a good job, keeping everything reasonable and I'm just not
concerned about anything at this point.
That said we do have one thing that becomes a problem.
For us and not necessarily for our customers is that when we are in
the the cutscene mode and we look at the profile.
Everything's fine.
Right?
We're still hitting 60 frames a second with no problem.
And in fact for the cutscenes, we're hitting it.
At a point where we aren't, you know, we're waiting for the monitor
most, most of the time anyway.
If however, we switch to the game mode we drop and you can
If I close the debug you I so we're not doing anything in the debug UI
you can see that we're still we're getting closer to 60 frames a
second but in you know when we don't compile in release mode takes a
lot more time.
We open the debug view obviously it slows down more but you know,
that's okay.
We don't really care because we're when the debug view is open if we
have a slower frame and that's okay, but when we're looking at the
game and playing in debug mode, we'd like it to be faster.
When we look here you can see we kind of have not, you know, not a
whole lot we can do about that.
That we've got, you know, our render volume stuff.
In fact let me pause it so it's not jumping around.
You can see our render volume and render pieces stuff, which really
needs the optimizer to kick into inline, the functions in order to be
fast.
So debug mode, I don't know how much better that's going to get.
Unless we just wrote a custom one or peephole turned the optimizer on
just for that, which maybe we could consider doing
And then we've got debug collation, which again is probably not going
to get a Priestly faster without the optimizer turned on.
Although we could go look at it and the same with debug end opengl
better commands is not because of debug compilation.
That's the same slowness in retail compilation.
It's just that function is such that we would need to do the texture
packing to accelerate it because it's the driver texture change
overhead, where we have to break things into batches.
That's the problem there, as far as we can tell.
So the interesting thing about this is that just looking at it here we
would have to make the decision to spend a bunch of time optimizing
this stuff in debug mode, when really, we don't even have a frame rate
problem in release mode and that's just not a very good idea, but we
don't really have too much of a choice if we looked at that as our
only option.
And the reason for that is because if you look at what happens here,
when this little saucy,
It is jumping around, you can see now that if we were to tune the game
like this, it would be completely wrong because it's supposed to be
hopping around at the 60 frames a second rate.
But instead, it's hopping around half as fast because it's only
running at 30 frames a second and so that just motivates what I wanted
to do today, which is 30 frames a second, is a perfectly usable frame
rate for development purposes, right?
If all were, you know, maybe if we're talking about the shipping
version of the game and it's and you know, it's an action game, maybe
we're like it's really important for us to it.
64 second that's fine but we are right in our release build.
So now we're talking about debug build.
What's an acceptable frame rate for the debug build?
Well, 30 frames a second is plenty acceptable for the debug build.
So really what we'd rather do is have the game Run.
Okay.
At 30 frames a second but in order to do that, we need to know we're
running at 30 frames a second.
Because what's happening right now is the game always updates itself
as if it was running at 60 frames a second.
So if it's not running at 60 frames a second, we end up in a
A bad problem, right?
Because that is exactly the situation where we will get a, you know,
an update step that doesn't correspond to the actual speed at which
things are being updated on the user's machine, right?
So just taking a look at that and thinking about that a little bit,
what we need to do to make that usable is in and, you know, I'm also
going to go ahead and set it back to since we don't care what the cut
scenes at the moment, and we fixed most of the stuff we were going to
fix in there already.
Anyway.
I'm going to stop the game normally boots in the cutscene, I'm going
to stop that and instead just let it boot straight into the game game
here, because this is what we're working on right now, and the
cutscene runs at 60.
The second in debug mode anyway.
So when we look at what we set ourselves up, as you can see that we,
you know, we set our game to run up in this way where we've got game
update and friend or into thing about game update and render is it's
actually getting past the information that it needs to get past to do
the right thing here.
Right?
What we did is when we set that up, let me go ahead and get that here.
When we set it up, we have this game input structure here, that gets
passed to it.
And says right here, dt4 frame, and actually everything in our game
update and render is actually using that.
And for
A life, I believe.
If we were to set that dt4 frame 20, the game would just stopped
updating, right?
We'd be looking at the opening thing, and nothing would move, right?
So, our game already properly respects a variable time step, we can
set it to whatever we want.
We can make the game Run incredibly quickly by setting the time step
to an artificial officially huge value.
You can see it happening here, right?
We can go and set it to some more reasonable but
till faster value and can see everything looks like it's running on
speed.
So, you know, we we did the work of having a variable frame rate, but
the reason we're not getting that variable frame rate is just because
that value is getting past arbitrarily.
So if we go back to the win32 layer, what you can see here is the DT
for frame.
What it's getting is the target seconds per frame and the targets.
It's per frame is always set to the same thing.
It's whatever we wanted the update frame rate to be in an Ideal World.
So since we wanted that to be the monitor refresh rate.
So if you had a 60 frames a second monitor at 60, if you have 120,
it's 120 whatever, right?
Since we kind of just took that at face value, it means that if we
ever miss our frame rate, we're just woefully wrong, right?
And so, if we take a look at what's going on with this code here, we
can see that.
It never bothers to look as to whether or not it hit its frame rate.
It just always blindly assumes that the target seconds per frame is
the target seconds per frame is how many you actually got, right?
So if instead we were to set the target seconds per frame separately,
right?
So if I instead said well, okay, let's look at where we're setting
game update hurts, right?
And here's the monitor refresh rate, or whatever it is.
If instead of that I magically just knew I was only going to get 30
frames a second, right?
Because remember here's what this looks like.
If I
Run this.
Here's what it looks like, right?
And it's kind of sluggish to move around.
It's not nice.
Like the 30 frames out of the 60 frames a second version terms of
speed if I instead said well okay, what if I instead the game update
Target seconds for frame was going to be twice, what you thought it
should be.
So it will be 30 frames a second?
Is what you think the target should be?
Well, now, when I play the game, hey look.
It feels exactly like the 60 frames a second version and yet
Might not be as smooth of a look because we're not getting as many
frames.
As we should be getting if we were getting 60 frames a second, the
game plays properly, right?
And that's what we care about here is making sure that the game always
plays properly.
So if the player does have a machine which in all cases they will.
Because you know like I said this is a machine that even this seven
year old machine with a really old graphics card is fine for this game
at 60 frames a second in release mode.
Load.
But in debug mode, what we could think of that as being as like okay
or user, has a really slow machine, right?
In that case, if they get 30 frames a second, that's still perfectly
playable.
You could totally play the game like this.
And so we don't want them to like basically not be able to play the
game just because we don't set the timing update, right?
So in both cases both because we want our debug build to play properly
and feel correct, even though it's running at half the frame rate of
the release mode version,
But also, because maybe sometimes people will play this game on a
really old really slow machine and needs to have it.
Run it only 30 frames a second for them.
What we need to do here is figure out a way to set the target seconds
per frame adaptively, so that as we see that we're not making our
frame rate budget, we bump the target seconds per frame back up,
right?
And this is a really tricky thing to do.
It's actually very difficult to get, right?
And we'll probably have to play with it a bit at the moment.
We don't have to do an industrial-strength version.
We can do something slightly, not all that great.
And in some senses, something that's not all that great might actually
be okay in a lot of cases because again, for this particular game, we
know that most of the time on most machines, it will be able to hit 60
frames a second and maintain that for the majority.
Of the frames.
So in our particular case, we aren't really that worried about having
to have monitor framerate fallbacks be all that awesome, but you never
do know.
So, what I want to do is start by taking a look at this how we've
structured it here.
So, what you can see is we actually have some interesting baked in
assumptions here.
You can see this samples per second samples per
Buffer, second, buffer size stuff here.
This stuff is pretty much all I think going to be okay, because
nothing here depends on the target seconds per frame.
The sound output is sort of run on a separate clock and I don't think
we have to worry too much about it.
So really what we're looking at is the people who look at Target
seconds per frame.
And what you can see here is we don't have a whole lot here to worry
about.
Basically, we're looking at a couple things in sound anticipation,
here they are, just
Try to estimate where the sound cursor will be.
And then we also have this sort of waiting this frame rate waiting
stuff here that we don't turn on anymore which is just to allow the
game to go to sleep occasionally and I don't think we need that
anymore because for the most part swap buffers will take care of that
for us.
So I think this can stay safely off probably but we'll see about that
as well.
And so then what we really need to know
Here is just for, for the one, real use of Target seconds, for frame
that we care about here, which is DT per frame.
How can we adjust, what we expect our Target seconds per frame, to be
based on, you know.
What we see happening in the game.
So the first thing I want to do is I want to take this target seconds
per frame.
And I want to move it down into the game Loop.
So, so what I'm going to do here is basically say like, okay, what if
I were to set this down here?
Does that create any problems, right?
And no, it doesn't, so that's good.
So if I were to set targets seconds per frame on every frame, what I
could do is I could adjust this multiplier here, which is how many
frames of the monitors.
Refresh rate, we think it will take us in order to safely finish the
work that we
to do before that next V blank, you know that next monitor refresh
rolls around and so essentially what I want to do is I want to
introduce a value here which is like, you know, expected
Frames per update, and I'm going to set that to 1.
now, but if put a suspected frames per update here and what I need to
do now is I just need to be able to twiddle
Value.
I guess we don't have one of those yet.
There we go.
I just need to twiddle that value to be you know 123 hopefully never
higher than 3 because 3 is already down to what 20s frames a second.
20 frames a second I think would be pretty unfair.
Happy as a play rate for a action game, you know, an action game at 30
frames a second is pretty much your your bottom that you'd want to be
at a non-action game.
Not so,
Important, especially not one.
That's if you're in 3D, sometimes it can make a difference because the
I can be frame rate sensitive there.
But for a 2d top-down game, you know, 20 frames a second, probably
fine if the strategy game, but for an action game like this one, if
that multiplier went up to three on a 60 hertz monitor, not so great.
Now, another hand, let's say it's 120 hertz monitor which does exist.
If you had a really high frequency monitor, then three,
He is not such a big deal, right?
Waiting?
Three 120 hertz blanks.
Is not is not an unfortunate frame rate.
So, you know, you could imagine different monitors sort of based
giving us different flexibility in terms of how many frames we can
wait.
So what we need to do now is have some way of figuring out what we
think.
The number of frames that has elapsed is
Every time through the loop, right?
Like, how long did it take us to do the processing that we need to do?
Like, what are we actually seeing as a frame rate?
And so what I want to do is to introduce an actual just straight up
time here and I don't know if we've got yeah, we've got get wall
clock.
So we have the ability to get a wall clock here.
And what I want to do is just have a wall clock, but times are frame
that allows us to adjust.
Now, I don't
If we're using that anywhere already, we might be.
So you can see us timing some things here.
In fact, right?
Yeah, you can see us using this with the, the wall clock B here.
Yeah, so we have we actually have quite a bit of information and we
have like an end counter here that gets the wall clock.
We subtract that from last counter and encounter.
So if we take a look at what's happening right here, this bit of code
is already giving us the information.
We need this.
Win32 get S 2 laps last counter and counter right?
This is our measured seconds per frame.
That right there.
And so with that measured seconds per frame, we actually have the
ability to set.
What if we took a look at what that was, we actually
Have the ability to figure out how many monitor refreshes, we think
went by, right?
So for example, if I just pop over to the Blackboard for a minute,
Here on day 380.
So what I know is that my target seconds per frame so whatever.
I don't know seconds per frame or I guess maybe I'll talk about s
Target, right.
So my target seconds per frame is going to be 1 over, the refresh rate
of the monitor, right?
So this is the monitor hurts so this is, this is
HC.
So my target seconds per frame is going to be 1 over the the monitor
hurts in the best case, right?
Another way to say that is the minimum time.
So in fact, probably I shouldn't say Target, maybe what I should call.
This is the minimum amount of time.
So in other words, if we want to be synced to the monitor refreshed,
which we do the minimum refresh rate for them, the minimum amount of
time we could possibly take in a frame, is one over the refresh rate.
And the reason for that is that
We don't want tearing, right?
I know some players prefer tearing but not in a 2-D game like this, I
sure hope they don't.
So the minamata time, that any sensible thing would happen.
Here is one over the monitor refresh rate and so we want to do is we
want to set our frame Target to, you know, some some other value over
the monitor refresh rate here, right?
This is what we're trying to figure out, so that we know how many
frames to expect to have to
wait, to be able to display the results, right?
So what we're interested in knowing now is we have a seconds elapsed,
we have how many we took for a given frame, right?
And so we want to know is how many of these occurred in one of these?
Right?
So we want to know the, you know, what is the multiplier on the
minimum seconds, right?
In order to produce the seconds, elapsed and that will give us
X that we want here, right?
Another way to look at.
It would be.
We want to know if we wanted to set our Target frame rate to what we
were observing in practice, right?
Because this is how much time we see going by.
We know, this is the equation.
For how much time will we will expect to go by?
How about we solve this equation?
So, the view that we see, however, many seconds we see, we've got the
monitor refresh rate here with our X on top, so that seconds elapsed
times the monitor Reef.
Fresh, right, equals r x.
If that makes sense.
If I did that math correctly.
So our measured time plus X.
Our monitor Hertz is going to be what we think our x value,
I'd be on top there, right?
That's just what that looks like.
And so let's see if that makes any sense what I just said.
So let's say 1/60 of a second went by, right?
And I'm going to multiply by the monitor refresh rate, which is 60 and
I'm going to get an X.
Well, the x value is 1, which is exactly what I would have expected.
Right?
On the other hand, let's say that quite a bit more time goes by than
that.
Right.
Let's say that 1/20 of a second, goes by quite a bit more and I
multiply that by 60 and then
My ex well in this case, right?
All right, I cross these here, I would get a 3 here to divide out and
that makes my x equal to 3 which again is exactly what you want.
Because 3, 60 frames a second frames is 21.
22 of a second.
So what I want to do here is say something like well okay, you know
I've got a Target seconds per frame here, right?
This is my exact target seconds per frame, I guess you might say
that's going to be that measured seconds per frame times the monitor
refresh rate, right?
Exactly like we said there, but the problem is, this is now going to
give me back a floating Point number and I
Can't wait uploading Point number of frames.
Now, if we had G sink or something, or one of the whatever, the AMD
equivalent is of these Saucy gentleman, that monitors that can like
switch it at arbitrary frame rate, then maybe that's fine.
And we just set it to whatever.
But even in that case, I don't really want it to be variable.
So even if we were going to set it to some thing, I'd still want
something smarter than this.
So we could talk about that a little bit later but, you know, in the
case of a normal monitor which most people have
Or a TV set.
It can't flip it, an arbitrary frame rate.
So we need to now round this, right?
And the question is, how are we going to round it?
Well, if we strictly round it up, we're going to get a problem of
overestimating the frame time, right?
Because if you think about what happens, 1/60 of a second is what we
would get.
If we measured it perfectly with no overhead, no Jitter, no nothing
but we're never going to get that exact value back.
When we
The clock.
We're going to get something.
If you know, here's the the graph of x, right?
And I've got you know, 0 S down here and one second here, you know,
and so somewhere in here we've got you know, 1/60 of a second.
We're not going to come back right here.
We're going to Jitter around there even if we're kidding, 60 frames a
second.
The time that we receive measurement wise is going to Jitter around
the 60 frames a second, quite a bit and you can see this happening.
I mean, if we just run the game you can see this happening up here,
right?
So you can see right here that we're just jittering around and even in
the case, where we build in release mode, which I'll show you here.
So let me
Switch us to release mode there.
Even the case where we build and release mode, what you can see is
that it's not always sixteen point six, six milliseconds, which is
what we would want it to be.
Instead it's like jumping all around, right?
And that's just because of whenever our thread got, you know, the
clock back.
And what was the latency on the clock measurement?
And how long did it take to get back out of the driver?
After the fleece blanket and all this other stuff it's just not going
to be a precise value.
So certainly any
Human can look at that and say that.
It's 16, .66, okay?
We're getting 60 frames a second good.
Keep trying to hit 60 frames a second, a computer that just does the
divide.
It doesn't know that it doesn't know how to look at a value and go.
Oh, it's basically 60 frames a second, right?
So what we have to do is put a little bit of logic on here to try and
say, well okay, what is the region around 60 frames a second at, which
we still feel fairly confident that we are hitting 60 frames a second,
not missing, 60 frames a second.
And the answer there as well.
If we were to miss 60 frames a second then we know we should shoot up
to more like 20 or some other frames per second that would be
significantly higher than 16 milliseconds.
Right.
We would expect to to kind of have that a bigger jump there.
So for the most part, it should be safe for us to go.
Okay, let's take a look at what the value is and if it's within a
reasonable region around, a 60th of a second.
That would be fine.
Okay?
So here's what I think we want to do.
What I think we want to do is say well okay, let's round this value.
So let's take a look at the value that we're going to get four
expected frame.
Presented famous for update, and I'm going to call this new expected
frames for update.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to round this value.
That we got back and so this is going to give me a rounded version of
the expected frames for update and that will be something that we
could just use directly write if I wanted to, and it'll have all the
drawbacks that I just said, if I take a spending plan for update and
just set new expected frames for update to it, that should work just
fine for certain circumstances.
So if I go ahead and run here, you can see that.
That, we're not getting any.
In our 60 frames a second version, right?
So that's all working just fine there.
Do do, do.
It looks reasonable.
And the other thing that I would probably want to do is show what the
DT / frame is there as well.
So that we can I don't know why we're still printing those out but we
thought we probably want to Output that that value as well.
The just the DT / frame so we can see what it's going to be.
I don't remember how to use our debug system because we use it so
infrequently.
But let's just pretend that you know we can
Maybe I'll put it here, I guess I want it kind of below.
Well, no.
You know what?
We can do?
Expect a French update debug you through to expected frames for
update.
I don't know if that'll work, but let's just find out if it does.
Apparently, that's not
Do we have?
What do we have up here?
Oh, so I guess we can just say debug value and it will automatically
determine the type.
It's just Boolean since they wanted to be specified.
True or false get specified separately.
All right.
So I think that's all we need to do to show debug value again.
I don't really remember, but let's find out.
There we go.
That should probably be just under platform.
And so, it's only expecting one frame per update, which is exactly
what we would want.
I don't know if we can slow this thing down enough to make it go,
okay, so you can actually see it happening now and it's a little bit
weird.
I'm not sure what the difference is here, but if we sort of look
between frames, you can see that the opengl renderer commands is
taking drastically different amounts of time in these two cases.
You can see it like
And it's like, weird, we must just be on the edge of missing so you
can see us flip from, from one expected frame to to.
So, you can 16 to 30, you can see us like hopping between those two.
And so you can even kind of see, already happening.
What I was sort of saying, we need to why things need to be a little
bit smarter, but basically,
Go ahead and return that on.
But basically this works just fine in any circumstance where we're
hitting the framerate.
OK.
And so I suspect we could also go here and turn this.
To debug, which will reduce the frame rate.
There we go.
And
Imagine that.
We could look at this and see that.
Now, it's picking two frames for update as well, right?
Now, what?
I don't know, and I guess this might just be because of oscillation
is, I don't know why we're getting an in-between Ms value here.
Because as far as, I know, if we told it to wait for the vertical
refresh, right?
If it's a 60 frames a second monitor, then the frame rates should be
Like it should be 16 milliseconds.
I mean just hear me out here.
I'll do it on a calculator just to make sure I'm not crazy but you
know if if we were to look at respect if we're going to go one
sixtieth of a second that's you know one six point six, six
milliseconds which is what we were observing If instead I was to
change it to two vertical.
Refreshes, that's 33 Point, 33, milliseconds and instead we're seeing
something like halfway in between those two, right?
We're seeing like 24 or something like this as the value.
And I don't know how if we're asking for a vertical refresh.
Timed flip.
I don't really know how that's happening, so I'm just going to double
check.
I don't know what we're setting.
The graphics.
The what we're asking the graphics API to do there.
So in swap buffers.
I need to take a look because what swap buffers is going to do is swap
buffers.
Which I don't know.
Where is where is swap?
Buffers, setting the opengl there or something?
Oh right, it's actually just cause I'm saying it should be GL
swappers, but it's not.
It's a GTI call.
Anyway, the swap buffers call is going to take up to the next V blank.
If that's what we told it to do, but I don't remember what we told it
to do wiggle.
Swap interval is the call that controls, what we want to do.
And you can see, in this case, we were passing a one there, which
means we want to flip on every monitor.
Refresh, right.
And so if we take a look at what we get there,
I don't think it should.
There should be some documentation for this summer.
Can I have sec please?
Here it is.
so, as far as I know,
It.
It should be the max.
The minimum number of video frames that are displayed before a buffer
swap will occur.
All right?
So I guess I don't know what whether it's going to swap, as soon as it
can after that, or what?
Because I had thought that there was a negative one value that you
pass, if you want it to do a swap like on the vertical refresh, or if
you missed the vertical refresh, as soon as you can thereafter, I
thought was a like, it was basically, like hit the, the sink if you
can, if you can't, then then tear, right?
And I know this was an extension, that was kind of added a little bit
later.
But I was pretty sure that that was not something that was actually
that you said if we didn't specify it, that would not happen.
But I don't know.
I, that's definitely not what I'm seeing, right?
Because as far as I can tell the frame rate in this case is is very
consistent and it's at 24 frames a second, even though we very
specifically told it not to do that.
Now, what I'm going to do is I'm going to crank this up to two.
Which should enforce a frame rate of 30 frames a second.
Just to see what happens.
And so what you can see here is that again, not 30 frames a second and
I feel like I don't know.
I feel like we're explicitly asking for that and somehow not getting
it.
Let me see here.
What happens in that particular call to wiggle swap buffers there and
just see
I'm sorry.
We're gonna swap interval.
You know, I guess what I would say is where we getting this from.
You know, I don't know that this is where we would want to be getting
that from.
Because maybe we can't, maybe we have to ask for it.
Maybe it's not actually working.
Like maybe we have to ask for it on this particular context because
that's the other context up there that we were asking for it on.
So I don't know, maybe that has something to do with it.
I don't think so but I don't know.
It doesn't seem
To be paying attention to us.
Yes.
Oh I don't know but what I can say is that, you know, from playing
with this value, it sure doesn't seem to be having any effect because
I should be able to slow this thing down tremendously.
By forcing it to wait many frames before flipping, and it definitely
isn't doing that right.
It's not ever waiting any more than one frame, so, I would be
interested to see why that is.
Let's take a look and see if we can gain any insight into what's
happening there because that's definitely very unusual at
As far as I can tell, unless there's something.
Stupid that I'm doing that.
I'm just forgetting about that would cause us to be having that
problem.
So I'm going to just jump to this point in the code and I'm going to
see if we get that function at all we do, right?
And then we're calling it here and you know, I don't know.
We have to look at what its return value.
Is it returned one?
I don't know what it's supposed to return, but presumably one means
they succeeded.
And you can see very clearly here.
It's is an interval set to a value of 2 means that the color buffer is
will be swapped at most every other video frame.
So in theory, that is exactly what that should have done right, at
least as far as I know.
So I wondered if this is actually not quite working.
One thing that could be the case and I don't know, is I wonder to what
extent?
This is because of the sort of not proper thing, we were doing due to
streaming.
So for
Pull the handmade streaming thing here, right.
This is, we were kind of using this illegally and I do Wonder to what
extent that
Is messing things up.
If I turn off handmade streaming which means you won't be able to see
the opengl window.
I think, but I want to see if that likes the wiggle swap interval work
properly.
So, it definitely makes the wiggle swap interval work more properly.
It's still not quite perfect.
It's a little bit wonky.
So I'm not really sure what's going on there, but at least looks a
little bit better.
Let me go ahead and try playing with that.
We go swap interval there.
So I'm going to set it to one now again and I'm going to see what
happens when we run the game.
So interesting enough, the game does not properly use setting to
21, if I set it to two.
So if I set it to two with, with double buffering flag properly set,
which I think means a streaming won't quite work.
Then it does at least mostly tend to hit 30 frames a second but it's
definitely an unusual pattern here and it seems to me like the
measured frame rate is quite wonky.
So for example, I'm just looking at it and I see that opengl renderer
commands takes twice
The time in on some frames than on others.
And I can only assume that as something to do with waiting to flip,
but I really don't know.
So again it's pretty hard to see.
Let me
Let me just verify that you can't see right?
If I if I turn off the handmade streaming you can't see it right?
But what's weird about that is even if I turn it off it's still not
quite right.
And I don't know why, right?
I have no idea what about what is actually going on there?
Why wiggle swap interval is not giving us proper V blanking, right?
And it could just be I don't know.
It could have something to do with the fact that OBS is running.
It could have something to do with the fact that you know, opengl is
poorly supported on Windows.
I really couldn't tell you but what I can say for sure is that it's
not behaving in any way that we can really reliably use because I know
this monitor is not capable of anything other than 60 frames a second.
I don't think, unless that's wrong.
and and I'm pretty sure that's not wrong because
you know, well,
I mean, here's a question for, for us all
I guess I could check to see.
What the refresh rate of this monitor actually is and I don't know
that I can really look at that on here.
Maybe I can let me take a look at what this
Catalyst Control Center thinks is going on.
So, it certainly thinks that the refresh rate is 60 frames a second,
that's what it thinks.
It also, if I'm not mistaken, seems to be drawing off the bottom of
the screen and I can't make this window picker.
So there's that which always is good.
I don't know how that
Happens, but that's great.
So I don't know.
Looking at this if the graphics card thinks that the monitor is 60
frames a second, then I feel like that's all we really need to know
because the graphics card itself, if it doesn't think it's outputting
it.
120 hertz should not be able to hit 25 milliseconds as a frame rate.
It just shouldn't be happening.
So I really have no idea what open jealous thinking.
At this point, I don't have even the slightest clue.
I would like to know, but I really just don't, I don't think there's
anything in here that will help me get any
Further down that.
Road.
I don't know why there's two of these either.
Because I think there's only one graphics card in this machine, but
maybe that's not true.
I don't know.
Well.
So I guess I'm not sure exactly what we can do here.
I mean one option we have is just ditching that concept altogether and
saying well if we can't get reliable waiting back from the graphics
card, which I guess we just can't and let me make sure I turn
streaming back on you.
There we go.
You know, maybe we just try to, I don't know.
You know, maybe we just try to say, well, we'll set, the target will
set the target seconds per frame to whatever we measure, as our sort
of reasonable stable, whatever are stable value, expectation is for
the seconds per frame.
I mean it's not a horrible thing, it's just it it's leads to a sort of
varying frame rate which can which has like micro Jitter that I really
don't want.
And so I want the game to have
Of a predictable frame rate and to stick at 60 and updated 60 all the
time.
And so I don't really know what to do here.
And then that classic way that Windows doesn't like to care about
things like that have real-time applications, it kind of leaves us
with not a lot of options here because I don't really know what we
could do to force the update to obey us and actually, only update on
the monitor refresh.
Unless again, like, maybe I'm
Just forgetting something that we did that causes that to not work
properly or something like this but I don't know.
so looking at this here, where we've got the
Refresh rate.
And where I'm setting this every frame by doing just an integer clock,
grab that there.
Maybe for now we just use a Target seconds per frame.
That's carried over from the free previous one.
I don't know.
I mean, that would look like this.
We're down here.
We just say whatever we got for the last frame time, just use that.
Right.
And so that would be exact target seconds for frame.
And then we would just say like all right, if you're running at 25
frames a second sort of oops that didn't work so well.
Then off you go.
Did I do that?
Right?
Exact target seconds for frame.
Goes measured seconds for frame times monitor.
Oh
This is frames per.
Update.
Again, I want measured seconds per frame.
There you go.
So there is, I guess what would happen if we just use the clock from
the previous frame.
And again the reason that I don't like what I'm seeing on the screen
right now at all.
Is look at how much Jitter there is in that value, right?
It's nuts.
How much Jitter I'm seeing?
I come here.
It's 24.
I come, you know, here at 25, 24, 35, 25 76.
There's just a tremendous amount of Jitter like what's that frame?
Thirty three point seven four.
I don't even know what's going on there and so it's really just awful
in terms of the stability and you could feel that in the gameplay,
right?
I can feel that as I'm driving around, I can feel exactly that.
Just feels a little micro jittery, right?
And so I hate that and I don't want that to be the case.
But again, it doesn't seem like a TI and windows are giving me any
options here at least not on this graphics card on this particular
setup, for actually, making it work.
So we may just have to live with that for now at least on this
machine.
And and go from there.
Hopefully, on other machines.
That would be a lot more stable.
Anyway, if it was coming back at a
All 33 value all the time that would probably be fine.
But again, I really just don't know why we're getting why we're
observing
Result?
Because it seems like it's basically just not obeying wiggle, swap
interval at all.
It's just ignoring it completely and be like, well, thank you for
taking the time to tell me, but I really just don't care.
About what you want to have, be the swap interval.
Now, I guess, one thing I should check is sometimes there's a swap
interval override on these things and I guess I don't know if that's
the case.
Sometimes there's like a graphics like 3D options or whatever.
And I don't even want to know what all this stuff is.
How can I get some 3D settings?
Here people
I do not know what any of this stuff is.
I don't want any of this.
I don't care about video at all.
I like the fact that apparently, like, it has hung itself, just trying
to display the video, the video at all.
That was good.
Well, alright.
Not going great.
If I have to be honest not having a great experience here with the
with the with the drivers not loving.
It is not a thing that I'm doing at the moment.
I don't know how to get the cows control center to give me.
Here, let's try switching it to basic.
So there were 3D settings.
How do I get those settings?
Like we saw them.
But we cannot set them.
I just don't even know sometimes
It's so ridiculous.
Like how is it possible?
Is it, is it down here?
Like in the place that I can't get to?
Because it won't show me what that like, what those values actually
are.
I wonder if wind spy
lets me Snoop that
Look, I don't suppose I can just force it to be bigger.
Yeah, I can't I can't edit things in wins by unfortunately.
It would be nice if you could just force it to send because you could
send a WM size message to it.
I don't know.
So I don't even know how to look to see whether it's doing that.
We could again go back to the basic one and see if the basic one has
it.
Let's see.
Is it just me or like I literally have no idea what's going on.
Like I have no idea.
What is supposed to be happening here.
I don't even understand how you ship something like this.
It makes no sense to me.
It just doesn't seem plausible that you could end up in a circumstance
where they call, this is a thing that has to have some buttons on it.
How does it?
How is it?
So broken, is this?
I have no idea.
Anyway.
If it was possible to see we would look and see because many times the
gravity drive or has the ability to override settings, like frame rate
cap like that.
So, you know, if players don't want the game to run vertical sync and
they prefer the tearing, they can go in and set that.
And so I would have liked to check to see whether the driver was set
to ignore frame rate limiting like that.
Which I don't know.
I don't suspect it is.
And the reason for that is that if we run below the monitor refresh,
it does seem to be waiting
But I have no idea.
Absolutely not.
So I guess,
Got to leave it like it is for now, it's better than nothing but it's
not great because I really don't like that micro Jitter that that that
little sort of wobble in the frame rate is for is like something you
can feel.
I feel it in a lot of games that do this sort of thing, and I don't
like it and I would much rather be locked at 60 frames a second, much
more cleanly than it is at the moment.
But, oh, well, so, here we are playing the game though.
And at least, you know, it's even, I can even open this up, and the
game still plays properly, even when we dropped considerably frame
rate by like, doing a lot of profiling stuff that tanks the framerate,
like, you can see that frame rate is now even less than 30 frames a
second.
But the game is still playable at this frame rate because as I'm
moving it around, you can kind of see it, maintains the speed that it
should have.
So all the entities are updating at the correct rate, which is all we
really need for now.
It's just, that's really disappointing.
That the graphics driver is not willing to play reasonably with those
settings, but that's okay.
We'll just, we'll just deal with it for now and be done with it.
Alright, well, that's
That.
Here is an example of us running at a very slow frame rate.
And again, you can kind of see hopefully that it's still playable in
terms of the correct speeds.
So things are still moving at the correct speeds so at least that's
better than nothing, right?
All right.
Oh well close that up so that's all I really wanted to do.
I just wanted something that would allow us to tune the game properly
and so that we wouldn't be in this situation where every time we were
in debug mode, the the tuning would be off and the speed of all the
things on the screen would be wrong.
I would like to do it better than what was just on there.
I don't like that at all, but I don't really think there's a whole lot
I can do about it at this point.
That's just the reality of Windows sometimes.
So
It's fine.
It's not the worst thing in the world, so it's okay.
And, you know, the other thing I guess I would say is at this point,
you know, the
At this point, you know, we can save that sort of thing for later.
I suppose it really just matters that the game plays at the frame rate
that we think it should play at and you know,
We, when we tune the speeds, they are roughly the correct speeds.
So, as we're making stuff in the game, like the speed of the hopping
or whatever else, it doesn't have to get drastically redone later when
we have a correct frame rate.
So if it's, you know, as long as it's close, which I think it is now
and it just has some Jitter in it, then I suppose.
That's okay, I suppose.
So, anyway, let's, let's get back.
Then to take a look at what's going on with the camera here.
Because I think that's really all that we wanted to finish up.
I don't know.
I guess there's one of the rendering thing we want to do which is, as
we go downstairs, we want to be able to eventually switch to got it.
We got to do work on our hopping to.
It's at this point, I kind of want to play the game because it's you
know, it's explorable but we have so such poor hopping code.
He always thinks that the closest thing is the that sort of
Those things on the side there and there.
So it's really hard to go downstairs and it should be nice and easy to
go downstairs for kind of want to work on that hopping code.
But anyway, once I hop down here, this is the other thing that we
wanted to look at and we could start looking at that soon as well.
Which is the camera is now technically operating properly.
Like this is probably roughly what should be happening.
The problem is, we're not fading out that upper-level, right?
Because we're actually probably at the right place camera wise to play
the floor.
That's
Louis but we can't see the floor, that's below us because of all this
stuff that's in our face right now, right?
So one thing that's, you know, maybe let's start looking at that
because I don't know.
I'm in a grumpy mood because 80 I was you know basically you know peed
on our cake.
It just you know basically just took a big old poop on our ice cream
cake.
We now have got fudgie the whale literally, we've got a TI presents,
fudgie the whale poop cake for our game.
What we what we want to do here is go like, oh,
A what can we do to make this problem go away, right?
We want something that's going to be reasonable, where we can have
something that's you know, as you have elements that are in front of
the camera, they are prevented from seeing what you're trying to you
play with or what you're trying to see for the level.
We want some way of taking care of this and you remember us doing this
manually back.
When we had everything into distorting, what we would do is we'd place
things into sheets, essentially, and we'd Alpha blend out those
sheets.
So, the question now is, can we?
Do something a little bit fancier than this.
Now that we have 3D at our disposal, maybe make it so that that is
automatic.
And so like the fog if you remember we had to do that manually before.
And now the question is can we do the fog that same sort of Tricks?
We did with the fog where they all happen, all the fogging happens in
the trader automatically now can we also do that with this this sort
of notion of
Things that are close to the camera.
And so, what I want to point out, just first of all, is that if we go
to the the code that setting the camera for the game, which is in
World mode dot CPP, we're setting an ear clip plane, right?
And what we could do, obviously, is if we move this in your clip
playing out, eventually, if we moved it out far enough, right, it
would clip away.
The stuff that was in front of us, right?
It would just go away.
I think that may have been a little bit too.
Much think that yet there but clipped away two levels.
Right?
That near clipping plane is actually just a value that we can sort of
scale, right?
And as we move the near clipping plane out far enough, we get into a
place where the things that we did in want to see any more I have gone
away.
So the question at that point naturally becomes well, if we can do
that, if we can clip it away using something automated like this,
might it not be possible.
possible to just,
You know, use that to automatically clip things out from and, and
Alpha fade them in, right?
And there's some issues associated with this.
It's not necessarily going to be trivial.
And what I want to show you, the reason I'm hopping up on here is I
want to show you the the main artifact problem that we will have.
And, you know, we have to kind of think about how we might want to
solve this problem.
But what you can see here is that as I hop up and down on this and
things slowly clip in what you can see is that the the faces peel away
gradually.
Lee, right?
And so that would be our main issue that we'd have to contend with as
we sort of hop hop in on these things, right?
You can you see how they're kind of clipping out like that?
You see how that's happening there?
Right?
And it's it's kind of interesting effect.
Actually to be completely honest it almost makes me wonder if we want
to kind of embrace it a little bit.
I was kind of going to say, maybe we should
Yeah, I was going to say like how do we work around him and I don't
know what to say about that.
At this point, it kind of feet.
It feels almost like a like a good thing.
yeah, I don't know what to make of that, but as a result of that, as
of seeing that, now I'm always kind of wondering what would happen
here if we were to just, you know,
if we were to kind of just Alpha peel that stuff away, maybe that
would be kind of cool.
I was thinking that we wanted to do a more sensible thing.
I don't know.
That's really
Cool.
I don't know, let's play with that.
I'm kind of interested in this.
So let's suppose that we took our near clip plane in the Shader and we
colored the values that were near the near clip playing with a
different like fogging system or something, right.
I'm just I'm just thinking of what that would look like.
So if I went to opengl right now, I've got my renderer here.
For my fragment Shader, you can see here that we've got this, this fog
amount situation here, right?
And the fog amount is coming from the from the vertex Shader, and it's
being computed by taking that inner product with the fog Direction,
and it's producing a fog distance, and then we're clamping.
We're mapping, you know?
That, that fog distance in here to produce this fog amount
And so, what I'm wondering is, you know, could we just do exactly the
same thing with a fade amount and, and fade the alpha out in the same
way?
Right?
So, I guess, you know, the thing that I'm wondering is, we're already
passing out a fraud color.
The frag color has an alpha.
If I wanted to modulate that Alpha, by something that was coming from
the Shader.
I don't know what would that look like?
So here what I could do is say, oh yeah, the
The alpha mount in this case is going to be a clamp.
We already know the fog distance.
And so that fog distance, we could also use the near and far clipping
plane to know.
Well, the near clipping going to start clipping out at at, at 5:00 at
the moment, is what I set it to hear, you know.
So let's say that it starts at 5 and goes to 6 or something like that,
and we'll just modulate the alpha by that value.
So we'll just say, alright, the
Colors output Alpha is going to be multiplied by that Alpha amount.
Again, I'm kind of just making this up as I go along, I'm not even
sure what I'm doing here.
I'm just, I'm just playing around with a stupid idea and seeing what
happens there.
So, that may be a little aggressive.
Or maybe not, I don't know, but it's kind of neat.
It goes a little too far, so I think we want it to be probably tighter
than that.
You know, maybe it's more like 5.25 so it's a pretty tight clip there
like so.
And honestly, the biggest problem with that, at the moment is just
because we're using Alpha to coverage and we only have eight steps of
alpha.
That's mostly what
What we're getting is a downside there.
So unfortunately, it's a little hard to know what that would look like
without the alpha to coverage.
So, I don't know what to make of that.
Exactly.
We kind of want to try one, it would be nice if we had a car that
could do more samples per pixel, like a 16 x or more multi sampling
because that would really be the best thing for us.
So thinking this through a little bit more, I'm trying to decide like
what I really want to do here, I kind of want to play around with this
a little bit more but I'm not sure what direction I want to go with
it.
I may still want to have it.
Be something where?
Look, I may still want to have it be something that that does the fade
in and out kind of moron, an object basis.
I should probably think out loud so everyone else can know where I'm
you know what what I'm thinking of in my mind.
So let me tell you what I was going to originally before I saw that
thing.
That weird sort of peeling effect and maybe.
Oops, I guess I already wrote that.
So let me just say what I was going to do first and then I'll talk
about sort of why I'm now, like rethinking it and what maybe I could
do as something that's more fun than what I was planning originally.
so, what I was thinking of doing originally was saying, well, okay,
so, you know, I've got this circumstance where, you know, I've got
these
Locks on the top level and then I've got blocks on the bottom level,
right?
And, you know, I know that I can make a clipping plane here and say,
well, everything that's below, it is what I'm viewing, right?
Here's the is viewing downward here.
So, these are the things that we're looking at, you know, the heroes
down here.
And this is in the way and I know that I can use the Z value of the
things on the screen to tell me.
Whether you're above or below this line, so what I was thinking might
be interesting to do is just draw everything twice, right?
Draw everything one time with the z-buffer, set to pass things that
are on this side of it, right?
So that I get just the stuff in this buffer and then another one
that's set to pass.
Things are only on the other side of it.
So I get a buffer with just these and then I would Alpha this buffer
on top of this buffer, with a specific Alpha based on
You know, maybe the per pixel depth, right?
Just remember the depth values and use the per pixel depth for that.
But now, I'm thinking maybe we want something fancier,
you know, maybe we want something fancier than that.
And I don't really know.
It seems like maybe we do want something fancier, than that, and maybe
we want to do a, some kind of a per pixel Fade Out, like we were doing
there where there's multiple layers.
So so, how about this?
Let's throw this out there is the possibility and you know, will just
run it up the flagpole and see who salutes it.
So,
What if we did something that was sort of like a depth peel?
It is sometimes called.
So what if we rendered this the whole thing once?
So we just rented the screen and so I'm talking about, you know,
I'm talking about something where maybe we just say like okay let's
let's not do this.
And we just render the screen this way.
So we render this View.
And then, maybe what we do is we say, well, also after the depth after
we do that first render.
So now we have one screen that's like what we can see.
We save the color, but we have the color buffer and the depth buffer
from that,
So we save this so we know every location we know what the Z value is,
right?
So we know what this is.
And the next thing we do is we render again but we keep this depth
buffer in place and say we only want to render things that are behind
like there got to be lower than this value.
So we like pipe the depth buffer in here, you know we also render a
depth buffer here for four depth comparison purposes.
But we also compared against the depth buffer from the previous one as
sort of a like don't
Draw anything that's above this thing.
So this would give us sort of the next layer back of a from everything
that we're seeing, you know, what I mean.
And then what we could do is we could Fade Out that top layer based on
the Z values of the pixels that were in it to whatever.
The next Z value down was
Does that make any sense?
It's a way of sort of getting that sorting.
Without needing to use.
Multi sampling.
Just a thought.
and now that I'm saying it to myself, I'm also wondering
I'm kind of wondering myself.
Why don't people just do that?
instead of alpha to coverage,
I mean in theory, couldn't we turn off multi, sampling all together
and just do to depth Peels and that would be it.
Because it kind of seems like that would be it, doesn't it?
I mean correct me if I'm wrong and again I'm just thinking out loud
here because it's not what I was originally planning to do today at
all.
Not that I really make a plan.
But you know what, I had in my head when I walked in
To the office.
I'm just thinking to myself, like, well, right now we're using multi
sample without for the coverage.
but,
Do we really need that?
Because if I have a Sprite
and the only thing that I'm trying to do here is take these values
that, you know, that are like marginal and blend it with what's behind
him.
Why couldn't I just do two passes where I peel away 1, depth layer.
And then just use the two closest step layers and blend together.
Those in a Shader that actually does a Perfect Blend.
Not an 8-step blend that, that you
It's kind of ugly Shadows like that junk right there.
Mmm.
That, you know, I kind of said before, you know, if we really want to
do that, right?
We got to do something better than that just to begin with.
It really sounds logical to me and I'm trying, I must be missing
something because I'm not sure why everyone wouldn't just do that.
All right.
Well, I have no idea.
I really don't know why you wouldn't do that.
It seems like what you would do.
It seems like it just kind of works and furthermore, it seems like you
could do that as many times you wanted.
I think I'm just going to do that.
It's not really great day for because I have 40 minutes left and
there's zero chance that something that complicated with the GPU in
opengl is going to work in 40 minutes.
It's just not going to happen but I'm going to start that because I
feel like that's just better than what I'm doing.
I feel like that's better than Alpha 2 coverage.
I feel like that lets me fade stuff in.
I feel like
I feel like it's just a win all around and there's not much of a
downside to it.
You might have to make a special concession for translucent particles.
But I think you could just have the Shader, be aware that they were
transition particles, and always peel back to the back, most
translucent particle in your set or something.
And be fine.
So, I think you just want to do this.
I really think you do.
And we're already attaching a depth buffer so we already have the
ability to sample from the depth buffer.
If I were to turn off the multi sampling and just use the regular
drawing, which we already have the ability to do, right?
I mean, if I'm not mistaken, if we just set this to, you know, not be
multi sampled, then you would okay.
Why are we calling?
I thought the whole point was we didn't call gl0.
We're still calling text image, multi sample for the depth component
here.
Let's try that one more time.
So if I want to hear, I can just call GL text image 2D.
Presumably
Depth blah, blah, blah.
I'm not sure what the format for this should be.
I probably just
This needs to be like GL depth or something.
We this needs to be a depth component, we're not actually specifying
it, so these values are meaningless, but let me just check to see what
GL text image 2D wants for a depth.
So the internal format we know.
So we just want this.
So it's probably luminance is probably what it would be.
Let me double-check that and Doc's dot DL.
Okay.
So in here it looks like it's just in the modern versus opengl.
It just as GL read like if it's a one component thing then it's just
GL read write and we don't care about this.
This is the only part that we care about.
So let me just check to see if I can generate one.
That's not multi sampled and we'll see.
And that's just getting this one to work properly.
So all right so we've got the slot type.
With what are the parameters to this?
That I actually care about, let me just make sure the target again
should be
Just whatever the slot is so that should just work.
I don't think there's anything weird going on there.
This should be supported so I think it yet GL, death component 32,
Well, 32f.
Or Jill, definitely at 24.
I don't see 32 in, there is one of the default ones, so maybe we
should back off of that.
Maybe I should.
Ask for something more like that.
Look at the width and the height, the Border value the format, which
is fine.
I assume this is okay.
So I don't know why it's thinking.
This is an invalid operation.
Sure doesn't seem like an invalid operation.
But unfortunately, it won't tell us anything more specific than that.
So we don't know what it actually does not like about that call.
I assume it has something to do with this specification but don't
actually know that that's the case.
So it's hard to sort of guess it's one of the downsides of open gels.
The error reporting on a lot of drivers is really bad.
So who knows what it didn't like, could be anything about it, right?
And so in this case, yeah, death component seems like the correct
thing to ask for with the GL text image 2D, I don't anticipate.
There's any problem with the slot value because that's again, just
going to be Geo texture, 2D, which is what we want and let me look to
see if there's any kind of tutorial version on the internet that would
specify this a little bit more.
Common mistakes which is probably what we made.
Well.
Fortunately doesn't look like.
It does not look like.
It does not look like it when else we got here.
For transfers of depth, stencil or depth sensor data.
You must use GL depth component.
GL sensor detects rgl depth.
Stencil so
In the format parameter.
So it's saying that that other documentation was wrong, or I don't
know.
One of these two is wrong.
So what you're saying here is GL depth.
Component has to be specified here, for transfers are normal.
All right, for transfers and or less interest when we could do much to
use following their vent for attention.
Anonymize RJ to Bubba, Bubba.
Bubba.
Okay.
Let's see if that's any better.
Hey look.
There we go.
So, all right, in this case now that we do not have multi sampling on,
you can see, we're back to our situation of everything, is kind of Z,
fighting with itself, and going nuts and all this other bad things
about which order you do things in.
But we know, we can switch to that mode, pretty easily right where we
can draw and in without having multi sampling on and if we don't have
multi sampling on them and we could if we want to have to frame
buffers,
What we can do is we can draw the whole thing to a frame, buffer
twice, right?
And so I'm trying to think if I need to do anything fancy with deputy
Since I can't, I think for Deaf peeling, I need an additional texture
in my Shader right?
So you know I've got this Shader here.
For the fragment code and that Shader is going to do the depth test
automatically, right?
But what it's not going to do is it's not going to be able to compare
against to arrange, right?
So what I needed to do if I wanted to do, deaf peeling, is I have to
have loops
I have to do something where I say, okay, you know, here was the top
level of stuff that got rendered.
And so I know what that depth is, and that's in a buffer, right?
So I've got this buffer, that's the depth image of the screen.
The problem is after I have that depth buffer image and I know where
all the depths are, I then still need a z-buffer to figure out what
the next layer of stuff is.
So I have to compare against the things that I was drawing down here
to say.
I need things that are greater than them or less than them in Z and I
need them to be going upwards.
Whatever definition we want upwards to be, but then I also need to
read from this buffer and say, oh they also need to be on the other
side of this.
So I need to death buffers, right?
I need the normal depth buffer.
That the graphics card would just manage on its own, but then I also
need the recorded the depth buffer, we record from the previous pass.
So I'm pretty sure unless I'm misremembering how deaf feeling is
supposed to work.
I'm pretty sure what I need to do.
There is actually sample from an additional texture, right?
And that texture has to be a screen space.
A screen space.
So yeah.
I'm pretty sure what that means is that on the second pass through, we
kind of need like some pound if code here.
Right?
We need this, this kind of stuff to happen.
And what we need to do is say well, alright, you know, if if we're in
the other mode of
Depth peeling or something.
Then we need another sampler here.
And and that's a is going to be the screen, you know, that the depth
sampler.
And that depth sampler, we got to get, you know, texture value from
it.
That texture value is going to be the depth that we expect to compare
against, right?
So we need to do
something like this.
So if we're deaf peeling we need to do a depth or rather a clip depth
or something like this.
I don't know if we want to call that but let's say clip depth is a
reasonable name for it.
We want to sample that text the depth sampler and we need here to
sample this in screen space.
Right.
We need to get like the actual like value of the pixel at the location
that we are drawing.
And that's a little harder to do than you.
Might think you would think that that would just be sending provided
automatically to you.
It may be something provided automatically to you in later versions of
opengl in this version of the Shader language that we're doing, which
is kind of an older one to be a little bit more compatible.
I'm pretty sure you don't have it.
So I think you need to sort of generate it yourself.
By using the display resolution and the pixel location and doing that
divide.
So I believe you need to do it that way.
I don't know that.
That's true.
So let's take a look.
Glsl.
Oops, I already had that they're 3.0 quick reference card.
Here it comes.
So, let's take a look here and see what our predefined information is
because that's really what we need is to know the built-ins that we're
going to get.
And so you can see in here like we get a bunch of stuff.
Let me zoom in on that so it's easier to see.
For the folks at home.
So you can see here like we're going to get some stuff in the fragment
language.
You can see that frag cord Point cord.
These sorts of things are all specified for us frag Court.
In this case, it should be the the screen space location.
I believe.
Let me just verify, that's correct.
Yeah, window relative coordinates x y z and 1 over W values for the
fragment.
And so in that case, right?
We know that
Well, let's see here, periodically with the additional and qualify
Universe origin upper left or pixel Center.
Integer, revolvers assume a lower left origin for going to
coordinates.
And as soon as PPL Center is located at half a sentence, for example,
the XY location 0.5 + 5 is return for the lower left.
Most excellent, a window, the origin of jail five, Korean changed the
values returned.
Can also be shifted by half pixel on the whole numbers.
Blah blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
So there you go, right?
That's that's going to give us just a pixel value.
Like I say it's not
Value can use textile wise to look up.
However,
not entirely true since it is an absolute pixel value.
And we know that the viewport and that we're rendering to and our
texture for depth should be the same, right?
We basically want are those the window relative coordinate to line up
with our texture 121 since that's the case.
What we can do here also is used that extra sampler, that takes the
actual integer floating Point coordinates, probably, and just be done.
So,
Since we don't need to blend, we could be off the hook here and not
have to generate these UV coordinates.
Because remember, what normally happens is, when we do a textile look
up like this, we are specifying floating-point values and we're
blending because we want that bilinear filtering.
Like the kind we implement the software rasterizer, but now I think
about it for depth, we're a little bit off the hook here.
Normally, when you're writing these, you care about actually creating
a UV because you want to do sampling a little bit more Civic.
So you have to back it out, but in this case,
And that's the case.
So if we want to
We can just do this textiles.
Fetch is a call that just gets one pixel out, right?
It's like I just am getting just just the color of a particular
fragment a couple picture Texel in the texter.
I'm not going to do any bilinear filtering and it takes an integer
coordinates into the texture.
It's just like here is the pixel value that I want to sample.
So, I think I can just do that, because in this case, I don't ever
need to engage the bilinear blend at all.
So I don't care what the fractional coordinates of.
This thing might be when looked up to do a texture because the texture
is always going to be exactly the right size.
It's a very good special case.
So what I can do here is, say all right.
Just past those through directly, knock yourself out.
And here's the clip depth.
Okay.
So at that point, what I should be able to do is take the Z value.
Now, I don't know how the Z value gets passed down here because I
don't remember.
And it says here that the frag court is XYZ 1 over W.
I'm hoping that means that the Z value is the pre divided.
It's already.
I'm sorry, post divide Z value.
That's actually mapped from negative 1 to 1.
I don't know that that's the case but I hope that that's the case
because if that is
Case, then I can just compare it directly with the values that are the
depth buffer and have a little bit of a party.
Right?
Because everything should line up at that point and I don't have to
think about the spaces that they're in now.
Granted, I don't really know how the depth buffer is going to come in.
In this case again we have to check when we set it to death component
24 does it come out as a negative 1?
The 1 value or is it come out as a zero to one value?
Which is not what I would want?
And I don't know but we'll have to verify that and and go from there,
but
Anyway, so in this case, I've got clipped death it comes out all.
I really need to do now is just introduce a way to discard the
texture.
Rated this card the pixel, right?
And so all I want to do is say, okay, if the frag Z is closer to me,
right?
And, and because it's going to be a less if the fragment Z is less
than the depth value.
That means this is in front of it and I wouldn't want it, right?
So, in this case, I want the frenzy to be greater.
I want the front of you behind, I believe, in this case.
so in the case, where it's behind,
Then we'll go ahead and do.
And you know what?
I could make this easier on ourselves and say, alright, actually,
let's do it the other way.
If it's
if the fragment Z value is either at this depth or behind or closer to
us, throw it out and then continue on
Right.
And that way, it's a nice little self-contained thing up here at the
top, I don't know what this is supposed to be that and so that would
allow us to fetch from a depth.
Sampler, at the location we were at as a another check to see whether
or not we pass as each a test.
In addition to the z-test, we already have to pass about being the
closest thing to the viewer, for the stuff, that's not being peeled
away.
So yeah.
So this again I can just keep going like this to get us a little
closer to where we need to be a next weekend.
We can focus on getting the debt ceiling working.
So let's take a look here at what I would want to do so because I
would now have two different shaders that I might want to run.
We have to extend our notion a little bit of how we're actually
keeping these shaders setup.
Right?
Because we kind of have all this junk sitting in here and we don't
really have any good way of managing it.
so we kind of want something a little bit more, you know, structured
like we probably want to say like, okay,
Here's all the information we were using for this program.
Let's put it all into some kind of a struct like so so that then we
can just say like okay here's you know here's our opengl program and
it's got the program handle.
And then it's got all this other stuff that we need to stay in there,
right?
And in this case, we also have additional things, we might want to
set, which is like the depth sampler ID, but otherwise it's pretty
much the same in both cases.
So then we could say, like, alright, we've got to opengl programs.
We've got the Z bias past 0 and Z by espace one because it be the two,
the two passes, the first pass at the second path or DC bias, no depth
peel and Z by a step peel.
Might be the better way to name them pass.
Zero is one
And in this case, now we want to do is want to compile these in both
ways.
So what you can see here is I actually set us up to build do this in,
not too annoying of the fashion.
You can see that we've got the format string that gets sort of printed
differently here.
It's not too hard for us to compile this Shader multiple times and do
all this stuff by just pulling it out into a little function and
calling it twice, which is kind of Handy, right?
So I can do something here where I say, okay.
Compile, Z bias program.
and we'll just take an opengl program as the target to fill out and
what we do is we just clip all this stuff out here,
And put it in here.
And then what we could do is say, all right, all of this stuff that we
were doing before that's off of the opengl.
Pointer is now it's going to be off of the result pointer.
And in theory, we should have a couple of the things that we need to
do here.
Kind of wanted to focus on this part first.
There we go.
So we need to know a little bit more about the read and write srgb
stuff.
In this case, and then we need to change the names of some of these.
These sausage gentleman down here.
Let's see what we've got for that.
And this all the
Handle.
I'm gonna go ahead and put the program handle into something temporary
so we don't have to do it every time.
So I'm just going to go like Prague equals great program and then I
can say something like this.
And now that should be a little bit clearer.
And the only thing that we're missing is these two settings, the
Shader Sim text, right?
And those were not on the opengl, but I want I'm going to put those on
the opengl because those are actually things we might want to know
often, right?
So, I'm just going to stick those on there.
So that we can.
Always access them.
Because those are just Global things that are like this graphics card
either can do it or can't and everyone wants to know that.
So then all we have to do now is say well alright.
You know to restore the functionality of this.
This thing here, I should probably go ahead and make setting up the
program.
In this way, just be something that you can use in a nice sort of
callable fashion.
So I can do something like this where I say, you know, begin
Program.
Or begin program, use the Jour begin.
Use program.
Again, I don't know use program and something like that and so then in
here I can say like, okay let's go ahead and pull that out.
By the way, where is my little, why did my head?
My little head.
Blocker, go away.
Does anyone know where that went?
Nobody knows.
Anyway, let's just pull this stuff out here.
All of this stuff.
I guess technically, the vertex array stuff.
I don't know about the, I don't know if the buffer data things should
come out.
Into that or not.
That's harder to say.
I'm going to try it like this for now and if that turns out to be a
huge tiny mistake then we'll we'll kind of go from what we'll pull it
back we'll pull it on back but if it turns out to be not as huge of a
tiny mistake then we'll be we'll be okay.
So we'll do use program again.
Then we'll use use program and here
Just just have that.
Do what that does.
Here we go.
Okay.
And so, in this case, what we want to do is say, alright, let's use
the Z bias program.
Yeah.
With, with no depth peel,
and so in both of these cases, like we're just going to pass
the program.
And in all these cases, I think we're just going to go ahead and say
that opengl dot becomes Prague arrow.
And I think that's really all there is to it.
So this needs to get the values from somewhere, which is just the
setup data and that's pretty easy for me to pass in.
So I think I just will
That is just this.
So let's take a look.
If me doing that.
And I don't know that vertex base.
Doesn't get used here.
So I think vertex base is really wants to be left out here.
I don't know if it gets used here either.
It doesn't.
So that's really just dead code.
Probably there from when we were pushing them on an in the other way.
It's like that's about all there is to that.
And in theory, now we have sort of abstracted ourselves away into a
place where we can call multiple programs.
Now, of course, I have to actually debug it but other than that
hopefully we're okay.
So let's see what message says, you have races field because they
operate your crimes are currently active program object.
You know what one of those things that probably helps here is if I
actually went ahead and compile the program, we're not actually
calling that at startups.
Oh hey, there's no program at all, in fact, but that's okay.
So let's go ahead and say can compile xevious program and let's say
that into the Z bias, no deaf peel.
Furthermore, let me compile 1 into Z bias depth peel.
And in this case I'll just say well, hey, there's no DC bias here.
There is a bias here or something like this.
And then what we can do is say, you know, that gets passed in
And this will literally be.
No one or zero based on depth of field, which I think we can really
just do that.
I've got what I call that defined depth feeling.
Got to make it feel.
All right.
So now in theory that should compile two programs for us at one of
which has the deaf peeling in it and one of which doesn't again that's
just in theory, looks like we've got a compile error here, pop
probably on the depth of field code.
No matching reflection texture, fetch
See what the problem is here.
So first of all, I do need to do frags equals GL Francoeur .z and
hopefully that's in the right space.
What I don't know is whether that's complaining about the fact that
this is not an eye Veeck because I don't know, I think GL frag cord.
Yeah, it's actually a veck for.
So I actually need to convert that to an eye Veeck and I don't really
know exactly.
How that's supposed to get done.
I guess I could do this.
Which I think will truncate finisher but it should already be an
integer because we're not multi sampling anymore.
So in theory that should have done it but I don't know if that's what
was actually complaining about or not because it's not very specific,
no magical function called for texture fetch.
So let's take a look at what texture fetch needs to know.
There's probably a couple other things there.
Let me just take a look.
What texture fetch actually wants.
So it needs the LOD to sample from as well.
So mipmapping it's which mipmap sample from and we're not going to
have any of that for the depth buffer, it's one to one.
So I just needed a zero in there, that might be all that was worried
about, it don't know, find out
still doesn't like that.
So I don't know what it's complaining about.
We are passing a sampler.
We're passing an eye Vic to now and we're passing is 0.
So 0.
How about I name the function properly?
That's, that's a good start one might one might think.
Cannot convert from, for component, Vector of float to hypey float.
I don't know what that is.
What is the high P float?
I really don't know what that means.
High-precision, float.
Maybe.
I do not know, but a 4 component, Vector of float, too high P.
Float is, is not something.
I know what that error means.
So,
Oh well, this is pretty obvious here.
Sorry that's just it trying to tell me that.
Hey, the textile, fetch, it doesn't know that I'm going to be binding
a texture here.
That only has one component in it, right?
Like, I'm only buying a depth texture so there isn't an rgba to it.
There's just an R but text will.
Fetch is defined as returning, an rgba.
So I have to tell it.
I only want the our channel, right?
Because I'm only taking,
Just that one value from it.
So yeah.
What you going to do?
Alright so now I think we're at the point where I should probably stop
for the day we are now able to run the death peel or the regular
version.
And so now what we need to do in order and you know I can I can leave
us running in a more reasonable State.
I suppose as well by just taking the renderer here.
In opengl and saying, well, yeah.
You know, let's still keep that multi sampling for now friends because
we need it.
So we'll just leave it like that for now.
I'll go ahead to the Q&A.
There we go.
And next weekend, we'll get the death peeling working because that,
you know, it's going to be a bit of a, just a graphics to bugging kind
of a situation.
I carry Johansson ass while we wait for other questions.
Have you had a good experience with GDB not really?
I guess, what I would say about GDB is GDB I think is a pretty good
debugger from what I've experienced with it.
In terms of actually having all the features that I want
It has like a lot more features than like visual C++ has two buggered.
Does the one that I'm using on stream, right?
The problem is, it's just extremely cumbersome to actually use.
And so the, the human factors involved means that it takes way more
time to debug the common cases where you just want to have, basically
a heads-up display of showing me some variables, why I'm stepping
through the code that is just so bad on GCC comparatively.
That it makes the everyday debugging tasks, a pain in the butt.
But when you actually need to do a very complex debugging task, GDP is
actually usually better, but that's not the majority of the kind of
times that I use the debugger, like usually I'm just using the
debugger to quickly, see a simple error.
I'm not trying to.
Do stuff like oh set a memory breakpoint and record.
Once you hit that memory breakpoint and then stop when you hit a crash
and go back to the memory breakpoint and let me step forward to see
whether they like you know, it has all these features but the problem
is debugging.
I mean the way you think about it is a debugger is just there to save
you time without a debugger.
We could still do it.
You know, people develop software without debuggers even today they
developed software all the time without the buggers in the old days
when they didn't have the buggers.
So to bugger is
is just the only point of a debugger.
It's a save you time is to take a bug that would have taken you to
three hours to find and make it.
Take 10 minutes to find take a bug.
That would have take 30 minutes to find.
Make it take 5 Seconds to find, right?
That's it's just trying to save you time.
In GDB doesn't save you time because it's too cumbersome, like the nut
amount of fussing and the degree to which it does not clearly present
the information in quick to view ways is really, it's problem.
And for whatever reason I think some people try to explain why this
was at one point had to do with how you conduit the data back and
forth with GDB when people make friends to Judy be there always
Very slow and clunky and kind of buggy and stuff.
And so I've never really used a front-end to GDP.
That was able to, you know, clean that away.
But I don't think, you know, I strongly suspect that all the features
for GDP or there.
I don't know if the performance is there, it may be that it's just too
slow in wit and that's a problem as well.
Because again, the point of directors, save you time if it's too slow,
that's not acceptable, right?
So I don't know.
So it's really hard to say, but what I would say is,
No, generally I've not had good experience with GDB.
I have to use it on sometimes I'm platforms.
Like when you're on Linux you kind of have to use it.
You're either using GDP or using a front-end of GDP, one of the other
but I have not had positive experiences with it.
I don't like it and it's and it is almost 100% human factors related.
It's never you know I've never had the experience of I need GDB to do
something and it can't do it.
That's never the case.
It's always that.
The thing I want to do takes too long.
It's displayed poorly.
It's not just,
Contextualized properly, it's too slow to step or to do this you know
it's always human factors not feature.
That's been my experience anyway.
I can't think of a feature for example that Visual Studio has that GCC
doesn't also have actually be doesn't also have
Uplink code or how to stabilize the volume.
Outlines.
You're just talking about the fact that there because of the Z
fighting or whatever.
So, one of the things that we have an issue with right is anytime,
we're drunk, debug stuff.
It might necessarily like overlap, exactly, with with something in the
world.
And so you end up with Z fighting.
Like in this case, where the Z values happen to be right on the edge
of this thing and whether or not it gets drawn first or second to
determine.
So what we would see there and you know may not be pretty.
I don't know what the best way to remove that right now would be
Because I'm not really thinking about it, but obviously, we have some
tools at our disposal since we have Z bias as an option, one thing you
could imagine is, you know, when we do push volume outline and we draw
the stuff here.
What we could do is say that our line segment since they're debug
based information, we could throw a z bias in here, right?
So instead of having all of these things, be at zero they could all
have a little bit of Z bias which allows us to sort of like, pref
prefer that are
Our debug stuff gets moved a little bit for words, so we could say
something like, you know, why don't you just just give all of our
debug line segments, but just a little bit forward, just push them a
little bit forward so they don't see fight.
And I don't know if that's what you were asking.
But now, you'll notice that the z-fighting is gone right?
Because because we push them forward.
It does that does that answer the question?
There's other ways you know, you could be you can be more analytical
about that and if like what you really cared about a ton in in a game
was like getting lines and and solids that happen to go along in the
same place as to render well or stably
You know, there's certainly more you could do analysis wise, but for
our purposes I'm assuming that's fine.
I don't know.
Equal to 87 to follow the rule of writing the use of code.
First, the don't believe that the product is, at a point where it is
better to advance in the game now and when the game Need for more
engine features than go and implement it sort of yes and sort of no I
mean generally speaking one of the problems that we have on handmade
hero
Is, I don't really have any.
You know, we we sort of have this problem of typically, you would have
a game designer and the game designer has designs that you, you know,
would implement or something.
And you can do more of that as you go, you can sort of say, like,
well, alright, let me Implement more of the game and then go back and
Implement more of the engine.
And so on, in our case, we don't really have that because this is not
a game design stream.
And so, to a certain extent, I don't really spend a whole lot.
A lot of time.
Thinking about the game itself, I'm more just think about the game
engine and like I would like to add this feature like to add that
feature and I try to do those in a way that makes sure that we, you
know, right, the usage code or whatever is the most sensible thing to
write.
I try to let it go from there but I don't really have a strong opinion
about the game design side of that because I don't really do that kind
of thing.
And so in this case, no not really like I don't really feel like
that's anything in particular that I want to do.
You know, if other people who are more about, I have a specific game
design and I just want to make the game that goes with that game
design.
The engine that goes for that game design.
You could definitely take that approach and it'd be very reasonable,
right?
Because it, avoids, you doing things that maybe you don't really need
to do because, you know, maybe you find out that they're not very
necessary for the way, the design evolved.
But again, that's really more for I'm an engine programmer, not a game
designer.
And so going past, the engine part of things just puts me into
territory where I'm just like, I don't know, I don't care, right?
It's like, I have no, I have no opinion about how this should be.
I could just do it the way.
The
Even did it.
And that's the game design, right?
So in order to really start having the game design per se, dictate
backwards how the engine works, you have to be more of a game designer
and know more about how that should look for.
All I know, like, having a pretty multi-level fading will will be
something.
I just make happen in the games.
Like, I just want this look, and that is not a game design decision,
right?
That's not
That game designer probably would do.
I don't know, I'm not one but, you know, if I did go, oh, that's a
cool effect.
I'm like, well, guess what, our games going to have multiple levels,
even if it's stupid in the game, is not fun.
As a result of just like, I'm making an engine not a game because I
don't know how to make a game, right?
I'm not a game designer and so, that's really mostly.
Why?
I don't spend any time thinking about the game part of things.
Really?
I just know.
Okay, here's the basics.
There has to be a thing that moves around on a grid.
That's what the engine has to do.
So do it.
And then from there, I'll just be like well the game is whatever the
game is from there and the game, you know, exist within that engine.
And that's all I can really say.
I don't have really anything else I can.
I can offer in the way of advice there.
I think someone like John so if you can, I don't know.
John blows streams.
Tend not to really show him working on a game per se because he mostly
does
The compiler stuff now and some other things like that.
But I guess what I would say is he, he is the kind of person who could
show how to do that reverse process properly.
Because, when he does game,
He definitely does it the way you're suggesting, which is he works on
the design of the game in the engine and adds the features to the
engine as he decides.
He needs them for that, for that game.
And so he would be able to do a really good job, showing how to make
that work, but that's outside of my area of expertise, you know, I
don't do that.
Okay.
Uplink code or clarification.
What to do when the angles are too close together?
Oh, for the volumes.
So again, I think drawing cylinders or something with end, caps might
be the only way to really get them more stable than they are now
because again, we would need something to happen.
When you were hitting them Edge on since I don't care about that
because they're not in the end prior to the game.
They're fine for me right now.
Like I'm totally happy with where they are right now.
Just a matter of the debug Texas during behind the Sprites by the way.
Yes, that's true.
I don't necessarily know what we're setting the Z values for on those,
but one thing that I would point out is we really should just draw
those in a separate pass.
You know, like
If we wanted to, we could do something like this.
I don't really know what this would be.
Exactly.
But, you know, we would say in here, when we come through case
rendered group entry type render entry depth clear,
And then I would just say Jill clear Jill depth buffer bit and so the
depth buffer could get cleared at a certain point and then at that
point we we basically we're done.
Drawing the world, clear the depth buffer because we're going to draw
the debug text.
We want to Overlay it on top, we don't want the depth buffers,
interfering with each other, right?
And that would be all we would need to do there.
So let's go ahead and specify
Well, the header already gets Advanced so that's really all we need.
We there isn't a structure for that, although, I guess we could make
one.
But so then all you would do is you would say, in cure when we do
push, where is it push?
Do do, do do.
So here's our push, vendor element, and our push vendor element.
We could just have a like pushed up.
Here.
And it would really literally just call this and say, I need a clear.
And I want it to push on a render element with zero size.
And this type, right?
And so, then anytime we wanted to like before we do the debug stuff on
here, we could just say, Well when the debug stuff starts going before
it, renders anything else, let's just clear everything out, right?
So let's just say, like, okay in the render group here, we set up the
camera, transform for the debug group, and then we just want it to
like clear everything out of the depth buffer, so that it'll draw,
It on top and then you can kind of see that that just allows all of
this stuff to always be on top no matter what.
And that's probably what we want to do because that way we don't have
to save a z-buffer, you know, Z buffer space for anything or whatever,
right?
I don't know if that makes sense.
Yeah, so let's see here.
Hello.
Do you have any idea when Engine layer will be finished and you just
end you move to just gameplay programming not really but I don't think
there's very much left so we'll probably be doing mostly gameplay
programming from, you know, for you know, probably August on.
I don't know that there's going to be much to do, we probably have a
couple things the engine that will have to get upgraded like we never
really did the Collision detector stuff.
So and and and then we probably need to do something about like the
the
Queries closeness queries.
Those will get too slow when we have more entities in the game.
So some things like that but mostly the rest of the stuff will just be
gameplay because we kind of haven't I don't know that there's really
much else so you know I mean World Generation and that stuff I'm
including gameplay programming but you know, world generation is a big
one, so I don't know if you don't consider that gameplay bringing but
I'm assuming that's gameplay programmer because it's specific to the
game.
Jessie 23.
I'm not sure if the profiler shows some insightful information about
CPU cache, Hit, or Miss rates, how might you implement something like
that?
I don't think you can.
If I remember correctly, the only thing that you you can do is
actually
Install.
If you're willing to install some specific Intel drivers, I want to
say, you can get it, but I'm pretty sure that on x64 normally the
windows on Windows, they turn off the ability to access the cache Miss
information be because I think of a security concern, I want to say so
your can actually get that.
Just enough on a vanilla build like we have.
It is just a feature of the CPU.
The CPU has performance counter information that you can modify.
It might not be for for security.
It might just be because hey it's specific, can't be saved and
restored across.
Apps might be the real reason because you know, the CPU can only have
one set of counters.
I think it doesn't keep per thread counters.
Although you could just save and restore them, it may just because the
OS on Samsung.
I don't know.
I'm totally speculating here.
I don't remember.
All I can say is on other platforms, so let's say you're on, you know,
a dedicated machine like Linux machine or something.
And you're just doing Colonel stuff or whatever.
You can just get that, you can just ask, you can just ask the CPU.
They it has counters.
You can say, I want to know all the level 2 cache, misses and it'll
just count them for you.
And so, you can go look up information without on the web at how to
implement stuff like that.
It's definitely possible and it's just CPU and it's just direct CPU
instructions, that can do it.
The problem on Windows, is that as far as I remember, you can't get
that information without install.
Installing a special Intel driver.
Or being a yet to be a device driver basically so that you can do that
stuff at kernel mode because I'm pretty sure user most not allowed to
get it.
But don't quote me on that.
There may also be a way to get it with like event tracing for Windows
or some other huge heinous API that you don't want to touch, but I
don't really know because you don't want to touch it.
But what I can tell you is that information is very easy to come by on
the CPU.
So, if that's the sort of thing you really care about, you can either
install drivers that will let you query it on Windows or you can run
on a different operating system and get it.
Can the depth buffer contain Infinity as a floating point value.
As far as I know.
Yes, but only if it's actually a floating-point, depth, buffer.
So one thing that you have to remember is the depth buffer has to be
encoded in some way just like a regular texture.
So one way to encode, the death lever is to just have it be a 32-bit /
Texel depth buffer and that will add can actually store a floating
point value.
If you want, you can use depth component through to F and then it's
actually a floating point value with, you know, the mantissa and the
The exponent.
Just like we normally think of one and that probably can store
Infinity just fine because it's all it's doing is storing a float.
I don't actually know that that's true because I've never tried it and
there may be restrictions on the hardware as to what can pass through
where and so on.
So I don't know, maybe there's a caveat there, but what I can tell you
is that Infinity, would not be easy to store in a case, where you
weren't using floating point.
So, say used F component 24, maybe it's not floating point.
It's actually a fixed Point 24-bit, included, fixed point.
That wouldn't be able to store Infinity in any particular.
Ocular way because all of the values are actually used.
So there isn't a way to pick a special value Infinity.
Now you could make your own special value for Infinity by doing
specific stuff to try and make that happen but you know it's
complicated, right?
So you have to understand, I don't know the exact answer to your
question because I've never thought or tried that before.
But what I can say is that while it certainly seems like it should be
plausible in the case where you have a 32-bit floating-point depth
buffer in all the other cases, it sounds a little bit trickier.
All right, I think we're done.
I see no Mark, you colons?
Except for what part of game printed you enjoy the most engine
gameplay, etcetera, definitely engine.
I don't like gameplay programming.
That's why I try not to do it.
I am a beer, huh?
All right, let's close things down.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
go to handmade hero dot-org and pre-order the game.
It comes with all the source code so you can play around with it on
your own.
We also have form something good.
If you wanna ask questions a patreon page, you can go to if you want
support the video series schedule bot that tweets.
The schedule at you.
If you'd like to know when we're going to be live and also an episode
guide, if there's old episodes, you want to catch up on stuff, we
covered that you would
Like to, to see, that's it for today.
I kind of like the step peeling idea I've never really thought about
for.
I'm interested to try it.
So we'll be back next weekend to play around with that and hopefully
see if it if it is a useful concept.
I think it might be, that's about it.
I hope to see you back for, for that.
Have a fun week, programming till then, and I'll see you on the
internet.
Take it easy, everybody.