Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show recoded complete game live on stream here on Twitch.
We don't actually use any libraries or any engine or anything.
We just use Windows directly since that is the standard platform for
games these days.
And so that's what we're teaching on first.
But we try to write all our code in a very portable way.
And in fact, many members of the community have already done for its
to Linux and mac and so on someone even got it running on a
Pick a PlayStation Vita or something.
It's been cool.
So we try to keep our code very portable as well because at the end of
this, we'll be trying to Port the game to lots of different platforms.
We want to make life easy for ourselves, so that is also part of it.
But right now we're in the middle of sort of extending our notion of
what assets are in the game.
Like what, how we store assets, how we process assets, how we can mark
them up in preparation for having basically an asset pack file with a
specification,
Education that we can Define so that we can bring a lot of assets into
the game easily, and not really have to think about it anymore.
So we can just dump as many Assets in as we want and off we go.
So to that end, we've been trying to Define how assets are defined.
How they are looked up in the asset system and that is sort of the
exploration that we're doing right now.
I think we're sort of coming to the end of that.
Like, I think maybe by the end of next week, certainly we would be
wrapped up with any Explorations we're doing and be actually working
on finalizing details of it.
And so, that's pretty good.
But right now, we're still doing a little bit of expiration because
we're not 100% certain all the things we need out of that asset
system.
So we're kind of try to play
And with how we pull things out of it and how we talk about Assets in
it, so we can be sure.
We've got a reasonable first attempt before.
We actually make a sort of a definition and say here is what we want
our pack files to look like first go right before I jump back into it.
Let me just say that it is a 135.
So if you would like to follow along at home, and you have
pre-ordered, the game on handmade hero dot-org, download that Source,
zip and unpack day, 134 source code into a directory.
That is what I'm starting with now.
Now.
And that is what you should start with if you want to line up with me
and while we're at it in the code here,
All right.
So if we take a look at what we did yesterday, we had made a new file
something.
We don't do that often in handmade hero, but we made a new file that
contains all of our sort of temporary asset work here.
So we can start to focus on it and sort of get it into a, you know,
sort of a more, a more robust sort of definition of what, supposed to
go on.
Everything's working pretty well.
I don't actually remember what I was in the middle of doing this, is
the problem of actually
And a ton of other things.
I do every day in addition to handmade Heroes.
I don't always remember what we were actually working on at the time,
but I believe the last thing that we did.
Was we just sort of cheesed in a little thing that would get the first
bitmap out of a particular asset ID.
So that basically we could test to make sure that sort of our asset
tables were working and they seem to be working just fine.
And so now, I think the next thing that we'd want to do to sort of
expand this notion here, we've got really to vet two things we could
choose to add.
Next one, is we could start to work on a raised, the other is we can
start to work.
Con named elements like this things that have multiple Parts like
this.
And I think the first thing that I'm going to do is probably try to
work on the array stuff first because that well, mmm-hmm.
It's it's a question, isn't it?
It's a question.
I'm kind of, I'm a little bit leaning.
You know, I think, I don't know.
Okay, I do not know, but I feel like if I'm not totally mistaken, we
might actually be able to get all of these things.
In one straightforward way like it's entirely possible that we might
be able to do these guys somewhat directly and not really have to
handle these guys in different ways so so I guess I'm going to start
with a simpler one.
I'm going to start with the arrayed one and I'm going to go ahead and
make the arrayed one.
Actually work directly through the asset system.
Now instead of them being pulled out because right now there
About and I want them to go through the asset system instead.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to start to figure out how
we're going to do that.
Now, if you remember our asset types already have the notion that
there's multiple assets for that asset type.
So we shouldn't really have to do anything to make multiple assets
here.
All we need to do is start adding these to our asset table.
Here, we had asset grass, we had asset tough
Puffed and we had asset Stone like so.
And if I want to, I can go ahead and, uh, and start to try and pull
those in to sort of the, the system elsewhere here.
Right?
So what I think, well, you know what, actually, that may have been a
little premature, let's do one more thing first that I think will help
out a little bit.
So if you notice here, we still kind of got this stuff hard-coated,
right.
We're actually using the switch statement to load our bitmaps, but
obviously, we don't really want to do that at the end of the day,
right?
In the, in the final version.
We definitely don't want anything like that going on.
So let's go ahead and push that down into something a little bit more
stable.
Because we know that we have some things that we need to find with our
Maps.
We need a line, X and top-down align.
Why we need those?
Those pieces of information or we need some, we need some equivalent
of these things.
Right.
So let's go ahead and just smooth out that part first because I think
that will make it a little bit easier as we go to move more things in
their groups.
That was not what I want to do.
All right, so let's tackle that first.
So the first thing I want to do is we have this sort of dichotomy
currently with debug load bitmap and and this other one here that
doesn't align percentage of point five point five.
And the reason that we were doing that before is because we
A way to be able to load a bitmap by default but just uses its Center
Point as its anchor in order to know the center point you have to load
the bitmap first, right?
Well what I want to do is get rid of that concept because since we
know we're going to be working with an asset pack file that asset pack
file will already be able to process the Assets in any way that we
want.
Because we're going to have, you know, the assumption is there.
Some art pipeline at the head end of this thing and things come out of
it.
They get packed into the PAC file and during that packing process,
they will.
Set up those aligned percentage things for us that's that's my
thinking on it, right?
And so if we go into the renderer and we take a look in the render
group of the actual data that we actually need for the bitmap that
sanitation.
You can see that all we really needed is this a line percentage.
So what I'd like to do is start specifying that align percentage
directly and that way we don't have any more of this like sort of call
dichotomy stuff, right?
So the way that I
To do that right now is I'm just going to go ahead and and actually
compute those for these guys and then get rid of the sort of
dependency on the size because we can assume that it's going to be
taken care of for us as we go.
So the easiest way for me to do that probably is actually just to set
a breakpoint in the debugger and see what they're currently set to
write.
Because again this this is just sort of a manual process.
We're doing temporarily because we don't really want to deal with the
actual asset pipeline stuff at the moment.
We would much rather just we would much rather just have some sort of
a stand-in that we can do until we get things to find if that makes
sense.
So, when I come in here, after I've loaded all this stuff out, right?
I now know what, all of the alignments actually are.
So I'm going to go ahead and actually read out what those alignments
are.
All of these guys will, obviously all be .5 s, this guy will have
this, this
Alignment done for all of these guys will have to take a look at that
one in a second.
But these guys right here, we'll all be point five, so we don't need
to read them out, but the ones that we do need to read out right will
be all of these guys here.
So I think actually now that I think about it I'll have to let the
game Run a bit first because
Till we actually load the bitmaps in, I won't be able to to inspect
anything, right?
So there everything is kind of loaded in here.
Now we've got all the stuff.
Although now that I think about it we probably also need to issue a
load asset call for all of them at the end here, just to make sure.
So we'd have to do something like load asset.
For, for each bitmap, let's see, tree Rock, Rocco three test test
background, we do use that anymore.
Why is that even in here?
That that's not actually used.
Don't know why that's there.
Let's get rid of that.
Asset stairwell.
Is that stairwell?
Even used no asset.
Stairwell isn't used either.
So really all we've got is asset tree asset sword.
Yes.
Oh, and can we still fire sword?
I don't even remember if we took that out or not, but let's just go
ahead and see.
So, all right, so now we should have everything actually loaded in.
So I'm just going to take a look now and what they are because there's
very few of them and then we'll just copy those in and
Will serve as our stand-in, which is all well and good.
All right.
So let's see.
Trance State assets.
Here are the assets.
Here are the bitmaps, we have eight of them, apparently, so let's take
a look at all of these supposed bitmaps.
Let's see.
So, it looks like we've got one of them is not loaded, but that's
bitmap 0, which I think is what we were expecting, because there's the
null asset, right?
And so, here we go.
We've got bitmap, one bitmap to and bitmap three.
Those are all loaded.
And you can see that corresponds to Shadow tree and sword, right?
And so what I can do here is I can set these, like, you know, a wine
percentage or whatever.
I can set these to whatever they actually are in the actual bitmap.
So here is the aligned percentage here which I'll just go ahead and
copy out, right?
There it is.
So it's a, it's got an X of .5 and it's got a, why of some
ridiculously crazy number which is fine.
You don't really care how crazy the number is, that's the shadow
bitmap.
Then we've got the second one here.
I'll copy that out here.
Align percentage, right?
And that in there.
There's Ry.
And get rid of these now.
And finally,
Let's get this aligned percentage in here.
That is the last guy and there is that a line percentage, and
There we go.
Should be good.
So there we have it and once we are calling the line percentage like
that we can get rid of these guys here, right?
And we can just say we have it aligned percentage once we have it
aligned percentage, this call goes away, right?
Entirely I believe.
And this guy up here can just be V2 align percentage and the Align
percentage can be fault to be the point.
Five point five since that's all good.
And then we
Cure.
This is just going to be equal to the aligned percentage and it's not
actually going to be doing that top down a line stuff at all.
So we can get rid of top down a line like that.
And I should be able to recompile now.
Oops, guess I can't get rid of it quite so soon.
I got one more step to do.
So let's see here.
When we do load bitmap work, we can get rid of has alignment now
because we know that it'll just do that align percentage, so there's
work a wide percentage.
I'm like so and that kind of cleans that up nicely.
And then all these has alignments also can go away because we can just
set the default.
Align percentage actually right here, because we now know what it
actually is, it's always going to be that, right?
So again you can see I'm just kind of I kind of identified an area
where the coded a bit a little crusty because of the way that it had
been written and I just wanted to smooth that out, make it into
something that was more canonical.
If that makes sense and easier to work with.
So I went ahead and did that and we're still all correct.
Now it looks like our alignments are all proper and so on, so that's
good.
So now, what I want to do is I want to take another step here, which
is to stop having to do
This, this stuff here with the test hero, Shadow bitmap stuff, and the
Align percentage.
Although actually, I guess try to think about this here, I don't know.
Actually, if there's really all that much ways we can get anything,
although much cleaner till we actually have a pack file.
It's a little hard to say.
Hmm, it's a little bit hard to say but well
But in the end in the interim I do think I'd like to do this.
It's just the it's a little annoying because of the filename part of
things which we won't have in the actual fact, file file names will
disappear.
And so it's kind of annoying to have to preserve them but that's
actually you know, it's not a huge deal.
So I think what I'm going to do is I'm just going to start
By saying that there's sort of this the bitmap table, right?
You can see here that we had this asset that mapinfo thing which was
going to be something that told us about bitmaps that we're going to
load.
So we could sort of say that for the time being, we actually have the
data that we, you know, currently need for asset map info, right?
And then, what I could do is, I could say.
All right, let's pretend that we have this bitmap info table, that
that's slightly different from the one that's actually going to be,
In the, in the PAC file.
At the end of the day.
But let's just pretend for now that that we can just sort of get up
this data, right.
So I'm going to say that we have an acid pit mapinfo that's just
bitmap infos, right?
And we know that every one of these bitmaps has a bitmap info in it.
So we kind of know that they have the same number.
You know, that there's the same amount of them I could put it into the
bitmap structure, right?
I could put it into the assets, lot structure, if I wanted to, but I
don't
Really want to do that at the moment because I don't know whether or
not this will be something that remains loaded or whether it's
something that will be loaded out in chunks.
It's kind of hard to say so I'm going to, I'm going to leave it as a
separate thing so don't really know exactly what it's going to do.
I'm just going to have it be a parallel array that's indexed by the
same thing.
So it's really no harder to use but it just it's a little bit more
flexible that way in terms of stuff that comes out of files.
So
Oh okay, if I grab these bitmap, infos here, I make, you know, a
bitmap count of them.
What I'm going to do here is now kind of explode, the number of
bitmaps we have just allocate a ton of them because remember this code
is going to eventually go away and it will load that bitmap count off
of disk.
So this is entirely just test code.
How many we set up here?
It doesn't matter what we do.
I just want to make sure that we have a ton of them at the moment, if
that makes sense.
And then what I'm going to do is going to make a function that's like
debug ad.
Map info or something like this, right?
And what that's going to do is that's going to have something in here.
That's like a, you know, debug used bitmap count, something like this.
And that's going to be initialized to zero at the outset like, like
this
And so what I'm doing here is I'm essentially simulating what the
asset Packer would be doing.
And I'm just making a function that essentially imagines.
It's actually doing the asset pack that would have normally been done
offline just so we can have something for testing purposes.
So what it's going to do is for every bitmap that it wants to pack in
here, it is going to go ahead and call debug ad bitmap.
Info and debug add bitmap.
Info will take the Align percentage and the file name and it will
return to you what the actual bitmap ID was of the bitmap that it
added right?
So that's what that's going to do.
And we're going to reserve that first one.
As we often do so.
All right so if we're in here then we have our game assets.
Like so what this is going to do is it's going to create an ID and
that ID is going to be the assets.
Debug used bitmap count, right?
And we're going to increment that so that it just uses them in order.
We're also going to assert before we do so that it was less, you know,
than the bitmap count, the maximum bitmap count that we set
Again, this is strictly test code, so we don't actually need to worry
about how many we support because eventually, we'll just load the pack
file which will tell us exactly how many we need ahead of time.
So we have our debug at bitmap info.
It's going to go ahead and grab us a new ID.
We then want to fill out the actual bitmap info right asset bitmap
info here.
And asset bitmap info is going to contain, whatever.
We just got passed in but you know, the two things we got passed in.
So it's going to be the assets bitmap, infos, plus, whatever the ID
value was, it's going to set the line percentage, and it's going to
set the file name, which are the only two things that Action System
that structure.
And then it's going to go ahead and return that ID to the caller.
And so, what we can do now is,
Can actually make it so that we create these assets sort of, if you
will die, sort of in a dynamic call, kind of a sense so that we can
start to be a little bit closer to what the Packers actually doing.
So if you see here, the way that we're adding this particular guy is,
we're adding assets with a bitmap.
And so what I want to do is layer another function on here, so I can
basically just do this call each time and actually pass this
information for the shadow of the tree and the sword.
Right.
And so what I want to do is I want to do something like this here, and
I believe, if I'm not very much an error, we have an asset none which
is the zero asset.
So, the first thing I want to do actually, is, is on the asset count.
Again, I kind of want to do something.
It is not bitmap count, right?
The asset count should actually be this, right?
That is what should actually the
account going to push that on and then when I need to do here is have
again, a thing that's like,
Debug.
Used asset count, right?
And these are again strictly there for just doing.
Addition.
So we have the assets debug eustass account.
And what I want to be able to do now is say like I want to do add
asset or I should say a bitmap asset or maybe begin asset.
That's actually what I want to do.
So I want to do begin asset, I want to be able to say which asset I am
doing right.
And then I want to be able to do a bitmap for this asset or look maybe
add asset bitmap right and then I pass you know these two guys like so
Maybe this should be called a bitmap asset.
Maybe something like that.
Something like this think that seems reasonable and so that's what I
actually want this to end up looking like just something where I can
now do these ad calls.
So each time I do this it's going to automatically create the super
structure necessary to support all this stuff as if we had loaded it
out of a Pac file again, just simulating that pack file.
So I can see how it would be how it would all work, right?
Then I can, I can do something like this, right?
So yeah.
So this would actually want to work like this, right?
Where we can begin an asset type.
We can Define that asset type.
And we can add as many assets as we want in there and then off we go,
right?
So yeah, that was sword, right?
So yeah, so what I need to do now is actually defined these functions.
We've got that sort of debug notion happening here and I kind of like
that.
So that's kind of kind of go down here as a little thing to do Casey.
These should go away one.
We actually load a asset file pack file.
All right, so yeah.
So what I want to do is make this do what this was doing, right?
And that's should be pretty easy to do.
So let's go ahead and make that happen here.
Are you know, three calls I've already defined again, right?
The usage code first.
I've written the usage code, we have begin asset type.
So here we have that.
Like so we have what we want, the asset type ID to
So there's the thing, type ID.
Like so in this case, let's see we've got a file name and the aligned
percentage.
It's weird that those came in the opposite order here.
I think I want to keep them in the same order always if I can.
So I think I'm going to do it that.
A like, so just to keep that a little bit more consistent.
I don't like having things always go in different orders.
I find to be confusing.
So, there we go.
We've got the line percentage and stuff in there.
That's all good.
We're passing and begin asset, type blah, blah blah.
Yes that's all nice.
And then we have, of course, the thing that ends the game asset.
Okay.
So if we have this and we want it to essentially do what this does, we
now need to take this code up here and break it up into pieces, right?
And so what we can do is we can say, well, first of all, we know what
the type ID is that we're assigning here.
So, what I can do is maybe make something in here that's like, okay,
you know, debug defined type or something like this.
Debug asset type, something like that.
And what I can do is set that equal to whatever it would be when we
start to Define one of these, right?
And what I can also do is I can assert when I do that, this is a
pretty standard construction Mecca, methodology.
If you can only construct, one thing at a particular time, and, you
know, that you're not multi-threaded, right?
You just got of assert that no one else is in the middle of a begin
asset type right here by saying, this has to be equal to 0.
And you know what?
The other thing that I should mention here too is, I don't actually
know why I'm bothering considering these things to 0 because my
understanding was we always said that all this stuff was clear, 20
always anyway so that's kind of stupid that I'm bothering with that.
I should probably stop at that.
That's just the spec of how the initial memory comes in.
I should probably make.
Something here, like a push truck zero, or something like that.
And in fact that maybe something to do sometime soon.
Actually, something in here where we have a push struct to do Casey,
optional clear parameter.
All right.
We'll take care of that a little bit later.
Anyway, point being we'll set that here when we end the asset type we
will assert.
Oops.
This should be equal zero will assert that it's, you know, is actually
valid by the time I get down here and then we'll set it clean.
So we can begin and end in asset type.
So when we actually do this, we have a debug asset used asset count.
All right, assets and asset types, not the same.
So I thought this was a, this was a mistake.
This should not have been that way, right?
The asset type is supposed to be the same as the bitmap count at the
moment, right?
That's actually
yeah.
Hmm.
Well, we'll keep going, I'm having some thoughts, but, you know, I
often have them.
So we have a certain number of assets here and we want to have a debug
used asset count, which we have there and so, that's more correct now,
right?
That's all good.
Okay, so when we come in here, we want to initialize this.
So that the asset type, its first asset index should be equal to
whatever the debug used asset count is right because
That's what it would be and the one passed last should be initialized
to just be like, okay, so it's just the null.
It's a zero range.
Like there's no actual Assets in it, but it's set up for that so far,
right.
Then when you end, I guess there's nothing in particular we would have
to do when you end.
So it's really only during add bitmap assets that the rest of it has
to make some sense.
And so the way this would work is we would have to get an asset.
We'd have to do this work here, but then we'd also have to make sure
that we essentially take, whatever the type was that you were working
with, right?
So we'd want to assert first of all that you were inside a begin asset
type set, although we just crash if you weren't.
So maybe those
Help us at all but you know might as well.
So we go ahead and in here, we take whatever that asset type was and
whatever that asset type was, we're going to take whatever the last
one in the range was and we're going to increment it.
So that's the asset that we're actually going to use right?
And I guess we also need to set this debug used asset account.
So, I suppose actually, the way we could do that though is just do
that in here, like so, right.
So, that's going to be the new used asset Camp.
Okay.
So we go ahead and we start setting those assets.
Inside the asset, we set the tags to nothing and then we want to
actually set that slot ID.
The slot ID is going to be the result of whatever.
You know you know this call right.
So we're going to
Bitmap that the person asked us to add and that's going to be the slot
idea because that's where you would go and get this thing right.
Let's see here.
Type first asset into X actually want.
Well, I guess I can do it this way.
So,
Debug used asset count.
All right, so I realize that's a little bit complicated, so we
probably want to step through it.
Anyway, even if there weren't any bugs in it, we would want to step
through it just so you can take a look at it probably.
So let's go ahead and see if we can
Set a breakpoint there at allocate game assets just so I can sort of
show you what that's doing.
So in we come here and we start this sort of situation, I'm going to
go ahead and make the call stack a little smaller here so I can see
the asset structure a little bit more.
So, here's what we've got, we have a couple different things in play.
First of all, we have our asset types array, right?
Then we have our assets array, and then we have our bitmap
Map and bitmap infos array, the bitmap info is the one we're filling
out.
The bitmaps is where they'll go when they're actually loaded, right?
So, let's take a look at these, and let's see what happens.
So, when we begin this asset type, we're going to go ahead and grab
out of assets.
We're going to grab out the one that corresponds to Shadow, which is
one.
So we're going to grab out this one.
We're going to take our used asset count, which at the moment is
Zero.
Although I feel like we should kind of reserved slots for that as
well.
I feel like, I don't know, just just a hunch.
So that zero is a meaningless value.
But so in fact let's just let's just do that.
I would like to do that.
I think, you know, so we can say here
Debug choose bitmap count, debug used asset account so that we just
leave that zero slot as like a mail slot.
It's doesn't cost us very much to do that and I feel like it makes
things a little easier.
Oops, little too far there.
Okay, so taking a look at it again.
So we come in here, we grab that out and we grab out the asset type
which would correspond to this one.
We set its first SS at index 2.
Whatever the debug used asset count is, which is one, you can see it's
set the first set index there, and then we set the One path the last
asset equal to one as well, right?
So we're saying there's like, no assets and it right now, but if there
were going to be one, it would be.
Number one would be the first one, right?
So then we try to add a bitmap
That first we got to pack up that V2.
We grab out the assets, whatever is the one that that is the sort of a
pens to the end of the asset.
We're currently working with, right?
So there we appended one on and we push that index up.
We set the tags for that guy, and remember, that is one of these guys
in here, that's going to be asset one, right?
So we set that and those are both already 0 but were clearing the
matches.
In case we then have the slot ID for debug bitmap info right?
That debug a bit.
Info call is going to add a bitmap info into our bitmap info array.
So that's going to add it into.
Well, we'll see where it's going to add into.
I guess we figure out what idea we're going to add.
It's add one, right?
That's the first one because we're reserving slot zero.
So there's that first one.
And in, here we go.
All right, let's get that bitmap, info.
That corresponds to Ivy, we just picked.
Let's set the file name which we did.
Let's set the Align percentage which we did and let's return that ID
back.
And so now that the slot ID here gets set to correspond to that bitmap
info that we just sent out, right?
What's your name?
So yeah.
All right, so that's all good.
And then when we go to end assets, really all we're doing is just
finalizing.
This by saying, the debug asset count should be, at least, however,
many we added that guy, and then we're going to set that asset type
back down to zero.
Okay?
So now, let's go ahead and run it and as you can see, thankfully, we
are working just fine.
We've got our little
I will trees in there, which is what we wanted, and we're loading
everything fine.
So, let's go ahead and now push a little bit forwards.
Now, that we have this ability, let's push a little bit for words and
see if we can get.
Our grasses are.
Tufts, are these sorts of guys working that way?
So, what I want to do is say, I want to begin an asset type.
I want a bit in the beginning asset type grass to play with this guy a
little bit.
I want to take that, that sort of grasp, it map name.
I want to add that.
Now, using the system that we have in place, and this time,
Add two things to it, right?
Because we have two different graphs, that maps that correspond to the
same asset type.
They're two different grasses that we have right?
Unlike these guys where we were only specifying one bitmap.
So I'm going to make that work that way.
And then I'm going to pull this out of here and turn it into one of
these.
Right?
Because we already have that asset grass on there.
And so what that'll do is that'll Force compile error.
That'll Force compile error over 0 function is not take to Argus,
looks like I didn't put a default on their should have.
Here we go.
So what I want to do now is just forced a compile error, back out here
where we were doing this asset grass stuff here, where we were doing a
random Choice, sort of a situation.
And so what I'm going to do, I'm not going to do anything.
Particularly complex her will probably want to do something a little
bit more complicated later.
But what I'm going to do here is just say that stamp
Um you know this this this stamp here, what I want to do is get an
asset, I want to get an asset ID back, sort of at random from the set
of asset ID.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to first of all say translate
this, I'm going to I'm going to comment out the stone when here and
I'm going to say that instead of a loaded bitmap stamp thing here I'm
going to say that we have a bitmap ID for the stamp, okay?
And then I'm going to say that that bit
app ID for the stamp is going to be random asset from right?
And I'm going to pass the game assets and I'm going to say that I
would like you to pick a random asset using this series that
I have this random series, I'd like you to pick a random asset from
the set of assets that you have.
As long as they are of, you know, that, that type that I have here,
the grass type, right?
So look through the grasses that you have and just give me back a
random one and I'm not going to do.
I'm not going to do any of this anymore, and then when we go to render
it here and we do this little stamp thing, it's going to use the, the
ID based stuff in the it's going to.
It's going to use the
Debased drawing instead of the bitmap base drawing, right?
And so then what we have to do is we have to take this random asset
from and translate that over into our sort of load asset our whole
regime here, right?
So it's kind of a kin to this guy, this get bit first bitmap, it's
basically the same thing only instead now of just getting whatever the
one that happens to be first.
Instead, we're going to go ahead and get one based on picking.
Random value, right?
So, if I take this random series here,
We have.
And maybe that to make it look more like the other call, maybe the
random series should come last like that.
So, let's do it this way.
I think.
I like the look of that better.
It lines up a little bit nicer.
So here we go.
So we go ahead and grab out that asset type assuming that there
actually is arranged in the asset type.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to say, why don't you do a random
choice?
so, we have here, like,
Random choice for these two.
These two values basically tell me the range, right?
So, I've got a count here and the count is the range between them,
like, so,
That makes sense.
So, what I want to do is I want to figure out
Some random one that's inside the count of these, right?
So I want to choose among the the ones that I have available.
I then want to grab that one out and return that as the slot ID.
Right.
Let's see here.
Random Choice.
Can I cover everyone?
That's right now, it's already appointed so that I believe should give
us a random vote.
What happened?
It means set a breakpoint there.
Guess that was an old break.
Oh, dear.
Well
That was awesome.
Well, we're definitely picking an asset.
I just don't think we're picking the right asset to say the least.
That was pretty funny.
You have to admit, that was that's pretty funny.
All right, so we're still lining up with trees in our asset grass for
some reason.
So let's go ahead and debug that.
That that is.
That's pretty great though.
I kind of like that.
That's, that's pretty great.
Okay?
That's sometimes bugs are, you know, sometimes bugs are frustrating
and other times bugs are just kind of fun and silly.
All right?
Sorry, where was I?
So, let's take a look here and see what our tables actually look like
just.
So we can see if we've done anything obviously stupid before we try to
debug this in sort of a heart of your way.
So, okay, right now, we know that what we've got in the the asset
thing here, asset grass, right?
We know that it's this one here.
Number five, right 0, 1 2 3 4 5, right?
So notice this guy, so that means the first asset index there is going
to be 0.
Nice.
Yep.
I can already see the bug.
Didn't even have to step through it any further than that and I
already know what the bug is.
Yeah.
So it's the assets.
Obviously we have to still add the first asset.
We picked a random in that count there.
Do we have a random between
I don't know if we do random made, random random next, you into random
Choice, random you lateral render between we have a random between
right here, but I don't know if it includes the max or not.
Let's see.
Min plus random next Max Plus 1, minus min.
So it actually it actually does include the maximum value which is not
really what I wanted.
So I'm going to leave it this way.
Let's leave it this way.
All right.
So that seems that seems same.
Let's see how we do here.
Okay, correct me if I'm wrong but my trees have disappeared.
Do you see this?
Are you seeing what?
I'm seeing?
My trees, my poor, little trees have disappeared, right?
They're gone.
They're totally gone.
I do have a idea, by the way of what this probably is, but
If it's not one thing, it's another sometimes.
So there's thing that we have not talked about yet.
Oh wait, no.
But I haven't done this yet.
It's just not.
Okay, nevermind.
I don't need to tell her I was going to say, there was a thing that I
was going to be like, oh, I got to talk about this thing because this
could be what it is.
But now I think about it, this this has nothing to do with it because
I haven't actually done the thing that I was about to say.
So there's no way that I could be it never mind.
We didn't get that far yet.
Anyway, so yeah, so why am I not seeing any trees?
First of all I feel like that is a little bit odd what you say because
I don't understand why I'm not seeing my trees, my trees should be
there and I don't quite get why they have have disappeared from the
face of handmade hero.
So what I want to do first, let's just let's just take out the
round chunk filling entirely here.
Sadek Foo equals 0, if boo.
Equal 0.
There you go.
Are you happy now?
Compiler?
Let me just see if the trees are there.
So the trees are there if I don't try to render those ground chunks.
So what's going on there?
The act of trying to do this, the act of getting this random asset and
pushing the bitmap.
So if I didn't do that, right?
Then, we'd be fine, right?
So the act of doing that push bitmap is causing us to get a load asset
to occur.
Now that I think about it, did we ever actually bother to make that be
thread safe and so on?
I don't actually know if we did, let's take a look.
Let me see here.
What we've got load asset asset there is load asset.
Somewhere.
There is a call to load asset within the renderer
load asset.
Huh.
What did I did?
I what do they call that function?
So it's load bitmap asset, duh.
Yeah.
Alright are just little bit map, I guess.
So if we call that load bitmap function,
I want to see.
Whether we're all multi-threading friendly here and it looks like we
did actually do this in a way that tried to be thread friendly there
you call platform at entry to do that little bit map, work, 0 and 0
and this stuff here should is.
Yeah.
Okay, so I forgot to actually go in here.
It has been a long day.
So we did all that bitmap info stuff.
We're not actually using it right.
And it says what the ID that we wanted the bitmap to be, was we never
actually store it.
So what we want to do, right?
Is we want to get rid of this.
Stuff that we had here and we want to just go ahead and push just this
information on none of this other stuff.
Because once we get in here, we don't actually need the aligned
percentage or the bit, the bitmap file name anymore because both of
those things are actually going to come from the bitmap info table,
right?
Because that's what the whole point of it was.
I don't know why I forgot I just like, totally spaced.
You know, sometimes that's the way it goes.
So what we really wanted was this right
We wanted our bitmap info to be on assets in foes, right?
Oops, what happened first and then we want to use that work, orders ID
value to get the, to get the particular bitmap info that we're talking
about here and then we want to look at what the things were on that.
That's how we actually wanted to do it right and and so that's what
should have been happening.
And and so now we can at least debug the actual program we were trying
to write and not some other program which was totally different.
Okay?
So, let's go back there and re-enable, the thing that was causing us
problems so we can start to track it down.
Now that we have code, that's at least ostensibly trying to do the
right thing.
And okay, so now the question is, why are we not getting any of our
bitmaps when we call load bitmap from inside our other thread here,
right?
Why are we never getting anything to load at that point?
What is, what is the problem?
And so what I'm going to do, I guess there is I'm just going to set
load bitmap that load bitmap call.
I'm just want to take a look at what's going on in there just so I can
see ID value is 0 on push bitmap here.
Phil ground chunk random asset from.
How are we getting back?
A 0 from here?
All right, so I guess I got to start by De bugging this a little more.
Really because that's doesn't make any sense at all.
So, we come in here, we take a look at the count for grass, chunks.
We get a count of two.
We take a look at the Choice there, which was one.
So then we have a particular asset and that asset is slot.
ID 0, how is slot ID 0, ever being a thing.
What did I mess up?
Obviously, I messed something up.
Like with the debug a bitmap stuff.
I obviously
Did something stupid.
I'm just not sure what it was.
That makes sense.
Did I forget to assert on a size somewhere in here?
I don't think so.
I tried to be relatively careful with that, right?
We've got all these guys lined up.
We've got the assets and the bitmaps in foes.
Yeah.
Alright, so yeah, so let's take a look at what happened there so I can
see it.
So, here's our assets, I'm going to go ahead and just take a look at
all of them, right?
Oops.
I'm just going to look at sort of a set of assets and see what
happened.
So we start setting the slot IDs and then when we get up to assets
that are past number five, we just simply stopped sending them
entirely and so I'm not certain what exactly is going on there.
That's a little bit weird.
So yeah, let's let's see what happened there.
Let me jump up here.
Let's take a look at this.
We've
Set 30, but that's really all that should have been set.
Looks like, right?
So we're adding one in their slot for let's take a look at our take a
look at our asset types here, so 4, Type 4 and 5, so that's what they
should have been and there's the slot IDs.
Okay, so now let's go ahead and jump in here too.
Random.
Grab out that asset type.
Take a look at the type except the one.
We think it should be yes for 26.
Here are the assets.
There's four.
There's five, right?
It's, it's type.
First index plus count.
Let's see here.
Count is argh, man.
Just a mistake filled day.
Today, obviously, you don't want to add the count because that would
be at the end.
That's just super stupid.
We did that thing to pick choice, right?
Oops are my assets.
We did all this work to pick the choice and then we add the count,
which, of course will put us into no-man's-land.
So yeah, that's not very bright.
There we go.
So let's take a look.
See here.
All right.
So now we're back to being useful.
I'm not sure though.
I don't understand.
I feel like we still have some aspect of the bug that we don't totally
understand here because I don't understand why that always being zero.
I don't understand why that would have.
Aid.
So here's what I'm guessing happened.
I'm guessing that that somehow know.
I don't know, I can't think of exactly how
I can't think of exactly how that was forcing us to have all of our
get first bitmap ID stuff fail as well, right?
And I'm trying to think of whether it flooded our q but I don't see
why it would have flooded the queue because if you're trying to load
nothing it doesn't ever add to the queue, right?
I mean if it's a slight idea is zero the bitmap ID is 0.
It's just going to fail to load immediately.
I would think so we should test that out a little bit and figure out
what's going on first.
I'm just going to go ahead and
and finish this off here.
So that we can have ourselves a a working.
Array set here.
There we go.
Is this Stone?
I think guess.
Do a bitmap asset.
So now we can at least have these guys in here.
Operating properly.
and we can have our, we can kind of get rid of these guys and
correctly have are
Our stuff work this way.
So, okay, we've got a bitmap ID stamp here.
We've got random choice to stamp, equals something from the grass
array.
Otherwise, it's something from the stone array.
In fact, I guess we could say that.
It's just this right, random choice and either it'll pick asset,
right?
We're assets tone and then it passes the series, something like that,
That seems fair.
This guy here again, bitmap ID for stamp is just going to be a random
Choice, random asset from trance State assets.
And it's stuffed, right?
So asset tuft.
So that's all good.
And now if I run this in theory, it should be able to build those
chunks.
I don't know if it actually does or not.
Not a good day here for working for handmade hero stuff.
Working on the first try, you know, sometimes we get really lucky.
Other times, we don't still got two minutes left on the clock.
But all right, so now we've translated everything properly and we
definitely have a bug where where we are not properly, sort of
flushing things or something stupid, you know, we're doing something
dumb.
Ah,
I see what we're doing.
Well, we're doing one thing.
That's particularly dumb.
This is what it is.
You guys see it already on the stream?
I feel like you guys should always be faster than I am because I have
to talk this all the time and you're just watching so you should know
what it is.
And that is that if we fail because we have something that isn't
loaded yet, we still we suck up a slot.
We never actually call end, right?
We never free up our tasks live again.
Because we did this thing where we wanted to abort the task, but we
never actually aborted the task, right?
So, the task technically was just sitting there kind of pseudo running
forever.
Which is not what we want.
We want to just abort the task and say don't do this.
Once those tasks Ops fill up then we can't load anything anymore,
right?
So I think that's what we actually want to do if I'm not mistaken.
All right, so let's take a look here.
Can we actually end the task with memory from in here?
I think we can write.
We can testimony although although the machine thinks we can't and
tasked with memory.
Memory flush.
What why does it think that that was was bad?
I'm not exactly sure.
Begin test the memory trance state.
If task go through and try to do whatever it is that we're going to
do.
So let's go ahead and set a breakpoint there, right?
We've got our task.
Nah, it's just not set up yet, sorry.
Memory.
Yes, I think that that totally explains.
I'm glad that we went and found that because like I knew something was
weird there.
That was not right.
So what we want to do is we want to set this stuff up the render
group, The buffer, the task stuff, we want that to to be set.
We should probably just set it.
I don't know why it wasn't being set up here when we actually have the
information.
Seems like we want to do that.
I don't can't think of really any reason not to do that.
Because until we call platform at entry, it's not actually going to
ever get looked at.
So I feel like that's what we wanted.
So I think that's safer.
Anyway, just in general so that we don't have that problem.
Okay, so now we're working, okay, although I still
Maybe there was some kind of a bug there potentially, I don't know if
all of our assets are actually working properly but we're closer,
right?
And now we've kind of gotten to that nice place.
We're now the game code doesn't really know anything about our assets
anymore which is exactly what I wanted to be.
At least there's there's still a couple things we haven't done yet
like we have to tackle these hero bitmaps but now we've gotten to the
place where everything is kind of actually just a structured set of
information.
And so now the
Game just talks about things semantically like it wants a some grass.
It can go and ask for that and it doesn't even know how many there are
or where they're coming from.
It just knows them trying to fill some grass and I can get it.
And that's exactly what I was trying to do with this.
So we're definitely getting closer to where I want to be but we still
need to talk a little bit more about how we're going to actually pull
things out with tags and stuff so that we can actually start talking
about these structured assets and also about matching like types of
grass and stuff like that.
So that seems like what probably the right thing for us to start
working on next.
So I'm going to go ahead and call it here and we can go to the Q and
the a.
So if you have a question that you would like answered, please put Q:
front of it, so I can see it and try to, please, try to keep it to
stuff.
We're working on, so they can be on topic.
Let's see.
What do you mean when you say to write usage code first?
Also, is there any special handling of asset 0?
I am unclear on this.
So what I mean, when I say right?
The usage code first is, I mean, don't write the API for something
like don't write the calls and the structure of how it works first.
Write the code that's going to use that system first, right?
See how the user wants the thing to work?
And then write the thing.
And so that way, you'll be guided by the the side.
That's actually the one that's going to use it all the time rather
than having whatever you happen to Think Through in here, be the way
that gets exposed.
So, right in the usage code first is really, really important and I
always Advocate doing it especially because when you think about when
you write a little piece of software that's you know a little piece of
code that's going to be used throughout like the game.
You're going to write that once and then possibly hundreds of places
in the game are going to use it.
So if you write the way that it gets used by just like thinking about
the thing and implementing, the thing you are potentially sacrificing,
hundreds of people's use case, right?
Hundreds of places, use case for
You what looked clean right in that little one space.
What you would rather do is write a couple of those use cases out of
100 see what they want the thing to look like and then write it that
way because now a hundred people will be clean.
And only one person will be potentially messy.
If it has to conform to some way that it wants, you know, that the
other people want it to work, right?
That's always the way that you want to structure it as for the special
handling of asset zero.
I just want 02 mean nothing so that when people talk about an asset
they could say zero meaning there is no asset.
Like if there's a particular thing that
You know what asset should I display when the person wins the game and
it says zero means, there is no asset to this play in that situation
or whatever.
You used some, you went through to Tea in t here, instead of you and
32.
Argh, it's different working on different code bases, makes it a
little bit hard to keep that all straight.
let's just go ahead and
see what the situation is.
All right.
Are you expecting a new batch of art from Yankton?
I actually have a lot of art from your action, but it's more about
when I you know, decide to
You know, process it and put it into what we're working on.
Are you going to eventually downgrade the graphics to stir up some
controversy and get the game talked about on neogaf and Reddit?
Well, sure.
I mean there's no such thing as bad press, right?
So I think there's a number of things that we should probably do if
we, if we want to stir up controversy.
So, yeah.
I mean, clearly, we should downgrade the graphics at a minimum.
We should probably also, like, accept money from somebody to be
exclusive, right?
Like, you know, get get someone to get some console vendor to pee.
Off to not release the PC version.
On time we should have like some kind of a like you know,
discriminatory selection of characters or something like this.
There's there's all sorts of things we should do to generate.
Press.
So yeah.
Well just would have to make a big old list of all of our controversy
generating things that we can do and roll them out there.
What are some example changes to the gameplay that we require changes
to the tags?
Gonna go ahead and say I'm not sure exactly what that means.
The tags are more about describing the asset that's there.
And not really necessarily about the gameplay per se.
But you know, if you added some gameplay stuff that needed other ways
of describing assets, maybe that would require to start adding new
tags to things, right?
But yeah, I'm not sure that the gameplay in the tags are necessarily
the most coherent things to think about.
What certifications do I have?
I do not even know what that means.
Although recently because obviously I manage the office for Molly
rocket.
I had to like certif certified, get myself fire training, certified
and stuff like this.
I had to like, do a bunch of online things to certify that.
I was like a floor award in or something like this, that I knew what
to do in the case of emergencies and all this sort of stuff.
Do you feel sleepy when it's taking you a long time to solve a bug?
Sometimes I feel sleepy and it takes me a long time to solve a bug
because I'm sleepy.
But I don't know, I feel sleepy because it's taking a long time to
solve a bug.
Are you going to show the asset pipeline tools programming on stream
know, I've talked about this before, we're restricting programming to
just the game and that was just because I had to pick some manageable
boundary for things.
And so asset pipeline is like a whole different domain of programming
that has very little to do with the stuff that we're talking about on
the Stream.
So what we're going to do is we're going to spec our day
To file format which is kind of what we're in the middle of doing
right now.
And then I will separately take care of producing a pack file that
complies with that format.
As if you were handing it off to your asset guy pipeline guy, or
whatever, and being like go right,
I miss the pre, seems you talk about apis.
Like you said, you would on Twitter, I did not say I would on Twitter.
I said, if someone remembered to ask me about it, I would and no one
asked me about it so you didn't miss it.
What reason is there to use size T other than in 32 or un 32?
So size T is when you don't know whether you're on a
For a bit or 32-bit platform.
And you want to talk about how big something is in memory because in
in 32 or an N64 is talking about with you have a 32-bit or 64-bit
integer, right?
But if I'm talking about the size, something takes in memory, how
would I know whether I need a 32-bit or 64-bit or talk about that?
If I don't know, whether I'm on 32-bit or 64-bit memory model, right?
So size, T is just a type that you use to talk about something that is
that can hold a value.
That's the size of something in memory.
And so on 32-bit systems, it will be a 32-bit integer on 64-bit
systems.
It'll be a 64 bits.
So, you know, you always can rely on it to be big enough to
Hold any memory size thing.
Do you plan on implementing HTC Vive and Lighthouse support for
whatever reason.
I don't know how we can really do that with a 2-D game.
So, no, because you kind of need to at least have some idea of what
you would want to have happen in 3D before, a Vive would really be
worth it, right?
If you asset pipeline won't be done on stream, will you still release
the source for it?
No.
So we're like asset pipeline is not in the product at all, like it's
just assumed that there is a data set and the data set will be, you
know, part of the game.
But how that data set gets made?
I don't even promise that something that will compile on other
people's machines, right?
Like, it's just, it's whatever I want to do separately to make sure
that we produce something that matches.
Description that we have.
But obviously will make the description on Stream.
So, anyone who wants to build their own pack file.
It's not going to be like rocket science, right?
It's just a bunch of things concatenated, together in a file.
So it's not exactly something that's hard to reproduce, but, you know,
I may use a bunch of proprietary stuff that I, you know, I've written,
like my Photoshop parser and stuff like that that are not going to be
really like those are not public domain things, so they won't be
included in the
In the release at all.
Will you do is separate isolated session on databases mentioned
yesterday.
I would love to hear your thoughts on that at some point potentially
but it's kind of involved topic.
So, I don't know when I would be doing that since obviously, I've
Of handmade hero to get through.
And I don't know that it's like super pressingly valuable that I talk
about the problems of data did with databases at the moment.
Will you talk about apis now?
Yes, I suppose I can because we don't have it doesn't seem like having
any of it.
Other questions about what we were doing programming wise.
HTC is handing you five hundred thousand dollars.
Are you doing Vibe support?
Now, you know if ACC wants to hand the handmade hero project, half a
million dollars to support Vive then sure.
Right I mean I'll happily go ahead and I mean provided they allow me
to program it on stream, right?
Like I'm not going to add Vibe support to the game if they won't let
me like if there's some kind of endianness that would prevent me from
programs dream but
Sure for half a million dollars weed at it.
But again, I say, what would we add like, what do they?
What it's know.
Who would want to play a 2-D game on a 3D headset?
Like why would you do that?
I don't understand, I don't understand why you would want that to
happen, right?
Like, I guess we could make the characters like kind of stand up a
little bit like cards and tilt the backdrop a little bit, I don't
know.
It just seems like a really bad idea.
So yeah, for half a million dollars, sure will add support but I just
don't understand why they would even want that.
I don't understand why they'd want to pay 50 bucks for that.
Let alone five hundred thousand.
Will you accept chromatic aberration as the best post-processing thing
ever conceived?
No.
I will not accept that chromatic.
Aberration is in my opinion, a bad visual effect.
It is, it is not so there's so there's visual effects from cameras,
like chromatic aberration their visual effects from cameras that
Into the category of positive image technique that you actually use
for a purpose and cinematography and they're ones that pretty much
just don't except in really rare circumstances and chromatic
aberration is in the don't category like basically chromatic
aberration and lens flare.
Krakow tration lens flare and vignetting are the three that come to
mind basically.
Like any competent cinematographer is trying not to have happen pretty
much 100% of the time like once in a great while they'll do a very
specific shot that maybe takes advantage of some of those things to
achieve, some very strange thing that they're trying to do, right.
But by and large are very much trying not to have those on the other.
And like, hey, latian, and and depth of field are examples of things
that they use specifically in almost every shot where it could be
applicable to do certain things with the image.
And so those I consider to be positive, post-processing effects that
you do want in your pipeline, if you can, if you can afford them,
right?
The chromatic aberration.
No, no, no no.
Let's see.
Why do you support direct input 8 for supporting good old USB
controllers instead of just Xbox 360 controllers, we probably will
actually but again the platform layer is really just stand-in.
At this point, we will switch back to working on platform layers when
we are done with the game and are doing kind of our shipping work, and
because there's a bunch of things we don't support right now in the
platform layer that we probably would want to write.
So we probably will support, I would guess.
Anyway, we probably would support direct input.
Eight, as well as.
As xinput.
If the people in this chat collectively give you 500,000 dollars.
Will you implement VR?
Sure, but where are they going to get five hundred thousand dollars?
That's a lot of money, dude.
Half a million dollars is a lot of money.
And why would why does the chat want to pay half of?
Nobody seems to understand?
Just how an interesting it would be to add VR2 handmade hero.
I do not understand why they would even want that.
It just doesn't make any sense.
Okay, so I'm supposed to talk about apis.
I think and we have some time left.
So I should probably do that.
I'm just trying to see if there's any other questions here.
Let's see.
Okay, so what I was talking about with apis.
So I'm going to go ahead and close this down here.
So what I was talking about apis before I feel like we at some point
installed depends, did we not?
I feel like we did but I don't actually remember if we did or not.
So I don't actually know.
I don't actually know if we actually did, let's find out.
In program files.
Did we ever put this in here?
Program files, depends depends, depends.
All right, so let's just talk about API stuff for a second here and,
you know, it's extremely long topic.
I'm not going to try and cover hardly anything, but I'll just try and
give you a little bit of background on the stuff that I was talking
about on Twitter.
So here we go.
See here if I can actually use this.
Okay.
So here is if I actually go in to to handmade hero, right?
This is the game that we built.
And we were very conservative, right?
So you can see in handmade hero.
This is, if you don't know, depends, it's a program that says what
system Services, you're linking to basically, it basically shows you
all of your Imports that are things, you have to call, right?
And so we call user 32.2 LL be.
GDI 30 to 80 lb Colwyn multimedia, dll and kernel32.
Okay?
And that's it.
So in order to run our game whole game, that's all we needed.
Okay?
And we don't call any other services from anywhere else except for X
input, which we load dynamically.
And if it's not there then we just don't use it right?
So I'm pretty sure that's basically I don't know if we do any other
live virus I don't think we do, right?
So, if you think about the way that you would want your software
ecosystem to work, what you would like to do is you'd like to make
sure that basically you have a few, you have a small, well, defined
set of apis that you plan on supporting for a long time and that work
in a reliable way, right?
And so one of the important ways that you would, you know, that you
should a mindset, you should be in, right?
Is that if I have something like handmade here which has, you know, a
small handful of actual Imports.
You know, the number of imports is probably like 20 or 30.
It should be pretty straightforward to see how those things are
actually connected up in the system so that they're easy to maintain
from version to version.
And like when you come out with Windows 8, you can just make sure that
you support these things properly and all that sort of stuff.
Right?
You want a small set of well-defined apis that.
You know, have reasonable behavior and that are easy to link through
to explicitly so that there's no confusion, right?
Now in the old days when you ran this application, you would see
basically like just this like you would see just what we're looking at
right now because the operating system was implemented basically as
just, these few dlls there were not that many and the dlls themselves
really just only relied on a few other dlls like Colonel like you know
user 32 ft LL would rely on colonel.
2 dot, dll, or whatever, right?
and then,
And it's like if they just kept doing this, I do not know why.
At some point Microsoft decided that because they had had some
problems with compatibility with dll stuff.
What they were going to do is start adding all of these layers of
complexity on it year after year.
So they started introducing all these new Concepts like side-by-side
assemblies in API sets and all of these things that greatly complexify
trying to figure out what is even running and what is even being
linked to when something loads.
And so now, when we come to today, here is what you are.
Actually talking about when you're talking about how your program
Links at runtime, are you ready for this?
Look at this, it's absurd, right?
Like there's just all this nonsense in here for a game that hardly has
any thing going on.
Like check this stuff out, I don't even know.
Like I mean, it's crazy.
A single individual would have absolutely no idea.
What was even going on here, right?
Like you'd have no clue what was going on.
I used.
To be pretty straightforward.
You be like, here's the few things I call from Colonel.
Here's a few things, like all from user, that's all it needs.
I can totally think and reason about what's going on here, right?
And so that's, you know, that's the situation that we've sort of
backed ourselves into now and that's for handmade hero, which is
extremely conservative, right?
So let's take a look.
Now at something, that's not so conservative.
Okay, let's take a look.
Now at the kind of software that.
Microsoft ships.
So let's go in here to program files, right?
X86.
And let's go in to see about for example, their IDE, right?
Dev I think, is it?
See if I can load that?
All right, well I guess we can't really do that one.
Well, it couldn't actually parse the whole thing I guess, but this is
what we're dealing with, okay?
And it highlights two things, one that it's absolutely ludicrous,
right?
Like what,
These things are not abstract.
All of these things actually have to be in place, have to be the right
versions have to be functioning properly in order for this piece of
software to function, right and that never actually happens.
So to give you a very simple example on my witness dead machine which
is one that Johnson up for me, it's a laptop on the version of Visual
Studio that was installed on it.
You could not move the panel's around if you try to move the panel's
around, it would crash.
And I went to the website to look up the fix for that and they said
there is no fix for that, that's just some machines.
In the state and we have no way of fixing it.
I swear to God.
That's what it said right.
And that is exactly this kind of circumstance that is the mentality.
That is the software development methodology that you end up with when
you have this many moving parts that all have to work.
They don't somebody at some point will accidentally do something that
breaks this one thing here, right?
And then suddenly your app crashes, when it tries to do this thing or
it can't
run run because like something wasn't found, right?
I've even had this happen when we do the Indie, Mega Booth, I actually
have a little thumb drive, I bring around.
That's got all these dependency, installation things on it, because
invariably some poor developer brings the build of their game that
works just fine on their machine.
They try to run it on one of the Indie Megadeth machines and they
can't because some crazy side by side.
Assembly installation from the DirectX, runtime from June, 2013 wasn't
installed in the right order and so it's got the
Something and blah blah blah and like so I go in there and I put the
thumb drive in and I run through the install process and eventually we
hit the one that puts the right deal on the right place and the right
side by side assembly lined up and all this stuff and then it's okay,
right?
And this is just not a sustainable ecosystem.
It's why stuff just never runs right on Windows anymore and it's awful
it's just terrible and so it highlights that Ridiculousness that you
just you should not be writing software that requires this many other
dependencies to be correct.
It's
What you're asking for the kind of poorly behaving, software that you
do, end up getting in practice, pardon me while I close all these, so
we can see just the top level ones, all right?
And again, that it didn't even wasn't even know the parcel thing, but
it also highlights another thing.
Which is that you now?
Because their stuff is so full on crazy.
Depends can't even parse the whole dependency set anymore and even
tell you what is missing and what's not, it can only give you partial
information.
So for example, if we take a look at this,
It doesn't think that this actually exists.
It doesn't know where to get this guy, right?
It's like I don't know what's going on here, right?
We can't find it.
We don't know what it is.
But when we run this program, it works right?
So obviously we're it's not actually the case that this is an actual
problem and that didn't used to happen, right?
Like, who knows what's this?
I don't know.
It can't load it.
Who knows where it comes from, nobody knows, you know, maybe it's on
the drive somewhere.
And again, these are from IE framed dll, which is some system, utility
blah, blah, blah, right?
So at this point, I don't even know how to use.
Depends to look up dependency stuff anymore.
Like I don't even know.
It's so crazy town that if something doesn't work on a machine it's
like I almost can't even really help in the old days I used to just
load up depends see what the missing dependency was and then it was
just like shooting fish in a barrel it's like oh it's missing.
VCR.
120 that dll good.
We'll just go get that.
Will put it in place.
We just copied into the directory that the executable has and then we
can run and that would work, right?
You could, you could repair a broken installation.
Trivially, just by doing that nowadays, forget it because you can't
even install stuff into the side by side assembly stuff.
You, I mean, I don't even know how to do that, right?
I have to go learn how to do those things just to even repair it
anymore.
It's not as simple as just copying the files around anymore, right?
So this
Is not a sustainable model and it's why Windows is so darn unreliable
anymore.
It didn't used to be this way, right?
I mean, yeah, Windows was never like some Panacea or Utopia or
anything is true, but it used to be much more reliable and he 351 to
some extent mt4 to some extent Windows 2000, but, you know, pretty
much even as soon as nt4 things started going downhill, they just lost
that concept.
That you need a clean direct API interface.
Easy way to tell.
What are the dependencies are and and it's just been a complete train
wreck since then, not to mention the fact that they added all these
other things like manifests, which are completely unnecessary.
And I don't even know why they decided to do it.
That just complicate the deployment complicate, the build dependencies
complicate the runtime dependencies in ways that have just made things
worse, and they never seem to go back and assess it and go.
Wait a minute.
The old way we did, this was actually always better.
All the stuff that we try to do is help has only been
Hurting maybe we should stop adding all this complexity on the things
that discussion never happens of course generally.
And so that's the thing that I was complaining about on Twitter.
It's super bothers me because Windows used to be the stable platform.
It used to be the place where stuff ran every revision, the your old
software still ran.
And now that is so far from the case, basically, even new software
almost guarantee ably won't run on a system, unless you run a VC
redistributable.
Install first, I mean, it's just a end of DirectX install.
So there's no such thing as like copying executable to Windows machine
and running it anymore, unless you're like me and are super super
tight about your dependencies and build stuff specifically so that
doesn't happen.
Almost all commercial stuff, I see.
Canyon cannot even run new on a Windows system, it has all sorts of
dependencies baked into it that you have to go get redistributed as
for and that's like what the game's installer or whatever does when
you initially run it, and that's just ridiculous, right?
It just doesn't make sense.
It's not a sustainable.
All way of running an operating system and we see it all the time as
stuff continues to fail and continues to be this whole ridiculous
morass of like, which version of this do you have?
And did you remember to install this and did you patch the blond and
it?
Right.
It's awful.
So I don't like that.
And that's why I'm handmade hero.
We were very, very careful to make sure that we didn't do any of those
things.
We don't use manifest, we don't use side by side assembly or any of
that stuff.
We intentionally made it so that it was a straightforward as possible.
So that
Almost any system, no matter what side by side, assemblies were
installed or what version of whatever you had was installed.
We would work and we have more to do along those lines that we should
probably do.
So we're not like perfect or anything yet.
But even from the outset, we tried very hard to not lean on any of
that stuff because it is very, very unreliable and extremely poorly
maintained.
So, hopefully, that gives you an idea of what I was trying to talk
about.
And there you go.
Seems to me nobody at Microsoft.
Has any idea about why Windows is still even working properly?
Well yeah, and I mean, I feel kind of bad, I don't know, you know, I
don't really know anyone who works on Windows anymore for the most
part, but I strongly suspect and I could be wrong.
But I strongly suspect that there are still some good Windows kernel
guys there.
And I honestly feel kind of sad for them because the windows kernel, I
don't know that much about how it's in today, but just back in the day
Windows NT kernel was pretty good and did a lot of smart things and so
I feel like people really kind of crud it up.
A good thing that people at Microsoft had made and I don't know if
they feel upset about that, but I feel upset on their behalf because
it is not true, that Microsoft is like a monolithically, stupid
entity.
That is not true.
There are, or at least were very smart people at Microsoft, who did
some very smart things.
And so, it's unfortunate that those people are kind of drowned out by
The mediocrity surrounding them, in that sense.
And it really makes what would have probably been a very good
operating system that could have lasted a long time, much worse.
Right?
And so I mean it's kind of an unfortunate lesson but probably a lesson
worth heating which is that, you know, your operating system is only
good as its weakest link.
So if you let the user layer,
Where everyone's working, get credit up by mediocre programming.
Then it strangles, in some sense.
Perhaps, some very good programming, done by, you know, you're Colonel
guys or whatever.
Right.
And so, you really do run into this this circumstance.
Where if you don't, if you don't really maintain the Integrity of your
operating system through the whole, you know, the whole stack.
Whoever of that stack are the are the lousy programmers.
That's how lousy your applications will actually be because no amount
of a great Colonel can make up for the
Fact that none of the software works because the dependencies are on
or whatever.
Right.
Nobody can fix the fact that the Windows registry is complete
nightmare like no doesn't I don't care how good the kernel is, it
can't reach in and change the fact that the registry is a complete and
utter nightmare, right?
And so that's, you know, it's a really tough thing and it is
Organizationally a really big problem, right?
Because if you were looking and saying, how do we do this better than
Microsoft?
You're like, well, you know it's a really big undertaking because it
means having such meticulous attention to detail at every stage of the
pipeline.
It's no wonder that nobody has really been able to come and do it
because if you need, you know, if you think you're going to build this
really big operating system with all these people
How are you going to make sure that none of those people are going to
crap it up, right?
Like it's real hard and so so yeah.
In some sense when I get angry about this sort of stuff to, I'm like I
said I'm kind of angry on behalf of the colonel guy because if Windows
was just universally awful and it had always been awful then you know
I'm not that upset, right?
It's like okay, it was an awful thing, it stayed awful, it's awful
now, whatever, right?
But I don't really believe that I
I really enjoyed using NT 351, I really did and I thought it was a
pretty darn good operating system, to be honest with you.
And so I feel like the reason that it saddens me quite a bit is I feel
like a lot of the changes that have been made to the Opry system over
time.
Have really taken something.
That was honestly, my preferred platform and made it really pretty
lousy today and
And that's too bad, right?
Because that's like losing a really good operating system instead of
just never having one.
And that feels a lot worse in some sense because, you know, it could
have been right?
You know, it could have been great and instead it's really pretty
lousy.
Let's see.
Isn't the huge amount of dependencies and inevitability of complex
software looking modern full OS for productivity desktop.
I don't think it is, I really don't.
And the reason that I don't think it is is because like I said, if you
go back to NT 351 and then you look at you know Windows today
If you look at the difference in capabilities of the operating system
layer, it's really pretty minor, right?
Like, if you take a look at the number of capabilities, the US has
gained versus the amount of complexity.
It is introduced.
It's staggering to see the difference between those two.
Things, right?
It's kind of like, they added, you know, a million extra complexity,
and got twice the functionality or something, right?
And you have to ask yourself
Do you really think that's inevitable?
Do you really think that there was no way to get 2x the functionality
of Windows 351 without making it like that much worse?
And I really don't believe that was true, right?
I believe that you could have done a much better job.
Yeah.
Maybe it couldn't be as good because it has a little bit more and
there's growing pains and all that stuff.
But no, I mean I think that they could have done better and I suspect
it's because they just didn't have, you know,
They had too many teams that were mediocre just doing whatever they
want and being allowed to ship it and that just proliferated the API
count and proliferated the API problems and they never had that kind
of tight control that maybe you know like the colonel team was
exercising when they were actually thinking about what they were
making and and shipping a decent API or whatever, right?
And so I think that you know, it's really that it's just a cultural.
That was a cultural problem.
L'm that if they had had a solution for it, we're, we're like shipping
and API at Microsoft was like a privilege, not something.
Just anyone could do.
And you really had to go through a battery of people who would just
pound on you to make sure you really needed to and that you did it
right.
If that had been the culture, I don't think we would have been in this
mess, right?
But that was not the culture of the culture was just like any old
teams could start up and ship these things.
If they got any political capital and then it's just n, you end up.
With eight billion of these things.
ActiveX indirect show and all these nightmares and they're just in the
API set.
There you go, like that's out there, right?
Someone thinks that a side assembly is a good idea and poops it out
calm.
All this stuff just gets you know, kind of pooped in there and I think
that if you don't have an organization, a systemic organizational way
that you restrict changes to the core feature set of the operating
system, only two people.
Who are extremely competent have API design experience and know
exactly what they are doing.
Then you end up with the situation we're in today.
Do you know that your channel runs ads for an Esports gambling site so
my I don't get to control what what channel adds, get run on my on my
feet obviously and I make no money from twitch at all.
I make no ad Revenue whatsoever.
So I am not running any ads.
That's just what they run.
And if you subscribe to Twitch, then you won't see.
Ads.
And so I'm okay with that because, you know, if you choose not to pay
for the service then you know, and they want to show you ads and
that's fine.
If they didn't give you a choice to subscribe and not see the ads.
I would probably be upset about that but since they give you that
choice, I think that's fine.
They don't charge much for the service and they are handling all of
the distribution and broadcasting of the series here.
So I'm fine with that.
It's a reasonable deal.
All right, I think I'm going to wrap it up.
Yeah.
All right, I think we're good.
I'm going to go ahead and wrap it up.
Got a good API rantin, they're always fun.
All right, everyone, thank you for joining me for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game and handmade here at Oregon.
It comes with the full source code every night after I'm done.
I upload it and you can download it and play around with it and
experiment with it to your heart's content.
Tent again, he could do that he made here at or you can also go there
to see about our forums which place you can ask questions about the
series if you're trying to follow along and you have some questions
about previous episodes stuff like that, it also has a annotate
episode guide which members of the community have been working on
which allows you to kind of jump around to thing's pretty cool.
And there's also ports to Mac and Linux and stuff like that community
members have done.
So if you're trying to follow along another platform at you need a
little bit of help, there's some source code there.
There for you, that you can probably get you going.
We also have patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, always much appreciated.
We also have a tweet bot, the tweets.
The schedule at use of you're trying to catch the show live.
That's the place to go.
We'll be back here next week on Monday.
To start taking a look at how we can maybe expand our asset system.
That's kind of working relatively.
Well, now, kind of expand that into something that can represent a
richer set of data using maybe some of those tags ideas that we put in
there.
And so,
We'll try to Port the hero over to that and do a couple of other
things that will sort of.
Let us see whether that's going to work or whether we need some of the
things in there.
So that's what we'll be doing next week, I hope you'll join me for
that.
Again, it's getting kind of fun to kind of knock, all these features
off of our engine checklist.
It's starting to get pretty respectable and I'm pretty pleased with
it.
So hopefully you are too.
And yeah, and I hope to see you back here, Monday until then have a
great weekend, everyone.
And I will see you later.