Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here.
The show we could complete game live on stream.
We are doing.
We're really, let's be honest.
This is a bit of a beautification situation.
We're doing some beautification.
We cleaned up our layout code yesterday, and we're sort of making our
debugger UI a little bit nicer.
To use.
We added like a bunch of features to it over time, and did a ton of
work trying to figure out like, what?
The right architecture should be.
And I kind of used the system as sort of a way of showing how to
No exploratory, really build.
You know, an architectural structure that can support a large number
of Fairly intricate operations.
And now we're just in the the phase of kind of like finishing up it to
our satisfaction, which involves, of course, putting things up and
making the UI more usable in places where it needs to be.
But also another thing that we need to do is just print out data and
more useful ways and stuff like that.
So those are the sorts of things that we'll be doing and that's what
we'll be doing.
Again today we
still got a couple more days.
I think of putting those features in there because well, just in
general.
I feel like
We already even just the very basic thing that we did, where we showed
the profile bars, the first time it ever was on the screen, we already
found a bug in xinput.
Right?
That we wouldn't have known about.
So having like a lot of ways to visualize what's happening in your
program, the parts that you can't see is really pretty valuable and so
you want to have some of that there now.
Ideally, you know, you build a library like this and you can use it a
lot.
So,
You don't have to do it on every project and the other thing you can
do to write if you want stuff like this.
Is sometimes there are packages out there that you can buy or use that
help you, with debug code.
And one of the nice things about that is since, you know, the, since
the debug code compiles out of the game and doesn't ship with the
game, there's less risk in using some external package or some, you
know, third party thing or even in reusing your own code from from
Project to project.
Because it's
Not really on the critical path, right?
If there's like, heinous bugs in the debug layer, or it's super janky,
or whatever else, as long as it gives you the things that you need to
see that's enough and it won't adversely affect the users experience
because it's not ever running on the user's machine.
So that's kind of a nice aspect of it as well.
And it means that you can sort of like cut Corners as you need to or
other things like that.
And so yeah, I showed you how to make one care.
Surgery.
A lot of stuff that you can do in a debug system.
You're free to decide kind of what level you want to do there.
You know, or the obvious thing like I said, is, you know, you can turn
it into sort of a library that you use on every project which I think
would be a good thing, because debug code tends to be fairly similar.
So, you know, it's a, it's that's the basic idea and all we really
You do now is kind of get it to the point where we're happy with it.
So today is day to 66 and so if you want to follow along at home, you
want to unpack day to 65s source code.
That's what we're starting with today.
So,
if I load up handmade,
And I launch it.
Should see all of our stuff that we have.
So where we stopped yesterday is we have these like buttons and I put
some backing on them and now you can, you know, play with them and
stuff.
We can pause.
And we can move around and things like this and that's all fine.
But I guess the only I'm trying to think of like, what sorts of things
I want to do before we move on, you know, this stuff all is
Be reasonable and I can move.
Around on these and look at more specific things.
But I think really the main thing that I need to focus on because I
think we've got most of the other things here.
The main thing that I would want to focus on for finishing up here is
making this profile window.
A little more making the profile window more useful in the sense that
you know right now the rendering of it is still a little bit janky and
it's it's not so it's not so clear like you know
We currently are only drawing.
One level deep.
I'd like to draw on more than one level deep here.
Like we already had that but we turned it off.
Maybe make these solid bars and outline them in black or something
like that.
So it's a little easier to see, you know, just go through here and
really make this easier to use.
And also I want to maybe put one more button here which is just like a
top list which is more the standard profile or view, which would be
something that would kind of, let us see like okay for a given
function, like whatever function we pick.
Or rather, not forgiven function.
I should say more like across all functions who is taking the most
total time, right?
And have a way of looking at that in a sorted view.
So you know, be able to sort a list by that if that makes sense and
that might be I'm kind of in the mood to see that information, I think
that's something I might want to look at.
So I feel like that's a maybe what I'll start with today is just
adding another
Which allows the profile to show that piece of information.
So I'm going to go ahead and
make that happen here.
And I also want to double-check something to make sure that we're act
that it's actually working the way that we want it to work, which is
that in handmade CPP, my intention anyway.
When I wrote this was to allow myself to create multiple different
types of
Profilers really easily and leave them open by default.
And so that would be like in this situation here.
For example I want to make sure that works.
Okay and it does and that was just me making sure that, you know, if I
wanted to, I could make these these sort of, you know, get created by
default.
And they are probably a little too big because we might have multiple
of them up there.
Like I said, at any given time.
So I might want to go in here and say, like okay, this Frame bar
graph.
If and, and the thread into the graph, I want these to be it in
general.
I want providers to be a little bit smaller.
So in here, when we specify that, it sort of default size, I'm going
to make them not so Hefty.
So, we'll maybe half their default size so that they don't, you know,
that's a big.
Alright?
So, again, kind of nice and both of these are also switchable, which
is really great.
So,
Like I said, I'm really happy with kind of the way this is working.
All of this stuff has been pretty great so far and I'm pretty happy
with it.
So, that's all good.
So what I want to do now is add that little top view here, like a
thing that sort of shows us are sorted list.
And in order to do the thing that shows our shows us our sorted list,
that's probably going to be a thing which just you know again is
another one of these types.
Probably something like top time, you know, top clocks graph or
something, or tops, clocks a list, probably.
In top clocks list will actually just go through and print out a line
for each of the functions and that'll be that right.
Now what I want to do here is I would like to take a look at the code
that we have for sorting because we already wrote code for sorting
things and I'm interested to know if I can just sort of pull that code
out and use it again exactly as it exists.
So
Not have to redo the Sorting code.
Now, I don't really remember much about how we left that.
We, that's our sort key stuff, but I don't know where our actual sort
itself.
Is let's see here.
These are just the things that fill up, our render group, where is our
actual render.
There we go.
So here are sort calls and they work off this thing called tile sort
entry.
Now, tell sort entry is the thing, which tells us what, basically two
things, it's a sorting key and a push buffer offset.
And what you can see immediately about that thing, is that really if
all
Doing a sorting a bunch of those.
There's no real reason that this has to be a stylist or entry.
It's just a sort entry, right?
So, as long as we wanted to phrase, the sort key, as a floating Point
number, and the push, and the thing we're sorting as an index, we
could sort anything we wanted to.
So, for example, if I come in, I don't think I have, we don't have any
kind of a utility thing.
So I'll just make a file for sorting because why not?
So I still have never implemented anything in for Kotor 2.
Actually allow me to make files with my little boilerplate.
What am I going to do?
I got to do that.
One of these days, I have the thing in emacs.
I wrote which like added like allow me to open a file and add a
border, the boilerplate thing to it but I don't have that here.
So anyway, moving on.
How did stb truetype .h?
I thought we deleted that.
How did it come back?
What's going on?
I am 99% sure.
We deleted that.
That's a bit freaky.
All right.
Don't want to know what happened there.
Anyway, let's go ahead and and make a new file for that so I don't
know what's in Linux.
Handmade probably nothing, right?
Yeah.
So we'll copy Linux handmade to you know handmade.
I don't know if it would be utils or something like that.
I'm just trying to think if we should make it a general one, I'll just
call it sort for now.
So we'll have handmade sort dot CPP and and that should be, you know,
sufficient.
So I'm going to go ahead and open that.
So here is our
Sort function or other are sort file.
And I'm going to grab this thing out which is this as a just, I'm just
going to call this just sort entry.
And then I'm going to go ahead and grab out that, that code for, for
doing the sorts, which you can see, is kind of all in here.
And yeah.
Just grab all those guys out.
And so what I need to do now is I gotta change it from Taos or
identity to sort entry because I'm sort of renaming this to be more
General sounding even though the code remains identical and doesn't
really change in any way.
So there it is.
And I'm going to change push buffer offset.
To just be index.
And that's about it.
So here you can see where we do.
Our sort entries, call normally, what we do is we can pick from which
one of these we wanted to do, and what we do is we just pass.
Account of things, the entries, and then the memory that we need for
the Temp Storage, right?
And so, for the Temp Storage stuff, what we want to do is I guess make
sure we have enough room to store everything.
So, you know, maybe we could make a utility function, that would
automatically handle this, you know, I don't know.
But point being, that's really all we need to think about in order to
call one of our sort functions, they're all otherwise reusable, right?
Right.
So yeah, so I think that's everything that we would need.
I'm pretty sure that's just about good.
Yeah, so what I'm going to do now is I'm going to go ahead and and
move this out into maybe handmade .h where we'll include it.
So,
What is handmade shared?
That's probably not necessary anymore.
That was probably for the meta thing.
Oh, well, anyway, we'll put this in here.
I guess I could, since it's a CPP file, I guess it really could be in,
you know, maybe down in here even where we're doing our sorting.
So like so and now I've got to clean up everyone else who is using any
of that.
So tile sword entry is just going to be sort of Entry.
And push, buffer offset has to just be index.
And off we go now.
In opengl dot CPP since this thing needs to actually be able to do the
sort and so does render with that means is our win32 layer because the
rendering code needs, it is going to have to use that as well.
So in here, we're going to need our handmade sort dot CPP and but
that's fine.
Okay.
Again in here tell us our entries need to be sword entries, like so
and care about that at the moment and push buffer offset is just going
to be index at the moment.
And I'll sort entry, sort of Entry doo-doo-doo-doo-doo
doo-doo-doo-doo.
And I don't know what this is.
Our this is the frame display.
Needed sort sighs.
All right so that's I think everything that we need there and I'll
come in here and Define one of these things, the top clocks list
Tape stopped clocks list.
And I will also come down here and I suppose since we want, all of
these to generally be switchable between each other, I'll just put it
in here and, you know, we'll just say, okay, there's a, you know, a
clocks View.
And we can switch between those.
So all this stuff works the same way where we have the sizing and all
that sort of nonsense.
and,
When we go to actually draw it, I will do top clocks list and I'll do
draw top clocks list.
Passes act.
Same things we were before.
And that's that.
So, draw a frame bars.
I'll start with its function prototype since that's what we've got.
And then I'm not going to actually implement it at all at the moment.
I'm just going to leave it blank and make sure that we still work with
are sort of abstract did that I haven't broken anything.
So here I am running the code again.
Looking at the profile.
We now have a new mode.
We can set things to which is clocks as we white.
It might have expected.
It doesn't actually do anything at all but you know, otherwise, it's
all good.
So what I can now do is say, let's actually try to draw this top
clocks list and the question is, you know, how am I going to do that?
What I can do, I believe is I can go through all of the elements that
are debug.
I can go through all of the elements that are like profile times,
right?
And I don't know right now.
I don't think we actually keep that organized in any way.
We sort of had a little thing that did that in the past.
But I don't know that we actually have
Do that now like when we create a debug element I don't know if we
still add it to the profile group.
Let me look and see if we do.
You know, maybe we do can't see because it's behind my head.
Let's see here, profile group.
So we do so.
So actually this is a pretty easy thing for us to do.
If we want to we can iterate over all of the members of the profile
group and we know that those are all of the things that could take
time, right?
Those are all of the profiler events.
So if we go through each of those and then we look at whatever
particular frame that we're on.
We can sum up all of the blocks that it is recorded for that frame and
that's how much time it's taken.
So that's pretty straightforward, right?
So I'm going to start doing that.
And I'm what I'm going to do first is I'm not even going to try to
sort the list.
What I'm going to do is I'm just going to print it out, right?
And then what I'll do is I'll do something which actually tries to
sort it.
So the profile group in this case, here I am in the H file, the
profile group is a debug variable group.
Which has in it.
Where Are You?
The Sentinel which I can iterate through?
So what I would do is say, okay, there's a debug variable link.
It's the profile groups.
Next is the first one.
As long as the link is not equal to the profile groups, Sentinel.
Oops.
It's what I actually meant to do.
As long as it is not, as long as I haven't gotten back to the
Sentinel, then I know that I can iterate through this, this group of
people, right?
And so, all I'm going to do at first is I'm just going to print it
out.
I'm going to print out what each individual, you know, one should be
and then we'll work from there to you know, to figure the rest of it
out.
So here I go.
I've got a profile wrecked their I'm
Going to go ahead and just output lines of text and and go from there.
Now, there's something interesting that this, I think will bring up
that will want to kind of generalize out, but I'm not going to worry
about that quite yet.
So, if I take this link, I have to look and see what the link itself.
Has in it.
You can see that there's gets can either be a sub set or it can be an
element.
I'm going to assert for now that it's not a subgroup, because I don't
feel like there should ever be subgroups inside the profile group.
And so if there are, I'm misunderstanding how we were using it and I
want to know
So I can get the debug element by just looking at the links element.
Pointer that gives me exactly what I want for printing out information
about this particular person and so I can print out the element and I
can print out the clock amount here once I actually figure out what it
is.
So the first question is well, all right, how can I figure out what
what it is?
Well remember, a debug element.
Has a series of frames in it and we know that we look at a particular
set of
Particular frame, when reviewing things, right?
So what we want to do here is say, well, the element frames for
whatever the debug State viewing frame ordinal, is that gets us back.
What the event chain was for this particular type of block on this
particular frame.
We can then say, well, tell me what the oldest event was and that's a
debug stored event, right?
And if I Loop over this,
And I go through all of the events that there were right.
So, every last one of them, those are all of the blocks of this type
that occurred in this Frame.
If that makes sense.
And again, this includes events that started in this Frame but ended
after the frame was over and if we wanted to we could probably
actually make note of that.
But I don't think I'm going to need that for any particular reason,
because it'll be pretty obvious but because we know which functions do
and don't overlap in that way, but just point it out.
So if we take a look at the events profile node struct, we're going to
have in their adoration and that duration is the number of clocks that
it took.
So if I was to take a total clock, very value, initialize at zero.
Summing it over.
All of these events will give me the total number of clocks that were
taken by this type of a block on this Frame.
Now, granted it does not tell me about children, right?
So it doesn't tell me about people,
Who are like, who it called?
And that's a thing that we're going to probably want to account for in
a little while.
All right, so once we get that total clock value, then in here what I
can do, I don't really know why we were printing it out in this
particular way, but that doesn't really matter.
The point is in here I could say, well now I'm going to print out the
total clocks like so and that's how many clocks is thing took on this
Frame.
If I print it out, then I will print it out and I can advance by the
line amount.
So, all I need to do now is just say, okay, let's make an
Variable, which is where I'm starting to print, that can be the
minimum corner of the profile wrecked.
Or actually.
It's just that.
Yeah and once I have that, then I will just boo.
No.
Nah, I need to go back to where I was.
All right, so when I'm here printing out the text.
I want to start it wherever I think I am.
And then I need to do, do doot.
After I'm done and, you know, subtract my y value down.
So I move to the next line.
Now, if I'm not mistaken when we start printing to begin with,
obviously, we also need to have that understanding of where the text
should go and so I think we also want to do the the get text Baseline,
right?
This thing.
Like so, so I want to be able to do that as well where I can sort of
say, okay.
Where was I top?
I need to be able to start off at the right place.
So I also have to kind of do this, this sort of situation and so get
line advance, and I don't know if we have a get Baseline, we probably
should.
Let me see.
Do we have?
Get line advance.
So what we really want here is probably the same thing for Baseline.
And so, this way, this can be something that is automatically done.
So, you know it, we know that it multiplies by the scale and stuff
because somebody might forget to do that.
So we'd rather have it, always going through a known place where we
can adjust it if we need to.
So we do get Baseline.
There we go.
And think that's it, this, of course has to be
Adjusted as a vector.
All right, so if I go to the top clocks list here, I'm not getting any
output.
So I think we have made an error there.
Let me go in here so I can take a look at what's going on.
So here we go through and so this is not we're not getting anyone in
the debug profile group.
I thought I looked in that we were actually adding them but it looks
like perhaps that we are not adding them and so that's my problem.
What happened there?
I thought I looked at that.
I must have not looked at it particularly closely.
Okay, let's see here.
Okay, so the problem is, it doesn't add it to.
This group is is what's going on and I think if I remember correctly,
that's because I was assuming that we wouldn't have any need to do so,
but we actually do.
So.
Yeah.
I still want that to happen.
Get element from event.
This function is a little bit too overloaded in case you couldn't tell
but you can see here like we have sort of two things.
Do I want to add it to a group and
If I want to create a hierarchy for it and you know I kind of want
both of those things to be possible now which again just kind of gets
a little bit hairy.
What I can do here and I don't love it.
But I mean what I can do is
you know, debug
Element add up, you know, I can say here, oh, you know, debug like
create or add to group.
and I can say, debug,
You know.
Great hierarchy.
And I
Make those two things separate.
So instead of create hierarchy being, you know, a it sort of create
hierarchy being something that's a Boolean this passed in, and said,
it can be an OP value that comes through, then I can control more
fine.
Grained wood goes on again.
I don't love it, but it is the debug code and I'm not sure how much I
care about anything being particularly squeaky.
So in here, if I want to know whether I'm going to do the parent group
are real creation stuff, I can do that and
Then similarly, in here, I can, I can test the other way around, so I
can say, all right, well, if op, if I'm told that I'm supposed to
create the hierarchy, then off we go.
And similarly, if I'm told that I'm supposed to add to group, I can do
that.
And then all we have to do, is say, well, all of the places
previously, where we were doing, get element from event, just need to
have this this awareness, right?
and so I'm going to say here's the up like so
Will do this and I might say that you're going to have to specify
everything.
Now I'm not going to let you do.
I'm not gonna let you do invalids there, so get element from event.
In this case, this one had note, you know, it was using whatever the
default parent was and then it was doing both of these so it was doing
add to group and debug element.
Fred Harvey.
Elements.
Events.
What else you got?
So in this case this is the one we were talking about before.
And so this one, this one just wants to do, add to group, doesn't want
to do anything else.
Right.
This one wants to do both.
This one doesn't want to do anything.
It looks like
And that's it.
So all I should have to do now is put those in some place where
everyone can see them.
Which can be right here.
And off we go.
So let's see, if now, we get some things added to our group.
There we go.
Alright, so now we're oh and hey, if you're going to start something,
you might want to start the actual thing, you want it to be true.
Sort of the opposite of that, my bad.
Let's see, draw top.
Top.
So in here, I actually want to say assert that there are no children
was, what I was trying to say, big surprise at fired.
So let's see if I go to top clocks.
All right.
Oh, and by the way, I should have picked Max for that.
Shouldn't I?
Let's try that again.
All right, so this should have been Max because we start at the top.
All right, and so let's print it out.
and of course,
I need the two different ones now.
Because the X and the Y going opposite directions as far as human
reading.
Order is concerned all math too bad, you had to be that way.
So let's see here, if we look at what's going on, how much do I
believe?
This is actually telling us anything real.
I'm not sure.
We've got input processing, message processing, Mouse position, etc,
etc.
Game update, imitating render.
Let's see what happens when I switch into the game mode.
These should get a lot larger and they are.
I mean, I could believe that these are correct, right?
I certainly could believe that they were correct.
It's not a very scientific way of determining that, but I could
believe it.
So, yeah, okay.
So that's, you know, that's something.
So now, what I was going to say and I mentioned this before, when I
was kind of like this is going to bring up something we want to deal
with is you'll notice that we don't have any way.
Like we'd really don't
A concept of like a listing area and so if we wanted to now do this
sort of thing where we printed this in, could scroll this list or
something, it wouldn't like we'd have to implement all that custom
just for this.
And so one thing we might want to think about doing now is instead of
just hacking it.
So that just this one works, we may want to make it so that we have
the concept of some kind of tabular output that we can use in multiple
scenarios.
But for right now, I don't really want to do that quite yet.
I want to finish getting this listing more interesting before.
We start working on making it display well.
the other thing that I might want to do is I would like to go to
And made us sleepy.
And I would like to make sure that when we draw the frame graph stuff,
what I actually want to do here is I would like to make it so that I
am.
Drawing this one.
Okay so now at least it's coming up by default which is what I would
like.
I also feel like this thing is not it's not actually drawing a
backdrop rectangle at the moment.
Which I guess it is here and that I believe is because that backdrop
rectangle.
I'm going to move that.
I think I might move that out because I want everyone to be using
that.
So I think what I'm going to do is say that backdrop rectangle that we
have in some of these here where we do you know the this push wrecked.
I'm actually thinking maybe that that should just be a thing that's
that's handled outside, right?
So I'm going to go to where
We call this.
And I'm going to put it in here.
So when we actually grab this elements, I'm going to say let's go
ahead and do that black.
And I'm going to make it much darker because so we can see things
better on it.
So I'm going to say that the element.
The layout elements bounds should be filled with a fairly dark color.
They're okay.
But I have to wait till it actually make the element.
And that's it.
Yeah.
Just because that'll make it easier to see what we're looking at.
Okay.
all right, so now
we need to do some things.
First of all, like I said I would like this list to be sorted because
I would like to be able to quickly look at who is taking the most time
I would like to maybe know some percentages.
We probably want to clip out some of this information because we don't
need to see all of this.
Like we probably just want just the name or something and the rest of
the parts of the grid we probably don't care about.
And also since we have a debug element, haven't we've already parsed.
Those out I believe, right?
Because d
Element.
Correct me if I'm wrong.
Yeah, debug element already knows.
We're like name starts at and that sort of thing, right?
So what I could do there is, I can do it, where we do the top clocks
list, when we actually draw it in here, what I can do is say, well,
you know, when we're doing this thing with the grid, I'm just going to
advance it by the name starts at.
Because why wouldn't we do that?
You know, you that's like pretty obvious.
So that way in here it's much easier to read.
It's like
All those things are.
Now the other thing that I probably want to do is I would I probably
don't want to really be using the standard print out for this because
I would want all of the numbers to be aligned, I can sort of cheat
that for now.
But in the future I'd probably going to want to take more control over
that rendering process but anyway I can do this for now.
Which will be kind of the Poor Man's way to do it but when we should
probably have like a little bit better way of us, printing it out in
the future.
So there you can kind of see, I don't know why I'm rebooting.
Instead of just like monkeying with it from in here.
I probably should go do that.
So there you can see like, the cycle counts going.
And like I said, these are the cycle counts for people.
When they are.
That's kind of interesting.
Anytime I move the mouse, you notice we get drastically more time.
Spent there's like ten times more time spent in Windows message
processing as soon as I have to move the mouse or do anything.
That's kind of funny.
It's still not a long, it's not actually a much time in that sense,
but it's still like
Well, it's actually fairly appreciable.
That's actually a long time spent in there.
I wonder if Windows is taking that time or if I'm taking that time.
Well anyway, I'm gonna continue with what I was doing.
But you know, I'm already kind of interested in what this is showing
me, right?
Anyway.
So let's suppose that I want to show a percentage in there as well, I
think we met can't quite remember but we had some debug statistics
stuff in here and I would like to see if any of that is is relevant at
the moment.
Also, I guess we don't use this anymore so I'm going to get rid of it.
Debug statistic.
So there's like a min max average count thing here, right?
And so I just wanted to see like if since we have that
Do you bug statistic?
So, here's the thing.
and it accumulates values as real 64 is, and finds their boundary and
then
so that's not that doesn't really help us, unfortunately,
So that's not as useful.
I might maybe expand on this concept a little bit and but make it a
little bit more useful because right now it's not super useful.
So if we were going to do this debug statistic thing and have it be
more useful, what I was thinking is we could have a min max and an
average I'd also want the some
And and yeah the counts find that's how many of them there there
actually are.
That's totally fine.
But how many statistical samples there are.
But the other thing that I'm thinking is after we do that then some
kind of a like correlation to the total as well.
I was trying to think of how exactly I will do that.
So I think what I would want to do,
Is when we come in here, since I know that, I want to sort, what I
probably would do is start by saying, well, I kind of need to know how
many of these things there are right.
And so what might be nice is if these groups told me that number so
that I could create like something based on it.
So if I look at debug variable group here,
like, if I was to say something like, you know, child count,
That's not where I wanted that.
This is where I wanted that.
For Linked account.
If I did something like that, it might be well.
You know what?
That's just dumb.
Why would I do that?
Doesn't even make any sense.
There aren't going to be that many of these.
I'll just iterate the list twice.
That's way more saying and it doesn't clog things up.
So I'll just say we have we don't know how many of these are going to
be.
So I'm just going to find out how many and then what I'm going to do
is I'm going to make a way of tracking all of them, right?
So there's going to be something like a
Country.
In the clock, entry would have something like, what was the debug
element?
That I was talking about.
Yeah, what was?
Debug entry.
I was talking about what is the total clock value for it?
And that that may be it.
Is that really it?
In fact, it may not even, I may not even need that.
Well alright we'll say that.
It's got that and then it also has maybe it's a the debug statistic
thing is in here, right?
So maybe it has a debug statistic in here and here's the statistic.
I don't know, I'm making this up.
So here's my debug clock entry.
What I'm going to do is say, well, why don't we create a temporary
thing on the debug stack here, where I've got debug clock entries?
However, many there are and they I'm going to allocate that by using a
temporary push.
So I'm going to do a push array of the clock entries.
And I don't really want to clear these.
I don't think, you know what, I probably do because I gotta clear out
the statistics in order to summon.
So yeah I guess well now even that's not true.
I need to decide is listed Max so I don't really want to do it.
So I want to do a no clear on those guys.
But anyway, so I'm going to do a push entry on the debug clock
entries.
And I'm going to want however many of them that we found, and I'm
going to want to do that on the debug State debugger Arena.
And I guess I could actually probably do it on the periphery Marina,
but I, well, I don't want to over see if that's gone down to zero.
So I do have the debug Arena, and I can do a temporary memory boundary
here because this is just is just him, it's just temporary, right?
So what I can do is say, all right, well let's begin our attempt
memory.
This is going to be a function that just does some scratch stuff here.
And debug state32 Arena.
And then when I'm done with it, I'll just get rid of it.
And so, then we push, we will push off the arena.
And everyone will be happy.
So, that will get us enough entries that we can now treat them as an
array.
So, when we come through here,
And we record this information, instead of printing it out at the
moment, I can move that printout.
Oops until later.
So what I can do is say, all right, inside here, what I'm going to do
is take the debug clock entry that corresponds to the link that I'm
on.
So I guess I can just do it like this.
And for each one of these, I'm going to record which one it is.
So, I'm going to say this is, you know, groups, entry element equals
link element.
so,
And and then I'm going to go ahead and do this, you know, the the sort
of the summation.
And I'm going to do that with the statistic thing because why not?
So where is that?
That's like begins statistic or something like this.
You bug statistic.
Where is it?
You bugs to stick.
Here it is.
So I'm going to go ahead and do begin debug statistic and
Point to the entries.
Stats and then for each one of these, I'm going to do a cume debug
statistic for the entry stats.
And then this is the value.
I'm going to track so and then I'm going to do an Envy bug statistic
and while I'm doing this, what I'd also like to do is prepare myself
for sorting.
So I'll just make a sort
I don't know, sort space.
And I guess I've got two things here.
So this is like sorte.
And sort be.
And in both cases we're just again just grabbing some temp memory that
we're going to use from the debug Arena.
and in both cases, I just want
Some of these.
so after I create these sorts, what I do want to do is initialize the
sort a one
I would like the sort a one to be initialized so that the sort key is
whatever the MK stats whatever.
It's
Total value is.
So I want the the some and I want the index to be I guess at this
point I'm going to need it right?
Because I need to be able to do an actual index.
So I suppose in here we do have that and I could get rid of these at
that point, right?
That would just be entries.
Plus index sort a plus index
And so now I've got a sort thing set up as well.
So when I want to, now I can go into handmade sort and I can pick one
of our sorts, I don't know, I guess we might, as well do Radix sort.
I think that's what we were using in the other code.
I don't really remember but doesn't really matter.
Whichever one we want.
And we can say like, okay, why don't you sort Soiree and I'll give you
sort be as a backup sort, that'll sort for us.
And then when I can do is, I can go through here and actually print
these things out in order.
Boobs don't want to end temporary memory every time.
And so instead,
Let's see here.
This this index will get shadowed unfortunately that's okay.
Just do it like this.
So as I come through here, what I'm going to want to do now is I'm
going to want to pull out the debug element.
Well, first I'm going to want to pull out this entry, right?
The debug clock entry.
So I'm going to want to pull out the debug clock entry.
And that's just our entries array plus whatever index were on.
And then I'm going to want to sort of indirect that, right?
Because it's actually whatever the sort array is whatever that one
says the index is because remember, the sword array has now been been
sorted and we want to like, in directly jump to the correct entry in
our actual setup and I can grab the element off of the entry very
easily.
And then, in here, I can just print out.
whatever information I need from the
Here you Cycles 10 you.
So this is have to be converted to a you 32.
So total clocks is actually going to be whatever my entry, whatever my
stat value is, I guess, and I can dereference that as well.
So here's my staff value.
Whatever my staff value was
Whatever.
Its some was,
Right.
And I think that's all I really need to do.
Now we have one problem which is that I'm not actually.
Well, I'll tell you what it says in second.
Let's see here.
Are you 64?
Darcy before anything else?
Sort key truncate that down to R32.
We have one problem which is that our statistics at the moment, don't
keep sums.
I added that right.
But then I haven't actually implemented it yet.
So in here, when we do our accumulation, I need to make that actually
work.
So, here's the some in here, instead of adding the average, I'm going
to add to the sum.
And then in here, assuming that the count comes out to something
reasonable.
Then I am going to
Actually compute it.
Like so, so I'm just keeping that some around.
Instead of overwriting, it using the average as a scratch space for
it.
Then overriding it.
All right, so now hey look, it worked the first time.
That's kind of a nice thing and fortunately it's sorting in kind of
the opposite direction is what we want because I don't really want to
see the people who aren't taking time.
I want to see the people who are taking time at the top, especially
once we make this clip to a window.
Sighs.
I'm not going to even see these things down here.
So, all the important stuff had better be at the top.
That's the whole point in order to do that, it's pretty easy, right?
Because since we have a sort and we could sort on whatever we want
when we create the sort key, if we just flip the sense of it, right?
If I just negate, what I'm passing down, it'll go the other direction,
right?
So that's pretty simple.
So now we have a nice top list that's showing us the information.
I'm almost out of time, I'm going to print out a couple other things
here, but but the rest of stuff they're going to do.
We'll have to wait for a little while.
So let me just do a couple of things here.
The, you know, the account, for example, might be a nice thing to put
in there.
So like, you know,
How many times something was called?
That would be stats count?
Right?
And so you can see like, okay, we're asking for 17 assets here and
doing you know, whatever, blah blah, blah, right?
Go down to something that's a little more interesting.
We can see.
Like, okay, we're doing 715 calls to get World chunk.
278 times, were changing interview locations, you know, that sort of
stuff, and so that kind of tells us how much things are getting
called, right?
So, the other thing that I might want to do is show the percentage of
the time and showing the percent of the time would be pretty easy as
well.
What I can do is just do like a total time value and every time
through here, after I do the debug statistic, and I can add my entry
stats, some.
So the total time I can add in here and so that allows me to
accumulate that and and know that the complete time.
And so what I could do is I
Can say, you know, that, that summed set of Cycles.
It's a bit of a tongue twister.
I can invert that and give myself a multiplier that will produce
percentages from my other cycle times.
So like my percent coefficient, right let's look all that.
The PC is will make that zero at first and then we'll just check,
okay?
If the total time is greater than 0.
So there was some time taken, then the PC will equal 1 over the total
time and that will turn things into a percentage.
Now what I can do is pre multiply it by 100 here because
Sense obviously are multiplied by 100 from their their normal value.
And so in order to print the percent here, what I can do is just say
okay we'll do a percent 3D value here and before the count will print
and actually put a % there before the thing will print whatever that
some is times the the counter, right?
And so now we can also see the percentage of the time that each one of
these things is taking and you can kind of see here that we've got,
you know, the percentages sort of ranging in
What's running looking for?
We've got the the percentages are sort of all high towards the top and
low at the bottom, which is exactly what we expect.
But keep in mind that these percentages
Are inclusive of the children.
So if you have somebody in a person who's taking some sort of time and
somebody above them, who's taking a certain percentage of the time,
they're actually including the child.
So for example, looking at game update and game update and rendered,
that's actually the same piece of information that we're getting
there.
Right?
So those are the reason those are both 20 is because they're both
actually timing the exact same thing, right?
So if we look at
how this is actually adding up, we should be able to get to a point
where we well
We won't add up to 100%.
Right?
We should add up to 100%.
We should be able to get to add up to 100% if we sum of the
percentages.
Now, remember, all of these are small percentages that will add up to
something.
So yeah.
So we can check our math here.
I'd like I said, I'm pretty much out of time so I'm not sure if we're
gonna do that right now but we should do that.
So what is that?
That's like 60, let's say that something like 40 so it's a little
weird.
Like I feel like maybe I did something slightly wrong, although I
guess all of these combined probably are enough percentage because
well, I don't know, are they?
They probably aren't.
So there's something weird here because I feel like
No, there's nothing weird there.
This is the percentage of the total time.
And the total time includes that double counting so it's all fine.
Never mind.
I'm totally fine.
I'm totally fine with it.
So yeah, these would probably add up to about 100 that looks about
right to me, that's all good.
But this is not an actual useful measure yet.
Because like I said, what we want to do is take the child times out of
there, because in this case, you would say, oh, the game update block
is taking all the time.
Well, that's true, right?
But it's not the whole truth because really game update and render is
taking all of the time inside game.
So, game update itself.
It's actually just a little bit of Preamble code, that doesn't take
any time and then all the time is excellent, game engine render.
So it's not that useful necessarily to see it in this fashion and we
want to be able to see, like, just me, not my children.
How much time am I worth looking at as a code block myself and I don't
think I'll be that hard for us to add that, but it won't be able to
edit right now.
And of course, just double check.
Make sure we can still get everywhere.
We need to get, we can so that's good.
Okay, I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A not that anyone ever has
questions.
Why do debug code?
But what you gonna do?
It's interesting to, you can see these.
I'm just going to point this out while waiting for questions.
So, you'll notice that nowhere in here.
Do we have duplicate entries into the list, right?
And the question is, well, why don't we have duplicate entries into
the list anywhere or another way to say it?
Would when we get down to the debug code, why do we have duplicate
entries in the list?
And the answer is every time we do a code reload the grid for a
particular entry will change potentially because it's no longer the
same code anymore, right?
And so this is all from the fact that we were changing the debug
system.
So it's information, it created different blocks like new grid markers
for those blocks.
Whereas all this code didn't change.
So they stay the same, which is kind of fun.
Cousin games can I avoid taxation by reinvesting into capital gains in
America?
Yes, that's the whole point of it.
It's to make sure that rich people don't pay taxes.
That's why it was invented.
I mean why should rich people have to pay taxes?
Dude, in basement one.
Why won't we add to 100%?
We do add to a hundred percent.
I was what I was thinking in my head was I was like, wait a minute
since this is double counting this time, it shouldn't add 200.
I'm like wait a minute, no, our percentages are based.
The double counting so they should add to 100 and they do.
But I was thinking, oh wait, they shouldn't have to 100 because the
total running time I was thinking we were looking at the total actual
measured runtime and taking percentage of that.
And I was like we should add too much higher than 100% but that's not
what we're doing.
We're just looking at the total Cycles recorded.
So yeah.
So we do add two hundred percent and that's what should have happened.
Sean McGrath.
How would you self update and exit?
Right now, I have a second deck, see that copies a file that
overwrites, the current x z.
So, the main x equals update me close itself, update me sleeps for a
half second then copies, there's got to be something smarter.
so, you
So, let me see these other questions are asked about what we're doing.
So let me take those first and there aren't any other questions?
I will talk about the other question is death.
So as far as the question that's can the percentage support of decimal
place?
The answer is yes.
But at that point you need floating-point printout, which we probably
should Implement anyway.
So yeah, I mean, not, not a problem.
You just do it like this.
did I mess up the
What's the width specifier?
That says, I want at least three spaces though.
Because I want it to be aligned.
Is it that?
No.
I know.
I want this to be a lie.
I don't remember how to specify the width.
In any other way, it looks like it was ignoring me, but I'm not sure
why.
But that would be the decimal place.
How many you go about investigating the cycle count increase for the
input processing?
When the mouse is moved?
So
To be honest with you, I don't have a necessary.
I don't have a like, oh, it's obviously, you just go do this, and you
would find out.
So I'm not 100% certain what we could do is time some more blocks.
Now what we do know right is that it appears to be in here because we
know that the windows messaging one goes up as well.
So for example, if I was to go here and do a pause and kind of scan
back through here to ones where it jumps,
So you can see win32 message processing cut that.
So cool.
How awesome is that?
We just jump back to one where we click and then we can look at
How cool is that though?
That's so cool.
Like we didn't write any of that into this system, it's just because
it all flows through the same thing.
We can just jump to any frame and get all the stuff.
Gah, and it tracks all our threads.
Anyway so here we see win32 message processing rate and input
processing.
They jump together.
So what it seems to suggest is that Insight input processing.
This is really our culprit because it's taking up apparently that
extra time.
And so inside win32 process pending messages, which is here, this is
the place where we're doing it and I guess the question would be, you
know, is it in our code or is it in Windows as code, okay?
Because we don't really know who's taking that time.
So one thing we could do is drop another block.
Here is the only place that we're actually doing any work.
Windows is the only person doing any work anywhere else.
So inside win32 process pending messages, what we could do is say,
well.
Alright, let's drop a Time Block in here.
Right.
And what do I have to do?
Name it or something?
This is
This is WM key messages.
Right?
And so yeah.
So
Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Let's go back to one where that's taking a lot of time, so,
Wait.
But that never actually gets called, right, because that's keyboard.
So I don't even know why I'm looking at that.
So the answer is Windows must be taking a lot longer inside peek
message because what are we're not doing anything?
I guess it could be inside dispatch message or something but it looks
like it's mostly.
It's got to be inside peek message, right?
And I suppose we can we could you know we can verify this.
If it was if that was actually the case, we could check two things.
Right.
One thing we could do is we could do this
So, we could say, if we didn't get a message, we break out of the
loop, right?
And so we could do that.
And now, when we're running through here, let's unpause the profiler,
when we're running through here, and we do our little Fancy Pants,
whatever we could now say like, oh, okay, let's time the peak message
in a block.
And see what that does.
Oops.
Where are you pick message?
Why are you not showing up?
What is the problem?
Am I missing something?
Is there a reason why we're not getting that added?
I don't get it.
All right, I'm gonna set a breakpoint in there because I don't
understand why that's not getting up.
Hi, this is in the platform code.
It doesn't get, dynamically reloaded, that's great.
Where's my towel?
That's just stupid.
Yeah.
Why isn't it showing up?
How about?
Because that's not in a section of the code that actually ever gets
hot loaded?
That's in the section, the code that does the hot loading.
Brilliant.
All right.
Let's try this again.
So where are my Peak message at?
No and you know what God actually do the compiled.
Okay so do my compiled we have a new executable.
We Run The executable.
Do we see a peak message?
Yes, we do shocking.
You know what?
I feel like inside that debug control, things should just be inside
the profiler, that's where I want it.
I've decided
At least for now can always move it.
That's the nice thing.
Alright.
So here we go.
It's doing its thing.
I'm going to pause this and then we have let's see our Peak message.
So you can see the peak message took.
Basically the whole time.
right, it took point two five percent and these guys were just a
little bit over that
So it looks like the call to Peak message.
Is just Windows is taking its sweet time doing its thread.
DQ
I don't know why.
Do not know why.
But I don't know that there's a whole lot we could do about that.
I guess would be what I would say.
All right, so it's like no other relevant questions.
And someone was so someone said the same thing I actually thought I
just typed dude in basement was saying it's that but I thought that is
what I typed before and that didn't work.
Yeah, that doesn't work.
So I don't know why it doesn't work.
Maybe es printf doesn't handle with specifiers correctly or something.
Because that's what I would have expected.
I don't know.
I know it's going on there.
We can fix that ourselves later.
So it's not a huge deal, but it's just annoying.
Anyway, ssssss McGrath wants to know how you replace your own
executable on the Fly.
So two things about that one.
I would ask.
The question is, why do you actually want to replace the entire
executable on the fly?
Like why not just use a dll like we're doing here, but if you actually
want to replace the executable on the Fly, you can do that as well.
What we would probably do, is something like this.
So let's say we're in here and we want to replace the the dll.
Let's, let's look.
No ma'am, meow.
Meow.
Words happen.
All right.
Mmm.
Yeah, mmm.
Mmm, mmm, mmm.
Where I'm just kind of like forgetting where the code actually is that
That actually like, unloads the game code and all that, okay?
So you know, when we do this stuff and we do executable needs to be
reloaded.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that like, okay when we do this, the
other thing we could do is Maybe
Maybe do the same thing for our XE or something and and swap to the
new exit.
We can't hot do that, but we could, I could show how you would do that
if you want to do that as as like a patching Behavior.
so,
Let me ask one clarifying question.
Well actually, I guess I don't even need a clarifying question.
So if we want it to automatically start when there was a new
executable built, then what we could do for that is we just need a
place where that executable gets gets put, if that makes sense and we
need to check that.
So the way that would work is similar to what we were doing before,
where we have this sort of nonsense going on, where we have a bunch of
files that we use to determine what's happening, right?
And what we could do, I don't remember how the lock temp thing,
Looks to be honest with you, but we'll probably just try to ride on
that so that will probably use the same lock situation.
But what we need to do is we need to do the same thing we were doing
before.
So we need like this kind of a thing where we have source win32 code,
and temp, win32.
Right.
Or maybe x z.
So we need two of these things and we need them to be.
Let's see.
Temp win32 XZ, full half, empty 2xz full path.
Source.
32, I see.
And these would just be like winter, too.
Handmade out, XZ and went through to handmade temp dot EXE.
So once we have those, we would be able to check to see if it had been
updated right in the exact same way that we can check any other thing
that we want to know.
Howard, if it got updated.
so, when we do our compare file times,
Like here.
We can do, we could do the same thing, right?
We can say like, oh, you know, when to be to needs to be reloaded and
we could say, you know, compare the file times of
The.
New XE.
time and the old exit time and you know, I get both of those here so
I'd say like
Tell me what those are.
New XE time and bold XE time.
And when we have this stuff here, it would be win32.
Remember what we call this?
I need the names of these things, so it's
Where that at the top here.
So I need
this is not really source.
So I need to say, all right, the win32 XE full path and the temp,
win32 XZ full path.
I need to check those two things and if they are different than the
win32 thing needs to be reloaded.
If the win32 thing needs to be reloaded, that means it's basically
game over at that point.
and and, you know, we have to reload now the
I'm at this is this would make our game like go down and come back up
again.
So I don't know that.
I actually want this to happen, you know?
Like I almost wonder we probably might want to actually check to see,
we would want to, we would want to actually check to see if the two
files themselves were different, right?
So we'd want to compare the two files.
And if they weren't actually different, we wouldn't reload.
If that makes sense.
So,
But assuming that we actually did want to actually did find that to be
the case we could do, okay?
If win32 needs to be reloaded, then all bets are off and we got to do
our full, you know, win32 full restart or something, right?
And we would pass to that the path of the X Z and the path of the
thing that we wanted to like copy,
Or whatever.
If that makes sense.
All right, so if we have to do a win32 full restart the question, I
think that Sean is asking.
Now we've gotten to that part.
His question is, how do I do it right?
Because he's like I can't figure out how to actually make it restart.
So the way we would do win32 full restart in.
This case, here is our source, XZ and are dest XZ.
Right.
So what we need to do first is we need to move our executable out of
the way, so that we can put a new one in its place.
Now, we can't delete our executable because Windows doesn't actually
let you delete something.
When it's still being used.
It does, however, let you rename it.
So, what we need to do is we need to use a move file.
And I haven't done this in a long time, so I'm, you know, if it turns
out that we actually can't do it, I apologize.
But at least at one point it did work.
So the existing file name is the source, sexy, the
Well I guess that's not quite what I want to do first, the thing that
I want to do first is I want to move my executable to, I guess a
deletion place, right?
So we actually need one more of these.
we need one of these that's like,
Oops.
I forget how I
Replacing region gets that.
So yeah.
So Tampa is going to be delete
So in this case, we're going to do went through to full restart.
We've got our various executable situations happening here and the
first thing I want to do is I want to take the place that I want to
move things too.
And I want to say, all right, I'm trying to write to the desk.
That's the executable, I need to get out of the way.
So I'm going to move that to the delete executable location.
And some really what I could do here is say, well, I also know that I
want to delete the delete executable, right?
and,
Maybe old.
So I want to delete, whatever is in that location to start with.
I want to move myself the one that I'm currently running to the place
where it's going to get deleted.
I then want to move the one that you want me to use into the correct
slot for actually running it.
And then I need to, you know, run it, right?
So I would run it here and then I would exit process.
I would kill myself, right, commit suicide and so to run myself,
Right then, I just have to do like create process.
Actually, which we have.
All right, so we just need this.
So right, we got to create a start-up info and we got to make whatever
junk is remaking, we don't want SW hide.
Actually we don't want any of this, probably in the process info,
we've got the command line.
The command line is just going to be whatever the executables name was
because we don't pass any parameters to the command line.
Typically, if that makes sense, the path that we're running it in,
unfortunately, I don't really know what that would be.
We would have to figure out what that is for right now.
I'll hard code it right?
Just for fun.
It's just handmade data, right?
But we'll well we should take a look at that.
Maybe I'll finish this up tomorrow if people care.
Anyway, so the thing that we're trying to run here again is that dust
executable?
We want that to be to run and when
The process info that comes back.
Really, all I want to do here.
Well, I don't even care, I don't even need to close the handle.
It does not matter at all.
I mean, I can, I could do this.
And off we go, or I could just not and I think that's all we really
need to do.
Now, this would be an error here of some kind
But that's basically what we're talking about.
So this is the command line actually, so that's nothing.
We could run it with the same command line that we've been passed.
So, we could do this.
Which maybe makes more sense.
Yeah.
So anyway, that's
How that code would work.
And in here, what I would say is this thing should only happen
probably if the
If the actual thing that we're grabbing from, is there?
Because we don't, you know, if there actually isn't one of them, we
don't want that to be a thing.
Right?
Win32 doesn't have file exists.
It's like wait.
Do I have file exists though?
It's get file attributes.
It's actually this
Okay, so we did do it.
So it's already done the check and it knows whether or not it exists.
So I guess this will actually be equal to 0.
We could check to see if it is equal to zero.
You know we could do.
In line, 332 time is valid.
It's like high part and low part.
What is this thing again?
It's like DWI Part D W low part, something like that.
There it is.
So what I can do is say, went through two times, valid.
And say that we're only going to do this.
If I actually got
One of these.
I also think this is the wrong way around, not that it matters at all,
because nobody cares.
But I want to say, if the new XZ time is valid, then we can actually
compare them.
Otherwise I don't really want to compare them.
Alright.
So here we are running our mr.
Cody pants and I'll go ahead and do win32 full restart as a thing.
And so now, what should be possible, Right?
Is, I should be able to, like, do something ridiculous, like, copy
Windows system, 32, or notepad or something, right?
I should be able to copy notepad into
Two, handmade data.
Well, we're is win32 handmade.
I guess.
I don't really know.
It's a good question.
Do we actually copy that into the data directory?
So it's actually looking in the build directory for that, that's
actually where it is.
Okay and are these all going to be in the bill directory then too.
Well, I hope so so we'll just find out in a second.
All right.
So copy.
See Windows notepad into W.
Builds went through to handmade temp that XZ.
And is that the correct thing that we want to look for?
Yeah, I think so.
Yeah, all right so let's see let's get this working in doo doo doo doo
doo.
Take your handmade.
if I come down here and I say,
where is that code?
Loop.
All right, so new XE time.
Old XZ time.
What happened there?
Why am I unable to get the old executable time?
That's wrong weird.
A 2xz full path W builds win32 handmade.
Z.
It already executed that code.
How is that possible?
I set a breakpoint in a, didn't I?
How did I not get to see that happen?
I'm so confused right now.
Let's start this over again, somehow.
I didn't get to step through the code that I wanted to step through I
guess.
I'm not sure why.
Something happened.
Also.
This is backwards.
Okay, so let's try this one more time.
So in here, I'm going to move, went through to handmade old xe2 win32,
handmade
Exit.
Well, I guess I don't have to remind, it's all good.
So, I'm going to run it.
Here we are at our file time comparison.
We compare the two file times new XE time and old XZ time.
See if they're equal.
if thinks that they are not equal,
And that's correct because notepad is the other one.
Right.
Okay.
Let me just verify.
That that's true.
By the way.
In 32 and made 10.
Is there a reason that did not launch?
It is, in fact no pad.
But it's a notepad that refuses to run.
So that's a little less interesting.
All right.
I'm going to not, I want something that I can definitely know if it
ran.
So delete that
Let's get something else.
How about
What else can I grab?
It's on here.
If a builder proportion.
We have handmade stuff.
We've got four coder, guess we could relaunch the editor.
What about in program files?
How about?
It's kind of hoping that notepad would have ran but it didn't, it must
be missing a dll or something.
Nothing on here.
I need like a little.
Tiny simple.
Utility is color cop on here.
Let's try color cop.
Come on color cop.
You can do it.
Color cop, I believe in you.
All right, color cup and 32 handmade temp.
Bam.
All right, here we go.
Come through here, we test against color, cop.
We say we need to restart.
So, here we go and we'll see what happens.
So, first things first, here is the build directory and we are going
to try to delete the file, handmade old exe, see if that works.
And it does, we're then going to try and move handmade .exe to
handmade Old Dot exe and see if that works.
So
Do that.
And now you can see that the executable has moved to a new location
right now.
We're going to try to move our temporary executable on to our existing
executable like so.
Yeah.
And now you can see that we do have a win, 3-2 hammered Lexi.
I'm going to try to launch it with this.
There it is.
And then I am going to kill myself which I have
Right.
That.
So, what you're looking for?
It's time for me to go eat dinner.
So
That better be what you were looking for, but that's how you patch the
running executable.
So you're actually looking just look and do it.
You know, if you go.
So but again you cannot
Delete the executable.
You cannot copy the executable or any of that stuff.
You have to move the executable.
It has to be a move.
And the other thing that I would caution you about is you're going to
have to test this pretty thoroughly on a bunch of skus of Windows.
Because, like end like whether your administrator privileges or not,
because there may be things like it just
Doesn't let you start a new executable or it doesn't look like there
may be all sorts of stuff that it doesn't let you do.
Right.
So that's something to keep in mind.
I'm out of here.
And yeah.
Stupid, windows tricks.
With Casey.
All right, so let's go ahead and wind things down.
That's not what I needed to do this.
Thank you everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with the source
code, it comes the pre-orders of the game.
So you can go to handmade here at work and preorder it, and then you
can play around source code and have yourself a grand old time.
This is the button that makes that the all of that possible.
We also have a forum so I can go to if you want to support.
No, that's not how it goes.
They also form.
So you can go to if you want ask questions and a patreon page, we go
to file, export the video series.
We have a tweak bought that
This girl's about you.
And if you're interested in the tools that we use on this program,
obviously, we use visual Studios Community Edition which someday, we
hope to replace and thanks to Alan Webster.
We now use our own custom editor, which is for coder, which you can
get by typing for a coder into your browser.
It's actually want to go to this patreon link so that you can so that
you can become a patron of it.
We use the one from the $5 tier.
So yeah, that's
What you should do, I will be back here again in 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
You should come back here as well because you never know what we're
going to do on handmade hero.
Take it.
Is everyone