Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
You know, I was just kind of ranting about how awful dust keyboard is
at the beginning of the stream.
So I'm kind of a little bit worked up now, so we need to kind of
mentally Focus regain, our Focus pretend that we're typing on a good
keyboard, and just kind of rezone into a happy place in order to do an
episode of handmade hero.
Let me this be a lesson to everyone out there, picking a good keyboard
company is very important.
And I am certainly taking suggestions at this point that said we are
in the middle of doing some optimization work on handmade hero.
We yesterday finished doing most of the work of converting, all the
math operations, to Cindy in our texturing routine.
And we have a little bit more work to do on that.
But we're getting kind of close to the end and it's sort of time to
start looking at how many apps we have and how fast we think we can
make it go and other things like this.
I like to get right into that.
But before I do, if you'd like to follow along and you have a working
keyboard where you live, you can go ahead and unpack day 118 source
code because that's what we're going to be working with here on day
one, 19 now.
Let's go ahead and open up the editor.
So, if you remember where we were at yesterday, we had just completed
in our sort of, hopefully quickly routine, which I think at this
point, we could actually say quickly, I think we could drop the,
hopefully at this point because honestly, I feel like we have gotten
it to go rather quickly.
Now it's probably not as quickly as it could go, but we definitely
accomplished our goal of making it go quickly.
But at this point we really just don't know how quickly how
It is compared to what it could be and that's sort of what we're going
to be talking about today so I'm going to drop the hopefully and say
that we just have a routine that draws rectangles quickly.
And we're going to move on from there.
So, there we go.
Here is our routine working in all of its glory.
And as you can see, it is quite a bit faster than when we started.
When we started, it was taking some where in the neighborhood, I don't
even know what it was.
Two hundred.
80 Cycles.
Something like this.
Well, you know what?
We don't really have to guess because we could if we wanted to switch
to draw a rectangle slowly, and see.
So, if we actually go in here to render bitmap and switch it, this
All right, let's see here he is Undeclared.
PX py.
Oh right.
Sorry this is supposed to be draw a rectangle slowly here.
Go.
And if I remember correctly draw, a rectangle slowly, has some extra
stuff that it needs to take.
We pass it the X and y-axis the color and then we also pass it, sort
of the texture, the normal map and then the three bitmaps there.
So I think that is everything that that needs to get past so if we
wanted to we could sort of call draw rectangle slowly here if that
makes sense.
Let's go ahead and do that and we would need some time.
Ming on draw a rectangle slowly as well.
Which I don't know that we actually have.
It looks like we do have.
So you can kind of see draw a rectangle, slowly running here.
We can take a look at the time.
We don't actually have this one doing any sort of counting on it.
So we can't see what the cycles per pixel is.
So we should probably do is go ahead and and get get that the pixel
fill call and put that in.
So we can actually see how many cycles per pixel is and then we could
actually do
comparison.
So draw a rectangle.
Quickly.
See what we got here.
We have begin time, block process pixel.
So I want to do that in draw.
A rectangle slowly as well.
So that's going to be right here.
And then we're going to do the same thing that we did here where we
end time block counted.
And we go ahead and and count how many pixels we're actually trying to
fill and there we go.
So let's see if that gives us account.
There we go.
So calling draw a rectangle slowly.
As you can see, is five 353 cycles per pixel there.
And when we switch it, we are actually going
That's quite a bit faster than we were going before.
I guess it's like seven times slower or roughly something like this,
something like that.
So anyway, point being, we have done a pretty good job of getting it
down to something that is nice and fast and usable.
But we don't actually know at this point and this is thing I mentioned
way back.
When we started a week ago, we don't actually know how long it should
take us to.
Will any of this stuff?
So we know that we're running a lot faster than when we started.
We know that we're down in the 50s and we were in the 350s and so
that's all great.
But what we don't know is how long should it be taking us to fill each
individual pixel?
We don't really have any estimate so it's pretty hard for us to know
whether we're done optimizing this routine or not.
Now we could just ignore that fact and we could just say well we got
it fast enough for our purposes.
At the moment.
we don't really need to do anything else to it, and that's certainly
A totally fine tack to take if you just want to, you know, have a
crack at optimizing a routine.
And then, you know, if it pans out at pans out, if it doesn't, it
doesn't, you know, you don't really want to be super precise about it,
that's totally fine.
But what I kind of want to show here is some stuff we could do to try
to figure out roughly how long these things should be taking or if we
were you know, had Max everything out completely perfectly, how long?
Do we think these things should take?
And then we can sort of have, you know, an estimate as to, you know,
how close we are to, you know, to good, if that makes sense.
So let's suppose temporarily that.
We always had all the memory that we actually wanted was ready when we
needed it.
So we were not dealing with any sorts of memory latency or anything
like that.
And we're just going to talk about how many cycles do we think it
would take for all of these guys to complete, right?
So, for everything in here, that actually has to be executed, how long
will it?
Would it actually take us to to execute them, right?
And so, what I want to do is I want to try and figure out a way that I
can easily count the operations that were actually going to do now,
it's a little bit tricky, right?
Because each one of these guys is, you know, is every single one of
these guys has a different latency, right?
Every single one of these guys has a different latency in the, in the
thing, and it's hard for me to look at the code and count them.
So, what I'd like to do is make some kind of, you know, some kind of
Made a process if you will, that will take a look at how many of these
were doing and give us some kind of an estimate as to what the total
throughput for all of these operations should be right.
And again, this is best case assuming everything was pipelined
properly.
And so what I'd like to do is go.
All right, let's just take a look at all of these functions here.
What if I were to just Define all of these guys to do something else
entirely from what they actually
actually do, right?
And so, what I want to do is I want to go ahead and take this routine
here, right?
I want to go ahead and take this out, and I want to see about all of
the functions, the underscore, mmm functions that we have.
I'm going to pound to find them to do something else.
Okay, so what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and say, all
right, let's take all these guys.
Let's do.
Mmm, set PS, right?
What do you want?
Ma'am, set, 1.
PS and is I guess it's worth noting that this stuff here.
All right.
You know what?
Before I start that I'm looking at this here and I'm noticing that we
haven't actually finished Cindy, icing it.
We've still got some stuff here.
That scalar.
I doubt that this has very much to do with anything.
There were doing, but I'm going to, let's just say this to do Casey
remove this.
Because we can get rid of those, at the very least, you can see the
pixel p y is the same everywhere.
So that's not really part of this Loop, right?
But pixel p x is also a kind of a known value.
So we could actually just be incrementing it every time instead of
calling set where it has to hoist this x, i value out into the the
same deregister.
Does that make sense?
In fact, I guess it's so simple, we might as well just do it, right?
If I set this guy here, pixel PS.
If I set him to just be X-Men, the place that we're starting right.
If I set him to be X-Men.
Like so then every time through this loop, I could if I want to just
do an M&M add PS, right?
And add to him a value that steps by 4, right?
Because all of these guys, if I just add 4 to them, every time I get
the next Bank of four pixels, what the x coordinates are for the next
Bank of four pixels, right?
So if I do pixel PX,
Pixel p x plus the constant for.
And I just go ahead and do that at the end of the loop, right?
That is sufficient for computing, the new X values, right?
So I don't actually know if that's better or not like I said but we
can get rid again of some more of that scalar, right.
The more of that scalar operation that's happening there.
So if I want to do that I can just do this here and we can probably
remove those four X's now because remember I said, we don't really
need the scalar versions of
Anymore.
And hey, it actually does look like that helped, you know, every
little bit, it's weird, right?
But if you take a look, now we're actually below 50 sometimes.
Now, we're dipping into the 49 cycle, so yeah, making that wide was
also the compiler like that as well.
Now, one thing that's interesting here I guess also now that I see now
that I'm just looking at the stuff that we're doing here, we also have
this pixel py, right?
And
Origin y4x this stuff.
Gear really could have just been done once ahead of time.
Couldn't it have?
I mean, why are we subtracting?
You know, do we ever even use pixel p, y, and pixel PX other than in
that one instance, right?
And we don't right?
So these Subs subtractions are constant.
yeah, I mean
This this stuff is all actually not very good.
Now that I look at it, right?
We don't really need to be doing these where we're doing these.
So for example,
If you take a look at this, right?
The subtraction to get DX is actually something that we could have
just baked into pixel PX to begin with.
Right?
So we could have just said that this is pixel p x here right?
And we could have just done this n m sub PS just at the at the
beginning right?
We could have just done this right off the bat and said that's that's
the value of pixel PX.
And furthermore, pixel py will pixel peep
Why doesn't change pixel p y is constant across the road, right?
So pixel p y could be doing that, just the same.
So that was just us, you know, we hadn't really started looking at
optimizing the code yet.
So I guess, you know, again we sort of get
What we deserve their, which is fine.
But anyway, so there we go.
And hey, we were actually two cycles faster.
Now, it looks like roughly thereabouts, so that's good too.
When I look at some of these other things here, you can sort of see
oddly enough.
Like I don't even know, maybe the U and the V even want to be done
that way.
Because if you look at what's happening with the U and the V, those
are also going to be sort of baked in, right?
We're doing this.
Mmm mole PS.
This MLPs or pixel wide here is never going to change across the row,
right?
So these two values, these two values here, are not going to change
across the row, and if you take a look at these two values, they're
multiplying pixel PX, by whatever these two axes are.
We could do that.
We could actually have two variables that we incremented and, and sort
of pull those out as well.
But I don't really need to.
I don't think we actually necessarily need to do that just yet, but
what we can do is say, all right.
Let's actually just store.
May be the result of these two multiplications up and then do the ad
in there.
That seems pretty reasonable.
It does create two variables.
We have to store though.
Mmm.
Hmm.
That one's that when I'm less sure about.
Yeah, well, let's try it.
I'm kind of, I don't know, I kind of got into it now and since I'm
into it, I just want to see it's not not necessarily the fairest test
of them all, but let's just, let's just see.
So we'll just call this like, temp, 0 and temp1 just to test and see
what happens.
So, if I were to do that, if I'm going to get this out of here, temp,
Right.
Like so.
And get this out of here.
So this is kind of one.
And it's clear that those are constant across the road.
Does that help the compiler at all?
Does the compiler, do anything Smarter with
And I don't know, it actually looks like that's a little bit worse so
it would rather generate those values from the mall, that's totally
fair so we'll leave that as it is for now.
All right, so let me just do another since since that kind of
happened, let me do a quick pass over this and see if there's anything
else before we get down.
To actually looking at how long things take, let's make sure that our
Loop actually isn't doing anything to incredibly stupid so that we
aren't like wasting our time counting things that actually should
never happen to begin with.
So we're doing our clamping here of the U and the V, which all seems
totally fair.
We are doing our subs to get our fractional coordinates, and that also
seems fair.
We then have to do our texture fetching, which, at the moment.
Obviously is having to be done in scalar but there's not a lot that we
can really do about that being in scalar because that is just kind of
the nature of the Beast.
We don't have the ability to fetch wide, so that's just kind of,
that's just going to be that way.
When we do our unpacking cure, it doesn't look like there's anything
weird that we're doing with the unpack.
It looks pretty reasonable to me, right?
It's just it doing the standard stuff.
Need to do, obviously, the, and then we need to do the convert and so
on, let's see.
We've got loading the destination, we've got converting to brightness,
all of this stuff seemed pretty reasonable.
So I thought I don't think that we really had a lot of kind of pure
stupidity in there.
Like we did kind of the top of the loop where it looks like we really
hadn't played with anything.
So yeah.
Oh,
oh and incidentally for those of you who missed it, on Twitter, Bobby
and wrote in and said why the mask move you, si128 was not helping and
he said it was because
Actually it is an instruction that that should never be used for any
reason because I guess it is completely useless.
It bypasses the cash it's a non-temporal store which means it writes
past the cash.
It does not actually right into the cache.
So it's it's not just as simple as a mass move.
It's a separate type of thing.
We haven't really talked about that stuff yet so I don't want to go
into too much detail.
But he basically said,
Never ever ever call this.
Someone asked about it on the stream and so I wanted to show it there
and we checked it out and it was three times slower and Fabian was
saying, yeah, there's pretty much never a time when you can use that
function well, that instruction.
He said it's basically always bad.
So yeah, I guess that's just something to be aware of.
All right, we're down to 48 cycles per pixel.
So that's a good thing.
What we want to do now is we want to go ahead and start doing that
counting, cuz I think we got rid of any anything that was like,
obviously stupid in here.
So what I want to do is I want to go through all of the actual M&M's
things that we call and I want to just basically record the fact that
we're calling them so that I don't have to count these things
manually, right?
So,
So what I want to do here is basically say okay you know every single
one of these that we have and then add PS and then mul PS.
Let's see.
Em em cast PS.
We've got em em and
and I more,
Well, we don't have any more there.
I guess.
Never mind.
We've got cop Vee.
We've got cop Ellie.
And let's see.
So then we've got our load you
Which is loading in that pixel value.
We've got arm in PS and Max BS.
Then we have our conversions.
And we've got conversions in both directions.
Should probably go ahead and do this.
Here we go.
This will be much more efficient.
So we've got the Epi PS there.
There we go.
So that's all good and
I don't see anything in there.
We have the extraction to do that.
We're going to probably have to think about that, a little bit small,
you know, basically a little separately.
So, here's our.
And here is our shift.
and,
Looks like all of that is covered.
You got are squaring instruction.
We have a bunch of moles which we've already counted.
We've got our sub, which we did.
We already do now.
We did not do the sub.
Let's get the sub in the ad in.
There are sub.
We've got our moles moles subs and moles convert PS epi32.
Freddy got
Those and we got our shift left those.
We do not have yet so those got to go in there.
And there's our or finally.
So there's our four.
There we go.
And also an and not
So, this looks like basically all the stuff we do.
and I'm going to actually say that the load and the
load in the store.
I'm not going to look at right now but this looks like basically what
we do for all intents and purposes.
So what I would like to do
Is actually, this is very strange.
I know this is a bizarre thing to be doing but it is what we are going
to do.
I'm just going to Define these guys to be something that counts for
us, right?
So I just want this to basically count.
How many of each thing?
There are right.
Pretty straightforward.
So what I want to do is basically do something like you know that
Count off.
Like so.
And this count up will.
I guess probably what I want to do here is something like I want to be
able to print these out.
Right.
Well not really print them out.
I want to be able to do something with them such that they can sort of
be appended.
So what I can probably do is actually I guess I don't even really need
to do a count up on them per se.
What I could do instead is I could do something where we're just going
to go like counts you know plus plus something like this.
Right.
I think that should work fairly well.
Okay.
So just do something that looks like this and really I suppose this is
a good place for a macro I can just do something that's like okay you
know go ahead and search for that go to the end to a plus plus counts,
paste it in there, I guess.
delete that off the end and then at the end of it,
Crap.
So now I've got something that's going to count all those as they are
actually being executed, right?
And I'm going to need some way of actually making sure that these
Expressions all work right?
I need some way of these actually producing something.
So I think I probably also need to
These guys in something, right?
So I need to do sort of like a dummy, some kind of a dummy rapper that
will make sure because in this expression like a mole PS, it's going
to come out em.
You know.
It's going to need to be able to put something in there.
Although, you know what?
Now that I think about it, I suppose that's not actually true.
Because as long as these things are, all just stuff that takes
parameters,
I suppose it would just kind of work in a weird way.
I don't know if that's actually true, I'm not sure.
I'm not sure if that's actually true.
But I think it might be.
So yeah, that's weird II never thought of that before, but I guess if
I just actually put these in here, we should actually be able to get
the C compiler to just also do all the operations for us.
It's that's just that
Yeah.
That engine just count.
The other one, sir.
That's kind of strange.
I never really thought about that before, but I think that actually
might just work, we'll find out in a second, certainly, but yeah.
Alright, so that way it'll count.
As you can see, I'm making the macro so that it will basically count
its own up and then insert whatever was supposed to happen from the
previous Ops, which will be, you know,
Which will be some kind of a another count, right?
All right.
So we go.
and,
Almost done.
I guess shift by an immediate wouldn't need to count the immediate.
So, there we go.
Yeah, I don't know if that actually works or not it's pretty strange
but we're going to try it.
We'll see how it goes.
All right.
So then I'm just going to make a going to go ahead and make here a
little struct for our accounts.
And again, I'm going to go ahead and macro that.
I'm just going to go to the plus, plus I'm going to delete it off.
I'm gonna make an inch here, search for that and kill it.
And then that way I can just kind of run through these and turn them
all into something reasonable.
Yeah.
And what we want to do, 4M, M square.
Right is, MM, square is just a mole, right?
So we want to increase the mole PS count, when we do RM, M square, and
that takes one of these.
So, now, let's see if this ridiculous stunt actually works.
I, you know, when I say ridiculous stunt, I mean, it it's pretty
ridiculous.
So let's go ahead and
To make counts thing that we can clear cannot convert from intz.
Oh, that's true.
These Guys, these M 128.
That's okay.
We'll just pretend the number 128 is an intent for now, and that is
probably going to be that.
All right, initialising cannot convert from into mm1 to me, I that's
also true.
Gotta make sure that goes there.
And then, what's going on here?
Are load.
You si128 cannot convert in Star.
So our load you, we have to at least Define these to go away to
nothing.
Mmm score.
You 728 be?
All right.
See how that goes.
We still have a few problems syntax error on the semicolon so load you
si128 that's going to be in its original dust equals up.
You have to actually make it be something though.
Oh we forgot squirt PS and we forgot looks like we look what did one
other one in properly as well?
So let's make sure that
Got everybody here, fine, mmm, squirt PS, a-plus-plus counts.
Mmm, squirt.
PS
And we got to add that to our guy here, squirt.
PS.
And by the way, everything that I'm doing here is something the
compiler should output for you.
It's absolutely absurd, that it doesn't.
But that's just what you get when your development environment doesn't
care about low-level programmers, right?
I mean, use this should just be a thing that you just get
automatically from the compiler and it's kind of ridiculous that you
don't.
So, let's see here.
Convert p.s.
I guess I didn't have this one convert.
PS.
Did I did convert teeth?
Yes, but I didn't do convert PS, so there we go.
And that looks like the last one.
So, there we go.
Everything looks good.
There are mmm, add PS, binary equals 0, that's outside.
So we need to do an undef of mmm.
Add PS here although that add PS actually does happen.
So I guess technically we should really sort of be counting it.
So we're going to be one ad off because of this guy, that makes sense.
But let's go ahead and see here.
Undef mmm, add PS.
okay, so now
We do not need to be compiling in release mode anymore, right?
You can go ahead and do that.
And we can take a look at how much many things we actually asked for
now that's not the same as how many things happened, right?
Because the compiler is going to do a bunch of stuff to it but it's
just a way for us to count all of the actual, excuse me.
All of the actual instructions.
There were actually asking the compiler to generate on our behalf, so
when we get down to the end of this here so we're going to go counts
here, right?
We're going to go ahead through here and down to here.
I guess we will have to also get rid of our texture, fetch Loop,
because this is all going to be complete garbage data.
Let's go ahead and do that.
Okay.
Just got to clear these out because otherwise, compiler will complain.
And cannot convert to 2nt.
Oh right.
I didn't have to do that.
Those were integers.
So that's fine.
You can just do this.
All right.
so, if we do this count,
I shouldn't there a be able to run this and actually see what the
counts all end up being, right?
So, if we take a look at it here, here we go.
And you can see that we've got, I mean assuming that I didn't mess
something up, right?
We've got how many of each of these things.
We are actually calling every time through the loop.
Now I want to actually check to see if this looks like it makes any
sense.
I don't want to just assume that that's actually correct.
So let's go ahead and pick one of them.
Let's do Min, PS and see if it actually.
Looks like it's getting called the right number of times, right?
So that's 1.
2 3 4 5.
That's that's just right.
And then Max PS, similarly, 1 2 3 4 5.
Yeah, so that all looks pretty good and then Square looks good at PS.
So let's check one more of them.
Let's do a big one.
Now.
MLPs, well, that's 73.
Let's do em.
Add PS.
So, mmm, add PS.
we've got 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18
So, that should be 18 and it is.
All right.
So this basically tells us, right, what our total operation count is
right.
That's the whole thing right there.
That's how many operations we actually needed to do.
And we could if we wanted to also, go ahead and start to actually look
at these and multiply them by their actual latencies.
Right?
Like, for example, I could go ahead and
That counts tracked down here when it gets to the end.
I could produce another count struct.
That's actually the latency for these guys, right?
So if I took this count struct and I just come down here and I say,
all right, you know, right after we finish we're in here, I want to
take this count struct, I don't want to say latency counts, right?
Something like this.
I want to go in and do well, I guess I don't even need to make it
struct for it.
I could just make these
he's in be floats to.
Here we go.
And each of these can just be whatever the count was for this guy,
right?
Times whatever.
The throughput value is.
So we can go over to the intrinsics guide.
Doodoo.
And we can take a look at what these actually are right, and then add
PS and so on.
Now, of course, the throughput value differs sometimes, but thankfully
for some of these, it's going to be the same.
So the throughput on the ad is, is one, right?
The throughput on the sub is probably the same.
you would imagine and it is
throughput on the mall.
Oops, that's not what I want to do.
Is one on this one.
We are not a Haswell processor.
The through put on the cast, PS is really difficult to estimate
because I suppose the cast PS is is not really late, unless it has the
situation Fabien was alluding to.
So I guess we don't actually know what that one is, will assume that
we can do it for free somehow and and not counted for now.
All right, throughput here I guess.
So I don't actually know what processors family were running on right
now.
What I might do is just take a quick second to figure out, let's see.
I want to be able to right click on my computer and hit properties.
So this is a z on 5580, right?
So what is a z on 5580?
What is the family?
Or the core type.
I guess is what what I want to know, okay, it's launched.
Thank you very much for that.
Can you tell me that the core type?
I don't care about any of these things.
Give me some more.
Give me something better, nail, mmm.
So that's what it is.
So on an inhale emits 0.33, that's kind of crazy, if that's what it
says.
Let's hope that's accurate, right?
Mmm and PS is actually says that.
That's what that is.
So we'll trust him for now.
We should probably be looking at agner fog because that's probably a
more trustworthy Source, but at the moment that would take a lot.
Longer and time is of the essence on the stream, huh?
GE TS.
Again with looks like we don't have a throughput on here.
I believe the throughput on this is one, but we should probably double
check it.
Anyone who wants to go ahead and double check that on a on a on agner
that would be good cop.
Ellie
I think that's also one can't belly.
And then we've got Min and Max.
So, Min PS.
And Max PS.
Both one.
And then we've got convert TPS epi32 and convert.
So what are those convert?
PS epi32?
That is one
And this one is also won a lot of these guys are just one.
And if you're at wondering why I'm putting in x one, just mental note.
So it's like, okay, we got it.
Convert epi32, PS.
It's going.
The other direction also won.
Then we've got our and
zoom Italy.
This is the same speed.
It is.
Looks like the bitwise.
Are all a third of a cycle.
Presumably, I'm just going to go ahead and guess that the and not is
the same.
Yeah.
You know what should probably do.
1.0 F, over 3.0 F and do like third or something like this.
And and have these guys actually just used that so that it's a little
more precise than the ridiculous version that they were using on the,
on the form there.
All right, so there's the nth not.
So, let's take a look at the shift, right?
SL R II, slrs are iupi 32?
That's a throughput one as well.
And so, presumably the left shift will also.
Be that way.
So SLL.
I epi32.
Yep.
And the squirt.
Now, squirt, if I remember correctly, was a pretty brutal one.
So, on a Halo, that's a 16 cycle, all right.
So we now have all of these guys put together here, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and do a little more Ridiculousness.
I'm just going to put all these guys inside.
A some like so
These guys are.
I guess, just zero,
We'll go ahead and use our power of macro again.
So search for that.
So I guess I should do it this way search for that.
Okay.
And to continue the absurdity, we'll just do some of a equals.
A oops, sorry a and then total plus equals a right.
So yeah, that way we can do a total equals zero and then at the end,
we'll get an actual total right?
Seems reasonable.
What is the problem here?
You're sizing for into real 32?
Oh well, you know what?
That's pretty easy for us to to fix.
We can just go ahead and
and change all of the stars.
Man, today is some good hackery.
This is just some some good hackery we just change all the stars two
commas, right?
Then we can do like latency and the thing, right?
So then we can just do real 32 a wait-and-see times that thing like so
and we can make that
Be what we add to the total as well.
Totally crazy.
Don't try this at home.
So yeah, there we go.
And in theory I can now go get some sort of a throughput total for
myself.
And this is only in theory, so where we at, here's our counts.
And here is our total.
Well.
Isn't that fancy?
Ladies and gentlemen?
How does that number Look to You 218?
Total cycles of throughput that is if we were to do everything.
Exactly perfectly.
So that all the instructions, just slammed to the processor.
That's what we would get.
Well, we are filling for pixels at a time.
That means somehow.
Right, our actual measured, throughput is slightly lower than what the
theoretical maximum would be.
If all of those things were just issued back-to-back, okay?
So that's a good sign for starters.
And I assume that just means that a lot of these things are getting
issued in parallel.
That's, that's basically, the only thing I can assume in order for us
to have to be that low with, that essentially means,
Is that we're, issuing, multiple instructions per cycle, so that we're
not actually ever having to even weight, the throughput total we're
sort of overlapping things as we go.
So, in order to calculate a total for this,
The next like lowest total that we could get to.
This is just to say I was kind of hoping we would be above this total
already but we're not.
So this total is basically what the total would be if there was only
one unit executing all of the instructions, but they were all
perfectly overlap.
So you just stream them seriously through the processor maximum,
throughput.
Now, what we saw is we actually got that, right?
We're actually getting slightly below that.
It says that that that would give us about 50 for Cycles.
Total 55 Cycles, we're actually getting like 48.
Cycles right now.
So we're actually better than what that suggests right.
And I think we didn't count this ad, right?
So this ad, it should actually be a little bit higher.
So what that means is we're actually getting a lot of pairing in here
and in order to count the pairing, we would need to know essentially
how many is of these instructions we could issue at any given time,
right?
Now, I have no idea how many units this guy has.
I don't even know where I can get that data.
So, this ought to be interesting.
Let's go ahead and look at the W.
5580 again, I don't know where to find out.
How many units the thing has.
I don't think they tell you on here.
In fact, I'm pretty sure they don't tell you but we do know it's an
inhale.
Mm core.
So maybe we can take a wild leap.
And see.
Okay, so let's see.
What is it have?
Okay, we don't care about Cassius right now.
We don't care about any of these things.
Right now, we just want to know what kind of units it has in it and
this does not tell us that so maybe I can search.
Wow.
Look at this stuff.
Price for 1K unit.
Those are expensive.
All right, anyway, so I wonder if I can say like alus or something.
Just, I don't know if there's something in here that would tell us how
many ports it has, how many, you know things that can issue at once
because that's really
That's really all we want to know.
Let's see, technology scaling up issues rapid execution, engine, blah,
blah, blah.
now, if this actually helps
This may be one of those things where we just have to put it on, hold
for a minute and actually ask someone who knows better than we do.
Which would be nice to have here but unfortunately we don't, let's
see.
Yeah, I know this is, this is not what we want.
I just want to know how many instructions are can issue at a time?
Well, let's take a look and the hail, mmm.
How many l use?
Texas A&M.
Okay let's see here.
Cache hierarchy main memory virtual memory hey Lem data pipeline out
of order execution execution pipelines, load and store assembly
operations.
Well, this might
Have some of that for us but I don't know.
Let's see it.
Registers in helium core contains the authority to carry out to double
Precision or for single Precision positioning in each of the one of
the 2fp units assessable through Port 0 and 1.
Okay so we have 2 FP units that we can issue to so On Any Given cycle
that would assume assuming that I'm reading this correctly that would
mean that we could issue for example to multiplies or ads or things
like that.
Assuming that they're same.
Steady state conditions, each core can retire for double Precision or
eight single Precision, floating Point operations, each cycle.
So that, yeah, that would make sense the time idea, throughput in core
quad core Cycles.
So that, that is
That is reasonable.
See if there's anything else.
We can learn from this here.
So assuming that there were two of those and if we look at the kinds
of stuff we have here and separate these out, right?
So, these are all the guys that go through.
We don't, let's see if we can get.
Does this actually have the port listing on it?
So, unfortunately, what we don't get from this piece of information
here, right?
From this intrinsics guide, it doesn't tell us what instructions can
be issued.
What other instructions if you remember back to, when we talked about
CPU architectures and optimization, I was saying that, you know, I
believe in x64 oppressor can issue up to four instructions at once,
right?
But you know which, which instructions they are matters.
It can't just issue any for instructions at once.
Because as we talked about again, that same time when I was talking
about this, I was saying there has to be a unit free, that can
actually accept that instruction.
So if there is only two months,
Multipliers total on the chip right?
That it doesn't matter.
If can in theory issue for instructions, it can only issue to multiply
instructions because there's only two possible places to shove those
multiplies.
There are another two units to kick off.
Even though the front end of the processor would be totally capable of
doing so if those units do exist but they don't write.
So what we want to see here if we were going to try and get this
calculation down to something more accurate, what we want to see is we
want to know
To these instructions.
You know?
How many of them we can issue per cycle, basically?
Right.
And so, that would give us an idea of what these multipliers would
actually be.
Now, if everything could be issued to per cycle, if two per cycle was
this, the average that we could issue, let's say then we would know
that we just take the total and we divide it by 2, right?
So we take that total and instead of dividing by 4, we'd actually
divide it by 8 and that would give us twenty seven Cycles would be
sort of the maximum throughput that we could ever.
Hope to possibly achieve you.
This set of things that we're doing, right?
So I don't know, right?
I think we're at a little bit of an impasse here.
We're going to need more information about the particular process that
we're on in order to get a better estimate.
But I'm actually relatively happy even though I don't think we can do
that without a little bit more information and something they probably
don't want to do on stream.
Like we could go hunt through under fog tables.
The ports are probably listed on there.
We've actually gotten a piece of information that's actually pretty
valuable.
Which is that even just right now knowing that we're at about,
48 Cycles or something like that per pixel.
We're actually very, very close to the threshold.
We're optimizing it further just in terms of the actual mathematical
operations.
If we were going to keep doing them wouldn't actually get us very much
faster.
Right.
Because if it really is true that there's only like two multipliers or
two floating Point.
Things can be issued every cycle you know looking down here at twenty
seven Cycles it's like okay we're not running very far behind that.
Actual theoretical throughput right now we could we get a little
closer probably.
Yes.
But it's kind of a point of diminishing returns there right?
It's like we don't have that much Headroom to go so it sort of looks
like I actually got what I wanted from this even though it's not
particularly accurate yet which is I have an idea now of whether or
not something like say memory latency was hurting us and it looks like
it really wasn't, right?
Because look at how you know with with how close it appears that we
are there.
It looks like
The cash was operating quite well for us.
Very friendly.
It doesn't look like we're having a lot of problems with stalls or
anything like this, right?
So that's a pretty interesting thing.
That's a pretty good thing for us to know.
Now what I'd like to do as well is take a quick look at what happens
under a couple of different conditions here.
So what I want to do is make some way that we can, if that this out
easily.
So I want to basically make a thing that's like Define count Cycles or
something like this, right?
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to do an if on that, right?
So that if that is not defined, right then, it doesn't.
It lets things operate properly.
Right?
So we do it, if count cycles, and then down here we do.
And if count Cycles again, right?
Like so cycles and that way we can just turn it on and off.
Anytime we want to cycle count and it doesn't actually do anything
weird for us, right?
So, here we go.
Change this around though, okay.
so,
let's take a look at something here.
Oh, right, we're in debug mode, still.
Debug mode is quite a bit slower.
Okay.
Alright, so here we are.
At our forty eight ish cycles per pixel.
What I wanted to do is take a look at how bad One screwed us here.
Let's just, let's just get it out in the open.
Let's look at how badly Juan Chun one Chun screwed us.
That's, that's where we're at.
He is the person who demanded that we put in gamma correction.
Honestly, I don't think it made very much of a difference but he's
correct.
It was a good thing to talk about.
Either way it was, it was
Isn't that we looked at it even if we choose to get rid of it and
basically having the squirt in here is really bad, okay?
So what I'd like to do is see what happens if we get rid of the
squirt.
What will our performance look like then.
So, we've got two cases where this gets used.
We have a mole PS here, so we're doing our Square.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to come down here and instead of
em em squirt PS, what I'm going to do is we're going to remove that,
right?
So I'm going to say all right I want to Define m m Square.
We're going to undef that and I'm Square.
I wanted to find in the Square a as just a
So M squared is does not do anything.
And then I'm going to Define, mmm, squirt PS2.
Also not do anything.
So I'm just undoing the gamma correction so that it's just gone,
right?
It's gone.
and so, if I run that,
Let's see where we're at.
Oh well, it doesn't look right though.
So we've got some kind of weird fringing going on.
So what did I do there?
That should work.
Should it not to do the squaring?
I wonder do we have something gamma corrected that I'm not thinking of
here.
Let's see here Square.
We've got the mul PS but so that's just going to leave things.
The same after doing the inverse.
So that's all should be fine.
Let's see what happens here.
The desk gets raised to that power, so that's fine.
And then we do the square root after we're done to put things back.
So why are we getting that?
That's a little troubling to me.
What's going on there because that should not be the case, right?
That is not what we wanted to see.
Something is amiss, something is awry and I'm not sure what it is.
so,
It's like the clamping isn't actually working.
Where is our clamping.
So we do our sub PS here Texel, LPS dust our.
And those are squares as well.
Yeah, I'm not.
I don't know what the problem is.
Does anyone see what the problem is there?
Well, I got three minutes left but I'd like to know what what's going
on there.
Right.
You can very clearly see that around the edges, right?
We've got that problem.
Oh, I know what we probably have to do.
Yes, when we load the bitmap, I always forget exactly where we are
with things when we load the bitmap.
We actually converted the bitmap.
We converted the bitmap that way as well.
So what we would need to do here is we would need to not do this this
in and out, right?
That's all we would need to do, I believe oops.
That was not right srgb to linear one.
Linear one to srgb.
I take that back.
We would need to move this below.
That's what we actually need to do.
Of course that does not look good at all, but that's what should be
right.
Because if we post, if we pre-multiply the alpha
That's what actually should be working, right?
Because we can't leave it with the conversion.
Leaving it with the conversion.
Like that means that the alpha won't be the correct value for
compositing with premultiplied Alpha, right?
Because it's doing the premultiplied alpha as if we were going to do
an srgb conversion.
So it but we should be able to just leave it without doing the pre
multiplication and then pre-multiply after, right?
And for some reason that gives us completely garbage values,
Which I oh duh, because Texel a gets converted.
Yeah.
Try that one more time.
Oh, and see, everything's going to be 255 there.
Oh, wait, no, no, that's fine, that's still fine.
I just didn't use the variable actually, set up.
Slow down the street.
All right, so that's fine.
So we don't actually need to do any of that.
I just wanted to verify that we didn't have some other bug.
Obviously, we don't care.
I'm just doing a speed test, so that's all fine.
So that's all good.
Nothing to worry about there.
So doing this speed test, it looks like one has not heard us too
badly, right?
You know.
It's not great.
You know we've got we've got like six Cycles or something that we
saved from from not doing the gamma correction but it's not awful,
right?
It's not like it's twice as fast or something like that.
So at the moment without doing any more work to optimize this one
Could rest easy knowing that?
He is not ruined all of handmade hero with his gamma correction,
right?
So okay.
So, at this point, I am fairly satisfied to say that this is a pretty
reasonably optimized pixel Loop All Things Considered, especially when
you consider the fact that we've got this ridiculous and snapping in
here, that has to go fetch, all these pixel values, which is kind of
ridiculous, right?
So it looks pretty good to me.
Actually, it's not that slow.
Could it get faster?
Yes.
Could it get more than twice as fast?
Probably not.
And so,
I think it may be a good time after having done that count.
I'm pretty happy with where that is.
I think it may be time to move out one level and start to look at how
to optimize the things that are around this pixel Loop.
Because I think the pixel Loop itself is actually not so bad, so
that's probably what we'll start doing tomorrow.
And at the moment we will go do some Q&A so we can
Answer any questions that people might have.
Seller 7 asks, is this what you were looking for?
Oh yeah, this is what I was looking for.
That's pretty cool.
So there's loads and storage units.
We don't care about those right now.
We've got integer, m, x ALU branch in room associated, with an FP, a
deaf, be mole, SSE mole, integer m, x, ALU
oh,
Wait, but this looks weird donut.
looking at this diagram,
I should probably try to bring this this dial diagram up on the main
screen because because it's a little confusing.
Honestly Stellar 7
so, so let's see here, that is
Wikimedia Nehalem diagram, see if we can get that up on the screen.
So this guy.
Oops, not that guy.
This guy.
So it's a little confusing looking at this because if you look at
this, I'm just looking at where the multiplier unit seems to be and
and like, it looks like it's single ported, doesn't it?
Yes.
I mean I mean they said that it could do that.
It had two units capable of doing a floating Point multiplied but this
diagram would make it look like there's only one.
Wouldn't you say?
Because here's FP mole, it's on Port 80.
I don't see any other FP.
Moles there's an FB ad, right?
But but I don't see another mul so I could be misinterpreting what
this diagram trying to say, but that's a little odd.
but that's a little odd if the port if the 0, if you could only issue
1 x per cycle,
Then that would mean that we are basically at our, I mean, we're like
right at the limit of what we could possibly do if we have to do this
many multiplies, right?
Because if I turn on count Cycles again, most of what we were doing
was multiplies, right?
And so if we take a look in here,
Let's go ahead and stop in here.
So, if we take a look in here, right?
We had to do 73 multiplies.
So, if you could only do, if you could only issue 1, multiply if you
could only issue 1 x per cycle, that means that essentially we know
that, even if everything else was perfectly pipelined with it, we
would take seventy three Cycles just to do the multiplies, right?
Because they can only be issued once every clock at a maximum, right?
So
Assuming that we did that.
Let's see what that value comes out to be.
So that means just the multiplies our would take 18 Cycles by
themselves.
So that's that's kind of crazy, right?
But yeah, 18 cycles per pixel.
Would it be worth timing?
Just the load stores with no ALU Ops present to see how much is Just
memory bound.
Yes.
But you're getting a little ahead of us.
They're grumpy giant.
We haven't actually aligned our loads and stores yet and we haven't
actually talked much about the loads and stores at all.
And so, what I kind of wanted to do was do that in a separate pass.
So tomorrow when we kind of step out, one level will time it and we'll
we'll time it without the Ops and we'll see how it goes.
But if you want to try it right now, we can, we can jump the gun since
you brought it up.
I'm totally happy to just type it in.
So let's see here, you have an O2.
We turn off the count Cycles.
So here we are and we're running it.
Forty eight ish, right?
If we wanted to turn off all of the fancy operations that were
actually doing, right?
And we were just instead did some some loads and stores here.
Unfortunately, it's a little tricky.
Because in order to know where we're fetching from, we have to, at
least do this, many, but we can go ahead and get rid of most of this
stuff, right?
So once we have all of our samples, trying to think of, we have to
have a way of doing this so that the compiler won't optimize these
guys.
Out right?
We have to have it so that they won't optimize out.
So what I could do is do an if 0 here I suppose and we just go through
and before we write we just do something like this.
I guess.
I mean, 128, I out equals mmm or si128 sample?
A sample B.
So basically you know compositing all of the samples together into
some garbage pattern just to make sure the compiler has to actually
load them that make sense and then it'll go ahead and do that, right?
Right, another fantastic wild pattern here.
So looking at that.
That's 16 Cycles looks like right.
And I don't know if I can trim it down anymore to be any closer to
just memory Ops because we have to know where to fetch from.
in order to be like, if we don't face
From the actual locations, then it would change the cache behavior and
it wouldn't necessarily be the right kind of test at that point.
So I don't know that I can actually get rid of very much more.
The compiler will get rid of FX for us, presumably, because it is
never used, but it looks like that's like the minimum, right?
So 16 Cycles, just to put that into some perspective there, you know,
it's got to do.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
You know, yeah.
I mean, I guess I would say, I guess what I would say about that,
Is it's possible that we're stalling on the memory here a bit because
16 Cycles is probably a little bit High.
What we could do is we could try blasting out as another test, right?
We could try blasting out without reading in these guys, right?
So, you know, what we could do is say this stuff.
We're actually going to F0 around the whole thing, right?
And what we'll do is we'll take sample, ABC and d and will actually
just derive those from values, we already had, right?
So, what we'll do is we'll say, you know, we'll make this be an M&M
cast PS, right?
Of
You know, the x value or something like this, right?
The, the fetch X, right?
And
Oops.
I guess I just need to be a cast that can just be fetch X so we can
just do something like this.
In fact, I could just do it this way.
Out is fat checks.
Or checks, that's why.
It's not fetch, its fetch Forex course.
Xxxx.
and,
So that'll just write out complete nonsense and so, yeah.
So you can see that is three cycles per pixel which is quite a bit
better.
So a lot of that time there was spent, I guess doing sort of well, we
don't really know.
We know that
Had to compute fat checks.
So I mean technically like right we don't know how much the time was
just spent getting the crap out of the SS.
The mm 128 register.
Right?
So we don't really know what was waiting on the textures.
You know, we don't really know that it was the fetch, it could have
been other stuff technically, but it does seem like maybe this is a
fair chunk of the time, right?
Which is what we would have expected.
It's fetching.
Those textiles is is very expensive, right?
You counted, mmm, and PS wrong.
I'm surprised I didn't count more than just mnps, but let's go ahead
and take a look and then and PS.
So it looks like it's getting counted properly there, right?
Pound to find.
Mnps counts, right?
That that looks correct to me.
So let's take a look at the bottom one.
There we go.
Okay.
Thank you for catching that.
Are you doing premultiplied Alpha?
Yes.
Out of Interest.
Could you run the game with task manager?
Open I'm interested to see what the ram CPU are doing well.
The ram isn't doing anything because we just allocated all the memory
in the machine when we started up and then never actually touch it
after that, right?
And the CPU won't do anything either.
The CPU will be like, hardly anything.
What is take?
What?
Who is 0, right?
OBS.
I'm like, what's taking all the time?
Right?
The thing, that streaming, of course, makes perfect sense.
So yeah.
Task manager.
We're hardly using any of the CPU, right now, right?
I don't think anyway.
So, there you go.
This, what you want to see?
and like I said, you know, we're not,
We're on a miss this machine old.
As it may be, is a beast in terms of core count so you can see how
many cores we've got here.
We're only using one and these are not actual chords.
Their logical course.
So it's
Probably I don't know this machine probably has say 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10 11 12 13 14 15 16.
So this is probably a dual proc Each of which has 4 cores would be my
guess.
And and then each one of those course, has to hyper threads.
That's my assumption.
So eventually and hopefully not too long from now.
We will actually use all of these cores and will get quite a bit of
speed up but right now we're not we're not even close to maxing out
the performance of the CPU right now, not even close.
All we did was look at one core throughput on
On our pixel fill routine.
Right?
That's all.
We've done so far.
In terms of optimization, we're not even close to using all the power
of the CPU.
Will this game only work for your specific processor?
Know this game will work on any sse2 capable processor which is
basically any PC processor on a Mac or or on a on a Windows machine.
Are you going to update these textures?
E-x the yellow background.
Well the yellow background is actually there because we turned off
ground chunk updating right because we haven't gone in and redone it
with the new rendering system and we had a bunch of stuff we need to
do with that anyway, right.
So if we turned it on,
We could see the ground tiles right there in there, but we aren't
working on that right now, so that's why they're they're not there,
right?
The texture.
Fetch should be L1 cache, fetch.
Well, we don't know that right, you know, we would hope that that's
true in certain circumstances but we don't really know if that's
always true because it could be that the processor can't see it in
time or other sorts of things like this.
So we don't really know.
And so I feel like it's too early to say something like that.
In an alternate universe where Everyone likes games, but no one cares
for art.
So game developers don't need or use our assets.
Do you think those developers would spend as much time carefully
optimizing things?
I don't know what that means.
Probably, yes.
Because the reason you optimized stuff is usually, so you can do more
things not so that you can use art assets.
Like, you got if you want to have 100,000 guys, in a battle, it don't
matter if they're all red rectangles, or, you know, bitmaps of the
guy, right?
Or, you know, in 3D, it doesn't matter if they're little artist
mannequins or, you know, or you know, fully modelled dudes.
Now,
Maybe you could argue that, if you're doing art, that's going to look
bad, anyway, then it can be lower.
Polygon count, less textures, all that sort of stuff, which does help
you.
And yeah, that's true.
But you'd still have other things to optimize, right?
It's not just being able to Art assets, aren't the only thing that
that require you to do optimization.
Any ideas, why?
One of my core is get maxed out running handmade hero with the xeb
platform layer.
Yeah that's what should happen.
Basically.
One Core is getting maxed out when you run handmade hero,
Because we are running basically full speed right now.
Well, that's probably not entirely true.
Now we're probably running faster than 30 frames a second, but that's
separate issue.
But one core should at least be pretty heavy usage, but Windows is
free to move that around.
So it's not necessarily the case that it will show up on exactly when
processor graph.
So what you'll typically, see when you run handmade Heroes, you should
see basically a
Little percentage usage of the total CPU power which is 1 over the
number of course in your machine.
Right 1 over the number of hyper cours saleya.
How did taking out the gamma correction three square roots with a
throughput of 16 cycles and 3 multiplies.
Only speed the loop up by six Cycles?
Well the answer is that these things are overlapped, right?
Once the processor kicks off a square root, it's free to do other
stuff, right?
It's not sitting around.
Waiting for that square root to come back.
So the fact that we're getting rid of these things that are worth 16
Cycles well it's 16 Cycles end to end but it the you know, inside that
16 Cycles, the processor can grab all sorts of other work to do right
and especially with these sort of out-of-work, whores processors, even
if the compiler did a lousy job of putting of scheduling the
instructions, the processor is still
Bring all sorts of future work to do while we're sitting around,
waiting for those square, roots to finish.
So that is the key.
You know, that's the thing we talked about way back, when I talk about
pipeline processors, if you don't remember that, go back to the
original episode a week ago.
I think it was last Monday, or whenever it was last Monday or Tuesday.
Where I talked about how pipelining Works.
Basically processors have, you know, every cycle, they've got a lot of
things in flight.
The issue new instructions.
They pick up old instructions that got completed and there's this
pipeline of stuff, that's moving through.
So, getting rid of something that takes 16 Cycles, these things are
not put into end, so it's not like you saved.
16 Cycles.
All you did is get rid of 116 cycle thing that had to get overlapped
in there somewhere.
And so, usually what you end up talking about is more about when units
are free to execute stuff and how many total units you had and how
busy they all were right.
And so that's why I was trying to get a little bit more information
about that, but we don't quite have what we need to really compute it
all out.
But
If you were to use more cores for drawing, how would you split up the
work?
Well, we're actually going to do this.
That's what we're going to do next.
So stay tuned.
Next week will probably be all about splitting up the course for
drawing.
What's the floating head?
It's our little familiar.
I didn't see the definition of m m square but if it's a macro you're
calling it with an intrinsic.
So either a compiler isn't eliminating common sub expression and
you're losing perf or B.
It is doing common sub-expression elimination in your miscounting.
Instructions, nothing's, I believe neither of those.
Two things is true.
It is doing common sub expression elimination because we check that
the other day because someone asked about that and it did actually
correctly, do it?
But I'm pretty sure that we don't because you can see when we did the
count.
We just did we just count it as one multiply
Right.
So, I'm pretty sure the answer is actually C.
None of the above
But I don't know if that answered the question.
What's that drum, like background noise?
Yeah.
The drum, like, background noise is amazon.com.
They've been building buildings next to our apartment for a very,
very, very, very, very long time.
Do you see all the questions and select from them or should I write
again if you miss my question?
Yes I do read all the questions and select for them but I only answer
questions that are on the topic that we're working on.
Generally, I answer off-topic questions before the stream starts.
So if you have a question that's not about programming this thing that
we're programming right now that then it's usually you have to come
during the pre stream if you want me to answer it.
In case your processor supports concentrate, TSC could the
significantly just sitting really distort the reported cycle count in
a way that matters or such possible in accuracy in significant for
what we were doing here.
No, it can't.
So the answer there is it did very much depends on the operating
system and the processor whether or not things like this are
important, right?
This particular machine, I believe, is not in a state that that will
ever be a problem, but it's entirely possible to have
Remember this happening to me in the past it's entirely possible to
have a processor especially if it's on a laptop that likes to very
it's it's a cycle rate right in the middle of when you're trying to
time things and it creates a lot of problems.
So I have seen stuff like that happened before, it can happen.
What you want to try and do as much as possible is put your machine
into.
It's like, no power saving State, and all this sort of stuff.
But fortunately, I Believe on
Most modern processors.
Now, if your if your machine is relatively new, they don't have that
problem anymore.
I think they actually try to report back stable are dtsc's to you.
I could be wrong about that though.
How does the CPU do things ahead of time?
If the code is supposed to be executed in order?
Well, it just looks to see whether there's something further along in
the instruction stream.
That doesn't depend on anything.
That's still being done because technically when you write code it
doesn't have to be done in order.
It just has to be done in order for any things that depend on each
other.
So as an example, as a really simple example, right?
Take a look at all these guys.
None of these textile values depend on any of the other textile
values, right?
So if it issued this textile value,
And did these instructions.
It was, it was it was issuing these instructions.
It could easily go grab some of these other instructions and execute
them without having to wait for to come back.
So, for example, it's got a square that's going to be a mullet Sam.
All followed by am.
All right, so it can't issue the second multiplied until the first,
multiply is done because that uses the results from it.
Right.
But if it wanted to, it could just go grab another multiply, that was
totally unrelated like this one or this one, right?
These are multiplies that don't have anything to do with each other.
So that's how the processor picks.
Them out, it just goes and grab stuff from further down.
That's like these things don't depend on each other.
So the things that control, how many things you can issue are those
two things?
Well, they're really three things right there.
How many psych?
How many instructions per cycle?
Can the processor just decode at all?
Which again, I think actually for, is like for, but I'm not sure.
It might vary per processor.
So, it's how many kids to code then?
There's how many of them that it decoded like those go into like a
window, right?
And you're going to actually be executing from there.
So in that window how many things are independent right?
How many
Could it actually pick from?
And of those is can pick from how many units are available to do them,
right?
So there's a ton of things in that in that state, right?
There's a ton of things that depend that determine.
How many of the total number of instructions?
That a processor could actually push through the pipeline, you know,
will it actually push the pipeline?
And those are exactly the kind of things that, again, if you study
this stuff, if you're, if you're a serious Optimizer, I am not like,
I'm not an optimization guy, but if you're an optimization guy, that's
the kind of thing.
You tend to know for the processors.
You work on, especially if you work on like a console or you're
targeting a specific a very specific processor, right?
You're going to know that and that's the kind of thing that like for
example in tell people can help you with if you're working on a game
you know and they have devrel guys you can be like can you run this on
the Sim or something and tell me why it's not getting done it right.
And so you know there's I'm just showing very basic optimization
techniques on the stream here.
Because I'm not a hardcore optimization guy, and I can't tell you how
to do.
You know, super crazy optimization, not on this processor.
Anyway, I could probably do that on the 360 because I knew that thing
really well, but I couldn't tell you how to do that here and so, you
know, like just giving you the basics.
Do you expect a 16 x speed up from multi-threading probably not a 16 x
speed up?
No, we haven't actually done the calculations to know roughly what the
speed up would be.
So I'm not sure, but but it's pretty rare that you get a perfect and
way speed up.
How do you?
Select the instruction set for optimizing.
So we show this on a previous stream.
Basically, you know the answer is, it's not an exact science.
And I just use, I just use the steam Hardware survey, it's not perfect
by any means but it's, you know, it's what we've got and they're nice
enough to make it available and it's better than not having anything.
So, there you go.
So, you know, if you take a look on here, right?
You can kind of drop down this other settings thing and you can see
you know, by looking at this here.
Assuming that the stats were gathered correctly, sometimes they break.
There's, you know, caveat caveat caveat but you can look at this and
kind of go.
All right, you know am I gonna Target sse4a?
Well only if my game is targeted at the highest of high-end Gamers,
right?
Because a full 3/4 of the people almost four-fifths of the people on
Steam, you know, don't have it, right?
So I'm just limiting my potential Market there.
Bye-bye a fair bit, right?
Similarly like, you know am I gonna Target sse2?
Well.
Okay, nobody on Steam this month.
Apparently who played actually didn't have sse2?
So that's what we're using.
It's like it seems like kind of a no-brainer like you're probably if
it's a person who's going to ever buy this game, they're going to have
sse2 because you know pretty much any gamer who's even ever going to
hear about handmade hero will?
Played a game on Steam at some point.
Probably.
Right.
And so, so, you know, you're pretty but it's a fun sse2, sse3 looks
pretty good, right?
I mean that that's a very fractional amount.
So if you wanted to Target sse3 it looks like you're totally could and
even sse4 might be something you could think about 4.1 and 4.2 are
pretty well covered.
It's really just that a, that's new enough that it's not on there so
that's one way to do it.
I'm going
For the 99% case basically, right?
I'm saying sse2 if we wanted to use sse3, I'd be fine with that.
I rather not cut out a fifth of the market.
But you know, I mean, if there was something that we really wanted to
use in SC for maybe we'd use it.
I don't know, but that was fine.
And again, the suffer renderer is something that we're kind of just
doing as an optimization case.
So, you know, in the software renderer if we wanted to use something
in sse4a, that'd be fine.
It's really more.
When we're doing any Cindy in the main line of the game, that will be
running on all the end-users machines.
We don't really want that to be using something that the end-user
probably doesn't have.
Is it the unity survey results?
Pretty different from Steam Hardware, its harbor.
Results.
I don't actually know anything about the unity Hardware server.
Survey.
I've never looked at it before but I guess we can take a look at it
now so it's that Standalone stats probably CPU.
It doesn't say.
Let's see if it's in here.
CPU models.
Well I mean I guess we could try to back figure it out but they don't
seem to actually tell us unfortunately unless it's somewhere else.
Doesn't look like they say about the SSE capabilities.
I don't know.
Yeah, if they have that, then sure.
Let it be cool to check it out but I don't know.
You have to send me a link.
What are the gains you get from reading your own software renderer as
opposed to using something like sdl?
But does Hardware software rendering?
Okay, justjust to be clear, I'm assuming that's coming from somebody
who doesn't watch the stream much, you do not want to write your own
software.
Renderer we are not writing the software renderer because we want to
do something.
We're writing the software renderer because we wanted to show the
entire code that gets executed to run a game.
So, what we've actually done is we wrote
Essentially what the GPU does but we wrote it on the CPU so that we
could so I could show like how it works, right?
And so that's why we're doing the software rendering it so that we
can, we could have the whole code everything right?
And see how it worked.
We will actually be calling the hardware.
We won't be using sdl because we don't need it for anything, but we
will be calling opengl or something.
Possibly Vulcan.
If it's out in time, we will be calling the hardware to do the
final rendering for the game.
Can a processor work through different calculations add, multiply a
square root in each cycle.
Or are they do, they each need their own cycle.
So, basically, that's something again, go back and watch the things
from last Monday.
And Tuesday, I explained that basically the answer is a CPU, is kind
of made up of multiple pieces, right?
There's multiple units.
And those units can do various things like, multiplying adding,
whatever.
And so, it depends on the architecture of the CPU, some CPUs can do,
Do multiple things?
Some can't some can do things out of order, some can't, and so on.
And so,
The answer to question is like, on the processor.
We're working on?
Yes, the processor could do something like issue and add.
And I multiply that are separate on the same clock cycle and then get
them back later on the same clock cycle, for example, or things like
this, right?
It can have multiple overlapping things going because the it can have
multiple units and adding Unit A multiplying unit and so on it can
have these multiple units there to do these things.
As long as the unit of the processor is free that it needs to do the
operation.
It can issue it.
It doesn't matter if some other unit is still working.
Something.
And that's the square root example.
Write the square root takes 16 Cycles or whatever it is.
You know, while those 16 Cycles are happening, other things that can
use other parts of the CPU can still occur, it doesn't, you know,
block it out.
Now, that wasn't true of the original microprocessors like way, way,
way back when they just happened in order, and it was true that you
just waited, however many cycles.
It took to do something, that's what you did.
But modern microprocessors are much more complicated than they do a
lot.
Lot more every cycle so it's not.
It doesn't work end-to-end like that anymore.
All right, last question.
Sorry, for my total ignorance regarding the stream.
But what of things can be delegated to GPU instead of CPU.
So the answer there is really pretty much anything can be delegated
from the CPU to the GPU.
But you have to keep some pretty basic things in mind, which is that a
gpus hardware architecture is optimized for doing lots of the exact
same operation wide, right?
So the things that we're doing on the stream where we converted
everything 24 wide arithmetic gpus or like, much wider than that.
They're like 16 wide width.
To wired or 64 wide or stuff like this.
So, they're way wider and they really, really want to be able to do
things in ways that exploit large sets of wide operations on small
chunks of memory at a time, right.
Like they kind of want to maximize these sorts of streaming things or
they can like get some you know get a bunch of texture streaming in.
Do a ton of work on them stream it out to the to
To, you know, a chunk of the frame buffer after, you know, doing a
bunch of Ops locally on it or whatever they really want that look of
the workload, right?
So you have to have code that looks like that.
You can delegate pretty much anything to the GPU that you want.
You know, you could put anything you want on there.
Really?
They're pretty general purpose now.
But if the workload doesn't look like that, the GPU is actually much
lower than the CPU at everything else, right?
So Random Access single-wide stuff, the CPU is way faster than the
GPU, a lot of times because gpus are like,
Often time clock slower or they've got less, you know, cash stuff, or
they've got less whatever that, you know, that's necessary to make
these things go quickly.
So, you know, an Intel processor, is really good at doing
single-threaded single-wide code, you know, it's good at that and so
typically, you can't just offload, your whole game to the GPU and
expect anything good to happen.
It's going to be awful, right?
And so typically, when you look at CPU GPU break down, what
Are talking about is when you have these things that really do look
like graphical or number crunching workloads.
Those are the things you can really move over there, but stuff like
game, logic, and moving things around and executing scripting
languages and stuff are harder to make work on the GPU.
So typically you don't get a win there and you're better off just
using the CPU cores for that because, you know, you've got four CPU
cores usually, with two hyper threads of core or something.
In modern day, for example, you've got that to work with and so, you
know, that's really the better place for those things to happen.
and,
All right.
I think I'm going to go ahead and call it because we are over time.
So let's go ahead and close things down here.
Where do we leave it?
Here we left our things.
Running fairly pleasantly.
Yes, yes.
So cute.
Yeah.
Well anyway it's pretty fun to walk around here.
Now, it's going to be fun to Ping back to the game and and start
playing around with stuff now that we have something that can render
very quickly and it's just it's awesome, right?
It's like it's so nice to take something that was slow and make it
fast.
It just feels good, you know?
And like you know this is just kind of zipping along and like like
it's nobody's business and remember we could barely even move it
before.
So, that's pretty great.
And I'm pretty happy with that.
So we've got a little bit more, I wanted to kind of cover here when we
on the rendering side of things.
So tomorrow, we'll start maybe taking a look at the memory stuff and
then next week, we'll take a look at threading and so I think we've
got a little bit more to do here, but as far as rendering is
concerned, this has gone blazingly fast.
You know, I didn't expect it to necessarily be such a cakewalk but it
turns out the processors are so darn fast that we didn't really have
to bust out.
Any kind of craziness, just kind of converting our stuff.
24 wide actually ran.
Great until way to go guys, like seriously, good job.
So anyway,
Hopefully, I will see you guys back here tomorrow.
Again, I believe tomorrow's Thursday, right?
So it's 5 again, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
Hope, see you all back here for take a look at the memory stuff and
just kind of finishing up some of this, some of this optimization
stuff that we're doing on the pixel Loop before we move on to the
multi,
So, I'll see you back here for that.
In the meantime, if you would like your own copy of the source code to
play around with it home, you can go ahead and get that out.
Handmade Hero 2 or R by pre-ordering the game, it comes to the source
code.
You can download it every night after I'm done working, I upload it.
If you want to support the video series, we also have a patronage,
subscribe to.
We also have a forum site which you can go to to ask questions and
there's anti Depakote guy.
There's also ports to Mac and Linux if you're trying to follow along
on another platform, community members.
His have contributed ports and finally there's a tweetbot which treats
the schedule.
So if you're trying to catch it live,
That's the place to go for that.
It's always got the latest schedule up there.
So thanks everyone.
I hope to see you guys again tomorrow.
Until then have fun programming.
Take it easy, everyone.