Recycle.
There we go.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show recoded complete game live on stream, you know?
Yes, that yesterday, guess the previous dream was Friday over the
weekend there.
And we did a little something because it was a devstream of thought.
It was a little thing that be some people were organizing for for
raising awareness of streams.
I don't know if it worked at all, but it was it was something we
participated in.
And what I did for that as a special event
It was, I showed how to do a little bit of metaprogramming because
it's something that people ask about in this dream, all the time.
All all, all the time.
So I showed how to do a parser in an hour for part, for pre-processing
your include files.
And people seemed relatively happy with that.
So I thought, what we would do today is just finish up some things,
logical extensions of what we did on Friday so that you can see them
and you know just kind of have a basic understanding of how that sort
of stuff works.
I don't really want to go too far down that rathole on handmade hero
because it's kind of like a whole separate space to explore and I feel
like until you know what you're doing with regular programming.
You don't really want to know what you're doing with metaprogramming.
It's kind of putting the cart before the horse to a large extent, but
just so that it's out there and people kind of understand the basics
of it.
I'm totally fine with what we did Friday and I'm totally fine with
doing a little bit more solid just finish that up today.
So it's there and then you guys can make of it.
What you will now if you'd like to follow along at home with this and
you preorder the game on a me here to or today is day 2 of 7.
So 2006 is source, code, unpack, that and directory.
That's what you want to follow along with here.
If you remember from Friday, we had a little thing here, called,
Simple processor that I built.
We just build it in line with the game and when you run it,
Out, put some code and you can see here.
I'll run it on our code here.
We are in the code directory.
I'm going to run that.
Oops, that simple preprocessor and you can see what it does.
Is it outputs this sort of like array of stuff.
That's, that's based on the types that we annotated in our code and
the way we did The annotation, right?
If you remember.
So, Kira is handmade some region.
We have a camera.
We called it and introspect.
Yep.
Got an introspective marker and the way that that works is we
basically we have just a town to find in our handmade .h that
basically defines the ways we can Mark stuff up it.
So right now we just we Define this one and just like G and all it is,
is it's a way to basically Define something that will disappear.
So it's something that's free for us to put because the C compiler
will essentially completely ignore it, which allows us to put it
things like that, anywhere that we want.
And so what I do here,
Is I just gave an example of marking a structure for introspection.
I put that on there.
It means that the are preprocessor will know to read the structure and
do whatever it's going to do to it.
And so, what I have it do currently is it spits out some data.
As you can see here, this is what it produces, and you can see that
it, these are the members right of that structure there.
So what I'm going to do today is just kind of finish up making this
into something that might be useful, so that you can kind of see how
we would do that, right?
How we would sort of start to build a little
Metaprogramming sort of system here.
And so what we want to do is we want to take this information that we
have.
Because remember, on Friday, we started with a very specific goal and
that was to make sure that we could replace a piece of code here,
where is its debug value.
We just want to be able to replace this code where I had manually had
to type out all of these entity things.
It was just a replace that code with something that could be
automated.
So that we know that any time, we changed our energy structure, it
would
Manically update the debug code here.
For example, we wouldn't have to do that manually.
Things like that, right?
So, what I want to do is I want to turn this into a system that would
allow us to do some general things in our code that are not exactly
designed for optimization anything like that.
That's like I said, more metaprogramming sort of further down the
metaprogramming path.
All I want to do is make the simplest thing that I can so that we can
start to leverage some meta programming features in the game if we
wanted to using just this very simple set of things.
And so what I want to do is I want to basically produce some data that
we could read in the game that would allow us to work with our
Earth in useful ways, okay.
And so, what I'm going to do is I'm going to go over to that simple
preprocessor here?
And where we output things, right?
We're we're sort of printing these things out and we do the parse
direct.
You can see here we do like this number definition.
Here's the members of thing where we say, what the members of stuff
are and all that stuff.
We go through here and we print out these member things, right?
And all that sort of stuff.
So what I want to point out here is that this piece of information,
this little thing, right?
Right here, that's printing out this stuff.
What we want to do is we
To start putting in whatever the information is that we might need to
be able to work with the members of this struct in a data-driven way
basically.
Right?
And so what we need is first we need a way of saying, what like type
something is and we start have gotten off to a good start here by just
introducing like this thing, like type underscore World chunk or type
in a square Unit 32 or that sort of stuff, right?
So, that's good.
But if you imagine what we might want to do with this data, right?
We have a problem.
Where if you were to sort of iterate over this, you would still have
no idea how to actually get any of this information, right?
Because if you take a look at what this would tell me, like let's say
that I just have this.
This, I
All this into my game after it gets spit out, right?
Well what this tells me is very limited, it tells me that there is a
member called storage index.
It tells me that it is a un 32, but I have no idea where in the struct
it occurs and I know, I have no idea how big it actually is right now,
I could guess that it was 32 bits, you know, it was four bytes long
because it's a type you in 32, so I can maybe take care of that
problem with like a lookup table or something.
But, in terms of where it is in the same entity structure, I have
absolutely no idea.
Because I would have to actually go through, and sort of do some kind
of accumulation at hope that the compiler didn't do anything.
Where with alignment, I'd have to know whether I was inside a pragma
pack statement, for example, to even be able to compute the offset
inside the structure of where that data is.
So what I'd rather do is right inside the output, I'd rather output
something that will allow me to get that data directly that the
compiler can generate for me and so it's pretty easy for me to do
that.
I don't know if we ever made a macro for this, I don't know that we
did.
I don't know that.
An offset of anywhere.
Because I can't remember if that's something that we ever did anywhere
else.
Probably not.
You probably haven't had any need to do it but what we can do in here
is we can just figure out what the offset of something would be from
the structure that we are talking about here.
So what we need to do and there's a couple different ways we can do
this.
I'll kind of show you the sort of janky way first and then we'll maybe
make a way that's a little bit more.
Sort of festive is what?
The sparse member I could pass down the struck token, so I can pass
down.
What the structure actually was.
So that in here, I could go ahead and actually use that, right?
So I guess I should say struct type token, right?
So whatever, the structure type is, what I could do is say okay, take
whatever.
The structure type is, make a pointer pretend you have a pointer to
that although the pointer is actually just going to be 0, right?
And then off of that pointer access the actual member itself, right?
Whatever that member was take the VM
Location of that, right?
Look what that value actually is going to be that value would actually
be the offset of the structure because if I start at 0 and I go as far
as I need to get to get to this member, that's what I would actually
have, right?
So taking the address of that member that tells me, you know, if the
base pointer was 0, the address of that member tells me where it
actually is
So I can do something like this and then all I would have to do is
again pass that information down so you know I would have to do
something like this record type token, text length, struck type token
text like so and then I just need to pass whatever this trucks
actually.
Type is.
Here's the name token.
I don't have the type token because as you can see, oh wait, no the
name token is that because it is the type.
So nevermind, so that's what I already have.
So I just pass that down and now when I run it in theory, I should get
that piece of information, right?
That looks wrong.
What did I hoops and started it in the wrong place?
Is what I did retire.
There we go.
So now you can kind of see the way this would shape up, right?
So now we would get the name which we want.
We would get an ID that gives us the type which we would want as well.
And then we also have an offset so we know where it is, right?
So if we start at 0 and we go to, where old chunk is that address is
going to be the numerical offset from the start of the structure,
where this thing actually occurred, whatever, you know, whatever it
was.
That makes sense.
So that is the way that we would start to get some of that debug
information in there.
I'm noticed that I'm missing a semicolon.
So let's go ahead and add that semicolon in if I wanted to be mr.
Looks pretty about it.
Maybe I even put some of those in there, and then for good measure,
maybe I just go ahead and say, okay, you know what, every time we
actually go to do this game after we compiled the preprocessor, maybe
I want to go ahead and do something where I actually do the
pre-processing.
So, we'll go in,
Where we were before.
So we'll go into, like, the build directory.
I'm not sure how we actually have this setup, so I guess we just do it
this way, right?
So, we pop into that handmade code directory.
We Run The Simple preprocessor.
So, we do the build simple preprocessor to exe like, so and when we
run the simple preprocessor, it will output.
Some data will just pipe that output, whatever it is into handmade
generated or something like that.
Dot h.
Whatever, I don't know what you want to call it, but you know, that
some file.
So, then when we run it in theory, we will now have a file called
handmade generated dot h.
And you can now see that we actually have this thing here that is
generated by our own generator.
And so, what we've done here is this now, for the first time you are
seeing an actual metaprogramming workflow, right?
A metaprogramming workflow is I compile something.
I run that something and then that
Something can now be actually in like included in line with anything
that I want to do from now on like that code can actually be used as
part of the, of the program, right?
And so, that's what I'll do.
I'll just go ahead and say, okay, let's go ahead and include that
stuff.
I don't really know where I want to include it just yet, so I'll go
ahead and include it in here somewhere.
I guess.
In fact, I guess I'll do something like this.
Maybe we'll have a handmade meta .h.
Each right and in that handmade metadata H.
If I come out here,
What we can do is we can say that, you know, whatever this thing
needed.
Like this, for example.
Whatever this, this generated code expects to have, we will Define
here, right?
So we've got stuff like this and maybe I'll do meta type here just to
make it a little bit more.
Clear, what's going on, right?
We can just say we've got the meta type World chunk, you know, we've
got the UN 32, we've got that pool 32, we've got the entity type.
We've got what else have we got?
We've got
Threes.
And we've got real 32s and we've got Sim entity Collision, volume
Group which is in volume group.
And you know what, I should probably do too is I can make this a lot
easier on myself by just putting meta type in front of it.
There we go.
There we are.
And okay, because in volume Groove and you know, meditate
Type, what else we need in 32?
Meta type hitpoints meta, type entity, reference meta type V 2 and
meta type realtor joke.
Right?
And so if I have all these and I just said that's like a meta type or
something like that.
And I say this about a type, I say that.
I've got the name, you know, whatever this thing is.
And I say that I've got the
From the strut.
Now, if I want to, I can actually compile this, right?
This could be something that gets compiled and, you know, I could put
it in here, I don't know exactly how we want to do it but there's a
handmade generate dot h and it comes in through the metal system or
whatever.
And so that would sort of make our program start to use in a very, you
know, not actually doing anything but actually set up to do something
way the meta code, right?
And so, there we go and now you
See that we're actually compiling the code.
And we now have that member definition, right?
That tells us everything that we wanted to know about the types that
are introspected.
Okay, so here's our handmade generated, it lists like everything that
we need to know about that type and
One thing I should mention, that's kind of nice about this, is this
code is just generated and can now be checked into the project.
So that's kind of a nice thing as well, because if the medic code
generator ever breaks or it stops working, or we lose it or who knows
what we still have at least one complete working version of The Thing
to fall back on.
Like we have a
Working actual piece of C code.
We could pretend we just wrote ourselves, forget the generator, and
that's kind of nice as well.
Write it out, put something that we can save along with the project
and distribute if necessary or do anything else we might need to do.
Right.
Okay, so that's you know, that's that.
So now, what how do you know how would we use that?
How would we actually go about doing something useful there?
And so, what I would say is let's go ahead and take a look.
I don't remember.
Where we ended up on the handmade debug set side of things.
But for example, if you know where where we were at in here, where we
were sort of doing the, the debug text out stuff like this stuff here,
right?
So, I don't really remember where we were at their, but if we wanted
to, we could sort of do something where we may be, where we maybe take
a look at how we would use this data there, right?
So, how we might use this data?
There is, let's say, for example, I want to
Able to print out into the somehow or something like this.
Again, I'm not really sure exactly how we want to go about that
because we're kind of right in the middle of the debug stuff.
So it's not really in a state where we can start using it.
We were sort of making a bunch of changes to it and trying to push
forwards onto things.
It's not really ready for us to start relying on it, if it was, would
be done.
So, what I want to do is, I want to actually sort of use that, that
data from handmade meta to like, iterate over some stuff, right?
And so, the handmade generated thing, like this thing right here,
I could, I could just say, okay, I've got this amenity.
I want to be able to iterate over the members of cements amenity and I
could totally do that as long as I actually had an entity.
So the debug text out thing where do I actually say something like
that?
Where did I say the compounding think debug text line.
There we go.
So if I wanted to, I could imagine doing something here where I did
something.
Maybe I Loop through the members of this thing and print out all the
members of a cemento t
Whatever it was, right?
So let's say, I took one here and I just said, I've got a Sim entity.
This is our test entity that we're just going to create for the
purposes of demonstrating that we can Loop over it and print things
out, right?
So here is our Sim region.
Here are some of the stuff that's in there.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to go ahead and I'm going
to set some of the basic things.
Like, I'll set the distance limit to 10, right, I'll set the T-Bob
20.1.
I'll set the facing direction to like 360°, who knows?
I'll set the diab Stiles e25 or for what who knows, right?
So let's say I set some of those things.
So now I've got a test any that has those things set.
And now I want to print
A out, the values of that, you know, using the debug text line thing
or something like that, right?
So that's all I need to be able to do.
Okay?
So if I want to do that,
You know, we should probably do next.
Let's be sure to replace this bridge as well.
That's the next time.
We do a fun little thing.
That's what we should do is like bright our own printf.
It's time.
All right, so if we're going to go ahead and
Print out these values, right then oops, that was not where I meant to
put that.
And that's not what I wanted either.
Try that one more time.
There we go.
Okay, so
if I want to print this out, then you can sort of see like, okay, I've
got to read over the members, right, so I can just say, like member
index, you know, goes from zero to however many there are in that type
field.
So right, this guy right here, however, many there were in there is
how many I would need to iterate over right.
Then, I know that I've got the member definition for all of them by
just looking at this array plus whatever the member dicks it.
So I just iterate over the members of the thing and I know that that
will be all the
That exists inside the struct, right?
Then for every member I can just look at what type.
I'm actually, you know, talking about here and for the ones that I
know about I can print those out, right?
So I could do like anything, that's a Unit 32 I could do anything.
That's a rule 32, for example, I could do anything that's an in 32, I
could do anything.
That's a real pretty too, right?
Those are some that would be really easy for me to print out right
now.
We would have to write
Kind of fancy code for it or anything like that.
So let's say we just take
Something like this and then we just go ahead and actually print these
guys out.
Okay.
So
All right.
What we would do here is we just say, okay, we know what the member
name is right, we know what the member of the struct is that we're
talking about.
We know the member of the struct is whatever the member entities, the
that array, that we generated whatever it says it is, right?
Because that tells us the information we need.
So we know the name and then to print out a human 32.
I just now I just need to know what's the actual value and I know I've
got, you know,
Different kind of print out.
I know I have like the address of the enemy for example, right.
So I know I have that.
I know I have, you know, that as a pointer so I can start there and
then all I would need to know is how far I would go, right?
So assuming I cast it to you ate.
So we're moving in B.
I just need to know how far from the beginning of the of the entity
that you and 32 actually is and of course that's exactly what the
offset tells me.
That's what this thing tells me, right?
So I would just go however, far the member us it is and now I know
that I'm pointing to
A, you went 32.
So if I want to print it out, I just dereference it, right?
Makes sense.
so, all I did was say start having a structure go however, much the
offset is that is the
32 that we're looking for, print it out right now, the exact same
thing would hold for anything else, right?
I can do a Boolean that way I can do an integer that way.
Totally trivially, I can do a float that way, again, very, very
straightforward.
And that's it, it's so easy.
In fact that you can see it basically works exactly the same every
time.
So I can even do something like saying that, I just have a member
pointer, the member pointer is always going to
To be exactly the same.
I just don't know, what type, I'm actually pointing to until I go
through the switch statement.
So all I would have to do is this right?
That's all.
I always know the member name.
I always know the member pointer.
I always know.
Everything I need to know in order to print this out.
So if I go ahead and compile this, now all I need to do is print it
out.
So when I've got one of these, I can just say, you know, if text
buffer zero.
So if we actually printed in ink, every anything everything, whatever
we can go ahead and print it out.
So now I should have a way to, you know, sort of debug inspect, those
things in an automatic way, right?
So okay, so now I run the code.
Oops, that's the preprocessor.
That's, that's actually run the actual game.
So now I run the code right, and you can see there that we've got some
stuff Flags, distance, limit facing Direction T-Bob, right, actually
08.
No, Flags is something else.
What am I looking?
I'm sorry.
Distance limit facing Direction.
T, Bob, and abs tile Z or the ones were looking at right there.
Yeah, that's don't ask me.
Oh wait.
No that's those are actually just things that it picked up, right?
Because it's going to print them out just because I never said them,
they're just set to zero.
So it just printed out all the things that it knew how to print out
that's kind of fun, right?
So there it is.
There's the automated inspection, right in.
The nice thing about this is this right here is totally reusable.
Write this piece of code will print out any structure that we want it
to any structure at.
All right?
So for example, if we want to
Under this very trivially.
We could just have a think here, which is like debug dump struck,
right?
And debug dunk struck dumb struck with just take the struct pointer.
Right.
So we know where the struct actually is and then we would take a
pointer to this thing, right?
So remember definition.
Remember deaths.
And then, we just need to know the number.
Remember death count, right?
That's all we need it.
We didn't need to know which truck, that was, that was not at all.
And I don't know why that's still there.
That was not at all relevant to what we were doing, right?
So we can just come in here and say, okay, all we need to do is say go
through.
However, the
Many, these were, you know, there were and I guess this is technically
just a member count.
Doesn't matter whether their desks or anything else.
That's how many there has soaked ears, the member deaths, right
generically speaking just iterate over them.
The struct pointer is this thing right here.
And that's it, right?
So now, debug dunks, dump struct.
Will dump any structure that we ever have.
As long as we marked it up for annotation somehow, right?
And so, we can easily say we want to dump the struct.
There's this truck, we want to dump.
All we need to do is tell it how many of these there are.
So there's that.
And this
And now we can dump a structure, right?
So if you take a look and I guess I could have just left that running,
but just to prove that it's working, right?
We run it again.
So there it is.
If I can, just leave it running, we got hot look code reloading, so it
doesn't matter.
So anyway, that is the basic metaphor do anything now, just to show
how powerful that is, you know, this is obviously if we if we wanted
to we could augment this really quickly and say, alright, let's say
that this is debug text line.
This is
Are you know Sim entity test?
So now, you know, if we take a look there you can see.
This is cemented to printing out.
Let's say now we want to do anything else in our system, anything at,
all right?
So we go up here and we say, you know what, I really wish I could dump
something else out here, I don't know what it's going to be.
What do you guys want it to be?
I'm not sure.
Let's just say it's the same region for now.
I suppose.
Right.
All we have to do is that that's it, we just say introspect.
And now this thing will be introspected.
So when I compile the code, right?
We get all of the definitions that we want.
As you can see, in the only thing that we have to do is anything that
was a new type that was in here that you don't know about.
We have to add to our our list in The Meta thing.
Now, even that we don't actually have to do, but I'm kind of saving
that for the end for the for the next 30 minutes we're going to do but
you can kind of see here in fact, I guess I can just let the compiler,
tell me what they are all we need to do, is make sure that those
things are actually defined as type.
So that's what I'm going to do very quickly.
Like, you can see here.
Me doing.
There we go.
And done.
Right.
Again, that's really it, you know.
Now we have the complete definition of those compiled into the game.
So now, if we wanted to, we could again, inspect that with absolutely
no work at all.
If we had one of these things like, you know, whatever it was, I don't
know.
One of these guys, I don't know what will set here.
Let's say we set these real 32s or something like this and these you
and 32s.
So I do assume region, you know, here is our test region.
This
Pretend this happened somewhere in the game and we said there's the
test region.
So here is the radius, there's the velocity, there's the entity count
Max and account and the account, whatever something like this, all we
would have to do to dump it.
It just call the same routine again, right?
So literally the sum total of the work, it takes to read up.
That is just calling this routine.
Again,
Right, that's it.
And now you can see that we've got the same region printing out, we
didn't have to write a single line of code.
Basically, all we did was just ask for that thing to be printed and it
gets printed completely fully 100% automatically.
Now,
As you know, though.
Or as you've seen, I should say.
If we take a look at the process there, there is something very
unsatisfying about it, right?
And that something is the fact that if you look at, you know, at the
code here, every time there's a new type, we have to redefine it in
our handmade meta, and that's not the most troubling part, you know,
that's not great, but it's not the most telling part the most
troubling part is we don't actually have any way to, to print those
out, right?
So let's say, for example,
Tuesday, let's say, for example that I went into handmade math.h,
right?
So I go into handmade math.h and I say, okay, you know what?
Rectangle, as you can kind of see somewhere in here.
Probably struct.
I don't know where it is.
It struck rectangle.
Here we go.
So rectangle to, right?
I just want to say that I want to introspect this, right?
I want to introspect that thing.
I want to select a rectangle to, I want to spec introspect.
Rectangle.
Three, right?
So now, the inter Specter, as you can see, if I reload this.
Oh well, you know, we do need to do one other thing first.
I think our little test guy doesn't actually process all the files,
right?
Yeah.
It does not actually parse this all the files.
So we actually want to do this right?
Sorry about that.
I forgot we're not really doing all the stuff file names.
Supposed to file index.
File name index.
Okay.
All right, so assuming that we actually ran this on all of our code,
which is probably what we would do, right?
If we were going the full route there,
That's not going to work.
Okay.
And that's not find here.
Okay, so assuming we actually run it on our code, which we would need
to do.
You can see we get our rectangle to and a rectangle.
Three are now defined, right?
So really if you think about what this means in theory, we shouldn't
actually have to do anything to get those types.
Right?
Like The Meta code already knows about rectangle to.
So why am I sitting here having
To deal with this extra type, right?
Because what I'd have to do, let's say we want to inspect that bounds
member right?
What I would have to do if we want to inspect that balance member was
in here, I'd have to add every time we have a new type like that,
right.
I have to go in here and add it in, right?
So I have to go in there and do some nonsense like this.
Where I say like, oh yeah right okay it's the rectangle.
So you know it's got a bunch of these
Things like this sort of a thing or whatever.
It's going to happen.
So I'm saying like you know, sprintf all that stuff out.
Here's the member pointer.
So the member pointer points to a rectangle three you know.
So I do the pointer to a rectangle 3 and now I got to get out like the
Minn dot X, right?
And I'm doing this whole nonsense like so and like the max audax,
right?
Okay.
And then, you know, then I find Loops, I don't know why decided that
there's gonna be a lot of extra member names in there.
So at that point, right?
I could actually view those rectangles but I had to write all of that
code, right?
So I had to write all of that code to do that.
Now, why am I writing that code?
When you can kind of see that the meta generator could be doing it for
me, right?
The Meta generator in here already picked those guys up, right?
It's got the V2 and V3 there, right?
So really all that should have to happen.
This right?
I say, okay, I got to a rectangle three.
Let me just do a debug dumps truck here, right?
I'll use whatever the, the generator said for that thing, whatever.
That is, right.
I'll say debug dump struct of your account of.
This guy goes to the members.
And the member pointer is the pointer to the new struct that the dumps
truck should output, right?
Make sense.
So, you know, now when I run the code
I should get something to actually automatically outputs that stuff
for me if that makes sense.
Although wait, what happened there?
Debug jump struct or Tango three-member pointer.
Why am I not see?
Why am I not seeing that?
Oh, I know why?
Because it's a V2.
Right?
We didn't Implement these for these so I'd still do need one thing.
In fact, I should probably do this.
To save us the agony, right?
I'm going to type B 3.
Like so.
Okay.
So here
We have.
I guess I don't really need to do that.
There we go.
Okay.
Sorry for that.
Brief stupidity there.
Okay, so in theory, now we're putting that out although still have
some weird thing happening there member pointer for the V3.
Is that correct debug dumbstruck members of rectangle 3 and we come
through here to print these out.
I'm going to actually set these to something I know as well just so I
can double-check that.
What should what should remember is that show me some region?
Show me some region.
Okay, so bounds men are I guess we could do rectangle, you know,
angle.
Min max and like that and then just specify those.
So there's the updatable bounds and there's the bounds.
I'm going to be 1 2 3, 4 5 6 and 10 20, 30 40 50 60.
Yeah, so okay.
So yes I've got some.
Can I see that?
I've got some nastiness happening there.
What is the problem with that?
when we hit meditate rectangle, 3,
Ah, I undid too much code.
Okay.
All right.
So back to what I was saying.
So now we've got the min/max stuff printed out, right?
Although it looks like I'm one off.
Yep, x y.
Z we go.
So now we got that stuff printed out, right?
We're calling we're using the generated stuff to get those types,
right?
But I still had to write this part right here, right?
So, basically, what's going to
Here is that's going to happen, pretty much for everything.
Now, I could do some base types and that wouldn't really bother me.
So if I had to do like these two types, so we just have V2 and V3, or
something like that in there, that would necessarily bother me.
But what would bother me is stuff like this, where it's like, okay,
you know, suppose I want to actually have a thing where I can print
everything out.
Well, if I look at what's in here.
Okay, I've got like, you know, World chunk.
And like Sim entity Collision volume group, and entity reference and
hit point.
I'm gonna have to lead, like, putting all of those in here.
So in addition to all of these, like sort of more basic ones like
rectangle to, and rectangle three, I've got to like put every last
stupid one of these, right?
I've got to actually do that code myself which is not so interesting
to me, right?
Like that is just again, exactly the sort of thing that I was trying
to avoid to a large extent.
Looks like there wasn't a rectangle too.
That was exactly.
The thing that I was trying to avoid with the metal part, on the first
places, I want this code to be generated for me, I don't have to do
it, right.
So, there's a couple things we can do there.
Right?
And the simplest and most straightforward one, there's there's more
complicated things you can do.
But the simplest and most straightforward one is actually just declare
which one's of these we are actually going to print out ourselves and
and and let it go from there or a sort of another another way to do.
It would just be to say we can have the meta generator.
Perhaps remember all of the things that it has seen and anytime it
knows that it has the data for something, allow that to be something
that gets switch case.
Right?
So let me show you what that would look like.
Just again to sort of underscore how this sort of thing tends to work.
So let's suppose that I do my sort of read entire contents into file
contents into memory and I'll terminate sort of stuff here.
If I was going to do this,
Let me show you the simplest possible way.
This is the way that requires never not actually creating anything
inside the meta generator.
To actually, the actually understands what it's seeing.
It's still just kind of a macro processor, right?
So the simplest possible way to do it, is to say, all right, whenever
I'm going to see one of these guys whenever I see a par struct, I'm
going to take a look at, I'm sorry, not a struct whenever I see.
Actually no.
That is what I meant.
So whenever I see a par struct, right?
I'm going to make note of what that struct actually was, right.
I'm going to keep track of just all the ones that I've seen and then
at the end, I'll output something that's going to allow me to process
those as sort of switch debug dumps, right?
So let's say, for example, that I just do something here, where I kind
of have again, like something I have no idea, you know,
Strut seen struct something.
I've seen her like the métis truck.
I don't know, right?
Just have the meta struck.
All it has is, like, what's the name right of the Menace trucked.
And and I think that actually, you know what that's it.
It's just what the name of the meta struct is right, like, that's all
there is to it and maybe even just, you know, something like this.
We're gonna strike next and I just feel like first met a struct, write
something.
Like that.
So what I can do there is every time I parse a struct.
When I see that what I'll do is I'll just remember that that's truck
actually existed, right?
So I'll say OK, I want a new meta struct.
You know, one of these things I'll just grab one.
However, big that is and again I'm going to keep this to the end of
the program so you don't need to worry about it at all.
So I just meant like one of those.
I want to take the name.
I think it's turcotte.
It's stir.
What's the actual?
I never use the same runtime Library so I never remember.
It's not stir copy is it?
Or is it is it?
I don't know.
It's not stir copy its
The thing, there's a thing that like copies an outcast ring, or does
that just something?
I wrote I can't remember.
There's one that's like you know it just Kate's.
The thing, it's not mem copy, it's not stir stir.
It's not stirring cat.
I don't know.
You know what, I don't even care.
Doesn't matter.
I'll just write it myself.
So anyway, I want a name, that's trivial.
It's just whatever.
The I don't even need that.
I've already got that.
So whatever.
Name token is for this guy, the text length of that.
I just grab that space.
Store it and then I just say like, okay, right, wherever the thing was
on the I'll terminate and I'll copy the name in here from from
wherever we were, right?
So we've got okay into that name.
I will put the the text
and I already know how long it is because I already have that
information.
So this is basically just me storing this and then I'll just change it
on to what I was doing.
Right.
So it's all good.
And again, this is the since this is external to the thing, we're this
is using this isn't using our America Tour.
This is using the base, you know, whatever C wants to use for its
stuff.
I assume this is in memory .h don't actually remember but I assume
So anyway that gives us a list of all of the structures that we've
seen, right?
So now every time we see a struct we know that we have one, you know
we sort of have a record of it.
So at the end of the program after we've done
Else I can basically just print out a little thing that's designed to
Aid Us in that automated type Discovery process.
So I can just say like, all right, let's print out a palm Define which
is like, handle, you know, meta handle type dump.
I don't know, whatever it's going to be.
Right?
And what we do is we say metal handle type dump and then we say,
whatever the type actually was, or something like this.
In fact, I guess if I look and see what we're doing here, right?
It's just going to Output this thing right here, right?
So really all it needs to do is it just needs to have the member
pointer?
I guess is really the only thing that needs to happen.
So whatever the member pointer is that should pretty much do it,
right?
So you call a metal handle typed up, you give it to
A pointer and all this is going to do is just generate all of these
cases for us automatically.
So we don't have to bother doing it ourselves because we're just that
lazy.
Okay, so in here, I got a loop over these guys.
So I've got my meta struct, I start with it and I say first met
abstract I Loop until it's done.
Right.
Once I have those inside here, I just need to Output.
What is this?
Essentially, this exact case, right?
I just need that for each one of these.
So in here, we just do something like this.
One, two, three, four.
We just do something that looks like that.
Right where I say the type name in there.
So meta, type, whatever that is is just going to again happen every
time here, right?
Like that.
And then that member type is a member pointer is again the parameter.
So off it goes, right?
And in here what I can do as well is I can put in the back the double
backslash if necessary.
So I can basically say like, all right, continue the macro.
If necessary, by saying, if meta next is equal to something mean
there's going to be something next.
I put in that /, otherwise, leave it blank.
So there it is.
That'll do that for us.
All I have to do is actually pass.
Now the actual type name So Meta name and I got a pass that twice
because it are three times, really because it uses it three times.
And that's, that's really all there is to it.
So now if I go back and take a look at what's in my generated code,
you can see the down at the bottom.
We now have meta code which does exactly the stuff that I wanted it to
do, right?
It automatically handles any type that we might have seen.
So we don't have to and furthermore we could also Imagine doing that
for the other part of the process that we haven't seen yet you could
imagine.
If you were really trying to do this, the whole way, you could
actually do something where it spits out.
This array as well, right?
You could imagine that happening.
So
If you want to be tied down that way, you can actually do that as
well, but let's just take a look at how this works.
Exactly.
So once we have that, we now have the ability to inject into our debug
code, right?
We have the ability to inject into their sort of our own, you know,
our own set of switch statements, that do everything that they need to
do, right?
So that's all right, like that.
So what we can do is just say, all right, instead of handling
rectangle, three, we don't need to handle that anymore.
That just gets handled by implicitly.
Because that was a type.
That was seen, right?
And then, of course, we obviously have to make sure that those are
actually in here.
Though, this point everything, The Meta generator sees has to be
defined.
There and now, when we run the game we see that you know, that stuff
gets printed out for us.
And furthermore, some more new stuff that was never getting printed
out before is getting printed out for us now, what is that stuff?
Well, it's a little hard to read it at the moment.
So what I'd like to do is just go ahead and make one slight
modification to this and that is that inside here.
I want to add the concept of an in-depth level if possible, right?
So we could do is say something like all right, you know, when we're
printing this out,
There is going to be an in-depth level.
That indent level is like, you know, Kara star text buffer base may be
right?
We would just say okay.
We start text buffer at the base of it and this is just totally hacked
because like I said, we'll probably make this print out something real
in a second but just for sake of doing the part that we care about
doing right now and not focusing on other stuff, we started text
buffer at text buffer base, we then do like a for indent level equals
zero or indent equals zero.
Indent is less than indent level, you know.
Indents.
And so, this way, we can go through and just say, Okay, however, much
the indent level is will do something where we just like, add some
spaces in there, right?
Right?
Look, we just add some spaces to sort of push it forwards, if that
makes sense.
And then we have the null Terminator and do the rest of the stuff
normally.
And so that would allow us to say, okay, there's an indent level it
gets past here and every time we go down a level of indent, you know,
we increment it by 1 or something like that.
So here, and in fact, we could just say when you call debug
dumbstruck, you know that's in debt.
Level is set to 0.
But then inside this evil preprocessor, when we pass an indent level,
it always passes the
That level, you know, plus one or something like this, or maybe.
Like, the next indent level is something that it passes for example,
and that's just a parameter to the macro, right?
So then, you know, in here, we just say, what are you complaining
about mr.
Mann right.
Sorry about that.
We go.
We did what?
What happened sighs on Bap.
Something did its thing?
Oh, right that's his that is.
I hate this SM printf thing.
Something like this.
Are you happy now?
Mr.
Gets in the way of me trying to give examples.
We really need to write our own one of those.
There's nothing worse than a whiny C compiler.
Okay.
So
If we go ahead and make that happen, so we just say, okay, yeah,
however, big text buffer base, was we?
That's how much we start with and then we can subtract away from that.
Well, I guess what I could do is just say text buffer base.
plus however, big text buffer base was
- text buffer, that's how much is left.
Okay, so that oops.
Should allow me to finish the thing that I was actually trying to show
you.
Let's see.
Connector is from 3 to size t.
What cannot convert argument 3.
Oh, is this that God, this was so annoying.
Last time.
What was this thing complaining about?
I cannot remember.
It's something ridiculous.
Like, we tried to set it to the right stuff, but it didn't like it.
You know what I'm talking about?
It is I hate this thing, you know, people ask me why I don't use the C
runtime stuff it's because of this garbage.
It's like I don't ever want to have to think about these sorts of
things.
I just want you to do what I tell you to do.
God.
Alright what is what is this that you're telling me?
SM printfs, which is there, Kara star size, T size T.
So when I don't pass one of those, I have to pass this twice.
Is this what you're telling me?
Stupid thing.
I remember us going through this already once yes apparently it was
fantastic.
Yes.
Such a productive use of my time.
Thank you.
all in the name of security, which we are not concerned about
In any way.
Remember, the operating system can be hacked by a thought file.
So why anyone would care about how handmade hero handles things
securely?
I have no idea, but that's beside the fact it's fine.
Don't worry about it.
Totally fine.
Anyway, back to what I was saying.
I just wanted to make an indent level thing here.
So I could do that.
That was all we were trying to do nothing else.
So now in theory we should be able to read this a little bit better.
And so here you can kind of see that happening.
Now there's something that we probably would want to do here, which is
to say that we'd want to show which member it was that we were
actually outputting at any given time when we output things like this.
So,
For example.
Inside that metal handle type thing where we do this kind of case we
would probably want to do something where we would sort of do a debug
text line first, where we would say, okay, we're going to output
something here that tells you what the member actually was.
We could actually, I suppose put it sort of, as a, as an adjunct into
this thing.
But, you know, first things first.
So if we wanted to say what that actually was
We can just say debug text line and we can say, whatever that member
name was here.
Again, this is kind of a hack for until we get this in the hierarchy
but you can just so you can kind of see at this point like what we're
actually looking at here, right?
So now you can see when we print it out we get stuff like okay,
there's the bounds, it automatically jumped into the rectangle thing.
There's the updatable bounds, there's any count.
Here's an adiz entities happen to be array of Semana T.
So we actually start printing out.
What's in that?
Array right?
Which is again not actually something that we want to do but it's
something that we could do and the reason that we don't want to do
that yet it's because we're not actually handling array.
We don't handle pointers in The Meta code at all.
So this is totally erroneous here, right?
But this will start to actually do what we wanted to do, right down to
the point where, you know, in theory, if we wanted to, we could start
to to print out a relatively complex type in a semi automatic fashion,
right?
So if I try to find something, I don't know what would be
Better struct in carrier like and I know handmade asset .h maybe your
something like this.
Yeah, so I'm trying to think of what in our code would be a good
example.
So it doesn't require like a raise and stuff quite yet.
Since that's a little bit outside of sort of what we've done inside
the generator.
Maybe there's some other stuff in some region.
I suppose I'm not entirely sure.
So yeah.
So we're printing out.
Same entity.
and yeah, so most of these
Thereby pointer well entity reference is a good example.
So entity reference, we could do right.
Although I guess it's a union.
So maybe not like, I say that like a lot of these things require us to
upgrade our parsing, or I should say, are understandable, but World
position.
So there is one, right?
So if I go into handmade world and look at World position, right?
So here is kind of a good example.
If I want to, I can introspect this.
I don't know what category that would be probably were
old something like that.
So if want to introspect that, I could totally do it.
And in theory now when we output are entities, it should say what
their positions are, right?
And it should not only output chunk, extra quiet chunky.
But it should also know to go inside this V3 and get that out as well.
And again in order to do that, all I have to do.
The only thing I have to do that I haven't done.
Yet is make sure that inside our preprocessor.
We're actually processing all the files which again, like I said, I
don't actually do yet.
But I can just manually add it, right?
And so now I didn't do anything right, I didn't add any code, I just
recompiled that's it.
And you can see that.
Now our entity print out which is right here.
This is our CM entity.
You can see that it just prints out that origin struct.
It just totally nailed it, right?
Output 2 x, the Y, the Z, and the offset, right?
It knew the offset was a V3 again.
Totally automated everything nice and fancy, right?
Oh, wait a second.
No, I lied.
I totally love.
I totally lied.
That's not what happened.
That's actually inside the Sim region.
Is that correct?
Oh yeah, sorry, I guess for some reason I thought we were talking
about the same entity but assuming that he doesn't have one of those.
So yes it totally nailed it, but I was confused.
So there's the world position right there, right?
And it prints it out automatically and it's smarter than I am because
it actually knew where the thing was, and I didn't write.
So, yeah.
So that's right.
How that sort of thing works.
It's again, pretty straightforward, not really none of its rocket
science is just taking a little time to
Figure out how this sort of stuff goes again.
You can you can sort of take this a lot further than what I'm doing
right now, but it just gives you kind of an idea.
Hopefully, you can sort of see for yourself how this sort of thing
would progress and go a little further down.
If we wanted to extend this a little bit more, you could see how like
some of these things that are single pointers.
We could pretty easily handle just single pointers.
I like that in a fairly hacked way or we could do something a little
bit more fancy for them but, you know, if you want to do something in
a pretty hacked way, it
Pretty easy to even have pointers in there.
It's just going to do an additional dereference before it actually
looks at something.
So for example,
let's say we wanted to start targeting whatever this thing is some
entity Collision volume group, right?
Samantha T Collision volume group is this thing.
So, you know, I want to introspect, this.
Don't know why, who care?
I have no idea.
We're doing some things, I don't know.
So I just start inspecting everything because I'm crazy and I'm doing
stuff, and it's a disaster and whatever.
So, I managed to introspecting some stuff and I say that I want these
two things and respected, right?
And I go ahead and compile it and, you know, like I said, we haven't,
we didn't go the full monty there and actually, put in the thing that
generates those generated.
Guys.
But we could obviously if you wanted to, it's should be pretty obvious
by now, how you would do that.
But other than that right it starts to generate all this stuff for us
and that's all really great.
But when we go to actually run this thing, what you will notice is
like, okay.
So there's the total volume and it looks like it's doing everything
correctly and it's fine.
But what you will see is that actually fact, you can already see it
even before I don't need to give a demo.
What you'll see is it actually prints out the wrong data.
And the reason for that is because it's looking in the wrong place,
right?
Because
That thing is a pointer.
So inside that same region, right?
When we are pointing to the Collision volume, that is an actual
pointer.
But our meta are preprocessor doesn't actually use pointers at all
yet, right?
It doesn't, it knows that it's saw it like I did it.
When we wrote the parsing, you can see that.
It actually hasn't is pointer there but doesn't actually do anything
with is pointer.
So doesn't matter that it's saw that there was an asterisk.
It's not actually going to use that for
Anything, right?
And so there's a lot of different ways that you could, you know, that
you could kind of like start to approach this the simplest possible
way.
If we were just literally hacking it,
All the pieces is that member sort of that member concept there.
You can, you can sort of just have some flags that say to do
something, right?
You can say here like member definition flag, right?
And you would say you know, meta flag, you know, meta member Flags
like this underscore is pointer, right?
And again, this is really the reason this is so such a hack like I was
saying it's because it doesn't support like pointers to pointers,
right?
This
See why?
There's a lot of reasons that would be bad.
But point being if you're just just to show that the idea is we do
like okay if it's a pointer then we put one of those flags in
otherwise we just put 0 in there and now when we print this out, we
would actually have that information inside the generated stuff.
So you can see here.
Anytime there was a pointer like to the volumes or things like that.
It tells us that it is a pointer.
So now that we know and once we know that it's a pointer, then that
means that inside the thing, where we actually print everything,
Going out that gives us the opportunity to actually dereference the
thing first before we actually do anything else, right?
So what we would do is when we're actually doing debug dumbstruck,
when we get out our member and we look at that member pointer, right?
We would just first say, well, if the member itself was flagged that
way
you know, if we believed it to be a pointer because the generator told
us that was, so then what we could do
Is take member pointer and actually dereference it once, right?
So we could say, well, member pointer is a actually rent treated as a
pointer to a pointer and then dereference that pointer.
So now we've read like 11 pointer deep one, more pointer deep, right?
And then we can do is we can also test on member pointer.
So we can just say like okay, you know, if it's null, maybe we just
skip it, you know, we don't we don't draw that one or something,
right?
We skip that all together and
Move on.
So you know we do something like this where we say, Okay prep the
buffer and then just keep going, right?
So then when we actually do this print out,
Then you can see this starts to make more sense.
It's not showing up at all now because it looked in its other the
pointer is null.
So, it doesn't actually actually do any printing out there.
But now, if I was to go into our test where we're actually putting
these out and I actually filled in one of those pointers, one of the
pointers that's in sort of the meta stuff that I was talking about
here.
So inside, handmade Sim region, I don't even remember which one's was
I guess was Collision simply inviting group.
So ok, so inside our tests entity, right?
If we set a collision equal to something so collisions going,
Equal to test Collision.
Volume group.
So where is that?
That's some entity Collision volume group that for here, right?
So I'm going to actually make one of these guys.
First.
And I'll just set his prayer or something.
So, okay, he has a total volume, the total volume offset P, you know
equals, I don't know.
987 something like that, test Collision volume group dim equals 4 5 6.
Something like this and then the test sanity.
What?
No, total volume blah.
Okay, there we go.
And then like the other stuff like the volume count volume count
equals one volumes eek would equal the volumes right Sim entity
Collision volume like so volumes, right?
And here it'd be the same stuff, it just feel like, okay, yeah, these
are going to be like you know, 10 11, 12 13, 14, 15 and so on.
Right?
What?
So now, you know, if you look all of a sudden, all I did was tap back
and you can see that all of that information is totally reflected
properly in all of its there and that's all great.
The only problem, obviously, with this again, is like we taught about
printers.
We didn't really teach it about counted pointers.
So, for example, if I was to say, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20 21, and say that
the volume count was too.
Well, if we had a magical thing,
It would show up but you can see that there is only one volume
actually listed under volumes.
Instead of two, it only lists the first one that's because all it does
is it just sees that it's a pointer?
It doesn't know that this member tells it how many of those there are
right.
And so you can imagine lots of ways that we would do that.
Hopefully you can see the most General one.
For example, that you could do is inside
I'd
The same region code.
For example, we could mark it up by saying something like this on this
on this guy, you know, we could say something like introspect or or
like counted pointer volume count, right?
And then with no, the generator would know that and inside.
Handmade out, H, where we Define our introspection features.
We would just say how that went, right?
So that's, that's how that goes now.
Of course, if we actually did that, as you can see, we have a problem
which is the general.
The parser itself has to be aware that those things are there, right?
It has to be looking for them.
And so inside, parse member, one of the things that it has to do is
look to see if the first thing that it gets.
Is going to be one of those counted pointer things, right and then it
has to actually process it and act on it, but obviously you're going
to have to do that anyway because in order for the thing to work, it
would have to have passed parts that, you know.
So obviously that has happened, but hopefully that gives you a pretty
broad overview of how the basics of metaprogramming work.
Like I said, I don't want to cover it into much more detail, because I
think you've got everything.
You would need now to like go off and start building.
Stuff.
And, and really mostly what it's about from this point.
Forward is instead of this thing instead of the simple preprocessor
being kind of like a hack where it's just like a, it just kind of it's
like a thing that runs on the program spits, out some stuff.
What we would actually do here is we'd we'd build up sort of like an
abstract syntax tree or a data structure.
We build up some thing that represents all of the
Mission that we've parsed, then we do a bunch of operations on it in
that meta form and then we would spit it out and that would allow us
to do a lot more powerful stuff like it, seeing what things were,
where and how many we knew about and how big they were, we could do
all sorts of stuff, right?
And you can start to do more powerful operations on it and that debt
becomes more of the real metaprogramming.
This is more just basic introspection, right?
But you can build up more powerful metaphor and preachers from there.
So I think that should hopefully do it.
And give you pretty much everything you need to go explore it.
If you want to.
and,
Yeah, there you go.
So, let's go ahead and go to the Q&A for a little bit.
I'll just take some questions and but like I said, I think it should
be pretty clear, you know, there's kind of a, there's an infinite
number of things, you could go do.
Now, I think with that information, like it's pretty obvious, how you
can just keep going from there, so
So yeah, hopefully, for people who were mostly interested in the
metaprogramming, they've now got everything they need to do their own
Explorations on that.
As necessary.
Coronal Dragon says, so when you set, when you say, you've built up
multiple layers of metaprogramming, do you mean your meta programs
output things?
Like what we wrote today,
So Colonel, I'm not sure.
I understand what you mean by like what we wrote today.
Can you, can you possibly rephrase the question and nxs why?
When you say isn't offset of safe to rely on?
I don't know.
We can find out.
Let's see.
So if I'm in the middle of this code,
and let me make sure I get the syntax right for offset of
so, if I do an offset of
Which would be that.
In the middle of this code.
And I did this.
And I said, what's up in here?
Tight?
What would the compiler say?
Type is not.
Oh, you're correct, it's not.
That does look pretty safe.
I don't know if I actually needed to.
It looks like I need to include standard f.h for that.
So
If that isn't the case and I guess, let me see if it is or isn't the
case if I'm in handmade .h platform.
let's see, so if I did it here,
So I would see no it looks like it's not safe to rely on because
basically you're going to have to you're going to need another pound
include.
So that seems like a bad idea to me because you never want to
introduce a piece of code.
That depends on a header file.
If you don't have to, in my mind and external header file,
So so I would say no, I would not.
I would not do that.
I would not choose to do that, but you know, if that's, that's other
people's guess.
I guess that's the people's idea.
Black 238.
Someone said that the string function you were looking for was
flustered if yes that's I think that is the one I'm looking for.
It's been so long since I've used it.
I can't remember but yeah.
I think.
But yeah I think that is it Gary Johansson in the episode of Devon ke
show called The Wolf doesn't want to come anymore.
You mentioned that you use metaprogramming techniques to make up for
modern language.
Shortcomings curious, what functionality of use metaprogramming to
achieve that you would have found prohibitive in modern languages.
Can you suggest any specific usage has to pursue for either program or
business optimization etcetera.
I guess what I would say is I actually don't know of anything other
than basic arithmetic that isn't better in metaprogramming.
There's only two types of things, two types of code.
That other than arithmetic that I think of right now ones that I am
currently metaprogramming and ones that I just haven't had time to
meta program yet to build better parking systems for.
But I would not say that there are specific things that I met a
program.
It's more that I see.
Everything is a meta programming problem and the only thing is that
aren't getting any program right now by me are things that I haven't
had time to move to that.
So the only stuff that doesn't get meta programmed at the moment that
I wouldn't met a program is like, really, really basic.
look like, oh, this is a thing that is so
Is so only ever exist in this one way?
But almost everything should be metal programmed in my mind.
I pretty much think exclusively in terms of metaprogramming and
actually I'm frustrated, a lot of times they haven't had chance to
really sit down and build as many many pretty things as I might want,
but someday I'll get there.
Chronodragon to rephrase are your multiple layered meta programs,
outputting further meta programs or is it a single layer that has
enough complexity to be considered more than a single pass?
Not sure how to phrase.
I was mostly trying to prompt further discussion of what you've
mentioned previously.
Yeah, at the moment.
I don't feel I almost, I almost did one.
Where I met a program to the metaprogramming thing?
But I found that it was just a little too dangerous.
So at some point, I suspect if I really like had the like stomach for
it, I would go ahead and do metaprogramming like
You know, I'd met a program, The Meta program but I think the problem
is I've never had a chance to sit down and focus exclusively on
metaprogramming for like two or three years.
So I've never gotten my metaprogramming stuff up to like a really high
level of quality where I'd be willing to start metaprogramming to
relying on The Meta program, being thing always being there, you know.
So I try to keep the top-level metaprogramming layer written in just
like, straight C.
So I know I can always rebuild it anywhere easily.
So yeah, I would actually probably like to be able to met a program,
my metaprogramming layer, because it's actually a pain.
It's actually really annoying that I can't leverage the
metaprogramming layer features inside the metaprogramming layer
because it would simplify things.
James women, odd.
All setup is defined in a mess, species.
Type standard f.h and is specified in c89.
So long to that header.
Did I miss something?
No, you just, so, I don't like using the C runtime library at work.
I don't use the C runtime library at all.
I don't use any headers actually.
There are no in our current, in our current build of our game at
Molly.
There are no header files that were not written by me.
And well I guess and we also I think that we use SUV, true type dot h.
So there is one that was written by Sean and then the rest of written
by me, there are no other header files.
So I prefer things that do not rely in any way on any of that stuff.
So if it's free for you to just do it yourself, which offset of is
just, it's just what I did, right?
And furthermore, I
although, I could be wrong about that but I suspect
Let's see here.
Stop running the game.
If I go to our test project here,
That I made for yes, please Visual Studio.
Take several seconds to open a text file.
If I did an offset of
Right?
And I said like, you know, I don't know win32 window, or win32 find
data or something like that, right?
I said see, file name
I assume I can do go to definition.
But I really knew so yeah.
So okay.
So what you can see is basically if you were to use offset of all you
would be doing was introducing a header dependency for exactly the
code that I wrote.
Like it's just the stew, it does exactly the same code.
So all it is is it's like it's like when you define 0 null to be 0,
you're just, you know, or you include a header file to get know, it's
like just use the thing, you know, and like reduce the number
dependencies in my mind because this is not, this is not doing
anything for you.
Because there already is C Syntax for this operation and that is what
it is, right?
And if you don't like that syntax and just make a macro that is the
syntax you want.
But I don't like introducing dependencies on headers for no reason,
because they always, always always come back to ruin your life.
Especially if those headers have anything to do with Microsoft.
Benjamin based on what Jonathan Blow has so far.
Do you think Jay?
I will have the Mediterranean capabilities that you'd want.
If not, what do you think it is missing?
He has not actually demonstrated much of the meta programming
capabilities yet.
In fact, I think he's still working on the abstract syntax tree
modification stuff so I actually, I don't think even he knows quite
yet exactly what will be in there for that.
So it's a little premature to say.
I mean.
I I feel like knowing John, he will probably make it fairly complete.
So even if he does not add all the Meta Meta programming, like,
features, I might want I suspect, he will probably make it such that I
could add those features in the meta programming in the actual program
itself, which is all I really want.
Like I don't need him to do that.
Work for me, I just need him to
Both the ability for me to do that work and I can then build up my own
like library and that would work.
Paul Smith, you said in the previous stream that you don't really
program in C anymore, you basically program in que.
Si Lang, does that refer to your meta programming tools, or is there
more to it than that?
Yeah, that refers to the meta programming tools.
Do you Seven Samurai, you're not using header files for opengl
direct3d correct.
I do not use header files for opengl and direct3d.
Have you worked with any functional languages Haskell or maybe Scala.
Only the only one that I have seen much of his oh, camel
I have not ever ever even so much as I think, read a line of code in
Haskell or Scala.
But I have, I think I read a whole book on.
Oh, camel actually, I never did anything serious with it, though.
I mean, I didn't like, you know, I never shipped a library in it or,
or any kind of commercial product.
Blah 238 maybe a bit off topic, but going along with the master spy
thing, have you ever done a stealth game?
And if so, what particular programming challenges do stealth
mechanics, bring that you don't usually have to deal with, that's
really more of a game design game, code question, which is not really
my thing.
I mostly do game technology, and stealth mechanics.
I mean, the one thing that I would say is that, you know,
Sometimes depending on what you're talking about when you say stealth
game, like, for example, the team that did thief, the Dark Project
Looking Glass did a lot of work on sound propagation and sound
propagation is a good example of something that probably wouldn't be.
So important in circumstances where you weren't talking about like
very careful stealth game sort of things.
And so my assumption is that, you know, as far as game technology is
concerned, there might be some
Just like that.
That said, I have never been on a team, which had to do something like
that.
That is not.
That's not experience I've ever actually had.
But I could see that being true and I know it was true of the folks at
lookin'-glass, they did a much, much more complex sound propagation
system for thief, the Dark Project than anyone else was doing at that
time for any other first-person shooter e kind of title like Quake or
anything like that.
Maybe a bit off topic.
Wait, sorry.
Is the syntax of case of Langston?
Close to see the the like, the nitty, the nuts and bolts of it are.
It's more of a high higher level stuff, that isn't it so far as your
meta pregnant, with some very useful.
We ever open source them maybe in your will if nothing else.
Yeah, I would like to.
I would like to at some point release them, but I think it's going to
probably depend a lot on what format takes like,
What happens over the next five years or so.
You know, for a while, I was thinking maybe I would do my own language
sort of thing that incorporated them but I wasn't really sure about
that.
And so now that John is doing his language, you know.
I kind of want to wait a little while and see how that shakes out.
If that turns out to be a really good thing, then, you know, maybe I
could just, you know, I might even be able to ship it as a library.
Like, here's here's all my metaprogramming stuff that just shifts as
like, a j.
I Library, you know, like you just, you just grab K C.J, I.
And then, you can do the same stuff that
didn't doing that, it would it would work in that or whatever but
Choose a will you write your own installer for handmade here or just
zip it and be done with it?
So for installers, I think probably would depend on what the
requirements are of the target systems at that time.
I mean, in general, I prefer to ship things that don't require
installer but sometimes your its forces you to do one so that you can
like
register something with Windows or whatever that has to happen.
That's a requirement.
So, I think basically, you know, installers, I don't consider that
super much part of the project.
I don't care what we do for the installer of handmade hero.
So we probably just do whatever was most expedient if we can just have
something that's as simple as it's an executable.
And so, you know, we just can put an executable on Steam, you run the
executable and it runs and there doesn't have to be an installer.
That'd be my first choice but you know,
How about reading AKC approved.
Gooey debugger for J.
AI.
You know, if I had time to write a debugger, I would have written one
already.
Right.
Like I would have written one just for see even but I just haven't had
time.
I don't have time to even write the stuff that I'm supposed to be
writing.
Let alone extra stuff right?
Like
You know, like on our game project now, you know, we don't have a lot
of money, you know, we're not like a rich company, so, you know, I end
up doing a lot of stuff that's not even programming.
Like I haven't, I
I programmed anything in my rocket in like three weeks because I had
to do a bunch of artwork and stuff, that's just like the reality of of
how it goes.
So,
James Woodman.
I'm looking forward to additional visualize in the debug view, EGS
small grid view with a DOT or line from 0 0, to represent a V2 along
with the decimal digits.
Do you think that would be worthwhile generally?
No, I don't think that specifically is worthwhile what I was going to
do and I mention this, I kept saying the word diagramming.
Usually what works a little bit better is if you just write little
diagramming instructions, inside the debug like inside, as debug code
inside your code and have those come up in the debug thing which is
what I'd like to do.
And the reason for that is what you'll find is typically vectors only
make sense in reference to other vectors and you want to sort of have
a bunch of information there.
That sort of says here is the diagram that I'm trying to let
construct.
And so please like make that for me.
So you typically need a little bit more just putting like for a V2
just showing like what direction it goes.
I mean yeah.
It maybe it's a little bit better than nothing but for the most part
it's really not that useful.
Gary Johansen, do you ever met a program, The Sims stuff, and the job,
queue, The Sims stuff, and the job queue.
So job cues are a little bit of a tough subject at this point because
the code base at my rocket actually, isn't as multi-threaded as it
should be at this point.
And part of the reason for that is very long and involved, and I'm
kind of putting it off because in this particular case, we can and
there's some things I wanted to kind of do with it.
So in some sense, the answer is.
Yes, I probably will be metaprogramming.
Lot of that and that's
Of the reasons that I'm not doing it right now because I haven't had a
chance to build some of them over been approving things I wanted for
that.
But as for Sims stuff no I don't generally met a program stuff, that's
very mathy.
Like I don't generally met a program stuff that's just like math.
You know, physics or whatever, because I find that c and C++ operator,
overloading is usually enough to make that work.
Okay.
And while there are a bunch of things that I might want, they're,
they're kind of like, well, further down the road from where I'm at,
in terms of the meta programming structure.
I have the moment so I could Envision, you know, that being a
reasonable thing to meta program later.
But for right now, I don't, I'm not really in a position to address
those things.
Any in any
in any degree of efficacy, that would make it worth, doing those in
meta code, instead of just, just in regular code,
Okay.
CLS, is there any feature you would add to ja?
I, you know, I really I'd like to with whole or not withhold, but
rather postpone answering any kind of speculative features about j.i.
because honestly, like, you know, I haven't even written a line of
code in j.i., right?
John is the only one who has j.i.?
I don't know anything about it other than just what I absorbed from
watching his demos.
You know that's that's
So saying, you know what, I add this feature or that, or what do I
think of X?
It's like, you know, I don't know.
I like his attitude.
I like his approach.
I trust John and I think he's a good programmer.
So, I assume that most things work well, but there's not really much I
can do.
In terms of giving any concrete suggestions about ji because
programming is a very active process.
And, you know, if you showed me the spec to C++ and you said is this a
good language or a bad language, right?
I mean best I could probably tell you if I just grabbed it, I'd be
like well it's certainly not concise, right?
But until I actually write some stuff in it and have several years of
experience with
It's very difficult for me to say, C++ sucks, right now.
I know that C++ sucks like now, I know that C++ sucks because I've had
plenty of experience with it, and I know that it sucks.
And I can tell you all the ways that it sucks, but you can't just
look, you know, at at some cursory things about the language and kind
of say, you know, it's good or bad you need to really, you need to
ship a game in it or something.
Right.
You need to do the work.
You need to actually do that work.
And so all I can really say about jii until I start actually writing
things in it, which I assume, I will try.
I will do some experimenting, you know, when John decided to make it
into a beta or whatever he does, until I've actually had that
experience of writing with it and seeing what actually causes me
problems, what actually gets me speed wins, what what actually you
know, how it actually plays out there isn't anything out constructive,
I can say other than
I'm really happy that John is trying it.
and because I have a lot of respect for him, I suspect it will come
out well, but
You know, beyond that all I can say is I don't know who knows.
You know, there could be all kinds of like things in ji right now.
They're just really bad ideas that I would have no idea that they were
because until I actually go to do something go.
Oh my God, that's awful.
It's totally makes it hard to do all the stuff I do?
You know, I wouldn't know.
And so I think that's probably the earliest I can really start to give
concrete opinions about Jay.
I like, what would I add?
What I remove what would have done differently?
Anything like that?
I-it's too.
So premature at this point,
All right.
I think the stream has ended.
The Stream.
Has ended.
I'm going to go ahead and close it down.
Okay.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you is always.
So, hopefully combined with Friday stream, this stream gave you kind
of an idea of how you can actually use something like introspection
In your actual code, if that is something that you choose to do.
So now you've kind of got that and you can decide whether that makes
sense for you and whether you like that sort of thing or whether you
don't.
Like I said, it's not something that will probably pursue to
vigorously on handmade hero in general because I'd rather show sort of
the base layer of programming first, because I kind of consider
metaprogramming to be sort of like a thing that you do after your
already done, you know, after you've done something manually, then you
can think about how to do it automatically.
But typically, you don't really want to
The cart before the horse there and learn metaprogramming along with
your programming because I feel like that's you know if you if you
don't really have a super solid understanding of the first part, it's
kind of not such a good idea, jump to the second part but it's out
there now and we can make some light use of it in handmade hero.
So we will for example we could totally use this stuff if we wanted to
to Aid in our debug dumping or anything else that we might want to do.
So that's it for today if you want to follow along
At home.
You can always do so by pre-ordering the game on him a hero to Org,
the game comes to the source code.
So you can follow along Night by night and just play around with the
code C.
See what you can learn from it.
We also have a patreon page if you want to support the video series
it's always much appreciated.
We have a forum site, you can go to ask questions and there's also an
antidote episode guide up there that you can look at if you want an
easier way to watch some of the videos than on YouTube.
It's got kind of good jump lists and stuff like that in there.
We have a tweetbot the tweets ask
What you?
So if you'd like to catch the stream live, that's easy way to do it.
Take a look at the Tweet, but it will tell you.
And I will also tell you that tomorrow night, we will be right back
here at 8:00 p.m.
same time, same channel, and there is a special stream on Thursday.
We will be 8 p.m.
today 8 p.m.
tomorrow 8:00 p.m.
Wednesday, but Thursday, we will actually start a little earlier.
I think it's gonna start at 7:00 a.m.
7:00 p.m.
it will.
Say so the Tweet but already see the schedule.
So, whatever it says is correct.
But after immediately, after the Q&A of handmade hero, there's going
to be a special thing that me and Sean McGrath are doing Shawn
McGrath.
You may know as one of the main programmers on N plus plus previously,
he also made the game dyad
And he is oftentimes on the chat.
Actually as SSS, McGrath he asked me to sort of have not really a
debate, but sort of a devil's advocate thing because his next game is
going to be a f2p game and he wanted to have someone sort of argue
with him about it a little bit, just to see, you know, if he still
felt, it was okay for him to be working on an FTP game because he had
some concerns about it himself.
I guess it would say.
So for those of you who are interested in those sorts of things and
those sorts of discussions, we will be doing that immediately after
handmade here on Thursday.
So, please plan on checking out the stream that day and staying for
that.
Or if you don't have time to test the stream and just want to catch
It should be starting at about 8:30, Pacific, Daylight time.
That's about it.
Until next time, have fun programming and I will see you guys on the
internet.
Take it easy, everyone.
One.