Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could a complete game live on stream.
We are pretty much wrapped up with what we were trying to do at the
end of the new year and we have to start working on some 3D stuff that
we wanted to do.
However, I did want to spend one more day on a couple clean up things
that I thought would be good to do before we officially move on to a
fairly big new change and that
People who have been trying to compile on llvm, we try to keep our
code pretty clean even though we don't compile on multiple platforms
right now.
We try to keep it pretty clean in terms of allowing people to compile
on any platform they want.
So if you know, you want to compile handmade Hero on Macintosh or
Linux or Android, or anything else we try to make it.
So that all you have to do is just write the platform layer part.
That's specific to your operating system, but all the rest of the
stuff will work just fine and whether people have made like, sdl Port,
so you can even use
Use if the sdl is supported on your not STL.
But sdl, this simple directmedia layer, if that's supported on your
platform, you can use that port and so on.
But one of the problems that we have is just that most other platforms
like, on Windows, even to this day, it's fairly impractical to use
llvm or clang is probably the more correct way to say.
It's llvm is not the compiler part per se, but using clang as the
front end,
Windows while it is getting more and more possible every day to use.
Clang, instead of Visual Studio as your windows development tool, it's
still not quite at the point where that's probably what you would want
to do just yet.
Now, you know, like I said, it gets closer and closer every day.
So at some point that may be something that we consider doing and
there's a very good reason for doing that.
And that is, if you can use the same compiler on all of your
platforms, you might as well because that takes and one whole big
variable out of the
Out of the equation.
Now, you know that you're going to get similar code gen across your
multiple platforms.
You know, that you're going to have the same compiler errors and
warnings.
You know that this what the settings should be on everything and you
know it just it takes some unnecessary work out of the project for you
and that's always good because there's always more to do in
programming than you have time to do and so if there's ways you can
simplify your process it's good to do so.
Clang is certainly a good compiler.
It's it's as good as Visual Studio.
Certainly on any
Check that you might pick now, obviously there's some things Visual
Studio does better.
There's some things that clang does better, but on the whole it's not
like it's a step down.
So if you could switch to clean across all your platforms, that's
probably not a bad idea.
And sometime we may try to do that because like I said, it's getting
closer and closer to the point where you could probably just use clang
for everything on Windows as well, because they've made a lot of
strides in, like, getting it to Output to debug information.
That will work with, like visual Studios at debugger stuff like that.
So,
As those sorts of things start to become more and more usable becomes
more and more plausible to just use clang as your compiler on Linux
Mac Windows.
Android you know, iOS and and windows regular.
That's kind of this nice.
It just this nice uniformity to it.
So so I'm always interested in keeping that build going and for a
while we have had a problem that our debug system if you compile
without the debug system enabled,
Then I don't think we have any problem compiling with clang.
Right now.
If we do, then people haven't told me about it.
Is that?
So, people should tell me, so we can fix it, but if you compile with
the debug system on, then you do have a problem.
And the problem is that the definition of the function macro is
different between the two.
And the way that that works is inside the debug system, we use that
macro to tell us what the name of the function is that the debug
commands that we're issuing are inside, right?
So when we're inside a function, we want our debug counters, like our
our time counters, and our data output stuff.
We want those to be
marked so that we know what function they came from.
It's just makes it easier to read write.
And so if I come in, in fact, let me just load handmade hero and you
can see what I mean, when we come into the code here, here is handmade
hero, and if I run it, you can see that.
Like, if I open up our profile window, for example we get like these
nice function names here, right?
And that's you know what we want?
If we were to just show the
I'll name and line number.
It would be much harder.
Human readability wise to really know what these things were that were
in here.
And so having that function macro makes it a lot nicer.
It automate sit for the programmer, so they don't have to type in and
keep in synchronization.
Any sort of information there about what the the block is timing or
whatever the default is always the going to be usable in that the
default when you time something and use that function macro is it will
say to you exactly what you wanted to see there, which is to say,
it'll say what the function is that was taking the time, right?
And that's the sort of thing that we want.
So using that function macro is important to us and we need to be able
to do it.
However, what we were doing in this,
I'm stance.
Is we were trying to make it so that our debug system had the least
amount of work necessary in order to record a particular debug event,
right?
And so if you take a look at what that is, I'm going to go ahead and
load up handmade Heroes code here and just do a little compiled, just
for good measure.
And if I am here in handmade here and I want to take a look at how the
debug interface stuff works, you know, here it is, right.
And what you can see is that when we record
Of these pieces of information.
You can see it up here, but we want to do is we wanted to keep this
this brief, right?
So in a release mode, build this assert will go away and really all
there is is a one access of this event index bit right here.
After like we first atomic, add it.
And then we basically just mask it off to get which one we're going to
use and then we just go ahead and add that thing the event at that
location.
Right, and you can see that's that sort of Happening Here.
We then snap an are dtsc record.
What type of event it is, which core it was on which we don't have the
ability to do at the moment because we don't have our dtsc p on this
computer.
If we did have already TSC P.
We would have called that and gotten the core index as well.
We grab the thread ID and then we put the Grid in there, right?
And so we were trying to keep that pretty minimal old ready.
That's just kind of a lot of information to write down.
Which is kind of annoying, right?
But unfortunately, if you take a look at it, a lot of this stuff can't
be helped the event type and the grid are the only two things that are
statically known, right?
So really, those are the only we could get away with one less by
folding the type into the grid, right?
But the rest of these what thread we are on what core we are on and
what the Clock Was and where the event goes.
That's the minimum amount of stuff.
Actually kind of need to record.
Because the threat is dynamic, we don't know which thread is entering
this, this function, right?
The clock is dynamic because we don't know what time stamp.
This is executing at ahead of time and the core would be dynamic if we
were getting it from our dtsc P.
So, you know, there's not much we can really do about that.
But the quid and the and the type or two things we can control.
So the way we were doing the Grid in that right, is what
Doing is we concatenate a bunch of things together to produce?
That piece of information.
And so you can kind of see here.
We've got record debug and event and that's what calls this macro.
You can see that we pass it.
Like this thing like debug name, for example, right.
And you can see how debug name works is debug name, concatenates,
these strings together to make a single string and that single string
is made at compile time.
So that way we stuff the file, the line, the counter and whatever the
name part is we stuff all of that stuff in there.
like right and so that allows us
To get all of that information into a single string, that's produced a
compile time.
So that when we hit this debug event, we don't spend any time storing
information.
We didn't need to store, right?
Where's our problem with that?
Well, the problem is that the reason that that works, is this function
macro here that we're using
In visual studio.
And in my opinion correctly, not to play favorites, but I disapprove
of the way clang has decided to do this.
It is correctly, a static known string at compile time, right?
Just like file is right, what that means?
Is that you can use neighbored concatenation on it and it will work.
Now, for those of you who haven't,
Like had a lot of experience with this or, you know, like maybe you've
never taken really much time to consider this because, you know, it's
certainly in the esoterica of C.
But if you know, I was to go ahead and say string equals Foo
Right?
You can see that, there's a line of C code that I might write.
If I was to go in and take a look at what's going on in the debugger
here in handmade dot CPP.
Let's just take a look at right.
What that does.
So here is I'm going to step in here and I'm just going to take a look
at what string is right.
And you can see that with string is is it's just a pointer to a
location in memory that stores Foo, right.
And that's exactly what we would expect, right?
There's the data for it.
In fact, it's for long, right?
Because there's
Mel Terminator that it's going to put on there as well right.
Now, if on the other hand I was to say like, oh also, I would like to
do a bar there.
I can put two strings next to each other in this fashion and the
compiler will automatically weld the two strings together.
Again, this is not being done at runtime.
Like it would be in like PHP or something or with a string class.
This is actually going to compile time, so see if I come in here now.
What you'll see is that actually nothing.
And again we can even look at the disassembly here just to demonstrate
what's going on.
You can see that.
No welding of the strings happens at all.
All we're doing is loading a single constant pointer and when we load
that pointer here is what we're pointing to.
So, the compiler has pre combined those two strings together.
Stuck that into our executable as a piece of data and all we have to
do to access.
It is just load, just one pointer which is
Then exactly what we want in the debug case.
And so what you can see is that if I were to change this to some
pre-processor string like underscore underscore file, then when we
take a look at what happens here and we step in, you can see that it's
actually, well, I can just do it this way.
You can see that it's actually concatenated the file on there, get rid
of that truncation, it's concatenated, the file onto the end of my
string, which is
actly.
What I said it would do, right?
It's like it takes these two strings.
Both of them together puts that as one piece of data into the
executable, and then again, if we look at what has to happen in the
disassembly, nothing happens.
Other than the load.
That's all that happens.
Is we load up a particular constant pointer to this string that's been
stored in our executable already and that's all that has to happen,
right?
No combinations there at all.
So that's very important, right?
And if we want in Visual Studio to do that with function, we can
write.
So there's my function.
And if we look at what it says, now, you can see it just puts game
update and render on the end of that, right?
So, in my opinion, it's kind of obvious that, that's how it should
work.
The reason that I think it's kind of obvious that that's how it should
work is, that's how file worked.
So you would expect underscore underscore function and I was going to
sort of file to be the same
You would like to be able to have this automatic welding
functionality, certainly and it's pretty easy for the programmer if
they want something else to create that something else, if you want it
to be a local variable, it'd be pretty easy for you to generate a
local variable and stick it in there.
Whereas, the reverse is actually impossible, there's no way for you to
turn that into something that is stored without doing actual work at
that point, right?
Now, so that all works great and visual studio, did it the right way,
in my opinion.
However, if we take a look at what happens with function, apparently,
on Vision, clang, rather what happens is,
Function is declared as a variable and it can't be concatenated with
other literals, right?
And so I don't know if there's any documentation that anyone's linked
to here for this doesn't look like it.
But let's see here at GCC that's going to function because I wanted to
kind of show you.
And I since I said, I've never looked at this aspect of clang before
I'm going to go ahead.
See if I can find it.
Okay, so the inner fire underscore underscore function.
Plus the declared by the translator as as if immediately following the
opening brace, which function the Declaration Sadiq Khan scare
underscore underscore Funk equals function name.
Right function is another name for Funk provided for backward,
compatibility with older versions of GCC, right?
So what that means is that when we do underscore underscore function,
and again, I'm looking at the GCC documentation, but only because
clang follows the G.
SEC specs, usually.
What that means is that we don't actually have a way of referring to
this directly, right?
All we have is a way of accessing a faux local variable, right?
So you have to imagine there's a thing that looked effectively like
this.
Now it's not necessarily actually this because like the compiler just
saying it's as if this
True.
So it doesn't mean that it actually is doing static initialization in
exactly this way.
But it sags If This Were true, right?
And so now what you can see is if that was actually what we had,
right?
If that is what we were dealing with here.
Oops, I didn't mean to do that in this window.
My bad.
Close.
Do do there we go.
So, if that's what we actually had their right, if what we were
actually dealing with with something where we said, like, okay, you
know, we've got funk and there it is.
Right?
What you can see is that when we come through here, we can't even
compile this.
And the reason that we can't compile, this is because this is a
variable, right?
This is an actual just a variable, and while C++ is compiler, allows
us to juxtapose two.
Constant strings next to each other and Weld and it will weld them
together.
It does not allow us to to juxtapose two variables together and weld
them together.
Even if one of those variables is a const string, that it can see the
Declaration of for some reason.
And I guess, I don't know why this he'll suspect doesn't allow this.
But for some reason that is disallowed, right?
The spec does not say if the compiler can determine that a string is
constant and knows what the string is then, it can concatenate it.
As if it were a constant ring in that place, it does not say that.
So this is effectively what's happening in our llvm based Builds an
ark Lang based builds is that it seeing this.
It's a seeing it as effectively as if we had done this, right?
And it's it producing compile errors, that might not be exactly this
compile error, but they're
Be basic, basically the same compile, error, same type of compile
error.
Hey, you've placed a constant string next to a string pointer and I
don't know what to do with that.
That is not an operation that I can handle.
Okay?
so that is what's currently preventing our llvm build from working,
started playing bass build
From working out of the box.
And like I said, you can turn the debug system off but if people want
the device system on which, you know, why wouldn't you want the debug
system on if you're debugging?
Then you don't have that opportunity.
So if we take a look at what's going on here, our goal is to figure
out some way to work around this.
And to be honest I'm not really sure what the easiest way to work
around it is obviously there's a very simple workaround and I guess we
can read here in a second.
What the people suggested workarounds are but let me just talk about
it real quickly.
The most straightforward way to work around.
It is to just spend another move on every debug event.
Recording the function name separately.
Right.
Because the only reason we concatenate all these together, rather than
just saving them separately, is to reduce the amount of time that the
processor has to take.
Every time we enter one of these debug events, right?
That was the only reason we were doing that.
That's probably the best approach here.
Because I can't think of what else we would do.
Hmm.
But I'm thinking
yeah, I can't think of really a whole lot else that we can do and
still preserve the function name.
But let's see what people suggest.
Let's see, use the full function signature as grid.
What does that mean?
Let's see.
How about a not selling approach.
In the case of time function, you could just use pretty function in
place of debug name function when compiling Clancy.
It's still subject to the same kind of flirtatious.
It's just a character, but you wouldn't need to concatenate since it
gives you the full function signature, which should be enough to
disambiguate overloads, unless there's another reason to use
debugging.
Macro obviously the resulting output will be somewhat verbose because
it won't be neatly parsed, like the default path, but otherwise,
that's your problem.
So maybe something like pretty function.
So what is pretty function?
Because
I don't think I've ever used that before it looked like it was
mentioned in that page.
I was just looking at moments ago so we can go read about it.
It evaluates the string, top level.
It was it contains the signature of the function as well as bear
named.
For example, this program gives you output void a sub it, okay.
So it's just a, it's all it is, is just more, it's a non-ambiguous
version of the thing, right?
It's it basically includes the return value and the parameters and the
scope.
So, at that point, you would know that, you know, too overloaded
functions would not have the same function name.
So that's not bad, but we might want the file in line number for other
reasons, potentially,
Although maybe we don't, I don't know.
Let's think about that.
I don't know.
I mean that that you can see why that has some attraction because we
would be able to always use that we could still parse it if we wanted
to produce a cleaner function name at the end of the day.
And so then the question is, do we need the file and line number for
anything?
It would be nice to have the file on line number as well.
I feel like butt.
Yeah.
But I could see that.
I mean, so okay, so keep that in mind.
That's something.
It looks like number two is what I just suggested which was okay.
We just save the function value separately, right?
And the final one is just we don't get it, we don't we don't get the
function name at all.
which isn't really a, I wouldn't consider three or really an option
because I definitely want the function name
As far as concatenating function of transmitting, a preprocessor does
not seem like a good idea because I don't really want to go that route
and concatenate the strings at runtime.
I also don't think is necessarily good, although maybe they had a way
to do it, that would be cleaner.
Is there any certain to Define function as a as a very aware than a
macroeconomic state of the poor choice?
Right, that's not.
Where is the concatenated?
Runtime suggestion?
I don't know where that is.
so, I don't know where the suggestion to concatenate them at runtime
is
So it looks like this it looks like this is somebody at this is just
this block of code.
I see.
And so, how did they do that?
So, it looks like what they did.
Hmm.
Okay, but this this joy and strings thing, this is going to have to
happen every time through here which would be awful, right?
We definitely don't want that.
Right?
Because that means every time we enter a time to function, we can
catenate them and that's no good.
So we definitely want to do that.
We could introduce a static initializer that would only happen the
first time through but even that's not great.
Yeah, so I don't know.
It seems like maybe pretty function is the most sensible way.
To go about doing this.
Because yeah, then we can just record still one, only one thing and
let that be the the official signature of the of the op.
I guess, what I'll say is I don't know if pretty function
I don't know if pretty function exists on Visual Studio, probably not
at this point in time, but, you know, maybe it would in the future.
So we'd probably have to still have to sort of paths.
We'd have to support the debug name, the concatenated, version of the
debug name for visual studio, and then pretty function for for GCC /
clang, because I'm assuming that if we wanted to.
And here, there is no.
Like this is not a thing, right?
Yeah, so there's no real way to get that piece of information,
although I guess now I think about it.
I've never looked you know, Visual Studio, may just call it something
else.
So let's take a look and, you know, maybe just see what they have, if
there's anything in particular.
All right, so they've got some specific ones here.
Yeah which are just talking about some other things that are
interesting but not relevant to what we're doing at the moment.
So here this, this looks like it it kind of would be similar.
You can see that the function signature there you go.
Funk Sig Funk Sig looks like roughly
Same thing.
So if we wanted to we could have Funk Sig be what we use instead of
instead of pretty function and then that would keep both paths roughly
equivalent.
So you know, that's it may not be my first choice.
My first choice is I think the way we were doing it here and I again I
would I would say that it's really a black mark on clang to not
Not support that.
You know, it's not hard to Define another.
Variable there.
That's, that's a properly done string.
You know, if you want to keep the static version fine.
But, you know, you should support a way to get it as a as a constant
string, for sure.
And so I feel like that's really something they should fix, I don't
know, maybe it's something we can fix.
Do you think if we just went and downloaded the, the clang source code
and added that in there?
And then set sent a pull request thing with?
Listen, probably not, I'm guessing.
We'd have to go 12 rounds with somebody.
an argue with, with a bunch of people on a mailing list to get that in
there, but
You know, I suppose we could try, but in lieu of that, you know?
So if I was to go in here and say, all right, let's take a look and
see what we can do.
To make this happen.
Let's take a look inside our debug system and just see where we parse
those debug names.
Here you go.
So when we do our debug personname, you can see we do our elected line
number miss here and I'm just curious if we use that for anything.
So, okay, so at the moment, I don't think we do and, and that's good,
right?
Because if we had been making a lot of use of that, then it would be a
bummer if
With that was something that we wanted.
And so since it's not something we're really paying attention to, I
feel like it's, I'm okay, maybe with with having that go away, right?
Okay.
All right, so let's just just see if we go down this route, if we get
to any, if we get to anywhere in particular, that is going to be, you
know, kind of a little bit off-putting then we'll go from there.
But let's let's assume that this is going to work, okay?
And we'll sort of just assume that will go with a function signature
based approach.
And we're just we'll just jettison our previous approach of having it
be file name, line number and so on.
Now, the downside of this again, like I said, you know, one of the
reasons that I would have preferred to have this here is because if
you imagine a more robust debug system, like, so let's say we take our
doing system and we go, we want to make this into a really full fledge
thing.
We're gonna spend a bunch of time on it, in addition, to the time
we've already spent, you know, building it out for some reusable, nice
thing.
One of the things you might imagine wanting to do is click on
something, in the debug system and have it jump to the appropriate
location of that thing.
In the source code.
And right now that's trivial for us to do because when we have the
file name and line number, we can just do that, right?
There's no real thing preventing us from doing that.
so, if we had, for example,
In for coder, let's say.
In fact, I don't know Alan Webster probably isn't here today.
But it does sort of seem like, it would be cool to have a standard way
to send like a Windows message to for a coder that says, I would like
to open this file line.
Number combo to jump to it.
Do you know what I mean?
So, I don't know.
There's that.
That's something that would be kind of cool to have any way, you could
imagine constructing that extremely easily because in our debug
system, at present, we have the ability to do that, right?
We have the ability to say, oh, okay.
Here's the file name.
Here's the line number.
So a IDE of any kind can go ahead and jump there and, you know, it
knows where it is in the source code.
But with out that then you would need
Debug info because all we can provide you is the function signature.
And you know at that point you have to be able to parse the pdb figure
out where that function is and then jump to it.
And even then you're not at the line that the debug output occurred at
your just in the functioning.
And so it's not really the sort of the place where you're going to
have like
I don't know, it's basically not the place where you're going to be
able to jump to.
It's not giving you the information you need for most of your tools,
right?
If that makes sense.
Yeah.
So anyway, let's see I would go to
Maybe leave the sin.
I guess the question is do we want to leave this in as the grid for
the other version?
And the answer is maybe, so what we could do is scan for an or, and if
we don't see the or then don't do it right.
And I don't know, maybe maybe that would work just as it is.
I'm not sure, let's find out.
Let's see here.
So if I was to make groups, it's not going to help if I was to make
two different versions of this.
I could just if around just this one block.
And so, in here, when I do my debug names, right?
I guess what we could do is just say, like, okay, if we've got unique
file counter string, like it's doing here, I could just say that this
doesn't try to concatenate anymore.
Right.
Unique file counter string just uses.
Well, you know.
Okay.
I take it back though.
Now that I think about it.
I don't think this actually is going to work.
Right.
Like in theory, I would say,
Let's see here in theory.
I would say that's fine, but the function signature is not going to be
unique.
If you have multiple timed blocks inside something, right?
That's not going to work because let's say, we have multiple time
blocks.
Those signatures are all going to be the same and it's not going to
end up evaluating to a grid.
So yeah, I I don't think so.
So I guess what I would say is it looks to me like really the only
like pretty function isn't really going to be an option because we
would still have to figure out some way to concatenate, pretty
function with a counter.
And since we can't do that that doesn't really help us.
We still end up having to store two things.
We'd have stored the counter and the grid which is not really good
anymore, the counter and the string.
And once we do that, we might as well just ordered the the function as
a separate thing.
Yeah, so unfortunately I think that's just that's just the way it is.
I don't think there's going to be any way around that, so I guess what
we'll do is we'll just say that the debug system has to store one more
piece of information and that's just the way it is.
So there's basically like an event name in addition to the grid and
we'll just sort of make do with that.
I think that's the only really way that we're going to be able to do
it and then when you do unique file counter string you don't get to
pass the name anymore, right?
That name is not going to be available.
And so that's just gone.
And when you call record debug event, you have to pass the name to
record debug event and it will get passed separately.
I think that's the only really thing we can do.
And so it's going to have to look like this.
Right.
I think that's the only, the only option.
So, I'll put a note here from us, which just says like, hey, you know,
in record debug event the name
Is recorded separately now?
to work around the fact that
GCC and clang, don't Define.
Function, as a constant string.
so it can't be compile-time welded into a,
Along with the file.
Line.
And so at that point we're going to have to do this.
That means that the unique file counter string B.
We can leave this sort of route in place if you will and just not do
the concatenation, right?
So that'll just not actually happen and then we just have to make sure
that we pass it in both places and that way, we could re-enable it
again at some point, potentially
If that makes sense.
So when we do stuff like like here, where we do debug begin, you know,
begin Block in that sort of thing.
So we're going to have to have, you know, the name.
Coming as long as well.
Now, there's the name.
And so, you know, these sort of always always has to be passed along
every every time twice essentially, right?
Although I guess that that one's actually end block.
And anytime we're manually doing this.
How is that working with this care star?
Oh, there's that's the grid itself, okay, right?
So if we have the grid itself come in there, then we call begin block.
We actually don't need anything.
There we can, the name can be zeroed out because we've already
constructed a grid.
That's what we needed.
Right.
And so now I need to add to our debug event.
Here we go.
and here, and
Not enough actual parameters for macro record debug Event, open data
block those data block.
So, I guess, when we pass the name here to debug data block again,
like I feel like so how are we getting this for debug data?
But I guess it just passes that name and the name is all there is so
at that point, I guess we could, we could pass them duel, but I guess
maybe I'll just pass them as zeros here.
The more correct thing perhaps would be to put the well, no.
Okay, we'll just, we'll just leave it at that.
That that seems fine.
So yeah.
I thought just get passed twice and so in debug value not enough
parameters.
So where is debug value?
There we go.
So in here you can see us passing these things.
Again it's just like kind of a waste that exercise right but where
sort of having to
having to make these things.
I don't know if that's going to cause a problem because this may not
be unique anymore.
I don't.
Remember enough about how we were using.
It looks like debug named value is not used anymore so maybe we can
just get rid of it.
Let's find out if that's true.
Yeah.
So, debug begin data, block not enough parameters for debug.
Okay, so we just need again to begin.
Data block.
So, here we are in that, and that looks like it just ends there.
So again, that's probably fine.
We just need to pass that name a second time.
Let's see.
So these are in the debug b32, like, all of those things, right?
When there's get passed down.
So, let's take a look at those Hoops.
Keep you to write.
So, all of these right that are passing the debug name with the pound
value stuff.
Again, I think those just need to be duped out, but that's really all
that they would have to have
I've been I guess.
What else we got here?
UI element.
Here.
Where is that?
About you.
I own it.
Oh yeah, it's just right there.
And let's see, record debug events for here, debug, and data block
that should have handled it automatically.
So I must have messed up the, debug, and data Block B.
Yeah, it looks like it just needs to get past a second.
Let's see.
No Object file generated, not enough.
Actual parameters for macro record, debug event and the semicolon.
So that's frame marker.
All right, so that's just going to pass that as the name a second time
again.
So now everything should get past twice and let's go into the, parse
debug name stuff inside the debug system here.
And essentially, this part is the part that's going to change.
Tried.
Because we were parsing the good before and, you know, sort of keeping
a bunch of track of like, where we are at the different parts and the
parts name.
And so, I think, what we want to do now is just say, like, okay,
when we go through, our are parsed name here.
Instead, our name link stuff is not going to actually be based on this
at all.
Our name, length stuff is going to be based on the name field of the
debug event that comes in.
And so, when we say debug personname, which I guess, if you take a
look here, we have to kind of
We have to pass in a name for it to actually produce the parts name
for us.
So when we do this, it's going to return, it returns a bunch of stuff
like the hash value and things like that.
That we want but it can't actually get us back this part of the name
without us sort of passing that additional value in there, right?
And so what I think we want to do is basically say like, you know,
there's a proper name here that comes in and so when we do this thing,
this is how it used to work.
but instead, we know we've got this
and I think that's mostly it.
Let's see here.
Right.
Yeah.
I think that's mostly it.
Now, I don't know.
If that's everything we need.
We don't allow string lengths of zero.
Okay?
What do I not feel like we should?
In fact, I think I'll probably just support that.
Interface.
I think we just want to do.
Strange.
Yeah.
There we go.
So yeah.
When we?
Collate these.
We want to make sure that we always have something filled into that
field.
I think there was one time that I didn't do that.
Yeah it was here right?
And so I think we always want to sort of
Keep that piece of information present.
I have to see how we actually use time to block.
Cuz you can see that it does the grid, it produces the debug name from
The Grid and then that will lose that actual name.
So I think in here, we probably have to keep the name separate like so
again for the GCC reason.
So I think in here what we'd have to do is say, okay, the name comes
down along with it, right?
So that you kind of have this
This.
Sort of ridiculousness happening where it's like, okay, yep, there's
the name that comes in and we will pass that through to the time
block.
When we construct it.
So let me make sure there's no other ones.
So there is one there where we're getting a name of a data block and
presumably that name just has to be replicated.
Let me just verify when that happens.
So, okay, so there is one of the situation that happens.
It happens here, right?
So we probably want this as well.
Right.
And more specifically, it's really BISS.
so, in theory, that would keep us working properly now, but
Oh, but we got to make sure that we we get our stuff lined up.
So we actually are pulling out from the right places here, which I
don't know that we actually are.
So let's make sure we've got all that stuff.
Handled.
Because yeah, we may be passing incorrect, things down.
Alright, so we've got our debug event names set in there and inside
are handmade debug.
When we scan these, we're getting that proper name past separately and
that's what's going into.
The name length Fields here.
So if I go to debug parse name,
and we're I'm calling that when we do get element from grid,
I think we should never care about that because the grid should always
be sufficient in that circumstance.
As far as I know,
and,
These are pass those down.
Write, debug parse name.
Yeah, so I'm not sure why that would not be properly recording it,
because I feel like event name should be stored correctly at that
point.
But let me go ahead and make sure that that's actually true.
Because I don't actually know that it is.
So let me go ahead and actually take a look at, you know, step through
a couple things here.
So we can actually see if that's the case.
So, hopefully, inside this record, debug event B here.
Of course, it won't.
Let me set a breakpoint there because it's in a macro unfortunately.
Hmm.
Well because I just want to be able to see what these debug events
are.
So let me, let me instead take a look since I can't easily set a
breakpoint there, I should be able to, but of course, it doesn't let
me because probably doesn't record enough debug info to do that.
I just want to take a look at what it does in terms of getting the
results of these parts debug events.
So, let's take a look here.
so that name looks looks correct there and oh, and name starts at
I suppose needs to be set to 0, always here as well.
Which I cousin case, somebody chooses to use the name starts at field,
plus the Grid.
In fact do people do that.
Let me find out
Because we're going to have to get rid of that field basically as well
because the name starts at is not going to be valid anymore.
yes, you can kind of see here like
that is a problem because we essentially shortcutted that
and that's not really going to work, right?
We need to use those separately.
So I guess what happens.
The problem that happens here is we store those strings, right?
You can see us doing it here.
We do a push string on of the grid, right?
And then we store name starts at
So probably what we would want to do, there is just I guess story The
Grid and then do a push string on on the name, right?
Seems like that's probably the smartest thing to do and then get rid
of get you know just make name starts at not a thing anymore because
that's just not something we can actually use, right?
So then name starts at is is not going to be used anywhere and then
anywhere who won who was trying to use it.
Oops.
Wait, that should work, right?
Name is not a member of debug element.
Oh,
good point.
That's actually true.
It isn't
Okay.
So I think that's all good and then we just have to make sure that we
don't ever get in situations where these things are set to 0.
Which, in this case, it looks like it is, looks like and made code
handmade.
Debugs 1941 71 there.
So let's take a look at 1941, handmade debug
So it looks like debug name.
Oh, this is just only for the root profile quid.
So the route Profile Event.
It looks like the problem there that that's just a synthetic one that
we create.
So it looks like as long as we work to set that to one as well, we can
avoid that problem.
That may be our only one because we have to make sure those are never
set to know because now we're actually using the name it always has to
be valid or we can't print or show that
All right, so let's take a look.
So first of all, we have to stop the name starts at bit, so now we
always need to use the name field.
So everyone who was using the name starts at needs to?
Now?
Use name directly.
And so, when we are in here, we can just sort of say like, hey,
instead of doing that, that trickery, you were doing before you can
stop doing that now.
Just use the name pointer and that's fine.
And actually, I suppose we can just do this.
since that's what people are supposed to be doing in a why this
particular
Point in the code wasn't doing that and then maybe we're okay.
So let's take a look.
Okay, so now we've restored that.
But we still have a little bit a problem for.
You can see that like, for example, these guys are listed by counter
value.
So it looks like we're putting the wrong thing.
When we record those, debug events were recording for our data debug
events.
We're recording the wrong piece of information, so rather than the
string we're recording their ordinal, right?
There there underscore our counter and so we just have to take a look
at our is that spelled right by the way.
Yes, so we fixed the bug?
So now inside the system, we just have to make sure that nobody is
passing the incorrect thing down.
And so when you get down here and you're saying like, Okay, you know,
let's take a look.
What are we doing?
That's incorrect here.
So we pass debug value.
It looks like when we call record, debug event,
That we are correctly, passing.
That string eyes value but maybe something else is happening wrong
here, because here's debug be 32, it's passing the type, it's it's
calling debug name to generate the grid as it normally would write and
then it's it's also giving you the name of the value.
Directly there.
So I feel like that should have been doing the right thing.
But I guess it's not and so what I'd like to do is just take a look
here at what's actually going on.
So here's like a debug be 32, it's passing global renderer test, weird
draw, buffer size and so it's should be calling this macro.
It's passing that in here.
So I feel like it should be passing record.
Debug event the right value.
So my question is is it just the printout of these that's wrong?
Or is it the actual thing that's being passed?
That's wrong.
And I'm not sure.
So, again, let me just take a look quickly to see if anyone is using
name starts at, in some kind of
In some kind of way that they shouldn't be and so that we can kind of
figure that out.
So, it looks like the only people
Are really using it are in this.
These locations here, which again, doesn't seem like it should be a
problem.
So yeah, let's find out.
Let me walk through the handmade Hero opening code there.
Where we are
Let's see.
So, here's that Atomic add, let's take a look at the disassembly here
because we're not gonna be able to step into the macro.
So I just want to see if I can get a little bit of a picture of what's
going on with the debug event.
You can see the atomic add happening here.
So cures, a bunch of moves, right, that are happening.
I don't know what.
if any, here's the our dtsc,
Is there any others in here?
There's the get thread ID.
Although where is the get red ID?
Yeah.
All right, so it doesn't look particularly problematic anywhere.
Okay, so once we've worked all this stuff out, you can see generally
we're doing, we're moving all this stuff into position.
We should be able to see what we actually loaded as the as the size.
And so it looks like I'm sorry as the name.
For example.
What's the actual value here?
That we loaded in?
Is This Global render test where a draw bar for size?
So that's the address of oops, not on it.
That's the address of the Boolean I believe.
Right.
Yeah.
So we've loaded in the address of the Boolean.
That's the thing that's going to get Modified by debug set event data.
So we loaded the string somewhere up in here, but I'm not exactly sure
where there's get thread ID, it should have probably loaded just
before that, right?
So we should have loaded the string.
There it is.
We should have loaded the string just before that, and we did Right.
There Is Us loading the string and there is the string.
So presumably the debug event actually has it written down correctly
there.
And, you know, so are ax.
I guess probably holds the value.
Of our debug event at this point.
Let's just take a look here.
And it does so because you can kind of see you could see here, the
pattern of everybody was addressing off of RA X.
So that's how I knew that, right?
Like I was just looking to see like, oh, okay, you know,
I went to write that string into our ax + 18, H and I wrote 1 into re
X Plus 8 and so on, right?
So now we're just like, okay whatever is in our ax right now, the
register r x must hold, you know, where all the strings are and you
can kind of see them here, right?
You got the grid, you've got the name and I'm just trying to figure
out sort of like, if this is what I'm passing down.
Then it looks like the name has exactly what I would have expected
when I retire, this debug event and I'm not
Sure why I wouldn't then.
Why wouldn't be able to get sort of a?
you know, a reasonable
a reasonable parse out of it.
So the only thing I can think of at that point is that when we are
creating these debug values that we're doing them, in some way that
isn't properly a bang parsed name because if the proper name is always
getting past.
Down for these data blocks than I would have assumed that, that would
be sufficient, but I don't actually know.
So, let's see here.
It could be this right here.
Where we sort of copy that name over.
Hmm, so I don't know.
This is very intriguing, so we must be copying these out in some way
that we're not obeying here.
The that is the path.
We would have been going through.
So I guess maybe I can just step through it and see what happens like
when we restore a vent here,
Let's just step through there and see what happens because the debug
systems, pretty complicated.
As you know, and we never really refined it down to a level of really
good Simplicity or anything.
So, you know, there's a little bit too much complexity in there and
probably just best to take a look at what happens when we call get
element from event.
Come through here.
We're asking for Global pause.
So that's all good.
So let's take a look at what happens with our results.
Here's our results.
The name is Bilbo, posit is what we want it to be.
So all that's good and we can do whatever we want to do there.
So now we end up with an element and we'll just take a look at what
the element has.
So for some reason, we're resetting the original grid of this thing to
be what the element grid was, but I'm not really sure why.
So, to be honest, I do not understand that that assignment there.
Because we are pushing that string on and I don't know why we feel the
need to reassign in that way, right?
It doesn't make a whole lot of sense to me.
Fact, I kind of wonder if that should be there.
Okay, so then we go to store event.
You can see us during the event here.
And yeah, in this case, all we're doing is
It's really figuring out where we're going to put this.
Assuming that we did put it somewhere, we just copy the event
wholesale from one to the other.
I guess the point of the original grid bit is just because we want to
use that pointer for something later, right?
But that shouldn't affect the fact that after we do that store, we
still have the name, correct?
Right.
So yeah, so that all looks pretty reasonable.
all to me, like,
You know, there's there's one of these guys getting stored and it, you
know, there it is storing it.
And when we take a look in here to see what that stored event is,
there it is.
Right.
all right, so let's go over and let's just jump over here to take a
look at
where we print those out.
So let's just see when we're printing them out so we can, you know,
Try to figure out where we're getting that problem.
So here we are in debug event to text.
Excuse me.
And oh, well, that would do it.
It looks like we actually were sort of still using old pieces of the
grid here and just scanning them.
Right.
Which is probably not particularly useful.
And in fact we initialize the name to the element with ID which is not
what we want to do, right?
So that's well, that's good enough.
That's a pretty simple answer to our problem.
Let's take a look at where names assigned.
It looks like that's the only place.
So I suppose.
What we'll do here is just say like instead of this use name bit here,
in fact is I don't know.
Looks like that's not used anywhere.
Really, so technically we could just probably do this and say instead
of this bit right here, we could just do like, okay, whatever you're
going to use for the name, we could just say, let's go ahead and use
the event quid.
If you're asking it to show the entire grid, otherwise just show the
name and off you go, right?
And that looks much better now.
We've got our names back and, and we're in pretty good shape there, so
that's all pretty good.
No, real downsides there.
So, there you go.
And so I guess, let's see how much time you have here.
We've got it's 12:45.
So do we start it 11:30?
I think so.
We've got till about 1:30 to go, so I think that's good.
And I guess the only question I have now is did we actually solve this
problem or didn't we solve the problem?
Because again, the only reason that we just did all the stuff that we
just did is
So that we can compile using llvm, which I don't actually know.
Again, whether we will or not at this point, it's an open question.
So yeah, so the thing to figure out here I guess is just
Are we doing?
Is that concatenation happening anymore?
Or isn't it?
And and I don't know.
Let's try to double check here but otherwise we'll just have to sort
of send this code over the fence and say for people who are compiling
with, with it at the moment, how you know, did that solve the problem,
or didn't it?
So you can see inside time function here when we do this,
It looks like that's really the only place that's happening.
We also verified because now we can pile without that, that that
doesn't need to be there.
So, we've got this one place that functions being used.
You can see that it's getting passed down to the debug name.
So, and this field right here inside times lock.
When name gets passed down,
Really all that's happening.
There is that name is getting past eventually through as an actual
variable to the time block, so, that shouldn't be a problem.
So, the only question is, whether passing function to debug name would
create something and the whole point is we try to fix that.
So, let's just double check that.
That's actually true.
So here is debug name.
And here's when we're actually producing unique file counter string.
When we get debug name in there, you can see that we pass it as the
final parameter that final parameter is D which
Then gets ignored.
So, in theory, now we're at the point where that is is no longer ever
tried to concatenate as a string.
So I'm going to say that that is a good first pass and we'll have them
test it and see whether they, you know, are okay with that.
So let's go ahead and say that I believe we fixed this on day 356 but
we
Don't really know since we don't compile with lying on the stream.
I will close the bug for now but please reopen it, if it turns out
that there are further issues.
So yeah, as far as I know again I don't know of any other things that
because I feel like we fixed all the other clang problems because they
were
Minor they didn't require any changes.
They were just really minor issues that that had to be changed.
And so I don't think we've got anything else in here because we've
replaced the printf the glue in void pointer stuff.
We fix this well, so I think that's it and
We'll call that done for now.
All right, so that's about all there is to that and I feel like that
is it for our issues.
These are all enhancement requests that are for later in the project.
So I feel like those are all good and we no longer have any more
issues here to address and in theory we should be running reasonably
now.
And the only thing we had to go look at is we had to go look.
That the camera stuff and see how that is.
All right, so yeah, I think everything.
Been restored to regular working order.
I don't know if there's anything else we need to do here but it seems
like we're pretty good to go.
Everything seems to be operating normally
So that's all good.
All right, so I think that's it.
Good good, good.
All right, so I guess now the only thing I might as well go and debug
just so again, tomorrow we can start fresh.
I don't think we have any more issues to address and we could start on
3D stuff tomorrow or whatever else we want to do.
But I guess what I would say here is there's I don't know that there's
much point in it, but we still have the, like camera non-tracking
thing where we wanted to have like room based cameras and really like,
maybe it's best to not.
Fixing that because we're going to move to 3D anyway and we'll
probably clean out the stuff in that pass.
But again, since we do have a little bit of time here, I don't know
that there's anything else that I want to do.
That's like a
Any kind of particularly pressing need because I'm pretty sure.
Everything else is just on the sort of the end of the, the sort of the
tail end of the 3D stuff here.
So I don't really know that.
I don't really know that there's anything else to do.
That makes sense to do right now.
So I might just pop over here and take a look and see how that's
going.
If I remember correctly, the way that we were doing this as we called
up a camera for empty movement and in there we tried to
Out what you know, where the which room The Entity was in.
And once we figure that out, we just tried to figure out where you
were relative to that room and move the camera to correspond to that.
Although, you know, like I said, this is not really, this kind of just
a key code in this probably not how we're going to do it at all.
So
You know, I take that with a grain of salt, but I guess we, I think
what we figured out first without sort of getting into, how this code
down here was working, is that when we were taking a look at this code
here, we never actually.
And this is why this fix this testing was in here, we never actually
got any hits so we never found ourselves actually overlapping these
volumes at all.
So our problem to start with is just that
You know.
We never found any rooms that the player actually was in.
So, in theory, when we do this update camera to, you know, we've got
at least have one room that we can find.
And you can see, like, we're not ever finding a room.
So, even though the player is clearly inside a room, there's no way we
can never tell if he goes outside the room.
If we're never finding that he's in a room at all.
And so, what we need to do here is sort of stop
We need to come through here and figure out for things that are room
based right which in this case like this is a brain room.
We need to figure out why we're never getting any why we're never
getting any overlaps at all.
Right.
And so let's just take a quick look at what's happening in this in
these
Custer teens here.
You can see that like we're passing a position and that's the position
of presumably.
The player that we're testing, am I right about that?
How are we figuring that out basically?
There were passing the entity and that entity presumably came from an
attempt to get the player update.
Let's see here.
There's the camera entity, right?
And that's just to whatever it was fun.
Whoever it's following.
We get that.
Be by ID there.
So we assume that's the player.
I guess.
One thing that I would point out, in fact, let's go ahead.
And, and before we do that, I just want to know where the player is
roughly.
So, here's the player, like let's leave the player where they are and
presumably.
The players should be kind of like, very close to 0 0.
Although, if you look here,
What what's going on with this?
Like this is a little suspicious.
Wouldn't you say it?
Like, what's going on here?
Why is this the same region origin?
Oh, I know why.
Because we're running multiple SIM regions at the moment and we should
probably stop that.
because while we're devoting this and and really these aren't supposed
to be there at the moment, they were they were just for testing so we
really don't want
That stuff going on.
Right.
Okay so now we're in a little bit better shape.
We've got like kind of our origin information here now why the Sim
Region's origin is
Is where it is.
Is a good question to.
I don't really know where 00 is, I guess.
00 is the start of this tile.
We should probably verify that at some point.
Maybe when we kind of go through and start doing the 3D clean up.
But anyway, you can kind of see this is now stable, which makes more
sense.
And you can see that the offset of the same region,
From its yeah, from its position, is in keeping with that, right?
So that seems reasonable
Is it in keeping with that though?
Because how big are the chunks?
Is one question.
If assuming the chunks are big enough then that might make reasonable
sense.
But anyway, leaving the player there.
Let's go ahead and take a snapshot here.
What's going on?
So I think you know I guess I can pretty much say already what I think
is probably going on which is that I think passing the Sim Center as 0
is not valid, right?
Because if we take a look at the same region,
There's the origin and the origin is definitely not 00 in that sense
because there's an offset to it, right?
So that's in the world.
This P value is relative to that Sim Center origin.
However, I would assume.
So let's verify that those coordinates systems are actually what I
think they are because that's like, obviously, you know, the first
thing that I want to make sure that I know correctly.
So you can see me coming down through here.
And, you know, setting up this stuff where we actually
Figure out what our bounds are.
So here's our chunk Right Stuff?
What's our Min chunk pee?
Why are we simulating?
Oh, this is the creation region.
All right, let's try that one more time.
There we go.
That's like we need something that's actually got some area to it.
Okay.
And now we have some.
All right, so that's good.
So now if we take a look at what the same region origin is that's
where it believes this part of the same region.
Origin is when we're pulling these out, you can see in here where we
do try to figure out where
Things are relative to the chunk.
You can kind of see like okay where are things relative to the chunk?
There they are right?
That's the difference between this chunks location and wherever the
the same region itself is right there.
Some reason origin.
So that's the chunk Delta.
That's how far you go to get there.
We come through.
We take a look for every entity and we say like, okay, we're just
going to add that Delta, whatever that Delta is to the, to the
destination that the entities unpacked.
Here's the P relative to the chunk.
It was packed in now.
Here is it in the space of the same region?
So I think that is really all we should need.
So when we pass yeah.
I think that's really all we should need to pass.
So then when we go to our next test here where we're going to be
testing any overlaps rectangle in theory the Sim Center should be just
just the zero, right?
But now, when I'm looking at this, it looks like, oh, okay.
Since this rectangle, this actually again might be part of the
problem.
It may be that
maybe that I miss him interpreting.
What these are doing because this is basically saying hey does an
entity at this location with this volume overlap.
This rectangle and I'm sort of passing the opposite of that, right?
Which is not what we wanted to do there.
In fact, so yeah, so that's a little bit busted to say the least, but
let's just take a look at what happens.
So, when we look at the grown version, obviously, we would expect this
to grow because we're taking the volume of the room, which is what we
passed there.
So, here's the volume of the room and you can see it's fairly large,
right?
It's 23 by 12 by 3.
Right.
Which seems about right for one room.
and then we're going to say like, okay, I'm assuming
We're going to see whether this thing's in the rectangle.
We're going to take whatever the offset of the volume is and add it to
P.
Yes.
So you can see right away.
Why?
This is basically wrong.
It's doing the offset in the wrong direction.
If that makes sense, because what we're doing yet because we basically
passed these in the opposite order, we were trying to reuse a routine,
that's really made for something else and that's not what we actually
want to do.
So when we call is in rectangle, here you can see, we're going to do
this test and this test is sort of backwards, right?
So we want to do is we want to start calling that correctly and that's
probably most, if not all of our problem there.
So instead of calling an idea overlapped rectangle, that's really not
what we want to do.
What we want to do is just call is in rectangle.
Want to call is in a rectangle and we just want to see.
Okay, here is the test and it, he's Collision volume, right?
And we need to offset that Collision volume to be at the entities
location so this is the offset.
We need to do.
Right?
We need to offset it so we put the volume for the room in the right
place, and then we just need to see whether that is relative to the
entities placement, right?
So we need to say if this offset in volume is this entities position,
the the player inside the correctly placed World space Collision
volume of the room right?
And that is the actual test we want to perform
And so, in order to do that, we need to perform the offset.
And let me just double-check that here.
And, and so, let's see how we can do that.
So we want to test the isn't rectangle, so we need to pass the
rectangle, right?
And here's the rectangle or the volume.
I should say that we've got.
It's actually a, you know, it's a 3D Volume, and we want to test this
volume.
We want to offset that volume.
So we want to pretend that the volume is out in space somewhere, which
means that we're going to want to subtract a way that entities
position from The Entity position.
We're testing.
So we want to Center The Entity position.
We're testing around the origin of the entity that we're looking to.
To enclose, right?
And off we go.
What do I actually need to pass with that rectangle 3 V 3.
So this is a V3 and this total volume is a What entity Collision
volume.
So right, we need both of these.
We need the test entity p, and we need the volume pee.
Right.
I assume that that is actually offset not pee.
Let's just take a look because I don't remember.
Austin Peay, it was both.
and so just to make that a little clearer, let's
create a thing called volume pee.
Which is this.
So that's where the volume is right, in World space.
And so, then we can take the entities position and subtract it away.
And so,
The dimension here is not actually a rectangle, right?
Which is kind of begs.
The question, why aren't we using rectangles for our Collision
volumes?
Like why are they dim offset?
So that's kind of dumb.
To say the least.
I suppose what we could do is just say like, oh, okay,
Wrecked Center Dim, and just pass.
These two, but I feel like we're going to want to make that a little
bit more systemic.
So we don't have to constantly do that, right?
So we could just construct the rectangle where it actually is in World
space and then test the entity Point against it.
Let me just take a look.
I need to I don't want a break point there anymore, but I do want to
ask this one here.
And so now, hey look.
Now we actually get a positive result on that.
So we now we actually do know that we're in a particular room.
Now, we have an actually probably done everything.
We need to do to make that work better.
But at least now it's going to work.
Probably roughly like it used to work before, right.
So now you can kind of see also the problems that we'll have with
this.
We're like I said we're going to have to kind of clean this up a
little bit.
What we're not doing at the moment is a system that really makes much
sense because we're treating it exactly the way we used to treat it in
terms of how see here.
So you can kind of see when it hops between these since all of our
room based movement before was based on looking where we were in the
apron and moving it, you end up in this
Kind of nasty situation where you have to kind of have that movement
work correctly in order to like, it's all based on those Delta's,
right?
So when you're switching between rooms and stuff like that, it ends up
being a little bit confusing in that respect.
and you can easily get in places where also you would
you can get in places where it would be ambiguous as what's going to
happen because you need to look at the room next, to you, to figure
out exactly where you should be and all these other sorts of things.
So, we're going to want to redo this camera code.
But for now, let's Also, let's just take a second to do a couple more
things.
So, if you take a look at the room, Delta stuff, right, where it
records?
This piece of information
at the very least, we would all we
Start recording this as being something actual, right?
So what we'd want to do here is say like okay the room, Delta we
actually know what it is now.
It's whatever that came back to you know to be right.
And if you take a look in here where we start to figure out what we're
looking at, here we go.
Oh you know where is the entity placement relative to some stuff uh
blah blah.
This was all assuming a bunch of a bunch of information about where
the player would be relative to the rooms and how those were baked in
and we don't actually know that those are correct anymore.
So entity P needs to be.
To the center of this rectangle now, right?
If that makes sense.
So essentially what we have is
another thing which is like room R LP or something like that.
Where we want to also, write down.
What this entity p is relative to the volume.
The volume is location as well.
Oh, and you know what?
And I also forgot one other thing here.
In addition to the offset P, we need the test entities, placement as
well.
Right.
So that computation was wrong as well.
Okay, so let's just go ahead and say like volume P equals that that's
where the volume is.
We create the rectangle intestine it, if it worked then we do room.
Relative P equals that entity pee.
- the volume be, right?
So off we go and that's all good.
So now when we want to do this testing where we're looking at, sort of
the room apron, Delta camera nonsense here.
Right now we can sort of at least restore this a little bit and say
okay let's go ahead and change entity P for these purposes to be using
this room relative pee.
All right, so we want to take nadp here, you can see, we're using it
in a bunch of places to just feel like room relative pee.
It Go.
And then you get these entity P stuff.
Here is all operating of that.
It doesn't look at the entity anymore.
So, I think we should be good to go there.
Okay.
So again, not probably how we owe.
That's interesting.
Why has Ark?
I'm Road.
Was not expecting that our camera now thinks it's like needed to move
upwards as you notice that.
Just from having done that room relative p b.
Right.
I should probably look to see what the room relative P actually is.
At that point I suppose I wasn't thinking about the Z quite correctly,
at that point because the room relative would think that you are
potentially in a different location out.
Remember how?
We aligned those?
And it's probably, I don't know, but we probably don't want to use the
offset in volume P for the room necessarily for the room relative p in
terms of the Z offset.
So in some sense, that's probably because we need to do this.
If that makes sense to both have them based around the floor, which is
how we were doing it before, which is a little weird.
So that looks like it's still having trouble because it's it's
basically snapping back.
And I'm not sure if that's just because of how we're doing.
This is this code again is like kind of it's really kind of baked in
and it's all relative which is not particularly useful to me.
For how we want to do this at the moment.
Because it means when you move from one room to the other, you kind of
end up in a
A bit of a mess.
So, for just, for a moment, I want to take a look here and see how we
were doing.
So at the moment, what I'm going to do here for a second is I'm going
to turn off any of the relative displacement stuff, and I'm just going
to say, Hey, whenever we find what, rumor in, we're going to make the
camera point at the center of that room.
That makes sense.
So I'm going to call room campy.
I'm going to call that be whatever.
The location of the room entity is right.
And so, then, rather than doing the applied, Delta B.
I'm just going to say, hey,
Actually, I guess I can leave that in there.
I'm just going to say all right.
let's make the camera position be a mapping and into chunks face of
of wherever that room is.
Right?
So the room, we know this is a relative position.
So this room can pee is basically an offset and so I'm just going to
say I want you to map into chunks space wherever the Sim regions
origin is
And then, wherever that room camera is.
Right.
Oops.
And so, now whatever room were looking at whatever room, the player is
in, we should snap to, right?
And you can see that.
Now that we've got our detection working properly.
That's actually what's going on, right?
As soon as the player crosses that volume boundary, we immediately
move the camera and we don't animate the camera at all.
We just snap it, right?
Directly there.
And you can see that that happens.
That's happening pretty much correctly, right?
So that's all fine.
And so then the question is, how would we want to interpolate between
these two?
So when we've got one and the other and they're not the same, how do
we want to run that interpolation?
And that's kind of, again based more upon that, that sort of notion of
the apron the apron bit there.
But so let's get rid of this stuff.
The applied Delta stuff
And let's just take a look at it how we want to focus on this.
So here's our room, relative P placement and we're just going to have
that the how it was and what we can see here is when we're taking a
look at that room relative P, we're just going to use the apron of the
room.
How close we are to that as how much interpolation we're going to do,
right?
And I think that's all we need to do at the moment.
And I want to take a look at what that is.
Okay, so now that's much more sane.
We're getting our interpolation just based on the apron again and that
should be pretty stable.
Because again, now we're generating this just from a static.
Look, where are we in the room?
If we're close to the apron, let's bounce out, right?
And off we go.
Now we have another sort of situation here that we could imagine which
is, you know,
What if we created rooms that were different sizes?
Because now that we support this notion of room boundary, we should be
able to have rooms of different sizes.
So that when you exit one room and go into another room, the camera
will properly go to like how that room should be centered, right?
And it looks like I've got about 15 minutes if that makes sense to
sort of go ahead and show what's going on here.
So let's go ahead and just move.
Move.
Okay, so let's say I go back to where we actually create the world,
which is in here.
And I got my ad standard room situation, right?
And the thing with that standard room is when we are creating the the
rooms, maybe we want to be able to specify what the size of the room
is.
Right.
Like
Pretty pretty straightforward idea.
So the question is, can we maybe make rooms that are some size other
than than this?
And so if we take a look here and we say, like, what the radius of the
room is, we could, we could pass something in here that would have
that.
Now, the problem is we sort of are cheating, right?
We're returning back these room positions and stuff like this, that we
need to have for our when we, when we were using that.
That information outside.
And so when I go to look at,
Where this is used, you can see that it gets back, the standard room
thing and then it grabs out of the standard room, some information
that it needs to figure out where it wants to put things like the
snake and the monstar and whatever, right?
And that's how it like populates the room.
And the problem is that if we pass, you know, other sizes here that
we're going to run out of space in these arrays, but in theory, that's
okay, you know, we don't have to do this this way.
Right?
What we could do instead, if we wanted to is, we could make it so that
it's the arrays are big enough to hold bigger rooms and then they just
kind of slide around.
I also don't know why we chose to use the offset X.
I guess it's because we wanted to pass the center of a room which is
it's fine.
I suppose.
But so what we might want to do is just make these like bigger, right?
So you know maybe we want to make these just bigger to be able to hold
a bunch of
Stuff.
And then they just won't hold that stuff.
If we don't have any stuff in there for them,
You hold and then what we can do is say like alright.
Let's suppose we pass in a radius X and a radius Y for the room and
you know, again, this is just really messy code.
There's nothing.
This is not probably how we're going to do any of this stuff when we
do the world, Jen code path where we're actually trying to make a game
world.
But you know, for now it's the simplest thing that would give us the
ability to change the size of the room and so before you know it we've
got a what was it?
An 8 by 4?
I'm sorry.
A radius 84.
So it was a 17 by 9, right?
And so now, when we call this in theory, oh wait, one more thing, we
have to do.
When we place this information here, we have to make sure that we are
using these correctly, right?
So we've got a radius x.
The radius.
Why?
We know that this also has to be oops.
We know that these also have to be adjusted by that.
So there's basically like a array X or Ray.
Why.
And they look like this
and so, you know, if we get this
If you get this stuff right.
Then in theory, we should be able to pack into the array stuff.
Regardless of what the size of the room is going to be, right?
And I think that should be roughly correct.
Although actually the fact that that didn't work means that we've got
some other problem here, but I think this is right, radius Y is 4.
So be negative for 24 offset X radius of 8.
It would be negative 8 to 8, which again, is what we want.
Those offsets should work properly.
These are all just based on the offset.
and,
I don't see anything else that would be problematic.
So, in theory, I would think that that would work.
I don't know if it does.
Looks like we're creating too many entities, all of a sudden, did I
mess up my for Loop?
I may well have messed up my for loop I suppose.
Or maybe I was using the standard rooms size as something that we
actually.
Yep, that's what I was doing.
So that's not really allowed.
Obviously I need to have a idea here of how big the room is.
Right.
But that's fine.
So that's not really a big deal.
You can see how this stuff was going here.
So really all we need to do is say we need to know how big the room
actually is this left hole, right?
Whole stuff is not particularly good.
In fact, can we get rid of that now that we're not doing that stuff
anymore for up down?
Because again, we don't, this is just really, really hacky code that
we don't really want to be doing here.
So I would say,
Let's get rid of it now while we can so we don't have to keep trying
to make it happen here.
Target ref.
Yeah, because we turned off the auto boost, right?
And
I'm just going to go ahead and get rid of that.
Okay.
So then we don't have to worry about this part for now.
And then hopefully we'll be okay.
So then what I need to do is I need to have an idea of how big this
room is.
So room, radius X, and
Oops, room, radius Y.
And again, I'll just use 8 and 4 here.
Like so, and I will say that in general that just means that, you
know, for the room Dimension here we can compute the room with is just
whatever the radius is 2 times.
The radius plus 1 and the room height is going to be 2 times the
radius plus one because again you've got that many squares to the
left.
That means Square for the right and the middle Square.
So that's 2 times this plus one and the same
The height.
And so then if we come through here we've got room with sorry height.
So and I think that's it.
These tile values since we're in signed integer here at
How do we be consistent?
And let's take a look.
Well, alright, maybe not.
Looks like we're using all unsigned.
There we go.
So yeah.
So now in theory we're recreating the same the rooms the way that we
were creating them, right?
And you can see how that's going here.
And so what I would like to do potentially is now just try to align
these rooms like a little bit more cleanly and so that I can change
this radius to be different something.
Different
Right?
And so if you look at what has to happen here, where we are placing,
the room is really the important part.
So when we call this screen X tiles for with screen X, Y tiles for
height.
That's not really going to cut it anymore.
So what I need is like I need a location.
That I can use as sort of a way of saying, where the room is and so
yeah.
So this tiles per with and tiles per
With tiles for height.
Thing, here is not going to work anymore that's got to be room with
and room height, right?
So this is going to be room with
Oops room, Heights.
Both these places.
so,
And let's take a look here.
Okay, so I think that's all we would really need.
And we also don't need to initialize the camera position.
I don't think it would just well, I mean, I would probably have to
initial it to as it something, but the camera following stuff should
work, so I feel like probably
Well no, we're going to have to initialize it to elect where the
player is or something at the very least.
So, I guess we kind of have to do a little bit of that because it'll
always snap to the correct room once you find the player.
So, yeah, there's that anyway.
So let's, let's take a look here at what we're doing.
So when we do add standard room, now what we want to do is have a
position.
You can see that we've got an AB style X.
So we want to do like room Center tie.
Lex
And room Center tile.
Why and
You just want to move that around as we go, right?
And so, let's go ahead and
start that initialize to something.
00 is fine.
And then as we go, we'll just every time we're done with a room will
move out of that room by however much.
We needed it to move by, right?
And so here, when we do screen X screen, why you can see, the like we
were previously tracking, this piece of information, we're going to
get rid of that.
And just not use that anymore, right?
Okay, so
So, when we are updating those here, and then, of course, when we also
use them here.
So we've got last screen acts last green lie.
What we really want to do here is now just say, like, okay, when we do
camera tiles, let's get rid of all this nonsense here and just to room
Center Thai, Lex
And room Center tile.
Why
And I guess we put we're saying we are putting the camera there I
guess is where we're putting it which I guess seems fine.
So we're putting it on the last room we created.
I guess that's what we were doing before anyway.
So let's go ahead and say okay we've got the three necks and the
screen wine and we need to update those now as if their room Center
tile X and room Center tile.
Why?
And
Those two together are now going to be updated by like the room with
and the room.
Height, right?
That's how far they're going to move by.
So let's take a look at what that does now that doesn't look quite
right.
But what you gonna do, guess we're putting the player it sort of the
wrong location.
We'll, we'll deal with that later, but let's just see if this is
creating rooms that have properly, but it does.
So that's good, right?
And we can take a look at the
The debug View and see that they properly.
But right.
So now let's just see if what we see if we can change the size of the
rooms a little bit, right?
And so, what if I was to say that I wanted the room height to be a
little bit different.
So, for example, if I said, the room radius could be for, but it could
also be changed to, you know, to up to six or something.
So, add two tiles on either side, and
Happens there.
It's like we've run out of entities again.
When we're doing our creation, that really is just because the
creation phase, we only create one sim region as a cheat.
When we fix the world creation code, we won't have when we do it a
little bit differently, we won't have that problem anymore.
So here are our rooms that are obviously you know, much bigger, right?
Then the previous room size.
And so now the question is just like, okay, can we change that
dynamically, right?
Can I say like I want the rooms to be sized in a more variable.
So I'm just going to go ahead and pick a random count here, right?
and actually, I guess, I don't know what our
Gum and I don't know what our series is here.
So it's just that
So now in theory, we would have different sized rooms in different
places, right?
And so, you can see like coming through here, we would have different
sized rooms, and you can kind of see that they are different sized
rooms.
So let's go ahead and
And turn the let's see here.
There we go.
So you can kind of see that like these rooms are now different sizes
and in theory we could make that be a little bit more dramatic here by
making both of them have different sizes, right?
Both parameters.
Oh, that's no good.
Initially, we got to make sure we initialize our camera properly.
That's not going to be good.
Yeah.
There we go.
So yeah.
So now we have an additional problem, which I hadn't thought of and
should have thought of.
And that is just that we have to know the size of both rooms to know
how far we should go to connect the next room, right?
So we essentially need a thing that's like room, you know, last room
with and last room height like so.
And we need to do a thing where we're basically going to take
Well, I guess really, we would need to know what the next room height
was.
I guess we don't need to know.
That's not, that's not true.
So we don't need to know the last room with the last room.
Height per se.
What we need to know is what direction we went in, right?
Because when we do this particular operation here, we can advance by
however much
The room with their height was right.
But then at that point we need we could we could move forward by
however much we need to for this room and then the next time we have
to move forward by however much we should for the other room.
But the problem with doing that is we just don't know how much the
next room's width.
And height is going to be so we can't do it at this point.
So we need to know what the door direction is kind of like looping
around if that makes sense.
So really what we mostly need to know here is just what's the door
Direction.
That makes sense and that needs to persist across.
And so when we do here, we're going to want to add the room radius to
move us that far to get us basically to where we need to be.
And then the next time around, in fact we can and will do the plus one
in here for that one interceding tile, and then we'll do a drawer
Direction 0 or 1 here.
And we can make up the difference.
So now we know where our room radius is, we can just add that extra
bit that we needed to to get us to the right place.
So we add those two together to get the correct door placement in
theory.
And so now in theory all of our rooms will be lined up properly and
they can be arbitrary sizes.
And so the only thing that I wanted to do that, we're not doing now
because now you can see like these rooms are, just whatever size,
these rooms are and that's all fine.
But what you can see here is the other thing we're going to have to do
is that if we were actually, if we're actually in viewing it at game
distance, we now have to do something where we
Make sure that the camera zooms out.
Far enough for whatever room we're trying to be in in order to make
sure that we see the whole room, right?
And that's something we can do next time.
All right.
Let's go to the Q&A.
Cisco.
Hey Casey, is anyone planning on doing a more boiled down version of
handmade hero to take apart the game and give a breakdown of the
aspect of each system in the project?
I don't know that anyone is planning on that at the moment.
Yeah.
I think that's a good idea.
It's something that I was kind of going to consider doing myself but I
don't know by the time I'm done with handmade hero, I might not want
to go back and do that, right?
But I think it's a good idea.
I just don't think anyone's planning on doing it at the moment.
Mid low or make the camera pan with in the room?
Yeah, we could have painting within rooms as well, either.
One of those would be fine.
Let's see, longtime archive viewer.
But first time livestreamer, I have to pre-screen questions, but I
can't ever make the priests room time.
Do you have a strong opinion about why in Star p is superior style
than it star, space p?
Or are you impartial to whatever the dev?
Prefers was the first part?
Second part is does compiler optimizations - oh to guarantee that the
same output is generated for time, independent code.
Okay.
That is
Out of order processing ever introduced.
Some nasty logic control flow bugs that OD wouldn't.
Okay, I'll try to tackle that.
Let me answer the first one first.
So a strong opinion about why in Star p is better than insert piece.
Okay?
So, what what they're asking about is,
This like, you know, if I was to declare a variable and put the star
next to the P or before the p and the question was just do I have a
strong?
You know, I write it this way.
Am I writing it that way?
Because I feel like there's a really good reason to do so or am I just
arbitrarily running at that way?
And I wouldn't care if someone wrote this way.
It's the latter.
I don't care between these two so it's really just force of habit, you
know?
Code that looks like this.
Oh, that looks like this.
It doesn't.
I can't think of any real reasons why you would prefer one or the
other like overwhelmingly.
So I don't know, I guess what I would say is that in space star P
versus in Star p.
You know, I could see why someone might prefer the bottom one, which
is not the style that I use, but I can see why someone might prefer
the bottom one because they want to see the type information like kind
of all together.
Yeah, I guess I don't have a strong opinion.
I'm sorry I couldn't.
If you're looking for guidance on which one to do, I would say it's
probably really just mostly up to your personal preference.
You know you could imagine situations where you're declaring more than
one variable and then they do look quite a bit different.
Because in this one, it kind of looks like Q does not have a star and
then this one, it looks like Q does have a star, you know, to your eye
Maybe.
But I just yeah I'm sorry.
I don't have a strong opinion on that so I would certainly not tell
someone to do it one way or the other way for any particular reason.
But you know other people may have, you know, stronger opinions about
then I do the second question.
Does the compiler optimization - oh to guarantee that the same output
is generated for time?
Independent code.
That is that the out of order processing ever introduced some nasty
logic control flow bugs that OD wouldn't
The answer there is that it's kind of confusing a little bit because
it depends on what you mean by.
Does it produce the same thing obviously 02 + OD produced very
different code, right?
Like that's certain and if you look at what happens in the code you
can see that it's very different.
And what I would say is that if the code is properly barrier, dad,
meaning that if you have read and write barriers, and sorted in the
code for like multi-threading purposes, for example, then to the best
of my knowledge.
I can't think of any reason that 02 code, unless the compiler has a
bug, which compiler sometimes do.
And sometimes do with O2.
If the compiler, has a bug, all bets are off, but the compiler doesn't
have a bug then know in general.
Roll, the code should always work correctly, in both cases if the code
does not have barriers in it properly, right?
So, if the code itself essentially has a bug which is that it doesn't
have barriers in it, then in a
Threading context where two threads are operating on the code.
At the same time, I'm sorry on the date at the same time, then the
debug compiled version of the code will naturally have the rights
occurring in the order that they should be occurring in because the
compiler will just output them exactly the way that they go, right?
And on the other hand, if you do 02.
So you
Optimization sign.
It could reorder all that stuff around to do it in a whatever the most
efficient way to do it is and on a machine like x64 which has very
strong memory ordering guarantees on the CPU side that will very
likely mean that you could easily see buggy Behavior with 02 on that,
you won't see with Odeon in a multi-threaded context.
Again, this is not because the compiler necessarily has a bug.
It may
But that's very rare.
It is probably because you have a bug in the code that just isn't
exposed until 0202 is run.
Which does the reordering.
And then the memory visibility order changes on pieces of information
you were writing to which causes the bug, right?
So I feel like that's just worth keeping in mind in general.
I can't think of any circumstance where properly written code, where
the behavior will change between OD + O2, in a way, that introduces a
bug, that doesn't mean that there isn't one again, barring compiler
errors.
It just means I can't think of one, but I can think of plenty of
cases, where bugs, and code can be hidden by o.d.
and only exposed with O2, that is very easy to have happen.
That's what I'd say.
Let's see.
You said, you didn't want to use pretty function because that wouldn't
work because duplicate grids with the only place where pretty function
would have been used in time function, which should never be used more
than once on any function anyway.
So, not using debug name and time function would solve the problem.
All the other calls, the time block was still work with debug name and
thus use the counter to be unique.
So I think the extra field for the name is really not necessary.
Well it isn't it isn't.
Before Time function would have worked even if you put it multiple
times in a function, right?
And you would even have been able to differentiate those two in the
printout if you'd wanted to because we could have used the line
number, right?
So I don't know.
It's a bummer.
I would rather just be able to use function like we were using it.
I think that's the right solution but I don't know any way to really
like handle it, right?
Zen Mystic, you talked about, Jesus seek laying, at the start.
To be clear.
You will be dropping Visual Studio at
No, I'm not suggesting that I need to drop Visual Studio.
I was just pointing out that there are reasons why you might want to
not bother compiling with Visual Studio, you might just want to
compile the clang everywhere.
Because once you can use the same compiler on all platforms, it takes
a little bit of a headache out of the way for you if you want it,
right.
I'm not trying to say that you have to do that or that you'd like
there's the did that.
It's like an over W riding like a priority.
Or anything, it just it there's a good argument for that, right?
I let's see.
What is your opinion on minkowski Portal refinement?
For Collision detection and response.
I feel it's much nicer as it gives you much of the Collision
information.
Like the normal, the depth cetera without having to play an entire
separate algorithm like judicata does, I have not looked at that?
So, I don't know.
I would like to, and obviously, I like minkowski based stuff.
I mean, gjk is Mankowski based as well, so it might be very good.
I don't know, I haven't really had much occasion to do a lot of 3D.
lately because I've been mostly working on 2D stuff and so I just
don't have
any practical experience with most of the newer algorithms, and stuff
that people might be using,
Have you tried - 0 X4 optimizations?
I believe it gives even faster code it's a first-hand it's a fast and
for multiplication Flags.
No I haven't.
I don't know.
Nope, stop help.
Okay.
so,
So we definitely can do it here in 2013.
Obviously, that's a newer flag.
Like that was introduced, I don't know.
To what extent that would change things for us.
We don't have any good timing test right now, so we wouldn't be able
to measure the optimizations, but we can certainly see if the code
still runs.
Okay with it, just to see how that goes and you know certainly seems
okay but we are always sink locked to 16 milliseconds so we won't we
don't have any good speed, you know, perf tests.
I suppose we
We should probably have some at some point to be able to get better
handle on things like that.
So that's actually pretty reasonable.
Still with software rendering.
But yeah, like I said, I don't really know, I don't really know that
we have anything to run at the moment.
That would give us a good test to see whether it was better than 02.
But hey, it works.
So that's good.
So we can, when we get down to it, try some of that stuff.
Hey, Carrie instant.
I would like to cast my vote that we should do this slide someday.
Okay.
Well, we'll try to do the slides someday.
How long you think it'll take for ji to take over the C++ face in the
game industry?
It's not even out yet and I can already say that language is the best
thing ever.
Designed okay well there you go.
I guess what I would say is I really just don't know you know there's
so many things that
Affect language adoption that have nothing to do with whether the
language is good or not.
You know, like it's not like game developer sit down every year and
have like a big meeting and go like oh okay you know is C plus plus
the best thing to develop in guess.
OK.
Let's develop in it.
Like that's not how that works.
You've got like a very big built-in set of programmers who know how to
program this thing.
You've got platforms, that expect it, you've got code bases that are
like building up over time.
Time and stuff.
So I feel like the important thing to remember is that like you can't
necessarily look at a language and go.
This language is good or bad or better or worse than what I have.
So therefore it will like be adopted.
So I feel like it's impossible to predict something that no matter how
good of a job, John does nji that that's not necessarily going to
I'm sure it will affect how the adoption is right?
It like if it was really bad than the adoption, wouldn't happen.
But if it's really good that doesn't necessarily mean that adoption
can happen because there's other barriers to it, right?
And so I feel like it's embed something that's impossible to predict,
you know, because it's a social.
Issue.
Like, it's about how people are going to behave.
It's not a asking, you know, is it going to be better for our purposes
in C++ which is an easier thing to evaluate perhaps more objectively
Andrei Castor yet we are not using sdl on the Stream.
Don't have many thoughts in general and sdl because I haven't used it,
but obviously, lots of games do use it.
So my assumption would be that while there might be situations where I
would, you know, be like, oh, I wish it did this this way, or I wish
it did this this other way or something that it obviously works,
right?
Like lots of games ship on it.
So it's like anything else like Unreal Engine or Unity or these sorts
of things.
It's like, you know, while I might not
Not have design them in a in the way that they're designed or I might
want to do something differently, they have a good track record,
right?
So you know, if you decide to use sdl or something like that you can
at least be assured that you're not in any worse boat than a lot of
people out there who have ship successful games, and that's worth a
lot, right?
You know, using unproven technology certain, you know, while it may
Well, there may be reasons to do so because it has things that you
need or want or you like something about it or you believe it confers,
some sort of benefits upon you, right?
I guess, you know, I
There is something to be said for just going with a majority approach
like if the majority of things ship on sdl or the majority of things
ship on X, then at least, you know, you're not in any worst position,
right?
It's a, it's a way of bounding your worst case.
So I guess what I would say is, you know, if you're not very confident
about how you might want to write your platform layer or you have, if
you don't have a really good reason why you're going to do something
else.
Then it makes a lot of sense to go with something like sdl because you
don't want to put yourself in a position where your worst case is
unbounded like that, you know?
So
All right, so there's no cues on the other one, on the other chat.
Did I miss one on here?
Let's see.
Oh, I did this one.
So Zen Mystic was following up and saying, with the question about
whether I would be switching to clang.
So it's in Mystic.
Are you asking about that?
You mean like on stream or do you mean like at Molly rocket like
you're talking about for like nine for the for the 1935 4935 game or
are you talking about on handmade hero?
Because
I guess I'd say it's for 1935 it's very unlikely because I don't
usually like to I think I talked about this last week.
I don't like to switch Technologies in the middle of a development if
you can avoid it.
So I would pretty much always stick with how a plat whatever platform
setup I'm using on each platform.
I just keep it that way until the next time and then, you know, I'd
evaluate it then.
But for handmade hero, it's a little bit different because since its
educational things that I wouldn't necessarily do in a main line
product, I might do, if that makes sense.
So, I don't know.
Do you have any thoughts on when to use multiple threads?
The answer, any more in-depth than when single-threaded isn't fast
enough?
No, I don't think the answer is any more in-depth than that, honestly.
Single threaded code is always the best code in terms of reliability
and maintainability because there's simply less to think about.
And so, I think the thing to keep in mind, there is just that.
While multi-threaded code may be interesting,
Right.
As an exercise.
You never really want to write it if you don't have to, because you're
really only thing you can do is, introduce bugs, right?
Multiple threading multi-threaded code is never going to be, you know,
more sane than single threaded code because it it adds complexity in
all cases, right?
And so, usually the answer is exactly, as you put it, if you don't
feel like, there's a problem with the single threaded code that,
You have there isn't a reason to switch it to multiple threads.
However, as with all things in programming, that statement alone is
still a little complicated.
And the reason that it's a little bit complicated is because single
thread code
When you're writing it the first time depending on how much code
you're talking about, it, converting it to multi-threaded code,
depending on the code, can be very difficult sometimes.
And so if you have a strong suspicion up front, that you will need
this thing to be performance in a way that requires multiple threads,
sometimes you may have to start with multiple threads in mind, at
least.
And so, even though you might still write it single-threaded first,
because you probably always want to make sure it runs single fitted
for us just for testing purposes.
You may have your eye on
The fact that you need to multi-thread it and you may be picking the
algorithm differently.
Does that make sense?
So you still also kind of need to have a heads up there sometimes
because you don't
Write a big chunk of code with a bunch of assumptions baked into it
that require single threading and then have a huge headache when you
want it need to multiply when you need to upgrade to multiple threads.
So if you know going into it that you're going to be multiple threads,
that's maybe an argument for not necessarily running it multi-threaded
but picking the algorithms and picking the structure of the code to
make that more to facilitate that a little easier.
Do you still have to do this like you used to?
Could you show it?
I'm still on day 110 with the videos?
Sure.
Here's The To Do List.
It basically is the same as the original to-do list, just with some
things removed that we've done and I guess we added some things too,
but
All right, so I'm going to we're out of time here.
So I'm going to go ahead and and wrap it up, that should be it.
So yeah, I will go ahead and close it down.
Let's see here.
Okay, thank you very much.
Everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the series, you can
always prove to the source code on handmade here a.org and it comes
with the source code, which you can use to sort of do experiments or
practice coding at home, along with the series.
We also have a forum site, you can go to.
If you want to ask questions a patreon page, you can use to support
the video series.
I'll schedule a bot.
You can go to, if you would like
To to me, if you would like to know when the series going to be live
and then there's a past episode guide which you can use if you want to
catch up on older episodes and find out what you missed, we will be if
I refresh it and say it.
Yep we'll be back again tomorrow.
Same time, same place eleven, a m-- Pacific Standard Time to do a
little bit more coding.
Maybe we'll start 32 tomorrow or maybe we'll play with the camera and
multiple room size a little bit more but either way we will be back
here at hopes you
All there again until then have fun for everyone and I will see you
folks on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.