And start recording.
Okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we Cody complete game live on the air from scratch.
Using nothing new libraries.
No engine so that we can see how absolutely everything in a game
pipeline works right down to the pixels and all the way up to the high
level game code.
And right now we are working on what is essentially going to be our
primary character movement code.
And so I really wanted to be able to kind of start using
Saying, you know, the basic sorts of math that we use in game
development, just basic Vector, math, that sort of stuff.
I want to start using that but we had not actually covered that yet on
the stream.
And so last night, I kind of gave a little bit of a math overview, to
sort of say what types of math are involved in game development.
And tonight we're going to do our first kind of like experimentation
with some of that math.
I'm basically to show how to use 2D Vector math.
Just trying to, you know, give you the background of basically how it
works and show you kind of how we use it to allow a character to move
around that sort of
And that will kick off our work on getting some good character
movement into the game.
Now, before I go any further detail on that, if you would like to
follow along at home and you preorder the source code on handmade hero
dot-org.
You should have gotten a link in your email where you can download the
source code.
And if you take a look in that zip, it basically has a they're coated
by day.
You could basically grab the zip for day 41 and unzip it and you will
be exactly where I am today.
Now, of course, you can also grab the
It formed a 40 since we didn't do any coding yesterday.
It was just a math over you day, but for, you know, for completeness
sake, I still upload a zip every night.
So there is a day, 41, zip.
It's the same as the day for it.
Is it Anyway?
So let's go ahead and get started here and take a look at this stuff.
I will go ahead and I'm using the pain.
I'm seeing if I can use the pen instead of a mouse since I was using
it for drawing and I feel like I might have to draw diagrams and
stuff.
So we'll see.
It may come to a screeching halt if I decide that it's too much of a
pain, but we're going to try it maybe.
At least for one episode.
We'll see if I can get used to it.
All right.
So basically if you remember correctly, this is where we left things,
where we had done a bunch of work on basic stuff.
We, you know, we tested scrolling, we allowed ourselves to make a tile
map.
That could be huge.
And so, you know, we did sparse, tilemap storage.
We did a bunch of stuff, but we got to the point where we need to
start thinking about moving our guy around.
And right now, our guy has the worst movement code ever.
It's the most basic most annoying movement code, and I'm not even
talking about
Animation.
I'm not even talking about the fact that he doesn't animate yet
because that's something that we want to fix as well.
But I'm even just talking about at a much lower level than that, which
is just the act of moving him around, doesn't feel very good.
And there's a number of reasons why that is true.
Some of which are going to be obvious to people who've worked on games
before.
But if you haven't worked on days before, they may not be obvious to
you.
You may just kind of notice that it doesn't feel good.
And one of the big ones is the character doesn't have any momentum at.
All right now, right?
So, if you see, basically, all that's happening, is when I push down
on,
He's really, he just moves while I'm holding down the key at a
resolved rate.
And then as soon as I let go of a key, you know, he just stops, right?
Furthermore.
It's got some Oddities in it.
For example, if I'm going right, I go at a certain speed.
If I'm going down, I go at the same speed.
But if I go right and down at the same time, I actually go at the
combination of those two speeds.
So I basically go the full, the full speed to the right and the full
speed down at the same time.
Right?
And so that's also kind of another weirdness.
Because basically means that on the diagonals,
The character moves at sort of an accelerated rate, which is also kind
of weird.
So there's a number of things about that that are unsatisfying.
If I go up our kind of virtual door ladder, there and go up to the,
the sort of next layer of the tile map here.
Also, you will note, when I kind of go through a doorway or something
like that.
If I am going through them the long way, I'll speed my guy up here so
I can kind of go up somewhere that has a doorway going upward, which
is what I want show you.
I get sort of another really annoying thing that happens that we
Look out eventually.
And this is kind of a little further down the road, but just to
underscore our bad.
The player movement code is right now, I get stuck on just about
anything.
Like I can get stuck right there.
It's really hard for me to get through this doorway.
Right?
It's really annoying.
Any, any little misalignment causes me to stop entirely.
And so basically there's just a lot of things that are really lousy
about this player movement code, and all of those are things that we
want to improve.
So there's that and then of course, on top of that, what we want to do
is we want to make it
It more interesting for the player to move their character around
because moving their character around in a game.
Like this is something they're doing all the time.
They're always moving their character around on every single screen.
They're moving from left to right there, dodging, enemy shots, or
whatever.
They're doing.
They're moving.
The character around is a primary operation that they're going to do.
And one of the things that that ends up happening, if that's the case
is you want to provide a lot of good visual.
Sorry.
Visceral feedback, basically while they're moving around because
that's one of the things that will make your
I'm engaging like, I mean, at the, at the risk of stating the obvious,
one of the things that's crucial in making a video game is making good
audio visual feedback for everything.
And a lot of people will say stuff, like, you know, what's all about
the gameplay, or whatever, but those statements are kind of nebulous
because we all know that a video game is different from a board game
in that there is audio visual feedback.
That's what makes it a video game.
And so, a lot of what you're trying to do in terms of
In terms of making the game, fun and engaging.
Yes, there's a ton of stuff that's important in terms of game
mechanics and all of the stuff that exists, one level up from the the
pure audio visual feedback, but at that base level the audio visual
feedback is really what makes the game immediately engaging.
And it's what allows the players to be interested enough in playing
the game to get to those deeper things that you're putting in there,
in terms of your game, mechanics and whatever, it's what allows you
get to.
The next step of of design in terms of Interest.
Otherwise, you just have a game that feels off.
How to play that, maybe if someone's willing to suffer.
Through the awful feel they will discover the fact that you designed
it.
Well, right.
And so it's really crucial that we avoid that as well.
So what we want to do is make it really fun to move the guy around.
So we want to make him feel really nice and you can see he's a little
fellow that doesn't have any arms and legs.
And so one of the things that we'll want to do is kind of make him
have a nice kind of hop.
I want them to basically be able to hop around and have that hopping
feel really nice instead of right now.
It just feels really boring and uninteresting, right?
So that's our goal over the next, however, many days it takes as we
sort of
Learn about how to do.
Our Vector math is I'm going to basically be showing you how to do
basic Vector math through the lens of improving, this guy's motion, so
that he is able to move in a smooth, satisfying way for the player.
And so that his the visual feedback to the player receives while the
character is moving, is very engaging and satisfying, and makes you
want to do it.
It makes you want to just move them around like it just feels really
good.
And so, that's, that's basically what we're we're, we're we're going
with all this, okay.
So let's get started with some basic stuff.
Let's get started with that.
Moat first thing.
That was the very easiest thing to fix that momentum problem that I
was talking about before I was saying that he doesn't have any
momentum, you just stops on a dime and he starts at full speed, right?
So let's let's fix that momentum problem.
And while we're at it, let's take a look and see if we can fix the
fact that he moves faster on the diagonals, then when he's going up
down left and right alone, right?
And so, those are things that if we learn some basic,
Vector math, we can solve very easily.
So let's go ahead and do it.
So the first thing I want to talk about is just for the people who are
very, very beginner at this, at this sort of stuff.
I just want to kind of remind everything everyone.
What we're talking about when we talk about vectors.
So basically you've already seen in the code, right?
If I load up the handmade hero code base here, and I go in here and
look at my, my handmade dot CPP.
This is the code that we were using to move the player, right?
And as you can see,
In here, we basically we're saying all right.
We want to pick a new position for the player.
We want to basically take his old position which is what we're doing
here.
We're going to assign it to a temporary variable and then we're going
to add to its offset X and offset Y, which is basically how far he is
away from whatever sent the center of whatever tile.
He's on, we're going to go ahead and add, however, much time has
elapsed for this Frame, or a supposed to elapse over the course of
this Frame.
I should say.
We're going to take whatever his motion is in the X direction.
We multiply that and add it to the offset x 0.
We're gonna do the same thing for y.
Now, if you take a look at what happens here, you will notice that
this sort of thing, tends to be very common across a lot of the stuff
that we've already written.
You will notice that the X and Y tend to be handled together in a
number of ways.
These are they're both getting multiplied, my player speed here.
They're both get set to 0 here.
We do the same thing to all of them here as well.
And similarly, if we go into handmade tile, which still is holding
some of our
If we weren't sure exactly where to put, if we look at kind of what
happens in here to offset X and offset y, you will also see stuff
where a lot of times those get processed in the exact same way.
You can see them getting crossed.
Exact same way here.
You can see them getting in process in the exact same way here.
So a lot of times you just get this sort of pattern that you would see
if you didn't know anything about vectors, you know anything about the
math behind or anything, you would start to see this very clear
pattern in your code where you're constantly doing the same stuff.
Two pairs of variables, your exes, and your why, you know, the
horizontal and the vertical movement.
And that is really where this notion.
Of vectors in game development come from.
It's the reason that we start turning two vectors is because we do
start to have a lot of variables whose behavior is interrelated.
They are not really separate anymore.
Right?
They are always handled together and they form sort of a coherent
notion in and of themselves such that if we start to look at all the
operations that we perform on them.
We will find that we can boil those down to a set of basic operations,
that make it much easier and much faster to work with them.
And it just so happens.
That obviously, mathematicians beat us to this concept a long time
ago.
And I've already defined all of the sorts of stuff you might want to
do with vectors and already worked out kind of everything for us.
And so really, that is what this sort of vector stuff in terms of how,
why we care about it.
That's really what it boils down to is we have a bunch of operations
that we're going to constantly do with this notion of points and
directions and stuff that have both X and Y and potentially Z
components to them and we want to start thinking of those.
As coherent things that have operations on them.
It makes sense as a unit, right?
And so, you'll note, actually, this is a good point here.
One of the reasons I didn't want to fix this, this diagonal movement
problem member, I was saying the thing about the diagonal movement, I
wanted to wait is because that's a perfect example of when the actual
coupling between the objects between the X and the Y starts to be
important, right?
It's no longer something.
That's
Care that's handle in isolation.
So it starts to be something that's about the actual combat
combination of both the X and the Y at the same time.
And so, what we could do to start off to give sort of an example of
what's going to happen.
There is, you could think about what we actually want to have occur.
And we can sort of back out, maybe into what we, what we're going to
do based on sort of thinking about it a little bit, right?
So, if I were to draw again, not even talking about vectors yet,
right?
Not even saying the word.
Even if I were to draw what was going on, then in that diagonal case,
right?
We were basically saying, okay, the guys here and we know that he has
some amount of X motion that's going to happen over this Frame so over
the course of one frame, right?
And that's that's, that's this code right here, right?
Input, d.
For frame times player.
X the offset X, I'm adding.
So I'm adding this right here.
That's this quantity.
Right?
If I'm going to add that and then I'm also, it turns out that he has a
deep layer, why I'm also going to add that to his offset Y, which is
this of course, right?
So I'm also going to add something that's moving in the same direction
this way, right?
And so if I wanted him to move at a constant rate, no matter what
direction he was going in, I wanted to make sure he never exceeded
that, right?
Well, you can see the
Problem with what I'm doing here in terms of getting that result.
He's we're going to add both of these together.
So the combined motion, right?
If you think about where it's going to end up, is going to be here,
right?
And how long is that Vector?
You can kind of see if I rotate it up to here.
Right?
If I do like a rotation, it's longer than either of these two vectors
and it's longer because it's involving the contribution of both the X
and the Y at the same time, right?
Now it's not twice as long.
Okay, but it is longer.
Okay, and exactly how long it is is something that we'll talk about in
a second.
Okay.
And you may ask yourself also, why isn't it twice as long?
And the reason that of course it's not twice as long is because he is
not actually in as far as the viewer is concerned, right?
We here's one way to think about it.
The path that he took is in some sense twice.
As long, he walked this way for how for that for that length.
Right?
Because member these are both the same length and then he walked this
way for that length.
That's essentially what I had him do, right.
I had him walk that way and then
This way.
So I had him walk.
Actually, I guess, I should say he walked this way and then this way
he walked X first and then Y, and that would be twice the length,
right?
But the player doesn't see that motion, the player doesn't see him.
Walk in a stair-step, the player just sees his final location because
remember, we haven't drawn him in between here and here.
Instead.
We just added the two together.
So the players just going to see him at this final location and in the
players mind, they are going to reconstruct the motion of the guy to
have been this.
Diagonal line, right?
The player will never think about the fact that we actually moved him
along X.
And then Y in terms of what we did to the variables that contain his
location, they will.
Instead just see the fact that he moved from here to here and because
they are human, they will assume that motion happened along the
shortest path in between those two totally reasonable as assumption,
but that's where the Phantom distance distance comes from.
It would be twice as long if the player thought of it that way but
it's not, they think of it this way.
And this
Is a shorter distance because he's going straight between the two
points instead of taking that detour.
So hopefully that makes some sense there.
so,
We could ask ourselves.
Of course, if you remember your high school.
I want to say it's geometry.
I don't know if it's in trigonometry geometry.
I'm not sure when they teach this.
I don't really remember.
But if you wanted to know, precisely how fast this was, right?
I'm basically saying that I have some distance d, right?
That he traveled and he traveled D&D, right?
He traveled D this way and D that way.
And then we want to know this thing that the player observed, right?
I don't know what?
We'll call this.
Exactly will call this will call this m.
I don't know why we want to know how if we wanted to know how long am
was right.
We want to say.
What?
What actually is the speed that the player ended up moving at, right?
Who knows?
Because we knew we moved him, d-des Direction D, and D this direction.
So if the player was thinking about it in the stair, stair steps
fashion, he would think he moved to d, right?
He would move D, plus d.
That's How far the player appears to have moved.
But in this case they see this line.
So, how big is that line?
Right.
Well, this is that Pythagorean theorem that maybe you you would have
remembered from your from your grade school math.
You notice, there is a Pythagorean theorem.
It's a thing that basically says, if you have a triangle that looks
like this, right?
And you want, and it's a right triangle.
Let's say so it looks like that right in a right triangle.
I know that I can make sort of the Pythagorean theorem tells me that I
can make it a quality about the lengths of the sides.
Right?
And that is the a squared plus b squared equals c squared that
everyone hopefully can remember.
It's a very famous thing, right?
This is the Pythagorean theorem right here.
Well, that would give
Exactly the answer we want, right?
We have exactly that are only differences.
That are amd's actually happen to be the same.
So we actually have an even weaker problem to solve here.
So basically, if you think about it, we basically got D squared plus d
squared equals m squared right?
Is is a essentially what we would need to solve.
And so that's just to D squared equals m squared, right?
Or if we want to rearrange those terms.
We need to basically solve for r m because that's what we want and
it's squared here.
So if we want to know what it actually,
We m is we just have to square root this side, right?
We just have to square root that and say well, it's to D Squared but
square rooted, right?
And what you'll see is that since this is already squared in here.
Right?
What you will see is actually this, we can simplify it even further
and just pull the things out and say, well, to D Squared, we can pull
the D out of the square root by actually Square rooting it.
And just say that it's D route to, right?
We can't really simplify that any more because root 2 is not going to
be a whole number that's going to be, you know.
An actual long, long decimal.
But that, that right there is the answer.
And so, what you can see, is, if you have a movement where you're
moving by x and by Y, in by a certain amount, which is D, then the
actual movement, when the player starts walking by the diagonal, the
actual movement that they will appear to have is root 2 when they
start walking on the diagonal, right?
And so route to if we actually do that.
Jump over here for Emax fans, and do quick cow.
I don't know if it can do this.
I
The square root of two.
It can 1.4.
Right?
Is roughly where it's at.
So basically, they're moving at one point for roughly 1 .4 X.
The, the speed that they should be moving at when we're, when they're
going in that direction, right?
So there you go.
Very, very simple, you know, really really basic math, like anything.
Like I said, it's something that you would have learned in high
school, but it's, you know, that's just that's game development.
Even very, very basic math is important.
So that's how fast our guys going.
Now, what we would like to do is say that, for example, he always goes
D.
So if he goes this way, he goes D, if it goes that way, he goes D and
if he goes on the diagonal, he still goes D.
So we're going to basically say we wanted to kind of be on a circle
and we want to kind of make it so that you know, we truncate off, we
get rid of this extra that we were adding there.
We want to make that Vector actually be length d.
So, here's a question for you without doing any Vector stuff without
doing anything yet.
Let's ask the question.
What would we do?
And you guys should all be able to answer this yourselves if you want
to just pause the stream for a second if you want to go think about it
because you might take a little while.
But what would you do again?
Just using high school math.
Nothing fancy here.
Don't even need to use the term vector.
What would we do?
If we actually wanted to figure out how far to move the guy when he
was on the diagonal?
So we're actually just put with we're just going to straight up put an
if statement in our code and say, if the guys moving on a diagonal we
will reduce D.
So instead of moving him by D player, XD player, why we'll move him
by, like some portion of player ex-player.
White will just will straight up multiply this.
In the case of a diagonal.
What would be multiplying by to make it be only D law, right?
We want this to be D long.
Now, I'll give people second puzzle stream if they wish to, and then
I'll go ahead and talk about that.
All right.
All right, ready?
There we go.
Okay, so basically what we're talking about here.
Is we have a situation?
Right.
We've got D here.
That's what we've been doing.
And now we want to construct another d, right.
We want to construct a d, but we want to construct it.
Well, that's an awful Circle.
We want to construct it.
So, essentially, we have another d,
Right here, right?
So, we want to be able to construct the diagonal, the X and Y.
That will give us after they move the stair step pattern.
Right will actually give us a total length of D instead of each side
of the triangle being D.
Because before what we had right is we had each side of the triangle
being D and that's what lid that, you know, this was D and this was D
and that's what led us to the problem.
And so basically what we want to do is
Okay, for this tiny triangle here, where D is actually here.
What would we have to make these?
Well, like I said, I already told you the answer.
Actually.
I just didn't want to give away too much of a hint, right?
But I already said a squared plus b squared equals c squared
Pythagorean theorem, right?
So we know that we have that a triangle again.
We know that we have our triangle here again, right?
We saying that we want this to be D.
And now I'm asking you, what would I put here in here?
Well, we know we want to move on the diagonal.
Exactly.
So,
We know that they're going to be the same value, right?
And so whatever this value is, I'll call it V I guess I don't know.
Unless you want something else.
I can just use the Pythagorean theorem again, just in the other
direction before I used it to figure out what D was from the two
sides, but I could just do the reverse right?
I can just say well now V squared plus v squared equals c squared
right?
Again because this is my a this is my B and this is my C, right.
Sorry D Squared, right?
Just just copying those cut and paste it into the equation.
Cutting copypasta Works in math just like it does in encode.
Right?
So basically just got to V squared equals D Squared or V squared
equals D Squared over 2, right?
Or b equals root D Squared over 2, right.
And that's all real.
That's that's it.
That's all we really talking about.
That's the entirety of that's the entirety of thing.
And again, I'm really bad at math.
I say this all the time but I mean it I make mistakes in these sorts
of things a lot.
So I'll just go ahead and even reinforce that by saying, let's plug it
back in and make sure, make sure I didn't make a careless error in
copying the terms.
Because like I said, I will, if you don't see me, make one on the
stream.
I will be shocked.
I will, I will make them often.
And so anyway, if I have D Squared over 2 squared, I'm just taking
this equation.
Plus D Squared over 2 squared that should equal D Squared, right?
So, squaring this guy, it just removes the square root.
So I have D Squared over 2, plus D Squared.
Over 2 equals D Squared, right.
And then I could multiply Everyone by 2.
I think here.
Is that correct?
Well, oh no.
These guys add together, right?
So then I have basically two D Squared over 2, equals D Squared and
then I multiply that out.
And that's, that's right.
I mean you can you can cross out the twos cross out the squared equals
D.
And that's that's yeah, so that that seems that seems right to me.
Let's, let's assume that.
That's a, that's good enough match.
Checking for now.
But those of you who are good at math on the stream.
You will have to basically take note since I don't want to cheat and
look at the stream, take notes on everything I do here and you're
welcome to basically post at the end.
Maybe on a forums like here is Corrections where Casey made a mistake
that would be probably pretty helpful for people trying to learn.
So, anyway, if we wanted to implement something, we remove the right
speed.
We now know what we would do.
We would use D Squared over 2 square root it.
Basically.
And that actually, again, can be simplified further if we wanted to
because that square root we can
Pull out.
We could basically treat that as a 1/2 D Squared, right?
That's what that is, which means we can pull out the, the D again,
just like we did.
So it's basically just d square root of 1/2, right?
So all that means is since we're already doing the D quote unquote,
right?
This is our D.
In this case.
This is the amount we wanted to move by in the case that he was
moving.
Diagonally.
All we really have to do is figure out what's this square root of 1/2,
right?
So, what's this?
Square root of 0.5., Right?
That's all.
We actually need to know.
Can that gooey?
Paste that in there, yet?
Basically, that's all we need to do is multiply our value by this, in
the case where he's moving diagonal.
We just say, okay if he's moving to agonal.
We just multiply our values by that value, right?
There we go.
And so, we'll say, if, if D player X and D player, why?
Right, or I'll maybe I'll be a little more explicit here if they're
not equal to 0.
So, if both of them are set, then we'll do that.
And that would actually, I believe, if we've done the math correctly,
that will correct that motion.
And now, you can kind of see how he basically goes at a much slower
rate than he was going before when he moves downward.
There we go.
So, now, of course, I can't actually say whether it's exactly correct
or not because, well, kind of hard to eyeball these things.
To be honest with you.
I think he is.
I don't know.
It's hard to say, maybe he is.
I wish there was some way I could easily tell.
But I don't really know.
Yeah, hard to say hard to say, but there you go.
I'll double-check the Stream.
Yeah, it looks like looks like nobody.
None of the math.
People are like, oh my God, what did he do?
So I think that's a good, good sign.
All right.
So, anyway, now that we've got that straightened out, we can get back
to sort of the topic at hand.
Although that all kind of was leading up to the topic at hand, which
is again, if you look at this, if you keep looking at this, we're
constantly talking about these two valuables variables together.
And so again that kind of motivates us to start thinking about them a
little more cleanly.
So basically what we like to do with vectors is we like to start
having ways of
Not having to do all of this work all the time.
Just to do basic operations.
Like, make sure that something is the right length, right?
Ideally.
What we'd like to do is be able to say, let's create a system of tools
that allow us to quickly do this.
So we don't have to be writing math.
All the time.
We can just have basically a series of operations.
We can conceptualize that are things like make this be this long or
make this be perpendicular to that, you know, those sorts of things.
We want to be able to start thinking about them in those ways.
And that is a
Of what vectors also give us is that sort of mental good, conceptual
and semantic, sort of simplification.
So that when we're working on game code, we don't have to think at
this low level, right?
We can think at a higher level kind of like see helps us go a little
faster than assembly right.
Basically going up two vectors helps us be faster than its what's
called scalar scalar is when you're doing it as a single values
instead of being combined.
All right, so let's talk about those.
Let's talk about vectors little bit.
So basically, like, as I've already alluded to vectors are very much
just about putting together, multiple pieces of information that are
coupled in some way, because you want to operate on them and work on
them.
Other.
And so, you've already kind of see me draw the diagram because we just
started talking about it, even though I wasn't saying Vector,
specifically, we are actually already just to draw one.
If I have something like that Vector, for the diagonal motion, where
basically, you can think about a stair step, right?
A stair-step that stair, step pattern that right angle stepping
pattern.
That basically is an X movement followed by.
A why movement that gets to me to my final location.
Well, basically what vectors are doing is they're letting us start to
think about the this part.
Instead.
So instead of thinking about things in terms of this stair, step.
We can now just start thinking of them as the as the direct motion
from the origin directly, to whatever the final destination is, right?
And that works the same pretty much, no matter.
How many dimensions you want to have.
In terms of we're just talking about basic euclidean basic Cartesian
coordinates or whatever, you know, simple as long as things are
relatively simple.
And we're not talking about on the surface of a sphere or on the
surface of a Klein bottle or God knows what else might be happening in
in real math world.
If we
What kind of talking about this at a basic level?
This actually works pretty cleanly.
No matter how many dimensions you have.
So, you know, if we wanted to start talking about three-dimensional
stuff as well.
The principal is pretty much exactly the same nothing really changes.
You just have a third axis and you third stair, step pattern.
So instead of me just going along X and then up along Y, and calling
that the point, right?
I also now, move out, along, Z some distance and get a diagonal point,
that goes from the origin out to wherever that is, right, so, it's
basically,
Be like 123 kind of a thing, right?
Where there's two right angle, stair, steps, that happen.
And then I finally get out to a vector.
But the at the end of the day, the concept is still exactly the same.
It's just a motion along X motion along, y motion along Z.
And so no matter how long, our Vector gets right, no matter how many
elements we have ABCDEFG, right?
You know, so maybe we have vectors that are XYZ vectors and that's
what we're used to dealing with in games, but we can have them as long
as we want and we can conceptualize those as multi.
Dimensional things even that go up to four, five, six, seven, eight,
how our main Dimensions, we want that are all just about that same
process, right?
And again, there's lots of other ways to conceptualize vectors.
They don't have to be about these sort of right angle coordinate
systems that I'm talking about.
They can be a lot of other things, too.
Depending on what you need them to do.
but this is really what we care about for our purposes is vectors that
are constructed at these right angle or there's called orthogonal when
you basically have these coordinate systems that are nicely sort of
right at right angles to each other where X y&z or are all right
angles to each other and they make this nice stair, step pattern that
you can conceptualize again, doesn't have to be the case for
coordinate systems, but it's the kind that we typically deal with
Because they have a lot of nice properties that make them easy to deal
with.
All right, so all we're really doing when we say Vector right is we're
talking about that combination.
So in this case, we want to start talking about X combined with Y and
the typical way of writing it is like this where it with two vertical
bars.
And then the things go vertically.
To be completely honest with you.
I don't really know the history of why vertical is more more.
Typically the way that like vectors and points in 3D space are
written.
As opposed to horizontal.
Like, this is also a vector, right?
Basically, you can think of them as matrices.
Write a matrix is basically you make two bars, right?
And you start filling in entries into it and it could be two
dimensional or even more.
Could be three-dimensional, whatever.
And a vector is, kind of like a matrix.
That only has a row or a column.
Now why you would pick rows or columns specifically?
I mean, there's no real difference between the two, it just inverts
kind of how you look at all your operations as you'll see as we will
see when we go forward.
And so somebody at some point and if you know, math history, I'm sure
you would probably know this.
And I like I said, I don't somebody picked this as the preferred
method for talking about vectors in 3D space.
And in fact, this.
So so this is what you would typically expect to see written.
And when you see this, you're actually talking about a different type
of vector and we can talk about that.
More a little bit later, but basically, once you decide what your
convention is for, how you're going to write, if you write things
vertically, then writing things horizontally actually mean something
different.
And if you think about it, it makes some sense.
Again, jumping ahead a little bit.
But if you have a, let's say I had a matrix, you know, a two-by-two
array of numbers.
Let's say this is a column of that Matrix, but this would be a row of
that Matrix.
And so you can kind of think of this as being like the
L'm of a matrix and this is being like a row of a matrix.
And so when we actually talked about doing operations on these later,
it matters whether you're talking about something that's like a column
or like a row in terms of who affects who when they are operated on.
And so that's why I say the notation is a little bit.
It could be a little bit daunting.
It can be a little bit tricky.
It's true.
But basically for right now all you really need to know until we get a
little bit further up.
Is that the way that we want to write these for now to be consistent?
Mostly with mathematics, is that we're going to put them?
I'm vertically like that.
It's annoying in code because you can't make code vertical because
editors are from 1970 and can't write a stupid vertical Vector, in the
middle of your code for some reason, but that's where we are.
All right, so basically,
Talk about again is putting starting talk about this object and we're
going to write this object like this.
Whatever its X step is and whatever its why step is we put the X in
the top and the y in the bottom and that's our Vector, right?
Everyone's happy.
And then once we have that, we can start to Define operations on this
thing as an object.
For example, let's suppose that we had two of these, right?
So I'm going to call this x sub 2 x sub.
Well, actually, let's make it x sub 1.
This is the first one x sub 1, and then I'm going to talk.
About another one here.
That's x sub 2, y sub 2.
Right?
So, here's my x sub 1, here's my x sub 1 there, and let's say I have
another Vector, right?
That's like this actually, let me make it a little bit.
What whackier, let's say that it's pointing, like almost straight up.
So it's like this, right?
And so here is my right.
Here's my x sub 2, right?
It kind of goes over that way.
And here's my y sub 2, which is almost as close as close to.
It's a little bit less than that one, right?
Well, again, like I said, we're just talking about the object here.
But the point, that's very useful to sort of emphasize at this point
is even once we sort of talked about these as being composite like
this.
We can already start to do some interesting operations with them.
For example, right?
We can add two vectors together.
And basically that just does exactly what you would expect.
It puts one vector at the tip of another vector and finds the
resulting point, right?
It would basically move this guy.
It would say, what if he was at the end of x sub 1, right?
To start at x sub 1 y sub 1 and I'm going to move by this amount,
right?
Which is this Vector here.
So my new point is here and the resulting Vector, right?
Which I'll call x sub 3, y sub 3, right?
The resulting Vector.
Is this Vector right here?
Right now, you know, this intuitively because we already have done
this in the code to some degree.
We've already done.
X's, plus, X, is equals x is y, is plus y.
Equals y is, right.
That's how we removing our guy.
So, we already expect this to be true.
We already expect to be able to take some point in 3D space and add
some other point basically and have them be a raid tip to tip like
that.
Now, it's worth noting that sometimes there's a distinction between
points and vectors and we can kind of get into that a little bit
later, but for now,
Can kind of think as vectors as defining either a point or a like a
Delta, right?
So we could think of this as being a point and this as being like a
Delta and we are applying the Delta to the point, right?
But really they're both the same type of object as far as we're
concerned and they can be they can be interchangeable.
That's not strictly true in all mathematics.
And depending on how you want to talk about these things.
Formerly.
You may actually have a difference between points and vectors.
For example, that that make them behave differently, but we're not
really going to look at that right now.
That's kind of a little bit past.
What we're trying to do at the moment, but it's worth mentioning.
So we basically got a single type of object that we're using to
represent both of these.
All right.
Um, so again, same would be true for some traction.
Basically.
What subtraction would do is it says, what if I go in the opposite
direction, right?
So if I'm subtracting x sub 2, y sub 2, right from somebody, then, all
I'm doing is I'm taking this Vector.
I'm flipping it, right?
I'm flipping both its directions around and then I'm going to put it
at the end and move here.
So that result would be somewhere down here, right?
Make sense again, very very straightforward.
So addition and subtraction very, very simple.
They make a lot of sense.
Now, the other thing that's easy to understand and makes a lot of
sense is scalar multiplication.
If I had some amount of times I wanted to move like let's say I've got
this Vector here and I want to go two or three times its length.
So however, far I would go from the origin of my coordinate system,
which is that basic that zero zero point.
How far would I go if
I did three times this motion.
Well, I just go once I put the same Vector on the end of itself and go
again, right?
And again, right?
So scalar multiplication.
If I want to just say like 2 times x sub 1 y sub 1 scalar
multiplication is basically just adding the vector to itself just like
you would do just just like two times.
Some number is just saying that number plus itself, you know, twice
right?
The same is true here two times.
Something is saying exactly the same thing.
Nothing, it's saying I just want to add, right?
So all of those things are very should hopefully be pretty intuitive
to.
You should make a lot of sense because basically, they're just things
you would have done with the scalars already.
And all we're talking about doing is bundling them together so that we
can type and think about things more easily because we can start to
think about points in three dimensional space, more easily.
Now, what's going to be a little more confusing?
However, is when we start to talk about multiplication because
multiplication, actually, in Vector space gets
A lot trickier, so let's talk about that briefly.
And then maybe we'll going to.
We're going to go implement the basic thing.
It says we only got about 20 minutes left.
So I'm not really going to do much multiplication today, but let's go
and think about oops.
Let's go and think about that multiplication now, so alright, so here
is my coordinate system again.
Again, this is the origin of our coordinate system with a 0-0.
Let's say this is our x-axis or y-axis.
Here is one of our vectors.
Okay, and then I have some other vector.
Fire up here.
All right, and now I want to multiply these two together.
And so I'm going to start actually talking about these again.
Just I'll put them right here.
I'll say this is x sub 1 y sub 1 and this is x sub 2.
Y sub 2 again just like we did before.
Now, if I want to multiply these two vectors together, you might say,
well, why don't you just do the exact same thing you did before with,
with addition, just if I want to have x sub 1 y sub 1 x which we don't
actually know what that actually is yet, but I was going to write it x
sub 2 y sub 2 then Casey.
Why don't you just do exactly.
Only what you did before and just do it as if you were doing it to
each component.
Because, remember, when I did addition, right?
That's all I did.
I basically didn't do anything fancy.
I didn't seem to invoke any real math fanciness there.
I just did to the components.
What I would have done if they were scalar.
I just did, okay, you want to add, then add the exes, add the wise and
put the results in the X and the Y slot.
Right?
That's it.
And I did the exact same thing with some traction change that to a -
you just change these two - right.
So why not?
Not do the same thing with multiplication, right?
If this four times, right, you know, in there, why would I just stick
a times in there?
Well, the answer is because it doesn't really do anything that you
want it to do.
So this does have a name.
If I'm not mistaken, this is called the hadamard product.
It does have a name and it is a valid Vector operation.
It's defined.
It's something you could do, but what you will find if you actually
try to program with this.
Is that it's really only useful for colors.
And it's basically something that you end up doing to like, you know,
you've got some gray level and you want to multiply it by a color to
get out the color thing.
Or, you know, you got some kind of, it's really, you're not going to
see a lot of use of it in code for actually doing positioning and
movement things, which is what we're trying to do.
And the reason why that is the case, it's because the actual operation
that this implies
Doesn't really make any spatial sense.
If you look at what's going to happen.
We're going to take however far we are along one of these, right?
Axes like so, take X.
We're going to take however long the other one is and we're going to
multiply those together to get some multiplicate multiplied thing
here, right?
And then similarly we're going to do the same thing on this one to get
some multiplied thing here and we're going to get a result that's like
out there right now.
This result here isn't if you actually go and apply.
Well, I should, I should say that for one second.
Let's say that till the till the next thing we talked about, but
basically, this actual result, when you do these things doesn't have
really any properties that we would care about.
It's not something that's the two lengths of the vectors X.
Each other.
Really, it's not something.
It doesn't really give you.
It doesn't really give us anything that we would ever actually do in
practice.
Right?
And you'll notice that we've never done this anywhere in the
actual code either.
Like it's just not something that happens, very frequently.
So, typically the only time again that you see it is something with
like colors or something where you have like where you've just packed
things in in some way like this, you have an x-ray in ayr8 that you
want things to happen at and you've packed the main.
I don't know, weird stuff.
It's just, it's just not that common, right?
The other time.
You might see.
It is like some kind of a knockout filter.
Like you've got something where you've got, like a mask kind of a
thing where, like, oh, I
I want to knock out the Y component.
So I'm multiplying by this thing.
You know, there's there's weird weird circumstances.
You will see this sort of thing happen.
Certainly.
I don't want to say that it's never used but it's just not that
common.
And the reason is because unlike these other things like addition and
subtraction had very obvious things that we would want to do that made
sense like moving well on one in the moving, along the other or those
sorts of things are very common operations.
We'd want to do positionally
So the hadamard product is not really something that we want to focus
on.
Although we could implement it.
What we're actually going to do eventually is we're going to do the
dot and perf dot products.
Right?
Which are other types of ways of multiplying vectors together.
This would actually be more like a cross product in three dimensions
and these are terms, which you don't know yet.
If you don't know, Vector math, if you do not Vector, Matthew,
probably tuned out already because this stuff is very basic for you.
But basically, we will be talking about other kinds of
Of multiplication of vectors.
Because one of the things that's very interesting about Matrix about
linear algebra General on but Matrix math, is that because you have
lots of values you can start to Define ways in which they interact
that are more complicated than just going straight across.
And it turns out that those different methods that you use can get
you, some very powerful tools, but we're going to have to save that
for Tuesday.
Sorry, not Tuesday for Wednesday.
Wednesday.
So, come back tomorrow if you want to talk about those products and
that's what we'll be doing them.
For.
Now.
What I want to do is just do the basic work of replacing the scalar
code.
We've got at the moment with some Vector code, right?
That's all I really wanted to do.
Just very, very simple.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to make, I guess, maybe a
handmade math.h.
I'm just going to stick it in here because I basically just want some
place to start dumping our math code.
And I am going to make
Structure.
That is going to be a one of these things that we just sort of talked
about the thing that I just walked all the way through.
I just want to make something like that and I want to go ahead and
replace our code that we were using before with that.
Right?
And this is the place where we'll finally use a C++ feature that, you
know, that's not a non-trivial CSS feature.
Like I've said on the stream multiple times.
I'm like, we're going to use operator overloading running separately
will probably use it here.
I find that vectors.
Are one of the few things where I really like operator overloading and
most places.
I find it.
It's just not that useful but in vectors, it's kind of nice because
you can get code to look a little more like math even though it still
doesn't quite get you all the way there.
So really, all I want to do is encapsulate.
Exactly the stuff that we have been doing before.
I just want to say essentially that we do have, you know, an X and A
Y, right?
And I would like that ideally to be accessible in both ways.
So I want to basically say that I have an X and A Y, so if I want to
To type dot X, or Y to access the x or y component, I can do that.
And then I also want to be able to say, okay, I've
Element here and E which is going to have two components so that I can
access it procedurally.
And, you know, use a 0 or a 1 index to index into the element.
If I want to only if I want to though.
So that's going to be my my Vector structure.
That's really all I wanted to do there.
And then I'm going to define those operations on it that I wanted,
right.
I would like to be able to Define an operator to do that plus that we
saw happen, right?
So I want to take an A and A B.
And I want to be able to add those two together.
So I want to be able to basically say okay.
I've got a result and the result is going to be equal to you know,
again exactly the thing.
Where's my pen?
Exactly.
The thing that we did right here, right?
I just want to basically say, add the exes, add the wise and subtract
the excess subtract the wise, right.
So let's see.
Here we go.
So I want to be able to do, you know, that sort of thing.
I want to be able to subtract again.
This is really really simple, you know, I want to be able to subtract.
I'd like to be able to do a unary minus if that makes sense.
I'd like to be able to just say that a vector equals its - which is
that flipping operation.
Like I said before, just flipping a vector around.
So so to getting both of them and I believe in see, it's been so long,
but I hardly ever program anything fancy, but I believe you can.
Do you know what I think?
Can you still do that outside?
I don't know if you can do that outside.
Let's let's find out.
Can I do that outside to something or does it have to be in the class,
you know, can can result equals negative a?
I'm just curious.
Let's find out.
I thought I for some reason, I got that twinge in my head.
That was like, you got to put that inside the class, but I don't
actually know if that's true.
So let's find out handmade math.h.
And that probably, actually, I made that H.
That's probably something that we're going to want to use everywhere.
I assume.
Certainly, at least by here, okay.
Oops.
Oh, yeah, sorry, didn't quite finish typing that in there.
That was wishful thinking.
Okay, so I can do that outside.
So that's good.
Alright.
So basically I've got the ability to, you know, be able to say, you
know, b equals negative a that's what that guy does.
I can say a plus b.
And I can say a minus B like that, so, that's all good.
And then I also probably want like, like I said, the ability to
multiply by a scalar.
So I want to be able to
Say something like, you know, I've got an A and and a float of some
kind, right.
So I guess it would be something like this if that makes sense.
So then I've got a result and I do result dot x equals b .x x that a
Yeah.
Return result.
And so, you can just kind of see that.
All I'm really doing is just making some really, really basic vector,
vector math, routines, that are doing exactly those things, that I
just went over, on the, on the sort of, I don't know, the on the crito
Whiteboard, if you will, so now, if I want to actually start putting
that in the code, I can just look for the places where a previously I
was doing those sort of X and Y operations, right?
And I can start to actually, you know, make them a little more
concise.
Nice.
So what I can do is I can look through here.
I'm just kind of randomly sampling through the code and thinking.
All right.
I've basically got, you know, this this player ex-player.
Why thing here, right?
I can I could turn that certainly.
That's the one we were looking at.
Before I can basically say that I've got one of those that's going to
be cleared at the start and then if I just compile it, all I have to
really do is is now go every place that I was doing something to one
of the components.
I can just kind of do do it.
To the scalar and any place that I was doing something to both.
I can just make it operate on all of them and I can go add that star
equals as well.
Looks like that would be something that would be useful right?
So I can do that.
Certainly, that'd be easy to add and then here I've got this guy.
And again, this is like now a double.
Add it go and you can see that the code almost doesn't change at all.
Really.
All that's happening is is if I start to get rid of these, I start to
basically just get one line of code in a lot of places.
That I used to have two and that's really, you know, that's really
almost the entirety in the entirety of it.
So, let's take a look.
I need that x equals because I'm using that, and I also need to go
make handmade tile.
.H make that offset D of e 2 as well, so, there we go.
And now, let's go ahead and here and start to look at it again.
I can just quickly poured it by doing the dot, oops.
I mean to do that right there and then here, this is actually kind of
interesting.
So this
Looks a lot to me, like, something where I could simplify.
I mean, that's that's doing the exact same math there, right?
That's just a - be there and detail X detail.
Why I could just make this right here.
Also be a vector to, right?
So I could basically say that I have something like this, right.
Oops.
I could basically turn this into Vector math as well.
So there's that detail X.
And now that's basically the detail X Y, if you will, right?
And so, now detail XY plus a offset - be offset, actually can directly
do the result dxy in the tile map difference.
So, basically, there's, there's now one of those, right?
And you can start to see that maybe, okay.
Well, there's also a DZ, I don't know, should we maybe, you know,
we'll have to start thinking about.
Extending this the 3D, right?
But again, one thing at a time.
So let's keep going here, too.
Many initializers.
Why is it to manage the oh
Right.
That's true to think about how to get around that because I want to be
able to initialize that the union makes things a little bit grimly
there.
Doesn't it?
Because I can't quite do the initialization the way I would want to
because I think C++ in its infinite testing.
Ilysm doesn't let you just initialize the first thing in the union or
something equally awesome like that.
Well, that's no bother.
I can I can fix that pretty easily.
We can just basically say, oh and also these also should presumably
all be in lines there trivial operations.
That the compiler should just kind of throw in there.
So yeah, let me just clean this up a little bit here.
Yeah.
So what I'll do is I'll just basically say okay fine if that's the way
you want it.
Mr.
Lousy language.
That's fine.
We'll just say but basically we initialize them this way.
And we will do it like that.
Okay.
So now I've got a way to make them so I can basically say, all right,
here you go.
There's my V2, which is the kind of makes me grumpy have to think
about it.
I traffic if I fix that kind of thing in my own code before I feel
like I did.
But how did I do it?
You know what?
I probably did.
You know what I do.
I think I probably do know what I did.
Here's what I probably did because I think I have done this before.
What I probably did was, I probably did that, right?
And then I probably did something like this.
Like, you know, this sort of thing or or like, operator brackets, you
know, one of these things into index and I probably did something
like, you know, don't don't try this at home, kids, write that sort of
thing.
I probably did something like this, just guessing not really entirely
sure, but let's take a look.
So I think what I probably did
Something where I would go, okay, you know, take the address of X and
then and then get a particular index off of it, right?
So that basically you end up with a thing.
Yeah.
I'll talk about that in one second.
But yeah, let's finish our Port first and then I'll talk about that
because basically I like to be able to initialise things with this
syntax where I can just do my sander bracket syntax and so unions.
Unfortunately, don't let you do that.
And so you kind of have to walk her work around them a little bit.
All right.
So let's take a look here.
Let me finish all of my porting this.
So, I've got to have that x equals, which we haven't done yet.
So, let's go ahead and make a x equals.
Those.
I believe do have to be member functions, if I'm not very much.
Mistaken.
So basically, we do need a x equals and the x equals is going to be by
a scalar in this case.
And so that will be again.
Just I guess we could just call one of these guys.
Probably I don't actually know if that's true.
I feel like it should be.
Oops.
Relatively straightforward to implement one of those.
There we go.
So if I want to do
Yeah, I feel like, can I not just do star this goes a, that sort of
thing.
I feel like I should be able to do this times a U-turn start of this.
So any reason I can't do that.
Let's have it least one formal parameter of Class Type.
Operator.
Oh, and it's got to be a member function.
Certainly.
No operator found which takes a left hand type of V2.
That's correct.
Sorry having the wrong order.
Let's see.
There we go.
And then plus equals is the same thing.
So I also need to be able to make that plus equals happen as well.
So there we go.
And again, I'm not really doing anything.
Particularly interesting here.
That's why I'm not talking.
A whole heck of a lot is just because
This is just a bunch of Grimble work.
There's really nothing particularly exciting about it.
I'm just sort of going through and saying, okay, what are all the math
operations?
I was currently using and then let me go ahead and Implement them in
the most straightforward way possible.
And basically all I'm doing with these plus equals guys is I'm just
calling the same code.
I just wrote, but C++ is too dumb to figure that out.
But you could just use a plus to make a plus equals.
I mean, how could you possibly ever, imagine that could work?
So anyway, you have to write it yourself and basically, all I did was
say, hey, by the way, just call the plus operator on on you, right?
Which is all I really wanted to do.
So anyway,
Let's see here.
What did I forget?
I forgot that that address sign.
There we go.
And so again, just going through and finishing the port here.
So we're going to, this is an actual modification of, just the X
parameter.
So, that's actually okay.
And again, this is going to be one of these guys.
Let's see.
And I guess this that looks very similar as well.
Let's see here.
So although this one does look like it's actually because it has to
flip the why we may want to write that in a slightly different way.
But all of those could probably collapse down now to like, you can
take a look at that, right?
Like them in X-Men, why?
Those are getting handled almost identically.
Those could all just actually be Vector 2's.
So we've got a, it's kind of a rich.
It's a fertile ground here at the moment for things, but I'm just
going to go ahead and and, and finish porting them that way, just to
make sure that we're still running.
Okay, there we are.
Everyone's happy.
It looks like we're still working properly.
No, big problems.
So that's all good.
Okay, and then, just taking a look now at the stuff that we could do
here.
Again, Min X Min Y is kind of looks like and same with sin x and y.
So basically, if I take a look at that sin x and y stuff, basically,
this looks like a big old V 2 to be as well, right.
This is something where I'm Computing, two values, and then I'm about
to use them as if they were vectors basically everywhere else.
So this Min right?
This men could easily be computed basically like that.
The only question is I need this tile side and pixels as one so this
is basically tile side is its own vector?
So here we go, and so tile side and the max will also be side down,
cleans that up a little bit and the tile side and pixels.
We actually probably almost always use in this way.
We almost always uses the vector to we could collapse a lot of the
stuff down to Vector but still and so then our draw rectangle call.
We could also do the exact same thing.
We could start taking points there as well.
Could basically say all right, we've got our RV Min, something like
that, and our RV Max.
Right.
And that makes that function a lot easier to read now to and so, in
here, when we're actually doing the rounding, we could just go ahead
and do it out that, and that way, now people who call us don't have
any trouble.
It's no harder for us to deal with.
So we're all good.
And then this just takes Min and Max that
What did I do?
Here we go.
And so this one.
Let's see.
This is player left and player top.
So this is like basically player left top.
We can now basically say it, just say it like that.
Right?
And it looks like we are out of time.
So there's our player left top and then here we've actually got a
thing where I guess that's our player left top.
Plus this other Vector here.
And so we could actually say player with height, right?
Is actually going to be another Vector here that we can Define.
So, layer with layer height, and then we can actually just say it's
player.
Left top plus, m, 2 pixels x player with tight.
Right, and basically they can see how we turn that into a nice vector
equation there by just saying, well M particular to pixels, we were
multiplying everything by that.
So now we just kind of fold that into a multiply and again, just kind
of folding things down, really, really, pretty, pretty straightforward
stuff.
We're coming to the end of the stream here, so I got to stop but let's
see.
What did I do there that I should not have done, cannot convert from
initializer list to real 32, right?
These guys are supposed to be effective choose.
So, there we go.
And and again, we haven't like, you can see, we haven't changed
anything.
It's all working exactly the way that it was no, no real changes.
And so really all we're starting to do is start to fold that code down
into something that's a little more concise and also helps us avoid
the typos.
The more we can sort of compress things down into logical objects,
like that or we've kind of.
And I might say obvious.
I mean, mathematical objects, not programming objects, just to be
clear, although you could think of them as programming objects as
well.
I mean, this is, despite the fact that it's
Not in a class, right?
It certainly is an object, you sort of thing.
For those of you, like, object-oriented programming.
Hopefully, that's something that would be relatively happy.
I mean, I guess you probably wouldn't like the fact that I've got my X
and Y sitting out there instead of being like protected or in the
private section or something like this, but at the same time, it's
like, yeah, you know, it's it's the kind of thing.
You might think about as an object in programming as well, in the
sense that it's a bundle of things together that we're kind of moving
around and thinking about as a unit, right?
And so, that's basically what we've got.
I will go ahead and go over to the Q&A.
Out rather than continuing to go through and start to compress the
stuff down further, even though there's a lot of things we could do
now that we finally have a vector to class even though it only has
addition and subtraction in it, and it's multiplication by a scalar.
There's still a ton of code that we could start to collapse now that
we've got that and so maybe that's something that I'll pick up again
tomorrow and we'll talk about the dot product and the cross product at
that time for now.
Let's go ahead and end up.
Turn on the Q&A.
Please prefix or questions with
: and so I can see them.
And also, please try to keep your questions of stuff.
We've done today stream or on a previous Stream.
So most thing I spelled height wrong.
I don't actually know.
Where is that?
Where is it?
You spelled height wrong.
Did I?
How did I spell it?
But anyway, let's go ahead and here.
How do Union types work in C++ and what were the drawbacks of using
them?
So the reso unions.
I like a lot, I think unions are great.
Basically, what I had wanted to do was say that I wanted to add to
what I want to do is basically put two things in one spot, right?
I wanted to say that you could access the same two floating Point
values, either as a DOT X.
Delta y, or as a DOT e, brackets.
A number, right?
And I love that.
And I think it's
I think unions are very, very important.
I am of that camp.
I want to say that there's a bunch of category.
Theory starts with people who talk about discriminated unions, a lot
to, and how they're the basis of all good programming and stuff like
this.
I am in their Camp.
I think discriminated unions are actually extremely important and
that's a whole separate topic as well.
But basically I love unions.
Unfortunately C++ has support for unions is absolutely awful.
And so you can't even do like the basic thing that I wanted to do.
Because as soon as you do this, you can no longer initialise things
with this syntax.
You can no longer do like V 2A, equals 5, comma 3, but that's what I
wanted.
I wanted to be able to do that.
And so you would have to basically introduce your own syntax like a
Constructor for them or something syntax, which I don't love because
then it
Different from everybody else for no reason or you can make a function
that returns one, but then it still looks different.
I just want it.
So it looks the same and so what I did is I actually just said, all
right.
Well fine, I'll make like a bracket operator so you can access it.
That way.
You don't have to say dot e, so if you have a V2 a you'll just do a
DOT e to you know, where you would have typed that you'll just type
that instead.
It's like that's a, you know, totally fine compromise.
I don't mind.
And so that's that's what I chose to do.
Had height spelled wrong in that last bit of code.
There it is.
There we go.
Thank you.
Okay.
Let's see.
Pseudonym 73 is actually posting a thing about saying, who
standardized on what Victor Matrix.
Convention Circa 1993 1993.
There's no way math.
Only standardized in 1993.
Did it really?
I feel like math has been using vectors for column vectors for points
in space for a long time before that.
Is that not true?
All right.
In the first version of E2 with the Union weren't you?
Simply missing an anonymous struct around X Y, it looked like X Y,
where overlapping would it have worked that the way you wanted?
Oh, you know what?
You're right, but I don't think it helps meaning.
Yeah, I type that wrong.
It should have looked like this.
Like that, but I don't think it actually works still.
Maybe it does.
I don't know, we could find out but you're right.
That's a good catch.
You do need to bundle those in Anonymous struct.
So I'm not actually sure, but if that, if that works, if it were, if
it works, that's cool.
Okay, so that does actually work, does it actually work?
Let's hope that that works.
So that does work.
I can get rid of this.
Well, alright, so I take it back.
So we're good.
I just had to wrap that guy up a little bit now.
Well, I guess so there.
One downside, which is, is this, the thing again, that only works in
visual studio and you get complaints on it in llvm because we had this
problem before.
When I did it, I did this here.
Where is it?
I did this here where I had an anonymous struct inside there and my
understanding was that llvm complained about that is that not true?
I know some people wrote in about that.
And so I don't know, like, maybe we maybe we still don't actually want
to do this because it may be only Visual Studio.
That's happy about.
If I don't know, we can leave it like that for now because that's what
I wanted to write.
And and so I would like to, I would like to be able to leave it that
way.
Like I said, C++ is really
We bad about unions so they are problematic.
But you know in this limited case, I feel like if it compiles and
works on both compilers, I'd be okay with using it because we're not
going to ask it to do anything fancy.
So hopefully it would be okay.
Like these guys are never going to have Constructors or any weird
stuff like that.
So we don't need to worry about what's going to do as far as that's
concerned.
So maybe we'll just maybe we'll just cross our fingers and hope that
it's not a problem for the all of them people because I'm not
compiling on llvm.
I'm not compile this code up.
I am right now, so I'm not sure.
How do you remember all these commands and stuff?
I'm super new decoding.
I don't like.
That was just you saw that mistake that I just had to correct.
Their right.
I often times will make mistakes because like I'll just look at
something quickly and you know, I mean, granted like on the stream.
I definitely make more mistakes than I would normally, but I still
make mistakes all the time.
I'm just, I can't remember whether something works.
Well, one way or not.
And so, instead of looking for a bug when it was like this.
I just assumed it was like, oh, right.
There's all these problems with C++ and unions.
And I just kind of was like,
All right, I'll move on and I'll do a different solution that I know
works.
And sometimes I don't remember like wait, no seedless should be able
to handle that case, what's going on?
And then go.
Oh, right.
There's like a typo here or something, right?
And so it you can't remember it all, like, you often times forget.
Yeah, and unfortunately, all not only do you often times forget.
But unlike on this, this long, like unlike on handmade here are you
don't have a group of people watching you on a stream, who can remind
you?
Because there are like someone on the stream, will remember the wait,
It no or catch the typo or whatever, right?
And normally when your program you don't have that you're just program
by yourself, right?
And so you do, you know, it's true.
It's hard to remember all this stuff.
But you know, you like anything else, the stuff that you do most
frequently see is sticks with you.
So you won't make mistakes on that, right?
The stuff that you type.
Most frequently.
I don't type this that frequently.
So, you know, it's easy for me to get
Big mistake.
Is there a performance reason not to use a Constructor for v2?
Or is it just stylistic?
It's mostly just stylistic.
I don't like to have to have Constructors for them, but it's also
because you start to get
Proliferation of stuff.
It's not performance concern.
Like the compiler should be smart enough to take care of it.
Totally.
The reason that I don't like it is once you start to have a
Constructor, you have to write multiple Constructors.
So, for example, if I want to in C++ with the bracket syntax, I can
omit them entirely, and that'll initialize it, right, but I couldn't
do that.
If I started adding Constructors here because it would want me to call
one of the Constructor.
So I have to start adding a Constructor.
I have to add the null.
Actor as well.
I have to like, and then you can't just declare one that isn't
constructed.
Like, you can't just say that because then you have to have a default
Constructor and is the default Constructor construct the zero.
Okay.
Well, it doesn't, then I got to make one that constructs, it 2-0.
Like it's just this kind of annoying thing.
Whereas cephas the normal Syntax for declaring variables.
Actually.
Let me do everything I want to do.
I just want the u.s.
To stay out of my way.
And so, basically, with with the without the constructors, I can do
exactly what I want, which is that is uninitialized.
That is cleared to 0, this has the first thing set and then the
Set to 0.
This has two things that that's all the stuff that I want.
You just automatically creates for me.
And so that's way nicer to, I don't have to type a bunch of extra
stuff in there for no reason.
Let's see.
When would the fact that an object's members are public or private
come into play in Game Dev.
Well, I never use private personally.
So it never comes into play in my game development, but other people
like to use it to prevent basically they like to try an inch in sure
if you will or should say the goal of private is to ensure that only a
limited set of places in the code can touch.
The members of that class.
And so it's a way of confining the set of people who can touch
something down to a known smaller set.
And so it's basically just a tool that some programmers use to prevent
themselves or other programmers from modifying parts of objects and
places that they don't want them to be modified.
So it's an attempt to try and not have bugs happen.
If you didn't ever have any bugs in your code.
There'd never be a reason to type private.
It's
Only for the programmer, it has no bearing on the quality of the code
or anything.
It's strictly about trying to prevent bugs from happening.
If that makes sense.
The reason I don't use it.
It's because it basically makes it harder to work with the class
because you have less options, external, code, can't operate on it, in
an easy way.
And so I prefer not to use it, but other people like it.
So do we already fix the height thing or is there another?
Yeah, okay.
So I think we fixed the height thing.
Just making sure or yeah.
Okay, so saying that, you should be able to have compound assignments,
outside the object.
So, basically, I was thinking that you maybe had to put them in here
and there is someone on stream saying that I could if I wanted to not
do that and I would probably prefer not to do that.
So what they were saying is that as long as I Do's a reference member
for my first one, I should be able to do it.
And so, basically, you're saying this, right?
Is this what you were saying?
I should be able to do.
Okay, here we go.
Oh, right, and then of course, I need to return a
Okay, so it looks like that's true as well.
So I can get rid of those guys and I can go ahead and put them outside
we go.
Like I said, it's I almost never program C++ stuff anymore.
So I forget a lot of the notation notation stuff.
Like I used to, right?
Tons of templates and stuff.
But I bet like, if I tried to write a template, now, it would take me
forever to write a template because I just feel, like, wait a minute.
Where does the, how do I read the thing?
What did I do?
Wrong there a times B.
Oh, right.
It's
A bat.
Alright, still seems roughly correct to me.
All right.
If you're using vertical bars in your Matrix and Vector notation, what
will you use to denote the determinant in my linear algebra text, or a
square braces, are used on matrices and vectors and vertical bars are
used to denote the determinant.
Um, so my recollection and I could be wrong about this, but my
recollection is that I used to see oops.
I usually see it written like this.
But also typically determinant is like debt and then they, right.
Stuff like that too.
So I don't know, but in general determinant is not something you write
very frequently in most like we will take many determinants at all.
I would suspect.
So it's not really something that I would ever optimize around because
the frequency with, which you write determinant is so low.
Compared with the frequency, right?
Everything else that you know, I would I always would make sure that
vectors are the simplest possible thing.
So just straight line for Vector would be absolutely what I would
always prefer.
Let's see.
Can't you make the whole thing a union instead of having a struct
union structure?
Oh, I don't know.
That's a good question.
They were basically asking, could I just make it all the whole thing?
Be Union, V2 like that?
And I don't know.
The answer apparently is yes.
It would appear.
So I've never, I don't think I've ever tried that before.
I mean, I've had bear unions before, but I've never, I've never, if
you'd asked me.
Could you put, could you do operator overloading on unions like that?
I would have to say, I've never tried it before.
I guess I would have assumed it would work but I've never actually
tried it before.
So I guess the answer is.
Yes, you could do that.
So there you go.
We'll leave it like that.
Till something breaks because it looks like it works.
Just fine.
I assume that it's a, you knew just the same as a struct in that way,
but I'm not sure.
Does the altered V to work now?
If you comment out the Constructor Oh you mean this this isn't
actually a Constructor.
This was just a utility function that you can use to construct two of
them.
You definitely don't need it.
We're not calling it anywhere, but I usually like to have that around
anyway, so that what I can do is if I want to declare like we're going
to use this eventually, I just just didn't use it yet.
It's not a Constructor Constructor would have to look like that.
That's what a Constructor looks like.
This is not a Constructor.
This is just a utility function that happens to return a V2.
So it kind of looks like Constructor, but it's not a Constructor.
It's just the thing that makes one.
And so, basically, what I would do is, you know, some place in the
middle of code.
If I wanted to make one of these, I just could make one like, right
when I was going to call a function or something.
And it would be clear what I was making.
And that's kind of old school because I think C, plus plus 11x,
whatever.
/.
I don't even know.
I think there's now ways that you can just do this, right?
I think you can write this now.
If that makes sense, in fact, let's test it.
Or I thought you could write.
I thought you could write something like this.
I don't remember.
I thought there was a thing where you could where you could sort of
actually still now do what this allows you to do, but in the old days
you couldn't so I
To make one of these guys.
I think there's something you can do nowadays in mind more in the like
modern standards that allow you to do that.
What libs are you using?
We are not using any Libs.
Just tested the be to structure an xcode using llvm.
It compiles find.
Okay, cool.
I don't know what people were talking about before.
I just remember, there were some people who were having trouble with
this for some reason, I thought so, yeah, so hopefully, it's just, it
was a fluke or something, and we're not going to have a problem with
it.
Although DRT walk says, if I remember correctly.
GCC and clang will both complain about the union.
Struck thing.
I did something similar in a Vic three object a few weeks ago and
ended up having to use.
Operator brackets.
Anyway, so yeah, so we may have to turn this into an operator
brackets.
I don't know getting conflicting things here from people.
It probably depends on what warning level you're on or maybe what
version of compiler.
I don't know.
Can you explain how to use Boolean equations used in intro to
programming?
Sorry, I'm not sure what that means.
Can you be more specific?
Are you talking about my little test dream?
I did.
But that's entered a c or some other intro to programming thing.
Do you have any book recommendations for Vector math?
I'm not sure if I do, or if I don't, I could tell you what book, I
used to learn, but I don't know that I necessarily recommend it,
because there may be better books, but I'll simply say that.
Basically, this was I believe.
No.
Wait, that's the harder core one.
Just is this.
It introduction to?
Hold on a second.
Please open for me.
Open my web page open it.
Well, this is the book.
That I learned from.
Of course, the web page is not available.
Apparently, I don't know if that means that the stream is down as
well.
Let's see here.
Does, it doesn't seem like the streams having too much trouble
necessarily, but who knows?
Why can we not reload the web page where it is?
So this was the actual book I learned out of although it wasn't the
fourth edition.
It was probably like the Third Edition or something.
And it was pretty good book, but I've heard from other people.
I'll bet there are better, linear algebra books to learn out of.
And so you may want to go look at.
There was, if you go to Hameed here at Oregon, go to news and Forum
site for a while.
I believed there was a discussion about this on code discussion.
I don't really probably should pin it or something because, you know,
it kind of goes in and out but there's basically like something where
people were kind of were like talking about about books and I don't
know, there might be there might be some good stuff.
Tough in there or not.
But again, it's really unfortunately something that I don't have the
definitive answer for because I don't really know what the I haven't
gone and looked at what books are out there at the moment.
So let's take a look here.
So here's like here's the actual if you want to copy that web address
down here was the thread that people were talking about.
I don't actually know like yeah, if it really came too much in terms
of people sort of definitively knowing what books to buy or what.
It's not to buy, but there you go.
Let's see.
Will you define vector and scalar addition?
Probably not because that's not really a math.
Operation.
Are you talking about?
So are you talking about this operation?
So I'm assuming this is what you're talking about, which is to say
that you have a vector and you have a scalar and you want to add them
together.
And
I think maybe in my, in my earlier days when my math was better.
Like when I did a lot more math on a daily basis.
I don't do nearly as much math on a daily basis as I used to, I may
have had some pedantic reason why I would say that this doesn't make
any sense because basically like a vector and a scalar don't really
add together in terms of the way.
MathWorks addition, is defined really usually between two
Actors or, like, based on between two things of the same Dimension.
So, basically, in the same way that you can't add a vector to a
matrix.
Like, for example, if I have something that looks like this, I can't
add something that looks like that.
That's typically not defined in math, at least, as far as I know, far
as I'd ever seen.
And so, typically encode, I don't Define them either but really you're
free to make your own rules.
It's whatever is going to be useful to you.
So if you think it's useful to be able to
Turn this into something like, say that you were trying to turn it
into doing this.
Oops.
Then.
You know, go for it, right?
But I would caution to say that there are usually reasons why math
doesn't do these things.
And so, for example, in this case, hopefully it's kind of you could
kind of see why you wouldn't actually do this.
Because what does this do in practice?
Right?
Well, what it does is, it would essentially pretend that you had a
vector that was 55, right?
And then it would add it to some Vector that you had that was
existing, which in this case is
Me too, right?
Which is here.
So there's my two.
There's my three, right?
So you'd essentially be adding this Vector to this Vector, right?
But why, you know, when do you really want this?
When is it common for you to want to spam a single value out to all
the elements of the vector like that?
It's just not a very common operation.
And so typically you will find that this would probably induce a lot
more just typos in your code.
Where you
We add a scalar to a vector.
You didn't mean to do that.
And so I would caution perhaps against implementing that unless you
had a really good reason.
Any particular reason for not supporting both scalar, Vector,
operators and Vector scalar operators?
Not really.
I would say that I'm fine with, I'd be fine with with this.
Right, if you would like to do that.
I think that's totally fine.
In fact, I might even say just do this, right, assuming, that's what
you're talking about.
I'm not sure.
That's, that's what you're talking about.
But basically so, yeah, if you want to be able to write five times
vector or vector times 5, I believe that's totally math, fine as far
as I know.
And so that's totally fine with me.
I can't think of a particular reason not to do it.
so, someone is saying that the struct name syntax, the thing that I
was doing where I said, oh, if you do this
There are saying that that's maybe only see 99.
So I guess you can't do it in C++.
Maybe not sure.
But anyway, I know that there's something like that that you can do
now in fancier stuff.
Does not returning real 32, instead of V2 in x equal operator, trim
your y value.
Okay, what does that mean exactly x equal?
so, which
Do you touch you?
Does not returning real 32 instead of V 2 in x equal operator, trim
your y value.
I don't really know what that means.
But basically, all I can say, is this, what this does right here, is
it just calls the operator?
We wrote right here, right?
Which does the full multiply of scalar times both elements.
So for example, if I was to step into that code you can see what it
does.
Let me go ahead and and set a breakpoint their weak point.
Can I do operator?
Equals, oops, that's not what I meant.
That's not what I meant to do.
Readers x equals.
There we go.
So if I, if I stepped into this code, you can see that it just calls
this.
So really all this is, is just shorthand to not write this again.
So that we know that our scalar times Vector, multiplication all goes
to the same path, which is what I wanted to ensure.
So you'll notice I wrote these two guys, both the, the one for the
reverse where you have the scalar on the right side and sew the left
side, and the one where you do,
It as x equals.
I just wrote them in terms of one single multiplier.
And so that this is, this is just telling it to call this, right.
That's all.
That's all that's happening.
Okay, so finally are on the hopefully, this is correct.
Someone was saying in the Stream, So in c99, like I was just saying
someone was saying that.
See this was c99 syntax and somebody else was saying that in regular,
see, you can do it this way.
So I don't actually know if that's true.
Let's find out.
Yeah, okay.
So there you go.
So here's the way we can do it in C++ 11.
Which maybe would make it so that we don't have to type this anymore
and that's kind of nice.
Potentially.
Although it does mean that we have to be C plus plus 11, which I don't
actually know if we would want to do necessarily but it seems well
enough.
So we could, we could consider doing that.
So I'll say consider this as our as our syntax and who knows, right?
Almost almost out of time.
Let's see.
Do we question?
Don't you need some sort of Graphics Library display stuff.
Not in a console with C.
No, you do not.
In fact, handmade hero.
I don't know if you preorder The Source or not.
I can pre-order the game or not.
If you preorder the game, it comes with source code.
So if you come on here and you pre-order.
Name and then you'll get a link to download the source code.
The source code actually has 100% of the code in it.
That's displaying the stuff on the screen, all of it.
There's no libraries used at all.
And so, if you want to see how to put graphs up on the screen, you can
do that.
And also, obviously, you can go to the video archive where I talk
about how to put stuff on the screen.
In fact, if you take a look at the video archive here, in fact, or you
know, what you can do, actually, if you go to forums that handmade
hero dot-org and you go to the episode guy, that's a better place for
it.
Can see them all listed here.
I believe you can
jump to allocating it back buffer and animating the back buffer that
just shows how to put that's like when we were talking about how to
put cracks on screen opening win32 window.
Also just shows the basics.
So basically days one through five is like how to get graphics on the
screen in Windows using know libraries.
And again, each day is only an hour.
So basically it's only five hours of code of listening to explain how
to do it, entirely yourself with no libraries whatsoever.
And so it's really not that hard.
It's basic, it's less than a day's worth of work to do.
You'd certainly don't need a library.
Let's see.
Let's see here.
A lot of questions.
Oh my God.
Okay.
Let's see here.
Mass.
Couple more.
His 2015 time to update your copyright notice.
I guess.
That's true.
Although, isn't it copyrighted for when it's first published?
I don't know.
But we could I guess we can go in here to our to our misc.
See emacs go 2014.
There we go.
Alright, it's done from now.
On.
It'll be any new files.
We make 2015 copyright.
Let's see here.
Saudi Seven Samurai.
We did end up being able to initialize the union using brackets.
So that was just me with a typo.
So I was thinking it was causing me more trouble than it had to.
It was just getting confused.
I'm not really sure why it was getting confused.
But, no matter.
Let's see.
Do you have used for constant such as V 2 1 and V, 2 up cetera.
So, basically, what the person is asking, is, do I ever Define
constants of these?
And sometimes I do, sometimes, I'll do stuff like, I'll basically
Define Global's that are of the form.
You know, like using the syntax that we've got here.
I'll do something like, you know, Global x axis or something like
that.
And I'll do something like this or Global X2, you know, like that.
And I'll do something like this.
Sometimes I do that stuff.
Oops.
That sort of thing, but more often than not, I just don't bother more
often than not.
I just put the stuff directly in the code because it's not like the
x-axis or the zero Vector ever going to change.
And so, sometimes it's better for people just be able to see them.
So, I don't know.
So, I mean, they're not bad ideas necessarily, but but I just don't
actually tend to get that much use out of them in practice.
So, I don't know.
Let's see.
Looks like that's just about everything.
think we've got,
Pseudo cutter says copyright should cover all years in which content
was contributed.
Okay.
Well, so I don't know, our does that mean we have to put like 2014
Dash 2015 or something?
I don't know.
I'm just gonna leave it like that for now.
Copyright lasts for so long.
It's like 70 years or something like that.
Anyway, I feel like I'll be so dead and buried by the time that would
matter, and I'm going to release the code into the public domain 2
years after the game ships.
I've already stated that publicly.
So basically, yeah, why would I care?
That's true.
I don't have to care at all.
Everything could just be 2015, because copyright lasts so much longer
than we are actually going to need copyright to last on this code,
because it will become free for everyone.
In
Much less than 70 years.
Let's see here.
How about adding const references to function parameters to avoid copy
by value?
I don't really ever find const to be useful.
I've made zero constant stakes in the past.
Let's see.
I want to say in the past 14 years of coding.
I've never had a time when cons would have caught an error and I never
type const on the stream because I'm less concentrated.
I have made one error that costs would have caught but we it was an
immediate type of thing that we saw right away.
So it wouldn't have even constant really have saved at any time.
So maybe later on the stream if I find that I'm making some con
stairs, which I don't really ever make.
Normally when I'm coding.
I would consider starting to use const but only on the stream in
Normal.
I never use constants completely Superfluous.
I find.
Doesn't contest, help the compiler, optimize s enemy Mouse.
So the
It is not really so.
There is one specific case that technically, the compiler can optimize
when you put constant.
I don't actually know if any compilers actually do and it's a case.
That's so kind of uninteresting that it's unclear.
Why you would even care.
I mean, maybe once in a great while you would care about this with
this case, but 99% of the time, constant doesn't help.
The optimizer.
Because basically, if there are any pointers going on, then basically,
the only time that cost can help them is if it's a non.
If it's something that could never have had that.
The compiler can verify by looking that no one can ever have gotten a
pointer to that thing.
Right?
And so basically has to be something that is passed or declared on the
stack by
Value inside the function, you have to declare it const.
And then you have to call a function with a pointer to it.
That could modify it.
And that is the only case where where constant actually helps the
optimizer potentially and more specifically.
It's probably not the optimizer that it helps.
It helps the front end pass a better thing to the optimizer if you
will.
But but yeah, so people think const helps in optimization, but that's
not actually true.
It's very, very rare that cost helps optimization at all.
But yeah, if for some reason we had that one case that I'm talking
about and we actually had it in a performance critical part of the
code.
Maybe I would consider putting cost in there but I don't think I've
ever hit that case in practice because if I was actually optimizing
the thing, it would be an intrinsic or something and we wouldn't be
talking about that kind of a thing anyway.
So I think that's basically it.
I am going to to wrap up the stream now, hopefully everyone was okay
with the math that we did today.
It was pretty I think pretty simple.
I don't think we did anything to ridiculous.
Hopefully it was a pretty straightforward and basically ties directly
back to the code that you already saw working.
So they're really we didn't really do anything far out or weird.
I think.
So, hopefully if you know the pathet, if you knew the Pythagorean
theorem from
School math.
And you saw the stuff that we've been doing so far in the code.
I think that you'd probably be pretty comfortable with all the stuff
we did today in our math code.
And so hopefully that's a nice gentle introduction to vectors and you
will be be nice and ready for us to start getting into some more.
Complex, Vector stuff tomorrow, but you know what?
We don't even necessarily have to get into more complex, such
tomorrow.
What we could do tomorrow is just do some real basic stuff and and get
our momentum stuff working because that would be a pretty good thing
to do.
So, maybe that's what we'll do tomorrow.
We'll work on that momentum stuff.
And that'll be a pretty good way to sort of keep the math, very light,
but still make some bags, meaningful, progress in our code.
So hopefully you will all come back tomorrow, 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time.
When we will go ahead and Implement that momentum code using our
brand-new shiny Vector to structure that we create today.
Although it's a union.
Now, even, our Vector to Union, again, 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time tomorrow.
If you would like to pre-order the game and follow along with the
source code, you can do that at handmade hero dot org, and that comes
with a link that has a source code from every single day.
So you can go ahead and follow along with PBS days if you wanted to as
well.
We also have a patreon.
If you want to support the series, you could subscribe there.
And finally, we have the Forum site, which I pointed out a little
earlier in the Q&A, which is basically a great place to go for
information or for learning about stuff.
That's in the series.
There's discussion board.
You can ask questions on a coding resources page, that's ports to
Linux, and mac, and a bunch of other resources.
You might want to check out there.
There's an episode guide for catching up on the past episodes and
there's also the schedule which is posted here every day.
Basically it's posted on Monday for the whole week so you can see when
the different Broncos going to be.
So that's it.
I highly recommend checking it out, if you get a chance.
That is it for today.
Again.
Hope see you tomorrow at 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time.
And yeah, for anyone who's new to Vector math.
I hope that was a pretty reasonable introduction and that you will
take a little time to play around with it yourself and see, just how
easy it can be to sort of ease yourself into it.
And then, you'll be surprised just how far we can go with taking
little baby steps.
Just along along the way, all the math will suddenly start to pile up
and it'll be like, whoa.
I know all this math.
Now.
Alright, so, thank you everyone for joining me and I hope to see you
tomorrow.