Okay, hello everyone.
And welcome to another episode of handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
We are doing some debug interface code right now.
And at this point, we have done a little bit of work with the layout
stuff.
I like to do a little bit more of that today.
And I think today, I'd also like to kind of dive in a little bit to
see how we're going to maybe start working with with the interface to
our profiling code because one of the big things like I said that I'd
like to do with the Steal.
Interfaces be able to quickly sort of get around in the data that we
have.
And the profile code is the best example, right now of a big old pile
of data, that we really don't get very much from because we don't have
a way to really display it.
It captures a lot of data and we are not super able to process it in
any particularly useful way.
For no reason other than we just don't have an interface that allows
us to get into it quickly.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead and start working on
that and we can sort of use that to drive the improvements to the
interface system that we've created.
Because that system at this point, actually has most of the
fundamental pieces in place.
We just haven't actually had a chance to refine them to the point
where they do the stuff that we might need them to do, right?
So let's go ahead and keep going with that today is day 2 01.
If you are going to follow along at home, please unzip day, 200 source
code into a directory so that you can follow along with it.
Okay, let's open up a little command prompt.
Let's see where we're at.
Let us see.
Let us see, let's open up handmade debug and get everything.
Built here is where we were last time and we had just done some work
on, like, you know, making like this sort of stuff a little bit more
systemic, you know, we now use the same interactions for everything
and we have a little layout code that leads these things out
automatically, another kind of fun things like that.
And so now
We'd like to do is kind of start thinking about what we can do with
these things in order to make stuff a little more useful, a little
more interesting and like I said there's a couple things I want to
look into.
So like one of them for example is is being able to do something like
take this just you know, very rudimentary display that we have going
here.
And you know, we'd like to be able to figure out some way to like do
more with it, right?
And so figure out how we're going to make this interface work, which I
don't like I said don't really know how we're gonna do that.
At.
Oh dear.
What is what is going on here?
First chance exception.
What is the first chance exception.
So some invalid record.
It is, in fact an invalid record.
What is this code?
This is the draw profile code indeed.
Indeed, it is
I'm not sure why.
Would we be getting
One of the well.
So I will say that at the moment.
I don't think we're all in debug money.
We're not at all protected from this sort of stuff because we don't
save any of these strings right there.
Just things that are sort of already being transiently dealt with
When the dll reloads I think we are probably easily susceptible to
something where someone could remove a debug record out from under us.
Because at the moment anyway,
I'm see if I'm correct about this at the moment.
Anyway, I think.
Yeah, so when we call game update and render is when they're going to
be drawn and the time that they got, so the time that they actually
got updated, right, is down in here.
So debug frame end.
So in between debug frame and and when they are actually drawn, we
could actually have exactly that happen, right?
We could have the executable get sort of reloaded, it could get
reloaded right in here.
Where is that right here?
So, I again, nothing.
I've super care about too much, although I don't know.
Yeah, it's not something I super care about too much because again, it
is debug code, although it might be nice when we're kind of just
tightening things up here.
But to just go like okay you know we probably could have could avoid
that pretty easily by just making sure that the way that our debug
code works is a little cleaner.
And I had a pretty good idea about how to do that.
Actually, I thought about this the other day I was just kind of
randomly thinking about it and what I realized is that it's kind of
stupid that we do our debug stuff in two different places.
Like the reason that that's happening, you know, this part does the,
the frame and sort of collation and all that kind of nonsense, right?
But, you know, we put the rendering in game update and render, right?
So game update and render
Is actually the place where we do the rendering and we did it that way
because that's, you know, where we render everything else.
But what I was realizing is we really don't need to do that for any
real reason we could if we wanted to make it so that where we do the
debug frame and we also do the debug overlay at that point, right?
And since we don't super care.
Also where things are?
We are frame.
Beats are actually totally decoupled for where we process.
Is the frame and stuff.
We could just move this up above the display, right?
So we could move it right here.
And just have it draw directly on to the screen itself, right?
You know, I'm just going to do that.
I thought it was a good idea at the time.
I think it's a good idea now I think I'm just going to do it.
I think it's better.
It simplifies things and I'd like to see how it goes, you know.
Interest me, I'm interested in it.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to, you know, literally just take
this this debug stuff here.
I'm going to take that and I'm just going to straight up move it,
right?
It's just going to go up here.
So before it does the the frame, wait stuff, you know, right in here.
This is where our debug stuff happens, right?
So there's debug collation, any Theory.
I think this will still just run, right?
All we've done is just make a slight change in where the things were,
but nothing else should
Change, right?
And so if I then said, okay, debug frame end
Instead of having game update in render, be the thing that calls.
Everything, what I could do is say, Okay, game update and render is
here and it is taking like this buffer to draw to, I could just pass
this stuff to, to debug frame end as well, right?
So, I could just do this.
And I like this, a lot more.
This interests me a lot because this means that now the debug system
can be totally isolated, it doesn't have any hooks in the game at all.
So the game just writes to the buffers and then the debug System picks
them up later and that's just a much cleaner thing than what we were
doing before you can see in here, we're actually calling this like
debug stuff right in here, right?
And I don't really like that.
I don't like that idea and I don't want to do that.
Now, there is one problem with it.
Which we'll get to in a second.
But yeah, I'm going to take a look here and just grab the rest of
this.
So we just the only other thing we do is just debug end, right?
So all I'm going to do for starters is I'm going to get rid of the
debug start in the debug, and for now,
They're gone.
And then I'm going to go ahead and say that in handmade debug where
we've got debug start and debug.
And I'm just going to say that this stuff is just happens as part of
the as, you know, as sort of part and parcel of the actual code down
here where we call debug frame end, right?
So I'm going to move those down there and I'm going to take a look at
them.
Where is my debug?
And there it is going to grab that.
I'm going to move that down as well.
So now we've got essentially, these are the two things that we're
going to do, right?
You can see them here.
And so, all I need to be able to do is call these as part of this
single debug front frame and that we do here, okay?
So let's see how hard that would be to do if I wanted to, I have to
call it this way, right?
And I'm going to pass the debug state in here as well because now,
these are not blind, calls, their calls from inside the system, right?
So, I can go ahead and
And put those to good use, right?
I can say.
All right, I'll just pass that in.
So basically what this guy does is he just kind of initialize some of
this stuff, these things are really to be honest with you stuff that
we probably don't get a lot of this stuff is stuff.
We could simplify a little bit but it will ignore some of that for
now, just in the interest of sort of merging these two things first.
So if I were to call this from in here, when we go ahead and see if
we've got it.
And we look at, you know, a look at what's going.
Going on here when we're about to actually do stuff.
I feel like we probably want to do it like this.
We'd say right here.
Here's the whip.
Here's the height.
Here's the assets.
Here's the debug State, you know.
and you can see right now, the only problem we're going to have is
this guy because everything else we've got
All right, and debug end is actually much simpler debug end.
Just needs the input and and that draw buffer, that is all stuff that
we will have.
And so I could do that, right?
I could do it like this and we could see what happens there, right?
I don't know.
Technically, if we want restart collation, that might be something we
want to have happen beforehand, but I don't know.
I feel like this stuff, it's kind of should be get cleaned up a little
bit.
Now that we are going to do it all in one pass.
I think we could make it simpler.
It was a little janky before because there are multiple like
Places in which people were coming in and I think we can kind of get
rid of a lot of that.
And so now, you know, handmade debug doesn't have to have any these
things don't have to get exported, right?
They can just not be there at all.
I don't actually know why refresh collation was there.
I know we were using that in certain circumstances.
I don't know why it's in the h-file necessarily because nobody else is
calling it.
So, really I feel like that, you know, shouldn't really be there.
Probably, that was probably just a
Sort of hanging thing.
All right, so if we go come over to handmade dot CPP, then really all
we need to do is have a way of getting the trance State assets out,
right?
So what we could do here if we wanted to is, we can just have a way of
make of allowing the about system access to the assets, so that the
debug system calls into the game instead of the other way around,
which is much better in my opinion.
Because usually, instead of having the game, call out to the debug
system, it's way better at the deal existen, just reaches into the
game.
Because that way, you know that if you compile out the debug system,
nothing is happening.
The game doesn't ever like talk to the debug system if the debug
system that comes in and looks at the game and that's usually a lot
better, it makes it a lot simpler to separate them.
Come shift timing when you're trying to strip out anything that you
don't actually want to be in there,
Okay, so I'm going to pretend, we've just got to think here that's
like got the game assets or whatever and it's like get game.
Or like debug get game assets like that, right?
And that's just the thing which, you know, you go ahead and you pass
the game memory.
And it just like looks at the transient storage Direction directly.
We could say that there's the assets here and assuming that it's
initialized, it, just all it does is just grab it out.
Right.
So now
The debug system can just reach in there and grab it and that's all it
has to do.
So it looks like that would be all we would need to get the game
assets.
We have the game memory and then the width height draw buffer, an
input stuff is all stuff that we actually should be getting past now.
Right?
So we have it went 3-2 handmade for passing these things in.
So all we have to do is and handmade platform, make sure that the
input and that draw buffer, both get past, right?
So it's really just making making it.
So that game update and render is really, you know, debug frame.
End this thing right here is really just going to be the exact same
call structure as
Didn't render, you know I'm saying?
We could really call this debug update and render or something like
that if we wanted to, or even you might imagine.
So if we have the buffer then that means that really we just need to
take a look at at handmade dot CPP where we Define draw buffer.
You can see how we do things here, there's really not that much to it.
And so all we have to do is make our own same version here where we're
going to just create a full-screen buffer out of the thing to draw to
write and we already know from the off-screen buffer, we already know.
This stuff, right?
We know the width and the height.
So really all we have to do is right before we're about to draw it.
We can just do something where we go ahead and set the width height,
the pitch in the memory like this, have it drawn to that, and be done.
So I think that probably gets us into position to do what I wanted,
which is to have it be just a totally separate thing.
Alright, so let's take a look here.
Probably should make that a semicolon not a:.
Clean up the compile, errors.
Let's see.
Missing semicolon you are correct sir.
I am debug end functions.
Not take three arguments.
Is that is that really true?
I think that is true but I want it to take three three parameters.
There's that third parameter.
Okay so that
Little bit better there.
Okay, so yeah, starting to look a bit better.
What's going on with buffer cure is buffer something that only occurs
inside?
Yeah.
So I want to make sure that we actually have this buffer so that
people can write to it later.
And now I think we're in better shape.
All right.
So let's see here, debug gets state is having a problem.
It's not happy.
Why is it not happy?
Because it's not initialized yet when we get there and I guess that
makes sense because debug start is being called here.
So I like I said, that's just kind of a result of collapsing this
code.
So I need to reorganize it just slightly just very
Slightly right?
So what I can do?
Now, in fact, debug gets State, I want to stay at this point.
Who is calling that actually
Because all of these people, this is kind of weird.
Now, at this point, all of these people this stuff is never supposed
to actually go into that debug State stuff.
Yeah,
we don't really need this feature anymore.
So it's a little wonky, but what I'm going to do here is, I'm just
going to take debug start, going to take this stuff, I'm just going to
go ahead and put that in here because we really don't need this as a
thing anymore.
So what I can do here instead is is right here.
Well actually.
Yeah.
See here, let me see.
Well, I should really have to do is just do this right there, right?
so in debug start, before I call it
I should be able to just do this, right?
So we'll get it directly out here.
You going to start that it's initialized because we know that it's
not.
So we'll just go ahead and do this.
And then I think we are in better shape.
Yeah.
Okay, so now, I think we're in better shape.
And I think, also, we would have fixed that bug.
Yeah.
Which is that now, the executable can't get reloaded in between the
times that we collate and display.
And again, that's not really a bug that would affect the game at all.
It's just a debug thing, but it's nice to not have bugs in it, because
if we have bugs in the debug code, then you're less likely to use the
debug code.
And the whole point of the debug code is should be nice to use, right?
You're trying to encourage its use because it is there to help you
find bugs and help.
You see bugs, you might not see otherwise, right?
So I think that's roughly what we would want.
I think that's all fine.
And so I think we're, at least, I'm pretty okay with that.
Okay.
So that was a good change.
We still let you know, structurally speaking, this stuff can still
stand to be improved quite a bit more.
We still have not moved to like a rolling buffer or something for
doing that collation stuff.
So we still have that frame.
Robe annoyingness.
So there's some stuff there that I'd really like to do at some point
too.
But, you know,
One step at a time, but that's a good.
That's a really good.
Change that we've made there.
I'm really happy about that because now it means that pretty much
people are only ever, you know, doing sort of basic writing to
debug buffers and they're never calling into the actual debug system
per se, right.
Which is what I kind of wanted to make sure that they weren't doing
it.
I don't really like the game to be able to do that.
Now, I'm wondering to game debug dot h.
So all this stuff, I kind of feel like none of this stuff should be
necessary for anyone anymore.
I feel like handmade debug .h, I feel like can
Just start to go away would be my next question, right?
And there was do we have to even have that in there?
And I'm, so I'm just wondering, right?
I'm just wondering about that.
So, let me go ahead and take a look at handmade debug variables dot h.
Whereas that included,
Right.
Let's take a look here and my do both variables.
These are both in handmade, debug dot CPP and that I assume handmade
debug dot CPP is at the very end perfect.
Okay.
So now you can see what I've sort of done here, which I really like
this means that basically, at the very end of our entire compilation
unit, we include the debug code which means if we didn't want it at
all,
We should be able to get rid of it entirely and you can see that I've
done that right there, right?
And the only link era that we get, is the fact that debug game frame
end is not defined, and we set it was supposed to be exported.
Now, that's perfect.
That's exactly what I want to see because that means all of this,
debug code can just go away with an absolute triviality, right?
All I would have to do is this
Okay?
And now if handmade internal were to be switched off.
Like, so we would have absolutely, because, I don't actually remember
what what this is actually supposed to return should probably check.
Debug table a debug table, huh?
So I'm just going to return.
0 is the debug table.
How about that you like that?
If people don't like having Zero Turns debug table, they better buckle
up because it's gonna happen.
So, yeah, I'm sorry showing a global debug table that I believe.
Would go away with handmade internal as well.
So I feel like we don't, in fact, you know what?
Let's just go for it, I'm in the mood.
I am in the mood for this, so let's take build up at we have handmade
internal and it's zero, right?
So I would like to see what happens if I turn that off.
I also don't know handmade profile.
Well, it doesn't really matter.
So anyway, handmade internal, I'm going to turn that off and I want to
go through and kind of get rid of the stuff that we don't, that we
don't use anymore or won't have any more, right?
So handmade internal
Because we never really done this, right?
So let's see, do you prepare for file memory?
These are all internal.
Right?
Seaweed entire file, execute system, command and get processed State.
There we go.
Debug free file memory.
So all these guys are handmade internal.
And then we just have the global debug table.
So the global debug table is just something that's in platform.sh
global table.
And so I believe all we would have to do for that is just to make sure
that all of this stuff right would go away in if we were doing
handmade internal you know I'm saying.
So I think that that just means.
Yeah the only things really we would do there is to just say if you
know handmade internal
We have all these and if not, then we don't right.
and I believe,
So the interesting thing about this is I believe it's actually it's
kind of a little tricky.
We have.
I wonder if maybe we should try to reduce the number of these.
We have like we have handmade profile and handmade internal.
I'm wondering if we just want handmade internal to be like just
The only thing.
You know what I mean?
I feel like maybe we do.
Let me take a look at this and made profile because it just might be a
little bit too much.
It might be like a bit of an orgy of switches.
Yes, I think handmade profile is going to go away for now.
So handmade profile will go away.
Goodbye.
And then we just have handmade internal handmade slow.
Handmade win32.
That's it.
So this is like the platform.
This is whether or not you have like assertion that stuff and this is
whether or not you have stuff like debug output.
That seems good to me at least for now, right?
okay, so in here we would have you know if handmade internal, what is
this else end if doing here, which
And lift are there.
It's going on there.
Okay, I just added that.
So what we want to do is want to get rid of this and then we want to
have the else in here.
Okay.
So that's all good.
Global debug table that isn't win32 handmade and that is only if
handmade internal
And the same is true here.
So, when we do our Global debug table, like, unload code, and all that
sort of stuff, looks like we don't have to do any of that either.
Let's see, frame marker.
So we'll have to do that one and if handmade turtle
So it's a little spammy, we could probably stand to clean some of that
stuff up, but on the whole now we can at least more cleanly compile
everything out.
There we go.
All right, so let's see if we could run, okay?
And we can
So that's all nice.
And now, let's make sure we can turn it all back on.
There we go.
And run it.
Lovely.
I've got a fix our camera here.
I don't know why we left our debug camera on there.
I was kind of playing with that a little bit.
So let's let's go ahead and not do that, because that's not really
what we wanted at all.
So, alright, so there we go.
So that's using the current state of things.
And then we can turn off him and turn all and then we can run.
And now we are back to running the game regular.
Perfect.
Yeah.
So I'm reasonably happy with that that seems pretty good and we will
go ahead and exit out.
Okay.
So yeah I think that's a good thing I think having handmade profile
him an internal might have just been a little bit too much.
I mean it's already a little too much.
I feel like Adventure Ali.
We could simplify that down a bit so we don't have quite so many
pound.
If handmade internals in various places you know there's some things
we could do to kind of simplify that a little bit and that's probably
something that we would want to do.
But for now
It's fine.
Okay?
So that's all good.
And we still have about a half hour here.
So even though I chose to go on that detour, we still have actually a
fair bit of time, so we should probably kind of come back now and take
a look at what we could do with our profiling stuff or are you know,
let's just whatever the next logical thing is to do here to move this
sort of stuff forwards a little bit, right?
So yeah, we've got got a couple things to do.
So let's just think about this just briefly, right?
Let's just think about this guy and think about how we might want to
deal with with what's going on here.
Right now, you know, we've got a thing.
This is like a, this is like basically frame bars and, you know, we
don't we kind of got rid of our, debug menus, and all that stuff.
So the first thing that I'm kind of thinking of is, you know, we had
that little radial menu thing in there that we sort of did briefly.
But that we never really did much to.
And what I'm thinking now is, I think, now that we sort of have this
state, we got this sort of stuff working where we've got these little
guys, and we also have the ability to do, you know, kind of the tear
off stuff.
We kind of got the ability to sort of set up debug things a little bit
here.
What I'd like to do is I'd like to add some kind of a debug interface
sort of a thing where we can where we can actually sort of.
Now, do the thing.
I was saying where I want like the right Mouse button to be like a
clutch that comes on and you can get at some features and stuff.
Because like remember we had a thing where we've got these guys
streaming by, we want to be able to like stop and investigate a
profile without it recording any more data you know.
I mean, and so that's the sort of stuff that I want to sort of maybe
get into now.
Okay.
So I'm trying to think of what the easiest way to do that is so like,
if you think about how this would be working, you know, I want to kind
of have something where, you know, maybe like these guys, maybe
there's a bunch of debug interface, sort of stuff that happens, like,
these guys have buttons or something in them, that you can click on to
do stuff like action buttons.
And some of those action, buttons would be things like, you know,
pause, pause the running game or whatever, that sort of stuff.
You know what I mean?
And then we would have this notion that certain groups are like, when
you, when you like, go into the clutch mode, those groups expand, and
when you go out of the clutch mode, those groups collapse again.
So that way like some of these groups would be expanded all the time
and some of the wouldn't be so I think that's what I'd like to do in
order to do that.
I think we
Address.
Now, the thing that I was talking about before where we sort of have
this problem of when you duplicate things, or when you use another,
when you three try to make another one of those debug car keys, you
have this problem, where the state of the hierarchy and stuff isn't
actually copied, it's just kind of a reference and that's a pretty
easy thing.
I think for us to well, it's not that easy but, you know, it's, it's
not a huge deal for us to start looking into that.
That's not, it's not a really big deal.
So if you remember the way the stuff works, we have these debug
variables and the debug variables have stuff in them.
Right there can be like a group of things, could be a bitmap display,
can be a counter thread list, it could be whatever, right?
And then we have debug variable references and debug variable
references or kind of like these sort of other things and they're sort
of like a shadow of the hierarchy there sort of the thing that
controls the hierarchy.
But if you notice we kind of have them.
They're kind of smushed together a little bit because if
if you look at what,
Ends in the debug variable, right?
We've got a debug variable group and the debug variable group is the
thing that actually has these like child pointers in it.
So, I think what we want to do instead is we want to move that
variable reference sort of concept.
We want to move this, debug variable group up entirely into the debug
variable reference completely, right?
Meaning we want we want this.
Does that make sense so that all of
Of the meta information about that structural stuff is all in the
variable reference and there's no such thing as a debug variable group
in the actual, like variables themselves, the variables themselves are
nothing.
They are just data right there.
Just the data of the thing, whatever that thing is right in order to
do that.
I think what probably what we'd want to do is we actually, you know, I
would suspect.
Actually want a mirror like a like a traffic of the right wrist right
here.
We probably won't like a split right?
We want debug variables and then we want a hierarchy that's on top of
the debug variables and so things for example like the size that a
bitmap is being displayed would be like separate from the concept that
there is a debug variable which is a bitmap that should be displayed.
You know what I mean?
So we kind of want to split these out into something.
You know.
That's, that's, that's just not doing a very good job explaining it.
Maybe I should draw it on the Whiteboard, just so it's a little bit
clearer.
Of course, drawing it on the Whiteboard will take a while because we
did not open up our whiteboard thing it and it takes a while for it to
load it.
Let me see, Miss Chief Blackboard.
So while that's loading, I'll just keep going.
For a second, right?
So we have a debug variable and like one of the examples would be
maybe like the the debug bitmap display thing.
You know, it sort of has in the debug bitmap display.
It has two different sorts of information in it.
It's got the dimensions and whether or not you want to display with
Alpha.
We're just like random attributes.
We chose to assign, but then it also has the ID.
The ID would actually be the piece of information, actually being
debugged.
Right.
But the other things are really just a property of that display into
the data.
You know what I mean?
So I think what we would rather do here is we would rather have some
sort of a way of splitting that out so that we don't have, you know,
two pieces of information that armor that are fused together in that
way.
Okay, I guess so.
Maybe I don't need the black graph.
That maybe that's clear enough.
What I'm saying?
Hopefully it is, I don't
and furthermore, we could even probably do that in a way that, you
know,
Maybe isn't we could almost imagine doing that in a way that's not too
heavily typed, you know.
So we could have something like, you know, we've got a debug kind of
want a better names to these guys.
Like, I kind of want, like, debug hierarchy or debug debug tree and
debug tree entry or something like that, right?
And I'm
Thinking that maybe these guys, we could probably even collapse these
things a little bit more to be completely honest with you.
And that might be something worth doing right because it's unclear
whether we really need multiple things of those.
But yeah, so let's see.
In fact, I might just try to do that.
Just even in this just this, this pass directly.
So suppose we have a debug tree
Entry group.
And that's the thing that would have, you know, the first and last
child in it, it would have the expanded.
Like so, and it might even have something, you know, like like, like,
if you to pee, and maybe that's a bit fatty.
Because maybe it's not always use or something like this.
And then in the tree entry thing, you know, we've got a pointer to the
variable, but then we've also got that Union, so that we can get in at
the, the other data here, right?
So we have the group, there's that next pointer.
Okay, and yeah.
And so, we've got the group there.
We have probably want a debug, you know, probably actually, it would
go right in here, right?
So we'd have a debug tree.
Yeah, in fact, I think this would just work, we'd have a debug tree.
The debug tree would have a debug tree entry, that was like the group
for it, right?
And it would just be one of these.
I think I feel like, I don't know, we'll find out.
So sometimes it's a tree, sometimes it's a group, right?
And then again, sometimes it's a
Let's see, I would need the VIP.
We have that they're correct.
I could actually just name the same things for Less confusion.
We have the group and we don't need the next in the previous probably
because it already has a next pointer, right?
So yeah we can just piggyback on top of that, I would think we're
using a sentinel for that one.
So yeah, I mean, I don't know if we want to switch up how that's
doing.
Haven't thought about too much.
We're going to leave it for now.
This would go away.
So that.
Yeah, we'd have debug tree we'd have debug tree group.
I guess this is something that looks like that, or
Naming these rabbit weird.
If this is a gibbet re-entry, I've got to entry like a subtree, write
a 3 or a group.
Yeah.
Of course, now that I say it now I'm saying it out loud.
I also don't know how useful that actually is because you can't like,
do you ever actually want to put trees in the middle of their so that
may just have been dumb, right?
I mean, I think about it.
It's like
I kind of got overzealous compressing that down but it's like why
bother like there was nothing.
You can't have a tree show up in the middle so that just seems kind of
stupid in my mind.
So I think it's probably more like this.
You just have the entry group and you have a debug tree entry, you
know?
Bitmap or maybe I should say like window something like that.
And so anybody, for example who just wants like a dim, this sort of a
thing can just use that, right?
And they won't have to, you know, they won't have to worry about about
actually defining it.
Some other kind of thing that's in there.
So, just be like a debunked re-entry like, you know, just just a
little like that's the window, seems guess.
It seems kind of fine to me.
So we have groups in Windows and then we just have like regular
variables and in fact, I guess we don't even need to Define what
Wouldn't have any actual parameters, I don't think.
And then this stuff would kind of get rid of some of these things.
So we wouldn't have anything in the profile settings at the moment
because well, I'll leave it in there but we don't actually have
anything so be more like in place holder, right?
Because we'll probably want something there eventually but that seems
roughly roughly more in line with what I wanted, right?
So then we have a debug variable type and now we have a second type
that sits on top of it for our tree entries.
So we have a debug tree entry type
I'm the diva tree entry type.
It's just going to be.
The one that we had there.
So it would be something like Liberty type like a variable or like a
basic variable something like that.
Then we'd have group and we have window and I think that's really all
we would have right because that's all we actually have in there at
the moment and these guys would all go to like debug tree entries.
Debug yeah, Tree on trees everywhere else.
So now you can see what I did there very very simple stuff.
I just kind of massage it around a little bit so we have essentially
two parallel sets of information, we have debug variables which are
just going to be any variables that someone
Expect can inspect and stuff like that.
And those can be sort of like, you know, created by the, by the
running application as necessary or we can create them, however, we
want to write and then we can, you know, sort of put something on top
of them that knows how to inspect those things as we go, you know what
I mean.
And that way we can have multiple trees viewing the same sets of
information but viewing them in different ways which is sort of what
we wanted to do here, right?
Right?
So if I go ahead and do this, especially just going to be cleaning up
all the compile errors that this creates, but to basically will make
exactly the same thing.
And then when we do our clone, we would just do is essentially like a
deep copy of this, you know, of this information, right?
And that's really all that we would need to do.
So, let's go ahead and start that it might take a while, right?
So we've got our debug tree entry here.
We have to pre declare that because we're creating a linked list of
them in the entry group.
Okay, we have our debug variable hierarchy that is now called a debug
tree.
Just kind of simplified that name started typing hierarchy.
It's too hard to spell man.
It's too hard to spell.
So there we go.
I could probably just do hierarchy becomes tree.
I'm guessing battle just work.
Pretty much everywhere.
Yeah.
Yep.
Pretty much good.
Okay, so, variable references, this is just a debug tree.
And I guess well it's not really debug tree, to be honest, right?
It's actually just a debug tree entry.
I suppose is the route group and then the debug tree tree, Sentinel I
think that's actually more correct.
So when we're doing these definitions, this would just be a debunked
re-entry that it's pointing to and that would be whatever the group
was right?
And I suppose debug variable reference.
So, debug variable reference is actually going to be like debug
At re-entry.
I think that's pretty much straight straight ahead port.
Right.
Okay.
All right.
So what we need to do now is when we're creating these, we sort of
have again, two sorts of things that we're doing here, right?
To sorts of things that are going to get to be created.
We're going to create the debug variables themselves.
And then we're also going to create the hierarchy that like, you know,
inspects those, right?
That kind of looks into those
Which again is kind of annoying, right?
It'd be nice if you didn't have to do that, but at the same time,
there's not a lot of ways that we can get around that.
Now there are some ways actually, it's
so enough that we can kind of get around that and that's if you use a
system that's you know, more about sort of cashing a caching Centric
system which, you know, to be honest we could in fact try to use
It looks basically the same as this but the iterators are decoupled.
Should think about way, maybe if we do want to do something like that
just to show at Sun.
It's a little more unusual than what I'm about to do right now with
with just manually, creating the hierarchy itself.
Basically what it entails is, you know, you you just look up into a
table to see what the state of something is rather than keeping it
around.
Mmm-hmm, it certainly is a bit tempting.
I feel like it's maybe a little more interesting because hopefully you
see what I was going to do is create those two.
I think it might be a little more interesting, if I didn't do that.
to be completely honest with you,
I think I might, I think I might go to cashing route.
I think I might do it.
Alright, so here's how that would change.
I think it's a little more interesting and honestly, it's a little
more powerful to so might as well if we're showing how to do this
stuff, we might as well show how to do this stuff.
So the way you do, right, the way that I was going to do this right?
As we have a tree that store as you know, the it's literal, it's
what's on their right?
And then we have the debug variables and I pulled the gripping stuff
out of there so that you could have like you know, different groups
that sort of thing.
But when you think about it all the rest of this stuff is really just
just data.
That's kind of like the
Sides.
The the actual like fact that you created a group, all the rest of the
stuff is really just properties that are for a given tree and a given
piece of debug information for Giving Tree into given debug variable.
It's just telling you you know what what the sort of viewing
parameters were for that thing, right?
So if we wanted to, we could instead just make it so that
Each of those debug variable things just looks up into a table and
says, I'm in this tree, and here's the debug variable, I'm looking at,
how should I format it, right?
Like, what should I do?
Like what, you know, what would I do to this debug variable in that
case, in order to like, you know I'm I know that this is a bitmap or
something.
So I want the the data that comes back for that, right, whatever that
is.
So, in that case, you would still have something like this.
But instead of it being like a debug tree entry, you you'd back off a
bit from that.
And you'd say something like, okay, I have, you know, I have something
like debug
very,
View type.
or just debug view type, even
Right?
And then what's in here, is those synthetic variables.
So like the debug view like a basic sort of maybe you know and I don't
know, maybe Windows a little bit grandiose so maybe we just call it
like a block like we're just viewing it as like a little inline-block,
right?
We could even call it, just just that debug view, inline block and
all.
Its got some Dimension, like, how big did you want to see that thing?
Right?
And so we have debug view type, like, you know, you know, basic
debugging type inline block or something like that.
And that's really it.
You know what I mean?
So we just have debug View inline-block.
And then we just have debug few basic with doesn't have any additional
information on it at.
All right.
Nothing at all.
So then we would just say, okay, the tree information in so much as
that still exists is now still considered a debug variable, meaning
the structural the piece, that structural that part we still keep in
the variables themselves, right?
And the reason that we do that is because that's actually sort of a
thing that the user is then creating the structure like the the actual
tree is actually just something that we want to keep that something
that we think is valuable.
And, you know, if they made a little window, we want it to always
Say around and we don't want it to get like addicted or anything like
that.
Wish, I had more lemonade, but it don't.
So anyway you know inside the debug variable or whatever it will
actually have whatever needs to happen in terms of lists or that sort
of thing will actually be in here.
And the way that I'd like to do that at the moment is I'd like to make
this thing.
Be some kind of an iterator that works a little more, smartly trying
to think of how exactly I want to do that.
I'm going to say, I'm going to say
That's well, you know what?
For the moment.
I'm going to say that we just have something really kind of
rudimentary, which is, you know, inside debug variable, we would have
a debug variable, or debug variable list or array.
And it would just have like a count maybe and debug variable star
vars, right?
So it just has like this notion that we have some set of variables in
here, you know?
That's it.
And so, one of the things that debug variable can be now is it could
be a list, right?
So it could be a variable list or just a list, maybe carlist, I don't
know, something like that.
And in here, we would have debug variable list.
Sorry, Ray.
Bareilles.
Probably should have called it a wrap their huh?
And so now, you know, like people can build write their own arrays of
debug variables and put them in here and that's all fine.
And like I said, that's going to be part of the actual.
It's like, considered legitimately part of the debug information that,
you know, gets gets capped for now, that's what we're going to say.
And then inside here, you know, got the debug variable array.
And that will actually, you know, produce those, those variable sets,
we could even cheese out on that.
We wanted to we could make those be something that was a fixed size.
Like you can only have a few of them or something like this, I don't
even know but point being that's you know how that would work.
Okay.
So assuming that
Assuming that we leave it that way.
Yeah there's no way that I'm going to have this change done by in 7
minutes and I think but I think it's probably the better way to go.
So in this case we've again switched it over then to these are going
to be like ways of viewing, the thing debug View.
And it's probably just a debug view.
I guess in that sense and instead, what we would always have here is
some way of getting back to what it actually was that we were viewing.
So it'd be like a variable and a tree would probably be what it would
be like, you know, looked up on and we would just have some hash table
that hashes these things together.
And then gets, you know, it back for a says, like, oh, cure is the,
you know, here's the debug view that corresponds to that thing, right?
And then we have the debug tree which would remain pretty much
entirely the same and that would just point to a variable that's like
the route.
Of the tree, right?
So that's the the route group.
So I think that's it.
I think it's really that simple, so it's not a huge change from what
we had before.
So I kind of like backed off on wine create that superstructure for
everything.
And instead we just lazily sort of cash, those things by putting them
into some kind of a hash table, right?
And so, then what we have is inside the hash and we could make it here
so that in the debug view, right?
We have something where we just kind of, you know,
Do something like a debug View.
next in hash,
and so these settings, they would kind of just
They just kind of like chain onto whatever the hash was, right?
So as we got new ones off, they would go and that's pretty much it.
I think that's really all that I think we'd have and so in the debug
State, we would have a hash of these views.
So in addition to the tree Sentinel, right, we would have a debug
View and we would have the view hash and inside the view Half, I guess
we just say like, okay we just have you know, some some set of these
however, many some big old, hash worth of those and we just look up
things in there and then be it, right?
So let's see.
Okay.
So we've got to fix some of this stuff, we've got, debug view, we've
got which tree it's in.
That's going to have to be pretty cleared, right?
So, we've got a debug tree.
This stuff again, is going to kind of go away.
We've got expanded, right?
Oh and that is something we have.
So the debug view for a particular variable, we'd have a Nema, debug
view.
This was the thing we want to do.
Originally was change the, you know, make sure that the expansion
state was stored per thing that would just be a debug view collapsible
or whatever.
Right now, it's got one of these things in it.
Something like that, right?
And we'd probably have it, the something like, okay it's you know,
expanded expanded, always or expanded in in expand it in right.
Click in alt view.
I don't know whatever you want to call it, so we'd have this
collapsible
And that's another type of thing that you could have.
Right.
So I feel like that
And there'd be one of those for every one of those sort of array,
guys, in the tree.
So something like that.
Seems reasonable to me again.
I don't know about the VAR a thing, whether I want it to be that way
or not, but it seems again pretty reasonable.
So I think I'll just leave it that way.
All right, so I'm going to take a look at a few more compiler errors,
before we go.
Oops, it's not supposed to be an enum that is supposed to be a struct.
Yeah, and even tree entry does not exist anymore, debug tree and do
the variable or the two things that exist.
And so yeah, this is just a debug variable, that's the route group.
And this is just do the variable that's the route group as well.
Okay.
So now you know the nice thing about that too is that now we don't
have the concept of variable references and variable separately we
only have variables.
That's the only thing we would have.
So we pretty much only have to do we don't have to do any of this
stuff, right?
This is really just a thing that will would add as we're adding it
would add those variables to an array as we build that that sort of
Set right.
And that's all it does.
So if we want to take this system, right?
We could just say like okay you know we're going to do debug add
variable there's no such thing as a reference to run reference
variable that's just stuff that that is literally just always going to
happen, right?
So you'd have something in here where you're like okay
Second group breath VAR.
So this set here, right?
Well, I guess if we want, both of them, if we want to add a variable
to a list,
We kind of want to be able to add things to and from a list so I'm not
sure I quite want to collapse those yet so maybe I'll start a little
bit further down, right?
So, yeah, so if I want to do any of these things really, what I need
to do here is this right here would be the array to which they're
being added.
You know what I mean?
So if you called one of these things and you're supposed to be adding
a reference to it, you don't ever really push a struct or anything
like that.
You would just need to make sure that
You added it to the group, right?
Whatever the debug group is here.
So, you know, whatever this thing is.
Where it's got the count and we've got sort of the very here, it just
needs to be able to add things to this, this vars.
You know what I'm saying?
And I'm trying to think of like probably the best way to do that would
actually, not quite be this way.
It would probably be to go something like this, right?
It would be like, oh, you know, VAR count and debug variable star
vars, and we'd have a pointer to know, some crazy number, that's more
than we're ever.
You want to put in a group so you would start this guy out.
You would fill out those vars.
In fact that's already way too big too much it's just too much.
We'd fill out those vars as we go.
And then we go ahead and and push them like we when we were done, we
would go ahead and package them up to put them into the variable
array, right?
We just kind of like slot them in there and again like I said, it's
kind of annoying.
Like this is a place where I'd probably want to use some kind of an
expandable.
Like, I'd rather use some kind of utility class here especially in
debug code.
I'm just not sure.
I actually want to really write one of those that we would then use it
might be Overkill but we could see, you know, maybe we will write one
for that.
It's pretty, you know, it's pretty simple to write obviously but like
I said, I don't know.
That's, that's kind of a, that's kind of an open question.
So anyway, if we were in here we just have like a how many of ours are
there, right?
And when we add these things in, we would just kind of add them to to
the of our slots as we go.
So we don't really have to do any of this sort of more complicated
stuff.
We're you know, we're doing kind of fancy things.
Really all we're going to do is just add them to this thing here.
Ear, right?
So when we call, you know,
And I suppose we could even have a way that to saying whether we
wanted to or not but it's really just something like okay whatever the
context is and I guess we don't quite have a context here when you're
pushing a variable.
Yeah I guess you can still push, you can do a debug, add variable like
that's just straight that will do this and then when you do debug, add
variable reference, I feel like that's actually it's like I said I
don't feel like this
Has ever a thing anymore.
So I'm just gonna get rid of that this one here again, also not a
thing.
When we do debug, add variable with the context, then in the context,
this is the place where we do it.
So it calls into debug add variable this way.
Right?
And then it would go ahead and say, okay, whatever the context of our
count is is going to go up, right?
And we are going to put ourselves into that slot, so you know, the
context vars of that.
VAR count is going to be equal to whichever variable we added.
So now we've got the list of them and that's really all that has to
happen there.
So that would be it.
We would probably want to assert here again that the context of ours
Sighs can hold it.
But that's about it.
Something like that.
Then when we do this stuff, a drupe internal, I don't know.
I don't feel like this stuff actually has to happen anymore.
I don't think it doesn't really super look like you would have to just
because there really isn't much there.
I mean, we can we could do a drupe internal here but I don't really
know.
Yeah, I don't really know if we
A half to do any of this stuff anymore because it was really just when
we do begin variable group.
It was really, it's really, the end variable group part that matters,
right?
So, I think, at least for the moment, I'm going to delete those and
we'll come back to revisit them later.
So I think we can just get rid of those.
Say, you do it doesn't matter.
And off we go.
So we've got the bug, add route group, gonna ignore that.
Debug begin variable group.
That just goes ahead and adds one of these debug variables.
And again, these are all these should all just returned to you about
variables, all of them, right?
Because they don't do anything else now.
So now we've got debug, add variable.
So when we're creating a variable group again, same thing really
really straightforward.
Word.
Now in fact a lot of this code just gets a lot cleaner if we do it
this way.
So that seems like a nice thing but I guess we don't really know to
World we're completely done.
But we just want to add one of these arrays right like so.
Maybe I should still have called those groups but think it's nicer to
change the name it for the moment, just so we can see it and we don't
have to set anything on those except for just that one see here,
variable, debug variable except just that one situation where the the
we need to set the count, right?
20.
So we know there's nothing in it, that's about it.
So yeah, we do debug begin variable group and debug and variable group
that should that should pretty much do it.
Although I just think of there's a little something that's not as good
there.
But anyway, so debug at variable for pool.
These should all just now be the exactly the same as they were there.
Just going to take variables instead like so.
And they get rid of that sort of tree that whole tree thing, which
again, I'm kind of feeling good that I decided not to go down that
route any further because it's just me, I created just too much cruft
in here.
You can see there was or we didn't even really have it all doing the
duplication and it's still which the lot of cruft.
Right?
So yeah, so that's good.
And I think this stuff again.
Nah,
Caring about this at all.
So we're going to get rid of that for now.
Yeah.
So that all looks good.
Let's take a look at that here.
So this is all vars, vars.
No more refs just of ours.
There we go.
Okay.
And all these regards as well.
Nice.
Okay, and let's see.
Anything else we got here and Navarro group?
So yes, at this stuff.
Again now is actually where the work is going to happen.
So when you do an end variable group, you're going to have to take,
essentially off, whatever it was here that you were, you know,
whatever the debug variables are that had piled up right on there and
you know, we could do that.
The thing we could do here is do we could do this in a fairly cheesy
way and make it so that we actually still do.
Do it in the group itself.
You know, something like this.
And the way that you do that
again, I'm not just not sure if this is a good way to go or not, but
the way that you do that is inside when you do the debug begin group,
Like so oops, that's not the one I met in here.
You'd actually allocate
Some amount, right?
You'd allocate some, you know, some some larger than you need amount.
And as you created those groups, they would just be fatty
And again like I said I really just don't know what the right thing is
to do here.
It's one of those things where pretty much because you're just doing a
sort of general like editor style, Behavior thing.
Usually these are the cards that things where you just want more of an
anything-goes attitude, right?
You kind of want to just be like I don't know I allocate the stuff and
I freed the stuff and I don't really pay too much attention to it
because I don't have any actual knowledge of the usage pattern, right?
I don't know what the users going to do with it most of time in.
As we know we're like okay you know, we know that this is going to
happen, we know that that's going to happen.
So you don't tend to want to do stuff where you're just going to be
like, okay, let me allocate this willy-nilly and and not really care
what's going to happen to it.
Because usually, you actually do know.
And then you end up with a lot of stuff that's not necessary, right?
But in this case, it kinda does feel like like, maybe you, you know,
This is the sort of place where I would usually just say it's fine,
right?
Like, I don't I'm not worried about it and it's only it's again like
it's it's only a debug code for the game.
So don't care about their and also, I think it's for editor code.
I'm like it's perfectly appropriate.
I think to say, you don't know what the users going to want to do to
it, so it doesn't really matter.
You're not like creating some kind of Problem by it completely
ignoring how it might be allocated
All right, I think we're basically out of time though.
So I think I may pause this temporarily.
And say that I will just go ahead and turn off and made internal.
And that way the game is still in a compelling State and nobody is
broken if they're trying to play with it, but I can finish up tomorrow
doing that Port over to the new way of handling the variable stuff and
that'll be nice because then we'll be able to actually kind of do a
little bit more of a reasonable kind of organization of things and
they'll be able to store their parameters separately which is what I
wanted.
So you can have
Like more tear off stuff, but I'll go to a brief Q&A here, just in
case.
Anyone has any questions right now?
We're not done yet, so it's probably not really useful to ask a
question quite yet.
But if you do have one, I do actually have Linux has been working long
enough that I would actually be able to see it today, which is
unusual.
So, I will actually be able to see it today.
And so if you do have a question, you can put a colon in front of it
and I will be able to see it.
Insofar as now that the amount of debug code is being larger, when you
create a debug debug system, to debug the debug code?
Well, the debug code is capable of devouring itself actually.
So I think we already have
Right.
in fact, you can see
this whole time.
I don't know if you remember, but we have been timing, the debug
system with the debug system which is kind of nice.
America.
Nobody is this the link you were looking for earlier for Martin Cohen?
Let's take a look.
Let me see.
Okay, so
yes, I think this is
or well.
It may not quite be the one.
In fact you know what no it's I don't think it is necessarily.
Well, maybe it is so II implementing.
The ALU looks like the one I was thinking of
So yeah I think that is or if it's not it's pretty darn close.
It's another similar lecture by him so probably probably good enough
either way
Thank you for finding that.
Gary Johansen, what do you think about the use of prefetch catch
instructions?
Are they a viable option?
For general-purpose programming to get maximum performance?
Will a precache prefetch instruction is exactly what it sounds like.
It's just a way of telling the CPU ahead of time what memory you're
going to touch.
And so if that is a problem, that you have in a particular piece of
code, meaning you're about to load something from memory and you will
stall.
If you can, if you're in like a loop or something, if you can go put
the prefetch, you know, many instructions back, 300 Cycles back
somehow.
So the processor has plenty of Runway to go, oh, I should go fetch
that memory.
Then they were quite well, they don't work.
If you don't have the Insight ahead of time into what member you're
going to touch, right?
So it's all about whether or not, you know, what member you'll touch
ahead of time or if you don't
That's that's really where.
Prefetch instructions, help you and my new prefetch instructions.
Obviously, also only help you if you're not running at memory
bandwidth but most of the time you're not, but if you're running it
can full memory bandwidth.
That a federal judge doesn't do anything because you're already at
maximum memory.
Throughput, there's nothing you can do, it's not the cast so it's only
if the it's only if you're actually strolling on the cash and the
memory is not fully bandwidth is not fully pipelined that that will
help you.
How to rinse after the two-year period, will we be able to mod the
game?
Could you be more specific?
I'm not sure what you mean.
Captain craft.
Does the architecture of your target system?
Have a big effect on how you design your debug system?
No, it does not.
Typically, the debug system is relatively the same, no matter what
sometimes you have to do, like if the debug platform, well there is
one thing, if the target system that you're running on is like really
lame.
Like let's say it's like, you know,
Uh, Nintendo DS or something.
Then you're not going to have like debug overlays probably on that
because you don't want to like use up any of the system resources.
So you just be trying to do something that like, spams out to like, a
debug port and is captured on a different machine or something and
that's where you display all the debug stuff, right?
So like sometimes you might make some decisions about that but on a
full powered machine of some kind you're typically just fine, right?
So sometimes I guess I would say is if the
Platformers like a console or a weak system, you may design your debug
system such that all the debugging actually happens on a different
machine.
And you know, you get that idea, right.
Would be it, an idea to pass built up at a parameter which would use
to switch off turns on and off on the different build units.
Like if lb % 1 equals opted to do this, otherwise do that.
Yeah, you can do that.
I don't really have much of a use for it because I build in the side
of the editor.
And so I want to be able to select set it and then every time I build
it just use whatever my current setting is, so I don't really want to
have it.
Something I pass
But, you know, if you want to do that, you totally could or, you know,
we could hook up.
So emacs set the variable and then pass it or something, but I'm
probably not, you know, certainly do that.
What do you think about no man's Sky?
I have not played no man's sky.
I can't even think about how it works.
Now, will I get some idea after learning from you?
No, man's.
Sky is pretty straightforward, right?
It's a procedural World Generation just in time for the region is the
same as Minecraft in that sense.
Right?
You go somewhere and it basically like issues a, you know, it's sort
of like I need this region of the world at this level of detail and it
comes back.
I mean, I shouldn't say like Mike was my cat, doesn't have a level of
detail, but and then it's like, okay, I'll generate that, right?
You know, it's it's not magic how that's done, we've done those sorts
of things before.
It's more, just like the system power is at the point now where they
can generate things at very high levels of detail, which is kind of
great, right?
Kind of rinse.
I mean after release the source code will, will we be able to create
our own bosses worlds, Etc?
Well, I mean, obviously if you have the source code you can do
anything you want, right?
I mean there's no there's no stopping you with the source code you can
add anything you can that you're capable our programming.
Stegosaurus.
Will you be crying to game?
Civic coding soon?
I don't know.
One of the things I want to also underscore is I
Make sure it's not really supposed to be about showing a particular
specific thing, right?
He made pure is a programming educational stream, so I don't super
like people who are impatient about wanting to see uh particular thing
coding because that just makes it so that we don't spend enough time
on various things that we're trying to learn.
So I'm never going to rush through something.
And since this is all video-on-demand, you know, if it's something
that you're not interested in, you can always just tune out and then
tune back in later when we're doing the thing that you are interested
in, but gameplay coding is actually some of the most boring code that
there is, you know.
It it's really really really basic and doesn't really often have very
much to do.
It's really rudimentary.
It's like scripting a lot of times, right?
So if anything, the more interesting code is stuff like this which is
actually tricky and difficult to do so, you know, getting a UI system
that doesn't take, you know, a hundred thousand lines of code and 50
hours to build like cutie does or something like this is actually the
interesting code.
That's the code that's actually hard in the kind of code that you want
to learn how to do gameplay.
Coding is really, really dumb.
It's like, oh, I moved an object like, you know, I set its position
somewhere or you know, I had it spin around or
Right?
It's really straightforward and it doesn't really do anything all
that, particularly interesting.
So as far as that's concerned, like I don't, I don't particularly feel
any specific need to rush to get to gameplay coding because it's just
not, it's just not as interesting as a lot of the other pieces of
code, right?
Could something like a Raspberry Pi or other arm desktop, PC run,
handmade hear, well enough and is that the kind of system where you
would want to do the debugging on a separate machine?
I think that probably a Raspberry Pi could run handmade hero.
Well enough.
Yes.
But I think we would would definitely well
I don't know.
The new one has a much better processor than the original one did
that, the Raspberry Pi 2.
So I don't know, on the Raspberry Pi 1.
What I was going to say is you definitely couldn't run handmade hero
rendering and software like we're doing now.
You would you would have to use the graphics subsystem on it, right?
Because it's just doesn't have the kind of power that Intel CPU does,
right?
But the new one is a lot better.
It's a fork or and you know maybe maybe you could maybe you wouldn't
do 1080p but
You could so I don't know.
So I don't want to speak too soon.
I've never played with a Raspberry Pi 2.
I don't really know what it's capable of it so I don't want to sort of
like pesum eyes that right?
But
Coming in.
I meant for usage inside the game so you could switch off position on
and off from the debug menu.
Yes, we could totally do that.
That would be really easy actually, because we could I think what we
want,
Do is I think we want to change it so that we use the pragma optimize
trick because then we could just make this be a standard variable
that's in the our variable listing file so we should probably do that.
Let's see.
Do you think it would be totes baller to make a gooey visual language
for games?
Shifting like, what unreal has um you know, I've never been a fan of
visual scripting.
I don't super know what the point of it is because I've always found
it to be.
You just end up with this tons of nodes in this giant mess and like
what did that turn out to be 0.
It's like actually just really only 11 lines of code would have done
that or something, right?
so, you know, you get something that's like
This is what visual scripting feels like to me and this is probably
because I'm a programmer but this is what it feels like, right?
So if you're at Day 2, 01 here we go.
Actually, I guess that's not the heir to a 1.
This is not a on-topic thing, visual scripting usually feels like this
to me, it's like oh in my scripting language, you know, or you notice
the text language, I wanted to write something like, you know, Foo
Arrow Health, you know, two times.
At plus Foo, you know, aim amount or something.
Over, you know, I don't know.
I put it in parentheses and I wrote like / 5, you know?
And I'm going to set that to be like, whatever food is like, you know,
gold is or something, right?
Okay.
I wrote out something like that and it's one line that's really easy
to understand and I can comment right above it and I can say like what
it does if I wanted to in the script in visual quote-unquote scripting
language the stuff ends up being stuff like oh.
Okay.
Like I had to make a driver node with like a 2 in it and then I had
like to make like some kind of like you know, the
I had to pinfu on here and he had a ton of stuff lift listed.
It was like all like that stuff, right?
And then I had to like pipe it.
So I like grab this guy and then I made like a note here that was like
a times node and like the input came from these two things, you know
and then like the output of that went into like a plus node or
something that had two things, you know, when in there and then the
other one came out here and it was like the arm, the aim amount which
was this other thing.
That was like down here you know and then I got to divide it by 5.
So then there's like another driver node here.
That's like the 5 and then there's the
Node and it's like, oh my God, right?
And all of a sudden, you're like, okay, this one line of code that's
trivial for anyone.
Understand is this and what, in God's name is that, you know, so I
can't stand visual scripting languages.
I feel like they're really driving me nuts.
But I don't know like maybe I'm missing the glory of it or something.
Quarter on.
Couldn't you call it just the last frame, every frame instead of doing
all of them in chunks.
Yes.
So the problem the reason that we can't do that right now because that
actually is basically what we're doing right now.
The reason though that we can't just keep doing that because every
frame we only process the latest data but eventually we have to reset
and the reason for that is we don't have a rolling buffer.
So eventually we run out of space to write our data into and we have
to like clear
And then we have to like start all over again to like grab all the old
data.
So it's really just a question of having a circular buffer and then
like the code already works incrementally, it's just that would get
rid of that one time where we like rap, right?
so, that's
I think we're done with cues.
It looks like to me.
I think so.
Looks like it.
All right.
I'ma close this down.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game and it comes to the source code even today when we
are not done with the game, you can go ahead and play around that at
home or do experiments with it or whatever you want.
We also have a patreon page, you can subscribe if you want support the
video series and a forum site where you can go, if you want to ask
questions or do anything like view old episodes or with annotations
stuff like that.
that we also have a tweetbot between schedule,
I could stream live and we will be back here tomorrow for the last
stream of the week.
Actually, because I'm off on Friday.
I will not be around.
I have to catch a flight which is right during streaming time.
So I won't be able to stream but then we'll be back the following
Monday.
So yeah if you want to know the schedule you always check the Tweet
Bop but it'll be 5, p.m.
Pacific Standard time tomorrow.
So daylight time tomorrow.
So I hope you'll come back and join me for that.
We have a bunch of work to do to kind of clean up the way we were
doing those hierarchy things so that I can get us.
System that allows us to do kind of more ridiculous stuff with placing
things around the screen and getting different variables and that sort
of stuff.
So, yeah, we're getting close on having the debug system to be more
where we want to be.
But like I said, it's a little few more days left in that for sure.
And that is a pretty big undertaking, but it's basically writing into
our GUI system, right?
You have to write the whole thing.
We had to write the whole debug log system and write the whole gooey.
It's a pretty big undertaking and that's generally true.
It is definitely the sort of thing that you can reuse, though.
Like if you notice the way that we've been writing it, there really
isn't
Handmade hero specific about it.
You could drop that debug code, pretty much directly anything else.
And the primary thing that's, did, you know, prevents you from
literally just reusing the code, exactly.
As it is, is just that one part where it has to interface with the
rendering, because you do have to go, like, okay, well, you know,
different renderers would have different ways in which to do except
math, but that's really it.
So that's kind of a nice thing to.
It means that once you build one, you can use it on all your products.
You don't have to rewrite it every time because it just doesn't have a
whole lot of specific stuff.
In it.
It's not like you know oh this piece of the code work this way because
handmade hero work that way or you know that sort of thing there just
isn't that much of it.
So that's kind of a nice thing as well.
So even though it is a bit of a Time investment to make one of these,
once you make one, you can reuse them as opposed to maybe certain
other aspects of the game where you're like.
Okay this is kind of very very tied to the game itself and could not
really be leveraged, you know, for some other project that I was doing
or that sort of thing.
So that's good too.
Anyway, I hope you guys have a good evening and until tomorrow have
fun programming.
I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take these everyone