Start recording.
Hello everyone.
And welcome to handmade hero.
The show recoded complete game live on Twitch.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just us and our little typing fingers typing away.
And right now we are typing on sound mixing, I guess to be a little
more specific.
We pretty much did all of the sound mixing stuff.
We wanted to do preliminarily and we've got Sounds playing.
Got some streaming.
We got Pitch changes.
We have volume ramping and painting stuff like that, but one of the
things that I kind of wanted to do with
Is just drop it down to be wide Vector.
So it's, you know, I wanted to basically have it in Cindy like our
render is just so we could see how that affects the architecture at
all just to make sure that there's no sort of snafus in there because
it's pretty simple to do.
You know, it's not a huge ownerís undertaking, so I wanted to kind of
do that maybe today and we don't have to go overboard with it.
We're not even I'm not really even thinking about it as us.
Optimizing the sound mix or anything like that.
I'm just strictly.
Want to make sure.
Sure that, you know, if we decide to do for sample at a time wide
version that it's all you know kosher.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
I think today just so we can get a feel for it.
But before I do that, let me just mention that if you have
pre-ordered, the game on handmade hero dot-org, you can download the
source zip and today's day 144.
So what you want to do is take one day 143 source code and unzip that
into a directory because if you do that, then you will be exactly
where I am right now and you can follow
With me.
So, you know, maybe that's something that you like to do.
And if it is, that's what we're doing.
So day, 143 sort, they 143 source, code is what you want to look at
their.
In fact, let me just make sure that I'm right about that.
The machine kind of logged itself out the other day, said started up.
Yes, 01:43 was the latest Source sip, so there you go.
All right, so let's go over here to the sound code.
We've got it kind of isolated in its own file and this is the entirety
really of that sound code, right?
But we're looking at here, it's this output playing sounds function
and it really does pretty much all the stuff that we wanted it to do.
You know, it's basically got everything in there for now and so what
I'd like to do here is I'd like to just take a look at making this
into some D now if you don't know what Cindy is.
Or what SSE is, I apologize.
I'm not going to explain it again because I already explained it in
detail before when we did the render.
So if you're if you didn't see that go back and watch that in the
video, archive, the Cindy introduction.
If you're lost with what we're doing here, go back and watch that.
And I explained it in quite a bit of detail, so I'm not really going
to mention anything other than brief refreshing stuff as we go through
it.
I'm just going to assume everyone seen that or we'll go and see that
if they want to know.
So, if we come into the render group, if you remember here is sort of
all of our Cindy intrinsics that we were doing, right.
And the big thing about me, Cindy intrinsics is in order to
Leverage The Sim d-unit the CMD operations on the x64 processor, which
is what we are writing our code for or the x86 in this case as well.
We need to be able to process things in batches of at least four at
once, right?
We need to be able to do things in chunks of for.
Now some of the stuff in here will be pretty straightforward for that,
right?
The other thing that we need to do is we need to make sure they're
aligned, right?
And we can work with unaligned data if we want to.
Too, but usually it's better for us, not to forecast reasons anyway,
and also sometimes it's faster to do aligned reads and writes and so
on and so forth.
So, what we probably want to do is we probably want to make sure that
at the very least, our are temporary buffer, here is aligned to the
way that we would want it to.
And remember, we've already done some work to make sure that we can
align it.
So, if we want to do that Cindy alignment in line things to 16, bytes
we actually can just go ahead and
Tell our allocator that we needed 16 by the lines.
We already did the work for that and it should be fine.
And so, the first thing I'm going to do is take out the take this
clear out the mixer channels thing.
I'm going to go ahead and see if we can go ahead and make that four
wide.
So what I want to do is I want to say that that we're never going to
ask for an output sample count, right?
That is it going to be an even multiple of four?
So I want to say ahead of time.
Look, I'm just, I'm just expecting you to always give me a multiple of
four samples, so we might have to go back into the platform layer and
ensure that it always does something.
To round it to that.
So I'm going to put in assertion in here to force us to go do that
work.
Once we're ready.
Now, I suppose now I think about it.
As I'm saying that in my head actually I don't care about that at all.
I thought I cared about that but I don't really.
These are temporary buffers.
So really what we could do is we could just say, you know what, we
have a sound sample count and we really just need to make sure that
the sound sample count can fit, all the samples in there, but we don't
really care if we get went over, right, because when we copy out at
the end to the 16-bit values, that's the only place we would have to
care about that.
Overhang for the for
For examples.
So what we could see here is we could you know we could go ahead and
just round this to a power of 2.
I don't know if we ever we probably should.
This was confusing people a little bit because I just I tend to type
this in because it's kind of second nature to me, a lot of the times.
So I don't know if we have it, aligned call anywhere in here II.
Don't think that we ever wrote one.
So, okay so we have an aligned 16, right?
And so what?
What I think was confusing, people a little bit.
It was this sort of Value Plus 15 and not 15 kind of stuff.
And someone asked question on the forums, I explained it one time.
Basically, it was just it was just saying that this is just saying,
okay, I'm trying to round up always to the next nearest power of two.
I'm sorry to the next nearest, multiple of some specific power of 2.
And this case it was 16.
And the easiest way to do that is to add 1 - the power of 2 and then
knock out, all the bits that are below that power of 2 and explain
that on the stream one time.
But really, you can think of this as a fairly generic thing.
You can think of a line in as like if you have a value and
Alignment right.
Something like this, like a line power to or something.
I don't know.
Something like this.
You can imagine as long as alignment is a power of 2.
You could actually write this macro to be completely generic, right?
All you're trying to do is take that alignment and subtract one from
it, right?
And and that produces the right thing in both cases, right?
So, you can actually round to any one that you want here.
And I tend to like, to have
Ones that are, you know just kind of the convenient ones that I tend
to use.
So I tend to do stuff like that but you can you can think about it if
you want.
You can think about these as just being a generic way of rounding as
long as the thing you're trying to align to happens to be a power of
2.
This will work.
If it's not a power of 2, this trick does not work and you have to do
something.
Smarter probably actually using a mod to get it to work, but I'm not
sure there might be fancier tricks.
There's there's some crazy.
Chuck tricks out there that people have figured out.
So you never know, anyway, so if I want to take this sample count and
produce a, you know, like a sample count that's going to be aligned
for
To round that up.
I can do that, right?
So I can say, all right, I want to do a sample county line for and
then I also want to do a sample account for which is basically going
to be that divided by 4, right?
In other words, I want to, I want to actually have one that's divided
by 4.
So that when I come in here, what I can actually do is make the
channels actually DMM 128, right?
So they're actually will just be packs of four of these things to
begin with, okay?
And so what I'm going to do here is
That I want to allocate the, You Know, sample count divided by four of
these and 11th, which of course each contain four.
So that will give me room for my mix buffer, right?
And then if I want to clear it right, I should be able to clear it.
Pretty trivially in here.
I should be able to say, okay I'm just going to walk through all of
the values and I'm just going to, you know, use mmm, set, 1, PS to
make something that's just replicated, a bunch of zeros.
He's right.
You know what I'm saying?
Just just totally zero.
Fact, I could just do this like so and just say all right, you know
what, we've got a zero.
And these guys are just going to be equal to 0, 's all the time.
So that would that would do it, right?
And of course, I only want to Loop over the sample count for version
of it.
That would clear all of my stuff out.
Now, we have to do a little bit hips.
We have to do a little bit here because these are still, you know,
sort of working with them as if they are in 128 or sorry.
This is this is still think of them.
7/28 and this is going to be real.
So I'm just going to cast it for now since that's free for me to do
and let these guys work in there.
Away, so that I can just test the clear 20 and make sure that that's
working relatively well.
So let's take a look.
Yeah, so that's all good.
No problems there.
So the clear 20 looks fine.
Let's go down now to the to the bottom.
And let's take a look at the conversion, right?
And we have a clamp in here as well.
So we actually had a little to do that was like hey remember to go
ahead and clamp these guys.
So what I want to do for clamping those guys is I would like to sort
of make some clamping information here, right?
So something like Max 16-bit or Max sign, 16-bit, and Min sign 16-bit
or something like this.
Maybe Mass Max s 16.
Min s 16 something like that so that
Can put that clamp in as well.
So what I want to do here is I want to set these guys, to be the
floating point because remember, all of this mixing is taking place in
floating point, but it's taking place in floating Point versions of
16-bit values.
So basically, we're not even converting room in the renderer, we
convert all our stuff to the 0 to 1 range or well, I guess, we even
change that to start working in 0 to 255 in a bunch of places.
We're doing that same 02:55 kind of thing here where we're letting it
run from - 32k to positive 3.
82 K, right?
We're letting that actually take care of the mixing in that range
instead of trying to bring things back to the 0 to 1 range because we
don't really have any reason why we need to bring things back from 0
to 1 range.
So when we talk about clamping of the values, what we want to do is
clamp them in six, we're clamping especially as 16-bit values, even
though they're stored is float.
So we want to produce some floats.
That would be the maximum and minimum sign 16-valve.
Use if that makes sense.
And so I'm trying to think of what the easiest way is to get those.
I mean really, it's just, I mean, I don't know.
I'm thinking maybe the easiest way to do it would be to say like oh
I've got it, I've got an s 16 of, you know, of that, right.
That would be the minimum.
And then I've got a Nexus teen of that that would be the maximum,
right?
I think that would probably give me what I wanted, but let's since
we've never done anything like this.
Let's let's let's do this first.
Let me just see.
Let's do it this way, just so you guys can see what I'm talking about
here, right?
There we go.
Okay let's see.
So can I actually make it do this?
I don't think I can.
Yeah, well I tried I tried and I unfortunately failed, I kind of just
wanted it to look at these guys and do them as if they were, you know
about 16 to tell you so I could force it.
Look at the Min and the max without me actually having to do anything.
But it doesn't look like that in the car.
Unless I just am thinking about this slightly wrong.
Basically, what I'm saying is, let's let me
Comment these out, I'll show you what I mean.
Okay.
So, if I go into the sound mixer here, or if I just, I can go anywhere
right?
Like so.
So if you know, I, if I take something and I want an F-16 value,
right?
I want a, you know, a short value.
If I was to take the 65536 / to hear something like,
As you can see in hexadecimal, see if that's not quite the highest.
Why are you not?
I want the highest value because I actually typed a to buy.
Exactly, exactly.
All right.
Do that 65536.
So, if I actually type the the
The highest value there, right?
That I could actually get in practice.
Oh, that's what?
Oh, okay.
I just typed that wrong.
There we go.
So if I actually get the highest value that you can fit and I guess
what I could do is I can also show this in binary so you can see it.
If I wanted to get the highest value, I could possibly fit in a 16-bit
value.
It's going to be all of the, you know, all of the binary places are
going to be set to one except for the final one, right?
Because if you're talking about a signed value, then as you get, when
once that top bit,
It flips, 21 your value is now assigned value a negative value, right?
So this is the maximum value actually could produce.
So what I wanted to do right was I wanted to to make it so I could do
7ff, I wanted to make it so that that would be the device.
So I think that would actually work now.
Yes.
So I just I just that was just a stupid mistake on my part so it was
fine.
So if you want to make the minimum value, we
Make it that way, making the maximum value what I actually want to do.
Yeah, II don't actually want to do it that way.
I don't even know why I typed it that way to begin with.
I guess it's just a bad.
I'm just a oops.
Sorry, that's not the main.
That's the max well man brains fried today.
I don't know why I'm thinking so slowly.
It's kind of one of those days where I don't know the brains just
foggy.
Anyway so yeah the maximum value which we just showed like this,
right?
If
If I, if I look at that without the binary on, right?
Then that's the seven, f f f, right?
So that's the value that I would want for the maximum value.
I don't know why I typed it in for the man, for the Min.
I just want all FS, right?
You know, I just, I just want it to be to be flipped around.
No, sorry that be negative one.
So that doesn't help me either.
Well those, yeah, so I don't actually know I guess, I don't actually
know why.
It wouldn't let me do FFF.
Cast.
I guess it's because there's really no way to tell it.
Hey I wanted this value to be negative, right?
But that's okay.
So what I actually want is this right?
I actually want the highest positive negative value, which would be a
one on the top and all zeros.
I don't know if it will.
Let me do that though.
Yeah, so it won't so.
But just to show you what that is right if I was to actually take this
value, you know, x 8000.
What that actually is because of two's complement, which you've never
actually covered on the stream.
I think so, you might have to double check that guy but because of
two's complement, the way that they tend to work with.
Values that are in binary on CPUs, is unlike the floating Point math,
where you have a sign bit that literally just get set, or unset,
whether or not, the number is negative, they integer math, they do
this trick called tubes compliment to make it simpler on the hardware
because basically, you can do all the operations, the same, whether
the value is signed or unsigned.
And the map.
All works out exactly the same way.
Now, this is a little bit confusing, so I'll just kind of mention it
briefly, I don't know that now is a great time to spend a bunch of
time talking about 2's complement, but since my brain is fried anyway,
obviously today, maybe it wouldn't hurt, right?
Is this the right thing?
Hello, mischief.
Mischief takes a while to load our giant Blackboard now.
I don't think they were expecting people to use it quite like this,
but we do.
So, you know, I usually just tend to leave it running soon.
Have to wait for this but like I said, the machine accidentally logged
itself out the other day and so that was kind of unfortunate to say
the least.
But anyway, so
Two's complement.
You know what?
But I always felt compliment wrong.
So we're actually going to check that out, too.
Is it compliment?
And I it see.
Okay, so I did spend I spelled it correctly, good, but that's totally.
I always felt compliment the wrong way.
Since there's multiple.
So all I was saying before was, you know, if you imagine let's take
the simplest case or a very simple case, which would be like let's
suppose that we had a value that's only four bits long, right?
So, it can really only.
It can only represent values between 0 and 15.
If it's unsigned, right?
This is the one bit.
This is the tube at this is the 4-bit, this is the 8-Bit, right?
And so if it's unsigned then the maximum value that it could support
was ones in all the places which is 1 plus 2 plus 4 plus 8, right?
And so that's just going to give you 15, right?
It's you know, just basic math.
So the question is, what if I want this to be assigned value though,
right?
Well if I wanted to be assigned value, I need some way of telling the
difference between whether it's signed and whether it's unsigned.
And so what you could do is say well that top bit, right?
Is going to tell me whether it's signed or unsigned.
And and so what I'd like to do is make it so that I just can set that
you know you know, if I just think about that bit if that bit is set,
I know the value of signed if that bit is unset, that I know the value
is unsigned, that would be pretty nice.
And that's the way that floating Point, does it right?
Floating Point has the high bit and it just sets it on and off
directly.
But what happens is if we were to actually literally make that the
rule meaning, okay, this bit is now just the sign bit.
But these bits still mean for two and one, right?
If that were the case.
Then the processor would always have two special case this bit, right?
It would always have to go if I have a plus b where they're both these
kind of numbers it would first have to go.
Oh, is you know, what are the signs of these two like is the sign bit
set in both of them?
Or is it not setting?
Both of them.
Okay.
Well if it's set in both of them or not setting both of them, then you
can actually add the bottom together and then let's leave the science
at the same.
If it's not, you got to turn this from an addition into a subtraction
and write it just gets kind of annoying.
But it turns out that you can do a nice trick here with the way that
you conceptualize the numbers.
If instead of thinking of the negative numbers as the same as the
positive numbers.
But just with this bit set, what you can do instead is think of it as
counting the opposite direction, right?
So normally what happens is you have one, two, and four and the zero
bit like Get Set, you know, on I'm sorry I should say the one bit the
0 in the one B Place gets set to on that becomes one, right?
So, you know, in unsigned
And right, oops.
In unsigned.
I have 0 0, 0 0 equals 0, I have 0 0 0 1 equals 1.
I have 0 0, 1 0 equals to write and I keep going, like this, this is
how I count up, right?
Make sense, and I can keep going like this to get all the way up,
right?
And so, as I go, I count up in unsigned.
Now when I get, if I wanted to do a sign,
Value instead, right?
If we were doing this trick where all we did was set the sign bit, you
would expect it to again just look you know, this would just be ones
the whole way down, right?
And now it would be well there'd be no such thing as negative zero
right but you'd have negative 1 negative 2 negative 3, negative 4
negative 5, right?
And maybe you would have a negative zero who knows, right.
That's what you expect to see but like I said that would produce this
kind of nasty special casing that has to happen in the processor and
know.
And they just did one do that.
They don't have to be right.
So two's complement is a trick that says, no, don't do it this way.
Instead of using that value for a negative 1, Let's actually use all
ones to represent negative 1, right?
Why would you want to do that?
Well the reason is because now if you just Implement your addition
operations, the same way.
And so what you actually can do to her, as you can see, actual I'll
take a little bit further.
So here you go.
There's negative 1.
You can see it's all FS - to, right?
- three - four - five - Six - seven - eight and what you can see is it
just it's literally just counting down backwards, right?
And so if you look at what happens, right?
You'd have, if I wanted this to be a negative 2, what I would do is
I'm doing exactly the opposite operation as I was doing, you know,
Before on these guys, right?
In fact, I can, I can probably do this in binary for you, too.
You can see it a little bit better, right?
Do you see how this is going?
Like so and the reason that they do that is because well it doesn't
really matter to humans because humans you know we have to write a
routine to decode this binary to print it out in a ski for them
anyway.
So like who cares about that?
Who cares about the meaning of the numbers?
As long as there is a way to know what they mean in human form.
That's fine.
What we actually care about is what happens to the arithmetic in the
computer.
Does it produce the right results?
Consistently and what happens is if you if you treat this as the
encoding
For negative numbers, right?
Then what happens is all the arithmetic still works the exact same
way, right?
And I know that sounds kind of weird but that's actually just what
happened.
So for example, if I were to take all zeros, right?
And let's say we're doing scientific now so that equals 0, right?
And I were to add to it - one right?
Then I would get negative 1 which is exactly what I would have expect.
Right?
What I would have expected.
If on the other hand, I want to go ahead and add, you know, -1 and -2
and expect to get negative 3, right?
So I go in here and I say, well, alright, I've got negative 1 like so
and I got well actually, yeah.
I've got negative 1 and I want to add negative 2 right 2.
- three.
So what's going to happen here?
Well, I'm going to go ahead and add these guys.
Upright, I add these two and I just get a 1 in this position.
I add these two and I get a 0 in this position, but I have to carry,
right?
I get the the I have to carry the 1 again here.
I have to carry the 1 again here and I kept get the.
Excuse me, I get the carry bit as well, you know, actually now I think
about it.
How do they do the borough's?
I don't actually know how CPU vendors even implement this today is a
weird stream.
I don't even remember.
This is like, going way back into my into my the Crusty regions of my
brain.
So CPU Adder
I'll see how they actually do this.
Because basically, what's going to happen is they need to roll the
value.
Needs to wrap, right?
I mean, you can see this happen so I know what happens in practice,
but I don't know how they actually do it in the CPU and I can actually
remember.
So, if we could take a care, for example, let's say, I take something
like this.
This is definitely turning into a ridiculously off-topic stream.
Let's take a say, I take two unsigned integers, even right?
So this has nothing to do with the two's complement or any of that
stuff.
If I just have two of these and I take 255 and I add 3 to it, right?
Or are just even to to it, right?
And I don't care about any of this.
And so, I want to get the result and I do a plus b, right?
So you can see what happens in here.
If I actually switch over to the audio output, playing sounds
So if I come in here, right?
And I look at these two values, A and B
So you can see that when I'm going to in and I'll actually put these
in binary as well.
When I add these two in signed, right, what I what I expect to get is
the value to wrap around, right?
So, when I add these two together, right?
I'm going to get something that the equals, whatever the wraparound
actually is, right.
So, I should get one when that happens, right?
And I do so
Yeah, so I don't actually know what causes that actual wraparound to
occur in the other case.
Well, I guess, it doesn't.
That just works fine, right?
The ones add those will carry and it'll just carry all the way out.
So that's actually fine, I guess.
Yeah.
Hmm.
Well, alright so let's let's try.
More.
So let's suppose we add 255 and 255 together, right?
I guess that works all the way out.
This is turning into a Casey gets to experiment with things stream but
you know what?
That's just so have Friday's go sometimes and also, it is boiling hot
in here.
It's getting really hot in Seattle in the summer.
So like I am so in need of some air conditioning thing.
But anyway, so I'll if I do the, the 255 ads.
So I think I just, I think I was just asleep at the switch here.
Yeah.
Oh duh.
This is just me being dumb.
Okay, good.
This is just this is like stupid Casey Friday.
Because I was going to say, I didn't think they had to do anything
special for the wraparound.
They do.
This is three ones that I'm adding.
How did I get a 0 here?
I have no idea that just should have produced a 1 1 plus 1 plus 1.
Right equals a 1 plus a carry one, right?
And that carry one then makes this equal to 1 which exactly equals
negative 3.
Right.
Hmm.
Oh well.
So yeah, this is a stupid Casey Friday.
I'm afraid that's just the way it is.
Sometimes you know I'm pretty old these days, you know, these are the
kind of days when I'm pretty old.
So the brain is not what it used to be.
Although I feel like I probably would make kind of careless math
errors, like that even when I was little like I was really bad at
arithmetic in in like grade school and high school and stuff like.
So this is actually the kind of mistake that pretty much Casey at any
age, would do like a little baby Casey in diapers.
You know, that's a diaper Casey.
There's the nipples.
And then there would also be, you know, kind of like the old Casey
with a cane or something like this, right?
And a long beard I guess, you know, and he well, he'd be hunched over,
probably right?
Some of that something like this, like that.
I don't know.
That's that's horrible.
This is just don't even think about these.
But anyway, back to the point.
So the 2's complement stuff
Is just an excuse for CPU vendors, to not have to do any special
casing for the math to work out, right?
Because what ends up happening is if you just add these values the way
you normally would and you're a CPU.
So you don't make mistakes.
Like I do when you actually add the values, you end up with the right
answer, if even, if you didn't know they were signed.
So no one has to tell you that this is actually a signed value, you
don't have to know that there's a special meaning for this bit, the
arithmetic still just works out.
And so I don't actually know who figure this out, but
You know, somewhere way back when salsa figured out like, oh wait, if
we just treat negative values, the same as positive values and use
this encoding.
Then the CPU just always works, whether it's a signed value or an
unsigned value.
And that's why you don't need to add instructions, you don't need one,
add instruction for signed and one add instruction for unsigned.
You can just use a single add instruction and it works, right?
So the long and short of it is,
All ones equals negative.
Whereas a one with all zeros equals the maximum value right?
Like - I guess 16 in this case or I should say - 15 right?
And yeah because you can't actually so this actually also introduces
that other dichotomy, this is kind of this, this encoding.
This this sort of the top bit means - and we count the numbers down
backwards thing that encoding is also why you always get one
additional number in the negative space?
Has the positive space, right?
Because you look at the positive space.
The maximum number I could have encoded was this, right?
So if I have the 1 b 2 B, the this is not right.
The 4-bit and 8-bit write the maximum number of that I could have been
coded was going to be seven, right?
Because this yeah, this is assigned 4-bit number, right?
So it ranges from negative 8 to 7, right?
So I don't know why this this is -8.
Don't know why?
I said - 15.
Wishful thinking I guess.
So if I look at this, right?
The the bits here, I can't set this bit because if I set this bit, the
number would be considered to be negative, right?
And that's, you know, that's not what I'm trying to do.
So I'm trying to set the maximum positive number.
I can only do one plus two plus four which is going to be seven.
Right.
But I can set this bit and all the other zeros to make the maximum
negative number and that is negative 8, right?
Because you look at how far that has to count down.
It has a pretty long.
Wrong way it can count down, right?
It's still got all of these options.
It still has seven different options in addition, to this one to count
down, right?
Another way to look at it is it doesn't have to represent zero because
zero was represent, was representing the positive case, so you get one
additional value and that's why signed integer values.
Are always like - n, you know, to n, minus 1, right?
Whatever it is, whatever the range is, you can.
Only go to one less than the maximum value in positive that you could
have gone in negative.
Alright.
So that was like the dumbest possible explanation of two's complement
because although, I guess my explanation wasn't awful.
I managed to make so many mistakes in the actual arithmetic of it,
that it probably confused everyone more than it helped, but that's
okay, because two components, actually pretty simple.
There's not a lot to it pun intended.
So if you want to just go look at a two's complement, web page, it
should have an example examples for you without my math errors and
hopefully, that would be clear but the
Point is I just wanted an easy way to generate what these are and so
what I would like to do is be able to say oh I've got a 16 bit value.
So what I was hoping for is I could just say 0 X8 88000 to say, why
don't you just give me a one with with 15 zeros after it and binary so
that I can just have the maximum negative value.
Now I could just
Is that value instead by, you know, thinking about what it is right?
I know that it's going to be
I know that it's going to be this, right?
I know it's going to be negative, 32 768, so I could just type - 32
768 in there.
But since - 32 768 is somewhat hard to remember.
I was just thinking, maybe I could do something a little bit more
clever, but what it seems like is the case that unless I want to get
exceedingly clever, it's not going to let me do that, because you can
see it worries about the cash trunking their value, because it's
thinking that I'm trying to represent an unsigned value here, right?
It's thinking.
Okay.
Trying to actually represent.
The positive version of that number and if I were to cast that to
assigned, I wouldn't be able to record it.
So, long story short, we can't do that, that's fine.
So we'll just go ahead and say, 32 768 will be our value.
So our men will be negative, 32 seven, sixty, eight, dot zero, right?
And our positive would be not this because like I just said, you can't
quite get there.
This would be our positive value.
So right?
Two's
And you know, what are you gonna do?
Sometimes you just gotta sometimes the explanations on handmade here
are better than others.
What can I say?
That's the the, you know, you got to take the good with the bad, the
baby with the bathwater all those sorts of things.
So the good news is, you know, if we, if we have these things here,
right?
Then clamping becomes really trivial.
We've already done.
It.
It's pretty straightforward.
So we can clamp these guys, once we are ready to do the clamping, but
let's go ahead and work on the the other part of it first.
Yes.
So what I'd like to do here is I want to go ahead and read from the
source as M 128 instead of casting down for reals and process for
these guys at once, right now, the problem is, we don't actually know.
Like I said that, we have a buffer that actually fits a multiple of 4
in there.
We know that our, you know, our Ruiz do, we don't know that our output
does, but what we can do is we can make it so that it we know that it
always will by forcing the platform layer to always give us a little
extra padding so that we don't have to special case this Loop, right?
And so that's pretty easy and that's something that we can do pretty
easily in the handmade platform stuff, right?
We can just say when we go to the sound output buffer and output
buffer,
There we go.
We can just say something like note.
Samples, must be padded to a multiple of four samples.
Something like that.
Right, we could even make it bright yellow if they wanted to.
There.
Yeah, yeah.
So we can do something like that if we need to.
So, let's take a look at writing this and
Not really worried about over right at the moment because it may be
that we don't really care about that at the end of the day.
All right, so if we read in these two, these two guys here, right?
We've got one channel here.
When channel here, these are floating Point values.
And so what we want to do is we want to we got to convert them down to
16 bit, right?
And so we were doing here as we were just rounding them and then
converting them.
Now we know that we already have.
We already know how to do this for the rounding, right?
We've got that CV, DT, pts this
Guy right here, right?
This is the trunk, truncating one and then there's also a rounding
one, right?
I don't remember which one is it this one?
That's the rounding.
That's the truncating 1440p.
I know.
Where are we?
Where is our?
There is a rounding once our covert PS epi32.
I believe that is the one that would do the rounding for us.
Am I wrong about that?
Let's see here.
Yeah, yeah.
So this is the one that does.
The rounding not the truncation, right?
So that's the one that we would want to use.
And so what we can do there is we can just read from the source and
this will do that rounding for us, right?
So this will round the values really pretty straightforward, just
going to round the values.
So now they become integer values, right?
And so now what we've got here is them 128.
I write for our source is zero,
Are in our source, one.
So there we go, no big deal there.
And then what we want to do after that is these are still there going
to be put there gonna be converted for floating 32-bit floating-point,
32-bit integer and it will round them for us and that's fine.
But unfortunately it won't actually convert them to 16, bit for us,
right?
And we need to Output interleaved 16-bit sample.
So, what we need to do here is we need to down convert the 32-bit
values to 16-bit values and
I'm not, this is the place where, you know, I don't quite remember
exactly which options we have, but this is going to be a pact, right?
We're going to have to do one of those packs to pack down.
So let's take a look at what we've got in terms of packing.
We don't really want convert.
That's see storage and compare shift set, random move electrical load
store mask.
I don't know if the packs where are the pac's?
I guess I don't know where the packs even are in here.
So I'm just going to look for mmm pack because that's what I actually
want and I won't bother.
I, you know what I could do, I can use the little filter pack.
So let's see here, if we want to do convert packed 32-bit integers
from A and B.
Be too packed 16-bit integers, using sine saturation, and so, that is
exactly what we want, right?
Sign saturation.
Means that if the values were higher than 32 bits to begin with, they
would actually get saturated out to two 16-bit integers, right?
And that's actually pretty awesome because that means that we won't
even have to do a clamp if you're thinking about it, right?
Because what if the values greater than our range of - 32k to positive
32k, the sign saturation of the pack will just take care of it for us,
right?
It'll just threshold.
It down and we'll be done.
So I think actually, that's pretty handy.
Much more useful than I guess.
I would have thought
So, that's kind of nice.
All right, so let's go ahead and let's go ahead and make that happen.
That sounds good.
Like so.
So then we've got the combination of two, but the problem now is
they're not interleaved, right?
The 16-bit values are not actually interleaved together.
And so that again does not really help us because we've got now
essentially, what we've done so far, right?
If you think about it, we start off.
And we've got some buffers that look like this.
Without l0 L1 L2.
L3.
R0 R1 R2.
R3 and memory order, right?
And these are all 32-bit floats.
And so, in memory order, not processor odor.
But in memory order, now, once we do this pack, what we'll get is,
will get one, you know, we'll get a nice single buffer that actually
has eight values in it, right?
It'll have l0 L1 L2 L3.
R0 R1 R2 R3.
So that's great.
And that's exactly what we want for six.
We got 16-bit signed values now but the problem is we actually wanted
to it to look like this, right?
We actually wanted the things to be internally if we wanted L 0, R 0,
L 1, r 1, L 2, R 2 because that output buffer is expecting the samples
to be an interleaved.
So what we need is something that would pack these things together,
right?
We need something that would go, you know, take l0 first, and then an
L1, you know, like that kind of thing, right?
And so again, I believe we have pretty good options for that
hilariously after calling unpack, I think.
Uh, no, I think unpack actually would be what we would want for that.
If I'm actually if I, well know, I guess because that would be the
high of two things.
So, no, we don't actually want unpack.
Hi, I guess this would actually be some kind of a 16-bit shuffle.
Hmm.
How are we going to do this?
I don't actually know if we've got what we would may have to do before
we do the convert.
You may have to do something clever to interleave these guys.
I'm trying to think, right?
Because the unpacks that I know of and the shuffles that I know of
won't do a 16-bit shuffle like that.
There just isn't a way to do.
I can't think of any way to do that off hand.
Yeah, because if you look at the options that we have for rearranging
things, I'm pretty sure.
Look, what's the shuffle Epi in
May and service in death so we can Shuffle 32-bit values around all
that we want.
That's fine.
What's pi16 Shuffle 16 inches?
In a towing and soils, dest
So that one does only the bottom ones they're right or does it sucked
immediate 1032?
Oh well actually this is kind of a bizarre instruction Shuffle, the
16-bit integers in a using the control and IM 8 and store the results
in dest.
And so, it's takes a look at the source and the control.
So the control in this case, refers to
Though the 10.
Okay.
So, the, the control is the 1 and 0, B, which I of this, I guess is
what they're trying to say to the first two bits.
And so in the case here, I guess they're doing a temporary, they're
putting into a temporary and then returning the temporary out.
So it's this part that's actually getting out of control best.
This is
So, weird function.
I've never called this before, but that is strange.
So this is create, this is extruding some extraction here, that's
fine.
And then we have the destination, this is just doing 1616 to.
So it's only doing the bottom part of the destination which is not
really useful to us.
So again don't think that's particularly great and we can do Shuffle
high and Shuffle low.
But again that's not that's not really what we want.
So it doesn't super look like we have much.
In the way of options here, unfortunately, it looks like we would have
to shuffle things ahead of time if we wanted to make this happen.
So I'm just going to see if that's an option for us.
I don't know, we'll have to think about it a little bit more a little
bit later on if there's maybe a better option.
But I think we might have to shuffle ahead of time like, basically put
these guys before we pack them into an order.
That's more amenable.
So, interleave them ahead of time.
Right?
We could do two shuffles and put them in the right order to basically
do an L 0, R 0 kind of thing, right?
And so what I'm thinking is that's probably what we need to do.
So we do like an M 128, just at the head end where we
Say something like okay, you know, we've got we read out the source.
Two sources.
And then we do sort of a shuffle where we've got, we want to do like
a, our l0, like I'm sorry LR 0 and an LR 1.
Where we say.
Okay let's Shuffle these guys together.
So we'll do an M&M.
I think it'd be an unpacked basically where we're just going to
interleave them right.
Because all I want to do is I just want to take these two values and
pick one from here, one from here, one from here, one from here, which
is to typical pattern of an unpack.
So we do an unpack low whereas our unpack low at or unpack.
Low is right here, right?
So we
Unpacked low and I guess I can leave that conversion in there as well.
Now that I think about it this is the conversions fine, right.
So if I do an unpack low epi32 and I unpack the S, I guess we can call
this L and R as well.
These are the Left Channel samples, use the right, so we'll enter,
leave the left and right samples there and then do the high samples as
well, right?
And so again that's just taking these two guys, right?
And the unpack low will produce this part.
Right?
So it'll take these guys and interleave them.
Take one from here, one from here, one from here, one from here, dude.
And then the unpack high will do these.
These guys right, it'll produce, you know, L to R 2 L 3 R 3, right?
Okay, so then when I've got those then I can just do the pack and the
pack will just work right?
It'll just pack them down in there already in the right order and so
then I should be able to take sample out and Sample out.
I can now just right to it directly, right?
And so if I did em 128, I sample out and I don't know, cast this
directly to it, right?
I should be able to just say, all right, sample out plus plus is now
going to write.
It develops.
Is now just going to write out that S01 value, right?
Okay.
So yeah again we need to actually ensure that we're not going to write
out of bounds.
There is the only thing and we're not actually doing that yet.
So because like I said it for if we're going at forward to time that
means there could be some overhang.
So we're technically illegal right now but we could try running it
anyway.
Maybe we'll crash, who knows.
So not quite right?
I'm not hearing anything in the Left Channel.
So I made some calls
Kind of mistake here that we need to take a look at once we do our
packs.
Is this the right one packs, epi32.
Did I specify the right one?
We looked it up, but then, I don't know if I actually pack with epi32
or epi16 group activities assigned.
So, that's the correct.
That's the correct one, right?
Saturate, intertube 16.
Yeah.
So that's the correct one.
So I'm not sure exactly why I had a problem.
There, we converted our guys to 32-bit.
That's what we wanted, right of our sources, so that's good.
We do our pack, down to 16-bit signed values and we've got our unpack
lows and highs there to do the to interleave them before we use them.
So that seems like that should have worked.
I'm
Sure what the problem is there.
So I guess what I'll do is, you know, you've seen me do this trick
before.
So I guess what I'll do here is something like this, mmm set epi32,
you know and I'll do something like 0 you know, 0 0 0 1 1 2 2 3 3 of
course I always forget the reverse order things.
I'm going to say I want to set them so that these are in memory order
like that.
So
alright, let's let's see here and these are like the Left Channel so I
guess I'll do them left channel is a
And right channel.
Whoops?
Right channel will be be.
That makes sense.
yeah, and now
All right, we should be able to see these guys.
And again, I'm just all I'm really doing here is, I'm structuring the
values in the register so that I can see them properly.
So that, when they get converted down, I'll be able to see which which
values are going.
We're just to make sure that we aren't doing something stupid in the
routine, right?
That that's really the only thing that I'm trying to do.
Okay?
So if we take a look at El and I want to look at it as I 16s, right?
I want to look at it as .m 128 II.
I-16, right?
And then I'll look at our as well.
Our and if we look at hexadecimal, we should be able to see there that
we've got, you know these values as again as 32-bit values there and
when we go ahead and do the unpacks, we should end up with these being
shuffled properly.
So if I, if I take a look at just one of them like LR 0,
We should now have a b 0, B 0, a 1, b 1, right?
And that does look roughly correct.
Their see here, be one?
Yeah and then lr1 and 128.
I I-16
A 2 b 2, a 3, B 3, so that all looks good.
And now let's take a look at what the actual value comes out to be
after the packing.
Make sure that's saying a 0, B, 0, a 1, b 1, a 2 b 2, a 3, B 3 so that
looks totally right to me that looks all packed up.
Nice.
So yeah, so I think we're in good shape here.
I've also going to
Just make sure we don't overwrite our bounds.
Not sure what's going on there.
What did I do?
Sample?
Count.
Four.
Minus one.
I guess it's possible that sample count went well.
Cert simple account for.
It is 0.
Why are we not hearing anything?
What is happening?
so, I feel like
That should be, we're up.
Okay.
So I guess the problem was just that that overwrite was probably over
writing something important in the puffer.
So all right I take it back.
I think our routine is probably fine.
We just have to make sure we actually allow that padding to be padded
out.
So let's go ahead and do that over in the win32 side of the code,
right?
And so are we do our samples when we actually go ahead and Alec those,
Let's let's make sure that we actually have those samples.
Let's see.
So, what we want to do here, when we do secondary, buffer size,
whatever the secondary buffer sizes, we have to make sure we always
align it by 4, just to make sure we've got enough room there.
And actually, I guess that's not true, the secondary buffer size.
Really doesn't quite tell us what we need because the secondary buffer
size.
We don't want to line that by 4.
We want to make sure the number of samples could be done by 4.
So, what we can do there is we can just say, well for samples right
times the size of a sample, right?
Which a sample is a you 16?
We know that we couldn't possibly mean more than that overrun, right?
And so we could just spacely say we have Max possible over run or
something like that, we could just say that we have that and we always
make sure that we have that much in there, right?
So that would be fine and if we did that then I think we would
probably be okay with the overrun, right?
Of course, also could have just been the mouse's and I forgot we left
that hooked up.
That is bad for testing.
I guess if I just always remember that it sucked up.
So that's all good.
And now, I guess these clamp values, the whole thing that made me have
to go on the stream and realize that my brain is too crusty to
properly.
Do two's complement math without preparation.
Wasn't actually necessary.
So we do not need to clamp, the clamp will just happen during the pack
automatically, which is kind of crazy.
So this is actually totally fine with this because the convert PS
epi32 after the unpack.
When we go to this packs epi32 when that takes a room 3216, it's going
to do the clamp.
We don't even need to compare against any values.
It'll just do us, do it for us.
So that's kind of awesome, I guess.
It's just yeah, just the way it goes sometimes.
So
we can also, if we want to do something like this and then store it in
It, M&M store.
Is it epi32?
Can I do that?
Si128, that's what it is.
So if I want to store this guy out,
Like so.
I should be able to do that.
Just to say that.
Hey, these are aligned by the way, cannot G 12 pointer, right.
And these are o store, PS.
And for some reason, it always wants you to cast into a float star,
which makes absolutely no sense to me, because why wouldn't you want
them to be the other kind.
So there's the M&M store so that should be fine.
And it is and we can also do
Give me the same down here, where, when we're loading these guys, we
can actually just say, okay, we've got em em, 128 SC row and then 120
s 1.
That can be an end, load p s of this value.
And again, have to convert it to a float star for no reason that I'm
aware of and that is it.
Okay, so our conversion Loop now runs for a wide are clear Loop.
Now runs for wind.
So the only thing that we really have to do now is we just have to
make our
Mixing Loop here run for a wide which will be a little more so we can
do that on Monday.
And that one will be a little bit more complicated, right?
Because we have to actually have our mixing Loop right here.
I guess, what did I interesting?
So this is our bilinear filtering.
Our non, by the, I think we decided that the bi linear filter didn't
actually help.
But anyway, we have to do this, this work, right?
So we need to do D volume increment, ER, we need to do a decent
People and commentor.
We need to do these guys wide.
And more importantly, we have to make sure that samples to mix is
always going to also be 4 wide.
Also, someone mentioned a bug.
That we have in here, fix the, to fix the both volumes, and at the
same time bug.
So yeah.
So I think we, like I said, it shouldn't be too much longer.
We probably would have finished it today.
If I hadn't gone off on the 2's complement tangent, which hilariously
was not necessary.
But yeah, but I'd like to save that for Monday just so we don't eat up
the entire time of Q&A on it.
But that's basically all we would really need to do the rest of this
routine doesn't actually do anything with the sound sample.
So it's literally just that one, little interior part, that would be
relevant.
So, we would basically just be Loft and these guys up to MMM 128 and
then we would have each of these things, you know, just be a mole PS
and, you know, to multiply the master volume by the volume and then
another my PS2 multiply it by the sample volume value.
And then we would,
Have to do, our incrementer is would have to be for wide, so that they
would go the whole way.
So really that, you know, converting that interior of the loop
actually would be extremely trivial.
It's converting samples to mix to be always up for a wide.
That would be a little more complicated.
So there.
That's yeah.
So there's that.
The other thing is I mean we could just write it so that it doesn't
have to be for a wide and we just have a mask at the end that we use,
but I don't know.
I feel like just writing it to work for a wide is probably the right
way and just padding, our sample buffers out so that the sample buffer
is are always multiples of 4 as well, if that makes sense.
Yeah, and thinking about that, I think that will probably argue for
actually making sure that the sample buffers are always four wide.
So that, you know, if we go back out to the platform code, where we do
our output sound samples, or game output sound, or as our output
sound, no well, here you go.
So when we do our B to lock and we compute out how much we're going to
do and we do this sample count here, I think what we're
want to do is always just truncate that possibly down to whatever the
next size down is, that's aligned by for because if we always make
sure that we align the sample, count down to four
Then all of these routines, all of the samples can always be playing
in lockstep in that for.
So, we can always grab for a process for, and nobody has to be finicky
about the edges.
And that means, I can also always also be aligned.
No one would ever be doing anything unaligned, right?
So I feel like, that's probably what we will want to do on Monday.
That's just my assumption, okay?
That's all there is to it.
Let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
That makes sense.
so, if you have questions,
I guess I can go while the questions are coming in.
Do perhaps a little bit more talking about the two's complement here
since I brought it up and now it's all been paged into my brain.
So if you want to see a complete example, right?
The smallest one we could possibly do.
That would probably look useful is 3 bits.
So here's the full three bit set, right?
So now we've got all the values here, right?
So in unsigned, right?
What are these equal to?
Well this is 0 1 2 3, 4 5 6 7 right in signed they're equal to 0 1 2
3.
And then when we get to for right that now it's the sign bit is set,
right?
So this is actually negative 4, right?
And then it counts down - three - two - one right.
Does that make sense?
And so what you can see if we pick any of these two and add them
together.
We always get the right math, right?
We always get the right math.
No matter what, no matter what you pick.
So if we pick this one and this one to add together, right, well I
guess I should fix things that stay in range.
May be would be, would be a little bit more.
Well, you know, you just have to understand that they wrap I guess is
what I would say.
So let's say that we pick these two guys to add together.
Right?
So if we want to pick these two guys to add together, I'd have 0 1 0
and 1 0 1 right and so if I add those together I get 1 1 1 right and
what's 111?
Well that's equal to 7 right?
2 plus 5 equals 7 that's definitely would think it would be and that's
all good.
Right now what happens if I do the same thing but just considering the
interpretation to be signed.
Well, same is true.
Two plus negative 3 equals negative 1 right?
And so you can kind of see that like, really the whole deal with the
two's complement thing is just because since we don't care what these
binary values represent, right?
We can choose the encoding to be whatever we want it to be.
Because the only time we actually end up, caring about that value
outside of the computer is when we go to print out the values and we
can have that routine, do whatever we want, right?
So it can decode them, however, it wants.
So, all we care about is that inside the machine, we have the most
Way of building the CPU.
And if we do it this way, it means we just build one, Adder circuit,
one, subtractor circuit, you know, etcetera Etc.
And that way we can get both positive and negative numbers with the
same CPU Gates.
And that's pretty cool.
Yeah.
And so the same, I believe is true for most opposite.
You would want to do like if you want to do multiplication or
something like this.
Obviously you know multiplying by 1 and 0 will always work because
that's going to be the same value.
Value in either case.
But multiplying by say to would also I believe be true if you take a
look at, you know, what happens when you when you multiply by 2, I
think you always get the correct values there as well.
So for example, if you, you know, if you were to multiply two times,
you know - one you would expect to get negative 2, right?
And so if you take a look,
At 111 and I want to multiply it by 0 1 0, right?
Well I'm going to get something that looks like this, right?
And this is obviously a carry.
So, if I take a look at the, the 110, here's my negative one.
Here is my to and hey, 110 is negative 2, right?
And the same thing, if I interpret them the other way 111 was 7, I
multiplied that right in.
I'm talking about an unsigned, I multiply that by 2.
I get 14 right?
14 is not representable here.
Okay.
That would be that would wrap around but hey guess what?
If I subtract.
if I actually look at what I would get, if I, if I were to multiply
multiply it and then, you know, do the wrap around
I guess.
Does that actually work out?
Right?
I get 110, which is 6, right?
It seems kind of odd, right?
Shouldn't I get if I have 7 times 2 is 14 unless I'm missing.
Something 14.
Should be 14 mod 7.
Let me see what this actually is that that's up to because that is
what the wraparound value is.
So let's make let's see if we can actually make that happen here.
Want to make sure that's actually true before I say it.
So, if I do two times seven, right and binary?
There we go.
And now I take 2 times 7 and I and it is, I don't actually know what
the rap I guess.
Trying to think if there's any way I can approximately because there's
no, there's no value obviously that would do that.
I guess I could do it with the 255 s.
So let's, I guess we could do that.
So if I take an unsigned care,
right of of
put this in code so it'll be a little bit easier, right?
So, if I take a, you ate and I set that equal to 128 and I said
another one, right?
Equal to 2 and I want to see what a times B is.
I'm interested to know what that will actually do, right?
And so let's do 255 in this case.
What we did is we did seven times two.
So, what we want to do here is take 255 times to write and see what it
actually produces when we do the multiplication.
Oops,
I want to make sure this actually produces something consistent.
All right, so let's see here.
So if we look at the binary,
there we go.
So it does exactly what we thought it would do.
And so if we take 255 times to, we actually get 510, right?
And so if you take 55 times 2, and you bought it, by the values, we
can actually represent.
You get to 54.
So that is definitely what happens with the multiplier which is
unsurprising but it's kind of a little non-intuitive the way that I
was writing that out, right?
Because we know what it should be equal to in that system but you end
up getting
Because they're sort of the phantom eight value that's their you end
up getting one less than that encoded value, right?
Because if you think about taking out that first seven, you actually
take out the first eight, right?
So if we look at like what happened with this 14, when we did two
times seven equals 14, right and then we see what the value was.
I was kind of thinking.
Well, okay, you're removing the first seven you should you should
still have 7 left over but really
Lee, when you wrap your technical removing the whole thing.
So it's actually two times.
Seven equals 14, minus 8 is the results.
You will get right?
Not 2 times 7 equals 14.
Minus 7, if that makes sense.
So it's actually the full end of your bit encoding.
Whatever that is, it's 2 to the M for that bid encoding.
So I don't know.
So that's kind of a little wonky but, you know,
What do you do?
Hey, man, that's binary, right.
That's just how that goes, but, again, that's only if you're
overflowing the values.
Anyway, so point being, yeah, two's complement.
That was just the unsigned case, but two's complement, and you could
see the negative case work just fine.
So all of its pretty straightforwardly, just the case.
That whenever you do an arithmetic up, if you encode them this way,
instead of encoding them in the other way, right?
The other way that I had talked about was if we had started doing it
like this, so that was - wow.
Um that was - 0 that's negative 1.
This is negative 2 negative 3.
That just does not help you because then you have two special case the
math because all of the math you were doing on unsigned is going to
produce the wrong results in signed, right?
Because hey when we did stuff like you know - when we did stuff like
this here, right, where we were doing two plus plus 5, right or 2 plus
negative 3, we're not going to get negative 1.
We're actually
- 3 4 2 plus -3 which doesn't really help us or I should say we were
going to get to plus that would have been 2 plus.
- 1 equals negative 3, right?
So that would have equal to plus negative 1 equals negative 3, which
really doesn't help anyone.
Right?
That's so you would have two special case the math.
If you didn't want to do it in two 2's complement, so
Cooper.
Caleb, why isn't two's complement used for floating Point numbers?
If it makes signed arithmetic easy.
Well.
I guess.
To be honest, I don't know.
I'm not
Enough of a low low level hard, very kind of guy to know the real
answer to that question.
but I would suspect that the reason is because in floating point,
You are never multiplying values that aren't in the range of 0 to 1,
so I or operating on values in that way.
So I don't know that it actually would help you because you already
have to deal with the fact.
Yeah.
So let's think about this.
So the way a floating-point number is typically encoded, right?
Is the sign bit is 1 bit always?
Then you have the exponent right, which is some number of bits, right?
And then you have the mantissa
which is some other number of bits, right?
And this is always like, usually there's an implicit one here.
So this, this is usually one point something is what's been coated in
here, right?
And then this is just telling you what the power is.
So it's like one point something times two to the whatever the
exponent is, right?
And so why you don't use two's complement here is I guess.
I'm trying to think, but, you know, once you have floating Point
values, I guess when you multiply two floating point or like, let's
say, you're going to add two floating Point values together, right?
What's going to happen is the exponent itself is what's going to
actually go up or down based on wrapping.
So if you have, I feel like if you have a negative number you've got
to know what to do with the exponents.
It's properly.
So I feel like, I don't know, I guess what?
Without
With the caveat that I just said which is like I'm the wrong guy to
ask.
I would suspect that the reason is because because the exponent is
pulled out, it's not going to just work either way, right?
So I feel like you probably would just
It's probably the exponent that actually is the thing that's going to
do that work.
And so you know, I wouldn't be surprised if you wanted to support to
store the exponent in two's complement.
Which I guess, you know, I don't even know.
Does that what they normally do?
It's been a long time since I've looked floating-point two's
complement exponents.
Let's see here.
That is not actually how they are stored.
That is something else.
This is not what we want.
Let's see, fluid numbers.
X1 is biased, sort of the actual value by the exponent bias because
they're assigned values in order to be able to represent battalions.
But two's complement you.
So yes,
so the problem is most manager Stuart but just against by to put with
the outside range so it looks like
Interesting, these are for a sign guys, would make comparison harder.
Okay, when interpreting the floating-point number, the by subtracted.
So it looks like at least in standard IEEE, you know, they don't store
that in two's complement either, but it's kind of cryptic, they just
say, would make comparison harder.
So again, we probably want to ask someone who's an expert in this
thing to have an opinion on it because mine is kind of not worth
anything.
So yeah, so I guess they do not do that, but I don't necessarily know
why.
So what they do instead is they just store it, you know, it goes from
zero to something, you know, like if it goes from 0 to 255, or
whatever 02 128, they're just like, oh well, the first 64 values are
positive in the next, ER, you know where the first 64 values are
negative, rather than the next ones are positive.
So we assume that it's always, you know, the Value Plus 64 is what we
actually encoded.
Two shoes.
Are you not going to profile it to see how much faster it gets?
No, I'm not going to profile the audio mixer not this point.
Anyway like I said, I'm not really thinking of optimizing and I'm just
trying to make sure that it's can run for wide.
When you implemented streaming in chunks of audio, believe the code
actually loads.
The entire file with a platform, like a virtual lock.
For each chunk, is this just an artifact of the debug nature that
code?
Yes.
So, like I said before, all of that loading code is going to be
replaced with just pulls out of the asset file.
So we don't care what that does.
As debug load wave, and debug load bitmap are complete, throw away,
they can do whatever they want.
They can allocate all the memory in the machine as long as they don't
crash our code.
We don't care what they do at all.
They just need to get us back the data for testing.
Does the audio make the frame rate in debug mode?
Yes.
When we don't run, it's really just the renderer.
That is the, that's the slow part, right?
So, because when the, when the renderer is running in debug mode, it's
much slower.
And that's you can see how slow it is even at the lower resolution.
So it makes the framerate just fine if we turn it.
On the resolution so you can see this is running in low res right now.
But when we turn it up to 1920 by 1080 that's when we in debug builds
it won't run fast enough and release filter runs just fine.
So yeah, that's just the nature of a software rasterizer it needs to
be optimized highly, right?
So one thing I was saying before and I think we could probably do this
pretty easily.
I suspect.
I mean I guess I don't know but like one thing that I was thinking we
could do pretty easily is in our build right now you
You could imagine pulling out a just just pulling out the compilation
step for just the render code if that makes sense and making that
compile with optimizations on.
And I don't know if that's, you know, the most efficacious way to do
it or anything like that, but you could imagine doing it so that we do
something like handmade optimized
Or something like that.
And then we did, you know, this sort of nonsense here, right and made
optimized dot CPP.
And we did something like, you know, don't don't actually link that
guy.
Just just do not put any of this stuff and just output in an object
file.
I think that's mine is see is usually the thing for that.
Let's take a look code generation.
Where is the actual?
Whereas the actual call for that now, see, is don't strip comments.
That's not going to help us.
I just want to build just an obj.
What would I do for that?
Let's see, linking LG.
No, no, that's not what I want.
Miscellaneous know, like, let's see, output files, code generation.
I'm not seeing it, let's see.
There should just be a way for me to just I haven't done this in a
very long time.
I just compile everything but there's just a there's just one flag
that you put which is just like hey by the way
Just compiled just to when I would be J.
Don't produce an executable, don't do anything else.
Fancy can I just search for it?
See look like to less
It's question.
And if I search for
Obj.
No.
Maybe if I just do / f 0, it will just end specify the output object
file name.
It will infer that.
That's what I want to do.
I don't actually know but let's try it right.
- fo and there we go.
So let's see if that does anything for us - 02.
And if I just make in here handmade optimized dot CPP, right?
What happens.
There looks good.
So let's go ahead and go into render group.
And you know if we were to pull the straw rectangle quickly out here,
See you go.
Would that work?
I don't actually know.
So the first thing we have to do is we'd have to include like handmade
.h probably and the other thing that we have to do, this would come in
here.
Right.
and,
Declared but up finds out we would have to deal with a bunch of
annoying things.
Like the fact that I declare some Statics that don't get called
unfortunately but that would be mostly it.
So all I'd really have to do isn't handmade dot h at that point I
would just have to say, I guess in handmade render group.
Maybe I just have to say, Hey, you know, there's this file that you're
going to link with
It's external that you're going to link with and there you go.
There's always gonna soon will draw a rectangle quickly that's true
because of this.
So all we would really have to do now is figure out how to get around
that static function.
I'm not sure exactly what to do about that.
Probably I would do something like this where I would go.
Okay, wherever internal is actually gets to
find which is probably in handmade platform.
Wherever internal gets defined, I would do something like this if not
find internal.
Define internal, right?
Like that and then that way you could just say in the optimize thing.
Oh yeah all that stuff.
I said was internal I didn't really mean it.
You know I'm saying?
So yeah, so we could definitely do it that way.
We've got debug Global memory is is a unresolved external.
So that's got to be an extern, you both Global memory.
So let's take care of that.
You both Global memory.
Let's see here.
Typical memory is memory.
Why is that?
That's an extra in though.
I don't know why that is not
Why is that an unresolved external symbol?
Oh, because it's still trying to build the whole thing, isn't it?
Let's take a look.
I think this is almost it though.
So, yeah.
If I get rid of this.
Yeah.
So I just need the switch now, that'll tell it, please don't build a
whole thing.
I don't want, you know, don't link.
Can I do that?
How do I not link?
Let's see.
Here, CL compile C file to obj.
It's all I want.
It is / C.
But it didn't seem to didn't seem to be it.
Am I, am I nuts?
So confused right now.
Yeah.
But that was it.
So if we want to, that's one thing we can do and I think that should
fix it for us.
So let's let's double-check them in 32 handmade.
So with optimizations on now that one file that the draw a rectangle
quickly should be optimized.
So if I go ahead and look for the 1920, if we switch back to high-res
mode Let's see if we can run good speed.
Yeah.
So that's probably what we should do is leave the bill ballet because
that way we've got one file that we can just always leave
optimizations on for
And so only when we're actually debugging that, will we ever have to
actually switch out and everything else can always just be in debug
mode because our render Loop is the only thing that needs that
optimization.
So keeper, Caleb, if 1111 is supposed to be less than 0, 0.
0 0, then how do number comparisons were
Work on the CPU level.
I believe that number comparisons are special cased, so those are not
generic if that makes sense, but you can pretty easily take a look
actually.
So, what you can do is, for example, if you want to look here, here's
a signed 8-bit value, right?
- 100 here is a, a
Another one and then here are two unsigned ones.
Right?
And so if I do something like that,
32A because a less than b.
CD c less than bait.
Right?
So if I do that and then step in and look at the code, right, what we
can see here
Is what the assembly actually produces.
So if you right click and this is a good thing for to do any time
you're curious about this stuff, just take a look at the assembly
does, right?
Just take a look and then we can see.
So let's take a look.
We go ahead and do move.
S, SX, move SX, we load in the A and the B.
We compare the two, right?
Is X EC X, which is just trying to see what these two values are
actually looking like these.
To the sound comparison and then we do jump greater than or equal to,
which is what we would expect.
So they now they do exactly the same thing.
So they must be able to do.
The comparison.
Must do like a subtract on them that would, then it would then look to
see.
In fact, now that I think about it that would be fine.
Right?
Because what's greater than less than going to actually do?
It's going to do, you know, a
It's going to do.
Probably some kind of like a subtraction on the two values and then
look to see whether it's greater than or equal to the high-value right
now.
Let's think about this.
I don't know.
It's a good question.
Let's take a look.
but the answer is you can kind of see your comp J JG e jump right comp
jge jump so it does not care in any way which is which so let's take a
look at that that instruction comp x 36
compare two operands.
So, let's see here.
Set the status Flags, according to the results.
The comparison is performed by subtracting the second operator, for
the first operand and then setting the status Flags in the same manner
as the sub instruction.
When an immediate value is used as an operand.
It is sign extended to the length of the first operand.
So yeah.
So
It looks like.
So it looks like to me and these are encoded the same 3, BC one.
It looks like to me that that subtraction actually just works, right?
Let's see here.
It's a size by subtracting the second with Arista and then say, let's
see.
So let's see if we can make sense of that by looking at the table,
right?
So what I want to know, right?
Is If I subtract one value from another value, if
Want to do a less than comparison.
I want to know if these two values are less than each other, right.
Well, if I go ahead and subtract the two values like, you know, let's
say, I say, I want to know if negative three is less than 2 or
something like this.
What I and I subtract I subtract the two of them.
If I do too - -3 that would actually wrap me, I guess, I guess I need
smaller numbers here.
So let's say I do 2.
Minus minus 1 which would put me up to three in here.
It would be to compared to 7, right?
And that would also put me up to three right due to rapping
Now, if I were to do the opposite way round, right?
So I was to do two compared to negative one.
So I'm going to do negative 1 minus 2, right?
That would put me up to negative 3 and same here.
Put up 25.
So I wonder if you can basically just do is the value right after I
do.
The subtract is the value negative.
If the value is negative, then that's my answer.
Or if the value is positive then that's my answer, right?
Greater than or less than because
Yeah, if you think about it, that should just always work, right?
Because if the values, we don't care, whether the values are signed or
unsigned to some degree at that point, as long as that behavior is
consistent,
So, yeah, I think that's actually fine.
If I want to know if 2 is less than 5, right?
Let's say, so let's say, I do 5, minus 2 that equals 3, right?
If I do 2, minus 5, right?
So 2, minus 5 would be 1 2, 3 4 5, right?
Is that correct?
One, two, three, four, five.
That's right, right.
So yeah, it totally, I think that totally works.
So again, don't we're kind of out of time, but like I think it looks
like they don't have to be such a case that all it looks like you
could just literally use the signed math on any value.
When you do the comparison, even though it's unsigned.
And then whether or not the value would have been - in signed tells
you the answer in the comparison, whether it's signed or unsigned,
it's kind of magical,
Do you have any tips for speeding up compile time when using multiple
translation units?
Yeah, a few but it depends on the circumstances that probably be a
better question for when we have more time.
It's move, SX4 signed.
It well.
But that's that doesn't really have anything to do with it Sean though
because that's just making sure that it's sign extends the value,
right?
That's just making sure that because we're doing these on full-on, you
know, not on 8-bit registers.
Right?
That's just making sure that it loads in the values sign extended.
I don't think it changes the way.
The comparison works at all.
That makes sense.
Right.
So when it loads in these guys, right?
It's gonna
If we go to this assembly, when it loads in these guys with a sign
it's just going to sign extend them, right?
That's that's all that's doing because the value was only 8 Bits.
And now it's I'm extending, right?
Same thing with these guys sign extension.
So I'm pretty sure that it doesn't affect this at all.
That's literally just because of the of the fact that needs to sign
extend them.
Does that make sense?
All right, we have come to the end.
We have come to the end folks.
Yeah.
So, you know, not the best handmade hero stream, I was kind of out to
lunch today, it's true, but that just happens sometimes, you know,
can't always be on top of it and especially because it is so hot here.
I am literally melting.
Well I guess I'm not literally melting.
I just feel like I'm literally melting because I feels like my skin is
melting off.
Me in a very real and literal sense.
Okay, let's get rid of these guys here and let's leave that guy.
Is we can also if we want to maybe let's see common compiler Flags.
What we could do here is some kind of an OD 02 thing.
I don't, I don't know how we want that to play out.
I don't know how you unknown how you tell it.
I don't care about that but we can worry about that in a future
stream.
I suppose so.
Okay, we're all good, I guess.
I don't want to actually exit.
We saw how long it takes to load Mischief.
So we'll just leave that up and running until Monday.
And we'll go ahead and close these guys off.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, if you would like to
follow along with the source code at home, you always can handmade
here it out or you can pre-order.
The game comes with the
Full source code and you can go right ahead and tweak it.
Play with it experiment.
See how it goes.
Which is a great way to learn from the stream.
We also have Forum site.
You can ask questions, get forced to Mac or Linux and stuff like that
for trying to follow.
Along with those, you can also see an anti-democratic episode guide
maintained by the community.
It's pretty cool.
We have a patreon page if you want to support the video series, we
have a tweet bought the Tweet schedule.
You're trying to catch us live and in fact now would be a good time to
subscribe to that because this weekend will be posting schedule for
next week as we do.
Weekend and the sweet part is what will tell you when the video stream
is live.
So we'll be back here Monday and I will go ahead and drop the main
mixer Loop into s SE and then we will pretty much be done with audio.
I think there's not really much else you want to do, so we'll be able
to ping ping pong, back to our asset loader button up, how we want to
do the memory and then Define the asset file, and that'll be it.
And then, we could finally be loading out of a real asset file.
I'll make one for us and then we
and yeah, we can party on it.
It's going to be pretty wild actually.
So many of these things, getting checked off, audios going to get
checked off asset, loading that checked off, render is actually not
that far from being checked off.
Its got to go work on the lighting a little bit, letting particles
it's going to be good.
We're getting their people, we're getting there slowly, but surely
just like the little turtle.
All right, so that's about it.
I hope to see everyone back here on Monday until then have a great
weekend and
And, yeah, if you're doing any coding this weekend, best of luck
coding to you.
I will be doing some coding this weekend as well.
So hopefully, I'll see you on the Twitter's stop by and say hi.
Take care.
Everyone will see you on Monday.