Here we go.
Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game from scratch using nothing.
But our barest typing fingers.
No libraries.
No engine just so we can see basically everything that goes into a
games execution.
Every last thing and we're basically trying to make sure that we
understand everything that a computer does when running a game and at
this point in the process where actually fairly far along, we've made
a win32 prototyping layer we
Made a tilemap storage system for ourselves.
And we're starting to kind of we're trying to basically figure out
what our engine architecture should be like so that we can start to
write the engine, proper that will run our entire game.
And so one of the things that I push a lot in terms of good
programming practices that I think everyone should do is always
experiment and explore first before you design, it's always a good
idea to kind of let designs come out of an exploration rather than
trying to force them by
By doing design up front without really, knowing what you're getting
into and then trying to follow the design and finding out that it's
not so good.
And so that's really the process that we're going through right now.
We did that.
And we sort of came to a place where we were pretty happy with our
tile map system, which is just one aspect of how we need to design the
engine.
And so now we're kind of looking at just kind of wrapping that up a
little bit and then moving into some other things that we need to do.
There's a bunch of other stuff, obviously, beside the tile map that go
into, making a game.
And so we have to kind of start thinking about what those are.
Now, if you have pre-ordered the game, and there's a little bit more
to talk about today regarding this.
If you have pre-ordered the game on handmade here at dot org, using
the pre-order button, you will have gotten a email with obviously you
get access to all the source code.
But you also get access to all of the art assets that we use during
development.
And so one of the things I want to point out is normally I say at this
part of the stream, go to the link that's in that email and make sure
that you download the right source code to start with from today.
If
Want to follow along and today is the 36.
So you want to unzip day 35 source code, but for the first time today,
also, if you look on that link, when you when you go to that link, you
basically get presented with a bunch of things that you can download
that will kind of increase over time as we add more things to the
distribution instead of just the source code.
Now, you will also see a link to download the test assets and
basically these won't change very frequently like will only update the
test.
That's SS.
Every once in a while.
But since this is the first time everyone has to go and get the test
assets for sure.
Basically what they are is they're just a zip file that has in them
One Directory called test.
And what I want you to do is I want you to go ahead and put that into
our handmade directory.
So basically, you know, here's our source directory, right?
We have our code, we have our data, we have our misc and so on.
I got to remember to turn off Arrow Shake.
Someone sent me how to do it, but I forget how to do it.
But basically inside this data directory, what I want you to do is
basically go into that.
At data directory.
We're just going to drag the test executable.
I'm trying to test directory right in there.
And so then if you look inside there, now, we basically have a bunch
of bitmaps that I've prepared for us, which just have you know,
they're very simple files that just have some stuff that we're going
to use to experiment with and you can kind of see if you click on
them.
We just got some stuff.
None of these are final assets for the game or anything but they're
basically like pieces of a character and a shadow that we can use.
There's some layers for for basically.
Like a for a scene that we're going to test with if for some reason
and I don't really know what the reason is Windows, doesn't display
bitmaps properly.
I'm not sure if you've noticed this but like basically like if you if
you have a bitmap a BMP file that has like I'm trying to think of all
those one of them here if you have a BMP that actually has
transparency in it like it tends to go wonky on me.
Like you can see this has transparency here, right?
Like or something.
What was the one that just looked really weird?
So like this looks really weird.
Testing layer 0 1.
So testing layer 0 1.
If I open that up with gimp, I believe that it looks correct, right.
Yeah, you can kind of see that looks correct.
There's a transparent region.
All the colors look roughly like they do, right?
And this is the background from like the website and stuff.
But for some reason, if you look at them in the windows photo viewer,
like Windows couldn't manage to load a BMP.
Now, this is amusing because
well, I mean windows, they're the people who invented the BMP file
format.
So somehow they don't know how to read their own file format.
What you going to do?
That's just that's life in Windows.
Ladies and gentlemen, sometimes you don't know how to read your own
file format, I guess anyway, basically what we're going to be doing
possibly later today, if not tomorrow, depending on where we get to
is, we're going to be starting to use these assets.
I'm going to show you how to load them in, and I'm going to show you
how to use them.
You know, on the screen and stuff just to get things started because I
wanted to have for us to be able to start looking at the scale of
things and how things looked on the screen.
And so we're going to have to write, probably not really the renderer
yet because that's like a huge involved process that will start a
start on and do many days worth of like explaining how render is work
and how all the math works and how we want to approach them and so on.
But we're going to write basically some very simple little system that
can just load bitmaps and put them up on the screen.
So that we, as we
We sort of move forward with our engine architecture.
We won't be Flying Blind because rectangles can get us a certain can
get us only so far.
Basically, in terms of making good decisions about how things are
supposed to work.
So, please make sure that if you're trying to follow a home that you
go ahead and do that.
Hopefully you've already done.
It should be pretty simple again.
Just go to that link, download handmade Hero Test assets, zero zero,
one dot zip and I will notify you guys any time that you need to
download a new one.
But like I said, they should be pretty infrequent because
They are batch up a bunch of new assets that I when I know we're
working on something in particular and I know we're going to be
assets.
I'll patch them up.
So we shouldn't need.
You shouldn't need to update.
This it hardly at all.
It should be very infrequent.
But once in a while, you will have to do it as we start using
different assets types and stuff like that.
All right, so that's basically the situation that we're in.
So now that we've got that going, let's go back to where we were on
Friday because we had a couple Loose Ends.
If I remember correctly, that we need to tie off namely just walking.
And up and down through doors.
So basically up and down through like stairwells.
Basically, if I remember correctly.
What we sort of said is okay.
We've basically wanted to have two planes of our tile map system, one
like sort of an upper and a lower plane that we tried to make and we
have like this concept of a Dora but we are sorry stairwell.
Like in between them when we have tile that goes, you up a level and a
tile that goes down a level, but we don't actually have any code to
handle what happens when you actually move on to one, right?
So, basically, when you
Move on to one of these.
We need to have some way that allows you to kind of change up and
down.
And again, this was not to do anything specific.
It was just to make sure that we could have our tile map system
working with two different planes.
So that, you know, we could have basically a z component.
And once we handle this e component properly, we did it in a generic
way.
So it should be able to handle as many planes as we want.
We can have as many layers like stacked on top of each other as we
want to have.
Okay.
So basically what we need to do is we need to make some changes.
Has to the to the player code and since we don't really have real
player code yet since we haven't really addressed that, it's going to
be a little harder than it should be because basically all we've got
is a thing that just kind of like checks to see where the player is
going to be and then moves them, right.
This is the player code that we have.
We basically create a new player position.
We check to see whether the player can move wherever it's going to be.
And then we kind of have this sort of acceptance function which
basically says, okay except the new location.
And so what we kind of want to do here is if the player moves
Is onto the style.
We want to do an action at the time, when they move on to it, right?
That's basically what we're trying to do.
We're trying to do something that basically says, you know, if they
moved on to a new tile.
Meaning, basically, if new player P, if the new player Pete, I'll
index is not the same as the old player Pete.
I'll ex-player tile index, then we want to do something.
So basically what I'm going to do is I'm just going to introduce a
function here that I can call.
Basically.
I just something I want to I basically want to
Predicate, I want to be able to say, you know, tile are on same tile
or something like that.
I just want to be able to make that statement.
I want to ask that question and say, if they weren't on the same tile,
then what I want to do is just take an action.
I want to look to see what this is.
And now, when we do more player movement code will actually have a lot
more formalized ways of doing this, and what happens with some of
these onto a tile.
But for now, I'm just going to go ahead and check for the two things
that we set up again.
We just had sort of, this is all.
Scratch code to see how things work, but we basically said that door
ups were three Door downs were for.
So I'm just going to check for those and again, because this code is
all getting nuked for much more for different code later.
I'm not actually being specific about these things.
I don't care about pound to finding them to real things, or making a
numerous or anything like that, because we're not going to be doing
anything like this.
In the final code.
This is just sort of glue code.
That allows us to test other systems.
And then later, when it comes time to actually focus on it.
It will all get blown away and will, you know, kind of move forward.
Same with like that, you know our level generation code is all exactly
that.
It's just total crap code.
That's just there to sort of glue things together and let us move
forward with our experimentation.
And the reason again that I don't try to do a good job on that kind of
code.
I only do the bare minimum is because I just don't want to waste a lot
of time thinking about how that code should work at the wrong time.
I would say one thing that's worth mentioning is there is a context
which cost oftentimes encoding where if you're working on one thing
and you go switch to working on another thing.
There is a cost in terms of your brain and how
Like sort of ready it is and how much stuff it's got paged in almost
like a virtual memory system, right?
For the particular problem that you're working on.
And so one thing that I'd like to do is when I'm concentrating on one
thing.
I like to try and just keep concentrating.
That one thing even if that means putting bad code in some other
place, as long as I know that the bad code is there, and I'm aware.
That that's the code that needs to not be there.
Eventually.
I'm okay with that because basically I want to focus on the thing.
I'm focusing on and get as much sort of utility out of my brain sort
of focus.
On that part as I can.
And so I don't want to spend a lot of time doing things like thinking
about how to specify tile values because I know later, we're going to
spend a whole bunch of time thinking about how we specify table hours.
So, any time we spend Now is really just kind of wasted.
So that's said, what I want to do is I want to get the tile map value
at this point that the player is at when I determined that they move
to a new location, right?
So this new player pee, wherever they are.
I'm going to go ahead and sort of grab with the tile value is there.
So basically, I'm going to go to our town map functions that we
Have, if you remember, we pulled them out into the separate file here
and I'm basically going to just ask what that tile value is.
So I'm going to basically try to, let's see where it is, get tile
value right here.
And I'm going to, I'm going to want to get that towel value.
Now, one of the things we probably want to do.
We're probably going to want a function that gets the tile value
directly from a player position, because why not?
And so, I'm probably going to introduce a tile value call AB, it's
just basically a proxy call to our other call, which will do that sort
of cracking for us.
It takes a player position in brakes.
It out into the smaller values.
So basically we have a tile map and I'm just going to put past that
new player key and I'm going to say, give me what the tile value, is
at that location.
So this is like the new tile value and then I'm going to say, all
right, if the new tile value equals, what did we say that?
It was three and a four, I believe is what we said.
So if the new tile value
Is a three then we are going to go a door up.
So 3 is a door up.
Means that our new player P is technically going to become a, whatever
their abs tiles e was, is going to go up 1, right this.
And if it is a, if the new tile value is a 4 then they are going to go
down 1, right.
That's all I want to do there and then we'll accept the player
position.
Now what we could also do here, we could actually treat this as
another check move.
We could verify that the tile and the other side was empty, but at the
moment, like I said, I don't really
think we want to deal with that kind of stuff because it's really not
important that's going to be something we have to think about more
when we get to later stages of things for now.
We know we always Place doors up and doors down symmetrically.
So it's fine.
So is tilemap point empty.
We also have to modify because at the moment is tilemap empty.
Was only basically allowed to return true if the tile chunk value is
1.
But really what we're allowing it to do now is sort of say there's a
bunch of things that sort of classify as empty if you will, right?
There's there's threes and fours are now also considered empty, right?
So we need to kind of say oh you can move on to something.
That's a 1, 2 3, A 1 3, or a 4.
And so what, it's go ahead and do that.
And that way, these these checks won't fail when the player tries to
move on to a door.
And then similarly, the get Tau value function.
Like I said before I want to be able to pass a tile map position to
that as well.
So we'll go ahead and do that here and that is just going to call get
Tau value.
It's really just a pass-through that's going to call.
Excuse me.
Me that get Tau value function for the the poses components.
So that's just it's really just a utility.
It's so that I don't have to type that if the something that I'm going
to call fairly frequently, which I suspect that it is, I'm just going
to go ahead and do that, right?
Oh, why is there still an empty there?
I got mixed up there.
This is actually a return value.
That's just lazy code that surround it is a bit hard for me.
Like I said, many times programming on the stream is a little bit
tough sometimes because
Basically, like it's hard.
It's harder for me to focus when I have to talk and so code kind of
gets a little strange.
It's weird.
I can't explain the feeling.
It's just a little.
It's like a little hazy.
It's a lot hazier than I am when I'm normally programming.
So it's tough.
It's definitely, it's definitely like running a marathon with the
weight belt on.
Anyway, let's see here.
So are on.
Same tile.
Now, we have to implement.
We did not Implement that before.
So I'm going to go ahead and put that in here.
I don't know, eventually.
I feel like we probably
We want to put stuff like, you know re canonicalize physician and
stuff like that.
Now that I think about it like these things really don't have anything
to do with well, I guess they do have something to do with the time.
I because they involve the time applications and that's how sided M
cross the tile side and M isn't really related as much to the time of
blah blah blah blah.
I can see moving.
Basically.
I guess here's what I'd say.
There's stuff in here that really doesn't have anything to do with the
tile map and I think I might kind of
Not that those things to be capped off at some point like these things
really are about tilemap positioning and they have nothing to do with
the actual tile map.
Like the only insofar as they care about the tile map.
All they really care about is how big a tile is.
And that really has nothing to do with the tile map storage.
Right?
And so I'm going to kind of Mark these here, I'm just going to say, do
these really belong in more of a positioning, or a geometry files.
Alright, like and, and sort of just think about that because I feel
like that's probably going to be the case that there really if they're
inappropriately part of this tile map, and they don't really need to
be there.
So, anyway, we now can go back here and say, well, we've got these two
tilemap positions, right?
I've got a Tom, a position, a, and a Tom at position B, and I want to
know, like I said, when there are on same tile, I want to know whether
or not their tile differs or not.
Now it's going.
Nora basically these do things right?
And so whether or not the tile differs is really trivial.
If they're on the same tile than all of their tile in to see portions
will be the same.
Right.
Each individual.
One of these groups should be an and each individual, one of their
components should be exactly the same.
Otherwise, they are on a different tile like that, and then we'll
return that result.
There we go.
And so then I'll go ahead and compile that let's take a look right.
These need to be addresses of these.
These fellows here.
And there we go.
So I believe.
Now we should be able to walk onto this and hey, look, it worked.
We went up a level.
We can go back down a level again, right?
So when we move on, there we go, back up a level and I can, of course.
Go ahead.
I think I've got a speed key.
I do there is a down.
Whoa.
Okay, so that seems a little bit busted.
So I think I've still got some broken code here, because if I remember
correctly, there should only be one exit other than the one you came
in.
So the only
Two exits from any room, but we're clearly adding a door to every
room.
So, basically, that's that's just not at all right?
In terms of the generation code.
So let's take a look at the generation code because I think the
generation code is just plain busted, and we'll take a look at what's
going on there.
So, let's see here, what we have
Okay, so I based, I see what's going on.
Yeah, this is this is busted.
So basically, the way we were doing things before is we basically
said, okay, we have a door up and we have a door down.
We pick a random choice.
And if the random choice is to, we go ahead and we make a door up or
add or down depending on whether or not we're on the top or the bottom
layer.
Right.
Now, what that means is when we get to the end, when we move to the
next room, if door up or down was true or false.
We should we want to do the
For the other room because we're going to make a room below it or
above it.
And we want it to have the corresponding door.
So we basically flip those.
The problem is when we come back through this, again, the next time
door up or down is now set to true or false.
We make that corresponding door, but then we toggle it again.
So we're just going to keep on making doors ad infinitum.
What we really wanted to do here is if we come into the random Choice
with door up or door down.
Or already equaling true or false, right?
Then what we want to do is make sure that we don't make that we want
to remember whether we added a nude or not.
And only if we added a new door do that thing where we keep it.
Otherwise, we want to clear it.
Right.
So, basically, we have a couple things we need to do here.
First of all, if there's already a door up or down, we don't want to
add another one, right?
So we want to basically say, if not door up and not door down and
random choice.
We'll see you basically or I guess we could say.
Oh, we already did that nevermind, if door up or down.
Okay, we already took nevermind.
We heard he took care of that case.
I'm one step ahead of myself.
We already took care of that case.
So we won't do that.
So the only thing we have to do is remember if we created a door up or
down, then we do the toggle.
Otherwise, we don't want to do the toggle right.
Now.
The other thing we could do here is when we do this toggle, if we do
the door up door down toggle, we could also just check to make sure,
you know, we could do something like this.
Basically, we could do if door left or door, right?
Forward, or down or door up.
Sorry, or door, top or door bottom, right?
We could say something like as long as we know that we didn't have any
other door.
Then we know that these doors are the ones that we came through and we
need to toggle the right, if that makes sense or rather.
I should say the other way around as long.
We know that we had one of these other doors in our thing as well.
Then we know that we need to toggle them.
If we didn't have another type of door, that means that we were a door
up or down.
So we should come through here.
I'll think that's going to work though because
Yeah, I think that's still going to be I that's going to be just dumb
because that's going to also hit another bad guy.
So I don't even know why I was thinking of doing that.
That's dumb.
Let's just leave it at basically doing the if here.
We're we're only going to do this toggle, basically, trying to think
of what the easiest way to do.
This year is I guess we want to do.
We just want to basically say if created vertical, you know, if
created Z door, right?
If we create a disease door, then we want to we want to do that.
Otherwise we want to do the false and I think we want to assert here
that the that we only have the two cases if that makes sense, right?
And in fact, if we know we created a z door.
Or then we really know.
I guess that these are just toggles, we know that whatever it was it
just a toggle, right?
So we're just going to we're just going to go ahead and toggle these.
There we go.
That's I like that better space.
We're going to say if we created if we created one of those to Z doors
on this particular.
Yeah, if we created one of the Z doors on this particular one, then we
know that the next one has to have the inverse doors of that.
But if we didn't create a z door, then there shouldn't be a door.
There shouldn't be any Z doors on the next one at all.
It should write only be corresponding doors.
So I think that's a little bit easier.
So I'm just going to say created Z door.
That is false and then I'll basically say, well actually, you know
what, I can do it.
Yeah, no, I have to do it this way.
So basically, in here will basically say created seed or will equal
true right there.
And then when we do it, that should do the toggle or the clear.
And I hope that will be a relatively clear way of avoiding that
problem.
All right.
So if we look at here, now, I go up.
Let's see.
We should not have a z door, and that's true.
And we should only have another Z door.
Once we get to a dead end to basically, here.
We are at the dead end.
We go down a level.
There we go, we go up.
Here we go up again.
There we go.
So there we go.
We're starting to get pretty respectable tile map here people.
I mean this is basically done, you know, this is dungeon ask.
I'm feeling a little dungeon a here, you know, I could I could see
being in a dungeon at this point in time in my life.
You know, that's something that I feel like a lot of people need to
leave and find themselves in Europe and so on.
And right now we're finding ourselves in a little tilemap dungeon,
right?
And there's nothing in the dungeon and there's no loot to be had.
So I'm not sure why we're in the dungeon, but I guess the reason that
we're here is to program all that loot and make it there be a reason
to walk around these but hey.
Hey, it's pretty Pleasant already.
So there we go.
All right, so we basically now know roughly an API that works.
Okay?
For creating a tile map, and that gives us a good starting point.
So, I would say that we have sort of succeeded in, in sort of our, our
goal of getting a first pass design by experimenting.
Like this is a reasonable tile map API.
And if we wanted to go, start implementing good, Spar storage for it
or other things like that.
We could and know that it would be somewhat usable now.
That doesn't mean it's perfect and we're probably as we get a little
further along, going to find, we need to revise it.
But that's okay.
We've kind of done the exploration that we need to be a little bit
comfortable in the sorts of things that happen here and I'm okay with
that.
Now, I'm looking at this and says, should this be, should these be
from the center of a tile?
I believe we already did that.
I'm so I can get rid of that.
And for now, I guess we'll kind of just leave this this way, the tile
rail X and tile.
I guess we'll call this offset X and offset why?
I don't know and say,
They know Casey.
These are the offsets from The Tile Center and then I will go ahead
and and change all of those.
So tile rail will become offset for now.
That's my that's my official verdict.
So there we go.
Doo-doo-doo-doo ago and now and I think that's that's, you know,
pretty reasonable.
I can I, you know, I'm okay with that.
Yeah, so at this point like I was saying before, what I kind of wanted
to do is I was thinking about what's the next thing that we're going
to want to do?
And I, like I said, we are probably going to want to start dealing
with things like player, motion and collision and that sort of stuff
and sort of animation and all that sort of thing.
Because once we have a tile map to move around, there's really two
things we can do, we can start trying to figure out how to draw the
tile map with better graphics, but we also have to figure out how to
make the the game kind of
Bowl and replace the player movement code with real movement code and
get some monsters in their stuff like that.
Right?
We need to, we need both of those things.
If you think about the next sort of things that we're going to do.
And so I feel like no matter which of those, we pick, whether we want
to do player movement, code, and stuff like that and collision
detection, or whether we want to do better tile Maps.
We're going to have to start dealing with putting some graphics on the
screen that are at least place of look reasonable Place holders for
what might actually be on the screen when the game actually ships.
And so that's why I was thinking.
The next thing we kind of need.
To do is start loading bitmaps if that makes sense.
So that's what I'd like to do for today.
Maybe our goal for today is just going to sort of be to put a bitmap
up on the screen.
Nothing particularly fancy, but just get a bit map up on the screen
from a file so that we can sort of pull art in as we sort of like that
we can start using for our prototyping purposes from here on out.
Hopefully everyone's okay with that as some sort of a decision point,
but let's go ahead and take a look at that.
Basically what we're going to
Do is we're going to try and load one of these bitmap files.
Like I said at the beginning of the stream, which is where I need a
little handmade shortcut there.
So basically, what we need to do is we need to go to handmade and I
need to, like, do you know, like this, this needs to be pinned?
There we go, handmade.
So in the data directory inside test, right?
We've got some various things here and test background is a probably a
good example of something we should.
Probably try to load.
It's basically just, you know, some trees, some mushrooms.
And some grass, right?
Just it's just like a background image, right?
And if we take a look at the size of this background image, right?
If I go into details here, you can see that.
It's 1024 by 576, right?
So if I go in here and take a look at our code inside win32, when we
open up basically our window, right?
When we said, how big we wanted things to be,
If you remember correctly, I kind of was saying well for our renderer
will make it a little smaller.
And so there was some geometry that went on here and I'll put a note
in so that it people can remember, basically, 1920 by 1080 is
currently like a standard HD resolution for a game nowadays, right?
You know.
if you're trying to run a game in HD, typically, 1080p is
Good standard.
That's, this is this is 1080p display mode, right?
This is how this is the resolution on a 1080p display.
And so, you know, if that was sort of what we were targeting for
handmade here, I was saying well, that's what the GPU will be doing.
That will probably try to do that with a GPU.
But if we don't have a GPU so for our own renderer because we will be
much slower than a GPU.
Obviously.
What I want to do is basically say, Okay, reduce that by half, right?
And
And if we take a look, see if I can use the quick calc thing.
We discovered.
Let's see 19 20 divided by 2.
You can kind of see that.
Basically, if we divide both values by 2, we get this 960 by 540.
So basically half of that is 1960 by six by 540.
So as the saying, let's run it half resolution because then it'll be
easy for us to just imagine.
Well, okay, everything will just be twice as dense.
Pixelize.
It'll just look much nicer when we go up to doing gpus, but basically,
our screen aspect ratio and everything else will be basically the
same, it'll be nice and easy, but what you'll notice is the details
here make are a little bit weird, like 10.
For by fences by 576.
Doesn't really make much sense.
When you think about the fact that our screen is 960 by 540.
So why did I make a bitmap?
That was that sighs.
The reason that I made a bitmap that size is because, at least in GPU
land, a lot of times you want your textures to be a power of 2 in size
for reasons that we can talk about later on.
Basically, when we get down to GPU things.
We'll talk about that a little bit more, but for right now, we'll
simply say that power of two textures tend to be a very handy thing.
To be able to have on GPU side.
So thinking about powers of 2 and looking at 1920 by 1080.
The first thing that you might say is well, 1920 by 1080 is a pretty
inconvenient number in terms of a power of 2.
If you wanted to round it 1920 is pretty easy to fix.
20:48 is a power of 2 that's very close to that.
And so if you think about it 2048 - 1920 right if I oops that's not
good.
Let's do a quick calculation.
So
48 - 1920 is only 128 pixels difference.
Right?
So you're only losing 128 pixel band.
If you went up to 22 to 2048 on the other hand, the closest power of
2.
And again, it's not really the close of our to, it's the next power of
2 up, right?
Because you can't have less than that.
I need to fill the whole screen.
So if I wanted to do a 1080 as a power of 2, I have a problem because
basically 1024 is too small.
That's the closest.
Power of two, right?
But 2048 is massively away, which is the next pair of to up from that.
So too, if I do a quick count there of 2048 - 1080 I'm wasting 968
pixels, which doesn't really make
Very much sense, right?
That is just not very economical at all.
And there's even with screen Shake.
There's no you no chance.
You're ever going to use 968.
So you would never make a bleed.
You would never overdraw by that many pixels.
It's crazy.
You're just throwing away.
Good memory at that point.
So what I was thinking was basically what's the next power of 2?
You could basically use that would be sort of 1024 plus another band
to store the bottom of the image.
Well, basically if you think of what it would take to get past 1080 at
that point, you could, if you wanted to add 64 to it, right?
You could have one power of two texture that was 1024 or one power of
two that 64 and basically what I'm talking about.
Just in case so that you can see it as I've got, you know, oops.
That's that's a that's one heck of a, of a rectangular Casey.
So if I have 1920 by 1080 and I want to figure out how to fit this
into a power of two thing.
Basically what I'm saying is well, okay, 20:48, if you if you add 128
pixels here, then 2048 isn't really isn't too much of a waste.
Is there.
Especially when you consider the fact that you know, if you had a bit
map that was drawn, that was meant to fill the whole screen.
And you want to be able to do a little bit of screen shake or
something like that.
You're just going to be a little bit of bleed.
Right?
So 64 pixels on either side is not too much to think about in terms of
bleed, right?
64 here and 64 here is not too much.
So 1920 + 64, + 64 ends up.
Getting us to 2048 which would be roughly the you know, the size of
what would be a nice power of to size that we could use with gpus.
Right, but the problem is the next power of 2 that we would have to
break too.
Attend 1080, we don't want 2048 for that.
That Dimension because it would be way too large.
We wasting a ton of space.
So we only have 10 24.
Now, 1024 is going to cut off a little bit too soon, right?
It's going to cut off.
Where did I do the calculation?
I don't know.
I thought I did it but I guess I didn't do it.
So if we do a 1024 1080 - 1024 is 56, right?
So we have to store 56, more pixels, which means that we could
Could use a 64 wide texture we could stop at 10:24, and then use a 64
wide right here.
Another Bando.
We could basically store screen size things into chunks one chunk,
that looks like this and one chunk, that looks like that.
Right.
But now we've got another problem if we're saying that we want some
screen shake and we want like 64 is a good, is what we're saying is
might be a reasonable number for screen shake or maybe 32.
I don't know how much we're basically saying.
With our 60 for the actual number that this ends up being if I go
ahead and do the quick Cal combat, right?
If I do 1024 + 64, I'm only at 1088.
Which means I only have four pixels on either side, which isn't very
much for screen shake.
So I probably want something that's going to be higher than that.
And so basically, what I when I was kind of working this map out
myself and trying to think about how I wanted the source art to be
done for the The Source bitmaps I was saying well, okay, if I go with
sort of so 576, right?
If you go ahead and double 576 you will see that it ends up being
11:52.
Is that, is that correct?
Yeah.
So if I - 1024 from that list, I think this is correct.
Maybe I made a mistake her.
Yeah, it's 128.
So basically what I was what I was basically saying was okay if we use
a 128 texture instead of a 64 texture.
So we store it into chunks of 2128 texture then we'd have
Then we would have a number that was that was more closely able to
more able to give us that apron at the top and the bottom is basically
I'm saying.
So if I subtract 80 from that I get 72, right?
So if I divide that by 2, I get 36 pixels on either side.
So now I have 36 pixels on on top and bottom for screen Shake.
I have 64 on either end for screen shake and that seemed to me like a
pretty reasonable sort of breakdown of screen geometry.
Now, I
It all sounds kind of crazy and it is a little bit crazy.
But basically, I was just trying to figure out.
I was like, I kind of want everything to sort of fit into power of two
sizes as much as possible.
What would be the most reasonable way to sort of do the source art?
So that's going to be amenable to that kind of packing and that to me
seemed like the most reasonable thing.
Now that may not be the smartest.
I don't know.
But that was just my opinion.
This sort of, this is the sort of thing.
You don't deal with in 3D Graphics because 3D Graphics work in a very
different way than this, because of the way.
You do sort of wrapping of textures around models.
And that's the way I'm usually used to thinking about things.
So this may be a bad decision.
We'll see, but it seems like a pretty harmless one because at the end
of the day, all the sources are being drawn with an apron around it.
We can always get rid of the apron if we don't want it.
So if you don't want that extra room for screen shake or whatever, we
can always get rid of it, but I figured having it drawn with the apron
was actually probably a good idea.
So long story short or tldr at this point.
Basically, if you want to skip all that isolation,
Reason that these are larger than the actual size that we're going to
be just displaying in terms of one screens with is because of that
apron, that's there.
So they're all a little bit larger and they're designed to be a little
bit larger for that reason.
Okay, so given that fact.
And now we kind of have this sort of I'm going to I'm going to leave
this Ridiculousness in here for now.
Right.
There we go.
So I basically said, 1024 plus 128.
I need to find a key to quit calc.
That's what I need to do.
1024 plus 128 is a
52.
So basically, yeah, I should probably fill that in a little bit more.
Densely it eventually but we'll just leave it like that for now.
So basically what we want to do here is we want to load these images
knowing they're a little bit big, but we're going to basically try to
load them and get them up onto the screen just so we can kind of see
that things are working properly.
So basically we want this draw rectangle call.
We want the equivalent of this draw rectangle call, right, but what we
want to do with the draw a rectangle call is.
We want to be able to instead of just passing a solid color.
We want to instead.
Of just just having one color that the rectangle fills in.
On the screen.
We want to be able to pass essentially, you know, a bitmaps worth of
data here.
So that the draw rectangle call can actually draw, you know, a real
set, a real set of artwork to the screen inside that rectangle, right?
And again, we're not going to focus too intently on this here because
this is stuff that we'll be doing much more industrial strength and we
start the renderer proper, but I just need to get something working
here.
So I'll explain it lightly and I won't belabor it too much, but
You will sort of knowing that will sort of drill down a lot of this
stuff later.
So I'll try to give you enough context to understand what's going on.
But at least for the rendering side of things, putting it up on the
screen.
I'm not going to kind of believe it.
But so, anyway, right now, we basically just need to type in some code
for load for loading a bitmap.
Right?
And I don't know what that's gonna look like.
So I'm just going to go ahead and create a blank function here.
I know that we have in our in our platform code, right?
We have our handmade platform code, we set ourselves up for Success.
Hopefully here.
Because we have this this sort of debug file reading system, right?
Where we can call anything that reads an entire file into memory.
So what I want to do is make sure that this function takes that thing
right, whatever that is and where do we actually put that?
So that was debug platform.
I don't even remember where we stuck it.
So, inside, game memory, we've got these.
When we pass the game memory.
It's got these in it, so
What's going to happen here is this guy is going to need this
function, this read entire file.
So basically, I'm just gonna go ahead and pass that.
This is the function that he's going to need.
This is obviously a debug function as well.
I guess now, I think about it because we're not going to be probably
loading bitmaps for the final shipping version will probably want to
load something that's compressed.
At least bitmaps are really compressed air if they are compressed and
uncompressed very well.
So what we're going to do here is we're going to have this read and
tar file.
We're going to call it and presumably we're going to need a file name,
I guess as well that we're going to have to call.
All that we're gonna have to pass Orient, our file.
So we know which file to read.
So basically we are going to do at least that much to read this file.
So what we need to do there is when we go ahead and read the file into
memory.
Let's see what the debug platform read entire file thing, takes.
I don't actually know it takes a thread context.
So it's going to need that as well and it takes the file name.
So basically that's it.
Really.
That's all there is to it.
Not not particularly interesting.
So basically it just needs to do
So when we read this entire file into memory, we're basically going to
get a buffer, right?
We're going to get the file contents.
So that's going to literally move all of the bits there in this file
into a memory buffer for us to look at.
So then the question is, what do those bits actually mean?
Well, this is basically if for those of you haven't done it before,
here is your crash course in how to read file formats.
Assuming that you don't know what the file format is.
You first have to look it up on the web.
And typically I do this literally by typing in something that looks
like that.
I type in the name of the file that I the like extension that I want
to know about.
I type in file format and I hope that's
Somebody has actually documented what it is.
I then try to look at these links to see if any of them look even
remotely plausible.
And I don't know if any of these do.
Let's take a look here.
Let's see.
This looks pretty plausible.
It looks like it's actually got sort of the stuff that we actually
need to know here.
Let's see.
It's running file, type file size.
These have BM in front of them.
These don't ddb only file, header.
Yes.
So this looks this looks relatively.
This looks relatively straightforward for us.
I think I'll see anything wrong reason.
We can't use this.
So if we look at the file organization here, basically what it shows
us is, it shows us the layer.
The layout of these things right here, since Windows one point, x is
probably not something that that anyone is using these days.
I'm going to assume that the bitmap data here is in the file format
that they're talking about for two, three and four, right?
And so basically what they're showing me here is they're just showing
me what they think is in the file.
They're saying there's a file header a bit.
I've had her a color palette and bitmap data right now.
I know that I saved these files as rgba data basically, so I know that
there isn't going to be a color palette.
I know, you know, I know that I don't have to worry about palletized
colors.
Like palletize, colors are basic things where we store indexes into a
palette instead of the actual colors, but I know we're actually
storing colors.
And in fact, I when I, when I was exporting it through gimp, I
actually selected like that.
I want it to be a RGB like 88 or whatever.
Like basically the same format, a roughly, the same format as we were
using
And for all of our rendering, so I'm assuming that should be pretty
easy to get it out of the file.
Alright, so basically what it says here, for that version 2, which is
I'm assuming, what our, what our version is like, or though.
Maybe I guess version 3 is probably more.
We're like, I don't know, Windows NT.
I mean, these are going back real far.
So I'm guessing that we're probably.
Let's see.
Let's see here.
This version has three additional Fields.
The bitmap header is 40, bytes in length and has the following format.
There it goes.
So yeah, I guess I don't know if this is the best resource for this.
They're not really this map for.
They're not really saying much which one I'm kind of going to which
one I'm likely to encounter here.
And yeah and which one?
Well, so let's just take a look.
So rather than find another resource.
I think I'm actually going to kind of go with this one just so I can
show you some things.
So we're going to load in the contents here, right?
And then what I'm going to do is I'm just going to go ahead and well,
you know what?
I'm just going to go ahead and and have that sort of end here.
I'm just going to do some Dummy Line of code.
I can stop on and then I will.
What is this saying?
Cannot convert from debug read file to void star?
What are you trying to convert to void star?
Oh, right.
We have a debug file read.
Result is what we have platforming file read results.
Where did my platform?
It's debug read files out.
There we go.
So, basically, this is going to be our Central, ER, result.
It's the, the read result.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
And then we have our read result has the contents in it and how big it
was.
So that's totally fine.
So now all I'm going to do is
To go ahead and call this basically, in game update and render, I
guess when we initialize.
So when we initialize I'm just going to call the loading function and
I know that we always run in our data directory or that's where we're
always supposed to be running.
Anyway, so I'm just going to ask it to load load this test background
up, BMP background that the MP and I'm just going to look at what the
data looks like.
I'm just going to look at it because I should be able to figure out
pretty quickly, which one of those things.
These are by just looking at it.
So I'm going to go ahead and and compile it.
I need to pass that Fred.
Context, let's see here.
And I also need to pass the file function.
So I need to pass the memory, debug read entire file, right?
I don't remember what exactly that was called.
Let's see here.
Debug platform read entire file.
So I'm just going to call that.
There we go.
So, when I come in here now, where is my debugger?
Where is my debugger people?
There's my debugger.
Okay, is this guy still on?
Oh, he's still on.
Thing I used to download its get rid of that.
Okay.
So basically now that I've now that I have cleaned up my screen a
little bit here.
When we come into the game update and render, right?
I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to run through here and I'm going
to step into this function and take a look at what it returns for me
when I come back through here.
So, basically, when I come in here and I asked it to read the entire
file, first of all, verify that it actually did read the entire file.
Because, you know, I don't know.
You know, if it did, it looks like it did.
There's the, the size of the file and then I have the content.
So I'm just going to go ahead.
I'm just going to look at the contents basically, as, as just a series
of bytes.
I'm just going to take a look at what it looks like.
I'm going to put a comma 64 after the end of it, so I can see a bunch
of the bytes.
And so, I can see here that it starts with a beat, the BM syntax,
which I believe I saw them document in here.
So, they were saying that it starts with a header.
That is, that is BM.
So, here you go.
So file type.
Always 44d 42 H.
And it says, all versus Beauty profiles, begin with the following
Fortune by headers.
Okay, so that's a guess, what we were.
The file type, there's a file size, two zeros, and then an offset of
where the image is right in the file.
So, let's see if that looks like it looks like what we think.
So there is the be in the m and then there's the size of the file in
bytes as a dword.
So that's basically this right here.
So is that actually accurate would be, I guess, be my next question.
So let's say that we have something like
Like this.
So we have the contents.
I'm going to add 2 to it, there.
To get us to where we said we were yet.
There we go.
And then I'm going to go ahead and look at that as a unit 32, right?
As the UN 32 pointer.
There we go.
So it is that actually reasonable.
That doesn't actually oops.
Am I doing that?
Right?
No, I'm not.
Let's try that again.
People.
It's so hard to edit things in this.
Nothing.
Basically, what I want you to do is I want you to make read result be
a un Tate star.
Okay, there you did that.
Oops.
Sorry result, contents, be un8 star, which you did then.
I want you to add 2 to it, which I hope that you did, right.
And then I want you to treat that as a you went.
You went 32, I guess maybe it doesn't actually know what those are
those.
So maybe I have to do in done signed and Care star.
Unrecognized token.
What is the unrecognized token?
What are you complaining about?
I do not actually know that.
I've got one too many parentheses.
Is that what you're complaining about?
That is probably what you're complaining about.
There we go.
All right.
Okay, so there I'm just telling it to look at the second thing as a
unit 32, and it looks like.
And so, by the way, just for my own sanity.
I just want to make sure that it was okay for me to do this.
Because I'm assuming that it knows my types inside the debugger
because it should, I'm going to guess it doesn't have to but should
yeah, there we go.
So basically I'm just going to look at that as a un 32 which is a d
word and there it is.
That does look like the file size.
So that's all good.
Then we're supposed to have two zeros after that.
So we've got 0
Let's see.
These are the that was the d word.
So they've got two zeros, which it does look like they are because
those are both 16 16 B 0.
So there's the 16-bit zeros right there.
And then we've got the bitmap offset, which is where in the file, it
actually is.
So there it is.
And that looks reasonable.
That just be a deer that be 138.
So I think that we are basically looking at exactly this.
Right.
This is exactly what we are looking at.
And so we could just go ahead and and assumed that, that was all true.
Right, so, I'm just going to go ahead and I'm going to copy this into
see if I can get back to my editor there.
I'm going to say that that is basically what we are looking at at the
outset, we're looking at this and so, that's good.
And so, then the question only is what happens after that.
The question now is like, basically, what you know, what did the
Of the things look like finding the file header in V, 2.0, ours to
point.
X bitmaps is going to be this stuff.
What is it in other ones?
So it looks like the stuff that we actually care about, though.
So as a bitmap to do pal and element, size, hores resolution, color is
used.
So basically these things, these things are the same.
It looks like, right.
It looks like we always do that, but we once we get to compression
they may or not, they may or may not be there basically, right?
They may or may not.
Actually, it may or may not have compression or size of bitmap or the
resolution or colors use color important that sort of stuff.
But that's really the only difference.
So if we assume temporarily that were only going to be reading
uncompressed, we could just look at these fields and assume that we
always have them and that there and just and just read them in, right?
So we can just, again, this is just debug code.
We're not trying to read a file processing Library.
We're only ever using assets that we ourselves load.
So, basically, you know, this is, this is pretty good.
In terms of what we're actually looking at, you know, in the file.
So, what we could do here is we could just look at it this way, we
could just say, okay here is a struct, right?
This is the bitmap header or something like that.
Right?
We could say that this is the bitmap header and you know, I don't
know, just, here's the actual sizes of each of these things.
This is a in 1616, right?
You went 32 Unit 32.
In 32 and 32 un 16 un 16, right?
And we could basically just say, all right.
This is the, the layout that we are expecting to look at.
And we can say, all right, this bitmap header.
I am going to go ahead and take a look at that read result contents.
So contents.
I'm going to take a look at that as the bitmap header, right?
I'm just going to look.
I'm just going to cold-cast it.
So assuming that read result sighs.
Right is not equal to 0 assuming that we were able to read it.
Then I'm going to take a look at the header.
Now.
We've got a problem here, right?
And I guess I can, I can probably demonstrate it as well, so that you
can see it.
What did I call that?
Again?
Where is what is the results?
Whereas my read results content size?
Content size.
So if I go ahead and I actually run this, we have a problem and I've
talked about it on the stream many times before, but just to solidify
it for people who again, might not be familiar with this sort of
thing.
If you notice, when we actually do what, I just said, we'll have a
problem.
And so when we, when we open this up and we look at things, you'll
notice that it doesn't
Like what we had hoped, right?
We looked we expected it and we were expecting the file size.
We looked at the files and socially.
Correct, like what's going on here, right?
Why do these look wrong?
Well, the answer of course is because like I said on the stream before
when we lay out a structure, basically, C++ is under no obligation to
actually pack that structure tightly.
So we, when we say that there's a un 16 and then there's a Unit 32.
It doesn't have to put those adjacent to each other and in fact, it
won't what it does.
Is it aligns things?
Things to a boundary that is the same as whatever their size is.
So if this, this is 4, bytes, this is only to B.
It will skip to B to put this on a 4, byte boundary basically because
it is 4 bytes.
So basically, if we want to read the memory in a nice layout here, we
have to tell see 2Pac that structure tightly.
And so what we have is kind of this really janky system.
I think there is in certain compilers.
There's better ways of doing this, where you can just label the struct
as tightly packed.
But that is a new relatively new thing.
Basically, there's this thing, Padma, pragma pack, push and pop.
It's kind of ridiculous, but I'll basically show you what it looks
like.
Essentially what you do, if you can, if you can take a look here, you
can basically do this thing where you do pragma pack, and then you can
say what the packing level is, right?
So you can kind of do something where you do something like this,
pragma Pack 1 and then it will pack everything.
To be one, you know, one bite, aligned, even if it would have packed
it, otherwise, which is what we want to do.
Now.
Unfortunately, at the end of this, we'd like to set it back to
whatever it was, but we don't know what it was.
We don't know what the default packing was going to be.
Right, and we don't know it, whether we might be inside, someone
else's packed block.
So basically what they do in a lot of in a lot of cases just to make
things easy.
Is they do a pragma pack push, which basically is a thing that says
push a
On the stack, which is basically going to be a know if you can see it
here.
Here's okay.
Here's a good example, right?
Basically, what you can do is you can use this push pop thing to
basically tell it to just, okay, for the region that I'm in.
Start.
It's like a stack push this new value for packing on the stack.
But then when you're done pop it off and go back to the previous value
that you're at.
Right?
So if you do this pragmatic pack, push one and then pragma pack, pop
in theory, you get a thing.
We're just in between those your tightly packed but everywhere else,
your regular packing, right?
So now when we come in here and we look at the header, you can see
that everything actually looks right now.
Look, here's the actual size, right?
Here's the width and height of the bitmap.
And there, the there, what we expect, here's the bit for Pixel which
Is what we expect 32 and so on.
And so really all we need to do is jump to this bitmap offset and load
the bitmap.
That's about all.
We actually need to do.
And so there's one other surprise waiting for us with bitmaps that
will see.
I don't know if we'll have a time to blip this today.
Probably not.
If it's the
That wording.
But basically, we now know what the header is.
So we know what the width and height are and we now know exactly where
the data is.
So we also know that basically our pixels right are going to be read
result, contents.
We know that they are going to be wherever the contents are plus the
bitmap offset that we got in the header.
But of course, we don't know what that bitmap offset is relative to is
it relative to the start of the file or what?
So I'm going to go take a look at the
That spec again and just see if it's a little, if it's specific at all
about what that bitmap offset actually means.
So starting position of the image in B.
I don't know if they are any more specific here, bitmap us the
strength of the bitmap from the beginning of the file.
So basically we did the right math here, that's going to be the start
of our pixels.
And then we're expecting to have basically width times height pixels
worth of data, I believe because it's 32 bits per pixel.
Should be well aligned.
I think, I don't know.
Basically, if
I don't know if they talk in here at all about that image data
uncompressed data.
Series of values represent the color.
Each scanline must end on a 4 byte boundary.
So, one, two or three bites of padding, they follow each scan line.
So the only other thing we have to worry about is basically our pixels
are going to be four by the line.
Since they are already four bytes that should never actually be a
problem for us.
But if we were going to load a 24-bit one here for some reason, later,
then we would actually care.
But that is our pixel pointer.
And that is basically all we actually needed to
Uno.
Now, if we want to, we could probably do something cheesy here to test
this just real quickly in the three minutes that I have remaining.
So, let's see here.
So this is a unit, 32 star is the is the real.
What is the contents pointer?
It's a void.
Yes.
So there we go.
I'm just going to go ahead and cast that.
So what we could do here, if we wanted to just as a test, we could go
ahead and say, all right.
Let's return that for now as a Cheesy thing to do.
This is this is totally temporary.
Not at all, what we actually want to do, but let's just do it for now.
So I'll return result here and
I will do result equals pixels.
Okay.
So when we load this into memory now, we're going to have a pixel
pointer.
So I'll stick that temporarily down in here, which is just say, pixel
Right?
And I will go ahead and say, all right, the pixel point that came
State pixel pointer equals that and now we have a pixel pointer.
And now what I could do is I could basically just copy our draw
rectangle function or I could even just split it to the screen.
Yeah.
Basically, what I could do is I could say, let's just copy the screen,
it will be a line incorrectly.
But let's just copy to the screen.
So at the end of the frame to will overwrite everything we did
basically that buffer that were writing to, we'll just go ahead and
overwrite that.
So I'm basically just going to say, alright for y equals.
Y is less than buffer height plus plus Y.
And then I will do an X here, x x x width.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm just going to straight up copy
the pixels from the pixel pointer.
So I'm basically to say, all right, the game State pixel pointer.
I'm going to go ahead and say I've got that and then I've got the you
went dest and that's the buffer pixels and I'm just going to go ahead
and pull on just do.
The dest pointer equals the source pointer and of course the stride
won't be, right.
So our image will be all sheared and weird, but I just want to see if
reloading anything even close to right in the in the short time that
we have left.
So, okay.
I think I have to cast that if I'm not mistaken.
Do I?
Oh no, its just pixels isn't a member of the buffer.
So let's take a look at what that actually is.
So the buffer is a memory.
There we go.
So
Never, there we go.
Oops.
Signed unsigned mismatch.
Oh, those are those are integers, I guess.
Okay.
There we go.
And let's take a look.
So that is not a particularly good sign.
That doesn't look particularly good to me.
I don't know about you, guys.
We have a bunch of things that are expected problems there.
I can fix the sheer, but that's, that's pretty funny.
So yeah.
Okay, we will, we will pick that up next week because
That is not at all, what we want to look at and and rather than
debugging that now because there's a couple things we have to do.
So basically we have to do the stride so that this copying correctly
without cheering, then we have to fix the color ordering if the color
ordering is wrong and all sorts of other things like that.
So I'm just going to not act, you do that because we'll just eat in
the Q&A.
I'd rather keep doing on time and tomorrow we can be basically how to
pull it that stuff onto the screen and then we can also
so, do our like are
Our debugging of loading the bitmap in case we had bugs in that code.
For example, where we were saying that the pixel pointer was might
have been wrong or something like that.
It looks like our header is correct.
So just whether our bitmap offset is correct or not.
Okay, so that's it for now is time to go to the Q&A.
Please prefix your questions with Q:, so I will see them.
And if you could also try to keep questions to programming questions
that are about today stream or previous dreams.
That would be very helpful, so we can stay on topic.
All right, off we go to the Q&A.
Yes, perfect.
Blind shift that, I totally agree.
Well, so basically a lot of times what you can do is just, you gotta
sell it, right?
If you have a bug, right?
Like this.
And you're just like, okay, that's not so good.
What you need to do is say, okay.
No.
Wait, this is
This is like an indie game.
That's about your perception of reality and how you need to be able to
see things beyond the way that they're normally presented or whatever
and just sell this as intentional, right?
Like you just got to have a good Fiction.
It's the same thing that they do in like art galleries, when they put
like a little thing, they have a picture and it's totally random and
then they have a thing on the side.
That's like a little placard and it says something like, you know, in
this
Evocative piece, you can see how like the suggestion of a windmill at
Sunset evokes, you know, you know, servantes and all the sort of, you
know, that's, that's that's what you got to do.
If you cut, if you have this, it's not going to sell itself.
So you're going to have to sell it.
That's that's, you know, that's game salesmanship right there.
That's what you got to do.
If you don't want to debug it, I'd rather just a bug it.
But if you don't want to, you have other options.
I missed the part where you handled endianness of the file or a bit
Maps, always the same.
Well, so yeah, bitmaps.
I want to say that, I don't know if they can be a different
indianness, if they're saved on a Mac.
We don't care.
Because we'll always know that they're in our native Indian and Enos.
If that makes sense.
If you were loading a file, like, if you were loading a PSD, for
example, it's always in the wrong indianness.
It's always in old Power PC and in this.
So, yeah.
Today nowadays, Max also use little endian.
So if they saved a bitmap, it would be little endian as well.
I don't know.
If there's ever been a time when bitmaps for saved, big-endian on like
powerpc Macs or something, I'm not sure.
But basically, for bitmaps that are saved on any modern computer.
They will always be little endian and we're a little endian, so it
doesn't matter.
We're always fine.
Do I prefer pragma pack or what?
I prefer.
GCC like annotation.
Probably GCC like, annotation, but I don't really care.
I mean, it's a little ugly.
I'd prefer to just be able to say yeah, like pack this thing or
whatever and GCC has attributes like that.
Jesus.
He and Lov on have attributes like that, but it's not really a big
deal.
I don't do this, like you don't do this very often.
So that's it.
Usually isn't that?
That's why it's usually not that big a deal.
What's your threshold for number of function parameters before putting
them all into a single structure, as a single function parameter?
I don't really have a threshold for that.
I'm rarely thinking about that.
When I do that.
What I'm thinking about is whether there will be a lot of times when
things will get passed through as that structure.
So, basically, if I think of, a lot of people will be passing around
the same group of stuff, then I'll condense it into a structure, but
if a function itself just happens to have a unique set of stuff, even
if
It's 30 long.
I don't care.
I'll just
Them as I'll just do them as as individual parameters, so it's not
really about how many, How many pairs of function has its whether
those things can be bundled together in ways that lots of people use
because then that just condenses the code and it's nicer.
Could you please describe how the sparse tilemap storage is done so
far.
Watch last week's videos, but couldn't figure it out.
Sure.
I can totally describe that.
So if we take a look at tilemap the handmade tile .h,
So basically what we have here at the moment and again remember the
only reason we were doing this to figure out what kind of API we
wanted, right?
So you can see we even have it to do here that says real sparseness
because we're not really doing real sparseness yet.
But okay.
So basically what we have is we have a two level or a scheme that's
implemented currently.
What happens is we have an array of tile chunks, right?
We have tile chunk EXT.
I'll jump can't watch out Z.
We have that as an array of tile chunks.
So it's a three dimensional array of tile chunks, right?
So if you think about what that looks like, it's a cube, right?
And imagine.
This is a cube that contains the world, right?
This is our whole world.
It's got some number of slices in Z, right, which is this tile chunk
count Z.
So how
Many this this year is the tile chunk out.
Z it then has some number of slices in y.
So those are, those are these slices this way, right?
Makes sense.
So we have some number of slices and why, and then we also have some
number of slices in X, which we finally slice it this way, right?
Slice, slice slice in here is X, right.
And so, that is how we dice up the world to begin with.
And, of course, these lines all continue all the way through, right?
And you can imagine pulling this apart, one layer at a time, the
biggest, the most primary index.
And you can tell this by
Going into when we do get tile chunk.
Right?
And we pass it, the indices, you can see the operation.
It's Z.
The each individual Movement by one level of Z moves us all the way in
all the tile chunk context all tile chunk cut.
Why, right?
So what that means is z is the is the price is the largest accessor.
When we move up one in Z.
We move up a whole to d block of X Y.
So you can think of it as the z-index peels off.
Off one whole thing of this.
So a single z-index pulls off, basically one.
Of these guys, right?
Makes sense so far, hopefully.
So a single z-index like this might be z-index one, right pulls off an
entire chunk of these that still has all of the exes and all of the
Y's right.
Next.
They are indexed by y.
So next you can use a why to pull out one chunk of the exes.
And again, that's the same operation.
It's pulling out one chunk.
Now, we're pulling out a chunk.
That's just one dimensional, right?
Make sense.
So now we're pulling out that chunk.
And this is z equals 1, y equals, you know, to or something, it's some
some number.
It doesn't matter what these are right, Z equals a and Y equals B.
We're pulling out some row.
And then finally, we use the X to grab one in particular one.
And you can see that right in the math X has no multiplier.
It's just something that once you have one of these, you need to go
that many tile chunks into it, right?
And similarly, y, only moves by
1X is worth, right.
So moving in, why just moves you one of these rows for words, but
moving in Z moves, you both, right?
So it's moving like a whole Plate at a time and we could keep going up
into higher Dimensions, right?
And that indexing scheme, still works.
This is the indexing scheme.
I talked about that basically flattens.
Any uniformly, multi-dimensional thing into a one-dimensional thing.
This is the indexing for that right now.
Once we grab one of those, we just have a tile chunk.
So finally, when we have something with an x y, and a z of the tile
chunk.
We have a chunk, not a tile and a title chunk.
Right?
And I should be more Civic.
We have a towel chunk pointer, right?
So, we have a chunk star, if there's nothing to find at the world in
that location, anywhere in there.
Venice is 0 and we know there's no tiles in there at all.
But if it's not 0, if that chunk point that we pull out of there after
doing this is not zero, then that means it has a tiles pointer, right,
that that tiles pointer Works were talking about, it's not zero.
Then that means that we actually also have a two-dimensional array of
tiles in there.
And that two-dimensional array of tiles is chunked in by chunk, Tim.
And I believe we said that chunk.
Tim was 16.
Is what we're doing.
So basically, when we pull out that chunk, it's actually another 16 by
16 flat piece.
Right?
So it's basically, you know, it's pretty dense.
It's like it's even one more denser than that.
So it's like, it's a lot of tiles right in both directions.
So it's crazy dense, right?
But it's a 16 by 16 by one deep.
Right?
So it's only one deep.
It has nosy.
It's one flat plane.
That's 60.
In by 16, we then look up the tile in there and that's where the tiles
are stored.
And what this allows us to do is it allows us to basically store a
reasonably sized chunk.
So they're reasonably compact 16 by 16.
Nicely arrayed in memory.
We don't have to spend time figuring out how to get to them or
anything like that.
But we lost that up into a scheme that is sparse, so that we don't
have to store that.
Everywhere in the world, right?
Because we don't want to store this whole Cube.
Even in our, our current size would be too big to store efficiently.
Probably.
So we don't want to have to do that.
Now.
This is not a particularly good storage scheme because we still have
to have this upper this or upper array.
The tile chunk array is dense, right?
This is dense.
So we've subsampled it by 16 times 16 at that lower level.
But it's still dense.
And so what we're going to move to when we actually write the engine
code proper.
And again, we're it's all hiding behind an API that doesn't care.
So we will be able to do this without affecting the light code that
calls into it, which is kind of the goal as well.
This is dense and we want to turn this into sparse.
We want us to be fully sparse.
So there's no cost for storing basically a giant world.
If you don't, you only pay the cost of how much world you actually
fill in.
You never pay a cost based on the wingspan of that world and what that
means if you
About it, right?
Is I don't want to have to be constrained to a bounding rectangle size
of things.
If my world is literally only this one long straight path that goes
from here to here.
Right?
If we were storing everything, as a dense array and worse yet.
Actually, let's make it, let's go 111 worse, right?
Let's say I've got something that looks like this, so it's actually
fully three-dimensional.
It starts at the bottom here and goes all the way to the top corner
there.
Right?
So it's basically this Meandering thing that crosses all three.
Options in a diagonal.
I don't want to have to store this whole Cube because that'll be huge.
I only want to store a little local regions of tiles that cover.
This.
I want to pay a cost of storage, commensurate with the area.
I actually filled and not the bounding rectangle of that area.
If that makes sense, the axis aligned bounding wrecked on that area
and a raise.
If things that are dense, arrays are essentially storing bounded,
access aligned bounding rectangles.
Worth of data and that's just not going to fly here.
So that's why we need is the sparsity scheme.
Hopefully, that is a reasonable explanation that you can work from
when you go back and try to understand how that code is working.
Why not use a function template to redraw B into any struct?
You cook up one primitive at a time instead of quirky compiler
commands, then you could ignore whatever weird shape it wants to give
your struct in memory.
Well, if you want to do that, that's probably fine.
I certainly wouldn't say that anyone, you know, I wouldn't fire you
for doing that.
Let's put it that way.
And there are certainly times when that is a useful thing to do.
The times when that is a useful thing to do the template part, I would
probably never do because that doesn't sound like a good idea to me,
but ignoring that part, if you want to do it in templates, go nuts,
but in terms of having individual Primitives that read in, we could
imagine writing the code that way that code would basically.
Look,
Like this, right.
It would basically look like something like this.
Right?
Where, you know, you had a series of functions that look sort of that
red in things like this and you basically would call them
individually.
So you would kind of go through and say all right to read in the
header.
The thing that reads in the header creates one of these parts are
things which is basically just an index into the file, right?
So it's got one of these and it initializes it to be, you know, index
into the file like, you know, beginning of file, right?
And this this basically like reads a 32
Value and advances the pointer, right?
I don't know if you can understand.
Basically, I'm trying to construct here.
I don't want to have to write the whole thing out.
But basically, then what we would do is to read this.
We'd say, you know you in 16 file type equals U n-- 16, parser like
this right?
File size equals Unit, 32 parser and so on, right?
And then you just you read them in the reason that I don't think that
is particularly useful.
Here is because it's just a it's just a lot more work that's going on
in terms of what the compiler would have to flatten out to make this,
right.
I mean, this is way simpler for the compiler.
It's like a cast, right?
It's the most trivial thing.
The compiler could ever have to handle, and there's no question that
it will be able to generate good code.
If you write it this way.
If you write it this way, the compiler has to realize that you're just
reading out of memory using a structured pointer.
And so that they know that, you know, it doesn't have to do.
Actually do these reads one at a time in all this stuff.
You're just making a lot of extra work for the optimizer.
That really, there's no point to doing.
Look.
What did you gain from this?
All you had to do is know to put pragma packet, practical pragmatic
pack push and programmatic pop, that's pretty simple.
And you didn't have to write any of this.
So it just seems like a real big waste.
I really don't see why you would ever write that.
Now, there are times when you would write that the time that you would
write that are, for example, let's say you did have an endianness
issue and any
and things had to be reversed that might be one good example of when
you might do this because you can bake the endianness reversal into
the read.
Another time is predicated files.
So for example, let's say that the file saw this reserved if this
reserved was not zero, then the second Reserve doesn't exist stuff
like that.
Then this structured format doesn't work anymore.
So then you have to do reads and it's sort of like a state machine.
That's how that's working to figure out what's going on.
It's not what state machine.
It's a predicated read and then at that point, you're much better off.
Not using a structure method.
So this is what I would expect to see in the case, where you're
reading, a more complicated file format, like PSD liked, if things
like that.
But when you're reading something this simple, it just seems like that
would be a real big waste of time.
Both yours and compilers.
How will we handle memory when reading files, would?
We would it be wasteful to read into our memory pool than only use
part of it.
So basically, that is a question that we want to save for a lot later.
We will be doing resource streaming which means that what we will be
doing eventually, when we stopped using debug loading calls is we will
be reading in essentially stuff that we've pre-processed into a
format, that's going to be real easy for us to kind of stream in as
fast as possible.
Whether that means like,
You know, that it's compressed or whatever.
We're going to, we're going to be focusing on how to make that
pipeline smooth.
And basically what that means is probably what will happen is the data
that's read from disk, probably won't be usable directly.
So what we'll want to be doing is just reading the chunk that we need
out of the file.
The exact amount that we need, because we'll have set up our files so
that we know exactly what we need to read in any circumstance.
We won't be having a bunch of cruft in the file that we don't care
about like reserved one and two will read
Exactly the part that we need.
We will decompress it directly into the place that supposed to go.
And then we will basically use that memory that the memory that gets
used for that temporary read that we before we do, think impress will
just be part of the transient buffer that we just reuse over and over
again as we load assets.
Dragon master, 047.
I'm not sure.
I understand this question.
Exactly.
I'm going to read it out loud and then see if I can see exactly what
you're asking.
If not, you may have to re-ask, it.
Could you explain how handled platform specific behavior, parentheses
Windows needs bitmap info for stress GI B, but only pass a platform on
specific struct back to the game code.
Would you just use a void Star platform data, if you need to pass
something platform game code platform.
So I think what you're asking, if I understand correctly is you have a
platform service?
Or a platform specific piece of data that exists.
In the platform layer, you're going to call the game code and you know
that the game code is going to call you back.
And when it calls you back you need it to hand you that data that is
platform-specific and you're asking how do you architect that?
Like, what should that look like?
Ideally the answer is we sort of already have one of those.
And I will talk a little bit about it.
So thread context.
Probably will have some platform specific data in it, eventually
possibly.
So there's two things you can do here one is you can actually just
declare there to be extra space at the end of thread context for you
to actually work with it.
So you can basically do something like this.
Right.
So the basically you have a place to put platforms that big data and
you just
At size B.
However, big needs to be for the biggest platforms storage.
I don't love that, but it does have some nice titties too.
It means that the game can copy those trucks around.
If it needs to, or things like this.
What I tend to do instead is I will basically just elongate the
structure when I pass it to the game and count on it being unnie
unnie, counted on it being really long dateable on the way back.
So basically what I'll do is I'll pass thread context.
In to the game and the game thinks it's just this but secretly, what
I'll do in the win32 layer.
Right is, I'll actually have something that's win32 thread context,
which is a different structure, right?
Like this.
And what I'll do is sort of the common or the the common part of it.
I'll put in there and then the win32 part.
I'll put out here, right?
Something like this.
Basically, so, what I do is I wrap the platform nonspecific structure
inside a platform specific structure.
Then when I pass the game, the thing I pass it, the address of this
knowing that that address is also the same as the address to this.
So when the thread context comes back to me, I just cast it back out
to win 3-2 thread context and I know that I've got my extra data
sitting there at the bottom.
Does that make sense?
So that's often how I do that?
I don't know if that answered your question, but that's how I would
probably do that in this circumstance.
Suffice to say, I try to minimize that sort of thing as much as
possible.
Anyway, because I don't like to have round trips through the code.
I think I mentioned that several times.
So I try to limit the amount of times when you ever would have two
round-trip anything, let alone platform specific data.
I try to minimize the number of round trips period.
So something to think about,
Would it be easy to implement a generic sparse array to solve our town
that problem possibly overloading, brackets?
Probably not.
I mean I'm thinking probably what I would do.
I mean not that it wouldn't be easy.
Yes.
It would be easy.
I don't think we necessarily want that.
Probably.
What I will do is I will use a hash table that hashes on the the
abstract but the absolute tile chunk indices or something like that.
So I don't think a sparse array is probably necessary and probably
would be slow.
Slower to index than I want it to be unless the generic sparse array
happens to be a hash table.
But even if it was a hash table, how would it know what the hash
function is?
So we're gonna have to do something specific to try and make a hash
function that's good for our purposes or do something smarter and I
don't know.
We could do something like a quadtree sliced, Claude tree, or
something like that.
I don't know.
I don't really want to do an octree because I feel like it would be
wasteful.
Since our Z is we don't have a lot of Z probably but who knows?
Rose.
So we have World chunks and tiles.
Didn't we also have screens.
I'm still fuzzy on the map abstractions.
So we did have screens but we don't really have screens anymore.
Because essentially, we decided we wanted our tile tile map to just be
nice and generic.
So we can scroll through want to or not.
And so screens are just going to be a gameplay con struct where we fix
the camera to be looking at just one screen and that will be where
screens come in.
We don't actually store screens explicitly ever.
They're only going to be a game.
Contract with they'll basically be marked up or just built into how
the game happens to move around.
That makes sense.
Why wouldn't you ever use a function template for the Primitive
readers?
I mentioned that seems just like the sort of thing function templates
are for the reason is because I hate templates.
I hate templates because I think their syntax is bad, and I think the
implementation of them in the debugger is bad and the compiler.
So basically most of the time, if you, if you use templates in your
code, I find that the error messages, get bad, the debug visibility,
the ability to inspect things of the burger gets worse and too.
Cast in the debugger gets worse in almost all the buggers.
Although mstc is probably the best case for those they usually are.
And you're basically just introducing that complexity for really no
gain.
I mean, think about what has to happen.
I mean, let's just Let's do let's do the basic thought process here.
How many values are you really going to read out of a file?
Right?
Basically, we've got, you know, you ain't 16s and in 16s and in 32 or
something, right?
So you've got, you know, something where you do read you in?
I mean, you know, something like this.
Right, we've got something that looks like this.
Okay, and it's got some file, parser thing that it's that it's that
it's, you know, taking as the pointer and it's going to return these
things right now, each one of these has to do a slightly separate a
slightly different swap, operation, right?
If we were going to do the endianness thing, like I talked about
before, right, so assuming you have to do some work on these because
otherwise, if you didn't have to do work on them, then you shouldn't
be doing it.
Really?
So assuming you have to do some work on this.
Let's assume you have to do an ND, a swap on this.
So we basically have, you know, our value here.
We're going to do whatever.
It takes to read it from the parser, which is basically it's going to
be like, you know, something that probably looks like this, right.
It's going to it's going to do something like this and and the parser
value is going to be plus equals 2 or something here and then it's
going to return the result.
It's got to do the any Nisswa.
So the Indian is swap is going to have to look, you know, whatever.
It's going to look like.
It depends on how you want to write it.
You could write it like this.
I suppose result equals results shifted up, you know, eight or results
and shifted down 8, I don't know, something like this.
I don't know.
You're gonna have to write something, right?
You're gonna have to write your idea, swapping here.
So what do you really gain?
And this is going to be different on each one.
Right?
Like the endianness swap for read and 32 is going to be different
here.
You could write them so that they all kind of roughly look the same.
I guess the way you would do that is you'd, you know, you'd have to
start writing a for Loop, right?
You'd have to write if you wanted them to be templatized.
So you only had to write it once which would be the only reason.
I think you would use a template, you have to start writing it, like
to Loop over the bike count.
So you'd have to do, like, white count equals zero.
Byte count is less than 4 or less than size.
Of the type that you're templatized on + + B count, right?
And so I should say B Index, right?
And then you're going to have to read in the thing in here in the
opposite order.
So you can start at the end and you read into the beginning, right?
Of the of the byte order and whatever and that's what you looks like.
I just don't understand why you would bother doing that when you could
just write the couple functions that you need and then they're easy to
read.
They you
can see which ones are calling very easily.
They're easy to refer to.
They all have actual names, that make sense.
It's just
I think people who write templates, tend to write templates a little
prematurely if you really had something where you're going to save a
ton of time by template, sizing it.
Maybe that's okay, but I just find that the tool chains are so bad at
working with templates that you're just inviting a lot of complexity
and a lot of unnecessary stuff into your code.
When it really just not that much to write it properly the first time.
And, you know, this thing is basically just the same here and here,
you'd
Your swap here.
And in fact, this this and this function could be the same.
I could just call this function from this.
This in 32 1 could just read could just use the unit 32 and cast it
right or whatever.
So, these actually don't have to be written separately.
This could just call that one.
And so, you're talking about a tremendously, small amount of code.
It just seems crazy to introduce templates into that, given how bad
templates are throughout the rest of the tool chain.
So yeah, so I never used templates ever.
And basically, I use metaprogramming for anything that other people
would potentially legitimately use templates for.
So if I looked at the use of templates and said that was a legitimate
time when I would have used templates, I don't actually ever use
templates.
I always met of code that so, because metaprogramming is much more
powerful than templates.
So, basically templates is kind of an exercise in trying to figure out
how to do metaprogramming with a real weak sauce.
Right?
You're, you know, you're trying to flavor a good burger with a real
weak sauce and
and,
I feel like you should use good sauce on a good burger.
Will you write asset importers exporters to get the asset data into an
efficient format?
Or will you rely on the tools?
The asset creators used output, a raw style file?
We will be writing.
Well, I don't know if we'll write this or not because this is kind of
outside of the scope of what we're doing on handmade hero.
We might.
I mean, I don't guess there's really no reason not to so we because
it's not very much code.
But basically what we'll be doing is we'll be packing our data into a
single file.
Basically that's, you know, got all of our resources in the format
that we
I'm going to be so yeah, we probably won't ever directly.
We will never in the shipping version of the game directly, use asset
data, that came out of an art tool.
Let's see.
Easy twitch metaprogramming is, is C code to generate C, code is what
I'm talking about.
I almost always use C code to generate C code anytime that I would
have considered using a template.
Hey, we're at the end of the questions, right?
At 9:30.
That is got to be a good omen people.
Well, thank you so much for joining me for another episode of Hamming
here.
It's been a pleasure programming with you.
As always, we did our bitmap loading tonight, but unfortunately we
didn't have any time left in the Stream to actually put it up on the
screen.
So please join me tomorrow at 8 p.m.
PST, it p.m.
Pacific Standard time when we will go ahead and put our stuff up to
the screen.
And then that will finally give us.
Graphics, we can start using to start playing around with what the
game is going to look like in terms of, you know, how do we, how do we
structure our map screens to actually look good?
How do we have sort of, how do we deal with all of that sort of stuff
that comes with trying to make a good-looking game?
Instead of a just a straightforward, tilemap kind of scenario.
So I am very much looking forward to that and I hope you are too.
So, please join me tomorrow.
Right here.
Same time, same place if you would like to
You preorder the game you can do so you can do.
So right here on handmade or hero dot-org.
You can pre-order the game and you will get all of the source code
that you see us working on every night.
I update it.
And I always starting today was the first time, but going forwards,
any time.
I'm using resources to develop stuff on the stream.
I will also put those up there so you can completely.
If you are someone who pre-order the game, you could always
completely, follow along with everything I do at home and then play
around with it yourself.
And that's really important, too.
Because one of the best ways to learn game programming is to play with
game code.
And so, I highly recommend that anyone who's interested in learning
does take the time outside of the stream to kind of play around with
what we've been doing experiment.
Learn.
Self and kind of, you know, maybe try to do some things that I haven't
done yet.
Just kind of get familiar with with programming sort of this low-level
stuff and it's usually a very rewarding experience.
That's my that's what I found.
So yeah, I highly recommend that and also if you would like to support
the video series, just just separately, we have a patreon that you can
subscribe to and if you're trying to study at home, we have a news and
Forum site.
That's really good for that sort of thing.
If you go here, it's got the schedule.
It's got an episode guide, that's got sort of annotated videos to help
you.
You catch up on previous videos, that you may have missed.
It's got a coding resources page, which has ports, like people have
done ports to Linux and mac and so on.
So if you're trying to work on a different platform than I'm working
on, if you're trying to work on something, other than Windows, that's
a great place to go to find out how to do the stuff that we do in
Windows on those other platforms.
And finally there's a Code discussion page where you can go to post
questions or to talk about stuff that you've seen on the stream.
So definitely check it out.
If you're trying to learn from the series, that's a great place to go.
There's a lot of resources there.
So thank you everyone for joining me.
I hope to see you here tomorrow.
A'ight, have a good rest of the evening and a happy Tuesday.