We're going to start recording.
Don't ask me.
Why?
That's just how things go.
Alright.
Hello everyone.
Welcome to handmade hero.
The gate.
Well, let's just say the game.
It's not a game to show where we code, complete game from scratch live
on Twitch.
No engine, no.
Libraries just us in our typing fingers.
We are actually pretty far in now, like we've done a lot of stuff.
We have gotten to the point where we've kind of got got a lot of our
prototype stuff working, and we're at, we just finished up a
A major change to how we were sort of.
We've been sort of working on how we want our engine to be
architected.
And we just finished up a pretty major change which is we change to
using these things called update like simulation regions, which are
like basically regions of space that we update together that solved a
bunch of problems for us.
So I'm pretty happy with how it went and we have one more thing to do
with them that I at least I think is probably something we should do
with them.
So that's what we're probably going to do today and then we'll be
moving on out of that system into looking at some other stuff.
So if you would like to follow along at home and you pre-ordered the
game on handmade here a.org, you should have gotten a link in your
email.
And that link allows you to download the source code anytime you want.
So if you take a look here, we're on day 67.
So you would unzipped a 66 has source code into a directory, and then
you would be exactly where I am right now.
So you could follow along with coding at home, which I highly
recommend doing, if you can because it's one of the best ways to learn
is to code stuff yourself.
So let's go ahead and get started.
If I remember correctly, we had pretty much finished up looking at the
stuff that we want to look at.
And we actually already sort of put in a little test of shooting an
entity out from our entity.
We don't really have any graphics for it or anything yet.
But it's essentially just shooting a rock in place of something where
we might actually put something a little plate and so that was
basically all done.
And so the only thing that really I want to take a look at was what
happens in the apron of our update region, right?
And so I'll just go over briefly what that was just so because people
may have forgotten because we did a bunch of work with the update
regions that had nothing to do with this part of it but I mentioned it
kind of briefly and now would probably be a good time here day 67 to
go to the Whiteboard or I guess in this case Blackboard and draw out
sort of what I was talking about.
So basically
There's day 67.
What I was concerned about in the reason that I want to add one more
thing to the simulation region, is, we sort of, have a couple of
different Scopes in our simulation region, usually, right.
We've got the area where the camera can see, and we know that we
always want to simulate that.
And then we've also got surrounding that sort of a wider region.
And that is the simulation area, right?
So this is the simulation area that we want to actually simulate
everything in and the reason that I wanted that too,
Be bigger than the camera area was just because I would like to be
able to simulate people off screen at full speed and have it.
So that, you know, if they did something like let's say,
Aii over here sets a bomb.
You would hear it, or it might blow through, you know, like, let's say
there's a wall here, it might blow through the wall here.
We want to be able to support any kind of like Rich interactions
immediately in the vicinity of the player that might be interesting
for them to see or feel the effects of even though that they're not on
screen.
What happened the effects of what happened might sort of be off screen
that might might spill onto screen if you will.
So these are our two areas but there's another area that I wanted to
include right.
Which is just
One more layer out, right and this is sort of the Collision area.
And so what this was about was if you are simulating everyone in this
region that includes obviously people who are sort of right on the
edge of the region.
Right there could be people who are sort of right on that edge and
those people may decide that what they want to do, you know if they're
a i driven or whatever.
Obviously the players going to be in the camera area but the a eyes
are not necessarily.
They may just be trying to do things like move outside.
They may be moving in the in the
Correction, that would take them outside of the simulation area.
And what I'm afraid of is that if we just allowed the simulation to
occur as, you know, as is only using this as the boundary of the
envies that are pulled in there, may be entities right there.
That should be stopping them from doing that motion, but those
entities will never get seen by the Collision protector because the
Collision detectors, only working on the things inside, the simulation
area.
And so what I wanted to do is say that we've got one more sort of
boundary that's a little bit wider.
ER, and that is basically growing the simulation area by however, much
the maximum movement speed is per frame, right?
You know, if that's .01 meters or something, I mean, who knows what it
is?
Maybe it's point one meters, we'll figure it out, right.
Whatever the in a thirtieth of in 1/30 of a second.
How fast can the fastest thing in the world move or more to the point
we could even do fastest thing in the simulation area if we wanted to.
But how fast is that?
And then make sure that we make
Something that big and that way we will know that we will include in
the simulation area anything that might have essentially collided
with, you know, with this, with this object, right?
So that way it'll stop that bug potentially from happening which would
be a bad bug for us to have.
And there's it's sort of a this is this is not entirely accurate
either.
Because this, this sort of ignores one thing that we haven't talked
about, with our spatial partition, which is the size of
Titties.
Right?
So size of entities is actually also something we need to think about
because what we want to do as well as we want to make sure that we
bring in any entities like let's say that you know we've got these
tile chunks, right?
And the tile chunks are the things that we bring in that.
We see what tile chunks are within our region.
Well, if a particular entity, we're just we're putting entities in
tile chunks
Down there center, right?
But the entity itself might have some size, right?
The Entity itself might be fairly large.
Let's say, I mean, it might not be that large relative to what we're
talking about here, but it could be, you know, fairly large, right?
And so if something could be fairly large, we also want to make sure
that we would include it in here.
If it's, if it's total size, would cause it to sort of protrude into
that area right into the simulation area.
Sorry into the question area.
So really what we have
Is we have when we grow this area, we actually want to grow it by
essentially a distance, both in X and in y right to make sure that
this the band is proper.
We want to be able to grow by the radius of the biggest entity.
Right.
And we also want to add to that the speed of the fastest entity,
right?
And really, we don't need to necessarily do both of these because it's
really when you combine the two.
So what we could say is for all entities, if you took their radius
plus their speed, right?
We want radius plus speed, we want to basically say the maximum of
that.
So we want the maximum whoever is radius.
Plus their speed is, the largest that is the size we want to enlarge
our region by and then we would know that everyone who might be
involved in a collision would be
Sort of grabbed, right?
And maybe we add an Epsilon here in for safety like because it is
floating point.
Maybe we don't want it to be quite so exact.
Maybe we want to make sure that we've got a little bit of a buffer as
well just to make sure that we don't have, you know, rounding errors
or something that are going to cause some kind of really bad problem.
But in general, that's what we want to do, right?
And so figuring out that number is not something we need to do now,
because we don't even know something like that.
Right now, we haven't defined all the types of entities that might be
in the game.
But what we would like to do is, make it so that
Oh, that this is supported.
And the reason that this is not supported right now is because things
in this region, we could easily expand the region and run it.
The problem is the things in this region, would then get stimulated
but we don't want to simulate them because if we did simulate them,
we'd then have to keep on enlarging the region to see what things they
could collide with, and so on and so forth, right?
So, what we really want to do here, is we want to say that anything
that's inside this region isn't going to get simulated, right?
It's not going to get a chance.
It's not actually.
Get its chance to do its move whatever its move is right only the
things inside, the simulation area are going to actually have the
opportunity to move.
And these things are just going to be brought in sort of as stationary
static objects.
That cannot be moved, but that will serve as colliders for these other
things, right?
And so that's basically what we would have to do.
So I you know, this is the one thing like I was saying before that,
I'm not super thrilled about because it does, it is a little bit.
There's a little bit that I don't love about that.
It sounds, it's almost totally fine.
But the one part that I don't love about it, just in my head is what
it means is that, when two things Collide?
If one of them is in that static State, then they can't be moved.
And whereas normally they would have been able to have been moved.
So for example, we could have written Collision routines before, that
would flat-out just teleport somebody if we wanted to and that's not
really allowed.
Anymore.
Right?
It could teleport them as long as it was going to teleport them to
somewhere inside the simulation area but it wouldn't be allowed to
teleport them anywhere outside necessarily or other things like this.
Right.
It certainly can't move them to outside this Zone and so it does
impose a restriction.
I don't know if that restriction would ever actually matter in
practice.
I can't think of a particular reason why we need to do that but it is
a restriction.
Whereas almost everything else we've done with a simulation regions
has gotten us to a place where almost everything is
And free and are all the code can be written as if it doesn't even
care about the simulation region.
And that was kind of nice.
Whereas that's one thing that does have to kind of be aware of it.
And I don't love that part of it.
But I'm not sure there's really much else you can do about that.
So basically yeah everything has to basically have a marker in it
which says which will say whether or not it gets to be Sim din that
way.
So let's go ahead and
let's go ahead and add that because that's really the thing that I
want to do today to finish up those simulation regions.
And again, we don't really have to do anything, particularly fancy
here because we're just doing our engine spec stuff.
And, you know, we'll have plenty of time further on down the road to
think, about optimization and, and, you know, sort of other other
things that are going to impact this, as we get, more information
about how the game plays, but I just want to make sure that the
concepts in there, so that we kind of are familiar with it know that
it's there and
That when we make architectural, decisions, we're aware of it and not
just sort of going blind.
So, here's the same entity Flags, which are already storing our
special States like collides and non-spatial.
We have entity flag siming right now, which is basically a thing,
which says that it's in the same region.
So that's not what that particular thing means.
So we also have like an enemy flag.
Basically that I wanted to find here.
That means the thing that I just described on the Blackboard, I'm not
sure if that's what we should call it, but probably,
I'm guessing something like,
Can update or you know updatable, right?
I'm not sure what it would be.
Like an update will say.
Now the thing that's a little bit strange about this, you know, I
think I might actually not do that.
Now that I think about it, I think I might not actually do that.
What I think I'm going to do is do it slightly differently than that
because the flags or something that gets persisted and this is not a
persistent thing.
This is only true.
Inside the same region itself.
So it's kind of like, the storage index which is it something that,
you know, basically and I should probably put a note here, these are
only for the Sim region.
Once we start separating out this entity type into things that are
stored where they should be stored in that sort of stuff.
Once we break start breaking this apart, this is actually something
that would that would go with like just the Sim region part of things.
Right?
Whether or not this
Entities updatable.
And so I think that's probably just a better way to do that.
I think that's probably just the right.
Yeah, that's probably just the right call.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and say that things
that are updatable.
Are going to get that marker and then we'll come in here and we'll
sort of do the the most lightweight thing I can think of to do there.
Which is that when an entity gets added, right?
What I'm going to do is I'm going to say that if that entity is inside
a certain rectangle, then it's okay to be updated, right?
So the same region will store inside it.
It's got this bounds right?
And then it also will have a new thing which is basically update
bounds right?
Or updatable bounds and so that's the area where it's
Actually going to be allowed to.
If someone's inside that they will get like a tick.
Basically.
And if not, then they won't get a tick.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that the updatable bounds are in the
same region.
I'm going to go ahead and here and check to see every time an entity
comes into the active set.
I will basically set when I set it storage index, I will set whether
or not it's updatable based on whether it's in those updatable bound.
So I think we've got already, we already wrote the code for this,
right?
If you remember down in
Begin Sim.
We're already doing exactly this operation.
We do.
It is in rectangle, right?
Like this and so all we really need to do is we need to do just that
is in rectangle where we sort of do, the check on the updatable
bounce.
Now what I don't remember is I don't remember what we did with mapping
the the world space.
It looks like the world space gets mapped out here in this identity.
And so the only thing that I'm not sure
Our about is basically exactly how exactly whether I should update.
These are not in here.
I'm guessing I'll just leave them outside for now.
So if you call Ed, and if you brought your responsible for setting
that updatable yourself and it will soon, the anything gets added is
not an updatable entity otherwise, right?
And so assuming that it got added by the call, that actually does know
the location of the thing, then we will go ahead and set it at that
point to be updatable based on the Family's.
Okay, so we'll do groups updatable and we'll do Desta pee.
Like so now I again don't really know if I actually need to do this at
this point, I could just do this check when we're actually rolling
through and doing updating and then I wouldn't have store anything at
all.
The only reason I'm not sure about that is because I'm thinking that
sometimes will want to Mark things as updatable.
They don't necessarily have a position things like this if we have
synthetic entities or something like that and so I think I'm just
going to leave it as a pool because obviously it's easy to do it that
way and that way we'll be able to quickly set it in the future if we
want to.
So I'm going to say that that's a pretty much the entirety of it.
And then when we do our simulation step, right, which we're currently
still doing out here in hanbei dot CPP, we haven't pulled it out.
Yet when we're doing our simulation step, we're just going to go ahead
and check that.
And we're going to check to see if this thing is not supposed to be
updatable.
Then we won't actually update it, right?
so,
how should we do that?
It's a little bit.
It's a little bit problematic at the moment and the reason is a little
problematic is are still going to want to render it potentially or
maybe we won't now.
I think about it.
No, I guess if something's out in that region, we shouldn't be
rendering it either.
So really this entire I guess it's not janky, it's totally fine.
This entire thing should just be skipped.
Basically, for anybody who is yeah, who is not updatable.
So, we'll just say if the entity is updatable,
You know, it can have its day in the Sun and if it's not, then it's
not and it doesn't get to do anything really at all.
And so I think that's about it.
What I do have to do now, is figure out how big that updatable region
is, and or really, that's not true.
We already know how big that region is its we got to figure out how to
enlarge our other region.
Because remember, the update region, is the region that we're already
using.
What I'm talking about is expanding it out a little bit.
So really the updatable bounds are actually the bounds that get
Passed in, right?
And the same region bounds are actually going to be those bounds plus
some additional size, right?
And so for now like I said we don't actually know what that size would
be.
We have no idea so I guess we'll just say are our safety margin.
Right?
Our update safety margin will be something and we'll put it to do here
that says important Casey and this is what were the
Do we're doing right now, actually important.
We want to say that this is
calculated eventually or whoops, calculate this.
Eventually from the maximum value of all entities radius plus their
speed
Right.
And then we will know that we are safe.
So for now we're just adding a meter but in the future we should add
something totally different than a meter once we actually know what's
going down.
So we've got that, that should be basically enough now.
So all we need to do is be able to, you know,
Enlarge those bounds.
Now, I already told you about the minkowski sum, right?
I sort of was stating before that, I don't know if you guys remember
when we talked about Collision detection are sort of saying that a
rectangle plus a rectangle equals another rectangle, right?
And the way that you do that is if you imagine these were radius' of
the rectangle, right?
So you have like half the width, this is this is the height over to.
This is the width / 2 right of these guys.
So, if this was a and this
Is B.
Then this guy is just a plus b, right?
So basically adding two rectangles together is pretty darn simple.
You just take the center point and the center point stays the same and
you add well, that's not, you know, I shouldn't I shouldn't say that
that's not entirely true.
What I just said technically, if you were doing a real Mankowski, some
you'd actually add the points without considering the center point.
So really what we want to do here is not really a minkowski sum what
we really are sort of saying here.
Them is a minkowski sum but smykowski some with a rectangle that's
centered around zero, right?
Which is sort of a special case.
So yeah, that's sort of like kind of through the term around a little
lucy and I shouldn't do that.
So really what we're all were saying, here is whatever the width was
of this guy with in height, right?
So if this was with one height 1 and this is 2 with 2, we just want to
add those together so that we end up with something with H1 plus H2
and with 1 plus with to right.
And so in our case, we know that we want to expand our like, are
additive region, is just going to be that, that value, that one meter,
write the update, safety margin.
So all we want to do is take our rectangle and add the safety margin
to, you know, to all sides of it basically, right?
So in order to do that, I think I might add a thing to our rectangle
code that does this automatically.
So that I can basically say that, you know,
The updatable bounds if we want to produce the bounds of our Sim
region, what we're going to do is we're going to do something like a
ad width height, look, something like this and yeah, so we'll add, I
guess add radius to or something like this and we'll do something
where we just say, We'll add that safety margin, and that will go
ahead and add it and and maybe will allow you to pass in.
Hey, a width and a height radius essentially to add to either side.
So inside our math routines, we just have to go in add that which will
be really simple.
Obviously we've got sort of our rectangle calls here.
All we need is a new rectangle call, right?
Where we do add Radius 2 and that will take one of our rectangles.
The Source rectangle, right?
Okay, so let's call that a and then it'll take two things will take a
radius width and a radius keeps getting close to my head there.
Radio site.
So again really really simple here all we have to do is is you know,
do a subtraction and an ad.
I guess alike separate this way from the Min and the max of the thing
that's passed in the minimum corner of the rectangle will just get it
subtracted the radius, right?
And the maximum Corner we'll just have the radius, get added and
that's it and that should produce for us a new rectangle.
That's you know, bigger by that much.
All right, so let's go ahead and check that out.
There we go.
And now I think that should just sort of do it again.
We haven't we don't really have any good ways to test this at this
point, but that should just about just about do that and of course
we're still doing this here.
Yeah.
All right, so the last thing that we have to do is we kind of got to
figure out how we want to deal with like this sword and stuff.
So should the sword still work?
Because once we do know, do we have to make things updatable?
Or will they just automatically handle that?
Let's find out.
I guess was the thing that that's probably the easiest way to do it.
So inside, where is it here?
Where's our sword code handmade?
I probably should also pull out this stuff into the Sim region since
it's pretty much where it's at or maybe into the end of the file.
So, if we go through here and we're doing our hero, and then, we're
going to go ahead and do
Update for the storage and we do the make entity spatial thing which
moves it into the spatial set, should that that gives it a position.
So, the next time through, you would think that it would get pulled in
right to the simulation region and get updated.
I would think
that seems like, what should happen, but let's find out if it's what
actually happens.
Okay, I'm not seeing a sword there.
So I feel like I'm not thinking it through properly.
I'm just trying to figure out whether we need to move things into the
update set that aren't, you know, these things are obviously not
updatable or whatever would be 0.
Well, no, never mind.
I just trying to, well, let me let me check, let me go ahead and show.
So what I just realized is we may never set positions properly on our
thing.
That hoists things in from references, right?
When we do load into the reference, what are we doing here?
Yeah, okay.
See, that's yeah.
So this is actually just a bug.
This is just totally a bug.
We never saw the bug before, but it was always there.
When we load an entity reference in, we should go ahead and get its
position set here, right?
Because just because we happen to be loading it in Via reference,
doesn't mean we wouldn't want to position it if it had a valid
position, right?
And so that seems totally
August to me and not at all like, what we would want it to do, right?
So we'd want it, we definitely want that.
They get some space Peak all, we definitely want to do that.
So it's sort of starting to feel like, yeah.
Well, no, because we, I guess the reason that we did it this way to
begin with, right, the reason that we had to get some space people
that is because we needed to do that ahead of time to see whether it
was in the update region or not.
So I guess we should just keep doing it this way.
But we should do I think is just going
Ahead and do that gets in space p, right on the the, the low entity.
So we'll do it this way, right entity.
I think we should just probably make it a fact that we always do this
additional call when we're loading the reference.
So that we know that we'll always actually have that guy in there
properly.
All right, so we're going to do that, get low entity, gave State ref
index, we will actually slow entity.
We will get some space pee on him and we will go ahead and pass that
to this call.
Like so and there we go.
That's about it.
And also does add entity.
I don't even know where this is actually getting called now.
I guess it gets called it gets cold only when someone actually does
have that same space p.
So it's a little bit weird.
Yeah, it's a little bit weird and we just did that.
To do as well.
So, let's take a look.
I feel like that could be simplified a little bit.
I feel like we've got a little bit more than we need, now, in terms of
stuff, but but who knows it's not that much.
We'll see.
All right, so there's, there's that, so that's fixed.
And that's what we would expect now.
And I think everything's pretty good now, I think we're pretty happy
with that.
Don't think we need to do too much else.
So, yeah.
Where are we on time?
We still have a half an hour left.
So I think maybe what we should probably
We should start doing now is start actually going back and looking at
the stuff that originally motivated, this sort of things, which is
just having hit points being able to do some stuff at that.
Hmm.
Having a trouble.
Getting the water in my mouth today.
That's not good at all.
You'd think that after a while.
I'd be good enough drinking from these things that I wouldn't have
that problem but you know, it's not true at all.
Absolutely just disastrous here.
The problem is, of course, I suppose it's not almond milk.
I was drinking water from this today and so you know at that point the
viscosity change is obviously is really the problem.
It wasn't my fault.
It was it was this different liquid.
So yeah, so I think probably the easiest thing for us to start playing
And at this point is just maybe like working on some of these guys, I
also feel like our familiar has stopped going because I don't know.
We have reported his code so I feel like we could do some of that
work.
So maybe let's just go through and just tidy up some of this stuff,
get everything ported.
Make sure we're working and take a look at like the mon star on the
hit points in that sort of stuff because now that we've taken care of
the same region stuff, and we've gotten that sort of in their
situated.
Now might be a good time to kind of deal with some of the stuff.
So, let's see, our familiar is not does not appear to be working
properly, as far as I can tell, because before are
ER would follow us around and he's not, he's totally not following us
around, right?
Like, he's not following us around at all.
So, why isn't he following us around?
Let's take a look.
So, when we're in update, familiar, and I guess I'll also take a look
at the code that calls update, familiar update familiar.
So in update familiar, we're just getting normally called as I think
we would and we are passing a Sim region, empty unit.
In a Time step we then say that we're going to search within 10
meters.
We go through here and we search for inside.
Oh well, that's pretty obvious.
Some reason we never incremented the test and be pointer.
So we did Port it, we just poured it badly.
Let's all go ahead and recompile that and see if the familiar
And there we go.
So we were just weren't looking through all the entities, simple
simple bug problem solved.
Alright, so there's our little familiar and off, he goes make sense.
So, let's take a look at the monstar.
And let's take a look at the Collision detection, The Sword, and that
sort of stuff.
So, mmm.
It looks like, you know, we've got this non-spatial flag here and I
feel like for the most part that doesn't really need to be like,
depending on how we decide to do things.
We wouldn't really have to check for this at.
All right?
Because now since we only pull things into the update region, if those
things are actually we only call the update function if something's
actually
Inside the update region.
If the sword is not inside the update, mutant it wouldn't get called.
So, you know, this may not even need to exist anymore, right?
If I were to get rid of this, I don't think it would matter anymore
because we sort of fixed.
We sort of got rid of the need to even have that concept now.
Because since we don't since yes, they get brought into the simulation
set, but the simulation set has a concept of updatable that doesn't
include any entities that would have had non-spatial set.
So that's kind of interesting that I wonder if
Allow us to simplify some things even further.
I hadn't thought about that but it's kind of interesting and kind of
neat.
So kind of an accidental thing that happened there but you know, I'll
take it.
So when the sword moves
We're calling move entity on the sword.
And what we want to do now is we want to figure out a way that we can
sort of use our Collision detection to actually do some kind of an
operation when the sword hits something right?
And we talked a little bit about having a table, that would record
when things got hit and that sort of stuff.
So let's go take a look at that stuff because we want to be able to do
all that stuff.
So we might as well just pick up where we left off way back when and
actually start coding some of that.
So we've got our move entity call, right?
And the way the move entity call is it
The equations of motion for this thing and you know, what else I
should probably do while we're at it.
While, we're just cleaning stuff up.
Because I'm thinking about it right now, we've got like this DZ update
stuff that should probably be inside, move Envy as well, right?
It's like the move entity, should update Z coordinate.
I feel like for stuff like so and so, you know, for now, I would say
we should probably do this in here.
Now, we want to integrate it in a little bit better than it's been
integrated in right now.
But let's just go ahead and put that there for now.
And then that should allow us to have.
You know, RZ get handled along with everything else inside the move
call and that seems just better, right?
So let's just do that and that's done.
So what I was going to say was when we do our move entity call, right?
We're doing this test for collision and, you know, it's totally fine.
We haven't really done a real one yet.
It's kind of, it's not a really very it's not a complete collision
detector but it does let us know when things hit other things and when
things hit other things, we have the option of doing something about
it.
And obviously that's what we would want to do in the case of the
sword.
But what we have is we've got sort of our
Are colliding flag doesn't really tell us everything that we might
want to know about what we should do to handle the movement of this
entity because we really want to things for the entity as far as
Collision are concerned.
We want to be able to do collisions and we want to be able to respond
to collisions but those should be separate things.
Some things right may want to actually stop when they hit things,
right?
Like we may want, you know, the like for example, the reason we were
We wrote this when the hero hits a wall we wanted to stop moving.
That's one thing we can do with Collision, but another thing we might
want to do a collision is allow the player to pass through the wall
but just you know, do something about the fact that, right?
So imagine not a wall and instead this time it's a floor plate.
We may want them to be able to walk over the floor plate, but we want
to do something in the case where they have walked over it, right?
So really we want to start breaking our Collision response into
multiple pieces, which is the detecting the fact that it happened and
responding to it are not going to be the same flag or not even gonna
be the same like idea, really?
We want to separate those out into different things because the sword
might be an object that works exactly like that.
It may not stop when it gets a monster, it may you know pass through
the monster and do damage but do damage to other monsters as it goes
like perhaps that's piercing and that sort of stuff, right?
So you want to be able to sort of have individual control over which
one of those is going to happen.
I did the drinking correctly that time, so how do we want to do that?
Well, it's pretty easy for us to do something very simple, right?
And so the complicated part is actually going to come in how we sort
of want to break this routine out into something that's a little more
usable by the higher level code.
And so we've got we've got a couple different things to talk about
here all of which are very very intricate and complicated.
We might not do all of them right now, but we'll sort of talk about
them.
So the first thing that you'll notice is inside a single Collision,
inside a single move, call we have iterative system, that's working,
right?
And I'm going to go ahead here and draw this out for you because it
was, it's been a while since we did this.
I just want to make sure people remember.
So let's say that we have well actually I'll draw a little bit
different.
Let's say that we have something like this, right now.
That's even that's not what I would have.
What I, what I really wanted.
Oops, let's bring that back.
Okay.
So let's say that I have something where I've got a wall like this and
then I've got another wall like that, right?
And the player is trying to move like this, okay?
And so when they hit this wall here, we are stopping them and that's
good.
But we're allowing them to continue to move along the wall, right?
And what we're doing is we're saying well, wherever you could have
moved to, if you had moved the regular
Correction.
You were going will allow you to go that far along the wall, right?
But the problem is there may be another wall like in this case.
So we would then do another Collision step to find where you hit that
wall, right?
And so really there are two iterations inside a single call to move
entity.
In this case, we would have had two iterations one, that moves the guy
to here and hit this entity, whatever this is, right?
And another that moves it to here and hit this entity which could
technically be a different entity, right?
So this could be entity a and this could be any be.
Now what we want to do, what we want to start to start doing here,
like I was saying is for any of the A's Collision.
We may want to have a response, right?
We may want to do something when a and and whatever are any that we're
moving our, we'll call that eat when he and a Collide, we may want to
do something right?
And then furthermore when Ian be Collide, we may want to do something.
So we're now in a position where we have sort of this this need to do
a dispatch, but we need to do the dispatch from inside of an
iteration, right?
And so the normal way that people handle this is with a call back,
right?
What they do is they come in here because this is, this is the part of
the code, excuse me.
In.
This iteration here.
We would want to do this inside the iteration, right?
So when we do hit entity, this right here here is where we would
process, whatever the entity that was, that you hit.
Here's where we process it.
So what they typically will do here is they do like something where we
do like, you know, process Collision, right?
And they would call out into something that handles the Collision.
Now I don't know if we necessarily want to do that, right?
We might, we might not what I
I do know is that typically it can be a little bit annoying to have it
work in a callback fashion.
Because a lot of times callbacks lose, a certain degree of important
flow control that you might want.
Now this is the first time that this is really come up.
And so I think I'm going to spend a little bit of time talking about
it because we do have plenty of time left and we don't have anything
particular that we need to get done on the Stream.
So now might be a really good time to talk about this.
So let's talk about it.
So let's talk about callbacks
Right.
So basically what we have right now is we have a pretty nice system,
we have a function that's called move entity and anyone who wants to
can call move entity to move their entity, right?
And we can use that in any way that we want, there's no restrictions
on what we can do with it, right?
We can just do it.
And if we have an entity that we want to move, we move it.
If we don't, we don't, you know, and we can also call move entity
multiple times if you wanted to, on a single entity or move different
pieces of an entity with new vanity, we can do all kinds of stuff,
right?
There's all kinds of things we could do.
Mobility.
And the reason we can do that is specifically because it doesn't
really do anything inside it except the one thing, right, all it does
is it moves The Entity to wherever it should have been given the
Collision that's involved in the simulation region.
So a callback introduces something into here.
That's and this is true of any situation where you introduce callbacks
anytime that you have something that does an iteration, right?
So typically there's some kind of complex iteration involved, right?
And we saw the iteration, it's a collision it.
Duration.
But there's other iterations, like, let's say that you had something
like a binary tree or you had something like XML file, right?
And you've written an iteration that iterates over it, but you want to
do something on every node or you want to do something.
When you find certain things or you want to test, it, callbacks are
typical way that you introduce that functionality because you can sort
of pass the call back in right or something like that.
To the function and then the function will sort of do something.
We'll call that and allow that to work.
Now, other languages and also in C++ 11 have slightly better versions
of this, right?
They have they have closures and lambdas, right?
I don't know.
I spell Lambda Lambda.
Yeah, they have other things which allow you to access different
stacks and kind of do some other things that make callbacks a little
more painful but the
bottom line is, callbacks are always kind of
Not really what you would prefer to have happen.
If you could have written the code to, to basically never have to
share anything, right?
And why is that?
Well, the reason for that is actually pretty straightforward.
If I have a piece of code, you know, if I have code a write and I
wrote it, and then I have code B, and I write that right code.
B, is the thing that does the iteration
I want to be able to share, you know, with my I got codes.
See down here, I want to be able to share this iteration with both
code a and code B9 s code C, right?
I want to be able to share probably nobody's bitch.
No, let's call that b and that c, right?
Or better.
Yet code s for shared.
So I have Cody and I have code B, and they both want to use code s,
right?
They want to use that iteration, but they want to do different things
when the iteration happens, right?
So the reason that callbacks are kind of a nasty way of doing this, is
it forces whoever wrote code a right to basically bundle up something,
that's capable of doing whatever it needs to have being done and send
it over to code s, right?
So that code s can actually do whatever the thing is that needs to be
done.
Now, it basically introduces this nasty, coupling of the S code,
understanding the sorts of things you might want to do in A and B,
right?
And preparing it such that it can use whatever this black boxes that
have been passed.
Furthermore it assumes that code a has to go to bundle up all the
stuff.
It might want to do which is kind of cumbersome for it, right?
And it has to sort of have this sort of
Ocean of context and all the things that it might want to do, bundle
them all up and then send it over right?
Really for no reason because if we were only going to write one piece
of code, let's say, we just had code be in CODIS, right, BS.
Okay, let's not say that.
Let's say we had code A and S, right?
Or I could fill the could do code s be put in the other way around.
So let's say we had codes S and B and we were just writing that's all
we were writing.
We never had to share it.
Then what you would do is you just write the iteration code, right?
You just write this.
This and then whatever this code that was going to do, whatever it was
going to do, you'd put it right in here and it could be made nice and
clean and optimal and everything would be great because everybody kind
of knew exactly what was supposed to happen and you didn't have to
have this part where two sides of the program were written without
knowing what the other person was doing or without being able to
really change what the other person was doing.
And that's where you get through this, callback nesses comes in,
So again these things make them a little bit easier because you can
share stack frames or some stuff that you can do in languages that
support other things.
And again, C++ 11 ads.
These guys, I believe, I don't think it.
I don't think it adds these.
I don't really know.
I don't stay up to date with C++ 11 much but
Pretty sure.
Lamb doesn't put it that way.
And so really, if you can avoid it though, it's nicer.
If you can get out of this business altogether and just allow
whatever.
This was it, you're going to write in here.
This, this, this, this s-code the thing that does the Adoration.
It's often times much nicer.
If you can just expose that as a sort of tool that these guys can use
to write an iteration, right?
So, basically, whatever this was doing, if you can package it up as an
iterator that these guys can use then
Are able to sort of reverse that flow instead of having to pass this
into here.
If you can just fragment this iteration code up into basically two
parts, right?
The initialization and the stepping through the iteration.
If you can break that up, that gives you a lot more flexibility to
write the code.
I mean outside anyway that you wanted to without having to deal with
this sort of Black Box, passing kind of nonsense that's just you know
makes life a little more difficult for everybody.
And so, what I would probably recommend doing depending on how we
decide to go forward with this, and I'm not sure exactly how we will
decide to tackle.
It is if we decided to keep calling move entity the way we've been
calling it.
I would probably go ahead and break this iteration out into its
Preamble.
So I just take this portion here, break that out into something that
basically sets up a struct that has these variables in it, right?
And then I would have an iteration call which does this stuff and that
call would just return the hit enter.
And you can call it as many times as you want, and then when you're
done, you would just, you would say finish, right?
And it would do this post amble.
That'd be a really much cleaner way than like introducing a call back
in here.
That does the Collision on the times.
When that happens, right?
So that's one way I could go, I'm just trying to give you the full,
what's in my head when I'm thinking about this?
That's one way I could go and I'm totally fine with that.
That seems like a good way to go, but there's another way I could go,
which is if moving entities.
It's something that's always going to be handled in the central.
Local like a central logical fashion.
So, basically moving into these just, is it something that's allowed
to be done?
Pretty much ever except by the centralized concept of the update?
Then what I could do is totally change how this works entirely and say
when you do your update call, you are not allowed to move your enemy.
You don't get to call move entity.
What you do.
Is you latch in what
You want your acceleration to be because that's what your control is,
right?
You get to set your acceleration and then once you've set it, the
movement will happen automatically somewhere down the line, right?
So that's another way I could go.
And if that's the way I could go, then this doesn't become a callback
situation because there's only one thing that can ever happen in here
which is, this is the place we're dispatching.
Entity collisions actually gets processed, but it's always going to be
process exactly the same way.
So we don't have a situation where we've got
Voice that out.
Now to me just on the whole that kind of sounds like the right way to
go.
And the reason that I think that kind of sounds like the right way to
go is because in the future we don't know exactly how we might want to
do our actual updating.
We might want to try and do some simultaneous Collision solving where
like multiple people are moving at the same time and we find their
intersection points.
That's our stuff, we met?
Who knows what we might want to do.
And so what I probably don't want to do.
Do going down.
You know what?
I probably don't want to establish as an early on policy at this
point, is the concept that entity is all called new vanity themselves.
I think I might want to take that out of their hands and say spatial.
This is just an inherent aspect of gaming, we will handle it in a
centralized fashion.
You aren't really going to do that, right?
So we're going to do that for you and basically like we'll just have a
flag and then the flag which says, you know, I am a movie, I'm an
entity that can move or something and that.
Or you know, maybe the only have to have a flag, it's just whether if
acceleration was set, then it goes right and to me just thinking it
through, I feel like that just feels a little bit better to me.
It feels a little bit more, like probably what should happen.
So I think that's what I'm going to start with and then if it turns
out that that doesn't work then we'll we'll sort of address it a
little bit further on.
So for now, I think that's what I'll do.
What will sort of say here is?
Maybe we'll just say when we're doing our entity update for now.
Again, this, you know, not at all set in stone.
What will kind of do is say, let's set this move spec and this DDP
here, let's go ahead and say that those are going to be things that
are sort of, you know, are sort of set in the end of these update.
And then the actual movement call is not something that the end of the
actually gets to deal with.
That's something that that
Happens somewhere down the line.
So, like this stuff right here, that doesn't get to happen.
Instead, what happens is, is this moose back up here, right?
We'll set that to the default move Spectrum.
Now, like so, and then the Moose back, we'll get set in here for each
individual entity, and then this doesn't actually get to happen.
So the con hero DDP, excuse me,
becomes that GDP.
Right?
So this starts out with no acceleration the con hero DDP that gets put
in there.
Actually, I guess.
And the entity DZ would also be that as well.
I would say.
No, that's that, that's discontinuous.
So, that's fine.
Alright.
Well, we'll talk about that later.
This is our stupid jump code.
That's shouldn't even be in here, but yeah, it's lingering.
So, yeah.
So instead of calling move entity, that move entity called will get
pushed out to the bottom, right will be do that here.
and what we said we're going to do is we're going to say that this
right here just sets what we want, the
Relation to be and that's it, right?
Similarly, the rest of these guys, don't get to do that either.
They all have to do the exact same thing and I'm also wondering why we
even bother having these?
Well, I don't know why I have like these calls separated out this
thing, like kind of useless functions to me.
These should just be inside the switch statement, and this switch
statement should be out here in the handmade entity.
But you know what you gonna do sometimes, you know?
Yeah, you can't win them all.
We'll think about how that structure little bit later on.
So we want to do here is we want to be able to sort of have this
worked out and maybe you know what I could do to?
I could sort of say that that move spec.
No, no, I'm not gonna do that.
Alright, so when I update the familiar wants to be able to set a moose
back as well and it's going to have to set its GDP as well.
So I need a convenient way.
If for as long as I am keeping these guys out here, you can see why I
don't love having these out and separate functions for no apparent
reason.
I can't just go ahead and set these things that I want to set.
Which is kind of annoying.
So I might just go ahead and just stick this in here.
Let's go ahead and say that we're going to go ahead and there we go.
So now I can just set my moves.
Back directly I can set my DDP directly, of course Source don't have a
DDP and get rid of these guys that's gone.
We can get rid of this, that's gone.
So see update familiar.
There we go.
Bye.
And that actually makes this a lot a lot nicer to work with.
And then I just go ahead and pull this out and this would be the
routine that basically holds all of our update calls.
Again, A lot of people are always like, oh, you got to pull it out
into a function but there's no difference between a function and just
a case statement, right?
You still have a file that lists all these things right whether their
functions are inside a switch statement.
But if you put them inside a switch statement, you have the option of
having the Preamble stack be shared which is just so much nicer to
work with, right?
Yeah.
So I don't tend to agree with people who
That you know, it often just seems like a really bad idea but, you
know, I guess everyone has their preferences.
So what do you do?
So I guess what I'll do is, I'm just going to go ahead and pull this
out.
Going to put, put these things in there, and I'm going to pull it out.
So that all of our entity update is just in one file, and it's
basically a set of case statements.
One for each guy for now.
That's probably not how we will do it, eventually, because I've got
sort of bigger plans for how I want any of these to decompose, but
that's a separate issue.
All right?
So now that this guy's in here, we
Can just have the Moose affect the set directly and the DDP will also
be set directly.
In fact, we can just delete that and now it works exactly.
As we thought it would.
I believe, let's go ahead and compile that process Collision.
That's not a real thing.
Let's see, more than one vote, and made entity, that con hero.
Okay, so now we need to do are actually
Call, we've got some Regional entity.
We've got our dt4 frame, we've got the moves back and so now we just
need to change that to the regular GDP and then I think we're good to
go, right?
Am I right about that?
What happened there?
Move entity non-spatial right.
Got about that.
So what we do have to do here as well as we have, to make sure that
we're actually only moving people who should be moved, which actually
is not to owners because really, that's just
50 DPX or GDP why, right?
If there was actually any movement that someone actually wanted, that
should be sufficient to tell us, right?
Yes.
I think so.
That would be my assumption.
Yeah.
And that does look like boo.
What's happening there?
What's going on there?
I've got, I've still got, I've got something.
There we go.
That should not be happening.
TT moose back.
Oh, and you know what to it's actually whether their velocity is, is
there, that's right.
It's, whether they have velocity or they have acceleration, not just
whether they have acceleration.
Although really again, like, I don't know if maybe we should have
something, this is a little bit of a weird way to see whether it
entities should be movable or not.
We might want something a little, a little smarter than that, but I
don't know for now.
I suppose it's okay, we'll see.
Gotta get a little further down the line.
So that's a little weird.
That guy doesn't look like we had for our sword.
There, it didn't look like our sword was properly.
Using its distance remaining.
Let's see here.
So if it says judge make any non spatial.
So yeah we also now that I think about it, we're once something gets
made non-spatial, this would move them back into spatial NE, so that's
Probably not good either.
So we may still need to check that now.
I think so basically we may have to actually we may have to actually
just say that we're going to still have am.
I check on the flags there and then only spatial things will actually
get to do that.
So we'll do that.
We'll do.
If is set annatee non-spatial right?
Then it can go ahead and do it smooth.
Let me see how it.
Let me see if that's a little more sensible.
I sort of understand why this guy can go forever, though.
It doesn't make a whole lot of sense for me, shouldn't his distance.
I guess I must have when I cut and pasted the code in there.
I must have not updated, everything distance traveled equals The
Entity po.
Right.
Because now we're since we moved we were counting on the fact that we
knew how far it had moved since the last frame, but now we don't
actually know that anymore so that that is the one place where we were
counting on the fact then and so far anyway, then entity would
actually get information about that.
But we already had a bug of that form, which was that we essentially
didn't handle the fact that inside a move, it shouldn't have been able
to be allowed to move further than when the distance traveled timer
would have happened.
So what we really probably want to do is handle this in a more robust
way where the Collision routines actually understand the concept of a
limit to the motion, and we'll stop it at that limit.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that.
That's something we can do tomorrow and this will be are important
too.
Do for tomorrow, add the ability in the Collision routines, to
understand a movement limit for, you know, a foreign entity.
And then update this routine to use that to know when to kill the
sword.
Yeah, because that was a bug.
We already had.
That's this to do down here, right?
And so we kind of want to go ahead and actually fix that so that it's
not going to do it that way anymore.
That's what we'll start with tomorrow.
And then, we can also finish our Collision stuff.
Figure out how we want to do that.
We'll move this guy out as well.
I think I want to put the two in here.
Move this out into handmade entity dot CPP and then that way we'll
have a special place where all of our MD updates live just so they're
easy to spot and understand.
All right, so that's about it.
We can go ahead and go to the go to the Q&A.
I don't know how it's been going over there on the chat, but I guess
now we will find out.
Please prefix, your colon, your quest, your colons priest.
Please prefix York,
students with q: or are prefix or Colin's, with Q your choice, and
Yeah, well actually I guess you have to prefix or questions with Q: if
you want me to see them and please keep them the stuff that we did on
today's stream on a previous stream.
If you want to ask off-topic questions, do that during the pre stream.
Just come 50 minutes before any scheduled start time and we take off
topic questions then.
Handmade here.
How will Collision be done with moving background such as mazes and
moving tiles?
Or that won't be in this game actually.
So the code already works with that.
I guess, I don't know that we have any way to demonstrate it right
now.
I suppose what we could do if we wanted to write is is
so here's what I'd say.
So right now, we know when that happens, we just don't do anything
about it, and that's the thing we need to do anyway, for other
reasons, just for Collision robustness because right now, we would get
into situations because of floating point in this where you could get
stuck in an entity, right?
Because we don't handle like, I don't, I can't quite demo it right
now.
There you go, I've got it now, right?
We're, you can get locked in an entity because floating Point,
Precision wise, when we do our Collision detection, we don't try to
You we don't try to ensure that we actually put you outside of things
and if you don't do that you will always get in situations where you
get like janky Collision Behavior.
Once we add the code to do that, it will be pretty easy for us to
handle moving backgrounds because we already support Collision
detecting with moving backgrounds.
That would already work the problem right now is we just don't respond
to them.
So when they hit you,
They would stop instead of you getting pushed, which is probably what
you wanted.
And so, as our Collision, routines become more sophisticated, we
should just hit the moving, background stuff will just should just
work.
It's not very hard to handle, but that's really the problem right now.
Detection is easy, but handling it, we haven't done yet.
So we would need to do something that just when at two objects
Collide, we just need a notion that one of them would take priority.
So when that background object, it's you, we just need
Some kind of a notion that says it's has the right of way.
So you know it will push you, right?
And we should be able to handle that pretty easily.
There are a bunch of things, you have to watch out for when you do
support that.
Like what do you want to do?
If somebody is like pushing, you know, if a pushing object pushes you
up against something, what do you want to do, you know?
Does it lock up, doesn't stop at that point and you can scoot out of
it or you know, who knows what happens?
Exactly.
But, you know, those are the kinds of things that we have to decide.
Probably more based on gameplay like what we want to have happen.
So it is a little bit of work to handle those things but it's not like
the end of the world especially since the bar is pretty low like most
games, kind of flail pretty miserably handling.
A lot of those things.
You always see all these weird bugs and stuff but we should be able to
do a pretty good job of handling that once we get there.
Why don't we use C instead of CPP?
Because we do use, we don't we try not to use too much random C++ this
because I'm not fond of it.
But we do.
It actually is not see.
It's actually C++ so you can see for example you know that would not
compiled in C so we do use some C++, just not very much.
That's a good question.
Someone just asked when I started enums.
Why did I start with one?
Shifted up one?
Instead of one shift of zero because I was not paying attention.
There's no reason that could totally just be that.
Yeah, that just totally totally asleep at the switch.
How big are the source files getting?
Are you feeling overwhelmed by the size yet?
Overwhelmed by the size of the source code, as it currently stands is
the source.
Code is like, Wicked, tiny, isn't it?
I don't know if there is there.
A lines, counting groups lines bok-bok.
Do we have any line counting program?
We don't have a line cutting program count lines.
Region.
So if I select this whole thing and do count lines region oh well I
guess it says the bottom 117.
428, I don't know, I want will have to download something that counts
lines so we can actually see how many there are, but I mean, just
looking at the size of the code, just even ignoring the line count.
But I mean, look at, look at there's nothing here.
It's like
It's like 150k a code or some like it's hard.
There's like no code here.
This is like so tiny and like a huge portion of that is the random
number table, right?
And the win32 platform code so there's there's like hardly know code
at all at this is like
This is so tiny.
What happens when you somehow glitch through a wall?
Will the game crash?
It certainly wouldn't crash.
You just get stuck in the wall at the moment.
You mean like I mean obviously in the final version of our stuff we
won't allow you to glitch through a wall at the moment.
Nothing would happen.
Other than you getting stuck behind the wall but you could probably
try to click your way through the wall again, I suppose.
Oh no heavy moderation tonight.
I'm sorry about that guys.
Do we need more moderators?
Maybe we need more moderators.
I don't want you guys to be too swamped if you need more help.
Let me know who you would like me to add.
How many lines are written so far?
Yeah, I don't know.
That's the thing.
We need like a line counting program.
I'll look up a look one up.
There isn't one on this machine.
I don't think so.
Yeah, I don't.
I don't know, at the moment but not many.
I mean, like I said, this is very tiny for me.
This is not a lot of code.
In what situation would you prefer callbacks to a huge switch case
block?
I can't think of any offhand.
There probably is a time.
I just can't think of it off hand.
Switch case blocks are almost always far superior to callbacks in my
experience.
They're better in almost every way you can possibly measure in terms
of code quality like in terms of like flexibility of the code ease of
reading ease of use ease of compression like they're better for just
about everything but there may be some things.
I'm trying to think if there's some things so one reason why you one
place where I can think just trying to think where you might have a
problem with them it's like if you're trying to isolate platforms from
each other,
What you don't want your win32 code, in your Apple Mac OS, X code, and
stuff intermingling.
Then that's a place where you would want to keep those files
segregated, right?
And you wouldn't be mixing things in with a switch statement.
So, you know, I know something like that.
I tend to always architect those for the platform layer of stuff,
flows forward.
But but we've already got like an example of a call back in there for
the debug loader code, so that's an example.
But yeah, it's not often.
I do, I think
I'm still stuck by the way.
So there's a little bit of nose blowing going on.
Basically my opinion on switch statements is that somewhere around the
object oriented apocalypse, you know in the 90s everyone kind of got
it in their head that like for some reason like objects that
inheritance and virtual functions and all this are like a good idea
and switch statements.
Got this sort of bad rap, but the opposite is really true.
Like the switch statement is the superior method of those two and so
almost, every place that people use like a virtual function, they
should
Using a switch statement in my opinion and you know like you know
upfront Partners would will get mad at me for saying that but I have
written the code both ways and I am totally happy to go to the
mattresses on that one because it's just true.
Like it is far superior code in the switch statement, there's so much
more stuff you can do with a switch statement then you can do with
virtual function, calls and virtual function calls, are almost always
worse, right?
And
You know, the list of things is non-trivial.
To give just a couple examples, but like there's the Preamble post
amble stuff.
That's, that's really easy to see and understand a switch statement,
right?
It's not in some weird inheritance hierarchy, where the person who's
adding a new virtual function, doesn't even know, like what things
might happen, pre and post amble and all that stuff that they can just
see it.
They can access the member, the variables directly inside their thing
in the pre and post amble without having to know where to look for
them or to get them from some extra thing.
The switch statement switches off of a value and that value can be
persistent whereas a virtual function cannot be, for example, right?
Like there's no way to persist the type of a class automatically in
C++ you have to introduce a secondary scheme which guess what ends up
being an enum, you could have just switched off that enum instead of
introducing a virtual function table for no reason, right?
It just goes and goes and goes.
There's like, there's never
It's all bad with like virtual functions and that sort of stuff and
and function pointers, they're just always worse than switch
statements, but I shouldn't say that they're almost always worse, but
there are a couple times.
I mean, I'm sure if I go through my code I can find places where I've
used function calls.
Callbacks I never use Virtual functions but I might use like a
function call or a call back for a legitimate purpose.
One is platform code stuff where you're trying to keep the code out of
a thing.
I'm trying to think if there's other cases there might be a couple I'm
forgetting.
So always is the wrong term.
I don't mean that but but almost always you should have.
You should have written the switch statement.
Do we load and draw everything manually to a dip section, then blit
the final image.
Yes, that is correct.
The way we handle GDI drawing is basically we try to do the minimum
amount of cruft between the two.
So we just we don't even really use a dip section.
Technically, we just use a buffer of B and then we asked GDI to put
that buffer B to a window please.
So we can see it.
After you mentioned the do all collisions at one time thing.
It seems like in addition to being great deal, easier to implement it
also matches the real world better like summing all the forces to get
the net Direction.
Why would anyone ever want to do an update function for each object?
It seems like that would just introduce problems.
Well yeah, I mean, I think most of the time people, do we do it the
way that I'm suggesting, we do it.
But you know, I mean,
It's six of one half-dozen of the other.
I mean, you there's reasons why I like you saw how we introduce.
We had one example, right?
That is harder.
If the object custom code, can't control when it does updated, can't
do things, like, look at its previous and last thing cleanly, now that
has to be something that gets hoisted out, right?
There's like there's reasons why it's more convenient for the object
to be able to say when it gets updated.
In a perfect world, you'd have it so that you could probably do both
things.
Like, it's, it gives the pre and post amble in a still clean fashion.
Like this is probably something like, John blows language will let you
do write it as if you did it this way.
But then pull it out so that it ends up running it the other way,
which would be kind of cool.
But yeah.
So, but no, I mean, it's true like like you say it, the reason I
suggested it because it's, you know, it is a common way to do it.
It's not, I'm not suggesting some really radical new thing, that's
that's a common way that people Implement their engines.
And I suspect, it's probably the right thing for us to do.
But, you know,
I just clocked account lines and it's pretty decent.
Says Jonathan Blow.
I don't know.
Can we get?
Can we get that clock?
Clock.
Download.
There we go.
I'm looking for the latest version.
Is it downloading?
Yes, we're download start in 0.
So why don't you just download because you wanted me to watch your
ads.
Course, maybe sourceforge will tell us what the latest flavor of
Mountain Dew is, since I don't have an Xbox One.
Okay, so there we go.
So if I actually start up downloads
there's clock.
So I will go ahead and put that nice.
I don't know where I'll put that guess for now.
I'll stick it in w.
I don't have a better place to put it.
Go.
This doesn't require an install.
Does it or does it run?
No, it doesn't.
So that's good.
So we'll just call that clock and I'll figure out where to put it
later, but now we can run the code.
So it looks like this is all code in here.
This is all of our code, I believe.
So if I just run clock on the code and I just do star.
There we go.
So yeah so four thousand lines of code right?
That if I mean I'm assuming that I'm reading that properly so that's
like really tiny.
I feel like
I don't know.
I just don't feel like that's very much code to keep in your head.
It seems pretty straightforward unless I'm missing it.
So yeah.
So there you go and if you add them all up, you know it's
it's what something like, you know, six thousand lines of code.
I know it's not very many lines of code.
A bit off-topic besides the bits that are obviously tacked.
On, would you consider the windows gooey?
A good API parts of it.
Seem pretty intuitive and clean and clear.
But I don't have much to compare it with.
So I don't get through that off topic because we've done win32.
Programming on the stream, a bunch.
So talking about that API is totally reasonable.
I guess, what I would say is win32, the C API for win32 isn't bad, but
it's not good.
Like the original win32 API is okay.
There's a lot of things that I wouldn't have done the way that they
did it but it's not horrid the stuff they've done since then is mostly
horrid like most of the newer stuff as it's gone.
Like if you actually were to program the windows API the way they want
you to today, it's an epic epic disaster.
So I think to really answer that question, you'd have to
Specifically talk about a particular part of the API and say you know
is this part good and then you could say about the pros and cons of it
because it really does.
It's very, very eerie.
Microsoft's, a giant company.
Write an API was not signed by one guy.
It's been designed by hundreds of people by committee now over many
years and it's in many different port parts.
And so it's really hard, you know, to take a particular piece and say,
you know, it's
Really hard without taking particular piece to say, good bad ugly.
Becker 929, I guess I should have asked how big it has to get for you
to start feeling overwhelmed.
Probably like a hundred times that size.
I would say I would I would expect to be at like four hundred thousand
lines before I'd start to be feeling like I had no idea it was going
on probably would be my guess.
I think 10 times the size would still be pretty easy to manage like
40,000 lines.
Doesn't sound like a lot.
Four hundred thousand lines might be pretty big.
I don't know I don't think we'd get there.
Programming like an hour a day, I don't think we'd probably get there.
So 40,000 lines might happen depending on our speed and sort of the
later the later times when I'm explaining less and typing more.
How did you decide on this order to build up the engine?
Was it Intuition or experience?
Well, again, I think
I've tried to kind of show how that goes as recently as I can.
Obviously, there's some degree of experience in there that you just
can't avoid, right?
And I'd be lying if I said that the experience isn't a huge part of
it.
But what I have tried to do, for the most part is show you how you can
sort of muddle through something like this.
By always taking the next
Logical step, right?
And that's what I've tried to do.
I haven't tried to make any giant leaps.
I've always said, let's try to do X and then we kind of work towards
that and we see what falls out of it.
And you'll note that like I started off, I just made a simple tilemap,
right.
And we sort of so how that was going to go and then I said, oh well
let's we want to be able to make it so that it can be infinitely, huge
well, not infinitely.
But very very large.
So we can't just use floats.
So how we going to do that?
And we did that and I was like well okay I don't really want these
things to have to be on tile boundaries so let's let's try getting rid
of that and I was like all right I do.
Like how this is going, let's try to make a system so that we can
actually make it so that we don't have to work on the on using the
weird positional stuff and I want to scale the number of entities up.
So we did that.
And we kept we've kept just doing like what's the next thing I'm going
to do.
Let's write some code that see how it goes.
And we've been letting the engine architecture emerge out of that,
which is the whole point of this first, you know, hundred days.
Let's say
Which is which each day maps to roughly an hour?
So 100 hours isn't much time to spend on a project, right?
100 hours.
If you work a 40-hour week, 100 hours is a little more than two weeks
of full-time work, right?
So spending 100 hours on figuring out, what your architecture should
be is cheap.
And so in this, in the scope of a whole project.
And so, the reason that I'm approaching it this way and encouraging
other people to approach it this way is because I think it's really
valuable to spend the time just writing the code, seeing how it works.
And then letting that,
Picture emerge, and so that when you actually go to do the final
component, like when we want to go do the final Collision sector, we
want to go do the final renderer when we want to do whatever, we're
not just designing in a vacuum, which is where bad designs come from.
Right instead, we're not even really designing at that point, we're
just programming because the design was already there.
It already already exposed itself in, you know, in by uh sort of
drilling at it.
It's sort of like sculpting, right?
We chiseled away and shows it away and shows it away.
And then we were left with something was like, yes, this is the piece.
Now we just have to go do the detail work, right?
And that's way better than trying to do it the other way around, where
you just like sculpt each part, totally separately and then bring them
together and hope that they form a sculpture and then they don't in
your, like, this piece doesn't fit.
And what are we gonna do now, get the glue out, right?
It's like a disaster.
And so, you know, I'm just kind of that's the way I've been doing
this.
And again, I do have a lot of experience, programming that is true,
but I don't have a lot of experience program, your 2D game.
Like it's not something I do.
I don't program to any games for a living.
Like I like this kind of game, like Zelda games, I've never written
one before, right?
That's not what I do.
And so it is true that I've experienced program.
It's not true.
They have a lot experience with certain aspects of this development
and so I've been trying to do those things.
Exactly, the way I would go and discover them if I were doing it in a
regular professional setting so that you can see how
I approached that problem and arrived at good Solutions because as
much as anything that's the most important thing to learn is
How to tackle a new problem and arrive at a good solution.
It takes hard work, it takes effort, but most of all, it takes the
right approach.
And I really do think that approach is exactly what we've been doing,
right?
The most obvious thing you can first pick a goal, right?
The most obvious code, see what it looks like.
What doesn't work?
Get a little bigger, get a little bigger, right?
Keep picking new goals and pushing that code outward.
And then it, you can sort of see the things start to form in there and
pull them out as they become obvious, rather than trying to
To guess ahead of time how to do everything, which in my experience
just does not lead anywhere, good?
Oftentimes.
No matter how much experience you have, because the only time that
that really works is if you've done exactly the same thing as you're
already doing, but most of the time, that's not that interesting.
Most time you want to be writing things that you've never written
before it.
You want to make new things that people haven't done, right?
And so that's how you do that.
Speaking of uml and diagrams.
You ever use class 1 schematics for code planning know, I'd never do
that.
That is not something I would recommend.
I feel like diagrams pretty much leave out the important parts of code
the complexity of code and so they tend to not be very useful.
I always say start with the code in an abstract upwards from it.
Do you need to be able to enumerate every possibility in order to use
a switch statement?
What if you want to make a system that can be extended?
Well, extended in what way is the question, right?
So, if you're talking about extended, as in people adding stuff to it,
well they just add to the case to switch statement, right?
That's not hard.
And you can even do that if you want to by making separate files like
you can use the pound include in there if you want for some reason,
but I wouldn't do that.
I just put in the switch statement.
If you're talking about you want things to be extensible outside of
changing the
Code.
Well, at that point you've got to have scripting languages or
something like that.
Anyway, right?
So because if people are loading code dynamically, you've got to have
something that allows that to actually work like a dll or something
like that.
And if that's the case, it's still not that big of a deal, right?
You can you can still do most of the same stuff as you would do with a
switch statement but unfortunately if you go that route you give up
kind of one nice thing which is the ability to have the Preamble post
amble stuff, be directly accessible by the things the switched.
Payment.
So, you lose one thing if you do that, but other than that, you can
still do a basic same way.
People just have sub switch statements, right?
They basically make their own switch statements, and you're calling
each of them, or whatever.
But I don't know, I think most of the time, if you're talking about
stuff that extensible in a game, you're talking about a switch having
Scripting language.
Because if you want players to be able to quickly and easily modify
stuff, they're probably not going to want to be using your C++ code or
whatever, right?
I don't know.
I mean, so, the answer that question is I can't really give a total
answer, unless, unless you can tell me a little more about what you
mean by extended, in the case of this type of code,
Why you switch statements instead of just big if else blocks?
Yeah, if else blocks are fine too.
Either way, I you switch tables because they're less typing.
Will the way in which collisions are handled the order independent?
Mmm.
I don't know yet, that's a good question and I don't know I suspect
probably not because I don't know that we have anything in the game, I
don't know that that has Elda game tends to have a lot of reasons why
order independent Collision is important.
So I guess what I would say to that is probably not, unless we find
some reason, why it should be.
And maybe as we get through the further along in the game, we will
find a good reason why we have to make sure that it's order
independent.
And then we would, but otherwise, I don't think we would introduce
that complexity unless I had a reason why I thought we could use it
for something.
Is it better to debug as you go or towards the end of a programming
cycle?
So I would say that personally, I don't think there should ever be
bugs in the code that you know about, right?
like,
For the most part I always try to debug a bug that I see when I see
it, I don't leave bugs in the code unless it's a case of like, oh the
as the case of a bug in the sense that I know that there's a big thing
that needs to get implemented in order to fix some problematic
behavior.
And I don't have time to do that right now because I have other things
I got to do and this is like a several day tasks or something.
But you know we've done the stream before.
It's like oh I don't like the way this is working but I can't do it
right now.
So will you know kind of put it off a little bit.
But in terms of bugs, like if it's just a bug like I don't know what's
going on.
There's something broken the code.
I always like always fix that, right?
Right away.
Like when you see it, the instant you see, it should be when you fix
it.
That's the way I look at it.
And the reason that I do things that way is because I feel like
I feel like, first of all, it makes it easier to write whatever code
you were going to write.
Because now, you don't have to worry about the fact that you've got a
bug in there and who knows what the bug is from, and maybe, whatever
is causing that bug would also cause you problems on whatever you were
going to write.
So it might, it make compound, the difficulty of writing, whatever it
is, that you're going to write.
And similarly, I think it may lead to less buggy code at the end
because if you debug all bugs, when you find them, there's no
Chance that whatever you're doing is going to mask some bug that you
did see.
And now won't see later because you change something.
And now whatever the bug was that was exposed has been hidden, right?
So if you are ever fortunate enough to be able to find a bug that you
can reproduce when you are coding, you should bug it at that time.
I think that seems to be the best way to go about it.
My opinion.
Actually want to pass dash dash.
No three.
Otherwise it is lying about the number of lines.
It is dumb.
Dash dash.
No 3.
Woahhh.
What is dash dash no.3.
That does not seem to be understood at the moment.
You will have to John.
You'll have to send me how to use this thing because I don't, there's
dash dash three.
But not dash dash.
No 3.
Oh wait.
Oh it's just because I didn't pass.
There we go.
Okay, sorry, I'm I'm dumb.
That's the same.
Isn't that the same?
Is that the same thing?
That's the same.
That looks the same to me.
Did it change something?
I don't know but if you send me an email and let me know I'll run it
differently.
I do.
Yeah.
I've obviously never used it before to use your set it so I don't
know.
Will the game have multiplayer and our Co-op so we're allowing
multiple player-controlled entities in the engine.
So in that sense it allows multiplayer but we just don't know the game
design.
I don't really know if will support it, so it will.
The engine will support it but I don't.
A game design will support it if that makes sense.
So we're going to allow for the entire duration of development,
multiple players to play, but the game design may not be such that
that actually works.
In terms of when we release the game, that may be turned off for the
release because it may just not be a fun.
There may not be a way to really play it with multiple players.
That doesn't break the game.
So we want to support it in the engine just so we can show how to make
sure that you don't tie things to just the concept of one player.
Exactly.
But I don't, I don't know if that will actually be in there at the
final game.
All right, I think we have we are out of time.
We have run out of time so I'm going to go ahead and close things up.
Assuming that we don't know.
Maybe did we run clock correctly?
I don't know if you're in clock correctly or not, but 4090 to is
actually a power of two, so I feel like that's a good number of lines
to go out on your right, that it did change slightly, right?
So, that's kind of weird, and some sense.
Yeah, that is kind of weird, kind of weird.
And I felt like that number was different before.
What's the deal here?
I'm getting a little weirded out, John
How come it said, 69th?
Oh, that's the lines per second.
Okay, that's just its speed.
That's just want to let you know how fast it is with its line
counting, okay?
So that's has no bearing on anything.
All right, so that's that's the same number.
So, if I think the no.3 was not necessary for whatever we were doing,
it seems like it part did the same thing, but either way,
All right, so let's go ahead and wind things up here.
Thank everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure programming with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with the source
code, you can do that by pre-ordering the game.
You could do that on handmade hero dot-org.
If you get the little pre-order button, it comes with the source code.
And every night I upload the new source code that we do on the stream
so you can download it and follow along.
Also, if you want to support the video series, we do have a patreon.
You could subscribe to.
If you are trying to catch up on old episodes or ask questions about
things that you saw in tonight's program, we do have a news and form
so you can go to with a lot of great research on it.
And also has ports that community members have done to Mac and Linux
and that sort of thing already.
So even though we haven't gotten to those ports on the stream, if you
are trying to follow along on a Mac or on a Linux machine, that's a
good place to do it.
There's also now people who ported to IOS and Android as well,
although I don't know how far along those ports are but they're at
least nominally working.
So that's kind of cool too.
So check that out.
And finally we do have a tweet bot.
If you do want to know what the schedule is, you can subscribe to that
tweet but or follow the feet Bott or whatever it is and it will treat
the schedule that you and let you know when we are here tomorrow
night.
We will be back at 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time, same time as tonight.
So if
Would like to come back and join us for that.
I guess tomorrow we will start looking at how to do well we have that
to do that we put in there just tonight and then we also have looking
at the Collision detection and how we want to sort of do that.
So we can start actually having some more energy interactions like
hitting people and taking damage that sort of stuff.
So I hope you'll come back and join me for that and until then have a
good Wednesday and I will see you tomorrow.