I'm okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live from scratch here on
Twitch using nothing.
No libraries.
No engines.
We write everything ourselves both as an educational process and just
because it's fun.
Honestly, it's, it's kind of fun to get in there and see how
everything works.
And it's, it's really kind of very gratifying to know that you had
kind of have like, a complete complete control over, absolutely
everything that's going on.
So that's why I like to do it and it seems like we've been actually
making really good progress here.
We're at the point where we've got a little little hero running around
the screen, and we're kind of at the point where we're starting to
learn like, equations of motion.
We're starting to learn how to move the guy properly, how to react to
things in the environment.
And yesterday, we stopped right at the point where we needed to kind
of think about how to do, how we want to do handling of running up
against edges and stuff properly.
And so I'd like to go ahead and Dive, Right.
Into that today, but before I do, I will mention, of course that if
you have pre-ordered the game on handmade here at a torque and would
like to follow along with the source code.
Remember, we are on day 45.
So you will get a link in your email, go to that link.
You can download the source code ZIP.
And inside that Zip There Will Be source code for every single day.
And so you want to do day 44 unzip that because that's what I'm
starting with here on day 45, so you'll be right where I am if you
start there, okay, so let's take a look at what's going on at the
moment.
So where we left off?
We had just kind of started playing with the equations of motion.
I showed everyone how to do both types of sort of, handling of when
somebody runs into something.
We did a bounce version where the guy would kind of bounce off of it
and also a deadening version where he just stops.
So, and what we wanted to do, of course, is it doesn't feel very good
if he's just stops and sticks.
So we want to do is have them keep moving along the edges when you
kind of grind against them, because that's the standard thing to do in
games is that, you know,
It doesn't feel good.
If you just stick against a wall, you want to kind of Glide against
the wall.
So that you keep moving, with, whatever downward velocity.
You should have had when you come against like a vertical wall, and
it's only the horizontal velocity that gets eaten.
But we have a sticking problem that I explained yesterday.
And that, is that we're not, we haven't written our Loop properly.
I'm sorry.
It's not even a loop.
We haven't written our game update for the character in a useful way.
And so, actually, what happens.
Is we get we get a sticking problem and the sticking problem that we
get is that if you imagine that, this is the wall, right here is the
wall and the hero is coming towards the wall.
And what, the way that we wrote our, our quick stuff when we were kind
of just testing our tile map code out.
We wrote in some little Quick Test code to collide the guy against the
tile map.
But it's not very sophisticated yet.
And so all it was doing, is it moves the guy to the new location looks
to see whether or not he could exist.
Are like is he in a wall or not?
And if he's not it?
Epps the movie, if it's not, if he can't stand there, then it denies
the move completely and it means the guy will just stay where he is on
that frame, which leads to a nasty sticky problem.
Sticking problem, which is, first of all, you lose at least one frame
when that happens, but if you got into a situation where the guy was
right up against the wall and then when we're are we correct our
velocity and then the acceleration for a frame, puts it back inside
the wall.
Again, he could just stick there indefinitely and it's kind of hard to
get that to happen.
Floating Point Wise, It's a more of a rare case, but you can see that
it does happen.
Occasionally.
Did you see that stick?
You can kind of see how it'd be like right there.
So it definitely can happen.
It's just not as common as maybe I would have thought it would be
possibly a little more common than it actually is.
But it's not as common, but it still happens.
Right?
And so it's not, it's not something that we want our final code to
have.
And so, since the whole point of what we've been doing, these past few
weeks, in addition to, of course, learning math and learning about
sort of the stuff that we need to do, is, we've been trying to come up
with all the things that we need our game engine to do.
Rest and obviously this is one big area of the game engine that we
want to work really well, which is how the player movement is handled,
how the Collision detection is handled.
And so, it's important for us to think a little bit about how we want
to handle this.
Now, there's two ways that we could handle this, but I kind of alluded
to yesterday.
There's probably more than two, but at least cover 21 is kind of the
standard way of handling it.
And the other is sort of the way that I'm not sure if anyone does it
this way, but it was a way that I
I did it on the witness recently.
And which I think is pretty interesting.
I'm just not sure if it can work in the larger scheme of this game.
And so I'm not sure if we want to do it long term, but I was going to
mention anyway, so typically what games will do and this this this is
gets into another problem that we had.
So well, we didn't really have the problem but we would potentially
had a problem.
Which is that if you think about what happens in this kind of a seam,
which is like check a new location.
Station and then move there.
If it's free.
You get into a situation where theoretically and we didn't ever
construct any cases that could really do this.
But theoretically, if you had a very thin wall, right?
You could teleport through the wall because if this is the region that
you can't stand, but you could stand out here, then it's only checking
to see if the final location is okay, for the guy to stand that.
And we know that we're never checking in this whole distance.
That he moves, right?
And so, that's also another problem that we are not dealing with that.
We might want to deal with in the final version of the game.
Right?
So it's something to consider when we're thinking about how we want
our Collision detection.
Work is whether we're worried about that, right?
And since our goal here is to create a professional quality game.
I feel like we should handle that even though we may never actually
have any maps that actually have this problem.
I think it's it's the right thing to do to show how you would handle
it properly.
So anyway, let's suppose I'm back to my Standard wall case.
So, a typical way that game might solve this problem is, if we have
this movement, right?
Then the first thing we would do is we write a collision detection
routine that actually will check to see when collisions occur, rather
than just whether they occur, right.
So rather than taking a new position, which is here, right?
This is our P Prime.
This is our P.
This is our hoops.
This is our old position.
This is our new position rather than just checking P Prime.
It will actually check essential essentially, an extruded volume.
It will it will test this whole volume here.
And since we're in 2D it's more of an area than a volume.
But you know what?
I mean, it will test that against everything in the world as sort of
like a geometric operation and it will find even if there was a thin
wall and there's nothing on this side.
It will find that intersection in the middle, right?
And more to the point for are sticking problem.
It will find the place where the intersection first occurs.
It'll say,
So, okay.
This is the point at which he hits the wall.
And so when you do that, you then have the ability to place the guy at
the location where he was going to hit the wall, right?
Instead of only having the choice between the new position and the old
position.
We now generate a third position which actually becomes the P Prime
and we throw that one away and say here is the place where he actually
would have ended up.
Right.
But
Doing that is still technically going to cause sticking problems.
In two ways.
One.
We haven't talked about what we would do with the velocity problem
yet.
And the other is that we would when we do that step.
We now have thrown away a bunch of the players actual momentum, right?
Because the player actually probably should have ended up here because
they still had enough downward momentum to get all the way there.
So the only thing we really wanted to throw away.
Was this this momentum?
That was going
To the wall, right?
So we want to basically move the player to hear as the movement not to
hear.
So often times, what they'll do is they'll resolve these things in
sort of a loop like I saying before, where they'll move the player and
then they'll they'll take whatever the remaining, they'll correct the
velocity just like we were doing yesterday.
They'll take whatever remaining time step there was because you know
how much time it took to get here, right?
You know how much of the time step it took to move you?
There.
You'll take how much time it was and then you'll try to move them.
In the resulting velocity direction that's been corrected for the wall
to see if you can do that.
Right?
And you can see that this is kind of ugly because it's, this is
essentially a search in t, you might say, it is a iterative loop.
That's that that is basically searching through time for answers.
It's
Your time, it's doing some part of the delta T here.
So, you know, it's some fraction of this.
It's one over a which is some fraction of that time step.
It's using.
And then it's trying to use one over, basically the rest of it when
you know this kind of thing.
It's using the rest of it to move here.
And this just gets kind of messy because searches in t, are very
difficult to Bound in any real way.
Because what if I had a very complex sort of
All situation at the end here, right?
And this is kind of exaggerated.
But just to sort of show you what I mean by the problems, you know,
what exactly should be happening when he goes against here, right?
Am I going to do this thing?
Where I actually take tons of time steps, tons of little portions of
the time step and have to do like eight resolutions of my Collision
Loop to move.
The guy all down through there, you know, and is that really a good
use of time?
Is that the way that I want?
My inner loop there to be running?
And it's, it's unbounded in some sense.
Right?
Like, I don't even have any idea how many of these I would have to do
in order to actually get the guy to resolve this position.
And I feel like, you know, you could imagine this being the case with
a wall that was curved.
Like let's say I wanted to do a rounded wall like this.
Well, if I have a rounded wall and I'm pushing against the wall like
this, you could imagine this being the very worst case, where it keeps
having to correct that velocity.
And it's almost like
It's almost like the number of iterations goes to Infinity, because I
keep having to move a little bit down, a little bit, down, a little
bit, down a little bit down.
So the when I correct, because remember, the way we correct, as we
look at the that normal to the wall, and we correct this way, so we
correct it.
So he's only moving lateral to the wall.
But lateral to the wall in a curved wall, will constantly still be
pushing you into the wall.
Right?
So there's all these problems with this approach and that was really
what led me to look for a better solution then.
I'd seen presented before when I was working on the witness and I'll
tell you briefly right now, the solution that I came up with which I
really like and it works fantastic on the witness.
I just don't know if it's appropriate for an action game.
So I'll go and I'll sort of say what it is.
So what I decided to do was say well search in tea.
Is is not good.
Let's not do certainty.
Certainty is unbounded and unpredictable and doesn't work very well
for a lot of scenarios.
And what a lot of games do is they just cheese out and either just do
some number of Loops or they do some cheesy Stuff where they kind of
like don't handle a bunch of those cases like you if you grind into a
curve.
Well, you just do something awful.
So these are just, you know, search and T is just is just busted.
It was, my was my official opinion.
So, what I decided to do was, let's turn
Turn a search and key into a search in key, right?
So instead of searching in time, right, instead of searching in time.
Let's search in.
Mission and see if we can find a position that will work because the
search in position is much more easily bounded and much more easily
understood, right?
So what I do in the witness is I think about whatever I have in terms
of geometry for the Collision.
So let's say I've got this sort of a thing here.
Basically, what I have is, I have, you know, a grid that that is used,
that is tessellated out.
For a bunch of reasons that would be clearer if we were actually in
talking about the witness, but basically, like it's got a tessellated
out thing.
That's very fine, resolution.
That sort of says exactly what the you know what the Collision
geometry looks at like at any given point and it knows, you know,
basically that you can't be in here like that but at you can't be in
here, right?
And so what I do is when somebody is moving in this space, what I
Is I go back to the old scheme which is just, let's just take the
location of the guy that he would be at.
And then what I say is, let's search in position because I know that,
however, long this is, I can basically make a rectangle around,
however, long the span is that he moved in that time.
Let's just search in the grid for the closest point to where ever, he
would have ended up, right?
So that just
Is it into a nice bounded search?
Where I know?
I'm just searching a predetermined number of cells and in each cell.
I just look, what is the closest point in this polygon to this
destination point and that always gives you a 100% perfect.
100% predictable result for that metric, right?
It's really really nice and it's buttery smooth.
You never get caught on little weird Edge artifacts and it even has
the ability to do something that I consider beneficial in the witness,
but that I wouldn't necessarily consider.
Official in this game.
I'm not sure that's why I'm a little hesitant about it.
But basically it has the ability to Glide over transient errors,
right?
So if you have a wall that looks like this because of some weird
computational geometry stuff like the artists, you know, had some
walkway.
That was kind of sticking in there and errant way and you got this
sort of thing and I'm trying to grind along this wall.
Well, if you are actually grinding along this wall in a normal engine,
when you got here, you'd stick on this.
This tiny little microscopic bump that, you may not even really be
able to see, but it's in the Collision geometry, right?
You'd stick and it feels crappy, right?
But in this scheme because what it's doing is doing that search.
It finds the fact that you could have moved around that and allows you
to Tunnel through things like that, if you could have walked to them,
right?
So it's buttery smooth on edges, way better than anything else I've
ever seen.
And it was really, really good when I, when I
Used when I switch to using this system.
And so, so I was pretty psyched about that and it feels awesome to do.
So, search and P is actually way better than search and T4 Collision
detection.
I don't know if anyone's ever actually, I don't know.
If I'm the first person to have done that I assume not because,
usually, anytime you do something, someone's done it before.
You just haven't heard about it.
So, I don't know if there's more write-ups about that somewhere, but
that's a pretty I mean, I think that was a pretty complete explanation
in terms of just what you would need to do to write it.
So really, this is probably, this is what I would like to do, if we
could do it.
I'm just not sure how appropriate that is, for an action game because
producing the searchable set is actually a relatively hard problem,
right?
You have to be able to search your geometry and I don't know if we've
got lots of things that are moving around and whatever.
I don't know how easy it would be to really produce that searchable
set.
Very, very easily.
Because remember, we have to
You know, like let's say we had something where, you know, this is
what a cell would look like, because there's a guy, you know, a guy
with cylindrical Collision or something who's in there and we want to
know what the closest point is.
It means you have to know how to do closest point on something that
looks like that, right?
And you can do stuff where you kind of tessellate it out and don't
exactly do it that way.
But point being, it's not it's a system.
That's that's much easier to implement when you're talking about a
world that looks like the
Switch everywhere.
Everything is stationary and known versus something.
In an action game where there's lots of, like, small things moving
around in that sort of stuff.
It's unclear necessarily how you turn things into a search in P
problem in an efficient way, right?
Okay.
So that is basically the Dilemma that I face now is this is what I
pretty much know to be a better way to write things.
But I've never I since I only just came up with it on the witness.
I haven't had any experience trying to do it in action game.
I don't know if we would struggle to make it work.
Well, in terms of producing the search and so this is the way that's
kind of a little more tried and true.
And I really don't know which one we should do for our current setup,
where we have a tile map.
And the tile map is actually definitive because right now, we haven't
done any of the other stuff where we've got guys, moving around and we
haven't done any of this stuff, where we populate, the tile map with
Collision geometry and then stop colliding with the tile map and
collide with the actual things are in the tile map or things like
that.
We haven't done any of that stuff searching P would be trivial for us
to implement right now and would definitely be the right way to go.
But that doesn't mean that it would be the correct way to go.
You know, at the end.
So I don't know what to do.
I really don't.
It's a very hard question since I believe this to be the superior
method in general.
My inclination is for us to just do this and say will struggle with it
a little bit.
We start to do the more complex stuff, but maybe that's just what we
should do, and it should be a little bit of an exploration.
And so we'll start with this as the way we do things.
And then, as we see how it goes out, if we need to turn to something
like this, we can.
But at least this, I believe, is personally, I think the more stable
way to do it.
So really all we would need to do to implement that in our current
system, right?
Because our current systems of tilemap.
It's totally rectilinear and
We haven't gotten to the point where we have more complicated
Collision geometry in there.
So in a tile map, if you were actually doing Collision detection on
tilemap, then there's no question that you would do it this way
because it's really simple.
All we have to do is take the guy and his new position.
Right?
All we do is we say we've got the guy, we've got his new position and
all we really need to do is like make some conservative boundary
around that.
So we just make some rectangle around that and say what are all the
tiles that are touched by this rectangle, right?
And so in this case, it would be
You know, these tiles here, right?
Like that, then what we do is say, all right, for each, one of those
tiles.
We just Loop through the tiles and like a for Loop straightaway and we
say for each one of those tiles.
Right.
We just need to kind of go watch.
I guess you wouldn't do for never mind.
That's, that's wrong.
We then do a flood fill.
We say, for this tile, which of the tiles, you know, could I actually
get to like, which of these tiles can I get to write?
So can I get to this one?
If so add it to the set?
Can I get to this one?
Add it to the set?
Okay, get to this one, add it to the set.
Right?
I get to this one, add it to the set.
So the ones that I can walk to add to the set, right?
Because you only want to get to ones that you actually could get to.
So, you need to know that there was a path to
I'm from your current location.
So you basically flood fill out words and you don't have to flood,
fill past whatever you set that boundary to write.
Once we've done that.
We then check all of the tiles that we actually picked up there.
All those towels that we actually picked up.
We then say, okay, for that tile, is it solid?
If it's solid, we don't consider it because you can't stand there.
If it's empty.
Then we say, is the point that we're trying to stand in the new point.
Is it in there?
If it's inside there?
Then that's the point.
We can move there.
Just go right and we're done.
If it's not, we say, Okay along the edges of that guy.
Where is the closest point, right on each of the edges?
Where is the closest point to the to this point?
Right?
And that handles the case where you're actually standing right on the
edge, right?
And we produce that point and say, okay, then, that's the closest
point for me.
We do that for all of the tiles and for whichever tile at the end has
the
A point that produced the point that is the closest to the one that we
wanted.
That's the move that we accept.
That's it.
So it's really, really, really pretty basic if that makes sense.
All right.
So that's it.
Yeah, I guess that's, that's really the entirety of the algorithm for
a tile map.
It's really pretty straightforward.
And so yeah, we can just go ahead and do that and we don't even have
to really do the flood fill.
If we don't want to at this particular point in time because we have
Simply Connected spaces.
We could just do it without doing the flood fill, but the reason to do
the flood fill is just that well like, you know,
Let's say.
Let's say that I've got my guy, right?
And and I want to move him.
Oh, there's one more thing.
I.
Yeah.
Okay.
There's one more thing that I do have to actually talk about.
But that makes this actually harder, and it actually makes makes
everything.
That's one thing.
I should talk about, has nothing to do with with, with this scheme.
But the reason for the flood fill is, let's say that there was a wall
here and a wall here.
Then, technically, like we're not supposed to be able to move through
that.
Little like, that little part in the corner.
So if you just checked each of these,
Tiles without actually doing the flood.
Fill to see where you could go.
You would think that you could just move directly to their right, but
you don't want to do that, because there's no way to actually get to
that Square from here.
And so that's why you do the conductivity thing.
To make sure that you actually could walk to that square before you
accept any points that are in it.
So, here's the problem that's talking about.
Are they thinking of?
So the other problem that we have with any Collision scheme is
currently, we don't really have an answer for what we're doing about
the fact that the guy is not a single point, right?
So any Collision scheme that we start to work with has an extra
problem to deal with, right, which is that whatever it's doing.
It has to deal with the fact that the guy is like a fatty, right?
The guy is like, you know, he's larger than a point, you know, right.
He's
How do I raise my?
There it is?
We were checking.
Basically, this line is what we were saying was the guy.
But eventually we probably wanted to be like more of like a like a
circle.
Anyway, like sort of this, this region that I'm kind of D marketing
here would be his Collision region, but he would bump into things.
And so right now he's infinitely thin and why, but he's thick in X
which means it's easy for him to fit through doors this way, but
harder for him to fit through doors, the other way, right?
I'm like, if I go, let's find a door.
Yeah.
So if I go through this
Door.
It's harder for me because I can always hit.
I can hit an edge like that.
And so that was just, I mean, we haven't really done any thinking
about any of this stuff.
But that was what we had sort of done.
It's made it so that he wouldn't, you know, clip into things.
So turning him into a point is another problem.
And the reason that that we would want to turn him into a point.
The reason that we'd want to think about him as
Point.
Instead of, as a sort of a circle is it's much harder to closer to
check with the circle.
For example, if I have a wall, you know, and I want to know if the guy
hits the wall, if he's a point, right?
Then I'm just talking about checking a line segment against another
line segment.
Right?
So I'm basically checking for the intersection of two line segments,
which doesn't sound like a very hard problem.
Right?
But if he's a circle now, I have to check an extruded Circle, right?
Versus a line segment, which is
definitely a more, you know, a more serious problem that you would
have to solve, right?
So in in the first scheme, if for search and T, this is definitely a
problem, right?
Definitely, definitely a problem because now you have to have a more
serious Collision routine there and and you know, that's that's a bit
rough.
So similarly in our scheme that I was proposing we do which is
searched P for search and P.
It also is a problem just in
Different way.
And the way that it is a problem is that if my guy has volume again,
right?
If he has an area then that routine where I check for the closest
point is a little harder as well right now.
It doesn't happen to actually be harder in in just this one isolated
case.
Meaning the thing that we're going to implement today.
It's actually pretty easy.
The reason it's pretty easy is because if the guy is just a circle or
an ellipse or whatever, then all we really have to do is
Is when we're considering the rectangle that he could be in for,
finding the closest point, instead of using the whole rectangle.
We just look to see if the if the square on a side of the rectangle is
filled.
And if it is we just assume we just treat the rectangle as if it was
the the ellipses long radius in that direction away from the filled
area, right?
Like that.
And again, this is just another way that search in P is superior to
the other method is like, this is way easier than trying.
To do that, continuous Collision detection, get it handles, the Kill,
The Continuous case just fine.
You will never tunnel through anything as long as you do, that flood
fill pattern.
So it is a little more complicated than I originally said, but only
slightly when we do it this way, but you can see when we go forward,
why it will complicate matters to have him be a circle because let's
say that we had some arbitrary Collision geometry, right?
That we were colliding against and now the guy is a circle.
Well, doing the closest point figuring out what the closest point in
the walks pay is
Is space is 2.
Here is definitely harder.
Now, that we have to consider like this sort of fact that he role.
He, you know, his, his closest point region to search is like this
thing that looks like that and we have to determine that.
Like you can see this is really ugly now like how to do that.
So if he was just a point we would just search along the edge of the
Collision boundaries.
Any time we hit them, that's a lot easier than trying to figure out
how far away we would have to be for our circled fit.
It's not even a simple as just thinking.
Oh, I'll take a point and
It out because you never know, there could be a sharp Bend.
We're moving it out from there actually, still makes you collide with
some other piece here.
So it's it's definitely something to think about.
This is also where Mankowski the Mankowski shape algebra stuff comes
in potentially which we might use when we go to stuff.
That's more complicated like this, but for purposes of spec'ing out
our engine, this would be fine.
Because if we say that we want to go a certain P at least at the
beginning then that at least gives us a good.
Way to find what our engine needs to do, which is the whole point of
all of our Explorations now, which is that we just all we know.
All we need it to do is be able to give us back with a p and a p
Prime.
Give us back the closest P that we could have gotten to from there in
the connected space.
That's a very easily defined problem.
It's very clean.
The API is obvious.
So all of that actually does exactly what we needed to do for now,
which is tell us what we, what the the sort of API is to our engine
and that will
Was to know exactly what problems are engine.
Does have to solve when we write it.
Okay, so hopefully everyone is pretty clear on that.
So, how do we write that?
Because really that's just a bunch of code, right?
That's a there's not much math involved.
They're really in terms of what's going on.
So alright.
Let's write it and let's see what's going on here.
So right now, what we're doing is we have this is tile empty or
whatever.
It is that we're not get tile is tile map point and be right.
This is how we're doing it.
This is our routine.
And so what I'd like to do now is is sort of totally change the nature
of what we're doing here.
I'd like to basically say all the stuff that we were doing before this
stuff is over.
It's done, right?
It's not it's not the case anymore.
We're going to, we're going to get rid of all of this stuff that we
used to be doing like that.
And honestly, this, this guy could have been outside here before.
Anyway, because this is always true that are on same tile.
All we really need to do is say that this is an old player P, right?
And a new player P kind of a thing.
So, what I'm going to do here before actually, before I have zero
doubt, actually, let me just actually change it to do that.
So that our post our post execute stuff.
Is it still going to work properly?
So basically I want to know if he's on the same tile.
So I'm going to set old player pee.
When we first come in here, right?
I'm going to set old player P to be equal to the position that he
started at.
So when we very first, when we come right in here, just to begin with,
I'm going to set the old player P, right old player, P equal to game
that game State.
Remember, we've got his player Peak here.
I'm going to set it to equal to that player P, right?
And actually, you know what, I'm going to do that, even outside.
Side here, really?
Because this is this is the part that updates where the player is and
then the part that responds to that.
Let's just do that entirely outside, right?
Because all of this stuff has nothing to do with that, right?
That's all stuff that can happen up here.
Right?
So what we want to do is say, if the old player P and his and his new
location, right?
What I want to do now is get rid of that, that use of new player P at.
All, right.
I want to, I want to directly operate on the, on the game on the game,
State version of the player.
Right?
And so, let's compile, that just make sure that that we can do that.
So, this is time that position.
And let's take a look here.
What is this saying to diff multiple?
Oh, do I have another function called?
If I do?
Oh, and that happens to be the same.
That happens to be the same dip.
So really all I need to do here is just update that if that's pretty
funny.
Yeah, because that's, that's funny.
Well, you know, what do you do?
All right.
So let me just verify that.
I've still got the this guy working properly.
So off we go and it looks okay.
You can still go up and down the stairs.
Still runs into walls as he should, so we're all good there.
All right, oops, and so, I don't know, like, you know, this is
starting to get to the point where we might, this is starting getting.
This is starting to get to the point where we could think about
starting to pull it out to.
You can sort of see it breaking out into some obvious pieces.
Like those parts that I just moved out there.
You can kind of see that there's two separate, you know, logical
things that's happening right?
There's this update that happens after the players done.
The kind of handles a bunch of stuff.
And so this may be a good thing for us to move out now because that's
going to be kind of this is this is basically a update function that
updates the the sort of the state of the game based on where the
player moved in and the camera, we might want to consider moving that
out to a new function.
I'm not sure if we do yet hard to say exactly what that's going to be.
But like I'm going to put a note in here update camera.
And and player low z based on last movement, right?
And then here we'll get render.
So I'm just going to start to divide these up and we'll consider at
some point.
Whether we want to break that out because we're getting closer to the
point where it's where it looks like, we can start to see, you know,
real real chunks that happen.
And by the way, this is a good point to mention this.
Somebody was saying in the on the forums,
A while back that they felt like the code was too messy.
And again, I really want to stress the fact that I don't really want
to try to tell people that the way that they code is wrong because,
you know, I feel like that just leads to a lot of pedantic arguments
that aren't particularly instructive.
But what I can say, is nobody in my mind.
Nobody should be
This code is messy.
This code is exactly what it should be.
It's code that we are writing to figure out how we want to structure
our program.
And if you're spending time right now, thinking about how to make this
code, not messy, whatever that means to you, then essentially, what
you're doing is you're wasting time, right?
You're spending time.
That should have been spent thinking about the problem, thinking about
the code and the end State, the end goal of your program is not to
have can encode.
It's to have good working code, cleanliness has nothing to do with
those things.
If you have the ugliest code in the world that someone would look at
and call very messy.
But it has no bugs and runs great then it didn't matter.
Right.
And so, to the point that we care about how clean code is, we only
care about that as insofar as it has an effect on our end product.
And what we know right now is what we're trying to do is just Define
the structure of the code.
So none of this code will ship in the game or if it
Does.
It's because it got pulled out and like, changed around a little and,
you know, put in its proper place.
And so we know that it will clean up over time as we know what it
should be but prematurely cleaning it.
It's actually worse than just wasting time.
It may lead us down wrong paths, and, and end us to end up having us
to making us have to do gyrations to make stuff work together because
we've segregated it in a bad way too early on.
And so I really want to stress that fact.
That like if you if, if the way you look at code,
Code, is that you think of it as messy or clean?
That is a very bad habit in my opinion.
And so all I can really do is say a strenuously as possible.
Stop thinking that way instead.
Think about the problem you're trying to solve when you are done and
to your satisfaction solving that problem in however, messy away.
As you can.
Then that is the time to start thinking about cleanliness of code.
And what we mean, when we say cleanliness of code, there is, can I
find the bugs in it?
Easily?
Is it easy to read and understand?
Is it easy for me to reuse in the places that I need to reuse it?
Those sorts of things and never some set of prescribed things that
somebody said, was clean code, because there is no such set.
There is no, there is no set of rules that tells you whether a
particular set of code is clean based on.
What the code looks like?
It's only based on what the usage looks like and what the debugging
process looks like that.
Actually tells you whether a piece of code is clean or not.
And I really can't stress that enough.
It's a big difference between good programmers and bad programmers is
whether they understand this, right?
And that's like I said, it's my opinion.
Nobody has perfect metrics for code.
So we don't know who's right about those things.
But all I can tell you is I'm 30 years.
I've never seen something truer than what I just said.
All right.
So moving on from there, from that little Public Service Announcement.
What I want to talk about now, right?
Is, is sort of
Vamping.
What we're doing here to something much simpler and much better.
Right?
So we still have our physics stuff up here.
So, this is Computing, the player velocity.
Right?
And what we want to do now is right here.
We want to sort of, if zero this out and say the old way that we were
doing stuff, that's not going to happen anymore.
That's done.
Right?
That's over.
And we're going to do something else, that's going to be better.
And I'm leaving that in for now, just because we might want to switch
to it, to see what's going on, right?
So, that's all, that's all good.
All right.
And then what I want to do is say okay, let's go ahead and say, let's
do that thing that I was talking about before.
And for now, we'll just do it without any concern.
For anything will do will do it in the worst possible way and then
we'll refine it a little bit.
So I'm just going to go ahead and do a for I loop around basically, in
that sort of a region where the player is and where the end where his
destination.
Some point is so we're going to basically say, I'm still gonna, I'm
still gonna keep this part for now of the physics, right?
So we produce that new player P.
I'm going to keep that and I guess we want to do this.
So but the rest of this stuff where we do all the Collision texturing,
the testing.
I'm going to, I'm not going to use, right.
So what I want to do now is I want to basically Loop over the search
region in tile space, right?
So I want to be able to go
Go over each individual tile there in X and Y.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that and we'll take a look at handmade
tile H here.
I'm going to go ahead and do that and say that, you know.
Ben tile x max tilak's like so.
AB style X like that.
And I think so.
There is one kind of nasty thing about this.
This is, this is kind of
yeah.
This is one of those things that's like it's unclear, whether we
should change it going forwards and I thought about it many times on
the screen when we've been doing stuff.
Basically, the unsigned versus signed integer thing.
So there's a nasty thing here that happens where we're right on the
edge of a tile.
Where, let's say that we were, let's here's the let me, let me just,
I'll get this out there since I've thought about it multiple times,
but I've never mentioned on the stream.
I'll just say it here.
So, let's say we happen to be at tile 0 0.
Right.
So this next child here is, you know, tile for billion because we
wrapped around, right?
If I want to do a for, I Loop over these tiles.
There is really it's hard to write that Loop cleanly.
If that makes sense because you can't do a less than.
So you have to kind of do an equals 2.
Which maybe is okay, we're starting knot equals 2.
Because if you think about it, when you go back here and I start
looping over this guy.
When I Loop over him, we're going to see that he's already greater
than the stopping tile, which is the one that we were looking at over
here because of that wrap around of the unsigned integer.
So, I don't know.
Like, I'm just going to go ahead and keep on with the current way that
we're doing things.
And see, I thought about a couple times but basically we have to do
this.
Like that kind of we always have to do a not equal to one past the Mac
style because that's the only thing that will actually work.
When we do this Loop.
We can't ever really check for Less stands, even though that's the
word easier, natural way to think about doing the loop.
Usually, for me, we have to do these, not equal to S because we might
be right on that boundary, where we're we're wrapping around.
That makes sense.
If we, we don't have to do that.
We don't ever have to let the world wrap around if we don't want to.
But I'm saying if we wanted to actually make the
Correct, so that you could have a full giant 4 billion Loop.
For some reason for a brilliant.
I'll Loop if you really just wanted to get something to think about,
right.
So anyway, if We're looping over here, then what I need to do inside
each of these ones is just figure out whether what the closest I'll
would be.
So the first thing I need to do is I need to look up that tile, right?
So I want to say, what's the tile value in the in that area?
Right?
And so, I believe we have a way of doing that, just flat out which I
do and, and so, I can pass these guys in there and get what the tile
value is.
So here is the tile value.
Look at that tile value and say if tiled.
Oops, if tile value is empty, right?
I believe it's a this one is are blocking thing.
Let me make sure yeah, like that.
And for now, I guess maybe since I've got enough of it, I'll also do a
thing that is tile value empty.
So write something like this.
That makes sense just so I can reuse that check get style value, empty
value.
So on.
That way I don't have to keep thinking about it.
And again, we're going to replace this stuff anyway, because we're
going to have to decide much later on.
Probably, after we do the renderer and we start thinking about what's
actually in a given game tile, will have a representation for the game
towel for right now.
We just have some numbers.
We throw in there for no apparent reason just so we can have some
variety and think about what's actually in the tile, right?
But that way we can say empty equals is tiled value, empty.
And then we pass that.
And this tells us whether it's empty.
So then I'll just do is tell value empty.
So on and if it is then we can actually check to see if we can stand
anywhere in the tile or see where the closest point the tile is and if
not, we won't, right.
Okay.
So the next thing we have to do is check the tiles all around us,
right?
We need to figure out what our rectangular space looks like for this
for the for the purpose of checking.
Now one thing I got to think about here because I'm not even sure
myself.
I gotta think about this, never done.
This before.
Tilemap.
Tom apps are new to me.
By the way.
I just decided I kind of wanted to do them for this gangs.
I'd never done the tile map game.
So, you know, stuff.
I got to think about, too.
So in the tile map, let's say that we've got a guy here, right?
What does that imply for our for our circular if we had a circular
style hero, right?
Well, it means that from at least right here.
We've got the radius worth where he could stand and then I guess so, I
guess what it does is it makes it look like this, right?
Meaning he can stand anywhere.
We're in something that looks like this.
Right.
And that is rounded right there in some sense, right?
He could get closer to it.
So it's basically like a narc that's his radius wide coming from the
corner that cuts out that segment of the of the thing, right?
Because if you imagine the dude standing and he has to stand, you
know, I'm talking about this right?
You imagine him coming up.
He's a circle or something.
He's coming up to this point and if he's going to touch if he's going
to run.
In to that point, then basically what's going to happen to him.
Is this radius of the circle?
This are he, if it came into it this way along this Edge, he would
have stopped our away from it.
He'd hit it are away from it.
And if they came into it, this Edge, he would stop our away from it as
well.
And then he could walk all around.
It always maintaining ours distance.
So essentially you've got that kind of Notch in there, right?
So, basically, the shape of the area in which you can stand
It is, if there's a solid wall here, then it's just our, it's that,
whatever that radius is moved in.
But if there's, and if there's diagonals, then there's notches like
that, right?
That makes sense.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
So basically there's like four walls, that could be there for him and
four notches, that could be there for him.
And we don't really have to handle The Notches right now.
If we don't want to, we could just not handle those cases.
Like I said, we just have to spec out that we want the engine to
handle them.
So, maybe we'll skip them for now so that we don't have to spend a lot
of time doing that when we're just trying to do spec code.
But you know, we got to know, we gotta we gotta say that.
That's what we want to have happen, right?
All right, so it's tile value map empty there.
If it is then we have to go and say, all right.
Let's define the actual valid region where the player could actually
be inside this.
I'll and so, essentially that's going to be a min/max x and a min max,
why, right?
And so let's say let's will make those V2s for now.
So let's say we got our men corner and our Max corner and we'll
initialize where those are like where the actual Min and Max Corner
are.
We know what those are.
Those are the tile side and M.
It m, right?
/ /.
To right.
So basically I know that the Min corner is there because remember
everything style relative.
So, you know, from the center of the tile it's half that that tile
side M, to get out to them in corner.
And then the max Corner goes like this, right?
So, I can also say if I wanted to and you know, what, here's an
interesting thing to again, for Vector, I could do this, which is kind
of kind of Handy.
Right.
And that so
I believe, and I got to do these guys in tilak's.
Been tile, why?
So got to put something actually in there.
One past next I'll one test.
Okay and the ABS tile Z4 right now.
We don't actually check he's not really allowed to walk upwards at the
moment.
That's something we might want to do.
Eventually.
I'm not sure how we're going to handle upwards movement in terms of
how the player actually does it.
I assume that he they can't really move upwards.
They just walk up like specific tiles, are like ladders that go up or
something.
That's typically how these games work.
So we'll have to see
You know what we want to do, when we actually get to the point where
we've got, you know, where we're really thinking about, how we want it
to look, when the player goes up.
Right?
But the ABS tile Z is just wherever the player was and the tile side m
is.
I believe a property of the town map, right?
So that's about it in terms of initializing that corner.
So now we know where we're going to, what we're going to do here.
And we can we could do just right now that search we could do the
search right now.
So the first thing we could do is say well and let's walk through this
search.
We don't have a whole lot of time left.
So I don't think I'm going to finish this today.
We've got, we've only got 10 minutes left.
So we'll do maybe part of it today and will do part of it.
Start picking up again on Monday.
So, if we think about how we want to do this search, right?
We've come up with a tile, right?
We've looked at and, you know, this is the part we're going to do
next.
We've looked at, let's say What's blocking him and we've come up with
a rectangle.
That's where he can.
That's where he could stand inside this tile.
And now we have a point somewhere, and we want to know what the
closest point in our rectangle, is to that point.
So, what are all the cases?
Right?
Well, the cases are either the points inside our rectangle, right?
So the points like somewhere in here, right?
If the points inside then it's just the point, right?
So one case is, you know, it's just the point if it's inside.
So if it's inside, it's just the point, if it's not inside, that means
that no, we're inside this rectangle could possibly be the closest
point.
The only places that could be the closest point are on the edges,
right?
It has to would have to be on the edges.
So if it's on the edges, then what we need to do is we need to check
each Edge, right?
And which Edge do we need to check?
Right?
Well, we need to check.
Whichever.
Heh.
Is implied by the Delta between the Tile Center and the sky, right?
So when we check and we look where this guy is.
All, we really need to do is go.
Well, is it less than or greater than in X for us?
Right?
If it's less than x for us?
In fact, you know what, this is going to be such a cakewalk.
All we really do is say, okay, if it's less than that.
This is basically just this is the space of just a trivial clipping
problem.
Right?
It's really nothing to it.
We just start with this and say, okay, if he's less than R minimum
bound, then just put them at the minimum bound, right?
Anything is less than R if he's less than our maximum bound yet.
This is, this is going to be really, really simple.
This is gonna be really, really simple.
So, the closest point, right would be here in this case.
I believe, right?
Is that correct?
So if we're looking at
We're looking at what the closest point is.
No, that's not true at the closest point would be here.
Yeah.
Okay, even better even better.
All right.
Sorry.
I got distracted.
Therefore s thinking the problem through.
All right.
So the closest point to the to a rectangle is actually just going to
always be a perpendicular to the edge, right?
Because I was thinking closest point to the center there and I was
like, oh, we gotta find the intersection not true because we're not
looking for the closest point to Center.
We're looking to the closest point to the rectangle.
So basically this coordinate, whatever this coordinate is relative to
the center is the closest point.
Once you actually clip it's it's coordinates to the coordinates we
have so if it's less than R Min X we just
To arm in X and Bam is the closest point, right?
If it's less than, you know, if it's greater than the, the x or the
greater than the, why we just clip it to.
And as long as we just sort of clip it to whatever it is, then we've
got that closest point.
I think that's it.
And that'll handle the corner case is properly too because it'll clip
it here.
Like, if it was out here, it first, flip it to here and then clip it
to here and that's exactly what we would want.
So basically, all we have to do is just go through each axis X, and
then y, clipping it to the bounds in that, and we've got the closest
point done.
Right.
So to me, that sounds like something that I just want to call here.
I want to say closest.
Right point in rectangle.
Seems like something we might want to do just in general.
It's a nice easy thing for me to say.
So I'm going to say that our test p is whatever the closest point in
the rectangle is.
I'm going to pass that rectangle mean Corner Max corner, right?
So, the closest point in the rectangle to that new player, P new
player P.
So relative, new player P.
And so to produce the relative new player P.
I just need to know the difference between that new player, plea,
right?
This guy right here.
Where's that subtraction?
I've got that dysfunction.
That's what I want.
So what I want to do here is say, alright.
I've got that diff function, I want to subtract.
Be still guys, I want to subtract.
The tile point.
So this is going to be my test tile, and this is going to be my new
player pee, like so on.
That and the test.
I'll pee, I need to build out of the ABS tile X, AB style, Y, and we
don't actually even have a function for that yet.
Do we?
So our tile map position?
I'd like to be able to make one of these easily without having to
specify the offset which I could do just by doing it directly, but I'd
like to be able to search for those.
So I think what I'm going to do is introduce something here where I
can sort of say, you know, centered tile.
Point or something like that.
And I just passed AB style.
X, AB style.
Y + AB Style zx0 on and can basically produce the result that way.
So result is just a straight copy of those things.
And it is assumed that I just like the other fields of zero, so we
return that like that and that way I can quickly generate this guy,
you know with with actually know.
And again, we're not thinking about speed here at all.
That's important to this important.
To remember you're just thinking about writing code that works at this
point and all the stuff that we worry about speed.
That's all going to come later on down the road.
So I try to be aware of algorithmic problems.
If there's a speed problem in that sense, but you know, I try not to
think about that in terms of in terms of when we're just working on
the code directly.
All right.
So let's go ahead and compile that and now we have
Let's see.
What is the problem here?
Cannot convert argument to 0, right?
These are, these are addresses.
Correct about that.
Yeah.
And so this is r.l.
New player P.
So now we got that relative one.
And so all we now have to do is do that.
So assuming that we have that, we have our best point.
Our best point is going to be wherever we start.
So the way that I'm going to treat this as going to say wherever the
player is right now.
That's going to be, that's going to be the best point, right?
So the tile map.
Mission that we expect our our best, our best player pee.
Right is going to be wherever he is right now.
That's just what we're going to do.
And then so when we're actually doing this resolved here, I'm going to
say when we get back the closest point in the rectangle for that test
P.
I'm going to then see whether that's better.
The distance is better.
So I also say best distance.
Will be whatever.
The best distance, D is the distance between the new player P.
And the old player P, which is, which is again that diff do we have?
I feel like we have this so we know how much we added, right?
So I'm going to actually save that.
So this is this is the player, Delta, right?
However much we added to the guy is this
Right.
This is what we're moving him by.
You go.
And so that's player Delta plus.
I could actually just say that as well.
So, that's the player Delta, right?
And so, if I want to, I can say, however, long that player Delta is,
is the best distance if we just stood still.
So we definitely don't want to move the guy if moving him would cause
them to move further away.
So when we start out the
Oop we're going to say that the best distance and the best location is
just right where we are.
And then each time we check a tile will see whether where we would
move in that tile would be better than if we just stayed still.
And if it does we'll update that to be the new best distance of the
new best p and we'll go from there.
Right?
So we've got the best distance here.
So we've got that best distance is going to be the length.
And in fact, I'll actually do this squared here.
Let's talk about this for a minute.
We're almost out of time.
But but oops, I don't know if you remember, we actually implemented
this, but we actually did the math for this the other day.
I said, if you wanted to find the length of the vector, you could just
do the square root of the vector with its own inner product, right,
but we never actually type that in.
So there's actually, if I just want to get the length squared of a
particular Vector.
Maybe I'll call that length, SQ.
It seems a little bit better.
We go.
If you just want to get the length squared, we actually already did
the math for that on the previous stream.
It's just it's just that right.
And that's we don't even we wouldn't really even have to choose a
function is just a little easier to read.
It's like easier for the person to read now.
Why am I leaving at squared instead of taking the square root to find
its length?
Well, square roots is extra work.
We don't actually have to do because we never actually care what the
distance is.
We just care if the distance is less and we know that the square of a
number, that's less than another number is also less than the square
of that other number, right?
We know that if x is less than
why then x squared is also less than y squared as long as the numbers
are both.
The same sign, right?
As long as they're both positive.
For example, we know that that's true.
There are - they might flip and this case it might be different,
right?
But but that's this is the case for positive and we know that
distances are always positive, like the length that you go, the length
is always going to be positive.
There's no way for it to be negative.
So we're totally fine, right?
So,
In this case, that's totally sufficient and all we would do here is is
is actually test to see whether it's better.
And of course, I'm out of time.
So we'll do that tomorrow.
I'm sorry.
We'll do that on Monday and finish that up.
So we'll just leave that as a dot dot dot.
In order to not leave our code in done compiling State.
Let's go ahead and flip this back and make sure that we're still
working.
Oh no.
Oh, I broke something.
Yeah, make sure we're still working and I did not make sure that we're
still working.
So it's good that I check that let's just quickly see what I actually.
Broke their.
Oh, whoops.
That that's, that's what I wrote.
Sorry about that.
Slight, slight error there.
Slight error.
There we go.
Okay.
Everyone's happy.
Here we go.
So I'm moving around.
All right, so let's call it for now, and we'll go to the Q&A and then
we should have really no problem on Monday, finishing that up.
Since we've already explained everything that we're going to do.
We're just do that.
Will implement this function and then we'll implement this check to
accept it.
Well, it'll basically be, you know, something that looks like this
sort of thing.
So this would be this would be a new player P here and the best
distance squared will be the test.
So this will be a test different Square here that will do and will
basically say if the, if the best distance squared is greater than
whatever that test census is, will accept the new one.
So we basically just keep checking in.
Keep picking a new best every time we see one.
All right, let's go to the Q&A.
If you wouldn't mind.
Find prefixing your question with Q: so I can see it.
And please keep the questions, two things that we've done on today's
stream or on a previous stream.
If you want to ask off-topic questions, you can do.
So in the the stream the if you show up a little bit before the stream
starts about 15 minutes before the stream starts.
I'm usually on answering questions that can be as off topic as you
want.
But for the official accusing is here that get recorded.
Please keep them on topic.
Questions.
Do we have any questions?
We don't have any questions.
There's no Q must not.
Be very many people on the stream today, perhaps.
Ah good the person who asked about the handmade Tha that CPP question
before has asked again, and that is exactly what I was hoping because
otherwise I probably would forgotten and I would have forgotten.
So thank you for for
Question again.
So, what the person is asked, is that there's multiple versions of the
get tile value function and they all do the same thing.
Right?
So there's three of them, you can see if I actually do the three of
them there.
There's this one.
Get Top Value.
In fact, I could I think I could put them all right next to each
other.
If we want to just take a look at those together.
Where am I get to evaluate?
There we go.
Does that still work there?
Okay, so here are the three versions and the person was wondering why
we have free versions.
The answer is just because it's to make it so that when people want to
call it, they can do the most convenient version for them.
Right?
So basically, if you
Open to happen.
Do the tile chunk that you're in.
And you just want to get a tile out of that pile, chunk at find out
what the value is.
Then you call this function, but if you don't know what Tau childcare
and you just have because remember again, let me be more specific
here.
Remember how we're storing this?
We have a giant world.
It's it could be massive right in terms of its Dimension.
And so we can't possibly store it all.
There's just, no way.
We couldn't even store it all.
If we if we did disk-based paging.
There isn't enough room on a hard drive to even store the maximum
Dimensions that we allowed for the world, which is 4 billion by 4
billion tiles.
You couldn't your.
There's no way to even store it.
So that's not on the table.
So what we did instead is we have little chunks and wherever the world
actually is, right?
We fill in the chunks that are just where the world actually is.
So that way the world can be however weird and snaky, it wants to be
without having to worry about fitting itself into some predefined
Square.
That's the way we decided to define the world so that it can be kind
of
Trey, that way.
So what that means is when we're asking for a tile, we need to ask
about a tile in a particular chunk.
But in order for people to work with them easily, we want them to be
able to ask about tiles using just an absolute tile location, right?
So that they don't actually have to worry about what top sockets in
when they're just using code.
That's external to it and not try to do anything, particularly
performance optimal.
Just like here's a bunch of absolute tile coordinates.
Get me the tile value.
I don't want to worry about the chunks, right?
So basically what we have is we have a three tiered structure here.
If you are using the like bundled position format that we that we
introduced to keep track of things, a little more easily for people,
then this function, all this function does, is basically just a little
cracker function that like, cracks that thing, open and passes, the
three absolute values into the next tier of the function, right?
So it's basically just breaking the function up into segments.
So, if you have one of those, you can call it.
If you don't have one of those, you don't need.
See this.
This
That position has an additional piece of value, piece of information
it, right?
This offset, which you don't actually need to get the tile value.
You don't care where the person is inside the tile.
So this just peels that off and passes.
Only the necessary stuff down to the next layer.
What the next layer does is.
It goes ahead and looks up, what chunk those would be in?
And then actually gets the chunk and then at calls down to the next
level of the function.
Finally, in the next level we go.
Okay, inside that tile chunk.
Now we can actually get the value which actually calls the real
function which is get Top Value in checked.
So these are all really just helper functions.
Technically.
These should probably all just be inlined, really.
I mean, we haven't.
We don't like I said, we're not we think about performance doesn't
really matter but in terms of notating to myself, these are probably
All in line because most of them just want to directly call this
really, this is all you want to do is just do this direct thing right
here.
And so these are just there for the utility.
So that no matter what you have, in terms of information.
You can easily call something in the external code, that will get you
back the tile value directly.
So you don't have to worry about copying pasting this code or anything
like that.
You can just do it and know that it works.
Does that make sense?
You start with variable names with uppercase struck names with lower.
Is that the standard see way or just how you do it?
I'm used to the opposite which is why I'm asking, it's just how I do
it.
I think the standard way is actually to have everything be lower case
with underscores.
Maybe is more standard.
I don't know.
But that's just that's this is just the way that I did it.
It actually originally comes from Chris hecker's style because I was
programming the first job I got.
When I
First programming in the game industry was with him and that's the way
he usually had his coat structured.
So I just end up picking that up.
I think before that I did everything was lowercase with underscores.
Abner.
When winter, if NPCs are introduced, will they reuse some of the code
shown here?
So I suspect it.
They will there will be a lot of reuse code.
But again, that's that's the kind of question that you want to let the
code answer for you.
So when we start writing in PCS, we should see immediately.
If they have to, if they want to ask the same kinds of questions as
the player does.
And if so, then we would use the same code and if not, then we
wouldn't, right.
So, usually you don't want to think about code reuse in terms of a
forward-thinking thing.
You want to think of, as a backward, thinking thing, you want to go,
am I about to do something that I've already done?
And if so, let's figure out how they can both do the thing, using the
same piece of code.
You don't want to do the opposite, which is go.
Let me think about how to write something that I think I could reuse
in two places.
That's really bad typically, so I try never to do that.
Are you going to implement push?
Squeeze on walls like say?
Shoulder budding into wall and automatically pushing the player out a
bit to fit through.
I think you are.
Do you need walls or do mean doorways?
Because you can't really fit through a wall, but I guess.
Are you asking?
Are you asking about this scenario, which is
To say if I'm walking this way will I will?
I do something so that the player doesn't get stuck on this Edge and
the answer to that is actually, we could do some stuff there and we'll
have to see how it feels, but just the Collision, just the change that
we're making right now, we'll actually helped us a lot because if we
do go with a circular or elliptical model for the player, he will kind
of automatically do that because when he hits this thing,
And we're moving this way that search in P thing.
I talked about will automatically find that moving him out and in,
through the doorway, is the way to make him go.
So this search in P will actually automatically improve our, doorway
handling drastically already.
But but yeah, we may want, if we may want to do additional stuff like
making a funnel here, that sort of like sucks the player into the door
when they're going.
If we find that that feels better.
It seems like the possible movement positions are, more of a pizza
slice than all the squares around the player.
Why did we do a generic thing around all the players positions?
Instead of that?
Just because I don't want to really deal with risk Computing, the
restricted area quite yet.
So that's why I think I mentioned this when I said, let's just do the
obvious thing of like, looping them over right now.
Pizza slice is not what I would call it.
But basically, the tiles that are used will basically be something
like this.
And so we actually I think we may actually end up with the correct
bounds even now that I say it just by using because we're got a search
over tiles.
So pizza slice doesn't really help but it's just going to be something
that looks like that, right?
And and you don't know that it's a pizza slice because it could be
that the closest point is is very much directly above you almost or
directly to the side of you like that.
So it is it's more of a rectangle.
It's more of something that looks like that.
How do you think we would determine using this system if the player
should be killed by a collision like walls closing in and crushing you
or whatever?
Well, that's a good question.
I don't know that.
I don't know how much I would necessarily say that I want to have
stuff where that necessarily happens, but the
Easiest way to do it is just to go.
Well that first move that you make.
So I'm here and I try to move here whatever you were inside.
At that time could have consequences.
So if you're trying to make it so that if you touch a wall that kills
you, you just do that.
So, if I, if I would have been inside a spiky, Killy thing then, that
kills me on the other hand.
If I end up in a situation where I cannot stand in my current
position.
And I cannot find a point that's close to me.
That's that's that would be, that would be, I cannot find a point.
I could move to that's within the boundaries of how far the player is
allowed to move.
Then I know that walls have closed in on me.
And again I would do whatever.
Is the place that I'm standing I would just do whatever is in that
location would have its effect.
Right?
So it's actually really easy to handle, both those cases.
But like I said, I don't know if
Have those are not if we do, that's how we would handle them.
Well, we have to push Boulders out of the way of doors.
I don't know, probably not doesn't sound like very much fun.
Abner Abner wants to know if I ever fall for some of the dogmatic
traps anymore when I'm coding.
I don't know.
That's a good question.
Not very often.
I don't think so.
But I do write lousy code still write, like I don't think I fall for
the dog dogmatic traps, but the bottom line is that like I'll still
sometimes, write code.
That isn't very good, right at.
That's algorithmically not very good and you're just like, Yep.
This was not very good.
And that's because you can.
It's easy to eventually train yourself to avoid problems with your
coding style, that are making that are causing you to do, like more
work than you should have.
Honor to do things poorly.
But the bottom line is there's just a lot of work that goes into
writing something correctly.
And sometimes you just don't do that work and it has nothing to do
with like what the code looks like.
It's that it's actually just struck the actual algorithm is not very
good.
Right?
And I definitely do that on projects, you know.
like Fabi and recently had to had to deal with one of my
Generators, which was super janky and like, you know, I was like it
only did exactly what it needed to do, for what I had in mind for it
and like, of course, he was doing some stuff on pink to afterwards and
had to deal with it.
And I do not relish being in his position, right?
Because I definitely did not set him up for Success.
So he had to do a bunch of work to it, to fix a bunch of things that
were bad in it, but I don't like most of those were not because I had
some dogmatic coding style, but I thought it was just because the code
was lousy, right?
And the algorithm
thumbs were lousy because I just did the simplest thing that needed to
get done.
Instead of going.
Hey, I should take some time here to think about.
This is something that people are going to use later.
Let's go ahead and actually do more work on it.
And so sometimes, you know, that's something that I still do which is
I don't go and take the time to go.
Okay, hold on.
Now that we've got things doing what I needed to do.
Let's push a little further.
If I know that this is something that's going to stick around.
Let's push a little further and actually go do the cleanup and the
extension that you
Should do if you are going to actually, prepare the next person for
Success.
So I definitely have that problem still.
So, you know, there's that.
So, does the search method here?
Give us a sense of rounded Corners?
Yes.
Well, the search method doesn't care.
It's one way to think about it, the third search, the search method is
whatever you end up Computing in your search.
If you compute the search space based on rounded Corners, then it
will, if not, then it won't.
And so when we right now, when we do our closest point in rectangle,
right?
When we Implement that tomorrow, that will not give us rounded the
rounded.
Diagonal corner, right?
So in the case, where you're looking at this and this, we're looking
at these, this Square, it will not properly.
Give us.
That rounded corner at the moment, but we will then up maybe maybe
even will just upgrade it immediately to have that rounded Corner
because it's not that hard to do, but I just don't know if I want do
that right now, but basically it's just whatever you generate.
The search space to be for searching P.
It could have rounded Corners if you generate rounded search spaces,
it won't.
If you don't
Hmm.
I don't really understand the searching stuff.
Why not?
Just adjust the players Vector based on normal vectors, so I thought I
kind of explain that in terms of what had to happen, but maybe I
didn't
So let's say I'm here and this is my velocity Vector, right?
So if I don't do search in P, if I do search in t, which is the
standard first, I have to write Collision code that checks the
Collision of these two things, right?
So, I have to generate something that will produce this point.
At least that's the first thing.
And rather it has to actually produce the correct point for the
circular Collision.
So it actually has to produce this point, right?
Then I have to update based on the normal, which, at that point.
Be here, right?
So, now, here's my new velocity Vector.
I then have to rerun this and find.
Oh, he can't step two here, either.
He would actually only step to here, right?
And then, I have to correct the velocity Vector again, right?
And then, if I still had some left, I might find that he couldn't step
to hear either.
He would actually Step 2 here and here and here, and I would end up
doing one, two, three, four, five, six, six steps of that thing and
they're all super numerically.
Fiddly.
Right?
Like I have to make sure that numerically I
Did this correctly because oh I'm adjusting these vectors and doing
all the stuff in this in this sort of weird crenellations space.
And and again this has the problem of if I had a little sort of chink
in the wall that'll like thing that kind of opens up there.
It would handle that.
I would just stop dead right there.
There'd be no way to fix that because when I dead in the velocity,
when I, when I use only the remaining part of the lawsuit, he just
stopped right in that corner, so searching tea.
Is lousy in my opinion?
Searching p is just way better.
Because it doesn't have any of these problems.
So so there's that.
I'm not sure if that's what you're asking, but
Are you going to worry about how many objects collisions the Collision
detection system can handle?
Or will you not worry about that until you have more objects
collisions?
Honestly, I don't think there's any way we could possibly get up to a
high enough number of objects to worry about Collision in 2D.
There's I just don't think there's any possible way.
We'll hit problems with that.
But
We may have to think about it more when we moved to slower platforms
like the Raspberry Pi or something.
I don't know on a PC where we've got like, you know, two cores at a
minimum these days and they're running it three gigahertz or whatever
and like the GPU is going to do all the rendering for us eventually.
Like I mean, we could have 100 objects on the screen and we wouldn't
care.
So and and I don't know that the player could manage 100 objects in a
zelda-like game.
I mean, you wouldn't
A human can only think about a certain number of them before it starts
to turn into like a bullet, hell game, where you're really talking
more about an abstract shape that the bullets are making or something.
But I was, I mean, I'm thinking more like a Zelda game where, you
know, maybe in a really crazy battle.
There's 10 enemies and 30 projectiles on the screen or something and
there's just no way that that's going to ever tax the system.
So so I feel like our focus should be on making the best possible
system for good movement and not on What's the
Fast as possible thing, that might be kind of lousy, but that's geared
towards doing a lot more.
Because in this case, what we want is high quality lower quantity
because we're just not going to have the kind of quantity Where we
would start to make a trade-off.
In the quantity Direction.
For searching P.
Don't you have a problem with passing through walls thinner than the
players movement, Vector know.
So the reason you don't is because that flood fill, like I said, so
you always start with when you're doing your cell search, right?
And this is true in handmade.
This will be true in handmade here as well.
So even though we may be never have the case in handmade here.
It's true in him here as well.
If you want to do this, the search has to flood.
Fill out and reach the wall, and reach the Target location.
And so, assuming that there's a wall like this and you're trying to
pass through it.
Um, you know, he's only allowed to basically go a certain distance in
the flood fill.
So he can't actually ever get over to here because he'd never actually
reach those cells.
If that's why I was talking about that flood fill before because it
prevents you from ever considering this at all.
You could do something really weird where you allowed the player to
teleport through walls, if if he could ever get there, which would
allow them to search much farther away, which I don't think you
actually want to.
To do.
But it's interesting because it would enable a interesting type of
game which is like allow you to phase through walls.
That well known as I'm gonna go there.
Will the search code work if the player hits a slightly angled wall,
that should make him bounce a little away from the wall depending on
that angle.
So you're talking about like a wall.
That's that's like a rubbery wall because the way that we're actually
doing this is we're trying to make it so that he Glides along walls.
That's our goal.
But you're talking about if I wanted to bounce if I want them to
bounce.
It's still just works.
Right?
Because basically what happens with the search thing, is it goes?
Oh, okay.
He's you know, he'd be here and then I know what the normal is.
So I'll do the reflection of that velocity and I'll do that.
It might be slightly less accurate, but
If we wanted to do that, we actually still could because what we could
do is we could say, if he's bouncing instead of doing the closest
point to the location.
We'll just do the closest point.
We'll take the closest point to along the line, do that search.
And then, you know, we could say that he comes out from there.
We do whatever the bounce would have been from there and take the
closest point to that.
But I don't know.
I think you probably still want to do this.
It's a little bit less accurate, but it's probably more interesting
and more robust in terms of keeping things.
Right?
I'm not sure yet.
Remember these are very small time steps.
So
Like a microscopic situation that we're looking at here, so I don't
know.
So you still could Implement bouncing but this is more optimized for
gliding because that tends to be more what happens in games of this
nature.
Will you implement some Secrets while none of us is watching?
So that we don't know where or what they are.
I have thought about that a little bit and I'm not sure like
what I have considered and I don't know if I'll do this or not.
But what I have considered is basically for the last month of the
project or something.
I will no longer do the live stream.
I'll work as much every day as I want to.
And I'll record it all but I won't post it live and then when the game
ships all the stuff that I did in those in those weeks will still be
documented but no one will know about them.
So anything that I snuck in there, you won't actually know and then
I'll release it like
After the game is done.
I'll release the video, so you can still go see how everything was
done, but they'll be like a month of stuff where there could be things
in there that you didn't know that I put in, I thought about it.
I don't know if I want to do that or not, but I thought about it.
Think we're at the end of the questions.
Hmm.
Well, the characters have skeletal or old-school Sprite animations
skeletal.
Just because it's more work and you know, for educational purposes,
it'll show more stuff.
Let's see.
That's it.
Girl, and oh Bloom, that sounds like a good idea since the game needs
secrets.
Yeah, I think it is possibly.
I mean, I don't know.
Like like I said, I don't really know I can Implement a ton of stuff
in a month.
So basically, if I just turned off the stream for one month at the
end, I could add all that stuff, right?
And then, but I want everything to be recorded, So it basically be.
There would be, you know.
A month after handmade hero came out.
There would be essentially how much so 4080 160.
So something like over 100 hours of new video to go watch.
If you wanted to see how all the secrets were implemented, don't know
if that's a good idea or not, but, you know, something to think about,
With a search in P approach.
Also work for colliding with other moving objects.
Yeah, I mean basically there isn't really any difference in with
searching p and certainty in terms of what they can handle.
Really, it just is what's
use it just
I want to collide with moving objects.
You have to decide how you want to do them.
Whether you're doing in order movement or not.
I tend to prefer in order movement.
Because I feel like it's just a better abstraction.
And since it's all happening at 32, the second.
I don't feel like the player really sees those differences.
So usually what I would say is searching P within order, movement is
probably what I'll Implement for this game.
Unless there's some really overriding reason not to do it, if that
makes sense.
Create a supports Infinite Canvas.
What does that mean?
What is infinite canvas?
How do I turn that on?
Is that?
Is that something I can?
Is that I don't know.
Infinite Campus.
Does anyone know what that man?
I don't know what that means.
A great deal of the problems.
You have faced have seemed to me to involve some sort of assessment,
whether implicit or explicit of a trade-off between storage and
processing.
Collision detection, has always bothered me a little because it seems
as though that trade-off doesn't exist.
I mean, is there any way around cheap Collision?
I'm not sure exactly what you're asking.
First.
I'll say almost everything is a trade-off between storage and
processing.
In some sense.
There are very few things that aren't so like you can almost always
trade off storage for you guys space and time often are a trade-off in
anything.
You can always choose to use more space to give you less actual time
processing.
Now, it's complicated nowadays by the fact that memory accessing is so
expensive that you can't always trade space for Speed because pull
In the stuff you would need may take too much time, but there's
usually a space and time trade-off.
Yes.
What that has to do with Collision?
I'm not sure.
I mean, it is definitely the case that we could pre-process everything
into some kind of very smoothly discretize Grid or something that
would allow us to just do quick lookups to see if you could move there
and stuff like that.
But, I mean, one of the reasons that Collision is difficult to trade
storage for time is because since things are moving, it means that
there isn't anything to pre-compute.
So when things are Dynamic, you can't pre compute them.
It's sort of like Dynamic lighting also has that problem where there's
not a whole lot of
Ways that you can trade off storage at some level because you there's
only a certain amount of people amputation you can ever do now.
Certainly still do it.
I mean, there's a bunch of lighting schemes that still use storage to
speed up Dynamic lighting.
Like there's tons of that, right?
But it is definitely the case that anything that's Dynamic can't it
has a limit to how far it can be pushed.
Let's see.
Could you comment?
What you added at the end?
So that the uploaded code compiled?
It does compile, doesn't it?
Yeah.
It we're in a compelling state.
Let's see.
Alternative for Secrets is just to let people know when you're going
to be doing the secrets coding but still do it live.
I don't know because then you have a lot of downtime before release
other way, might be more exciting and less weight.
That's hard to say.
Okay, so, so someone was saying that the create an infinite canvas
thing, I can just scroll, and then a button pops up.
Whoa.
Oh weird.
That is bizarre.
Thank you for that.
That's I wonder how long I could do that before we just roll over and
die.
That's pretty sweet, though.
Don't you think I like that?
Oh, yeah.
All right, we're going to get some use out of that.
Thank you very much.
All right, I think we have finished.
We're out of time for the stream.
Thank you.
Everyone for joining me.
It's been a pleasure coding with you as always here on handmade hero.
If you would like to get access to the source code, you can pre-order
the game on handmade here at Oregon.
It comes with all the source.
You can download it every night.
I upload it after we finish every day, and it also has the test assets
that we use for development.
So you can actually follow along exactly with what
You do.
We also, if you want to just support the video series.
We have a patreon that's up.
Now, to, you can subscribe to, and we also have a site that helps with
learning from the stream.
It's the news and forms link, forums that have made here at org.
And it's got a bunch of great stuff on.
It's got the schedule for the week.
It's an episode guide that a bunch of people have volunteered to make
and it's really really cool.
It's basically got time-coded.
Links to the videos and all that sort of stuff.
So if you want to catch up on older videos, it's really good.
There's also coding resources page that Sports the Linux and Mac that
people have in the community have contributed.
If you're looking for that sort of stuff and we have a code discussion
board that you can go to that's basically place to ask questions and
talk with other people out stream.
So it's pretty cool.
If you try to learn from a stream.
I highly recommend it.
It's an excellent resource.
So we will finish our Collision detection stuff on Monday night.
When will finish doing the search stuff.
And so, I think that'll be good and that
Set us up for success, in terms of knowing exactly what the engine
needs to do.
And what kind of figure out where that code wants to live as well,
which will be interesting.
So, please join me.
Monday night.
8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time, for the next live coding stream.
I hope to see you all there, and until then.
Please have a lovely weekend and I'll see you guys online.
Okay, take it easy.