Okay, hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream.
I am going to do depth peeling this weekend and yeah there's not a
whole lot to it but because it's one of those things that is GPU
oriented and we don't have any way to debug GPU on this machine at
all.
I just have to wing it.
It
Can be an adventure, you know, it could definitely be a pretty nasty
Adventure.
So let me just explain what we're going to be doing and yeah that that
does not look like Milton is happy.
I really need to.
There's only a couple things in Milton that I need to fix.
I should just like we should do a weekend streamer we just go fix them
because it's almost perfect for me now but it
It has some weird like things where it loses sync with the pain all
the time.
And it also has this weird pause, like, every time you lift up the
pen, it stutters like that.
And I'm pretty sure I could fix both of those but I just, I've never
and the source code is available.
So I've just I've never spent the time to actually go in and and and
figure it out.
But I should, I mean something I use every day, well every weekend.
All right, so let's talk about death peeling.
So, deaf peeling is essentially the idea that if you want to, right?
You can sort of get multiple slices through your scene, to capture the
information that's at more than one layer through the scene, you know,
like kind of like a cutaway view.
And I talked a long time ago when we were sort of talking about.
Stuff I talked about atomics and what atomics are is their ways of
using the frame buffer in a way that allows you to write more than one
piece of information to it, kind of like a linked list or whatever.
And as you know, if, you know, if you, if you're going to write to a
location and you need to do something coherent like a linked list, you
have to have the ability to access that atomically because if you, you
know, imagine a GPU is not single-threaded a Jeep.
EU has many, many threads, doing rendering just like our software
renderer did.
And so, you know, if you wanted to say, do all the rendering to the to
the screen, and instead of like blending all the pixels together that
stacked, we know when you had two things stacked on top of each other,
you just wanted to keep a list of all of them, you could use atomics.
And what the atomics allow you to do.
Is they allow you to say?
All right, I want to atomically update this location in the frame
buffer such that I can basically keep a little link list.
It says, here's the color I rasterize than the depth a rasterized it
at and then here is like essentially an index to the next one.
That's also existing at this pixel location and you just stream those
out into memory and you have some maximum amount that you're willing
to tolerate per pixel.
And off you go right now.
I know it sounds a little wonky because that's not the kind of thing.
You're used to seeing on gpus, but you have to remember, gpus are
basically just cpuc stays.
They have different performance profiles in a number of ways, but they
are incredibly powerful, especially desktop ones and they can do just
crazy stuff.
So building a linked list per pixel is a absolutely ludicrous thing
to, to have said in the year, like, say 2000 but here 17 years later
That is not a ludicrous thing to say at all and you could do it.
Now, the downside of that is again their performance implications for
using atomics and that way, the same kinds of parenting's occasions,
that you have four CPUs and perhaps ones that you are quite worried
about in the case of GPU rendering because you do have so many threads
for writing so many pixels.
You really don't want people locking up cache lines, probably all the
time.
And trying to get them for exclusive use in that way.
You'd rather probably let it, you know, do whatever order it's going
to do and allow things to overwrite each other as necessary.
But at the end of the day, you know, it has to ensure certain amounts
of information like depth ordering and stuff like that.
So you know, it's not necessarily the end of the world but it does
introduce a bunch of stuff like, okay.
You're doing a lot more memory Ops now and you're storing a lot more
stuff because you're
I think every single thing that happened to this pixel and that could
be, you know, hundreds of things.
So again, you know, you end up in the situation where you have to
start a to think about how many things for Pixel, we're going to store
and all this other stuff.
So atomics are kind of the general purpose way of getting more
information there, but depth peeling.
Is sort of a lighter version of that depth and it has the advantage of
it works everywhere.
It doesn't require atomics at all.
So you don't have to worry about whether you're running on something
that it supports atomics or not.
And you don't have to worry about the performance implications, that
atomics might have on any particular GPU that you're using.
So what does depth feeling do well?
What deaf peeling does is it says, I know that when I render, whatever
I'm going to render
I'm going to end up because in a z-buffer world, I'm going to end up
with two things, right?
I've got the the Z, or in this case, I'm going to call it depth
because, you know, it could be whatever you want.
Doesn't have to actually be a z-value, it's whatever you fed down the
Z Channel, you got the
Depth buffer and the color buffer being produced here in the case of
our renderer.
And so when you draw something into it like the hero you end up with a
depth buffer that says we're, that was right.
So all of the values in here on the depth buffer are however, far away
from the camera, the hero was is recorded.
And if there's something, you know, behind it that's a deeper depth
value and so on,
And we know that that works because we see that the result is correct,
right?
We see that things have gotten sorted properly, so we know that that
depth, buffer is getting filled out properly and exist but we never
actually use it for anything else.
It's just there to do that sorting of the fact that you know, I drew
these two things and I want the closer one to overwrite the further
one you know
But what you can also, Imagine is since you are producing a depth
buffer, you then have the option of a using that depth buffer for
something meaning after you produce a you know a depth buffer, during
a render pass you could choose to do another render pass that actually
reads that depth buffer and does something different with it, right.
You don't have to make the depth buffer just to be something that's
used for z-buffering.
It can also be considered an
But surface that gets it fed into future rendering stages because at
the end of the day, just like you can render to multiple textures and
then use those later and composite those onto the screen, you can have
the depth buffer exist in multiple textures where you render one pass
to one texture and one pass a depth electric and so you can end up
with depth sources as well as depth you know, just used in inside a
single pass.
So
What death feeling does is it says, well, let's take the depth buffer
and let's feed it into another render pass as a maximum depth
essentially.
Or in this case, maybe you might say a minimum depth.
What we're going to do is say, okay, what if we rendered these two
things, you know, like, like you see, I've got the hero in the square.
What if I wanted to have the information about both the hero,
and the square behind the hero, you know, I want to have sort of two
For lack of a better term.
I wanted to have two slices of the world so that I can know what's
immediately behind the hero in addition to just the hero and, you
know, it wouldn't go any further than that.
It just go one step back.
But, you know, I just want those two pieces of information.
Well, what I could do is I could render the scene again, right?
Exactly the same scene, just render.
It feed it to the GPU a second time.
and the second time when I could do is I could
Take this depth buffer, as input.
So instead of being just the depth buffer, now it's the input and I
use a separate depth buffer, right?
So I have essentially two deaf buffers, I have depth buffer, 1 and
depth, buffer to depth, buffer, one still looks like this but depth
buffer to is going to only be used in this next pass here.
And for this past, what I'm going to do is I'm going to set the Z
function such that in addition to having
having to be the closest Value so far.
It also cannot be greater or cannot be closer to the viewer.
Then whatever is in depth, buffer 1.
Which means that all of these things that are here right now that we
see in the front will go away.
They'll get clipped out by this requirement.
So what I'll end up with is just behind the hero, right?
So if you imagine the hero was, you know, was kind of here behind the
hero.
I will have.
That information about the rest of the square and behind the square.
I will have whatever would have been buying the square, which maybe is
nothing in this case, right?
And so what I will draw on the screen is just this part here, right?
It's just the part of the square that was behind the hero.
And so, you can see why it's called death-dealing because I'm
essentially peeling off the top layer.
And going to the part just below it, right?
One below it.
And so, the reason that I'm interested in this is twofold.
So the first reason that I'm interested in this is I'm just curious to
know.
Could we get rid of multi, sampling all together, meaning using
turning on actually the the multi sample buffer, which is what we were
using?
Could we get rid of multi sample all together?
By using deff peeling.
I never thought of this before for some reason probably because I
don't work on 2D stuff very much and maybe there's some papers out
there that talk about doing exactly this.
But basically what we were doing before is we were saying when we
wanted to composite Sprites together, we just used multi sampling to
do that for us and that handles edges pretty well, but it doesn't
handle Alpha blending very well because again you only get as many
Alpha steps as Jimmy,
You only get as many Alpha steps as you have multi samples and you
never have 256 over sampling.
Which is how many bits per gun.
You've got, at least in UHD.
You're going to have more like 10.
So it doesn't produce a very accurate blend when you do alpha blending
in any way,
If we did Death feeling instead.
So instead of keeping eight jittered samples per pixel that are
jittered spatially, we're going to Jitter them in-depth, essentially
not Jitter, but keep them into to death slices.
If we have two depth slices then I can just blend the front and back
one together using the actual Alpha and it should be perfect, right?
So this seems to handle both, the a the case of edges and the case of
alpha things that Alpha out, very gracefully and armas.
Assuming I'll find out some snafu as I get a little further in, as to
why I'm wrong.
Because it sure does seem like a little bit too easy to be true
because why doesn't everyone just do this?
And I don't know that everyone does because it doesn't sound like
something.
I've heard people do but, you know, I'm sure someone somewhere is done
it but I just don't know why not everyone has done it.
So there must be some reason why it doesn't work and we'll find out
that reason.
The other thing, if I go ahead and run the game here for you and of
course, you'll have
To excuse the fact that oh wait, no.
I at the last minute last time I turned multi-sample back on so this
is still with multi sampling on the other reason is because I noticed
before, let me go ahead and hop down here.
Nope, a little further.
Let's see.
Okay, there you go.
There is this weird effect that I would playing with.
It was it was sort of an accident, you know.
I was just sort of showing some stuff about the near clipping plane
and I kind of like this weird effect that was happening.
Where if you kind of like if you progressively clip out the Z buffer,
if you just set the near clipping plane to something that's pretty far
out, actually
Let it clip, it does this weird thing and I was kind of interested in
exploring that affect a little bit and actually maybe making it into a
real effect that we do.
So as you kind of go down a stairwell and you hop to the lower level,
it does something like that, just for fun, right?
Like a cleaner version of that effect, that doesn't have so many
artifacts, right?
As it flutters in.
And there's a number of ways that I think we could do that.
I'm just interested to see.
So I felt like at that point that was another really good argument for
having deaf peeling because if I have deaf peeling, then I can make
that Fade Out happen properly, right.
And you know, there's a little bit of an issue with the deaf peeling
that I can imagine Jimmy.
In this case.
So I don't really know how good that's really going to be.
And the reason for that is, I'm just not sure if I need more than one
depth peel to really make that work.
And at that point, you know, if you're going to do two, three, four
depth, feels at that point, it kind of sounds more like you just want
atomics, you know, but I'm really curious to see what we could get
away with with only one depth peel and just to sort of also motivate
this a little bit if I go over to
My, what was it?
The opengl layer here and I turn off the multi sampling.
Let's go ahead here.
So here is what it looks like currently in a without the multi
sampling.
As you can see with the with the multi sampling off and I also
probably guess I should take Alpha to coverage off.
If I have all of this stuff turned off, you can actually see.
This is what you know the game looks like.
Without multi sampling on, you can see that, you know, we were
definitely relying on the multi sampling tremendously because once you
start sorting everything with the z-buffer rather than your own sort
of manual versions of sorting, right?
You end up in a situation where
You no longer have the ability to just use Alpha as this thing that
magically works because the drawing order is now arbitrary, right?
Because you're letting the z-buffer, sort it and so everything like
you know, shadows and and out, you know, the edges of things if you
just throw things down in arbitrary order which we are, you then can't
use any of those effects properly anymore, right?
So you need some scheme to handle this and there's, you know,
No various ones you could do the multi sample, buffer is one of them,
but it has that really big drawback that I just pointed out, which is
that the alpha is only as many steps as multi sample buffer on this
card.
It was eight another cards.
It might be 16 but that's the mat.
That's as much as you're going to get in terms of alpha steps and of
course it costs that many to do.
So if you it costs you know, 16 samples you're actually shading those
samples.
So you know unless you switch to deferred rendering
Or something like this, you have to pay for those two.
So again it's you know, kind of pushes you towards having to deal with
more substantial stuff there.
So again like looking at this with the mother sample, buffer off, you
can see why it's like, okay, if depth peeling were to just work, we
could avoid the multi sample situation altogether and it would be
roughly 2x cost as opposed to.
So you need X cos now, that's not really a completely fair comparison
but it's sort of a fair comparison, right?
So yeah.
All right so let's take a look at how we're going to do that, right?
How would we do that if we turn all of this stuff off so we turn off.
Multi sampling, we turn off Alpha 2 coverage.
We turn off the switching of the Alpha 2 1 as it goes and we're just
like, all right, our only goal here, we're going to ignore the weird
flattery effect thing that I want to play with later.
And we're just saying, look, we really
Have some way of just fixing just the alpha compositing part of this.
How are we going to do it?
Well I threw in some stuff at the end of last stream.
But, I'll go over it again here.
It's just really, it's really basic but basically, you know, but what
I did is I said, well, okay, let's just make a version of our existing
Shader program that we had
And let's allow ourselves to pass in a Boolean that just says whether
we want deaf peeling on or not, right?
Because what what's going to happen here is we don't really need to be
comparing against the depth buffer.
The first time through, right?
Because the first time through, we're just going to draw the scene as
normal.
The only time we need to start looking at a secondary depth buffer and
incurring that extra cost of reading from a second death, bummer.
Is going to be the second time through when we need to peel away that
top bit.
So we have the ability to compile this two times now and we do compile
to X and the second time we compile it, we don't change anything about
the vertex Shader, right.
You can see the vertex Shader pretty much stays the same the entire
time.
But what you see here in the fragment code is that we've got a depth
peel section.
And what that death peel section does is says okay, why don't you do a
textile fetch?
Out of the depths texture that we're passing in here.
This new option for Deaf peeling.
And what I want you to do is I want you to check the fragment Z to
make sure that the fragment Z is actually going to be different than
the one that you recorded for that front pass.
Right?
And since we're only doing one depth feel here, we actually could make
that be not equal to but in order to set it up.
So you know if we
Decide to do three depth peels, for some reason we could use this
Shader, we want to basically keep being behind the one that we use the
previous time, right?
So what we're saying is any time the fragment Z that we were going to
use is closer to the viewer or at the same depth of the viewer of what
was already in our buffer.
We want to discard this, don't do any further work.
Sample from the fragment Shader texture that we were using before,
like the actual image.
Don't don't do any of that don't do the blend or do anything end right
now.
Yeah.
So that's it.
And that's all that we really did.
So now we have to do the rest of the work that's involved here and
it's a little bit more complicated, right?
Because now would we have to do is here's our render Loop, right?
This is the thing that actually pushes everything to opengl ugly as it
is because we don't have any texture packing here.
So, it's a pretty gross, right?
You can see that we've got this, these bitmap changes are just absurd.
A many and yeah, that is something that we probably will have to start
addressing especially with the step feeling.
We may be forced into addressing it.
We haven't had to address it because our frame rate still 60 frames a
second.
Even with doing these this may texture changes on a card that really
isn't capable of doing texture changes.
Very efficiently but yeah we'll see.
As we do the death peel that's going to double the cost of that,
right?
Which is
Is going to be expensive.
All right, so this is going to get more complicated now because what's
going to happen is this render Loop.
Now effectively has to operate in such a way as to sort of properly
prepare and Target these render buffers, right?
It has to be able to do, you know, multiple passes and those passes
have to work properly with the, you know, the the saving the original
Buffer.
And then setting up that debt by threats input for the next pass.
So we can kind of cheese this a little bit for now, like, there's ways
we could make this sort of a more virtuous if you will render system,
which actually encodes more logic into it, you know, more fanciness
into it.
But you know what, we can do for a Cheesy version of it is just have
some way of encoding essentially like a cheat, right?
Like something where we basically say, oh,
You know, here's the place in the render buffer that we're going to
start a group of things that gets rendered twice in this way and would
just put a marker and then another marker.
And that's like all you get, right?
So we're not going to try to do something fancy.
Like create, you know, some kind of a dependency graph where we're
like, okay, you know, here's all the stuff that needs to happen and
you can sort it out and figure out how you have to do it and we can do
kind of fancy stuff or we have many different passes and all that
stuff.
since we're just trying to figure out, if this effect is even worth
it, I'm going to do something more basic than
Right.
All right, so what I'm going to do here is I'm going to have something
and in fact, you know what, I could look at what I could do as well as
sort of like make something like this render group entry type
rendering tree depth, clear.
I can just make a couple of these right and maybe I'll sort of put
these up at the top because they're sort of a little Saucy ER in that
sense.
And I'm going to go ahead and change these.
To like render entry like begin, you know, peels or something like
this and end peels.
And so, one of the interesting things about this, right?
As you can see, we have the header and that's what we're iterating
over.
And so what we could do is just set a Boolean here and say, you know,
peel count or actually help, you know, just do a peel, count equals
zero.
And what I could do is say like okay when we're going to begin the
depth, feels what I need to do is save the like Pele header or, you
know, peel header restore.
Right?
And what I can do is when we get to render entry, begin peels, I can
just say well.
OK, let's save where we were in the command stream at that point.
Okay, then when I get to the end marker, what I can do is go, oh, all
right.
Well, if the peel count is zero,
Then that means I haven't done the depth of field yet.
So in here, I could do all of the state set up that I need for
restarting, right?
But if I have done the death peel yet then I don't really have to do
anything.
I can just let it fall through.
So when I come through or I'll add to the pill count and then let it
you know the next time it hits and peels it'll just fall through.
So basically what I'm doing is I'm creating a little jump.
Struction essentially, in our render buffer.
So I'm going through all the things to render.
When I hit the begin peel, I say, okay, this is the, this is like the
while loop location start, right?
I get to the end Peels.
And I'm like, Okay, jump back to where that was, do it again.
Do everything again.
And when I get to the end the next time I've looked at the increment
and go okay.
The incrementer now says that I've done as many deaf people's as I
want in this case, only one fall through and continue doing the rest
of the rendering like the debug HUD and stuff which isn't going to get
It depth peeled, right?
So when I hit the render entry and peels, what I want to do is say,
okay when I see that, I've I'm on that first peel.
So I have to re jump.
I'm going to set the header at to peel how to restore and that will
restart the loop, right?
That'll jump me.
To where I am.
And that should just work, right?
So looking at that.
We now kind of have to think about the other side of this, which is
what do we want to do in these two different death?
Peels because now we've got sort of two separate things that we want
to have happen.
And so what we're going to do here is we're going to say, well, you
know, substantively speaking really all we're trying to do is we're
just trying to produce a front buffer.
That's exactly the same as everything else that we've ever done.
Before just it's just a single rendered image that we're going to say
to the screen.
The only difference is we're going to track the alpha of that, right?
And since we've got that Z buffer on the alpha of that we're not you
know what?
I need diagram.
Right?
So all we're trying to do here is produce to pictures
Right, the front and the back picture.
Now the front picture is basically the same as what we've always been
drawing, right?
It's basically this.
The only difference between this and what we want to produce is we're
going to turn off the blending and in fact, you know what, let me just
do that so you can see what I'm talking about.
So here's our GL and able GL blend and here's our blend Funk where
we're saying, here's what we want, you put in, that's just going to go
away, right?
What we're going to say instead is no, you're not going to get to
blend.
There is no blending allowed.
Let me see here.
Jill blend.
Yeah, there's no blending allowed.
You don't get to blend, sorry for you and you're just going to write
the actual stuff.
The actual values that you have directly into the frame buffer and
store them, right?
If that out, will I do this?
Okay, so now what we can see is this is the actual front picture and
you can even see where there's like Alpha bugs in the source art,
right?
There's a pixel that's Alpha is is set to like, you know, 254 or
something like that, right?
But what you can see here is anywhere that the alpha isn't perfectly
zero.
We actually store the value.
And that includes things like, you know, the Shadow and the, the, you
know, the sort of alpha doubt softer pixels around.
The edge of the hero and blah, blah, blah blah, right?
But this is the front picture.
These are the front, most Sprite pieces that we can see.
And I've just turned off the alpha blending, so you can never
See anything behind the the front most color before we were seeing
Behind These colors, right?
Especially when the multi sample was on and proper.
We were seeing what was behind it.
Sort of alpha faded in, but here, we're just seeing that actual front
picture, right?
So, what we want to do is we just want to produce that, which
obviously we can't cuz I just showed it to you, right?
So that's just if we didn't change anything, that's what we're going
to get and that front picture, right?
Has, what is in the front and it actually has the color.
And the alpha value of what should be in the front and that Alpha
value may be very low.
It may be like one two, three four, right?
Other places is 255.
It's full, on other places, it's quite low and that's the front
bumper, but we no longer draw anything behind the front buffer in that
first pass, then in the back, we draw what's just behind it, right?
So again you know that Fringe that was right here for example, right?
You know that back buffer is going to have whatever was there in that
Fringe.
One step back.
Right.
And it's also going to have the alpha value, but in this case, we
can't do anything with that Alpha value because we can't draw anything
behind the back buffer.
If we did another depth Bill, we could write.
And so all we're going to do at the end right after we produce these
two images is we're just going to combine them together in a single
pass that just Alpha Composites them, it's going to read.
One thing from this image and one thing from this image and then blend
them together, right?
Just 100% straight forward.
Alpha blend of the two.
It's going to take the RGB from this and the Alpha from this and use
it to blend with the RGB of this.
And the alpha of this will get thrown away.
Now we could use the Alpha from that for something else and maybe we
will if we have some kind of effects, we can do that require some
forth.
Well, some fifth component right rgba and blah but we would only get
it on the back.
Buffer.
So unclear that that is really all that compelling.
Probably it's just a waste and we probably could even set that buffer
to just be RGB and not have it RNA.
If it turned out to somehow be faster on in different situations, all
right.
So, there you go.
That is what we are doing.
And so, let me go ahead and re-enable those and what we want to do
here, let me first go to the render group and I'll just sort of get
these, these sausage gentleman right here, didn't have a didn't have a
enums for them.
Here we go.
And so you know we're not using this at all yet, but this is just sort
of sketching it into place.
So what we can do here is the first time through, we should be pretty
much good to go, right?
So the first time we hit begin.
Pain pills.
Probably we can just leave all the state, the same because what we
want to do is exactly what's already getting done render to a frame
buffer and a depth, buffer ready to a frame buffer.
That's a color buffer and of depth buffer.
That's just the front most stuff.
And that is what should happen right here.
So, all we need to do now is swap that around, right?
When we hit the peel count and you know, we're going to need to do a
restore here.
So just insert
And he'll count equals 1.
We're going to have to now swap around when we jump back and render
everything.
A second time, we're going to have to fuss with the frame buffer,
right?
We're going to have to fuss with the frame buffer, and do a different,
a different operation here, right?
And so what we can probably say is, all right, there's the max render
Target index thing, and there's this sort of render group render entry
blend Target stuff.
We don't
We probably want to do that at the moment, right?
Because that was allowing us to program.
How this worked on the back end.
From the render group and what I want to do right now is just sort of
do it myself in here specifically.
So it's only doing one thing.
So I'm going to stub this out for now, right?
I'm going to say that we get to render targets.
They're going to be rendered, Target zero and rendered Target one.
And oh, sorry.
Ready.
Targets during intertwine.
That's a Mack sennett Target index.
Not account.
So 0 and 1.
It will create these for me, right?
And
I don't know if Global frame buffer count.
Excuse me, I'm pretty sure it creates one for each.
Yeah, it does.
So it's just going to create two frame buffers now and they won't be
multi sampled anymore and hopefully we can ditch multi sampling all
together, right?
So they won't be multi sampling anymore and then they'll get set up
and we'll be ready to go, right?
So now what I need to do is when I come through here, I need to switch
which frame buffer, I'm targeting
I need to bind a different frame buffer, right?
Then I would have otherwise
So let's jump through here.
You can see we never bind a framework because there's only one frame
buffer to bind at this point.
So, what I want to do is I want to essentially control that here.
So you can see.
All right, I'm going to do it.
Opengl buying frame buffer.
When I hit peel count equals 0.
That means I finished drawing the front frame buffer and now I want to
draw the back frame buffer.
I'm going to switch which frame buffer I'm looking at like so.
And then going to take a look at opengl bind frame, buffer here and
and say okay when you're done with that depth deal, I want you to go
back and do the previous, you know, draw on the front buffer again.
Now why do we have to draw the front buffer again?
Well, because the debug HUD and stuff like that, right wants to be
drawn only once.
Now I could draw it twice right but it's just a waste of our rendering
time.
So it doesn't seem like a particularly good idea to bother with that
we could and then we don't have to switch back to framers, but it's so
little cost for us to switch back.
It just doesn't seem like it's worth it, right?
So, I feel like we might as well to support that switching back.
Okay, and so the other thing I want to do is set a little thing that's
like peeling, equals true, or false and all that's going to be.
Here is the thing that says, oh okay, if we're peeling, you know, let
the rest of the code, no, because it's going to have to do potentially
some slightly different things.
Alright, so here we're targeting the two different frame buffers.
Like so, and what I want to do is I want to go down here to where we
actually do the rendering of quads.
And what we want to do here is say, okay, we used to be doing this,
this stuff here, where we allow the render Target to be picked per
quod, batch by the outer code.
So we can Target to render buffer server wants to.
And right now we're saying not anymore.
That's, that's not true.
Right.
So that code kind of goes by the wayside.
And instead, what's going to happen here is we're going to say, okay,
we know that the frame buffer will be bound properly.
We're not going to, we're not going to allow this code to do that.
We know that the frame buffer will be bound properly by the depth of
feeling code itself, right?
And similarly, what we probably want to do at the outset here, is just
make sure that we bind a frame buffer zero at the start because since
we're no longer doing that bind,
Elsewhere.
I want to make sure that we do it at least once.
Now if I do this in theory, I should still just get the same thing
because we don't, we're not using those depth peels anywhere.
So I should still see that front buffer and that's what I'm seeing.
So that's, you know, that's fine.
So now I come through here and I've got this render entry textured
quads situation going on.
And you can see how I'm loading the Z bias note that feel program.
And so, what I want to do here is I want to be able to switch which
program I'm using based on whether I'm definitely or not.
And furthermore if I am death peeling, I need to set that texture into
the second texture slot because
Now we doing that, right?
So if you take a look up here, where we have used program begin and
use program and you can see here that I've got sort of a texture,
sampler ID set to 0 here.
What I'd like to do is set this uniform
You can see here, we've got the depth, a sampler ID.
I want to be able to have a second texture that gets set in here and
I'm going to have to do that as well.
So I'm going to set the tip sampler to the second texture slot so that
we can set a the the depth buffer into that slot and read from it,
right?
So I'm going to go ahead and compile gear and run this and I just this
is exactly why I want to run it.
I want to see if it would give me an error so you can see here is
I believe in this what this complaining about at least, what I assumed
it would complain about and I want to check is that if there is no
depth sampler then you can't set it, right?
So in the case of when we compile this program and we look here, oh
well actually, you know what?
We never got that.
Let's try it this way.
We want to make sure that if we don't have depth sampling, we don't
get that are.
Okay?
So it looks like it's fine because it returned to sort of like a know,
like this is not a thing.
Okay, never mind that was just big slip.
I just want to make sure that that could get bound silently like that.
Okay, so we now have the ability, right?
Because we do bind the second texture unit and you know, you can kind
of see this GL, bind texture is not going to cut it anymore, right?
It's only
Finding one texture.
We're gonna have to buy into textures, but other than that, we're
pretty Home Free, right?
All we have to do is just switch this use program.
Begin end to go to the whichever one we're using.
Whether it's the no deaf peeled of the that feel.
And then we just have to bind to different textures.
One texture will be this one that actually does vary per quod that
picks the Sprite.
We want again in a very inefficient way that we're probably going to
have to address, which I really don't want to who but we probably will
have to
But the only other thing we're going to have to do is bind it, a
texture at the outset.
That's, that's going to be that, that, that depth texture, right?
So again, this should be pretty simple.
Let's go ahead and and grab that program.
So, here's opengl program.
And I'm just going to grab it like this.
And use it thusly.
I am that way.
In here I can just say, oh, okay.
Now I could just say, well, if we are peeling
Use the Z bias depth peel, otherwise use the no depth of field, right?
So now we know which one of these were using and we can switch
accordingly.
So the only other thing we need to do now is have the ability to read
from more than one texture.
And in order to do the do that, we need our multitexture, we need the
ability to.
I wanted the actual spec, though.
Well, you know, it's probably fine.
Famous Last Words.
The okay no it's not just need to show you the well, you know what?
It's it's so mainstream at this point it's going to be in here.
So let's let's, you know, let's yeah.
Let's take a look.
Is this?
Yeah.
Okay, so what I need to do now is well, I need to specify the texture.
And I need to be able to specify a texture for more than just the
texture.
2D I need to be able to specify it for multiple textures, and I don't
know if this actually covers it.
Let's see here.
I just want multitexture, please.
There it is.
That's what I wanted.
All right, so I believe if I'm not remembering incorrectly that the
way I have to do this in opengl is because you can't quite well maybe
buying texture unit would do it.
Yeah.
Okay, so buying texturing would do it.
I don't know what that's an opengl for though, so, I don't know that
we really want that.
Yeah, as usual, if you use the latest opengl, it has sensible API,
things.
Often times, but not so much in the past, so, okay, in order to be
relatively compatible, we got to do it this way.
So GL active texture is sort of a predicate that will allow us to sort
of briefly switch to using a different texture unit.
So we can say oh at the moment I want to be talking about texture unit
1, instead of texture units, 0
I will then do a buying texture on that, that will change, what's in
that unit, right?
And I guess in this case, I already know what it is.
So we can do that when easier and then a Switchback, right?
And I only need to do this if we're peeling.
So what I could even do here is sort of make this a coherent.
Like what do I do when I'm peeling kind of a loop loop
And that would be something that looks like this.
So we just assume we're doing no death beam that in.
If we are doing peeling, then we have to come through your use a
different program and bind a texture in here.
And then what I can also do is, if we are peeling, then I can go ahead
and on the way out.
Get rid of it.
And I probably should do that here just to make sure it's not left in
a slot.
There's not really a huge drawback to that but probably a good idea
not to write.
So we can we can really do this with only one additional call which is
this GL.
Active texture call which says, hey I'm targeting the second texture
set up.
Not the first one because I know the shooters going to read from slot
0 and Slot, 1 and off, you go.
So, GL bind texture.
In this case is just has to get that depth buffer.
And again, we know
The depth buffer is, it's whatever the whatever peeling were on and in
fact we could support multiple feel peeling pretty easily here if we
wanted to.
So here's our Global frame, buffer textures, right?
And for Global frame, buffer textures, we are.
Let's go through here.
Boo doo, doo doo.
We are storing the texture handle zero in there but we're not storing.
The Depths which we need.
Right?
So we need to keep that that depth handle because now that's a thing.
We actually want to pull from in addition to potentially the color
buffer as well, right?
So, now we have those two available and I can go ahead and grab it.
And, I know again that I'm grabbing from the zero with one.
Now, we could support sort of arbitrary peeling in this case, if we
wanted to, which maybe we do, because we don't really know yet.
But if we wanted to support more appealing, what we could also do here
is say, well, you know what, what we could really do is say whatever
the peel count is.
It's whatever that is minus 1, right?
Because we're on the peel, count one.
Then I kind of want to you
I want to get the the the depth of her from the previous, you know,
run through and we would keep going in that way.
So we can, you know, we could do it that way and that seems pretty
reasonable.
So this should bind the texture.
Use the different program produced that separate output, and in
theory, that's pretty much it.
That's an S.
There we go.
And all we need, is that GL, active texture call.
And so, what I want to do here is just grab that out into our set of
API things.
You've got.
In here.
So yeah, that's just this.
And I will go ahead.
Put it in there.
Let me also load it.
And that should be it.
Hopefully,
Did I not specify that correctly?
Oh, oops.
And so now, if I run it in theory again, nothing should change.
Unless we actually broke something, everything should be working fine
as the previous version was, because there is no actual
Nobody's inserting those markers into the stream so we're not ever
even calling the depth of feel at this point.
Okay?
Now we have one final thing that we're going to have to do in order to
see this at all.
But what I can do, right, is I can just to get an initial sense of
what's Happening Here.
What I can do is say, well, instead of going from Global frame buffer,
one in displaying that, let's go from Global frame buffer.
Or rather from zero.
Let's go from frame, buffer 1.
And if I go from Global frame, buffer one, you know, now we can see
what's in that back buffer.
Which is nothing.
Right?
So now, if I go ahead and add the depth peeling markers in, we should
now be able to look at our front buffer and back buffer and verify
that they're both getting drawn to roughly, what we would expect.
Then we can go ahead and do the final part that we need to.
Finally, see if this debt ceiling is worth worth anything or not,
which is right a Shader that just draws the screen.
One time as a giant quad, and when it does that, it will combine the
two Source frame buffers and you know, smoosh them together, right?
So it'll just smoosh.
And that would be it and then we'll be like, I don't know.
Was that worth it?
How did it go?
Did anyone care?
Nobody cared.
All right, so let's go ahead and go into the
World mode rendering here.
And what I want to do is when we actually do our entity rendering, I
want to bracket that in 2D rendering, you can see here it is.
We got update and render particle systems and simulate and and all
this stuff in here.
What I want to do is I just want to bracket this with with that render
and I don't know if we ever actually clear here.
I don't know who clears our who's supposed to clear.
It's one of those things where just like, I don't know.
Clears.
Yeah, you Claire.
So I want the clear to happen in both cases to the background color, I
think,
because if the background happened to show through it, you'd still
want the depth going to work properly.
So what I want to do is I probably want to do begin depth peel on the
render group here.
And then end up field down at the bottom.
What am I looking at?
Here we go.
And then in the render group itself, I just need the ability to do
these two things.
So you know,
real boring stuff.
I'm literally just putting these in there.
And that's it.
So now if we did anything correctly, we should well we definitely at
least bracket it properly because okay Jill active texture as Jerry an
error invalid enum.
Oh yeah, so that active texture is probably needs its own G.
Lem.
I don't know, I just kind of threw that in there.
Didn't even think about it but that's probably not the case.
Hold on a second.
Yeah, we have to use these special fancy texture enums here, right?
So I actually need to do it this.
I was being a little Cavalier there.
I actually need to do it like this because these are actually specific
enums that Target which texture you're talking about here.
So I need to cut and paste those from core are as well.
And those are just enums that apis, right?
Wow.
Have some texture units.
I don't think we're ever going to be pulling for more than four
textures.
I'm going to be conservative.
You can always cut and paste them more, I suppose, but I think that
will be quite enough for me.
Thank you very much for the for the option.
Okay?
So here we are looking at the depth peel.
And what it looks like to me, is it's sort.
Of working in once in some places, but it doesn't look like it's
working.
Others.
So if I look here, you can see that like the tops of the cubes are
properly cut off, which is what I would expect.
But like the hero for example, is not cut off, he should be right, I
should be seeing what's behind the hero, and I'm not seeing what's
behind the hero at the moment.
So it seems to me, like, maybe there's some kind of problem with
With this in terms of the depth comparison where I'm not getting it
reliably but I'm not 100% sure why.
Since we're should be sending down the exact same things, right?
And yeah, I don't know.
Hmm.
So that is a bit of a Puzzler.
How is it?
that in one case I'm properly comparing the depth, but in the other
case, I'm not
Right.
Because even if we had that
If we were doing some other things wrong, I'm not sure why we would be
able to see the hero because that should be the highest Z value.
It should not allow it to draw.
So, you know, we would expect to see like nothing there, something if
we like weren't drawing the other parts properly.
But
We actually are seeing something there.
So let's take a look and see if we can debug that.
I don't really know.
I don't have a good guess for what's going wrong there.
So, you can see that text will fetch from the depth sampler here.
The frogs eat, you know, what else I might want to do.
That's kind of fun.
Is we could draw the frag Z as well, which is kind of fun.
Let me, let me do this.
Oops,
what just happened?
All right.
Oh, that just re comments everything.
Okay, well anyway, so if I did text sample rgba equals
Frag Z.
And you know what?
I think it might be from negative 1 to 1.
I don't know.
So I'm just gonna just in, give myself a little.
Oops,
A little Insurance there.
I want this to replicate out to everybody but I'm not sure hoops.
How I would do that float champ.
Man, I wish you wouldn't do that.
Let's see, temp equals 0.5 up.
I don't know why it's commenting inside the string like that.
Why it's indenting things inside the string.
Because it should preserve strings but for some reason it isn't
anyway.
Undeclared identifier frag Z.
Ah, right.
And only if depth feeling is on sorry.
Here we go.
I feel it.
So maybe what I did before would have worked, I just wasn't paying
attention.
Wow, that is really interesting.
So what I'm doing now is I'm drawing the Z value right?
Of each of these things.
And I'm drawing the Z value course.
It's getting modulated by the by the alpha function.
So it gets darker as things Fade Out, which, you know, we wouldn't
want to do normally.
But what's interesting about this is, I don't understand why the why
the cubes still have color
Like how is that happening?
I guess it's because they actually have a color value that we modulate
on, that's why.
So, they have a color value that we actually modulate on here.
Hmm.
Alright, well let's play around a little bit here.
Go ahead and say, you know, let's we're looking at the back that peel
here, right?
And let me also just really quickly, oops.
Let me also just really quickly go here and take a look at the front
buffer.
So, the front buffer still looks correct to me.
Right.
And it still draws this stuff in there, right?
No, it doesn't have blending on.
so there's that, but
This still all looks correct.
So it's only our depth peel, that isn't quite right.
And what's weird about it is rather than being completely wrong.
It's sort of, right?
And it's sort of right in a truly puzzling way.
It seems like everything with a texture.
Is wrong.
And everything with the white texture.
Which is still a texture.
It's just the white texture is correct.
like if you look and you if you look in there, you can see
That, for example, even the hitboxes are correct.
Like, the hitboxes are drawing.
What's underneath the hitboxes?
Not the hitboxes.
And I don't know what's going on here, like that tree just just
flicked from being correct, to being incorrect.
did you see that if it is if it wasn't weird enough,
So I really have no idea what's going on there.
That is just pure mystery to me.
I mean, I guess one question would be, are we accidentally drawing all
of our Sprites twice?
Which doesn't seem likely.
And I guess by twice, I mean, more than twice like four times, right?
/, / twice per peel.
Give me.
Cuz that would explain it, but I don't think we are.
Are you never do know.
So let's think about this.
How can I go about constructively to bugging this?
so, I guess one thing I can do here,
is say that well,
Well, you know a my properly.
Am I properly setting which texture unit to go?
To would be one thing.
Because let's say so here's an example that I could test.
So here, you know what, if this had to be the GL texture, enum and not
the integer, right?
And I'm just grasping at straws here because I don't have any way to
debug it, really.
This is where you would definitely want to be using.
A graphics card that had a debugger.
Let's just see because changing that the depth sampler idea to be
sampling from the color buffer instead should have a potential effect
here, right?
Let me just make sure I'm still drawn from the right place.
Yeah, so I just want to make sure that we get a different result in
those two cases where, you know, if I if I go from the color buffer,
if I sample, The Depths and the depth samples from the color buffer, I
should get a different result and I do.
So that's at least.
Reassuring it suggests, at least a little bit.
That were probably changing what we're sampling from although I guess
I don't know that for sure.
It could be that we change from sampling from something to sampling
from nothing.
Not from the correct buffer so I guess I don't really know that that's
the case but I at least suspect now that that is the case, right?
All right, so the next question would be well.
Okay, so we don't know anything about how this depth buffer is stored
though, right?
Because, you know, I'm just I'm sampling from the depth buffer but
Do I know that the GL frag chords e value in this case is actually
stored in the same fashion as Texel.
Fetch from a depth buffer will return because it may well not be
right.
So I kind of need some information about what will happen with Texel,
fetch on a depth buffer.
What values do I get back?
And I don't know.
This seems like it could be a reasonable source.
So that's updated that's looking at the frag depth.
Which maybe I should be looking at.
Let's take a look at how it's documented.
The averroes you steps to death value for the current fragment.
If death organ is enabled and no shit eraser gel fact that the fixed
function value for definitely.
Use the values contained in the Z component of jail free card.
So that is what we're using the value written to Jeff artists is used
if a Shader, should set a CLIA signs 2gl frag depth than the value of
the fragment?
Then the value of the fragments depth may be undefined for executions
of the Shader that take that path.
That is, if the set of like Furniture start.
Yeah, okay.
But what, yeah, can you GL
Depth or maybe GL.
Depth texture value.
I just need something.
The talks about it.
Yeah.
So I mean, here is just what I'm thinking, and I would like some
documentation on this, just so I know what to expect, but my thinking
was just that, well, if the frag cord, .z was between negative 1 and
1, but the depth that we fetch from textile,
Between zero and one.
I don't know that that would really produce the artifacts were seeing
but, you know,
It would be wrong.
Anyway, in order to look at that.
Right?
What we would want to do here is say oh yeah.
You know, when we when we fetch a Texel or maybe when we use the frag
Z what we want to do for the frags you say well okay, you know,
Add 1 to it, to bring it to 0 to 2 and then divide it by half to bring
it to zero to one and then maybe now that's in the correct space,
right?
Because again what I don't know is Texel fetch knows about the
underlying format of the texture.
It knows it's a depth texture.
So what comes back from the depth texture could be different depending
on the circumstances?
I don't know what
Specifying right now.
As far as the format for that.
But it's not a floating-point format.
And so you know, it could be that that's just it's getting packed into
the zero to one range and then when you text will fetch, it's not
going to do that.
I don't know, right?
I really don't know what's going to go on there.
What I could do to is, I could maybe say that I want this to be a
floating-point depth, buffer.
You know, maybe I could say that.
And then in theory,
Right.
It should give me back the actual same floating point value that got
stored to it, which should have just been the frag Z, I believe, don't
quote me on this.
But yeah, no, still nothing.
So that's really strange.
I'm not sure it's very weird and it seems to be oddly very accurate.
For those cubes.
So it is just something with the Sprites and I just have no idea why
that would be the case.
I'm literally stumped as to a plausible explanation, which is tough
because it means I don't know where to investigate,
I suppose on handmade hero since the the main character has no arms or
legs saying stumped, is kind of weird.
But anyway, so yeah, I really just don't know.
I do not know what the most likely culprit would be there.
What I think I'll probably do is go make the compositing Shader
because we know we have to do that.
And then tomorrow, I guess we'll be the day where we try to figure out
what's going wrong with that deaf people because it's so close to
working.
The other thing I would like to do is I'd like to turn on culling
Think it's or is it?
Yeah, because what you'll notice is, if we temporarily, let me just go
ahead and draw the main front buffer.
if I go ahead and
Draw the main buffer.
One thing you can see is that when we when we look, when we clip away
parts of the cubes, we see the back faces of parts of the cubes, which
we don't really want to do in this case, right?
And so if I instead turn on back face culling, but back face culling
does, is it just says, hey, if a face is pointing away from the
camera.
We don't want to draw it and so I could do that for my cubes.
And then we wouldn't draw those faces right?
And that would be handy.
Now, it looks like me GL.
It looks like it did.
I wind my faces backwards.
Jill, coal face.
And so, we want to do is we want to call back faces.
And then we need to do front face to specify which ones they are and
counterclockwise, but that should have been the default.
Oops.
That's right.
There we go.
so,
That is relatively.
Disturbing.
Because if you think about what that means, it means that everything
in the game is wounded backwards.
Right.
Like everything.
Because I wanted all of the outward faces of the cubes to be
counterclockwise wound.
So I guess that means that the way that weird.
Oh, and I know why it's because we're doing try strips.
Right now.
And the try strips are going to change the winding.
Of the quads, I suppose.
So how did we
Here's our push quad.
And I feel like in general if we had wound these properly we should
have gotten clockwise wounding on them, right?
Because I believe
So if we had done P0, P1 P2 P3, then in theory, doing a try strip of p
0 p, 3, p, 1.
P 2 should have been front-facing
That would have been my assumption.
However,
that is not what I'm seeing.
Now, if we wanted to do a push quad,
so like, for example, here in push bitmap,
Here is the push quad.
You can see me doing Min Min, Max min max max min, max.
So that's the exact same sort of quad order.
So that should be wound properly.
I would think but that's definitely not.
We're seeing.
So we have actually two nasty problems here.
One is, we don't know why the peelings working and the other is that
that we don't know why our faces are wound in properly.
Right?
But that's really bad.
That's like right cuz there's there's no question that that should be
wound properly.
So I'm very nervous now because I have no idea why it wouldn't be
around the correct way and I can't you know that's like it's getting
mirrored or something in there.
So I'm just going to test a couple things here, but yeah, that's
That's really bad.
So here the GL drawer raised call with GL triangle strip.
That's drawing these vertices as they are.
I would be interested to know if I switch to GL quads just quickly and
I can do that.
If I'm incompatibility context, not core context, but I have to switch
that because we'll get an error here.
If I don't since since that's not allowed, that makes sense.
So let me go back to the win32 mode.
And let me switch it.
What did you just do?
Did I not just?
I said, compatibility did I not?
What am I missing here?
If one profile Mass carb is contact, compatibility profile, bit are
not core.
Right.
I'm definitely specifying compatibility profile bit in the win32
opengl at ribs.
So does someone want to tell me why?
It thinks it's a core context.
It's not a core context.
What's going on here, folks?
Things are getting Stranger by the second here on handmade hero.
I'm specifically asking for a compatibility profile and yet it claims
its opening quarter.
Context, I guess, it has no obligation to do so.
Right.
But still, like I would be surprised if it couldn't.
I mean, we're not in this Branch, are we?
Right.
So it's it is using the other branch.
And so somehow, even though we're asking for one, we can't get one.
Well, I guess so much for that test.
We really need to get him new machine something with their graphics
card we can actually test on.
All right, so that's not going to be particularly helpful.
So let's go ahead and try GL triangles because then at least I can
specify the order directly.
So here in render group, what I'd have to do is I'm going to have to
draw only just one triangle from each set that I would have drawn
before.
But what are you going to do, right?
So what I'll do here is just say like okay let's go ahead and draw.
P0 P1 P2 as a triangle.
And ignore this, this Final in here, right?
Like so.
Yeah, okay.
So I have at least confirmed that we are winding our triangles
correctly.
It's just the triangle strips.
I was out, putting the triangle strips must be backwards.
That's not so bad.
Let's go ahead and fix that and they probably there's just some weird
requirement about how the triangle strips have to go.
So let's take a look.
Show me the documentation, okay so it's the problem is it starts at
the top and goes down.
Looks like it's v-0, V1 V2, right?
Then be 3.
So it's dude to dude.
So in order to do that we have to start it at 3 because that was our
top one, then go down to zero.
Then go up to two and then come down to one.
So now we should actually get that coloring to work properly.
And it looks like it actually now is so that's good, right?
So now we're seeing our only front faces.
And so now when we click through like so you can see that we don't get
those back faces.
Which is good.
That's what I wanted, right?
I wanted those to be
those to be invisible.
Okay, so you know, that's all fine.
It doesn't really help us with our main problem, but I just wanted to
get that out of the way and so we're still at this point, where we
have
Sort of this this weird issue where, okay, yeah, you know, there's
there's drawing exactly what I think should be drawing everywhere
where we're using a white texture and everywhere we're using a
texture, that's not white.
Somehow somehow it does the wrong thing.
So I guess you know, let's
Let's take a look at the Shader and see.
So if I look at the Shader, you know,
I guess if you take the texture sample,
And the texture sample.
Actually like, how could that possibly be affecting it?
I really just do not know.
I also wonder if I can get for a coder to indent this for me.
In some way.
I guess not.
Hmm.
Yeah, I don't know.
I'm going to probably have to ruminate on that one.
So I'm going to go ahead and do the work that I can do now and then
we'll have to come back to that and figure out why that's not working
using something clever.
I'm just not sure what.
So what I need to do now is just have another one of these little
compiled dudes, right?
This one's going to be a lot simpler.
Here we go.
So in this case, I don't really have the deaf peel bit anymore.
Look, so although I could actually just keep this symmetric because I
guess it doesn't matter.
So maybe that's a better idea because maybe we can sort of make that
more generic.
In fact, what we could do is just put this format string on the
outside which is kind of interesting as well.
Or something like that but you know, for now we'll leave it.
So the header code since its standard for everybody, I want to kind of
Loft that out.
So I want to say like, okay, this is the global Shader header code.
And that's never going to change.
So instead of, you know, passing header code here,
we'll pass Global Shader header code.
Double Shader header code.
so we have the ability to do the Z bios program compile and now we
need
the heel composite.
Compile feel composite.
And yeah, so this is going to be much simpler.
The vertex code in this case is pretty much going to do nothing
because we don't actually need to transform it.
We have like essentially no inputs other than just a straightforward
vertex position, which we will then use directly.
And so the UV is the only other thing we need.
So I think we're literally talking about this, right?
So z l position.
Oops.
I deleted one too many things there.
We go.
Oh no I didn't.
It's still got the photography at, never mind.
So we're going to take in a Vertex position and we're just going to
write it directly to the output.
We're not gonna do anything to it.
So we're going to assume that we just get handed the correct things.
Why?
Because we're just going to draw a single full screen quad.
It doesn't get transfer by anything.
We just need to composite are to peel layers together, right?
So
Same is true for the frag movie.
We're just going to pass it directly through.
Nothing else to do, right?
Did I delete the very v as well?
Yeah, I did.
So, I did delete one too many things.
Here we go.
So we're literally just to pass through all the rest of this stuff
doesn't happen in this mode.
So it's literally just like taken the inputs and assign them to the
outputs that the only thing that's going to do, then we have the
fragment code.
And the fragment code only has to do a very simple thing, which is
pulled the two textures and blend them together so it doesn't need any
additional information, right?
It doesn't need anything else.
Other than just the thing that it's drawing,
And and that UV coordinates to pull from right?
And even the UV coordinates actually.
Now I think about it, we don't really need UV coordinates because
they're going to be
Well, okay, so I'm going to leave the UV coordinates in there.
And the reason that I'm going to leave the UV coordinates in there is
because if I don't leave the UV coordinates in there, like let's say,
I just drew a full screen quad and I made that the fragment code
generate the UV to look up or even, don't even use it.
You vlookup, it did a textile Fetch and just use the fragment
coordinate in screen space to fetch into the textures.
That would work just fine.
If I never wanted to scale,
All right, but maybe I want to use this Shader as the final scaling.
Shader to likes musher stretch the image to better fit the screen or
something, right?
Or to do letterboxing, or who knows what?
So, I'm going to leave the frag UV in there and I'm going to actually
do the textile fetch.
Using actual UVS.
I don't have to do that, but I'm going to do that.
So that I could get by linear upsampling, if I wanted to.
So, actually, this is just like he'll 0.
And peel one.
And yeah.
So in this case I've got pl0 pill 0 and peel one.
I'm going to sample them both from the same UV because again, I'm just
compositing them together.
And then, what I want to do is I want to Output a shaded color.
So in this case, if we don't have srgb, I have to again.
Emulate it, right?
So let's go ahead here and see if I've got Shader semtex read.
So, a couple of other things I'm thinking about will get those second.
So I do want to still simulate this, right?
So I want to square on the way in, if I don't have that normally
And screw it on the way out.
Because I only need to do one.
I don't need discarding.
At least, not yet.
And so now all I should have to do is say well, the first peel and the
second po.
So in this case I've got a kind of a choice about which PL.
Let's number them the way we would number them.
So appeal 0 is the first is the frontmost thing.
So we want to do is take the alpha of Peel 0 and use that to blend
with the the thing that's behind it.
Now we might as well just use the actual premultiplied Alpha properly
here.
So we might as well.
Pre multiply the alpha of this thing we're blending.
So what I want to do is say well okay I don't really need to lerp in
that case.
I'm going to add peels peel zero directly.
So the only thing I really need to do is just take one - its Alpha
value.
And multiply that by peel one, right?
So all I'm going to do is I know I'm going to use the full
contribution from peel 0 because I know that it's already been
modulated by its own Alpha, right?
Because that's how we had it set up.
That's all we have everything set up.
So, what I want to do is now take the background peel and I want to
turn off that Alpha darkening for it and then just I'm just going to
use a final composite that just one - that that Alpha four of the
front peel to pull in as much of that background color as I should
based on how far I can see through it.
Right?
And that's all I should really need to do.
I think for the compact for the peel composite,
Now, the peel composite doesn't have most of these things, right?
It's got peel, sampler, one or sorry, peel.
Zero.
Sampler.
And peel one sampler, like so and it's got the view the UV P.
It's got well,
I can still query these but they'll just get bound to nothing's, which
is probably fine.
So, all of, that's fine.
And now I will have a program that actually does this.
This composite for me and which I can call it the end to bring the two
shaders together to bring the two depth peels together.
And so what I can do is I can call that and basically make a thing
here.
And now I've got a third Shader, that's does nothing other than that
one.
That one operation.
Global Shader.
Heather copes.
I got a capital l there.
And this should be compiled, he'll composite.
And so now I've got that one in and if there's any errors here, it'll
tell me Undeclared, identifier GL position.
That's not good.
There we go.
Okay.
Let's try that more time.
There we go.
On it.
If I'd identifier Undeclared identifier result color.
I agree with you.
We did not declare that and we should have, let's grab that again.
Yeah.
Alright, so now we have the ability to composite the to depth Peels
and so what we want to do is have a place where that actually gets
done and that is, you know, going to be right here at the end.
So previously what we were doing is binding, frame buffers and
bleeding from the flamebook frame buffer using the split.
The reason we were doing it that way was just because we already had
to do.
We knew we had to do a blind in order to resolve our multi samples.
And since we're not multi sampling anymore, we can sort of say, okay?
This is no longer the way that we do, our final draw to the screen, so
we still do want to set.
Drawing frame buffer to the screen but now what we want to do is more
of a used program sort of a situation, right?
So what we want to do here is say okay, let's go ahead and use that
program Open Jill.
Peel composite.
So now we'll like have a use program.
Begin and end as before and we need to do the active texture stuff as
well.
Same way.
Oops, what happened there?
And so, what I want to do here is I want to be able to bind these two
textures.
I want to.
Instead of pulling from the depths, like I was doing for, I want to
basically pull from the to peels the actual color values.
I don't care about the depths anymore.
And then I want to you know I probably still want to do this deal
viewport call to get the draw regions set properly.
And then what I want to do is I want to just output a single triangle
strip that occupies the entire screen, right?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to do the exact same thing I was
doing here.
In terms of like the buffer data and vertex, dreaming, and all that
stuff, except what I'm going to do is we're going to point it out of
buffer that is just a hard-coded buffer of four vertices that are
exactly the screen size big, right?
So, this textured vertex thing we've got here.
With puv color.
So I know that it's p UV color, the color in this case is irrelevant,
it doesn't get used.
And here I need to Output that try strip.
And so what I need to do to Output the try strip is I need to since
I'm not doing any kind of a mapping from from anything to anything
here, I'm literally just passing raw values down.
I know that it's going to want clip space as the output, right?
And I'm not doing a transform.
So I know that I'm going to start at negative 1 on my far side, right?
And I know I want to be at the top,
We're doing a try strip.
So I know that I'm going to do - 110 I didn't get to go to the bottom
of the screen.
Right.
See what I'm getting at here, I then got to go over.
And again.
Similarly, now I've got the UVS so I now know that, you know, I'm at
the left side top, right?
That's going to be 0 1 for the UVs.
Then I'm in the left side, bottom.
And then do the same thing, but over one.
So basically I can just pass this directly down to the buffer data
like so.
Any Theory, everything else here should work, right?
And let me go ahead and put that up before I use the program, there we
go.
We'd be saying here too few Arguments for call.
How many arguments did you want for the call?
Haha.
Miss my stream, embrace my hint, my usage hint.
There we go.
So now in use program, begin that takes that setup thing.
And I don't really have one of those.
So I want to see what that's actually used for.
So you can see it.
Sues for setting like a bunch of parameters, we don't care about in
the Shader.
So in theory, I should be able to just say hey, there's a render
setup.
It's not going to do anything by the way.
And in this case, we're just drawing the first four things, so that
should be it.
Alright, so, in theory, now, if we debug this, we should be able to do
our final composite
Invalid by.
Okay, so it looks like what happens here is when we don't have a
Vertex array of a particular type, we are not allowed to specify that
right because what it's complaining about here is, you know, we don't
have a color array on this one.
And so, it's complaining about the fact that we don't have a color
array, and it can't set that vertex to trim pointer.
What I might do here, just to make it a little easier on ourselves
since we don't care.
If they all right, fine, you do get a color.
If you really wanted a color so badly, you can have one and you know
maybe we use it to tent the screen or something, we could come up with
an excuse for why that might be the case.
Just so we have less variability in here.
Is literally the only reason I'm doing this because I could go check
the value as well.
Etc.
So all I'm going to do in here is when the frag color comes in.
All I'm going to do is say well, alright, let's do frag color times.
So it's a modulation if you want additional modulation on there, you
got one so then I'll say oh okay, you know, you've got an inn before
Frog color.
I just burped color.
Smooth out before.
Red color.
And in this case, I'm just going to pass it directly through.
So then what I need to do is just make these so they actually do have
all white because at the moment, I don't actually want to change the
color and then we'll see if that takes care of that.
Are 132 parse error on in.
I must have been sloppy with that there.
Let's take a look.
Yep, just forgot a semicolon.
Philip, I'll just a fragment Shader field compared with the following
are wrong, operand types, no operation Stars.
This takes a left hand type of smooth and quote, Vector for, and okay.
So that's a 3 & A 4 problem, fair enough?
All right.
So now what we're actually seeing
I guess in reality even is, we are now actually seeing the real
The real result of the composite even.
It's not correct.
But we are actually seeing it draw, right?
Because we don't have a frame buffer blind anymore.
So we are actually doing this this draw and we are actually seeing it
come out, which is nice.
We're binding, texture, 0 and texture one here.
Oh, I've got these backwards.
This is texture one that's texture 0 and we've got a little bit more
work to do here but we'll take a look at that in a second.
So we have to go fix that.
I don't know why, that, that should have changed.
The fact that the switching, these didn't make any difference as a
little disturbing to me in a day, full of disturbing things.
so, let me just go do one thing though that I wanted to do before I
forget,
Which is if you look what's happening here, you can see, we've got
this disabled GL blend happening here.
And, you know, the, the, the blend Funk is assuming that that everyone
already has been pre multiplied by whatever their Alpha value is,
right?
And so, I just want to make sure that that's actually going to work
properly.
So when people actually draw with
With the depth of feeling stuff.
I want to make sure that they're actually going to produce the correct
color.
So if I take a look here at
like, if you look at the fragment code here for when we're drawing you
can see that we pass through the the alpha but the RGB
Value.
Let's just make sure by frag color.
So you can see that we are properly modulating all of the colors by
the frag color but not necessarily by the alpha, right?
So,
Just looking at that.
That seems to be incorrect, right?
Like the texture sample that's being written out here, Alpha value
wise, when I, when I pull in a texture sample, the alpha value, the
RGB of the texture sample is going to be properly, modulated.
But the fragment colors Alpha,
I, I don't know if it actually is right.
I assume it is if it is then it's okay.
As long as this frag color is properly.
Modulated, then we're okay if it's not, then we're not.
Now the problem that we then face is if we are depth peeling.
We want the back most depth that's, you know, it's not going to get
pulled in.
Nothing behind is going to get pulled in.
We don't want it to be darkened, by its Alpha value.
We want it to still be Fulbright because we're never going to draw
anything behind it.
So even if it was Alpha, we don't want it to be any more Alpha than
that, right?
So I don't know what the best way to do that is probably the best way
to do that, I guess is to just handle it here.
So basically what we do is when we pull in the peel, one that were
sort of
Going behind, we want to undo the alpha fade on that right.
We want to basically say hey Pele 1s, Alpha value.
We want to undo, you know, previously we had done this to it.
We done like the red channel, right?
Like if we imagine what the red channel is,
We wrote out the red Channel times the alpha value, but we just want
to actually use the unadulterated red, but we only have this.
So, if we want to solve for this, in terms of this, right?
We just divide both sides by a.
So we have our Prime over a equals R, right?
So given that we want to do is do something like, oh, okay, we've got
An inverse, a equals 1 over a.
Now, a might be 0 is the only tricky part and if a is zero then
there's really nothing we can do because there's no way to get the
value back at all and yeah you know it shouldn't have drawn.
So in theory we shouldn't ever really see that except in the pretty
pretty much ever but we can if we want to try to work around that as
well, and just say
Inverse a equals, you know, 0 and if he'll one a is greater than zero.
Then in verse a equals 1 over, I basically just the safe divide right.
Then what we want to do is say all right, the peel one color that was
in coming for us, right that RGB.
I just want to multiply it by its inverse Alpha so that will undo that
that fade that would have been on it and that's the end of it.
All right.
So that's it.
That's where we're pretty much out of time.
So we have a lot of divulging to do because there's some strange stuff
going on and really wish I had a GPU debugger.
I don't on this card.
Can't do it.
It's too old.
But you know, that's just where we're at.
I do want to do a quick check here for result color.
I want to set the red Channel, 21, always just to make sure we're
actually seeing what we think we're seeing.
It doesn't look like we are so it looks like we're still kind of for
whatever reason here.
So something's up, right?
Because we should be seeing a red screen at this point.
If we were actually using this this peel composite Shader.
So when we're getting to the end here, it's unclear to me how we're
seeing this Frame.
Buffer zero here.
So something's very strange and maybe this has to do with what we're
seeing as well.
I don't know.
So, let's see what's going on here.
Are we not creating our frame buffers consistently?
Let's see.
So if we do an opengl bind frame buffer,
And we get out the global frame buffer handles can see in theory.
We should always be drawing to one of those and never drawing to the
screen.
Right?
So if I come in here and say Max render, Target index is 1.
And I've going to do these two, I'm going to go through and the global
frame.
Buffer count is should start out at zero, right?
And in fact, let's just make sure that this is actually the case by
stepping into it, because I guess there's no sense in just assuming,
So now we're going to generate two frame buffers, right?
So here is the first frame buffer.
Sector seven and texture eight.
Did we already do the global frame buffer handles Parts?
Where did we generate Jill?
Jen Frame buffers.
New count is one.
That is incorrect.
That is totally, totally wrong in all possible ways.
Totally wrong in all possible, ways, ladies and gentlemen, that is so
wrong.
Totally wrong.
And that is probably part of the reason.
There are other thing wasn't working either.
Much better.
Now, we're getting actual problems that we should have seen.
Okay, good, let's quickly go back to what I was doing before where we
were bleeding.
These two,
And now, let's see what we actually see.
So, here's what's in frame buffer 0?
And that does look like what I want to be in frame by 40 and now let's
look at what's in frame buffer.
One
And that is lovely.
That is exactly what I wanted to see in frame by 41.
Happy day.
Happiness is of special deliciousness, right?
You know what I'm saying to you?
Look at that.
That's gorgeous.
Perfect, wonderful.
So now, all we actually have to do tomorrow is do this Shader
properly, which probably won't take too long, because it's very simple
and then we will have finished our deaf feeling for now, I will go to
the question and answer.
A brief question-and-answer.
Sasa superb.
I tend to see a lot of apis.
For example, sdl things like destroy window calls, if this is the last
thing you do before, exiting the app, doesn't the operating system.
Take care of this for you.
Yes, it does.
But of course, you know, you need
Sometimes the ability to when you're not exiting the app close and
reopen window or open two windows and then close one of them later or
stuff like this.
So you know you don't need if you're actually exiting then no, you
don't need to close your window.
But if you're not as exiting and you need to close the window for
another reason, that's why those apis exist, I don't know which part
of sdl you're talking about there or whatever.
But like for example, if you're just
Can white sdl has the ability to shut down the window.
Well, you know, maybe your game created a window on one Monitor and
was like drawing some stuff, but then wanted to close it down and open
it on a different monitor or something.
Or, you know, it detected that the user asked it to switch from full
screen to windowed and wanted to close the window and open a new
window to do that.
Who knows?
Right.
There's lots of reasons you could have.
Del Conte, have you considered keeping the Shader code as separate
files so you can do automatic reload on Save and the editor, for
example, or do you think there won't be enough Shader code to motivate
the work?
Yeah, I don't know.
Like
I don't didn't anticipate doing much Shader code, so I don't really
know how much will do, but at the moment we haven't had too much
trouble with that.
So it's not super worth it.
Keeping them in separate files.
I don't think I would do that.
Anyway, since we already have like full Kobe loading, I'd probably
just move the shaders into something that just happened.
When we recompile that way, you get a recompile and your Shader code
and your stuff around the Shader code.
Both happens like keeping shaders in separate.
Files is kind of weak sauce, right?
Because that only reloads the shaders, whereas I would rather have the
whole thing work since we already have that for the other part of it.
But yes, so why were we not seeing anything?
With this guy, here's the vertices.
Is the depth.
We want to get Jill to save all the depth test here though, right?
Not that there should have been any depth testing.
It's weird that we don't see anything at all.
all right, so we know that we're at least seeing
that the viewport is act is actually set correctly.
So what we're not sure about is ygl.
Draw arrays is busted.
Probably should set the scissors as well.
But I can't say, I know why.
Anything else would be wrong.
I said, why don't I just disable scissor?
Then I set it at all.
It from bit.
I think your last heart could have giant triangle ship UV mapping
credit has a cut-and-paste bug that may well be true.
Yes, it does.
Thank you.
Unfortunately, I don't think that is enough to save us.
Hope it was but it's not.
Yeah.
By the way, it was pointed out that the compatibility B only works in
3.2 and I think it says 53.0, okay?
So that's why it wasn't there.
But off topic, but why?
Is not the Jeff and Casey show season 5 on my rocket website.
I haven't had time to really clean that stuff up.
So yeah.
We're correctly.
Drawing to the front frame buffer.
We're reading from those two textures.
But I ain't seen anything.
And I don't know why.
But I'm definitely not case anyone was wondering.
Because we should just see bright red, right?
Anywhere that this thing is drawing anything.
I don't know if it's possible that it's getting cold if I wound it
wrong.
Still no.
If it couldn't get front clipped.
I don't see how because it's going to pass this Z value directly
through.
It really shouldn't be in pixels.
Because it's not going through any kind of transform.
Yeah, I do not know why we see nothing.
It's bizarre.
What if I use a different program?
One of our programs busted or maybe.
I'm misremembering.
What I would need to do to do a pass-through program.
what happens if we just like,
Donuts, you know I'm saying?
Presumably nothing.
We're just not getting anything out of that Shader.
All right, well at least we got our death pills working.
Daniel Colin I was told that you had some issues with rendered talk
to, you know, if it was related to you having an old GPU, or was it a
real bug and render doc?
Well, I guess I don't know what you're referring to exactly the bug.
We had on stream, trying to use render doc, I think was just because
it's too old because the graphs cars too old.
I assume I don't really know.
I mean, I have no idea when render dark doesn't work.
I don't know.
Why it doesn't work, right?
I just know that it doesn't work.
So so I'm not 100% certain I assume that it's just too old but it
might be something else as well for all I know, I do know that I've
never really successfully gotten rid of dark to work except on one
machine like a, my laptop.
It doesn't work to you to use the Intel.
Yeah, like I can't use the the Intel chip.
I can't use it with the Intel chip.
Don't think I've ever been able to use it with is the one Nvidia card.
So my main demoscene, I've never been able to get using anything else
and that doesn't mean it doesn't work on other things.
Just I haven't been able to
Could you view in the debugger and see if the Shader output sensible
values?
No, because we don't have the ability to step through Shader.
That's would be nice if we had an Insight, you know, if you're running
inside or something, we could but we can't.
So the moment we're flying a little bit blind, such a superb in the
future.
When John was language is released for public in case, it will be for
handmade hero, completion.
Will you switch to use for finishing unfinished parts of the game?
Or would you stay with C++ to The Bitter End?
Well yeah, I mean I'm not going to switch languages mid-project that's
nuts.
All right.
Think that is it?
Let's go ahead and close it down.
Thank you everyone for joining me for handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pair to the game on handmade hero dot org and it comes to the source
code so you can play around with it.
We also have a forum site, you can go to if you want to ask questions
a patreon page, if you want to support the video series and a schedule
about the Tells going to be live and an episode guide for catching up
on old episodes in the series, that's it for today.
We'll be back tomorrow and an unusual time.
I can't remember exactly what time.
In fact.
That's one of the good reasons for checking.
The schedule bot.
Let's see what it says.
3:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow, which point we can debug the deaf
peeling composite.
Which I think is the only problem now because the depth peels, when I
looked at them individually looked about, right?
So that's about it.
Thanks for joining me and hope to see you back here tomorrow, till
then have fun programming and I'll see everyone on the internet.
Take is everybody.