Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The sure we could complete game live on stream today.
We are having sort of a special event on the stream.
First, I will be doing the regular episode of handmade hero where we
will be doing some coding in.
This is actually going to be some pretty.
I feel like this is going to be some fairly instructive coding for
people who are interested in code architecture.
I think we're going to be doing some interesting things today.
Just in terms of, like, sort of showing how some code Transformations
work and stuff like that, so I hope you'll enjoy that.
And then after the stream at about 8:30, basically, whenever the
stream is over.
So after the Q&A, we will be going to a special like a mock debate
between myself and Sean McGrath, you probably have seen some of his
work.
He actually just recently was one of the main guys, on N plus plus the
PS4 and he is,
During doing a free-to-play game as his next game, and he is a little
apprehensive about free to play as I guess.
He is, he is not completely sold on the concept.
Perhaps I should say our baby, he feels a little uneasy about it and
he wanted to try to have a public discussion in the form of a debate
where I'm sort of taking the The Devil's Advocate position to all of
the reasons why he is thinking that this might be a good idea for him.
So I tried to prepare some some interesting points for him.
To think about and we'll see how that goes.
But I'm relatively excited for.
I think it would be pretty interesting and I'm also kind of interested
to hear his perspective on it because I honestly don't know that many
people who think free-to-play is a good idea.
But also our apprehensive at like it's he sort of he's obviously very
aware of the problems of f2p but still thinks that maybe it's the
right decision and so that sounds to me like a more interesting
position for me to hear about and explore than the standard people are
just like
Capitalism itself, whatever it doesn't matter.
As long as people buy it, it's fine, right?
Or whatever, like sort of the the more traditional f2p Zing geryon
position on these sorts of things.
So, I hope you'll join us for that again.
You shouldn't really have to do anything assuming that we don't have
too many technical difficulties.
You can just keep on watching handmade hero but I believe Shawn will
also be trying to stream it on his channel as well.
So if you do subscribe to, or watch his streaming channel on Twitch,
you should be able to catch it there.
So either place will work.
All right?
That's said today, we are on Day 2, 10 of handmade hero.
And so if you would like to follow along with the code that I am doing
here, you
Do that by unpacking the previous day.
So, I'm packed Day, 2009, source code and then you'll be exactly where
I am at the moment.
So, yeah, where were we right?
Do you guys remember where we were?
I hope you do.
We ended the last stream at a place that I was actually pretty.
Happy with us, pretty excited about where we ended up getting.
And the reason for that was because we had finally gotten to the point
where our debug system now supports both profiling and data written
through the same stream and it all kind of gets collated.
After the fact, which means that if you kind of turn it off, it's just
not there doesn't really cost you anything, you can also compile it
out and do all those sorts of things.
And it also means you can kind of look back over time.
So it means that when we're displaying data, we're not just dumping it
to the screen.
Dean.
We actually have 32 frames worth of back data.
We can even go look at in other sorts of kind of neat, stuff like
that.
So, I'm pretty, I'm pretty interested in this.
It's kind of neat, it's just a kind of a neat thing.
And so what I want to start doing today is getting us sort of more
towards a well working code base because basically what we did is we
did all the stuff necessary to make all these things work, and it's
very exploratory.
I've never written debug system that really works like this one does.
And so I was just
Trying to figure out sort of how do we structure the code to allow
these things to work in a nice way?
And so now I kind of want to start taking what we have there.
Now that we see it working and it's all fine and start to sort of
piece it apart into something that I'm were confident about Its
Behavior, how it's structured and its ability to kind of add things
and so on.
So for those of you out there who are novice programmers, who are a
little unsure about how to make architecture decisions and stuff like
that.
This dream is sort of going to be largely about that sort of thing.
So the first thing that I would like to point out here, kind of want
to show you a fairly obvious thing that I think we should start with.
And this is like, I always say, I'm a big fan of compression oriented
programming, right?
Which is sort of a made-up term that I use.
I don't
Do you know if anyone else uses it but basically what it means is
trying to allow code to be exploratory, be free, be fast and loose.
And then the way that you sort of start getting architecture out of a
place that you don't really know what the architecture should be is to
start looking for how things tend to work, and then taking common
pieces, and collapsing, them into things that can be used in more than
one place, right?
So it's this, it's this concept of taking sort of a big repetitive
mess of code and going on.
Oh, I see that.
This is doing some things in common.
I can compress that out.
I can press this out until you kind of get it down to something that's
nice and concise and where things are only done in one place and so
on, right?
And so that's what I'd like to point out here.
So if I just start thinking about it, you know, we've got there's just
a lot of code, right?
The debug system took several days, I think it was like 10 or 20 days
which is, I mean, 10, 20 hours.
So I don't know half a week.
Something like this of us typing and code, trying things, and
whatever.
And so there's there's a lot of code
I'd there, right?
There's a lot of stuff, we wrote not all of it was necessarily
considered holistically.
It was just us trying to sort of
To the point where we felt that it was doing the sorts of things we
wanted to do, right?
And so, one of the things that you'll notice is we have a lot of
things that sort of do similar operations, right?
And have things that look kind of similar.
So if you look, for example, in our handmade debug dot h, and you look
inside our handmade platform date.
So, in hammy, platform H is just the debug usage code is the code that
people use to access the debug Services when they need to access those
services and what you will see there, right?
It is, you've kind of got this structure in there.
That's like okay, here is a debug event.
It's something that goes into the debug lock, you can see in there
that it's kind of got a type, which has some sort of different data
members that it might be or like, R32 you 32 X 32, those sorts of
things.
And we have some things in here, like, a union, that stores different
types, like this look seconds, elapsed, or whatever.
And then some pointers to things and some instant on-site into
whatever, right now, if we go back over here to our ham,
Debug .h, you can see that.
What we have here is almost the exact same thing, right?
You can see that we have this notion of a debug variable type right
and it's got a lot of similar things in it.
Now there are some things that are not like we've got these counter
thread lists, and the bitmap display, and those sorts of things.
But we've got this whole set here are like the same sorts of things,
right?
And then, if we come down to look at an actual debug variable itself,
you can see that we have almost the exact same things.
Could these two sets of places as well, right?
So there's just there's just a very, very significant amount of
overlapping what's happening there.
And there's a reason for that.
It's because this is actually a conduit essentially now to this
system.
Now, we didn't know that when we design it, but that's just how it
started to shake out.
It means that basically people who want to put data out to the debug
system
They shove the data in here, whether it be a profile, a profile
counter, or a piece of data, from a struct that they would like to
inspect.
It's all going into this stream and then later on that something, get
sort of constructed into a hierarchy here for the debug variable
system so that it can be displayed or stored later or done things can
happen to it, whatever we might want to do, right?
And so the part about that, that's significant.
And the reason that I think
that's worth noting is because every time we want to add a new type to
our debug variable system, it would mean we'd have to add it in two
places.
So although it's not maybe the biggest deal that it's duplicated.
This one time what it really means is that going forwards, all changes
that we will ever make and all editions, we will ever make to the
types of values that we can display at a base level that are
considered sort of atomic types.
That are tracked in the debug system, will incur a cost where it is
created on both sides.
And it's just a lot of busy work for not a lot of payoff, okay.
So what I'd like to do first is take a very simple code,
simplification step there and try to make these two things do use
exactly the same code in all cases, so that there's no longer this
concept of carrying things around and translating from one to the
other and switch statements that have to crack out 12 to put it into
the other one.
All of that is just busy work and we would like to basically eliminate
it entirely if we can write.
Okay.
so, the first thing that I'm going to do to me,
The first thing I'm going to do is I'm just going to go ahead and do
the simplest possible thing in terms of collapsing.
These guys, which is to say that I am just going to full-on say that
debug variables can just contain a debug event, right?
So I'm going to say instead of storing any of this stuff, the way that
it's being stored.
Now I'm just going to allow it to be stored the way that it is stored
here, right?
And so I'm going to go ahead and take that and say that's what I would
like to.
Do.
Now, there is something that's a little bit annoying about that, and
this is sort of the thing that we're talking about before which is
that some of our base types here, like V2, V3, V4 and rectangle to.
So, on, those are not actually defined anywhere in these sort of
platform code because they exist only in the actual handmade hero
code.
And so, I really don't know whether we want to move those internet,
but I kind of think that it might be nice if we did, right.
Because I like these, this method of accessing things here, a little
bit better than this.
And of accessing things here because it better represents us after
what's going on, right?
So I think, like I said, this is the step that I want to take.
So the first thing that I'm going to do is I'm going to actually have
this thing work effectively like this, right?
So I'm going to sort of move the the data block stuff from this over
into here I'm going to make it a mirror at first and then I'm going to
fix anything that that in you any problem that that caused.
So I'm just going to say because I like it better I would
All of our sort of our stuff here, are v4s V2s, all that kind of
nonsense.
I'd like all of that stuff to now be sort of considered base types.
So they're just going to be in here because I think they're important
enough and we use them enough that I would like them to sort of be
accessible to the platform layer as something it can use and and
something that we can use in the interface boundaries and so on.
I think that's just a reasonable thing to do.
So I'm going to go ahead and put that in there.
So now we've got V2s v3's and before is in there and I'm going to do
the same thing with rectangles.
So inside the math Library.
We've got rectangles as well and I'm going to go ahead and add those.
So here is them, right?
And I'll grab them out and I'll just put them in here.
Okay, so that's all I really wanted to do there just to start with
that and that means that I can also add now the rectangles directly
into the API themselves.
So inside debugger
Here, I can say we also have rectangle to right?
And rectangle, 3.
All right, and now I'm going to deal with the Fallout of that cost.
Also note that the simple preprocessor at the moment.
I don't think it's pre-processing handmade platform that 8.
So I'm going to go ahead and let it do that as well since now, we got
introspection in there and so let's continue on.
Alright, so in order to port to that, what we have to do now is take
him a platform.sh and all the places where this stuff was happening
before, where we sort of have these, these debug values stuff that's
happening.
All of that stuff needs to now, be handled properly for the
Types that are there, right?
So when we have an F32, I'm going to take that as to be too.
When we have a you through to Matt take that you 32 and so on it and
assign it directly to the right place.
And I course I have to actually also figure out what I just call this
because I don't remember because I am old and forgetful.
So, here we go.
Let's go ahead and get those.
There's a real 32 is the UN 32?
There's an in 32.
Okay.
So then these guys are even more straightforward.
These guys have a vector2 or whatever it's called.
Let's see what that is actually called.
This is Where I wish emacs had the concept of storing back state for
different views.
Mr.
Fourth dimension.
If you're out there, I can explain that in more detail, some time if
you're interested in adding it to the awesome editor that you are
constructing.
Okay.
So
We've got Vector to.
We can now just assign that directly, which is nice.
We've got Vector 3, which we can also sign.
And that's also nice and we've got Vector for or sorry rectangle, too.
There we go.
And rectangle, 3.
And that also cuts down on some potential typos that could have been
happening in here like for all we know, we don't really know what's
going on there.
Furthermore, now that those things are defined, this stuff can kind of
come out of here, so it doesn't have to be in there anymore.
It doesn't have to be in the math one, it can actually be in here.
So this is kind of consolidate a little bit, which is actually a nice
thing in my opinion.
So there's all that and that's good.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and compile that see where we're at?
Okay, so now we've got to fix the vector pointer one.
We don't have that one at the moment.
So that's actually being used sort of in here for our open data block
stuff that we can still I guess for now.
Since we don't really have any particular opinion about how that such
at work or any real reason why that stuff has to change.
We can leave just that one alone for now.
And you know, later on, we'll think about what we want to do with
that, right?
Okay, so this is going to be an R32, this seconds.
Elapsed value is just going.
Artists in our 32 obviously, so that's all good.
And then in here, where we've got sort of the debug event translation,
all this really quickly, go ahead and translate it over directly.
And again our goal is to get rid of this whole switch statement to you
know just entirely.
We don't actually want it to be there at all but I'm just kind of
doing this mechanically so you can see each individual step.
I might take a larger step in this normally, if it were just me.
But I'm going to kind of do it a little bit more slowly.
Just for anyone again, this is kind of
Of more of a stream for people who have are sort of new to
architecture.
I want them to be able to see what's going on here.
Okay, okay, so, in handmade platform.sh, now that we've got the
introspection stuff kind of hanging out in there and which is
something that we probably would even continue to do for doing
introspection.
It means that these guys should really exist up here in the
introspection code, something like this.
So I'm going to leave that there.
And now we've gotten to the point where we're pretty much done.
I have to change the second to last thing again.
That's
Actually store that way.
Now, stored in the real 32 because we kind of got rid of that, special
purpose code.
But now we're back to the point where we should be working.
And you can see that we're sort of passing the same values and seeing
the same things that we were before.
So, that's exactly where I wanted to be.
All right, so now let's get rid of some code.
Friend of mine from a long time ago.
Something I was more of an acquaintance someone I work with that
Microsoft, very briefly, we were interns are together once said a very
I think, why statement?
He said some of the most productive work you will ever do will be with
the delete key.
This is this was his statement and you know it's true.
So, basically, what I want to do here is start to delete some code.
So, here I am in debug variable.
And what I would like to do is start by saying, well, I should be able
to just use the debug event structure directly in here as one of my
types.
And then debug variable type should not actually need to sort of have
any additional type information in it.
Right.
That debug variable type can just be like that, it was an event,
right?
And that should be sufficient.
So I should be able to get
With doing something like this, right?
And what I can do now is when I add a variable, instead of having to
have all these different kinds of variables that were adding here,
which are not particularly useful to us, where we have to kind of have
all of these different cracking functions.
What I can do instead is say, well, if I want to add a variable, maybe
one of the variable types that I add is just going to be straight up
and event right now, again, this code actually is all code that we can
probably get rid of as well, all of this stuff.
And the sort of those those toggles and stuff.
I feel like probably eventually we're going to want to do in a
slightly different way.
In fact, what I may do for now since we're not really working on this
part of the system, I may just kind of get rid of this code in its
entirety for a moment.
I may say let's just kind of
Let this this this code sort of sleep for a second where I'm going to
kind of like just say yeah the debug variable stuff let's just kind of
let's kind of let that be.
Let's let us do its thing.
In fact, how much of this could I actually remove?
Can I get rid of most of it for the time being?
I don't actually know, but we'll see if we can or not.
Let's see here.
That's going to be in handmade debug dot CPP, route group.
Route.
There it is.
Alright, so I'm just going to say that this stuff doesn't ever blink
or happen.
It's just not going to happen.
Okay?
Not going to happen, never going to happen, didn't happen, not going
to happen.
So in here where we do all of this stuff, I'm just going to get rid of
all of that.
I just concentrate on the other part of it.
So when we have a debug variable event, write something like that.
What we're going to do now is say that, okay, all of this stuff that
we were doing before where we were printing out all of these
additional items.
Right.
What I want those to be is that sort of a separate thing now, right?
That's going to be a separate thing.
So this is all going to be under debug variable type event.
Where if we see an event, we know that now we're actually going to
look at a secondary value to determine this
Is this is like a whole shared system that doesn't have to go with any
of the other stuff that were, you know, with that we might put in
here, right?
And we may be able to collapse it down even further than that.
But at the moment that's really all I want to focus on for now.
Okay.
So what that means is that all of these types that we were previously
using again have gone away, and we can just use the types that we were
using inside the debug system directly.
So now, they are not duplicated anywhere, they're just going to be
sort of, let's see, here we go.
They're just going to be shared so we can when we change one we
automatically get that change in the other one and there's no need for
you know all we have to do is add the minimum amount of code
necessary.
Ready to support it in the other system.
There's no busy work anymore because I hate doing busy work, right.
I wouldn't be so into Metal Coating if I didn't hate busy work.
Right?
So in the debug event system looks like right now, there's no bull 32
at the moment.
So I'm going to go ahead and add one temporarily even though that it
doesn't actually get used here yet, I assume that it will at some
point.
Okay, so there's our debug event be to, there's our debug event to be
three.
There's our debug event to be 4.
Okay, and then we also probably want to do something we're in here.
We can support the other types that we had.
We have rectangle to, and so rectangle.
2 is just going to be like something like wrecked to, and it's going
to be like that sort of a thing, you know.
Same to you.
So we've got a rectangle, too.
rectangle, 2 Min EX
Rectangle, 2, Min y rectangle, to Max X and rectangle, to Max y.
So that's a rectangle 2.
And the rectangle 3 is going to be the same code, right?
Exactly the same thing.
It just now Prince that one additional element.
Alright, so now we handle all of those and that's nice, but we need to
also get them out of a different place.
So now it's going to get just out of our event, dot, whatever the
thing is, right?
And so, you can kind of see me taking a look here at what's happening.
There we go.
Event event.
Event Event, Event, and Event, Event Event Event.
so,
but I do not know whether that is because this was something that I
was trying to turn off.
All right.
What is happening here?
Introspection is only supported Force trucks right now.
Oh no.
Nice.
Yeah, this is something that we never actually did.
It doesn't actually affect us at all, but this is kind of funny.
We didn't actually write any code to ignore the fact that if we try to
do a file in which the introspect itself occurs, that's probably it's
due to do have the meta parser ignore pound Define, its pound of fine.
so anyway,
At this point, I don't really know what that debug Max variable stock
stuff.
Why that really has to be there anymore, but it does at least for our
traversal, I guess, that's, that's kind of the case.
So, inside the debug variables, I'll just lift that guy continue to be
outside and that'll be fine.
Alright, so in here, when we're doing hot interaction types and we're
working with variables and stuff like that, this stuff is all going to
want to use.
Sort of the other.
Is going to want to use the other information as well, right?
So now,
Theory, what we should be able to do, is some sort of a situation
where we look at, whether we're doing events or what?
Exactly, we're working with.
So, again, this is going to have to be something where we just kind
of, we kind of do a two-tiered look, right?
So if we want to do something like debug variable type,
Event then we can do things where we just take a look at what are the
different things we might, you know, want to look at in that system.
And again, this is just the exact same thing as we're doing before.
It's just allowing us to use that, that guy sort of indirectly, right?
It's allowing us to use a different system for storage.
And again, I'm not saying this is the last one I want to do, I just
want to get it working in a way that it's just kind of included now.
So yeah, so debug event be 32 and debug event are 32 or the to that
existed in here.
Oops, and so that's all we should need.
So if we take a look at this guy here, we should be able to look at
that event type and do the comparison, everything else should stay the
same.
Nothing really interesting happening there.
So in here, this stuff again, we don't have at the moment and the
reason that we don't have that the moment is just because we're sort
of changing up how we're
In those trees and stuff like that.
So we'll get to those again as we continue to clean stuff up.
What kind of move those in?
And so here again with debug and interact, this is the case that
again, we've got sort of a two-tiered thing if we are working with an
event, then maybe we've got something that we want to do in this case.
There we go of our event type, we just want to do something with that
pool.
Okay, so that's fine.
Nothing, particularly odd going on there.
That's just again, this debug event, B, 32 thing and then let's keep
moving down.
So, oops, that's that's not an arrow.
That's a DOT.
Okay, so in this case, we're just going to set the pool.
This is actually editing that pool and again, we're just using the
exact same logic.
Everything is exactly the same.
I don't know why I decided to name those.
I named this kind of weirdly.
I don't love it.
I should probably change the way that I'm doing that.
That's my suspicions, but what you going to do
Anyway, so yeah, again, like just doing the bare minimum cure to
translate this code so that things are starting to line up a little
bit better, right?
so,
let's see where we're at.
So, in this case, now, all of this stuff, all of this code here, that
was doing this translation before, all of this code should actually,
now not have to do anything.
All in theory, right?
So all of this code is if if anything came through, if any kind of
debug event comes through it, all right, if any, if we see any kind of
debug event, then, all we really need to do is just capture it, right?
We just need to capture this data block, right?
And in fact, I think what we probably want to do is say, you know what
just it doesn't matter what since we don't have to do any different
code.
Now it actually doesn't matter any event that we don't understand, we
just save as data and assume that
Someone will try to print it out later and if they can't print it out
then we'll just come as a little just come through as like I don't
understand this thing.
so, now, all we have to do is say, okay, we're going to make an event
And the event equals event, we got so all that code is gone now and
it's just a straight-up pass through right.
It just comes straight on through except I need to dereference it.
There we go.
So all that code and all of that nonsense went away and so that's
pretty handy.
I don't know what happened here.
Did we this probably never initialized our tree stuff when I came out
to.
Where are you?
Because there is no debug tree here anymore.
I got rid of all of our stuff, which admittedly is not something you
can necessarily do directly, although I
I want to be able to make sure that is allowed for now, so I'll make
sure that, that's okay.
Yes, you can see that in this case, group can't really be 0 here.
So I'll just go ahead and make sure that that's allowed.
We'll just say, if group, and we will go ahead and push that out.
Yeah.
Yep, all right.
Oops, don't want to break point.
So now we're again running everything through just one type of struck.
Now to encapsulate debug data which again is a nice little collapse.
I'm that I'm very happy about I like the fact that we did that.
And that's all well and good.
So let's continue onward from there and see what we can do, right?
So now inside handmade debug our sorry, handmade platform.sh, right?
This is now the canonical way that things are actually stored inside
the debug system in general.
Right?
Meaning we're actually just this is the place that that we would add
new values if you want to do values and these are the values that it
stores inside itself.
How's it goes, right?
And that, that all just feels much better to me.
So, that's a good thing.
And so the question now though is, we kind of have this two-tiered
thing happening inside this where we've got, you know, this sort of
debug variable type thing happening.
And we've got, you know, one,
That it breaks out in here and then we've got these other ones in it.
And so the next question that I would have that's kind of a relatively
obvious question is since these are just debug since since there's no
like I mean there there's really no reason for us to have a two-tiered
test thing there where we're actually sort of swapping those out.
We could choose to simplify things even further just by merging these
two enumerated types together, right?
That's something we certainly could do if we want to.
Because remember, this one is only an 8-bit thing.
So we could just Jam this all of these guys into this type itself and
just have them all just work that way, right?
So we could do something like the lower 255.
Entries are reserved for the ones that actually go in here.
And then all of the other things that happen like this counter thread
list and all that stuff just exist higher, right?
So they would be something like this debug event, you know, first
first, you I type or something like that.
And we could even call this just debug type instead of event type to
signify that.
But we could do something here, we just say, okay, we started to 56
and we go up from there.
And then these guys,
We're just going to live in here, right?
As part of this, right?
That's something we could do.
And that would get us out of the business of having sort of this
other, you know, this other sort of, you know, pre-existing value.
All right.
So I don't really know whether I care about that too much or not, but
it just seems to me like overly complicated to have two types there
for no reason.
So it seems like maybe I want to collapse that down a little further.
So I'm going to try doing that and I'm going to see what happens.
And what I'll do here is I'll just say like I'll have a single debug
type kind of a concept and I'm going to just, you know, do it like
this.
okay, so the first thing I'm going to do
Is I'm going to call these debug types and then I'm going to change
anywhere that was using them before to use something else, right?
So we've got this set up the way it is.
Do it like this?
Yeah, so I'm going to go through and say, okay, debug event type
equals debug type and I'm just going to see where those sorts of
things occur.
So let's see.
Frame marker was it's debug event, okay?
So debug event underscore equals debug type underscore
And then I'm just going to go ahead and get rid of all these things so
that they're all just talking about debug type and then I'll recompile
then in here I'll just do the exact same thing.
So B's all
Debug types as well, right?
There we go.
Okay, and then inside handmade debug, if we go down and look at debug
variables,
Right?
So if we look at how this works now and we put an event in there, we
have a debug variable type of the top.
I could just change that to being a debug type itself.
And now that would just be, you know, would be used directly.
And so, what that would mean is that when we add one of these things,
when we add the type here, we would just add whatever the events type
is like so.
And now we wouldn't really have to use that secondary switch method.
Anymore, we could just switch directly on the type and know that
they're all kind of stuffed up in there specifically, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and do that as well just to see what sort of
What Becomes of it.
So here we go.
This is going to be a, oops.
Not that not that I say.
And not that either we go into handmade 20th and also get rid of debug
variable type because this should go away and this is one of those
now.
There we go.
Okay, so now when we're doing these sort of these switch statements
here, these can just now be promoted back up to the top.
Like I said, which is kind of what I want to do so you can kind of see
them all happening together and that's all very well and good.
And you don't have to actually sort of do step Downs to sort of crack
those types out as a separate thing, right?
And similarly it, through all of this debug variable type underscores
is going to be debug type.
Oops,
You got variable, type underscore.
R equals debug type underscore.
There we go, just replace those
Okay, and now debug type event anywhere that we saw that, we can just
re promote these guys up to the top level where they were before, and
we know that that will be fine now, right?
And so that gets us out of the business of having to do double switch
statement.
The the sort of cracking of the double switch stations there.
This is a debug type now.
Okay, and that should take care of that, right?
So now I think we're all good.
Everything should still be working as we expect it to and that's good.
So we're getting, you know, we're sort of making slow, but sure
progress towards something that's a little bit.
Or, you know, coherent and a little bit more thought through.
All right.
So that's all nice.
And I think this is starting to look a lot nicer now, because now we
just have that in our handmade debug is starting to simplify right.
We don't have sort of this this whole other situation here with all
these different sorts of things.
But we still got a lot of business in here.
There's a lot of things going on, a lot of moving parts and it's not
necessarily clear that all of them are doing what they should be doing
or that they're actually necessary.
So now let's take a look at something a little bit more direct.
So, okay.
Now if we start to take a look at what is an actual debug variable, or
debug variable, is the thing with a type, it's just, it's got a name,
right?
So it's a type in a name and then we know that it could be a debug
event.
So that could be there or it could be one of these things.
So what is a debug profile settings will debunk?
Profile settings is actually meaningless.
You have a profile settings actually doesn't exist anymore, and the
reason don't exist anymore is because we moved the concept of things
like, settings out to stuff like the debug view, right?
So that's gone.
Now, that doesn't actually need to be there the code compiles fine.
Without it, a debug bitmap display is just a bitmap ID.
Now, if we wanted to display a bitmap ID, now what we can do is we can
just go ahead and move that bitmap ID directly out of
This right.
And into the debug system, right?
So the debug you know, the bitmap IDS.
Those can now come directly through here.
So you know something like a bitmap ID can be in here.
Or a sound ID could be in here.
So we could see those when we're in the code, we could just output
something like a bitmap ID and then we would just know that we have
one of those things that we want to display, right?
So instead of needing to have this, this could be in the event itself,
right?
So I again, I'm going to go ahead and and try to make that change as
well.
Okay, so I'm going to get rid of debug bitmaps play like so.
And then I'm going to compile this.
All right, so first thing we need to do is actually get those type
definitions in here, which again, is requires this kind of to move
things in a little bit.
But, you know, like I said, I'm okay with that.
It's fine with me.
I don't care that those get moved out to the platform layer because it
doesn't really harm the platform layer to have those in there.
So I think that's in the file formats thing.
I don't actually remember.
Yes it is.
So there is our different IDs bitmap sound that sort of stuff, right?
All of those things.
Those are now going to come in here.
So those are just little based rapper types and the pragma push on
these guys kind of needs to be respected, right?
So I would like to keep my pragma push, I'd like to continue pragma
push in that.
So I will do pragma push here.
And pragma.
So, there we go.
That's again, just the packing that we want those things pack now,
granted.
We don't really need to do pragma pack on those because I think they
only have one variable, so I don't know.
That that actually makes any sense, it's probably worthless, but it's
interesting to just leave it there.
So people know, those are things that have to be remain the same
because they go in and out of files, but you know, whatever.
So anyway,
Here we are with our get bitmap code so now this stuff doesn't exist
anymore.
So we would have to do something like this, right?
And we probably also want to change this to a bitmap ID as the
fundamental type of the thing as well.
Now if I recompile it we should be at a place where that actually just
works relatively straight through, right?
And so if I go through here now and do bitmap, display bitmap display
is now
I d, right?
Like so and then I've got stuff like okay?
There's a sound ID and a font ID as well.
Right.
And then down here where we push those things on like through this
sort of system.
What I can do is I can add those here where I've got bitmap ID is one
of the things I can do and I've got bitmap ID is one of the things I
can set, hopefully this is really obvious the way that I'm doing this
and it all makes good sense to you but if not well, that's what the
Q&A is.
For, Okay, so we've got all of that set squared away and now I just
need to add that in here since I didn't actually put it in there and
now I just have to take a look.
Okay?
So whether things should be written this.
Debug should be written thing is going to go away.
That's I mean I can tell you right now that stuff's going away.
So let's take a look here.
What we've got?
Let's go there, bitmap display.
What is this?
This is from our printing this out.
So the bitmap display that idea stuff is really just going to be event
bitmap ID, right?
And there we go.
So now when we actually run this stuff although we can't really
interact with these it because we haven't solved a few of the problems
in terms of permanence what I'd like to do is now actually just output
the debug.
I doubt like the output a bitmap to our debug ID to our debugging
system, right?
So the same way that we were outputting things like energy storage
index and stuff like that here.
I just going to find like I've got these like you know, bitmaps here
and stuff like that, that I could choose to Output so somewhere.
Where I've got a bitmap ID, what would be a bitmap idea that we could
output?
For example, we've got a bunch of them here, I think let's see, we
have loaded bitmap test if you slowed it bitmap but I'll loaded bit
map.
Bitmap.
Yeah, do we have anymore?
Well you know what?
I'll just do something like this.
Where I've got sort of the hero this hero stuff here.
Do we still have the hero bitmaps thing?
By the time we're actually outputting this guy.
I don't know that we do.
So we've got the hot anything.
Yeah.
We don't we don't really have.
I don't think any bitmaps for this guy, but I'll see you just in case
maybe we do.
So if we do, I could do something like this where I say, like just
output here a bit Maps like that torso or something.
Oops, that torso.
Okay, so we can.
So now there should be a thing where we're like outputting the and you
can see it right here.
Like there it is we just can't interact with them yet.
Oh, I guess we can.
It's just until it go it.
Till it gets deleted is the problem right?
But there it is.
Right.
So now we're actually outputting bitmap display is directly.
Unfortunately I said we have some interaction stuff we selling to do
and that's just that just has to do with properly storing information
about about who, exactly?
We're interacting with again pushing that on the stack, I kind of
know.
I saw as we went through all this code, it all started assembling
itself in my head.
So I kind of know everything should work now and I'm just trying to
kind of go through them and explain each individual step as we go.
Alright, so now we've got in a row.
We have gotten rid of a whole bunch of stuff there.
Because now if you look at what we're actually doing, you can see that
that debug variable class is basically going away, right?
You can see that.
It's winnowing itself down.
It's like smaller and smaller and smaller, and remember name is now
almost entirely like this.
These two things, both exist in the event itself.
So the only difference between a debug variable now, right?
The only difference between a debug variable
and a debug event is the fact that a debug variable can store sort of
like a group inside it.
Right.
It can say that well in a, you know, here are some data that I'm
displaying.
That's one thing I could say, or I could say here is like a group, but
remember we've got these debugged variable links, right?
So, what we could do is instead of doing the debug variable thing, as
something where you points to a variable, in the variable, has the
group in it,
We could choose to elevate that concept up one level, right where, the
debug variable link itself is actually the thing that stores the
grouping on top of it, right?
That's, that's where I think this is going.
Then the concept of a debug variable goes away entirely, it doesn't
exist anymore.
So I want to look at that.
I want to look at that as a possibility.
And the thing that I want to look at for that possibility, is just to
think about, is there anything that that does that, we are worried
about it doing specifically, like when we want to maybe do, like, drag
off cloning of stuff.
And I don't think so.
Because I tend to not really want to drag off clones in ways that
aren't going to be at least somewhat more flexible there.
So I feel like deep copying is
Okay, on the other hand I just don't know.
I mean I it's always hard to tell whether you're going to be up
whether that's going to be a bad thing.
At the end of the day, I'm not sure right.
But what we can do at the very least even if we can't do that.
And I guess I like I said I'm just not sure, I'm not 100% sure which
way I want that to go.
Even if we couldn't do that, we could decide to just put the debug
variable link directly into our debug event and collapse them.
Right?
Because this thing already is like for 32-bit values long it could
trivially support one of these things.
Right in line with itself, right?
So of our group could literally just be this thing right here, right?
Hopefully, that makes sense.
Hopefully that makes some sense.
Maybe it does.
Maybe, it doesn't, you know, who's to say at the end of the day, but
there you go.
All right, so if we wanted to collapse this, just a little bit
further, that's the thing that we're looking at.
How do we actually get there?
And the other question, too, is
Does it pose too much of a problem that something like the name is?
Now something that has to get kind of looked up dynamically, right?
Because remember, this doesn't have the name in it.
It just has a debug record index that you can use to get the name,
right?
So it has the way of going out to figure out what the name for the
thing actually was but doesn't actually have a name as a direct
pointer.
So there is a little bit of that, although I don't know how
realistically how much of a problem that would ever posed to us?
It's just something that's worth noting, right?
Okay.
So let's do let's do traffic of which Step I want to take next and I'm
not 100% certain, which one I want it to be.
I think what I would like to do is I think I would like to maybe just
try to do that last compression on this guy and then tomorrow because
we got about 13 minutes left on the stream tomorrow.
I'll go through and maybe take a look at some more.
Some more, like some different parts of that.
All right, so being here, the way that we're dealing with debug
variable links, I guess really.
Let's see how we're doing our.
Let's just take a quick look at how we're doing our like, our draw,
like our, you know, our iteration, where we Loop over things here.
Is that sort of Step where if we get to have our group, which is like
here,
Then we kind of do a little depth push.
So we push the depth there so I'm assuming that if we wanted to we
could pretty trivially have the variable have the variable link
itself.
Be the thing that gets us to that because here is the link, right?
So
Could do something like, okay, there's debug variable VAR and it's
also got like, debug variable link like children or something like
that, right?
So it could have sort of that notion that there's some stuff
underneath, this particular, dude, whoever he is, right.
And then that information is just
Is just purely.
It's just a purely thing that exists in the linking layer, right?
In the linkage layer.
So if I wanted to do that, if I wanted to get rid of our group here,
so that it basically becomes this now, right?
That's the step we would take next.
Can we do that, right?
And and I guess that debug variable-length the only.
Well, the only problem is that we were treating that Loops that's no
good.
We were treating that as a doubly linked list thing.
So there is a little bit of a problem there which is that if we point
into one of the people of the linked list,
there's really no way to deal with the Sentinel part.
Like where does that Sentinel actually go and I'm not 100% sure.
So it's more like you would need to do something.
It's a little janky, right?
it's like,
That.
Right.
It's like you have to sort of have an on demand created Sentinel now
at the linking layer, which is kind of ugly.
I mean, it's not the greatest thing in the world, I don't know if I
love it or not.
And it creates a little bit more weight at the link layer instead of
it being in the variable are where it could easily be, right?
So you know what I think.
I think if you look at him a platform that age, you can see inside
debug event, there's going to be debug events, like open data block
and close data block and opened a tin box and close data.
Block are actually the things which sort of say that they are sort of
the construction of the Sentinel.
And those things, you know, would have potentially they have plenty of
space to store that ring.
So,
It's kind of a little wonky.
And I'm just not sure.
I'm just not sure what I think of it.
Well, I feel like because I'm so torn on it, I think.
What I'll do is I'll just go ahead and sort of push through it.
Go a little bit further down and just see what happens because I find
like that's usually the only real way to go when you just don't really
know right where you just like I'm just not sure, I'm not sure what
should be happening here.
So if that was the case, then what's going to happen when we come
through here?
Is when we grab out like a group like this, we don't really need to do
any of this stuff I guess.
So we've got group group is coming in here.
It's a debug variable at the moment.
So what it would be actually is it would be a debug variable link,
always.
That would actually be the thing that you start with.
And so, you're basing, your passing the Sentinel.
And I suppose you could do something where those things were actually,
you know?
So here's the thing to do debug variable group, you could do something
like this.
Right, you could do something like that.
And then each one of this, this just has like children.
Which is very close to a way that we did have it before, right?
Could do something like that and that maybe seems a little bit more
sensible to me.
Okay.
So in this case you would say okay, we've got a group group equals,
whatever the tree group is and that again, would sort of be something
that just implies that these things that have groups on them.
Now, right wherever we have like route group and those sorts of
things.
Those are all going to be talking about a debug variable group
pointer.
You know, and yeah.
And then all of this stuff, I'll just do the surgery necessary to make
that happen.
So that comes like so
and then these guys have to be like just worked through again.
Nothing particularly unusual Happening Here.
Yeah, it's all good.
All right, so this will take me a little bit, just to kind of work
through the changes necessary here, but again, nothing particularly
unusual happening.
This is just the, if I have a group we've got sort of that Sentinel
there.
So this is all going to look.
I think just like that, right?
Yeah.
So again, it's almost exactly the same, there's really not much to it.
So in this case if we have it's not going to look at the VAR type
anymore for that.
What's actually going to do is say that in this case we're just going
to look to see if there's a children pointer.
So if whatever the link is that we're on if that has a children
pointer at all, then we just assume that now is the time for us to do
that.
Reversal down to it.
So we would do link children.
Sentinel
Oops.
And off it would go.
We can also simplify this iteration it was not a very well-written
iteration but that's a separate issue.
Again, everything gets cleaned up in time.
There we go.
That's an at sign.
Do you list link insert so it debug variable group is now a thing.
So now groups, I guess we would do that to it.
I suppose.
I think so.
Yes.
Keep On Truckin through that.
And This Crew Cooley create variable group.
Now needs to
needs to return a variable group, right?
And so when we do create variable, it's should not actually be doing
this stuff anymore, right?
I mean, it should meaning, this is the, this is the VAR, so it should
actually do that and it just needs to also do debug variable group.
Okay.
Oops, that's not what I want.
And then the group itself, right?
Which is this guy.
So the link that got created, the link that gets created for this guy
where we do when we create a variable group, the link that gets
created for the group is just going to be and I guess we don't even do
a VAR.
So it's just, it's really only.
If you actually add this group to another group, right?
It's only if this group appears underneath some other group that you
actually need a variable for it, which is actually, I guess a little
bit of an improvement over the way that we were doing it before.
But yeah.
So
When we do collate create variable group.
It's just creating just a variable group initializing it and that's
all it does, right?
So anyway, let's take a look.
Here you go.
State colita de Rana.
Let's see what else we got.
So this is just cold.
A crude variable group and just takes the debug State.
This is one, okay?
So in this case, when it does collate add variable to group, that's
the point where it would actually, that's that's the point where it
actually does.
Something with the naming.
So when it creates the actual debug group,
It would then also create a variable for that guy.
So here's the variable.
And I guess really, what we need to have is we need to get the link
back, right?
So the key part here is we since we're operating at that link layer,
we want to be able to do a thing where when we do collate create
variable
We want to be able to see what the link was that got added, right?
And so this part right here where we do co-ed variable to group, we
want to be able to do essentially this, right?
Or when we do collate create create grouped variable, right?
That's again it's doing that link and we don't have any way of getting
the link back, right?
So what we want to do here is we want to be able to get that link
back.
So when we do click create variable
and we pass it, the name, we need to pass the debug State as well and
the type
Oops.
Okay, so when we go ahead and create that variable, then we add it to
the group.
We want to have that debug link come back to us so that we can set the
pointer to it, right?
So we want debug variable link.
That's us creating that link there.
And when we add, oops,
We are adding the VAR and then when we take that link, we just want
the children pointer the child pointer to be that debug block group.
Again a little bit, janky, and messed up.
And that's just because we kind of have to take this one step at a
time.
And we're we still have a few more steps to go, right?
That's probably going to be that way.
Yeah, let's return that link.
There we go.
So I think I got everything there and but I'm not entirely sure.
Oh, we didn't.
What's happened there?
Let's see it early link.
Varr.
Okay, so that is a very bad.
Say the least that is a very bad pointer.
So what we want to do here is we're going to want to fix this guy,
I'm going to go like just a little bit into the Q&A because I'd like
to fix that first since we're right in the middle of
Injera don't really want to leave it till tomorrow and try to remember
exactly what I was doing, because this is kind of again, a series of
Fairly subtle steps necessary to make things end up in a good place.
And that can be kind of difficult especially on stream when I will
talk the whole time and it's kind of hard to keep it all in my head
properly.
So what's actually happening here, right?
Is, we move that stuff up to the link layer so that we can collapse
down debug variable even further from where we had it.
And so now, I have to make sure is that when we actually
We do add cult, you know, when we add things to the tree, I just need
to make sure that they're actually relatively correct when they get
out of here.
So we're adding to the debug block.
We create a variable group that we're going to put our variables in.
We create a variable for that one, which we do here, right?
We create, you know, we put them in whatever the correct group
actually was we add the variable there and then
Make sure that the chill that, you know, whoever the children were.
For this, for this particular entry is going to be the group that
seems correct to me, that looks like what I would expect.
I should jungle check, what happens with debug block group, but I
don't think really anything else in particular happens with it yet,
doesn't.
So when you close the data block, or all it does is pop up to the next
round.
Doesn't touch those groups at all.
So I feel like I don't know, maybe that's an iteration bug of some
Kind where this is actually not quite proper.
So if link children, when I create these debug links, I don't set the
child pointer.
That's that's probably the entirety of it.
So debug variable link.
When I create one in here, I initialize everything.
But I don't initialize the child.
So that's almost certainly the problem there.
Yeah.
And that is what the problem is.
Okay, good.
So now again, we're getting a little bit closer.
We're simplifying this a little bit further down, we've kind of got
Relatively good State now, so that debug variable could now
effectively just go away, right?
If we wanted to debug variable actually doesn't have to even be
called, debug variable, it can just be called debug event, and the
debug event could be used directly.
And that's where look at tomorrow and as well, as well as solidifying
up our interaction stuff, which I think we could do now very cleanly
and making it so that that'll work as well.
So that will be something that will tackle tomorrow.
For now, I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A in advance of doing
the
The the live stream with Sean McGrath.
So if you have any questions about what we're doing, please go ahead
and ask them now.
and if you could put Q colon in front of it, so,
See it.
That would be great.
I see in sohbat is continuing to,
To demonstrate its Mastery of the English language on the Stream.
why call it Sentinel, instead of head even though it is a sentinel,
I'm not sure what you're asking, why call it Sentinel, instead of
head, even though it is essential, well, I call it a sentinel because
it's the Sentinel, which is sort of what you're saying, it is as well.
You don't think it should be called The Sentinel.
What's your favorite data structure?
oh,
what's my favorite data structure?
I don't know.
I guess I would say that I really do like doubly linked lists a lot
because they're like very easy and they can do a lot of stuff.
Unfortunately.
I feel like you know, these days with cache coherency being what it
is, they're not really that efficient.
So, you know, it's hard to make them your favorite data structure,
these days because of performance concerns.
So it's like, you know, but I feel like in terms of the stuff you
can do with a doubly linked list.
And how easy it is to program.
It's kind of awesome singly linked list.
I would say that singly linked list, hold kind of, is
Place in my heart as well because singly linked lists can can actually
be done.
A lot of stuff can be done with no actual
No real atomics that could look like.
I mean, with with only very basic swap atomics like you know you can
add something to a free list a singly linked free list with just one
exchange and you don't they don't have to be checked or anything that
can just as long as you can see realized exchanges you're good, you
know.
So I don't know.
I don't know.
It's hard to say
It's pretty hard to say.
Hash tables are also.
Also Obviously good, very easy to implement and do a lot of stuff.
But like everything else you know, it's really hard to pick.
See you Soros?
Not sure if you specified this in a previous post but do you plan to
implement side-scrolling or any kind of platforming alongside the top
down view?
No, it is not a side-scrolling kind of game.
It does not really do that.
I have no game design stuff in there about that, side-scrolling
So does the in sohbat?
Answer you of.
Does the in sohbat, answer you, if you ask it a question, does it try
to like respond?
So, it does sort of.
Legend of Zelda has some fo side-scrolling rooms.
Yeah.
The original Legend of Zelda had like like when you get like an item
but they were really stupid rooms.
Like I don't know why they did that.
It's not like, they weren't good.
So I didn't really want any of that.
It didn't seem like a good idea.
Stegosaurus.
What has been your favorite thing so far writing this engine probably
was the fact that the software renderer Ran So Fast, even though we
only did the most basic optimization on it, it was kind of fun to see
just how fast it the software renderer runs.
Kind of crazy.
Terror.
OE asks, I had an idea that's probably stupid, but I was wondering if
a vector that when deleting an element just left an empty spot that
skipped over when iterating would still be cash friendly and still
efficient when deleting and inserting, this is slightly over my head
though.
So the problem with that approach
Is is that, you know, there's nothing fundamentally wrong with that.
If if what it turned out that you did is you do a lot of deletion, you
need your things to be stable and you don't want to do mem copying
then maybe that's you know, interesting, right.
But you have to understand that there's a lot of overhead that you're
going to incur to support this operation, right?
Because first of all, you need a way of marking, the fact that you've
deleted an entry into the vector.
So, where does that need to get stored?
Right?
Do you now have another Vector?
That's neck.
That's like a alongside that Vector.
Do you expand each slot in the vector to include a Mark that says,
whether it's filled or not, right?
And now during iteration, which is the thing that you want to be as
fast as possible.
Usually, you're checking every time you increment by one, you got to
check to see.
Not only am I at the end but also am.
I do I got a skip this guy or skip some
Number of guys and so on.
Right?
So you know it sounds a little iffy to me, you know, it doesn't sound
great.
But like anything else, it's not a stupid idea.
It's an idea that may have a time when it's valid and really what it
depends on is, how are you using this Vector?
What are the best like, what?
What is the core benefit?
You're providing there, right?
And and, you know, there could be cases where something that did
something like that was actually useful.
I don't think it would probably be a great General replacement for
Vector know, but, you know, that doesn't mean it.
Couldn't that concept couldn't have its place.
How about your favorite equation?
My favorite equation.
Is well, I think I answered this before is linear blend.
My favorite equation is.
We've definitely said this before.
How do I get back to a, some kind of drawing mode here.
Hello, Mischief, I would like to draw an A please.
There we go.
So my my favorite equation is is definitely like f of a t.
B equals 1, minus t, A+ T, be
that is definitely my favorite equation.
By far.
Do you use DirectX?
No, I do not use DirectX.
What do you think of clang cc-1?
Is that C1 or CL?
C1, clang c14 Visual Studio, I do not know what clang.
See one for visual studio.
Actually is to be honest with you,
Any other questions?
Muju.
1, 2, 3 x.
If you were doing these compressions, the ones you did today at work,
how different would your process be?
Well, you know, it's the process would be basically the same.
I would just be skipping a lot of steps.
So, you know, I could probably make a much larger jump in a lot of
places.
So basically the places where you see me go, hmm, well I'm not that
place where I'm scratching my my chin.
Those are actually the places I would be stepping to and all the
places where I'm like, I'm just going to go ahead and move this thing
into blah and I do it.
I'm gonna do it moves about.
Usually, all of those would probably be just be done in one step
Roberts, like, okay.
I know I'm gonna move this thing here.
I'm going to put that over there and we take this drug on my side,
okay.
It's that
And then I just like do that change, right?
But that's not really very useful on stream because a it's really
Be really hard for me to do that stream effectively.
It would be hard for me to mentally do that while talking all the time
and not mess something up but and also it would be extremely difficult
for anyone to have any idea what I did.
It's hard enough when I'm doing big changes like this for people to
follow.
But at that point, a b, forget it.
They have no idea what I did, right?
Because it just be like, oh it was this thing and then it's magically
this other thing and we have no idea like how it got there or why he
got there, right?
Microsoft is making clang for parsing intermediate, a first-class
fully support system.
Fragile suiciding, November intermediate and to machine is still
Microsoft C2.
I mean, like I said that seems like a reasonable idea.
I guess, I don't know.
You know, I would prefer that Microsoft's did a good compiler.
At the end of the day, I don't care about C++ so I actually be fine if
they just did a good C compiler and so maybe this is that sort of what
they're kind of doing, right?
Is like they're saying, let's leave the parsing to clang because we
don't care and we'll just work on the code gen and that seems fine to
me.
That's totally reasonable.
Clang is a good front end for C++.
It seems like it handles, just about anything that people throw at it.
Even crazy C++ people, I don't know.
No, because I'm not a crazy C++ person anymore, but you know, that's
just it sort of seems that way.
But like, anything else, I don't, I won't really have an opinion till
I actually use it in practice and see how it goes.
But let's be honest, if I'm real lucky that day will never come
because I'll just be programmed in ji or something like that.
And I won't have to deal with Microsoft scrap the compiler anymore.
How long do you think it will take before?
Someone makes a Linux to bugger that can rival visual Studios?
I mean, Infinity long.
As far as I mean,
There's hundreds of Linux to buggers out there and they're all lousy.
So, you know, I don't know, probably people have to start putting some
money behind.
It would be my guess.
People who actually do low-level programming have to start putting
some money behind it.
You know, because it's pretty clear that whatever is happening.
Now just has not led to a good day butter because if there's been tons
of them made and they're all lousy
her Domina.
What do you think of Purdue and competitions?
Have you participate in the?
I have not
I don't have a particular opinion about them one way or the other.
Mr.
Bass 21.
What role do you think seven security has in modern gaming?
Is it not worth wasting CPU Cycles to guard against different
exploits?
How good of a job is the game which we doing to to implementing it and
should they be doing more or less?
In my opinion, it breaks into two categories roughly.
So there's Competitive Gaming and non competitive gaming, so
Competitive Gaming would be something where you're talking like
Esports and that sort of thing where there's like, you know, you might
win a million dollars.
If you win this tournament or something.
So let's assume that that would not talking about that.
And we're just talking about all the rest of the games.
So just games that I play on my computer by myself, in my opinion,
security has zero place in that sphere at all game.
Developers should literally, never think about security.
There should be absolutely.
It should be assumed that every game will ship with the most possibly
severe exploits that
that could possibly occur.
That's just be assumed.
And then the responsibility for running those things securely should
fall squarely on the operating system.
There is no question in my mind that that is absolutely the only
correct route.
And the reason for that is because there are literally thousands of
games developed every year.
There is no way that each of those people is going to be a security
expert nor do we want them to spend their time doing that.
And furthermore, there is no way that each of those games will get the
kind of testing and
Is necessary to make sure that they don't have exploits in them.
So it is imperative that operating system treat games in a sandbox.
They should have done this from day one.
There is absolutely no excuse for the reason that they don't and it is
completely ridiculous.
That Microsoft has still not done this after 7 Operating System
iteration since they started supporting gaming.
It's like
Absurd a person should be able to run a game written by a hacker,
trying to infect their machine on Windows, and it should not be able
to do anything.
Because that is the that is like one of the most primary things in
operations me supposed to do process, isolation games, do not have to
access anything on your machine.
They don't have to work with documents.
They don't have to save any data that gets used outside of the game.
They also they're entirely sandboxes.
Well, and there is absolutely no excuse for the fact that this has not
been done.
It is absolutely pathetic.
So that's my opinion on that.
And to me, that's like, very clearly the right way to go Competitive
Gaming is a different thing.
Gaming that is where the game itself is a security problem.
Meaning that even if I run the game in a sandbox that doesn't actually
help me because it may be the game itself whose Integrity I need to
verify, right?
Because if I'm trying to prevent someone from cheating in a game, then
I need to know that they're running and version of the game that
hasn't been modified.
That to me is a very interesting security problem, and I don't know
how you solve that security problem.
Write to me, that starts to suggest that you need Hardware
verification if things, and it kind of gets into a nasty, like who
owns this machine, the person who bought the machine, or the person
who the software vendor can verify that the software is, is proper and
all that stuff, right?
And so, I almost think that like, you know, in the future, I would
actually be okay with the concept.
That people who are engaged in serious Esports, use different Hardware
from other people or something like this, or that's a separate section
of the, if there are two separate things because I don't know how you
solve those problems, I don't happen to care about those problems.
So in my world did was ruining have them like we just wouldn't have
Esports now.
I don't care about it at all, like I kind of nothing about it.
I don't care about cheating in online games.
I don't care about Esports, it's irrelevant to me.
But
I realize that that they are relevant for a lot of people and I
understand why they want those
Why they want to be able to have a cheap free experience or a hack for
experience in those cases.
And so I would say that if that really is saying that needs to get
solved, then that itself is a separate security problem.
It's a very hard one and I feel like it probably requires Hardware
authentication and digital signing, which gets you into a huge
nightmare world of like who owns this machine and who trusts who, and
is Microsoft like being now telling you what you can and can't run
your machine and all these sorts of things, right?
I just that world scares me and I don't like it and Esports is
irrelevant to me.
So I just give it up and not have to go that route.
But if you actually care about those things, if you're like DOTA is my
life or whatever like or League of Legends is all I care about.
Then you have some kind of hard problems to face, you know, which are
about like do you want to have a machine where you don't actually
control the software, that's on it, you know, and I don't know, maybe
you do.
All right, I'm going to go ahead and close down the Q&A.
And I'm going to see if we can get the chat link setup for for Mr.
McGrath.
So I'm going to start doing that here, so we can be ready.
So I'm going to go ahead and close this down.
Let's go ahead and do this.
Okay, thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of
handmade here at some pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with me at home, you can
always pre-order the game on handmade here at org and it comes with a
source code.
So if you'd like to sort of experiment and play around with it, you
can do that.
I also have patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, that's always very much
appreciated.
We also have a forum site.
We can ask questions or viewed episode backlog stuff like that.
We also have a tweetbot the tweets this
Schedule it you.
So if you want to know when things are gonna be live, that's the thing
to tune into, or when you want to know about special events or to
happen.
Like the one that's going to happen right now where we're doing a live
mock debate with shama graph about free to play games which is what
I'm going to go set up now.
So if you're interested in that, please stay tuned.
I'm just going to go ahead and cycle the recording and then we'll get
right to that.
So,