There we go.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade.
Here are the show Rico to complete game live on Twitch.
We don't use any engines or any libraries here.
There are no engines or libraries here.
I fully expect you all to have left your engines and libraries at
home, because if I see anyone out there on handmade hero using an
engine or a library, there will be significant consequences.
People.
Okay.
This is not fun and games.
All right?
It's not some big circus where you can just program anything you want
and everyone's going to be okay with that, all right, this is serious.
You know, this is a serious topical game about an orphanage for
limbless children and if you cannot get on board with that, all right,
then I just don't know what to say.
You maybe you need a timeout but while you're taking that time out,
what I would like you to do is think about the fact that today is day
1 41.
And so, if you would like to follow along with me without engines and
libraries, you will want to unpack day 140 source code into a
directory because
That is the source code.
We will be starting with today.
That is it
Now that we've gotten that out of the way and I hope everyone is
behaving themselves out there.
We need to decide what we're going to do today.
So let's open things up here.
If you remember, we left things off, we had made some audio mixing.
Fundus is here, which I think we left it, where I actually launched
the entire new musical score every time you threw, one of the Little
Rock's out, one of those little test rocks and So eventually it just
got absolutely
Confidence of weird but I think we were just doing that because
someone asked whether you could play the same sound multiple times and
of course, the answer was yes.
And that was the best way to demo it.
So we've got that straightened out now so I hopefully we can, you
know, maybe not do that anymore.
And switch this back to something that isn't going to be too
cacophonous, like asset Loop and here we go.
Alright, so there we go.
Oh good.
So what we want to do now I think if I'm not very much an error is
we've got like two things.
We might want to take a look at in terms of how we are dealing with
sound mixing.
One of them is whether or not we want to support streaming sounds.
And if we want to support streaming sounds, how do we do that?
And again when I say streaming sounds I don't mean like asset
streaming, which you've already implemented.
I mean more like a single sound instead of being streamed in as a
chunk.
It
You streamed as like one chunk.
It can be streamed in as like many chunks.
So you know, if you have a piece of music, that's 30 megabytes long,
or something like this.
Don't have to pull the whole thing in at.
Once you can pull in little pieces of it, which maybe takes off a
little memory pressure.
Maybe takes off a little load pressure.
You know, do we want to support something like that?
And maybe we do.
So there's that we can take a look at the other thing that we want to
take a look at is adding a little bit more functionality to the mixer
stuff like volume ramping over time so you can kind of fade things in
and fade things out.
Instead of only being able to just set one volume for things and leave
it there and that would also give us like panning back and forth if we
want to like move things around over time.
So we have some stuff like that that we probably would like to have
happen.
And we also probably want to drop our mixer down into SSE just to make
sure just, you know, Cindy eyes.
It just to make sure that everything is kosher there.
So we have a lot of things that we could look at in that respect and I
don't know which one is necessarily the most logical.
I think probably what we would want to do first is take a look at the
streaming stuff, because that would affect the way this Loop kind of
works at a higher level than the other things would like the other
things are kind of about interpolating.
Values inside this Loop which is not really all that relevant to
anything meaning.
You know, we can add interpolation in these Loops in there really
isn't going to be a whole lot of consequence to the external code.
But if we do want to have our sound loaded in pieces, that has a bunch
of ramifications that we might need to think about in terms of how our
asset handling works.
And so we might want to, you know, we might want to look at that a
little bit more carefully, so let's try that.
so,
Here is what I am thinking.
We have our assets stuff, set up here, right?
And when we have a loaded sound, you know, that loaded sound, we bring
that in as part of our asset streaming system, obviously it comes from
an asset slot.
That's backed by one of these info things, right assets and info.
And so as it sounds info, eventually will probably contain a little
bit of information right now.
It just contains
File name because we don't have an asset file format yet.
So we're just actually loading wav files just straight off raw
directories on Windows, right?
But in the future, that will probably have stuff like where what the
offset is in the PAC file, that we're going to read out of.
And if it's compressed or any of the other things that we might need
to know that's going to go in there.
And so it seems relatively cheap for us to take a look at this asset
sound info thing here, and we could add to that
That something that just says Hey There are some number of chunks to
this sound, right?
We could say that there are certain number of chunks of the sound and
then we could load those chunks independently.
Now, the problem with that
that's kind of the obvious thing to do, right?
That's kind of obvious thing to adhere the problem with that is that
Entire asset streaming system works off of the concept that a slot is
the fundamental thing that controls whether something is loaded or
not.
And so what we really don't want to do is extend that concept any
further than we have to because if we have our whole system working so
that we can stream assets based on whether you know, on what their
slots at us is.
So we can basically say oh, is this thing that I need loaded or not?
I can look at the slot and find out, right?
If that's the way we're doing things, then it seems like what we would
want to do is
Is figure out a better way to put that asset info into to put to pull
that asset info out of step further.
So that every chunk of a stream will sound has its own assets lat and
then that way when we go to streaming it's just it doesn't have to
think in any other way any different than any other of the sound
streaming components would work, right?
And so, let's take a quick look and see if maybe there is an easier
way for us to do that, right?
So if you see here, we've got our asset tagging system, right, and our
asset tagging system would actually allow us to do this.
If we wanted to write our asset tagging system would allow us to do
something like just sort of having a tag that advanced through time,
right?
We could have a tag but the idea value was like, you know, tag sound
section or something like this.
And we can have values that just went like 0.
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 whatever and then you know break it up that way and look
into the tax.
Now that's actually would just totally work.
I think all you have to do is in the asset sound info.
We could just put a little thing that said, what the maximum tag value
was for this particular sound and then it
Just work through the tag system, just fine, right.
But I don't actually know that we want to, there's a consequence to
doing that and the consequence is that will now get matched along with
with everything else and I guess we could use waiting to avoid it.
But what that means is that if you look here, we've got asset music
and presumably the way that will use asset music is will have a bunch
of tags that describe the kind of music and then we'll ask for a
match.
And we'll get back, you know, and a match for a particular type of
music that is then the the music that we want to play, right?
And so then we've got a sound ID and the sound system going to get
that sound idea.
It's not really going to have a way of getting back to what the tag.
The tags are that it needs to feed through in order to rematch that
entire sound ID, right?
So it has consequences.
I'm not sure that that would actually be
All that easy to do.
We could obviously make some changes but I don't know that.
That's the best way to do it, right?
So if we actually have just the sound ID and we
Somehow get to like the next sound ID, what we could do instead and
this again, like seems maybe like an easier way to go of it is if we
already have going to have a loaded sound, that comes back from this,
maybe what we could do is just introduce the concept of chaining these
sounds together.
So for example, is there any reason that I couldn't just say?
There's a sound ID here, right?
And it's going to be the next ID to play.
I write something like this and so when I load a sound in, I'm going
to have it right in the data, where if I get to the end of this sound,
I'm going to want to play this other sound back-to-back like lined up
perfectly with it.
And then allow the streaming to proceed that Wade actually because
that way we just pull out, one of these sound ideas from the tag match
and we really don't have to do anything else beyond that.
So just thinking it through out loud to myself.
Here.
I feel like of the options that we have.
That one seems to be the most promising and if that sound ID with her,
just need to set to zero, that would mean that you don't have to do
that anymore.
Furthermore, if you set that sound idea, I guess you could.
Imagine setting that sound ID to yourself.
That would be a sound that looped forever.
We just keep playing and playing and playing.
I don't know if we want to take advantage of that but we could write.
So if we were going to do that, what I guess I would say is, you know,
in this asset sound info, we just go ahead and put that in here.
Next next idea to play and that way when we go to load, you know, that
that sound info, we would just get it.
And in fact, I guess, since those are lined up with slots, to be
honest, I guess we really don't even need that because assuming,
That we know what the sound ID actually is.
We can always go ahead and get the next one from it too.
So just looking at this, let's take a look at what we would do if we
wanted to.
Just, just leave it in there.
So here's me getting the loaded sound out and we're playing the loaded
sound here.
Now, assuming that I got the loaded sound, it's a good bet that I'm
going to want to make sure that it's next sound would also be in
there.
So I want to do something where I say oh you know what?
Why don't you go?
Go ahead and and load whatever the next sound is as well.
So the assets lat right.
Where's that assets?
Lat assets lat, right?
I want to be able to get this out, right?
So I want to be able to do a thing.
I'm sorry, asset sound info.
I want to be able to do a thing where I can get back the sound info.
That went with this loaded sound, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and say info and what I should be able to do
here is say something like, get
Sound info and know that as long as I had a valid, if I was able to
get a valid loaded sound, I'm going to be able to get a valid info as
well.
So when
At that info out.
I'm going to want to say next idea to play that should actually give
me something right.
Info.
Next I need to play.
There we go.
And I'm just going to say cue it up because whatever it is you know
you're going to want to play it now.
I assume I guess I don't actually know I assume we guard 40 in here.
Yes we always do so that's good.
So it's always free for us to just say hello to sound.
Even if there is no sound to load, it will just ignore our request.
So when we do this, we now know that we will have another playing
sound, that will come back.
So what happens now is if we get to something where we have samples to
mix here and we get to the end of samples to mix, which you can see us
doing here, what I want to do is instead of just exiting out of here,
I want to end and removing, you know, the the sound, right.
I want to go ahead and play the next sound and what, I'll do a simpler
version of it first.
That will actually cause a
Skip in between them.
Basically, what will happen here is
if you imagine getting to the end of the sound, the mix buffer, maybe
a certain width, and the sound buffer is less than that.
We would leave zeros, we wouldn't feel anything in that end of the
sound buffer, but then the next frame, we do more.
So I need to do something a little more complicated to make the
playback seamless.
So for the for the minute and I'll guess I'll do here, make playback
seamless for the moment.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to actually just convert this
Click to an f and we'll do something a little more fancy in a second.
So I'm going to say, all right, if the sound would have finished,
right?
Then what I want to do now, instead of just assuming that the sound is
over, I want to see whether the next idea to play, right?
Is actually valid or not, right?
So I don't know if we have in hand main asset asset.
I don't know if we have an is valid of some kind.
Looks like we don't at the moment.
So I'm just going to go ahead and put one in here.
That's like, you know, bull 32 is valid and you can give it a bitmap
ID.
Like so and you can also give it a sound ID and oops, sound ID again.
And what I want to do here is I want to check the value and I want to
say if the value is not equal to 0 then it is valid, right?
And that is, that is the entirety of it.
So, I'm going to check to see whether this particular sound is
actually valid.
The next one that's supposed to be playing, if it's not, then we'd the
sound actually is finished, but if it is, then what I would like to do
is, you know, you can take a look and we've got this, this playing
sound guy here, right?
You can see that the only real thing that he has about that.
He knows about is just the idea in the samples played, right?
So all we really have to do to change him to play.
Another sound, is we just go ahead and set the ID to be whatever that
thing was, right?
That we wanted him to play next and then reset, the samples played to
be equal to 0.
That's that's it right?
There's nothing really to do about it that you know there's really
nothing fancy about that.
This is a prefetch here.
I guess you know the other thing I should say this is a prefetch.
So the other thing we might
I want to do is actually just make it known that this is a prefetch
meaning.
We don't actually need the sound right here, we're just prefetching.
We're just requesting a prefetch of the sound, so maybe what I
actually should do, is name it that sorry.
I just thought of that because we haven't actually talked about
prefetching, that's just to say, hey asset system, you know, this is
going to be coming up.
You probably want to get on that, right?
You know.
Don't don't be the kind of person who just leaves it to the last
minute.
That
Would be bad, right?
And so we've got let's see.
We've got loads sound load bitmap, so I want another thing here which
is like prefetch sound and prefetch bitmap.
So and really for now these are just going to be literally you know
passing right right through.
They're not going to do anything at all.
But in the future we may want to
You know, the difference between something that's saying, hey, I need
something right away and something that's like, you know, well I'm
letting you know that I'm probably going to need it, right?
Because those are two different actual requests in some sense.
Okay, so let's see here.
Well, we've got a sound ID.
Is that these guys need to be moved up if we're going to be talking
about them.
So there we go.
And we need this actual call to get sound info, which we can put in
here, we've got our call.
To get sound, which is here.
And so, our call to get sound.
Info is going to be very similar, so get sound info here is our game
Assets in our sound ID, like so and I am just going to go ahead and
grab it out of the assets.
So there's our results, return result and we can start asserting these
as well.
This is a place, we could put in a little assertion.
Just to you know, check to make sure that nothing bad is happening
right now.
So we could say, make sure the ID value is less than or equal to the
the assets sound count or something, right?
Because we know that they need to be within that range.
Okay, so here we go.
Let's double-check these just in various secret map count.
Like so the other thing we might want to do here is say that if it was
0, we might
Maybe a little bit more forthcoming about that.
Like, you know, we might want to say like value.
If the ID value is something, we actually grab it.
Otherwise we don't, of course.
That'll actually, I guess work here.
So, the only the only one where we, the only place we actually need to
do it.
I guess would be in here, but maybe we just want to return the null
sound info.
I don't know.
That's a tough call, I'm not sure.
All right, so, let's see where we're at here.
Here, when we actually, the only thing that I think we'd have to do
here is when we actually add these sound infos, right?
We're going to have to do a thing where we say, okay, whatever that
next sound to play was excited to play.
We're going to have to assume that that is a zero for now.
Right?
What did I do wrong there?
Sorry its value.
But other than that, I think we're okay.
So let's go ahead and see how we're doing here.
All right, so that's all good.
So now we got to do is we have to extend our notion of sound info a
little bit, right?
So you know, our asset sound info thing here, we'll have to have some
opinion of what section of this file, we're actually looking at,
right?
So we're talking about saying, oh, we want to read a particular sample
count and we want a particular sample Index, right?
Now our asset sound info would actually say, you know, here's the, the
range that were actually talking about for loading.
The sounds right.
If that makes sense.
Now, what we can do here, when we actually go to, to do our load
sound, let's take a look at how the info works out here.
Debug, add sound info.
Where is where is the actual load sound work.
There we go.
When we load the info out of here, right?
And we ask for that file name, what we would want to do is we'd want
to pass, you know, the sample count.
And that first sample end.
Right?
We want to pass those from the info.
And so when we when we initialize them, what we could do, just to make
it a little easier on ourselves.
Now, these could all be set correctly in the future because they
would, in fact, they wouldn't you wouldn't even need any of this
stuff, really?
I guess sample count will would probably be in there once we actually
have file format because going to say like basically how big the sound
is in the PAC file or something like this.
So it you know, you'll have something like this in the in eventually.
But what we're doing right now.
I'm just going to make it so that if the sample count is set to 0,
then I'm going to assume that it just means read the whole wave file,
right?
Because you
Never actually make a sound truck that had zero in there.
So, what I'm going to do now is say, all right, we've got that debug
load WAV file.
And here, we're now going to be passing it.
A first sample index and we're going to pass it a sample count, right?
And then when we go ahead and read these things.
And, and I guess we'll also say window sample, count and window
because we're kind of looking at a window into the sound.
So maybe we'll call it that or, or section something like this.
So, when we come in here, we've read everything.
We do all this result stuff, right?
And again, we don't care about this code at all.
We really just don't care because this is not going to be code, we
actually use at all.
It's strictly stand-in until we have that pack file setup where we can
just know exactly what we're reading.
So, when we do this, this debug load at the very end, all we really
have to do when we do, the result is, is just sort of monkey with the
result a little bit.
When we have this loaded sound, we can basically say that, you know,
if the section first sample index, oops, didn't mean to make that
still be cold window.
There we go.
Well, if the section for a sample index is not equal to 0, then we
want to sort of do an advanced, I'll do a little assert here that the
section for a sample index, you know, plus whatever the section sample
count is less than or equal to the actual sample count of the actual
file, right?
Because that would be bad if we, you know, didn't do that.
But anyway, you know, assuming that it's set properly, we're going to
set the sample count equal to the section sample count.
So we'll just get rid.
Of what the old sample count was going to be just just truncate it and
then the samples each of those both 0, you know, I guess we'll just do
for, you know, Channel Index.
Right?
32 Channel, index, down equals zero Channel, index is less than result
Channel count, plus plus Channel index.
And for each of the channels, we will just go ahead and add whatever
that first sample index is so, you know,
Moving them up to where we would want them to be if we were just
playing out a chunk of the file, right?
So hopefully that makes sense.
I keep forgetting a.
I'm experimenting lately with doing this.
I don't know how I feel about it.
I don't know how you guys feel about it.
I've been kind of liking it lately.
To be honest, the terseness I think in my old age.
So you know I basically have been saying, you know what if we just had
things that look like this?
I think this is the way I was doing them.
right, this is kind of like, you know, Jeff
Roberts, I think often does this, he has, you know, defines for things
that are, you know, as terrorists as possible.
And I don't know, they're so fundamental that I kind of liked it, Ivan
was playing around with it at work and I was kind of liking it.
So I don't know.
I don't know how people feel about it, but but I kind of feel like it
was kind of cool.
I don't know.
That was my opinion.
Oops, I always manage to get those backwards.
I always think of, type deaths like they were defines, you know?
And so I get the parameters all the time confused because I think of
them as being I'm saying what I want to Define and then I'm saying
what it should be just like a defined would be, which is the opposite
of what you actually want.
But anyway, so let's take a look here.
So we've got result sample.
Count there.
Looks like we need this too.
That looks like our only actual one is results a camp.
So now, if I run this, I'm hoping that we essentially won't.
Yeah, we won't have any
And that's good.
And so now, what I'm going to do is I'm going to take that music
asset, right?
And I'm going to start experimenting with the music asset to put us
into a position where we can test to see whether streaming in this
way.
Streaming the music in this way works, right?
So when I do add sound asset, what I'm going to do here is I'm going
to say, let's just take only one second of music, right?
And.and justjust extract a chunk from it, right?
And then add sound asset is going to obviously have these guys.
So it'll have like, first ample index, index and Sample count, right?
And those will default to zero.
So that people who are just adding one, don't really have to care
about that at all.
Wait a minute, though, where's my info at debug sound for so it needs
to pass it in here, right?
So I need to pass it like this first sample, index sample count.
There we go.
And then this guy up here, we'll have it.
Like so, there we go.
So that looks reasonable to me.
First sample into oops, Frist sample, index, always good.
Sample count.
And so, let's see if we can get it to just play one second and then
stop.
Right?
Which is what should happen.
Alright, I'm just gonna go on a limb here and say that that did not
work.
You know how I know that because the sound was still playing after a
second.
That's regrettable it's unfortunate.
It's not what we wanted to have happen.
It's true.
So you know, probably the right thing to do at this point is just
Give up and to stop programming, you know, forever, because really
it's about just saying that once you've been defeated, you should
never ever try again, or another thing we could do is externalize
blame.
We could say that that had something to do with the sound card or some
kind of, really lousy compiler bug, that was messing us up.
So, there's a lot of things we can do here to avoid having to actually
Confront the fact that we did a lousy job and when I say we I mean me,
but that of course, is another way to externalize.
Blame is to widen the scope of who is responsible for the problem to
people who really probably didn't have a whole lot to do with it at
the end of the day.
You know that's that's obviously you know, one technique that I highly
recommend.
Now let's go ahead and just say for the sake of argument that we were
actually going to be
Urgent so-and-so's who are going to look into the actual problem and
solve it.
What would we do?
Well, we know that we're playing a little bit too much.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I want to see that load WAV file
call and I want to see that, it's actually processing the section.
Okay.
So that was my first guess that, it wasn't ever actually processing.
The section turns out.
That's correct.
So basically we come back here and we see, why are we not passing
something?
Oh, well, this is great.
We didn't actually use
Use the value that I said, we were going to use.
I said it was Sample count.
First sample index, obviously could be 0.
No question.
Right?
That's the first one, we'll always have that being zero.
It's the sample count that I said, would be the one that we switch on.
So that's just a case of mean not even doing what I said that I was
going to do.
So, let's try that again and see here.
There we go.
Now we're in there and, and doing a little bit more of what we said we
would.
So let's take a look what happens now.
Much much better, right?
We just get one and then it's over, right?
So that's good.
That's a good start.
But we've got more work to do here, obviously.
There is also.
Well, alright let's let's just keep going here.
So what we want to do here is we want to go ahead and allow ourselves
to do add sound asset in a way that makes sense, in terms of this
extraction.
Now, what I think I want to do is I just want to say like One S equals
forty, forty, eight thousand for now we'll just, you know, we don't
even know or will say one, chunk, you know, one music chunk music
chunk
Girls, let's say, 10 seconds of Music.
Something like that, right?
And we'll say that we want to do one music junk.
What I want to do is I want to have ad sound asset automatically sort
of
The work of like of tracking as we add those chunks, this is just a
convenient feature to me, like I said, this code will be removed
because the actual asset pack file will already have these things laid
out for us, but we need to do something, you know, for example, index
0.
Now that I think about it, I guess I could just do that though.
Yeah, nevermind, nevermind.
I was about to say something stupid or rather.
I already did say something stupid, and
Now, I'm just going to have to take it back, so that's fine.
So what we can do here is just tracking both ourselves and that's
fine.
So the only thing I really need, add sound asset to track for me is
the next sound to play a bit and I guess even that I really wouldn't
have to.
In fact, I guess yeah we could just have it so that this thing Returns
the sound info and that would really be it right?
Add sound asset.
Just return the asset like this.
Right return asset and oops, not return.
Assert, that would be bad.
So what we could do here is just say asset last music equals zero
because again, like I said, this is just code for just doing our
testing.
So we don't really have to care if it's sustainable or interesting or
anything, it's just whatever.
Makes it simple to put things into sort of the fake format for our
testing purposes.
So when we're done here, we can basically say all right, asset this
music equals whatever.
And then I can just say last music equals this music and now we know
what the last music is.
So what I can do is say, all right, if there was a previous music,
then whatever its slot ID was, I just need to go ahead and get out
that sound info, right?
I just needed to get sound info on that slot ID, right?
Well, I guess I can just even do it like this, right?
So I can say sound infos of the slot.
So whatever the last music was I want to set its next idea to play
equal to whatever this slot index actually was right?
So this music slot ID that right, that should do it.
So really all we have to do here is is know how long the actual file
is, right?
And so if we wanted to do a few different chunks, you know, we
Could do something like this, but I'll actually go look up.
What the actual sample indices are.
Let's see here, slot ID.
There we go.
And one of the things that we probably would have to do, is actually
double check in here, when we do load wave, we'd want to make sure
that the sample count itself.
Maybe maybe instead of doing this as an assertion, we could do this as
a truncation.
Well no I guess we could do this in assertion, the assertion would
probably be fine and then we'll just take care of its head end.
Good, perfect.
We are now streaming and music and you can hear well, you probably
couldn't because you're in secondary compression land, but there's a
little Clique because, like I said, we're not doing that gapless
playback yet.
So the, the mixer isn't actually really doing what it needs to do
quite yet, but the streaming is working, fine, so that's good.
So let's take a look at how many sound samples.
This wave file actually is, so we can finish up our little loader
thing there and make sure that it's
Bubble.
So I want to take a look at results, sample counts, of course, I can't
do that because the magical compiler, never knows where any of the
values are.
And that's always good because, why would, you know?
It's not like you out, put the code or anything.
So let's go ahead and copy and paste that in.
And so inside a handmade asset when we actually make that sort of fake
thing here.
What I can do is just say
Total music sample, count equals that.
Whatever that number is.
That's how many they said there were.
And so then what we can do is say, well, we want to go until then
right and sort of the the sample count that we're going to want in
here is going to be one music chunk, unless that's actually going to
be greater than however, much was left.
So I guess what we could say is do it actually this way.
We'll say the sample count is however, much is remaining right in the
in the file and assuming that that's less than one music.
Chunk will use it if it's greater than musician, will just use one
music chunk and then we move along like that, right?
So that should get us right to the end of the file and then stop,
right?
So I think that's all we really want.
That should be fine.
Let's take a look here.
All right.
I forgot.
Of course, we we don't make our framing debug mode.
I think what we should probably do to stop having to, you know, switch
between these two is just compiled.
Just the blink code in the texture.
Mapper basically.
Just that one, we could compile that in a separate file that has
optimizations turned on.
So that we basically,
get you know all the speed that we normally have but without having to
constantly switch back to debug builds,
Does the rest of our code?
And plenty of runs, plenty fast.
It's only just that Graphics intensive part.
Yeah, so I think we're all good there.
So let's go ahead and ping back to the mixer, and take a look at what
we're doing with the mixer there.
And we, maybe it might be time to pull out the mixing stuff into a
separate file just because, you know, we can kind of button it away
and just say, here is sound mixing just like we did with the
rendering.
So if we sum all the sounds here, what you'll notice is we've got that
skip because, you know, in our little to do
Playback seamless.
What happens here is if we run out of samples, we just full-on stop
the mixing process here, but we actually want to do is first allow
ourselves to switch to another sound.
If there was another sound that was supposed to happen after this one,
right?
And if there was keep on mixing, right?
That's what we actually would want to do.
And so, what we, what we might think of here, right?
Is, is actually having this guy in like some kind of a loop, right?
So I'm just sort of thinking out loud here but suppose that we go
ahead and do this.
We're going into this Loop.
We want to do this Loop until we actually fail to load a sound or
there.
The sound is actually finished right?
Oh and so I guess one thing we could actually say here is
We could actually make this a while on sound finished set it to true,
or I should say.
While the sound is not finished, we come in here and we will do this
until we consume all of the samples in the fill up, an entire samples
worth of sounds, fill up an entire buffers worth of samples.
Or, you know, we get to the end of the sound or we find that we can't
load it.
So we have a bunch of reasons why we might want to break out of the
loop, right?
So all right, so first of all, we would break out of the loop if we
had to load the sound because that means, there's nothing for us to
play, right?
So that's fine.
Let's see here, we pick out lupus or something else to play.
We break out of the loop.
If the sound is finished, which is, which is also fine, and then we
would remove it, right?
And so, we will also want to break out if we ran out of actual
samples, right?
So, if, if we consumed all the samples, we would break as well, right?
It's kind of a nasty little Loop.
There's a lot of reasons why we would exit.
Maybe there's a better way to structure it.
Watch think.
At that as we go.
So we come in here, we're loading the sound.
We do all the stuff we want to do if we get to the only thing, that's
a problem here is right.
The samples to mix and samples remaining in sound this
This stuff is needs to actually be kind of nice to now persist outside
of the loop, right?
I guess that might be a way that we could make this work a little bit
cleaner as well.
Yeah.
But anyway, so we coming here, we know that we want to try and mix
sound into the sound buffer to fill it completely, right?
We know we have a certain number of samples to Output, we want to fill
that.
Completely.
So we're going to start with that.
We know how many are remaining in this sound, right?
And so we want to do is say in here, we've kind of have like this is
almost like a total samples to mix, right?
And so when we come in here, we've got a samples to mix equals total
samples to mix, right?
And then we will sort of truncate that and then what we would do at
the end when we sort of update.
Our well, actually.
Where is that?
Oh here it is.
Playing sound samples played right shooting.
When we update this stuff, which I think honestly, should probably
happen up here, right?
Like, isn't this a little busted isn't this is this, right?
Like, if shouldn't this check be happening,
This this truck should be happening after we advance, right?
We mixed all these samples, we should then right?
I mean that was in the wrong place, it would still work because the
next time through it would it would do its thing but that was not in
the right place.
So we want to actually do that check here.
So, when we actually update the samples played, we will also now take
the samples, the total samples to mix.
We will subtract however many we mixed, right?
So, this will decrement 20 and so that's actually also a thing that we
could do there that we could also
Break on.
You know, we could say while total samples to mix and the sound is not
finished right?
Well both of those things are the case because that would also then
allow us to just sort of do this.
And let's see if
it's not equal to, that's okay.
The total set.
So all we would have to do is just basically say.
Yeah, assert here, that total samples to mix equal zero because we
assert that if we didn't finish the sound right.
If the, if we didn't finish playing the sound, we should have consumed
all of the samples in the park.
We should have, like, filled all of the samples of the buffer.
So that's a little janky.
It's hard to write complex loops on stream.
I find and talk through them.
So I don't know how reliable that code is going to be, but let's see.
Oh, and the other thing that I guess we could do here to make this a
little bit easier to hear problems, as we could reduce this down until
like two seconds, you know?
So, I'm still hearing a little skipping there, so I don't think we're
quite ready yet with what we're trying to do.
So, let's see here.
Let's see, I might just want to set a breakpoint and check this case,
but I want to read through this one more time because like I said,
it's hard to write these on stream.
I wanna make sure I actually wrote The Loop.
I thought I did.
And, you know, that's, that's a little bit hard to do sometimes.
So okay, we start off with however, many samples are in The Sound
buffer that we're trying to output.
And we say that's a total we want to mix.
And so as long as the sound is still playing that, we're trying to
play and the total number of samples that we have left is, you know,
not zero right there.
Still
Left.
We're going to go ahead and try to get that sound.
Now, if we don't get the sound, then we are going to go ahead and try
to load it and break out because there's no way we can actually put
anything in the buffer at that point, right?
It's just it's a non, it's a non-starter but assuming we can we're
going to do is get the info.
And we're going to try to prefetch whatever comes after this sound
because we know we're going to need it relatively soon, right?
Well then, grab those volumes out and we'll get the destinations here.
Well, that's that's obviously a problem there.
These guys also need to be persist through the loop, right?
Because, as we move those four words, we need them to.
Yeah, we need to continue.
So, yeah, I didn't write the loop.
I thought I did as I surmised.
That's how it goes sometimes on Stream.
So anyway, we've grabbed the samples to mix and we set that equal to
however many there were left.
We then clip that basically, say, well, if there were
Remaining in the sound.
If there weren't enough in the sound itself, then we're going to need
to stop early, right?
We then go through, however, many sound samples.
We said we were going to mix, we mix them in.
We advance the to destination pointers.
We then come back.
And we say, all right, the number of samples we played in this
particular sound we advance by the number, we mixed.
The number of samples that we were trying to mix.
We just crease that by samples to mix, and I guess we could also
assert here, write the total samples to mix is greater than equal to
samples to mix like that should never be the case that that it goes
any other way.
Um so we do that we then go ahead and delete that because we're doing
right now.
We then go ahead and see if we got to the end of the sound we're going
to see if there's another one to play.
If there was we set it and then we come back through the loop, right?
We're not going to break out of the loop.
If there isn't one then the sounds done and we're out of the loop.
Like that's just a done done deal and if for some reason we did not
consume all the samples in the sound that must mean that we filled the
buffer completely.
So let's assert that we actually did that and and off we go.
All right, so I think we fixed at least one obvious bug there.
And that sounds nice and smooth to me.
Lovely.
All right.
So I guess what I would say is that seems so easy for us to support
with the way that we've architected things.
I feel like we just should, I don't know that we're ever going to
actually need it.
It may be that, you know, we've just got so much memory on most of our
platforms that the right thing to do is to load the whole sounds at
once anyway.
But that's just so easy to do.
I would say why not load music.
10 second chunks, just in case we want to run on more memory,
constrained platforms that will put us in a better position to do.
So, right off the bat, if we know that all these systems are capable
of working in very confined spaces and being able to swap things out
as necessary, so that seems pretty good to me.
I'm going to go ahead and say that's a useful thing to support, so
that's good.
We've got all that done and so maybe now I've got about 10 minutes
left here.
What I'd like to do is I guess just pull this.
Audio mixer out into its own separate file and at that point, you
know, we can start to think about do we want to go ahead and Cindy
eyes it, do you want to start adding some of those other features that
sort of thing?
So I'm going to call this handmade audio dot CPP.
For now I don't know if that's particularly good weird for it or not
but I think that's what we're going to call it.
So there you go.
So I'll grab this guy up here which is our test sound wave our sine
wave.
Rather
I'm just going to call this like output test sine wave or something
like that.
And I'm going to pound include here handmade.
Oops handmade audio dot CPP.
And I will also up here include a handmade audio .h.
There we go.
So we've got two new files there, and I'll go ahead and grab anything.
I see here with the audio stuff.
We've got a playing sound, right.
That's going to go in here, I don't know that we've got really much
else will pull.
These guys will pull.
These guys out potentially will take a look at that in a second.
All right, and let's grab that mixer.
Right.
So here's the mixer Colonel Boyd.
Let's see.
Output mixed sounds, something like that.
A Darlene 0 output, playing sounds.
So let's grab all that up.
Here we go.
And see what this guy actually needs.
It looks like he needs sort of that that sound buffer, right?
He's going to need the sound buffer so that's like what is it game
sound output buffer.
So sound buffer, he is going to need is the actually need trance
state.
Or did you just need to know what arena?
He is supposed to use?
It looks like he needs the asset array and the arena.
So I think he just needs game assets.
He just needs
Asset array and he needs, you know, a memory Arena, right?
Like so
and and this is just, this is just a temporary Arena, right?
So that's all he really needs is a temporary Arena.
I don't think he ever needs.
Did you need anything else?
No, I don't think so.
So let's go ahead and save temper.
Inna their temper Inna here and here.
So he's just, you know, ya doing some very, very simple
straightforward stuff there.
Okay?
So he needs the first playing sound, and let's see.
So that's assets.
Here assets.
There we go.
Still game State.
There's the assets again, the first three playing sound.
First we playing sound?
Okay, so now I'm not really going to go overboard here, I'm just going
to say that we have you no game audio or something like this game.
Vo State, I don't know.
But basically that game State structure, I'm just going to grab out
these two here and put them inside this thing, right?
And I'll just say audio State like that and then when you call this
function output playing sounds, you know, you'll have to do something
like this and then when it does game State, it'll just say, you know,
audio state or whatever.
And that'll just be a
Way for us to keep this isolated a little bit.
Make sure we kind of know what's going on here.
So audio State.
That's all we really have to do.
Yeah, this is just a well, you know, what?
In this play sound function, probably should go in there too, huh?
Maybe we'll do that in a second.
So, audio, State and audio State.
There we are, state
Okay, so we've now pulled it out into its own file.
Oh well.
And you know what?
It's probably not going to play anything if we don't call the
function.
So let's go ahead and grab that and actually call it.
So down here, what we want to do is call output playing sounds.
We want to play that on.
The audio State like this.
We want to pass it to sound buffer.
We want to pass it, the assets and the temporary Arena.
Right?
So that's really it I think.
Yeah.
So I think that should just play right.
Yep.
So that's all good.
And I'm going to grab out again.
That's that one that play sound function.
I'm going to try and grab that guy out as well.
Just because that seems like kind of a obvious something that would be
in the in the audio State there.
So really what we would need to do here, I'm going to put this in here
for temporarily but what we would want to do is we want to figure out
what arena these guys are coming out of and it probably
Be the World Arena, right?
It's probably going to be something that has to do with the audio
State.
What we can do, however, is we could just for now to make this
actually code be relatively correct without actually knowing any more
about it, we could just say that, you know, it's got an arena that
it's gets.
It sounds from, right?
This is It's, you know, it's a sound tracking Arena basically and you
know, it's permanent Arena.
I guess you might say.
And so we could go ahead and say that we're it's going to get its
memory from there.
And then, you know, you pass audio state in here, right?
And it just always uses whatever that arena is that you initialize it
with.
And so, when it does, it's push direct, it's going to use audio State
Karina, which is going to be whatever Arena.
You told it to use when you started it, right?
And that way, that'll let us not have this code, won't have to care
anymore.
When we go do some a little bit of our
Any reshuffling when the time comes you know we'll just pass whatever
we want to pass to game audio State and make that work, right?
Okay, so let's see here.
So we've got our audio States stuff so we just say audio States.
Like so and when we do place and game State body estate,
And that is all we should have to do.
We do need one of the thing which is then, which is when we, you know,
start things up, we would need to sort of initialize that.
So, you know, somewhere in here, when we actually do our
initialization, I want to do something where we see we just as we're
now onto something.
Here we go.
Initialize, You Know, audio State, and we just say game State audio
State and I'll pass
Pass that the game State World Arena likes.
And so then inside handmade audio, we'd have a function here which is
just going to do exactly that.
It's going to say audio State.
Oops.
Hey, we're right at the end as well.
I wonder if it should just be there.
A reason why I said game audio's day, I'm still say audio State as
well.
Game.
Audio State seems like a waste of typing memory Arena.
Rena and so audio State Farm Arena is going to be that and then you
know first playing sound will be the same as first free playing sound.
All those will be zero and that's that.
So I think that's it.
That's everything.
That we need.
And yeah, good deal.
Not bad for an hour's work.
Excellent.
All right, so let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
There we go.
If you could please prefix your questions with Q: so I can see them.
And please keep them.
The things that we talked about on the Stream.
On topic, please also, while we're waiting for the first set of
questions, coming in, I'm going to help out folks who are on Linux.
I think Martin's road in, and I asked, you know, what do you guys want
me to put in here for, for letting
Llvm properly handle this.
He was saying that that sink Val compare-and-swap doesn't want you to
do the long star.
It wants to automatically determine what the correct thing is.
Otherwise it was going to it was going to actually do a 64-bit swap
their or something like this and so this was actually the better way
to do it.
We're not actually compiling on lvm but there's a lot of people out
there who actually are.
So I try this, tell them post on the forums, whatever you need me to
replace the platform header stuff with for now just so they can all
stay a compiling until we actually go do our
Reports to llvm platforms.
I kill team 03, you should apply for a sub button.
Actually, we twitch already allows us to have a sub button.
The reason that we didn't do it was just because they had a
restriction in the contract about not being able to post YouTube
archives of our of our episodes for 24 hours and I didn't want to
delay that that posting so we just didn't want to do it.
So twitch actually offered that to us.
They're they're very nice people.
It was just a contractual thing, so that's the reason we don't have a
sub button.
Let's see here.
What is your favorite genre of music and do you see it influencing the
atmosphere of the final game?
So I guess that's a that's a very interesting question and I guess
I'll say a little bit about it it's not super on topic, I guess.
But since we were doing music, what I would say is
In general.
I would take, I take a lot of time to Define.
How things work artistically in games together, when I'm working on
them, in the case of handmade hero, there's a lot less of that, just
because of the nature of the development process, like it's an hour
and night, and it has to be very, it has to be very different in the
way that it develops as a result of that.
So, handmade hero is not really a game about fanatical atmosphere
curation which might be something that I would ordinarily do.
It's more about just sort of going with the flow because I feel like
it kind of has to be that way in order to still work in the way that
it is being developed is so a typical right with this one hour and I
thing and so no it's not.
My favorite genre music is not really going to influence the
atmosphere of the final game but that isn't to say that that couldn't
be true of some other game that I worked on.
It's just this particular game has to be more about.
Letting things happen, organically and less about controlling them.
Because just the way that it's being developed, you keyed is really no
way to do that.
It's hard enough to do those kinds of things when you're working eight
hours a day on something and have the ability to make those kinds of
specific moves.
But with the way that this game goes, it just has to be very organic.
So we will play it fairly fast and loose with a lot of things and
that's why I also tried to make the sort of theme of the game in
general to be very light-hearted because I didn't, it really wouldn't
be.
Appropriate, try and Tackle like a complex subject.
Given the way that the game has to kind of evolve,
could you sell your game to a major company for a lot of dollars?
No, I mean, I don't know what that means.
Sorry.
I think I missed the day, you added, the music.
What is the track from?
Will it be in the final game?
Know that that track will not be in the final game?
I mean unless you want to stick it in as an Easter egg I have a long
time ago, I did a piano practice blog where I would just like do ad
lib practice.
So I just sit down at the piano and play for like an hour.
Or whatever.
And then I would just take a chunk of that and upload it.
And so this is just I wanted a thing that I knew would be completely
copyright free, right?
Because and then well not cover fee.
I need something where I knew, I owns the copyright entirely and so
that was something that I owned the copyright entirely, too.
So I put it in there so I knew that
Just release it and not have to worry about it.
What is the reason you use a temporary reign in the mixer instead of a
normal Rina?
The reason is because it is, it is memory that only exists during that
function, right?
So what you can think of, right?
Is when you come into and this is just a artifact of the history of c
and of course, you know, the C++ C plus plus never really thought
anything through or added usable features to see.
So we're kind of stuck with
when you're, when you're writing and see your basically still writing
actually says,
when you're ready to see code, you're effectively writing in a
language that was absolutely breathtakingly, well done for the 1970s,
right?
So I have a tremendous amount of respect for C and what it achieved in
the 1970s.
Essentially, the C++ are screening, has never actually made any
meaningful improvements to it.
So, all of the things that you actually would want to do as a
production programmer that have changed since the 1970s,
Can't actually do right?
And so one of those is the fact that you don't have the ability to
talk about memory in a useful transient way.
And so, they had a thing that was allocated, which was poorly
supported and not really a thing that allowed you to say.
I need a certain amount of memory, but you couldn't actually do that
very reliably, with allocated on the program stock and all these other
sorts of things.
So, as a result in see, it's very, very
be simple for you to have temporary local variables, right?
Like, if you think about where this stuff lives, like, where does this
pointer real Channel 0?
Real Channel, One desk 0?
Where does where do these live right?
Well, they live on a piece of temporary memory that see itself set up
for you, right?
Because the programmers, who wrote, see knew that it was important to
have temporary scratch space.
Where functions did their work and you didn't want to have to manage
it all the time, too.
All right.
Well, unfortunately, that logic actually extends much further than
simple temporary variables.
And actually, most lines through a path of code can be thought of as
one or more overlapping temporary stacks of memory.
The get Unwound at different rates and I think if the people who had
made see, had been in their programming prying today, they would have
known that, and they would have had that
That ability in C, but they didn't.
And so what we have to do when we program in C, is we have to be able
to represent.
That fact that there are multiple overlapping stacks of temporary
memory that are
Used by any individual routine.
Some of them unwind when the routine ends, some of them unwind, when
The Logical operation, that this routine is a part of ends.
And you've seen that as well.
When we did our task stuff and managing those is very easy.
Once you create something like these little Arenas that I made.
But unfortunately you have to do that work yourself.
Because again, like I said, see belisarius too many doesn't understand
things like this, so they don't put in proper support.
In the language for them.
That's just the reality of having people who don't do serious
production programming, you know, making your language decisions or
maybe it's just designed by committee.
I don't know, I don't know why C++ doesn't understand these things,
but they don't.
So as a result, we have to do them.
But once we've done them, we can basically make our routines work.
The way I work.
The same with arbitrary blocks of memory that need to get on wounded
different rates, or that are very
Arjun wouldn't necessarily fit on the temporary stack or things like
this or where, we don't know how big they would be ahead of time.
Like that's a big thing, right?
We don't know how big this is going to be ahead of time because we
need some temporary memory here that's based on a thing that's
actually passed into us.
So we don't know how big that's gonna be.
So all of those things, we can actually do very well and do them in a
very convenient, sort of zero, almost zero cost way, unlike something
like, you know, garbage collection or things, which have a lot more
overhead.
And things to think about, we can do them very easily just by using
these Arenas.
So,
So the reason that we use this temporary memory here is because what
we need to do is we need to make floating-point mixdown buffers where
we can mix all of our sounds into it and then only at the very end
actually convert those buffers into the Final Destination buffer which
is a 16-bit integer buffer.
So what we do if actively here is we do exactly the same thing that
the C language is doing for us with our temporary stock variables.
So just like this temporary stack variable here.
Are effectively temporary stack variables.
It just happened to be huge, right?
They happen to be sample count times for right?
That's the size of this thing, big, and we have two of them.
So we're talking about, you know, you know, 8K or so, I don't know
what we're talking about.
We're talking about something like that.
Right.
So, we're basically just reserving 8K of space out of our memory pool.
We're doing all of the work that we need to do and then we're going to
release immediately that in there and because we don't want to spend
any.
We don't really want to spend any CPU time.
Do this.
We can use these Arenas are set up to do this very quickly.
All they do is just increment a value, it's just like you know a plus
and then a minus right?
It's just a very simple add and remove there's no thinking that goes
on it's always 100% deterministic and clean and so that is really
important.
And again you saw me do some the more extended things about this back
when we did the task system where I said, let's make an arena.
That just works this one task and that creates essentially like a
secondary overlapping stack, right?
That can operate.
So, typically in
Complex environment.
You often have three overlapping Stacks.
You have one overlapping stack for your temporary stack variables and
the program calls that you have one.
Temporary thing which is basically like for large regions of memory
that you need to work on temporarily which is what we're using here.
And then you have a final one, which is kind of like something that
persists for the length of an up of a logical operation, not a not a
function, right?
And that is what you saw in the task thing.
That's very, very common.
If you manage your own memory and get memory management out of the out
of the equation in terms of CPU cost.
So you literally are spending almost no time doing any memory
management like not doing you're not doing a locks you're not doing
any thinking you're not doing any free, you know, rearranging or any
of this stuff you're trying to get all of that out of their instincts
and efficient.
You typically have like a three overlapping stock pattern like that.
And so that is what you're seeing here is, you're seeing one of those
overlapping stack.
being used to get some mix bins, that we can use to put stuff into
We got some new blood asking about the absence of job.
I could you please help clean the chat by doing another Java rant.
I don't usually rant against Java because I'm not, you know, really a
job.
It's not like I you know I programmed in a lot of C++ heavy stuff and
I feel qualified about ranting about that because I know it's very
bad.
Java is just not interesting.
It's not that I like you know I'm going to rant against Java.
Java is just not a very low level language.
Write Java runs through a virtual machine or a jit
Which means you really don't have any control over, what the actual
computer is doing.
You have what you're doing is it's sort of a rubber pencil, right?
You're trying to tell some other person's very large sort of unwieldy
piece of software.
What do you want it to then tell the machine to do?
So, it's kind of like playing game of telephone, write Java is C,
already has a few unfortunate parts of that where you can't really
tell the compiler exactly what you want it to do, but you can pretty,
it's pretty close, right?
Write Java adds this really big stock in there and also it's garbage
collected, right?
Which is, which is no good at all.
That's just a huge waste of time and resources.
And so that's, you know, and I mean, maybe, you know, you can turn
that off to a certain extent.
But again, once you start turning off, all those features of java, you
basically end up back getting back to see and that's like, well, why
did you get all this encumbrance?
And, you know, it also it's an encumbrance that costs you something at
ship time too.
Because now you also have to ship all of this Java bulk.
You know, you write something in.
See you could ship it by itself, it's an executable just runs, right?
In fact, I often make things that just run.
They don't even have to have a redistributable.
It's just an X, you can just run it just works right?
And that's completely out of the question for
A Java, right?
I mean Java you have to at the very least bind all of this stuff into
your
Secure double that's like a Java VM or a jit compiler, or all of
these, like, additional sort of dependencies that that brings in for
you, not to mention the fact that if there's something wrong in those
dependencies, there's nothing you can do to fix it.
You just have to wait for the Java world to come and and do it, right?
So, you know, I really don't like things like that.
I don't want.
I don't want any additional stuff between me and the CPU, right?
I want just things that
allow me to make it easier for me to tell the CPU what to do.
I don't want people making decisions for me about what the CPU should
do.
That just doesn't help me write.
That just gets in my way.
And so, any of the things that Java might do for me, I can just write
them myself once.
And there's typically not that many things really that I would ever
want from java that I've ever seen, But if there are, you can just
write them yourselves once and then you're off and running a new done,
right?
You don't have to worry about it.
So there's really just not a lot of benefit of job.
I don't see the bonus of it, and I would also just add the fact that
if you're talking about game, programming will gain primary, just
isn't done in Java, justjust period, right?
Pretty much all games are written in C or C++, you know, there are
very, very few notable exceptions, you know, Minecraft is probably one
of the only ones that comes to mind of an actual game that anyone's
actually heard of that was written in Java, pretty much.
Every other game that you ever heard of is written in C, and that's
not an accident.
While C++ I should say.
That's that's not an action.
There's a real reason that people don't use Java for games because
it's just not suited, right?
It's not the appropriate platform for writing games.
Let's see here man.
There is a lot of questions today but not a lot of those questions are
actually on topic.
I'm just trying to scan through and see if there are any questions
that are actually on topic before, I just add some more off-topic.
If I answer some more
Fad gasket says, are you now streaming long?
Audio assets from disk tuned?
In late, apologies?
I realize it's probably already has been discussed.
Yes, we are now streaming long audio assets from disk, that's what we
did today.
Let's see here.
Yeah.
I can't remember, the Technics, patience tally, but one thing I think
we need is a fade-out when audio stops rather than a dead stop.
To avoid a loud.
Click well, yes, and no.
So
Only time that you need the fade out when audio stops is if the sound
assets themselves do not properly, attenuate at their edges which they
normally do.
Right?
And so, you know, typically you don't actually need it for that.
So I guess the way I would say it is typically you don't want to fade
out your audio when it gets to its end, the audio should be authored
to properly, go down.
So the thing that I that you're possibly talking about, I don't know
if that's your times want to
In that first.
But the part where you actually do need, the thing that you're talking
about is when you want to stop a sound prematurely, right?
And that's definitely true.
And that is what is one of the things that we would like to have
volume attenuation for.
We would also like vomit insulation.
So that what a sounds wants to start, you know, in the middle of it
potentially or things like that.
We want to build a ramp it in.
And even if those weren't true, even if we weren't trying to avoid the
click, it's just jarring to the user, right?
We don't necessarily
I want a sound to stop immediately like if there's full volume music
playing, it sounds very odd for to stop even if it wasn't a problem of
the of the clicking.
Right?
What we want to do is be able to attenuate it over time and so that's
one of the reasons that volume ramping is important and one of the
things that we want to do and I talked about us want to do that last
week.
So we will definitely do that this week, possibly tomorrow, possibly a
little later on depends.
But that and also like I was saying, volume attenuation.
Overtime is also what gives you
Reopening if you want it.
So, you know, we need it for like a number of reasons.
Once Upon a Time, the number of Hardware channels available on a sound
card was important do most game these days not care because doing
these things and software as fast enough.
Yes, that is that is exactly the case sound is now very small compared
to the power of the CPU.
And so, most of the time mixing is not really relevant in terms of
your performance profile.
I mean, you can kind of see this already, right?
So what you saw on the stream was
You know, just trying to fill the hole 1920 by 1080 screen when we
didn't optimize our code just doing that was too slow.
Right, because there's just a lot of pixels on a 1920 by 1080 screen.
Now we were able to optimize it and now we run really well at 1920
1080.
That's true.
So certainly, you know, we were able to make that work in all, but we
had to do some actual work to get a performant graphics system,
written by hand, right.
So you can kind of understand why using a GPU like if when, you know,
when you're talking to using GPU, we wrote everything in software, so
we render everything ourselves with the CPU, right?
But when you think about a GPU, you care about how powerful it is.
Hugh is because it's still on that cusp of not being powerful enough
for all of the things that you might want it to do.
Right?
It's still Graphics there, still so much.
Why did I accidentally hit the ramp?
There's still so much horsepower required to do Graphics because
there's just a lot more pixels than there.
Are sound samples to get output for any given frame.
You're just in this situation where you actually really do care, how
powerful your
EU is because it makes a meaningful difference.
Sound just is not that way sound.
There are only you know, eight hundred samples or something.
I mean just you know you do the math and you think it through, right?
It's like okay for a sound buffer, I've got 800 samples, maybe I've
got seven channels, and those things are like too long.
So we're talking about 11,000 B back-of-the-envelope that we're
working on 11,000 B.
I mean, think about that 11k.
Or 10K.
It's so tiny, right?
Compare that to 1920 by 1080 for an HDTV, write something like this
and and consider that you have to do.
You know, at least 44 bytes for color on there and you're doing 30 of
those whole ones.
A second, I mean, look at that number, right?
So the previous one, we were talking about something.
I guess I should also
So multiply the other one, let me let me multiply the other one out to
30 the second.
There we go.
So yeah, I do remember what I said.
Maybe 800 times.
30 times to, right?
So there you go.
So you look at the magnitude of the numbers involved here and I
apologize.
Like my calculator skills aren't great.
I may not have quite done that.
Exactly.
But I believe this is should be roughly.
Correct.
If you look at the magnitude of how much processing has to happen,
like how many individual things you are trying to calculate
They're really just is no comparison between sound and graphics.
And so as a result CPUs, nowadays are so overpowered for doing sound
stuff that it really just is not relevant.
You don't need a separate processor to take any of the load off
because it's just miniscule compared to what a graphics workload.
Looks like and CPUs are now capable of doing Graphics workloads, you
know, at those at those scales even as we as we proved on handmade
hero,
So yeah, so sound cards are just not useful and that's why they try to
differentiate themselves with other things.
Like how many speakers you know, weird configuration processing stuff?
I don't even know.
They try to add extra things to make themselves valuable because they
need to because there's really no need for them.
What is not true?
Is that compression is not always or decompression, I should say.
Isn't that always free?
You know if you want all of your sound files to be compressed with
fairly heavy weight compression such as
P3.
Bestie, sorts of things that decompression can start to get expensive.
And so if you're in a really rich soundscape, you know, you're talking
about 256 sounds or something like this all happening at once and
those are all getting decompressed in real time.
Because you want to say, memory footprint on, like a console, or who
knows what's happening?
You can start to get into cases where you do care about the CPU load
on decompression.
But that's exactly the kind of thing that sound cars don't actually
do, right?
So if you actually had sound cards,
That were about doing like adverb is decompression or something.
Then you might start to care again, how many channels they could do?
Because, you know, that might be actually valuable, I don't know, but,
but that's sort of more what it's about.
If you're just talking about mixing, doing it in software, is really
just just two simple.
There's no need to make that a coprocessor job.
See.
Would you ever need any kind of MP3, OGG support in handmade hero or
as wave?
Okay, for music here.
So I think that answer is going to come down to
Do we care about the game's disc footprint, right?
Because I think we wouldn't, we wouldn't really care about good music
compression.
Unless we cared about disc footprint and disc footprint, can be
relevant in two different ways, right?
Disk file and print can't be relevant.
If you just plain care about the disc footprint, right?
Meaning, if you just try to make your download size, smaller or patch
size smaller, just like if you if you just actually
Care about how much room the thing takes up on servers across the wire
and on the user's machine, you care about that music, compressions a
big deal, right?
Because it's going to give you 8 to 1 or something, probably, or
possibly more.
If you do MP3 or OG sport, depending on how much quality you want,
whatever right in 82.
One's a pretty big deal especially if you have a lot of music in the
game.
That's that's a big deal, right?
And the other place you care about it, is transfer time, like we're
doing all of our assets streaming already, right?
All of our bitmaps love.
Our sounds are all streaming in and we haven't really tried to work on
this end of it yet.
But you know, when we get towards shift time, we're going to be a
situation where we want to make sure that our asset streaming always
stays ahead of what we actually need.
So that you don't have dropouts where you don't have, you know, things
blinking away like right now, right?
You know, we're just in development, so it comes up and you see the
stuff stream in and that's fine because that's just all we're doing,
right?
We don't care about that.
But
Uno in the final shipping product.
We won't want that to happen.
That's unprofessional, we don't want that, right?
So what we want to do is make sure the streaming system is always
ahead, and if the streaming system can load less,
Rita like if they can get the MP3 decompression time down to less than
the amount of time it would take to read it off the drive in a slow
drive scenario potentially, right?
Which is entirely plausible these days given the fact that a lot of
people still have you know they're playing on a laptop with a 5200 RPM
drive like the slowest drive, you could imagine right but they've got
an Intel Core i7 in there or something like this, right?
It's entirely possible that you might be able to verbally
Compress them stuff in less time than it would take to load.
The equipment chunk off of disk.
And so that again, also saves you some time.
So, I don't know if either of those two things, if we will care about
them.
But those are the reasons that we would have to start looking into
music compression of some kind, right?
I would like to avoid it if possible because it's kind of a rat hole
that doesn't really have a whole lot of interesting stuff in it from
my perspective because I'm
Not really music compression guy.
So, the amount of insight I'm gonna be able to give to people on the
stream about what it means to have something out of orbis.
Compressed, whatever is just not going to be that great.
So, you know, there's that but, you know, if we did come and end up at
some point, we need it.
You know what I might do is ask somebody like like Jeff or Fabien or
Charles to maybe just do a guest stream where they explained, you
know, how to think about music compression or something like that.
So that it wouldn't just be a waste of everyone's time.
Is time like okay here we're slogging through and I'll gorebyss
decompressor, blah, blah blah, right?
Let's see what do you wish you could change the certainly on topic to
mrs.
Bennet, let's see.
Would a garbage collector, help us with managing the sound, buffer and
chunks.
I'm not sure what you mean by that, but assuming that you mean in the
asset system, the answer is no because so I think people seem to get
this confused a lot.
We've actually had a questions about this before so
You have to show just being virtual memory and garbage collection,
they're not really even related.
If that makes sense.
They're completely different things that solve completely different
problems.
So, a garbage collector is when you want to keep memory around data,
you know, around until nobody is knows about it anymore, right?
So basically a garbage collector is about who in the program can see
this data and might use this data and then a
as soon as nobody uses the data anymore, we
Get rid of it, that's a garbage collector, right?
That's why it's called the garbage collector because it's once
something becomes literally garbage.
Like you don't need this data anymore.
It's garbage, The Collector comes and collects it, right?
Virtual memory is about having more data than you can fit in your
working space but you want it all.
And so virtual memory is about saying, what a bit do.
I want right now?
Let's make sure that is resident, right?
And so, what we implemented in the asset system was virtual memory,
basically, a form of virtual memory.
There is no garbage in our asset system.
There is it's not garbage.
Every single sound is valid data that we want to play in the game.
Every single bitmap is valid data, we want to display in the game and
will display again and know about the entire time, what we don't have
the ability to do is necessarily load them all in, at the same time,
For two reasons, one, it be too slow, be this giant loading screen,
right?
And two it would cause us to require very large memory footprint,
Or give up like like maybe our worlds would have to be smaller to fit
all those assets in, right?
And so what we want to do with the asset system is just say let's
create sort of a dynamic you know view into this where we're only
going to have the stuff in memory that we're actually using at any
given time and when
Something new has to come in, we're going to evict something old based
on whether or not we think it will be used again in the near term,
right?
But it is not garbage.
We are not throwing it away and a garbage collector would not be able
to help us at all here because the garbage collector is not about that
knowledge.
A garbage truck is about knowing that something will never be used
again and throwing it away.
But in our case we always know about everything.
Everything is possibly to use so it's not, it doesn't.
The algorithm does not look like a garbage collector, you know.
Any real way.
All right, I think that's about it.
So I think we will call it because we are out of time and most of the
questions did not look to be on topic.
So I guess I'd say is for people who have off topic questions that
you'd like to ask, we do off-topic questions at the beginning of the
Stream.
So if you come back tomorrow at like 4:45, let's say the stream starts
at 5:00 typically come back tomorrow at, 4:45, that would be the time
to ask you off topic questions and then I can answer what
Whatever questions you have, but I try to keep the on stream questions
to ones that actually related to the stuff that we're working on so
that we can not get too wildly off topic as think sometimes want to
be.
Alright, so let's go ahead and close things down here.
There we go.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me.
For another episode of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, if you want to follow
along,
And play around with the source code.
You can always do so by pre-ordering the game on handmade here at org
and it comes with all the source code.
So you'll get a little download link that you can use every night to
download the source code.
After I'm done with it then you can play with it.
We also if you just want to split the video series, we have a patreon
page, you can send subscribe to.
It's also very much appreciated if you would like to do that.
And we also have a forum site where you can go to ask questions and to
get ports to Mac and Linux that community members have done.
If you're trying to follow along and platform, it's not Windows.
Those until we get up to those platforms.
That's a good place to go.
We also have a tweetbot that will tweet the schedule at you and so if
you want to catch the stream live, that's the place to do it.
I think that's basically it.
I said everything that we need to say, don't think there are any
additional items so that's about it for today.
I will be back here tomorrow at 5 p.m., so please join me.
Then, if you would like to see some more audio mixing coating will,
probably do volume ramping.
And maybe look at like, panning in that sort of stuff will probably
start doing that tomorrow.
And, you know, I don't know how long that'll take maybe a day, maybe
two.
And then from there, we'll probably go into the SSC stuff.
Cindy is the mixer and then that's it for the mixer.
We can probably just put it away.
There are some interface things we might want to play with, in terms
of how you can control sounds that are playing.
But we'll look at that probably when we're doing the volume ramping.
So, that's about it.
Thank you very much for joining me.
I hope to see you here tomorrow, until then have fun coding and I'll
see you guys on the Internet.
Thanks everyone.