There we go.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we code a complete game live on stream.
We are at an exciting.
Eh
what can I say, right?
It's just, it's bristling with excitement.
We're at a bristling point in the code where we finally get to dive
into our debug data that we've spent a bunch of time figuring out how
to collect reasonably well and yesterday.
We added just a little bit of interface code to our debug overlay, to
allow us to kind of hover over things and get some info on that.
So today, we're going to get to play around a bit and do some fun
things I think.
What I'd like to do is I'd like to make it so that we can kind of
interact with that.
Debug data do something kind of fancy where we can, you know, like
drill down into it and like, look at individual sections of it more,
that sort of thing.
So, I don't know exactly what we're going to do there.
I don't have a concrete plan.
Not really in terms of what we're going to do in the code, but more.
So I don't necessarily know the best way to visualize some of this
stuff.
So that's a little bit of a, of a thing that's up in the air.
But we will start playing around with it and see what shakes out.
Basically, our goal is just to make something that'll be kind of easy
for us to use and allow us to do something, you know, to quickly kind
of inspect our data.
So I'd like to kind of jump right into that it's day 18.
Nine here.
Which means that if you preorder the game on handmade here a torque
and you would like to follow along with a coating that I'm doing.
What you want to do is take day 188 source code, unpack that
introductory and then you will be at the same place that I am today
and so if you are interested in following along, that is the thing to
do.
Alright, here we go, let's get started here.
Where we left off, if you recall is we had sort of the ability to now
like
Pause the game.
Well we don't really pause the game like the game still runs but we
pause the debug processing, right?
So as the game is running you know as we're coming along we can at any
time pause and then we have this sort of information over here and we
can go through and look at what it is.
So if we want to know what that was, we can see that.
That's like something called do tiled render work.
Which of course, we know is in our render, we know how many cycles it
took that sort of thing, right?
And furthermore, we can kind of see just by looking at this.
Now what takes the most of the time, you can see that game update, is
this giant thing here, right?
So we kind of have a good idea of what's going on.
Like, here is frame frame rate, wait here's frame display.
Here is our debug collation, right?
So you can kind of see you like pretty quickly, right?
What's going on?
And it's kind of nice, right?
It's pretty, it's pretty handy.
However
Handy, as it may be.
What the problem that we have is we have a lot of more debug events.
We can't, we're only as playing the top level ones.
Here, we don't have a way of like getting
And finding out like all right, you know, I see that game update is
taking this big chunk of time.
I would like to now expand that and say, what, you know what's
actually in there like what's actually underneath that it taking its
time, you know?
So that's what I'd like to do.
And I was thinking, you know, these framerate bars maybe they'd be
better off going horizontal in the reason I was thinking that is
because, you know, if they were horizontal, we could probably put the
name of the thing, inside their potentially, even or if there's stuff
that we could probably do,
Do that would make it a lot easier for us to use.
And so what I'd like to do is just kind of start working with that.
Like I said, get get this, get this into some state where we could
kind of expect it.
Maybe put it, maybe put it here, so we can kind of interact with that
way.
I don't know, but that's what I'm going to start playing with.
So again, we have most of the stuff we need we just have to now do
some work to kind of pull it together and make it into something.
That's kind of usable, right?
So I'm going to try, I'm going to start to try a few things in that
area and see what we can do.
So here we go into handmade debug dot CPP.
So if I wanted to do something like that, where I was going to turn it
sideways.
If I wanted to turn it sideways, that's actually not too difficult to
do, right?
Because this is the this is the only code that really has anything to
do with the chart, right?
This is the thing that draws it.
So all I really have to do the turn it on its side is changed sort of
the way that I'm interpreting these variables instead of saying that
you know I've got the chart height and width and they mean us
Thing I can just sort of rotate it on its side.
So if I want to I can say alright you know the chart with is going to
be instead the chart height and that's going to be like how many we
have vertically and the chart with is going to be the thing that's
fixed, it's going to be, you know, a certain amount however, much that
is.
And, you know, since it's going to be running from left to, right, we
can also make it a little bit bigger.
We know we could make it, 1000 could be the entire width of the chart,
so that things could be able to bigger.
So that's also kind of cool.
And then for our lanes, right?
We're going
To have laid Heights, not laid widths so that's good too.
Same thing with bars we got bar Heights that's going to be the lane
with or sorry the length height right times the lane count and I'm
going to make those Lanes.
I'd like to make those a little bit bigger so I'm going to make them
20 pixels High.
I don't know if we've got enough room for that will see, you know, I
hope we do, but I don't actually know if we do and so the spacing
there again, bar height, the spacing on.
It's going to be oops, spacing whatever.
The bar height is plus some little spacing.
So,
Can leave some Space Between the Bars, right?
Okay, so there is Arthur's are kind of chart height.
That's the total height of you know, of the chart there is our chart
left is still going to be the same right?
Our chart Min Y at now we don't really have a Min y so much we kind of
have like a starting point and we're going to go down the screen on
that so we're just going to call this Chart top for now and I think
that that is what that would be, right?
At the very top of the screen and going down for now, right?
And we'll sort of, think about maybe doing some fancy stuff, as we as
we pull up right now, we just want to kind of get it, you know,
drawing reasonably.
So the scale is again, going to be the same sort of stuff, but now
we're going to we're going to be scaling based on the width.
So, that's, that's really all we need to do there.
So, as we come through here, now we just have to kind of re rework the
way that we're making these rectangles, that's really the only thing
that we're going to have to do.
And so now what we have is we've got these
Guys, the sense of these guys is kind of going to be a little bit
reversed, right.
Instead we've got the stack X.
Is going to start with the chart left, right?
And the stack, why is going to start with the Chart top?
And then it's going to go down based on how many bars we have, right?
So we'll kind of come down, down down down, you know, so then we've
got our Region's here.
We're going to make our, you know, same same stuff as we were doing
before.
We've got our colors and the Min and the max.
Why are actually now going to be Min and Max X?
Right?
So we're gonna start at that X.
That's not guess that's kind of advancing forwards.
We're going to add the scale just like we're doing the for and get'em
And Mac, Mac sex, and then we've got to sort of put those in here.
So now we have to do is say, all right, we've got to this Min X and
this Max X, we know those.
But now we have to sort of do the equivalent that we were doing before
for the Min and Max wise, right?
So the min max wise are going to be a little bit different.
We have the stock why that we're starting with but the max is actually
since it's coming from the top down and again why gets decreased
decreases as it goes down the screen that's stacked.
Why
Why is going to actually be the maximum value, right?
That's the actual maximum value.
It's up at the top and the minimum value is actually going to be
taking that that Top Value and subtracting away how big Elaine height
actually is, right.
So that's that's how that's going to work there, right?
And so this is actually the value that we would be using and you know,
to place the actual lane and then for the one that's that's lower
down, right?
The one that's lower down is actually going to just be the
Lane height plus one.
Right.
Okay.
So once we get that rectangle, we can push it on there, there's not a
lot more that we would have to do, that's pretty much it, but now we
have to make sure that we actually Advance our stack properly.
In fact, where is that code?
I guess we don't have to do that anymore because I guess now I think
about it that stuff's all handled in the collation code.
So we don't even have to worry about stacking things on top of each
other.
We're kind of just done at that point.
That's really all there is to it.
So yeah, that's that's kind of nice and there we go.
So never mind.
I guess that's
Much it and so then what we would need to do here is this this guy
where we kind of Mark off the the territory that's going to be an you
know an up-down kind of a line.
I'm going to turn that off for a minute because I think we should
probably think about
What we actually want to do there.
Think about that, a little bit harder for drawing in like marker
lines.
You can tell a fascinating.
So I'm just going to see if we got our chart turned around reasonably
here.
So there we go.
Okay so it looks like we're almost there but it looks like I messed up
a little bit on the you can see like these guys are really thin for,
you know, they're getting wider.
So it looks like I didn't quite do the the width, I'm sorry, the chart
highlights properly, so let's make sure we've got that.
That set up properly.
So we've got, oh, yeah, right.
That was just, that's just a stupid mistake.
I incremented the wrong value.
I wanted to go to the next Lane index.
I didn't want to change the lane height, so yeah.
Okay, so now we've got a more sane looking thing.
This is roughly, what I was expecting to see, right?
So that's all good.
And now we've kind of got a thing that we could work with little bit
more.
It is still a little too long but then again, like I was saying that's
just because our frame rate is really bad at the moment.
If we were to actually do this at a reasonable frame, right?
Which we could do pretty easily,
We could probably do it just by having this be optimized for starters,
then I think it would fit on the screen relatively well, right?
Or maybe not, I take it back.
So, you know the other thing that's kind of interesting is I don't
know why our frame rate weight is is so crazy.
You know why the framerate weight is taking such a huge amount of
time?
It's kind of interesting, right, because it doesn't really make any
sense.
And if we look at that code,
Do we have a bug in there?
That made us?
Because that's our code, that's doing the sleeping.
I'm not entirely sure, but we could see here.
So, here's our, here's our code for framerate, wait, right?
You can see that really all it does, is it just, you know, tries to
figure out how long we do say that it's probably buggy so that's fair
being fair to us but let's take a look.
So what happens here is we have a work counter
We see what time the work counters.
That we see how long it's been since the last time we marked the
counter
And that's the last thing we do, right?
So that's how long it's been since the last one of those, we then say
that we would like that, I guess to be seconds left.
We would like that to be however, many seconds.
We expect her to be prefer Aim, so if it's less than that, right?
Then we kind of need to do.
We need to do the sleeping.
So, you know, now that we're doing a bunch of stuff, kind of, after
that, that does create a bit of a problem.
Like, what we really probably want to do there is we want to just see.
We want to see how much time has elapsed since the last time we
displayed this.
You know what I mean?
So because really, that's, that's what we're trying to trigger the
time to.
And if too much time has elapsed.
Since the last time we actually displayed something we would want, you
know, we would want to not, wait at all, we'd want to just keep going,
at least that's, you know, my understanding of, that's, that's what I
feel like should happen, right?
And so, then as we go here, we do like some spinlock stuff to try and
get us right up to the time and that's
About it.
Nothing.
Nothing to nothing too.
Weird going on.
So yeah, I mean, again, it's kind of a problem.
One of the downsides of putting my windows is, there's no hard Real
Time stuff happening there.
So it's pretty hard for us to actually say, hey, operating system, you
can give some time to somebody else, but you need to come back to us
in time for thing X, whatever thing X is, right?
So yeah, it's one of the reasons why you tend to try to use V blank
when you're presenting through something that actually has the
Support because it's more reliable than trying to do this.
So yeah.
So this is a little janky.
So, you know, one thing we could do for now is just just turn it off,
right?
We could we could just say let you know this guy goes away and we
don't
We don't try to give any anything back to the OS.
Right.
But that also means that our
What happened there?
Don't know what we're gonna have to look at why our region counts,
sometimes.
Overflow probably.
It probably has something to do with our threading stuff, right?
But so let's take a look at this.
So now we have our frame display and we have our debug collation, but
we don't have any more of the frame wait in there.
And so, that's a good thing, right?
Debug collation is still quite a bit of our time.
In fact, it's taking up a tremendous amount of time, right.
You can see all that that extra time in their being taken up by the
debug collation.
So, yeah.
But at least.
Now, we don't have that particular thing in there, so we don't have to
worry about it.
Kind of ruining our lives, right?
So that's good.
All right, so, you know, definitely better, right?
Definitely better but still, not still, not perfect.
So let's go ahead and take a look, too.
I mean, the other thing, I guess we could do today if we wanted to
start doing if we wanted to, to end out the week and start next week,
focusing on the user UI stuff rather than doing some of you.
I now the other thing I could do is
Is try to start keeping frames incrementally so that we can cut down
on that debug collation time.
That's another thing that we could do.
I don't know what the, what the right solution is there.
But yeah, getting rid of the frame rate, seems like a pretty important
thing to do because obviously this code is just causing a little bit
too much of a pain.
You kind of want to be able to sleep to give some time back to the OS.
But in this case, I'm not really sure how useful that would
necessarily be how reliable we could actually get that to be.
So we may want to just wait until we have
Be blank support there to actually do it.
So to do Casey, leave this off until we have actual be blank.
Support question, mark.
Or something like that.
Okay, so moving back here.
So what I would like to do and again, you know, like I was saying if
we if we take a look at what's happening, now you can sort of Envision
how?
Yeah, we should probably take care of that as well.
In fact that hits enough, I think I'm just going to make that decision
since since it's the end of the week we get this problem a bunch and
we have the the speed problem as well, right.
Where we have this problem where
Typically she just taking a ton of time so I feel like we should just
go ahead and kill to try to kill two birds with one stone and say.
Let's go ahead and try to make debug collation, be incremental right?
Instead of debug collation being this thing that you know, that we
have to have all these like constants for and just nasty stuff like
that.
So if we wanted to do something like that, right?
Here's the way that I would suggest.
We do it, we have debug frames.
And what I'm going to do is I'm just going to have a debug frame.
Thing where we just do like, I don't know.
Well, you know, we can still actually probably do debug frames in just
in just an array and we could just say, all right, we're going to keep
some number of Prior debug frames, I don't know how many of those we
should actually keep but we will, you know, will keep however many I
guess however many the the data supports or something.
And then what we can do is we can have our collation be more of a
permanent thing that runs for words, right?
So the way we would do that is we would say something like these guys
are these guys are not removed.
Like every frame like this stuff doesn't re re do every frame, instead
what it does is it restarts itself.
Every time we ask it to, right?
Because right now what's happening is we have a memory Arena and we
start
Things.
And then every frame we restart and start coding again.
But what we could do instead is just say, oh keep collating.
And then, the only time we're going to actually restart is when we
actually decide that it's time, you know what I mean for a restart,
right?
So let's do the simplest possible version of that first and then we'll
try a slightly more advanced version of that, right?
So, here we go.
What I want to do is to see if this works is assuming that we are not
paused.
What we're going to do is we're going to allow the collator to run
forwards and and we're not going to do this.
Begin temporary memory.
Right.
So instead we'll let begin temporary memory happened here.
And then what we will do is we will only restart well, we'll call
Kool-Aid, debug records.
Like so we will only restart when we actually run out of frame
storage, right?
Does that make sense?
So this is going to be something and in fact I guess we can test it
like this as well.
We could do it in two steps.
Here we go with, internal void, restart relation, like so.
And the way that would work is we would say this thing here.
Yeah, this thing here.
Can happen whenever we want.
So we'll go ahead and do that.
The books date, you hug States, and we just call restart collation
with debug state is ME.
So, yeah, assuming that we don't, you know, want to do anything else,
we just restart and this is the same way that we were doing it before.
Oh, and I guess I have to still have this defined until we finish that
part off, right?
So pound to find my freezer per frame.
I don't know how many, but there's a bunch.
So, there we go, right?
and that's just working the same way as before and we still have a ton
of debug collation time on the, on the wall there on the wall clock,
as you saw,
So now the question is, what if we just, you know, kind of did it in
sweeps.
So now we just left debug, you know, we look at Co ladybug records and
if we take a look at this, you know, click debug records, kind of does
this sort of initialization thing, right?
What if I move that out?
In fact, we could even imagine moving this out and still running it
this way.
So inside restart collation, we actually do that.
So the whole thing gets done, right?
Like at that at that restart point, right?
Again, should
Work, and it does.
So that's all good.
So now in Psycho, ladybug records, when this thing's going through,
what we can do, is, we can sort of move through those event array
index.
He's, we can just remember the last one we processed and start there.
So, instead of starting at the invalid array index, plus 1, we can
just start at the last array index that we used.
Does that make sense?
So when we do a restart,
We do we start collation.
We do something like debug State you know event or collation array
index, something like that.
We can just say OK there's the invalid event array when we do the
restart.
We remember which one that is and we start at the one immediately
after that.
In here, instead of passing that in, we just always start from
whatever the collation array index is.
And in fact, we could even do this as a while loop.
We could just say
Well, actually, you know what?
Yeah.
I guess it's literally this now, which I realize is not particularly
exciting, but then the event array index is now actually debug State
collation R and X.
So we're just going to we're just going to kind of move that guy
through right?
Like so and he is now a stored value, you know what I mean?
And we could actually we could just avoid doing that for the rest of
this by just sort of grabbing it out as well.
Something like this.
Okay, so we've got collation array index now but we need to store that
up here so that would be something like you know, you 32 relation
re-index.
There we go.
Invalid event array index is an Undeclared.
Oh right still have to pass it in.
I take it back so then we start collation.
We have to pass the the invalid.
One and the invalid.
One of course is this one.
Okay, so there we go.
So now as we do this, well, assuming that we can get past that sort of
annoying roadblock here, which we're sort of working towards removing
permanently,
So, now, when I do this, everything is still working the same way.
But now we're using a permanent variable for the collation.
So, now we should be able to do is actually just do this
incrementally.
So, we only, we only actually process one, the new information.
Every time we only we just process, we don't restart every time we
just keep going incrementally through.
So we don't have to reprocess all the debug events.
We only process the ones that came in since the last time we were
called.
And then in terms of
Starting the collation.
What we will do is we'll only restart the collation when we hit an
actual limit of the frames that we can store.
So, you know, whatever that frame count is whatever.
Our Max frame count is, so in here, right?
When we did our frames, you can see that we only have room for Max,
debug event or a count times 4.
That's how many we've got what we can do, is as the frame cap gets up
when it goes, you know, I'll just for now, say, it'll be this or
Something like that.
Just for the sake of argument, I'll do if the frame count has gotten
up above that.
Max.
What was it?
Do you like Adventure account?
There we go.
If the frame count gets up above that, then we'll restart again just
for now.
So debug State frame count, if it's, oops, if it's greater or equal to
the max debug event.
Array, count.
Then we restart.
So let's see what that does besides just instantly crashing.
Oh, and we'll probably have to store a current frame as well, if that
makes sense.
So yes, obviously one thing that's probably a thing thing that we need
to do is actually call this once, right?
That's pretty obvious because we have to start somewhere but then we
would restart every time here.
But yeah, good point, current frame.
There is going to have to be tracked as well, because that's actually
a global variable outside that Loop.
So it's got a persist, right?
So,
Same goes away and it comes into here, right?
So this is like, you know, collation frame.
And so when we do that restart, debug State collation frame,
We set that to no.
And again, all I'm doing here is I'm making this Loop be something
that runs incrementally, instead of just, you know, one time through
the loop.
So now we just replace everywhere that was using current frame.
We use debug State collation frame, that's it.
Oops, current frame.
Debug steak relation frame.
And that should be it.
And so now we'll see.
I don't know how this will end up working.
Looks pretty good so far, let's go ahead and break out here.
Okay, so unfortunately now I it still looks like there's a fair bit of
time being spent there.
I'm not actually sure why.
I feel like that should have dramatically decreased the amount of time
involved.
And to be fair it did decrease the time, just not as dramatically as I
would have expected, right?
The time appears to have gone down, but it
Not go down to the extent that I would have expected.
So I'm a little confused about why that would be.
Let's figure that out right now.
So okay, what actually has to happen in here?
Collate, debug records, we don't do anything else, right?
Yeah, we don't do anything else so collating, the debug records is the
only thing that we're talking about there, right?
That's the only thing that's actually,
time spent, as far as we know, anyway, so if I go up to collate, debug
records,
I take a look through here, we're going to come in.
We've got a particular invalid, array index.
What we know is that as we go,
We yeah, we start on whatever that that indexes.
Whatever the last one was that we were using.
And
Go till we hit the invalid one.
And that should, I feel like that should have worked and we should
only process like one of these, right?
We then go through all of the events which is what we would expect to
do and that's all totally fine.
Nothing particularly weird there, right?
I also think we don't need this code is never going to get used
anymore.
We sold could get rid of it.
Let me go ahead and move this up as well.
Yeah, so I'm not really sure.
ah,
you know what, though?
I do think, I know what this is.
We need to be able to store more frames.
Otherwise, we're always going to be at that Max debug event count,
right?
So as we run through, if we don't check for that or something
high-hazard reset condition, the sort of fake, you know, fo reset
condition.
I set up temporarily here.
If we don't check for that, then we actually would restart every time
because there's always going to be that many frames in the buffer.
So that was kind of dumb to be fair.
Let's see how this does this.
Does any better?
No, no.
Yeah, a little bit better, still not as better enough as I would have
hoped, but you can actually see.
Now the bars don't even extend to the end.
So it still takes a lot of time to do that operation.
It would look like right for a lot of these guys and so I don't know.
It seems like a little unrealistic but maybe there's just that much
data and maybe the stuff that we're doing is, you know, maybe the way
that I'm doing it is janky enough.
That it takes so much time, I don't know it warrants a little bit
further, a little more attention, I would say.
Because it feels like it feels like there shouldn't probably be that
much stuff necessary, you know, it's it doesn't seem like it should be
quite so.
So time-intensive I'll double-check and just see what happens if we
compile, the collation code with optimizations on just so I can get a
feel for where it's at there but we'll see.
All right, so with optimizations on it's not so bad.
It looks like when we actually so you get you get obviously spikes in
terms of how long it takes to collate when we when we hit things like
the ground chunk filling and that makes sense because
Those things really pound on to the renderer and stuff and I think and
other things that we have instrumented so that's not surprising.
But yeah.
So at least in, if we, if we go optimized we can actually sort of have
these guys running in the collation running.
Totally in line with everything else and it's not a problem at all.
Apparently.
So that's pretty good too, right?
Yeah.
Now, I'm not sure why right-clicking turned off everything.
So if the debug state is not paused,
What is the problem?
Why when I right click and we go to be paused, why am I why is it
erasing all of my all of my data?
You know.
That's a little strange.
I'm a little uncomfortable with that.
That should not be happening and so I feel like I messed up one other
thing.
They're right.
Because I don't know if you guys saw that.
We're going through here.
I right clicked.
And now we're gone.
I right-click again and we're back and I don't know.
Right?
I don't know why.
That would be happening so that's that's off-putting.
It leaves a bad taste in one's mouth.
And so I feel like we should try to figure out why that is.
So that's just all that is, is setting paused, right?
I mean, all that happens.
When you right-click is you set to pause.
And so, the only thing that pause does is actually called these guys,
so it means that collate, debug records would not be getting called
but I don't see why.
Kool-Aid debug records getting called would have anything to do with
it.
Like it doesn't seem like that would really cause all that much of a
problem.
So I'm going to have to I think step in there.
Also, the thing I guess, the other thing I do is
Is that some kind of weird bug?
We have that only happens in optimized mode, I assume not but since we
were in debug mode I'll go ahead and just double check since I don't
know.
Okay good.
It happens in debug mode.
That's, that's always nice.
You never want to have a bug.
That only happens in optimized mode because that's a lot harder to
inspect the code.
But, you know, sometimes you get unlucky.
So, when we do hit that right Mouse button, I'm going to go ahead and
see what happens here.
Why we end up in a circumstance like we did.
So, I'm going to set the break point.
I'm at the break point, right?
At when I hit that right Mouse button, you know what I mean?
So we can take a look.
Let's see.
Is that right there, I guess?
Okay, so there I hit the right Mouse button, we set the state to be
not paused anymore.
So, here we come, we've got the frame Count Their weirdy but we're
setting it.
So that's all good.
And this stuff is just doing its little frame drawing thing.
And so I'm going to go ahead and just set a break point for the next
time we come in through.
Frame n since I'm assuming, that's the place where things would go
wrong.
Let's take a look at our our debug state.
so, if we take a look at this, oh,
Okay.
Paused is set to 0 is that?
Because we have not grab it.
Yeah, that's because we have not grab the debug state yet.
So that's understandable.
There we go.
It's set to 1.
We are set to uninitialized.
Okay.
I'm very interested to know.
How that happened?
You have to admit, that's a little bit odd.
And it gets reset every time.
I'm going to switch back.
Here we go.
And what I'm going to do here is I'm going to set a breakpoint now to
see does that happen every time?
Oh man, you're kidding me.
So this whole time we never actually set initialized equal to true.
That's pretty good.
I feel like that deserves a little out of Shame.
It's like we have a thing that says whether we're initialized or not
specifically for this purpose, we never actually check it.
That might have something to do with it.
Do you think shocking?
Shocking, I say.
Let's try that again.
Oh, hey.
Guess what?
It turns out that now we don't take very much time to do the collation
either.
How surprising.
Yeah.
So now it makes a lot more sense.
Why we were seeing that?
Because it was redoing the whole thing every time.
So now our collation is not too bad and that's pretty great and you
can see the spike, right?
That happens in there.
Occasionally there it is.
You can see the spike that's when we get that reset event because like
right now, we still do a clean reset every so often because we don't
have it set up to, to do like,
Lot of movement in there.
So yeah, so that's that's totally fine.
But now we should we should go ahead and address that as well.
However, you know, there's one, I don't know.
Yeah.
So there's so many things I want to go do now because now that we're
starting to get like kind of interesting little setup here I'm kind of
it's going to.
I think that's going to be a lot of fun.
But anyway, so I think what I'd probably like to do now is make it so
that these frames get stored kind of permanently in a more sort of
concise way.
Something like that.
And so that when we do,
The frame analysis, like the kind of get get put out there.
And so I think what I'm going to do though, honestly cuz I'm trying to
juggle these things in my head, I think I might do the expansion thing
here because we've got, you know, we've got 20 minutes, 25 minutes, I
might go ahead and do the expansion because if I do the expansion then
that's going to tell me a little bit more information about what sort
of stuff going to have to do in terms of reprocessing things.
And so I'd like to kind of see I want to see that in action first
before I go any further, I think.
So I'm going to go ahead and try adding the ability to like expand
stuff out here and I'm not sure exactly how to do that yet.
I'm not sure exactly how to visualize that as I guess what I'm saying?
Guess we just like blowout that bar to be that size.
Or something.
I don't know.
Let's figure it out.
So right.
At the moment.
You can kind of see in here that the way we're doing things is we do
this first open, block parent equals zero thing.
So what that does is it says we're just throwing away, any timing
blocks that happen underneath some other timing block.
So the top-level timing blocks show up, but the timing blocks below it
don't.
So all I would have to do to modify this to show me things.
Low a certain timing block, right?
Because I just need a way of making this.
Detect some other case like things that are below something besides
just zero.
You know what I mean?
So if you look at our, handmade platform stuff here,
Our debug record structure definitively, identifies a particular place
where a like a particular timing block.
So what I could do is instead of looking at the parent thing here,
where I do like first open block parent or whatever, instead of
looking at just that parent pointer.
Which again if we look at what that is that parent pointer is actually
pointing to one of these things, right?
Instead of looking at that
I could do is look at the debug record to which that thing corresponds
and check against that.
So for example, in one of these open debug block things,
Right?
I could say this is like the source and so, then when I create one of
these open D, Bud blocks, you know what I could do is when I create
one
And I write down the stuff I could just write down its source as well.
So now I know for whatever, you know, block that is, I know which
source it is in that in that little list so that when I can say is I
can I can do something like you know make a thing that's like if is is
direct child of or something.
And I can say you know is
Is this event that I'm talking about here?
The thread first open block.
So the matching block, right, this was this was this.
So it's that, it's that original guy, the guy who was open when we're
about to close, whichever block that we're looking at when we're about
to close it.
What we want to say is is that guy's parent
This, some debug record.
Does that parent come from a particular, debug record?
Right?
So we can ask or we could even say is from debug record.
So we could say, matching block, parents, whatever that is is that
from our, you know, scope to record whatever that is
Right.
And so what I'll do is I'll say, well, you know what, I could even do
this slightly differently, I could do record from
Equals get record from.
For or just script record.
So that would just say for this guy, give me the record to which it
corresponds to, I don't want to access it directly and the reason for
that is because it may be no.
Right?
So I'm just doing a thing here where we say, okay there's an inline it
returns a debug record, it's called get record from like so it takes a
debug or open debug block.
And all it does is it goes like okay the result is what if there was a
block.
Then it's the block record, otherwise 0.
So it's just like passes a null through essentially.
Then we can implement the exact same functionality we had before by
setting our debug state to just have a permanent record you know
that's like debug record scope to record like that and then when we
initialize things in here,
When we do our initialization, we could say stuff like.
Oh, okay, you know, right, pause the equals false.
Let's go to record equals 0.
Something like that.
And and you know, off we go from there and we could also do right?
Didn't we set?
Where do we set?
So I guess we
Because we call restart collation.
I guess that initializes the rest of that stuff.
So scope to record is now this thing that we can set permanently it's
set to zero at the beginning.
So this should do exactly the same thing that we were just doing you
know, sorry source.
And so, you know, this is just gonna produce the exact same output, so
we don't get anything from that.
But now what we could do is when we left click on this, we could just
say, Okay, show us, whatever is underneath that, right?
Show us like show us the things that are underneath that particular
block that I just clicked on, you know.
And so to do that, all we have to do is say well, we know what
happens, we know we gotta was pressed, right?
We have that and we know it and is inside rectangle.
So
We have to do is when we know we're inside the rectangle of a
particular region.
We could just say like, oh well, you know, was the left Mouse button
pressed, if the left Mouse button was pressed, then let's set the
debug state.
Scope to region, just go up to record, you know, to be equal to
whatever the record is that we're on.
Does that make sense?
So here we are in here and now we can go like right click then
presumably we can go over this guy and we can like click on him and
well or are totally not do that and that was a little anticlimactic.
I was I was so ready for that to actually do something and then it
totally didn't do it at all whatever programming.
Like sometimes I just
Don't even know.
All right, so let's go ahead and let's go ahead and find out what kind
of stupidity is happening there.
I'm clicking on this.
I'm not getting anything.
I should go do the was pressed thing and see what happens.
We click record is actually something scope to record is actually
something.
So we're actually setting rui is working fine, but apparently right.
Good that never gets called against.
That's working.
Just right?
But apparently, this little guy here is is not working correctly.
So, let's take a little Gander, what happens?
There, F5?
Hmm.
Oh duh.
We have to write.
Got about that.
So it was working fine, as it turns out my bad.
It's a little mistake there.
I admit that, I apologize.
We don't actually Rico late, anything, unless we're running, that's
kind of how that was supposed to work.
So, that's unsurprising.
But what that means is that we have to do a collation restart, right?
Andre collate the records when we actually click something because
we're you know, we only kind of inspect that one, we only kind of
produce the output for that one area, right?
So what we need to do here is we would need to do something like when
we have recirculation and it does that.
And then we also have like the collate, the collation routine, where
we do Co ladybug records.
Like so what we want to do there is we want to actually have a way to
kind of do that.
Whole step.
So we'd want to do something where like restart so like, you know,
refresh coercion or something that where we can do that and that would
literally just do this thing the whole the whole the whole bit, right?
And so then up at the top here, I don't know.
Yeah.
I guess we'd have to have it somewhere above debug overlay although I
guess I could just leave it down here.
Like this.
So internal void, refresh relation.
And that just does the restart.
You big state, Steven State, we go and I'll just go ahead and make
that be something that we Define out here.
Okay so yeah.
Yeah now in theory we can drill down in theory although that does not
seem to have been happy about that at all oh right.
Yeah.
I tell you doing these kind of, like, Little Billy debug things is
fraught with Peril.
It's fraught with Peril, I tell you, but it's fine.
So obviously, we can't refresh the collation in the middle of that
because we're in the middle of doing something.
So we would have to sort of delay that until the end because we're in
the middle of looping over these regions that were drawing.
So we don't want to like, invalidate them all in the middle of that,
that would be rude to say the least, but very unseemly.
So we just do this.
Again, pretty easy.
The script record
There we go.
And then at the end here we do something like this if you know, debug
scope to record.
In fact, it could even do something a little bit more like this.
So we could do hot record.
Like that.
So when we come through this this this Beast right here and we go
ahead and take that record information.
So out here we do like you know, that record, hot record 10
Then we could just do something like when that's pressed.
I don't know why that's still here, we'll get rid of that.
If the mouse button goes down, then we'll do something like if Hot
record
Then we will take the the debug State scope to record.
We'll just set that.
So we'll say okay that's the new script record.
If there wasn't a hot record, will just say, okay if the debug State
scope to record is actually valid, then we'll make, we'll make
whatever is like, go up up a block.
Well, I guess we would need to know the open block for that, though.
So, we need to trace
One more thing, right?
Which would be the actual like we need to know who the caller was.
So I guess that's a little premature.
So I guess for now I'll just do, I will just clear it but we should
probably think about how we want to handle that eventually.
But yeah.
So now we're in their right?
And we can we can pause and Theory.
Now we can actually look underneath these things and see what's
actually going on here, right?
There's a render group called, there's the same region stuff.
There's some, some debug render group things.
There's a little guys in there.
Move entity, begin Sim, right?
And so I guess, what's that tiled render group output?
What's under that?
Okay, here's some stuff tiled render work, Todd vanderwerff, Todd
render work, right?
See what's under there.
Okay, here's so we can now drill down.
Pretty good, I guess.
Unfortunately, we eventually get to a part where there's too many
regions and we can't show them.
So that's a bit of an issue but we're getting there, right?
You can sort of see how it's starting to take shape, right?
We've got a ways to go.
And again, we're not trying to make some kind of professional
profiling tool here, but we're getting there, so, I don't know.
Like, I want to go in here and see, like, something's happening.
Cloud vendor work.
I'll see what's in game update.
What's this input processing, don't think there's anything else
happening there, executable refresh.
So they go into game update.
What's this game update and render?
That's unsurprising inside game update and render.
Okay, so let's see what's in begin Sim.
So there's begin Sam.
There's these little tiny piece of times, get World chunk.
All these get World chunk calls, right?
So, yeah, you know, it's starting to be kind of cool.
And we can always restart it running and see the actual like, you
know,
Stuff happening in there.
And then we can also pop back out if we want to.
And so we still have we still have a ways to go before?
This is actually like anything.
That's that's not super terrible everything.
But we're kind of getting
You can also see, we've got problems in terms of like these things are
really slippery and we'd want to be able to like zoom in there or get
some other stuff and, you know, we we got a ways to go, we have a ways
to go.
There's no question about that, but at least we're starting to get
there.
We're starting to get towards a little bit of a better thing.
So, yeah, I would say, if I want to start something new.
Yeah, right yet.
So I think what I'll do because I've got a few minutes left.
I think what I'm going to do
Is I want this debug text line thing to become a more General thing.
So what I want to do is I want to do something like internal void D or
a text out at or something like that, right?
And I'm going to grab this guy.
Grab him right up.
And what I want to do is kind of trim this down to something that
takes that doesn't use any Global's there, right?
Well, not any Global's, but it doesn't, its positioning is said
specifically.
So if you pass into it, the string that you want printed, right?
So you do you pass in that, but then you also pass in, you know, like
a V2, like a point like a p.
So at X and at why are actual things that kind of get get
I survived here, you know, at X becomes like, you know, p.x something
like this.
and groups and at y equals, you know, p.y
that sort of thing.
And so then this code right here can actually do will actually take
out that get lined advance for so that get light advance for goes
away.
The rest of this stuff basically stays the same, right?
And so, then this code can just use that code, right?
So what it would do is it would do the exact same thing and then I
don't know these are not
Really expensive things.
For the most part.
So, I don't know if I really want to deal with that, but what this
would do is it would just call that with ADD X at y, like so.
so this is like text out at
and it's just,
Yeah, this would probably be.
Debug text that out.
This was like left Edge, right?
Something like that.
Yeah.
So now if we take a look at that, it's the same thing, right?
But now we can sort of draw text anywhere we want.
So instead of this kind of nonsense here, where the render group
output is kind of annoying and doesn't really look right, you know
what I mean?
I can I can maybe fix that to be something a little more usable and
say, okay, instead of debug text line,
Oops, text line that's getting called there.
What I'll actually do is I'll just call debug text out at right.
Oops, not there.
There
Right there.
So what I'll do here is say, okay, give up text out at, what I'll do
is I'll just use the mouse pointer, the mouse where the mouse is and
I'll print out the text buffer there.
And the reason that's a little bit nicer, at least for the moment,
right?
Is because that allows me to actually do something where it just it
kind of hovers with me, right?
If that makes sense.
Now we should also probably get rid of that that string nonsense.
So there's this giant
Gapping there for no apparent reason.
So we should get rid of that as well.
And then we also have a sorting problem where, you know this thing is
going to show up behind the bar that it's ostensibly supposed to show
up towards.
And so the thing that we can do there is we can also just kind of
offset it a little bit just for now, there's probably better ways of
us doing that but we can make a little offset now where we do
something like, okay, you know, will offset it by 10 pixels up or
something like that.
So now
When we pause, we can just see, you know, exactly what's going on
there.
Right next to where we are.
So we have to look up the top of the screen and you can kind of see,
like, Okay so we've got we definitely have sorting problems there.
So we want to, you know, once we actually sort of upgrade the rendered
do like a little more sorting stuff, we probably want to have a way of
saying draw that on top, you know, of whatever it is that you're
drawing.
So you don't get this that kind of like hard to see thing but yeah, so
it's getting a little bit better and that's it that's a pretty easy
way for us to be able.
To inspect what's going on and see pretty quickly.
So we can click on game update.
Say, okay, there's what's happening game update, there's Taliban group
output, there's Ence, and there's the right.
You know, all these little guys in here we don't care about because
they're don't take a Time.
Apparently begins in ETC.
Push Bender element.
So yeah looking pretty good.
You know it's not it's not great yet but it's getting there.
Right?
One hour at a time.
Eventually end up with something pretty cool.
All right, so let's go.
To the Q&A.
If anyone has any questions about what we're doing here?
If anyone has any questions now would be a good time to ask those
questions.
Put a q KO in front of it so I can see it.
Let's go.
Insofar as are the events.
Keeping the same colors across frames the long one.
Looks like it keeps changing.
No, the events are not keeping the same clothes craft frames.
I'm not sure how we want to deal with that, but the events are
actually just purely randomly plucked by order into this color array,
what we might want to do is try to make it so that there's a more
clear way of drawing.
What is going where?
But I just haven't given any thought yet.
It would be nice to maybe track the colors across frames and there's
actually pretty easy ways to do that.
It's just they you may have two things that stack up next to each
other that get the same color, right?
Because we could trivially make it like we know what the debug record
is.
You know what I mean?
So we could do something like oh yeah you know whatever.
You know, we use that instead of, instead of this, you know, we just
do.
Okay, we've got the record.
That's a pointer, right?
So we just cast that to a u-32, we shift it down by 4, right?
And then we mod, you know, the
or something, maybe maybe too, right.
What's the record?
What's the what?
What is the record?
It's called region.
So, you know,
That obviously would always keep the same ones, but we'd have to have
a better way of making it so that they were, you know, it picked more
distinct ones or, you know, so these are all do tiled render work.
So they are all the same color but then we have these guys, I guess
part of it is I don't know what the I don't know, the best way to kind
of re randomize that since they're going to go on even amount.
So you know like we can multiply by a prime number here or
Bang.
And I mean, you know, like I'm just this is just pure lunacy at this
point, but
You know, let's see here.
So, if we go into game update, there you go.
Begin soon.
Render.
That's that's no better.
Is that right?
Yeah.
So I don't know.
I mean the other thing we could do is try to actually assign the
colors based on the universal index.
We know we don't have enough for however many there are but like, you
know, in that debug region thing where we're actually recording that.
Let's see.
Where is that?
Bug thread, debug frame.
Debug frame region, right?
What we could do, there is also store like a color index.
You know, and I don't know if that's going to be particularly useful
or anything like that, but we could, you know, we could even do it
relatively for basically for free, right?
And so if we wanted to do that, then we just do, okay?
Whatever the color index is.
We looked at up, you know, and the color index for the region could
just be based on the counter or something.
So you know, inside inside where we actually record stuff for Regions
down in here, we do region color index.
And we'd use the debug the debug record index.
You know, to do that.
Something like that.
And so then they be stable across frames, but again, yeah.
So we just need, we need to draw lines because like, these are like
back-to-back all the same function, but they're different invocations
of the function.
And that might be nice to see, you know.
But yeah.
Now, everything stable across across frames, which is obviously kind
of nice, you know, certainly
so,
Yeah.
K just 0.5 Pixar, initially stream matter a lot.
I mean, it seemed pretty a pretty easy thing to overlook.
Would it make some calculations erroneous typically off by a half
pixel errors?
Just result in slightly worse visuals except once in a while where
they really cause you problems like with seems or with something that
shakes a little bit.
So yeah, I mean what I would say is your mileage may vary.
It depends a lot on the situation how much that affects what you're
doing.
Or not, most Persnickety, Graphics, things like that.
It's it's, you know, it's really about the specifics of what you're
doing, whether it ends up biting you that you didn't do it, right?
You know,
Soy sauce, the kid why are there blank apps on some of the bars and
why are the collated frames?
Not flush with the other lines.
Why are the collated frames?
Not flush with the other lines?
I think I might understand the first part of the question but I
definitely don't understand.
The second part of the question, can you elaborate more on your
questions?
So I can answer them K.
Is there a reason why we have many different starting points for
coordinate systems center versus top left versus top right Corners.
Windows, direct3d, verse opengl wouldn't are lions, be easier if there
is a standard for them.
Yes that's true.
It would be easier.
I mean the problem is the problem is it's not like there's some right
answer and so the reason I think that we have multiple coordinate
systems just because like I guess we've seen on handmade hero, there
isn't like some specific overwhelmingly, right?
Place to Center the coordinate system.
You could just you know whatever and so it's hard you know as
different systems evolve they just have different coordinate systems
that's just natural and absent.
Some driving force that like goes.
Okay we're going to have this big event where we all can
Her coordinate systems, right?
It's just not going to happen.
Chronodragon with handling sorting here will be finally handle sorting
of the other Sprites in the game.
Or will we just push that off further?
I think probably we should just do all the Sorting in one go like
because the renderer just should have a Sorter and then we'd use it
for everything.
Elven, why do we have both bull 32?
And in 32, that's answered back when we introduce them.
So, check out the archive and I talked about that.
James Whitman, pretty cool.
It does seem like a lot of calls take very different amounts of time,
even though they're probably not doing anything different.
Is that due to other active processes?
Probably not.
Probably not all that much.
I mean, maybe a little.
Are you talking about any particular one?
Elvin, how much valued and valuable do you think seedless, operator
overloading actually is?
I'm thinking a feeling moving to just purpura?
See, do you think it would be inconvenient to program without them?
Operator overloading for math is pretty important.
I probably would not want to use it.
I in granny, I did not use it and I miss it.
So, operator overloading for math is pretty important.
That's what I would say.
Cuba Caleb, will you show us how to do hit detection for obscure
shapes that may or may not exist in the debug you?
I know.
Because I don't even know which shapes you would be talking about.
I only really
How to do stuff that we have.
Some plausible reason why we might do
racer in a.
Have you seen the ue4 GDC trailer and what are your opinions on it?
I understand we are all Indies but just in general from a player
standpoint
I have not seen the ue4 GTC trailer.
I don't think.
Are you asking, just for my opinion of how the engine looks like, does
it look good?
Or I'm not sure what you mean.
First off, the kid, the longer bars, which I assume was when the
Collision have was happening, are farther left on the screen than the
shorter bars.
So let me see, I'm not sure I understand.
What you're talking about.
So what are we talking about?
Are we talking about?
Are you talking about why these bars don't line up with this bar?
Is that is that what you're asking about?
Kb3.
Obscure shapes.
I mean, a slice in a pie chart
Well, there's there's two different ways that you can check for shapes
slice in a pie chart happens to be convex, which means you have a
get-out-of-jail-free card, you could just check, check the winding
order.
And it works if you're talking about obscure shapes, that can be
concave like a butterfly shape, or something.
Then you need to do an edge Crossing test again.
Really simple.
It's like 20 lines of code.
You can look it up point point in polygon is like real, pretty pretty
simple.
Right?
Like point and polygon.
I don't know if any of these is good, that's why we don't use.
We still don't actually check the active thing.
It's pretty funny.
So, this looks reasonable.
And so like the the this looks like a pretty reasonable traction.
I mean the idea is just that when you have a point, you know that
there's going to be an odd number of edge Crossings if you if you're
inside it and an even number of edge Crossings if you're outside it so
you can just start looking at the edges of the polygon and see how
many of them a single line.
And this case they pick horizontal because it's the easiest one to do
like a horizontal or vertical line is going to be the easiest thing to
test because it's aligned with one accident.
Axis.
So you know, you can see 1 2 3 4 5 that's odd, I must be inside.
If I were to move out here I would have one two, three, four.
And now I'm I would know that I'm outside because
You know, you got the idea.
It's really simple.
Okay, sorry sauce.
The kids says, yes, to my question about his question.
So what's happening here right?
Is that this is one frame.
This is one thread.
So This Thread goes, excuse me, refresh input processing.
Game update, you know blah blah blah.
This point right here is where the renderer kicks off.
And so the renderer actually invokes, you know, pushes those jobs on
the job queue and you can see that we get all of this renderers.
So the other are other threads 1 2 3 4 5 6, right?
The other 6 threads all kickoff render work.
So while this thread is rendering, all these stones are rendering when
they are done.
They all stopped, we do a little bit more work and then we kick off a
second render, which is right here, which is the debug stuff.
So this is actually where our frame would be over normally, but
because we have debugging happening, we see these and this is just,
again, the same thing.
It kicks off a render, This Thread is rendering, but it but all the
there's plenty of work in that work queue.
So the tiled the other tiles get picked up by the other threads and
worked on.
So that's what these are.
So the reason that nothing's happening in here is because we haven't
multi-threaded anything else yet.
So there's nothing else for them to do.
These threads don't have any work to do, so they just sleep, waiting
for someone to stuff something on their cue, when we get to the
renderer, they can.
So in the future, you know, we might try to do is fill those holes
with like, simulation work or something, you know?
Racer in a yes the graphics check it out whenever okay so I don't
really need to check out a video for the unreal Graphics engine.
It's a totally fine Graphics engine.
It always it always has been and you know, if you want a 3D, you know,
first person shooter e Graphics engine and you don't know how to build
one yourself or don't want to build one yourself.
It's quite good quality.
It's a good quality renderer.
I can't speak for the engine.
I have never used it myself.
There may be a lot of really bad problems with it or something for
all.
I know that would make it very unpleasant to develop with I don't have
any idea that's not really my sphere of knowledge.
I've never used Unreal Engine or the unity engine myself so you know
your mileage may vary in terms of whether you enjoy working with them.
But you know, my experience.
General has been that unities rendering engine does not look
particularly good.
It looks pretty amateur to me.
Whereas on reels rendering engine, looks does look really good and you
know, I don't know to what extent, that's a fair assessment.
I'm just going by what I see them demo and what I see games ship with
with the two engines.
You know, if you're someone who really cared about visual quality,
you're you're pretty much going to go with the Unreal Engine as far as
I can tell.
But
What?
Between between the two.
Because, like I said, you know, and he's don't have access to
frostbite, for example, which also looked quite good to me.
Let's see, James, I've been in re function taking different types of
time.
I mean, if we don't send any input and essentially the same image
keeps getting ready to repeatedly, we still see a lot of fluctuation
in the amount of time being consumed per frame.
We have a lot of chop where I would have expected relatively calm
Waters unless we're losing time to other processes on the machine.
So yeah, I mean if you want to take a look at this,
As it is and you're saying that you see a lot of chop their to me.
If I look at this, I actually don't see that much chop.
I mean remember this is something like, you know, 16 milliseconds of
time.
And it's coming in pretty darn close every time, right?
And so yeah, you know, is there a shop there?
Yes, but not really that much.
I mean, we probably are losing some time to the system, especially
since OBS is running stuff, but
It's really this is actually pretty consistent timings.
I would say, because remember memory effects being what they are and
you know, there's so much unpredictability in modern execution, even
if nobody stealing any time from you just the fact that every frame is
a different processor State as it goes through is enough to make your
timings different, you know.
So yeah.
But yes I mean almost certainly
We are seeing swap out time in there.
I would assume.
And and, you know what, more so than swap we might not even be seeing
swap out time, right?
What we might be seeing more of is like the operating system taking a
longer time to do something.
We asked it to do or stuff like that to write.
Like, you can look at frame display.
Look at how long it took their right versus how long it took here and
that's an operating system call.
So it's not really about swapping us like, went it decided to do that.
And if you look at the primary difference between these two guys, that
was mostly in there, right?
So yeah and so there's some other differences you know like input
processing again, that's calling the operating system and that's what
accounted for this shift here.
So swap out is not necessarily the same as operation taking.
Longer to do something for you or stuff like that.
Character, Hanson curious.
What point represents the amount of time it takes the operating system
to set up the parallelism.
If parallelism is the right word.
Right now we don't have a very good way of viewing that unfortunately.
And the reason for that is we haven't really finished doing the sort
of drill down thing.
So what happens is, you know, we drill down on something like game
update and render.
We lose these other guys because they are not Underneath Him.
You know, I'm saying.
So what we want to do is get down to here, where we can see tiled
render group to Output getting invoked and then, look at how long it
takes for the other threads to kick back up.
And you can kind of see, well unfortunately, we're going to get a
different set of frames so there's really no way to even look at it
there.
Yeah, we just were a little bit before we could really do that.
We could really see what you're asking for.
So
sorry about that, but
Kubrick Caleb.
Do you know why one of the Rooker threads started after the others?
Know.
I don't.
You know, in general, I don't know why you sometimes get, you know,
Windows might decide to do something kind of a little wonky, with
what, it's, what it's kicking people off.
I have no idea, right?
You can definitely see some anomalies there and I don't know what they
are.
That's just Windows is doing what Windows is doing.
We might have a bug.
So when we get into when we swim, we try to start to like nail things
down harder, you know, many months from now, when we're like trying to
drill down on like performance issues and things, you know, you know,
Shipping work.
That might be something we have to look at.
It's always very hard to say, right?
So yeah.
Elephant every once in a while it seems like a frame gets missed.
I've noticed that happens and things I do as well.
Is there a way to get around that are reliably not on Windows?
No, there's definitely things that we will be doing in the future,
which will minimize it more.
Like, for example, not going through, stretch to stretch bullet.
So when we're going through like opengl as the way to display frames,
that will help us not miss frames, because that's going through a pipe
that's supposed to be for on-time delivery.
Unfortunately, even that doesn't help you.
Windows is not even a soft real-time operating system.
Let alone a hard real-time operating system.
Windows is just bad at that.
It's bad enough that I wish they would put more effort into making
that work.
They don't.
And so as a result,
V, you're going to miss frames on Windows.
Even people who spend like all their time, trying to not miss frames
on Windows, like the VR guys.
Still have problems where every so often every couple of minutes they
miss a frame and the reason is because Windows just decides to swap
them out and redraw, you know, the title bar on Visual Studio or
something and you mr.
Fraim
I said wish they would wish Microsoft, a thing, I thinking more,
seriously, they never have and they probably never will.
What do you think is the theory that says we already know everything.
All the knowledge there is but we just don't remember it.
So when we study we start remembering things.
I think that is a
I think while there are well, there exists constructions of the
universe, for which that could be true.
I think, even in those constructions, that is a very poor way of
stating it because the what people, the term that people use when they
say, remember or know,
It's that is obviously not true, right?
Because we know we've seen how neurons get built and stuff and so you
know what people think of as knowing and remembering it's obviously
not true that we already know things we just don't remember them.
But an alternate way you could think of how neurons worked was.
If there was some, you know, global system in which knowledge there's
a specific configuration for every
Drill piece of knowledge as as the brain conceptualize it.
So every configuration and all that's happening, is your brain is
actually sort of placing one of those into itself as it becomes
something that enters your brain.
You know you could argue that there was something like that.
We're all every configuration of knowledge is already exists and it's
just your brain is like placing new ones in or something like that I
suppose in general it sounds like a pretty stupid statement of me I
guess the
Closet, that the capsule review.
All right, looks like we've come to the end of the questions.
And I'm going to have a little mini announcement after the stream is
over.
So if you would like to stick around, after the fact for handmade hero
friends, I will have a little brief announcement.
Yes, thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, I'm excited to see our debug system, slowly start to come
together because I like being able to inspect my programs doing.
And we've been Flying Blind for a while because we just been working
on other things.
And it was important to kind of get everything up and running.
But now that we have a relatively good foundation, it's kind of nice
to start to be able to see what things are actually doing.
So that we can figure out what's, what's not working.
Well, and also be able to troubleshoot problems and get all sorts of
kind of like, nice higher level, sort of feel for what the code is
doing.
It's pretty cool.
And I'm very glad that that we're getting that now.
So that's what we'll be doing next week.
Now that we've got the ball rolling, I think we should just keep on
rolling it and put in some pretty cool stuff kind of get that you I
working.
So it's pretty easy for us to kind of go and inspect things.
And so that's what we doing.
Hopefully, you'll come back next week for that.
And if you want to know the schedule for that, always check the
tweetbot.
But this guy right here from Hammer here at or you can go to the
tweetbot, it tweets, the schedule.
So you can always tell when we're going to be live.
In the meantime, if you would like to follow along with the source
code, you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero to org and it
comes to the source code.
Even as we are developing the game right now, every night after we're
done coding here, I upload it.
So if you want to play around with that, this is the place to do it.
And you can use it, you can get it by downloading a zip.
There's also a sort of unsupported GitHub that you can use that it
comes with if you're a get kind of person.
So you got options there, we also have a form so you can go to ask
questions and a patreon page.
Age, you can pledge, support the video series, check those out.
If you like the series are good places to go that's about it for
today.
Until next time, I will be back here on Monday until then have fun
coating over the weekend and I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.