Hello everyone, welcome to handmade hero.
The the show where we could complete game live on Twitch.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just us.
And basically, we're trying to make a sort of a complete survey of
absolutely everything that's involved in the development of the game,
so that if you actually follow the series from start to finish, you
will know absolutely everything that goes into the execution of a
game, right down to how the pixels are drawn and all the way up to the
very highest levels of like how the AI works and stuff.
Like that.
And yesterday basically we had a little bit of a problem which is that
I could not seem to figure out a very good way to explain how we need
to transferred and normals without getting mired in a lot of Matrix
math and stuff like that.
Which I realize is challenging for people, especially because we
haven't really done much of it on the stream and specifically, I do
know that that me blow on on the chat was like I cannot follow this
and I totally appreciate that.
I do know that it's difficult.
So I was trying to think if we could possibly do it in some other way.
And I think I may have thought of a relatively easy way to describe
how normals have to be transformed without having to actually talk
about matrices at all.
I'm not sure.
But I'll try and then you can see if this makes more sense as we go,
right?
So I'm going to try it and you can tell me whether this is is better.
So this is the Matrix version of what we are trying to say, but this
was very complicated.
People.
So, I'm going to try a slightly different version.
All right, so I want to talk about the following example, suppose that
we were to draw a house and it's a Sprite, right?
It's a Sprite house.
And so, here is my house bitmap.
And this is, you know, the actual this is the color bitmap, right?
This is the actual house for drawing on the screen.
So we have a y axis and an X axis.
And we're drawing this house right now.
If you imagine the normal map,
For this thing, right?
You can imagine that there is going to be normals.
For example, if I wanted to point out off of the side of this house or
something like this, you could imagine putting a normal and that
pointed off of the roof of the house.
Like so now, how would you have found what that normal was like, what
does it?
What does that normal mean?
Right?
Well if you imagine these two points here, okay, let's say that I have
one point here.
Let's say that this is P1 and I have this point down here which is P0.
And so if I took the
ER, from P0 to P1, I would have that Vector, right?
And you could imagine me saying, well in fact, Let me let me do it the
other direction.
Just so our perp goes the right way.
Let's do it this way.
Let's do it.
Let's do it like that.
Let's let's stay right hand rule for now.
All right.
So if you imagine this Vector here and the one that goes from P0 to
P1, right?
I'll call that V for now.
Let's say that Vector.
If you think about how this normal is related, right?
The normal is the vector, that's perpendicular to the to this roof of
the house, right?
That's kind of the definition of the normal, right?
It's the perpendiculars there to the things that we have constructed.
Now this is in 2D yes, but you'll have to just bear with me for a
second because I think this extends the 3D for us just fine because we
don't actually have any 3D rotations.
Or 3D scaling, right?
We're just scaling and rotating Sprites on the screen.
We don't actually have to tilt them in 3D, so if you imagine what
happens right here, you can you can sort of Imagine, writing some kind
of equation for this normal.
That's actually very simple, right?
I could say that I just wanted to take the perpendicular right of P.
1, minus p 0 or the perpendicular of V, right.
And now if you remember,
We already talked about how to get that perpendicular, right?
The perpendicular of some Vector, right?
We already said that.
If the vector, you know, is vxvy, right?
We already talked about how to get it.
It was - v yv x, right?
And the reason for that was very straightforward.
It's just because if you imagine how to make a 90 degree rotated,
Vector from any Vector in the plane, right?
Whatever my whatever my Y and my ex are well, the
Corresponding version, just has the Y here, negated, right?
It's going off that way, and it just has the X here is this the same
positive, right?
The same, the same sign as it was, right?
So it's really just, it's just swapping which coordinates are using
and the gating one of them to get that 90 degree rotation, right?
And in fact, you can imagine doing this all the way around, right?
You could imagine doing this is the negated Vector entirely, right?
This is - why - x, right?
And here's the other, the other 90 degree
Station.
Right?
Because there's two perpendiculars.
There's a perpendicular in either direction.
This one is just the other way, round.
This one also, right?
Has exactly like, it has the why, right?
But the Y is positive this time and the x is the thing that's negative
on the right?
So there's actually two perpendiculars.
There are sort of you might think of it as the counter clockwise,
right?
And that's the one we have been using, but there's also a clockwise
one, right?
And the clockwise one would be exactly the same thing.
But just negated, right?
So, hopefully you still remember
All that.
And that's true.
And that's not confusing.
You'll have to tell me me, blow at the end if for some reason, your
computer's about this stuff as well, but hopefully, that stuff is all
really straightforward.
It's just a case of constructing those vectors.
So if we were to look at how we would construct this normal, right?
Well, you can kind of see how it would work, you just say, well,
whatever, the vector for the roof is, I want the perpendicular Vector
to that.
And so, when I construct the perpendicular Vector, that that's my
normal, right?
But now we've gone and done something, we've created a normal map,
right?
So we've essentially saved this normal constructed as if we were not
doing any kind of work.
Transforms to this thing, right?
So if we wanted to later, if we were to go ahead and rotate our map,
right?
So we want to rotate it in the world like so and we want to rotate our
house.
Well, all the points we talked about how we would rotate the points.
So all of the points like especially P1 and P0, right?
They would rotate by the standard rotation that we were using the
standard rotation, the way that we were using
Before it to build up our coordinate systems, right?
If you remember, we have an X axis, we have a y-axis.
We can just find the points by saying p0x write X.
The x axis plus p.
0, y times, the y axis that gives us a vector.
That is @p 0 and similarly P 1 x times, x axis and P1.
Y times the y axis that would give us write the new points in the
world.
And so if we wanted to find out what that new
Norma was, right.
You could imagine applying the exact same transform to it, because all
the normal has done in this, in this case, it is, that is rotated.
Exactly.
As if it was one of these points, right?
If we imagine the normal, doesn't have early a location to it, right?
So you have to imagine, it's being coded as if that's all pointing.
All the normals are just kind of as if there are pointing out of the
out of the origin, right?
But you can imagine it would just get the exact same process would
happen to that normal.
Write the exact same thing would happen to it and its direction.
Ian would change appropriately, right?
So if all we were talking about was rotation, we would not actually
have to do anything differently to process our normal map, we could
literally just use the same algorithm we were using.
We could just use MX x + NY y to compute, what the new normal would
be.
That would be totally fine, right?
There'd be no problem with that because that would allow it to rotate
just the way everything else is rotating and if it were to scale.
So if we were to scale this up, let's say we
Scaling it up to twice, the exercise of the x-axis, and the y-axis
that would be fine too.
As long as the scale is uniform.
Because if the scales uniform, the direction of the normal doesn't
change and we know we were already going to normalize the normal
anyway.
We already said we already have code in there that that changes it
back to length 1, right?
So it so we really could do anything that we wanted to as long as we
did uniform scale, right and rotation.
So the only problem and the thing that I was trying to get at the
other day was what would happen is this we wanted to do non-uniform
scale, okay?
So what happens if we do non-uniform scale so non-uniform scale, we
have our house
Okay, there's a there's rp0, there's rp1 and there's RN.
Oops, that's really bad.
There's RN.
Okay, we then want to do non-uniform, scale to it.
Let's say that we go ahead and
Take this this x-axis and we're going to scale out the x axis quite a
bit, right?
So it's going to be very elongated, but the y-axis is not going to
change.
The y axis is going to be the same, right?
So if we did that, we would end up with something that looked a lot
more like this, right?
That's what we would get.
Okay.
And what you can see here is that our normal has actually done the
opposite thing as what the points of done, right?
So imagine what happens to the normal here.
Think about this normal, as if it was down at the origin, right?
We've got a normal that's basically pointing 45 degrees.
Here we scale out the x axis, what we would think we would get.
If we scaled out, this x-axis is a normal, that's pointing much more
like much lower.
If this is the 45 degrees, it's pointing much lower.
It's deflected.
Up to 45 degrees but actually if you look at what the normal should
be, the normal should actually be pointing higher than the 45 degree.
It can actually be pointing that way.
Does that make sense?
I hope everyone's on board with that, okay?
It's a very subtle thing that's very important.
Okay.
So using the same transform, if it has non-uniform scaling, it using
the same transform for the normals doesn't work, right?
It doesn't work.
And the reason that it doesn't work is because as surfaces elongate
right, the normal, the perpendicular follows, the exact same rule, as
what we were using to construct the perpendicular before, right?
If this is how a vector is constructed in the space, then if
These things are scaled along X differently than why.
Well, the normals got them flipped, which one is the Y and the X,
right?
That's where it came from.
So if you scale the X up, it's actually the Y component of the normal
that's going to get affected.
So hopefully that makes some sense, right?
And let's see exactly how that works.
So, if I want to compute this normal, right?
I've got, like I said before, I've got that n, I'm going to call this
vector v.
Okay.
And I've got here this vector v over here and I guess we'll call this
m Prime and V prime or something like this, right?
Just can see there's difference between them, right.
So, if I want to create these, these vectors here, right?
What ends up happening?
Is my normal, is that perpendicular right to V?
Okay?
And the normal here, M Prime is the perpendicular to V Prime, right?
And so what happens when I, when I look at what, what?
What goes on with v Prime right here, V is equal to v x v, y, right?
Which means that the perpendicular here is going to be negative V.
VX, right.
That's what it's going to be but here my V Prime is equal to its you
know, let's say we've
How long this x axis is right?
My V Prime is going to be to VX essentially v y after that transform.
Right?
And so the perpendicular to it is actually going to be negative v y.
Same thing up top to VX.
Okay.
That's actually going to be the new perpendicular.
So what I hope you can see here is that the action the activity of the
X and the y axis
He is flipping, right?
It's, it's whichever is getting elongated.
It's actually affecting the other axis for the normal, okay?
So if the x-axis went by 2X or went up by two, right?
Then it's actually the why I'm sorry, then it's the, why of the normal
that's actually getting that to multiplier, okay?
And so this is the part that really important to understand, okay?
The normals because they are perpendicular to two vectors in the
actual transform space because they're perpendicular.
They they are affected in a perpendicular way by any transforms that
we might do.
And so if we were to transform them without respecting that,
We would end up having very incorrect Reflections, right?
So how can we work around this, right?
We know we're going to load this normal, right?
Because this is the normal that your written into the map, right?
Basically, the original encoding of whatever the our asset was with no
transform whatsoever.
This got written into the map, right?
And we know that we can't use.
N XX + n YY for our normals because we know that the links are wrong
here, right?
But we also, right, so that's not that's not allowed.
I don't know how you do that.
Not allowed.
That won't help us, right?
Similarly, we can't use n.
We can't use n.
XY, plus NYX, we can't just flip which acts as we're using, because
that will actually rotate our normal, right?
Because the rotation for the normals actually, correct, right?
We actually do want to preserve the direction of the X and y-axes we
just want to make sure that we we treat the
the scaling differently, right?
So, what we actually want here, right?
What we actually want is we want NX X, right?
But instead of its size, we actually want the length of Y to determine
its size.
So, essentially we want a normalized x axis X however, long, the
y-axis is Right plus RN y.
Then we want the
Axis normalized.
Whatever Direction.
The y axis is pointing is times the length of that x-axis, right?
That actually performs the flip that we actually wanted right, but
preserves the direction of the axes, which we need to capture the
rotation, right?
So if you take a look at how this actually works out, it ends up being
NX, right?
And this, you can see that this right here.
Basically forms a coefficient term on the x-axis.
So it's length of the y-axis over
Length of the x-axis, right?
Like so plus NY length of the x-axis over length of the y, axis, X Y.
So these are the terms that we actually care about here, okay?
And we need to make sure that we compute those terms and apply them to
our normal transform.
Otherwise, it will come out wrong.
And what you can see, if you take a look at this, right?
Is that when we have a transform,
That does not scale the axes in a non-uniform way, right?
Just like I said, remember I set up here as long as we have rotation
and uniform scaling, we're fine.
Well, you can see exactly why because what would be true if we have
uniform scaling uniform, scaling is when the length of the y axis and
the length of the x axis both equal each other, right?
And if these two are equal than both of these ratios will be equal to
1 at which point the transform is the same as the old transform,
right, and xx + n YY.
So the only thing we need to do is just adjust for that non-uniform
scale, okay?
So, does that make sense to everyone?
Hopefully, that makes more sense.
I didn't have to use any of this but suffice to say when we get, maybe
we can come back to this someday later when we talk about matrices
more extensively.
But basically, this activity here, inverse transpose is, what does
that operation to The Matrix?
It basically finds out essentially exactly.
It does exactly this this sort of perpendicular.
Armed to the lengths without affecting the direction of those vectors
inside.
It does that for our specific type of Matrix, but that's a separate
issue.
All right, so does that make sense?
Hopefully, that makes sense.
I will check with the stream at the end and see if me blow is now on
board with this.
And and hopefully, that is a, is a solid enough, sort of explanation
of how everything needs to work.
So that when I go code, it here you will know exactly why I am doing
what I am doing.
So let's open up emacs.
Let's go ahead into
Are handmade.
Render group.
Okay, and we have to draw a rectangle slowly.
Here we are.
And we are at the point, I believe where we were just letting a little
guy rotate around there.
I could see that it was incorrect.
Right.
You can, you can see that it's it's not actually rotating those
Reflections at all.
And so, if I go in here now and start to account for that when we pull
our normal out, right?
So here we go.
So right before we normalize it, we don't want to normalize it yet.
Probably because we'd rather rotate it first and then normalize it so
that we end up just only have to do that one normalize and I feel like
there's really no reason why we wouldn't do that because only the
direction that we
Only care about their so.
So, what we want to do is right here, we want to do, our rotate
normals based on X Y axis.
Right?
And the way that that's going to work, remember, we don't actually
have a 3D rotation, but our normals do have three components, right?
They have X Y & Z.
The Z doesn't rotate, right?
The Z pointing in and out of the screen, we don't allow you to rotate
that at all, we're only rotating this way.
So really it's just the
And why it's just that Vector is the only one that we are actually
trying to affect, right?
And so what we want to do is actually do that transform.
I don't know.
Does are handmade Mass support assignments to just x's and y's, it
does so.
So there we go.
So if I go ahead and update that all, I really need to do is say, all
right, I've got my normal x times my
Where's my x axis?
I don't even remember what it's called.
It's been so long since we've looked at this x axis.
Okay, so we've got x axis.
Where is my x-axis.
There it is.
We've got x axis.
We've got normal, y times, y, axis, and remember on the Blackboard.
So we've got those two terms.
We need length of Y over X length of X and length of X, over length of
Y, right?
So basically what we need, I don't know what we should call this.
We basically, this is our, this is our n x coefficient will just call
it right and
Then we've also got our rny coefficient like so.
And what I want to do is now I want to compute these guys, right.
So I've got this, I want to compute the length of the x axis
and the length of the y-axis, right?
And let's make sure we've got these right.
So we've got length of Y axis over length of x axis for that for the,
for the, for the X term, right?
And then for that y term, I just want it flipped, okay?
And now, these are not going to change.
We don't need to compute these per pixel.
They're just coefficients, right?
So what we could do is also just bake those into the, to the axes
themselves, right?
Does that?
You see how that would work?
Because what we could do,
Do is just say, you know what, let's just go ahead and make a normal
x-axis and a normal y-axis, which are just these terms baked baked
into the axis that they are affecting, right?
Like so.
And then this just becomes a single X.
By this actually.
So it's the exact same transform.
It's just using slightly different axes, okay.
And so I'm going to go ahead and put that up at the top since.
Like I said, doesn't really need to be and you can see that these are
all common terms to the length and all that stuff.
All things we can factor out for Speed later and stuff like that.
Oh, that's a V4 though.
Oh, and lovely.
So much like yesterday.
My keyboard is now again, having trouble processing fee, the up and
back.
He's okay.
There it go, re-registered.
I'm gonna send this stuff keyboard back.
It's giving me so much trouble.
I'm very disappointed in it.
All right.
Anyway, hopefully it'll last for the rest of the stream if not.
I may have to take a break and switch out to the o to the other
keyboard.
So R V4 is right now don't actually have the ability to assign
Just to, you know, X Y, or y, z, or those guys.
So we really would probably want to go ahead and stick that in here,
right?
That would basically be be this ignored 3 2014 that y z.
And then I guess we've got one more which is this sort of thing for
5zw.
That's right, that look right.
I think so let's give it a shot.
not actually sure I should probably verify that well,
That doesn't quite look like what we wanted.
So, hold on one second.
Let's, let's take a quick look there at what we did wrong.
Ah, well.
So we do have one other problem, which is that are normalized.
This will actually affect the size of everything.
It won't affect the Z sized properly, right?
If we only were, we really, we have this problem of, we can't just
normalize afterwards because since we have affected this, the X&Y
sizes, but not actually touched the Z size with however, much the Z
should be, scaled that creates, you know, a dis symmetry there.
Basically, you know, we need to do normal z x equals something.
You compensate for whatever the size changes are here.
So that it scales up properly.
Now I'm not sure what we actually want to put there.
It's sort of like we would want the user to probably specify how they
want that to be handled but you could imagine just doing it as, you
know, like like an average of the two or something like this, right?
So if we did something like
X axis blank.
Y axis length.
so,
Yeah, X is length x axis.
Length length acts like
And then our Z scale, or I guess I should probably say NZ scale.
Maybe I should make those more like that are rnz scale would just be,
you know, the average of those two, let's say x axis, like this, Y,
axis length, and we'll talk about that in the Blackboard in a second
here, and Z scale.
Oh, and I forgot to actually use or n YN x axis.
There we go.
Okay, so now in theory, we are accounting for that rotation, actually
correctly.
And I guess it's kind of a little bit hard to even know if we are or
not.
That's one of the, the tough Parts about these, I suppose, but it now,
at least you can see that.
When it rotates the sideways, it fades out, which is what should
happen.
Because as it rotates to sideways, it is, it is pointing off into that
map that we have.
We don't
Actually use yet, the sort of the around it map kind of a thing.
And so, you know, you can also see that red is on top and stays on
top, right?
Which is correct.
Whereas, before red was actually moving whether it was on top and
bottom.
So we're, at least handling them, not only correctly now.
Right, we can actually see that that's you know, that that's that's
doing a more correct thing than what we were doing, so that's good.
Okay.
So we still I believe even though we've taken a brief aside to handle
normals there, well let me explain the Z's, the NZ scale part first.
So what happens once we do our our transform, right?
Is we have a normal
and after we do our transform, right?
It may look like this.
In fact, that's this.
Is what's happening?
Think we have a very scaled up the thing happening right now, right.
Our normal becomes much larger than it should be.
So if this normal is, you know, if this is length 1, this is actually
going to be like something else, right?
This is going to be length, you know, equals 100 or whatever.
Who knows?
How big it got?
You know, scaled up.
So if we just use those directly, right then we end up in a situation.
Where we would have normals, that are much too large, they aren't
actually normal length and so the math that we worked out with them
assuming they were normal length wouldn't work, right?
So we want to ensure that their normal length which is why we're
calling normalized which means we're taking the normal or making a new
normal out of it which is whatever the old normal was divided by its
length.
So now we know that its length
One, right?
The problem is when we were doing, when we do the normal transform,
we're only actually transforming the the X&Y, right?
We're only transforming the X, Y Vector, the Z Vector, is it.
So the nxy, right?
It's length is might be large, it may have gotten to be a hundred long
in the XY address but it's Z is still somewhere in the range of 0 to 1
it never got scaled up right?
And this is what this would basically be equivalent of is
if you imagine what happens in 3D you could think about what we were
actually doing in 3D.
If you think about what's happening in 3D, here's my x axis here is my
y-axis.
Here is my Z axis, right?
Effectively, what we were doing, is scaling up, the Y, and X to
whatever they need to be and Z stays the same.
It's as if we would make something that's very wide and tall but
almost no depth, right?
And so, when we would normalize, we would basically lose that that
normalization would normalize a giant huge Vector in x y, and a little
tiny.
Movement in Z.
When that normalizes, it's going to turn out to be something, that's
almost entirely dominated by its X and Y components.
And so to compensate for that, we want to at least pretend that we're
scaling up this object in 3D.
So if the normals which are themselves of 3D and coding get respected
properly and that's why I was saying we want to scale up the Z by some
notion of the scale that we're using in X and Y and really we could
allow the user to specify that like when the user is saying, I want to
elongate something
You know, in various ways, they could also tell us how much they want
to elongate it along the other axis so that we would know what the
normal should do, right?
And you can imagine that being a real thing, right?
If you, if you think about us having say a cylinder in coded, in those
normals, like, we were doing, right?
So it's kind of like this sort of a thing, right?
And so if you want to think about it, it's like it's it's a view from
from here of a cylinder, right?
It's how much you want to elongate it this way, right?
That's what that Z scale is.
How much did you want to do that elongation?
And so, a uniform scale would be where the length of the x-axis equals
the length of the y axis, equals R Z scale, right?
And you'll note, that's exactly what I did, right?
Hey, big surprise, my Das Keyboard is dying.
Hold please for one second while I replace the keyboard.
All right.
Back back in business, with an old-school keyboard.
A keyboard that's many, many, more years old than the dust keyboard,
but it is actually working.
So as you can see, what I did is I actually set the NZ scale exactly.
That way.
If the x axis and the y axis were both the same length and the NZ.
The the Z scale will be exactly what that is if they were different,
it'll just pick like an in-between and pretend well it's scaled up on
Z.
The average of how much it scaled up on X and Y.
Right?
But like I said if we turns out for some reason we want to be doing
something a little more careful there with whatever we're animating
stuff, when we actually have stuff in the game that we want to
fine-tune then we could decide to make this a parameter, right?
And so I could even say no and Z scale could be a parameter.
If we want people to have control over the amount of scaling in the
In the Z direction that the normals appear to, right?
So I think that's just about it for the normal transform stuff.
What we really need to do now is go back and I believe we never.
We kind of got sidetracked on this because we made a rotating thing.
We never quite finished.
Making sure that we're actually sampling from our other Maps correctly
because I thought our
Fear was still a little busted and stuff.
So I want to kind of go take a look at that.
And try to make sure that that's working correctly before we go and do
a coordinate system, sweep on the code base, basically, which I think
was our next thing to do.
So if I go to make sphere normal map, I believe, what I can do here is
get rid of this and we can get back to a sphere.
If I'm not very much in error, let's find out if that's the case,
there we go.
So there is our sphere.
and,
Yeah.
So, there's a couple things that are interesting about our sphere,
right?
Like, you can see we've got sparkly reflection things happening, kind
of at the borders of, it would be nice to figure out what was going on
there.
We also have, you know, a question about whether we're actually you
know, is that the right reflection pattern and I'm not certain about
either of those two things, it's a, it's a little hard to say, but I
would think
Think.
I mean I'm just trying to imagine this is where you kind of want to
reference renderer to kind of go like a lot of
And if I'm doing like this, all actually have written a ray Tracer or
something that does exact computations of stuff.
And so I can see like, all right, if this is where we were at.
So if we take a look at this though, I would have expected.
Actually I feel like I would have expected it to be bowed the other
way, right.
I would have expected.
It probably to be bowed that way, not this way.
And so that's why I say I think we want to just take a look at that
and see if we can get a little bit more.
Of a, you know, of a clear idea and make sure everything's okay.
And also our sparklies I'm a little worried that like some of that is
like us degenerating as we get, because those are where that's
happening, is right at the edge where the the reflection is almost a
bleak.
And so I want to make sure that that we're not having some numerical
weirdness there.
Like, you know, divide by zero or who knows what's going on or getting
really funky results back
You know, over there, I feel like that warrant some attention as well.
So I feel like there's plenty of things to look at in here.
The good news is this.
As you can see, our normal rotation stuff seems to be working quite
well, because our sphere is like completely stable as this thing spins
around, which is pretty awesome, right?
Like, if you think about what's going on there, all of the normals are
actually getting translated a transformed in order to make sure that
the sphere is still reflecting as if it was, you know, had never been
dated because no matter how much we rotate the sphere, it should never
change how its reflecting, right?
Because it's a sphere and so that's pretty cool that that's working,
right?
All right, so let's take a look here.
We've got about a half hour, so we've got plenty of time to dive in
here and see if we can and figure out exactly what's happening with
all of our normals.
So, let me go ahead and take a look at our render group.
Let's see.
Actually think I'm wanted on the other side.
Here we go.
So let's see.
Let's start with our sample environment map code.
Just so we kind of maybe like document this a little bit and just make
sure that we know what we're talking about here.
So when we go to sample environment map, the screen space UV.
Basically gives us where, you know, in fact I might just put this here
screen space, UV tells us where the ray is being cast from
In normalized.
Screen coordinates, right?
So that's where we're at sample direction, right?
And in fact, I guess maybe what I'll do is I'll just open a long
comment here.
Okay.
Sample Direction tells us what direction the cast is going.
And it is supposed to be normalized.
It is expected to be normalized, right?
So if I verify that, let's make sure that's true.
I don't actually know if that's true.
Maybe it's not expected to be normalized now that I think about it, I
don't know that it actually has to be normalized.
So, bounce Direction.
Yeah.
So it's not actually necessarily normalized.
Well.
I guess, actually.
Yeah, I guess it technically would always be normalized, still,
probably.
But do we expect it to be?
Do we care if it is, let's see, sample direction, we don't care.
So never mind.
So really, it does not have to be normalized because we're dividing by
the why here?
So it doesn't matter.
We're just finding out how far we have to go in terms of that
direction in that direction could be any length, really?
Because we're it's all going to be proportional in there, so that's
fine.
All right, so it does not have to be normalized.
Roughness says which Maps which
Odie's of the environment map of of map, we sample from.
And right now we're only supporting really the first one.
I mean, it actually does pick one but we have initialized the other
LOD, so the map yet, so that doesn't do anything.
All right, so that all makes sense.
So, the first thing we do, right?
Is here we go here.
We pick which LOD to sample from based on the roughness.
So, we do that.
That then we compute the distance to the map.
And it looks like we always expect why to be positive.
Right?
But why, but it's why must be positive
So it expects to always be looking in that same direction, right?
And I, guess what we could do instead of that, you know, we wouldn't
have to actually do that.
If we had distance from map in Z actually be
if we had distance from a pansy, be a parameter passed in because then
the people would just pass in
Have one or something so that must that actually seems a little bit
better to me, right?
So instead of doing that maybe we do a thing that's like distance from
map in Z, right actually gets passed in
And then we don't have this restriction anymore because it's just
assumed that you put the map out where in whichever direction the, the
sample would that the normal was actually pointing, right?
So that seems pretty reasonable to me.
And so what we would do for that is we just say, real 32 distance from
map in Z and this is kind of a weird, I guess we
Want to see in y, actually, might be a better way to say that,
because, why is really the thing that we're using for that?
So it's a little but the distance,
That's just the encoding of the normal.
Let's think about this for a second.
We need to think about this for a second.
Yet.
So this is just a really odd thing about this and I guess we're not
doing it wrong, but it's just very strange, right?
This is part of the problem of the fact that the games pretty much
most almost all 2D games including RS, right?
Is the ground, right?
Is flat on.
So like if you were to have stuff on the ground, right, it looks like
actually you're looking top down on it but stuff that's in.
It is is not that way.
Right.
So if you were to light these things, it's kind of this fake
transform.
That happens here.
We're like even though you're pointing off in this direction which
should mean that you're looking at the stuff that's like off the
screen to the top.
What you're actually lighting with is stuff, that's above this thing
here like on a, let on the Z level above it, right?
It's like
If you imagine this case here, even though the normal is pointing that
way, we're actually lighting it with the stuff that comes from here.
And this is just again, like I said, light certain things in 2D games
are just really annoying to do because there is no the way that we've
built the grammar of how the art is drawn is so unlike anything that
could ever happen in the real world, you end up having to do kind of
these weird gyrations in the code to be like wait a minute but there's
really no other.
I mean that's just how you have to do it.
You you don't have the luxury of using the correct math, right?
So really all we're
flipping is that distance from a pansy and that also means that our
ground map and our sky.
Can be different distances which is why I did that.
Because now we actually have essentially you know, that sort of
We've got a way to move them separate so that they don't both have to
move the same amount, right?
And I think that might be useful.
So there we go.
There's our distance from map in Z and that should leave us exactly
where we were right.
Pretty much.
Yeah.
So because I mean that should compute the exact same results and does.
So, let's go ahead and keep taking a look at at this function over
here and continue to verify it.
So we compute the distance to the map here by doing
This right?
You've he's per meter.
I guess we're doing two things here, right?
We're both Computing.
The distance to the map and we are sort of scaling up the map.
We're we're not only Computing, the distance.
We're also sort of scaling up the the units into UVS because that's
what we actually want.
Oops.
That's what we actually want to compute here at the end.
So
We've rolled those two things in their compute, the distance to the
map and the scaling factor for M to you've.
He's right.
And then we find the intersection point.
Like so we clamp to the valid range.
And then bilinear sample.
Right.
And we're just using the UVS.
Yeah, so I don't see this seems like a pretty simple function.
I don't see anything particularly troubling here.
I don't know if anyone else does, but it looks pretty clean, right?
It looks pretty clean.
And so I guess the other question is, is this correct?
So we have the sample Direction, X, right.
That's pretty uncontroversial because, you know, as as we're sampling
we're going to move in X that much and I guess sample Direction Z is
one that we don't really know whether that should Flip or not.
Because we kind of like this to do says that one's a little iffy
because we need to go through and decide exactly how all of our
coordinate systems are going to go.
But in general,
I think we pretty much are saying that we're going to use bottom up as
our sort of you know, I want to say namik later but our bottom-up is
our scheme which would mean that the Z as the
Of.
Moves in and out, right?
What we would want to do is presumably that would flatten out sort of
this way.
Let me see if we can draw that out.
So we could figure out which direction that should be sampling in the
map.
Right?
So if we have, let's say our our sphere here, right?
So if we have something that's, that's sort of on this side of the, of
the sphere, versus this side of the sphere, right?
So, it's X is are going.
Way.
It's these are both going out.
I guess, when you reflect off of these, I guess you'd have to get
somewhere fairly steep before the Z is actually going in the other
direction, though, right?
Like, if I have trying to think of when you'd actually, but how steep
you'd have to be before?
The reflected Vector is actually pointing backwards, I guess.
You'd have to be past 45.
So essentially, when you flip 45,
I've here, you know, here, somewhere, right about here.
Let's say this is still reflecting such that the reflection Vector,
the sampling Direction, Vector is going to be having a positive Z
coming out, right?
But by the time we get back to here somewhere you know in between here
and here then that's going to be casting back to negative Z and so if
we imagine, let's say we were to take the ground map and we're saying
that the ground map is supposed to start here, right?
So this is negative and
Up to here.
So this is positive, then it does seem like this is actually going the
wrong direction, right?
Because things, you know, if it was sampling the ground to be
sampling, the ground behind it and behind it in our terms is actually
positive.
So, I think we actually do know what this should be which is that
Which is that Z that Z is actually wants to be negated there and I
don't actually know I think we want to push that up to the head end.
So I don't think we want to touch that here.
I think what we want to do is negate it here.
So we basically have bounced Direction, Z equals negative, bounce,
Direction Z.
And this is going to be a to do, which is eventually we need to
support.
To mappings.
14 top down view which we don't do now.
And one for sideways, which is What's Happening Here?
Right,
So that's what's going on at the moment, right?
So I believe that is technically the the more correct thing to have
happen there.
I feel like that should be saying, I don't know if that that shouldn't
actually have much of
Friends, I wouldn't think meaning, if we, if we do this, it should be
basically the same.
I would think, but I'm wrong.
It looks like it does change the direction of that curvature.
That's not what I would have expected to be honest with you because
our map is symmetric.
So I wasn't expecting it.
The curvature to change in that way, but I guess it did.
So that's a good question.
Why did the curvature change?
Based on that does the bounce Direction.
Have some other effect that I have.
I'm not thinking of because I feel like it really shouldn't have
mattered.
This is whether we were casting backwards or forwards in the map Z
wise, right?
That didn't that doesn't make a lot of sense to me.
So, bounce Direction
When that gets passed here.
Yeah, that that just feels very strange.
That that, that was true.
I am at a loss to explain that behavior.
Let me go take back to the sample environment and take a look.
So it is only used here, right?
So it is only is only changing what direction we step in y.
So in theory we should do exactly.
It should be doing exactly the same stuff but it's just changing the,
the direction it's stepping in the y axis of the the map that we're
sampling.
And so why would change the curvature Direction?
I'm not sure.
I guess it could be because it
Scrolls it sort of flips which area of the map we happen to be on.
I guess I could convince myself that that was true.
Like if we were on we were immediately centered on some part of the
map, right?
I could imagine flipping it would just kind of move where that line
was.
Let me see if I can convince myself that that's actually reasonable
because I'm not sure that I actually buy that explanation if that
makes sense.
So, I
22.
It's over here.
I want to see that again.
Because it feels to me like that line is not even really moving
though, right?
So it feels to me, like it's still totally aligned.
It's just changing what the curvature is there, right?
And so, I don't know that's very strange to me.
I'm going to go ahead and make the distance less so I can see more of
the checkerboard, if that makes sense.
Yeah.
See that seems wrong to me as oh wait, no, that does seem right to me.
I
no, that's seems
To me as well.
I think we've got a bug in here because if I move the map closer,
right?
No, no.
Okay.
We don't have a button here.
Never mind if I move the map further away, I would see more of the
checkerboard, right?
Yeah.
That I think that is actually true.
So if I move the map further away, I should see more of the
checkerboard.
Let me continue to move it further away.
Yeah, so it's very interesting.
So the bottom
Looks pretty reasonable, right?
But the top looks totally wack.
Like what is going on there?
It's super bizarre.
Right.
I mean, I have no idea what that's supposed to be showing me, that
seems very strange that could, of course, be a problem with the
normals that we've actually encoded.
Although, no, we know, it's not because we're rotating now.
So we know that this is purely sampling based because if it was a
problem with the normals, we'd see it, go around.
All right.
So our top reflection, let's take a look at srei bottom reflection.
Let's take a look at what is happening there.
That's making that be so weird.
Right?
Like what is happening?
That's that's
Saying such weirdness.
So if I, if I go ahead and comment this out, right, just so I know
which path were talking about, so it's this path.
So basically we suspect oops.
We suspect.
This path seems particularly broken, right?
So this seems particularly broken to me, the tea Farm app value is
only used for learning the color values.
So I feel like that's not really something we need to worry about
because I don't see how that could possibly be affecting anything,
right?
So the next question is, let's think about how the reflection works
because this happens to be the path where we are talking about the
negated direction of computation, right?
So, maybe that is, you know, being done incorrectly in some way.
So we're only in this case, when we're happening pointing downwards.
So boy, bounce Direction y will be negative, right?
And we're saying that the map is below us, and then we're doing the
sample, and I feel like I looked at this relatively closely, but I
guess I must have not looked at it closely enough or I'm missing
something special about about the way this is happening.
But assuming that this is negative and this is negative, it cancels
out.
You're still gonna get the positive and you're just going to get a
scaling amount that's going to be how much you should sample from that
map, right?
And I feel like that's what we want because the maps are actually
facing opposite directions so we don't want to negate the direction
that we're going.
Say we don't want to like flip power reading from the map or anything.
It seems like it should be the same.
In either case we just need to know how far we were going in that map
right.
There doesn't seem to be anything.
Particularly odd about that to me unless I'm again missing something
special there.
So I don't see immediately.
What would be wrong about?
What we're doing there?
We sample from the farm app, but I mean,
I mean it really does seem like it's busted, right?
I mean if you look at that I just I don't see how that could be a
plausible reflection pattern in any case, right?
So I guess the other question is, is there something weird that's
happening with our, with our normal values when you happen to have
one?
That's pointing up directly up like that, right?
And I'm not totally sure.
We could double-check this math again just to see if there's anything
weird happening here as well but I don't know like the spouse
Direction.
Z, minus Z equals 1.
I mean, I feel like we worked it all out relatively carefully so I'm
not sure.
Why would I suspect it?
But it is one of those things where I'm just, I'm a little bit curious
to know if perhaps there's something strange going on there.
So let's take a quick look at that.
So we're taking the Bauhaus direction.
We're saying, 2 times the normal Z normal XYZ.
So basically whatever the Z component is.
And that's I assume that's because we're just starting with the I
Vector which is 0 0 1 whatever, the normal Z component is, we need to
move essentially the the negated I Vector up by that much, right?
And then we just need to subtract negative.
I the vector, which is what's happening.
And here, right?
So that all seems pretty solid e transpose n which is just going to be
normal Z times normal XYZ and we all want the whole thing doubled,
right?
And that that does and that is what I would expect to do there.
That's not an odd equation to to be doing.
And we do know it's normalized or at least we tried to normalize it,
right.
So all that's true.
So yeah, then we come down here when we want to change the bounce
Direction, Z just because we want it to sample in a different
direction than it was sampling.
And again, I don't think that.
Let's see what effect that also has on this guy just to try and get
some more data here to see what's
Wow.
That is just Ultra Ultra Ultra weird to me.
So it's almost like it's actually sampling out of a the wrong are
because so changing what the bounce Direction, Z sampling is actually
changes.
Where that sort of anomaly actually is, which is super bizarre to me.
I do not see why that should be happening at all.
This is a bit of a Puzzler.
This may have to be like The Puzzler for today like who could figure
out what is happening.
Strangely here, I guess if sample Direction Why simple directions see
was Zero?
Yeah, I don't know.
I don't know.
I mean this could be our motivation to go write some actual debugging
tools here because I'm trying to think of how to debug this without
some semblance of debugging tools.
And I'm not sure that there's much of a good way to do that because
I'm stumped as to things we could try and we definitely.
I mean, I just can't see any way that that could be right, it just
doesn't seem
Plausible to me and you can see that it's it's right in a circular
like a well and ovular region as well, which is sort of as that
reflection passes through some, some critical point, it would seem but
I don't have a good explanation for exactly what that is.
Yeah.
so, I guess I'll leave that as The Puzzler, I'll leave the code
exactly as it is right now, and we'll leave that as The Puzzler to see
if anyone can figure out what's going on before tomorrow when we, when
we take a look,
And let's see.
Let me go to Q&A.
so,
Grumpy giant says draw the sampling Vector as RGB to visualize it.
We totally could do that.
That is a good idea.
To draw the sampling Vector.
We just need to go in here instead of doing any of this stuff.
We would actually just take our bounce Direction.
Like so.
And say, all right, the Texel RGB is going to be the, well, I guess
the text effects are.
Well, I guess I could do it this way, is going to be 0.5.
Plus 0.5 x lb direction, right?
So, that shifts it up from negative, 1 to 1 to 0, to 1, right?
See here, right?
Got to do.
Vector for that.
Light.
Undeclared.
Identifier, that is true.
It's because I didn't actually want that.
That's what I wanted.
So, there is our sampling Vector pattern.
it's kind of pretty actually, I mean, you know,
You got to respect that sampling pattern.
Wouldn't you say?
It's a little confusing to read right now.
So I think what I might do is say let's knock out the are and the the
G.
So now we're just going to visualize the Z component of it, right?
Or at least try to
Why am I still getting?
What's wrong here?
Why am I still getting
Text illegals, hadamard text, the color color is not being fed in.
Oddly is it?
Yeah, I don't understand.
Textile de R equals 0 x, 0 dot g, equals 0.
Oh that's the wrong path.
There we go.
So, there is our Z Direction.
And that seems correct to me.
Right?
Because remember we're going to gated.
So this is negative 1.
This would be directly back at us and as we get out to the sides, it
gets less and less, right?
That seems correct to me.
Let's take a look at at the
At The X sampling.
That seems
Pretty reasonable.
It's hard to say in here?
I mean I guess it's encoded in srgb now, which is a little odd, but I
could believe that's true, right?
You get the brightest part here in the darkest part at 40, 45 and 45?
I think that's about right, right?
That's seems plausible.
I could believe it anyway, you can see again that kind of I feel like
we do have
Miracle stuff.
We want to work out around the edges where things are probably
degenerating in a bad way but that's not part of the problem we're
seeing right now obviously.
And so let's take a look at finally the green and that that looks
right as well.
It's so, I mean, we're, we're having that problem is where the Y gets
Particularly negative.
I mean, so we do kind of now at least know that it's where the Y is
negative but I don't really understand why the why being particularly
- would cause problems that are different from the why being positive,
like what is the difference in here.
If we have
Doing that divide.
If the why is, you know,
I'm not really sure why that would be the case.
I guess one thing that would be interesting.
Is.
Let's take a look at where the equal zero line is for y, right?
So, basically, like
what I'm kind of interested in doing here is saying, all right, what
if we were to say that if the bounce Direction, y equals, you know,
and maybe I'll give it a little bit of a range, right?
So if it's greater than or equal to
groups, and
Less than or equal to.
So if it's within that range, the bow show and I guess I we're not
shifted up anymore so I guess I actually want if it's greater than
equal to negative 0.1 positive 0.1, something like that.
So if the bass directions within their I just want to know where where
Y is close to zero.
I want, you know, Texel rgb2 equal, you know 111 and otherwise I want
Texel rgb2.
12000.
All right, and so I just want to see where that is.
So that's exactly what I would have expected, right?
And we never draw the map that we never do the sampling there.
So I feel like we aren't getting some kind of like, dividing by a high
number.
Kind of a weirdness happening there, right?
That doesn't seem to be true but it still is definitely the case that
if you take a look at what,
Happens here right around where you know where that's occurring.
We see that.
We're kind of getting that weird sort of why?
I wonder what that value.
Well, you know what?
Let's do this, I guess we could try to find what that range is so you
know it's called this isoline and we'll just say, let's take a look at
where the isoline is near -.5, right.
And so we'll just do
Isoline isoline.
So, and this will just show us
And right around where that is happening, right?
And so then we can see what kinds of values.
They must actually be where we're getting our bug, right?
So here's a step.
It up, 2.7, Step It Up 2.9.
I guess so it looks like it's it's right about right about there.
Right, let me let me increase the resolution here of where we're
looking at are banding, right?
So that's that's looking sort of sort of like what we're talking
about.
So when we're sort of getting up two numbers that are very close,
there were getting that discontinuity but I don't really know why.
Me Blair, is the mapping clipped on, either the top or bottom Edge.
Don't know if that makes sense.
I don't know.
It might be, I wouldn't think so because the cross section of the map
that we're looking at, seems
Seems like it should have plenty of room, you know?
Robot chocolate.
Dino could be calculated value for the NZ scale from the normal X and
normal wives.
With the normal Z is unchanged after normalization.
I mean, we certainly could make sure that the normal Z is unchanged.
That's that's certainly true and the way that we would do that.
So if you wanted to do that, right?
If you know what the normal Z is, so what you want to do is you want
to say that like x squared plus y squared, plus Z squared, right
square?
Rooted you want this to equal one and so if you're saying that you
want to hold,
This term fixed right essentially, what you're saying is you're saying
well you want because I can square both sides, right?
Like so, essentially what you're saying there is you're saying okay I
want my x squared plus y squared right?
I want that to be whatever it would have to be
To make sure that it's it's combined.
Length was 1 minus Z squared, right?
So what you'd end up doing is you end up saying, okay, you know,
instead of normalizing, the whole Vector, you would take the vector,
just the X Y of the normal, you take just that portion and you would
develop
I'd buy this, right?
You would you would, you would make it so that this length,
Is equal to that, right?
You would make it so that that I'm not explaining myself very well
here.
So if this is your normal Vector, right?
Sorry
If this is your normal Vector, right?
Then what we were doing before is we were basically saying like The
New Normal is going to equal to the old.
No moral will however much scaling it had in it, you know, rescaled
like this, right?
And so if your pre saying that you don't want the Z to change, right,
then you're just talking about this part of this term, right?
So instead what you want to do is first,
Of to get the the amount that you're actually talking about that, you
want X and Y to be right.
And so I could square root both sides here, right?
Like this and say, all right, I want the length of my of just the X Y
of just the X Y Vector to equal the square root of 1 minus Z squared,
right?
So then when you take n, XY and you're producing the new nxy, what you
do is you take the old x y and instead of
Normalizing, it like this which is what we were doing before, right?
You would normalize it by first dividing by its current length and
then multiplying, by by this, right?
You know, I'm saying so that you would actually so that you would turn
it into a length of that, I'm sorry.
Put that in the wrong place.
You'd you normalize it and then multiply it by this, right 1, minus Z
squared.
Because now you would know that you'd have this would be a unit length
Vector, right?
And now you're multiplying by this which is the length you actually
want it to be.
And then I believe in theory, then it would all work out.
So that now you would have, you know, an x + y squared, that would
would come out to those values.
I believe, I'd have to go sit down and work out that work.
That out more carefully to make sure I didn't miss something there.
But you see basically the process, right?
I just solved for the length that these guys would actually have to
produce in order to to make this to make Z state.
Same in the final thing, right?
Only flip the bounce Direction Z when you use the top map.
So yeah, the
Problem with that is that obviously would fix the problem but we don't
know why, right?
And so I don't want to just like, flip a variable and be like, well,
we flipped a variable and now it's not a problem.
We should have a reason why that fixes the the issue, right?
And if we don't have an explanation for that then we're in trouble.
So I feel like we need to go take a look and actually figure out
what's going on there before we do anything weird.
Like that because that's that's kind of the old just keep adding
negatives to it works.
And the problem is that always comes back to bite you eventually,
right?
So, yeah.
And so, someone was asking how this about how bounce Direction,
effects effects, the, the map drawing, right?
And it looks like it does not well, obviously bounce Direction Z would
not affect the map drawing at all.
So that's interesting though.
The way that's actually a very interesting piece of data, isn't it?
Because we know that bounce Direction.
Z does change who has the bug, right?
When we do it.
But the Y values don't change.
So it isn't really about what's happening with the Y values.
It's very interesting.
This is a bit.
This is such a weird, such a weird, little guy.
I do Wonder like I'm trying to figure out if there's any way you could
have clipping.
I don't feel like you could because the screen space u and v should be
fairly close to this to the middle.
And so we're only just displacing off of that u and v.
It seems odd that we would.
That we would ever end up clamping right now.
We could, we could see if we were clamping by just saying, you know,
assert that that we're not right, we could do it, we could just flat
out say, you know, hey let's let's make sure we're not clamping,
right?
But you know, it certainly doesn't look like we're clamping because as
far as I can tell, the the assertions, never fire, which means we're
well within the map boundaries when we're actually doing our sampling,
right?
And
Yeah, and all of this looks pretty straightforward rights doing the
srgb by linear blend stuff.
So yeah, so it all seems pretty reasonable.
It just doesn't seem like there's a lot of Aditi going on there and
it's interesting that this is primarily.
What causes that anomaly?
the fact that the sample Direction Z,
Because right, that's that's what determines whether we pick up the
anomaly or not, right?
Is whether we whether we've got that guy in there, right?
So there's something about the stepping in why?
That's not obvious how it's working, or why it's working that way,
right?
And I'm not sure, I'm not sure what's going on there.
You know, it's just it's we've we've done something stupid with the
way that we're sampling the maps but I just don't know what it is and
I shouldn't say they were sampling.
The way we're Computing the reflection because this does seem this
seems fairly innocuous.
Like it's not clear to me.
How we could have that bug in here really
So it feels like maybe it's a more subtle thing with what we're asking
it to do is different.
So yeah.
so, yeah, and eventually this euv, permeated this actually needs to be
A parameter, I do Wonder.
Hibiscus exit as well.
Oops.
That's pretty interesting.
So as we sample more of the map, the anomaly doesn't look as
pronounced or even if it's there at.
All right, so
As I zoom in.
With auvs for M there.
It's kind of interesting to, it's like it elongates, it's elongating
part of this reflection much more than its real on getting this
reflection.
Right.
I wonder if that's just based on where it is on the screen.
I do wonder, I want to add another parameter.
U2 system here.
Right, let's keep going here 5.
Four.
So yeah, that's what's actually happening.
We're almost puncturing through the map.
How is that possible?
It's like we've we've gone much too close to them, it's like we've
inverted the map, I wonder and that, wow, this is going to be
interesting one to solve.
This is the first interesting bug.
We've really had on hand made a hero.
That's just fascinating.
So, what we're seeing there, I think, is actually the map inverted
cell.
That's very strange.
And the bottom one is always seemingly correct.
It does never have that problem, no matter what we do to it, it seems
fine, right?
So fascinating.
So how is that guy getting punctured in that way?
And why would that be tied to the direction you're stepping in?
Why in the map?
Right?
Those are the questions.
Those are the key questions.
We're picking the map.
You don't care about tea far map.
We're taking the distance.
The distance is becoming negative.
In the path.
That's broken.
But the fact that the distance is negative, we know that the actual
bounce Direction.
Why the thing that we're passing, we know that the bounce Direction Y
is actually
Also, going to be negative.
So those divided out
And it's always that way for the entire reflection.
So it's not like just part of it, it's always that way for the entire
reflection.
I'm not sure, I'm still not sure.
Maybe you can try to write code to show points on the textures from
which it is doing.
Sampling.
Yeah, I think that's a, that's an excellent idea.
That's a very good idea, actually.
Yeah, so that's okay.
So the next person said, how would the anomaly shift at the server to
move up or down instead of up, right?
That was the thing that I said, I was about to, to do.
I'm glad you just reminded me because I kind of lost that.
I thought I said I wanted to add a new parameter, I want to see what
happens when it moves up and down, although I'm a less.
I'm less sure.
Now that that's actually going to be useful, but let's, let's see.
Let's see here.
Let's go ahead and Boop's
Let's go ahead and make that disp and go ahead and make display V2.
And so we'll do you know, whatever that is will sign angle.
Alexei.
So, that's even more crazy, right?
It's
It's like we're not.
I'm just puzzled.
It's like we're somehow not sampling, the why correctly?
But only for that one map.
It's so quick.
You'll Eur.
I am, I'm really stumped.
As to why that would be happening.
It's got the answers like right in front of our face and it's going to
be like a bit of a head slapper when we finally find it.
But yeah.
Grumpy giant 256 wondering if it shouldn't maybe be F ABS sample
Direction.
Why
Well, certainly, I am in no position to say yes or no.
Since we don't know why this code isn't working.
But what I don't understand is why would it be that way?
Because distance from mapping Z is going to be the same sign as
sample, Direction y, right.
So I feel like the only thing it would do and maybe this is where I'm
just not understanding things or something.
I feel like the only thing that would happen, if this were F, ABS is,
you would flip the direction of the reflection, right?
But why would it produce that pattern?
And I mean, we might as well try it.
It doesn't help us know, why it's wrong.
Unless, you know, in which case you should tell us,
Yeah, that did not help.
Because like, it's just completing an offset.
So, the only thing that would happen was this would flip, right?
This, this, this Vector would flip it would go, you know, the opposite
direction.
Screwface uv+ offset.
We clamp the X and the Y.
We
Multiply out the TX by taking a look at the, the width and the height.
And blowing that out, which makes sense.
Of course, we haven't really handled the fact that the UVS parameter
is should be different for both for the X and the Y.
Clamp it, we do the t x to Y.
We take the fractional value, that sure does look right.
And so, it seems like there's something going wrong out here.
We unscanned bias, our normals.
That's good.
We do our normal XY pass, we normalize the mount, we compute the
bounce Direction.
The bounce fraction is direction.
We're going from the point that we are on the screen.
Space UV rays are screen, space UV.
with Max x, x, invite mass times y, That's
Seems right.
Can't can't fault that logic really.
Let's retrace UV, we passed the bounce Direction.
We've got the normal W which is just for the roughness.
Doesn't really have anything else to do with it?
Got the farm app, you pass the distance to the mapping Z and then we
lerp
so,
No.
So yeah, showing the sampling on the texture would be the nice thing
to do.
I'm not sure we really have time to do that.
That might be what we have to do tomorrow, right?
Like I'm not sure there's really a lot of ways that we could do it.
I guess what we could do.
Is have bilinear sample, actually just draw into the texture so we see
where we're sampling from.
That's interesting idea.
So let's say we turn this off.
How does this sound?
Right, so we're only doing that.
And now let's actually just go in here and just just right straight on
into the texture, right?
So what we'll do is we'll say, Okay, instead of just sort of like by
linearly sampling from that X and Y, what will actually do?
Is well, I mean we'll also do the bilinear sample, obviously, but what
we'll do is we'll right into that location, so we'll take LOD pixels,
right?
And basically we'll do we'll do this, we'll just do Tesla pointer
equals log, memory odd, right.
Look, so we'll do it.
Our text the pointer equals 0, this will do it this way so it will
actually just go ahead there and bright white into it wherever we're
sampling.
Right.
And I guess I didn't need to turn that other guy off.
Now, I think about it is he's sampling from a different map.
So yeah, the reflection is totally different.
Right?
What is is reflecting this extremely thin?
What on earth?
Oh, that's just because these guys, right, that's fine.
So one is extremely thin, this is kind of, this is what's so nice
about having your own when you're not using opengl.
You don't have to go through all the mental steps of like, how do I do
this?
You could just go like a, let me just draw a directly into the
texture, right?
I mean,
That is exactly what we expect it to be.
And that is totally not, so the streams over.
So, let's let's call it a day, but we pretty much have our work cut
out for us.
Now, we have to figure out why we're getting such a lensing
reflection.
It does kind of seem like maybe our normals like our computation for
the bounce is just wrong.
It's rotated in some weird way because I like RI Vector is not is just
it's not proper compared to what it should be.
Or something is happening weird?
I'm not sure, but it does seem like maybe we're Computing.
We're just flat-out Computing, the balance wrong.
I think that's what's happening.
But this is a pretty cool Vis.
I'd really like that.
That's neat.
That's that's really cool.
All right, let's, let's close it down for the day and we will pick it
up tomorrow and go ahead and save the Mischief board.
There we go.
All right, thank you for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
Hopefully, today we cleared up the whole thing about how to transform
normals properly, because I know we went down the math, whole deeply
and me blow at the end said that he understood it now.
So, that's a good sign.
I think so, mission accomplished there in the real sense.
The word not the George Bush sense of the word but we do have another
mission that is not accomplished in any sense of the word except maybe
in the George Bush.
Sense of the word, which is that we had to figure out why our
Reflections on the top are being computed seemingly very strangely.
And I think maybe we might have a problem with that reflection Mass.
So we'll have to go over it again and not necessary.
The math of the reflection that we worked on the board but how we end
up implementing may just be incorrect and we'll have to think that
through and make sure that that we're not doing something stupid.
So we
We'll do that tomorrow and then hopefully we will have our normal map
stuff complete and we can move on to getting our coordinate system
stuff straightened out.
And then I think we're getting to the end of rendering stuff we have.
I think we have one more real thing to tackle at that point, which is
how we're going to do that near-field, light sampling.
So that's going to be a bit of a trip because I'm not sure how we're
going to do that, but we'll figure it out when we get there.
And so we're closing in on the end and then wear it, then it's time to
start render optimization, which is going to be, I think probably a
lot of fun cause we haven't talked about
Position at all in the Stream and it's going to be kind of interesting
to shift gears and Baton to show how some of that stuff works.
So I hope you'll stick with us and come back tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time on Twitch.
It'll be good to see everyone here.
Hope you tune in.
If you would like to follow along at home and want to play with the
source code, you can go to handmade hero dot-org and click on the
pre-order button.
If you preorder the game, it comes to the source code every night.
So if you want to follow along, that's an easy way to do it.
We also have a patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, you can subscribe there and
we have a forum site.
You can go to with an annotated episode guide, porcelain X and Mac.
If you're trying to follow along a different platform and a place to
ask questions, if you just want to ask questions about the code, maybe
four previous episodes, that sort of thing.
There's also a tweet but you can check out if you want to know what
the schedule is for the weak, it tweets schedule at you.
And also, let you do an hour before it starts, other can be things
like that.
So subscribe to that if you want to be able to catch the live stream
to eat easily, that's about it.
Thank you very much for joining me and I will hopefully see everyone
tomorrow.
Take it easy.