Birding start recording.
Okay.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we code a complete game live on stream.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just us here.
Although as I do mention now post, Sean Barrett's Birthday, we did
show how to integrate one of his libraries into the asset.
Packer if you would like to use it there's an f-zero in there that you
can go check out because like I said, many times people ask me what
Could I use if I was going to use a library it would be a Sean Barrett
library.
And so I showed how to do that for people who are interested.
Anyway, that said we are in the middle of making some updates to our
asset system because there was some bugs in it, and I talked about
yesterday that I want to fix.
Just get them out of the way sooner rather than later, and we aren't
really finished with that.
We still got more work to do before we get the bugs out.
And so I'd like to finish doing that today, if possible today is day
one.
66, which means that if you have pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
dot org and would like to follow along with my coding you can unpack
day, 165 source code.
That's the thing I'm working with here.
My friend that is what I am doing.
So yeah, the problems that we have at the moment is that we were kind
of right in the middle of something here and we haven't really
finished.
There's there's a couple things that we haven't done yet.
So first of all we never you know we haven't actually implemented this
generation ID concept, I
Talked about yesterday which is something that can protect our assets
from being evicted.
It helps us, get out of the business of using the old locking concept
for assets, which I wanted to get rid of and it also helps prevent
bugs.
Now that we have moved the asset eviction into the memory allocation
part which can happen, anytime you try to use an asset.
So
We need to plant that.
We also have some other problems, which is that we kind of need to
extend this notion cure.
The atomic compare exchange un 32, this little lock here.
It's kind of a little optimistic lock sort of a guy who is in stit
responsible for keeping us from accidentally modifying, the linked
list on two threads at once.
We got some problems that we have to address with that as well and
that is that since the linked list involves
Sentinel and involves other links in the list.
It means that really nobody no two threads should ever be touching the
linked list at the same time, right?
And so really what we'd rather do here because there's actually in
addition to the fact that we took the Sentinel, which would be a
problem here and some people mentioned that on the forums, there's
also something that nobody has mentioned yet but I least I don't think
so.
But it's also true is that we also just have stuff in here that
touches the linked list, right?
We've got
We've got stuff that like fries and asset and freeing an asset.
Also touches the
That's right.
So really what we want to do here is inside this, you know, code here
that does linked list stuff.
We really want to do is isolate the stuff that ever works that linked
list and make sure that nobody's ever going to use that linked list in
any way, unless they've got the lock, right?
So we kind of want to just add the concept of this lock in so that any
time anyone's doing something that is sensitive.
We can just make sure that it's only happening on one thread at a time
because again, that linked list data.
Is you know, we did not write that in a lock.
Freeway the linked list cannot be operated on two threads at once that
data is can you know kind of has to be touched atomically?
Right, so you can kind of see it here.
We've got these two guys, and those are essentially the operations
that we have the atomic at the very least, but we also have some of
the things, you know, that we might want to think about when we're
looking in here.
Like we have a choir asset memory, right?
And when we're doing choir asset memory, one of the things that's also
worth looking at, is we pretty much want to make sure that
No, two people are doing acquire asset memory at the same time either.
Because this is also, you know, something that's that could be
contended in some way, right?
I mean, if you think about what's happening here, when you do acquire
assets memory, you're going to have situations where people are
merging stuff and all these other sorts of things.
And so, we actually have a number of things that if we really wanted
to open this up and allow multiple threads to be doing whatever they
want with the asset system, it's going to be pretty delicate, right?
We're going to have it's going to be you know, it's going to be a
little tricky, right?
And so really the only things that we can choose to do, there are
either limit these things to only happening on one thread at a time or
accepting.
The fact that we are going to take a look around actually doing them.
And I don't necessarily know that there's a right answer to that
without actually trying to do some profiling or, you know, having an
opinion about what actually is going to happen.
But if you take a look at some of the stuff that works here, right?
You can kind of see most of the time we're in a situation where
everything's okay and would be working, you know, without having to
worry about anything in that, you know, without having to worry about
multi-threaded stuff too much because like, for example, when we're
doing stuff, like loading things, I think most of this stuff is
relatively safe.
Now, I guess what?
I'm not sure about is like when we do begin to ask with memory, for
example, and we're doing like load
That sort of stuff.
I guess.
I don't actually know if that stuff is protected.
So like we should probably take a quick look at these.
I'd like to just get a bit of a assessment there because the rest of
this stuff is is fine, right?
Right up until we get to here.
So, it's basically like a choir asset memory
Add us at her to list that are touching things, that kind of like
linked together, right?
And so those are going to be threading problems, right?
If we want to allow them to do that.
but,
I don't know about begin past with memory.
I would like to know a little bit more about that one because I don't
remember what we were thinking about exactly when we made it.
So I kind of want to make sure.
Yeah.
So if you take, if you take a look at beginning tasked with memory,
you've kind of got a situation there where it's also, it's in a
similar kind of, it's in a similar, kind of state.
And so, when I think about this guy, it kind of feels to me.
You know, it feels to me like, if you're already on a background task,
I don't feel like the background tasks should then spawn a background
task to load something.
Right?
I feel like that's just kind of getting a little bit ridiculous,
right?
So it seems to me that the more you know useful thing probably to do
here would be to make it so that we don't have to make this
multi-threaded like only the main thread would like kick these guys
off, seems like a bit of a smarter thing to do that's just my
assumption.
Right?
We don't have to again, we can have begin test of memory.
Also take a lock because it just needs to search over this list.
So for example, it could just do a thing where it quick takes a lock.
Then does it's you know, it's searching and then on takes a lock, we
could totally do that but I'm not sure again how thread crazy we
really want to be with a lot of the stuff because again, threaded
programming is always kind of a bit of a nightmare because it's a lot
more complicated than single-threaded coding and so
The more of it that you add kind of the more pain and suffering, you
are going to to, you're going to feel that make sense.
So if you can you would like to keep your things relatively segregated
such that the number of things that actually have to kind of talk to
each other and synchronize with each other is as minimal as possible.
So yeah.
So I do wonder if the task oriented thing is really the smartest thing
to do.
And the reason that I wonder that is that it kind of feels like to me
if that maybe what we should do here is it is depending on who is
actually issuing, this load bitmap, whether or not it should be
spawned in the background.
I feel like it's kind of something that's, you know, worth analyzing a
little bit.
So the place that that it gets called right the place that that load
bitmap gets called.
Take a look here is I believe any time someone tries to use a bitmap
that they can't find that it can't find, right?
And it'll do that.
So when we're actually doing that load bitmap call
I feel like what we would want to do is say okay if the render if this
render group was a render group that's meant to sort of be the main
line main thread render group, then sure spawn a thread, no problem.
But I think what we would rather do for everybody else is say, you
know what, let's not actually do that.
For anyone who you know is, is going to be sort of on one of the
peripheral threats because you know, that thread can just all waiting
for the asset that is trying to load.
It doesn't have to do.
Do an overlap kind of a thing, right?
That to me seems a little bit more sane, seems a little bit more like,
what I would expect to have happen.
And so, you know, to me that just feels a little bit better.
So, you know, I'm thinking it's something like this, you know, it
would do sort of a get bitmap call right?
And if it gets back a bitmap it pushes the bitmap.
What I might say is you know okay if you don't have a bitmap you know,
maybe
It would load that in like so and kind of force the bitmap to be
loaded if that makes sense.
By using some kind of a, like a way of saying, hey I need you to load.
I definitely want you to load this bitmap in, right?
I want you to to force the load to happen at this time, right?
And so we could do something here that something like, you know,
background.
Renders in background.
If that was what was happening, then we avoid kind of that that ever
having that happen, right?
So, we'll and we'll also assert here, right?
That that that's not the case.
Like so yeah, something like this.
So, that's what I'm thinking.
So, that way we can we can do, we can force it to load the bitmap.
We could also say that they're, you know, this thing could potentially
return the bitmap directly.
I don't know if it's probably not really worth it and we'd like it to
go through the get bitmap path anyway to make sure it gets marked and
all those other things.
So anyway, that's what I think we would probably want to do and and
that way we can force the bitmap load and in here.
I guess what I would say is we should have something that's kind of
like you know a Boolean
We do little bit map, which is like immediate, right?
And so know, normally when you call it you would call it with with
with false.
But if you call it with true, then it won't do the task based load,
right?
So basically this thing here is going to like assume 0, something like
this.
And then what we would do is we would say, okay if the this is an
immediate call our say, not an immediate call.
Then we would go ahead and do begin to ask with memory write something
like this.
And, you know, assuming that either, we are immediate or we have a
task, we would go ahead with our attempt, right?
So if we come in here, we then do all this sort of stuff.
The way we normally would.
This is something that's going to have to get locked again because
that's going to be contended.
And then what we would want to do here is say alright, either, we're
going to add it in the case of the task, right?
We're going to go ahead and add it on here.
Either we're going to add it or we're just going to execute the load
asset work essentially directly.
Right.
So if we take a look, I think we could actually do that relatively
easily.
If we take a look at what load asset work actually does, you can see
that like the interior of it is pretty straightforward, right?
So you could imagine us having a little version of this here.
That's a little more straightforward something.
Thing that would just do this part of it, right?
Something like this.
And so that's going to be like load asset work immediate or directly
something like that, right?
And that thing would get past all the stuff that it actually needs
here like whatever these things are, right?
So that would get past the file handle that would get past the offset.
And the size.
And again, all I'm doing here is making it so that I can call this
thing.
Oh, whoops, that's pasting that into the wrong place.
Not always so good.
Yeah.
So we got the offset, the size, the destination, like so.
So let's go ahead and handle offset size destination, right?
And that is it.
Fixed up for the asset in the final state.
Looks like so get rid of the size to the destination.
So we've got the asset and the final State there they are, right?
So there's the asset.
And there's the final state.
Okay, so if we wanted to do that directly, we just go ahead and call
that here.
So no change to this particular part of the function, right?
There we go.
And that would just kind of do that work there inside the sort of
deferred call back.
Right.
But what that lets us do now as well?
Is that lets us go.
Okay, you know if we didn't want to do that, right?
If task was not actually set up and said we could do it a little bit
differently.
I'm not sure why that asset.
To list is there specifically like before this thing I have to look
and see if there's some kind of reason for it.
Let's see there we go.
So basically what I'm saying here is that like you know if we're going
to do load asset work directly, now what we could do is we could just
do all of these things the exact same way, right?
So the final state is s uploaded the final destination.
In fact, you know what, we could do to, we could do this even a little
bit more ridiculously
Lee.
We could just say, oh, okay.
We've got the work like so and we are going to set it all up like
this.
I don't know why I didn't do this to begin with in fact now that I'm
thinking about it, it was pretty stupid for me to not do it this way
to begin with, but you know, what can I do?
Sometimes you do things that are dumb, because then what you can do is
you can just say like, you know oh we've got to push work here, right?
We're like, you know, this is our, this is our task work.
So we'll just go ahead and do start ass, work equals work.
And in this case, we just pull them out.
Like so, but we could just pass the actual pointer if we wanted to
which would have saved me the trouble of doing all the junk that I
just did, which is why I said that I was pretty dumb.
For example, right?
You just do that.
You had a clue, which I didn't, but there you go.
So then, you know, you'd come back up here and you done do your
stupidity, rather slowly, something like this, where you could then
go, oh hey, you know, all those things that I took out before just
kidding.
My joke was a little in joke that I had.
We all had a good time about it.
We all laughed and it was great.
Everyone loved it.
and looks like, this is actually happening now
Right.
So they're yeah and so now that we can get rid of this kind of passing
festival and there we go.
So yeah.
So that's a little bit more again, just kind of pushing it sort of
slowly into that direction.
What else do we have here?
So, whoops, at entry tasks work like so, just get that cleaned up a
little bit there.
Okay, so yeah.
So now if you
You look at what's happening in here, you can kind of see that.
We have the asset header.
Add acid here to list stuff.
And these sorts of things, right?
I don't know how much we care about making the sound stuff work
properly.
Threaded, because I don't think anyone ever does that.
We could always sort of think about doing that.
Maybe a little bit more in the future.
But point being, if you take a look at what's happening.
Now, if you're doing this sort of that Acquire, if you're doing the
immediate version of this, which is what would be happening on
separate threads.
Then what we really have is we just have to worry about these these
things here as being the things that actually need to happen.
Sort of inside of a
Lock, right?
We want to be able to lock to the acquire asset memory for this guy,
and then we want to do this this stuff here, right?
So what would be nice obviously is if we could do just take the lock
once and then do both of these two things, I don't know if how
realistic that is, I suspect, that's pretty realistic.
I feel like a choir asset memory.
Never happens in a case where you wouldn't add asset header to list.
You can see that it happens in both cases when the asset memory is
acquired.
So it seems to me like, perhaps we could just make that happen
directly meaning.
As soon as the asset memory is acquired, the asset could get added to
the list.
And I think that is probably a good idea because that way you could do
all of your locking at once.
And so if we were to coming here, for example, right?
And we were to say, all right, there's the asset index, there's the
size, there's the asset.
Right?
I think that is probably what we would have preferred have happened
before.
So if we just got rid of that, that would probably be better, right?
And I think that's what we would want.
That way, that law can only be taken that lack of route would be taken
when time and then all the work would be done at the same point,
right?
Yeah.
Oops.
That was the wrong thing.
I didn't mean to push.
Hawaii.
Put it there.
I wanted to acquire asset memory.
Yeah, so in here we would come out the result, their acquire asset
memory, the problem with that, I guess is that it doesn't quite know
what the asset index is and it does need to know what the asset index
is.
So we'd have to add that in here.
So we'd have to do like a choir asset memory and it would have to then
take an asset index at the end, but that's not really a big deal
because we always know what it is.
We're doing require memory
so, when we get that Acquire asset memory back,
I guess I don't know why we don't just treat it as an asset memory
header.
Always because that actually is what it is.
So that's kind of another weird thing.
I guess we wanted to make it so that it could have done multiple
things.
Maybe I'm not really sure.
I don't actually know why.
I don't actually know why that would be the case.
It's a good question, but I think we could probably change this pretty
safely to say, okay?
Actually it always returns a massacre.
I had her right and so when we do result in here, we would just go
ahead and and yeah and make this.
I don't know why.
That was a, you ate star, that doesn't really make much sense.
Because asset memory header was a void, so that was not necessary, but
I guess that's just what was happening.
And that's fine.
So yeah, so that seems reasonable.
And then down here
here, when we do, add us at header to list,
We would know that we're adding this asset memory header itself.
So let me take a look at which one that is ADD.
I want to take a look at that.
Add asset memory to list her to list.
So it just it gets the memory header, as the first thing, it does, and
it uses the acid and extra that, and then it sets some things, right?
And add asset header to list.
Only happens ever in one place, right?
It only happens there, so really, we should probably just get rid of
this thing.
Kind of in its entirety.
I guess really, what should happen is this should come up here right?
And this should happen.
Right.
It should do this.
So it should be, you know, if the results exceeded which, you know, it
pretty much is guaranteed to always do.
We could almost just sort the result here, then we're going to do this
stuff, right.
And we know what the size is, because there it is, right?
So really we just need that that was all we actually needed.
Nothing too complicated there.
And so when we do,
This, we would just pass the ID value.
And then when this guy does it down here, right?
It would also pass the ID value, and that is pretty much that, right?
That's, that's all we would really need to have happen there.
So, we need to go do that render background stuff obviously, but yeah,
that's fine.
So let's see.
So now our total size in this case, I guess is not allowed to actually
be a memory index, so I guess this has to be just a regular size.
Is that true?
Ooh, it does appear to be true.
Let's see what else we got.
And so there we go.
Insert asset header at front.
And so now we would have, is basically, we need to take the lock on
this guy.
And then we would need to take the lock on the other guy.
Now, you know, the the other guy is pretty harmless.
This guy is pretty harmful, I guess I would say
so, in some sense,
You know, really you might want a more fine-grained lock here.
So the reason I say that is because we take a look at all the stuff
that this guy has to do is pretty substantial.
If you take a look at what has to happen with the other linked list
stuff, it's really not that complicated.
And so you know that that is one reason that would argue against sort
of bothering to do what I'm doing here, which is like, putting them
into a single lock and it's like, maybe they should just have their
own separate locks because of the difference between those two.
Because basically, this is an incredibly small amount of code move
header.
To front is like really pretty irrelevant, right?
Move header to front, looks like that.
It's really, really kind of boring, right?
And insert asset header up front.
It's this little, you know, it's so it's so droll, it's almost not
even worth mentioning.
Its this is the entirety of the code, right?
And so, you know, locking this guy up so that he can't keep doing this
while this other guy is doing this whole huge Ridiculousness.
We're looking for blocks and all these
Of the sorts of things, right?
That seems less good to me.
Does that make sense?
I'm hoping that makes some sense to people and so really it seems like
what you would want to do throughout this thing is like try to get
that try to get that lock.
For the outside.
But that's just my that's just my thinking.
For the moment.
We could try doing it with a regular lock.
We could just do something where we're like, okay, you know, begin you
know, asset lock something like this, right?
And and then we would do
And asset lock.
Write something like that.
And the same thing would happen out here.
Right, we do a begin a set lock.
And then we would do an end asset lock.
Right.
So yeah, so you could do something like this where we would lock
around those guys and we will take a look at that in a second and
that's all fine.
But
You know, looking at it.
So kind of the thing that I am a little worried about, right, is what
we would like to do is we would like to have a way when we're doing
this locking.
You know, if we're checking to see something about whether like an
asset is loaded or not, right that can sort of go away at any time,
right?
And so, you know,
We almost need to do something more like this, where we say, we're
going to sort of take the lock, right?
We then
To see whether the asset is loaded.
Right, and then we would do the end asset lock here.
Sort of thing.
It's not fabulous.
I'm kind of playing around with this that make sense just to see what
I want to do.
So when you come in here you're going to try and get this this asset
whatever it is.
You begin the lock you check to see what the situation is and then you
know you see if you can actually do whatever it is you want to do you
wouldn't do this, right?
You just do this sort of thing, so you'd say like okay, I'm the only
person who's allowed to access that state variable the state list at
this point.
So then you start, you take a look at what the state is.
You you know, something like this.
Right?
You take a look at what the state is.
Assuming it's loaded, you go ahead and modify the list, you set up the
generation ID and then you use set the state to to whatever it needs
to be.
Right?
What was this?
This was just, that doesn't even need to happen, right?
It's really just that all were talking about is is doing the move
headed to front thing, right?
That's all we're talking about.
So you take the asset lock, you check to see if it's loaded.
Assuming it is, you do the move to front and then afterwards, you you
exit, right?
And you wouldn't need to do this anymore because the asset, the lock
would presumably do that, right?
Yeah.
Well, yeah, so anyway,
That would be that and we'd have one here.
So we would want something like that, which just guarantees that these
two things always happen that way.
Now, I want to make sure I'm just going to take a look at remove as a
header from list, right?
Yeah.
And, and move header to front as well.
Yeah, you can kind of see that.
That doesn't get used anywhere either.
So it would really be something where it's going to be up in here.
So, you know, it's something like this.
Got that asset header.
So it would be something like this, right?
Putting that in there, trying to get things down to us.
The smallest possible set of things to look at basically.
So there's the result, there's the result, remove the S editor from
list, then we would assert it at the front like so
Remove acid header from list.
And so, these two guys would be the entirety of the work that gets
done outside there, so it would look like that.
There we go.
Yeah.
And so that's let's see how I feel about that.
Again, like I said multiplayer program was always kind of annoying but
how you know, what do you do?
so anyway,
We go ahead and get the asset we say.
All right, let's optimistically take that lock their.
So we'll just kind of spin on here till we can get.
It will move the thing to the front.
If it's loaded.
Otherwise we'll just pass through it immediately release it right?
All good.
And that's the only place that that really, ever gets done that
happens on, but that would happen on both sounds and bitmaps.
In case we ever do, want sounds to be a thing in the future.
And again, that's that's just touching.
That list, which, you know, anyone could be touching, you know, at the
same time, basically.
So that's why I wanted to to block that off.
Now, begin asset.
Lock also, what happened here on acquire assets memory, which is the
other thing that that does this kind of work.
It basically has to look through that same, you know, kind of another
one of those lists that keeps all the free store stuff so that's all
good.
And then after it's done, it would release it.
Taking a look here at
What the other things do?
Yeah.
Taking a look at what the other things do.
I feel like, really?
Now, as you can see, they don't really do anything other than call a
choir asset memory, and potentially push a task on, which is again all
fine.
Since I don't think there's anything else that would have to happen
there, I think that's all good, right?
We're checking against asset State loaded since
We're only care about the fact that something can move something to
unloaded.
The only place that can really happen, right?
Is is when we actually free stuff, right?
So the only place that can really happen is in here when we evict
stuff and that's inside the lock as well.
So in theory, as long as something was equal to a state loaded, it
could never go to unload it again, except for some other piece of
others in the lock.
So we wouldn't have to worry about that.
So I think that's a little bit better now.
My assumption, don't quote me on it, of course, but but that is my
assumption.
All right, so if we go ahead and do in here, something to actually
make the asset lock thing happen, what does that look like?
Again, this is just going to be a pretty pretty brain-dead little
lock.
It's just going to be something that sits there and Spins to try and
get access.
And again, this is only for a situation that would be
Pretty lightweight, which is why I'm a little worried about the fact
that the allocator would be behind it because the allocator is not
very efficient.
But again, you know, that's something that we would start to tackle
once we have profiles and actually know that, you know, what's a
problem and how are things working in that sort of stuff.
But in order to do that, what I would want to do is I'd want to have
some way of, you know you know, just having a lock here, it would
literally just be a thing that was like, lock right operation lock or
something like this and then what we would want to
Say okay, the operation lock always has to be set to 0, so we need to
just do something where we spin.
Like so, and right and when we're doing the spinning, jenny and asset
lock is pretty easy.
We just set the operation lock 20.
That's that's really all we would need to do, right?
But in this case, we need to do something where as we do our spinning.
I keep forgetting we don't need this because the the Acquire The
Exchange actually does it for us.
So all we would do here is say okay we want to do an atomic compare
exchange to you know with our lock we want to make sure that we get
back the right thing.
So we're just basically saying okay you know assuming that that we
actually that actually worked we'll stop trying right?
And normally what you would do
Here is you'd potentially put your thread to sleep if you couldn't get
it and you thought it was going to be while we're not going to do that
because we tend to only have as many threads as there are cores.
We don't ever want these locks to actually take very long so they kind
of just want to sit there hammering on them, as often as possible for
the most part, that's what we would actually like to see happen
because so probably we really don't want to do anything else.
Particularly fancy there.
Now I'm going to go ahead and check because I always forget the order
of the parameters here.
So there's that value that we're setting, right?
There's the operation lock, that's a new value, we want and then
there's the expected value and we want to see that we get back a zero.
If we don't get back a zero, then that means there's already one in
there and if there was already a one in there, that means someone else
has a lock.
So we don't want to do anything at that point.
So we only want to actually stop trying to take the lock.
Until after right?
So that's what we want to do.
So I don't know.
That seems like that's mostly what I was thinking again, we'll have to
take a closer look at it because multi-threading multi-threading code
is hard.
Let's go shopping.
But yeah.
So in here, all I need to do to finish up.
What we were doing is say, okay, you know, in here, there's going to
be a thing called renders and backgrounds, renters and backgrounds
going to be set to false.
By default, but remember exactly what the function is that creates
things here, let's take a look there.
Allocate render group and so assets should be locked.
Should actually now be renders in background, right?
That's what we actually want.
Render some background.
Oops, that's not good.
What happened.
There we go.
Printers in background.
And so, what I want to do here is say,
renders in background equals renders and
And so, and I think that's it, that's probably all that we really
needed in here.
You can kind of see, whoever says, if we go up here, to allocate
render group, if you go up to allocate render group, you can see that
the ground chunks, all say that already because they were doing that,
they're passing that is whether they should walk or not.
So that's just renders and background.
And these guys don't render in background, which is exactly what we
want to have happen, right?
Right.
And so that seems all pretty normal.
So now when we just have to finish up, let's see here.
How many that's it load fit map.
Now when we call load bitmap we need to actually have in here since
there's that immediate parameter.
We need to actually have that in here, right immediate
Prefetch bitmap, you really probably don't need that.
Obviously, it's not going to be immediate if you're trying to show
prefetch.
So that's fine, right?
So inside push bitmap, cure, we want to do an immediate here.
We don't write that makes sense.
So, so off we go, right?
And and I think that's just about it.
So I don't know that was a bit of a, you know,
Kind of spamming a bit there, you know, expand it out a little bit,
but let's, let's start taking a look and see, you know, where we've
where we've got to we don't have any catastrophic bugs at the moment,
right?
We're still running.
But like I said with multi-threaded code, you really don't really know
if you're coated it, right?
Until you actually dig down into a little bit.
So I would say it's a little premature to declare any kind of Victory.
I don't know how much we want to really investigate it at the moment
because like I said, I think this is maybe something we want.
Kind of weight a little bit on.
But I did want to kind of have something in there.
That was at least a plausible argument for how this thing could be
multi thread safe, so that when we go to lock it down a little bit
more, when we have some debug visualizations, that sort of stuff and
can sort of maybe compartmentalize the code a little bit.
There we aren't finding that like we just wrote this horribly awful
thing that that could never possibly work.
Right?
So we want something that's at least plausibly going to work there.
Okay.
So let's
Let's continue on just a little bit more, just to finish up a few more
of these things here, which is we have not actually finished the
generation ID thing, which is the other thing that I said that I
wanted to do.
And like I said, we've got about 20 minutes left, I guess because
that's I was very long, pretty stream.
So yeah, we've got got 20 more minutes.
So let's take a look.
See if we can't get that in so we at least have this stuff sort of
nominally in place.
All right, so what have we got here?
This is gone, right?
That's out of there.
Goodbye.
So we've got that.
We now have this generation ID, the generation ID was the thing that I
was saying would allow us to kind of set some kind of indication, you
know of what was happening.
You know, when this guy was getting used right?
And so that we had some, you know, nominal notion of which generation
ideas couldn't could not be freed.
So let's take a look at what would be involved in tracking that
obviously, in order to track that we
Need the generation ID to sort of be, you know, to be known by the
render group so that anytime a render group is using an ascetic can
set that thing properly, right?
So what we need to do here is we need to in the place where you set
the generation ID, we need to now start actually thinking about what
that generation ID would actually be.
So when we call get asset, we have two things.
We have an you know, the ID of the
A thing we're getting and then also the generation ID of the thing.
You know, that that was requesting it, right?
Like so makes sense and so that will kind of push push things back.
Oops.
Nice tidy that'll push things back so we can kind of see who's calling
that again using the comparator kind of guide you to the right place.
So in here we could just say oh whatever the generation ID is of this
render group, same thing here, right?
Whatever the
And ideas of the surrender group.
No big deal.
And so now all we have to do is actually have one of those generation
IDs in the render group itself.
And as far as the sound is concerned, not really sure what the easiest
way to do that is, but I guess we'll kind of what kind of have to do
it.
Well, to kind of play that by ear a little bit, we'll probably have to
get a generation ID every time we issue one of these things, right?
We'll probably have to do.
Something like right here where we access a generation ID, right?
So yeah.
So that's roughly what we're talking about.
So if I have a generation ID here and maybe I'll switch that
generation.
I need to be a struct as well, just so we can keep them straight.
So it's not just a u-32 that's flying around and get some extra type,
checking from the compiler, which is usually a good thing.
So I guess what we'd say here is a new generation ID.
Something like this, we pass the assets in.
Like so, right?
And and the same thing would be true here.
So every time we do one of these, like allocate render group things,
this render group, every time it gets allocated is going to do thing
work.
It's a generation ID, New Generation ID from the assets, right?
And go to do,
Raishin ID like so.
So, that's, you know, that's how that goes.
I'm actually gonna set that right at the top, to be honest with you,
we're going to go ahead and just going to make that be right on up
there.
Although, I suppose it should come technically a little bit after the
assets itself, since that's who it's actually calling.
So that's fine.
All right, so something like this, where we just have a way of getting
you generation ideas and then those generation IDs our past.
And if
I go into handmade asset.
What I want to do here is make it so that people can get one of these
generation IDs, right?
Any time that they want.
So you can get a generation ID by calling New Generation ID, you pass
it the assets and it will go ahead and make one of those for you.
So, if I, if I have the, the game assets here, game assets, we have
something in here that's like, okay, you know, we want that S ID.
I want to keep it away from the operation La Crosse with you.
So that the cache line is different.
Nothing is actually probably matters, all that much, but I'm going to
go ahead and say that there's just one up here, that's like the
generation ID, right?
Or the Next Generation ID, Star Trek, the Next Generation ID.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm going to say, all right, anytime
you want one of these, it's just the generation ID + +, right?
And return, a result.
Now, unfortunately, I can't just do that directly because if these
things are kind of, like I was saying, going to be issued for multiple
threads potentially,
Then we kind of have this problem where every time that you're going
to do this, you could potentially get the same generation ID from two
different people and that might be bad.
We want everyone to have a unique generation ID.
We want to be monotonically increasing.
So what I really want here is I want to be able to do an atomic
increment, right?
And there's two ways that we could do an atomic increment one, is we
could just do an atomic compare Exchange in a loop but that seems
unnecessary because really there already is one of these, which is
Atomic increment.
That's actually already a thing that processors let you do already, so
you can do like an interlocked increment.
Like so and just to give us a little more flexibility.
I might do an atomic add, right?
So we have you in 32 value like so or add end which basically just
takes one thing and adds it to another, but it does it in a way that's
guaranteed to be Atomic.
So we know that we won't get that race condition where two people are
accessing the value at the same time and end up.
Not actually implementing it twice only incrementing it once because
they both read the same value, incremented it
And wrote it back, right?
So, you know, they both read five, they both, incremented 26 in both
wrote it back, it was supposed to be one of them gets five.
One of them, get 6, and it ends up at 7:00 instead, both of them got
five in both wrote six, which ain't no good, right?
We want to do that.
We could do that.
We just do something like this where the assets Next Generation ID
gets passed in like so and then it does that interlocked add.
Now the problem with interlocked ADD is that, I never remember whether
it returns because it changes on different platforms.
Whether the macro is defined to return the old value or the new value
because I believe it's different, the function Returns the result,
okay, so it's returning the new value so this is actually correct.
But what's going to happen here in a second, right?
Is we're going to have something like this on lunatics, the operating
system for Europeans and what we want to do is we want to be able to
do sink Val, probably add or something, right?
Because I'm just going by what, you know, this, this is stuff that
people who report to other platforms sent us like, could you do that?
And think Val underscore something is that?
There's, there's a sink Val ad or something like that, right?
It's like sink.
Val.
Add something like this sink Val increment.
I don't know.
Let's see, there's there is a set of these.
There we go, sink.
Fetch an ad.
That's what we want.
I believe sync.
Fetch and add and return.
See, you see how they get you?
It Returns the previous result.
So if you were just like do deter, you know, and you did that, you're
very sad Panda because now, your code doesn't work, but it turns out,
Let me just do that, right?
You can do the actual operation because it Returns the previous value.
That's all you really need to make sure that you get the right
results.
So we still can do it.
I think people who are running on links right now, you feel free to
tell me tomorrow when you go to build, if that's if that keeps working
for you, hopefully it will.
Ya.
What's wrong with my interlocked ad?
What, what is wrong with my interlock add interlocked?
Add.
Somebody want to tell me why?
Oh, it's right there.
Even
Good luck.
Dad.
I just looked at it.
Why am I not getting that?
Did we not?
Why is interlocked compare exchange available, but not interlock dad
interlocked pair exchange.
I didn't make that an intrinsic, did I?
A little strange, isn't it?
Wouldn't you say?
Wouldn't you say would you say?
I don't know if you would or if you wouldn't
but it's a little odd.
Yeah.
Well
See if we could find out.
Why?
Maybe, maybe they just isn't a.
I'm just scared version of it.
I don't think so though.
Maybe we have to clear it in terms of car sells interlock compare
exchange.
Oops.
normally, I have to declare these myself because I don't actually
linked with any of these things, but
I'm not sure why we were able to do interlock compare exchange, just
fine and nobody else, which is a little bit weird one has to admit.
Well, you don't have to admit it if you don't want to.
Let's see here blah blah blah.
interlocked variable access interlocked API compiler, intrinsics
Hello.
I clicked on you.
Did you not hear me?
I'm clicking.
Boy, that web speed.
Huh.
All right, there we go.
Let's take a look.
X 64, MB intrinsics list.
No rush there.
You know, take your time.
It's not like we're trying to do a stream here.
so let's see, let's see what we've got interlocked and and and
It's like a exchange interlock, decrement interlock exchanges.
You for interlocked exchange ad?
Okay.
well, let's take a look at that, then
Provide compiler support with blah blah blah blah.
Travis initial value.
Oh, look at this.
We can get it.
The same on both one.
Well, the real point to buy the ad in parameter.
Look at that, look at that.
Now, ours won't be different.
That's cool.
So they like unify their intrinsics, well, you don't see that happen,
very often things actually get better with a new release, that never
happens.
Like how did we luck out there interlocked exchange?
Add Plus at, and
Like so.
Lovely.
So, I believe that is actually giving us our generation IDs now.
And so, in theory, you know, if we go in to get bitmap now we would
see that's no good.
We would see the generation ID, be something reasonable, right?
And it is and hopefully, you know, if we take a look at what comes
back, that thing is stamped with our generation ID which it is right.
And so that's pretty good.
Everyone's pretty happy about that, you know?
Go right.
So that's all good.
Nothing particularly strange happening there.
And so now all we really have to do to be honest is make sure that we
don't evict anything that has a generation ID.
That's still in Flight, right?
That's really all we have to do.
And so when we are in here and we're evicting assets, actually
probably the easiest way to do that is just to keep a little list of
which things are actually in Flight that that might actually be
easiest.
And worrying about retire and order or any of that stuff.
Since there's so few renderers that can actually be inflated time.
You know, we're talking about less than 16 at any given time for sure.
Probably far less than 16 most of the time because we don't have that
many task that's been up.
We don't have many cores.
So there shouldn't be sitting out there doing rendering anyway, so
when we're doing that, you know, when we when we're going to delete an
asset we could look to see if it's a state is loaded.
And also we could say
And asset generation ID generation is completed.
Generation has completed.
I know what you guys think about that?
Hopefully you like it and or love it.
And or like love it.
Oh, I'm starting to see something cool.
We could do here too but maybe not quite on this stream.
Anyway, so up on handmade asset,
Inside game assets.
We just do something like in-flight generation or in-flight
Generations, write something like that.
I guess that wouldn't actually be in-game assets.
What it?
I guess it would be.
Yeah.
Inflight Generations.
it's going to be a little tricky because this actually
this actually wants to be kind of a little bit protected as well but
that's okay.
So anyway, we've got in-flight generations and that's going to have a
little thing here.
That's like you know, Generations, flight, generation count, write
something like this, right?
And so all we would do here is when we initialize those game assets,
I guess we, when we actually do that initialization, I guess we just
clear it ever.
We do not sow in here.
I would like to do a thing where we do assets.
Next Generation.
I'd equals zero Assets in Flight, generation, count, equals 0, and
then we're done, right?
And so generation ID.
When we do new generation ID, I guess we'd kind of make this a little
bit.
You know what?
If we make, if we actually do this in one step two, we don't really
even need the.
We don't even need the atomic add.
Now that I think about it.
because what we could do is we could just do begin asset lock and
asset lock around those to basically say all right the result is the
next-generation ID we increment it
And then, what we do is we say, well, we should also do a little
assertion in here.
Right.
But all we're doing here is saying, okay, assert that, the Assets in
Flight.
Generation count is less than the number that we're ever allowed to
have in Flight Generations.
So we start that, that's true.
Assuming that that is true.
We then just go ahead and put that in here.
Right?
So we say okay, the in-flight generation count is going to be
Sets.
So,
That way, we just store these guys in the little array, right?
And then all we have to do is, you know, if we did that now, we'd
immediately blow that out.
Oops.
Like we should immediately hit that assertion right?
Generation has completed also.
I suppose has to be an actual called somebody actually implements
header.
We go.
So we have generation has completed and that's got to be inside
handmade asset as well.
Okay.
And since that's only ever called inside the lock, it's safe for us to
go ahead and make this sort of
Damn iterate over this array and just go.
Okay, double check that this guy.
Is or is not still in Flight, right?
And so, in order to do that, all I have to do is go through sort of
the indices
Of all of the generations that are in Flight here which can only be a
few.
Oops.
So we've got those in Flight Generations.
If?
Like the check ID.
If I find it in the list, then the result is true.
Right.
Oh sorry there's all this false.
I guess it's the other way around.
The generation has been completed if it's not in the list, right?
So the only thing that I need to do now to finish that up is I need to
change this so that the new generation ID thing.
There's basically like a begin generation, right?
And an end generation
And generation.
Like so.
Pretty straightforward.
And that would take the Jen patient ID and it would do generation has
completed.
It would do exactly the same thing here and all its going to do is
remove that guy, right?
So it's going to go through here, it's going to say if equals the
generation ID then it just needs to collapse list by 1, right?
And break.
So it's going to go like, okay, the whichever one were on here, we
would like to swap it with the count, right?
Like so.
Like this.
Right.
So I'm just going to say, okay we're going to erase this one, the one
that's in the slot.
So the one we found that's equal to this one.
We're just going to then decrement the count by one and take whatever
was in that final slot and put it here, right?
That's it, nothing particularly fancy, that's all there is to it and
then we don't actually have a results to return.
So that's fine.
Right.
All right.
So in allocate render group I guess the thing that I
Don't really know is what gets rid of the render groups.
Been a long time since I wrote any of this code.
So I don't actually know that we always get rid of our render groups.
I assume that we do, but I guess we probably don't.
We've never really had to do that before, right?
I don't think there was really any shutdown.
They were free, right?
They never had to be blocked.
They never had to be like blocked out before.
So for example in foul ground chunk, you know, here comes the render
group, we do all this stuff with it you can see right.
Like so I guess decide what I pushed, buffer sizes, blah blah blah.
So that does all this stuff.
Yeah, it does, it's little ad thing get this code.
Now could be written.
This was written very protectively, we could
Will be do most of that stuff.
Now directly, we were, like, actually doing all the assets tough on
one thread.
If you take a look at it, but that stuff now we could do on multiple
threads, through wanted to.
But anyway, yeah, it pretty much never really ended that stuff, right?
Render group to Output, was it de facto the end?
Right?
So yeah, so I guess we can just make render
ER, two output be the thing that ends it
It means you can't render to the same render group to two different
things.
So we would have to kind of change that eventually if you wanted to.
But, you know, that would probably be fine too.
If we, you know, that's something we could cross that bridge when we
come to it.
But rendered group to Output, right?
Grouped output and tiled render group to Output.
Would end it right about here.
so,
I think I want a separate end call.
Just looking at the way this works.
I feel like we want an end call.
So I think we want something like finish render group, you know I'm
saying, just looks like the right thing to do there to me.
I'm just going to say it seems, right.
I don't know.
Result goes push struct Arena render group.
It just seems kind of odd.
Yeah.
That just seems kind of odd.
This one makes sense because hey it already got cleaned up in this one
and I guess we are, it's already inside a memory thing, so yeah, well
yeah, I guess so, I guess that's just how that goes anyway.
So if we have finished render group
And then we just takes whatever the render group is.
That's just going to do the end generation group Assets, Group
generation ID, right?
Assuming that it actually exists.
Like so,
That's fine.
The render group to Output.
Right.
But that kind of thing.
We've got one more thing to do.
There we go, let's get this in here, right?
We've kind of got one other thing to do there which is that where we
do this whole like assets missing thing right in the film ground
Chunk, we don't really need to do anymore because we're it since it's
a me.
It'll never have any assets missing, right?
So we never have to do if all resources present thing.
That's just not a thing, right?
That's not an issue.
So we can just assert that, that's true.
And that way we do not, we, you know, we always know that it will get
added as a task and finished, right?
So I think that's good.
Begin generation and generation.
You should ID assets.
So this is just, you know, all the sounds here and presumably, nobody
needs to do anything after that.
So yeah, so now in theory and I can only stress that enough, only in
theory, we've implemented something that fixes the bug from before.
But only in Theory without some testing, we have no idea.
If this works properly, it's purely conjecture.
And there are probably other bugs lurking in there.
So this is more of a to be continued.
But again,
Because we knew that there were problems with it.
I felt like it was better to at least address them structurally for
now because we want to try to get all of our stuff structurally.
Correct.
As we wrap up the engine code, we do not want to have stuff that we
know is structurally wrong, but that's different from saying that,
then saying that we have actually fixed it all properly because that
will only come with some testing down the line.
But there we go.
So at least we're
I kind of, you know, we're a little bit, little bit little bit more,
sure that things could be made to work properly with the structure
that we have now.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A.
See here.
yeah, if you have questions about what we're doing,
Let's see.
So first of all, yeah, well so for Atomic ad, I'm just going to get
rid of it.
Because we don't need it.
Atomic, add does not need to happen so we can stay with just the time.
I compare exchange.
These don't cast value to long star for sync.
Fetch an ad, it will generate the wrong code.
On 64-bit Linux OSX.
What about this one?
well, okay, so I think we're fine as long as we
Do you think fetchin?
Add then which I don't really want to do because we don't want to add
an additional dependency there if we don't have to.
So if we can get away with using, only one sinc function, that's kind
of nice.
That means we only ever need that on any platform.
What's the advantage of calling load bitmaps from other threads?
Wouldn't it be better to just have Push pit.
Matt fail when called from of the thread so that there are no assets
missing from the ground chunks.
And so that all the bitmap memory could be acquired on the main
thread.
The grand trunk should probably wait one frame to have their assets
loaded if they are prefetched ahead of time.
The reason is because I feel like it's not that I feel like it won't
be that hard to debug the multi-threaded code when it comes time to do
it.
And it's just kind of nice to know we can render from separate threads
without having it be a big deal.
Like it seemed like it was kind of the thing that was okay.
I mean we're just taking a lock there, that's fine.
It's not a huge deal because it's just like an ink and assuming and
you doing a couple quick things and then getting out, right?
So it's really the only thing that concerns me about it mostly is the
memory allocator because that thing's kind of slow and so that's that
thing but but that's the thing that I think we have to rewrite to be
much faster.
Anyway, so that may be fine as well because we eventually, like I
said, when we wrote it as like, we're going to do something better
here further down the line.
So
Is it get every vote online.
If so, how does one gain access right now?
It is online but you can only gain access if you're a maintainer of a
main Port, the general access is coming very shortly but it's not
quite ready yet.
So it's not quite ready to be in the wild.
But it's coming.
I was actually working on that right before the stream.
Basically, it's just a question of getting the web stuff all set up
to, like, authenticate people and stuff like that.
Who is man, the black, will you get rid of standard NT?
Potentially, although you don't really have to worry too much about
standard and because it doesn't bring any real code into your thing.
It's not like using a library like standard in is just a header.
You can include it even if you don't include the standard Library, if
you want to, it's not too hard to do that.
So we could get rid of it eventually just for fun, but it's not like
like we want to get rid of like, you know, sine and cosine this stuff
because those
Actual pieces of code and we'd like to replace them with our own.
So that part of the C runtime Library, we actually want to replace
standard in T is really not that useful because it's there isn't any
actual code it's just a couple type deaths so that's not really a
problem but we could also replace it if we wanted to
Is volatile actually needed in your compare and exchange.
You're talking about this volatile.
It doesn't really matter since it's an inline it really doesn't matter
because the sink Val compare and swap.
It will become a volatile here.
I believe.
So I don't
Matters.
I don't think it matters particularly much there because this this is
the actual operation and it's declared as volatile.
This, this will treat it as volatile I believe.
So yeah, I don't I don't think you actually need the volatile there.
It's more.
It's more like a thing that just is telling you.
Hey by the way, this value is going to get treated as volatile just
you know, but you could delete it and it wouldn't
I don't think we have any would make no difference whatsoever.
How difficult would it be to have the letter particles fall
independently of the hero?
Probably pretty trivial.
I mean all you would do is just have an ad end, right?
Like you're talking about if you don't want them to move when where
the heroes moving.
So, you know, if you want to do that right?
Then you just want to know what the camera move was between the last
frame and this frame for the particle.
So like when you're updating the protocol and you're in here, you
would just put that motion in here that
There's a little bit.
Right?
You do you just you'd have this, right?
You'd have camera displacement.
And you subtract the camera, displacement from everything you did
here.
And then when you updated particles, you Dad the camera displacement,
right?
So,
See here.
Let's see, I don't remember what we did.
All hits your here.
Basically, at the very end after you compute the protocol P, all this
stuff, right?
You would you would also displaced by the camera.
So, pretty much when you probably right up on load actually, so I
would probably say you would want to do it here.
Where you uncreation, you, you negate them on the first Loop through
on particle index.
You would do you would do particle p.
Let's equals camera displacement.
Something like this.
And then what you need to do is you just need to make sure that
particle camera.
Displacement is actually something that you know, like like what it is
right?
You need to know how that actually was going to to happen.
So you need to take where the camera was last time and where the
camera was this time.
And so, you know, probably the easiest way to do that would be to have
some kind of a notion of where that was.
So for example, inside the game state,
You know.
Here's the camera P, right?
You just have a last camera P probably would be.
The easiest thing to do would be my guess, right?
It's, you know, we'd have to think about this a little more depending
on how we want to do it.
But like something like this right?
Last camera.
P like so and then you would just do like okay, you know, last camera
P was canopy, you know, this sort of thing.
Right.
Something like that.
And I think if we actually okay that is not obviously not quite right.
I think if you actually compute that correctly that would be fine,
right?
Because then when the camera moves, the particles would move with it.
So, yeah, particle P should be protesters.
Why was that?
What's the problem there?
Hey Murphy subtract some Center.
Oh, that's not quite what I wanted.
Let me let me take that back.
I want that.
Actually, I actually want the full displacement of the two.
So we would do, you know, gamestate camera P, like that.
And we do this, I guess would actually be what we do the game straight
camera p and game State lab shampoo.
So we'd actually do it in the in the full.
The full thing.
I think that would give us the displacement on a given frame that,
right?
Or not.
Sorry, I'm kind of just talking this together.
Almost correct.
Oh, well, there's one other thing that we'd have to do, right?
Yeah.
So there is one of the things that we'd have to do that.
I forgot about which is the fact that we're doing sort of our alerian
thing, the or alerian stuff would have to actually be on a grid that
mood with the screen.
So that part actually would be a little
Here, it's not hugely tough, but that would definitely be a little
trickier, right?
So basically like the part where you actually do account for Stuff,
based on the
Based on the cell right?
Select dispersion this stuff like that dispersion, that part ain't
going to cut it, right?
That part is is problematic because the grid right now doesn't
understand how to do that stuff, if that makes sense.
Yeah, so yeah.
So it's not, it wouldn't be too hard but there's a bunch of things
that we would have to do, like the, the why?
You remember, the Y is kind of hacked, so that's why I like, right
now, if I move up or down, right?
It's not gonna do the proper thing because it's just using Y equals
zero as a, you know, as a displacement off of a hero which isn't going
to quite work.
So, right now we're, you know, we're almost there.
You wouldn't require very much more if you want it to just kind of be
there.
Yeah, but that's just really happy.
You would have to do something if you're
Actually do this for real.
I'm going to back these out because I these are not quite exactly.
You know, this is not exactly what you would want to be doing.
You'd want to do something a little bit more realistic, especially if
you want to keep that or Larry.
And in there that's a little bit of a more important, more important
bit.
There we go.
What was that / so just place?
So yeah, so thinking about a little bit more.
Yeah.
If you wanted to actually have it be independent of the hero, the part
of the system as it is now the or Larry imparts the harder part
because since you have that grid that you're using for simulation, you
have to make that grid move along around the world properly because
you can't simulate the grid everywhere.
So you can't just have it be throughout the whole world because it'd
be too expensive.
So you have
Make sure that you would just kind of aligned it roughly to where the
screen is and kind of move it around with you, so it's going to that
would take a little bit of work.
That would definitely be a little bit of work.
Steven last.
Don't you need to move all ground, chunk work into the separate thread
at the moment?
It looks like it's only actually doing render to Output in the task.
Yeah, I mean, we don't have to move it there but we now probably
could, if that makes sense previously.
We weren't doing that because we didn't the rest of the stuff wasn't
thread safe.
I don't know that.
We want to add that complexity like week that gives us flexibility the
fact that that's not happening right now that those are only happening
from one thread is kind of nice, right?
I mean in some sense, you could say that if we leave it this way it
gives us the ability to back out the the locks
It gives us the ability to get rid of the locks that are in there
right now, right?
Because it means that the generation ID stuff is the only stuff that
has to be correct.
Be locked, right?
And that's kind of a nice option.
So I'm not going to move it in there until we actually need to because
it gives us some options that we wouldn't otherwise have
Why are using usage for instead of size t for buffer sizes?
I guess.
Where is that?
Where are you saying that?
Exactly.
Which one are you talking about?
It may just be an oversight, if that's the case.
I think we use memory index for a lot of them so that we can control
what it actually is, if that makes sense.
In memory index is a size T.
So in a lot of cases, that's actually what it is, right?
So like this is not a you 64.
It's the size t.
Alger add.
Why are using Windows?
We use Windows because that's what all games ship on.
Basically, you know, games are consoles and windows.
There really isn't any other place unless you're talking maybe about
mobile.
Consoles, windows and mobile.
You might say there are no game sold on Windows and Mac.
That's just that's, that's not like opinion.
That's just, you know,
That's just the reality if that makes sense.
So if you kind of go and you take a look at that,
What what it looks like you know those are that's the sad reality of
it.
Ain't nobody buying no games on on Mac or Linux, unfortunately, wish
they did, right?
I'd love to see these numbers invert.
I'd love to see this number be 95 and and this number be 0.89 percent,
but that's, that's not the reality.
So, so if you want to program games, you got a program on Windows,
unless you're programming on like, a
Or or, you know, your your mobile game.
But if it's doing a PC game, which is what handmade hero is, you're on
Windows.
Now, we do everything, cross-platform, obviously handmade hero.
So like, you know, people have already ported it to all sorts of other
platforms.
Someone to the PS4 Port.
Someone did a Vita Port already.
Someone did a macports.
We did a Linux Port already.
So we make it really easy to do the port's because we architected it
well for that, but in terms of what your primary development platform
has to be it.
it pretty much has to be Windows because you want to
The running in testing, the game is often as possible on the primary
platform.
You're playing to ship on, that's the easiest way to make sure that
you don't have a lot of platform bugs and stuff like that, right?
Steven last.
I only ask because for now it seems like you'll be stalling for that
load bitmap on the main thread.
Oh, that's a good point.
Actually, we kind of did that prematurely.
So I suppose technically infill ground chunk.
Yeah.
That would stall while we load the asset, which is not awesome.
That's a good point.
Hmm, I'm not sure what we want to do about that.
Exactly.
I mean I suppose we could try moving it all to the other thread.
Kind of risky, right?
But we could try it.
Just go Hog Wild.
I guess it would help us find bugs to and the other in the in the push
bitmap stuff that I just said that we should do, right?
Yeah, we could try it.
So if you're going to do that,
if we do, fill ground chunk work.
I guess we really would just
put all the, I mean, basically, the entire thing would go in there,
right?
I mean, literally, actually everything the whole thing.
Is that correct?
Cuz yeah.
I think, literally everything wood.
Let's take a look here.
so,
I think maybe not that one last one though.
I think maybe this still wants to be there just so it's gets recorded
as being in a particular location.
So I think that wants to say everything else.
Not so much, so yeah.
So let's see, what does this actually need?
Because I don't know.
so, let's see, we need the trance State assets,
We need what was actually passed to fill ground chunk.
Ground buffer.
Star ground buffer.
And then World position chunk P.
I guess we just passed those things in, and let it have a party.
Just gamestate.
Get used in here anywhere.
Just a chunk Doom in m is really it.
Right.
So we could try it.
You could try it.
This is dangerous.
What we're doing here.
It's a little bit dangerous, you know, just a little bit.
All right.
There we go.
so, work state
Ground buffer.
Jumpy.
Here we go.
So work game State just came State work, buffer around buffer work p
spunky.
And yeah, trance state.
Transient State.
Oh, that's the assets needs that work?
Translate
Oops.
Here we go.
So, just grab Mike that I guess.
Task.
Is work tasks.
And that's worth going to state.
We're trying state.
and these are just
just that.
So I don't know what this is going to do.
Yeah, probably something like that.
So, let's take a look.
Allocate render group.
Phil ground chunk work.
Push size.
Size.
88.
What is actually?
is it the arena of the
Nina's uninitialized.
Why is the arena uninitialized?
Did we not fill out the task?
We did not fill out the task.
That would do it.
Work fast.
Assert not renders in background.
So we did a load bitmap call with immediate set to true.
We then failed to get a bitmap
Which is not fabulous to say the least.
And this is a renders in background.
How did we fail would be the interesting question?
But that was good that actually tested that code path which we had
never done before.
So let's let's take a look at that.
Very interesting.
so if we have two people, right, who both hit this thing at the same
time,
Then they can't necessarily guarantee that they'll get it, right?
Which is kind of interesting.
That's pretty cool.
That's a pretty cool race condition.
You have to admit, right?
This is why I was saying like, yeah, you know, do we really want to do
this?
Do you really want to do it multi-threaded, or do?
We always want to leave those things in the same thread?
I don't know, it's handmade here.
We're supposed to be doing things a little harder than you would
normally maybe make them so, why not?
But yeah, so you saw kind of what happened there and get asset kind of
have that nastiness where
Sorry in you I guess it's in use bitmap or get bitmap or whatever it
shouldn't be.
Wait.
Wait why isn't here?
Where is it?
Oh, it's in the renderer.
I'm a banker.
Here we go.
Use bitmap.
Or push bitmap.
There it is.
So inside push bitmap, right?
It's taking a look at, if the renters in background, then it tries to
force the load, but it can't actually guarantee that that's true.
Because if two people call this at the exact same time, only one of
them will actually succeed, right?
Only one of them.
Will actually succeed in getting the asset if that makes sense.
So, you know, if I come in here, oops.
To load bitmap to people on the stomach compare exchange hit it.
Only one of them is able to actually take the queued, right?
And so that person is the one who actually will load it and the other
person will return before it before it's actually loaded, right?
So this person would have to, you know, stall, essentially a person,
the person who didn't get to do to do the load, right?
So we do something like
No, you something like this?
So if we were unable to do the atomic compare exchange, you would just
spin lock on the load.
I'm assuming, you know, while it's not equal to cute.
The only thing is, we do allow you to get an asset State unloaded,
which is presumably if you could not actually get a task, you know,
that kind of makes me wonder.
That kind of makes me wonder if we should just always do it, right?
Meaning hey if we couldn't get a background task, maybe we should just
load the thing.
Right.
I don't know, maybe not.
I guess you just want to not have it that frame potentially.
But anyway, while the thing is cued, you would want to wait here.
You'd want to wait here to get it cute.
So you'd want to do something like, you know, okay, I tried to load
it.
I couldn't load it so I'm just going to spin until it skewed State
goes away.
So I basically say, you know,
You know, this sort of thing.
Right.
But the problem is, you know, the compiler doesn't know that it has to
reload that every time.
So we would have to do something like this where we would tell it
first that it's a volatile, but it's a volatile load, right?
So we need to do something like asset State Star State.
Equals s estate, volatile star asset state.
You know.
Walt skewed do absolutely nothing, right.
Hmm.
So we're working but sadly.
We are not rendering the correct bitmaps.
It's like our are chunks are wrong or something, right?
Which actually, I think I know what that is.
We probably set it in the wrong order, right?
Junk P equals chunk p.
Oh wait, we set that as a pointer.
That's no good.
That's, that's wrong.
That's not, that's not good at all.
Right.
Yeah.
So that's more like, that's not like that.
That was accessing some random garbage, so that's no good.
There we go.
So yeah, I don't know, like I said at this point, we just don't have
very much in the way of debug Vis so I don't really know how well
that's working.
But yeah.
So right like I'm going to put to do in there because I don't know.
Like it's kind of like that was a question on the string that I just
you know, in one of that thing for us.
So we didn't really have a chance to sort of think it through so I was
But you do, do we want to have a more?
Coherent story here for what happens when 24 slowed people hit the
load at the same time, right?
I don't know.
How difficult would would it be to make this boot alone in a Raspberry
Pi or something like that?
Well we're going to find out someday.
Load asset work for you.
64 is not equal to size T.
So load asset work you're talking about.
This.
These guys.
Is that what that we're talking about?
So the reason for that is really just because these are filed, these
are based on the file API, right?
And so we were just forcing you 64 is 4 file for the file API.
Technically you could.
Yeah you could change it to a size T because obviously you wouldn't go
to allocate enough memory on 32-bit in order to fit anything bigger
than that.
But that's that's why that's a size.
That's why it's easier before.
We're dedicating one thread to asset loaded, which has an atomic Cube,
be a bad idea.
I don't know that it would be a bad idea, it might be an okay idea,
right?
I mean things are a little complicated in the asset system and the
asset like thread management thing at the moment.
And so it might be that like considering a slightly different design.
Like oh we just have everything on this one Q or something.
Right?
Might be good.
You know.
It's hard to say
So, yeah, I mean, without investigating other designs at the moment,
it's hard to say.
That's sort of something that would have to be investigated a little
more in depth.
All right.
Looks like that's the end of it.
I'm going to wind it down.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, we did some restructuring of the asset system, whether it's
better or worse.
Now, I don't know.
It's hard to say, we kind of our kind of feeling our way through how
we want the multi, threaded stuff in there, to work exactly the asset
systems.
Obviously, the most complicated thing in terms of threading that we
have in handmade hero and in fact, it's probably going to remain the
most complicated thing that we have in hand made here are probably
forever because
Scott multi-threading and also memory management which is something
that most of the code just doesn't need.
And so, it's kind of a Nexus of a couple of tricky problems and I
suspect that we'll have to spend more time on it later as well.
But it's good now and again, to just kind of go through and go.
Okay, let's play around with architecture, see how it goes, see if we
can improve some things fixing things and we did get rid of the
concept of locking assets which is kind of nice as well.
And we also added the ability now to do multi-threaded asset requests,
which might come in handy.
might not maybe that just opened up a can of worms that we'd rather
just not do and so maybe we won't do that in the future but that's
where we're at at the moment and tomorrow I think probably will go
back and finish up fonts
Try to get fonts.
Well, shouldn't we finish up go back and start the process of doing
the font Media stuff, which will allow us to kind of finish up fonts,
maybe by the end of week or something, kind of have fonts working
relatively comfortably in the game so that we can start using them to
do or debug print out, which would be really nice because we haven't
ever really had debug output and it would be great, you'll be a lot of
fun to have that.
It make things easier.
It's really good thing that you, you know, you want to have, you can
for debugging.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that tomorrow if you'd like to
To join me for that.
That would be I think tomorrow we return to the registers at eight
tomorrow.
Nope, it's still eight tomorrow.
So tomorrow, we're 8 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
Hope to see you there back here on Twitch until then if you want to
play along with with hammer here.
If you want to follow along the source code at home, if you preorder
the game on a meteor dot org you can get the source code and download
it.
I upload the changes every night so you can grab them.
We've also got a forum site, you can go to ask questions.
You like there's also ports to Mac and Linux and anted episode guide,
things like this.
We also have patreon page.
If you want to support our video series, you can subscribe to that and
we have a tweet bought that tweets the schedule at you.
So if you want to catch the series live that's the best way to do it.
Thanks everyone for joining me and I hope you will have fun coding.
Until I see you back here tomorrow until then I will see you on the
internet.
Take it easy everyone.