Okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to aim.
The Morning Edition of handmade here of the show where we can code a
complete game from scratch.
No library is no engines.
So we can see the entire process and learn about absolutely everything
that happens in the full pipeline of a game, right down to how every
single Pixel is drawn.
We are at the point where we are experimenting with our sort of game,
what it's going to need.
We're basically making this a little, some little
Bug stuff where we can move like a little rectangle around a tile map
and do some stuff with it so that we can kind of Define what our
engine architecture needs to be.
And basically the way that I always do architecture as much as
possible as I write the code that uses what I'm going to make first,
without it being there.
So I just pretend that I have stuff that does whatever I want.
And I hack something together, that sort of makes it work.
And then when I'm satisfied that that sort of like definition of what
it needs to do is good and works.
Well, then I kind of break.
It off and say this is the design.
This is what the it sort of API, the interface needs to be to that
part part of the code and then I can go start making it for real and
doing sort of an industrial strength engineering job on it.
So that is the point that we're at and so I'm going to go ahead and
Dive Right In because we have some stuff that we wanted to finish up
from yesterday around basically how we're structuring our tile map
interface.
So I am going to get right into that.
If you are following along at home, if you preorder the source code on
handmade hero dot-org, using the
The Dandy pre-order button, you should have gotten a link in your
email.
If you click on that link, it will allow you to download the source
code in a zip file, that zip file has zip files for every day.
You are going to want to unzip day 32 because we are on day 33 right
now.
And so, you always unzip the previous day's, so unzip days, 32 and you
will be exactly where I am in the source code.
If you would like to file follow along at home with the video.
So let's go ahead in here to handmade code.
Here we are.
Let's start up our editor and our debugger.
And if you remember where we were at, we basically had it so that we
were running our little dude around and we had just finished making it
so that all of our units for the guys motion were in, sort of we move
them, basically, out of pixel space.
We move them into real space, so that everything's happening in meters
inside the game and then it only translates them out into pixels when
it's time to render.
And this was important because we want to support
Basically, any resolution of the game, we don't want everything to be
hard-coded in pixels.
So that is why we were doing that.
So what I want to do now is start to work on the tile map structure a
little bit because I said that there was some stuff in there that I
wanted to do.
We talked about it yesterday.
So there were two things.
In one thing that I wanted to do was I wanted to change to a math,
friendly coordinate system.
So one where y goes up and X goes over, you know, the standard
coordinate system and right now we're not doing that we've got
Going down because that just happens to be how our bitmap is set up,
right?
That's about it.
And so similarly to that.
I also want to make it so that our tile map is accessed in a more sort
of coherent way that I talked about and we'll cover what I want to do
with that.
Again.
I'll just just a brief refresher.
So I want to do those two things today if I can.
So basically all we really need to do is just flip everything upside
down to make our y, go up.
We haven't defined any real information about the maps or anything
like that.
So we should be able to
to do that pretty easily and start to think about what it means to
have our stuff flipped upside down, in that sense relative to the
bitmaps, but I'm not sure which order I want to do them in.
So I'm going to go take a look at the code and see what it whether I
want to flip things upside down first.
And then do the time I have stuff or was I want to do the tile map
stuff first and then, flip up.
Things upside down.
I'm not sure.
So, let's go take a look where we're at.
Inside are handmade .h.
Here, we have this canonical position structure which now
We've kind of worked it down to the point where it can sort of be
considered a World position.
And so one of the things that we were going to talk about is possibly
just renaming it from canonical position.
And I think that's a reasonable thing for us to do.
Just right off the bat.
We can replace canonical position with World position and we shouldn't
really shouldn't really worry about that anymore because there's only
going to be one world position struct and that's just a trivial change
to make.
So that's pretty easy to do.
And yeah, and so let's do it now.
Now just flip.
Why to going up?
Obviously, I could easily flip.
Why?
I could easily flip these two.
These are just offsets from a tile.
I could easily flip.
Why from going up here, but the other thing I want to do is
potentially make it so that they're based on the center of a tile.
We could also do that.
I'm not sure which of these we want to do.
Like I said, if we wanted to switch, why to going up?
And everything from being the lower right now, if you remember, oops,
didn't mean to do that.
There we go.
If you remember right now, when we're talking about a tile, we use the
upper left corner and we create an offset from there to say, where
somebody is relative to the tile and then if they move out of the
tile, we start tracking them in the next aisle over.
And we use the upper corner of that tile to say where they are.
Right?
And so what we could do is we could switch inside the tile to being
from the lower, right?
The the lower left corner instead of the upper left corner and that
would flip the direction of all of the guys motion.
But the tiles would still go in the wrong order, right?
The tile.
Why would still be going down as you went down?
So we would also have to flip that I'm guessing that probably the
right thing to do since we have this working is to maybe just go ahead
and actually think about flipping this actually go ahead and flip this
with what we have right now.
So let's let's look at what it will take to do that.
So first of all, we defined these Maps.
And we defined these Maps, the way that we type them in here.
We defined them upside down, if we were to go bottom up, right?
If you think about the way, we wrote it in the code.
The first row in the array is at the top and this makes sense, because
we're defining it in, ask me where we're going from top down.
Right?
So, you know, if we were to switch it, so that y was up then the first
row that we drew at the bottom of the screen, right?
Because, remember, if we start drawing, you know, if we were to
Drawing Tiles at the bottom corner of the stream.
This is this is the 00 tile.
All of a sudden.
Well, the 00 tile in this array is up here, right?
So this would it be flipped upside down all of these prefab tile maps
that we created would be flipped upside down.
And since we're actually, I mean, we don't really, we are not wedded
to this.
We didn't really spend any time making anything meaningful here so we
could just flip this upside down but it's worth noting that that's
what would happen.
Right?
Our entire tilemap would be flipped.
Upside down.
So, for example, and we could do that right now, actually it pretty
easily in our drawing code.
Right?
The only thing that made it so that this stuff Drew in the way that it
drew for the tiles.
Is the fact that when we started off on row 0, right, that we did the
upper left corner right plus so this is the X, which would say the
same, the upper left corner is y, plus, however, many rows down.
We were times the side and pixels.
So this was essentially
Way that we were drawing as we started here.
And we said the first tile is here.
And then for every row we went down, we added however long, this was
to get to the next one.
Right?
So we're just kind of doing this process on the way down.
So the if we wanted to invert The Way We Were drawing, it's pretty
darn trivial, right?
All we would have to do is say that this now is going to be the
lower-left right from now on.
And instead of adding this in, right?
We're going to actually subtract the tile side in pixels, right?
But in in subtracting
This this Min X now, this Min y Max X thing, right?
We actually have to draw from the base up and Min and Max is kind of
an incorrect terminology now as well, because our coordinate system
that were actually outputting to still has why sort of going down on
the screen.
So we would actually have to pass the Min and Max backwards, right?
And I think it's see what's happening here.
So this basically would do the inversion if we wanted to flip things.
Side down, we could do that and it wouldn't be that hard for us to do.
So, let me just show you what that looks like if we just do that flip
right here.
So let's set the lower left like that.
And so the lower left X is still what it is, but the lower left Y is
actually now going to be instead of 0 it's going to be the height of
that buffer.
It's right.
It's going to be when the gain buffer comes in and tells us what the
entire screen is.
Want to start drawing it.
Basically, at that bottom corner, right?
And so that is this height parameter here, right?
And so that, that buffer that we get passed in in game update and
render basically, if you remember it takes this, well, that's good
sound samples, or is it this one time?
It takes this off-screen buffer, right?
And so what we want to do there is we want to say, okay that buffers
height is where we're going to start in the lower left corner, right?
Right, so, that's that.
So, that would be where we would start.
And then what we have to do is what's this?
Oh, I got convert that to float.
And then what we'd have to do is when we draw the player, we'd have to
repeat the same math.
We're now at the lower left corner, the X computation stays the same,
but the why computation is different.
We start at the lower left corner, we subtract however, far, we have
to go for each individual tile.
So, you know, if the tile by 5:00, we start, we're still exactly where
we are.
Then we go to
Excuse me, the relative, why?
And the tile relative?
Why for the guy now will also be based off that bottom corner, right?
And now our guy motion code is is busted, but in general, we should
still be able to see the game.
And so, as you can see here, like when I'm moving, I'm actually moving
backwards.
You can't see me pushing the wrong key, but now we flipped our tile
map upside down.
And so, why is now going up in our world instead of down, right?
And that's, you know, obviously pretty.
Forward.
There's really nothing else that has to happen in terms of handling
the world, because everything works upside down or right side up,
obviously, but you know, you get the idea.
So the only other thing we need to do now is fix the guy's movement
code, so that the guys movement code is not is going to be sending him
in the right direction.
So instead of using the negative version.
So right now I'm pushing down to move them up or it right.
Like I'm pushing the S key to move them upwards instead of that up in
our
Our guy movement code, wherever our guy movement code actually was.
Let's see here.
It's one of the things about not breaking things off into functions is
I can't use the Alt-J to jump to them.
I wish there was a jump to comment but unfortunately, there isn't.
Oh, the things that a good editor could do.
So anyway, inside our movement code here, right?
You'll notice that basically we have things inverted.
So ended down for move up and move down are inverted from what they
are here left and right.
It's - and
Positive but move up if - so what we'd want to do in our guy movement
code, right is we'd want to move him in the opposite way.
And then when we come here, now, he's moving correctly around the
screen, right?
And so now, I'm pushing s to go downwards and off we go.
So, I think that was the right order to do things then because that
was pretty simple to do.
And now we're in that order.
And now when we do our tile map stuff to that, we're going to do will,
or we'll just start out in the right coordinate system when we won't
have to rewrite everything.
Right?
So pretty straightforward.
Hopefully that made sense.
Sense, all right, so it flipped our world upside down.
But like I said, we don't care about that yet.
Basically.
All that means is when we write the code that does our world
generation.
We will just write it knowing that our coordinate system.
Has why going up?
And it will, you know, think about when it's putting a tile above
another tile, it will use plus 1 instead of negative 1 and we never
have to really make stuff in a ski.
So we don't really have to solve the problem that these come, that
these are backwards from how they appear on the screen.
That doesn't really, you know, there's nothing particularly special
about that.
So,
That seems like not really a big problem.
Okay.
So we're chopping through our to do is here.
That's good.
Why is going up whether or not?
These should be from the center of a tile is something we can deal
with a little bit later.
Certainly because it really doesn't have anything to do with anything
other than the player movement code.
So when we look at the player movement code, again, maybe we can talk
about that.
But basically what we need to do now is we need to start thinking
about this, right?
And so, here's what I want to do.
I've said it a couple times, but I think it keeps bearing repeating
because, again, it's kind of complicated.
It's a little bit of an advanced thing to some degree.
I'm just going to state
Thing one more time, just so we're all clear on what's going on.
Okay.
So what I want to State very clearly is we need a lot of precision as
to where people are in the world.
So if we were to use 32-bit floating Point values, right?
Which are, which are what we're calling.
We're calling those real 32s in the code, right?
And that's type Deft to be a float, a C++ float, right?
That gives us 24 bits of
Actual data.
Basically, there's an exponent there's a sign bit but we have 24 bits
of actual resolution.
Right?
Well what ends up happening there?
Is ice as I explained before.
I need at least eight bits of fractional, Precision per pixel, right?
So for each individual pixel, on the screen, I need eight bits that
say how far through that pixel you are basically.
And the reason for that is I want to support the full color.
Range of blending and colors are 8 Bits, at least, on most modern
displays.
So, when we output colors, we need to Output a level of color between
0 and 255.
And so, when we are alpha blending and we're talking about
Someone is this is a pixel right here, right now.
We're talking about where a shape passes through it.
I want to be able to talk about how much of the pixel is covered X and
Y wise, I want to be able to talk about that at 256 steps of
resolution, which is 8 Bits because that will make sure that I have
full color resolution to do like anti-aliasing and stuff like that.
So I need eight bits.
That immediately.
Chops us down to six bits of resolution on our, on our floating point
value, right?
16 16 bits of resolution is 65536 pixels, right?
Because this is fractions of a pixel is I took the 8 Bits for that.
So, we have 65,000 pixels, right of resolution, before I start to lose
resolution and I lose some of this.
I lose some bits here.
I lose bits.
In terms of my, of my rounding.
So if you imagine the guy starting out at 0-0 in the world, what I
want to talk about, I'm just a nice.
Like I said, I've said this again, but how far can he move from zero
zero along X or along y before I run out of this Precision.
Well, like I was saying before, we know that a screen on an HD display
is going to be like at least 1920 across in X, right?
And let's plays are getting even higher res than that.
So that's being generous.
We may want to run handmade Hero at a higher resolution at some
It than that.
So, 65536 / 1920.
You can see that basically, we have 34 screens that we can go in this
direction, right before we lose Precision.
So 34 screens in that direction.
We'd have 34 screens in this direction, which means the maximum span
of our game world would be 68 screens right at 68 screens.
I don't know.
How long does it take to walk across the screen.
I'm trying to imagine a game like, Legend of Zelda.
It only takes a couple of seconds.
Maybe let's say five seconds to walk across the screen, so I don't
know, just doing
A ballpark if the max I could have with 68 screens and I want to take
five seconds ago, across them.
How many minutes is that?
Well, it would take five minutes to walk from one end to the other.
Right?
That's not very long game.
Time.
6 minutes course, you'd have to clear out the monsters there.
I suppose, you know what I'm saying.
So, so we could we could consider just using 32-bit floating Point
values to store where we are in the world, right?
We could consider it.
It would be a game.
Limitation.
We could consider it.
I don't really want to consider it.
Because again, part of the reason.
For this is to sort of show programming techniques.
And so if we just slap some floats in there were sort of we're only
showing a technique that doesn't really scale very well.
So what I'm doing instead is I want to show a technique that will
scale to basically an arbitrary number of screens something that the
player could never walk across.
And so what I'm doing instead is I'm going to store what tile you're
on as an integer.
So I'm going to use a 32-bit integer to store what tile you're on,
right?
And then which is what we're doing right now.
We're using the
Alex.
Tell y.
Now we have a secondary layer here and that's the part.
I'm going to talk about in a second.
So we have 30 minutes to.
This is what tile you're on, write X and Y and of course, our wives
going up now, so I have to start drawing it that way.
Right.
So here's why here's X and there's the 00 tile, and then there's tiles
that go out.
And of course, there can be 4 billion tiles in any direction, right?
And then I'm going to use the 32-bit floating point value, right?
That 32-bit floating point value would just tell you where you are
inside a tile which basically gives me way.
Overkill resolution.
Now, we
We really only need, you know, an 8-bit or 16-bit value for that, but
there's no real benefit to it because storing 16 bits for something
versus storing 32 bits for something.
There's no way to really go in between those very efficiently.
You kind of have to pick one of the other.
So what I'm trying to do is I want to pick something.
We're essentially, I can take two things that are on the same screen,
change them into floating Point values that operate just only in the
screen space and then do everything in 32-bit float from then on.
But I want this 32-bit integer for the tile index.
I want to have that for storing, my canonical positions everywhere, so
that I can always talk about wherever you are relative to something
that keeps the Precision.
And so, what we'll do in general, I think is will take, like, sort of
the stuff that's on the screen, will map it all into the space of the
screen or something like that, you know, some around some Center tile,
right?
Well, map, everything into one set of floats for doing our
computations about like, you know,
Checking where people are relative to each other or that sort of
stuff.
We can do that mapping once and then do everything in 32-bit float.
So we don't have to use doubles or anything like that.
And we'll just have this sort of tile index as a thing that we
preserve when we're sort of talking about stuff in the permanent
storage.
So that we never have to worry about losing Precision.
When and we can make the world effectively, infinitely large like much
larger than a player could ever hope to walk across four billion
tiles, obviously.
With each tile being 60 pixels.
So four billion tiles.
I don't know how many we said was on a screen, but I think if there
was something like, you know, 16-bit, so be something like, it'd be
something like 200 million tiles across which is a pretty darn big
world for 200 million screens across which is pretty darn Big World.
All right, so that's basically what I wanted to do and that's why
we're using this system that has multiple things.
But if you notice the way we implemented it, currently we have a tile
Map X and Y, and a tile X and Y, and that gets kind of
Some what I'd rather be able to do is switch to a scheme.
That's a little more agnostic about that.
And also people were concerned about scrolling, they were saying they
didn't like the fact that we were going to use a fixed perspective on
things because they thought scrolling would be harder to program in
more interesting.
So I also am just for for educational purposes.
Also going to point out that we want to pick a scheme that would work
for scrolling as well.
So we're not trying to cheat here.
I'm going to write this thing as if you could scroll, anytime you
wanted to.
And then that way if we ever do find that we want to turn on scrolling
for some reason we can I just don't like scrolling from a gameplay
perspective that separate issue anyway, so what I'd like to do now is
what we were doing is we were thinking about tile Maps.
This is the screen right?
In fact, well, let's let's let me make that a little bit bigger.
This is the screen and what we were doing before.
As we were saying that a tile map is one screen Worth, right?
That's how we were drawing it.
And so then we had like a tile map for every screen and we index those
using this.
Then we talked about the tile on each individual tile map.
Once we, which is basically a screen, we used these to index into
those.
What I want to do now is switch to saying that the screen and the tile
maps are unrelated.
The screen is just a window into our four billion by four billion.
Tilemap.
So we have a giant tile map.
And the screen at any given time is just looking at some portion of
that world.
Right now.
We can't store a 4 billion by 4 billion.
Tilemap.
There's no way to store that, right.
We there's just it's not possible because if we were to actually store
that if you
At how big that would be.
So, we have a four billion, 10 2014, 12 4, Giga tiles.
It's really Giga tiles.
Right?
We have four billion even just a store for billion tiles, right?
Would be even his one byte per tile, which we're going to want to
store more than one byte per tile.
I strongly suspect right there.
That would be 4 GB, right?
Just four gigabytes, just for one row of tiles in our town map, but
now we would need four billion for
GB things to store our tiles, which is, there's no way that's not
impossible.
You can't even get a hard drive that we store that many right, let
alone in game memory for that many.
So what we want to do instead is we want to store this sparsely.
So, if you imagine are four billion by four billion, tilemap, here's
four billion by 4 billion and we imagine we create the world.
The world is only going to exist.
You know, our whatever our world is, it's only
Going to exist in some small kind of sparse set of things.
Right?
And so, the game doesn't need to store all of that empty space.
We just want to make sure that it could be as long as it wanted in a
direction and never doesn't have any constraints on that.
So we just want to make sure that we can store it all.
So what we're going to do is we're going to partition it into tiles
like our tile map system from before, but instead of making them
screens.
They're just going to be arbitrary chunks.
That are however big it happens to be for efficiency, right?
And then we're only going to store the chunks that happen to be where
there are things in the world.
So if there isn't anything, we don't store a chump.
Look, we don't store chunks out here, but where there are things we
store chunks, right?
So our chunks can be whatever we want.
Let's say they'd be 128 by 128 tiles or something or 256 by 256 tiles.
And that would basically be based on how much sparseness we want to
exploit the bigger the tile size, the less sparseness we can exploit
because you're starting to get
Into things where you know, you kind of maybe are too big for the
thing, you're trying to represent.
So if a screen is, you know, I forget what we said 17 by 9 is that we
said 70 by 9.
So the screen is 17 by 9, right?
Then if we make something that was like 64 by 64, that might be a good
fit for something, right, but if we start to get up to too high, we
might be losing some sparseness.
So it depends on how much we want to do.
And if we look at the calc for that, right?
If we look at what 256 x, 256 is that
64k 41, B /.
And let's say, we were storing something a little more aggressive.
Like, maybe we're storing instead of one byte per.
Maybe we're storing 128, bytes per that would still be pretty large.
That'd be like, eight megabytes for one of these tile chunks, right?
And so, like I said, I don't know how big we want those to be exactly
but we, you know, that's a parameter we can do.
So we could start out by doing them to 156.
That would be 24.8 as our format for our 32-bit integer where
basically the lower,
It's of the index into the tile map would tell you which of the tiles
you were here and the upper 24 would tell you which of these chunks
you were right.
So to be more explicit about that, essentially what we have is a
virtual addressing scheme here, right?
We've got our y position of a tile in our exposition of a tile and
they're just 32-bit numbers, but instead of accessing the like 32-bit
numbers, we can have the value for x and y, in half and the lower
part, however, many bits, we decide if it was 256 by 256, to be eight
bits on the lower.
Part, however, much that lower part is tells us where in the Chunk we
are, which tile which in the to G6, Like a G6, would mean there's 26
tiles across two interfaces tells down in each chunk, which of those
tiles were in a particular chunk and the upper 24s.
So, we have an eight.
We have an 8-bit comma 8 B, which is a 256 by 256 tile map for each
chunk.
And then we have a 224 comma 24-bit value, that would tell us, which
of these were in.
And we know that we only store some of these, right?
So this would
Would be a sparse look up into our tile Universe, right?
So that's what we want to do.
Here for the screen.
The screen.
We'll just remember, for example, it could be whatever its Center tile
is we could say, the screen is looking at this Tile Center tile and
then it's got some offset from that Center tile.
That's looking at.
And then when it does is it will ask this guy to please give it
whatever the tile maps are that overlap it.
So maybe we're looking at a tile boundary here.
So this is one tile, this is one chunk.
This is one chunk this winter.
Unk this one chunk and so creating a screen will basically be about
drawing up to four of these tilemap sections sections of the tile map
chunks right to fill in the whole screen.
So this might be a this might be b c and d and up here, right?
That would be a b c and d and this is essentially the screen mapping
to that area, right?
That region of the of the tile map sections.
So, that is what we are trying to accomplish.
Now, is moving to this.
This thing where the screen is just a query into our tile maps, and we
get out the tile maps that we wanted, and we draw whatever portion
them happen to overlap the screen, right?
And again, it should be immediately.
Obvious.
How you can now, do smooth scrolling if you wanted to, with this
system.
Of course, you could have done it with the other system as well.
But you know, this support smooth scrolling exactly.
Like as far as regular schooling because you can query any region and
get out what it should be.
So if you want to move smoothly along it, you could.
Or if you
Want to just do a fixed position like I'm going to do, you can do that
as well.
Right?
Alright.
So in order to do that, what we now need to do is we need to switch to
using just one tile X and tile.
Why?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and change our world
positions to be that.
Now, I've put an underscore in front of them, so I can see everywhere
they're used.
And that way, I can go look at all the code that's using it and fix
it.
So, for Rican, analyzed canonicalizing, coordinates, we
No longer have to worry about the tile Map X and Y.
And we also don't have to worry too much about the world context or
the world can't lie, what we really need.
Well, we'll need a different value that we'll talk about in a second,
but we so we can get rid of those for now.
So what we have here is we're just going to for Rican, alkalizing
coordinates.
We're just going to pass those in.
And when we re canonicalize the coordinates, we now just have the tile
value and the relative value, right?
And we still do all the
The same stuff.
But when we get in here, when we do these adjustments, that we were
doing for the tile map, we can just get rid of them.
Right?
We no longer have to worry about what towel mapper in because that's
just baked into the value.
Right?
And furthermore.
This value is actually now, effectively, a un 32.
I'm probably, I don't know if I'm gonna it's a little bit tricky,
right?
Because basically we haven't 32 here and we need to then subtract or
add from this value.
So I don't know if it makes sense to start calling this.
A you in 32 or not.
We're still going to have to deal with the negatives here.
So it doesn't really matter.
So what we could do is say that the center tile of the world is 00 and
things.
Go out to negative 2 billion, positive, 2 billion.
I don't know if there's any real reason to care one way or the other
about that, but I think what I'd rather do is say we never have
negative numbers just to make maybe things a little bit easier.
I'm parts.
So I want to say that that's just a Unit 32, right?
And the UN 32, then can be subtracted or added from by the offset that
we compute.
But we want to basically assert that it never goes - and so basically,
what we want to do is before we do this, we want to assert
essentially, that whatever, whatever whatever we would have been doing
to our number.
It's not going to be any
It's not going to cause it to underflow.
Right?
So basically the assertion here is that the tile, sorry, the tile
position that we have is going to be greater than the offset is, and
it's assigned unsigned comparison.
So basically, like I just want to, how should I do this?
What's the easy way to do is I want to say, like, basically the
absolute value, right?
I want to say that the absolute value of this offset.
So, I'll just going to say absolute.
In 32.
Our sorry, absolute Infinity to 2 Union, 32, something like this where
I can basically say whatever this is.
I want to make sure that in the case where it is - I want to make sure
that this value is always greater than it.
So basically it would be assumed that offset is either greater than 0
in which case we can add it if offsets greater than 0.
Just yeah.
I just I almost just want to do this in debug code.
So, what's our debug code?
We have it here.
Let's see.
It's called handmade slow.
I believe.
Yeah, there we go.
So, if we're in handmade slow, then I'm just going to write this out
explicitly, because it was getting too hard to pack into a search in
there.
So what I want to do is I want to say if the offset is greater than 0,
right?
And then if the offset is less than 0 will do something else or if
it's zero.
What I want to do is say if the offset was less than zero, then I want
to basically assert here.
That the tile.
Is less than the negative offset, right?
I'm sorry.
Greater than the negative offset.
So, basically, if this value well as well, it can be greater than
equal to.
You could move right to the 0th tile if you wanted to.
So basically if this was like 5 and negative off and offset was
negative 6, right.
I really don't want you to ever do that because you'll wrap around and
go back to the other side of the tile map.
Now we could argue.
I mean, I guess the other thing I could do is just allow that I
suppose there's no harm.
Our minute, we could say that our worlds toroidal.
I guess now that I think about it.
Do I really care?
Right?
Maybe I'll just say that the world's toroidal and then we don't care.
If you walk off one of the world you walk it back on the other side.
I mean we're saying you can't get to the end of the world anyway, so I
guess I could just say that that was true so I could just say
World is assumed to be toroidal.
If you step off one end.
You come back on the other.
I guess, let's just say that's true.
And then that's it.
And so what for those of you don't know what I mean, when I say to
Royal basically, there's a concept called topology, a branch of
mathematics and so on, which honestly I'm not an expert in.
So if you want to know more about it, you really got to
Some better sources, but basically, there's the there's the sort of
concepts of how things are connected house, faces are connected.
And so what I was thinking about original originally would be called
disk topology, which is basically to say that essentially my my world
was was sort of they call it homeomorphic.
Usually was basically or isomorphic to to a disk.
So basically what that means is where
Ever, I could go right.
I've got a guy and he's walking around on the surface of this world
that I've created wherever he would walk, right?
The rules are the same as if I was just on some kind of a flat disk,
right?
It is no difference between these two.
I could warp this one into this one and the connectivity is the same.
Another way of thinking about it is if I had a tail, if I had a, if I
had a tail that was pinned.
The center, right?
And I started walking around the tail would loop around the exact same
way on a disk.
As it would on me.
There's no sort of fanciness that you could play.
But toroidal topology means that my world is actually homeomorphic to
a Taurus.
Now, I know that sounds a little weird, but basically if you've ever
seen a tourist before, this is going to be kind of a trick to draw,
but it's basically a donut, right?
It's basically a thing that looks
Kind of like this sort of a thing right?
Where it's got a hole in it and and sort of it's got rings around it.
Right?
Like the sort of thing, you know, I'm saying?
And so you kind of go along the edge, right?
Like a life preserver that sort of thing.
Right?
So if the world is home you over to a tourist, if you think about what
a Taurus looks like, it means that in either axis, you can walk along
and just keep walking, you can just Loop and loop and loop, which
means if I walk off one end.
I walked back onto the other, right?
And if you think about this, this tourist, you could cut it.
You could cut it along the seam and then cut it along.
This seam.
I could I could pick two seams and cut it and unwrap it into my world.
Right?
This right here.
Is this seem right?
And this right here is this seam, and you can see how I could bend
that back into my, my, my Taurus and the rules.
Here are the same as on the tourist.
If I walk along it, right?
And I can walk like this pattern on it.
The same is true on the torus, right?
It just it loops around the torus as it goes around right?
And so when I say toroidal topology, what that means is that I've got
a world that's actually a Taurus.
Now, even
It's not shaped like that in terms of its physical form.
It's behaving as if it were on the surface of a torus knot on the
surface of a plate or a disc, right?
And so, so this is toroidal topology.
That's what that is.
Yeah, if you're into topology and want to read more about it, I don't
know what to recommend.
Maybe everyone has a tail.
Let me see.
Everyone has a tail kouga.
So let's see.
That's what's called, gal was dream.
That's what it's called.
Most books aren't kept topology are very hard to read.
This one is not perfect.
But it would, it would probably be the best one to start with.
I don't know, maybe topologies hard to kind of get into but, but
Galvez dream is
Pretty good, and maybe people on the forums, could recommend something
some other things as well.
But that's something, you know, if you're into apologies.
There's a lot of other things.
Yeah.
To think about anyway, so I'm going to go ahead and say that and that
way we don't even have.
Problem there, we can just go ahead and wrap, we don't have to assert.
If you walk off when you walk on the other.
Everyone's happy.
No real problems.
I think this will do the addition properly with the signed edition,
but we'll have to check to make sure that's true.
Although it shouldn't be too hard to verify that's working.
We then don't have to check that at all.
It's an unsigned integer.
We don't have to care.
Oh, wait, that's the towel relative thing.
So we have to check that at all.
Are we not checking to see whether tile relative is greater than or
equal to 0, and I must have deleted that by accident.
So we'll put that back in and we'll save that.
Alright, so there we go.
We also need.
So that's all we really need to do for that because it's just, that's
a standard adjustment tile X is not a member of world position, right?
So that's that's fine because I just changed what it was meaning
there.
Okay.
So let's move on to here.
It's World Point empty.
I passed the canonical position.
We no longer have to do this.
Get tilemap thing exactly this way.
Really, what we would do here.
So as World Point empty, what we want to do is we're still I guess we
could still call get tile map and we just call tile X and Tau Y and
that will get us back the tile map for that tile location.
And then when we do is tell my point empty, we would pass the tile map
and we pass those.
Okay.
So so if you look at what has to happen here, this is basically going
to be our query into
Ooh, the tile system to get the chunk that we're on, and then we're
going to have to query inside the chunk.
And so, what we want to do is we want to have basically a mapped
result.
So we have these World positions that we're going to use and then
we're going to kind of introduce a lower-level thing.
And this will never.
I think the exposed.
Well, yeah might be basically what we're going to have to do is have
our tile chunk position, right?
Which is actually going to be something that's a little more explicit.
And this would basically be like,
Sort of a tile map.
This this would have our town map X and our tile map Y in it which
are, which are essentially chunk.
So I'm going to maybe start to call them not maps anymore because
tilemap kind of sounds like something that you authored and that's not
the case and then the tile X and the tile why inside that chunk,
right?
So are basically moving that stuff that we have in here into a
transient variable transient struct, which is only used during the
accessing.
Right?
And so what we would do is we'd essentially have a simple function
Ocean that's going to be trivial to implement.
It's just like a shift in an ad and kind of a thing where we do, you
know where we do kind of a get chunk position for a canonical, right?
We get that back.
We have our chunk pose.
Right?
And then we just say we can get the tile map for a chunk pose.
And this will basically a tell chunk.
Now we can get back at I'll chunk.
And then we can also ask for on a particular one.
Whether the chunk pose is
You're not right?
So we can say, for the time after we got back.
Does this tile X and tile y and
This is a, this is inside the tower.
Now.
These are going to be named the same thing.
So this is a real tile X I guess.
And this is kind of we've got, we've got Shunk relative X and chunk
relative, why?
So it's kind of hard with these sorts of things.
But like I said, this is going to be kind of buried, so that's okay.
Nobody in the interface now has to think about those anymore.
So they can kind of think about absolute tile X.
Absolute Taiwan.
We could call these app style except style.
Why.
If we wanted to, in fact, maybe that's
Maybe that's a good thing and then we can have real tile ex Rel tile.
Why.
And then these right here, could be, maybe I might change these to be
calling these offsets as well.
Like offset X offset y, well, to think about that.
Okay.
So again, we're just moving down the stuff that we had here.
We're moving it down into another layer, that kind of will always do
it.
So we don't have to track those.
We're just everyone who actually uses positions will only know about
their absolute tile X and Y and then we'll only compute those relative
ones on the Fly and the computation will set up to be basically free,
so that it just really doesn't cost anything to actually do it.
So, we'll have this get chunk pose.
Right?
And our internal get chunk post here again.
This will probably this one actually death.
I think we'd want it, make it in line because it'll be so easy.
This will be a touch of position.
Sorry.
This will be a world position that it passes in, right, that world
position.
Choose me.
Basically, we're going to use the ABS tile X and the ABS tile why?
And in fact, you know what, we could just do, we don't really need the
Rolex in The Relic.
Well here, so this could just take the X and the Y so that even people
who don't aren't using anything particular can look it up.
Generically, we could basically say, okay.
Get the the trunk position for these two things, right?
So there's AB cell extract, those tab style.
Why, right?
So basically these to come in and all we need to do now is make a tile
chunk position and that tile chunk position is going to have which
tile chunk X and Y, you're in and, and where you are relative to that
one right rail tile ex Rel tile, why, right?
And then I said before, basically that what we want to do is we want
to basically Define our tile map.
I should
We passed the world here so that we can have worlds or dynamic size as
we may want to fix this so that the math can be computed at compile
time.
But for now, we'll do it in a dynamically.
Right.
What I want to say here.
Is this enough?
The tile chunk X is going to use the app style, X shifted down by
however, many the Fret.
However, what that, whatever the fractional bit count is, right?
So there's going to be essentially a chunk shift value, right?
So, ABS Telex gets shifted down by that Apatow.
Why also?
And so, all that's doing right.
Remember I said, I want to store it, something like this.
So there's going to be fractional.
This is a 32-bit value here, right?
There's gonna be fractional B, maybe there's eight of them may be so
two days by 2 is trunks.
I don't know.
We'll start with that and 24 bits here.
All I want to do for the chunk index.
The chunk index is just I'm shifting that down.
So I'm getting rid of this.
I'm shifting down the 24, so we just have the 24.
So we're basically looking at our new value is going to be 24, bits
and 80's at the top and 24 bits of actual value here, right?
So we do those two shifts down.
We might do something different here in the long run and just compute
like a hash value directly for how to look up the town map.
But that's going to be down when we actually start implementing the
engine.
All right, so we got real tile X and real tile.
Why those are now going to be the exact same thing?
In Reverse.
We're going to end with a chunk mask, right?
Like this.
And the chunk mask is, just the thing that will that will mask it out.
Now, if the chunk, if the shift down is 8, then if you think about it,
if we actually wanted to, we could probably do something that compute.
Well, let's just, we're just gonna Store The Mask.
There's no point in making getting things fancier.
Alright.
So basically the chunk mask is going to be all ones down here and all
zeros up here.
So that we and with it, we get rid of that 24 part.
We get rid of it's gone.
So we're just left with an 8-bit value.
You know, that would say what the relative Telex is.
And that's it.
That's the entirety of what we need to do there.
So in the world, we now have these two values, right?
We have a chunk shift and we have a chunk mask and those two I'm going
to set them at the moment to basically be to basically be the two
values that I that I said before.
I'm going to say that we have a chunk shift and a chunk mask.
The chunk Mast is going to be, I'm going to assume that it's 8 Bits
for now.
So we shift down my 8 and we mask out by f f so that we basically are
using 24.2., No note.
Casey.
This is set to using 256 by 256 tile chunks, right?
So, there we go.
So that's that.
Excuse me.
And then we have to go ahead and say in actually use this.
We do the get trunk forward, get tile map.
That will have to now take those and is tilemap point empty.
I think for the most part, this stuff just works.
I think these will just work the same as they used to count X and
count.
Why will now be set to 256 by 256?
And furthermore.
They will basically be only, they'll be only one.
So they'll be a word.
Old basically, chunk dim will call it.
Let's say we're a chunk.
Tim will basically be 256 across.
So now we'll just switch to using chunk.
Tim instead of count.txt come by so chunk them, jump down that and off
we go.
Wow, only 15 minutes left in the Stream.
We are not going to finish this today.
Unfortunately, that's unfortunate.
Good stretch.
Haven't got the neck worked out today yet.
All right.
Chunk Tim is not.
That's right.
It's true chunk.
Damn.
There we go.
We got all those and let's see.
So test ilex test tile.
Why we could those are never allowed to be negative.
So we could just make them always be positive, which I think is
probably what we want to do in here as well.
So we'll just say that these always have to be there.
We don't have to check against that.
In fact, these are
To do lookups into the chunk map and style all tiles are valid.
So we don't even need this check anymore.
We can just say that all of these are unchecked basically because
there really isn't any way to do them.
Otherwise, so basically, yeah, basically all we need to do is check to
see if the tile map is valid at the town.
Map is valid.
Basically everything should work from there on.
It's only assertions because there's never going to be a way to look
up something else.
So wait, where's my empty?
Betel nut values that.
Okay, so get Tau value and checked that's going to pass the tile map
tile test, textile test why I like that and that will basically do a
check here.
These are all un so they don't have to check against zero, but they do
have to check these.
Let's go ahead and put leave those assertions in there to make sure
that we're never outside the chunk Tim, right?
So they have to be below that.
And then we will just go ahead and and and dupes.
Type countdown.
Not right?
Tim.
Come on Tim.
And that is that I think, right.
Let's take a look here.
Tell really like these should be ABS.
Tie Labs tile and Chuck position for function needs to take the world.
Certainly get tile map tile, chunk.
Of course, we now have tile chunk, which is exactly the same as our
tiles from before, and then we still have our town Maps array, and
then we need to do our sparseness that to do is still valid.
We get rid of these.
Is got these, here we go.
These are going to, this is going to go away.
In fact, it already could, I think this is going to be something that
we can just just put in here.
So lower left X.
That could just be here.
Okay, and where are we at?
Tile chunk and this is really good tile chunk now.
So these are actually map is really chunk and all of these places.
Yeah, Mariah, and so these for now we're also basically saying that
these lookups yeah, this is kind of a meaningless check as well.
But we'll kind of get what one thing at a time.
We've got to actually sort of get things into roughly workable shape.
Before we talk about how we're actually cause right now, I haven't
talked about how we're actually do the sparse look up.
And in some sense, we don't even want to do this for us.
Look up yet.
That's an engine thing.
So we want to do a speck at all to work properly and then move it off
into a file that will basically say when we start doing the engine.
This is one thing we have to do.
Right?
But we don't need to worry about are about that yet because we can
just do a dense look up for our testing purposes.
And not have to worry about it.
Okay.
So tile chunk.
There we go.
Tile chunk value.
And let's see.
Yeah, there we go.
So those chunks same here.
Let's just do map to chunk.
There we go.
And we don't really want that.
It shouldn't be, is Taichung Point empty.
It's just is tile.
Empty, right?
How did we do?
Did we, what do we do?
We call that from is World Point empty.
So this is just is tile empty and I guess this one is.
Yeah.
It's tile, chunk Point empty.
I guess that's actually true.
So is tile trunk tile.
Empty is probably the correct thing because it's not testing a point
anymore.
It's just testing a tile to see if it's empty.
It doesn't even get
Information.
All right, get jump is good for can pose ABS tile X.
Can pose ABS tile.
Why?
There we go, and let's see.
The chunk pose tile X of Tau y, or is it?
What is it called?
It's like tile relative ex Rel.
Tilak's.
Yeah, you have a bit of a naming problem.
I we'd have to think of your nice think a better names for a couple of
these things because there's like, which relative or Utah.
Talking about relative to what and you don't want things to get too
verbose.
And yeah, it's always a bit of a struggle to name things properly.
Alright, so now we have a problem, which is that we have to actually
do something, which, you know, which actually has one of these.
We're basically saying it's 256 by 256.
So that makes it a little bit harder on us, of course, what we could
do and is what I'm going to propose, we do is just weld these together
for now and just have one that we can store.
That's a 256 by 256.
Ur.
So here we go.
I'm going to just go ahead and do that.
So this
oh boy.
Oh boy.
I don't know.
This is a bad idea.
I'm sure this is a bad idea.
Probably shouldn't shouldn't do this.
I really want to though.
All right, let's take a look.
Let's see what happens.
If I do it.
You ready for this?
This is just stupid and I apologize ahead of time for what's about to
happen.
It probably won't work, but I'm going to try it.
Anyway, here we go.
Record keyboard macro comma, space space.
Alt w.
Control space End of Line.
Back up.
Delete, go back down to the next one.
Come here.
Paste it.
Down to the previous row, previous there.
There we go and recording doot.
Doot, doot, doot do do doot.
Do 222-2222.
There we go, emacs keyboard macros, ladies and gentlemen, to the
rescue.
We have now welded ourselves into a single tile.
It is not to be 6 by 256, but see will explore fill in zeros there for
the rest of them for us.
So we just have a thing called tiles now, which is 256 by 256 least, I
think see will fill in the rest of them for us.
Will it or will it complain?
It didn't complain.
So basically, we now have our world and the world is essentially just
He has one tile set in it.
That's 56 at the moment and we're going to have to just start with
that and we'll have to fill it in a little.
We can we can make it bigger later anyway, so then we have tile chunks
is going to equal our tile chunk here, which is this guy tile chunk.
There we go.
And so yeah.
Yeah, you get the idea and so
Do tile chunk count, X and Y.
We only have one now.
So there we go.
World tile chunks.
What is the problem of cannot convert between?
Oh, yeah, you're right.
That's, that's not what I meant to do at all, is it?
That's a bad idea.
So, basically tile Chunk, we can actually say this is a tile.
Well, no, we can't really.
So we'll say tile.
This is, this is our actual tiles, temp tiles.
Essentially, so we'll just say here.
We have to define a fake tile chunk tile chunk.
We're going to point that at this and tile chunk tiles equals our temp
tiles and that should be better.
What is what are you complaining about?
Right?
You at 30s are going to cast that because it's a two-dimensional
array, which doesn't like alright, so we got that out of the way
already Tom a pecs Tom at the Y.
So this
Now they're just on tile 33.
They don't need to know that anymore.
So we basically just have that.
We've got the tile map that we're on is just going to be.
Yeah, to get the tile map for the particular player.
So we can do that the way we're doing here and we're going to, where
do we actually use that tile map, though.
We don't use it till till down there.
So really let's go ahead and make this super piggy for now.
Maybe, I don't know if I should put the pig hat on.
It's possible that the pig at should go on for this, but let's take a
look.
So, really the only thing
I have to do now is update our drawing code, right?
Because I drawing code is wrong.
And so our drawing code has to be able to draw a tile map.
So what I could do is just literally do get tile function.
If I'm going to put the the hats going on because this is super piggy
right now, what's happening?
This is going to be super inefficient, but it's probably the right way
to go, just to test the things are working as we go forwards.
So I'm going to make a function here like is World Point empty, right?
I'm going to
Actually make a thing that just gets the tile value, right?
And so I'm going to do something.
That's essentially.
I'm going to change.
This is, I guess what I'm saying.
I'm going to change this to something, that's like you and three to
get tile value right from a can post.
It'll do this, do this.
And then instead of is child tongue is tile, chunk tile empty this guy
right here.
Instead of that.
I'm going to change this function around to basically be get tile
value, right?
It's
To be this it's going to be debt tile value and it's the the checked
version.
Right?
And so instead of having the empty here.
We're going to move the empty down.
We're going to say, okay, we've got the tile chunk value will assume
the top tank value is 0.
If we couldn't find anything there.
We will return that the actual value.
And then, we'll make this guy Israel Point empty.
He's actually going to do that empty check.
So what he'll do is so basically say that this is
Is the value their right?
Empty equals that.
And so he'll say tile chunk value equals get tile tile, chunk value.
Here we go.
Well until that so he'll pass those kill, get the Top Value.
He'll do the check to it's empty and that way, I can now have a thing,
but does get tell value with a Campos and that Campos will then pass
it directly back to the user right tile chunk value and and similarly.
I guess we can just reuse this now.
So basically this this can just be called in here directly.
So I don't have to have two of those so we can just go ahead and
collapse that down, right?
Like that.
At.
So, what we can do now is we can just say, all right.
Well, we're we want to view on the screen.
We basically want to view.
In fact, we could even say
Be one of you wherever the player is at is at the center or something
like this.
Yeah, I don't know exactly how we want to save that.
But basically if I just draw the, the 9 by 17, what I could do is just
say get tile value and when I call get Tau value, I just pass it.
The row in the column for the absolute ones and I don't have to pass
tilemap at all anymore.
And that would give me exactly the value.
I don't, we don't have
Yet where in the world were looking at?
And so that's the thing we'll have to do tomorrow, but get tile value.
What does get Tau value?
Take get tell value, takes a can pose.
So what I'd like to do here is make it so it doesn't actually need a
can pose as well.
I've liked this guy to just take a nap style X AB style.
Why?
For now?
Of course, we might want one that actually takes Campos as well.
AB style X can put those abs tile.
Why?
And we may want to yeah, we met in want to change some of those things
and so on.
But for now, there we go.
Up Q&A.
Yeah.
Not enough time in the day sometimes people.
All right.
Anyway, what we're checking with here is these and that's fine.
We've got a few more things to do signed unsigned smash as well.
There we go, lower left X lower left.
Why?
Yes, they are.
Not a member of the world.
That is true.
They are now just members of this routine because they don't actually
have any meaning anymore in the actual larger sense of the of the
world.
So there we go and this stuff all now needs to get redone tomorrow to
to allow us to do other supplement.
Want to do, that is not good.
That does not look like what I want to look like a tall.
People.
We've got a bug, do Ida bug it.
Now.
I kind of want to debug it now.
We made so many code changes.
I just want to
This is the problem with limited times on the stream.
I'm going to give myself, like, like till 11:05.
Let's say, because I want to take a look at this.
All right.
So so when we are drawing, we are going through here.
We're saying get tile value for a column and a row, and that is going
to go ahead and go up into the get Top Value call, right?
It's going to be looping from 0 to 7.
18, the get Top Value call will go ahead and say let's Hoops.
That's that's not it.
It's this one, get Tau value for call.
It will say let me get the chunk position for those to let me get back
the tile chunk for the Rel 0.
Nope, that's wrong.
That's totally not right.
Get tile Chunk.
We are supposed to look up the tile chunk X and the tile chunk.
Y/x tile jump.
Why?
Right, so it's look up the top.
X the tower chunk Y which we do.
We'll get back at uh, chunk.
Look up the relative tile X and low to try y to get the actual Tau
value.
And that's good.
So that was the bug, which is now thankfully gone.
When we actually do our ketchup position for, we shift down by
whatever the shift is to get our chunk X and Y and we mask out to get
our relatives when I go, I want to step through all this to make sure
it's all working properly, obviously, because there's so many changes
that we made here and on the stream.
I tend to make, like I said, I make sort of typos a lot that you don't
want to make.
So anyway, let's take a look.
We can look at that, uh, chunks.
Because World touch is blah, blah, blah.
That seems those should always be 0.
All right, so let's just see if that one bug, was it?
And then I could.
Yeah, so there we go.
Alright.
So now we're in.
Good shape.
We got all that stuff working again, but we do have a problem, which
is now we don't have a notion of moving from one screen to another at
the moment.
So, like when for example, the player goes off, they're just off and
they're still drawing up there, but they're they're we're not telling
the screen to move to follow the
Player.
Now we could try to do something.
You know, where we, where we actually do, do that.
Unfortunately, right now.
Well, you know, I mean, I guess we could even, we could, I guess in
theory just do something just to test it.
We could do something where we said that, the actual thing that we
want, the actual values that we want to check, you know, something
like
I'm just going to do it.
So we could say is we could just take wherever the player is, right,
we could say wherever the player is minus 10, or whatever, Rose in
that direction and then plus 10 in this direction or something like
that.
Right?
We could say that.
And and then we could say, oops.
This should be why because that's the row and then you know, whatever
and we're drawing more than we need to hear but whatever.
And so we could go ahead and say say that.
And then instead of using just the row and column here, we would use
whatever the offset is of from, from the players location.
So we basically say, you know, Rel column equals column, wherever
whatever the column is - the players location game State player P dot
ABS tile X and similarly
Ali railro Stripes, right Row, game stay tab style.
Well, I like that and then do this.
I kind of slammed that in there.
It's probably wrong, but you get the idea.
These are supposed to be reals everywhere.
Convert them up.
Oh, my, that was not good.
What did I do?
I don't know what I did wrong there.
These will course wrap around, but I thought we handled wrapping.
So I don't know that that's necessarily a problem.
Oh my God, and I'm at the time I said I was going to be, I just wanted
to put something in here to see if we could do kind of trivial
scrolling.
You know what I'm saying, you know what I'm saying?
But, I didn't do a very good job of throwing in Trivial scrolling.
Apparently.
Wait, what is?
So it's not actually drawing anything Rose.
Oh, right, when it wraps, it won't be less than.
Oh.
Yeah.
Well, you know, we could do this, we could do it this, I suppose.
Right.
Do something something a little fancier.
So what basically what's happening there is that it would just stop
immediately because of course, when it wraps around to because it was
a, you know, when railroad when the player is here and you're
subtracting from it, you end up with a really huge number.
And so, of course, it was failing.
The check the first time through the loop.
Sorry.
I'm I should have explained all that in detail, but we're right at the
end.
We could do it in the Q&A.
If people want me to explain it in detail, what was going on there.
We could restore the code.
I just, I just wanted to see if we
It's just kind of I wanted to move the map around a little bit before
I ended the stream.
Anyway, so we are going in here and these are the Rel.
These are now Rel column and Rel Rel row, right?
And so what we actually need to do when we look it up in here is we
need to compute, the actual column and row, right?
So we need to actually do these two.
And again, this is all just total nonsense code.
So it'd be it'd be
Be it be done like this.
Basically absolutes, AB style+ that rail ABS tile, X, plus the rail.
Column we go.
I think that might be more correct.
Well, it's not quite right, not quite right almost there, almost there
sometimes.
Sorry.
I'm fixated on this.
I know I'm supposed to end the stream just fixated on this.
I just wanted to just test the scrolling.
You're never, I really shouldn't throw things in like this, because I
don't have time to actually write them properly, obviously, but I just
kind of wanted to to try it.
And so if we were to draw the map this way, then where would the
player be the player would I guess be at the same we could get rid of
this law.
Lower left and this thing entirely, right?
We could just do it that way.
And so basically, if the player was drawn to the center, we would need
to add.
Offset for the center of the screen, right?
So we basically need we would need a center.
How is this working before?
Yeah, so we would need, we would need a center.
Why the screen and a center X for the screen, right?
And then the player would just be drawn.
Would we would delete all of this stuff?
Right?
The player would just be drawn at the center of the screen roughly.
He would never have that offset.
It would just have the world M, the regular World M offset that he
normally had.
Yeah, so that would basically it and then Center X and Center.
Why?
Would be equal to I again, apologize for fixating on this.
I just really, really wanted to see if I could make the screen scroll.
Sometimes, you know, you get into that and I will explain all this
tomorrow or in the Q&A.
So, I don't mean to leave everyone in the Lurch there.
I just really wanted to see if I could get it working.
So close, so close.
So you can see, it's sort of working.
Now, in the sense that my, my player is not quite drawn, right?
So he just needs, he needs that Center X, the center y offset as well,
which I forgot.
Of course, Center X Center.
Why?
There we go.
All right.
So now this guy is like the worlds.
That's kind of odd.
One more bug.
There we go.
Yeah.
All right now.
I think we're good.
Do you do?
Okay.
So now our guy is actually properly walking around on the map and of
course, we are not actually bothering to smooth.
Scroll, anything.
We could smooth scroll, pretty trivial at this point, but I just
wanted to verify that we were fetching into the tile Maps correctly
now, which we are and I just didn't feel like we could quite do that
without something that actually allowed us to see more of the tile
map.
And so now we can see the rest of the Tama.
Okay.
All right, pick hat off.
For that diversion.
I just really wanted to slam in something that would allow me to view
the whole map, which we can now do.
Okay.
All right.
Sorry, I went crazy there.
I just really want to get that in there.
Okay, now now we can go to the Q&A.
Please prefix your questions with Q: so that we can
See them on the stream and please try to keep your questions to the
code that we've written today or that we wrote in previous day's so we
can stay on topic.
If you want to ask an off topic question.
You can always come 15 minutes before the stream schedule to start and
ask if there.
We always filled any random questions no matter what their about on
the free stream.
All right, see if we got any, Q&A is
How about chunk chunk mask equals chunk?
Chef - yeah, so that is a pretty good idea.
Let me show you what someone was suggesting there.
Let me close that down.
Let me show you what son was suggesting basically to avoid typing the
same constant in twice.
So choose me.
What I was saying before, and I kind of explain this this part in
detail, right?
Is that what we need to do?
Is we have a thing, that's 24 bits in 8 Bits, and we're using them
separately.
We're using this part to access the chunk.
We're using this part to access tiles are going to chunk.
So we need to extract the to.
So if I say what I want to do to get the to get this value down,
right?
I need to shift it down by eight, to put it into the bottom part.
So that's how I access it, but then I need a mask, too.
At this part out to get rid of this part.
So what we want to do is we want to produce a mask that works the same
as a shift down by eight in Reverse.
Right?
So what we want to do is say okay, something that's going to shift
down by eight is going to move the 24 into here, right?
We want the symmetric operation, which is something that masks out the
the 24 and just leaves the eight.
Can we do that using just this value?
And the answer is we can because if you think about what happens,
It's kind of at this is just one of those binary tricks.
Basically, if we were to use the shift in, reverse on one, right?
So let's say we put a 1 in here and we use the reverse ship.
So instead of 8 we shifted down by 8.
We shift up by 8, that would move the one into this location, right?
So, it would essentially create the value 256, for what we have now,
right?
It would create 256 one shifted up by is 256, right?
So that's that would create 56 if we then subtract 1 from it.
So we just say, we shift it up, we subtract we shift one up by
whatever the shift value is.
We've tracked, one for it that will basically all of these are zero
right in here right now at 00:00, right?
It's like it's eight zeros and a one on the 9th bit, right?
To me if we subtract one from it, it will carry through and set all of
these to one until it gets to the one, which will set to 0.
And that is exactly the mask that we actually wanted, right?
We wanted all of those.
And so, if you think about what happens here in our in our actual
code, right?
So we look at what we have.
We have our, our world chunk shift, and our world chunk mask.
Oops, typing typing skills, right?
You can see that we want 8 and 255, right?
Because that is basically, the eighth is a shift and the FF is the
mask that we would use, right?
You can see if we and with
We would knock out all of the things up here and only leave the bottom
eight, which is what we wanted.
So if we wanted to do, if we wanted to produce this value, from that
value again, what the what the commenter was suggesting is we could
say instead that the chunk mask, right equals one shifted up by the
shift amount, right?
And then we just go ahead and subtract one from that value.
Right?
So we do 1, minus that value and that should give us that same mass
that we wanted, right?
And you can see that happen.
Now, if, when we step into the butter, so we have the chunk mask, it
becomes 256.
Like I said, right?
See because we shift up that one and we shift it just out of the area
that we were in.
We then subtract 1 and that borrows all the things over.
Oh, except.
I typed it wrong.
That's one - junk mask.
I want to subtract one from chunk mask.
Nice, work Casey.
All right.
There we go.
Try that one more time.
We get that value, we subtract one from it, and you can see that it
carries, right?
If we want to look in binary, we can do this as well.
Right?
So if we come in here, we can see that.
We basically take that one, shift it up.
There we go.
We have the one shifted up by 8.
So it went one, two, three, four, five, seven.
Eight up to there.
And then we do the subtract and that'll Say, it'll do a carry.
We're just basically tries to pull from the next number.
Next to the next owners are all the way to the guests of the one so
it'll leave all of those ones filled.
And that is the mass that we wanted, right?
So, that was a good suggestion.
Thank you site.
We've never talked about that in the Stream.
That is a kind of convenient way.
You can make it.
So you only have to type in one thing and so that I can, I'm just
gonna simplify that.
Now since we've walked through it by just doing that, right?
And now we can see when we step in that we have that mask and we've
only added one place.
So if we change this to something else, if we change this to for it
would still work, right?
Which is kind of cool.
How did you make the map randomly generated?
We haven't gotten there yet.
The map is not randomly generated.
We just kind of put in a test map.
We haven't started doing generation work yet.
That's coming.
Later.
I have a question to the new time of system.
How do you want to make that third dimension of your world?
For example, when you go up a ladder, so what we'll be doing for that
is as soon as we have everything done for this.
We will just add a z only to the chunks.
So the Z's, they'll be a z on the chunk so you can go up or down and I
don't actually know, we'll add an ABS tile, a z here as well.
I don't know if we'll have a Rel Z.
Z or not, but we'll basically just add one.
Our coordinate and which will be pretty free to do, but it's not
handled the same, quite as X and Y, because you can't see up and down.
When you do like games are weird the way that they work.
Like you, you go down a level and you can't see the level below.
You exactly.
You can't move smoothly between them in the same ways.
So we may have to handle it a little bit differently, but it'll be,
it'll just be another parameter to our look up once we get to that
point.
Let's see.
Well, there are a lot of non question questions in the street.
What are your thoughts about how to handle screaming boundaries now?
Since now tile chunks are not equal to screens, so I don't really know
exactly how we're going to handle it.
I thought that's a good question.
And so I one way to handle it is to not make it explicit and just make
it implicit.
So, the generator that generates the, the world always generate
screens worth of content that are kind of a line that way.
And then the camera always just Moves In in as as it wants to in that
way, but the other thing we could do,
Is actually placed explicit screen markers so that basically, we could
have different sized screens that you move into and it would scale up
or down based on how big they were or something.
I don't know.
So we'll have to play with that.
So the answer is I don't know yet how we'll handle it.
But I wanted to get to the point where we could essentially freely
walk around the world so that we know that we can basically do
anything we want and then we'll figure out how to fix it.
Two screens that are gameplay related.
Is a chunk a quarter of what the map is right now, at chunk, is 256 by
256.
Which means it's even bigger than what we specified.
This the part we specified is actually a small fraction of it.
It's only, you know, a tiny fraction of what a chunk would be.
So we'll probably reduce this chunk size, potentially will look at
into that sort of stuff more tomorrow.
Let's see.
How about operator overloading for manipulating role positions?
Yes, we will be adding stuff like that.
Once I start introducing vectors.
We will be looking at operator overloading, simplify things, but we're
not quite there yet.
So I'm doing most of the stuff without operator overloading.
There's just there's not too much code so I don't mind doing it
manually, but yeah, once we actually
The time lapse up straightened away and I start talking more about
moving things around, we're going to want to introduce vectors and
talk a little bit about how that'll work.
Let's see.
Should you be considering multi-threading and networking right from
the scratch?
Well, networking is not really a goal for this game.
So not that one but multi-threading.
Yes and no.
Since we want to run on Raspberry Pi, there's not much we can do with
multi-threading for the main game code, but for the renderer will be
doing a lot of multi-threading because the render on Raspberry Pi will
use the GPU.
And so for our CPU renderer will do a bunch of multi-threading but
there's not, I don't know how much
Other threading we can really do.
We might have to accept some things like we might multi-thread the
world generation and then on Raspberry Pi will accept the fact that
there's like, sort of a world generation, loading screen, or
something, because maybe we can't really do anything about it.
We'll have to see.
So, there's a lot of ifs in there but, you know, I don't really think
so.
Like, there's not a whole lot, you need to do to consider
multi-threading.
I mean, multi-threading is something that you should be able to if you
have your code set
Well, you should be able to pull out multi-threaded threading Parts as
you go, if you really need to.
What does the?
0xffff value represent.
Oh, you're talking about these.
So that's just the largest possible, 32-bit integer, right?
Unsigned 32-bit integer.
So basically that's all the bits set that's in hexadecimal.
So if you go in here and you imagine typing that into something like
this,
Right, you can see that.
That is that's the largest possible 32-bit unsigned number because
this represents 32 bits.
In fact, we can see it in binary if you'd like.
There it is.
It's 32 ones in a row, right?
11, 11 11, 11, 11.
That is all that is.
And so you use it if you want to just quickly, write in the biggest
32-bit number.
That's, that's what that is.
Colonel Dragon says, I'm a little surprised.
You find flipping the y direction to be easier to work with
considering you've been programming and dealing with plus y down
display buffer is for so long.
Are there a lot of cases where the math is easier to deal with for
positive y.
Yeah, so
basically, having
Having worked in 3D, you get pretty used to right-handed coordinate
systems, which are basically, you know, coordinate systems where
you've got stuff that kind of obeys the right-hand rule.
So if you draw something like X and Y, and you look at sort of, if you
imagine a curl Circle, right?
Going counterclockwise from
Um, X to Y, then sort of the, the right-hand rule is if you curl, if
you curl your right hand like this, in the direction of the circle
from X to Y.
So you curl from X to Y, your thumb is pointing where the z-axis
should go, right?
You get really used to this coordinate system.
And so what you expect to see when you're on a tile map, is you expect
to see X going this way.
Going that way and Z going up, right?
So Z is coming out at you, you could equivalently, if you wanted to
maintain a right-handed coordinate system.
You could do it the other way around.
Where you've got X going this way.
Why going this way?
And then Z would be going into the screen.
So instead of Z like, in this case, coming out of the screen, right?
In this case, z is going sort of into the screen, right?
If that makes sense.
So you could do it that way, but then you'd have to deal with all your
circles always go the wrong direction, right?
So when you're thinking about all of your trig, it's going the wrong
direction.
So I prefer to just flip it and always be in right-handed with Z
coming out at me when I'm when I'm thinking of Tom apps.
Thanks a bunch.
I've never done hex as integers.
Always been blessed with you, Aunt Dot Max.
So if you want, if you're programming in c and you do just want the
max, you actually have that as well.
I think there is a thing like, you know, like that.
I don't remember what it is.
Exactly.
So I guess it actually is just that value, right?
So you can actually do that at Sea as well.
It's in standard in, I think but you you have those if you want them.
I see five minutes left.
Let's see.
I don't see any more questions related to the code that I can find.
Yeah, I don't see any more code related questions.
So I guess I will just answer in 5 minutes.
Anything that was sort of code related at all.
So basically
Someone was asking about why we don't use a high-level more high-level
code and the answer is because the whole point of this project is to
show how to write everything involved in a game, not to use someone
else's COBRA.
They already wrote stuff for us, and then we use it.
So, that's why we're not using any higher level stuff.
But also, I think that a lot of higher level stuff is overrated.
I just don't think it's very good and it doesn't take very long to
write these things yourself.
I mean, here we are.
We're 30.
Three hours into it.
That's not even one workweek.
A work week is 40 hours were 33 hours into it.
By the time you get one work week in, we will basically have all of
our tile map stuff.
Suspect.
We'll have our movement stuff, kind of.
We have our win32 prototyping layer done.
By the time you get two weeks into it, which is 80 hours.
We'll probably have part of the renderer finished as well.
Unlike if you just think about it, like if you spend a week doing
these things and we need to do like four of them, whatever, you know.
In based on what ends up, being a month's worth of programming time.
All told will probably have most of all the stuff we would have gained
from a high-level language, but we wrote it all ourselves and it's
going to be better because it's not going to have all kinds of janky
crusty stuff in it.
Like that makes things slower or that, you know, doesn't work the way
that we want to or that we can't optimized for Speed all that sort of
stuff.
So, at the end of the day, I would like to program in high-level
languages.
Eventually.
It's just most of the high-level stuff that's out there.
Right now just isn't very good and so someday,
A, I feel like I will start programming in more higher level stuff,
but it's got to be a lot better than the high level stuff.
That's out there right now, like maybe John blows programming
language, for example, that he's working on.
Now will be something that I could get into, because it will allow me
to do more high-level stuff, but it won't ask me to sacrifice things
in that.
In that transition.
It'll just be high level when I want it, but it won't force me to
accept all the compromises that high-level things of forced me to
accept.
Oh, okay.
So got some new questions here, some of which are let's see here.
Why did you introduce M as a unit?
So the reason are integers, m is a unit is because we wanted something
that wasn't in pixels and M is the most standard SI unit to use for
Stuff.
Basically, you know, M.
KS is typically M kg s is a very typical convention to use.
And so I wanted a real world unit so that we would basically have a
way to sort of tie things back Loosely to the real world.
Obviously.
These characters are gonna be very cartoony.
So there's no way to really tie them back to the real world, but just
so that we're
In the ballpark, you know?
So that whatever our guys sizes are.
There's somewhere between you know, you know, three feet tall and 10
feet tall or something but not ridiculous like 100 feet tall in for a
kid or something like that so that we their physics will behave
properly.
If we Implement things like gravity and stuff, we can tune it close to
real world and so it feels better.
So that's why I introduced m
That basically, everything would be in a real world unit.
Will you be checking your code complexity and creating smaller
functions as necessary?
So we already do that all the time.
We've already done, lots of that.
If you've been watching the stream, we often times will take things
and break them out right now.
We're just kind of defining the spec for the engine.
So this code is just kind of waiting here for a bit.
When we're totally done with the town Maps up to my satisfaction.
It will get moved out into a new file.
That will basically be the spec for our tile map system.
Let's see.
Did I set up a Kickstarter?
No?
I have not set up a Kickstarter.
There is a patreon which I will point out at the end of the stream,
but there is, we do not have a Kickstarter.
There's nothing really to kick-start at the moment.
Let's see.
Let's see, anything else?
Wouldn't it be nice if tiles were 1.0 M instead of 1.4 meters?
Yeah, I mean maybe but I don't know.
I'd rather have the freedom to set the tile sizes to whatever we want.
Then have to constrain it to 1 meter.
I don't know.
It's interesting point though, but I don't I don't think I'm going to
I think I'd rather leave it because it's right now.
Everything's going to be in tiles, was just an offset from the tile
anyway, so it should be fine, but you're right.
It would be nicer.
If tiles were one meter.
It'd be a little cleaner.
I don't know.
We get think about it.
You could think about it since everything's parameterised off.
That currently.
Anyway, we're it's
Free for us to change it to something else so we could think about it.
All right, that is the end of the stream.
Ladies and gentlemen, thank you so much for joining me is been a
pleasure coding with you, as always, if you would like to follow along
with the source code at home.
Let me close.
Well, I got tons of stuff open here.
Close, close, everybody.
Everybody close down now, please.
Yes, too many things open.
All right, if you would like to follow,
Along with the code at home.
You can pre-order the game and get full access to the source code.
So everything that I work on gets uploaded right after we finish the
stream so you can download it every day and follow along at home.
You can go ahead and pre-order here at handmade hero dot-org.
We also have a patreon since someone was asking about that where you
can subscribe, if you just want to support the video series, you can
do that.
There's also a news and four of us page, which I highly recommend you
check out.
It's got a lot of good stuff on it.
It's got the schedule for the week posted usually on Monday for what
the rest of the
Will be if you want to know when we're going to be live on Twitch.
There's also an episode guide for helping you catch up with episodes
in the past that maybe that you have missed, there is a coding
resources section.
Has like a pork to Mac and a port to Linux and stuff.
So if you want to take a look at running on different platforms or
other sorts of guides that are available there.
That's a great place to go.
And finally, there's a Code discussion board where you can ask
questions about the code and talk to other people who are working on
it.
So if you're trying to learn from the series, I highly recommend going
there.
It's got a lot of resources that will help you.
So thank you everyone for joining me tomorrow.
I believe my post the schedule, I said tomorrow is going to be evening
again.
So eight pm are.
So we're in our standard slot tomorrow, 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time and then our standard slot on Friday, as well,
10 a.m., Although I guess we moved it down from 11 to 10, but we're in
the morning on Friday as we normally are.
We always try to do one stream in the morning.
So so these two will be basically the same as they normally are during
the week.
But today was a special kind of early one for holiday hours.
So yeah, tomorrow night 8:00 p.m.
PST.
I hope to see you there and that is it for today.
Have a happy New Years, everyone, if you
Are in a part of the world that celebrates mirrors today.
So thank you everyone for joining us.
And, and I will hopefully see you tomorrow.