Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we code a complete game live on stream.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just us.
And our little typing.
Fingers are a little baby typing.
Little sausage fingers typing away today.
We are, we kind of wrapped up yesterday, a couple of days worth of
stuff that we've done, where we basically, we added font support to
handmade hero.
And we've got nominally all the things in there now, including kerning
and all that sort of stuff.
But
I don't feel like it's quite an everything is not quite buttoned up
like it's not quite where I would like it to be in terms of everything
being finished and cleaned too, because there's still some like cruft
in there, in terms of like how things are positioned stuff and stuff
like that.
And so I'd like to make sure that we actually go through that with a
little bit more slightly finer tooth comb just to clean out any of the
that sort of nastiness and then I'd also like to make sure that we
have at least some plausible story.
We would support multiple languages because right now we're not really
considering that we do support like arbitrary code points.
So you could have multiple, you know, you can have Unicode code points
in there and stuff but there are certain limitations that we've kind
of baked in that there's really not that much reason for us to keep we
can get rid of them, I think without too much trouble and we probably
should.
So that's what I'd like to start doing today and maybe just spend the
next couple days just going through everything and until we're
relatively satisfied that we've got everything covered pretty well.
So that's why I like to do today.
Today is day 173.
If you would like to follow along at home and you preorder the game on
handmade here a.org, please go ahead and unpack day 172 source code
because that's the source code that I'm going to be starting with
today.
So if you want to follow along, that's the source code, you should
start with.
Now where we left off, just to give you a little perspective.
If you don't remember what we did yesterday, where we left off,
because we had just finished actually putting in all of the sort of,
through the entire pipeline from
Asset Packer through to the game font metadata.
So we can do things like Kern our fonts and so on and we also put in
things like the line height.
So you'll now notice that these lines are the correct distance apart,
no more fudging necessary.
But there's a couple things that we haven't done yet.
One of them is just a little thing in actual handmade hero, which is
that you'll notice the first line is off the top of the screen, right?
And the reason for that is because we actually need to do some code to
position things.
Curly that we never did, that has nothing to do with our font.
Our font is not malfunctioning.
That's just the debug line stuff that we sort of put in as a test
case, just isn't doing very much smart there.
And the reason is that doing the smart thing is you can see that the
@y right is doing some kind of nonsense here that has nothing to do
with the actual information that we want.
But we'd rather do is start the at why one line down because of
course, we're working off the Baseline of the line.
So to start with, let's do that.
And then, that will, I think hopefully also.
Sort of.
Us in a better position to think about what we might want.
For some refinements on stuff like these values because there's more
information that we could be storing and possibly should be storing
for that.
So let's go ahead and start by just noticing that if I went in there
and I put in that font scale there.
Oh.
And I need that font infrastructure as well, right?
Like so, so we need to kind of do this sort of thing.
And what I can probably do is, I can probably initialize this stuff to
something reasonable first, right?
And then assuming that we get the van info, we can we can sort of do
that.
All right, although you know what?
Now I think about it.
That's actually not the case.
We don't need to push the font because it's in the font info so we can
actually do that without actually.
Yeah, without having to do anything further.
So whatever the font idea is that we actually want to use, and I think
we probably want to get that early because we want in our debug reset,
to be able to use it so hard.
Like reset, what I think we want to probably do is put this up here,
right?
And get that van tidy like right off the bat, which means that our
debug reset is going to need to know what the game assets actually
are, right?
So that it can do this.
Okay, that means that our font ID is going to be something that comes
in here, right?
This is our debug font ID or something like that, right?
We can just call it font ID for now because I've got we're going to do
something a little bit different with these things here because of
course we want to fix them for a loop live coding as well.
So for now I'm just going to do it like this and let it go, right?
So that's game assets asset and that's all we really need.
I believe so there we go.
Okay.
So if we want to do this when we call a, okay?
So this actually also tells us something.
Remember I did heard about this before and now I kind of have my
answer which is that I don't want to have to rely on the font for
getting things like this.
Probably I don't want to rely on some kind of load time thing.
I'd rather have that always be known specifically so it can do resets
and stuff like this.
That sort of suggests to me again that I want to be able to get that
information directly.
Which means that stuff like this get line advance for.
I kind of do want them to be able to operate only on the info, right?
Because I did third about whether I wanted to pass in the font just in
case and I think I don't want to because that means that now I won't
have any sort of Randomness there and that's going to be.
I could always kind of count on it being there, so I think that's a
better State of Affairs personally.
So I think just do this.
There we go.
I think now we should be back in better shape.
In terms of our placement, right?
Oh, although we're not that's way too far down.
So something went wrong there.
If that's the distance between the two things.
That's a little bit odd, don't you think?
Well, no bother we will simply take a look at why that happened.
Did I what happened there and made?
Oops, debug reset.
So at y equals font scale times get line advance for.
So it's just going to be whatever get line advance for actually is,
right.
Then it's going to use at why directly in here.
Presumably right?
Yeah.
And then it's going to subtract from that the get line Advance four
times the font scale.
So it should only have move down by
By that amount.
I wonder if that means do.
We have some kind of problem with our Baseline alignment?
I think we do.
It's a little bit hard to guess but that would suggest that we do,
right?
Hmm.
So yeah, I think we want to take a look at that because that seems
busted.
Let's take a look at what what's going on there.
Because if you look right,
That's right.
You know that I'm feeling slow today.
I'm feeling slow.
I don't know if I'm just not in the groove yet, because that doesn't
make sense.
Like, what, what's the deal there?
What did I do?
Because see I've set at y 20 now, and it's here.
All right, duh, because 0 is the center.
I'm just stupid.
Yep, it is a slow day so we want to start at the top of the screen,
right?
Which is there and then we want to come down by one line.
Duh 0 0 is at the center of the screen not the corner, right?
So that's what we actually want to do, right?
Okay, so now that we're we've warmed ourselves up and we're not doing
obviously stupid things, which is good.
If you take a look at what's going on here, I'm just going to call
some things.
I'm going to point out some things, right?
First of all, good job us because as you can see, you can even change
like the size of things in the middle of sentences.
And, and all of our current and all that stuff works properly it.
So that's kind of fun, right?
And it means that we can means that our fonts are at least getting
into a more reliable sort of set of
Metrics.
So that complicated operations.
You might want to do with them are actually working.
Okay?
And so, if we were to go in here and do a little more playing around
with that right, where we wanted to sort of change the sizes
frequently, we could do that.
Right?
If we wanted to say, okay, there, this one's going to be a one, then a
5 and 3, then a 9, right?
Then a then a 2, then a seven or something like this.
If we want to do some crazy stuff, we can do it.
It and in theory, everything should work.
Right?
Oh
although,
Although I'm glad I did that.
That brings up a pretty interesting thing.
So if we want to support this, we need to do one more thing.
And that is that the kerning
Has to be broken up across two letters.
Because if the two letters can be of different sizes, the kerning
amount would change.
Right, which is kind of tricky.
I don't even know if Windows gives us enough information to even do
that properly but let me just draw what's going on here because I
think this is kind of worth thinking through.
Right.
So
If we start with the letter, right?
That's tiny and then go to a letter that's big.
Who's kerning do we use if we use the kerning right, because remember
the kerning value we get back.
We'll be the same but it's the scale.
This letter had one this letter had one scale, you know, this point to
or something and this one had, you know, 1.0 right.
So the kerning value that we get back.
How do we interpret it?
Do we interpret it at this scale or do we interpret it this?
Kale
Because it's going to make a very big difference.
If we interpret it at this scale, we're going to move to too little
and the, oh, will like overlap the see quite a bit, but if we
interpret it, this scale will move too far and they'll be a giant Gap,
right?
And so, to some degree, it's almost we just really don't have the
information that we would need.
We really, really don't have that information that we would need.
Because really that kerning has to become a more procedural.
Thing at that point, especially when you consider the fact that
kerning changes the alignments of the letters.
So for example, let's say that you had a lowercase C
Right?
And an uppercase t and they recur and like this if I shrink the tea
down so that the bar comes in line with the top of the see it should
now be spaced quite a bit further to this side because it can't
overlap without running into the other letter, right?
So I'm going to have to say, I feel like you're not allowed to change
characters inside of a word because we just don't have the information
we would actually need.
We could write our entirely own kerning system to support that and
that would be kind of entertaining to do.
But I feel like with the information we get from Windows,
There's nothing that's going to happen there.
So I feel like any two adjacent letters have to be the same and that
even though I would like to be able to do something crazy like that.
I feel like there's really no way to do so
At least, not in a way that actually is reliably good, right?
Yeah.
So, that's a bummer because that's kind of, we're not doing anything
wrong there, but I think there's no way we can really do something,
totally right.
Yeah.
Well, something to think about, it's useful to kind of understand
like, okay, that's you know, that's a limitation.
Of the way Windows does kerning in the first place.
There's really nothing we can do about that, or I should say the way
truetype fonts does kerning.
Anyway, all right.
So, we'll ignore that limitation for now, because I don't know this
much that we can do about that without going down to kind of a big rat
hole of kind of doing our own font stuff formats and stuff like this.
But the things that we can do something about there's a couple of them
First of all, this giant space here.
What's that coming from right?
Well what that comes from is the fact that our spacing tables are
currently not initialized to know what happens when you have a letter.
That that follows nothing right that follows.
No other letter by default.
It will just use a generic width in that case, right?
And so I think we would like to do here is we
Like to set up our creating tables to say that we don't Advance at all
if the previous Cara was the 0 glyph, right?
Because that's what we start out with, because you can see what
happens right in the debug line.
Right in here.
If we were to set get rid of this, right?
We start at the left edge of the screen, you know?
And we say, okay, we're starting to left edge of the screen.
We want to line up flush, to the left edge of the screen.
So, why is it doing that?
There's that left Edge, we initialize X, to be that left Edge.
But when we come in here, the first thing that we do is we ask for the
horizontal advancement that we're going to advance between the
previous character and this character, right?
But we don't know.
Anything about that because there's nothing there, right?
It's set to zero.
And so it's going to look up into that table and find out.
Whoops, like that is actually some entry and it's an entry that we did
initialize to anything meaningful, right?
So if we go back and look at like our test asset Packer, for example,
when we actually do those kerning tables, what we could do is say, oh,
okay, you know, whenever we do our current, a what we're going to
start off with instead is if the
First kerning pair, right?
Oops, that's wrong.
I meant this one when we initialize the tables, if the first skirting
pair is going to be the null glyph.
We're going to do something special, right?
So what we're going to do here is say alright at first or you know we
could even do it special case here.
We could do something like saying R32 W equals 0 0.
If code Point index is greater than 0, right?
Or it's not equal to zero then fill it in with an actual ABC with
So I think that's a pretty easy way to make that problem work relative
to make that worked relatively well.
So, here we go.
And so now, let's run it.
Oh,
That was not what I expected.
If the code point in X is not equal to 0, ah, got to get rid of that
are 32 little variable shadowing, start the day.
Okay, so now we get more what we would expect, right?
Which is that we line up with the left Edge that we're actually
starting with at least to a greater degree.
There's still a little bit of space here and that space is not great,
right?
If we told our system that we want it to line up directly with the
left Edge, we would like to line it up directly with the left Edge,
right?
That's a pretty straightforward thing that we might want to do if we
were actually cared about typography.
Now, granted you might say we don't care about typography very much.
This game and that is probably true.
But for the benefit of a just discussing the problem, at least being
aware of it.
I'm going to explain why that's happening.
And then the other thing I wanted to point out is this giant Gap here.
The same thing is true for this.
The problem with that is that the line Advanced, right?
That we're using is the distance from a baseline to another Baseline.
That doesn't tell us where the top edge of the font actually is.
So if we wanted to align that top Edge, that would be a problem,
right?
So that is that sort of the two things that I think in terms of
metadata or Allah or working with alignments, right?
That we haven't really addressed.
The first one is kind of a little bit Squirrely and I'll talk about
that s.
Actually, the second one is actually little bit easier.
All we really need to know about that is we just need to store an
additional piece of metadata, which is how high the font itself
actually is and that's information.
That we already had right?
We just chose not to store it, so we just need to actually store that
and then use that as the initial starting point instead of the line
advance.
So let's do that because that's very simple.
And then the other one is a slightly more complicated and we'll talk
about that.
So, where is that getting storage?
Well, you can see our line Advanced here is being stored as the height
and then the external editing, right?
So we added those two together, all we would have to do is actually
store them separately, right?
So we can store the height.
The external letting as two separate things that occur in our font.
And that way, we now no longer have that situation anymore.
We're, we're talking about a combined value in wouldn't be able to get
them X extricated from each other.
So if I come in here to handmade file formats, I should be able to go
in and change that.
So instead of storing line Advanced right?
In the HHA font we're just going to add another thing into our storage
format that's going to be the external loading and then we're going to
change line advance to be the height.
Like so right.
And I'll say this is the maximum height or
Ders.
actually no it now that I think about it, we actually want a little
more information, either even more than that because
I want to know where the Baseline is, right?
So we really want to kind of get all of.
We want all of that information that was had there.
Instead of height, we kind of want, like the Ascender and the
descender, right Heights.
So that we can advance just down to the Baseline, right?
Think it's called a scent of descent.
I don't remember what they call them asset a decent.
Asset decent.
And so this way,
I guess it's like sort of the totals here, right?
This way, we'd have all the information that we could possibly want.
Sender height.
Now that really doesn't need an explanation because it's what it is
and then we've got the external lighting.
And so now with those we can now do as any kind of vertical
positioning that we so choose we can put the Baseline a particular
point.
We can put the total font that a particular point.
You know, we can put the base, the bottom of the ascenders, at a
particular Point move the line get Advance.
The line we could do anything we want, right?
So I feel like that's a saner approach to that problem.
It means that will be a little bit more flexible with what we do and
The assets, right?
When we come down here and made asset and we're getting the line
Advanced now we know, it's really just, okay?
It's the Ascender height, it's like all these things out of together,
right?
So it's going to be that.
What's that?
And then we can add in additional things here for other stuff.
Like get just get starting
Baseline y, or something like that.
Basically what that's going to do is just return that to Sender the
thing that you know, where we want to start a line from that makes
sense.
And then instead of using that get line Advance, we're going to
actually just use this when we're doing that positioning in the debug
line.
Or I should say the reset function, right?
So something like this where we're going to do that.
I think that's really all we need.
What is the problem here?
It's not a member of loaded font.
That's true.
It isn't.
Why are we storing that here?
Actually, if I may, why is that even getting stored there?
It should be stored here.
That's where it actually should be stored.
So I don't know why we were doing that.
Be completely honest with you, no idea whatsoever.
That's when that should have happened.
So that's fine.
Here we go.
And we'll just run that repack.
And now we will go
All right, so let's see, still not quite that's that's not right.
Oh, that's good.
Because I use the descenders instead of the ascenders, which is
actually what we wanted, right?
Should draw on the Whiteboard to remind my own self.
If we have a g, then this is actually
We want this one which is actually the ascending height, right?
Not this one, which is the descending height, right?
So yeah, that was just kind of me.
Not even typing in the thing, I actually wanted
Could you be that?
So let's try that test again.
See if they're any better.
There we go.
So now we're looking better, right?
It's definitely an improvement.
It's not exactly lined up though which is a little weird.
Now it's possible that that's actually correct and the reason I say
that it's possible, that's actually correct is because I don't know,
for example, if the character map includes things that would have gone
in that space, right?
So for example,
That's not what I want.
That.
So for example, we come down here and we see for example, this my
assumption is that, that is included and you can kind of see that it
sort of is like if you look at the you know, if you look at the a that
a and this a look like the same a but with extra space on top.
So I suspect that that is just the space where the accents would go.
If you were looking at sort of the other pieces of the font.
So I don't know what to say about that.
Technically
That is probably correct but I don't know.
You know, if we were going to be a little bit more.
Exacting about it.
We might go and actually measure all the font glyphs ourselves and
change that value to actually be based on what we observed to be the
highest thing above the Baseline and what we observe to be the lowest
thing below the Baseline.
Does that make sense?
And I don't know if we really want to do that because it's sort of not
really using the font per se.
But an argument could have been made for it.
So for now we'll just say we know that that's there and we'll leave it
at that.
We know it's there.
If we decide later that we don't like it, it's not too hard for us to
remove so be aware of it.
Okay.
And so the other thing, oops.
The other thing to think about, like I was saying is the lining up on
the left side.
So if you take a look at how these characters are lining up,
You can.
That even though we asked for them to be aligned directly, with the
left Edge, they are not aligned direct with the left Edge.
The reason for that is because of those ABC widths, that we were
talking about, we chose to have the offset for the character, be part
of that a, the a b and c width part, right?
And you can see the consequences of having that occur of putting sort
of the placement there, is that.
Now, if we try to draw something right at that left Edge, it actually
to place this place.
Is it by that?
At that part of the width.
And so what I'm thinking we probably want to do is we probably want to
bake that back into the kerning right instead which we have the option
of doing and we you know we didn't do it because we were sort of
playing with other reasons but I think what I'd like to do is see what
happens if we go ahead and place that back in there.
So that lifts always line up flush with the edge and that ABC with is
actually something that's done.
A little bit differently if that makes sense.
So let's see here, if we come in here,
how are we actually doing that?
Min ex - priest up.
So that's the that's what we're putting in there, right?
We're using that.
And what we'd rather do, is have that actually go into the kerning
table.
I think the problem that we have with that, of course, is that in
order to put that into the kerning table, we need to process all the
characters and we don't process the characters prior to actually doing
that right out.
Now, we could choose that, I feel like there's a pretty easy way to
cheese that and that way
Is to run the characters.
First, like I feel like we could actually do that.
Hmm.
By making sure that fog lifts always come before fonts that would be
the way to cheese it, right?
You can see what I'm saying.
Right?
So the reason it doesn't work right now is because the horizontal
Advanced table is in an asset type who comes prior to write that comes
prior to the font glyphs potentially.
Right?
And the reason that that was the case is because of the way we added
them, I believe they get written out in that order, right?
So if we come down
You're too right, fonts.
You can kind of see that if we weren't wanted to, we could rearrange
this, right?
We can move this over here and then that wouldn't be the case anymore.
It's kind of ugly though, right?
To do, this is kind of janky, because it means you have to get this
order, right?
Always.
Right.
So, I don't know.
I know how you guys feel about that.
But assuming we were to do that.
What that would mean is that this Min X here - priest up, this thing
that would actually instead of being baked into the alignment that
would come out of the alignment entirely and it would actually just be
moved into the kerning
Right?
And so if we take a look at where that kerning was actually happening
that horizontal advanced stuff we're is on total.
Advance.
If I went in and set it to include that, like so we want to take
whatever the kerning used to be in this table and I guess, you know,
to be honest, we kind of have to do it to the entire table, right?
We've got to go through all of the code points and do it here, right?
Something like this.
All right, so for every other code point,
In our entire table, we have to go through and adjust it by whatever.
This this step value is,
So, we would compute that first kerning change.
It would be this.
And in order to compute that, yeah, I think we just want to say, okay,
we need to move by whatever this amount is, we used to be doing it to
counter position something.
So I believe this is now going to is going to be the opposite way
round, right?
Because if the minimum X, let's see if the minimum X is past the
priest up.
We want to move it.
well, that actually call me crazy, but that actually looks
Like, it's the right way around for our purposes.
How is that working in here?
Doesn't that seem like the wrong way round for the aligned percentage?
The precept X is how far over we were starting.
And then the Min X is going to be further than that normally if their
space at the beginning.
So if you want to know how far you should move from the previous
character,
You would want to subtract Free Step from Minix, right?
But if you were going to put the alignment Point, yeah, that's weird.
I wonder if we just had that wrong or if I'm just thinking it through
wrong it's been a slow day.
We already know that it's a slow day.
So maybe I'm just being slow again, you know, sometimes that happens.
It's totes fine.
All right, there we go.
So let's just see what that does because I'm a little weirded out
right now.
And I feel like I need to
For this a little bit because I don't really understand what's going
on, but that's fine.
Alright, so now we have corrected that and you can see that we're
lining up properly with the edge, and it does look like we're pretty
close in, to being exactly right.
In fact, we might be literally exactly, right?
I think we are hard to say, but, but it looks pretty darn good.
And then let's take a look at how our kerning looks.
Otherwise, I'm going to go ahead and load up notepad compared to our
reference, which we're assuming Windows is able to follow its own
creating tables but you never do know.
With Windows.
so, okay, if I line this up here,
Is that roughly the size of the D?
That looks like a bigger that looks bigger came and render.
Yeah.
So our kerning is definitely wrong.
So I must just be right.
I mean that's definitely it's displacing it the wrong way, you can see
that it is.
So I'm obviously thinking about that incorrectly and so I'm assuming
that it actually is my assumption that it had to be reversed was
correct.
So I'll do it and try it.
But really I would then I'm going to want to go back and draw it out
to figure out why like, what my mental?
What was my mental problem there, if that makes sense.
So yeah.
Because that just based that seems it seems wrong to me.
Of course that looks wrong to, right?
That's not enough kerning.
Okay, so something else is wrong, which is good, because if something
else is wrong, then I don't have to quite worried about why I was
being so confused by that particular thing.
All right, so that's good.
No, no real worries there.
Because like I said, at the end of the day, I'm totally happy with
with having to investigate that a little further since I would rather,
they're just be some other bug in the code than then that part.
So let's take a look at the horizontal advance.
Okay.
So normally, well there's our problem right there.
So the ABC a is now no longer something, we actually want to include
right because we're pulling it out in here, right?
So really what we want to initialize this table too.
Is just the be within the sea with right because we don't the a with
is now getting sort of sucked out in the in the other step.
So that that makes a lot more sense.
That makes a lot more sense.
Okay, so let's see here.
Did I actually run that?
This is the problem with not having the asset builds be.
Medically updating something.
We might want to think about doing eventually.
Although since I will do the most good thing so that still seems a
little wrong to me, right like that.
And and stuff, is there still not enough space in here, right?
You can see, you can see that that's much more Airy.
So we're definitely still occurring in properly compared to the
reference.
It's pretty good, like that.
All looks pretty good until you get to that a right.
Which happens to be one that has a little bit of that spacing there,
right?
Right.
So we're clearly still interpreting that a little bit incorrectly and
so we've still got a little ways to go.
So let's press through it, just a little bit more and see if we can't
nail that down a little bit further.
So what I, you know what, I might suggest as well?
I might suggest that we just say
You know, the heck with with the ABC widths at all.
we could just use the sea with,
And the see what would be the only thing really, right?
And the be with we compute from the actual width of the character
itself, right?
Like I could say, now that we're building the kerning table this way,
I could just say, alright, let's go ahead and take that that align
percentage stuff and I'll be like a up the the Korean Tech change
calculation here.
What we could do is actually subtract the max X from the priest.
Right.
And that would be how far you move something like that, right?
Something like this.
Even just the width, the total width, so you Advanced by the total
width and then we only use the sea with
You know I'm saying?
I don't know how I feel about that but that may be a little bit better
than what Windows was giving us.
We already know Windows, kerning is not fabulous so I'm not that
concerned with reproducing.
It
So that's kind of interesting.
That to me.
Is super weird because that means that that see with is actually
doesn't is actually not much compared to what's actually in the glyph.
So weird the way Windows works.
right, like, look at how much extra space is actually, in the B, width
of this thing, not to mention the sea with
That's so weird.
All right, I think we've got another bug in here though anyway because
some of that doesn't quite line up.
So I'm going to go back a little bit here and just say, alright let's
let's go back to saying we're just going to check out the Min X.
Three step.
So how far we have to go there?
That's going to be part of our kerning change, right?
And then in handmade art, right?
In the the part of the asset Builder where we do those ABC with
I'm going to take a look if we've got the, the
So, that's back to having to be with them to see what, right?
Hmm, hmm.
What's the smartest thing to do here?
See, the problem is Windows doesn't actually let us do the thing we
want which is just no where the left Edge actually is.
And so,
I'm just trying to think of the best way to still use their their
kerning information.
Well, not having that be a problem.
How about this?
How about we?
Look at them all at the same time.
Okay, let's suppose we look at them all at the same time and consider
them a little more carefully.
So instead of doing this stuff right in there will never, we won't
actually do any of this.
What we'll do instead is, we'll just zero this array.
So the horizontal array will start out completely zero.
so,
This.
We'll just be cleared.
Then we go in and we set all of the ones that we know about to
whatever their current amount is and we can still leave it as a plus I
suppose if you want to, that's fine.
Then here is where we will actually do the kerning change.
For our code points.
Right.
And in here we will use the ABC widths and be able to have all of the
information in one place so we can sort of look at all of the data and
see if we can come up with a reasonable algorithm for figuring
something out, right?
So, for example, we can look at the difference between the ABC with
and this actual pre step, right?
Which would be different.
I think if we line this guy up, I'm trying to think of why this
wouldn't work.
Exactly.
If we're lot aligning, this totally properly.
Now, which I believe we are.
I wonder why it doesn't work to just use the ABC with sums.
Exactly like we did originally.
And then stop doing.
I don't remember why.
So I'm just going to go ahead and put that in here.
Because I don't remember why that was like, if we just do this, why
did that not work for our kerning value, right?
I suppose it probably didn't work because we are not including the
empty space.
That's actually the puts that that's be with should have done that.
Kind of confused, kind of a little bit confused.
So let's see, I just want to see what this does.
Yes, we're still getting really weird results from that.
Right.
I feel like I've got some kind of weird bug.
I think I've got some kind of weird bug because we should not be able
to be getting those results.
This way, it doesn't it doesn't it doesn't have something doesn't add
up right?
Hopefully you agree with me that something's weird some things, a
little weird so
But the question is, what is it?
Hmm.
So let's start with something simple.
That's not update the kerning at all.
We should just get all of our fonts smush together, right?
Perfect.
That's what we expected.
That's what we got.
So we know we are actually updating the crane tables.
That's good.
It's at least something but why we're getting such small amounts of
distance from the ABC with I don't understand.
And so I wonder if there's something about the ABC with that I'm
interpreting like wrong.
Because that should be the total amount of advancement, right?
But maybe not.
I mean, maybe that's not the actual value that we should be using.
Is there a thing that's like,
It says what the kerning pairs should be.
Relative to.
Because it doesn't say, of course in classical documentation fashion,
they leave out the one piece of information.
You actually wouldn't have been able to guess from just looking at
this which is what I current amount is relative to right.
Which is a little unfortunate to say the least but
Let's see if it's in here.
Let's see, it takes a string.
Portable truetype metrics, this sort of thing, maybe.
Do we have any additional info?
Retrieval design metrics placement occurs on a line.
Font embedding.
So we only and I thought this one said, it didn't work with your type.
Or something like that, right?
Cannot be used on truetype fonts, you have to use care, get care ABC,
which is what we were using, right?
What does this do?
Hello, thank you.
It's probably his recent right.
Oh no, it's pretty old actually.
Let's see who Point character so it gives us the exact same stuff.
It actually gives, I guess long pointer to an ABC float.
Why is it a pointer?
So, it's an array.
So, it's okay.
I see you're getting them all out the same way we were doing before.
So, ABC float, presumably is exact same data, just for floating point,
which is fine.
We could get that which would be more accurate since we are stowing
for storing floats, in case it wants to do it that way.
But I don't know that that has anything to do with our particular
problem, right?
It seems like it's
But, at least here, it says, the character increment.
Total width of a character is the sum of the, a b and c spaces.
And so I feel like that
That should be it.
Well, okay, let's think about this a little bit more.
Here we go.
So, assuming we wanted to reverse engineer this as much as possible.
Here is a letter.
And I'm using the uppercase a because that's the one that happens to
be Troublesome, right?
We asked to draw it here.
And we know that it actually drew it like back here.
Now what I don't know is what Windows actually does.
How does it determine this part?
I know that it picks some value here, right?
Which we thought was ABC widths plus each other, right?
And then this location, it will then apply the kerning amount, right?
This is Ike earn to move backwards, and that's fine.
however,
What we don't really get is exactly how we should interpret these
interpret.
This part of the motion, right?
If this was the location, we asked it to draw.
Presumably the next location, is whatever that location is plus the
ABC.
With now we're actually drawing the character flush with that thing,
which means that before we draw the character, we
Need to move it back now, normally, we're just going to add that into
the kerning oh, but it's the curtain for the next character.
You see how that goes?
If we want all of our characters to be able to be flush aligned
Then we need to put the a with part of the thing.
The pre step.
We need that to actually be in the next, the next guy.
That's not that hard.
The problem is Windows, doesn't really give us.
I think the information we actually need for this because of how it's
sort of breaking things up.
Those ABC was aren't really what I think they really are supposed to
be, but yeah, man.
Anyway, so when we do this kerning change, it's actually the other
side that gets changed, right?
It's actually other code Point index Plus Code point.
It's this part right here that actually gets moved by this
Right.
It's this part.
If that makes any sense.
And so the actual this the the part that's the part to move after this
particular guy would presumably just be this if windows isn't lying to
us which it you know, probably is right?
So that care advance.
Because the character advancement is the B and C that a part, the
blank space since we're sucking, the character over to align with the
left side, that actually becomes kerning, that happens when it's the
character being drawn.
Not when it's the character that was already drawn.
That makes sense.
So that's a little more correct.
But it's still because of the fact that I don't think a those ABC
which are actually correctly set in Windows.
I'm a little apprehensive about it but point being, I think that's
closer to correct now.
Okay,
All right, so now moving back a step.
Now if we take a look at that, kerning that kerning is pretty spot-on.
Now I would say there's still a little bit of nastiness like that's a
little bit more space, I think.
But on the whole, it's pretty darn close and I think I don't know like
I said, if we can get it, quite exactly right.
And the reason for that is because I don't know if we have those ABC
with reported properly,
I have to think about that.
What we might do, you know what we might do?
There actually is a one way.
We could probably do that the amount that we're going to do the
adjustment.
Maybe we do it this way.
We say, okay, we've got this is what the total amount Windows would
have updated by right.
So we're going to use that - however much for that that little kerning
change was there right - ever much.
We're saying happens after the fact,
All right.
So, I don't think that really helped though.
Very, very close throughout.
In fact the our is are much closer now.
This is still ours, looks better than theirs does oddly enough but
it's obviously not correct.
In fact, ours looks better almost everywhere except maybe the DP and
the D.
But that doesn't look too good.
That's all messed up.
Hmm.
All right.
Sometimes gets better sometimes gets worse.
Oh!
Typo.
That's not a fair test.
Let's try one more time.
Yeah.
Well
Better don't know if it's low if it's if it's quite right yet.
Yeah, still still.
We've got a little more tightness in some of these than they do, you
know, just looking at it.
So yeah, I don't know.
But anyway, right.
We need to do one more thing, obviously, which is that, hey, we don't
actually want to change the kerning.
The critic should always be zero if the first code point was zero.
So assuming that we're coming through here and doing a code point zero
as the first character, we don't want to do this creating change.
So we only want to do this.
If code point is not equal to 0.
Because otherwise we ruined, that's why you know our alignment here is
now wrong again, right?
Because it's going to add that number in.
So assuming we take care of that then we should be good to go.
Or not.
I do that wrong.
I did that wrong.
Yeah, it's when other code point is zero.
Sorry.
So we don't want to add that that slight increment, right?
See other code Point index.
And there we go.
So now that's lined up flush.
And that's good Arc, earnings?
Mostly matching Windows.
Although it's again.
I don't know if we can ever get exactly right.
I have to think
About if it's possible to get it.
Exactly right when we don't know, we don't know how much the ABC with
Correspond to how it decided to line that stuff up.
It's really kind of maddening, but yeah, but that's pretty darn good.
I think we're now at least accounting for most of the things that we
should be and that's a good thing.
So yeah.
Yeah, I'm relatively happy with that.
I'm pretty happy with that.
So let's go ahead and think a little bit harder perhaps about doing
like another language.
Right.
Let's think about that because there's some stuff that I would like to
fix that.
I think we want to do in order to support other languages.
So you know, like
Actually no.
Does this thing have ime?
Just we have ime support.
Probably don't, but that's actually.
Okay, here we go.
So if we were to grab some of these guys in here, right?
So Jimmy.
So what we would like to do, right?
Is we'd like to make it possible somehow.
For other people who you know native language is not representable in
Roman alphabets, to be able to translate potentially if they'd like to
the words and handmade hero.
Like like I said, they'll probably be like item names I'm guessing and
stuff like that.
I don't know how much text will have in the game.
I don't know if we'll have that much text, but at the very least,
Have we know, we will have some I think.
And so as a result we know that there will be things that could be
translated into other languages.
So if we have things that can be transmitted to the language is what
we'd like to do is be able to support other character sets.
And, you know, if we think about what this character actually is, let
me see if I can actually do a search.
Right?
So if we look at what this actually is, that's that value hex.
Right for EAC.
Now, for EAC is going to be real high, right?
If I if I was to go into Dev Studio here,
That's what good point.
That is 20,000 140.
Now, if you remember how we implemented our kerning and stuff like
that, I just did it as a flat or a lookup, which I think is better,
because then it's just instant, right?
And when you only have something like 60 characters, or 120 characters
or even 250 characters, right?
That's not a very big table, hmm.
It's going to be something like 200.
Okay, even if you do mess floats.
But if we had to have a 20,000
by 20,000 table, right?
Suddenly, that is not such a good size for a lookup table, right?
If you want to know how many actual MB that is right,
It's 1.5 GB for the kerning table.
Not a very good idea, right?
So, you know, in handmade hero I'm assuming that like maybe there
would be something like, you know, a thousand maybe characters for
doing a Japanese translation, for example, maybe less maybe we'd only
be seven hundred or something, but point being 1.9 Meg's is a much
more manageable number for a look.
Table for kerning right?
And we can further compress that down by just using it B, because we
don't really need to throw them as that.
And then it comes down to about a half Meg for current information,
even if we were to have 700 characters, right?
And so, the point that I'm getting at and I see that we're coming to
the Q&A now.
So that means I should probably stop talking but we'll pick this up
tomorrow.
What I would like to do is find a way to compress font ranges down so
that we don't have a bunch of situations where Jimmy
So we don't have a bunch of situations where we are constantly having
to deal with a very expansive.
This sets just because we're trying to store.
Hi code Point values even though the total number of code points in
any given font pack might be very low.
So, that's what I'd like to do.
And we can take a look at some things about how we might do that
tomorrow for.
Now, let's go to the Q&A.
I really need.
Remember my drink.
I've got my drink today and now my throat sauce, or let's go ahead and
the Q&A.
I will be happy to take any questions that you might have.
Please prefix them with q:.
So I can see them.
No questions.
Midlow, the War.
I see the kerning and notepad compared to her as the more awful it
looks to me.
So yeah, I mean really are kerning is awful to it's just it's the
font.
Kerning is a big sore subject with me.
Nobody Does it right?
And its really annoying.
Pseudonym 73.
I realize that this is Uncharted Territory, but it seems to me that
font rendering is taking more time than the rest of the render.
Is that normal?
That's, that's, I don't think True by any stretch of the imagination.
I think, we've only spent like four or five days on how long have you
spent on fonts?
Let's see.
One, two, three.
These were not that.
4.
5.
6 7.
Wait.
89.
I lost count 1 2 3, 4 5 6.
78.
And remember, you know, it's really we did it with two different
things, so it's really 7 days.
That's nowhere.
Close to how long we spent on the render?
I think we end, we spent something like 20 days on the render, maybe
more.
I did a infographic of this a while back actually.
In fact, we could probably, we could probably look if
if it's Auntie witch,
We can probably look to see.
Highlights.
Right here.
So if we really wanted to, we could probably look and see at the graph
that I showed in this presentation, assuming that t, which is able to
actually play, which it doesn't look like it is.
Is there a reason I can't see anything here?
well in this presentation, I showed a graph of how many days we spent
on everything so that, you know, you can double-check that if you want
to see, but yeah, I think we spent quite a bit more on rendering but
As far as the part we're saying font rendering takes more time.
The rest of the renderer is actually true that fonts are fairly
complicated, right?
Because normally bitmaps have very little in the way of alignment
information, right?
Like bitmaps that for like Sprites typically have like one maybe two
reference points.
On them tops.
They don't have a concept of a baseline, they don't have the concept
of kerning, they don't have pairwise interactions, right?
So typically actually yes, fonts are more demanding usually on a
renderer than other things.
That's actually, that's actually is true because they have more
complexity than what you typically use for your regular character art.
For example, we are going to World art and so on.
D matsuki isn't Japanese evenly spaced.
It is unfortunately, our fonts doesn't doesn't know that.
I mean, we could have an exemption for Japanese and Chinese, which
say, hey, you only need to know about very simple spacing rules, just
for that language.
But you know,
I'm a queen Bray migraine.
Glad to at least cascoon.
A oh no.
Sorry about the migraine man.
Rob Robbie I was testing kerning in notepad word, wordpad, no kerning
there.
Where do you have synchronous?
Notepad is cast everything in Windows is uses the kerning.
It's built into the OS.
The size of don't forget the boilerplate.
Well, we didn't have time today though.
We were working on the fossil time so
John Carmack programmed, low-level graphics and got a Ferrari font
rendering guy.
Never got anything.
When are we going to go back to programming?
Cool Superstar things.
Well II, don't as someone who certainly chose to be a game programmer,
like John Carmack did.
I'm not trying to tell you that you shouldn't do it.
But the real answer to your question is the font rendering guy was
John.
Warnock he founded Adobe and he has so many more Ferraris than John
Carmack, if he wants them.
Like Adobe is a mini, many billion dollar company.
Whereas Carmack, probably sold, whatever his share of it was for, you
know, several million dollars or something like this, right?
Not billions of dollars.
So no, the font rendering guy pretty much crushed.
She's the game rendering died because business software is way more
profitable than game software by like one or two orders of magnitude
probably too.
Next met to I'm in my second year at Uni for programming and I am
still having problems getting my head around simple things.
My question is, how long did it take you to have a good understanding
of programming in general?
I would say,
Probably about ten years.
Or so.
I would say.
Pseudonym 73, fair enough.
Maybe it just seems like progress is slower for some definition of
progress.
Well, also, if you factor out how much of that time is fussing with
Windows, which is like a black box because remember in the renderer,
we were just writing our own code and that saves a lot of time.
So if you actually want to do the fair comparison, take the renderer
plus the windows platform code time, right?
G 7.
I'm confused.
Why the font rendering relies so much on windows isn't all this stuff
stored in the font files or is that harder without Windows text
metrics and stuff or to put it another way?
How would we do a be different if you're using SUV true pipe?
It wouldn't really.
Windows is just reading the truetype file and so Sean could presumably
give us those same things values, as you type, but the values are
still going to be bogus, they're not going to be left aligned
properly.
So we would still have the exact same problems we're having now, it's
really the true type files that are the problem if that makes sense.
On the msdn entry, you describe glossary ABC values.
Is better explained how Windows understands it?
Msdn you describe glossary, oops?
ah,
This is a good find my friend.
When two or more of those are displayed as a unit, usually only the
leftmost glyph contributes to the, a width of the run and only the
rightmost bits corners of the sea width of the Run.
However, this is not a strict rule.
If the first glyph in a run, is the narrow letter and the second good.
They're hella separate glyphs diacritical.
Mark might actually send beyond the letter.
Well, how do, you know?
Though, like how do we get the advance with?
That's what we want.
Right.
How do we get the advance with?
Great.
Nice job guys.
You couldn't come up with anything better than that for the acronym.
the under hang is a width of white space to the left or right of the
solid portion of living are supposed to the positive, a or C with as a
scribe for ABC with
Hang it.
Snows padding flowing it.
Yeah.
So unfortunately it doesn't really tell us how we can just get the
advance with
Windows, get Advanced width font.
Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Not because you use get care with 32 except it's document is not
working with truetype fonts, but we'll ignore that for second which is
the advanced with original characters or symbols in student experience
with is the distance that the cursor on the video display or print
head of a printer must advance for bring the next character.
In a string of text to get care with 32 function returns, you advance
with as an integer value for users, you can use to get for, okay.
Yeah, an application can retrieve actual character with data.
Person-to-person opentype fonts, fine.
Illustration shows the three components of a character with, yes, the
a spacing is the with to add to the current position before place the
character, you know what I'm gonna ignore.
I'm just curious what happens if we just ignore the documentation of?
It's a, the documentation is wrong.
So instead of get care with w and adding those together, right?
Which by the way, I could just do out here.
Instead of that, I'm just going to say like what if we just said, no,
we're going to just
Out to get care with 32.
You say it doesn't work.
We're going to not listen to you and we're going to try it anyway,
right?
so,
here we go.
The HDC is the global font device context.
The code point is the code point.
Code points code point there too.
And we're going to take an integer, right?
So in this width,
and then we will say care Advanced close this with
What does just what happens if we do that?
What's the deal?
Oops.
Like does it do anything?
Does it Crash and Burn?
Where are we at?
Well that sure looked like it worked so I think that documentation is
just flat out wrong but that's a separate issue and let's see how that
kerning looks.
Looks roughly about the same to me.
Compared to where we were at before.
Like it still looks a little wrong in some places like that's closer
than that in my mind, right?
so close close, but no cigar
Right.
That's what I would say.
It's a little hard to tell.
Maybe that's actually exactly right now.
I don't know.
Let's say, you know what?
It's gonna like a vertical rule in there.
Maybe that's exact now.
It's pretty darn close.
That's pretty darn close.
I think we've I think we've got it, folks.
That might be a little off.
That looks a little off to me.
Yeah, it looks like there's a little bit of difference right there.
So still not quite right, but pretty, darn close.
Danny wag do you use the graphics card at all?
When rendering, no.
Currently.
We do all our rendering ourselves.
At the moment.
Child Z.
I'm sure this has been answered.
So feel free to narrative true.
What are the features of C++ that you use that?
Keep you from using to spend on?
See right now operator overloading function overloading and declare
anywhere.
If you mean plain old see, but it's like.
C99 has declare anywhere now.
So that one's like less of less of one.
Let's see.
Robbie, when you say windows uses kerning, why is every letter never
overlapping in the space of the following letter of the followed
letter in your code, I see the letters.
Overlapping did I understand kerning wrong?
Well, I'm not really sure what you mean by that, like, you can see
that they're doing roughly.
The same thing that we're doing, right?
That is overlapping.
Right.
Overlapping overlapping.
So does that does that help?
D mitsuki.
Oh yeah.
Well, John Carmack also got to make rocket ships so he wins.
Sorry.
He doesn't win because if you think there's something even more boring
than font code, well, it's going to be banking code and that would
have been Elon Musk.
And right now he actually has a functioning rocket as opposed to John
Carmack who does not have a functioning rocket.
L.
Cuba.
Caleb, are you saying Adobe has better programmers than ID?
No, in fact, they probably have much worse programmers in it.
But like I said, your Market segment games are not the highest
profitable market segments, not by a long shot.
And so, the suggestion for the of the previous questioner was that,
oh, programming low-level Graphics is better than programming font
code because you're going to get a Ferrari.
It's like, nope, fault code actually could make you a lot more money
because
Like, if you look at the old, 2D Graphics companies that were doing
stuff like document layout, that's like Adobe.
And they're massively more wealthy than, then, people from ID
software, but it's tougher.
I mean, who has the better programmers?
We did probably has the better programmers, but that's neither here
nor there.
How good of a programmer you are has very little to do with how much
money you make.
D mitsuki.
Why didn't we use bitmap fonts in use ttf bitmap fonts are
cross-platform?
Are they not?
So these are cross-platform because we just extract them once.
They are now bitmap fonts, right?
So when we run the asset Packer, we now have bitmap fonts, we turned
two types into bitmap fonts and the reason we don't use bitmap fonts
as a source is because most have bad thoughts aren't very good, right?
Whereas truetype fonts tend to be very good and so it's easy.
It's better to pull them from there and then turn them into bitmap.
So we can use whatever we want.
Game Devi.
When I render on a GPU is their way without copying the render result
back to ram.
When I render on a GPU, is there a way without copying the render?
Result back to him a ray to do what?
I don't know what the a way to do.
What without copying the result back to ram.
Judah 12 Japanese isn't evenly, spaced some characters, like the upper
and lower brackets rely on kerning.
Yeah, I mean and to be clear, it's not evenly spaced.
It's just not kerned, those are different.
So in Japan, Japanese, I don't know of any circumstance where you
actually need pairwise kerning because you either have full width,
half with or punctuation, and you can just handle those and you don't
have to worry about like two different say hiragana,
Being space differently.
I don't think they do that as far as I know, but it's neither here nor
there because like I said, I'm not going to special case a language
like that.
So I want to make sure we work.
I want to make sure that we work by allowing Korean tables for any
language, even if it doesn't need them.
Danny Greg, how do you render?
The GPU.
you use a programming API that the GPU manufacture ships drivers for
such as opengl, direct3d mantle, Vulcan metal,
Glide in the old days.
Opencl Cuda.
Guitar freak favorite font for reading.
I don't know.
I don't know, I haven't spent that much time with it.
Jame Devi to display the result.
Okay, so, rereading your question, you're asking, when I render on the
GPU, is there a way to display the result without copying the reserve?
The render back to Ram?
I mean, the answer is obviously, yes, because the GPU is the thing
that's plugged in to the monitor.
So, it's actually the other way around.
There's no way to display the result of rendering without a GPU
Without copying it to the GPU.
If that makes sense.
I mean assuming you're talking about discrete part there's there's
integrated Graphics Parts, which all uses the same memory.
So there's no copy there obviously.
But you get the idea.
Gaston 5, I almost got a headache when you set alignment is not the
same as kerning, please expound so
Okay.
So in some languages, the actual concept of a box in which the letters
exist is formalized.
And Japanese is kind of one of them Japanese has what are called full
with characters and half with characters.
So you're either talking about a box that looks like this or a box
that looks like this.
It does not matter.
What characters are appearing next to each other, right?
If I actually go in here and write something in Japanese,
Right?
It does not matter.
What these two characters are the spacing in between them, only
depends on whether or not they were full or half with characters.
If this is a full-width character, it is then you advance from the
start of the character by a full width.
And if it's, if you had a half with character, right with, for
example, I don't know.
Which would be if I if I do it this way.
If I had a half with character, I would Advance by one half with but
at no time.
Do I actually need to consider
both characters to determine the advanced size.
That's the kerning part kerning is pairwise.
If you can determine the spacing of a language without using the pairs
of characters, it is not technically being current to the best of my
knowledge.
You would not say that phrase.
But even if you throw the kerning, throw this phraseology aside
because that's just typography language lettering.
The important thing to internalize is that there are pairwise
spacings.
And non pairwise facings, right?
A language might be entirely composed of non pairwise facings.
The character itself may always determine how much you move to get to
the next character and you may never need to know what that next
character was.
And if that's true, you don't need pairwise spacing tables.
You don't need a current what we're calling kerning table.
You don't need that because you would never actually need to look up
into it.
You can just look up into a 1D table, right?
It's like one day versus 2D table, right?
Kerning is a 2d thing, it's too.
It's, it's code points.
This way, code points this way, I have to look up the one I started
with.
And the one I'm going to and I find a particular value in a 2d table.
Now you can compress the 2D table down by just having Korean pear
arrays or whatever you want, right?
But it's still a 2d look up at Heart by contrast.
Something like Japan, I would argue is a 1D look up, right?
Whatever the character is tells me how far to advance that's all I
need to know pretty much right.
And someone was saying maybe not the punctuation, like, maybe if you
have these guys, right?
And you want those things to overlap properly, right?
Maybe you do still have it and so you can imagine that, well, we're
not completely wasting the kerning table because there is like, one or
two glyphs that use it, right?
But on the whole, if you were only dealing with languages like
Japanese, you've never make a crafting table, you just special case
these two characters because they're the only ones that ever going to
use it, right?
You wouldn't go add a table that allows you to look up arbitrary.
Pairwise things between, you know, 1000 characters on this side and
1,000 characters on the other side, right?
Kubrick Caleb.
Would you rather have a CPU with more cores than a GPU or enough clock
Cycles to outperform the GPU with software rendering?
I'm not sure, I understand the question.
Judah 12 said you can look at Japanese language layout, requirements.
Under the W3 for more information.
Which I will do.
Yeah.
And that kind of to me does does specifically say exactly what I just
said, which is that.
It's very regular eyes.
Debasing so you really probably would not care about kerning, right?
You would do you would handle it, you would not make a generalized
lookup system for Japanese because it just doesn't need that kerning,
right?
But yeah.
So there is a Section 3 though that says Sue megumi right and that
does support kerning.
So, you know, I mean, we could argue that we're just being supportive
of other of more expressive Japanese typeset typefaces, right?
If that makes any sense.
You can see it in there.
It's, they've got an example of a type of a Japanese type base that
actually does use kerning, right.
They suggest that that is not a common thing.
But, you know,
Robbie went thinking, Adobe has a market value of over 40 billion
dollars.
Why?
No great programmer wants to do a better photo shop.
I think part of it is because a lot of that is because Photoshop is
the standard.
Like, you know, it's hard to take on the established understood market
for Photoshop.
I think that's a really hard business problem.
I don't think it's as simple as shipping a program.
That's better than Photoshop.
And then everyone just switches to it, you know?
It's like the standard format.
Everyone uses psd's artist deliver psd's you know every artists are
trained on it so it's pretty hard.
I don't know why someone doesn't go after that market you know
holistic way but I suspect.
It's just
It's lower hanging fruit elsewhere.
I mean when you can make Instagram, which is a way of sending pictures
that look worse than they did, when you originally took them and you
can get bought for a billion dollars or whatever it was.
Why would you bother running a program as complicated as Photoshop?
You know.
I mean, so if you're just trying to make money, even adobe's kind of a
dumb idea because you actually had to make a program that was useful.
Instead you can make like, Snapchat or something, right?
Which takes almost no programming effort and make way more money.
So, if you're just trades chasing the money, it's more about just
coming up with, like, a fiddly little idea that you can convince
people is like a web thing and then you just get Acquired and you
never even have to even make money, right?
So, yeah.
So
Why don't people go out to the 40 billion?
Well there's even easier money to Chase.
You know, and I think that's probably the answer is, if you're just
looking to make money, even photoshop's way too much way more
programming than you should have to do, right?
Way way more programming than should have to do.
Damn it.
Sookie, there are actually a lot of people competing with Photoshop
and you are using one of those products on stream right now.
Yeah.
Just some degree.
I mean, not really though.
That, like, Mischief is not a Photoshop replacement.
It's a very different program that doesn't accomplish the same things,
right?
I actually don't know of any products that compete with Photoshop.
All the props, I can think of are four different market segments.
Like gimp or corita which are free are, the closest thing is, I know
to competitors, but I don't know of any commercial competitors to
photoshop.
There used to be some like Coral drawn, fractal painter and stuff like
this.
And I don't even know what happened to those.
They went away, got bought multiple times and I don't know and like
high-end people, you know, they use 3D paint stuff, like Mari or
mudbox and and stuff like that, but, you know, those aren't those
aren't Photoshop competitors either.
All right, I think I'm going to wind it down.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home with the source code,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade here at our org and it
comes to the source code.
Every night I upload it.
When we're done programming here, and you can grab it.
We also have a patreon page, want to support the video series.
You can subscribe to that, we have a forum site, you can go to ask
questions or pickup Community ports, to hit of him, a hero to other
platforms stuff like that.
There's also a tweet bot that tweets the schedule at you.
So if you want to catch the series live that's the place to go and if
you would like to catch it live tomorrow I will of course be back
here, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time, same time, same place.
So yeah if you want to come check out our I guess probably what we'll
do is start down that language path and try to support another
language.
Cleanly.
With our van system, if you would like to come along on that little
journey, they'll probably be the next couple days and probably try to
finish up all of our font stuff by the end of next week if we can
because I think we pretty much got everything under control.
We just want to do, like I said, some support for multiple language,
kind of stuff.
So, love to see you back here for that, until then have fun coding.
And I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.