Start recording.
Okay, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on stream.
No engines, no, libraries.
It is just us.
And looking at the complete process of game development right from the
little tiny list little pixels that make up our game screen to the AI
that controls the characters or anything in between, we show how to do
it and right now we're at a Crossroads in some sense just yesterday we
finished
Our asset pack files and they're pretty darn cool.
The stuff that we engineered for them.
I think is pretty darn neat.
Considering we didn't take very long to make them in, they're awfully
powerful at this point.
So I'm kind of psyched about that and there's really two things we
could do.
Like I said, yesterday, one thing that we can do now, actually?
I guess there's three things we could do.
Even the first thing we could do is go back over the asset pack file
stuff and just take a look if there's any features we want to add any
little things that we think we might want to do differently or you
know, we had
Talk about some things like adding the ability to suppress assets from
other pack files.
So like if you wanted to you know, patch or do things like this, we
can go do that.
The other thing that we could do is we could move on to working on the
asset memory management.
But, you know, there's always the third thing, which is like we've got
two days left in the week, Thursday and Friday.
And so, the asset Mary memory management is going to be a pretty big
deal.
That's going to be a hard thing for us to do because it's the hardest
memory management.
It will have to do in the entire project.
It's a virtual memory system basically because we want to have a
system that will optimally.
Well, not optimally, that's probably provably impossible but that will
very efficiently manage a certain prescribed footprint for our asset
data and it will cycle through the art assets for the game through
that system, based on what the most Necessary Things Are For any given
scene in the game, right?
So it'll kind of be trying to think about what needs to be brought in
and what needs to be done.
And and that's going to be, I think, you know, I one of the more
Tweaky things that we do on handmade hero where it's going to be kind
of a little bit finicky and so, you know, that might be a better thing
to start on Monday.
And just do, you know, this week, we're going to start on that rather
than doing a Thursday, Friday thing and then jumping the weekend,
right?
So the other thing we could do third thing we could do.
Is something else.
And so, what I'm going to do here again, I'll briefly mention if we do
coding today which we probably will do some coding today.
I don't have anything planned for the Blackboard that would take an
hour day.
155 is the day that we are on.
So if you pre-ordered the game on handmade, here it up org and want to
download the source code that goes with what we're doing today.
Download day 154 source code.
That's the source code from yesterday and that's what I'll be starting
with today.
So what you want to do is start out with that and you will be right
exactly where I
I am when I start now.
And what am I going to start doing?
Well, I am going to go look.
To do list to see if there's anything else that we might want to pick
out.
That's a two-day thing or something like this.
That we might, you know, that that might be something we should do
instead of, you know, instead of what we're doing before.
So, hey, guess what we did this?
So that's all gone, right?
We actually did did these as well, kind of, I mean, I think we really
just pretty much did all of this, so we kind of just have these left.
There could go fix some audio bugs.
We have this sort of on the reload system.
We wanted to flush the red cubes before we load.
In the dll to avoid any crashes, that might happen.
I don't actually know we haven't ever actually had one, so it might
not be a problem because it's not something that will have ever happen
in the shipping game.
So unless we're having trouble in development, we don't really need to
care.
And so the question is like, is there anything else you might want to
do?
You know, we've got, we haven't really done.
We haven't done fonts, I don't know if that's a two-day thing.
Might be a little more into anything if I want to walk you through the
whole process.
And so I feel like debug code wants to wait for that.
So in our architecture exploration we got metagame savegame stuff,
these are
Things that we will start on, I think in kind of going with the with
the game itself.
So I don't know.
I don't know.
Let's think about this for a second.
so, I guess what I would say is,
Yeah, I guess what I would say about these is, you know, we could just
do something fun for two days, just for no apparent reason, you know.
Uh-huh.
So maybe, you know, maybe we just do something kind of kind of, maybe
we can just pick something that's going to be, kind of fun, for two
days, something kind of weird.
I don't see anything particularly obvious.
But, you know, the one that kind of jumps out at me, here would be,
you know, what about this guy, right?
Systems are pretty darn simple at the end of the day and that might be
a kind of interesting thing just to, because there is something you
notice, I've got it up here on the renderer.
It might be interesting to have that in place because I think they
might slow down the renderer a lot.
And it might be interesting to see how much they slow it down and to
see if we want to put them into the renderer in a more specific way,
just so we can, you know, play around with that a little bit.
So maybe we'll do particle systems.
I don't know.
That seems like kind of a fun thing.
I know what you guys think.
Particle systems.
Maybe we'll try that.
Let's just play with that for two days and then we'll start on the
asset memory management stuff tomorrow.
So let's take a look here at what you know what I would do for
particle systems.
Okay, I'll do a brief kind of diagram on the Blackboard, will get me
steef up and running here.
Blackboard at Art and I don't know, it's just kind of loading, I
think.
Come on, Miss Chief, you can do it, you can do it.
I know we're asking it to do a lot.
Are handmade hero.
Blackboard is so massive.
Now, it just kind of goes and goes and goes and goes at infinitum.
That's why.
Usually you leave it running.
But of course, I had to reboot the machine recently, to do the the
Microsoft Windows update to fix that.
Lovely thing they have where you people can root your machine.
All right, so let's talk about particle systems briefly.
Just
So you can have a little bit of perspective on what these things are.
So particle systems.
And, you know, if you think about how game Graphics Works in general,
we've got sort of a few different buckets that we put things into
depending on what it is that we are trying to draw, okay?
And so, in a 2-D game, for example, you've kind of already seen
actually two of these buckets that
Have implemented already in the course of building.
The handmade hero engine is things that I know that we will want.
And so we built them in.
I showed how to do them in that and that sort of thing.
And remember what they were is ground tiles, right?
Are the things and and Sprites, right?
And so if you remember, we did these in kind of different ways.
They both flow through the same renderer.
But like when we did the ground tiles, right?
What we did is we broke the world up until like these tiles, right?
And we made sure that they would, you know, be seamless.
So then we drew things in them, you
It would work or whatever and things would be continuous across the
lines.
But we fundamentally thought of them as like a grid where we would
paint into the grid and as things came on the screen we would, you
know, draw the new tile to put it on the screen and so on.
And we had to think of it about it that way as opposed to about a
bunch of Sprites.
Because fundamentally speaking, the actual graphic that we were trying
to represent, he's a whole world worth of non-repeating texture,
right?
It's this gigantic infinitely.
Retching thing that represents the ground and I didn't want it to
repeat.
I didn't want to be some cheesy tiled grass thing or whatever, right?
I wanted to be unique everywhere.
And I wanted to be able to us to do any kind of special effects you
wanted in there, like drawing and Footprints are drawing in.
You know like a river or anything like that.
And so fundamentally speaking what we basically made here was like a
giant virtual canvas and we draw into the giant virtual canvas and
only fill in the parts that you can see on the screen because
generating the whole thing would be completely impractical.
Oil.
So that was kind of one thing that we did in the other thing that we
did was Sprites which are just you know the standard things that we
make little characters up out of, you know, we'll take a head Sprite
and a body spray and a torso Sprite right there, rectangles that we
put little bit maps in that have an alpha Channel.
And that's, you know, what makes up our little guys, right?
So, you know, when we, when we run the game and we have our stuff in
here, right?
We've got kind of this little little dude, and he's made up of three
pieces.
And then we have some other stuff there and we'll test things and
we've got the ground textures and of course,
He's that sort of stuff and Sprites are very good tool, right?
To build up a 3D game, they can express a lot of things to the players
and they're a good way for us to take art assets that an artist can
paint and put them in, you know, bring them alive, right?
And so they're they're one of the oldest and most, you know, sort of
their real Workhorse of a 2-D game, right?
And sometimes even in 3D games, you'll see them.
But in 2D games they're like, they're the, the bread and butter,
right?
So we have those two things, but there's another thing, right?
That kind of happens, which is that sometimes we have things that
don't have a specific shape, right?
Sometimes we have you know, and maybe the word we would use for these
are phenomenon, right?
Right, like things like liquids, right?
It was well, smelling smelling it literacy, ladies and gentlemen,
liquids, you know, gases, you know, missed right things like this, and
these sort of a more fist shapes are very
For cult to describe, in terms of the things that I'm talking about
because an artist can't really draw the shape of a free-flowing missed
like, a, you know, Miss that kind of swirls around on the ground or it
doesn't really make sense.
It has to react to things and it's kind of this continuous shape that
deforms in weird ways and there are early pieces to it, right?
And we've got other things like, you know, smoke Trails, right?
Are this sort of thing, explosions, you know, very common in the, you
know, shootie kinds of games.
You've got just a
whole bunch of things that these sort of natural sort of Amorphis
phenomenon and they are just not that amenable to doing to tackling
with either of the two things that we built so far.
So what you typically want to do these sorts of things is that's where
you use a particle system, right?
And a particle system.
Particle system need to go back to grade school here.
Clearly to practice my handwriting.
A particle system is exactly what its name sort of suggests that it is
it is a series of little particles that are treated together to form a
system and the
System itself is supposed to represent one of these bigger phenomenon.
So for example, if we did want to make a trail of smoke or, you know,
a fire or whatever else, what we might do is create a particle system
to capture the sort of feel of a fire.
And that is how we would solve that problem in game development and
there's levels of complexity of these particle systems and a lot of
other things we could talk about.
I'll mention some of them briefly, but I'll simply say, the basic idea
behind it.
So, what you typically see?
See in a particle system on the effects house side of particle system.
So this is the kind of effects.
You might see in a Hollywood movie, kind of pearl girl system and also
in a game that's being kind of authored, in some sense typically what
you have in a particle system is you have a thing called an
Her.
Right.
And as its name implies it is some kind of a shape on the screen whose
job it is to emit particles, right?
So, you know, let's say we're making a fire.
So we've got, you know, some log, a log Sprites or something on the
ground.
And we want there to be a fire that comes up from those log Sprites.
So we place a emitter for our fire particles onto this place on the on
the logs, right?
And that emitter typically has some things like parameters like you
know,
Shape.
It is, you know, where do the particles start?
It has a bunch of parameters, for how the particles behave, right?
But the basic idea is that it's going to take this shape, and it's
going to put little points, right?
It's going to spawn little points at the location inside that shape,
right?
And, again, particle system.
Basically means these are particles their little points their little
points in space.
Right?
Then what's going to happen is, as these are spawned, they are going
to have some kind of simplistic.
Simulation to follow.
So, what they might do, for example is be told that they should kind
of have a random Direction within some upward-facing cone and they
will kind of flow out in that direction.
They will kind of come up and as they come up, maybe they'll wobble or
something like this, you know?
And as they get taller, they will go from being, you know, maybe down
here, when we want to render, them will do one thing.
And when they get up, cure, to run them to do something else, and that
kind of gets into the Second Step, which is we have these particles.
They're going to start down here, they're going to move.
Right.
They're going to, they're going to be simulated up.
New ones will spawn, and those will move.
And so you kind of end up with this kind of upward motion particle
kind of thing, right?
And then what you do is you have these points right in your particle
system and what you do is you end up on any given frame having a bunch
of locations where all the particles are right after you have updated
them after you have stimulated them forwards.
And at that point, what you will do to render them is, you'll
typically do something that involves putting down sir.
Out of a fuzzy blurry, kind of a shape down over the top of them that
may be like kind of dark in the middle but get kind of weak towards
the edges.
Right?
And the idea behind that is they kind of form, this kind of Blobby,
you know, kind of amorphous shape by sort of, you know, being dark in
the middle and and sort of amorphous at the edges.
So you get kind of the Shifty sort of again like fire gaseous or
liquid kind of effect Happening by the fact that the way that you're
feeling it in kind.
Blends the shapes together.
And there's no, like hard-edged outline of what the shapes actually
are, right?
So that is what a particle system is, right?
And it's pretty simple to think about, if you followed handmade hero
so far, it's actually not very difficult to think about what a
particle system might entail implementation wise.
Because when you think about it, really, all of these things are
fairly obvious how we Implement them there.
Are there things that we've or you done in a lot of ways, right?
All we need is some
The particles like some way of tracking, what the particles are and we
just need to make up for I Loop or something that goes over each
particle every frame and simulates it forward and we've done the
equations of motion on handmade hero.
You know, a little bit about that.
There's really not much more to it for updated particles.
So really, the only thing that's a little wonky is how we would
actually render it.
And to start out we could certainly just shove it down the steam.
Pipe line that we've been using by basically taking a Sprite, you
know, that is sort of a filled Blobby circle like that.
And just rendering one of those Sprites at the
Ian that is indicated by the particle.
So what I want to do to kind of get you warmed up to particle systems.
I'm looking at the clock here.
It's 5:25.
We started like about 15 minutes late.
We're only 10 minutes in the Stream.
So we've got a good 50 minutes to go here.
Go go to about 6:15 to get our our in.
So in 50 minutes should be plenty of time for me to kind of get you a
little warmed up to the idea of these particle systems, just take a
look at what the code looks.
Like at a very simplistic level and we won't try to make anything
fancy.
But we will try at the end of that 50 minutes to get to a place where
you can kind of see the protocol system operating.
So what I'm going to do again, and we say this very often on handmade
hero, I like to say it very, very often.
Don't overthink it.
You just want to make the simplest thing.
First, you write right now, you know, like especially out there.
You've never seen a particle system before.
Don't go over thinking, it just go.
What is the bare?
Minimum thing?
I would need to do to get something on the screen.
That's what you focus on and then we build from there, right?
We always
Has built from there and you've seen me do it many times on stream.
We start with something simple.
We start with something, we understand.
And then it becomes very clear to us through the crafting of that how
it needs to start integrating up and becoming a more General component
of handmade Hero's engine as a whole, right?
And so don't overthink, it just go exactly what I just said in the
Stream.
That's exactly.
You know, on the Blackboard, that's exactly what I do.
Let's just do that in the simplest possible way first, and then, we
will start to generalize out from there and generalize out from there,
right?
So okay, so let's start just by saying, you know what?
I've got are sort of our came straight here, and I'm just going to
straight up say that I'm gonna want these particle systems, right?
So, I'm just going to want, I don't know a particle, right?
And I just want to track that list of part, right?
I said, I want a group of particles.
I'm just going to say flat out.
You know what?
We've just got some particles here.
How many particles do we have?
I have no idea.
Let's say, we have 64 a particles because that's how many I'm feeling
like doing again.
Just literally just the simplest possible thing.
To get things started.
And I will say that there is a next particle or something like this,
right?
All right?
And so in our particle we're going to need a couple things obviously.
Like I said, we need a position, we need a location where the particle
is.
We need maybe a velocity for the particle so that's how fast it should
be going.
And maybe I also want something like a color for the particle so that
we know what color we want the particle to be.
And, you know, I mean like I said, I don't want to get
it to overcomplicate it first, so that maybe
That will allow us to place some particles down and watch them do
something on the screen which is all we really want to do for today to
get warmed up.
Okay?
So let's go ahead and do that.
Let's go in here to our our game update and render.
And again, this is kind of game update.
And render is the main Loop for the game.
It's kind of our home for misfit toys, right?
It's the place that everything lives right now, that hasn't matured to
the point where it breaks off into its own sort of like a
self-contained thing.
Right?
So we still have like our enemy code and stuff in here because we
haven't really gotten to that and that sort of stuff when we have our
ground chunk stuff in here because we haven't really decided how those
will be doing, you know, their final thing, we did all the composite
work and stuff like that, but we haven't actually gone and said, oh,
you know, how does the world, you know, it generation integrate with
this because until we have our sort of our game running and generating
world to the player to explore, we don't really know how we want to do
our ground chunks.
And so, what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to pick a place here.
I'm just going to go down to the bottom where we have.
We appended like our test code.
And you can see right here is where our render updates are just right
before the render updates.
I'm just going to go ahead and say particle System test, right?
That's all I'm going to do.
And so what I want to do here, oh you know what?
I forgot one of the thing and I guess I'll tell you.
Well, you know, I don't really have to do that yet.
I can just show you why we need it as it comes up.
So what I want to do here is I want to Loop through all the particles,
okay?
Just want to Loop through all the particles.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to start at the first particle.
I'm going to go to the end of the particle count.
Right, here's that array.
So I'm just going to say, I want to go till the end of that.
And then I want to go ahead and increment that particle index.
And so I'm just going to Loop through the particles again absolutely
nothing fancy here.
I'm not thinking about speed, not thinking about any of the things
that we might think about.
Eventually, when we go to say, we want the process to be fast or
capable whatever, nope, singing very, very basic, keeping it very
simple.
So I'm going to Loop through the particles and on each particle.
What I would like to do.
First, I would like to simulate the particle, right?
So, I want to do stimulate the particle forward in time, right?
And then, I also want to render the protocol, and I have two choices.
One thing I can do is I can render the particle and then simulate it.
The other thing I do is simulate the particle and then render it,
right?
And the consequences of the two of those is, if I simulate it after I
render, it means that the results will not be displayed to the next
frame.
And so it has some benefits when you do that, it means that when
particles are spawned, they are drawn.
At the location, they are spawned rather than being simulated right
away to a new one, but it has some downsides, which is that you won't
react to user motion that happened on that frame until the next frame,
right?
So I'm gonna do is I'm going to simulate first and then I'm going to
render second to avoid that problem.
And we'll deal with the fact that things move when they are spawned.
We'll deal with that baby in a different way or we'll try to address
that in some other way, right?
So now, I want to do regular protocol now rendering particles like I
said, doesn't really seem like something that will
be very difficult if we,
Want to do a simple test case.
What I can do is I can take this sort of drawbitmap call right, where
we call into the renderer.
And what I can do is I can just use our existing renderer to draw our
particles for us without really happy to do anything.
Any other work, right?
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to again leverage that call
we can take a look at what that call does, right.
You can see draw a bitmap and all we want to do is pass our particle
bitmap.
So what I'd like to do is you know, make sort of
Of a test bitmap so we'll just call it test particle, right?
And we'll put that in the game safer now and then I need to pass it.
Whoops.
Sorry, that's the buffer.
My bad don't want to draw to the test particle.
I want to draw it to the actual render output.
So that's, that's a little bit of mistake there.
Sorry, cut and paste it from a bad location.
What I actually want to do is just run to our standard render group.
That's that that was all.
This is old code, this is old code.
What can I say?
Yeah, there's a reason it's all if zero doubt, we could probably get
rid of it, but we may want it again when we do the lighting test.
So my bad, sorry, you know, how it happened.
Of time.
So we want to push him out to our render grips.
A here, we're going to draw this thing.
We're going to draw a test particle and then we need to say like how
high that you know, how big we want that to skirt protocol to be.
I don't think we want to be very big.
These supposed to be like little small particles will tune that later.
So it doesn't really matter.
But, you know, just pick something, a tenth of a meter is what I
picked their 0.1.
All of our units are going to be in meters, I believe there.
So that's roughly what?
That should be.
Then we have the offset and the offset is just the, you know, offset
from the placement of this particle, which is
I don't think we really need to have it all, so I'm just going to say
you don't really need to offset it and then we're going to have the
color.
Right?
And so I don't actually remember although, you know that I think about
it.
The offset is actually the only thing that we use for positioning now.
So actually, I guess technically that positioning is possibly going to
be actually.
Yeah, that might actually be the full position because we probably
won't need to use the transform.
We wouldn't want to use the whole transform system for every
A particle and we'll see kind of why later.
So maybe that's that was the wrong thing to say there.
I think maybe the easiest thing to do would be let's actually pass
that position.
So we know that the particle itself does have a position.
So we'll go ahead and pass that position down.
And then we know that the particle, like I said, also has a color.
So we'll go ahead and pass the color to it as well.
And that is how we would render a particle, right?
And so, let's go ahead and we'll typo there, got to access that off
game State.
And so now we need to do is we need to find a way to make this test.
Oracle.
And if you remember correctly, we actually have a way of drawing a
sphere.
I believe we had some kind of a test for sphere thing that we were
using for our normal Maps.
I think makes fear makes here diffuse map, right?
And so what I'm interested to know is
Our makes fear diffuse map thing.
In fact, we even already have one might be another question.
I think we do.
Okay, so there we go.
Oh, we do test diffuse.
Right right there.
So I don't know.
Test a few Smite already kind of be what we want.
We should totally see because really, that would be that kind of a
Blobby shape that I was talking about.
So we'll see here.
We'll see if make a sphere, just diffuse map ends up, being something
that we want.
In that case, we don't even need a test particle, we can just use test
diffuse as
Are bitmap and that should actually be fine.
I think we'll find out in a second, actually.
All right, so I think we can do that.
Although I also don't know.
Let's see, we need anything else here and I don't think we do.
So we can just go ahead and do it like that.
Push bitmap.
What do we need?
We need render Group, which we've got bitmap, then we've got a float
of each.
Ooh, that's a V2, my bad.
We want our particles.
Presumably to be fully 3D, so that they can kind of go up in Z as well
since we do have Z Stacks.
So that's it for rendering the particles similar in the particles.
Forward in time, we've got a position for the particle, right?
And so this is going back to the equations of motion.
Again, you know, exactly the ones I'm talking about, which basically
we could do a very simplified version here because we don't have an
acceleration for the particle at the moment so we don't have to
account for celebration.
So all we have to do to simulate velocity is just say, well, whatever
the velocity of the particle was which are saying we're going to track
per particle, whatever, the velocity was.
We want to go ahead and take that velocity.
and,
And update it by and multiply it, by the time step.
So however long it was supposed to be between last frame in this Frame
it will it will move the particle by however much that was.
And we do have DT up here somewhere right there.
Input dt4 frame right?
And so we can go ahead and just multiply out our particles and that is
pretty much the most basic the simplest particle update Loop.
Now, at this point, our particles aren't even like placed in the world
anywhere.
They would literally just be always rendering like at the origin you
know what I mean?
Which is kind of wonky.
So we'll want to take care of that as well, but that in and of itself,
right there is the basics of a particle of rendering Loop.
Now, at this point we don't have any, you know, reason to, we don't
even omit the particles anywhere.
We don't even really start the particles up.
So all of their colors are going to be 0 0, 0 0.
So presumably, they won't draw right?
Although I guess I
Could go ahead and see what happens if I just force a color, just so
we can make sure that we're actually drawing something.
But, yeah, you know, since they have no Alpha, they won't draw.
Doesn't look like, I'm actually seeing any particles here though.
So, let me go ahead and step in here, just so we can make sure that
we're actually drawing things through our through our render group for
us.
And also since it's been a while since we've done this test diffuse, I
want to make sure that that that's actually valid as well.
So we have a bunch of things here that I would I would
To go ahead and validate first.
So I'm going to go ahead and break in there.
Let me go to handmade dot CPP and just take a look and make sure that
everything's kosher.
Although, you know, the other thing I do actually also want to do is I
need to make sure I set the render transform Stanley for these guys
because we never, you know, we set the render transform in here for
all of our enemies and stuff like that.
And that's not something that I actually ever did.
You know, if you can look in here, we set the, the global Alpha and we
Set some other stuff here.
So we should probably make sure that we clean that stuff up first to
let me go ahead and do that before we step in just so I can know that
we've set everything up, you know, relatively sanely been a while
since we do anything with the renderer.
So you know, sometimes it's a little bit crazy.
All right, so I'm going to go in here and just make sure that it's and
make sure that we've sets kind of all the things that are render a
State might have just so we can make sure that we're at a clean
starting point before we start kind of playing around with it.
And also, let me see about setting that render group transform as
well, which of course requires me to page back into my brain.
How we ended up to architect AR for transforms?
I might also want to stop the incessant piano music.
We should probably have a kill switch for our music now that we
implemented audio, we neglected to actually Implement any way to
making it.
Stop, you know, which can be kind of tough.
So we've got the render transform their right.
And if we look at that render transform, we're going to want that
render transform to be controlled for the particle group.
And so I want to, I want to take a look at at the places where we set
the transfer get see there that offset P getting set to the ground at
some point.
I would like to make sure that we kind of clear that out for now
again, just so we're not looking at any kind of residual stuff from
our old from the code.
They rendered the entities.
All right.
So now what
Going to do is, I'm just going to step into that code and I want to
validate that we're doing things sanely there.
Let's take a look here.
So, there we go.
So each time through this Loop, I'm going to take a look at the
particles and I stretching all the values to be 0, right?
Which they all are, right.
Everything's all zeros here, all zeros here.
And then I'm going to take a look into the when we do a push it back
up here and I just want to make sure that test diffuse is actually
something that's validly.
Drawable, because I don't actually know that it is.
I guess, you know, the other thing that I could do
Do there.
You know it now that I think about it, maybe I'll just take that out
of the equation entirely for the moment because what I realize is
actually the other things I could do is I could just say I'm going to
draw a shadow, right?
Because we know that that works properly.
I don't have to go back and look at the test if you stuff, which was
kind of things.
We were only really doing for our lighting test, so there that should
definitely render something.
And so, if that doesn't, we've got kind of another up, positioning bug
that we have to that.
We have to go address, right?
So yeah, let's see.
Yeah, so it should I mean, that should be showing us something and
it's not.
So I feel like I've got some little bug in there that I want to take
care of.
I can also make, oops, make sure that it's very large so that there's
no chance that it wouldn't be showing up, right?
So we should be seeing something showing up there, right?
So I think we've got, you know, problem with our render transferring.
So, I'm going to go ahead and step in there because we should be able
to draw something with that render group at that location and see like
a little kind of
Blobby thing show up if that makes any sense.
So, let's go ahead and take a look at what's happening with the push
bitmap call.
Obviously, it's going to get the bitmap from the asset system, which
it does, and then it's going to go through here and try to put that
bitmap on to the renderer stack.
So, let's see what the size ends up.
Being for that guy, here's the size, that that gets computed after it
seems like totally reasonable and saying, then we go ahead and do some
alignment on that guy, which puts us in
See where that position even seems relatively sane.
This of course, is the part that I was a little bit confused about I
wasn't sure because it's been a long time since we did any rendering.
We've been in kind of asset land for a little bit.
And so it when we do our transform here, right?
What's the transform actually saying it's doing standard perspective
here, it looks like right.
Our orthographic flag is set to zero, we've got the offset.
P, which is going to be nothing.
And I guess, I don't know for sure that the offset piece should in
fact, be nothing.
That's, I guess a good question.
Then we've also got the scale which is, which is regular, which is the
1.0 scale so that, you know, that looks pretty sane to me.
So I don't actually know why that is, you know, why that is being
grumpy with us.
Because it looks like that's a fairly same thing and I'll go ahead and
and double-check but looks like that's a fairly same thing to, you
know.
To want to inspect, right?
So, of course, we've got that nasty problem of Visual Studio where it
doesn't.
Let us inspect anything when we step to the end of a function.
All right, Visual Studio.
How about if I jumped here, could be inspected, then would you?
Let us see it.
Thank you.
So that seems assuming those are in pixels still, you know, that all
seems relatively sane to me.
I don't know about you guys but that seems fine to me.
Me.
I don't know why that would be a problem, right?
That looks like it's on screen and well.
You know, I'll be honest.
No, I guess it really doesn't seem like it's on screen, mmm.
Because if that Center, does that centered about 00, let's take a look
at the drawing code for that.
Maybe, maybe I'm actually wrong about that because obviously we have a
1920 by 1080 screen so I would like to just verify that that's in a
same location.
I guess, the other way to do that would be to
Sort of gang on to the hero if that makes sense.
So, for example, if I wanted to, I could just go ahead and make sure
that this guy was actually rendering all of the particles, right where
the hero is, you know.
So that would that would give me that extra level kind of assurance
there if you will let me take a look at that.
So there's the hero.
Okay, so I was wrong.
I guess we were just off screen.
000 was not on the screen because you can see at the bottom of the
hero now.
Now there's like all these little there's that really dark black dot
and that's exactly, that's exactly what we wanted to see.
So, right The Next Step here for doing our particle system is we're
going to have to actually give these particles some color and give
these particles some actual life to them, right?
Because they're just sitting in one place right now, and that's like
completely useless, right?
So what we'd like to do is we would like to go ahead and actually
start using the particle color and we need some way of
In the actual particles, like getting the particles themselves to sort
of exist for that, lack of a better term.
And so what I'd like to do is I'd like to do something that spawned
some particles every frame, right?
So maybe what I'll do here is I'll just do like particle, spawn Index,
right?
And I'll do particle.
Spawn index is less than I don't know.
For this one for particles of frame, something like that.
And all I'm going to do here is I'm going to do is basically a round
robin scheme.
I'm just going to take this value, right?
Right?
The starts at zero and I'm going to say gamestate next particle,
right?
So I'm going to say that the particle that we're going to spawn is
just equal to whatever game State particles is, plus a get whatever
that next product goes and then I'm going to advance next particle,
right?
Then I'm going to say, if the next particle at that point went over
the size of the array.
So, if it's gotten to the end of that game State array,
Then I'm just going to go back to the beginning, right?
That's all I'm going to do.
That's that's it right?
I'm going to say go back to 20 and so all I'm doing is I'm stepping
through the park or a sporting protocols and when I get to the end I
go back to beginning an overwrite, it just like a circularbuffer.
I just keep over writing older particles with newer particles, right?
That's all it's going to do.
So, when I do this, I'm going to set the particle P, right?
Whatever that particle P.
I'm going to set that equal to, let's say just 000 again for now, just
back to the base.
But this time, I'm going to set that particle DP, right?
The the velocity of the particle, if you will, I'm going to set that
velocity of the particle to go upwards, right?
Just Z up words like so.
And of course I don't actually know if we really want to do that or
why upwards but I'm going to I'm just going to let that
Do its thing at the moment, right?
So let's go ahead and see here.
Oh and I forgot one more thing we need to set the color to something,
right?
So we'll set the color right now to just be.
Yeah, I guess we'll just
Make it Fulbright for the moment.
Okay.
So let's see.
We've got our guys, they don't see any moving upwards.
I wonder if we need to, like I said, I don't really remember where we
left it on, RZ stuff.
So, yeah, so there we go.
So now we just got these little guys, moving upwards, right?
And when they could only go so far because at some point, right?
The the circular buffer will come around and kill them.
I can spawn less particles per frame if I wanted to and then they
would get higher before being replaced, right?
You can see
And there's no kind of variability in the particles yet so they just
kind of Stack up there and just make like this very even cylinder,
right?
But even so we're starting to get the hang of it right.
We're starting to see that there are some little particles here.
What can we do next?
I'd like to do a little bit something, you know, to kind of get that a
little bit more like a particle system.
So one thing I'd like to do is I'd like to make our particles Fade Out
over time, right?
Like when they're spawned, I want them to be there and then when they
get to the end, I want them to kind of fade out, right?
We should also do for the love of God people.
Let us stop playing the music.
Okay.
No more music launch this time that was just a loading call my bad.
Where is the?
Where is the call?
That actually plays this music?
We got the volume change who actually plays.
Oh, so you know we could do we could just make this music be something
that's going to end immediately, right?
Or we could make it be something that's that's that's not there or
something like that.
I don't know what can we do?
Because if we don't I guess we have to make a thing that just the
change volume, call can handle a null pointer.
That doesn't seem actually particularly bad, right?
So we could do that, we could just make it so that handmade audio.
If we just wanted to give ourselves the
To turn off that music which I really do.
We could just say that sound can be a know, you can pass a know and
it's fine right, it'll just deal with it.
Not really a big deal extra if in there is not going to kill anyone to
say the least.
So let's let's just get that music out of the way.
All right, so what I'd like to do now is I'd like to fade those out
over time and maybe this would be a good place to use our kind of code
editing or Live code editing, just so you can kind of see what happens
as I edit this stuff, right?
So you can kind of see the results as it goes right.
So let's maybe, let's maybe set up the screen, something like this.
We've kind of got the the just the Hero part over here.
And then I can I can use almost all of the screen at that point for
editing still, right?
And
Can just do it that way.
That seems that seems pretty reasonable.
So alright, let's go down there to our particle system.
What I'd like to do now is fade them out over time.
So when I spawn a particle, I give it a color here and basically what
I want to do is I want to say oh, you know, the particle P stuff.
Let's pretend that our
Dollars had a velocity as well, right?
So I want to do the same exact thing two colors as I did to my
velocity right to my position, right?
So each particle is going to have a d color value as well.
So that way, over time, I can set my particles to have some kind of a
negative effect on say their Alpha.
So their Alpha over
Second will fade out to nothing, right?
Because I have a negative Alpha velocity on the color.
So again this is just like treating colors as if they were physical
quantities, that move through space just like positions, nothing fancy
going on here, red green, blue Alpha, right in this vector.
And so I'm just setting the the velocity to negative one on there.
Now I don't know if we clamp colors in the renderer, I don't know
that, I don't think we do.
So we may have to do clamping on that in the particle itself but for
now we should be fine for that.
I'm going to go ahead and rebuild this guy here.
And let's go ahead and rerun that, right?
Okay, so now you can any fact there you go, you can see exactly what s
with a non clamping, right.
That's probably something we should just do in the renderer because
it'd probably be pretty free for us to just clamp in the render.
So, I don't know.
But, you know, I'm gonna, I'm gonna put it to do in there basically,
and say to do Casey.
Shouldn't we just plant colors in the renderer?
You know, and I don't know, maybe we shouldn't, I don't know.
We will think about that.
But anyway, what we can do here is, we can say, if particle color
Um, you know, is less than 0 x.
I guess we could do we even have a real?
We even have our handmade math.
I think we even have a clamp, right?
So there's our clamp right there, clamp 01.
We can just go ahead and do that.
So we can basically say particle color is 0 or I guess you could say
color R equals clamp like so.
All right, so I'm just going to clamp the for and that's not
particularly efficient obviously, but that's, you know,
will kind of look at the efficiency concerns of this later.
So there we go.
And now we can see it working a little more properly.
Maybe that was a little too aggressive.
Maybe we want to be a little slower on the fade out and so, there you
go.
But now, you can kind of see that those particles spawn at the heroes
feet, right?
And they go up, you know, towards the ends towards his head and they
fade out into nothingness before they are ever replaced.
So you almost can't even tell that we're using a circular kind of
buffer for that.
The other thing that I might want to do is kind of puff these
particles up a bit because remember, the shadow is kind of weirdly
shaped in that way.
And so I is
I almost want to.
Yeah I'd like to get that.
Maybe it's a good time to use that test if you shape we can see if
that's actually useful.
I don't know if it is or not but we can we could try and and the very
least we could make one I guess so we could do game state test
diffuse.
Look so
That's got to be an address of probably, huh?
That's I don't see anything, so that's not good.
So maybe that's not the right thing for us.
We might have to make our own particle, so I'll leave it at Shadow for
now.
There we go, but maybe off to add some particle Sprites to the asset
Library.
So we'll leave it at Shadow for now and we'll just live with that for
a little bit while we do some sort of playing around here, right?
So, the other thing we can do is we can make, you know, we can make
this value above 1.
So it takes.
So the thing is darker for longer and doesn't start fading out till
like a further part down.
Although actually, I think about it.
It's, this is kind of slightly wrong.
Instead of clamping, the actual color value, what I should do is, make
a new color value, because that won't allow us to set color values
above 1 and track them because it will immediately clamp it down to
1.0.
So, yeah, I set it to 2 here.
But then it will immediately clamp it to one.
So what we really want to do is just clamp the output color, right?
And so what I'd rather do is introduce like a synthetic variable here.
That's only used for the render path.
We clamp that and pass that, right?
And then we can do that sort of thickening and then you can kind of
see how that works there, right.
And of course, we'd have to, you know, we kind of have to fade it out.
I suppose a little bit quicker than that.
In order to not run out of rope there but there you can see now
there's like a while where it's full brightness and then
It starts fading out so we can actually do things that don't kind of
linearly fade our time.
They can have kind of like a delay until they start fading out even
with just the very simple to parameter scheme.
We've got a color in a d color, right?
So, that's that's the basic idea of particle system, right?
So now we just got to get some chaos in there.
We've got to get some motion in there because really, that's the
majority of the sort of the basic.
Your very basic, vanilla Workhorse particle system is already, what we
wrote.
There's not a whole lot more to it.
You can go kind of infinitely far with these things.
We like to do now is start to put some Randomness in there because
only once we get some Randomness, well, this actually start to be kind
of useful to us and you can sort of start to see how it takes shape
across.
We kind of also need a good particle Sprite.
But that's, you know, something.
We'll take a look at in a second.
All right, so how do we get some some Randomness in there?
We need to go back and sort of get our random or random stuff going
here.
I think we still have a series.
Do we have a series that gets initialized?
I don't know if we actually have a series that we actually use for
anything.
In particular.
Let's see here, random by letter or so we have we I don't even know.
It doesn't look like we have just a running Series.
So I'm going to introduce one because I'm going to want this, right?
So I'm going to want a random series that just a source of
entertainment.
He that we can basically use that random series is going to be you
know for effects.
Right?
Effects series.
And the reason that I do that is because I want to separate things
like particle systems out in terms of entropy because remember the
random number generation for a particle system doesn't have to be
particularly good.
It can have all kinds of weird.
In biases in it because it's not doing anything like generating, the
actual game map or something where we wouldn't want you know, it to
generate the same thing every time or do weird stuff like this, but
the effects can be much more loose.
So I'm going to break that out.
Just so we always kind of know what's using, you know, entropy that we
care about.
And what's using entropy that we don't care about.
In case, in the future, we want to do different random, number
generators that are better or worse, for different things, right?
Although I have a feeling that a permuted congruential generator is,
Is going to be awesome either way but yeah, we don't know yet.
So better to split it out.
Now when we can keep track of it easily then not I would say, all
right so when we go in initialize, the game state, right?
Oh there we even have General entropy entropy so I guess we did
actually have one right there.
So what I want to do is maybe put that up here and call this affects
entropy.
So there we go.
So I don't actually know what general entropy was being used for.
Let's Take a Look place.
And so maybe General entropy really was that looks like that kind of
was with that was.
So maybe I even don't even need this but that's kind of not the best
name.
I guess I would just say affects entropy is a little clearer than
that.
I feel like that's and maybe I'll even put a note there.
This is entropy that doesn't affect the gameplay, right?
So that's what I'd like to do, okay?
So effects entropy, that's our name for that now.
Facts entropy let's go ahead and change the name of that anywhere that
it was getting used.
I don't like the fact that we've been squeezed into this little corner
here, affects entropy.
Here we go.
So there we go.
And this guy still working just fine over here.
So let's go ahead and now actually start using that affects entropy,
right?
Because we can do random between we can use all of our calls that we
were
Using now to, you know, to actually sort of, create a, some chaos in
our particle system, a little bit of interesting motion, if you will
in that in that system.
So, I'm going to go down to the particle system when we spawn it.
And now, all I'm going to do just very very straightforward stuff,
right?
Nothing fancy.
I'm just going to give it a little bit of x velocity by just I'm just
pacing in a little you know that random between going to use the game
State affects entropy, right?
And I'm going to say that.
I just want to do something between, you know, negative 1 and 1,
right?
Something like that, right?
And so now you can kind of see already and I'll move that over a
little bit so you can just keep watching it as I play with it.
Right?
You can kind of see already that just by giving the deal-making that
velocity kind of spread out you're already starting to see something
that kind of looks like a problem.
It's not a good effect.
We have not done a very good job with that but of course, like I said,
we kind of need a better Sprite for it if were ever going to make
something better with anyway.
But you can sort of start to see already just with that very
Simple, you know nothing fancy just very simple.
We've already kind of gotten to the point where you can see.
Oh yeah, right.
I get it particle system, that's that
Sense, right?
And so maybe that's a little bit.
That spread is a little bit wide.
It doesn't really make a lot of sense.
So let's let's maybe narrow that down a little bit, right.
It's kind of like, pigpen.
He's kind of like a stinky Hero at this point, right?
It's what I'm reading out of that and maybe I want to do the same
thing with the with the spawn, right?
Maybe I want to make the spawn a little bit wider, you know, maybe not
quite that wide.
But you know, I want to I want to kind of Spawn some kind of magical
effect off of his sort of ground layer there and you can kind of see
that rising up like it does.
And you know, you
You usually want to put a lot of Randomness into these particle
system.
So we probably also want to randomize that sort of upward velocity,
even though all the particles are going to go upwards and none of them
go downwards.
If we still, if we just, if we just change that sort of, you know, if
we just give it a little more variability in how fast it rises, you
can also see that it just it kind of adds more character to the
effect.
If we just give it a little more, it gives a little more depth.
It gives
A little more interest if you do that, right?
And and it's also it's, you know, it's interesting to me, I guess we
decided to just stop using the Z from these offsets.
It's interesting to me that that just doesn't actually go up but you
know, that's a, you know, renderers.
They're always complicated anyway.
So, you know, that's, that's the basic idea behind particle systems.
Let's keep going with a little bit there.
What we could also do is, you know, maybe maybe it's just a little too
boring to be.
Using this particular Sprite.
So, the other thing that I guess we could do, we could say that we
wanted.
You know, I don't know, heads, right?
And we want to kind of just just spray a little heads out because I
mean, who doesn't want to write and, you know, they've got an offset
so you can see they're offset from the ground because they're not.
There Sprite is, has that hot spot there.
There's a torso spray right, a torso, sprays always pretty good.
And you know what, how about a quick second for how awesome our render
is.
It's not even batting an eyelash.
Josh, right?
It's just like whatever you can spray as many torsos as you want at
me.
I don't care, right?
So that's pretty cool.
Anyway, put that guy back where he was?
So yeah, so we can spray something else there.
And the reason that I wanted to spray something else there, you know,
whether it's heads or anything else is because another thing that we
might want to do, right?
Is we might want to give these guys some randomization in their color
as well, right?
Because again, the more entropy
The that you can pack in there, the more interesting, the effects
typically tend to become right?
And so what I'll do here is I'll kind of kind of just give it a little
bit of entropy there in the r g and B, right?
And and so we'll do a random that will sort of give it just, you know,
just a very little bit of kind of color variants in there.
So you can kind of see, just what that looks like, right.
And so, you know, you can you see how that's kind of doing it's you
know, a little bit of a, you know, just giving a little
Have of color to the the effect, right?
So the other thing that we could do there is we can make the alpha be
a little bit variants as well, and we can make the alpha lower in
general to the other.
I mean, the thing we could do is, you know, something like this,
right?
So now we're starting to get more of that kind of Cloudy effect going.
You'll notice however, there's there's another problem that we're
seeing, which is when we do something that's obvious like the head
like that.
You can see you can very obviously see the particles come into
existence.
Science.
And that's something that will want to address two.
I don't know.
Yeah, I mean, it's 601.
We've got 15 minutes left.
Probably, I don't know.
I started pretty latest are at least 10 minutes late today, so we
could address that as well, but let me just keep talking a little bit
more about this before we do that.
So, what I'm going to do here is I'm going to, I'm going to try
actually just beefing.
Our particle count up a bit, so we can play with little bit more.
Let's go ahead and go up to 256 particles about four times.
The number of particles.
That we were using before.
So yeah, let's go ahead and just put that over there while we look at
it, right?
So there's our particles going and I'm going to go over here to our to
our protocol spawn.
And I'm going to say, alright, let's let's make them last a little
longer again.
Just get kind of a bigger if oops, that's the wrong direction.
If you want them to last longer their case, let's make it last a
little longer again there, you can get.
There you go with that.
And so, you can kind of see, and I can also spawn a little more
densely, right.
And you can sort of start to see, you know if you if you do lots of
little things Blended together you can sort of start to see how it
forms an amorphous Mass.
Obviously you don't want to do it with the head of a guy because
that's not going to look like anything reasonable but you can sort of
start to see what I'm talking about in terms of getting that sort of
really odd Amorphis kind of shape stuff going on.
And I feel like what I really need though is I need these to back off
a bit on their opacity
T, right?
I need these to be kind of much lower opacity.
Oh wait.
That's the G color needs to be lower.
Opacity there.
So there we go.
Let's make that even lower.
There we go.
And so yeah.
So you can sort of see how it starts to do things that are kind of
cloud like and again we're only just doing the most basic a particle
system sir, because I just wanted to kind of get you warmed up, but
you can see, you know, you can kind of see how this sort of thing
starts to go.
Now, the other thing you can do is you can give particles and
acceleration as well, and of course, that's the, if you want to do
things, that kind of art can do gravity, like things.
And we can do all kinds of things, like feel defectors, and all that
sort of stuff.
But, you know, we'll look at those, maybe a little bit more down the
line.
That's more something that I'll put in the game code.
I kind of wanted to get some particle systems in here so we can start
talking about them.
The thing that I was going to say is one thing that we do probably
want to take a look at is the fact that this as a system where you
just have D color.
When X is not exactly what you want.
D color is often not expressive enough for The Coloring variation.
And usually, what you want to do with a particle system, is you want
to have a very explicit way of kind of doing a color ramp through a
series of colors so that you can start off at Alpha 0 ramp quickly
into a full Alpha and then ramp back out again and so that you don't
see that kind of popping down at the bottom, right?
You want these particles to kind of fade into existence
And so you need some way of making that work.
And you know there's ways that we can pretty trivially sort of Hack
That in, right?
There's there's ways we can, there's ways we could Hack That in even
with just we had now.
And basically, what they would be, is, instead of treating that color
value, that it Alpha value as a straight color value.
We could just choose to put it on a curve, right?
And we've talked about these curves a bunch of.
I don't know if we've ever actually made a quick curve function.
I don't think we have and so that might be something that I'll maybe
this is what I'll start with tomorrow because I don't really want to
start it today.
I won't have time to fully explain the curb, the curve stuff.
You.
So yeah.
Yeah.
I mean to give you the an example this is not how I would normally do
it but just to give you a quick example.
Something that I don't have to explain the curve for, but that would
allow you to kind of see what I mean by that would be if we were for
example to make the alpha value, say something like if color dot a you
know, is is
Gosh, I don't know how I want to say this.
So what we could do is say, all right, let's start the color values at
at at at one point.
Oh, right?
And let's, you know, we'll go ahead and do whatever the necessary
thing would be to.
Oops.
To make that happen and Fade Out at a reasonable rate, right?
Yeah.
That's just the weirdest are nothing.
Yeah, okay.
Well, you know, that's just sometimes you got a bunch of head spring
out of you, that's just how it goes.
So, you know, I've got something like this and, you know, maybe this
is roughly, what I was trying to do with the effect, but I want to get
rid of, you know, I want to, I want to make that ramp
And that bottom part, not note, so noticeable, like that, right?
So you know again I'm going to show you how to do some more advanced
stuff with that and maybe tomorrow.
But for right now, we'll just say, okay.
If the color Alpha you know is greater than nine point .9 F, right?
What I'm going to do instead is I'm going to treat the range of 0.9 F
to 0.1, F, I'm going to treat that range as actually ramping back out,
right?
So what I'm going to do is I say okay the color a, a
Actually equals 1.0 - the color a at that point.
So you know it.
It'll it'll basically say you know, take that little range between 0
.9 F + 1 point 0, f, which is point 1 where 1 F worth and I want
subtract it out.
So now I need to blow this color a, which is, you know, going to be
0.92 20.1.
You know, what?
Why am I even saying this?
We already covered this whole thing, we even made an entire thing for
this, right?
Clamp, 01 map to range was actually the function that does exactly
It's a thing that takes a range.
Of values and produces the T value that goes from zero to one that
fits the range.
So we were to cover this on a previous Animated Hero.
I don't have to say it again.
It's your job to go back and re-watch it.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and and map that 0.92 1.0 range.
I'm going to map that into make it.
So it's the full range from 0 to 1, right?
Like so
And then what I'm going to do is say, well, okay, and I guess we could
even do this range backwards.
I think that that works just fine or should work just fine?
Although well, it does a clamps or what?
Yeah, it should work just fine, so I should be able do that.
So it goes from 1.0 down to 0.9.
So what I'm going to do there is I'm going to make that be the new
metric for Alpha.
And so what I want to do is say when it gets to its maximum height
weight, just to 1.0 it's going to be at 0.9 and then that way, as it
continues down, it should be
Tenuous, right?
And so there you can see what that does.
Is it starts those guys out at very dim and ramps them in so that you
don't see that noticeable popping, and it just kind of looks a little
more sane in there, right?
So that's just a really simple way to kind of keep that from
happening.
All right?
So what I think I will do now that we have done our, our particle
system, our basic products is I will see, I would like to do the Q&A.
Someone was saying that if I just deleted my hex chat log,
Ugh.
That this would be, this would all work.
So I will see if that is true because like I said, earlier, it was not
actually working, which is unfortunate.
So let's take a look.
If that is actually true.
Let's see.
REM.
And now I will try to delete bugs and yeah, so I will just delete
those logs.
I guess I will just in
Do you know what I'll do?
I'll just move the whole log directory to home.
Here we go.
Chat, log twitch old.
There we go.
And now I'll see if I can run my extract because if I could run my ex
chat, that would be pretty great because then I could use the question
prompter.
Oh no, it seems to still be seems to still be crashy, but it still had
the log.
So how is it getting that log?
I don't know, maybe I'll move the whole log store.
Casey config hex chat logs to Casey.
Config X chat old logs.
Does that help you hand?
Me text chat.
It's still getting the old chat somehow.
I do not understand how.
Yeah, that's kind of weird LS.
Casey, config extra, yoy Oreo.
It's maybe it's the scroll back.
That's what it probably is, huh?
It's probably the scroll back.
So let's just do that.
Let's just do r m- r on that.
So I don't even want the scroll back.
One more time.
All.
Yeah, all right.
Let's see if the scroll back works, it does.
Okay, thanks everyone.
Who told me that, that was the problem.
Now, that's good.
We can actually do our Q&A with the standard, handmade hero.
So, there we go.
All right, everyone now is the time for questions and answers.
If you have a question about particle systems that, you know, would
like to ask please go ahead and put Q: in front of it, so that it will
Up on my little question prompter.
Which thankfully I was able to actually get working, thanks to people
who said that it was the fact that X chat was was messed up.
Jonathan Blow.
In fact has joined us and he says for a while.
I have felt that interpolating particles in RGB leads to results that
are dull and muddy I have been wanting to try YC R CB and maybe even
LED some time I guess you can compensate virus flying through RGB but
I think you'd be doing a lot of Tweaky work all the time to get better
results.
Even though YC R CB is just a linear transformation.
I think there's a substantial amount of skew.
So what I would say is I actually have used HSV before even and
You know, it's actually not that expensive to do HSV transforms,
especially not if you're already on hardware and using a pixel Shader
or, you know, in our case on SSE.
It's actually not that many instructions to switch from HSV over and
I've done HSV particles for and it is pretty darn cool.
It's like really easy to make rainbow effects and stuff like that.
So I have not tried why CRC be myself or any of the other XYZ color
space.
You know, I haven't tried any of those kinds of things, but
I can say from experience that HSV particles are a good way to go.
I don't know if handmade hero will need that but, you know, it might
be fun to do an optimized, HSV transfer, you know, transform and so
maybe we should just do it that way.
Because yeah, I would agree.
I don't really like RGB particles that much.
Although, you know, they're certainly the most expedient kind and
since particle systems are usually a speed thing, you know.
X, that's a good thing.
But but I would agree with that.
Rohit in, not sure I missed it, but will particle pre-warming be
supported.
So I guess I don't really know what we'll be doing in terms of
pre-warming.
What the person is asking about is the fact that like particle systems
take a while to evolve to their natural state, like for example,
right?
Right now you can see that this is what this particle sting.
Should normally look like, but when I start up the game fresh, right,
it doesn't look like that.
It takes a while for the heads to get, you know, to fill out and be in
the state that they're supposed to be at.
And so if you
No, for an effect that doesn't matter because the effect is something
that happens, and then the particle spew out, right?
But for something that's kind of a continuously rolling affect the
classic examples, like a waterfall.
You don't want your game to be in a state where, like the first time
you start seeing the waterfall, there's no water on it.
And the particle start at the top coming down and then eventually it
looks right.
You don't want that.
So how we would actually deal with that is a good question.
It I would rather hold that off till we actually find out if we have
that problem on handmade hero.
But because there's
A lot of different ways we could choose to address it and it probably
going to depend on what kind of particle systems are having that
particular problem, how we would choose to address it if it was a
problem.
When you were messing with Z Direction, it seems like kind of a puddle
on the ground.
Yeah.
When you don't have any, why motion?
It did seem a little puddle like
ever messed with using some kind of stateless system for doing this
like one function parameterize by another function.
If that makes any sense.
Yes, I have done that before.
I don't love it.
It's not my it's not really my favorite thing.
I find that it limits the particles too much and a lot of the things
that you want to do with particles that are cool, don't really lend
themselves to that kind of parameterization with unless it's
incredibly slow because it's just such a huge set of things that has
to do.
Is rain a particle system?
Yeah, oftentimes rain would be implemented as a particle system.
I wonder if head particles like this could be used in the game.
For example, as an effect of magic related to disguises like when you
dissolve, this guy's of the super, super fish?
Ha ha ha.
I think sure.
I mean, who knows?
Right.
Never Say Never.
Witnesses RGB and probably too late to change but we don't rely on a
Wow, Wee, particles much.
Yeah, I don't know that the witness would really need it.
I mean, maybe there's a couple of places that could be cool.
I don't know.
I definitely wasn't walking around the witness going.
Oh man, the particles in this game.
Really need to be a chess vide.
So I doubt that it's something that would really, it's not that it's
not the kind of a game that has a lot of, as you describe them.
Wow, he
Goals.
But yeah, I mean there are some places where maybe it would be fun.
I don't know.
But yeah, like the HSV thing is only a limited degree of.
I mean, you know, it's it's very specifically for doing rainbowy kinds
of effects because if you're not moving through color or saturation
space as a thing, then, you know, it doesn't help you at all.
So it's like you have to actually have something in mind where you're
going to want color variants like more than this kind of color
variants, right?
Z still points toward the screen I think?
Yeah, I think you're right.
I don't like, we kind of still, we are last pass on the render.
That's still up there on The To Do List is got to be going through and
getting the whole layer thing.
Because we're still in weird, we're still in weird town with are going
in and out where it looks correct.
But we don't have any, we don't have the floor layers, stacked up,
right?
And stuff.
And so we have to go in and kind of finally get all that stuff.
Lay down, right?
New khals.
Does anyone ever use layers or just Z sorting layers?
I'm not sure what you're mean by layers.
What times does handmade hero stream?
Saw this on the front page?
And it seems interesting you can go to handmade hero dot-org actually.
And if you go to handmade hero dot-org, first of all, there's a live
button.
You can always see it counts down to the next live stream.
So you can always look at that.
But then we also have a tweet bot.
So if you go to the Tweet bot, it's always got the schedule.
It's got your back.
It tweets a schedule and it tweets the video from the from as soon as
it's up for the previous show in case you missed it.
So the tweetbot is your
And if you're trying to catch the stream live or catch up with the
stream, the tweetbot is definitely your friend.
Jonathan Blow, maybe for the gala game.
I will switch to HSV, dude.
I don't want to hear about the gala game again until you add a bonus
round.
Okay, where is the bonus round?
Everyone knows that Galaga is all about a fighter capture and be the
bonus round.
And you were like all about denying me the bonus round.
I don't even know if I want to play this Gala game at this point,
because if there's no bonus round of the Galaga game, why is it even a
Galaga game at that point?
It's like Space Invaders or something?
I just tuned in will these videos help someone learn C and C++ has
absolutely no experience.
Sadly, not.
That is some a project that I would really like to do at some point,
but I had to start somewhere and so I decided that making a game for
people who already had.
Some prior experience was the best place to start.
If you do go to handmade hero, if you go to hammy here at Oregon, you
go to our video archive.
There actually, was, if you go to playlists a test stream, I did down
here called intro to see on Windows and you can go to there and you
And look at a little just test course, I did to show people a little
bit of how C programming works, but it's not enough, right?
And so, you know, yeah, someday I would really like to expand on that
and it's definitely a plan but, you know, I just don't have time to do
that right now.
And so my goal is to make a companion to handmade hero in the future.
That's like, here's how to, you know, if you know nothing about
programming at all and you someday want to do the handmade Hero Of
course.
Here's the thing that you can
that will take you from knowing nothing.
Like, I don't even know how to program your turn on a computer or
something all the way up to like, I can program in C, okay?
Because this doesn't actually take that long but it is much more
involved, certainly than five episodes of a one-hour show.
So,
Okay.
Is that it for questions?
Looks like it is.
Everyone's good on particle systems.
I take it, everyone's good on how to make heads kind of spew out of
your belly.
It's kind of looks like what that's happening there.
I guess it is a little bit.
Let's see.
Have you or will you explain how shaders work eventually?
Well, we wrote Our Own renderer.
So we wrote shaders like we actually wrote the part of the code that
is the Shader.
So we already did that actually.
But if you're just asking like how do I write an opengl Shader like
the syntax of the language or something?
No, we have not covered that and we probably will cover it lightly
when we pour it.
The thing, this thing to opengl or you know Vulcan or something way
down the line.
Well these particles be able to react to things like impacts.
Yeah.
I mean that's that's exactly, you know, the sort of thing that that's
exactly the sort of reason why I said I don't like to make particles
be functions, be closed form functions.
Someone was asking about about doing that because I like to have the
particles if they're all just there, you know.
And and being simulated like regular physics, kinds of objects, you
can choose to spend a little more CPU.
It not much just a little more CPU to have them do stuff like react to
Oceans or wind or stuff like that.
That's variable through the game and not have to worry about how to
constantly fit that into some crazy closed form way, right?
How many particles as 286 particles at the moment?
That's kind of spewing out there.
how many till we see and
Little slow down Edge well.
So I don't know because we haven't there's a cup, there's different
timing.
Things here there's, there's a couple different things.
This is not a very good way to process the rendering.
First of all calling push bitmap for every particle is not really what
you want.
So, what we would probably do when we get to, you know, instead of
playing around particles, when we're like, okay, we want to do a
high-end, you know, particle thing.
Here we would do more efficient throughput than this, but right now,
I'm guessing that
It's actually the scaling the it's actually the rendering of the heads
that's going to take the most time in since that's the case it's going
to mostly be about how big the particles are as well as how many of
there are.
You know, not just how many but how big so I suspect that I could slow
this down.
I could I could put a lot more strain on the renderer by making the
heads much bigger right than they are, right.
So you can kind of see that starting to slow down already right?
Because now there's just a
Kind of overdraw.
It's happening to overdraw that like like really ridiculously much,
right?
And so you know again that's something that's like
I don't know that we're going to try it.
You re not going to kill ourselves to make to have tons of particles
on the screen on the software.
Renderer, I'm fine with with, with it being the case that
That maybe we don't actually do our particle systems in the software
under, we only do those on the hardware.
But even that said, there is kind of a way that we can do particle
systems pretty fast and software.
And so we might just for fun, show, a little bit about that, because
there's some interesting things we can do that would allow us to scale
to very high particle rates in software.
And, you know, maybe that's a fun thing for us to play around with
just because you know, hey, it's an educational stream.
It's not always about doing the most expedient sometimes about doing
science.
Cool.
Right.
Are using emacs outside of Visual Studio inside of it outside of
Visual Studio.
When do you plan on implementing a way to adjust the position of the
individual particles, when the entities move?
Well, you don't really have to do that, right?
I just kind of stuck it in here because I didn't want to deal with it,
but you can just put it outside, right?
So, you know, a lot of that is just figuring out the the, the
placement, you know, one of the problems with the particle systems is
we have to figure out how we want them anchored, right?
And so, you know,
I'm not sure what the what the right way to do that is, but we
presumably want to Anchor them in the world and I don't know, maybe
also have some that are kind of screen space e.
So it's hard to say
What do you what made you pick C++ over C sharp.
Well C, sharp is, is not really a language for programming computers,
right?
C sharp is a language for programming.
Other programs.
It runs on top of a virtual machine, and it has, like, garbage
collection and all of this other stuff.
So, the point of this project is to show how to actually program a
computer.
So I wanted a language where you wrote code that is directly
translated into assembly so that you could see, you know, that kind of
direct correlation between
What you're doing and and what the computer is doing as opposed to C
sharp which is more about telling Microsoft's code, how to do what it
is.
You it's more about selling Microsoft's code.
What you wanted it to tell the CPU to do, which is not at all, what
we're trying to do on this stream,
What parameters were you tweak with curves, scale, position, color
rotation, external Force, etcetera, and will the curves depend on time
only.
Maybe this question is for tomorrow though.
Well, I don't know, like I said, you know, particle systems tend to be
very ad hoc you know, I mean unless you're sitting down to write like
licensed engine particle system like you know if your if your epic or
you know your Unity or somebody right and you have to ship a particle
system, that's like this General particle system.
This design to be used by like all the games ever or whatever.
Gotta think through like, how you're going to support all these crazy
diverse cases, and you can't support them all perfectly.
So you do some kind of like thing that maybe works for some most of
them and whatever, right?
We'd only have that problem because we're hand writing our games.
So we can just, as we come to things that we need, we can do whatever
makes the most sense for that, right?
So we don't really need to think about that.
We can just go, okay.
We, you know, I showed, you know, we took today and will probably take
tomorrow to display the products.
I'm so now everyone.
What they are, will put them on a shelf for a while.
And then when the game is up and running, and we're mostly doing game
code, then we can just go, hey, you know, what would be nice to have
some particle effects in here and then we can write the particle code
for that particular circumstance as it as it arises, right?
How many times have you said, right?
In this Ruckus?
I say write a lot.
The other one I say or a lot is basically, so, I would not try to
count those two.
You're going to get to very high numbers.
You're going to overflow your counter
Vertical flow.
Now, how about to show?
How to fix horizontal?
I don't know what that means.
Nichols is your e max, if it open source, it's not open source but it
is included.
If you pre-order the game at comes with the source code.
So it's in some sense.
Can you explain what procedural level generation is?
And are there other types of generation?
And if so what is the difference?
Well, procedural.
Level generation is usually the phrase that's used to distinguish
games.
That generate their levels fresh every time using algorithms versus
games, where there were level designers who made the levels by hand
and positioned the things where they're going to be.
So it's like procedural.
Level generation is just the blanket term for this game has actual
That runs when you start the game to figure out what the levels will
look like so that they can be different every time instead of always
having to be whatever a level designer sort of laid out if that makes
sense.
Gary Johansen off topic.
What do you think about using Unity as a platform layer and using all
your own logic?
I've never really looked at doing something like that.
So I don't have much of an opinion about it.
Other than to say, you know, I don't like C sharp.
I wouldn't ever program in C sharp and unity is kind of about enabling
C sharp as the logic layer.
So I feel like that would be kind of an automatic know for me.
But you know, that's not an informed opinion.
That's just my, you know, immediate thought I write my own engines
from scratch.
So obviously I don't ever need to ask that particular question.
So I, you know, I'm never going to go look at Unity to see what I
think about thing X because I you know, know a priori that I'm going
to be happier with my own code, so I always use my own code.
Why do you pronounce nightmare as night mirror?
I didn't know that I did.
Do you have someone making the game assets for your they self-made.
Yes.
Yang Stanley is making the art assets and she is a very good painter
and she makes the art assets for this game.
Will you be making development tools for handmade hero like a map
editor?
No, because it is procedurally generated.
So there is no map editor.
It is the maps are created by the game and they're different every
time.
I mean is your config public domain?
Can I give it to someone who'd like to get started with Emax?
I myself pre-ordered ages ago, best, $15 finisher of my life.
No contest for you.
New clothes, of course you can
You can use the allows I have done this much using rust, FYI.
So
I'm saying I've just a patch it back to the original question.
You're saying using Unity as a platform layer but but driving it with
compiled dlls I guess what?
I don't super understand there is how do you run the dlls on the other
platforms.
So like you can't load a dll from that you can pile on Windows on
Android, right?
So I guess I don't understand what you mean by platform layer.
If you're saying dll because dll is Windows and sometimes Mac, but
that's more or less it.
And so
So I'm not sure I understand what you're advocating at that point
you're saying dlls linking dlls to Unity.
Because what do you mean it's by platform layer at that point it's not
really a platform layer unless you can run it on all the different
Well platforms, right?
Noodles.
I don't know how to pronounce your name.
I have no idea how to pronounce her name.
I feel like if you want your name to be pronounced properly, you have
to put a little pronunciation guide next because K KN e w.
KL e.
S is really hard to guess.
I was saying k'nuckles before.
Now, I'm saying new colls, but you're saying maybe it's
snoo colls.
I don't I don't know how to say it.
I do not know.
Hank 07, I mean the particular flow or direction is now from bottom
up.
Feels like it's not hard to do left to right, for example, you mean
use, if you are you just talking about, I'm not sure what you're
talking about.
Still, are you talking about the fact that the particles go that way
because yeah.
Sure you can make the particles.
Go anyway, you want because DP the direction, right?
The velocity Vector can point in any direction you want.
I mean here's the velocity vector.
Written out explicitly, right?
And if you wanted it to go in some other direction, you could totally
do that trivially, right?
You just say, oh, you know what?
It's going to have a sideways motion to it as well, right?
And now they spray off kind of in that direction or something, right?
And you could, you could obviously say, oh, you know what, I want to
cut, you know, I want to I want to keep it chaotic up and down and so
it's kind of a spray out to the side, right?
So yeah all that stuff is really pretty.
Pretty straightforward because you just have a velocity vector.
And so this velocity Vector is just the whatever Direction it points.
Is the direction, the particle will go, you know,
so hopefully that answers that
Get new goals gun, new goals.
K new coils.
K Nichols.
Okay?
So K new coils is how you pronounce it.
K knuckles.
I like that other people are selecting like Chuck Norris.
We could just call you Chuck Norris.
K new coils.
All right.
Well, I think we have come to the end of handmade hero for today.
We are now spraying heads around, and let's be honest.
That is always something that I feel like we want to be able to do.
Who doesn't want to be able to spray a bunch of heads around.
I feel like I speak for everyone when I say that.
That's something that everyone wants to do.
So let's go ahead and close that up.
And get our Dev Studio closed down.
Save our, you know, our mischief and let us go back to the handmade
here web page, okay?
Everyone, thank you for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with the series,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org and it
comes with a source code.
So you are every night.
You can go ahead and play around with everything we're doing and
To experiment with it, do whatever you like, and that is updated every
night.
So, after I'm done, I put it up there, we've also have a forum site,
you can catch up on old episodes by taking a look at it and see it
episode guide, the community's done, you can get ports to Mac and
Linux that members the community of done.
If you're trying to follow along on a different platform, you can
check those out.
They might help you.
We also have a forums like, page where you can post questions or if
you have things that you want to ask about the series, that's a good
place to do it.
We have a patreon page.
You want to support the video series?
It's always much.
And we also have a tweetbot that tells you when the video series is
live, so check those out.
If they sound interesting to you until then I will be back here
tomorrow, same time, same place, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time, right here on Twitch.
So if you would like to play around with particle systems with me some
more that is when we will be doing that until then, I hope you have
fun programming and I will see you all on the internet.
Take it easy everybody.