Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we go to complete game live on Twitch.
And, you know, we are at the point we're at the point where we have
some decisions, some hard decisions to make here we ended the previous
stream.
Well, I'll just I'll show you I'll just show you where we ended the
stream last week before the long weekend before Labor Day.
For those of you who are in the u.s.
we ended the stream and you can
See that we had some performance graph stuff that we've been working
on and here it is.
Right.
You can see it running.
And one of the things that you'll notice about this performance graph
stuff, if you remember, is we kind of have this, this system that we
done, which can take these performance cars that are really easy to
add and then I have this other sort of thing where we could take a few
snapshots in time and sort of draw them on this graph, right?
And the problem with these two systems is they don't go together and
it's pretty clear you know, after looking at them, what I'd really
like is I'd like these all to go together.
But there are some hard problems with this.
And so what we're going to talk about on today's handmade hero is
we're going to talk about, you know, what, our options are there.
What do we reasonably want to try and accomplish in the context of
handmade here in terms of having built-in profiling stuff, etc?
Etc, right, so before I get started, let me just mention as always, if
you are someone who pre-ordered the game, it's day.
1 81.
So you want to unzip day 180 source code also.
Or if you're using the GitHub you want to get day 180s which would
just be the latest source code.
But if you're watching this video you know after the fact you got to
go in get specifically the day 180 source code.
Which, by the way, it was supposed to be tagged but it doesn't seem to
be tagged.
I'm wondering if GitHub is doing something weird.
There, could talk about that some other time, though.
Anyway, point being, if you want to follow along with that unzip, that
and directory, that's the source code that I'm starting with today.
And so then, you know you can you can follow along as we sort of
talked this through.
So let's recap what the problem is here.
So these up here are performance counters and they have some pretty
nice advantages.
Completely thread safe there almost zero overhead.
Like they have extremely low impact on the actual performance of the
program, so it's pretty much free to throw them in anywhere.
Now they do cost a lot to actually draw at the end because there's a
whole bunch of renderer work that has to happen here, but that's an
isolated thing.
That happens after the frame is basically completed.
And so we know for to a fair to a certain degree, we're not affecting
the actual routines, much that
We put them in right?
It doesn't really have much effect on the cash.
It doesn't have hardly any instructions.
A test executes, a couple ma, it's like two or three mobs in our dtsc.
And that's mostly what we're talking about, right?
At the beginning of the end and so that's about as low overhead is
you're going to be able to get on a performance counter and it's
again, completely thread safe at the moment.
So you can have these being called from all over the place and they
literally just do not conflict with each other.
They never even have to lock or check to see if each other is running.
You just it just works, right?
And again, that's really nice because it means you can just throw them
anywhere that you want and you can be happy about life.
That is all stuff.
We would like to keep, right?
That's what I would like to have, but what I don't get from this is
any sense of when those things happened, in any way that I could
display like this, right?
So if you look at what's happening down here, I was showing a
color-coded set of bar graphs where you've got, like a couple
different colors and you can see the colors of the bar graph here.
Blue is the the region that's taking up the most time.
Green is very little.
There's a little bit of red down here and there's a little bit of a
yellow up there, right?
So you can see that basically okay, you can instantly see that are the
blue section of our program takes all the time.
Well the blue section happens to be the part where we call the game
for stuff and you know you can see me making that some improvements
here where like, you know, I hover over one of them are something and
it shows us what, you know, what section that is because like it's
hard to remember what the different colors would be or anything like
that, right?
So I can just hover over it and it would tell me oh, that's this.
You could imagine them being kind.
Of hierarchical.
Like I could click on one and drill down to see what the time of.
So maybe it only shows like some top level set and goes in right
there's all sorts of things we can do here to make this a pretty nice
profile view by improving the rendering in the interactivity with it.
If we have more data but we don't have right now is more data.
We only have those few actual time stamps that the external the
platform side of the code takes and these guys right here which are
littered throughout our program which would
Give us a much better would give us a lot more visibility into who is
taking the time and when we don't have any visibility into that
whatsoever, right?
We've got no idea how those things sort of lined up and furthermore,
we don't know.
So for example, I know mentally, because we put the timers in.
I do mentally that game update and render 669 is inclusive of game
update and remember 1685.
So I happen to know that this amount of time here is actually
we counted inside this amount of time there.
But the debug system doesn't know that, right?
It has new idea and part of the reason that it has no ideas.
Again, some of that low overhead Miss.
Okay.
so,
there you go.
Keep that in your brain for a second.
While I explain for you to you the problem.
Them that I see going forward.
So if we wanted to keep most of the advantages of this system,
We want to avoid doing much work when a timer is actually active,
right.
We don't want to spend a lot of time and we can spend an arbitrary
amount of time at the end of the frame.
And yeah, that does create some some stuff that may skew the
performance of our program.
So for example, it may make it so that the performance of our program
doesn't have the same cache effects because at the end of the frame,
there's all this extra stuff we do.
And so frame-to-frame there, maybe a little bit of a sort of General.
They're that's inserted by the fact that we do a bunch of work.
But other than that,
Doing a ton of work at the end of the frame to figure out what are
perf.
Actually looked like is fine as long as we keep the actual things that
do the sampling relatively efficient.
Right?
So for the most part, I don't really care if we come up with some
really cock cock eyed scheme, right?
That's like super crazy and Genki that has all the stuff that has to
happen at the end.
I don't mind that.
I only mind if we have stuff that sort of crazy.
Happening right at the timers because the that crazy is happening.
If the timer is done, I'm afraid it's starting to affect the
performance of the program and that's not something that I want to
have happen with these timers.
So if that's the case, again, when I, when we started this, I was sort
of saying, well, one approach we could take, right, is to have a log
based system, right?
We could have a system where we write log entries, and then collect
those log entries, after the fact, and that has the nice property that
if we do log entries, we can stamp those down in a much more efficient
fashion, right?
We can say like, oh will stamp down a log entry?
And now we know that that
Log entry can say like what the actual are dtsc timer was and even
potentially what, what processor actually was on.
And so we can have a lot of information about what our program is
doing at that particular time.
So that's you know, that's where my head's at, right?
The problem with that, is this, these numbers right here.
The problem with them is that when we look at these numbers, we see
that the emember of log entries were going to write is actually fairly
large if we want to start timing things like get, rented render entity
basis P, you know, that's 5,000 hits that, that it's having per frame
or something.
And that seems like, actually a totally reasonable number that doesn't
seem outlandish for that to have 5,000.
Thousand hits.
If there's a lot of entity things on the screen right there could be a
lot of those.
In this case a lot of those are coming from the text.
I believe, actually but you know we could have a lot and he's on a
screen like
Of these trees is an entity and every enemy.
Excuse me, Majesty bullets are probably going to be entities.
We have, you know, there's going to be high numbers of these things
coming through.
And so, if you're talking on the order of thousands, for some of these
things that are getting recorded,
If we take a look at what that means, let's say, I take a 5000.
Did I launch e?
Max twice?
No, I did not.
If I have something like 5,000 things.
And each one of my records is, you know, something like, I don't know.
16, bytes or something like this.
Then we're talking about, you know, a good 80 k, or something.
Like this.
Let's say conservatively like, you know, 128k that's 128k of rights
that are just happening.
Kind of willy-nilly, right?
Now, I don't know that.
We care too much about that.
As I think about it, I I'm feeling like maybe we don't because at the
end of the day that's not very much right.
Bandwidth.
Certainly and it's not really necessarily polluting the cash either
because it's something that's just a right?
It's going to happen.
This never going to be read read from again, you might even be able to
do it in some kind of non-temporal storage way, where we tell it,
don't pollute the cash to spew spew, this data out there, right?
So, I don't know, so it may be that what we want to do is move to more
of a lot of a system and then we could gather up those log events.
After the fact and kind of use that as more of our way of seeing
what's actually going on.
Right?
And so since I don't have a really good handle on it, like I said I
don't really have a solid idea of what I want to do.
You know, we've got we've got the state of our code, it's stored in
our, you know, in our ZIP file.
So we can always revert if we need to.
I think what I'll probably do is I'll just start playing with that log
notion a little bit.
Like I said way before, you know, maybe it's the right thing to do to
have a log there.
I'm going to play with that log notion a bit and see what I think
about it as we go now.
Something I want to see if we've got and I don't know if we've got it.
I'm a little bit suspicious that we probably don't have it and that's
sad but I'm going to see.
I'm just going to do a test to see if we have it.
And what that is is a thing called our dtsc P.
I think I may have even tested for it on handmade hero before and I'm
quite I think we may have tested and we don't have it, I think is the
answer.
And so Hope Springs Eternal.
I'm just going to test for it again.
And if we have it, I'm going to talk about it a little bit.
So I'm just going to call our dtsc P.
I'm going to see if we've got it.
Of course.
I guess.
I have to give it the actual.
What does it take?
A d word?
Normally I think or DTS EP,
I just want to see what the situation is because if we have it I'm
gonna do things a little bit differently than if we don't so that
takes an unsigned int.
So here is our inside auntie.
And I'm just going to see what happens.
When we call that now it's going to be pretty obvious.
If it is there, nothing will happen.
If it's not there we will crash.
Well, well, well, I guess I have not tested for this on, handmade
hero, aren't we?
In luck, ladies and gentlemen, aren't we?
The spoiled little child?
Whose mommy is doting on him?
It would seem it would certainly seem.
Is this really true?
Let's find out.
Well, what do you know?
Very interesting.
Let's double-check one of the thing.
Less less, good.
I'll just go and say that's less good very much.
Less good.
Yeah, well, it was fun, while it lasted, I guess is what I would say.
What's going on there, let's find out.
So I'm sorry for being cryptic.
I wanted to find out if we had it first before, I actually explained
what it was, but I guess at this point, we're a little bit too far
into it.
Artie T, SCP.
It's actually calling it so unless I guess I don't know if saying if
you could be getting trapped I suppose.
Mmm.
Yeah, well, I suppose it's possible that that's actually returning for
us the right thing.
Let me I'll talk about it anyway.
All right, so our dtsc p is the same as our dtsc.
So you've already seen me use our dtsc stands for read time stamp
counter.
And what it does, is it gives you back when you actually call it?
It gives you back a value which is a register
Sickly you could almost you can think of it as reading a register or
reading a sort of a counter on the CPU.
That tells you what time it is effectively.
And as you execute as the CPU executes instructions, that that time
goes up.
So by calling it a different place in the program, you can see how
much processor time has elapsed between any two places in the program
that you called it.
And it's guaranteed to always be sort of monotonically or while just
increasing anyway.
Way.
And so while you can't necessarily make hard inferences about exactly
what happened to the processor, it does give you a nice reasonable
fine-grained estimate of how much work occurred between two places and
so that's fine.
Our dtsc p is supposed to actually do two things.
Instead what it's supposed to do.
Is it supposed to give you?
At least it used to maybe it maybe or at least this way I thought it
did and maybe I'm, you know, just having one of those sort of
delusional days used to I thought, or should have given you back, what
processor you are on as well.
So here is here's what I thought of it as and what it would do is it
gives you back both the our dtsc which was the thing that we were
already getting, but also some indication of
Are you were actually running.
So if you take a look here you can see that.
It sort of says lose the current value of the processors time stamp
counter obviously that's the thing that we were already getting in
that so important.
But assuming that we have
Our dtsc p and not our dtsc, then it's supposed to give us back.
Also the let's see if it says here, it was when predicting the time
stamp to the Emulsion is Falls Justice, lyrics of a Pious ones, like
session with prison 0, she waits until a blah blah blah.
Okay cpuid.
So to one person, the processor change instruction Behavior.
Doesn't actually say.
Returns.
You have 32-bit.
Iatse aux value, right?
It's you see aux?
Okay, let's see.
So I felt like yeah so let's take a look.
Maybe I just have to do a little more work to get this to do what I
want it to, but what I was hoping we could do with, it was also know
which core we were on if that makes sense.
So here you can even see someone asking this question, right?
And let's see here.
Yeah.
So, you can see that this is what I was expecting.
Or what?
I was, hoping I should say, what I was hoping for our dtsc P until
reference manual.
I wonder if I can get inside the PDF and actual explanation of what it
expects it to do.
Because I wanted to use this, I actually could.
Now, I didn't even think of this, I the reason I don't already know
how to make this work properly, is because the machine.
I was had at Molly rocket for up until literally last week.
Was so old that didn't have the arditi SCP instruction.
So I was never able to actually use it in my profiling on my, in my
storage space.
So now I actually have two machines I could
We do it, but I was hoping to be able to use it on here, made here as
well.
But then again, maybe it does isn't as useful as I thought, but I was
pretty sure.
So let's see.
Bubba, Bubba, Bubba, the values have started sorting a sir.
The value of the cpuid is, sort of the ECX register, which is exactly
what I was thinking.
And so I felt like it should tell us that exact information that we
need now, maybe they mean CPU and not core in which case maybe all our
stuff is running.
On just one
CPU, but we should eventually have gotten.
I would think at least something and this machine actually has two
CPUs.
So I should have thought that one of our threads, when we spin up all
our bar threads, someone should have returned something other than 0,
right?
But nobody did, I've got an assertion there and it never actually
traps so it seems kind of bad.
It seems like it's I'm not getting what I want, their assuming Foo.
If mu is not equal to 0,
Let's go ahead and say, we'll do it.
Exactly.
Just to make sure we're doing it there.
No assertion necessary.
Go ahead and run.
anyway, that's, I mean, that's pretty clear that that's not
That that's not doing anything now, let's see.
We can also I suppose take a look I guess we're not really stressing
out this machine much.
I suppose it's plausible to imagine that.
We're only running on one CPU and it's the CPU number, not the core
number, but like I said, I never got a chance to actually use our dtsc
pee myself.
So I have no experience with it.
So I could be just totally wrong about that because I never had a
machine that had it at work.
So this machine is newer than the one I was.
Using it work, which is kind of crazy.
That's how old my machine is, so I don't know, I don't know.
That's, that's pretty strange, but I can't think of any other
explanation for that.
So, unfortunately, I guess that will have to wait.
Maybe since I like I said, want that in my code base at work.
Anyway, I'll play around with it myself.
And see if there's, maybe just some stupidity that I'm not, you know,
slip stuff that I don't know that, once, you know, you're okay, and
it's, and it's all good, right?
So, anyway, point being, if we don't have that at the moment, we have
a little bit of a problem with multi-threading because we don't have
any way of disambiguating what thread where on, but there are other
techniques, we can probably employ for that.
It's not the end of the world and obviously, we could certainly get
things working properly on on just one thread and then we can
Just know that will be wrong for our other threaded stuff and that's
not a big deal.
We can certainly do a bunch of the work without having to worry about
that and hopefully, if we're lucky, we'll figure out why the rtt SCP
is working and hopefully it is, does do what I hope it does and it's
not some kind of like Lamer thing, but who knows, okay, not the end of
the world.
Would have been nice to kind of get that for free because that's well,
it's kind of nice to get stuff for free.
Who doesn't want stuff for free.
So anyway, we'll ignore that for a minute because like I said, there's
plenty of other options that we have.
It's not the end of the world.
So what I wanted to start talking about then is just, what would we do
here?
How would we set this up such that we could start to get a more
logging oriented system in place?
Instead of what we had before which is something that only works with
kind of those locked arrays.
So we've got these debug records and I don't really want to mess with
those.
So I'm going to call them debug events for now, which is like a
Of a separate thing.
And the reason for that is there are some things like, in this, debug
record, like the file name, the functioning of the line number, we
don't want to store those every time, there's no need.
So I feel like we can we and we don't want our debug events to be huge
or anything either.
So I feel like we probably want to have a little bit of a.
You try to be a little bit conservative about this stuff is so that we
can kind of like work with it a little bit more.
So this debug event stuff here, what I'm going to go ahead and do is
say the Deep.
There's a debug event and the debug event is just going to have the,
the clock.
It's just going to have the, whatever our dtsc returns were, just
going to store it.
And then the only other things we're going to store.
I guess we probably want this to be nice to sort of padded.
So it's an even thing.
But the only other thing is that we really need to store is some kind
of an index into the debug records, right?
So we could have the debug record in
Looks like so, and I think that's really all we need.
I guess, you know what we could do?
Since we have eight B there.
We could just store a pointer to the debug record and the reason that
that's potentially a little bit.
Nice is because since we have this dual compilation unit problem,
where we don't know which array, we're looking up into that seems like
kind of a nice thing.
Now, the only I don't really love that though to some degree because
at some level,
I would rather not have if we get our dtsc P working, I would like
space to sort store that CPU number so that would have been nice.
So I feel like we do want a little bit of extra space for their.
So, I'm trying to think if there's any useful way, that we can encode
this without taking too much time.
I guess what we can probably do is just say, which array you are in,
right?
So, there's something like,
There's a u16 for the thread index or the, or the core index,
something like that.
And maybe a thread index as well, because we know we're not going to
have too many of these.
So I feel like those should be able to be smushed down to something
reasonable.
And then we could have, like, the debug record index and the debug
record array.
Index or something like that.
Right.
And yeah.
So, that would be 128-bit, just 11.
You know, it's basically one sec, registers, worth of right for every
debug event, you know, something like that.
And you know, a bunch of that data.
We don't actually have yet.
But that's basically what I'm thinking.
So if we came in here
And we wanted to start writing these things out.
I'm just going to do a global right?
And I'm going to do the same thing we did before in our build for the
multiple translation unit stuff.
I'm going to have just like we had to debug arrays.
I would have two different log arrays, right and actually take that
back.
We don't need that at all.
These don't have to be uniquely indexed so we can literally just have
a debug event array.
Just one of them, and everyone can write into the debug event array,
that's totally fine.
So, we'll just, you know, store the debug event array as a thing
that's like, you know, going to be forward declared.
And then we have it in here.
We can actually just make one.
And we want this thing to be really big.
I don't know how big we can make it before the compiler will start to
complain or rather our program will run properly without a bunch of
fiddling because it doesn't have enough.
It tries to take too much static memory thing.
Like this.
But we're going to make it pretty big.
For starters.
And then the other thing that we want to do is we want to make a
counter here, that's the debug event index, and that's going to be
something that lets us know where we're writing into that array.
You know.
Something that's like, okay, we're in the that debug, or are we
actually trying to to right?
Yeah, so we've got a little, there's a little bit of I even kind of
know what we're going to have to hit here.
We want this thing to be relatively thread safe.
We're going to have a problem where somebody has to collect the data
at some point.
And in, so, doing where are things writing while the day is getting
collected.
So I probably want like a ping-pong buffer kind of a situation where
I've got a buffer that people right into and a buffer that we're
collating and we just swap them so that we know that nobody's ever
writing into the buffer were looking at.
So, kind of a double buffering scheme just like we do with, with the
Bitmaps and stuff, right?
So what I'd like to do here is probably also say, okay, we actually
have two of these debug event arrays, so it's like Diva event storage,
you know, something like this.
And then there's the debug event array is actually just a pointer to
one of these two, you know what I mean?
So that we've got something like that happening where, you know,
you're using these guys to write, but you don't really know which one
this one's writing into and you're just assuming that it's going to
ping pong.
Ang, you know, those behind your back, right?
And then that's and that's fine.
Okay.
So let's take a look at how we would do this.
I'm gonna go ahead and compile just to make sure that we're not doing
anything wonky yet.
So the debug event array, what we would do.
Inside our time, block is when we go to do, like our Atomic adhere
instead of doing our Atomic ad and doing this sort of like counting
and stuff, we would do something else.
So I'm going to leave this stuff in here for now, but we're then going
to condense it down later because like I said, I don't want much
happening during these timers.
So I'm going to try and condense it down to the minimal amount of
stuff, but I'm going to leave in what we had before.
Or just so we can use it for reference as well.
And what I'm going to do here is I'm going to call our dtsc like I was
doing before.
And I'm going to into the debug event, debug events, right into the
debug event.
I am going to write all of these values.
So we're going to write the clock.
I am going to write the thread index as if I had it.
I don't, I'm going to write the core index as if I add it.
I don't I'm going to write the debug record index
So that I have, it's this counter.
So I know that there's not going to be more than 65,000 profile points
in our in our code.
So I'm okay, casting that and then I'm going to write the array index
in the array index.
I don't actually know yet because that's not something that's actually
defined in any good way, but we can certainly make that Define pretty
easily.
When we do our build, all we have to do is say something like debug
record array index or something like
And we'll just call them zero and one.
So are optimized 1 is 0 and our main one is one or maybe I'd do it
that way.
So the main one is sear on the is right?
So, so now we do have a way of actually knowing which one we're doing
because whichever program path is being compiled, it will get the
right Define you know.
Easy peasy lemon squeezy as they say, I have no idea where that comes
from but you get the idea.
So that is what we would need to do.
And so the only question is, where do we write it?
And so here is where the actual Atomic comes in for us.
Right?
If you look, we've got handmade, I guess in our intrinsics here.
We've got Atomic, add 64.
I'll just instead of introducing a new one.
Let's just make this
Stay for a bit for now and I'll actually do the atomic ads you 64 here
even though we don't really need 64 bits of address.
So you know, well yeah.
Do we really want to do that?
I don't know, here you go.
Let's just do this for now because we may not need the 64-bit one
afterwards so I guess it's premature to say let's keep one and not the
other.
Things like this, right?
So let's go ahead and just see what happens if we do it this way, just
try it out like that.
So if we take a comiket, you 32, and I know that I now can increment a
value and get back, the original value.
That was in there.
That means what I can do is, I can Atomic increment this debug event
index and a know that I will get back a number that
That nobody else will ever get back right because all of the cores are
guaranteed to see these things atomically.
So I know that nobody else could see the same number as I do because
as soon as they see it, that means that wouldn't be the one that I
saw, because everyone's going to increment it by 1.
They're going to look at the value and increment it by 1 in, 1 Atomic
step.
So no, but no two people could see at the same time because everyone
is looking at, it is always looking at an incrementing by 1.
So all of the threads that are adding events will also
get back unique, debug event, indices
Which is exactly what I want.
So then that Atomic ink, you know, index that increments that I get
back.
I'm well, I guess what I'll do first is, I'll store it.
So this is our event index.
Is this one.
So I can start there and just so I can assert in debug mode that the
event index is less than, you know.
However, many we said we were going to have which, I guess we haven't
said here.
So I'll introduce a variable for this, which is like pound to find,
you know, Max debug event count or something like that.
And
I want I would really like it to be very large because I want us to be
able to stream as many do events in there as we want, but we'll play
with that a little bit later, but I don't want it to be dynamically
allocated because I want it to be running right for the beginning of
the program.
So, you know, it could be dynamically, allocating the windows platform
layer.
That's something we could do.
We, we've got options, but you get the idea.
So, anyway, when we come through here,
And I thought if we added I'm just going to assert that it's less than
the max count just to make sure that we're not reading into something
illegal.
So we know that we've hit a boundary in the debug code or something
like that but then I can get the event just by looking at whichever
one in the event array.
That is I can grab the clock.
I can put fill out the other values which again, I haven't done yet
and then I can do the exact same thing.
Write this code can happen exactly the same at the end of the time of
Lock.
And so what you can kind of see there is really there's only
Nothing.
There's just a record, debug event thing that puts something into the
log.
They're exactly the same and the way that we would know how long
something would take would be to look at like where it got stamped and
then where it got stamped again.
And so what we can actually add and this is again why I said I wanted
to make sure there's extra room in here.
We know that, you know, we're probably not going to be running on
something, that's got more 256 arrays or something.
We could even say here, which is like, you know, type or something
like what type of Entry this is.
In the log or something like that.
So I can even in these debug events I can actually sort of State in
the log, what it actually was.
So I can stay debug event type for something like this and that type
itself could be like debug event underscore begin block, debug
underscore n block.
You know.
Something like this.
All right, so if that's the case, then you can sort of see again in
here, we've got event type equals debug event, you can block
And then a Shear I'd have to debug event and the block and that way I,
you know, have have sort of a notion of when things started and like I
said it's exact same thing.
So what I'm going to do is say that there's just an inline here,
right?
And in fact, I'll just even make it a macro which is just like record
debug event.
And the macro is just this exact thing, right?
It's just, it's just that
and so when you say record, debug of it, you do all your stuff like
so.
And the only thing that you need to tell me is what type of event you
recorded like so?
So I just do record the event like that.
And then down here, I would do record debug event and block and
eventually I'd eliminate this entirely this would just go away.
And so with this and and so really the only thing that would
Happen, is this stuff here?
Because I wanted to kind of keep that stuff written.
And what's interesting about that is that so few things I never really
know.
It might actually be more efficient to just store them in every debug
event.
I don't know.
It's one of those things that you're just you wish see was just had a
clue because again if C++ had added the right thing so language would
have been trivial to make this happen at compile time because there's
only n counters and we know where they are at compile time.
So the fact that
That I even have to do this.
Here is ridiculous.
It should never actually have to happen but there's not really much
you can do about it.
Unfortunately, you can only kind of have various ways of hacking it.
So anyway,
It's not actually true.
There are.
There are some things we could.
I don't even want to go in anyway.
But yeah, point being C++ should have made it really easy.
Didn't make it really really easy Q pre stream rant about strip.
If you were listening to that, this is one of those things where if
someone knew what they were doing, we would have had these features.
Okay, so anyway, see backslash region.
There is my
Crow.
You can see it doing this little macro thing, I was put event type in
there.
So it's clear.
What you want to do?
That is and I think that's all we really need.
Their looks reasonable to me and I might make these called Global.
Just so that's a little clearer since they are going to have to remain
Global, you know.
So I'm going to call those global on both cases and that looks fine.
So, let's just let's call that a day.
There we go.
And we've got the to debug event records there.
So that's all good.
We'll call that Global.
And this also Global, we also need this guy in here.
Just come in there.
And so these guys actually need to be defined, right?
What interlocked exchange is it just at introduction to add with no
32?
Yes, it is because I assuming that that, that was what it's
complaining about.
Yes, it just didn't know that.
Yeah, so interlocked exchange Dad, it's a point.
It wants pointers to Long's.
Okay, that's what you want.
That's what you should get.
So, there we go.
You 60 for too long.
Oh so that wait.
So then what's what's what does the problem?
What's the actual interlocked add interlocked and 32-bit?
What's the actual msdn for that?
Show me the msdn please.
Interlock variable access.
Let's take a look.
Interlocked and is not what I want interlocked compare exchange.
Not what I want.
Color intrinsics ecstasy for transics list.
Let's see here, interlocked ad.
Exchange ad.
There's a 16 and there's a 32 and there's just this one which is
Long's.
So why isn't interlocked exchange ad?
That should do it right?
Interlocked exchange ad.
Ah, that's I'm just stupid.
I just felt change that variable.
Wasn't paying close enough attention.
Okay.
So, debug record re-index.
Oh, right?
That can't be in there.
So I should probably I should probably make them in the, in the build
a little more, a little more blatant so that you know, which ones are
the defined ones.
Something like that.
And we're better now.
Okay, so we have to store the counter.
I forgot about that.
So, because we have to store the counter, that means it has to go
here, right?
And that's not really too bad because we can get rid of all of this
stuff because we're going to be able to get rid of these things for
example.
So that's not the end of the world.
That's not really that that bad.
I'm okay with that.
So in here we would just do, you know, counter equals counter in.
It's like so
And then we could easily have it in here.
And I should probably do like this is debug record index like so and
there we go.
Record.
Debug events does, in fact need more information.
I agree with that.
And right, this guy has to be 0 macros and your wonderful name
conflicts.
There we go.
So I feel like that's basically it honestly it's really not a whole
lot else to say about that.
So we do have one problem.
Again, we have 20 minutes left on the clock.
So,
We're good to go.
We do have one problem and I don't really know.
How we want to solve it.
So the problem is when we go to flip these things over, we can do a
synchronous exchange of these pointers and that's not a problem.
But what we can't do is exchange the pointer and clear the event index
at the same time, right?
So that
that is a little Troublesome, right?
Again, it's a debug system so we don't have to be that careful because
multi-threading like over, right bugs, or whatever, here would show up
as a spurious timing thing.
Not a problem with the actual program, but it would be nice to get it
as clean as possible.
And I'm not sure, exactly how we would do.
That.
So I feel like that that to me implies that we actually do need to be
a little bit more.
A little bit more careful here.
So I think, I guess what I'm what I'm saying is we need to do
something like this probably, which does get us back to the the
interlocked increment thing I suppose we need to do something like
Global, debug Global debug array event array index and debug event
index where we pack those two into one variable, right?
And if we pack those two into
One variable, then we can just do something where we, when we do the
record record, debug event, we do the atomic ad and and hey, guess
what?
That's pretty great.
Because that means that we don't need this anymore.
I can get back to having just one happy day.
We can get back.
The array index event index pair and then use both of those two to get
what we want.
You know, so so yeah.
So we could say something like rid of that.
Manta ray.
inside here, we would say here is our global
Debug manta ray like so.
And when we want to actually access it, we would just use this guy to
pull out the important parts that we want.
So we'd say Global event array brackets, right?
Just the top 32 portion of it and then the event index would be the
masked 32 portion of it, you know.
So something like this
We would say shift that down by 30 to 60 and I think you do LL to sell
it.
I want that this is a 32-bit situation and then here I would do a x FF
FF.
I don't even know if I really need to do that so it'll be like that
for now assume it's smart enough to not do the wrong thing.
So there we would have right a pretty straightforward way of getting
both of those things at the same time.
And again the only reason I'm carrying
At this at all is I just want to make sure that I have at least some
semblance of a reasonable thread thing going on here.
So we don't have just a complete disaster when multiple threads are
going and we're trying to use the log, okay?
So let's see.
Global debug event index is now called this giant unwieldly name and
that's all fine.
There we go and event index here.
Where is that happening?
Oh, right, so I should probably pull that out so I can still do the
assert here is the relevant part there.
Here we go.
And I forget, this was one of those things where I never, I always
forget the why these things need to be written the way they're
written.
How do I tell you that?
I want this to be in here?
Why do you not have it in here?
Who are you?
Who is complaining handmade?
Dot CPP.
Why is it unresolved?
It's right.
Oh no, it's not.
I thought it was, it wasn't.
All right, so, that's pretty much it to be honest with you.
So I think all we have to do now is when we do our gather, right?
So we come down here and we've got the debug frame end when we do our
gather.
We just need to exchange this guy, right?
So what we want to do is we want to take the global debug event index
and do it.
You 64 like event, or array index,
Index, like so.
And we want to do a synchronous exchange of the values.
So we can just do something like Atomic.
Oh, we've even got a comic exchange 64 right there.
So, we just do an atomic exchange 64.
We say, we want whatever was in that variable before, and we just want
to exchange it with zero.
So it so that people start writing a fresh.
Okay, and that's it.
That's all I really wanted to do.
So that was it, of course, we're not actually working properly here.
What is the problem?
Mr.
In fact, you know what, I probably should do to.
I should probably make this an inline function for now, because
stepping through macros Heaven forfend, you should be able to step
through that grows after how many years of Visual Studio.
Still can't step through macros.
I thought the I thought they added that I guess.
Yes.
It's in like 2015 or something.
I don't know.
Anyway, so let me just make this be a thing that we're actually
calling here to bug event type and record index record index is just
an ant, right?
Yeah.
So, we'll go ahead and
D backslash, that guy.
There he is.
And just to, now we can debug him a little bit more easily, okay?
What has happened here?
My goodness, we already wrote 65,000 of them.
Is that is that actually plausible?
How do we feel about that?
Global debug event array index, event index.
Huh.
Don't know if I believe that how plausible that is.
to be completely honest with you,
Because we're clearing at every frame.
Just just blatantly right now, we're not really doing anything correct
with it but I don't feel like that should be getting up there.
So I let me just let me just double check to make sure that it
actually is getting up there.
That does seem to be getting up there while we call this a lot.
All right, let me double check that it's getting cleared although
maybe it's not getting cleared of course.
Like I said, so we don't really know but like debug rain and
Mmm.
Alright.
Well
I will bump that number.
Temporarily.
Just to see if that really is happening for reals, apparently, that
really is happening for reals.
We just have a lot of debug vents in there.
See what?
I mean, there's a ton of them.
That's just a lot of bandwidth, although not really.
But anyway, Sookie now we're actually logging those debug infos,
right?
We're having.
We are now have a complete log of the debug events.
We're just not doing anything with them but now we know basically, you
know, when everything happened completely so we now also know things
like nesting, right?
So at this point we actually could do some relatively crazy stuff.
So let's just take a look at what we would do here if we wanted to
start playing with this.
And actually Gathering it back up.
Now we now have to deal with this part where we actually do the
changeover.
And so let's talk about this, what I did right is I bundled the two
things, which debugger a you were writing into because they flip-flop
back and forth, right?
And what event it was, I bundle them together and the reason I did
that is so that I can atomically exchange them both at the same time.
And the reason for that is because like I'm writing into a buffer in
on a bunch of threads and I want to come along and see what's in the
buffer, but I need to be able to make sure that other threads when
they are going to come and start writing to the buffer.
Now don't accidentally right into the same buffer that I just said,
stop writing into.
So I want to be able to clear the event index and
The array index at the same time so that's why I bumbled them together
as a single thing.
So what I want to do here is I want to have some opinion right?
Of what should happen on the next flip?
I need to know whether the
Double array index should be 0 or 1 so I need to have a think, you're
right.
That's like some kind of an extern Global.
That's like, global current event array index, or something like that.
and that's just going to start out right at zero because it's a, you
know, it's a value that we're just going to know unless realized
since these are extra and they're not necessarily initialized.
So I should also be initializing that guy 20, just to make sure
That's true.
No I you know I don't know that it might not be that sad.
Ecstatics it may be that all extern Global's are 0 by default so
that's probably not true but I'll just put it in there.
Just to be can't hurt to be safe anyway.
So what I'd like to do
Is this this global current event array index tells me which array
index I'm looking at.
So what I'm going to do is every time through her, I'm going to say,
okay, whatever it was before, right?
I just want it to be, you know, the I want to toggle between 0 and 1 0
1 0 1.
So I can just do that to toggle it then what I'm going to put in here
is I'm just going to shift that up by 32.
To get that top, debug array index value to just flip flop back and
forth.
So that people right into one buffer, I read the other one, the right
into one, I read the other, right?
And so that's all fine.
And so here, you know, I've got when I, when I do this, I then know,
you know what, the array index that I was looking at is the array
index, is whatever.
The array index is swap down by 32.
I know what the event index is again, it's the same exact thing that
it was before, it's the event index and it with all
Ones on the bottom B.
And so now, I know this value right here was effectively how many
events actually got in.
So I could call this actually an event count, right?
Because it tells me what the next event would have been if someone was
going to write it, which is one past how many there actually are,
right?
The equals the count, which is one past however, many there actually
are.
So this tells me everything I need to know to go process that buffer.
And so, what I can do now is, I could collate these into some debug
piece of information.
Yeah.
Okay.
So instead of update debug records, I'm going to go make us some other
function here that we can test called collate debug records or
something.
Like this seems seems reasonable enough.
And so, what do I want to do there?
Well, I got a call it with, with some stuff, right?
I gotta call some things, I gotta pass it, some values, I'm going to
pass it that event count.
You know how many of these events do I want to actually do?
Do I want to pass it that Loops that Global event?
Ray already pre-selected for the one that we know we're actually
looking at.
So it knows that these are the debug records that it's going to go
ahead and plow through to do its analysis or whatever it is that it
wants to do.
Obviously it should take the debug state with it.
That's kind of a no-brainer because it's going to have to look right
to that.
And that is probably all there really is to that, right?
So if I come in here to collate debug records, I now need to actually
write the
This thing where these guys actually are, here we go to books and Line
Tech statistic, the big reset update debug reference.
I don't know why these guys are separated so much temporally.
That's I mean especially that seems a little bit stupid on Casey's
Park but what you gonna do?
So if I go ahead and make these guys actually a real function
prototype
Something like this.
Now, we have the ability to kind of spin over those and see what the
values are, right?
And so let's see if we can effectively recreate what was going on here
by using the collated information?
Get back.
Exactly the same information that we were getting from the other
counters, right?
Just as a first step and that would probably the end of what we'll do
in this room today and then if we can do that we then know that.
Not only do we have all the information we were getting.
Before but we also have a ton of other information about when each of
these things happened, who happened inside whom right and we can start
to build some kind of crazy amounts of debug inspection at that point,
right?
And so, we'll see
Okay, so step one collate, debug records.
I'm going to go through and I'm going to, I'm going to clear
everything right.
So I'm going to say, all right, here is a state.
I'm just going to do a zero struct on this thing.
It's just it's it's just it's gone.
It's clear, right?
What's up, although you know what?
I guess, I don't really want to clear the whole thing.
Why would I do that?
What I probably want to do, is just set.
Whichever.
One of the snapshots
I just want to clear those because these things I guess don't don't
really need to be cleared at all right?
Those don't have to be cleared.
So then what I'm going to do is going to run over all our debug events
Right.
So here is a, you know, event index.
I'm just going to run over all the events.
And for each event.
I am going to vent.
I'm going to look and grab that clock value out of it, right?
I'm going to use the exact same trick that I used before when I was
just summing.
Is up into.
When I was summing things up.
I take it back.
We have a slight problem here not to do with any of the stuff that we
just wrote, but just in the way that we're storing these things, we
still have two separate arrays of stuff.
And so linearizing them out is kind of a little bit janky, right.
So we actually need something a little bit smarter there.
We want to know how many there are in each of those things.
I'm going to move this guy down, so that's, that's actually a little
bit jankier or a little bit a little bit rougher, right?
It's okay.
It's not a big deal or anything but it's basically just something that
again, it's a little.
It's it's just a little bit jenker than we would like it to be.
And it's again because of the whole trying to assign unique counters,
to stuff situation with two different compilation units.
And even that of course, the only reason we have to do
That is because visual C++ doesn't allow us to tell it to just
optimize a particular function fantastically.
Otherwise we wouldn't even have be in this situation in the first
place.
But anyway,
So okay.
So if we take a look at this, we can see that we've got.
We know how many so we know that the total number, right?
We could we could even say debug state, right?
Counter count.
We can just say that we know that that's this plus this
Right, because we know exactly how many there are actually going to
be, that's how many we have.
So when we come through here, we can just call this counter index.
And now we've, we've cleared all of all of our stuff, right?
Everything that we had.
Then when we come through here, we need to kind of know, which one of
the two arrays were looking into.
So what we want to do is we want to have for these desks counter
States.
We want to have a notion of where the two of them are right.
So we want to have our counter state or I guess our counter array.
We want to have one that points into the the part for our main array,
right?
Which is just going to be the base.
And then we want one that points into the part for the optimized,
which is just going to be however many of these.
There actually were
In the main one it's that far forward.
So now we've made one linearized array.
That's got two segments.
It's got the first part which is all of the counters from the main
program and it's the second part which is all the ones from the
optimized part of the program.
And then
In here, we can always grab the one that we want by using that debug
record array index.
So, when we want to know which counter corresponds to this event, all
we do is we say the counter equals the counter array for that events.
Debug record array index.
and after we grab that out,
We just add to it whichever record index.
It was in that particular array.
Now we've got the counter so we can just say if the counter type is a
begin block.
Else.
Certain and block for now.
And in either case, we just take the counters, this thing right here,
right back to me, just call that d'Este event.
So if we take the dust and we want to write into it snapshots, all
we're going to do here is say that, you know, if we if we ran through
it will increment the hit count by one and we'll take the what's the
what is it?
Hit counts know.
Where is the state?
Where's the state stuff?
Kind of Snapchat, hit count and cycle Camp.
So the cycle count, we will just add to it.
Whatever the our dtsc was although we kind of have a little nasty
thing which is this is not a 64-bit value.
So I guess it would technically still work.
Wow, that bends the brain.
A little bit.
Yeah, we are pretty much out of time on the stream, so I'm just going
to do this, but we should probably talk about this and take a look at
it to make sure it's even doing the right thing a little bit later.
But yeah.
Alright, so we would subtract the clock there and we would add the
clock here and cross our fingers.
But that is effectively what we would need to do.
Alright, redefinition.
What are you talking about?
We've got a redefinition of this you're saying, where is it?
Redefined
Let's see, global debug event.
Ray, where do you think?
The first one was?
But that's an extra ah because I put this equal zero my bad.
Okay.
Conversion from you 60/40.
You 32 possible loss of data.
Yeah.
So I can I'm not gonna be able to do that.
Alright well just for now I'll change this but this is not something
we actually want to keep just going to go ahead and make the cycle
count 64 for now for now and then we'll actually we'll chop it down.
Later.
Okay.
Oops.
Shift count - or too big.
That is true.
I apologize.
You're going to have to up convert that to 64 bits.
Otherwise it would shift right on out and event index is Undeclared.
Yes this was just a typo Festival down here, wasn't it?
Okay.
Alright, so now we still have one more problem, which is we don't
actually fill in the file name or anything anywhere.
So none of these guys are going to show up but that's pretty easy to
do right when we're actually doing the collation here.
Any time we see one of these guys, we could just Boop's we could just
grab out the correct value.
That back to where it was we can just grab out the the value and write
it in there, right?
So what we would do for that, is this stuff right here where we live,
right?
In these various values that we actually need what we would do is we
have to grab that Source from somewhere.
So we need to know what the counter index was for this guy.
And we need to know what the counter base array is for this guy and so
again we can use the exact same trick here.
We know that debug record index is the counter index for the guy.
What we don't know is the counters array.
If that makes sense.
We don't look, we don't actually have any way of getting at the moment
at that that that base counter set right the debug record.
So what we want to do here is
Use the concept that we've got the debug record arrays.
Something like that.
And again, we're using exact.
We're just use the exact same trick, right?
We'll have one of these guys that's set up for two different ones.
Will just look up into it, with the array index and that unpacks for
us, whichever one, it was.
And again, we just know, we've got the main one and the regular one.
And we can access both of those because we already know how to do
that.
It's these two things right here, right?
So we just plug those guys in.
like that, and it
To go.
So, yeah, in theory, we're sort of getting there.
Although right, why aren't we seeing the rest of our dudes?
Unfortunately, we're pretty much out of time, so don't know that I
should debug this weekend and debug it tomorrow.
But yeah, it looks like only one of our folks is actually properly
writing it.
Oh,
That's backwards for starters.
So that's probably not a good thing.
Hey, look, that was one of the problems, obviously, so yeah.
Okay.
Now we've actually got, you know, in theory, something working here, I
guess the other thing I should say, is this, hit count should have
been plus plus, right?
It should have just increment of the account, not done it as one, but
it looks like we're not far from having this working to some degree.
It's just not quite there yet, right?
But these values look similar to the values.
We were getting
For so the hit counts.
Look roughly right.
These look like plausible.
Saigon and so I you know, it's not we're not done but it looks like
we're actually doing debug event logging now for a reasonable
definition of debug event logging.
So we're close so that all went relatively smoothly.
Again, we got some things to iron out but we're at the point now where
I think we're closer to being able to actually, you know, do what we
would expect.
So, so we'll look at that in more detail tomorrow.
For now we'll go to, I guess, what will be a relatively brief Q&A if
you have questions about what's going on there?
Go ahead and put Q Cohen in front of it and I'll answer them.
But then also tomorrow we'll finish up that stuff and then we can have
a more extensive Q&A tomorrow as well on the same subject basically.
Elvin, you mentioned that, you use a known Base address for your
memory management.
Could you talk a bit more about that?
Does that mean that I can now find things by just offsetting from that
address?
And does it mean that if I write this whole block out all essentially
F rating, the whole game?
Yes, that is all exactly what it means and we talked about this pretty
in detail.
If you just go back and watch the first, you know, 10 or 20, handmade
Heroes, they show how to set up all that stuff.
So you know, it's pretty straightforward.
Word.
What happens is you just allocate a big block of memory at a known
Base address.
That means that now pointers are actually just going directly into
that address.
So you can tell the offset of anything by just subtracting.
It's pointer from The Base address and that's the offset.
That's like the offset of where it would be in the file.
If you block written it, wrote it out, for example.
But why not one you can specify which function is to optimize by
kneeling optimization of the command line and surrounding code.
You don't want to visit pregnant optimized off.
No.
So we tested this and there was no way to just that we were unable to
get that pragma to Works efficiently.
We actually tested that on.
Handmade here are trying to just turn off optimizations Everywhere by
using pragmatic.
Nice off at the start of the program, then turning optimizes back on
just for one function, then turning it off again.
We were unable to get it to work.
If you can verifiably, make it actually work properly.
Something handmade hero forums.
How you did it because we were unable to make that work.
And by the way, verify that it really does fully optimize the
function.
But I think that was the problem too is that it wasn't actually
optimizing the function or something like that.
I don't know.
We can go back and look but
K.
Do you ever find use for size T?
Yeah.
We actually have a size, T, its memory index is I think what we call
it, I don't love the name but we have a tight for that because
sometimes you want to just say, well, whatever would fit a pointer
size thing, whatever would fit like a memory sized thing.
Do you keep track of struct padding when you add a new Fields?
Yes, I do.
Or is it something you don't think about too much?
So order feels doesn't matter.
I actually always do think about it.
I probably shouldn't spend much time thinking about it, but I just
kind of as a force of habit.
But why not also what's the point of the core number, in the debug
info?
It seems the thread ID is the important part.
So the reason is because that way we can see when things moved cores
So, like it's nice.
If you're looking in certain debug views, it's nice to see.
You can see that you got task swapped or something happened.
If a thing moves from one chord to another, it also helps, you know,
forecast coherent, see if things are, if things should be happening
on.
Same car, but aren't you like to go to see that?
So I would like to have that, but
No more questions about what we were doing.
Looks like
Well, that's good, I guess.
All right.
Okay then.
Well, that was good.
That didn't.
That wasn't too hard.
We'll have to see tomorrow how it is in terms of like how what the
performances of it and whether it's affecting the run of the program
too much or things like this.
But that was pretty good.
And so now that we have done that, I'm kind of interested to see.
It'll be fun tomorrow to play with to see if we can get some
interesting.
Debug visitors is happening.
Now that we have a lot more information to play with, so that'll be
pretty fun, I think least.
Yeah, at least I think it will be pretty fun.
And O, couple last-minute was, how will you avoid collecting or
displaying stats on debug rendering code?
Well,
That's actually something that maybe this log will allow us to do
which we could not have done before.
And you'll have to see tomorrow or, you know, a couple days this week.
Plain flavored our profilers is baggage debuggers.
Oftentimes, yes, in liverty, what do you think about checked
exceptions?
Checked exceptions.
I don't think I know the term checked exceptions.
I really don't like exceptions just.
But
Yeah, I don't really know what a checked exception is or maybe I do,
but don't tend to call it that name.
Anyway, thank you very much for joining me for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the code at home,
you can always pre-order handmade hero the game because it comes with
a source code and then you can play around with it at home and
experiment with it and do fun things like that.
And you can do that by clicking on this handy, dandy pre-order button,
right here.
We also now have a GitHub that's up and operational and part of the
pre-order comes with GitHub access, it's not a supported feature
because I don't know, get
Been so if it doesn't work, it doesn't work.
I don't pretend to guarantee that that's a working feature, but if you
are someone who is interested in GitHub access, please do check your
send, I will download page, whether you are buying it now or whether
you bought it six months ago, your send, I'll download page, should
have a little authorization code on it.
And that authorization code will allow you to attach your GitHub
username to our GitHub and sink the code with get.
So if you are one of those people who likes to
Apply to everyone on Twitter saying switch to get now.
Is your big chance to switch to get yourself?
Check that out again.
It's just a thing that we added as a bonus feature to people who
pre-ordered it's like there's it's not like you don't to pay extra for
anything like this.
It's just in there so play with that if that's something that
interests you there's also a bunch of people working on repositories
in there right now that are like ports to other languages.
Like there's a rust repository where people are doing ports to rust.
There's a go repository itself like this, those repositories.
Things.
When community members, who are interested in maintaining an actual
full port, they've asked me and I set that up for them.
So if you're somebody right now who's been working on a port, like you
have the Delphi or the New Port to c-sharp of handmade hero and you
would like to be a maintainer of something like that, please let me
know because I can set up a repository for you as well.
But again it's only for people who are actually going to actually try
to keep the whole thing ported, so you know only only let me know
about that if you're actually pretty serious.
Got it.
Otherwise you can always just do it in your own private GitHub and and
be doing it yourself.
But if you're someone who wants to be, do a really serious one and
would like other people to be able to kind of collaborate and do all
that sort of stuff.
In a way that's facilitated by me, sort of like officially adorning
that repository, let me know and we can take a look at that.
Otherwise, the private ones as far as I know when you do a private
Fork.
I don't really know much about get up like I said, but I believe you
can still invite other people to that private Fork.
As long as they are,
So people who are on the private GitHub.
So I think you can also just do your own little private collaborative
projects and that's actually fine too.
But it's just again, if you want the sort of official Focus point of
having an officially designated one that's like, okay, this is a going
to be the community port to blah.
Let me know because I can set that up as well.
All right.
In addition, to all that good stuff, we also have a patreon page, you
can pledge to if you want to support the series, that's always very
much appreciated.
We also have a forum site that you can go to ask.
Questions.
There's an antidepressant guide on there.
That's pretty cool too.
We have a tweet bought that treats the schedule at you in case you
want to catch the stream live, you can check out the Tweet button and
that will always keep you up to date on when handmade here will be
broadcasting live if you want to be able to catch the stream live and
ask questions.
All that stuff, that's the place to check it out.
That's about it for today.
I will be back here tomorrow to sort of play with that new debug log
and stuff that we've created and see if we can get some interesting
information out of it that we couldn't have gotten with the other
system.
Hope to see you all back here to for that.
That's 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time tomorrow.
Until then, please have fun programming and I'll see you guys on the
internet.
Take it easy everyone.