The start recording button.
There we go.
And the stream has begun.
Okay, everyone welcome to gosh.
I think it is day 14.
It is day 14 of handmade hero.
The the show, where we code and entire game from scratch live on the
internet.
Basically, using only using only our wits and Ingenuity which are
sometimes lacking, you know, it can happen.
But we do the best we can and we're making pretty good progress.
Yes, I daresay.
Today.
What I want to talk about mostly is memory management, or at least the
beginnings of a philosophy of memory management.
We're obviously going to talk about it quite a bit throughout the
entire stream as the need arises.
But basically that's we're going to talk about today.
If you have pre-ordered, the game and are following along with the
source code.
This is day 14.
So you want to unzip day 13 source, and that is what you will start
with.
That is what I am starting with today.
So, so let me tell
Tell you about why I think now is the time to start talking about
memory management.
One of the things that you will notice so far in the Stream is we
haven't done any memory management and that is a good thing.
So basically, if you look in here, this is actually kind of a typical
nowadays, you know, most programs, most programming, languages, most
anything you cannot.
You cannot really.
We get into Maine without allocating a ton of memory crazy garbage
collection.
God knows what's going on, you know, you fire up a PG pH sorry, PHP
program, which I was having to deal with over the weekend.
In fact, for the forums, you fire up a PHP programming, God only knows
how much memory is getting allocated and freed on every line.
I mean, it's just crazy town, right?
Memory.
Allocation is just a willy nilly thing these days.
It's just it's just full banana cakes.
And so, one of the things I'd like to point out is we have done no
memory management so far.
Basically, all we did was we needed a sounding
Buffer and we needed a bitmap buffer.
So we just ask the operating system for to flatbuffers.
We never free them.
They're just there forever and they're used but our program is
completely stable in the memory sense because of that.
There, it just runs forever.
You're never worried about if you, there's no such thing as running
out of memory in this program, for the most part.
If it starts at all, it's good to go.
Right?
And that's a pretty interesting thing to think about, for a second.
Because technically any time you do a memory allocation, you have
introduced a failure Point into your program, right?
Memory is a limited resource.
And basically every time you do a memory a lock it could fail and so
if the result of that memory allocation was important to you you
basically have to handle that or just acknowledge the fact that your
program better run on essentially an infinite memory device now.
Fortunately these days a lot of times you are on what is effectively
an infinite.
Memory device for all intents and purposes.
Is you probably won't be able to allocate enough memory to force
Windows to run out of its own virtual backing store, but you certainly
can hit circumstances where you will, you know, start thrashing and
stuff as the virtual memory starts paging and all these other sorts of
things.
There's all sorts of masses involved there.
And also, what can I say?
This is an old school programming stream and in my mind, I kind of
like to think about what it means to have programs that that don't
have those failure cases.
That just then just aren't going to fail if they start.
They will run to completion and they will never fail.
I like that idea.
It's fun for me.
And in case you haven't noticed, a lot about what the stream, a lot of
what this stream is about, is making programming fun again for people
who really like to kind of get in there and, and sort of do the real
sort of work of like coding, something, meticulously, and doing
something interesting.
And so to me, I really like thinking about things that a cot different
level than what a most people like to think about.
I tend to like to think about it is, can we just never do any mail and
memory allocation at?
All?
Right.
Can we just never actually allocate any memory?
And so one of the things that I guess might be slightly surprising to
people as we go forward here is, I don't really anticipate us doing
memory allocation.
Basically, what we are going to do is we are going to do sort of an
old-school flat partition where we just grab a chunk of memory.
At the beginning.
We pre decided.
Side.
How much space we're going to allow each thing to use each subsystem
to use and then those subsystems are going to be written such that
they must run in that space.
So it is not a question of memory, allocation down the road.
It is just a question of.
They are hard written to never be able to go outside of a boundary
that you give them.
Does that make sense.
I know that might sound a little odd for people, aren't used to it.
People who are used to it old school, arcade, programmers and stuff
are like, yeah, that's what we do.
Obviously these days, that's not typical.
So anyway, I'm going to go that route.
And so the techniques that I'll be showing you are going to be very
different from what you're used to seeing in most.
I would say programming literature these days, but I think that's a
good thing because yeah, I like to I like to show kind of different
ways to do things.
I'm not trying to tell you to do it this way.
Like I say on a lot of streams.
I'm just telling you how I like to do it and certainly almost every
game that shifts today doesn't do it this way.
Most of them are allocation.
Eels, but, you know, it's good to have different perspectives.
So, let's jump into things here.
Why do I even think we need to start talking about memory allocation.
Now, we had this little program running, it essentially doesn't really
do any memory allocation doesn't ever free.
Anything and doesn't really need to allocate anything on any given
frame.
So why am I saying now is the time?
Why do I think that's true?
Well, it's because of this stuff right here.
Basically what I did is to get this working while we were sort of
playing around.
Your platform API is, I said, well, we've got these local persists
here, which remember is just static and see, it's something I've
defined so we can see what it is when we grep for things, because
static has three meanings at least in.
See, if not more, especially when you consider C++.
There's even more meanings.
It's just a keyword that's really overloaded.
And so what I like to do is kind of get that down so you can rap for
it.
So local persist just means that this is essentially a global
variable.
It's you know, it's more or less like I put it out here.
The only thing that's different is its scope just to this function.
So it's kind of like a less.
Less obtrusive Global variable but it's still basically that and I
don't really like to have that sort of thing lying around.
Certainly.
I'm not going to be able to do that for all the stuff we need because
that would be kind of a little bit absurd.
You know, I'm trying to think if what you would, what would happen if
I just typed in to see right here, a local, persist persistent local
variable.
That was like, you know, four gigabytes of memory.
I have no idea what would happen there, but I don't expect it would be
good.
So point being, if we want this game to have some stuff like say a
large backing store for for images that are getting loaded off disk
our stuff and we're talking about allocating like a gigabyte of memory
to store stuff in or any of that sort of stuff.
We actually need to get ourselves some memory here.
And so I figured, I might as well go get to that point now where we're
actually storing our game State because we do have some game state
blue offset green and offset and tone hurt.
So let's just pretend that that's
Real game State, and not some tests game State and start to see how,
where are we going to put that?
How's that going to get stored?
How's that going to work?
Now?
I'll show you.
Basically, what would normally happen in a normal scenario?
That is not being coded in the way that I'm advocating coding.
Because I like to show you kind of the other way first.
So what would normally happen in a lot of circumstances is you would
see something that looks a lot like this.
Let's say, say game startup, so there might be a call like game
startup that we call.
It's got a game state that it returns.
Right?
And what it's going to do is it's going to allocate one of these so
it's going to call an allocation function.
So maybe that's Malik.
Maybe that's a lot of in a lot of cases that would be because it's be
C++ code, it would call new which allocates memory.
If not told to do otherwise.
Basically, what would happen is, it would new the game state?
It would check here.
Hopefully to see whether the game State actually got allocated
properly.
It would fill out some stuff in the game state.
So it would do something like this.
Let's say, we have blue offset here.
We'd have green offset here.
And you have to imagine if this is a real game, which this will be in
a couple months.
We will have a lot of serious stuff going on in here.
So you have to imagine if this were the real game already, there would
be a lot of stuff in here.
Not just these three things, but point being it would start up and it
would initialize anything that in need to initialize.
Is to whatever a need to initialize it to then.
At the end, it would return this game State structure.
And that would basically be sort of like creating.
A game, it's like, the Constructor for the game.
And if you were a C++ person this way, actually would be a Constructor
for the gamestate object.
For example, you could go many layers, deep into this.
And then later, they'd be something like this.
We'd have something called game shut down.
Probably it would take the game state right in here.
Right?
And then, we would go ahead and we would, we would delete the game
state, right?
Like that, something like this and then game update, and render would
take the game State as a pointer like this, right?
And then, from then,
N on.
It would basically be fine because we would just use those things.
Basically, we use the game State like this, so you can kind of see how
I pulled that out there.
You can see how I kind of got rid of those global variables by just
pulling them out into a struct basically and that strut, you know, we
would Define out here as like, the game State thing, right?
So we'd say something, I'm actually not going to separate that to do
from its thing there.
So basically, we would have something that looks like this and it
would have our variables in there.
Are
No, one hurts our green offset and our blue offset, right?
That's that's all that I'm talking about here.
So that's it.
That's like how that would normally go will compile that there and
then this guy would have to pass it.
So what I want you to see about this method is basically and and to
extend it a little further, everything in the game would look like
this.
Whenever you wanted to do something like you wanted to create a game
asset, you would do something like this you'd have
Game asset equals new game assets.
Not kind of a thing, right?
Something like this.
You'd pass maybe a filename to load it from this would do some stuff.
It would allocate that game asset, right?
It's game assert.
That's a nice typo, game asset.
It would allocate that here, you know, this sort of thing.
It would return it, right?
Like this, and then you have a corresponding free call that would
release it.
So you're basically our your code just it would be littered with news
and deletes and this is very typical.
I don't know what the status is of, say Unreal, Engine 4, but I
remember like with, at least with Unreal Engine 3.
It's like, news and deletes are everywhere.
There's all kinds of this sort of memory allocation going on.
It's crazy town in an inside, a given frame.
There's tons of news and deletes and all of those are technically,
failure points and most of them probably wouldn't get handled
properly.
Maybe they would, maybe they wouldn't, but it's just kind of assumed
for the most part that they aren't going to fail.
Because either, you know, you've kind of, you know, roughly how much
memory you need.
And, you know, you kind of know that you're running in that much
memory.
Or stuff like this, or they start to do things like they overload new
to like, you know, handle allocations in special ways.
All these are the sorts of things.
So basically like that's just typical and it's typical even in
high-end code.
So I'm not I'm not trying to say that this is something not to do.
I'm just, I'm just gonna say this is not what we're going to do.
So that's basically what what tends to happen in a lot of typical game
code these days, right?
So reasons why I don't love this.
The first reason is because you got to have a strategy for the failure
cases, right?
Either, you going to have to handle it.
Somehow one way is basically, you just say, all right, everywhere that
we do a new or an A, like we check for failure and we actually handle
the failure, propagating all the way out.
That's difficult.
Right?
That is, that is tricky in a lot of cases, because now you got all
these paths that can both fail and succeed and you got to know how
each of them Works.
What happens if I
Didn't get a game asset and I needed to.
In this case, what happens if the this particular system couldn't
start up because of memory, whatever do I just do?
I panic?
What do I do there?
But you got to have a story.
Another story might be.
Oh, well, we ran the game, lots of times.
I mean, look at how much it used and we always make sure we get that
much on Startup and we use our own allocator that's of allocates out
of there.
And we just know from having ran it multiple times, that we know that
it just doesn't overrun this much memory.
We hope.
And we just hope the player doesn't do something that we didn't think
of, who knows?
But you gotta have a story.
There's some story
Sometimes the story and there's plenty of games that ship and this is
the story.
The story is, we have no idea.
The story is just, we just don't know, it doesn't seem to run out of
memory when we've tested it.
So that's all we've got.
And those are all not my favorite answers so so I don't really love
that.
That's one downside.
But there's another downside that even people who who think that I'm
crazy about memory might agree with in a separate context as nothing
to do with that at all.
And basically, what that is, is it adds another loop back to your
platform abstraction.
And one of the things that I was talking about before is like one of
the reasons that I like doing the platform attraction this way and
like I said, almost nobody
Does it this way.
But the basically the way where it's just, it's to data pipes in and
out.
And you're trying to, basically minimize the cases where you ever do a
round trip through the game.
You pretty much just want the game to be a service to the platform or
the platform just says, I need the, I need the video frame.
I need the audio.
That's like what you're looking for, and it pushes down the input to
it.
Just as here's the input.
So, there isn't called.
There isn't like any time when the platform calls the game calls the
platform again, just to get rid it to completely get rid.
Rid of that round tripping because again, that round-tripping is what
creates complexity in terms of understanding how the platform and the
game layer relate to each other, and it means that if you want to do
some more advanced things like say, recording the entire session of a
game and playing it back for debugging purposes.
If you know that you have one defined input stream and one defined
output stream kind of a thing.
It's a lot easier to do that sort of thing.
Right?
And so unfortunately that argument is a lot weaker these days now,
Multi-core is such a thing.
It becomes extremely difficult to do playback systems properly because
of all the threading stuff.
So it's the least of your worries.
The thing I just said about but in the old days when things were
single-threaded, this was definitely a huge win in terms of playback.
Not so much anymore because you got yellow.
Headaches, you got to worry about in that situation.
So
What's the alternative to this?
What do I propose if I don't think this is good idea.
Well, what I'm going to do instead is I'm going to do exactly the same
tack.
I took before and just say, well, if the game wants memory, then the
game gets memory from the platform layer in a big old chunk at startup
and the game is responsible for doing everything else.
Right?
Basically, I'm just going to say, you know what, we just pass in a big
ol thing here called game memory.
And that's just a, that's just a struct, right?
And that struct is going to
Basically stuff in it that allows us to allocate what we need.
Dude, are partitioning on the game side and then all that's going to
happen.
Is the platform layer is going to call one, or it can cause major
wants really virtual Alex at startup to get our memory space set up.
And then once it is set up, that's it.
It just gets passed to the game.
The game is responsible for sub partitioning that memory and it is
responsible for ensuring that all of its systems.
Always operate inside a fixed space so they can be pre partitioned at
startup.
And you know that if that if the game started up at all, it will run
to completion period and
Is and and will be also seeing that.
I will take the same tack with disk I/O which I realize is a little
odd, but I'll be taking the same track with disk I/O.
So the goal here is like there's zero failure states in the game.
The platform layer obviously can have all kinds of failure States
because the operating system is not built with a similar philosophy.
The operating system is built poorly.
It is Windows.
It does not do a good job on any of the fronts that I'm talking about.
And so once we get down to the platform layer, we can't create
something that is
Reliable.
That's true.
But we certainly can create the game in such a way that is 100%
reliable.
And that is what we will be striving for.
We will definitely be looking as we go to hitting the highest
Benchmark.
We can in terms of making the game.
So that once it starts up, it does not fail.
And if things like disk IO fails, that just means there's Sprites
missing but the game works, right?
That's, that's sort of what we're going for.
And the, you know, we'll sort of have a like gold silver bronze
standard there and we'll see kind of How High we can hit.
Depending.
Circumstance.
Different games can hit that standard different levels depending on
what they need to do.
Basically it's a, it has to do with with space, but we'll get into
that later.
All right, anyway, so basically, all I want to do is I want to pass
memory here and I'm going to say a couple things about my memory.
Basically, what I want to do is I want to sort of subdivide this
memory into a few different partitions.
Basically, I want to have
Have scratch space sort of space that is not really about storing the
game and then in theory could kind of go away at any given time.
So it's kind of like space that is transient and and then permanent
stuff.
So basically stuff that stores, the actual state of the game such that
it definitely needs to persist as is from from one frame to the next
because it's what holds sort of the game together.
Right?
And so basically what will happen here is I want to be able to store
these things.
The blue off, set the tone hurts, the green offset.
Those are examples, right?
Of things that need to be stored in the permanent store.
And so that's really all I have right now.
And so, basically, what I've got is I've got
I've got a I guess I'm going to use it in 64 in case we ever want to
be absolutely giant.
So I'm going to say we have a un 64 which is are essentially our
permanent storage space and then we've got a void star which is our
permanent storage, right?
So all I'm doing here is, I'm basically saying, well, I, I'm going to
have some place to store.
Well, I'm a spelling genius tonight.
Basically.
I'm going to
Some place to store things that have to persist from frame to frame
because that's what I want here.
So all I'm going to do is I'm going to basically say, well that game
State thing that I had, right, that I'd find before.
Did.
I just go ahead and delete that.
I'm an idiot.
That's not good at all.
I wanted to keep that.
I just wanted to move it.
I didn't want to delete it.
There we go.
So anyway, let's get that back there.
Game memory memory.
There we are.
So basically what I want to do is I'm going to take this game State
here, right?
Right, and I'm just going to put that inside the game memory.
Now, I can put that here.
I don't know if this doesn't really need to be in the the stuff that
defines a platform.
So I'm just going to separate that out for now.
We'll see where I want to live later because this is not something
that the this is not something that the winter to layer needs to know
about.
So think about it a little differently.
But point being this guy is going to come in here and basically all
I'm going to do is I'm going to say that my game state, right?
Whatever this game state is, that's just going to equal for now.
I'm just going to go ahead and cold-cast straight to the actual.
That I've got for my permanent store, right?
My permanent storage right there.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm going to basically introduce a
notion here and that notion is essentially, let the game memory will
have some concept of whether or not.
This is the first time around because obviously there's initialization
that has to be done that initialization, that was going to have a call
before.
That did the round trip Alec.
I still want to do the initialization.
I just don't want the round tripping.
So I'm going to say for now, I'm going to say is initialized and
basically that's going to be false the first time through and true
every time thereafter.
So basically, I'm going to do here is I'm going to say if the memory
is initialized, I should say.
If not, then I am going to go ahead and initialize it.
I'm going to go ahead here and say that the
A the game State tone hurts are 256.
And then the other
Is let's see.
Green offset, equals zero game state blue offset equals zero.
And that's really all I needed to do.
Right.
So now, we've gotten rid of our local position.
Those are in there.
So now all I need to do is I actually need to pass this this memory
out to, to the game.
So I'm going to call that game memory.
I'm gonna go ahead and say, game memory.
And then I've got to actually do those allocations here to actually
get it.
Something that it can use.
So where's my virtual a?
Like, I've got
It in here somewhere.
There's for the, there we go.
There's the 14 sound.
So I'm going to still do separate virtual Alex for now, even though in
the future we may well, we may well pull those guys together because
that's something I wanted to do.
All right.
So the game memory, I'm going to wipe that 20 first and I'm going to
say the permanent storage size.
I don't know how big the permanent storage size for.
Our game is either going to be constants.
We're going to tune, but I'm going to say something like 64, MB.
Maybe.
I don't know.
Let's let's pretend that.
It's going to be 64 megabytes.
Just for now.
We'll see how much we actually need later.
And then I'm going to say that the permanent storage, right?
Like this is going to equal another one of these nice virtual Alex
here and that's going to be however much.
I just said storage size was so there it is.
We're going to men commit that because we're going to use it.
And then all I'm going to do is I'm going to go up in here into into
this guy and I'm going to define a couple more macros for me here.
These are ones.
I just like to hold around.
Basically kilobytes megabytes and gigabytes.
It's just in case you ever want to use those.
So basically whatever you pass in here, whatever the value is is going
to be the value, right x?
1024, that makes sense, basically, like, so if you said four
kilobytes, you're going to x 1024 and then basically, each one of
these, is just going to be the exact same thing.
You could think about it.
It's doing it this way, if you wanted to, it's a macro, so it'll
expand.
So it's kind of free for us to do this.
We do have to worry about any kind of a penalty there, anything like
that.
That.
So, we're basically going to say, oops, MB value x, 24 and 24.
So basically, you can see it there.
That's just a shorthand.
So if I wanted to allocate 64 gigabytes for some reason, I could do
that, but I'm just going to do that.
Right?
Does that make sense?
Hopefully that makes some sense.
So what we need to do here is just pass the pointer.
Then I think that's good to go.
Okay.
So basically what we're going to do is we're going to we have the is
initialized thing.
Here.
It will be set to 0 by default first time through.
And of course if I were just to run it now is initialized, will never
get set to true.
Now.
The question is coo sets is initialized to True.
Is it the game, or is it the platform layer for for the moment?
I'm going to say and I'm not 100% comfortable with this decision.
But I'm going to say that's the game.
The reason I'm going to say that is because it's one less thing the
platform layer.
To do and the game is always going to do in here.
So I'm gonna just say that it says to enter service is true here, but
I'm going to say this may be more appropriate to do in the platform
layer and will think.
Think about it later if it ever comes up, something to think about, we
will do that.
And so now in theory, we should be able to step through here and see
what goes on.
Now, basically, what happens,
Is when we get to that point in the code, I keep zooming right past
it.
People.
There we go.
So, we come in here, right?
And we've got our game memory, and it is just initialize to zero.
We then sticks how much we want to put on the, how much actual memory
want there.
So that's 64.
Megabytes is exactly what we wanted.
We're then going to do our virtual Alec and hope to get that space.
It looks like we did.
So we're all
There and basically what I want to do, you know, I forgot to do this
and we might as well do this.
Now.
I want to actually also check those because obviously there's going to
be another if here somewhere which is basically like hey if the
samples, you know, and the game memory are both valid then do the
game, right?
And that'll we're not really going to do it quite like that at the end
of the day, but it's sort of the same thing.
So basically if we can't get the memory, we're not going to run
because if we
Can't allocate the memory.
We need to run.
Well, there's not gonna be much of a game if it can't store anything,
right?
So we come through here.
And then we're going to go ahead and the first time through when we
call this guy game update and render, we step in there.
We take a look, we get back the game State, and that's just set to
point to that first bit of memory there.
And then we go ahead and do the initialization of it.
There it is.
And then we set the memory initialized to true.
So the next time through here when we
Back through again.
We won't initialize.
It will just skip right over it.
So off we go.
So basically what's going to happen is?
We should expect to see everything tracked.
It is tracked.
That's all good.
Everyone's happy.
At least, I'm happy.
And sometimes it's about making me happy most of the time, it's about
making the viewers happy.
Honestly, I'm here for you guys.
But sometimes, you know, you got to make yourself happy as well.
If you're not happy.
How are you making your stream happy?
That's that's the way I like to think about it.
We should all be happy together.
Ideally.
Someone has to be miserable.
It might as well be me rather than you, but if we can all be happy,
that's the best of both worlds.
So the next thing I wanted to ask about basically because I know this
is a little ridiculous.
I don't pretend that it isn't, but I'm just going to go ahead and say,
I'm gonna go ahead and I'm just going to, I'm just going to go out on
a limb here.
I'm gonna go out on a limb and say, what, what if Santa Claus is sort
of real, you know, I'm one of those people who who didn't believe in
Santa Claus, even when they were little, basically thought it was all
Big old big ol.
I was true.
It turned out that I was right about that.
It's unfortunate.
But what if I was actually wrong and Santa Claus, Santa Claus is real
and we can get everything we want for Christmas.
The thing I want to basically know is, is this memory allocated by
this function is automatically initialized to 0.
Do you see what that says now?
That is like, that is like the sleigh with the Reindeer and the
blinking red nose.
The only thing that's not in this leg, yet is the presence but we're
to get the goes to because what that says to me is basically the thing
that I always ask for the thing that I was like, I like having
initialization be clear to 0 so the basically just like as much as
possible.
You don't do any initialization.
You just clear 20 and things are initialized.
Well how happy am I?
Because basically that's exactly what happened here.
I don't even need to do those two things because now I'm just
guaranteed that basically the permanent storage is always going to be
cleared to zero on this platform and probably any other platform.
A security.
And it's not that expensive to clear 64 megabytes 20.
It sounds like a lot, but it's just, it's instant, it start up.
Its you don't even notice it mean.
You didn't see it happen, right?
Neither.
Did I.
So basically what that means is I can just go ahead and Define that.
I want this for Christmas.
I can basically just say permanent storage is basically required to be
cleared to zero at startup.
It just if the platform doesn't already do that, then we'll write the
code to do it in that in that particular.
Form layer.
So, that's good.
That is what we want to see.
So, that's that present one for Christmas.
But, but I'm sorry, that's, that's, I guess, that's I say it was.
I was my metaphor.
That was the reindeer.
I want the sleigh with the presents.
Now, the sleigh with the presence is this guy right here.
So basically that zero is, is that zero is is a is a sack of like as
the Santa Claus's sack ready to be filled with presents.
And I apologize for the
The young children on the stream for using the word sack like that,
but I meant it in a good way something that carries presence.
Basically what we're talking about here.
Is this parameter that we have been ignoring this LP address.
Basically, if you pass 02 LP address.
What that means is that the the address you're going to get back from
virtual.
Alec is going to be whatever the operating system wants to give you
and that is fine for most purposes.
We don't care where the sound output went.
We don't care where the bitmap is, but I'm going to argue for the
moment that we actually
Do perhaps care where the game memory is?
And so we're going to do a permanent storage I said before as well we
were going to do a transient storage.
Remember I said that I wanted to do a transient storage size as well.
Basically, something that's that's kind of just like ephemeral.
It's used for doing work, but it doesn't have to persist necessarily
those sorts of things.
I'm going to say that for those things.
We may well want to actually have a way.
To sort of, you know, you know, to, to make these be at fixed
locations.
In memory, when we're running on our machine.
Now, in the wild, it would be foolish of us to expect that.
We can always ensure that no matter what platform wherever running on
the future that we can mandate the location of an allocation.
If the world work, the way I wanted it to you absolutely would be able
to do that.
As far as I'm concerned, that should have just been locked down.
Like all addressing should have been totally locked.
So that you actually say, just where you want your stuff and that's
it.
Unfortunately.
I do not rule the world or maybe you think that's, fortunately,
because everyone would have to eat to katsu and lobster all day or
stuff like this.
But ignoring things like that, that are a little weird and the almond
milk situation that would probably result that, I think would have
been a much better way to go, and
Would have gotten a lot simpler.
And there would have been a lot things we could do.
That would be a lot more powerful.
But short of getting that present down the chimney.
This Christmas we can get something else and that something else is on
our machine.
When we run we can have the same memory location every time we run.
That means two things.
One.
It means all of our pointers will be the same every run until we
actually change code so that they, you know, are allocating more stuff
for something like this and that really helps for debugging things.
So that basically means that if you look at a pointer in one run of
the program, you can know that it's going to be that same pointer.
Assuming you do this, a deterministic set of steps in the next run of
the program.
Whereas normally with Windows where it does its address randomization
stuff for security.
That's not going to be true.
If we were just allocating off the Heap, it be wherever it was and I
see
Virtual Alec also returns random addresses as well.
I don't actually know because we haven't tested that, but I assume
that they're going to be different every time.
In fact, I think we may have seen them di different every time we step
through before.
I don't know, doesn't matter point being, we want to lock that down
and make sure that we know that we're always in the same place for a
number of reasons to buggies.
One of them, other things will come later that where it's like.
Hey, did you see how I did that?
Well, that was because of this.
So, basically, what I'm going to say is that basically are transient
storage.
Let's say is going to be bigger than that are transient storage.
I think, on the PC.
See realistically speaking.
I think we want at least two gigabytes.
I mean cuz basically PCS have a ton of memory these days and we're
going to want to use it on win32.
I don't think anyone's going to be running this game in less than 2
gigabytes on the bigger side.
Now, we could will shrink that will basically make that shrink down on
Lower platforms obviously, but when we're talking about running, the
big high-res Graphics, we're going to want that to be big.
So, certainly during development to gigs for gigs.
Let's say four gigs, just so it pushes us up to the Ford to the oops.
That's no good.
That's four terabytes.
So for gigs would be good because that actually gets us up to full
64-bit address range.
So it's make sure we didn't screw anything up with are Pointers.
So let's let's try this and just see and then later we'll make a low
profile version where these things are much smaller.
So let's let's
That let's go ahead and try that and see what we can do there.
And then I'm going to I'm going to specify these memory allocation
locations as well.
Alright, so um handmade here.
I'm going to go ahead and make another one of these.
This is going to be basically a minute replace permanent with
transient.
That's about the only thing that's going to happen.
And since we can will just require to be clear, 20 again.
Why not?
Let's just see what happens.
You know, I mean if it's going to do, it's going to do it.
I assume to I should mention.
I mean, I don't know.
I'm guessing.
Hmm.
Yeah, so that just work.
No, it didn't.
Work.
Did that just that did not allow me to what?
Why don't know what why not.
Why can't I why can't I allocate the memory?
So it did not like it that large apparently apparently.
Oh.
Awesome.
That's that's that's fantastic.
Well, you know, I guess you should just expect these sorts of things.
So what happened there was kind of it and it's good that this
happened.
Some point in the Stream so I can explain it.
This is annoying.
So basically what happened there, as we wrapped the exact thing I just
said to make sure that we don't have any bugs is exactly what we did.
Have.
The problem here is that c has decided in its infinite decimal wisdom
that it wants to do this in 32 bits this computation.
So, when I said, four gigabytes, it proceeded to take 1024 and
multiply it by 1024 and multiply it by 1024 and multiply it by 4
gigabytes, which perfectly gets to 4 gigabytes, but perfectly gets to
the four billion number that wraps a Unit 32 around 20.
Now I wanted it to do it in 64-bit, which I can't actually tell it to
do in any other way.
So basically, what I have to do here is I have to give it something.
I have to, I have to sort of poison the pot, if you will because the
way see does things is it will promote numbers up to higher bit
depths.
If something in the expression is requiring that, right.
So what I can do is try to convince it that I need this.
Be done in 64 bit by saying that that for is really a 64-bit for
please.
And then when I come in here and Theory, I will get yeah, there we go.
I'll get the actual number that I wanted.
That is really annoying.
I hate stuff like that.
It doesn't make any sense.
I don't like the way he does.
That sort of stuff.
I believe that's technically called integral promotion, and you can
read more about that nonsense, intradural promotion.
Let's take a look here and come on.
Hello.
There we go.
So, basically, this this old Ridiculousness.
This is kind of the Annoying stuff where it's just like, you know, if
this is actually it might not be all this point being.
I'm
I'm going to belabor it because first of all, I don't even know what
all the rules are like, at one point.
I probably read them, but I don't even know.
Like, if you gave me an expression with something complicated and I
wouldn't necessarily know what it decided to promote things to
unsigned, or signed, and, and bigger and smaller, and all this other
stuff.
Basically.
It's just really annoying.
It's one of those things where see has all these rules.
It does.
It should have just been explicit or had some way of saying, you know,
if it's all constants, then it just produces the result in constant
and if it's not that is something else.
I don't know.
His desires should have, worked something better.
Hopefully, when John does his language, they'll be something awesome
in there.
I don't know.
But point being, that's what we hit.
Now that we've taken care of that, it should be fine.
Yeah, there we go.
And so like, you see, there's no penalty, therefore, clearing, 20,
really?
Because what, I believe happens and like I was saying before, I don't
know this, for sure, but I believe happens is, I don't even know if
Windows ever bothers to actually clear all that memory, right?
Then.
I think what it might do is just mark it as needing to be cleared.
And then when we actually go to access the page, the first time, it
does the clear right there.
I don't know.
I don't know which it does.
I don't care.
It's fine with me as long as we don't see any kind of performance
weirdness from it.
We should be fine.
As soon as we start using the memory will take that hit and we'll be
fine.
If we if it turns out that we don't like the in particular that hit,
we could just write here, sweep through the whole thing reading
values, and writing to it arbitrarily or something like that, but we
don't really need to do that yet.
So anyway, that basically gives us everything we needed and now, you
know, not to be anticlimactic but
You have now seen probably all of the allocations were ever going to
do.
That that was it.
Maybe we'll chunk those up a little bit more.
We may also do a thing for debug allocation where we where we do some
stuff that doesn't quite work that way.
But I mean, that's really what we're talking about here.
That is that is really that's that's it.
And so we know that basically if we get here we're ready the game will
run.
It will never fail to it will never run out of memory it like the
operating system has to fail at that point.
Not
Us.
So we're good.
So that's kind of cool.
And basically what we're going to do from now on is we're always going
to use stuff in there.
So I know it's a little anticlimactic.
Like I said, very anticlimactic but the basic reason is that
everything else?
All the other systems we're going to do the other interesting memory,
allocation stuff that we're going to do is all just going to be part
of the systems that we write.
So there's really nothing to cover other than what we just did.
That was it?
We now have memory for our game.
We have all the memory we're ever going to need for our game.
We are going to run.
The entire game in that memory.
And so, yeah, party time.
So I think that's basically all we needed to do.
Let me double-check to make sure that we actually show that we have
gotten that memory and we have what we think we have.
Just to make sure there's nothing weird going on here.
There.
We are.
There's our four.
It's just like we thought.
So it looks pretty good.
And that is that is it?
That is, that is really all there is to it.
That's, that's, that's all.
So, that is basically it what we want to do eventually.
Like I said, when we start to play around with this a little bit more,
we're going to want different profiles here because basically what
we're going to want to do is say okay on 32-bit platforms.
We're going to allocate like one gigabyte of transient and we might
also take a look at how much memory
Memories in the machine.
We might allocate 8 GB.
If the Muse has got a ton of memory because you can always use more
backing store to make the game more performant and stuff like that.
So, so we'll see.
So basically this is the, this is basically what's going to happen,
but you know will fine-tune how much we allocate and how a little more
in the future.
Of course.
The other thing that we can do is just do these two as as one
allocation, if you wanted to pull them together, you just make this
pointer point to you Dad the two sizes together.
And then you'd make this
Point a little further up.
We could totally do that.
Right?
We could totally just do that ourselves, but I'm going to leave them
as separate pages for now.
Just in case, one of them over rights their boundaries.
We had a better chance of catching that.
We may do.
Men protects on either side of them, the future to actually guarantee.
We kissed that that sort of thing.
All righty, that's that was 40 minutes for two virtual out.
So I had to basically explain things but really that was it, that's
the memory management.
So what I wanted to do the
other things I wanted to do today.
Well, so maybe now is a good time.
I don't know if we should really dive into keyboard input today.
So what I think I'd rather do is, I'd rather spend a little bit of
time talking about something that I would want to do in this
particular circumstance, which is I'd like to start having the ability
to assert things.
Basically what an assert is isn't assert is a thing that you can put
in your code.
That's just for debugging purposes.
That lets you know, whether or not something worked that
You assume will always work if that makes sense.
And so what I want to do is I basically want to Define in handmade
CPP.
I want to Define an assertion function that basically takes something,
it takes an expression and then it is going to assert that if that
expression is or is not true.
Basically, if it's false we want to Halt the program.
So we want to do something.
Let's say like this, we want to do something where we go.
Okay.
If expression right is not true.
So the expression is not true.
Then I'm just going to like write 20 or something, right?
Something like this.
I don't know, just making this up as I go along here.
So basically what I'm going to do now is I'm going to come in here,
and this is the thing I wanted to do before.
I wanted to say, all right.
I have a requirement here.
And that requirement, is that the game State structure, right?
Has to fit obviously, inside the the permanent storage size.
Right?
Right.
That's just the kind of a given.
So I just wanted to say that that was some.
I just wanted to point out to the the program at this point.
And so what I'm doing is I'm putting in an expression that we would
normally if on but I don't actually need to do anything based on it.
I'm just trying to tell you this has to be true.
I expect this to be true.
If it's not true.
I want you to stop the
Program immediately.
So I can find out why not.
Does that make sense?
So, basically like if I run this, nothing happens, which is what I
expect.
But, if for some reason, right?
We were in the, the win32 handmade stuff here.
I went in and I just, you know, I was just being dumb, and I like, I
made this b 1 B long or something like this, right?
Then when I came through here, I would get a break right, right on
this assertion.
That just tells me, hey, you know,
You said this was supposed to be true and it's false.
Right?
And so what I did is I just made it a macro, right?
That I can drop in there.
My assertion micro and the macro just says, hey, if the expression, I
don't even know.
I put it on a separate line.
If the expression that you passed into it, for some reason isn't true
just flat-out right to the null pointer.
Just right straight to null because you know, if you write to the null
pointer, you're going to crash the code.
So crash it.
Boom.
It's done.
Why do I do that?
That because that was the quickest way to do it, platform-independent,
and I just wanted to put that up there.
Why not?
Now?
You've got other options.
Here's a, here's one of them.
You can just if you want to have a platform independent way of doing a
debug break and that would be this guy.
And that is just basically going to do a thing that launch the
debugger, all that kind of stuff, but I don't really care about that
too much right now.
So all I did is I just need something to stop the program and that
will stop the program.
So,
I like that because that basically, I like using asserts because it
basically allows me to put stuff in my code that should that, that in
general should always be validated.
So that I know that I didn't miss something in case, like I change
something later on and and, you know, and don't realize the
consequences that that change has.
There's a search, might catch it for me and save me some work.
So, I like that.
I like to put that in there.
It's a good thing.
Now, what you may be wondering is don't they incur performance penalty
and the answer is yes, they do.
So usually, what we do is we do something like this.
We typically decide that we have something called the debug build,
right?
And we say that, if you have a debug, you know, if you're in a
debugging scenario, then you will, you know, actually expand to
something.
But if you're not in a debug scenario, then you'll just make it expand
to nothing.
There's no cost to doing this if you're not debugging.
Now this brings up something which we have, which we've been dancing
around, which is right.
Now, we just have a straightforward bill that doesn't do any.
There's no differentiation, but there's no way to switch different
things.
We have the handmade win32, but that's about all.
We've got right.
So, what we want to do now.
Is basically defined some a couple pound defines like this debug thing
that basically allow us to toggle certain aspects of our code.
And so basically, I typically like to have debug is kind of, I find
that debugger not debug.
It's just too ambiguous.
It's like, what does that really mean?
Like do I want debugging code?
Or does it mean that I'm debugging?
I don't really know.
So I tend
Like to have some other sorts of things that make a little more sense
as to what you're doing.
Like, do you care about whether performance is happening right now or
not kinds of things?
You care about whether size is happening now or not, those sorts of
things.
So I tend to like stuff like is this a build that's going to be
released publicly or not?
That's that's like one thing.
Like is it only running on my machine?
So things like specifying The Base address that we're going to do in a
second here.
That's like one thing that might happen.
Only in debug things.
Like try to think about the other things are like, so internal build
or external.
Build would be one of them whether or not I'm testing performance
right now or not, those sorts of things.
And so basically if I'm testing performance I need asserts to go away,
right?
So basically I would like to do handmade performance, right?
So basically, if you know, if let's say maybe speed, let's call it
handmade speed.
Is it a speed build or not?
A speed build?
How about slow?
Let's call it slow, that works for me.
So if, if we have defined slow, we can do our assertions.
If we haven't this find slow.
We can't write.
So I'm going to say that we're building in slow mode now and that's
going to be fine.
Right?
And that that works for me and then we're going to have the other one
which is handmade internal and
Is going to be defined to one as well.
So then what I'm going to do is basically say, you know, you know what
we can also do here.
We can even say by default.
What we would build, although Apple.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's good enough for me.
But what I will do here is I'll put these in here.
I'll basically say handmade internal is basically zero means a build
for public release.
One is billed for developer only, right?
And then we're going to have handmade slow.
That is zero.
No slow code allowed.
One is slow code, welcome.
So that's what I'm going to do.
So if handmade slows to find we got a surgeon's.
If not, then we're not and then I'm going to go ahead and say that
internal build.
I'm going to turn right around and use it in the place that I wanted
to, which is down here.
We're basically say if this is a handmade internal build, then we are
going to try and set our base addresses.
And if not, then not that makes sense.
So I'm going to say that we've basically got what is, what is virtual?
I want their, what does virtual aliquot as that first parameter for an
LP address virtual Alla.
Why don't you tell me an LP void?
So we're going to have an LP void.
We're going to have an LP void Base address.
And That Base address is basically going to be zero when we don't have
an internal build, or it's going to be some magical value that we hope
we can get when we have an external build.
Now, if I remember correctly, and I probably don't, but if I remember,
I remember correctly in x64 on Windows 64-bit, the first 8, terabytes
of address.
Space are reserved for the application.
So, so basically, if I wanted to, I could do something like, say,
That's, I don't know, you know, this thing gets one more guy, which is
terabytes, right?
And that's GB x 1024 and I basically say that the Base address.
It's that one terabyte or two terabytes, who cares?
And of course we got to do our cast again.
Probably with terabytes.
We could just flat out say that you needed to cast it in here.
But yeah.
Yeah, I don't know.
We yeah, it's so hard to tell sometimes.
You see the thing is if I make it 64-bit that it always has to be done
a 64-bit.
Even if you knew that didn't need to be done a 64-bit.
I don't know.
I don't know, ladies and gentlemen, I do not know.
Should these always use 64 bits question, mark.
It has that total rise at the end.
That tells you that you don't know what you're coding.
You're just flat-out making stuff up as you go along, and
Gentlemen, that is a lot about what coding is.
So I'm going to basically say we're going to pull these guys.
First of all I'm going to do it like this and that way we just have
one Base address and we always try to get that Base address.
I'm going to say that we basically put the put the permanent storage
first.
Why not?
I don't see any reason why not.
So I'm going to say we wanted we want to take the the total size.
So let's say that we've got that value.
We've got total size.
Size.
And total size is just equal to the
Mm in size.
Plus, the transient size should be fun.
I don't see any reason why it wouldn't be fine.
And then I will allocate total size after we are done allocating total
size.
I will assign the transient store is to just be the permanent storage.
Basically bumped up by the permanent storage size.
There we go.
So I'm going to do it.
That way.
I said I wasn't going to but I wanted to anyway just like at That Base
address in there.
Alright, so there we go.
So that in theory should do it.
I allocate the total size, ask for it, the Base address, then I go
ahead and make the transient storage, be where the permanent storage
is plus, the permanent sort of size.
Seems pretty good.
Okay.
Yeah, let's take a look at that virtual Alec.
So here we go.
Come in here.
What's our total size?
Make sure that this is a nice big old number.
Yes, it is.
We're going to allocate that.
Did we get it?
We did get it.
And what is that?
Number come out to be.
That looks about right?
64 Meg's across.
Where's Great?
Can't?
Yeah.
Yeah, of course.
It doesn't want to play that I wanted you to play it in decimal.
You didn't do it.
I don't know why you didn't do it.
I could force it to but I don't really want to.
Alright, so off we go and let's take a look here at whether game
memory actually gave us the address that we actually asked for.
So we
We asked for Base address.
All right, that's what we asked for.
What what's going on here?
Oh, great.
So does that mean we actually do?
We actually have to force it to be inside the other thing because we
couldn't we didn't coerce it in time.
Basically, fantastic.
Ladies and gentlemen, so, I guess that answers our question.
We're basically going to have to force this to do it this way.
I assume, I don't actually know if that's a good way or not.
But it answers our question.
I guess, unless I'm wrong about what's going on there.
Let's take a look.
But still wrong, I know what's going on.
What am I?
Oh, do I have a?
Yeah, that's great.
I flipped the cases.
That's dumb.
So I never assume.
You know what the problem is.
Really?
That's the thing, you think something is Trivial, you know what the
problem is, but you don't write you just pretend.
You know what the problem is.
The problem is actually that I have this case reversed.
It was always initialize them to 0 instead of my terabytes value.
So I actually need to do this at least I don't think I did.
There we go.
Oops.
Cannot convert to LP void.
That is fine because we're just going to cast that.
There we go.
Let's take a look.
Now.
If I actually got my Base address, there we go.
That's what I wanted.
So does virtual Alex exceed.
Oops?
Awesome.
The Perils of undue as well.
Boy.
This is just this is just not going my way here.
These
Last few minutes, it was going so well, there and then I just kind of
spazzed out on you.
I apologize for that.
I don't know why I wrote the code.
Right the first time at least.
Well, I assume you read it right?
Maybe it was wrong.
The first time as well and then we can feel better about ourselves for
for being wrong.
I guess.
Let's see here.
Okay.
I'm going to add the permanent storage size in their cast.
This to a bite pointer.
So that we are advancing by B.
Add the number of bytes the permanent storage takes up, which gives me
the rest that.
It should do it there.
There we go.
And let's take a look.
See what we got.
All right.
So the transient storage size, the permanent storage size, both set
properly.
The total size looks right.
Base address looks right.
Let's see if we got our permanent storage.
We did.
It's at the location.
We want.
Even better is the transient storage up above where it should be.
Yes.
It is.
Everything is coming up roses Now ladies and gentlemen, it is
beautiful.
All right, so that's all well and good.
That looks fantastic.
I don't see anything wrong.
Wrong with that.
I think we're all good.
I think that was everything that I wanted to do today, even accept
keyboard, which I guess we'll save for tomorrow, but that is it.
That is all there is we can now have a full on party.
I'm trying to think if there's anything else we need to do here.
But really we are getting down to the last of it.
Ladies and gentlemen, we are getting down to the last of it.
There is not a lot left that we have to do.
Now, one of the interesting things here is the win32 resize dip
section Guy.
This is pretty interesting.
We could actually pull that allocation as well.
We could actually just have one Alec.
I don't know that we really need to do that, but we could that's all
I'm saying.
You know, I like I said, I think I think I'm out.
I'm out of stuff.
I would have to start on something, totally new.
We may go to the Q&A early.
That's how well that went.
Mmm-hmm.
Yeah.
I don't have, I don't have a lot to say other than to basically say
that that that looks like trying to think a lot through your did.
I'll eat?
Did I say like, oh, I'm going to talk about something and then not
talk about it.
So tomorrow we'll just clean up the input.
I think that'll be it.
That's looking pretty good.
Lookin pretty good here.
Yeah, I guess we could.
We could have tried to pass the timer.
I don't know if we really want to do that, but we could have done it,
right?
We could we got time I guess we might as well might as well past the
timer.
Yeah, I don't know some kind of seconds elapsed thing.
So we basically I could guess I'll just have to pass it and say we're
going to we're going to find it later.
So basically the last thing we need, right?
Is a game.
Clocks, you know, kind of thing, right?
And we don't know what's going to be in here.
Something's going to be in here.
Right?
And at the very least we know samples elapsed is kind of in here.
We're kind of passing that up.
Here, so I guess we don't need that that clock.
So really, all we need is the wall clock.
The wall clock is probably in some kind of ambiguous ticks per second.
So I don't know that we want to do that.
We may just want to do a straight ahead seconds elapsed since last
time kind of clock, that sort of thing.
So maybe we'll think about that for next time.
Let's just say this is a to do Casey.
What do you want to pass?
What do we want to pass here?
We could also pass like what we think our frame update hurts.
Is that sort of thing, but point being we know we're going to need
this.
So we might, as well, say, clocks here.
You know what?
The other thing we could do.
I might like this even better is, since that's technically input.
We could basically put it here, right?
We could do something here.
So, uh, you know what?
That's what we're going to do.
We're going to say to do Casey insert clock value here.
And we'll pass that in tomorrow.
Yeah.
That looks good to me because basically, I
Here, what we did.
We had a timer.
We did in our dtsc.
We did a query performance counters.
So we know how long the last frame took to complete.
And so let's, let's let's think about that.
Well, we'll put that in here, insert clock values here.
Those will be part of the input.
We could even consider making the sample, the sample counts as like.
How many, how far the audio clock Advanced be part of this as well.
We'll think about that a little bit later.
All right.
I'm reasonably happy with where this is.
I think that's about it.
So I'm going to say it is time.
I'm for the Q&A.
So please remember to put seem your atory.
In your question.
And please keep the questions to being about code.
We've already done as much as possible because otherwise we're
answering questions about speculative code in the future.
Like how do you do the physics thing?
Where it bounces off the wall, but we're going to get to all that
stuff and there's really no way for me to answer questions about that.
Now that are good aren't going.
Vastly inferior to when I actually show you how to do it for reals.
So please try to keep your stuff that we've done today or in previous
day's unless we literally run out of questions in which case, then we
can go Hog Wild, but for now, let's try and keep it under control.
Okay, let's take a look.
Let's take a look.
Can you go over the benefits and reasoning of a main memory pool
versus Dynamic allocation?
Yes, I can.
I certainly can.
So basically.
I don't like lying to myself when I'm programming is I guess how I
would say it and dynamic allocation is like lying to yourself because
they're either is or isn't a hard limit to the amount of memory in the
machine.
If there's no limit to the memory in the machine, then you don't need
memory management, right?
You just just allocate and never free.
You just you'd allocate Infinity GB and all your allocator would do is
just
Use the next contiguous b as you went to make stuff, right, but if
there is a limited amount of memory in the machine, which is actually
a real source, which is actually a hard limit that you think about on
something, like a mobile phone or a console, actually, right?
There aren't virtual memory systems on those, on those platforms.
Sometimes, depending on which one you're talking about.
If there is a hard limit, then Dynamic allocation is essentially lying
to yourself.
It's saying you think that there's
Some way for an alligator to to make this program run without
overflowing its memory bound.
But you never actually proved that for all, you know, your pattern of
allocation may leave holes in the memory that can't be refilled.
So you've got fragmentation and it can't fix that or you've got some
situation where you actually need more memory than you thought you did
and you don't.
And so you're running on 206 Meg, platform and it turns out you need
257 MB sometimes but you never realize that
So I don't like lying to myself in that way.
I like to say you have a certain amount of memory that your game runs
in and it is guaranteed to run in that.
So we actually wrote the code knowing provably that it does run in
that amount of memory, right?
That's that's what I prefer.
And so the reason that I don't like Dynamic allocation is because if
your allocations are truly Dynamic, then you can't make that
statement.
You have no idea actually, whether your game works or not.
You're just hoping that it does and on a PC most of the time it does,
because there aren't any hard memory constraints.
The operating system, just steps in and takes care of things for you.
So that's really why I do it.
I just like to know that I design systems that have hard guarantees on
the fact that they will run.
If you don't care about that, then there's nothing wrong with Dynamic
allocation, right?
You can just go Hog Wild and hey if the game runs it runs have done.
It doesn't.
That's really all there is to it.
So I don't necessarily think it's a pro/con thing.
It's just I like to design systems that that are guaranteed to work.
When I am talking about things that ship to an end user, who is not a
technical person, like, you know, a person who's playing game.
I want to basically say if this game starts up, if it can allocate the
memory that is required on Startup, then it will run.
And if it can't, it will tell you and it will print out an error.
Message that says, you need at least four gigabytes to run this game.
That's how I would prefer the world worked and not I got to the point
where I was holding down the button and it made too many shells fire
out of the gun and that overflowed, how many things there were.
And it crashed because I like was shooting for a really long time and
they're too many shells piled up in one place and and whatever, right?
I just, I just don't like that.
So I want to know that the game has hardbound.
On its runtime and its memory usage.
I hope that answered the question.
If it didn't ask again, Matt because I will, I will elaborate on a
different part if that was not the part you were asking about.
Are there, good?
Whoa, wait, okay.
I need a better system for tracking which questions I've answered in.
Okay, why use the void star instruct game memory?
Well, because we don't know what's going in there.
We could we don't know what's.
It's just a big old block of memory.
So we can't give it a type because we don't know what the type is.
It's just a huge block of memory that the game's going to treat
however, at once.
So The Voice.
As the saying we don't know what this is.
It's a glob of memory, do whatever you want with it, have a party.
It's not our problem anymore.
Right?
And then basically what the game's going to do is the game and it
already does this to a limited degree, right?
It just flat out cold, casts it, right.
It just goes, you know, I'm going to cold cast it to a game State and
now it's all typed from now on, right?
Because the game's kadel Point into it and whatever.
Can you elaborate on your screen?
Print permanent and transient storage with gameobject examples?
Yes, I can.
Basically, so the reason I wanted to separate those two was just
because the permanent store is non-negotiable, but the transient store
is.
The permanent store is basically what the game needs to run.
So basically that is like the entity states where the player is like
what the unlocks are like, all that stuff.
Right?
And I wanted to differentiate between that.
And like the render stack, the like cached version of all the
textures, the sounds that are playing at the moment, like all that
stuff that can be recreated and loaded off disk again, whatever.
I want to distinguish between those two.
There's a couple reasons for distinguishing, those two that are maybe
not obvious.
One of them is that we could flush the transient store and leave the
permanent store.
And that would be like if our app needed to minimize its footprint for
some reason, which was a real thing on iPhones, for example, but
another circumstance might be the transient store got wiped out by an
oh&s event.
Like, you know, I don't I mean I this is not realistic.
I mean, you could think of it, sort of like, mentally preparing for
things, like direct3d lost your surfaces, or stuff like this, that
used to happen.
I don't know.
So it's, it's really not that necessary.
I like to do it because it kind of, it's a little bit of mental
discipline, but we could throw it all in one place.
There are some things I might do later.
We're else I'll show you.
I'll be
Do you see why I wanted to separate them?
Because I pulled this little trick and the trick wouldn't have been
possible without it, but honestly, like is it a big deal?
No, it's not.
And oh, and another thing is
the always right?
The usage code.
First thing is still in effect here.
I may want more Arenas than three or two rather.
So this is the bare minimum that I needed.
I just I threw the transient storage in there because I knew I was
going to need it.
But really like, we haven't finished, writing the usage code.
The game will dictate what those actual things are.
How many partitions there are the outer thing.
So those aren't final either, we may we may decide we want three
different things in there or something like that.
So the right.
Is code.
First is still in an effect here.
We just haven't gotten to a point in the game where we actually can
write the usage goes first, but when we can will back change the API
to fit our needs not the other way around.
Let's see.
Is the code going to be posted on GitHub know, the code is commercial.
It's not, you can't post it on GitHub.
It's you have to, if that's part of the pre-order.
It's part of the like bonus.
You get for pre-ordering the game as you get to the source code.
So no, you're not supposed to release the source code, its commercial
at the moment.
Eventually, you can read down here.
It's got a license that eventually it will be released in the public
domain.
But until then, it's commercial.
Let's see.
Could you briefly explain what you meant by avoiding round trips for
memory allocation.
So basically a round trip is when the platform layer calls the game
and the game calls back to the platform layer, right?
So basically what that looks like is is this let's say I wanted to do
virtual a lock.
I want to do a virtual.
Alright, so I've got internal void platform, allocate write void, star
size, T size or something, like this.
I go.
Had.
And that this is I mean, we don't even need the size T.
We could say it 64 or something like that.
Size.
T is another type.
That's guaranteed to be the memory size, blah blah, blah.
You can ignore that.
It's not relevant and we're not going to use it.
But point being, you would have something like this where you did
result equals virtual Alec and then virtual Alec would take, you know,
the size and the other parameters here and then we return it, right.
And so, basically what would happen in game update and render, if it
didn't have memory passed into it.
It would call platform allocate here.
So basically, the platform layer called the game game update and
render, then the game turned right around and call the platform layer
back.
So, we've got a stack.
We've got a stack platform layer game platform layer.
The reason that I don't like that, is it creates this sort of?
I don't know what you want to call it.
It creates sort of a
Spiderweb sort of a feel of stuff if you loud that sort of thing to
happen and everyone does it.
So, like I said, this is just something I don't do but everyone else
does so you don't have to do this.
This is just how I'm doing things so you can see.
But basically creates this nasty spider web that looks like this here
is the platform, right?
Here's the game.
Okay.
This was written by Casey, but this may have been written by Bob,
right?
Because maybe I hired someone to Port the platform layer.
Now, in this particular case.
I'm going to be showing you all the platforms, but we've already had
David gasps.
Ow, right?
David.
Gal made an SD L version of handmade here, already.
He posts a sdl version that you can.
You can swap in if you want to follow at home, right?
So this may be written by someone who is not this guy, right?
It could be written by anybody.
It could be like the
Anyhow, that you hired to Port it, who knows.
So basically, if you set yourself up for Success, what it looks like
is it looks like this basically one call, right?
And that's what we've got.
We have one call.
This.
Is it?
The game runs.
If you call this call that is it.
All you have to know is that you have to pass these things to it and
it works, right?
This makes Bob's life.
So easy.
The only way that Bob can screw up is if Bob is just incompetent,
right?
But if Bob is any good at all, you have made his life wonderful and he
can write a perfect platform layer.
That doesn't need any Jank.
Enos that perfectly Services the operating system exactly the way it
needs to and knows that it just goes and gets the stuff from the game
when necessary on the other hand, if it looks like this.
It will take Bob a few weeks just to figure out what the actual thing
is that the game even needs, because the API is no longer one called
anyone can read, who knows anything about programming?
Instead.
It's now this, this giant sequence of operations.
The API is actually a sequence.
It's all these calls in a row that went back and forth.
It's like looking at a log, right?
It's like all these things happened in an order and the
I'm layer has to know that it needs to be able to expect to get a load
call after this call after that.
Blah, blah, blah, blah blah.
And it's just this huge nightmare of, like, learning what all that has
to be like, handling it properly.
And, oh, I didn't realize that in this case.
I would have needed to tell the game to refresh that thing and then it
would call me back and I wasn't ready for the call back yet.
So it crashed.
Just like no, no.
No, I don't like it.
It's it makes me unhappy and I'm unhappy about when I come into work
and it's bad, right?
We just we just cross that out.
And we do this, right?
And it's fine.
Now.
There's one thing you have to do, additionally, that we're going to do
later for asset loading, which is basically there is one Q, right?
And the Q is for disk I/O.
And if you want Network, you've got a second Q so you can never really
make it be just one call.
I mean, you could, you could make it be literally just one call.
But you still have the Q.
So you still have a little, you have a little bit of non one calmness
but that is the minimum you can get away with.
And so it is what I get away with if I can, because it's so nice and
clean and easy.
And then it makes everything just super-clean on either side.
There's no cruft.
Yeah, it's good.
Good thing.
Let's see.
Are you going to keep the sound before allocation to separate?
Probably just I'm defined as going to allocate that in the bitmap
buffer together with applies, do one big virtual Alec but I might do
two separate ones one for the platform memory, like the sound buffer,
and the bitmap buffer.
And one, for the game memory.
I don't know.
We'll see.
We'll see how it shakes out.
Why didn't you use lips?
He's a certain macro because we're not using any minute.
Any libraries.
I already had to use sign F because I didn't want to show you how to
make a sine wave right there.
I'd want to keep that stuff to a minimum.
So no more.
No more of that.
If we can avoid, it will use only the ones we have to because we don't
have time to study to get to it to do them in test code.
But when we actually everything that we ship, we should write
ourselves.
Let's see.
Dyslexic deity was pointing out that the assert has a couple issues.
Well if that's true, but that's because we haven't really written it
yet.
So the thing is I can put it to do in there.
If you're nervous about it.
I can put to Do complete a search in macro.
But really this, this is
The thing about this is this is not actually the assertion macro that
we're going to want.
We will actually want an else case in ours because we're actually
going to, we're actually going to have a way to get a dialog box that
says whether do ignore the assert and all that stuff.
So so just don't worry everyone.
It's coming later.
Let's see.
Let's see here.
Why did you pick an address?
Super high up?
Two terabytes?
No reason.
It's just what?
I just on a whim.
I want to make sure it wasn't something already taken.
I don't know.
I didn't have a reason that's just where I put it.
I miss the stuff where you coated the permanent and transient memory.
Can you go over it Again?
Guitar, 87.
Before?
Run out of time.
Can you clarify that question?
What do you mean by coded?
It?
Do you mean just where I allocated it or how I used it?
Just clarify that slightly and then I will do exactly that when you
were in task manager.
What exactly was the difference between each type of memory size.
Oh, yeah.
Well, you know what?
I'm the wrong person to ask these days.
I used to know the answer to that but they've changed it.
So now I don't.
So you want to ask like Mark russinovich or somebody who actually
knows or Raymond Chen.
What it really means.
But basically, so, let's see here.
So when you open the task manager, normally, I don't think it has this
stuff.
What you have to do is you have to go, there's like a select columns,
that sucked column view, select columns.
And then you can turn on all this stuff and you can turn on a bunch of
memory stuff, right?
Like this.
That makes sense.
So basically what these things will show you is is all of the sort of
memory stats that Windows.
Well, not all of them, but some of the memories that counters that
window has for your application, right?
So, basically, I believe I'm gonna give the wrong explanation and then
someone else can come in and correct it hopefully later, because like
I said, I don't know anymore.
I believe that basically what you have.
Is the working set is like well, no, you know what?
I'm not even going to try and give this because I'm going to mess it
up.
Basically what these are you should go read about them for yourselves
in a modern dock.
Basically, what they are is they're different versions of how much
memory your app has versus how much it asked for.
How much it is actually touched, right?
How much is resident in memory?
How much is not resident in memory, right?
Like those sorts of things and it's trying to give you sort of a
A snapshot of of that, sort of residency, allocation touch it, NE sort
of thing.
And like I said, I used to know I don't anymore because they changed
these things at some point and now I'm like, I don't even know what
they're reporting anymore to make matters worse.
If you really want to learn this stuff and if you're curious about it,
I highly recommend that you do.
I wish I knew like, maybe I'll go read about it tonight.
I just, it never comes up for me these days.
I just don't listen, especially
Do like what I do, where you just allocate a block of memory.
You never have like really concerns about it just kind of works, but
you should know.
These are things that we be good to know.
So so yeah, basically I would say it gets even weirder than just the
things that are shown in here because you can also go to perfmon.
I believe, still ships with things.
I think, I don't know if ships with Windows 8, but ships with Windows
7, at the very least perfmon.
on you, can, you can
And you go in and you can do this stuff where you go add counter,
right and you can pick like an application.
You can go to process.
I think is usually where it is process.
You can drop down process and then I think there's just a all this
stuff in here.
There's even more like virtual B is a good one that I think that's,
that's how much memory total.
For example.
I want to say and you can go pick your thing.
So like let's say we look at
At the open broadcast thing.
The thing I use for Twitch streaming, you can go ahead and say the
virtual B of OBS.
I want to add that as a counter and then, that'll just it shows you
like what that value is over time and that sort of stuff.
So, basically that's virtual B down there.
You can see, it's still pegs.
So, you got actually, it's kind of janky the way the graphing is
terrible.
You basically have to go find the right scale yourself for the thing.
It's really annoying.
Let's see.
Drop that scale down a little more.
There it is.
So basically.
And see there.
That's the that's the memory footprint.
I can change the color to so you can you can take a look at it.
There we go.
Great.
Yeah, and basically what that'll do is that'll if I click on it.
It'll also show us what the virtual B is.
That's like one point, three gigabytes or something that's got
allocated and that'll change over time.
You can see the processor time is also there for that.
I guess that's the not for the application, that's for everything.
But if I wanted to write, I could get rid of this thing I could.
Delete it.
And then I could go into that, right?
Click add counters again and then go down to process and add other
things to the process.
So, maybe I want something like, you know, the the percent sent
processor time used by this process, so that open broadcasting system.
I want to graph how much it's using over time.
I can add that as well.
So there we go, and that's on there now.
So basically, that just, yeah.
Perfmon, it's a thing that basically tells you that doesn't look
right.
Is that scale drawing again?
Yeah, it is.
So you can see it there.
So I got to scale it down to like that.
It's all right.
No.
The scale is just the worst.
I wish this just like, automatically scaled the things for you because
it's so annoying because I don't even know what I guess percent.
So that should be a clue, it's percent.
So it should be out of 100, right?
So there you go.
So basically, this is just a little weird application.
You can use for monitoring stuff and it's
got all kinds of stuff in there.
So that's another way you can get memory information for your app.
If you want a secondary source to tell you what's going on.
Let's see here.
Let's see.
Ryan riess has tell people to watch Mark, russinovich has he's the guy
just mentioned videos on msdn Channel 9 entitled mysteries of Windows
memory management.
So I've never seen that.
But yeah, that would be if Mark russinovich has a thing talking about
Windows memory management.
You should probably watch it because he knows that stuff like that is.
That is definitely a guy, you would ask.
Let's see.
Are there any guidelines for choosing a safe first argument address to
Virtual Alec?
I don't know.
You know, I would love to know the answer to that question.
Like I said, I'm only doing it on my machine.
That's why it's an internal build only thing.
So I don't care as long as you find one that works.
You're good to go.
But yeah, I would love to know if there was a way to just say, oh, you
know, when you start up that, you know, I'm marked executable to have
Range reserved.
I don't know.
So that'd be something interesting.
If someone does know that definitely right in because we can talk
about it later and put in some code here to handle it.
Let's see what happens if we try to allocate 4 gigabytes and users
does not have that much RAM.
Basically, the allocation will just fail, it'll just return 0 and we
will print out an error.
Now, what we will do in the future and I can put it to do here if you
want as well.
But I already kind of said this to do handle, various memory
Footprints.
Basically, what we'll be doing in the future is will have a few
different configurations are getting can run in 256.
Meg's a gig.
Two gigs for digs let's say, and each one will basically determine
what art assets.
You get, whether you get the high res or the low as our assets and
sound and that sort of stuff.
And so, so we'll be handling, what will actually be doing in the
future is seeing, whether the system has that memory and if it does,
we'll use the higher amounts.
And if it doesn't, we'll use the lower amounts and we'll also use the
speed of the processor and stuff like that to determine, as well.
Let's take a look here.
Is it worrying about the OS, not being able to allocate memory kind of
like worrying about huge meteors hitting the Earth?
No, because like on an iPhone, that's why most of those apps crash,
right?
It's because they they just treat memory like it's free and it ain't
it's very limited amount of memory on on a lot of iPhones out there
and it just always it always just pooped out and when we port to the
Raspberry Pi 256, Meg's my friend, no virtual backing store, so don't
come crying to me when the operating system can allocate any more
memory for you.
So that's going to
Crucial.
Like, we're going to be very happy.
We did what we did when we go to run on a real memory constrained
platform, which we will be doing.
Let's see.
Same is true of consoles.
By the way, obviously, like all game consoles, have very fixed memory.
Why are using memory pools instead of static allocation, for many
permanent structures?
I find static allocations easier to use.
Because we wanted to add a known Base address unless I'm
misunderstanding your question.
Basically, like, static allocation wouldn't allow us to give a to
specify where the Base address of the memory was and virtual lock
does.
So that's why we're calling that.
What mechanism will be used to hand out the memory to different
subsystems.
Well.
That's spoiler warning.
Where we can't say that that would give away the whole stream.
Why would you come back and watch tomorrow, you know, and well, it's
not going to be tomorrow, but when we do it in future, so you'll be
seeing how we do that.
That is one of the things that we'll be doing.
Let's see.
Having human a der.
After cooking session is kind of like a code review.
Was this your intention or just Serendipity?
No.
I just wanted to make sure that people could ask questions live as
opposed to having to always ask them on the forums or something.
But yeah, it is nice to have a code review because it means that if
anyone caught something on the stream, they can say it.
That's happened.
Like twice already 44, pretty cool things.
So yeah, it's been it's been awesome and we will keep doing it this
way because it does have a fringe benefit, but that
Wasn't my thought was not, oh, this will be good.
People catch things on the stream because I know if they're even would
be any experts on the stream.
So, it might have been all people who were learning for the first time
in probably wouldn't be able to catch stuff, but it turns out we have
a lot of experts who do come just are just enjoying the stream, you
know, for other reasons.
I just want to, you know, hang out in code or whatever.
And so, that's been pretty awesome, but I didn't know that we would
have experts on the stream ever, right?
So,
Let's see.
What about for example, modding support.
You can't tell if an in advance, if you allocate enough money for some
else's mod, right, know that it's not true.
So, all all the game needs to work in a certain footprint and if you
want to support modding, you still have a footprint requirement.
Now, you can allow mods to change what the footprint is.
If you want, you could say this mod requires eight gigs, set of four
gigs.
And then all we would do on Startup is we just have a way of going.
What mods do we want to support?
Because assuming they
Into the directory or whatever that they're installed.
We basically would do that allocation.
Right?
And so, you know, it's not it's not really a problem.
But also I don't think mods to change the memory footprint mod should
still work in the same memory.
Footprint would be my preference and so like I don't love having mods.
Expand it.
Maybe if you want to do a mob that comes like two years later, some
machines have more memory and that's fine.
But the way I would probably
Yeah, the way I would probably do that is I'd rather ship a new
executable later that expands what can be done.
I like that version better.
I think of it more like z-machine.
Like the old infocomm way of doing things there was like this was the
small version.
Now, we've got the bigger version or something.
I like that better than having be flexible.
Let's see.
Will our new 64-bit get GB break on Raspberry Pi.
Well, you have to understand Raspberry Pi won't be calling the win32
code because there's no word 32 on Raspberry Pi, right?
So on Raspberry Pi, we will always be in small memory mode.
So basically, the game memory that's passed in will always be like 64
megabytes and 120, Mega Twenty, Eight megabytes or something.
Depending on how much we have.
So that's just Raspberry Pi will be in a more constrained memory
footprint.
But remember this code never runs a measure by.
This is the win32 code.
Let's see here.
How do you ask the memory pool?
We allocated for unused available space.
For any given data or object again.
Got to wait till later.
We have once we allocate stuff from it.
We will see will the transient storage be freed or will you just take
memory off of its free end until it's gone?
In other words.
How are the married be managed again?
Wait, wait on those because we're going to see how that works.
The answer is, they'll be at least three ways that we do stuff.
You'll see them.
Let's see.
Is it better if we keep track of the size of the memory that is freed
instead of the total size.
No, not in this case.
We're trying to pass to the game.
So the game needs to see how much memory there is.
Can you explain your reluctance to have those constants be unsigned
long, long as?
Yeah, I just, I was worried that you wouldn't be able to do 32-bit
computations in it anymore.
I was all like, you know, I mean, I'll be more concrete so I compile
this, right?
Oh, alright, nevermind.
I guess it's okay.
I was worried.
I was worried about this.
But if it's always going to work okay with long long if I can always
just assign them.
That's fine.
So that may be fine.
If that's the case.
I'm happy to do it.
That was my only concern is I was worried that it wouldn't that I have
to start casting but if that's the case, then I'm okay with this.
If that's if that's what that'll do.
So thanks for that.
Yeah.
I just I was just a little nervous that it would, it would start
restricting me.
But if it's not then
Then that's okay.
If it's if it's able to cast down on the constant, that's probably
fine.
Now if I pass in it, well, the thing is though if I pass in a variable
there, of course, will I ever be passing in a variable?
Probably not.
I'm okay with that because because those are four constants really?
I'm okay with it.
I'm okay.
Now I wasn't okay maybe before.
Let's see.
No, I did not pass any different flags to Virtual a luck for permanent
versus transient blocks of memory.
The I'm just allocating.
Just the memory the same for both.
In fact now we only call virtual Alec once and all we're doing is just
take committing the whole range and it'll clear 20 for us because it's
defined it has to do that, virtual lock will clear 20.
Let's see here.
Oh, yes.
Sorry.
When I say someone asked what the other reasons were.
Specifying a memory Base address.
I don't want to show you yet.
That's, that's a little surprise.
We'll get to later.
So, so the only one right now is debug ability.
That's the one we're focusing on that, but we may do other things with
it later that are kind of fun weird.
Can you please play The Base address being so large?
I don't have a reason for it.
It's just where I picked.
I don't know a good way to get to pick something.
That's always going to be available.
I figured the two terabyte location.
Probably there isn't stuff sitting up there.
So that's why I picked it.
That's it.
That's all I got.
I had no better idea.
Maybe later on.
We'll do some research and figure out what the most recent safest way
to put that.
Again.
We're not shipping.
This this never ships.
We let
As a sign or address range when we ship which is the safe way.
So technically we could have picked anything we wanted in as long as
it works on our machine.
That's all we care about and it did.
So we're done.
So, it's possible even on Windows, that there isn't contiguous space
available for the pool and two different program, instances, end up
using different assets, even though on the same machine.
No, not really.
So,
You have to understand, there's a difference between virtual memory
and physical memory.
We've just started up.
So our virtual address space is not fragmented when we virtual a lot,
continuous memory.
It does not have to be contiguous in physical memory.
It can be arbitrarily scattered.
And in fact, will be pretty much.
It's highly unlikely that the whole thing will always be perfectly
continuous.
I don't know.
Maybe Windows does try to do that for some reason, but I don't think
it does and it certainly
Doesn't guarantee it.
So, there is no reason.
Our memory hasn't been fragmented at all.
At this point.
So we should always get that if the machine has enough physical
memory, or even virtual memory to give it to us at will as far as I
know, so, we're not even going to use just to be clear here.
We are not even going to use this.
We're not going to use Virtual Alex failing to tell us that we don't
have enough memory because virtual Aqua almost never fail when we ask
for the 4 GB because it'll give us virtual memory.
Even if it doesn't have the physical memory.
What we'll be doing is asking how much physical memory there are is
and we'll be trying to use a subset of the physical memory size.
But yeah.
So I think that's it.
Let's see.
I think that's all the questions.
There are questions in here that we're not pertaining to the code that
we've already written.
So I did not answer them.
If you want to talk about those come to a pre stream, sometimes show
up 5 or 10 minutes before the stream starts, and that's usually when I
answer kind of random questions, like what we're going to be using for
physics and stuff like that that I see on stream or what I've
programmed before.
So those are two things I do, answer on the free.
Mm.
So if you want those come come five minutes or ten minutes before and
ask them sometimes.
I might even more before that, but basically come come early and
that's when we do that.
All right, everyone.
I think that is a wrap for today.
Very simple stuff we did today, but we're totally good to go now on
memory.
So we're closing in on the homestretch of platform stuff.
I would say that it is not an exaggeration to say that probably next
week, will be our very last week where we really think about.
Too much at all with the exception of the May.
Well, you know, probably for a long time, probably until we do
streaming asset loading.
So we're closing in here on actually getting to some really fun stuff
too.
Although I kind of like some of the stuff.
So, to be honest.
It's kind of all fun to me.
But stuff, that's a little flashier.
Let's put it that way.
As always, if you do want access to the source code, you can pre-order
here on handmade hero dot-org.
If you want to discuss what you saw tonight, or anytime you can go to
news and forums, where there is a bunch of
Stuff on there.
There's coding waste, where you can ask questions.
There's a bunch of resources that other people have made that help you
study the series.
If you want to.
There's all kinds of good stuff up there as well as a schedule so you
can tell when the series is going to air which is helpful as well.
So all that stuff is up there.
I encourage you to check it out.
Of course, there's the video archive on YouTube.
If you missed episodes, you can go on there and there's also an
episode guide on news and forums that has the videos plus a with time
jumps on them.
Now.
I might make this link directly to that in the future because it's
pretty darn sweet.
Eat and also, of course, you can follow the Twitter feed which always
announce the streams the day of and what time they're going to be.
So everything you needs up on handmade hero.
Dot-org tomorrow is Friday if I'm not very much in error.
It is a Friday tomorrow.
Is it?
Not?
Which means is an early stream tomorrow.
Fridays are early stream.
So, Friday will be, I think it's 11:00 a.m.
Tomorrow on schedule.
So for those of you who can join us, I would love to see you tomorrow
morning, 11:00 a.m.
Pacific Standard time.
I typically see all the folks from Europe at that time, who can make
it because it's not in the middle of
The night there anymore.
So hope to see some of you tomorrow and that is it for tonight.
So thanks for joining us and I will see you then.