Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we Cody complete game live on stream.
We are actually, I'm pretty happy with how the lighting is coming.
I don't really know how much more stuff we want to do with it.
It kind of, we kind of have to make some finishing decisions here,
which is difficult.
If This Were a normal project, handmade hero, everything moves at a
glacial Pace because I can only program for two hours at a time, twice
a week at the moment or, you know, something like that.
Five hours a week is usually the amount of time.
The never gets spent on it and especially to keep it relatively
manageable for people who try to follow along at home, and which there
are quite a few people actually.
And so, what that means is that the amount of actual experimentation
and diligence we can do on anything is actually pretty limited and I
know it seems like we take a long time on things but like the entire
development time of handmade hero.
So far has been like, 3 months of programming time or something,
right?
If you add it up, it's nuts.
How small it is.
And, you know, I'm a game engine developer.
I'm used to say suspending, three months, just on the lighting or
something, right?
So you know what we would do, if we had the kind of time that we
normally have on full project that isn't streamed and isn't supposed
to be followed along with it, home is one thing and what we can afford
to do on the stream in a reasonable amount of time.
That doesn't take too many episodes is another
So obviously, you know, to make it clear, I would spend hundreds more
hours on this if it were my day job, right?
But we aren't going to do that here because it would be years before
we finished.
So we can have to go.
All right.
We've done a reasonable number of episodes on the thing and we have
some fairly workable stuff.
What can we make in terms of assumptions now and sort of start to
narrow in on something shippable?
Because you know again we just we just can't do the kinds of research.
We would normally want to do in a full-fledged project so just want to
make that clear, I wouldn't normally be sort of tail.
Telling things down at this point, but that's true of everything in
the handmade here engine, right?
Everything can always be done more, and if you have more time, you can
do a better job and try more options and come to a better conclusion.
So, given that.
The major decision we have to make is whether we want to run GPU
lighting or not and there's reasons to and not to do it.
And I'm not sure how, you know, what direction you want to go on that.
So I think what we want to do today, we multi-threaded the lighting
yesterday.
Sorry, last week on the last episode and it might be interesting to
just take a look at what we've got.
And see roughly
What kind of performance we might expect to get.
Out of this if we just kind of tune it a little bit, right, go through
and try to make sure that we're not doing anything too stupid and make
sure the compiler can do a reasonable job generating code.
Maybe work on the spatial hark A little bit just so we can get a sense
of like, okay how fast would this lighting run, if we were going to
run it on the CPU, and that may give us some perspective.
Once we have that kind of cleaned up as well, that might help us
determine, you know, what do we think this would do on a GPU?
Do we think that it's reasonable to run on the GPU and so on?
Because we are still way too slow, you know it's getting faster but
it's not nearly fast enough for what we probably would want to do in
most cases because remember there's going to be even more lighting
elements in there than there are right now.
And so we need to be a little bit more.
We need to make sure that we're better than we are right now.
If we're gonna be able to ship something solid.
So right now this is a example of a large number of
In the world that are all having lighting apply to them right now and
it's being applied, fairly reasonably.
Like I'm pretty happy with this lighting, it's not bad, you know?
And it's it's got everything.
You would probably want at the moment in terms of the lighting system,
how we're using lighting system is not great.
We can definitely do a much better job of Distributing lighting points
throughout the world and using them.
So that part I think can be improved but in terms of the core letting
system, which is what you care about at the moment.
I feel like the lighting is working pretty nicely at this point
actually.
So the question is, just all right?
Can we get you know a 2X 3x 4X speed up in the lighting?
What can we do to like get significantly better than we are right now
and just you know see what our what our chances are of making that
happen.
So in order to do that, I need to start taking some further steps.
Here's the sorts of things that I want to look at today.
So first of all, I want to just take a little bit of a survey through
the code to figure out to what extent.
I expect the code to be compilable, right?
In a clean way.
Because at the moment, for example, we don't really know very much
about how the code is being generated and for all we know, it may be
Generated very poorly, the code May yet at the present time.
We may be doing some really stupid things and we may be generating
code or the compiler may be generating code.
That's just very, very bad.
And so what I'd like to do is just take a kind of look at that and
see.
You know what?
I think about it.
And clean up any problems that might be there.
The other thing I would like to do is take a look and see how our
spatial hierarchy stuff could be improved.
At the moment, I can tell you, for example.
That you know, if you look at the statistics you can see that we have.
Oh we're not sorry we didn't actually for so that's one thing to do
to.
We have not actually
Hmm.
Total casts initiated.
Why is that still being recorded?
That's not good, folks.
We forget that one.
Oh man.
We're still bouncing a cache line around.
Wonder how that will affect our speed, probably not much, but because
the raycast is fairly heavy weight.
But that was, we missed that one.
Picked it.
It's a
doesn't look like it has changed it much though.
So that's okay.
All right, we can put the stats back in.
All we have to do is some them per thread and then when we're done, we
can add them together using a safe ad.
So
If you look at the statistics though, because I remember we look them
before we still check way too many boxes per raycast.
I think.
Really the number of raycast we do isn't astronomical.
The problem is the amount of work each raycast does is astronomical.
And so let's go ahead.
I mean I guess one thing we can do right now.
Let's just go ahead and start by just getting those stats.
Getting a Stat system in place so we can take a look at these.
I think that would be a good place to go, right?
So let's in fact we should have that lighting work.
Don't we have lighting work or something like this?
Yeah, so let's sort of promote lighting work here, right?
I kind of said that Canadian, stop, promote promote, let's promote.
So let's take lighting work and make that a real first-class Citizen.
And when we can do here is say, alright, let's grab these things out.
That we used to have here.
And I'll put them in here.
So the lighting work structure will take how many castes were
initiated?
How many partitions were tested?
How many leaves were tested?
And we will.
go ahead and keep those / lighting like
We will track those per thread, and then at the end, when the threads
retire, their work, we will only have that time sum them up, and we
can even do that without any locked increments, I'll show you how we
can do that.
So we can literally keep the cache line bouncing completely off the
table until the very end.
So we can do that.
I don't know if there is anything else that we had here, that would
have been /.
Work-related, I don't think they're really
Was a debug lines.
I guess would be one thing that would be per work-related.
However, I don't know that we really do anything with debug lines at
the moment.
So I think that's probably pretty safe.
So because the push debug line call is not actually doing anything at
the moment.
So I can, for example, get rid of this
And that should be fine.
So I don't think we really need to do that because we could make the
debug line system be thread safe.
I don't think we really needed to be because we can always just turn
off threading when we're trying to bug things.
So there's really not a lot of point to wasting that time as I can't
think of any reason to do it at the moment.
So I would say it's probably better to just not bother, that's what
I'd say.
All right, so what I want to do now is take the letting solution here.
And I want to go ahead and make the lighting work structure be the
thing that gets passed around to everyone so that they can actually
some their statistics, right?
So what I want to do is I want to start with compute light,
propagation probably here and in compute light propagation
Instead of passing these things along here, I'm just going to pass the
work structure along.
Like so,
And then, what I'll do is inside compute light propagation, that only
takes the work structure, what we can do is grab these out here.
And then we can have access to the stats for summation, which is what
I want to do.
All right, so there's all I really wanted to
do there.
So now when we actually were adding stuff in any of these routines, we
can go ahead and Sample them.
I don't know.
Do we just delete?
I thought we had well, I guess we didn't really need to add the sample
points here.
I guess that's already something that we know,
So that's probably fine.
So let's go ahead to me.
And take a look at where we want to add this data.
So it looks like here.
That's our initiation call.
Here's our other two stats here during the recursion.
And that may be all were looking at the moment.
So yeah.
So I think that's all good.
If we take a look at this, now these are gone.
And what I want to do in compute light propagation now so you can see,
we do like total cast initiated in this, our stuff here.
I want to pull those out and I want to go to the actual place where we
did the work distribution, which is here and compute light
propagation.
And so, what I'd like to do here is I'd like to Output those at the
end.
This.
And I'd like those to just be sums here.
And so what I'd like to do for that is just say well we know that we
have all these work structures and we know that we distributed all of
our work out, amongst them and so the work index value that we stop
with here would tell us that information.
Right.
So what I'll probably do here is say, alright, here's our work count.
Like so.
And yeah, I mean that's that's really all we're talking about here.
So when we get out of this, we know how many work
elements we did.
So then what I can do is I can just Loop over all of the work elements
that we did and some them.
So you can see what I'm doing here, right?
I've got these work orders that I sent out to everyone.
And then after everyone is done working, I just sum up whatever all
their results were and again, this is really nice.
Any way to do this because then the threads are all working on
different parts of memory.
If I were to do a locked increment it would be thread safe but it
would pull the cache line back and forth between korres all the time
for no reason.
Right?
And we don't want that because if they have to stall and wait on those
cache lines then we are effectively ruining our performance
All right, so all I want to do here is just some these guys up.
So I want to take each individual work structure that we know actually
got distributed dispatched.
And once that's done, and we get all that information back, then I can
send it out.
So we have to pull out each member of the ray.
But now we should have all of those statistics back and some correctly
without bouncing any cache lines around between anybody else.
That is bizarre though, so that actually spent a lot of that actually
still gave us time hit there to see that.
Hmm.
I'm not sure why it did.
Although so how big is this guy?
We should probably try to align these
So, the lighting work.
That would be eight and eight, that's 16.
So, we really want these to be 64 byte aligned if possible, Right?
And right now, they're not.
Here they would be right if we did that, we have the ability to do
alignment.
When we do our allocations, unfortunately, this is not allocated.
Now we could make it allocated
Let's, let's take a look here.
I want to see if I can make this not be bouncing around, so we should
probably be careful about.
This regardless.
So,
The things that are being written to hear accumulated PPS and
accumulated weight, and average direction to light, right?
These are the things that get everything else gets read to.
But these are written to.
And for that matter, we could say that this goes in here too, right?
So if we have those guys there, I don't think
to scratch a and scratch be.
Are those even used anymore?
So we use scratch a and scratched be.
Oh, those are, those are four boxes.
Okay.
So those are fine.
We don't care about those anyway.
They're not used in letting it all.
So, I believe the only people we write to our, this is what gets
written to.
In fact, I can move these down here.
I don't know about the entropy counter.
And to be counter only gets updated at the end of every frame.
That's also fine.
So this stuff is generally speaking.
Not written to
During the course of lighting.
In the multi-threaded section.
So we're really only talking.
About this stuff down here.
And so what I'd like to do is I guess I'd like to just make that
stuff.
I'd like to make sure this stuff is Cash aligned
And again, the reason that I'm doing this is because I want to take
out of the equation, anything that might bounce back and forth between
cores.
So the way that happens I believe the term is typically applied to
this is just false sharing which is a reasonable term for it.
I guess sometimes computer terms are not very good.
That one's okay.
And all I'm trying to do here is make sure before we get any further
into this, that you don't have the following thing happen.
So, here is 64 bytes of memory.
And here's the next 64, bytes of memory, right?
And when I say, 64, bytes of memory, I mean something that is aligned
such that the bottom 64 bytes worth of address is zero.
all right, so remember a address
has a bunch of bits in it.
Here's the bits.
Here's the 2 to the 0 to 1 to the 22 23, 24 25, 26, 27 28.
Okay.
So what I'm talking about here is it's got zeros all in the bottom.
All right, so none of these are set.
So the first thing is that our set or up here somewhere
So this is an address that's aligned to a 64 byte boundary.
And here's the next 64, byte boundary, the cash L1 L2.
L3 thinks about things in this size, so it's going to move things back
and forth to memory.
And in between the caches.
In this way, it's never going to think of things, like, more granular
has never had to think about like this one bite here or something, it
doesn't care.
It's just going to think of that trunk.
so what happens is if I'm doing multi-threading and one of my
structures that I'm looking at goes like this,
if I try to write to here,
Right, there may be no other thread sake or zero is running this.
There may be no other thread on any other core that's ever going to
try to write here.
I'm the only person who's going to try to right here so I have
exclusive access to it.
It should be full speed, right?
However, if another person on another core core one has to write right
here, nowhere near it, right?
There's a giant gap of like, you know, 50 bytes in the way or
something.
Nowhere near each other.
No chance of overwrite this cache line.
The 64 bytes will still have to negotiate between the cores because
they need to be able to resolve the fact that they both wrote to the
same cache line because cache lines are what the processor thinks
about.
In terms of who gets to write what we're.
And so we may be introducing overhead on the processor that will
Our code to visit significantly less Speedy, simply by.
Not making sure that the things that one thread uses are all on
different cache lines in another thread.
It's not about using less memory, it doesn't matter if the thing fits
in the cache line or not, that's a separate kind of optimization.
That's trying to optimize for the amount of cash or using
What I'm talking about is just making sure that no matter how much
memory they use, neither threat, none of the threads, use the same
cache line for writing.
They can all read from the same cache lines all day long reading from
Cache lines is free, it's not a problem, right?
If you never have to touch the cache line and you just read from it,
all of the cores can store their own copies of those cache lines and
since no one's ever updating them, they never have to talk to each
other about it, right?
The problem is when
I'm goes to right to a cash.
Now all the other cores need to be made aware of the fact that someone
change that cache line and if heaven forbid, they need to write to it
as well.
Now they've got to negotiate about who gets to write it when what
state it was in and all these are the sorts of things and who knows
how bad that can be.
So,
What we want to do here.
Is just ensure that all of these things are 64, byte aligned.
And they all have.
That they all have a memory address that starts on a 64 byte boundary.
So we know that they're perfectly chunked.
So that's what we want to do.
So in handmade platform we do have the ability to allocate memory,
right?
But we probably don't really need to do that.
So in the lighting solution here,
I'm just going to make it so that it has two admission lies.
And I'm also going to use again.
We've got the ability in our
System here to pass a memory Arena.
So I can just say like where do you want me to get my memory from?
And then when I allocate, I'm going to use the Ability our ability to
allocate sort of things that are aligned because we have that you can
see we've got these memory params, right?
So I can say that something.
Is an alliance piece of memory.
And we don't need it cleared.
I don't.
Yeah I guess we do need it.
Cleared this time so that's fine.
I don't think we really do because it was already clear but that's
okay.
So we know we want this to be 64 by two lines and we know that we want
it to be clear.
So I'll pass the clear through there.
So anyway, inside the
Inside the lighting initialisation.
I just want to do a push array.
I'm going to pass that Arena that we're using.
I know how many of this I want for each individual one and I know the
type of it as well.
So that should be pretty easy to get there.
Just these guys here.
So I knew that I want
Some lighting work.
Some accumulated weight, some accumulated PPS.
And some average direction to light.
so,
so I know I want these four things here and I know, oops,
Copied the wrong thing there.
And I know which types they are.
And that way they are all allocated.
Okay, and so inside the lighting solution, I just have to assign
these.
Oops.
And once, they're all signed, then this thing is pretty much ready to
go.
All we need to do now is like, if I were to run it, now, we would just
crash because that no one's calling that.
Right.
What is this Intex?
Oh,
Needs to be defined first.
So unfortunately, anyone doesn't array count, here is not going to
have that information.
Let me double-check.
This quickly.
I don't think anyone does use that, though.
So it's just this one.
Actually no it I'll just put it in here.
So, there we go.
Answer now.
Everyone should know where they're getting everything this.
Did I do this backwards?
I did do this backwards.
It's been a slow morning.
Some days, you know, your little slow in the code uptake.
There we go.
Wait.
Which it is Count first.
Yeah.
I am just smooth sailing, all of the place.
Coffee's not kicking in yet.
There we go.
So we need to actually call and it lighting at some point.
And so, whenever the
Node structure gets actually initialized which it's been so long since
we've ever looked at that code.
That code is like, you know, ancient history at this point.
But yeah, so here is the place where we actually put one of these on
so we can just do it right here, right?
We know that this is a reasonable place to do it because this is where
the world mode gets initialized in the first place.
So,
totally fine.
And that should, that should do it.
it's called Tessa lighting, just letting
So, that should be sufficient.
and that should basically take care of all of our alignment issues,
but we can double-check
intersect so inside in it, lighting,
Everything should go down located.
And hopefully this will run correctly as well.
No.
Yes so now we can double check that everything is aligned.
First of all and then we can check down check out why it's slow that
we do those tests.
So I assumed and I don't know I assume that doing these two right
here, right?
I assumed that doing those two was a cash sharing problem, but you can
see like if we reduce, if we don't do those two ads with the predicate
predicated, add their, we get massively faster.
And if we do, do them, like so,
We get way slower and the question is just we need to figure out why
that's happening.
There's a number of reasons why it could be happening and we have to
take a closer look, but I want to eliminate any cash concerns, first
before we go any further.
So, when we come through the rest of the code, I want to make sure
that it's all kosher.
So I want to make sure that every work pointer that we get out here.
So I want to make sure that if I am this value with 63, right?
Which is all the bits set that are not 64-bit aligned, right?
I want to make sure that they're all clear, so that we know that we're
never getting
So that we know that we're never getting any values that could be
interpreted as unaligned.
Alright?
So, you can see here that we're not getting a line value there, right?
So we're getting that assertion.
Let's go ahead and double check.
I'm going to go to debug mode for second here so I can expect
everything.
I'm going to run that.
Here's that assertion.
So let's take a look at the work structure itself.
And I also want to take a look at which work in dextran.
Run.
Next one.
So I think we just didn't make the structure the correct size, right?
So if we do size of lighting work,
It's 32.
So I got a pad it out.
So it's 64, right?
Sorry.
I think I was in the middle of this and then didn't
How did I make it?
Three to eight plus eight eight and eight.
Yeah.
All right.
So really we need
Quite a few of these actually or I could be explicit about it.
We need an extra 32 bytes at the end to do nothing, right?
Alright, so now we know that we are aligned at least that array is
aligned and so that we can see.
Now whether it was Cash, whether it was the the contention over that
cache line, that was causing us, our problem and it was right.
So you can see how now we are running at full speed again, which we
weren't before.
And so you can see that exactly what I thought was happening is
probably what was happening, right?
When we
add these set up so that it was
Well, you can just take a look at it here when we had these set up.
So they were only 32 bytes, there would be two of them per cache line.
So on two separate cores.
We would be fighting over that cache line to do this increment, back
and forth, back and forth, back and forth, back and forth, right?
And so that's a tremendously bad situation and that is what was
causing our speed hit.
So thankfully, we've fixed that now.
And this statistic is now free to gather, which is what we wanted,
right?
So again yeah cash very important to think about it was that was
almost a 2X speed up, right?
Just to make sure we got that right.
Okay, that's not know what?
What?
Look at these.
Okay.
So as you can see, we've neglected to actually clear those values.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Otherwise we will know the total number we've ever tested but I don't
know that we care about that very much so I'm going to print out a
little bit more information to here.
So what I'd like to know is for every cast.
How many leaves we test and how many partitions we test?
So I want a partitions, the cast and a leaves forecast.
So in order to do that, I'm going to go ahead and take it slowly this
way.
I'm going to take a total, I'm using 64 here because I don't know how
many of these are maybe getting up into the range where 24 bits is not
going to cut it.
I don't want to be pretty relatively precise.
So all I'm going to do here is I'm going to create these values by
Just dividing the total, the total number of things we tested in
either Case by the total number of cast.
So we know how many / cast we are testing.
That's all I want to do there and then I'm going to go ahead and clear
these out.
Like I was saying before because right now we're not clearing those
out.
What we could do here since the distribution isn't really take any
time.
I could just do this.
And leave it at that.
so, these may not
Give me an Avenue of 64.
It's okay.
I don't need to be printed as an x 64.
I just need the Divide cap and a semester 64's.
All I want to make sure
So now we should be able to see pretty good.
Sort of measurement here.
So what I hope you can tell from that is if you look at what what
we're actually seeing there are leaves forecast is not really that
bad, right?
You know, doing five testing five leaf nodes, 5-leaf boxes.
/ cast is probably not the end of the world.
That's probably pretty reasonable.
The partitions forecast is pretty high 17, right?
That's just a lot.
And so, it may be that we need to balance that out a bit, right?
We may need to do something a little bit more.
We may meet me need to do something better there and there's a couple
different things that we could do better here.
so,
the biggest thing that we're doing right now,
and you know, it's one of those things where it's like you really need
to do a bunch of trial and error but
Right now, we're effectively using a KD tree that's what we're using
but our KD tree doesn't actually take advantage of the fact that it is
a KD tree meaning.
It stores two sub boxes in it, but it doesn't take advantage of the
fact that it knows that it only stores two sub boxes in it, right?
We can make our test routine a lot, simpler and a lot faster probably
if we just did that.
So we have to think about it and again, it's experimentation is you do
we want to have more children per partition potentially or do.
We want to stick with two children per partition, in which case, we
should go ahead and make that test way cheaper?
And then 17 tests per partition mean be isn't a big deal, right?
So I guess I don't have a particularly strong opinion about that.
I'm really not sure what the best answer is there.
Because on the one hand, it does seem like it would be attractive to
just use a simple like binary tree because you can't reverse those
pretty quickly.
On the other hand.
Having just a couple cubes per level and recasting against them has a
certain attractiveness to it as well.
So it
it's tough.
so another thing I would like to see, so does our profile give us our
cycles per
It doesn't tell us cycles per or does it.
Yes it does.
It tells us how many cycles per up.
Per call.
So I want to take a look at a couple things first.
so inside recast recurse, I would like to know
just what's going on there.
Oh, did we run out of space?
In the profiler?
I guess we'd call that too many times.
Yikes.
Guess that makes sense.
Given how many times it was called?
You can also see how much slower we get now, because the debug system
actually keeping track of all this stuff, right?
You can see that debug collation takes a ton of time, right?
But I just wanted to kind of see here.
So you can see that our raycast itself that's just not very many
cycles per raycast.
Actually.
So that is a very efficient raycast already actually by comparison to
what you might think, all right.
CR raycasting threads operating now,
Here's the debug collation.
so, you can see all these
all these threads doing their lighting work.
Such a little cool.
This is so just a little fun system.
So anyway,
I would say just my gut instinct.
This point is just to say, all right we got to try and reduce the
number of operations.
We do to get us down our tree and it seems like probably the best way
to do that is to yeah, maybe
It may be let it be a KD tree.
Maybe get rid of the recursive function call.
As well.
We know, our tree can only be so deep, so maybe just have a nice
little stack there.
Let's just start with some basic Transformations and see how we do.
Right.
So, let's see how this has to happen.
If you look at re castra curse, really the only thing that we're
changing here is root box, right?
When we call Ray castra curse.
On a self.
We have work solution, Ray, origin, Rady and results are all just
passed, right?
They don't do anything differently.
It's really just this that changes.
In either case, we just pass a new box on, right?
So it seems to me that that's probably the way to go, right?
We write directly into result and then we break out.
So, you know, we really this should be fairly straightforward to make
work, I think.
I mean, all we have to really do here.
I think is have a while loop on the outside.
Which is, you know, well depth is greater than zero.
And have a.
A box back that's just which boxes we were talking about, right?
And you know we know that that can't be very large because we just
don't have the money boxes, that's probably massively Overkill, right?
So what we would do at the outset is we actually as right this little
more cleverly or cutely, we could do something like this where we just
say, right, you push the root box onto the stack.
And then while the depth is greater than 0, we go about our business,
right?
So if you look in here, the route box is only really used at the top
of the loop.
So we should be able to say
Maybe I'll still just call it root box.
And so the root box here is just going to be pulling off the top of
the stack.
So what we want to do is just decrease the stock depth right?
Grab the box that we're supposed to be working on and work on that box
when we need to call Ray cast your curse.
The problem that we're going to have here is that we wanted to do that
in the middle of the child index part of things, right?
However, I don't really know that we have to because as far as I can
tell, there's no actual reason why we would need to do these in any
particular order yet.
So we can choose to just do these in a completely different order.
It's not going to change the result of the routine in any particular
way that I can think of.
So what I would say is as we kind of come through here, we could just
go.
All right, we're checking these
It will change Behavior a little bit.
Yeah.
Well
So anyway, as we're checking these, when we come through here, we can
just say, alright, this is just going to be us pushing stuff on.
so, will
push on an additional box like, so,
And then the same thing is true here.
Like so.
And I think technically that would get rid of the recursion in the
function, right?
So oddly enough that just that alone and I didn't really do anything.
They're right, I just made it so it doesn't call a function just that
alone.
Actually.
Sped us up quite considerably.
We got 10, milliseconds back on the clock.
Just from that.
I have often said this dream that I don't really like it.
Recursive functions being used anywhere that you know, we were you
really care about how they're working and that's largely why to be
fair we don't know that we're getting the same results so we hope we
are anyway but we don't have it.
We don't have a very good test case.
I guess it's one of our problems.
We probably should have made a more standard like killing a little
Cornell box.
Sir something.
So we could verify visually that we're not breaking anything major you
know it looks like the letting still working but you know lighting can
be a little bit broken and still look like it's working.
So, it's a little bit hard to say.
anyway, so continuing on here, if we go ahead and look more closely at
this,
So working.
Stack wise on this now that makes it so that we really don't have to
have that recursive function.
So I'm going to just get rid of this as well.
Because there's really no point to it.
Now, we don't need two functions here.
It's going to just be one function.
And so all we really need is the thing that does the initial setup and
that can just be here.
And this stuff is is not relevant anymore, right?
Oops.
so,
Is that?
So we set up the results initially here.
So I set up all the things we were actually want to set up.
I think so.
So when we come through here now we gotta make the
Result be accessed as a DOT.
It's not an address anymore.
And so that shouldn't change our run time.
And it doesn't appear to have.
So now we just have a raycast function in the raycast function does
its thing.
It also probably doesn't need to take this anymore.
Because since it only pulls it out once and not every iteration, that
should be fine.
The, it can also be in line.
Now it wants to be
So that whole recasting can be inlined which may be a good thing for
Speed as well.
There we go.
Oops.
I accidentally grabbed don't know what I accidentally did.
Oh, actually close Ms.
Dad looks like he's, what happened?
All right, so yeah.
so now, at this point, I think I should be able to can I
Can I ask again about the distribution of these two functions?
Let me just, I want to know how much time I was spending in raycasting
versus outside.
The raycasting, it's going to affect our run time here but only
because the debug collation.
So I don't think it affects the actual product care about.
Too much.
So yeah, they're still twelve percent of the time spent in compute
light propagation.
So that's a little bit Squinkie there.
I'm gonna see if it's handmade slow.
I want to see if there's any weirdness with handmade slope.
What's this?
So, I can still get these even if I turn handmade slow off, so that's
good.
alrighty, so
What's to tackle next?
I am not sure what the most sensible thing is to start with now.
I think maybe I will save spatial partitioning stuff for tomorrow and
I think what I'll do now is just take a look at the raycast in general
and just figure out if there's anything particularly Squinkie going
on.
I also think we could probably multi-lane this guy because we should
be able to do all three checks at the same time, probably, right.
Let's think about this.
So, here in our raycast, we're going to go through the axes of a box,
and we're going to the exact same code for every axis.
The only difference you can see appear, right?
The only difference is is these set up calls, then once you get in
here there's they're pretty similar.
So we could stack some things together and probably do this all as one
like Cindy Lane.
Right.
That me my assumption anyway.
So that's another kind of thing.
So that way we could just do one set of Ops and get all three face.
All three Cube sides in one go.
So let's just sketch out what that would look like.
I'm curious
so, if we wanted to do that,
so if we want to do that, we would basically say okay
This could all be done in parallel, so could probably that.
Yeah, I mean, we could simply optimize this pretty easily.
You know I'm saying?
So I guess we could try to do this in parts.
Just try to think if I really want to start this now or not.
I mean that's a pretty straightforward thing to do right?
Because we're checking three things at a time with just different
initial conditions and it seems like that should be a pretty
straightforward thing to do.
I guess.
However, the question does remain about whether or not it's the right
place to do it like another way to look at this would be to just do
you know, for four different Rays at a time,
and,
I really couldn't say which one of those would be better.
So if you imagine instead of doing that, right?
If you did just for, if you did bundles of raised, right?
so in Sample hemisphere you produce for raised, then you reduce this
count by 4 so you were actually running this
so, if you ran this, and then you
Cast for a raise for everyone, Ray you were casting.
Then if you did things perfectly which you won't because those rays
will have to crawl differently through the boxes, so you won't get
perfect 4X speed up.
But you can see here that, you know, you would you would get a pretty
significant speed win from doing that.
Probably, if you could get close to this, you'd get down to 30
milliseconds or so which would be 30 frames a second, which isn't bad.
For the current lighting.
I think that might be the better way to go.
So if we were going to do that, how would we do that?
So let's suppose that we were going to take sample hemisphere here.
And we just call it four times.
so, we could
grab one of these guys, right?
So we've got a V3 for x.
For whatever, right?
so instead of sample, D being this,
We're actually going at four of those.
So I don't really know how we were meant to initialize these, I guess
we initialize them.
Do we have any way to initialize them?
Doesn't look like it so there should be a thing here.
That's like
so if we want to create one of these v34 X's, we should be able to
pass like, you know,
Something like this.
You know I'm saying?
And then have it Swizzle these things into place.
And so then when we go to add these or set these in, I think they go
low to high.
And paradoxical sense, when you use asset p.s., I always forget this,
there's a set RPS, which flips it.
So I think the High bits in the high position but
So something like this.
Where we pack?
Those in here.
And so we can do.
This bit here.
Just four times for now.
Right.
Then when we recast, we would pass down that whole thing and it would
write do four of those and it would come back with four raycast
results at the same time.
So, yeah, that's that's about it.
So really what we'd have here is something like this
Is what that would look like.
I got space to what we're looking at.
So, what I would say here is, I'd probably get rid of the raid.
On most things.
Yes.
And then I'll just copy those up here.
That.
All right.
So yeah, in order to do that, we actually need to get the re point
value back.
Since we know we always need that.
We might just want to put that in the actual array itself hard to say,
this code out here, would want to be done in a simple fashion as well.
Eventually, so that's definitely something that we would have to think
about.
Um, but I'm going to go ahead and say that.
That's something we can just grab.
So actually we don't even need re T at that point.
It's just the P value that we need the T value is not relevant.
So actually what we could do is say forget that let's just keep this
part and nuke that part, right?
so, the sample devalue
is not particularly hard to reconstitute.
I guess, what we could do here is say
For now.
so, when we do accumulate sample and we pass,
D to it I guess I'm not sure that's oh that's for the lighting.
Dot product between the two.
So that's, that's fine.
All right.
All right, so now we can see the update.
This function to work with that.
So in here, where We're looping through before we do anything else
here, when we exit this, we need to make sure that we actually track
that particular result.
Value that we wanted.
So we need to do, like result re P equals T re X sample d, right.
The
Coming through here.
So it's real origin + Rady.
So that's really it.
And so then when we do 16 of these, we put build these together, we
call the raycast and now the raycast just has to be able to actually
work on the set of values there.
So, at the moment, we can just use a loop on this and then we can turn
the loop into something that actually does it wide, right?
Sue.
Yeah.
This doesn't actually have to be 4X because it's I mean we could make
it for X, I guess.
It doesn't really need to be because it's not actually for wide.
It's just the same value duplicated, four times.
So you know this sample Point P thing.
Just gets duped.
and,
Off we go.
so now that we're getting past something where we could do for a raise
at a time,
it to look at which parts of the routine actually care.
So this part needs to be made 70.
And this part needs to be made 70, but the general structure of the
loop doesn't actually change.
So the reason for that is actually because
Although it may seem odd the way that this thing works, is it just
decides what boxes to process based on whether or not it thinks
there's any chance that the Box itself will have an intersection in it
with the Ray and some useful piece of geometry, right?
Well, normally we would go, oh gosh, we don't want to Traverse any
boxes that that we know we can't hit because that's a waste of time.
But what would happen if we did Traverse bar,
Is that we didn't actually hit?
The answer is nothing because the things inside them won't hit so they
won't produce closer T values.
Or if they do hit, they'll produce further away T values, and we don't
care.
So, the really nice part about this.
Is that because Ray casting has a discriminator in it.
It has a t-value that tells us whether to accept or reject a hit
irrespective of what we have traversed, there's no coughs to overturn
versal.
So when we cast for raised at a time, we literally don't have to do
anything special.
We can just make sure that we only update them, based on their
individual T values.
And we don't have to change our traversal.
We can freely traversed, nodes.
That have nothing.
To do with one of those rays and even though we're wasting some
computation by doing that, we're not actually failing to produce the
correct result because they'll all produce T values that are either
know hit or shit, is further away, and they will get discarded anyway,
so that allows us to just maintain one stack instead of four stacks
and only check one box at a time instead of four boxes at a time,
which is exactly what we want to do, to minimize the amount of memory
traffic that we're doing here and not down shift.
Per Lane, which is a big risk and Cindy algorithms because the x64
doesn't have scatter gather.
They introduced it in.
Avx-512.
But everything prior to that, which is ever any machine at all that,
you're that, and that game players would have today, doesn't have
scatter gather.
So lean scatter gather is difficult.
Fortunately, we don't have to do it.
All right, so let's start out with the most basic way of
Looking at this function, let's try to do it so that we're really not
going to symbolize anything other than just the fact that the things
came in that way.
And we'll introduce just a for Loop, right?
Just to make sure that the thing works at all.
It's not going to do anything.
It's just dumb.
And so, all I'm going to do is I'm going to do for Loop here.
And I'm going to pull out the real origin.
And the Rady manually.
So what I want to do is take the real origin.
XXXX here.
Actually, I'm going to make a function for this.
So I want to do that to get those out and then in our Cindy thing, I
want to have a way to do this.
So oops.
So I want to be able to say if you pass me a 3 V, 3 for X, right?
I want to be able to grab a particular one of those out and this is
the lean right that I would be grabbing out and this is a slow you.
This is not something we've generally ever want to do except at the
very end of an algorithm or something when we computed what we want.
So yeah this this part is I'm not going to spend too much time on this
part at the moment.
It's not really particularly important part, but eventually we think
about it more.
So let me do this part, we're accessing the various values here.
We need to do is pull out an x, a y, and a z, which are things we can
actually get right?
Like, you know, we can get the X.
Y&z problem is, they're all combined and we need a particular Lane
right now.
Fortunately, for us, we can actually get.
We can actually get those Lanes by looking at the mm 128.
You can see
Hopefully, the struct is defined in here.
Oops, I put too many underscores or not enough on the scores.
I just want you to show me the struct, please.
It's not too much to ask.
Anyone.
All right, never mind.
Don't care.
Do it myself.
Why do I even bother searching for things on the internet anymore?
All right.
Can't I go to the definition of this thing?
I know you've got it.
Now, can you give me?
It's right here.
All right, it doesn't matter.
I won't even get depressed about this.
This is all I wanted.
Just wanted to look at the name of that member because I was forget
it, because it's so weird.
So anyway,
Out of the X, we can use the sub component to pull that piece of data.
Where did that was weird?
Mr.
Pitts, D accidentally like f and B at the same time.
So in here I can pull out this particular index.
Again, this is not necessarily something that the compiler will
understand particularly well, so it's not something you can do in
necessarily in performance critical code.
If it's like right in the middle of
Things the compiler may or may not know what to do with it, so it's
not necessarily the best idea so we'll can address that later.
But
In this case also I guess here for a raycast results here.
This, we also want to do is see you next four.
At the end.
And again, all of these things will now try to do wide, right?
Because we don't actually want them to be done this way.
so, I think
For results.
He right here.
We only need four of those as well.
So and for the result that we get passed in, I think the only thing
that we need to set
Is that box value?
Nothing else needs to be reduced.
I don't think.
Yes, run as far as I can tell.
So when we come through here, all of that should should just be fine.
And then in here, we just need to actually set these
Like so, oops.
And again this is not how we want to do it.
I'm just trying to take some small steps and sort of work, the code
slowly into position where we can make it run more optimally.
Okay, so who knows what?
We're going to get out of this?
Oops, I don't want to run that project.
But again just starting slow or oh dear.
What were you complaining about?
Do we accidentally write something off the stack there?
Hold on one second.
So, what did I do there?
It really did not like that.
Take a look.
It's coming here.
I want to turn off threading as well.
so, if Ike and
So I'm going to turn off any threading.
And then I'm just going to make this pass.
Full range.
So now one thread will do everything.
Oh, and I guess.
Something like this.
So then we can assign this.
And let it do a single threaded re comp.
What is the problem?
Just hide that decoration so it doesn't go.
All right?
So I thought I said a break point right here.
But didn't obey.
My breakpoint.
Why did it not obey?
My breakpoint visual studio.
There we go.
So all I want to do here is just take a brief, check to make sure
everything is set to things that I think are you know, legitimate
right.
This seemed fine.
So, at some point we should get in here.
And then we should update these values.
Which we do.
I know one thing we don't update yet is this but that's going to get
handled outside.
So, we finish here.
Only this one hit.
And we're good.
So that was pretty straightforward.
So I can't say, I know what the problem is here.
Let's break in the middle.
I'm just looking to see if we ever get out of this routine.
It doesn't seem like we do.
So, which way are we on right now?
So it seems like it is still going up just fine.
We could have just gotten really slow.
Now, that doesn't seem right.
Right?
So it's running for a little while we were on 119.
Something.
Something's busted.
She's on Sample Point index, 125.
So, we are doing something really bad here.
You can see that it's got GS has a segment.
So,
you can see here that, like, if we,
This is just we're oh, presumably overwriting stuck somewhere.
I can say or bring stack, we're overriding memory somewhere.
I'm just not sure exactly where
so that's very bizarre looking in the debugger.
That was that was pretty strange so I'm not sure exactly what I messed
up here.
although, I guess
Should also double-check that we don't overflow our stack battery
there.
I mean this just doesn't make much sense to me.
I clearly did something really stupid.
This is probably an owl of Shame kind of situation but it I just need
a clue as to what it is.
It's definitely not a morning that I should have done this.
I can tell you that right now.
I'm waiting for it to fail.
There it is.
So at some point we actually get something that wants to go through
enough boxes.
That that's too small on the stack, which could be reasonable.
Now, that they're casting far.
He's at a time, we're not casting those raised in the roughly, the
same direction, which we want to do.
So if you get 4 raised to go out in all directions, you could Traverse
all of the boxes.
And so although you're retiring the boxes they each one can push for
new ones on.
So you know I could believe that that was the case.
So I still don't think that's the only thing wrong here but I'm okay
with making this a bigger stack if we want to
For the time being, but yeah.
Something else has got to be wrong here.
I mean, I guess it's possible that introducing that stuff because we
haven't seemed eyes that yet is adding enough overhead to see but it
just doesn't seem likely
So I must have done something really dumb there.
I'm just not sure what it is yet.
Oh, you know what?
The other thing is it'll be pushing those boxes on.
X as well, which we don't really need to do.
So, there is that.
I still don't think that's enough, but like,
Right?
When we come through here, when we check any individual re it can push
on the box.
We don't ever want it to push on the box.
If it's going to already Traverse that box separately, then we want to
just go ahead and let it do so we write.
So what we really want here is thing, which says, okay, we're going to
do this testing and we're gonna figure out whether we want to Traverse
into the box or not.
And then when we determine that, right?
We're just going to do it.
So really this stuff here has to be like a break.
It's like we're going to do the sub boxes of this box.
There.
Stop looking through.
Right.
And I think the same would be true with this.
So when we actually decide that we do want to Traverse this box more
fully, we need to break out of the entire Loop, right?
So this is a break as well but it's actually, you know, a full full
break because we push the Box on the stack and that's the end of it.
We don't keep checking
After that.
So at least that gets rid of some of the craft there but still not
nearly enough, right?
Like it's still a pretty crafty.
So even in release mode here, you can see it's pretty bad.
So we kinda have to push forward on that before we even got to know
whether it's a good idea or not because we can't be doing loops and
stuff.
In there.
Alright.
So yeah, we need some centralized in Easy Way of pushing the Box on,
but that'll fall out of this naturally.
I think when we actually start to Cindy, it eyes that here.
Now, if we actually wanted to send you guys this a little bit more, so
is in rectangle, centre-half.
Tim what we could do is try to symbolize that part first.
So is in
Rectangles centre-half.
Tim
it's just this code, so we can do it V3 for X of
Here, which we need, we know we needed anyway.
So
At least, I thought we did a relative.
Did we didn't?
We do that?
Maybe we don't do that anymore.
Yes, o re origin so you can see here.
We actually have real origin is an actual thing, right?
So Rel origin is the Box position.
So if we want to just load the Box position in, we can then just do
real origin here and get the point that we want to test, which is our
real origin, right?
And then we can subtract from it, the Box pee.
And that should give us this test value and then we just need to test
against the radius of the box which again is something we can just
lewd, right?
So we can do box radius X.
Remember what that's actually called.
It is just awesome.
So we can load those in right because we just want to blow this out to
multiple components and then we can actually test those all at the
same time.
So, this would actually going here.
Right?
So this test is just like, okay, we look to see component doesn't have
to happen until inside here.
So we can do the subtraction, we can do the absolute value and then we
can do.
This comparison operation and then we can look at the result of the
Mask value and see whether we need to do this at all right.
So, in order to know whether we want to do this in the first place,
presumably, we can predicate this on the child counts as well.
If the Box doesn't have a child count, then we know we don't have to
do this.
So this part can be predicated on that.
I'm not sure what the
Efficient way to do that is necessarily and also in terms of total
Leaf boxes tested.
Yeah, it's kind of a little bit difficult to specify exactly what
should be happening there.
But so assuming we do these, we now need a way to do an absolute value
of this circular we're going to have to do something like
We want to comparison operation.
And here, we're going to want something that looks like this.
Basically the same code only instead of actually producing a Boolean
it's going to have to produce an actual comparison value.
Because just going to be B.
And then the like is in rectangle.
Or is inbox is going to have to be like a function that we have which
is any throughs or something like this for the comparison.
So it will look something more like this will do this and say, okay,
if it's in the box and off, we go.
Now what we probably want to do here is just do a thing that says is
Inbox equals false and then do a box child count here.
Like so,
Right.
That way we're not doing the work on boxes, we don't need to do the
work on.
And here we can also put our
Statistics.
So we just need one thing here which will just do all the tests at
once and then I'll test it for all.
Four are raised and say does any re actually emanate Inside the Box?
Now one of the interesting things about this is that actually
technically Ray origin could just be, we could know that it was always
the same.
If we knew that Ray origin was always the same, there might be some
optimizations we could do here, right?
So for example, one of the things that we could do here is this test
wouldn't have to be performed Cindy.
However, since we pretty much wood could performance to me.
Anyway, the only difference is one move of the Mask register
it seems like it's pretty free to make this thing just work because I
don't know that there's really any reason to
It's all being the same origin.
We don't know.
We actually get anything for that.
So it seems like you might as well.
Let the person pass in different origins in case we ever actually need
that.
So but it's worth noting that for the most part, the outside routine
is just pissing picking different directions from the same origin,
right?
It doesn't need to pass in different Origins.
So we do have, if we cease a pattern developing where we think we
could do something with
that.
The options on the table.
So, if we take a look at our Sim decode, you know, we don't have very
much here yet, right?
So we need to do is augment that with some of the things that we need,
right?
Some of the functions that we don't have.
And so you can see here is essentially the ones, you know, it's pretty
obvious that we've got most of stuff that we need for the actual math,
basic operators problem now is we've got sort of some more sort of
specialized operators here.
So these are the things we would actually need in order to make this
code work.
What is the problem?
Oh,
Ah, okay.
I did that.
Stupid lie.
So, yeah, in this case, since these are the three, four X's, this is
just the Box radius itself.
I was thinking of that code a little bit backwards in my head.
So we can load the whole V3 up here and so this is actually just one
operation.
I don't know why so we don't really need the and they're right.
This is really all we're talking about.
Right?
Because this is not one, mmm 120, it's 3 and 128 so it can do all
three tests at the same time.
So we really don't need the and at the moment so I won't bother
implementing it or I didn't do it here anyway but that's all we
actually need.
Is there no subtract here.
Looks like we didn't do a subtract yet.
That was a good catch compiler.
And this is supposed to be.
Put a few four in there.
So I think in order to make that work properly, all we really need to
do here is make sure that these are actually implemented.
So one of these is Trivial which is this one right here.
These two are less so because they're not exactly direct analogs to an
operation.
That's insanity.
But yeah, it's not a huge deal.
All right, so if we want to do the operator one cure, so operator less
than or equal to, they actually have comp values.
They actually have comparison operators, right?
In Cindy Hsu, we can just do a comp less than, or equal to, which is
what we were trying to do.
And then I'll actually produce the mask values that we wanted.
So that's really pretty easy.
Any truth is probably the next easiest, one and absolute value is the
hardest only because it involves having to have a mask.
The reason that it involves having to have a mask is, at least, if I
remember correctly,
There is no absolute value instruction in Cindy instead.
What they do is they just say, well look floating Point values are
just they have a sign bit.
It's not like in two's complement where the value is like a different
value and you do some math up on it to get the absolute value.
In this case, it's literally just the high bit says whether it's
positive or negative.
So all an absolute value is is a mask of the high bit with 0 1, 1 1,
1, 1 0, no one, right?
So it's pretty easy to do that requires a constant so that's not
great, but they decided that welding that constant into the code was
not that big of a deal, right?
so they so they just don't provide a structure to do it because it's
just too instructions, one to load a mask in one day and it or do you
can generate
Tasks using some kind of a logical trick or something, right?
But you have to make just somehow have to get a mask in there and then
you use it.
So, let's take a look at any trues first, because, any throughs
actually is.
More closely.
Matching right there.
Is it mask move or move mask?
I never remember.
Set each bit of mask desk based on the most significant bit of the
corresponding packed single-precision 32-bit floating-point element in
a.
So that is what we want.
And so that basically says, all right look I know you did Lean based
comparisons of each of the values of the Cindy registers.
What I want you to do now is just tell me where any of them set,
right?
So that's what we want to do there.
So we do this move Mass, PS.
And then in here, I'm going to have this comparison now.
Normally we would just do that, but in this case we know we actually
have three different values and it wants to know if there's any truth
at.
All.
Right.
So this is an and
So, we actually need to do this.
Now, it's probably not like move mask, I don't remember, but I don't
think well.
So if you take a look here, it's a latency to instruction and the
throughput one instruction.
okay, on the other hand, if we take a look at and PS,
It's got latency one and throughput one and it's through puts even
better on Skylake, right?
Sue probably.
The smarter thing here to do would be to actually just and two things
together and then do the move mask, right?
So instead I'm just going to say all right, fine let's do.
Mmm, and PS.
Like so and just say, all right, let's and the X, the Y, and the Z
comparison results together first instead because all I want to know,
is, if any bits were set, I'm sorry or not.
Right.
This is if any of those were true.
Oh wait, no, no, no, no.
These were ins.
So this is not any truth.
This is all truths.
They all had to be true right for to be inside.
Nothing could be outside.
So we actually want both of these so there's an aura.
PS version right.
That's going to tell us if any of the values were true and that's what
I was initially writing.
But then there's also an and altars which is just the same exact
function of just with Ann's
Right?
And so that just requires that there be trues and all three of the
components instead of, you know, the other way around.
So it's tough to say what they should really be named because they're
talking about spreading over to different parts.
And this is why I got confused when I named it is because we want to
know if there's any trees across our 4X.
Not across the three wide.
We want those to all be true.
You know I'm saying?
Other words we've got four three wide for three element vectors and so
when you say do I want any of these to be true?
Do you mean across the four vectors or across the three vectors and so
yeah you've got kind of this.
Bizarre situation.
So maybe I should name these a little bit bit differently.
We say all true in at least one lane.
Like all three true and at least one lane.
Is it really more?
What it does?
and then there's any three true and at least one lane,
Yeah, I'm saying to you.
So it's a little confusing here.
And then there'd be in all Lanes would be if the result came back
differently.
So
I don't know those names aren't great, they're not great.
So then again, absolute absolute value.
Like I said, not a particularly hard one necessarily but it just does
it involves more work, right?
So you
Masks value.
And then to make the results, we're going to have to use the mass
value to knock out the high bit.
So you know, one way to do this, for example, would be asked me to
say, all right?
It's going to equal.
The or Ps of a, and the mask.
Since we probably want or anyway, what I could do is just say, look,
let's just put or in there.
Oops.
Actually.
Can I get ya?
so, if I just put or in there,
And I put and in there.
Then we can just do those operations, right?
I don't know why I said.
So, if I want to knock out that value, what I want to do here is say
okay.
I just need some masks value.
We're if I and the mask with the input, it will knock out the high
bit.
So it needs to be something that just has that one high bit set.
You know I'm saying?
So I might want to so I need something that will set actually and I
guess in this case we know the mask is the same for all of them.
So I can just do I don't have to actually construct a full V 3 for X.
It's the same.
We just need one for x value would do it.
It's going to be the same for every value.
So as long as I do set, 1 PS here to generate the value.
I need the question is just what's the value that knocks out the high
bit, right?
And in this case,
Presumably, it's easiest to just load it.
I would guess.
And so that's just going to be
One shifted up.
31 places, right?
And then knotted.
So I put the 1 there and then I flip it all the bit so that I have a
zero at the top and ones everywhere else and I and those together, it
should absolute value because the sign bit is the first bit in a
float.
And off we go.
Now we're at a time, but I should be able to step in here now,
Looks like we're not quite bug free either there, but I should be able
step in here now.
Just verify that some of those work before we go any further.
I don't think we're in debug mode.
So let me just quickly get us into debug mode.
And here we go.
So in his inbox should start out with zero and a zero and it does we
have the box position that were loading in here.
And so our box position
Which is this should be replicated for X.
So we should just see this, the X's the wise and the Z's, they're just
replicated, right?
This is just, this is replicating itself out.
The same thing should happen with our box radius.
So when we step through here, there's our value, and here's the values
replicated.
This is what we want.
So we're going to now.
Take the origin and subtract the Box fee from it to get the relative
origin.
This is where it is relative.
You know to the Box.
so you can see in here, we've got
the difference now between the two of these.
So this is the difference and I can
Sorry, the real origin here.
So this is the difference between the real origin values for negative
1 and negative 8, 7 there and the Box position, right?
So we've got like - 6 + 4.
So 10 is exactly what you expect.
They're right, because we're subtracting away the Box P.
You know, not if you don't
Alright, so now let's dip in to our attempt at doing this comparison
here.
So here's our absolute value call.
And so, we want to see here is, we want to see the mask coming in, and
we want to see that that if we looked at it as a u-32, for example,
that it produces the mass value that we would expect.
That is not even remotely.
Oh no no well there's our first problem.
So set 1 PS is going to take a floating point value.
I wanted to set it as an integer value so like you can see
hear what our problem is.
I can set it as a integer but it's kind of nasty because then I have
to cast it.
I don't know.
The eye versus em thing is so annoying in the interns.
I don't know why they did that.
I don't know that there's a particularly good reason for it to be
completely honest with you, but that's just the way it is.
So what we might want to do here is just you know, do something like
this.
And then just do.
Tell it looked, man.
I really need you to load this value.
Directly do not convert it to a float.
Let's try it one more time.
So here's our mess with you now, that's the actual mass value which is
correct and now it's make sure we can actually load that in here and
there it is.
So now it's actually loaded properly so here's our results value
that's alright, here's our input value.
And here's our result value.
And we want to see here is we want to see these things getting
absolute value.
So we should see our results end up being equal to ra, but with des-
has removed right.
And they do.
So there you go.
So that's what we wanted.
Then when we do our comparison here, we need to the operator, the less
than operator, right?
So that should be setting.
Our result values to like zeros or ones so these you can't.
They look like Nan's but if you actually look at what they actually
are, they're just all FS.
So because they're now like just bit patterns.
So if they try to interpret as a float it's going to think it's a -
Man - Nan because the high bid is
Set, right?
And that's the sign bit.
And then the Nan because it's all ones everywhere else.
So in here.
Yeah, we go through and we say, all right,
We did our comparison values.
So now is Inbox, we can do our move mask, operation, to see what we
get and looks like, we are not inside this particular box, is that
correct?
Doesn't seem right.
Although I mean, yeah, that is right according to this.
So it says, we're not inside the Box because we're only inside one.
We're only inside the wire Lane, the X, and the Z Lanes were not
inside.
So this is actually correct, but I thought the first box we should be
inside, shouldn't we?
Oh no, maybe we're only inside the other one so we would skip that
one.
As an inside, then next one, I suppose.
we would be though, we just
Loop back through here.
So Source index.
How is that the source index?
All right, I see.
Let's come back through here.
Good.
You say this time in is in box.
Should be true and it is, so that's good.
Okay, so
That's a good thing.
Let me just go ahead and
so we're still a bit janky here so we still aren't quite doing that.
Preamble correctly, right?
You can kind of see how our lighting is a little bit messed up.
so, even though we only really did,
Just this part here, this isn't box, testing must not quite be correct
because we didn't touch any of the other work, right?
So we didn't touch anything down here that was happening.
We only touched this part up here.
So we must still be doing something slightly wrong in our processing
of the
Of the Box values here.
Hubie.
so, what I could do here,
Is I could say.
I could introduce a secondary test function here that would just
compare the results of these two and stop whenever they were
different.
That seems like the easiest way to debug this because you know, unless
I can just spot check and find the bug.
The easiest way to find it would be to step through to the scalar case
that works and the non scalar case, it doesn't work and just look at
the difference, right?
so,
Yeah, I don't see anything particularly suspicious here, right?
I should make sure.
Whoa.
Yeah.
So yeah, I guess I will try testing that just because I'm not sure
which other way to do it.
And so, let's just try this.
I know we're over time but it's okay.
I started a little late.
So let's do a test here.
I'm going to call it test inbox and I'm just going to do is in the
rectangle haft centre-half damn thing, right?
The same thing we were doing for so basically, you know, oops,
This function and I'm going to go ahead and say we need box.
P.o.
box radius.
And the test is Right, origin.
I don't really need that.
so,
Once I have that, I can just say, all right, tell me if is inbox is
not equal or just break here whenever it's not equal.
So this way essentially, all I'm doing is saying, well, I'm was fairly
certain that the previous code was working correctly, least that's
what we thought.
So I have the same decode.
Why don't I just run them both?
And then just tell me when they disagree.
So that way, I can know that, you know, I've got a case right sitting
in front of me that I can just look at,
So in this case, r is inbox.
Our is in box value here.
Oh, okay, that's not quite right.
I have to
Make sure they're actually converted to boolean's.
So we want to say something more like this.
Okay.
That's really weird.
So, you're telling me these always agree.
And yet somehow we get different results.
That sure seems to be what you're telling me.
Did I miss something there?
So, those two are validated at that point.
And yet somehow that still breaks.
So what's the deal?
Let's suppose we actually just used that.
Oh, that's the only problem that break statement there is just
something that, yeah, that break statement used to break us out of
this Loop but that's not in there anymore.
So now it would break out of this Loop which is just patently wrong.
So, actually
Our code was working properly.
I think I don't think we have a problem there.
We were just inappropriately breaking out of the entire Loop.
So let's go ahead and take a look at what that looks like.
And I suspect it should now be correct.
There we go.
So much more.
Like what?
We expect to see.
So that's good.
So now we really need to focus.
Just on this part here.
I'm kind of in the mood to keep going, so I might just a little bit,
just a little bit.
So that's Cindy is now and then in here.
Now, what we'd have to say is like, okay so what do we do?
With the rest of this code.
So let's say we wanted to push this part down again, right?
One more time.
You know, maybe we want to just move it in inside one more.
So let's suppose we wanted to do to do this somehow, right?
Get this stuff working properly.
So how would we make this stuff work?
Let's go ahead and bracket this code here, just so we still have a
copy of it.
And let's try to reproduce it.
So at the end of the day, we're thing we're trying to produce here.
T right now.
Relative origin obviously is something that we need in both cases so I
might just compute relative origin.
Just right off the bat right?
So basically these two things, I'll just say that we just do, right?
We load in the boxes position replicated and then we get the relative
location of the tube those things.
So that way relative origin here is just automatically we just have it
box P.
We just have it box.
Radius will be just have it right?
We just those things are just shared values that are outside.
And everything's fine.
So then we come through here and say, so if I had to look at which
ones we're not doing it, so positive is redirection.
What's interesting, I guess now that I'm looking at this here.
So positive is actually just the same no matter what part of this Loop
were in.
So really, this is questionable.
And just reusable, I think.
Because it doesn't depend.
On this at all.
Like, in other words, these values, right?
They could just be out here.
Right.
I mean, I don't think they do anything so they could just be an array
of three things that you just look up into it, just the table and
you're done.
You don't actually need to generate them out of anything.
You don't need to test these values.
You just this whole thing is just always known, right?
And the same is true of the sign, like all of that stuff, is just all
just known.
So really, all you're talking about is grabbing that sign value out.
Let's just, let's just see.
I guess let me leave it in here but let's just see how that works.
All of that stuff is not dependent on anything about the box, so it's
just not relevant.
These two are dependent on the box and we already have them.
You already have that, right?
So really, the only part of this code we're talking about is this?
And this that's it.
This one is just the origin, the relative origin /.
The Raid direction for this particular axis.
Whichever access were on.
So it's a little nasty just because this Union here doesn't have an
overall Union for grabbing them out as indices.
Which is a little nasty.
To be sure.
And I'm not sure exactly how I want to do that.
So box surface index is only used all the way down here.
So that actually doesn't have to be symbolized in any particular way
at the moment.
Right.
It's literally just put just in that place.
So what we could do is say, you know,
since that will never occur any other place than literally right here.
We could just say let's put that down here for now and ignore it,
right?
Or more specifically like it can be put in here or something.
So it's really just this part that we have to know about here.
And one of the interesting things about this is now if you look at
what's going to happen with this whole situation,
We can actually change this to be something that's computed directly
as well.
Sorry, I'm still I'm just kind of playing with this, in my head.
so if you look at what happens here, we don't need to do an if at all
because if we just want a negative, a positive or negative value,
For the sign.
You can see what the sign is going to do down here, right?
The sine value here is just going to just it's just going to flip this
radius e-value, right?
So the radius e value has to be positive right now.
We don't use negative ones.
We don't use use - size boxes.
So what that tells you is actually that the sine value, this can
literally just be something that will flip the direction of this thing
based on which direction the ray is going, right?
We just want them to be the same.
So all we really have to do is just produce the high bitmask value
using, whatever this operation is, that will correctly make the same
sign there.
We don't even have to do a mole, right?
Look, we could do like an X or
Or something.
Probably we could we could do something creative there, right?
So yeah, this is going to simplify down to almost nothing and then
this is just a straight ahead divided, right?
Is all that is.
Yeah, that's that's just a straight ahead divided.
So yeah, I don't know exactly what to do with this.
I mean, really you want there to be the union array inside here so you
can still step over each individual axis just for conciseness of
writing the code, the first time, then you probably want to blow it
out to be unrolled so that you don't actually have any Loops over an
index like that.
Yeah, that's something the compiler would ideally do for you, but it
doesn't a lot of times there's no really clean way to just tell it.
Look, hey man.
You got to unroll this.
I don't really actually want this to be this way.
So yeah, I mean let's try it.
I guess.
So if you know
Well.
So what we can say here is like alright, in fact, you know, you can
see how we did this, it's the same as how we did it in.
In here so you can see we've got okay you know there's different
structures that we had here for these and then we've got finally at
the end one of these guys.
So you know it would basically say there's a struct that has these in
there or you can go ahead and access them as an array.
Like this.
Right.
Yeah, so you know we can do it that way.
I don't know how much more, that confuses, the compiler, it's pretty
nasty.
It's pretty gnarly data structure there to be sure.
But, you know,
I didn't design the language.
I wish I had.
So, you know, that allows us to access it either way.
So, if we were to literally just do this code fairly directly here,
Then what we have to produce, let's produce these things, sort of more
directly.
So if we want to produce a tear a here where we're trying to do for
wide, then what we're going to end up with is actually doing a div on,
just a standard single Sim devalue, right?
We're going to be doing effectively an M&M dsps here.
Oops.
Do we not have these?
I guess not.
It's got the other ones.
We have this one.
We'd be doing a divided here, between actually just one lane of this
thing at a time instead of all three.
Now, since we are at, I guess since we are going to do all three, I
guess, one other question would be why don't we just do it as one
divided up here that just executes across all three.
And I guess I don't have an answer for why we wouldn't just do that,
right?
You would just do this.
So, we just divide those two and then we'd get basically all of all of
the loops of these.
And that's a, I guess that's a negated there.
Why did we, I guess we negated it?
Because it gets used down here as a plus.
But why wouldn't we just swap those two and not negate it?
I don't know.
That seems kind of dumb.
That's probably just the just probably just a bug.
so, we'll note that
for the future.
So if you want to negate something I there's a couple different ways
you could do it.
This is probably not the most efficient way to do it because maybe X
soaring is the fish away.
But this one
It doesn't require actually generating The Mask or loading it, so I
don't know.
I haven't really thought about what's the best way to negate.
There is no negation instructions.
So you're just like, if you subtract the value from 0 that gives you
the negated version of it, you could in full.
So just do a thing that toggles, the hype it with an ex or something
like this.
So there's different ways that you could produce a negation and I'm
not going to think too hard about it right now which way is the best.
But you know keep in mind that
That's not.
There is no Cindy instruction that I know of for negation in sse2.
So when we come through here and we're doing now are negate negation
divide that can just be done.
All is one Fell Swoop up here.
So the other thing that we need to do is produce this special p-value.
Oops.
and,
It's that special p-value.
Presumably gets used later on somewhere for something.
Question is what?
oh,
Wait.
Does that?
That's why you never get to use anywhere?
Does this support was this supposed to happen before?
So that's presumably supposed to happen actually beforehand.
I must have moved that code.
A little prematurely.
They're right because we must have to do the sign test.
So this this relative origin is not actually the same relative origin
call, right?
So you actually this this operation actually wants to happen to adjust
the relative origin here.
That's being computed to have this Edition.
To it.
Right.
It's actually subtraction.
If that makes sense, I'm assuming because otherwise why would we have
done it?
Right.
We wouldn't have it.
Must this must have been done like that.
Before the railroad before, the real origin call.
Right?
So, in this case, since we're adding this value before the subtract,
it would just be a subtraction of that value.
That would happen in here, right?
So we don't need the the div PS, but we do need the the p-value.
So the mmm.
128 value here of P.
For example, right?
Sorry m120.
Value of p is just going to be the one we already had, right?
So it's the, it's the real origin for the lane.
But then, we're going to take that and we're going to subtract away
this expression here, the sign radius, right?
In order to produce the p-value that we actually need to use once we
get in here.
But that's it.
Right.
And again since that's the same operation everywhere, you can I think
just do it?
Like this.
So this doesn't have to happen.
It's literally just this.
Where we take the signed radio.
Version which is this thing right here.
And that's the part that that's really the only interesting part in
terms of how we need to compute it.
I think that's it.
So really all we're talking about here is saying, we need to extract
the tier a value, and that's literally just the axis set that we did
just pulling it out.
And then you also need to pull out eventually the P1, right?
Since that's going to give us one for each.
Ray as well, there.
This needs to be.
Moved inside temporarily until we want to actually make that.
Wider.
So this is pulling out the axis index and then it's pulling out.
The M 128 F32.
Of it and it's pulling out the key 4X.
Get component.
Right.
So that's going to get whatever the p-value was for this.
So, these actually don't have to be done / access, right?
So this is the only part that we haven't figured out how to do yet to
produce that signed radius value.
But everything else is actually just a straightforward.
Yeah, it's just, it's just a straightforward operation that we don't
really have to worry about this point.
So,
Sorry, and it's not the p-value here.
In fact, actually, we don't need this at all right.
That's that's just not relevant.
So all we really needed to do here was just say to produce the rail
origin, the local rail origin.
Which is this part here, that's the part we actually care about that
relative origin value.
Just needs to be modified on its way down so this relative origin
actually becomes the face relative origin, effectively, right?
Is what we're actually talking about and that's the thing we have
Actually produce here.
Because those are two different values.
Right.
So that's what we need to do here.
And this is obviously a 4X here, you know, this is a, this is per axis
and again, that's going to be something that soups and these are v3's.
So yeah.
So we're looking at something like that and this can be done once
because it's going to be the same for each Ray.
So
This is the part that we now need to worry about because we need to be
able to produce this operation which adjusts the relative origin based
on which face for on, right?
So we can actually move some of the stuff down as well.
So, you know this stuff now can be done sort of inside here.
What groups?
Like this.
so, if you take a look at what's happening inside the re origin,
radius stuff where we actually pull this stuff out,
For use later on in here.
We also need to be able to compute some of this other stuff.
So we need that.
Well, no, we don't.
All right, never mind.
That's gonna be like, well, we need to compute those, but we don't
need to compute those.
Actually, none of that needs to be imputed just box.
Surface index is the only thing,
All right.
Well that's pretty nice.
Okay, so we need to be able to check this positive value.
And that's pretty straightforward because it's just a comparison with
zero, you know, I'm saying.
So in order to produce a complete set of tests to see whether
something was positive or not, all we need to do is actually do this
comparison and we can do it all the way across at once.
We also don't care about doing it inside here.
It's actually just a constant value that can be done up at the top,
right?
So we can do a v 3 for X.
That's just whether or not
You know what?
We call this positive things.
So it's like Ray D+, I guess we'll just call it right, Andrei.
D+ is just like 0 V, 3 for x.
It's just a comparison.
With the zero vector.
So if we take the 4X and we compare it here, we're just going to get
back a value.
That just tells us the because they're ready, directions, they don't
change.
So we can test a thousand billion trillion boxes with this.
If long as we're talking about the same redirection, we're always
going to have the same re positive value, it's never going to change.
So that's a pretty straightforward pull out, right?
The same thing is true of the Box surface Index, this is just the same
stuff, right?
It doesn't matter which one you're talking about.
You're always going to get the same box surface value here.
You're never going to get anything different because you're going to
or it with the Positive value thing.
But that again, just doesn't matter.
So the only thing we really cure in sight.
In fact, I don't really even need to do this this way.
Right.
I could just because this is outside, I could do this the other way,
at the moment.
I don't know, maybe we don't want to hard to say, but point being like
Fox service.
Index, for example, when we compute that down here, we could just make
box service index.
Just get the value by doing the the look up, right?
Because this stuff is just is just wrote.
It's just going to be
Whatever the axis index is so this is for, right.
It's just going to be whatever.
I'm sorry 3, this is going to be whatever the axis index is, and then
it's going to add one based on, whichever one, this is right?
So
if you imagine looking at this, this way,
I guess in here, we also need to see index.
Something like that.
And we can also probably figure out a good way to flatten this down as
well, but if you take a look at this here we just say, alright, the
Box service index is just something that looks like.
this actually,
And then it's depending on whether or not the particular value of this
thing that we tested, whether that's true or not is just going to be
what is going to be.
What tells us whether or not this value should be 0 or 1.
You know I'm saying?
so,
We could actually look at it more like this.
This is a loop just because a loop that just outside everything else
because that's going to get really onerous to, right?
So if we imagine doing it this way,
Really / VIX Index, and the see you next week.
And then just say surface into x axis and x and x.
Equals whatever this thing would we determine here and then we just
look it up outside, right?
So now this stuff is just not necessarily more.
So the only thing we were talking about here is the sine value and the
sine value we could load as well.
Outside.
right, so we can do both of these so in here,
Excuse me, when I come through, we'll just say, all right, if Ray D+
.e, accessing, x.m 1/20 32c index, like so.
So, if this particular value here, actually, I guess it's the you
three, two one that you want.
We've done this comparison.
So we know it will be set to 1 if the ray Direction, was less than it
will be set to 0.
If it wasn't.
And so what we want to know is, was it positive here, right?
And our definition for positive?
So I guess what?
I don't quite understand this.
Why the rate erection?
Oh, it's because we're testing is the positive side.
In that case, I guess, right?
So if the redirections pointing - then we're testing is the positive
side.
So in here we just want to say like okay the Box surface index is
going to be the axis industry or sorry.
One, shifted up access index plus r, a positive.
If it's positive or negative, it's going to be set thusly.
Now the sine value here is a little more complicated.
We could just set it manually.
In fact, we could just do that right now.
And basically this is, you know, the non Cindy way to do it.
Since I set the top 13, it probably is a matter that much right now
but we should fix it.
Later, obviously, but all we need to do here is just say, in fact, I
can just make positive be this thing.
And then just do it like this.
And again this is Jen just do exactly the same thing as we were doing
here.
So I'm just literally copying the code and since its can be pulled out
to the outside and I don't need to worry about that much.
Now this can all be made much more efficient by making it actually be
70.
In the future.
But for now, we'll just load it that way.
So that takes care of all of these things, right?
And so now we just need to make sure that this stuff works, right?
So signed radius this case we need to move by the radius.
So if this is just a multiplication because we know what the radius
value is, it's the Box radius here.
So that's really just a case of doing a sub PS to get this.
It's just doing a sub, like so.
On the signed radius, right?
And again, we're adding the sign radius here.
Now, the signed radius value is something actually to generate.
So, to produce a sign radius value, we need to multiply the sine X,
the Box radius, that's easy to do like so.
And I think now we're gonna have to go through this with a fine-tooth
comb.
They do a lot of random stuff in there.
Is there really?
No, there was
Set zero.
Oh man.
Okay.
Because I did a lot of stuff there in probably a bunch of it's wrong,
so that's fine.
Let's go ahead and get one of these in here.
In fact, if we have this, we can just use this for our subtract, for
our negate actually, as well.
Oddly enough.
I think you could just do that since zero is zero.
So you know, we don't even need to use set zero.
I suppose although maybe it helps to tell the compiler that I'm not
entirely sure.
All right.
So in this case, I don't think we have that particular operator yet
for our special CMD type here.
So I think we can just generate it.
Like so.
So if I want a comp less than it's the same as Sir less than or equal
to effectively.
This should be an F32 that we're signing.
We don't have a multiplication for one of these.
So what's interesting about this is the sine value here.
Is a straight F32 value.
So this is not quite correct, right?
This sign value.
Multiplication here
needs to be the same one for the axis.
Yeah.
So that actually does have to be inside the axis Loop there because it
neat.
That's the, that's the part that makes it dependent on that value.
Cuz we need to use that specific sign value.
So it's not dependent on the sea index at all but it is dependent on
the axis Index, right?
The rest of the stuff isn't.
Get the sine value.
We do actually need to load the appropriate one and use it for
everything.
Yeah.
Right?
Because the sine value is only dependent on the axis index.
Yeah, so those those are I'm conflate.
I conflated those two indices in my head, right?
Just because there's three axes, and we can store three in there.
Doesn't mean that's going to produce the right results across, right?
So you still do need to have these replicated out, you know what I'm
saying?
So, in other words, the Rady positive value is steel per axis.
Jenna I'm saying and it's just replicated across, you know, it doesn't
need to be done here but like so the sign right needs to actually be
replicated out so it's really more like, okay, the sine value.
For this axis index.
Needs to be.
A replication.
Of the vector that stores yet like each Lanes, sign replicated into
all three elements.
Does that make sense?
Because it's a scalar and I was kind of conflating.
If I'm like, well, you can store the excess that you can't start The
Exodus.
It needs to be looked up by the axis index, just like everyone else
would have to be so that that was just me kind of again slow morning.
So this sign value here is going to be per axis index, and when we
test these positive values, we need to then load this as a three
element Vector that just gets replicated.
The sign language web page 31 Vector which then and then we put four
of those together to produce are our actual value, right?
So I don't know.
Where are loading?
What are loading function?
Looks like here.
So it's this
And so, in order to do that, yeah, I mean, I guess I don't really want
to load it that way anyway, so I probably would want to just say,
okay, the sine X and X.
So for each of these
Right, the see the element here.
This is.
So you can see how this is.
Just, I was thinking about this in, just a, in a stupid way.
So ignore this temporarily.
So if I take a look here at the sign, it has to get loaded as a Nexus
index and then see an X.
And then this is actually just going to be
For any given Lane.
We're just going to load all positives into the X, the Y, and the Z.
It's what we actually want to do.
Which we don't really have a load function for unfortunately.
But this is actually what we want, right?
We're trying to load a scalar here if that makes sense.
And we're trying to load a scalar and the scalar varies per Lane.
So you know, if we were to have a load function for it,
So you can see here like here's one that's the same across all lanes
and what we would really have is something that was more like this, a
different scalar per Lane.
Like that.
And so,
In this case, we would say like okay yeah, you know.
It varies across liens, it does not vary.
Across elements.
So, the X, the Y, and the Z of each lane is the same, but every lane
has its own distinct value.
So that's what we were doing here since we're doing it inside a loop.
We're not actually going to call that but that is the load.
That is the load.
We're actually doing this one, loads the full set.
This one load scalars in two lanes, this one loads scalars replicated,
and so that's why I was kind of weird thinking in my head just the
Arrangements of the values were bizarre there.
So, here, when we come through here and we want to settle these
values, you know, that's all well and good.
And we can sort of set the sign for the actual Rady positive value,
where I do this comparison here and now I know whether it's positive
or not, I don't know whether that is ever used.
So I think it's just just for that testing, right?
Yeah, so we only really need that here.
Let's let's again let's let's make this a little bit more concise
here.
And let's just do this, exactly, the way we were doing it before, just
so we know, just because that was a little confusing.
I want to take that out of the equation for now.
So here is, you know what we were doing?
So that part we really don't need to do because it just happens right
there, right?
But this part will keep the same way that we were doing it before.
So now the Box surface index
again, same as it was before, positive value gets tested as the Rady
value.
Like so,
And so this would set our two things that we actually are trying to
keep.
And for now we won't bother with that one.
Right?
So setting, this is going to be 20s trips.
So setting that sign value.
I think is loaded correctly now and that should be it.
I believe.
Okay.
So now yeah, we may need to do the sign a little bit differently
there.
I'm not sure exactly how we want to do that.
But just looking at how the sine value gets multiplied now.
Yeah, maybe we want to set that as something else.
But so let's cross that bridge in a second, when we come to it, I'm
going to look at the other part of it.
Now here, and I don't need to know where all of those are.
Thank you very much though.
And so I think we don't have a divided here, do we?
See.
We do.
Undeclared.
It facial origin taxis.
All right.
So yeah.
Face real origin axes.
Like I said this was just a wrong way to think about this, this is
actually does have to get done / axis.
I don't know why.
I was thinking I for some reason just like the I forgot like there's
an XYZ to each of these so I don't know why I was thinking in my head
like
Wait, no, am I I need to draw this out.
Like, this is definitely exceeded my brain capacity.
This morning.
These were acts of slices, though.
We were just doing them per axis.
No.
I mean you did so you need to track all three values so it is still
that way.
Yeah, tear a on the other hand that one is one that could be done the
whole way round.
Right.
So tear, a is actually correct, tear, a is something that could be
done the whole way round.
Because it's only slicing it right.
The problem is, it depends on Rel origin and real origin doesn't work
that way.
I don't think.
Also, the ray position is actually produced here.
So it could have actually just been stored.
Am I right?
so, I believe
That.
Obviously need for that.
Alright.
Alright, so again taking a look at this here.
So we need the face relative origin and the face relative or should
just does change per axis.
So that's why the face relative origin value.
Still has to be computed in here.
Right?
So you take all four lanes.
At once, you have to do the relative origin - the sign for this axis
X, the Box radius.
That's the only way to produce the actual relative origin for all four
raised for this particular axis and then unfortunately tear a axis
doesn't is smacked us.
Whether we wish we could do that here, but we can't really write.
We wish we could do it outside but we can't.
Because it
Hires us to know the relative origin, which is kind of cross axis in
this case.
And I don't see any getting around that, right?
So, you know, that's just the way it goes sometimes.
So tear a is actually an M1 28.
In this case
and,
you know, it can be pulled out here.
so,
That will pull the tyria and let us continue in our regular scalar
form.
So we just need these two to operate properly here.
In order to for these operate properly, like I said, they have to kind
of be practicing text.
So if you look at how T re has to work, it's got to pull out the X,
the, the y or the Z.
So it does have to do you know this
Oops.
And so we can just compute tear a Forex directly there and we should
be good to go now.
Yes, thank you for telling me.
so, taking a look at,
The rest of the code here.
What else do we care about?
So yeah.
That's correct there.
And so looking at the last of this here, so face relative origin.
Which is the same across all Lanes, the tear a in this case would need
to be replicated up.
and maybe so we just want that to be a replicated value of trying to
see where else that gets used times the rate erection
Again, that's a 4 x value.
So, really tear a, in this case,
We could just do it as a thing that was replicated out.
And we made us want to do that.
Yeah, so if you look here, we've also got like our, you know, our box
radius for example.
So in this case,
I think we can just leave that doing exactly what it was doing, so the
Box radius value in this case, in fact, we can just
Grab it.
Here.
And then we really now just have to deal with this one line.
I think that's it.
so it's that and well and okay in the T-Rex
So yeah.
So we want to be able to do face real origin times, the T values, the
T value really wants to remain replicated.
if you look at,
Here.
Producing this tier a value if we were to do this way.
So we were to say, okay, let's produce the tear a 4 x value as
something that's replicated across.
then what we can do is,
Just Produce the values and then Loft them up.
this is going to produce the lane so we really just need, you know,
The sort of thing.
So we've got this call.
And I'm just talking about this call.
Right.
And this could be written more concisely this way.
Because this is all the same value.
So, we could do something like that and then tear a 4X.
is what you would expect now and here where we're pulling out
something on a lane, we don't care which one so now because the X y&z
all have the same value, because the scaler effectively
So we can just use that and off we go.
Now we could introduce another type which would kind of be nice here
probably which is just an F32 for X.
You don't have one of those yet and we probably should and that's how
that would work and we could try that in a second.
So we really are down to just this guy now.
Yeah, and so, yeah.
So you can see what the problem is here.
So if I actually do that Loft, then it doesn't know what to do here
because this is a vector multiply.
So it's like, what kind of multiply when I be doing hadamard product
dot product cross product, right?
So that's why it would help if we had the interior type, you know I'm
saying?
So if instead here we were to say, okay we've got a F32 for X which is
Part that we didn't have before.
That would be kind of nice.
So then we just have, you know,
something like this.
See the packed value and an e value.
So and then we can just Define these operators.
So now this becomes like a lot clearer what's going on, right?
So this is just an F32 4X.
It's a scalar value.
You know, I'm saying and then this can be written naturally as well.
It can be negative face.
Real origin /.
Ready for X, right?
Because now we can define those operations in here and they'll just
work.
Now, what we want to do here is say that this, by the way, you know,
is one of these values, right?
Like so, and in fact, if we could just say this was a union, it's a
little dicey to do that but we could do it that way so that, you know,
it had either of those two.
But yeah, I'm not sure if I really wanna do that.
So anyway, yet if you, if you look at how that's going to go here,
then what you could do is you can translate all of these into actual
operations on the F32 version, right?
So we can kind of do that slowly but you'll see what I mean.
Second.
That's also what the sign ja you would become.
So here's an F 3 to 4X of the sine value and that way when we do it
this way, we don't have to load it like that we can just say OK the
sine value for this axis index is going to be loaded, you know?
Just just one value is going to be loaded in there and and then we can
set that the way we would want to and I did it this way as well.
So we could actually just have it be set directly.
So the sine value.
Can be can be accessed the way you would expect and that that's much
nicer.
That cleans things up quite a bit.
In fact I should have done that at the outset but I didn't for
whatever reason
Yeah.
So, moving on.
What we would want to do now is just clean up the way that this part
is working here.
So sine value X Box radius like that multiplication as to be defined
the same as to be true for these.
Divides here, but that's mostly all we're talking about.
So let me go ahead and Implement those.
If we want to do our negation it's the same thing we already did.
So here's write this thing.
If we want to do our negation, we can just go.
Alright, our F32 4X.
Our result p.
In this case, is just going to be.
Whatever the input was.
With a sub PS.
On 0, right?
This is going to take whatever that input was and it's going to do the
operation.
And so the same thing we could actually do that.
Same thing here, you know, if we want to then start writing these in
terms of each other, we could, I'm not sure we want to do that just
yet.
But again, then you can actually have all of the operations that you
would normally have as well.
But then you can have the cross ones in addition.
So, if I have a V3 for X, for example, and I want to Define what
happens when we multiply a scalar times a vector,
we just can and that just works.
So I can say, all right, the result value.
In this case is just going to be a multiplication.
And it's always going to use the same value from a because it's a
scalar, but it's going to Loop over the different dimensions of be,
right?
So that defines that operation here that we needed so that that can
just happen, right?
So we can get this to work now.
Obviously, we need to pull out the axis index, one of them, whichever
one was proper appropriate for the X and X.
But other than that, we're done, right?
So then here, we've got another problem.
We've got to what is this, binary?
What, where are you seeing a binary -
I wouldn't have called that a binary -, to be honest with you, but,
okay, that looks like a unary minus to me.
So not sure why you said binary, but it's okay, first of all just, you
know, it's fine.
So when we take a look at what happened, what's going to happen here?
We've had a innie operator.
For rv3 for X's.
So I'm going to try what happens if we just say that gives you back an
F32 for X, right?
So then we take a look here and are divided as busted because, you
know, we've got a workout, we're going to do there, but that's okay.
And then let's see what else we got.
Okay, so our kirei for X, we pull out our x value, not a member of
F32.
That's true.
This we fixed.
So now we can just pull out the value.
Normally this is making it much cleaner should have done this a long
time ago.
I apologize for not doing so and then, I think we're pretty much done,
right?
So tear a 4X times, raid d4x.
I thought we did multiplication of a V4 of a V3.
So right, that's an extraction.
So in this case, where we've created this, we can produce the rapey
value up here.
Like so,
With a rapey 4 x value.
And then in here, we can pull it out.
Right.
So yeah, if you take a look, what has to happen there.
Also, I don't know that Ray origin needs to get pulled out anymore.
And neither is this.
Right?
Because we can produce the whole thing at once.
So if we have the P4 value of the, sorry that's a getcomponent call
because it's a slice wise.
So
And then we've got our divide, which we haven't implemented yet.
So that's a divided between two scalar values, which now we do have
the ability to properly represent.
And so there's our times there is so here is our
No, that's not.
No, no, no, no.
It's the other one.
I should organize these a second here.
There we go.
so if I want to do divide here actually this is not what I wanted
either just wanted to basic times there guys
You're not have any operators between these, I'll be I guess we don't
have any.
All right, well, this is our first operator then.
So what you can see all I'm doing here is just making something that
does these operations.
In scalar form there, right?
So now we're compiling but you know, hey we just went willy-nilly on
this, so we're going to have to step through it here and see what
we're doing.
So and I am not in debug mode.
I want to inspect all these
There we go.
so in here, if I you know, start taking a look
Like so, so we've got sign values.
And box surface indices that we want to produce.
So I'm just going to make sure that those get produced correctly.
So here's our BarkBox service indices.
And, you know, their plausible.
Do I know if they're right.
No, but they're plausible, so that's good.
R sine values, look right or reasonable anyway.
So that looks okay.
We know that this stuff was okay or at least we don't have any reason
to suspect it being that we broke it in any particular way.
But then we're going to get down here and we don't really know what's
going on down here, right?
So the first thing we need to do is produce the face relative origin.
That's by taking the relative origin and moving in the opposite
direction Here.
Sign wise.
So really this sign we could just make this a plus and negate.
The direction of the sign.
We don't have to for any particular reason but just worth noting that
we could have done that.
Right the sign isn't it used for anything else?
So it probably doesn't matter but that's the way that goes.
So we're going to use to face relative origin by starting at the
relative origin.
And then just moving outwards along the radius to wherever we actually
needed to go, right?
Although wait, that's not correct either.
So
Fox radius needs to just be
Right, this needs to only operate on.
Just just the one component here, so
That's that's incorrect again.
That was just when I'd gotten confused there.
I made some stupid assumptions about which way we were.
Slicing this data.
It was just dumb.
We only want to add one slice of this, right?
So we want to take the face relative origin here like so and what we
want to do is take just one slice of it, whichever the axis indexes
that we're talking about and just that axis index, we want to subtract
away, whatever the Box radius was for that.
Right?
So we're trying to do this is what we're trying to do there.
We're trying to take the relative origin and just move it, right?
We're just trying to move it based on the axis that we're on.
Now, I think we could probably do that more efficiently.
Like that's probably not the right way to do it.
It's a right way to do.
It is probably to look at what we were using.
The face relative origin for and try to adjust that value.
Maybe a little bit differently, I'm not sure.
But you can see here that these
Are all based on the axis index in this case, right?
And then we compute the actual final location of the ray here, and
that should still be right.
Now mind you, we don't actually have to do it this way.
So
Again, it's really tempting.
Maybe I wasn't wrong.
The first time
It's since we don't actually ever need the facial active origin,
right?
Because let's say we just want to produce the where the ray will land,
If we all just want to produce where the ray will land, well, we can
just use the original Ray origin because once we know the T value, it
doesn't matter where we start from we, it doesn't matter which
coordinate system.
We do it in.
Right.
So, we can produce that Ray value here, right?
If we want to.
So the problem that we actually have is that when we come down here to
use, this re P value, this re P value needs to be based on whatever
the
this, this one needs to be based.
On whatever the relative origin was because it has to have its an
actually using the P value.
And that P value needs to be relative to the origin of the box.
Right.
That was how this worked.
So that was the reason that we needed to use the relative origin
there.
And I guess that's also why this rapey value can't be the same, right?
Unfortunately.
because this is really a relative one and this is an absolute
So that's pretty complicated.
Because you'd ideally like to not have to do that.
You know.
And so if you take a look in here, what you're checking based on?
The only place that it ever gets used, right?
Like the only place that that ever gets used is really just in this
check.
So you know the X and the Y check here it's just if the axis is 0
you're using the why
Otherwise, you're using the X.
Yeah, but unfortunately, I just don't see any real way around that.
So basically, we've got a displacement.
And, you know, we could do this any number of ways, but I'm just
looking at here and so, you know, we want to compute this re P value
that we're using before we have to get it out of the face, real pee.
Instead.
And it which that's really annoying.
But I'm not sure how it's we would do it.
We have to think that through, maybe there is some other way you could
actually do it.
I'm not sure.
So anyway, the point is yeah this actually needs to be moved in this
fashion.
This is just introduces a few more operators here which is fine.
We kind of want all these operators anyway but it's just a - equals
operator there.
So yeah if we just take a look at for example -
Plus like this one.
so, if we just do,
This I believe is all we actually need see here.
Yeah.
So we take if we just take the first one as a reference value,
so,
And then just say that.
Well, and just say that.
That's our - equals.
All right, so let's step into that again.
So, we take the relative origin now, we're going to take.
So if I look at face relative origin,
What we're going to do now is say okay for the exes, we're going to
modify just that axis Index, right?
And we're trying to replicate
this motion here.
So along the axis that we're testing, which in this case is the
x-axis, we're going to move the radius away, right?
But really the other values on touched and that's exactly what we did
here.
We're also going to.
Yeah.
Well then we're going to try to do that computation to find out what
the tear a values are and we're going to pull those out.
Right?
In here.
We go, right here and test them.
We're going to do our stuff and see where we go.
And so now,
You know, effectively, we're actually running the routine, we don't
know.
We might have bugs in it.
Probably we do.
But again, get a little closer.
All right.
so,
Finishing up here.
What I want to do is say.
Yeah, once we kind of come in here, so again, write like this part is
looking pretty nice.
Now, even up to here, it's pretty reasonable, right?
Like, not a lot of code.
This part should be simplified down, but this Parts pretty
straightforward, but this part is horrible, right?
So now, the last thing we have to do is actually make this stuff work
somehow reasonably.
This is the nasty part in here, for sure.
So that's kind of unfortunate.
To say the least.
Now rather than doing these via see index, we can just do our tests.
Now we should be able to do our tests just for wide immediately,
right?
So now we can do a thing where we just say.
All right, let's produce the test value itself.
These two can be moved inside the loops or this test value here can
actually be done outside.
Okay, so what we can do is say, let's first test will produce this
test value.
And we need to know when we kind of come through here.
What these test values are.
So I'm going to have an F 3 to 4X which is my you know, T check.
And here's the tea check and we just need to know if any of those are
true.
That makes sense.
So if any of them are true, then we can proceed.
Then we would come through here.
And perform the rest.
Skate serially right almost there.
So now we get to the point where, you know, the downshifting.
I'm not sure exactly how we want to downshift here because in theory,
we do sort of need to downshift potentially, maybe sort of possibly.
We could just avoid downshifting At All by just pouring in here.
The results that we actually need with a mask, right?
So that's kind of ridiculous that we could do that but we can.
I think I don't.
So we can we might be able to just do this entirely with no, for Loop,
right?
So we'd get rid of the seed.
See index entirely into the only thing we Loop over is the axis index
and we're basically done
in theory.
All right, so this part right here, yeah, it is a little nasty but it
just probably will just sort of work, right?
So we've got the face relative P.
So, what we can do here is just expand all of these two, for x's and
say, look, this is the face or LP now.
it's
I end that just works, right?
So we can load out for at a time there.
And that should be that should be fine.
Right?
Again this I guess we would have to
make a little equals operator for to make it be able to load them when
28, it's like that but that's fine.
The thing we could do is just say like E1 here because that one is
loaded that way.
So taking a look here.
The Box radius.
Is also loadable exactly this way, right?
So the Box radius can be loaded for a wide
and that would just work.
So then at that point after doing these wide.
So we wouldn't need to see index here at all.
In fact, this can just go away, right?
We could get it down to just this.
So we could get done, just this pretty straightforward there, we
wouldn't have to do very much work here, right?
So we would do again an F32 for and this would be our bound check
value.
It would come through like this, right?
And it would be checking, it would just be checking wide and then we
would do if any true there would basically a mask here.
It would have to be things that passed, both the T check and the bound
check.
If anyone passed both, then we actually have to look if nobody.
Did we skip it and we don't care, right?
Zombie sense.
So that's really it.
Then this part become.
This is the part.
That's nasty.
Maybe I'll save that for tomorrow.
But basically what has to happen here now is we have to select the
values that we would put into the results and or figure out whether we
wanted to do this situation here.
So, really, I think,
Close enough is also going to be something that comes out up here,
right?
So checking tear a 4X here we would know whether anyone was close
enough or not and if anyone's close enough for this that particular
Ray that particular raised going to get done in there.
Now the interesting thing about this is if you're going to go through
the process of checking off our raise any way by pushing a box on the
stack, you definitely don't need to do this.
So really all we have to do is just check whether or not the close
enough value, had any throughs at all in there.
So when we get in here we could
say, look if there's any truths in close enough,
Then we're going to do the Box stack push like so and then we can just
that's just a straight break out of here.
Out of the axis Loop, right?
Otherwise, if there aren't
Then this is when this would happen and also I guess the Box child
count.
Is the same.
So at that point, we're only talking about this.
And we would just want to load up these guys in here, right?
So,
You just want to like knock them instead of doing it the way that
we're doing it here.
So,
That's, that's that right?
Couple things we have it implemented there yet but otherwise seems
fine.
This needs an if statement, right?
For the time being.
And so to do that, we would need some way of asking but that's
actually pretty straightforward, right?
So what we could do there is just look at the pack value and say that
the u-32 version of that.
If that's true and so that's actually all we would need to know.
So, we can get rid of the concept of tear a 4X now, and just call it
to you Ray.
Which is nice.
Those are just things we have to Define.
It's complaining about c and x.
Where did we?
Are we still using see you next summer.
Oh, we are
So this result here a here results here, a actually now wants to act
be for wide properly.
So result, tear a, which was this value right here.
This wants to be a Forex and it wants to be a
Load up there, right?
That we convert.
Slowed it in.
These are just binary operators that we need to Define and these are.
What's this thing?
It's for operators.
We need
These are all just operators, we need.
Yeah.
Yeah, so I think that's all good result T.
This this now is, you know, you can see exactly how we're going to do
this now, right?
So this is just going to be combined via the mask
This could be confined by the mask, and this could be confined by The
Mask.
All of these could be basically mask operations.
So, you know, we're just going to have to do that slowly.
Because we have a lot of things to Define here.
So in handmade Cindy, I'm kind of tempted to break this out but I
don't know it's a little hard to do.
So, you know, I'm kind of having to break it into two files.
One for V, 3 is 14 f-22s, but I don't know if I want to do that or
not, it's a little bit Squinkie.
So, what I'm going to do here is I'm going to try
Just doing it this way for now.
And I'm just going to put all of these things.
Into their own section.
Like so.
All right, so if I wanted to find all the stuff that I might want on
an F32 for X.
Let's start with the basics.
So, here we have.
you know, re-
Let's get some basic option here.
A Plus
yours -
here's mall and here is div.
And then, let's go ahead for good measure and do the other versions.
So, plus equals x equals dou, V equals.
and if we want to, we can make these the sort of more platform neutral
by saying something,
Like that.
Right, because then we could all we could just pour just the one
divide routine and then Theory the compiler, I'll figure it out again,
it's a pretty big in theory there.
But what you gonna do
So, here is our various Ops.
Like so in the news will just suck down to these.
All right, so once we have all of those, we also need absolute value.
Absolute value works exactly the same way.
We just only need to do it on one.
Like so.
Right, we then have any true and all true.
I answer using these comparisons, here is pretty straightforward,
we're just going to use the move mask every time or it's going to
check it for different values.
So in the first case, we're just going to see if any of the move Mass
values were true at all.
In the Altru case we're going to make sure that it equals a predefined
value that we know about which I guess in this case is probably 15.
I guess.
I don't know.
We should go double check the documentation for that but let's just
say and then in the case of anything else we know
That it's just going to be.
It's just going to be zero because none of the values should be set.
So yeah.
All right.
Yeah, that's stuck P there.
oh,
sorry about that.
Let me go.
So now we eat our loads and I'm not sure how we want the syntax of our
loads to go.
So,
You know, one way to do it is to make them look like this.
Right.
And that seems pretty good.
I don't know if we actually have any of those in here.
I don't think we do.
And so inside here.
Yeah, we could just say, okay, we'll just call them F3 to underscore
for x and we'll just give it the value that we actually want.
So we just say here is our results.
We're still up.
He equals m M1, PS.
Is just a value that we gave for all of them.
This one, I don't really know again.
What the appropriate values here for these should be in terms of
loading Lane based because it's hard to say, which order run from
going.
In fact, I'm going to just not put that one in the moment.
Yeah.
Okay, so now we need our comparison operators.
Those are, you know, going to again be very straightforward and
they're just, they're just the same as these operators, like here,
comparison wise, right?
So, we just have to do compare here.
And we just want to give it all of our various comparison operators,
right?
So we want less than which is comp LT less than or equals 2, which is
comp le0 we want.
Greater than comp GT.
We want greater than or equal to
Just comp GE.
And then we want just our tube vanilla values which is comp equal and
comp not equal, right?
So that's comp not equal to that's comp equal to.
So now we have all of our comparison values and Theory
Sorry, I missed that mnemonic.
And in this case, Zero obviously is not an actual value.
So we need F3 for x or 0.
F 3 for X something like that.
So, we need that value to be in here somewhere.
Yeah.
And so then also are you to remind us that point could be written in
terms of our regular -, if we wanted to we could call this 0 and
subtract a from it like so.
And so, that's again, another way of taking the platform part out of
that in a nice way, so that we can make this easier to Port later on
when we actually care.
So, now, we get to our logical Ops and so on here,
So I'm down how good I need some updates.
Windows as updated like every day for the past several days.
Like, try to get your act together, people.
so we need an and here and
There's a couple ways to look at this.
So one of the unfortunate Parts about the and is that it's not really
doing a logical.
And technically
But we're not going to actually bother to do a logical and because we
know that our comparison operators, always produce all zeros are all
ones.
So a binary and actually works the same as a logical.
And for the case of we care about, however, it is a bit of a caveat
because if someone came along and actually expected that to be a
logical and all of a sudden, it wouldn't do it.
So it is a little bit Squinkie, but you just have to kind of be aware
of it, that, that is how that works, right?
So one way we could do it is say,
Yes, and just write that code.
So that it's clear to the people that they can't have the logical
version.
Even though we're using the logical version, it's not actually
logical, right?
And so that's kind of an important thing to just be aware of as you're
writing.
This kind of code, is there.
It's not doing a logical and you're actually doing a binary and and
you're just making that be the same thing.
So we need a way to do the conversion here from these and we can do
that pretty easily.
That's really only because we the way that we happen to write, this
was a little bit Squinkie.
What we can do is we could change these to F 32s in here instead.
And then that stuff would work, but we'd have to quickly rewrite all
the rest of our code, but that's okay.
We could do that.
I mean, you know, for feeling saucy, we can definitely do that.
Like so.
And now we're just going to get a lot of things here that are, that
are wrong.
However, one of the things that we can do here now is we can start to
make this stuff all work in terms of our other code if we wanted to.
So for example, like when we do operator plus we could now just do
Instead of add PS here, right?
We just we just do this.
so again now this all works in terms of that one, Cindy underlying set
there and hopefully you know, does the compiler doesn't puke face on
it but you know,
If the compiler can manage to figure out through all these ridiculous
Hoops, that c has us go through in order to make this look clean.
You know, we would it would be good.
Right?
And so you can see that that should just work there.
I'm not going to dress that one just quite yet.
Okay.
So yeah, again, same thing here.
And here.
And now, like I said, you know, this this is means that this is now
platform-independent, which is kind of nice because now you don't have
to Port it, right?
If you wanted to Port it to something else.
Some platform like neon, it just takes some of the work out of it
because they are all depending on just one set of those calls.
And, you know, that's not a huge deal because you can just use macros
or whatever.
It's not really a particularly big deal, but it's a little bit of a
leg up in.
That's nice.
You know, you can, you can continue to condense it down to something
that's pretty straightforward, you know, going even further than we're
going now, and just getting those base operations in place.
In a separate file and then you just swap out which file you're
talking about, right?
Honestly, these even are, you know, this this could just be that.
Right.
Oops.
Again, if I just started with this, the right way we wouldn't have
done this.
So that was kind of stupid.
But, you know,
Sometimes you got to just type and then you see the pattern, you're
like oh yeah, duh, right?
That was the right way to do it.
Obviously.
And again, it's worth doing, you know, it does make it harder on the
compiler.
Like I was saying before because, you know, like, for example, just
take a look at the transfer serious.
Did we want to call that function?
So that just gets done the way that it should get done on that
particular platform.
But, you know, this platform happens to require mask load.
If the compiler, can't figure out that, it can reuse that mask, that
just creates a lot of extra work there, right?
So, you got to be aware of the the extra stress replacement compiler.
Check to make sure that it knows what's going on later when we
actually care and Things Are
Potentially in a Squinkie State, you know, you don't you don't want
to, you don't want to be unaware of the additional stress that you're
putting on the compiler in this state.
Okay, so let's continue going here.
So if you have a f 3 for X here that we want to load, I'm going to do
an F 3 for x.
Wood on that value, and then do them all here.
Like so.
Oh, these are v34 X's.
Okay, let me fix that.
I'm like what's a complaining about in like that's right, we've got a
another type in here that I
Was using a different part of the code.
We want to do that as well.
Same thing applies here.
And these are just ordered together.
So in theory, we can just do this as an actual or now
So oops, so it's like or them all together and then do this.
And this one will just be like and them all together and then do it.
and so in this case, I guess we want to do here is say this is any
true
and this is any true.
Is that just a move mask?
This is what it was doing.
So this is just a load up again, same exact thing that we were doing
before.
So this is
Orion there.
Here's one that lives across the lanes.
So there's one that we do want to do that way, I guess.
So this is one that I guess we do want to do or where we would say F 3
to 4X and we would pass these in oops.
In that function.
again, it's just one of these and the difference here is that it just
has each of these
All right, getting there.
So now when we take a look here, this one is converting from an M1 28.
I don't really want anyone to be doing that anymore.
It's a, I'm going to vaporize that.
This can just be done by any now.
like so, and that's got to be an and
So this has to be a load.
Like so and that's it.
So now we just have to take a look.
What is this?
This is in our other code here and I'm set expression.
That's going to be this stuff here.
so that's just
That right.
Yeah.
Alright, so let's go back to the code that we were looking at before.
So here's the code.
You can see how we're pulling through here.
We do all this work.
Exactly.
The way that we used to do this work, and we do our checking and we
produce.
Well, we produce exactly what we thought were going to produce, right.
In theory, this code is complete.
Now we probably have bugs but in theory it is
So yeah.
I don't really want to run it and know how bad it is.
But I think what I'll probably do because we're way over time now is,
I'll probably just revisit this tomorrow.
Well, I'll be honest.
That was a lot better than I thought.
The lighting is still calculating.
Pretty reasonably actually.
So I wasn't necessarily expecting that, but that's pretty great.
So, I guess.
Yeah.
Well that was
Is it?
Alright, so now we actually are Computing.
All of these values pretty much all the way down doing for raised at a
time.
However, we are not actually doing the very last step.
It still has to do pull outs here which are not great.
Any other thing is with this, this Preamble code, is garbage the
moment, right?
Like, this part here is completely stupid.
So that part also could stand to be improved quite a bit, because
again, we don't really want to be down shifting all the time in that
way.
On the code on the outside.
It's got a loop over the sub raised here which again also isn't great.
So this part probably also would need to be symbolized in order to be
good.
So that's going to be a pain in the butt in addition but like I said I
can start tackling those tomorrow and then once we have all that done,
we can see this is the oh he's the nasty part about Cindy we can see
if we actually got any good performance improvements out of that, and
we can take a look at it tuning wise.
Yeah, and it's hard to say, you know, if we will, if we won't could
be, we were all memory Bound in which case, this is complete waste of
time, but we'll find out I guess.
Yeah, not sure.
I want to do this last part.
Well, you know, maybe I will,
So we do any true on The Masks, we can just check here too.
See if we need to push the Box on, if you don't need to press the box
that we need to do is update the results here and updating the results
is like a two-step thing that we want to do there.
So what we want to do is we want to take our are the way that we're
returning our results right now, this raycast result.
So we want to do is take that recast result and want to change the way
that's happening.
So, the first thing we do is just point out the fact that box into C's
can just be 32.
Just give me the indices, right?
They don't actually act have to
Actually be the boxes themselves.
The reason I know that it's because you can see like we do the get box
call right here and the get box call right.
Does a specific look up operation right?
It looks into the box table.
And pulls out a particular value.
So, that box table.
Here is the value.
We could just be returning.
If we wanted to could just return that directly out now, where is get
box actually called, it's not called that many places.
But we wanted, so we kind of we kind of want to do that without.
We don't necessarily want to pass this box index back.
We want to pass this one to avoid having to do those double lookups
there.
So you know I'm saying, so we really want to do here is
Is when we're actually in this routine.
Doing our a cast.
We want to do here is to be able to pass that box and X-Pac and have
some way of making that refer to which boxes were talking about.
We don't have a no box at the moment, which is kind of annoying, but
we can use the fact that the root box is not one that we ever return,
right?
We never, we never actually return the root box.
So we can took we can't take the route box index and make that one be
What we wanted to return if you know, if we decide to do that, right?
Something about
All right, so in here, what we could say is an, in fact, we could just
pass the other one back for now and just do the the other opposition
later.
So this is Source index that we would be returning here.
And so that way, what we could say is like, alright, let's pass back a
box in next in the raycast result.
So in here, where we've got this Source index, when we go to record,
which box got hit the box that got hit is actually going to be.
First index.
Like so, and the person on the outside.
Instead has to actually do that.
Look up.
Right?
And so that's just passing it back by a numerical index.
And instead of specific index, why do we have to do that?
Well, the reason that we had to do that is because if we want to pack
these, we can't pack 64-bit values into a semi register.
We have to pack 32-bit values into some your register, so just to
prepare for that, right?
So what we want to do now is figure out a way to sort of make these
things all and together properly and so that they can be loaded out.
So if I now go into handmade lighting and instead change the raycast
result here to a F32 for X, in each case here,
So instead of returning for a cast results, we're just going to return
one raycast results, but that raycast result will have all of the
values in it, then what we can do is say all right, let's clear the
Box index out first.
So the Box index is going to be equal to an F 3 to 4 x of 0.
Like so.
Guess that's floating Point.
That's okay.
Then we go through and we talked about that result value.
Such as in here.
Now we can just again do this in a sort of piecemeal fashion if we
want to and then pull it out at the end.
So for now let's just do that directly so you can make sure it's
working at all.
So yeah.
What I want to do here is say
Definition to save this for tomorrow.
We've got a way too long.
It's already 4:00.
It's already 5:00.
Disastrous, disastrous.
I say
I should say this for tomorrow.
All right, so I will save the rest that for tomorrow and that'll be
that we will take the briefest of q&a's.
They better be the most on topic that like I've ever
Seen before.
Like literally they have to be the honest of on topic.
see if there ain't, it doesn't look like there are
Also to clarify from earlier.
We don't actually stream at 60 frames a second and we don't need to
stream at 60 frames a second because even if the game is running at 30
frames a second, that would be fine with me or if it was six feet per
second.
Transfer 8:30 was.
The problem was that the capture card couldn't capture Progressive and
the computer at 60 frames a second and the computer can only output 60
frames a second Progressive.
So we end up with interlace
So even if we were streaming like 10 frames a second, it was still a
problem because it was all interlaced and ugly.
So even for game development where we're not running at frame rate yet
and everything.
It's like, it's got to be Progressive because
That.
Well yeah, it just you can't really interlace just as awful.
I think you call any true from within all True Connect, that's
intended.
Yes, that was intended.
So, what's happening there is
In this case, right?
We've got any true, all true, and all false, and these are ways of
testing what the lanes are in a 4 wide,
So, any true just tells us where any lanes true, right?
So I assume you're referring to this one in all three true.
The portent part his in is in at least one lane, so this is
essentially all true any true, right?
And the reason is because there's two Dimensions, your testing along
one is along the dimensions and here we're saying any for all three
dimensions or all for all three dimensions, right?
But then in both cases, we don't care which lane so we don't have to
use all true.
We could make another version of this.
That was any three true in all lanes and all three true in all lanes
and that would change this any to and all.
Does that make sense?
It's a matrix right?
This is what that data type looks like.
Right?
It's got an x, a y, and a z component in four different lanes.
And so any
And all.
Are plenty sufficient.
If you're just talking about a single scalar.
that's been replicated to four lanes because then you're just saying,
well are any lanes to are all Lanes true, but once you go to the
Matrix, you've got two enemies and all's there's any
and all on this axis and then there's any
And all on this axis and you can combine the two.
So if I said all, all that would mean our is this entire Matrix set to
True?
Right?
True, true, true true.
True too true.
Right, any here?
But all here would be like, is true.
Is any one of these rows have throughs all across and vice versa?
Is anyone column throughs all across, right?
Hopefully, that makes sense.
All right, I see no more on topic questions.
All right.
Thank you everyone for joining me for an extremely long episode of
handmade hero.
It's a pleasure cooking with you.
As always, we will come back tomorrow to finish our Cindy, ization of
this routine and then we will see if we can get it running any faster
that way.
Hopefully we can otherwise we just wasted a bunch of time doing
nothing if you want to follow along with the series at home.
Obviously, you can pre-order the game at hand made here at dot org and
it comes to the source code.
So if you wanted to play around with symbolizing it,
Self and learn a little bit about Cindy.
I symbolizing code that way, that's pretty good way to do it.
We'll be back here tomorrow to finish the 70 optimizations, until then
have fun programming everyone and I'll see you on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.