There we go.
I have stopped.
And then I have started the recording again known as cycling.
According to those of you who are experts on Twitch.
Here is the thing people.
I'm prepared to say it and prepared to say it.
Welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code an entire game live on Twitch.
No engines.
No libraries using, only our typing fingers.
Now, today is a very special day.
Because just before the stream, I decided I was tired of looking at a
bunch of yellow rectangles, while I was coding and so, I did it.
I just flat-out did it before the stream.
I decided it was time for handmade Hero Test assets to dot zip.
So if you are someone who's following along at home,
You will note that if you go to the link that you received in your
email, if you pre-ordered the game on handmade here at org.
If you go to the link that you got from the pre-order, there is now
the test asset zip has been updated from 1 to 2.
We are onto now and basically what I did is, I grab some of our assets
course, you can't preview them because Windows bit map, viewer doesn't
actually work even though they invented the format, but basically, I
grab some rocks.
Some trees and some
Tufts of grass and such that I wanted to use so that we could stop
using yellow rectangles for walls and we could actually start having
some actual things there.
We won't get carried away with it, but I was just at the point where I
just tired of looking at them.
So I decided it was time to grab some assets.
So, for those of you who like to follow along with the stream, now
would be a good time to go and grab that.
And it's got the old test directory.
It's got all the same stuff in there.
So everyone could follow along as well, but it's also got this test to
directory.
And basically what you're going to want to do is they're going to want
to go to the data directory and you're going to want to go ahead and
place that test to right on in there.
Right?
So now you've got that test to in there and now we can load stuff from
that and that will be good.
So, let's go ahead and Dive Right In.
We basically had a little bit of cleanup to do.
We have some testing to do, but basically there's one thing that we
hadn't written yet, so we couldn't
We weren't really backed a feature parity from yesterday when we made
our spatial partition for entities.
So I'd like to do is just go ahead and get that done.
And then maybe we can replace those yellow rectangles with some actual
trees or something, which would be nice and do some other stuff like
that just because it's the time, you know, you got to just go with the
flow sometimes and I feel like that's where the flow was going.
And so that's where we're going to go.
All right, so
If I go ahead and open up handmade dot CPP, you will remember that.
The thing?
Where we left it, we were not actually back tubes.
What?
Just happened.
There, Dev and there we go.
So you will remember that.
We were at the point where we were running again, but we didn't have
any entities, right?
Because we did the thing that actually supposed to bring entities into
the working set, actually hasn't been done yet.
And so we have to
I have to go ahead and write that actual code.
If you remember, I just basically straight up commented it out.
So, in the set camera, you can see there's an f-zero around it.
So I guess, I shouldn't say commented it out, if zeroed it out more
specifically, six of one half dozen of the other.
And so, what I need to do is I need to actually write this now using
our spatial partition, because it's exactly things like this, which
are spatial queries that are supposed to be accelerated by our
partition.
So now's the time when we have to start actually using that and doing
some actual real stuff with it.
So what I want to do is previously
What we did is we just looped over all the tiles in the world that
we're inside, our cameras radius.
And then we said, okay, we're going to take that and say all of those
tiles.
Anything that's that's in that range of tiles.
Will now come into the working set.
And so what I want to do is I'm going to do exactly the same thing.
But what I want to do is just do that by chunk.
So what I want to do is just say any of the chunks that overlap the
camera will pull those in and that will be sufficient for now.
Now, we might want to get a little more fancy later and actually check
for the entities inside the chunk to see,
They match the camera bounds specifically, but I don't actually know
if we really do want to do that or not because the high entity list is
kind of a fluid concept.
Anyway, we don't have to necessarily cap it to an exact boundary,
certainly not yet so we can kind of we can kind of fudge that a little
bit if we want it.
All right.
So what I'm going to do here is go ahead and uncomment this out.
This is no longer going to work, obviously, because we had the camera
p, and it was using the ABS tile stuff, which we got rid of.
And so now what we want,
Want to do, is we want to have a chunk X chunk y instead, right?
And then we have our tile span and our tile span is presumably, you
know, no longer that relevant either because what we'd really like to
do is talk about chunks, man's more specifically, right?
And so we do have something, I guess, one thing that I should bring
up.
That is kind of relevant here.
Is we don't want to be oscillating.
A lot where we're moving things in and out because our bounds don't
match up.
So that might actually be one good reason to sort of think this
through a little bit more carefully.
For example, let me go ahead and and do a little diagram here for you.
So if we imagine that we've got of course got it.
Got it.
Always ruin my colors, don't you Mischief?
This is pretty Miss.
Just pretty good so far.
I feel like we need to like email them and say, please just fix the
bugs in it and it
Be pretty awesome, you know.
Anyway, so if we're in a situation where we've got, you know, again,
we've got our sort of screen that we're looking at and here is our
active region that we're talking about.
Well the active region as far as the camera bounds are concerned is
actually exactly right.
It's a rectangle that we made centered around wherever the camera
happens to be which is the center point here and it is exactly
rectangle.
That goes that way.
Now remember our chunks.
However, could be at any alignment on here, right?
The chunks.
We don't know how the
Chunks are aligned relative to the camera.
There's no, the camera could be free-roaming.
We have no.
You have how the chunks aligned.
And so if we pulled entities into the working set as as on the just
tile boundaries, right?
That would include an entity that would say right there.
Okay, and it would come into the hiset.
So on the last frame, when we looked through the tile chunks that
needed to get pulled in and we pulled in this one, it would pull in,
you know, a guy it would pull it would pull him in, right?
But on the subsequent frame, when we go to check the camera bounds
which are here.
We would find that he was outside it and we'd move him.
Right back.
We basically just cycle him between low and high low and high low and
high.
So we kind of want to make sure that we line up our checks in both
cases.
And so I think that Argos to me that maybe I will be more specific
about the check.
So what I'll do is I'll do a conservative coverage.
So I'll say basically give me all of the tile chunks that overlap,
this rectangle, the camera bounds.
And then I'll actually Loop through the entities as I pull them in.
And if they would be outside of the camera bounds, we will skip them,
right?
So that way we don't pull in any one who shouldn't be
Pulled in, right?
And I'm just going to say that that's roughly how we do things.
And again, we're just kind of experimenting here and we're sort of
narrowing down on exactly how we want things to work.
So it's not essential that our calculations be right or even that they
work yet correctly.
This is why I'm not doing a lot of testing, that's our stuff.
What's important is that we've structured the code to flow properly.
So that we know that when we go to write each individual part for real
and Dot, the I's cross, the t's that everything is is wired exactly as
it should be and everything's in the right.
Lace flowing correctly, right?
And so that's the important thing to keep in mind not whether the code
is working at all.
Because also we don't care if any of this code works because we're
going to do really good implementations of every individual piece and
that is basically what we will call our engine.
And so, if you were to spend a lot of time right now actually doing
really good code for any particular part here.
That's just time, that's wasted because you don't know if you're going
to have to reshuffle that area.
Like a lot of the stuff we've done you seen, how many times we've sort
of changed our mind about stuff over the course of the past 20 hours
or so, you want to make sure that you know, the 20, 30, 40 hours.
However long we spend on doing this sort of pre work on getting the
engine set up, right?
You want to make sure that you're not throwing away a lot of work.
You want to throw away?
The minimal amount of work.
You just write just basically the stuff that does roughly what you
needed to do.
You don't care.
If it works hardly at all.
You just make sure that you've got it roughly in, you know, pipeline
bubbles fashion, that everything flows correctly and all the code
connects correctly.
And then when you're sure, that's already, that's when it's time.
Or when you can start saying, I'm going to write a really good piece
of code here and actually think it through and test it.
That's the only time you want to do that because otherwise you're just
throwing that work away.
So very important thing to remember, I've said it multiple times.
I will probably say it.
Again, in the future.
So anyway,
Now, what I'd like to do is go ahead and say, let's let's figure out
this camera bound situation.
So we did that.
This is Computing.
This is working properly.
But now, with this wants to do is we want to basically make a Min
chunk X and a Mac chunk.
Chuck X and am in chunk why and Animax chunk line.
And then, we're going to want to do is Loop over those.
And we're going to want to pull out all of the entities that are
inside those, right?
And so what we need to do is essentially take what our camera bounds
were.
And we need to map those camera bounce into our chunk bounds.
And so what I think we want to do for that is we would like to ideally
have a function that could sort of do that for us, right?
If you
Could imagine saying, okay, we have, we already have the ability to do
that.
Mapping.
Let's in our handmade world, right?
We have the where is it here mapping to tile space function, right?
And that map in a tile space function, basically takes the base pup
position which was the camera and an offset, which would be either of
the corners of a rectangle and that would produce those chunk offsets
that we need, right?
That would tell us what those chalk offsets should be.
Now, of course, map into tile space is a bad name.
For this now because it's actually map into chunks face, right, but
that's, that's fine.
Right.
So we'll just call that map into chunks pace and we'll go ahead and
call that here.
So we've already got the code that we would need to do this.
We'll just do it exactly that way.
So when we map into chunks face, we're going to have a Min chunk P
basically, right?
And that's going to be the mapping into chunks face again of the of
that camera P, because that's what we're checking right.
And let me just make sure I know
We're checking here.
Let's actually think this through for one second because we may have,
we may also have a slight mistake here or just something that we have
to think about it.
I should say.
So what we want to do is this is going to go through and move our
entities slightly, right?
And then it's going to do the move and then check against the camera
bounds, which is this right here.
So when we move in the new state, yeah.
Okay.
So we're good, when we check the new state, what we want to do is we
want to use the new camera position because that is what should pull
things.
That's what should pull in the new things.
So we're going to use the new camera position and then the offset is
going to be that rectangle, the camera bounds.
And I want to basically get the, the Min of that, right?
And I don't think we made like accessors for that yet.
I'm going to go ahead and add those.
I basically want to do a get man on the camera bands getman Corner,
something like that, right?
Get me in corner.
So I want to get that open a map it in that I get my Min chunky and I
do the same thing for the opposite corner, right?
So I can get the maximum corner of that rectangle, right?
And that will give me
the same thing.
Once I've done that, now, I know that I can just straight-up read the
minimum and maximum chunk positions right out of here, right?
So I really don't even need these anymore.
I can get rid of that entirely and I can go ahead and introduce the
for Loop here.
Like so,
Where I just Loop over all of those chunks that are involved, right?
So I've got, I've got my chunk X.
Let's see here.
Where's the position, right?
Ago, so, I've got my chunk X, and that's going to start from the
minimum chunks, chunk X, right?
And then it's going to go until it reaches, and we actually want to
include because this is the chunk that actually includes the maximum
bound of our rectangular, right?
So, I'm going to include it there.
So this will Loop over from the Min chunk to the max chunks X.
And, I guess I want to go by, why first that tends to be our
convention only ABO.
Since we're going through a hash table in this case.
It doesn't matter which one We're looping over.
First at all.
I guess I should also just go ahead and copy this.
And just say, hey, what that was a x.
Now, it's a why?
Okay, so that's going to Loop over all of the chunks and for each
chunk, now we can pull that chunk out and look at all of the entities
that are in it.
Right.
And this is probably going to be a common thing for us to do.
And so once we write this Loop, we want may want to consider the next
time love to, you know, make a little mental note.
The next time that we want to Loop over all the entities that are in a
particular chunk or range of chunks for that matter.
We met model, make an accessor that makes it easier for us to do that.
So I'm going to go ahead now and take a look at this world chunk
stuff.
I know I've got my, my get World, Chuck call here, right?
Going to go ahead and call that.
I'm going to grab the chunk.
And that chunk is the one that's our chunk X chunk.
Y&r chunk Z is just going to be whatever the new camera P was.
Because at the moment, we've really kind of gimped out on Z.
We don't really do anything intelligent with Z.
That's something we're going to have to think about and basically
before we kind of move on with the engine, I'm going to have to
basically add some stairs for real and or, you know, something go kind
of down into into like a cave or something.
So we can kind of see how we want to handle Z because I'm not still
not sure about it.
I'm not sure exactly how we want Z to work.
There's a lot of questions there, but we know how we want X and Y to
work, so we're making sure that those were.
All right.
So I go into the world chunk.
I grab that out.
Remember we may not have.
There may not be a chunk there.
There may just be nothing there and that's fine.
So we want to allow that so we check to make sure that they're
actually is anything.
They're assuming that there is something there, we can go ahead and
loop through the entity count on the chunk.
Because remember the chunks.
Oh, I've got there's one more iteration here.
Right?
We've got these blocks.
So we've got rolled empty block, world into d block.
We grab that out of the chunk first walk, right?
Like so we then just go anytime.
There is a next pointer, we Chase it and then we look at all the
entities in that chunk.
Right?
So for any one of these blocks, we do that and we get the entity out
by looking at the low entity index.
Array in there.
So there we go, and that grabs it for us at that point.
We know that they have to be so we could even assert or we don't have
to assert never mind.
We have to look to see that there isn't already a high index for that
low any index.
And then we can just go ahead and check at that point to see whether
or not it would be.
In the bounds or not.
And so that's kind of interesting actually, because that means that
the make entity high frequency where that is kind of, has to be broken
up into two two parts.
You'll see why in a second.
So this right here that actually computes the position of it, right?
This part.
I kind of want to be able to do that first before I commit to making
them high so I can check it against the camera bounds.
So really what I want to do is essentially have another version of
This right of May, Kennedy, high frequency, which is exactly the same
and does most of the same stuff, right?
But what it actually will do is in, in the, in the case where where
you're calling it at sort of the lower level you will pass in the new
P that you want it to use, right?
So this this P right here and in the case where you're not going to
pass that then it will just do this this code right here, right?
so basically, that
This is the this is the camera space key, right?
So what we'll do here.
Hopefully, this makes some sense.
What we'll do here is, we'll say, all right, we'll just set the camera
space Peak here.
And if someone who doesn't know what the camera stays p is, then it'll
do it like that.
Right?
And furthermore.
I'll probably take it one step further and say in line V to get camera
space p.
And that will, you know, you'll do that off of a low entity
essentially.
And and I guess for purposes of this as well.
I will also pass that low entity pointer because you're going to have
to grab that as well.
So the low entity pointer will be here like that.
Excuse me.
And again, this is just making sort of a lower-level call.
This does not really need to be in line out.
Think that's probably at this point.
Well, I mean, I guess it could be because it's probably only happening
at two places.
So maybe it should be.
I don't know.
Hard to say.
I don't think too hard about that.
Like I said, that's something more for the profiling pass.
But yeah.
Just chill.
Typically, those just tend to be notes to myself about things that I
suspect.
I probably will want to make in line at some point.
All right.
So here we go.
This will actually move up here now and entity.
So that's actually just this.
This is our result, go.
All right.
So this will compute that camera stays P that we were previously doing
before just right in line.
And you can see that it needs the game state to look at where the
camera actually is.
So that'll get the camera space p.
So if you call make high energy, high frequency.
Now, what we're going to do is just go ahead and punt to the other
call entity high, like so and we will just pass all of the same stuff
here, but we will go ahead and do that work.
That wasn't happening before.
So we will go ahead.
Ed.
And we'll grab the low entities like so.
Right?
And when we grab that low entity, we will at that point I guess so, I
guess do we really need to check this?
Because I guess what we really want to do is is sort of.
Hmm.
I got think about this little bit.
Hold on a second.
I think, what I want to do is say this is a low-level call.
Right.
So what I want to do is say that check, right?
Is going to happen here.
Actually, and this is actually going to be an assertion.
So basically, if you're calling this routine, this is the lower level
routine.
I'm expecting just flat out that you did not that.
This was not there, right?
And, I guess I could be, I could get, I could guard it a little to
make sure we don't go horribly wrong.
But I'm going to I'm just going to assume that it's not there in this
particular in this particular case.
So yeah, I think I like that better.
So then when you call this one, which is the kind of fire-and-forget
method, where you don't necessarily know what's going on.
I'm going to change this to my standard form.
So I kind of decided to stop using the addressing forms.
It's not what I normally do.
I was doing it for purposes of the stream, but it didn't stick.
So anyway, I'm going to go ahead and say, all right, get the entity
low, if it's already got a hype and do nothing if it does.
Then we'll do it this way.
And this has got to be obviously.
Oops.
Hi.
This is got to be declared out here.
Either we grab it from the ones that already exist, or we go ahead and
make it and then we return out the entity that we that we found found
or made and then this will stay still make it exactly as it did
before.
And, of course, now, we have to actually call this function to get the
camera space p.
In the case, where we have to actually make it because now to two-part
call, so this is the camera space pee right here and that will do
nicely, I think.
So that gets the camera space p and passes it, right?
So now because we have this broken into parts, now, it's a lot easier
for us to deal with here.
We know that we've already checked against all of this stuff so we can
grab the cameras based P.
After that point, we grab that low entity out, and then we can use the
exact same check that was happening here in offset, check frequency by
area.
And so, let's go ahead and grab that offset check frequency by area
and we will
Go ahead and grab that is in a rectangle call right here, right.
So we could make that call, we check the camera space p, okay, and
this is going to be our camera bounds like that.
And then, if it's
Assuming that it's in that rectangle.
Now, we know that it's definitely a candidate for moving into the
height space so we can go ahead and do that and we can do that with
the stuff.
We've already computed.
So we don't waste anything.
They're all right.
So we've done that.
And we're happy, everyone's happy in the world.
And so now, all we have to do is just we change that map into tile
space obviously to the map into chunks face right into chunk space,
like, so.
And now we just need our
Batman Corner, get Max Corner, making it a high-frequency.
None of the to overloads could handle the argument types.
What did I forget?
Is it that the low comes first or something?
Yes, I suppose.
That is, and so in our math Library, we've got those rectangles.
We defined them.
We haven't really done much work to make this a nice sort of struct to
deal with, but I'm going to have a get min corner and a get Max Corner
that so that I can, you know, grab those out.
And again, the reason I'm doing that is just because I
- nicer in the code to be able to kind of say, what I want to get out
of them.
And so later, I'll probably, you know, we could also do something like
this, get center-right, these sorts of things.
So, when I have my rectangle in any of these cases, what I'm actually
doing here is just sort of returning out whatever the part is that the
person wanted its result equals recommend.
So there's that and there's that.
So I will quickly blast
Those in so and then this one will just be obviously the Min plus the
max divided by 2.
That's the right.
I mean the equation for the center of a rectangle is just halfway in
between one, the minimum corner, and the maximum corner at the center.
So if you want to get the center of rectangle, we could do it that way
and so on.
So that just gives us a little more flexibility there and then we're
good.
Now, what's important to remember is, we probably have a lot of
debugging to do now because we have, we wrote a ton of code yesterday
and today.
I mean not a ton of code, but you know,
Was only in part part of a small part of an hour, but we still did a
lot of typing.
We probably got some bugs in here.
So we probably have to step through and see what's going on.
Just to figure out all what's happening and to make sure that things
aren't going wrong.
All right.
So first things first, assertion checks, we're getting the assertion
here.
Someone is actually trying to make any high frequency who apparently
already is high frequency.
And so I'm just going to go ahead and try to find out why that is
happening.
Let's take a look.
At that, so okay, that was from a call for get high entity, who is
doing that this was doing that.
So this was calling get high entity, get high entity is actually
turning something into, was that the intention of this call.
I'm kind of interested in that.
That's, that's kind of that.
It's making something high frequency when when I don't know whether
that's really what we attended, but will, okay.
I won't think we'll think about that.
A little later.
Anyway, when we go to make that high high frequency, obviously this
this function should have checked against that.
Right this entity low high, into the index should have guarded against
it.
So I'm kind of confused as to why oh, it's easy.
Wow.
Took me a while.
I just assumed that there is a bug but there actually wasn't a bug.
It's just the assertion.
That's broken.
That's the bug.
So we're trying to assert that it is equal to 0.
Not that it's not.
We want to make sure that
That there isn't one yet because we're about to make one.
Duh.
All right, good work.
All right.
So now we're in a situation where we should be seeing entities because
they should be.
There should be some entities moving into the high space there but
were they obviously aren't and.
So what we need to do now is actually start going through our spatial
partition, debugging it, making sure that it's working properly and
making sure that our query for it.
There is also working properly.
Alright, so the first place to start is where we actually add things
in.
Which is here, let's see.
Where do we actually put up?
Well, again, maybe we still don't have any bugs.
We just haven't finished yet, because really, where is the actual?
No?
Okay.
Here it is.
I say we we actually do add something, right?
So we do an ad wall call.
And so, let's take a look at our ad wall call.
That's the first place.
We really use the spatial partition.
Right?
And so, let's go ahead and step in there.
And let's actually try to verify that.
Spatial partition is working the way we think it is and it's actually
adding this in the right place.
And because we've got a multiple sort of specific parties here.
For example, this chunk position from towel position is something that
we also recently, which could be totally wrong.
The entities could be adding just fine into our system but could be
being added in the wrong place for example, so there's a lot of stuff
like that, that we want to kind of figure out what's going on with.
And there's something else that I don't quite remember if we did yet
or not, which is when we actually do that, dif that subtraction.
I
I want to check this first before we start when we do that.
Subtraction.
How are we actually Computing?
Where things are.
I just wanted to kind of see how we were doing that in.
In the diff function, right?
There's that there's open subtract rather.
So the subtract function here and this chunk position from top
position.
Obviously kind of have to match up to some degree.
But anyway, I just want to take a look at that here.
So, when we do that, what we're doing is, we're multiplying, the chunk
side and M by the difference, which is that's correct.
That's what I would have ejected.
So that seems fine.
OK.
Alright, so that seems
Totally reasonable.
All right.
So let's go ahead and step in and let's take a look at at that
process, right?
Here we go.
I believe this is the first thing that gets added would be one of
these walls.
And so, the walls being added at the nice location of
00, that's pretty darn handy.
We couldn't ask for an easier position to follow through than that, I
suppose.
So, here we go.
We go ahead and get them into the low.
And we assume that that is working because we haven't actually changed
that code at all.
That was working already.
So we get an entity type of wall here where we haven't set its
position yet or its width or height or anything.
And so the next thing we're going to do is try to figure out where it
actually is in terms of chunks.
So we go in here and let's take a look at what that ends up.
Being.
Our results should be 0, 0 0, which it is our X and Y offsets are also
zero, which I'm not sure if that's a logical or not.
We think about that for a second.
So the ab style x- the tiles per chunk has world says, yeah, so I
think we may have a thing.
We may have a problem here where tiles are going to kind of be off
center from chunk boundary.
We we should think about this a little bit harder about how we want to
align.
Our tiles for now.
I'm going to go ahead and put it to do there actually before we go any
further because I want to make sure we have a sort of, a coherent
theory for how tiles line up a chunks.
And I don't think we quite have done that yet.
So let's go ahead and here and made parole dot CPP.
And in here.
Let's go to do decide on pile alignment in chunks, that won't affect
any of the code, but it will affect how are things are aligned on
chunks.
And that might be important later.
Alright, so we come in here.
We do this little bit.
And so we have computed our offset.
Our offset is straight zeros all the way through, right?
So the the entities position that entity low should just be zero zeros
everywhere and it is that all looks good.
We set the width and height and we're done.
Okay, you know what?
I just realized, though.
Do we ever bother to insert it into the special partition into the
actual spatial partition?
I don't think we do.
I don't think we did that at all.
In fact, we did not right.
Yeah, so that's all.
So that's our problem.
Or at least one of our problems in order to use the spatial partition.
We're going to actually have to call it at some point.
It can't magically know.
So change entity location is going to have to be called at some point
here.
Right?
This is the problem with doing stuff days separated.
You don't remember that.
You actually have to go actually use the code that you wrote.
So that's fine.
That's easy.
Easy enough.
So what I'd like to do here is go.
Okay.
We've got these things there.
We're adding in the spatial partition since all entities have to be in
the spatial partition.
What I might do is say that that's just part of this from now on.
So basically, you know,
whenever you add an entity, you have to give it a PE, you have to give
it that that chunk position where you want it to actually start.
That may just be a requirement.
So I'll, you know, I'll do that here and teepee.
Tea or actually, that's right.
That's World position.
So and so that'll go ahead and get that for us.
And then we'll just pass that in and then you don't initialize that
yourself.
So when you add a little entity that will actually add that in here
like that and World position P will be there.
All right, so we've got that all set up.
That seems reasonable.
And trying to think about exactly what else I want to do here.
So when we do that, we'll have to do that for players as well.
That seems pretty easy because right now we're just doing this, right?
So our world position for them is that, so we'll just pass that as
well.
That seems totally fine.
And so, now after we've done that, inside the low entity, we know that
we can always, we can always actually update the entity properly here
by doing this.
So we've got our game State.
I don't remember exactly what
Irene has called in the game, State their World Arena.
That's what it was.
So we've got our World Arena.
So we pass the World Arena down so that it can allocate more space for
needs to, we pass the world down, which obviously, we will need.
We passed that low entity index, which at this point oats.
This is in the wrong place.
I went wanted to in here.
Sorry my bad.
We passed that low into the index, which is where what which guy, this
I actually is, he does not have an old position because he is
brand-new.
So we
Pass 0 there and then we hate does have a new position which is that?
That P location.
So that adds him to the spatial partition.
Of course, now, we need a way to actually update that where he is when
things move.
And right now, the only thing that can move is our move player call,
right?
I believe that's the only thing.
So when we do the update to move it which I which is right here.
I guess what we'll do at that stage right there is when we do that we
will also update the enemy's location to its new location.
So basically, the entities new position is now this, right?
And it's an old position.
We will remember.
I believe we already did that by doing old player Pi.
Don't know if we persist.
Oh, no, we don't actually we never save the actual old world position.
So let's take a look at
Player, I guess we would do that actually right here.
So what we would do is say World position.
New key equals map into chunks base.
There we go.
Then we would do change entity location and that change into location.
Call would take the old p and the new key.
So there we go that and then we still need to actually assign it.
I don't know if it'd be better to actually have change, empty
location.
Be the thing that does the assignment that does seem like something
that maybe would be smart.
But at the same time, I wonder if maybe these should
To be bundled together as the call that changes.
So, I think maybe this will be something like to do Casey bundle these
together as the position update.
That.
So, let's take a look here.
What is the problem?
Cannot convert.
Our went five provision star.
So this takes a pointer.
That's true.
Entity index here.
Do we know which entity index?
We're talking about.
We probably do because I suspect it is in this entity structure if it
isn't, it should be.
And so that's something to take a look at their it is the low index is
right there.
So that's good.
So all we need to do is pass its low index.
Like so and let's see.
We also have to pass these as pointers.
There we go.
Add low entity function is not take two arguments.
That is correct.
It does not.
And so we need to pass a world position here.
And so I guess we will just pass that as develop position and we'll
pass that in now.
It would be nice if this was not in the spatial partition, so I wonder
if there should be a way for us to avoid adding someone just for that
one.
No entity.
And I know, I don't know how I feel about that one way or the other.
Do we want them in the state?
We want them, or don't we?
Do we want more?
Don't we?
I don't think we do.
So when we do add low entity, I wonder if maybe we don't actually want
to do that.
What we could do is something like this, right?
And we could do something where we say like that, right?
Where, you know, you it's optional, if you pass that position in, I
don't know if I love that.
It's just something that we could think about doing so that way you
can look but it's only for that one guy and seems kind of janky, so,
maybe what we should do is just leave space for the low entity in a
different way that doesn't involve us doing that.
All right.
So that's about it.
Again.
We haven't actually gone through into bugged our spatial partition
yet.
So we're just kind of seeing what's going on that doesn't look right
at all.
So I think we still got bugs.
But at least we kind of know.
We're guess we're getting a little bit better.
So that's a good sign I suppose.
All right.
So let's continue on here.
Trying to figure out if everything's working properly, which obviously
doesn't I guess actually because that should look, you know, why
aren't those tiles there?
And they're, there should have been tiles there in there.
So we're already there's obviously some kind of bug going on here.
And also, if I hit the and that's, it looks like it's the wrong place
to.
So this look there's just looks like, it's janky but they're showing
up now, which is actually a plus, so that's kind of good.
So if I hit the spacebar, I don't see my guy either.
So that suggests that, that is broken as well.
Let's take a look at why that's broken.
First.
Because that's also something that that should be addressed.
Okay, so we're getting there and we just have a few more things to
iron out, but we're getting there.
So let's go ahead.
Run this and then I'm going to try and add a player.
And so the world position is wherever the camera was.
And so let's take a look at what that is.
I assume that's just basically centered at the origin and well, no,
it's a little bit off from the origin.
So that's fine.
So the player is going to be at that location.
So let's go ahead and add him in.
We go ahead and do that.
Get our entity index, which is actually extremely high now because
there's so many walls and stuff because since we created a lot,
but I think I'm still having it create a huge number of rooms.
Which is fine.
So I go ahead and do this.
It's going to be a player.
It's going to be a hero.
So we're going to assign to that entity low State indexing.
Know what?
I should probably before we start tugging this as well.
I kind of also want to go ahead and take the time now to do this,
right?
I'd like to go ahead and access that low entity by entity low, so I
don't have to keep grabbing it out of the array there, that doesn't
seem good at all.
So we'll do that and then we'll do entity, load type equals type.
And entity low P equals star p, and that looks a little bit nicer.
All right.
So let's try that one more time.
Oops.
What did I do?
Just get low entity.
Why did get money not work there?
Get them entity index.
Gives it less than learning to count.
That should have worked, right?
Because loaded account has been Advanced Beyond it.
And so,
I should be able to do that.
Shouldn't I?
What did I do?
I must have just done something particularly stupid.
So it's the, it's the zero entity.
That won't work there.
All right.
Well, that's fine.
What do it that way then?
All right, so entity index.
And now we are adding that guy in.
And so let's take a look at what happens.
So we go ahead and we add that low entity.
Oh, ah,
That's not supposed to happen.
Once you pass that P in, you're not supposed to touch it, bad, bad,
bad, bad.
That's no good.
No good at all.
So, we got to get rid of those.
Okay, there we go.
And now we'll see if we get anywhere further.
What happened there?
Block O, our block is no.
Oh snap.
If we need a better way to break out of this function.
Because right, this iterator here as iterates over when we find it.
That was dumb.
I don't even know why I try to do that.
That was stupid.
Trying to be clever.
You saw what happened there, right?
I wanted to break out of those.
So I'm like, oh,
You said it because the condition is blocked, but this, when it gets
to the end of the loop, it's going to do this, right?
So that's not going to work.
So we're just going to have to set.
Something, which is basically, you know, while we haven't found it.
So, so not found is true.
And so we just do not found block and not found and then we've got
this and not found and then, you know, not found equals false.
Not the not the prettiest thing in the world.
I admit that.
But at least that's, you know,
Least that's going to work in theory.
All right, so there is my dude.
He's there.
We're definitely in some Dire Straits, their looks or still got plenty
of debugging to do.
Let's take a look at where that that broke off offset and check
frequency by area.
How many high frequency entities?
Do we have?
What are we in now?
This one, let's go ahead and step through that.
I just want to see it.
Look like it stalled there and I wanted to break in and see what was
taking the time.
So, all right, so it finishes this Loop presumably.
I know it doesn't finish this Loop.
Interesting.
Because it's making it entity.
Oh, did we not think this through properly?
I guess I must have not thought this through.
Quite right.
When it's actually removing something from the high entity State.
We've got, we've got a little bit of a bug here.
So when it makes the entity low frequency, this is supposed to reduce
the count, right?
So go through here.
Any load grabs it, high index 0 but it doesn't have a high.
How is that possible?
Yeah, so we've got some, we've got some weirdness going on here.
Right?
Because when we all set Guys, these should always these are always
supposed to be people who are in the high range.
So when it goes ahead and let's let's take a look at that case.
I want to take a look at that case now since it's suspicious.
All right, so let's go ahead and see what happens there.
There we go.
So, We're looping over our entities and we're trying to offset them
and check to see whether they'd still be in the bounce.
We have found somebody who isn't supposed to be there.
Right?
So we go ahead and and in fact, I guess what I could do to, you know,
what?
Let me do this beforehand.
Just so we know.
One thing I like to do sometimes is, if I have a bug somewhere, put in
assertion, that would have would caught it just to sort of, make sure
that you don't have it happen again, right?
So, I want to assert that the the
The high entity.
Well, I guess, like, when I do make any low frequency, I guess I'd
have to actually grab its pointer here to actually do that sir, but I
could do that, right?
I could totally do that.
So what I want to do.
Basically this I want to do an assert.
I want to assert that the the low entity for this guy.
I want to assert that his high Index, right?
His is high into the index.
I want to make sure that that points back to this, this Index, right
like so, and it would be nice.
I suppose if this was called high into the index just to be clear
which because we've got two different ones here.
I think it's probably good to differentiate between those two so like
so.
All right, so I just wanted to do that just to make sure and let's
take a look.
All right.
So we're going through, we get someone who moves out and we find all
of a sudden that we've got somebody who's still in the high frequency
array.
And who doesn't have this as the high high entity index.
He's pointed wrong, right?
So that's just we already have a bug here and we should take a look at
that.
And again, this is relatively tricky code, right?
Having these two sort of entity States and stuff does does complicate
things certainly right?
And like I said, one of
Big reasons for doing that is just to show how to work through things
like this and to show how to structure things that are relatively
complicated.
I didn't want to make something that was going to super simple, but
you pay a price for doing some things that are more complicated.
Which is that you have to think them through a little more and you
have to spend more time to Buggy.
So there's always a price, anytime you want to sort of upgrade
something to be a little fancier.
You always got to pay for it.
It's no no free lunch, right?
All right.
So let's go ahead and and and think this through, how could we check
more easily?
What I would like to do is I think maybe do some kind of a have some
kind of a correspondence.
Check.
For example, what I could do is make something here, which is just
like, validate entity pairs or something like that.
And, you know, basically just say, okay, let's have a function, which
all the function does is cycle through all of the high entities,
right?
And I don't know.
Why do we have?
Why are we having hiding next year?
I guess because loading this point back to them.
So that makes sense.
So will cycle through all the high entities and for every High entity.
We should go ahead and assert that.
If we were to grab the low entity for that high of D that it points
back to it, right?
That's all it does.
Right?
So, you know, we could we could even make this a function that you
could call to validate and then you assert the validation.
So let's do it this way, I guess.
So we'll do valid will soon valid I guess the start and then it will
say valid equals valid and that this thing is
True.
Right?
Then we'll return valid and that way we can do this validate entity
pairs, really any time that we want to.
So we've kind of got a number of things that we could do, but
basically set camera, right?
We could, if we want to do a bunch of validation here.
We can validate it here.
So when we first come in, we can validate it.
So we'll do assert valid identity Pairs and then they'll just compiled
out in debug mode.
So it's not, I mean, release mode.
So that'll be fine.
We can do it after we do the offset and check frequency by area, and
then we can do it again after we do our high frequency, move like
that.
So just just some validation just to make sure that we catch a
As in as easy, a fashion as possible, and don't make things harder on
ourselves than they have to be.
So, there we go.
So, let's see what happens when we run this now.
Oops.
Forgot.
One more thing got to actually do the increment.
We weren't doing the increment here because we do the increment or we,
or we remove the item.
So, we had kind of a special Loop there, but there we go.
All right.
So what we've learned from this already?
Is that this routine is causing a problem where the high into the
index is, are getting the highest fee Loan Today, low entity.
Correspondence.
Is actually getting ruined right here because our validation routine
has failed, right?
So, we now know, we basically that told us exactly what we wanted
this, it fingered this code as the culprit, right?
So let's go take a look.
There's a couple other things we can do to make the code, less likely
to have these problems to which we may start doing.
Like I said, I don't I typically don't spend time on doing code that's
designed for defensive programming.
Until I actually have some bugs in something or I'm doing the actual
final version of stuff just to make sure that you don't spend a lot of
time doing unnecessary work.
But once you have a bug, you can usually trade some of that debugging
time for putting in more defensive code and that's usually a win,
right?
It's kind of like lazy evaluation, you want to sort of manage it so
that you're not doing a ton of work trying to catch bugs that never
going to happen, right?
So, all right, we're in here and we are looping through, we've got our
low entities and for each low entity.
We take a look at whether the high-end X was equal to 0.
If the high-end X is equal to 0, then we're going to consider it.
We consider it here.
We check to see whether
It is in the rectangular or not.
And then we make a high-frequency entity out of it.
If it was right.
And we're passing the Fantastic.
We're passing the wrong one, right?
So this is actually again, too many indices, right?
So really, what we want to do here is differentiate between Embassy in
the end entity indices and the indices in the block, right?
So if we do that, then we will
I'll actually have Arlo entity index here which we can grab out like
so low, entity index, like so, so there we go, done.
And that will hopefully fix that problem, right?
What you did and that looks like the only problem we had in terms of
stuff that was obvious like that.
You could see that was totally wrong, right?
So that's good.
So that means our spatial partition is at least nominally working now,
although again, we haven't really done anything to verify that it's
actually working.
We just know that it's not getting in our way anymore.
But like I said, that's good enough for now because all we really care
about is that it's set up properly.
So we know that it's all
all the code is Plumbing properly if you will.
So, one of the things that we probably want to do too is sort entity
soon as well.
So we don't keep having this like going behind this problem, but for
the, for the immediate moment, let's go ahead and take.
I think we've got a little bit of time left the stream just a little
bit.
Looks like we've got about 10 minutes.
Let's go ahead and test to see that those new assets work as well.
So I'm going to go ahead and say, let's replace those green things
with those yellow things with trees.
I don't know if I made the entities, the right size.
Like the hero still very large.
So I've got to do a bunch of work on that when we actually want to
start doing real work with entities.
But for now we'll go ahead and just do it this way.
So let's load in just a tree here, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and say tree and that's going to be test in
the test to directory.
I think I just called them 300, or something like that.
And then what I'm going to do is when we're drawing that rectangle,
we're doing an end of the sort of entity test here.
Or if it's type hero, right?
And otherwise, we're going to draw something else.
So in here, I'll just I'll go ahead and draw a bitmap instead, right?
So to draw the bitmap instead, what we don't have right now.
Unfortunately, as we don't actually know the offset of that guy, so
I'll draw it at the wrong place.
Just to start with and then we'll go actually see what?
It's hot spot, should be.
And then it'll draw at the right place as well.
All right.
So let's take a look here.
What we have to do is say will
Those ground points that I think that actually is what we want is we
want the ground points and the Z is yes, so I think that's all
actually the same stuff we want.
It's just the Align right?
We don't actually know what.
Oh, well loaded bitmap just loaded bitmap actually have that in there.
It doesn't have the alliance only to hear a bit Maps.
Do.
So.
We should probably push the alignment into the loaded bitmap at some
point.
Maybe that point might be now, but we'll zero those app for now.
And we'll go ahead and draw the game state tree, right?
And, and that'll, and that'll go ahead and do that.
And we're going to have to start making that code a little bit cleaner
now.
Alright, so we have some trees, and that's fine.
Of course.
Now, it's pretty hard to tell where stuff is because the trees are
drawn at the wrong locations.
So we probably should go ahead and draw the trees at the right
locations and maybe get rid of those trees in the background as well.
That seems like a probably a pretty good thing to
to do.
Say the least.
So, yeah.
Alright, let's go ahead and take a look at draw rectangle there.
Let's go ahead and go back to a clearing process here for now.
So I'm going to go ahead and do an if one around this guy not going
to, We're Not Gonna draw that that background anymore.
We'll pass that buffer.
Like so and we've got the the Min and the max I guess.
I don't really know what those are.
These are in.
I don't even remember.
It's been so long since we worked on the renderer.
I don't even know what they were.
So we've got we've basically got two things.
We've got, I guess this is how we were doing those.
I don't love this.
By the way.
I'm thinking of going back to the way that I was doing them before
where instead of doing that weird syntax that doesn't work, on a lot
of compilers or rather on older msv seasons.
A lot of compilers.
Sometimes it's just nice to do it this way.
All right.
So I think is this just the case that all we have to really do is just
this.
I don't know.
Let's find out, I guess, right?
And like I said, I would like to make it and I guess, what should we
do?
Let's do is do a gray that what I'm saying here is, I'd rather have
the ability to do V 2.
This is the way I write it in my own code, this stuff.
So I think I'm going to just stick with doing it that way, instead of
the other weird that old weird syntax.
I didn't know.
I don't love that syntax.
It didn't it.
Didn't thrill me?
All right.
So yes.
Gotta go ahead and treat these as floats obviously, but that's about
it.
And then in theory that should give us a gray background.
Well, alright.
So now we have to do is draw the trees at the right place.
So we want to do is we want to define the trees in some sort of scene
fashion where their width in their height, and the center point of the
tree.
I guess we want to
The tree at that center point, so let's think about this for a second.
If I go ahead and I open up the art Assets in see here in
Gimp, which I think I can do, right?
Come on gimp.
Gibbs Gibbs, give it a go.
It can do it.
It thinks it can do it.
Maybe it can, maybe it can't.
So I really just want to know essentially like what's this point right
here?
Like that's like sort of the center point of the tree, right?
Where its base would be and it's 40.5 79.5.
So we'll call that will say 4080.
Nice, easy to remember 4080 is the alignment.
On our tree, right?
So we basically just got 40.
80 is the alignment on our tree and now we have our tree, it might be
nice to draw the rectangle as well.
Just so we could sort of see where it was.
So I don't know.
Like maybe we should do that in addition.
Let's let's do that.
In addition, underneath it.
Let's go ahead and draw that rectangle just so we can kind of see
where it's actually
So, we'll do player left top and player left top plus, entity width
height.
I think.
That's right, and then we'll still draw that just on there.
So we can kind of see.
And and what I might do to is I might just make it a little smaller
like I did before so we can kind of see roughly where each individual
wall segment.
Actually was, oops.
That's not right.
That's the the m 2 pixels problem, isn't it?
So, I've got a multiply it by m, 2 pixels as well.
All right, down.
So that looks a little better and now you can kind of go through the
world a little more reasonably and there are the trees.
We kind of look a lot.
Like a regular Tom app game.
Now because we're not really doing anything to scatter our trees
properly.
So we look kind of like a snez game which is fine.
I like snacks games, but we would like to take care of that sometime
in the future as well.
But there we go.
So now our trees are there so we can probably vaporize the rectangle
call.
We don't really need that at the moment.
So, we'll get rid of that.
And there we go.
So now we're getting back to something that's sort of a little more
usable and now is probably the time to start thinking about I guess.
Like I said, I we've got the spatial partition in there.
It's may or may not be working correctly, but we don't care literally
at all.
We just want it to be structured properly.
So that when we go to write, the the full versions of everything,
it'll be correct.
We can clearly play the game.
Way, we don't have any problems and are smooth scrolling is working.
So that means our screen-based thrilling would also be working.
Presumably, I guess I could test that really quickly if I was to go in
here and, and flip which one we were doing.
I don't know if we actually ever updated this.
So maybe we need to update this one.
Okay, so we would need to update that as well.
So that's something to think about doing for tomorrow.
It's just to do our screen-based growing, but we're kind of at the
point where it does seem like we could now start to,
Pull that entity stuff out.
Make it really coherent exactly how all the stages of our entity
pipeline work and then put in some space for doing stuff like having a
monster in there and having him fight the monster and that sort of
stuff which is which is what I'd like to get to in terms of testing
out how the entity system works and how the scaling works.
And then we can also do some stuff where we, yeah, where we take a
look at that.
Sort of the scaling behavior and what happens with low entities and
that sort of stuff.
So that looks good.
One thing that, that might be nice here is like I would like to have a
way to zoom out, right.
And since we're only drawing the enemies of the hiset that does make
it a little bit harder for us to do stuff, like zooming out.
So, at some point we're gonna have to figure out a way to really be
able to draw like a nice debug view which something that's just like a
little pixel map.
That just shows how big everything is.
Where all
Entities are and what they're doing because otherwise it's going to be
kind of hard for us to debug what's happening in other spots of the
world, right?
But for right now one thing that I can do, obviously also is is in
move player.
Let's go ahead and go over here and move player.
One thing I could do is have a pool 32, which is Collide, right?
And what I could do is say that, you know, if you're not going to do
Collide, maybe there's just something that just straight up moves.
You write that, you know, just you can just walk straight through
things.
You don't have to worry about going through anything so that I can
zoom around the world really quickly.
Yeah, you know what?
I don't need to do that.
Now, there's no point.
Let's just leave it like this.
Let's just go to the Q&A.
Let's say it's, you know,
Let's say it's time for Q&A and we'll save the rest of the stuff for
tomorrow because because we can.
So, yeah, so maybe tomorrow we'll start by doing some sorting and then
will, you know, so that all of our Sprites will sort properly and then
we'll start thinking things through a little more.
We could also change which tree we're drawing so that there's maybe
more than one tree being drawn would also be nice, but there we go.
Alright, so we're in good shape.
Please prefix your questions with Q: if you could so I can
See them and please keep them to stuff.
We did on today's stream or on a previous stream.
If you want to ask off-topic questions, come before the stream starts.
I'm usually here about 15 minutes.
I was a little late today.
I was only 10 minutes early, but please come about 15 minutes early
and we can do off-topic questions then so yeah.
So, let's see if I can.
Am I white listed can I do it?
Can I do it?
I don't know if I can do it or not.
But yeah.
For zooming out.
Could you somehow modify m, 2 pixels to make things smaller as you
zoom?
So zooming out would not be a huge problem in terms of drawing.
Once we have a red door that can do scaling, but we don't have a
render, the caduceus going right now.
So that.
So, the Sprites wouldn't get any smaller.
They just get closer together if we did that, but that's not really
the real problem.
The real problem is right now, we only draw High entities.
So we
Loop that draws all of our entities even ones that are nowhere near
the camera.
So we need to go make a render Loop that Loops over the low entities
and then that would allow us to see some because otherwise, we'd only
see what was right around the apron, anyway, because we only draw,
what's in the hiset, which is good for the normal gameplay.
It's just not good for debugging.
What is in-line V2 in line.
V2 is just a thing that constructs a vector to, right.
So basically it's just a thing that allows you to make a V2 by just
typing in.
Oh, you know V 253 and then it makes a V2 with the with x 5 + Y3,
that's all it is.
It's just a little notation.
And so I decided I considered this and I don't like it.
So, that's not going to happen.
So basically, this is not going to happen.
You're done.
You're out of my code base.
Goodbye.
No, no, no, no, no to you, sir.
I just I don't it doesn't do it for me.
I thought about it and I don't like it.
So it's gone.
It's just it's just ugly.
I don't know.
It's weird.
It just it doesn't look right and it doesn't it doesn't work on older
versions of the compiler.
It's just, it's just annoying.
So there we go.
All right.
Goodbye to you, sir.
And we're still working.
I forgot how high you can jump.
He's a real jumper this guy.
Y.
Uz, Max versus visual Studios IDE.
Well, there's two reasons really.
One is just because I am more familiar with emacs and I like to be
able to use the same editor on many platforms.
So I program on lots of platforms.
I don't only program on Windows, so Emax works on all of them.
So that's really handy.
Like when I'm program.
The next, I don't have to like, learn a new editor.
I just use emacs everywhere.
So that's a big one.
But the other one too, is that editing inside Visual Studio is kind of
a pain because you, you have to do all these gyrations to get its
rebuild to work properly with the dynamic code reloading stuff that we
do.
It's like, they had conceived of that in their head or something
because I don't know why probably because all their code takes three
years to compile and they like being able to go to the break room for
popcorn or something.
I have no idea but you have to do all this stuff with custom build
steps and you have to build the game twice to get it like
People were trying to work it out on the forums and it took him a
while to even get it into rough position.
Whereas with e Max, it's just it's totally fine because I can just
tell it exactly what I want to have happen.
And I don't have to worry about visual Studios.
Weird ideas about what is and is not a time when you can build, right?
So that's also part of it.
I just don't like that hassle of having to deal with their build
stuff.
You see Max better than V I am.
Or is it just preference?
It's not even preference for me.
It's just what I know.
Like I learned emacs.
I didn't have VI M at the time.
When I first started using emacs on Doss actually I only had emacs I
didn't even know what v.
I VI M was or just Vi at that point.
I don't even know if I would have had access to V.
I am, I don't know what V.
I am happened.
VI.
But either it regardless not important, point being.
So I learned emacs and I'm pretty fast with it now, so it's not like I
was equally fast in VI and like decided that VI was not as good and
emacs is better.
It's like I just don't know VI.
And so the time it would take me, I don't want to spend the time.
Now to go learn how to be as fast as I am in emacs in VI, even if
maybe it's a better editor and I would be slightly faster or
something.
So that's mostly it.
So
So, I don't really have an opinion about one versus the other.
It's more.
Just what I learned.
Do you think that how fast code runs is the best metric for good code?
Or do you value Simplicity or extensibility as well?
So I would say that, I don't think that how fast code runs is a
metric.
It's a requirement in my mind.
So I would think I would say value, I would say the values listed
second, Simplicity and extensibility.
I would say that Simplicity and extensibility are things that you
should value once, you can guarantee that the code does.
Run fast.
If you cannot guarantee that the code does run fast.
Then Simplicity sensibility are interesting to me because I don't care
if code is simple extensible.
If it's not fast enough to be good, right?
And nowadays.
I feel like a lot of code people.
Sort of will say things like that.
Like, they'll be like, well, you know, I'd rather save myself time or
I'd rather, you know, this be easier to develop on then have it be?
You know, higher speed, that would be fine.
If all the software I riff.
All the software that I used was somehow really fast these days, but
my computer is slower now than it's ever been the software that I use,
as its lower now than it's ever been.
And so I feel like, nowadays, programmers are making very bad
decisions about what is the minimum performance requirements further
code?
And so I think at this point, normally I would not have said this in
the old days.
Maybe I wouldn't have said this, but nowadays, I would say, I don't
think you can think about speed too often nowadays because the
pendulum so far in the other direction that people just apparently.
Don't think about it at all.
And so once we get back to a culture of performance,
If we ever do, which I don't know if we ever will, but if we got back
to a culture of performance where people in general were writing
highly performant code.
That was very well optimized then it might be a good time to say.
Okay.
Are we doing too much of that?
Are we sacrificing too much of that?
But right now in today's landscape, oh my god, like people need to be
thinking about performance 10, 20 30 times more often than they are.
So we're nowhere near the point where people are
Eating too much on optimization.
Why are using visual studio here, if you use emacs.
So visual studio, I use Visual Studio as the debugger.
So, basically, I just treat this as my debugger.
I don't edit any code in it.
I just use it for debugging and then I so I alt tab back and forth
between Emax where I edit the code and visual studio, where I run it
and step through it.
I would use emacs to step through it.
If you Max has had a better integrated debugger, but it doesn't, so I
don't do that.
Did you ever figure out a fix for emacs whenever you try to create a
new file and the patch changes?
I'm sorry.
Could you be more specific?
Swag, Kitty.
69?
Could you be more strict about that?
I'm not sure what you're referring to.
I assume you're referring to swing on a previous dream that I was
mentioning was broken or something, but I'm not sure which what it is,
elaborate a little more.
What's guiding you to make steps towards completing the game, a list
of requirements for the game.
So basically right now I know that I want a game like I'm not really
thinking too much about this, all of the design things that I have for
the game right.
Now.
What I mostly think about is just showing how to structure a
reasonable 2D engine that I know will have the ability to do all the
things I want to do in the game.
And so I basically just have an opinion of all the things that engine
should be able to.
To and I'm sort of going through them one by one.
So for example, the thing that we just did where we put entities in a
spatial partition and we have a high and a low frequency update for
entities.
That is because I want to show how to make sure that your engine
scales to very high numbers of entities, right?
And so I want to be able to put something in where we can guarantee
performance leveling so that we know that even if we have five million
entities or however many entities you want we can
Ways guarantee reasonable performance, right?
And we'll just sacrifice simulation accuracy for it.
So that's like what we were doing it.
So, I'm going through those sorts of things that I know that we need
to show how to do getting those set up.
Right?
So that we basically have a working prototype engine and then we can
go through and write final versions for each part of the engine, as we
decide that it's locked, right?
And then at the end of that, we'll have everything that we need.
Now, we won't do it like the whole engine in the whole game will do.
Some parts of the engine that we know are separable like the render
and stuff.
And then some parts will leave fluid as we make the game.
So we'll cuz we'll kind of see as we're making the game.
What we want in those parts.
Do you ever get annoyed with reading a high depth of nested for Loops
sometimes?
Yeah.
But, you know, usually it's not that bad.
The problem that I have on the stream is people can't read the text.
If I make it the size that I normally have it.
Normally, I have a monitor that's running at higher than 1920 by 1080.
So normally a vermonter that's running it, like, 2,500 by 1625,
Whatever by 1600, right?
And I have the text significantly smaller.
So normally that number of for Loops would not even be a big deal.
But on unfortunately, when I have to make things really big so they
can show up on Twitch and YouTube.
It's harder to read it also makes it harder for me to work on the code
because I can't see as big of a window into my code as I would like.
But you know, that's just that's just the concession.
You have to make in order to broadcast it properly and the whole point
of this project is to show people how to do it.
So I just, you know, it's just something I deal with it as best I can.
What's working was watching some ROM hacking earlier and watching the
registers and memory update in real-time was really cool.
Do you think it bugger 4C could work as well as that?
Do you mean?
Oh well.
Yeah, I mean, I guess it depends exactly what you're talking about.
But yeah, I mean C++ the virus could be way more awesome than they
are.
Now mean they could show you all kinds of things that you should be
seeing in aren't seeing, right.
So, I mean, yeah, I don't know if they can be as awesome as an
emulator because one of the things about emulators often emulating,
some things that are very simple and so there's less to display, but,
but still even so
How much time do you spend outside the stream and thinking about the
code and game design?
If you coded 8 hours a day, would you be able to code consistently
with the same Pace as during your stream?
Actually, I code much faster than I code on the stream normally.
So the stream is much slower than I would normally code.
I would say I'm probably about four times slower on the stream at
least, probably more because I have to explain things and I have to
talk at the same time, which makes it much more difficult for me.
And like I said, I don't
Have I can't see as much code because the monitor because of the way,
the fonts are set up and so on.
So, yeah, so I would say the pace that codon stream is very slow.
It is not a pace that I would consider a good pace for programming.
If I was not explaining things.
Can you please put in a proper prng before you write, worlds, and
algorithms?
Yes, we will be putting in a random number generator.
I don't actually remember what we put in there.
What did we put in currently?
Oh, we were just using a random number table.
So that's pretty good.
Actually.
Those are very high quality.
Random numbers.
Probably higher quality than what we'll do.
But yes, we will put in a proper random number generator.
When we actually try to
Wait, what?
How is it possible that our random number indicates after this many
screens?
How is it possible that our random number index doesn't get higher
than the random number tables size.
Is it really that we do?
We actually copy in more than 2,000 of them.
Is that how many do we actually do?
I don't remember, maybe we did.
I guess there are quite a few there.
That's kind of funny.
I would have expected that assert to hit eventually.
Yeah, well.
Do you ever feel the need to use recursive functions?
I do when I'm just hacking stuff out.
A lot of times recursive functions.
I get nervous about the stack and stuff and recursive functions have
some issues, but they're nice to use quickly because you can lean on
the fact that the stack does the memory management for you.
And so, that's kind of nice.
It just, yeah, it can be handy.
It can be handy.
Do you build with build .exe in command prompt or batch file?
So there is no buildup EXE the way that we have, it set up.
You can go take a look, actually, if you want to go.
Onto onto probably the best place would be using forums.
Actually.
You've got a handmade hero dot org, you click on this news and forums
link.
If you go there on the episode guide, I cover all this stuff in.
If you just take a look at this, right.
So setting up the windows builds, shows you kind of how that was done.
And then later on, I talked about how to do the live coding stuff,
which is this week 5, you can watch these.
And I cover all how that stuff works, how the build works, and how you
can do the live.
Editing and stuff.
When you say renderer, what exactly does that mean?
If the drawing you have now isn't rendering?
Then at what point do we go from drawing to rendering?
So I mean anything is a renderer at some level.
So it's not fair to say that what we're doing isn't rendering or
something because that's kind of just being arbitrary.
I would say.
So drawbitmap is a renderer in some sense.
I mean, it does put pixels on the screen, but basically what I what I
would consider a renderer is something that satisfies a few more of
the criteria that we
Have would want for a game.
So some of them are much faster than it is.
Now.
I mean, it could be several times faster on this machine 10, 20 times
faster on a lot faster than it is now so much much faster than it is
now.
More operations, so the ability to change.
The colors of things would be an example, right?
We only have the ability to change the alpha right now.
The ability to rotate and scale things which we don't currently have
like, we can only just all we could do right now is just copy a
rectangle to a rectangle.
So rotation and scaling and then the other thing would be.
Maybe some intelligence about what gets filled and what doesn't?
So, for example, if there's a guy, if there's a Sprite on the screen
and there's something behind it.
Maybe we don't actually composite the stuff that's behind.
And it so Summit, maybe some calling and some occlusion.
Those are the kinds of things that I would want in a renderer in a
good renderer.
And so when I say, we're going to write the render, what I mean, we're
going to write a system that does all of that stuff, not just
something that copies a bitmap from one place to the other, which is
all we have right now, which I wouldn't really call a renderer, even
though technically you could call it a render if you wanted to.
It's just a really bad renderer.
Have any of your friends voice disagreement with design decisions
you've made in this engine.
I don't think so.
But to be fair, I haven't made a lot of design decisions in this
engine yet because we haven't really like finished with it.
And said, here's, you know, everything.
It's going to work or anything, right?
But yeah.
How do you distinguish between what a lot of people might call
premature optimization versus ensuring a good design that allows for
high performance, the difference there seems really subtle.
I feel that designing for high performance is simply organizing the
code and writing in such a way that does not unnecessarily slow down
the code to prevent future optimizations while.
Premature optimization is simply optimizing something, because you
think something will be slow without evidence.
So, that's an excellent question.
First of all.
And I think you're sort of answer that you put in there is also good.
What I would say is that premature optimization is spending time on is
spending time on something before, you know that you need to do it,
right?
And so, I would say that.
For example, let's say that what we were going to do.
Next is is the spatial partition, right?
So I made the spatial partition here, right?
And so this spatial partition.
An example of premature optimization would be, let's go figure out the
most efficient spatial partition to keep our low entities in here,
right?
So let's let's like go make this really fast so that we know the
insertion and removal is really really fast like time it for insertion
or removal will time iteration and the moving things from high to low
like that would be premature optimization because we don't even know
if this is the code that we're going to you.
We don't even know.
This is the structure going to use in the end.
However,
Hang it in my opinion, making a spatial partition.
Just a basic one.
That works.
Well enough is not premature optimization in my opinion because I know
I need a spatial partition.
Because with the number of entity queries we're going to do is going
to be very large.
I know I need something to handle that.
And so what I'm trying to do at this stage of the code is actually
figure out what I need to make sure my engine looks like in order to
ensure that a spatial partition can slot into it.
And so I think you need to go as
As far down that road as is necessary, to make sure that you
understand the consequences of sliding a component in, but you don't
have to go any further.
Like, right now, we don't have to do any more work to figure out
whether this is good or not.
As far as I'm concerned.
It has all of the aspects that we probably will have with a good
spatial partition.
It has the concert that you have to look up pieces.
Inside those pieces.
It has some notion of chunked lists of stuff, right?
You insert.
And remove things from it in a defined way and it's indirect
referencing.
So anything that we might have in a spatial partition is here, and I'm
pretty confident that in the future.
If we need to change the space of partition, we would not have to
re-architect the whole engine to do so, right.
And that's all you really need.
And so that's the key part.
When you're working on the structure things is put in.
Just enough to know that the devil in the details has been exposed.
But do not try to actually fight the devil.
Let the devil stay there.
Right?
So, you want to get the devil in the details, but you don't want to
Vanquish him later on.
You Vanquish them is what I would say.
4096 random numbers so we can draw a lot of screens.
We can draw 4,000 screens.
Will we have position-less?
Entities with something?
Like the current price of almond milk, Futures be an entity.
So maybe we now support position-less entities, but I don't know if we
will have them in the future or not.
It's a good question.
We'll have to see.
We've been making a level tile map editor for this game for easier.
Level creation know this game is procedurally generated.
So there are no prefab levels.
Everything's going to be different every time you play it.
What is your algorithm for a collision with three and more entities?
Don't follow you there.
So just to be clear, you don't have to there is, okay.
So I think I know where that question.
Coming from.
Let me try to be a little clearer on how this works.
Just so people aren't confused.
So we're talking about here.
So, I assume you're talking about this and why there's only four
iterations.
So, what you have to remember is we are talking right now about 1/30
of a second, right?
So basically the amount of time 1/30 of a second, right?
So the amount of time that were updating and every frame is this,
which is basically which is 33 milliseconds, right?
So, if you imagine how far the guy moves on the screen, right?
If this were the whole screen right now, right?
He moves, you know, that far or something, the 30th of a second maybe
less, you know, we may be moves like that far, right?
So you're talking about moving that far, there should be no way that
you can ever run in 24 different monsters moving that far.
And if for some reason you did it's okay that we only process the
first for you.
Right, so it's not a restriction on the number of monsters.
He's fighting he can fight a thousand monsters.
No problem.
The only thing is that when he's moving he cannot bounce.
Essentially off of four different monsters in that little tiny space
right there and again, so this is just like if you imagine this
magnified
Here's the guy.
He's moving here.
Right?
But there's a monster.
That's right here.
He hits it and then it truncates.
So he can only move in that direction.
So now he's trying to move here.
If there was another monster, he hit it.
But at that point, he can't even move anymore because he's had all of
his movement directions.
Truncated.
So he just stopped anyway, so, it'd be hard for him to even get
without some restoration velocity and without him bouncing off things.
It would be hard for him to ever even hit for and even if he did we
hard hit for because again, it's such a small amount of movement.
Talking about, so that's what's happening there.
So he could easily fight as many monsters as you want.
That will never be a problem for honestly is probably Overkill.
You could probably get away with one iteration through this Loop for
is probably way Overkill to be honest with you.
Do you plan to use some form of logging for debugging purposes?
Yes, once we have a little bit more, once I look at one of these days,
we got to bite the bullet and get thoughts going.
So we can actually have some heads up displays and stuff when we get
to that point will be, will be doing some good debugging support for
sure, but we haven't quite gotten there yet.
And since we don't have a lot of really hard to bugging problems right
now.
It hasn't been worth it like everything.
We've had to bug has been debugged in, you know, a couple minutes, so
When you remove a low entity from the chunk list you swap another into
its place.
Won't that mess with references?
No, because those are all already references.
Nobody actually points.
Into the chunk list.
The chunk list is just an array of entity indices.
So nobody is pointing into that.
So we should be fine.
Even Force low-frequency entities.
What is that in reference to happy vertex?
What is it?
Oh, even Force low-frequency entities.
So my plan and this may be wrong, but my plan is move player.
For example, this is only operating in high frequency in low
frequency.
We will never do Collision detection in low frequency.
We will do purely semantic, updating of entities.
I suspect because we want to we don't want to have
Map everything into high.
So remember this move player only happens in high because
low-frequency entities can't be near the player by definition.
So we're never trying to collide the player with those.
Okay, we have come to the end of the questions.
Which is pretty awesome.
Because we're right on time.
All right, we are right on time, for minutes from closing.
That's perfect.
So let's go ahead and, and, and and close things up.
Shall we?
Let's close this down.
Close that down.
I'm glad we got the trees in today.
It was nice to have those trees and I was tired of looking at those
yellow.
Rectangles.
Let me tell you that.
All right.
So let's let's wind up the stream.
Thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It has been a
Recording with you.
As always, I like, the way things have been going.
Everything has gone pretty smoothly so far.
I don't know if that's means.
We should quit while we're ahead, but I don't know.
I'm foolhardy.
I'm going to, I'm going to take The Optimist position and say things
will keep going well, because it's been pretty cool so far.
So, yeah, so we got to a point now where we can sort of start thinking
about making some World stuff, we can sort of start, we things are
starting to open up here for us.
So I think maybe we'll start considering a little more entities and
getting some of that stuff working and then the last real
a big piece that we gotta tackle after we look at that, maybe is
animation.
So but we're getting real close.
This is this is looking good and I like the way things are shaping up
and yeah, I got nothing but positive stuff to say about things have
gone so far.
So, yeah, so if you would like to join me tomorrow,
8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time again, we will go through and maybe pull out
some of that entity code and get it into sort of a more
straightforward fashion where we can clearly see, they put it in a
separate file, like exactly all the steps that we're doing and how
they always are supposed to line up and then we'll sort of make maybe
start making some more entities that move around, besides just the
player and maybe some stuff you can pick up your.
Like I started start to get a little gamey stuff in there, see how
that plays out and see what we need to do with it, just to kind of get
going in that direction.
So that's what we'll be doing tomorrow.
I'd love to
To see you here again.
If you would like to follow along at home with the source code, if you
Pre-order the game, you get access to the source code and you can
download it every night after I finish.
I upload the source that we did for that day.
So you can go ahead and pre-order that on handmade hero dot-org.
Using the handy dandy pre-order button.
You can also support the video series.
We have a patreon, you can subscribe to which you can click through on
here and there's also a news and Forum site.
You can go to where if you want to learn more about the series or try
to study different parts of it.
It's a great place to go.
It's got episode guide the schedule for the week so is posted and also
I made the
Handmade tweeting bot.
So if you go to the tweets page, you can you can subscribe to the
handmade Kuro Twitter and it'll tweet the schedule at you as well.
So, that's kind of Handy.
But yeah, point being the schedule is always posted here.
If you just want to check it out.
And then there's a three things you should know about the episode
guide.
If you want to catch up on old episodes.
That's the place to go.
The coding resources page, has ports to Mac and Linux, and stuff like
that.
So that's a great place to go.
If you want to work on a different platform than Windows for right
now, and we have a code discussion page as well.
You can go to which
Has sort of forum we can post questions or discuss things.
If you just have questions.
There's a bunch of people who helped answer that.
So yeah.
Thank you very much for joining me and I hope to see you guys
tomorrow.
Take it easy.