The recording.
Hello, everyone.
And welcome back to handmade hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream.
Although we have not been coding for two weeks.
We had two weeks off because I was with out of the country and unable
to actually do any sort of streaming so that.
Yeah, that pretty much meant the show was down, but we are back now
and we are trying to wrap up our debug system.
That's what we sort of stopped on and we still have a few
two more things left to do in that.
So I would like to sort of get into doing them.
Now, it's always kind of tricky, obviously, when you come back after
taking a, while off from the code, you know, your brain can kind of
sort of forget what it was working on a forget, what's going on.
So, people were asking in the pre stream about that and wondering
Lavetta and like I was sort of saying there and it Bears repeating
generally what I do for this sort of thing is, I tend to try and keep
my codebase very
Like what I try to do with code, is I try to, you know, sort of make,
you know, I try to make general rules about how I do stuff and you see
me often times type in things, they they sort of look the same and
follow the same sort of structure in general, when I'm writing code.
That is there for a number of reasons.
And one big one, is that the more consistent you are with the way that
you choose to make things work, the less difficult it is for you to,
you know,
To guess what code does if you've forgotten right?
So if I see a function and it's named a particular way and it takes a
certain parameters in a certain order.
All of those things are like Clues to me about how that function
probably was implemented.
And the closer, you can stay to having consistency in the code that
works.
That way, the less you have to remember about your code base, right?
And so there's no way to do that perfectly, right.
You can't really
Eliminate all surprises.
If you work on enough code and you make enough code, which I
definitely do.
You will forget stuff and you will forget some important things and
you will get bugs because you forgot something and that's just the
nature of the Beast and it's nothing to be worried about.
But you do want to try to minimize that sort of thing because just in
general, even from day-to-day coding, it tends to be pretty valuable
to sort of have
Of an expectation about what code does and to have that expectation
usually be correct.
It just saves a lot of mental energy and it prevents a lot of bugs
that might happen.
It's just a nice thing.
So, let's just take a quick look at where we sort of left off.
And you can see we've got our, our sort of game are running care, and
if I remember correctly, we sort of turned the debug system off.
Just to leave everything in a state where anyone who wanted to play
around with it.
Since we hadn't quite finished it yet, could play around with it and
be fine with that.
So what we want to do first is turn the debug system back on.
And we've sort of have this debug, we just just at the end, we sort of
pulled it back out the debug system, all kind of exists in here,
right?
And we've got some pound Defiance which turn it on and off, you can
see that.
Here's the one that actually turned it off.
So if I do that, we can turn it back on again.
And now we're building but I suspect we eventually crash or something
like this.
I would, I would think.
Yeah, there we go.
And so what I believe we stopped if I remember correctly where we
actually stopped was that we were processing frames.
Now we were actually processing them.
Fully incrementally.
But we had not actually gotten to the point where we freed everything,
so we would get to to a circumstance where, you know, we were building
up frames incrementally, but then nobody would ever actually free any
memory taken up by those frames.
So eventually you get enough frames in the debug buffer and you're
going to run out of Arena space, right?
And that's exactly what that was right here, right?
Jesse, we're just running along its collecting debug events and doing
whatever else.
It's
To do.
And then you end up in a situation, like, you see here, where it's
like, okay, we, you know, we've we sort of
run out of the memory that we had to work with.
Now one thing that's a little troubling to me and I'm not really sure,
I guess.
Okay, so it's not actually, I suppose it's not actually necessary
trouble to me, but it's just a little weird to think about this.
You can see that the this last frame time here, looks kind of weird
and garbagey so I'm kind of interested to know.
I guess we'll see when I actually go through and finish this up.
We'll see what's actually going on there but that's just a little
weird to me because you can tell the frame rate.
That frame rate.
If it actually the frame time was actually threaded, Ms, that would
imply, you know, somewhere between four, three and four frames a
second, right?
If I'm if I'm doing that right.
So three or four frames a second, this is running way too fast for
that.
That's way faster than three.
Firms is like.
So that's wrong.
Now it may just be displaying, only the first frame and maybe the
first frame took longer for various reasons but I just saying like
anytime I see some like that, I get a little bit.
Little bit nervous.
So I'm just going to put that in the back of everyone's mind is
something that shouldn't have been what it was.
And so when we sort of finish doing this, if we were still seeing
that, that probably is something that warrants investigation.
All right, so let's go ahead and jump back.
I think we left even some to dues in here for ourselves which meant
mentioned about sort of the freeing you can kind of see here like
okay, like we don't even have this free variable group stuff
implemented.
So if I remember correctly, basically,
Want to do is take this like free frame thing and we want to sort of
make this actually a actually work and be actually be called because I
suspect.
If I remember where we were at, I suspect we don't actually ever
really call that and I'm looking through here and I'm seeing that I'm
correct about that because this right here, all this is is the time
when, if you were paused it will throw out the latest frames so that
they don't take up any space.
Don't do anything.
Hey.
But if you, you know, if you think about it, when you do, if that's
the only time if they're getting free, then there's no time when we're
actually freeing the frames in sort of that circular in that in that
rolling buffer, right?
There's no time when we're actually doing any sort of freeing of the
the frames that are building up, which is what we want to do, right?
Like we want to free frames as they build up so that we don't run out
of that memory.
So
Those are the two things we need to do.
We need to call free frame at the right times and we need to have have
it actually do the free.
So this for example, needs to happen.
All right, so you can see we got to to to do is here as well.
All right, so that's what we've got to do.
And we also have a to do here, says remember to copy out the debug
events into the debug variable links and what that was talking about
this again.
I guess so.
Despite what I said, I guess what I'm sort of actually seeing here as
I'm discussing this, as I guess, my memory for the code actually, is
pretty good.
I remember all this stuff, so I don't know, I guess two weeks is not
long enough for me to have.
Paged it out, which I suppose is a little bit surprising to me at my
age, but I don't know.
I guess that maybe I'm just getting lucky who knows.
Anyway, point being, if you remember how the system worked at the end,
what we decided to do, as we sort of started boiling down and like I
said, we were kind of going through this period of like simplifying
things going to get
Although more sort of straightforward usable and a little more, you
know, better structured and not.
So sprawling.
What we did here is we took the debug table and we had all the events
that were being recorded.
We used to have like, all the frames would just sort of sit there and
those event arrays.
So, as you sort of streamed out into the event, to raise the event,
raised were actually with the source data was, then we have the
co-leaders that would kind of run on that.
It was kind of this all big proliferation of stuff.
So we did the very end there as we just reduce it down to just two
buffers.
It's so basically, the game code well, or, you know, all the code I
should say to the non debug code is writing into one of those event
buffers while we are using the other event buffer, right?
So it's just a, just a straight ping pong buffer scheme only two
buffers, there's one that's being written to and one that's being read
from at any given time, then that's it.
And what that means is that as we are preserving those events,
For later viewing in the debug system, we end up in a scenario where
those debug events themselves cannot actually be used out of this
buffers anymore because as soon as you're more than one frame back, if
you're looking at four frames back, five frames back, the events are
gone, right?
So when we do the collation, we actually have to move the debug event
out of here and into the actual permanent storage.
Of those those debug variables that we had.
Right?
So that the actual sort of collation step needs to actually store the
debug event where as I think if I'm not mistaken the way that this
works at the moment, is it actually just references that debug event
directly.
So if you take a look at
This code here, right?
If you take a look at this code here, what you can see is that we have
sort of these debug for everything that sort of thing.
And the debug variable ink just points to a particular debug event,
right?
And that's not actually necessarily bad because we probably want to
continue doing that since the debug event is the piece of actual data,
right?
That we're trying to keep their whatever.
But the thing about that is that this debug variable link is, you
know, there could be multiple of those that are all sort of pointing
to the same piece of data, right?
Because we have that thing, we can pull off piece of the UI.
We sort of did that stuff before all of those pieces of the you.
I might want to point at the same piece of data and so we you know
it's not necessarily bad that it's a pointer right?
Because we could just go like that and embed the data in.
So it's not necessarily bad that it's a pointer but
If if we do, in fact, even as a pointer, we need to, at least make
space for wherever that debug event actually is supposed to go, right?
And so there's that so I don't know again, that's the, that's the,
that's the sort of thing that we're I don't know.
I want to say, cut sort of wrestling with here.
That's that's the sort of part that's that we're kind of going back
and forth on, we know that these debug variable links will all sort of
are things that kind of get allocated.
And we
That we have these sort of standing structures there.
We know that we have debug events that are kind of getting written out
and then we were sort of pointing at those is actual data.
And then we also have this kind of concept of the collation step that
runs over things and sort of tries to line up events with other events
and do other sorts of stuff like that.
And again, it's a very complex system and it's been sort of a
winnowing process of figuring out how those things have to sort of
come together.
And so, it really is just a sort of, it really is a kind of
fficult thing to sort of understand or sort of to to know exactly what
the right thing is to do because again,
You also look at sort of the way that this debug frame stuff works.
It's tempting to say that the way that we were doing it before is
actually how you might want to do it.
Like, you could, it's tempting to say well, okay, could we not just
make a giant circular buffer of the debug event.
So the debug events all kind of go into that buffer, right?
And then we just point back at them directly.
The reason that I'm trending away from that is because when we did the
collapse down to just having the debug events,
I felt like it may have been a little bit too much of a collapse.
And the reason for that is that when we actually collate things
together, we're probably adding additional stuff there, right?
And so, when we kind of look at what happens in sort of the debug
interface stuff and and that sort of thing,
When we look at what goes on here, it's unclear that we really want,
you know that this is really enough, right?
This is not the thing that really store has enough information so that
collation step tends to sort of amplify the data or at least connected
up and want to sort of have a more complicated structure than the
things that we're writing to the debug log, which are meant to be as
small as possible, right?
We want those to be fairly concise and at the moment they're actually
probably bigger than we even really want them to be because we haven't
tried to do anything.
Make this Union, say, for example, actually be more compressed so that
it only takes up the amount of spot size is actually using.
Which again, is something we could do when we're writing this out,
that's relatively cheap for us to do, right?
So again, like I said, the debug system, this is by far the most
complicated structural thing that we've done, and it's the reason that
I wanted to do it is just to sort of show and also I'm doing something
that I, you know, this is not the style of debug system that I've ever
done before.
So I just want to kind of show how many times you tend to kind of work
through these things.
This is how architectural programming works when you're trying to
figure out a new architecture for something and you're not sure how it
goes, you go back and forth many times.
Things and you have to be willing to do that because if you don't, you
will never get to a good solution, right?
You'll always kind of be stuck with sort of the basic whatever.
First passed thing is, you'll never really get to the point where you
kind of break through that and get to something, that's better that's
on the other side, right?
And so yeah.
So again, I think nothing is still set in stone.
It's really just a process of winning way down.
And I kind of want to just sort of go go back and explain sort of what
that means there.
As we go.
So I don't know about that, right?
I don't know if that's the right thing or not, but it just sort of
seems like that's sort of where we've gone back and forth on it twice.
It seems like where it sort of wants to end up is, you know, don't try
to force these two things to be the same thing when they're not
actually the same thing.
We're building these sort of arbitrary structures up that, you know,
we want to try to collate into more usable things that can be
displayed or can be, you know, that we can do whatever with, you know
me.
Maybe I'm missing something there.
Maybe what I should be doing is just keeping all the debug events in a
giant rolling buffer because then it would be more efficient if you
always just kind of worked out of that buffer but maybe not.
Right?
And so that's just kind of I guess that's that's a there's really
nothing I can say about that other than it's sort of a wait-and-see
thing.
So, so that's where we're at the moment.
And so, what I want to do now is kind of go through here and, and
start to push on this a little bit and try to get these sorts of
things implemented, a little bit more.
One thing I will say is that, when we're doing these discs, debug
record.
Coalition, one thing that's kind of interesting about it when we look
at it here is and I think this may sort of again suggests a little bit
of how we move forward on this part of the design as well.
One thing that I was thinking is really what we
Probably want to do most of the time as well is we want to be able to
look at things over multiple frames.
Probably like the typical thing that you're going to want to do, for
example like especially with something like a performance counter or
anything like that or even something like a variable.
Just even that was a gameplay variable of some kind that had nothing
to do with performance with such as is just something that you wanted
to see if you want to look at it over time.
Typically you're looking at it from the standpoint of the of the
particular quantity involved.
Right.
And not in terms of the frame.
Because usually the frame has like all this data in it and I typically
don't want to look at the whole frame.
What I'm doing is I'm looking at a particular piece of code and I'm
trying to debug it or I'm trying to analyze it in some way that's
important.
And so I'm typically focusing on some particular part of that code,
right?
I'm saying here, is this variable, you know, like let's say we're
optimizing something and I'm looking at a particular performance
counter or particular whatever I want to look at that particular thing
across multiple frames probably
I want to see, like, what was it, you know, maybe like a graph over
the last sixty, four frames, or whatever it is.
I want to see, you know, where the spike was or how it was performing,
an average or whatever, you know, these sorts of things.
If we're talking about that sort of thing, then when we're collating
debug records, as we go through here and we do this collation as we
do, right?
What we might want to start doing is taking anything, that's a debug
event that we see in here and sort of moving it out into, like a list
or a sort of an aggregation that's based on whichever variable it was
so that we would just have one standing structure that ends up being
created.
That is like, here are all of the quantities or elements that the
debug system is tracking.
And each one of them, sort of shows overtime, right?
And you can see,
The other thing being true as well, whereas sometimes, we might want
to see the things happening over time, right.
So I feel like, one way of conceptualizing, what I think we would want
to do as we try to sort of lock this down into, what the
Form is that we're going to be using as we go forward in the game.
Is to think about that sort of dichotomy there, where we have these
debug events, they're coming in, in a stream, we're trying to pull
them out and put them into a sort of some sort of a structure that can
be viewed in either of those two ways.
So in addition to just having it be a conceptualization of like the
frames that happen over time.
We can see what happened in a particular frame.
It's also the constant that way, we can pick out one of these things
and view it the other way.
So it's kind of like a pivoting sort of a
Effect, where we can look at it from the perspective of time, or from
the perspective of the element and the other one becomes the other
axis.
So if we're looking at it from the perspective of time, we have the
elements sort of coming across and we're looking at it from the
perspective of the, the elements here, it's like time going across
that sort of thing.
I think that's sort of how we would want to view it and I think we're
pretty close to that.
And again that's the thing that sort of suggests to me that probably
it was the right idea to stream out the events and then copy them out.
But at the same time, I just don't know because in equivalently, valid
way to approach this problem, I think is to just expand the notion of
the debug event to have extra space here and then thread the debug
events with that information.
The fact, so the Coalition is just sweeping through that buffer, kind
of like, you know, placing pointer threads through the actual debug
events by like, you know, there's just space left up here, or
whatever.
You know, at the beginning of each debug event, that's not touched.
So it doesn't cost anything.
When the debug streaming is happening, it's just skipping over it.
So it's not taking up any additional memory bandwidth during streaming
and then when collation comes through it, just threads that stuff
together, right?
And so I don't know.
I really just don't know and so I'm not sure, I'm not sure we're doing
the right thing or the wrong thing here.
I just a really, really really tough call and
And I don't know, I I do not know but again I'm willing to kind of
like flip it again.
If we need to if we decide that we're just kind of wasting time here
with this additional stuff that we're doing, that's totally fine.
You know if you have to you have to.
So okay when we are creating this these frames here, you can see that
sort of the the frame stuff, what the main thing that we were testing
out with this was the ability to sort of make this this sort of thing
happen where we
we have all of these sort of pieces of debug information happening on
the frame.
Right?
And at the moment, those are just showing like for a particular frame.
Here are the the
But values that we were sort of that got announced during the frame.
So if we want to kind of move forward with that,
let's just kind of go ahead and finish up what we're doing there.
What we need to be able to do is a have some way of freeing the The
Knowing When We're supposed to free the frame.
So, like I said before, we've got to be able to free the frame here.
So, what I'll do is, I'll find a location.
I'll find a particular way where I want to start freaking the frame,
so we don't build up an infinite number of them.
And then what we should do is as soon as we get soon as we do that, we
should then hit this assertion because when it tries to free the
frame, it will fail to free the frame because it'll hit the certian
that it wasn't implemented and then we'll go Implement that.
And if we take a look, just to see here, and I suppose, this is
probably at in handmade, debug dedic.
If I take a look at the debug frame, by the way, I'm totally
jet-lagged as well.
So you'll have to excuse me.
If I'd gone during this Frame, just started during this some stream
because that that will probably happen.
So anyway, if we take a look at the debug frame here, you can see
that.
That really, if we look at it, we've got these these regions, the
Region's aren't really doing anything at the moment that was like a
holdover from
Or old profiler thing.
But so the only thing that really has to be freaking here at the
moment is the debug variable group route group, because that's the
thing that sort of holds that you I situation in there.
Right.
and so that,
is the only thing that I actually had to be freed and
looking at that.
I would again, say
That it's starting to taste to me like we're going to get closer.
So what I'm envisioning, what sort of coming up in my head that that I
think I was missing sort of, as we were sort of working this through
before and we never quite touched on it.
I'm, you know, I'm going to do, I'm going to bring up, I'm going to do
it here.
I'm going to bring up our Mischief.
Let's take a look here.
Blackboard a tart.
So what I wow, that loaded crazy fast.
How come that loaded?
So fat normally Eunice, you guys have seen how long it takes mischief
to load.
Normally, it's all there.
Weird.
It's just me or was that kind of weird, guys?
All right.
Well, I'm you know what I'm gonna do?
I'm gonna find a new area for us to start to.
I want to put us right in here.
See here to put us, right?
Right here.
Maybe.
I think how big it do.
I usually draw, I think I usually draw about that big.
Would you say?
Let's take a look.
Yeah.
All right.
I'm going to come in here.
All right, so day 216.
So, I just want to kind of underscores.
Something that I think that I wasn't overtly recognizing before, but
that was sort of implicit in the system that was causing, it was sort
of preventing the design from progressing a little bit because, you
know, as we sort of played around with things are pushing on things
that would be never quite felt to me like was quite gelling.
The way that I wanted to it and I think here is the part that I was
sort of missing which is that like sort of the the concept of like a
debug you know, sort of like a I want to say a debug element if you
will was kind of a little nebulous.
And I never really articulated before that whole thing about there
being time and elements and those two things being similar.
So what was happening is we
I have a number of different things here, right?
There's the debug events that happened in the log and we know that we
at least have those because that's the source of the stuff but we
don't really know anything else about them.
We don't know what else they have to be.
We only know that they have to dump the data that were eventually
going to display.
That's really all we know, right?
So we know that that's going to happen and that's fine.
But then we also have the concept of the debug you I right?
So there was also you know these things are like just going into a log
you know and we've got them and we don't really know much about them
other than they've got sort of data in there and you know.
So we've got there's some payload but everything else is like up in
the air.
What else they do?
We don't know, right?
We have the ability as The Architects of this to decide whether
they're just straight payload or whether there's actually extra stuff
in there and we've kind of gone back and forth on that a little bit.
And so on, we then have the debug you, I
Right?
And that debug UI has stuff like, you know, hierarchies of stuff in
that, you know, where we kind of have, you know, and sub hierarchies
and whatever we kind of played around with that.
Where we have, this is a sort of a hierarchical structure.
It's not like this where it's linear.
It's this kind of concept that things have parents and children, and
whatever.
And they can be expanded and collapsed.
And they can show, you know, values in here, or whatever else happens.
And we could drag, we just if we could drag and edit them, right?
So we have that concept.
All in there.
And then we also have the concept of actually like a debug sort of, I
want to say element, right?
And this has been a little bit nebulous so far, but that's like, you
know, this piece of UI right, is editing something, right, when we
were doing that thing?
Like, you know, we had, for example, in there, the debug camera
distance.
That was something that we were able to edit, right?
We have the debug camera distance and you could drag the debug camera
distance and it would change that value in the code.
And so, it was like, kind of a real-time way, you could edit stuff,
which was kind of nice.
It was, it was sort of nice to have it in there.
Originally, I thought we wouldn't really need it because we have Loop
live coding, but there's something nice about being able to directly
change a value, that might help us.
When we're trying to do stuff like edit some colors of things in the
game.
You know that there's there's some Merit
Do it, right?
So if we think about this and we think about the fact that there's
only here, the UI and the element are not necessarily the same thing,
right?
And that's kind of a little bit confusing, but we've never really
quite defined exactly what that means.
And so we were sort of having this problem where, you know, we've got
these debug events and reprocessing, the debug events, they give rise
to these debug elements, right?
As we see something kind of come up in here,
we're like, oh, whatever this thing is this value.
Like if we see debug camera distance to open your, oh, that's a debug
element, right?
But these debug elements were only existing for as long as that, you
know, State around.
If on some frame we didn't see that it would suddenly disappear,
right?
And that's a little bit.
Wonky in the sense that what I think we actually want to do is say
that these things are permanent.
I suspect that's what we actually want.
I suspect.
What we want to do is say that any time we see a debug element of some
kind, it becomes a man like a matter of permanent record if you will.
Right.
So when we see one of these and we see debug camera distance, I think
we want to create something that is the permanent concept of the debug
A distance and the debug UI is a transient thing that sort of looks
into here and edits that, right?
And so when The Frame data goes away, what we actually want to go away
as frames fall out of that sort of that rolling.
Buffer is not the fact that there was a debug camera distance.
I think we want that to persist what we want instead to go away, is
just whatever its value was.
Is on that frame, right?
So, I think the thing that we actually want, right?
Is we actually want something, which is kind of like this, this sort
of table, right?
Of, you know, we've got the debug elements here, whatever they are.
And then you know in here we've sort of got the frame 0 1, 2, 3, and
whatever.
And the information that we have about this element on, this Frame
goes in here, whatever.
And these columns go away, right?
So
Of the words, my my notion of what this V bug element was on this
Frame, that will go away, but this will not.
And so that element of permanence was getting conflated, it was
getting, it was partially in here.
It was partially in here and partially in here, and it was like, it
kind of half existed in half did in and who created it.
And when, and it was just like, we weren't sort of concrete about
that.
But I think, you know, like I said, as I'm looking at
At this.
Now and perhaps this is just my brain coming back after two weeks.
Thinking it has a good idea but it actually turns out that this is
dumb.
But you know, it's only one way to find out.
I think that's what I want to sort of congeal to, right.
That's where I want this this process to sort of end.
I think that's what we need to do.
Is basically make it so that we're creating a permanent sort of
structure of elements that structure is based on what we see in the
debug events, those debug events are tracked,
Act as sort of existing over time.
And as we sort of lose debug events, they fall out of sort of this
this Tableau of some sorts, right?
that is, I think the real thing that we were sort of missing
So what that suggests to me?
Now that I'm saying it is that that almost does sort of, that sort of
starts to feel like we do want to, kind of just take this
simplification one step further and and maybe actually keep the debug
events actually in here.
Not copy them, right?
And so like this, debug table, for example, we actually do want to
make the debug table, just be a giant buffer and you
But the thing is, is the reason we weren't doing that because we don't
have because it has to be a static.
Is that a problem for us?
And actually, no, because we do treat it as a static here.
I don't know, we could avoid, we could make it something that gets
allocated I suppose.
I don't know point being
Yeah.
You know we easily could make that be something is allocated.
It could actually be passed from the platform layer into the game now
because we actually the we no longer need to know those counts or
those sizes so that it may even be something that we actually would
prefer to to have happen.
But anyway so ignoring all that temporarily, let's just ignore that
part.
If we wanted to make this debug events just be a giant buffer.
So you know
Over the memory.
We decide we set up side, 64 megabytes or whatever, for the debug
system, right?
This would just be a giant buffer of 64 megabytes worth of events.
And when people write events in there, they just go ahead and write
them linearly and rap, you know, the buffer, right?
So as they're sort of writing those out, then all we do during
collation is basically, you know, we thread through those events we
thread through
I want to say, like just basically like this, this, this Tableau here
we basically said, like, okay, here is a particular type of debug
event that we've seen and we
Read through.
Like, here are the values of it for every frame, right?
That would basically be what we do now.
The, the only thing that's tricky about that and the reason that I'm
like, saying, well, you know, it sort of seems like we should do that
but I'm not 100% sold on it.
The reason that's a little tricky is because we don't actually know at
that point when those events have gone away because if you imagined it
just being a giant circular buffer, right?
You can kind of see
What I'm talking about here, hopefully let me go ahead and keep
forgetting.
I should just leave this in Pole Position here.
All right, so what I'm sort of getting at here again and I'll just say
it one more time, just in case it was ambiguous.
It's if we have Asus say we just had this giant 64 MB buffer and
here's where the debug events go.
So, we start off at the beginning of it and we just write debug events
in here, right to this is, you know, we're just writing them in, we
write them in, we write them in the right to Remember at the memory
and eventually some number of frames down the line, we get to the end
of the buffer.
Wrap back to beginning.
So now the next event like over writes this one so basically event 0
was here event zeros now gone and event like you know, two million
four hundred and fifty thousand.
I don't know what, you know, some number here event that event goes in
this place.
Right?
So the problem is that if we were to do that, we don't know when that
romping will occur because member we have multiple threads.
All right into this debug buffer, they're just going nuts, right?
And we don't know, at what point someone will overwrite this value.
So, if again, taking this example where we had like, you know, the I
think we were talking about specifically the debug camera distance.
So we have the debug camera distance, right?
And we go like, okay, we know about debug camera distance.
That's in there.
When we do our collation, we saw it was the first thing that came in
it was, it was event 0.
It was also event like for, you know, 593 or whatever, right?
And so we said debug camera distance.
Okay, here's the first instance of it.
Here's the second instance of it, right.
Here's the third instance of it maybe or something like that, and
we've got those now.
So, now in the, in the UI, we can display them.
We know the three events and when they happened, and we can display
those
oh,
To the user and let them do whatever they want.
Blah, blah blah, right?
Well the problem here is that some point this one gets overwritten but
we don't know when it got over it, right?
We have no idea.
So there's not really anything that we can do to maintain the
Integrity of some kind of a linked list or some kind of, you know,
whatever else needs to be there, right?
So, you know, that's why I still am like a little hesitant even though
it would be more efficient to leave the debug events where they are,
so they don't have to be copied out into anything.
if we were to copy them out that problem solves itself because then we
just have
A static stable thing where debug instance I start debug distance has
however many frames at saving right in there and we just free them
when we want to free them and nobody cares.
Right.
And so again, like I say it's something that I'm talking out loud
because this is actually what I would be thinking about in my head, if
I were programming, I would think probably all of these thoughts.
I would just hopefully think them a little bit faster than they are
when I'm trying to explain them and draw them.
But
But you can kind of see the Dilemma there and so the way that I will
rationalize this to myself because I don't necessarily know what the
right answer is.
So I'm trying to pick a reason why I might why I might plausibly argue
for one way or the other.
I think I could make a plausible argument that we do want to do the
copy out even though it's a little less efficient because it like,
basically doubles our memory traffic.
They're the reason that I might argue that is
Cuz I feel like we could easily get in a situation where we want to
store, a lot of previous values, for some things, and not very many
previous values for other things, right?
For example, the debug camera distance, we really don't need 100
frames worth of back catalogue on what that value was right, nobody
cares what that value is.
It's just the debug value.
We use for like changing the camera to zoom in and out so that we can
Test, like look at like, you know, more than just the reason region
that the player is seeing when they're playing, that's all that does.
So, the chances that I'm going to need to do something like record,
100, or 1000 frames worth of what that did are like zero.
That's just not going to happen.
Whereas other things, you know, like, again performance Cal kinds of
stuff that's something that may want to track.
A lot of hits of it over time or certain values that sort of
correspond to it.
You know, that could might want
Keep a lot more events in there because we're trying to do it.
Furthermore, we might, you might even say it doesn't matter what the
type is, it matters, what the users paying attention to?
So, for example, we may want to have the ability to build system to do
something like, say, hey, when I like shift-click on some value,
right?
In the debug, you, I, when I say flick out about you, debug you, I
want to set that debug you, I value to a state where it records, you
know, infinite number of frames are not infinite but like, you know,
thousands of frames it just
Means that that I'm considering that variable right now.
So go ahead and take plenty of memory and actually make sure that that
variable
is known for a very very long run because I'm trying to do something
special with it, right?
So that to me kind of is a plausible argument for why I might pick one
over the other because I'm just giving up some performance, does the
debug system?
So I'm not sure I ever really care about the performance of it that
much, but I can Envision a feature that is
You know, that it's more cleanly enabled here.
And so that gets me out of the business of having to worry about how
that threading would happen through this in for, you know, through
this sort of buffer.
And I can just say, I will actually do the copy out every time as we
go.
And so as I do the collation, I copy out into whatever sort of format,
we're using to sort of keep that information, right?
That seems pretty plausible to me.
So I'm going to go ahead and, and, and say that.
Is is the way it will go.
All right, so that's good.
That means that what we've got here is pretty much.
Okay, this is a reasonable way to make this debug event system work,
just use the ping pong buffer.
The events themselves will just be sort of whatever is the necessary
piece of information is that goes into those those ping-pong buffers
and then what we'll do is we'll have two additional sort of things
that sit on top of it.
Which we sort of already have talked about one of them and
implemented, one of them a bunch, which is sort of the UI elements.
And we've kind of got some of that where we did like, debug trees and,
and these sort of views, and that sort of stuff, we sort of worked out
this a little bit, but we haven't quite gotten to the fact that sorry.
We haven't quite gotten to the part.
Where we've actually sort of solidified that debug element part of it.
And so, that's the part that will kind of have to just finish up here
in order to make this stuff work, right.
And because this, this stuff is just it's not quite there yet, right?
And you can kind of tell by the sort of the way that things aren't as
disease is not quite there yet, and I think that was because we were
sort of missing that concrete.
I hadn't quite put it into words that concrete element, that there is
a, well, that concrete debug element the concept that there is sort of
this thing that exists across all the
That sort of talks about, you know, the two talks about that
particular piece of information.
All right.
So let's see what we can do.
That's that's good.
I think I feel like again, I feel like that kind of solidify some
stuff it crystallizes in my head, some things that we didn't really,
you know, we hadn't sort of put into words and that we're making us a
little more listless than we needed to be as we were sort of trying to
solidify this stuff and you got to make sure you kind of get through
all of those barriers.
But in order to really sort of get the system architecture stuff to
where it needs to be.
So when we go ahead and do our free frame,
R.
What that implies to me is that when we are doing a free frame, we're
going to free kind of from the oldest to the newest frames.
What that sort of implies to me is we're going to need a little bit of
logic there about what does get freed and what doesn't get freed if we
want to do stuff, like have things that have different sorts of life's
lifetimes to them.
I'm going to defer that part off just a little bit until I can have a
little more visible in the system.
And for now, I'm just going to say let's just
That we're not going to have everything is going to be the same amount
of time and we'll set a see how that breaks down.
When I call free frame, the most logical point in time I think to try
and reclaim memory by calling three frame is just if we actually go
ahead and say that when we try to get new memory.
Out of the debugger Arena.
If we can't get it then we call free frame, right?
So basically free frame is the thing that that sort of allows us to
sort of grab new memory when we need it.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to take a quick look here
for everyone who uses the debugger Arena, and this is a trick that
I've done multiple times on handmade hero.
I never get tired of it.
It's a good one.
All I'm going to do is I'm going to append an underscore to the debug
Arena itself.
So,
that I can go ahead and see everyone who's using it, and you can see
in here, you know, we've got basically the, the entirety I told you, I
told you I was getting yawn and I did
You can see the entirety of it pretty much exists in handmade debug
and so that's what you know, I would have expected.
So basically all I have to do is look at all these push trucks that
happen on the debug Arena here and all I'm going to really have to do
is make sure that all of those debug Arena allocations I'm just gonna
sort of I'm going to make them happen in sort of a secondary.
I'm going to insert a little step before allocation out of
Rena.
That basically says, if you can't allocate on this Arena, let me know.
Because I will sort of, you know, I'll give some memory back.
I'll figure out a way to get more memory there.
Now, there is something that's, I think a little bit concerning to us,
which is, I think we may have had a push truck turn hurt ya.
You can see right here, we sort of got this push truck in here.
So inside our free list allocate, we had baked in the concept of
things.
We're calling push direct for a particular Arena.
And what I'd like to do is maybe say well
L.
I don't know if we actually want that to be the case although I could
use a function or I could use overloading here to kind of help us out
I suppose, although not necessarily with, with type in there, the way
it is.
So what I'd like to do here again is make sure that this supports
being able to get the allocation from a different way and I think the
way to do that and I probably should have done this way.
Originally is what we're doing right now is they're passing in the
arena but probably what we should do is pass in just the entire
allocation itself, right?
So what we do here is like allocation allocation code, right?
And what we do is say like here's the allocation code that you're
actually going to call, right?
Here's that, that's the stuff that is what you're going to actually do
there and so if we take a look at what happens when I compile this
now, and of course I guess I got to put a debug Arena back together is
in this, in this case.
Wait, what?
Separate development, debug events star.
What did I do?
Did I forget to change something?
Yes, I did.
Okay, don't know why I did that.
Alright, so you can see now after I did that change vits, I'm just
passing the debug Arena here, but what I actually need to do is I
actually need to pass the the code that actually does the allocation.
It, so I need to do something.
That looks more like this.
That makes sense, and if I compile that they're at least in theory
that should work.
Oops, there that should work.
But I have to spell correctly.
There we go.
And so you can see what I did there.
I just made it so I can pass in the application code.
So that means this thing can be whatever it wants.
When I look at this, I also note that now, the type doesn't actually
have to be passed at all.
So really, this doesn't have to be there.
So mostly for frivolous allocate, you just need to put in what
I think the variable you actually wanted what the, what the pointer
was for the head and then whatever the thing is to get new memory, if
it needs it.
So that totally solves that problem for us at least in theory and
here.
In this guy, we just need to do the exact same thing, right?
So this is going to be a.push a.push struct with open debug block,
right?
Or at least it it.
So that allows me now to say, okay, whenever I'm going to get
something from this debug Arena, I could instead, say that instead of
doing something like push direct, I could make now, a way of sort of
thinking through there to get stuff out of two free stuff.
If I need to, if the arena is full, right?
If I'm, if I dont have space left and I need to get stuff out of the
debug Arena.
I can, I can sort of free on demand, if that makes sense.
The
Nothing I could do and I'm not sure I really want to do this, but you
can imagine adding that to the Arena's themselves.
So if we thought we wanted to do that, if we thought we were going to
do this sort of more generally, I could actually put it in here,
right.
I could put some concept of a call back in here that's like oh hey you
know I don't have the memory so please get me the memory.
I don't know that I love that.
So I'm going to leave that aside for now, but I wouldn't get angry at
somebody who was like, I just
Aunt, the memory Arenas themselves to understand this and be able to
handle it, right?
So what I'm going to do instead though, I just I just don't want to go
down that route right now.
And so, what I want to do instead is I want to make it so that I have
sort of a thunking through, to the debug Arena that will actually do
that.
And so, in order to do that,
See in here in precise we have an assertion right that assertion is
the thing that tells us whether or not there's room, right?
And so, what I'd like to do is figure out a way to sort of make sure
that I can ask the question of whether or not there is room and get
the answer back without actually having to call Push sighs.
Right?
Alternatively, what I could do is I could actually just make this an
if and I could make push size return 0.
I'm not sure.
Which one of those, I
Want to do.
It's a really good question.
And I'm not quite sure.
The reason it's a little complicated because as you can see, the
alignment offset sort of gets added to the size here.
So there's actually sort of a step an additional step that occurs.
It's not just you can't just use this assertion directly.
You have to actually compute this as well and so you know it's a
little bit of codification of do it that way and I'm trying to think
of you know do I want to like put it sort of make it more complicated.
I don't really know but it would look something like this.
I'd say, Okay, Arena has room, you know, four or something like that.
And this would actually be exactly the same code that you would be
calling, right?
So you basically pass it.
The exact same thing.
You would pass the push size.
It would do exactly the same thing and what it would return, right?
Is just the result of the recession if that makes sense.
So again exactly the same thing and just Returns the, the the result
of that assertion that
All it does.
And what I look at it and I think about this it looks like that's
really not that big of a deal because you could imagine doing this as
well, right.
You could imagine taking the memory index and going like Arena you
know, get Arena effective size or something or get effective size for
something like this.
So if you imagine passing these are values into something I could do
this part of it, pretty trivially.
As a separate thing and then return the size.
Like that.
And then this just becomes something pretty trivial where you have
Arena useless eyes, listening DeLorean size.
This size right here is just get effective size 4 and we pass the
arena, the size.
And the alignment, all this stuff goes away.
Make sense.
So that's, you know, that seems pretty reasonable to me for the most
part.
I don't know.
I probably was a little overzealous there, I feel like I might during
debugging want to inspect that sort of a variable.
So maybe that is a little bit, you know, more more my speed here, you
can sort of see, I would just literally do that replacement.
That seems us a little more, I like,
I like that better.
I'm pretty happy with that.
I would, I would give that some funds up.
I'm gonna get rid of the default parameter here because the only
people who should be calling this or people who actually know what the
alignment supposed to be in general, and that kind of looks like maybe
it's a little bit more.
It's a little more kosher in my in my, in my mind.
Ooh.
So at that point what we can do is we can make a function here that
would sort of be the equivalent again of of our push size, right?
Is the equivalent of this.
And this is like, push size with the allocation or something like
that.
What we'd want to do?
Excuse me.
Here is do something like while
Let's see Arena has been for so while we don't have room for whatever
the thing is that we're allocating, right?
So here's the size, here's the alignment.
And instead of passing the debug Arena, but we're probably passing
here is the debug State because we've got debug free frame or, whoops.
We've got your frame.
we need to be able to pass the
device state in there.
So this would take the debug state.
And we take these other guys and it's essentially saying we need to do
a push size, we want to push this much.
Here's the alignment that we need to use for it, right?
When we do this push size, and at this point, we should probably also
do this.
Because this is appearing everywhere now.
Right.
So when we do this, this guy push that I think I had seven minutes
left on the clock from where we started.
So I'm going to use them when I do this push sighs.
What I'm essentially going to do is say okay while you know there
isn't room for this thing.
I'm going to like three frames, right?
And I might also say that it's while we have room for something and
there is a frame to free, we would free the frame and then at the end
of it, all right, then
And we would call precise, right?
And we would try to allocate the memory.
So at the end of it, we actually just thunk through to our, you know,
memory allocator as you might expect.
And here's our results.
All up Lee, this is up, you know, makes perfect sense and there's
nothing particularly weird or odd about what I'm saying here, but you
can see.
So we've got this precise with the allocation we're doing our push
size here.
What we're essentially going to do is just say, all right, we're going
to keep going through here.
And try to free frames until we have enough memory, for whatever.
The thing is, we're allocating.
Usually, that would be only one frame.
You know I'm saying?
Because typically, after you for your frame, we'd have tons of space
for everything as we're allocating.
But yeah, you can see the structure of this.
We're just saying,
If we had memory for it already we'd never enter this while loop so
it's a non-issue assuming we do enter the while loop we freed the
frame.
Now if for some reason we're allocating some giant thing and you know
this should never actually happen in the code but if it did and we had
to free more than one frame, we could right let's sit in the while
loop just bring it.
But basically all we really need to fill in here in order to make this
work properly and be coherent with what we actually want to occur.
All we really need to know is where we get the frames from.
Right?
So we just need some way of knowing what the, you know, most
uninteresting frame as was truly the like the the oldest right?
And you can see we actually have that information, right?
We actually scoped it.
So what we can do is say, well, as long as the debug state has, oops,
And oldest frame.
Then we'll free that oldest frame, right?
But when we do that, we probably should also make sure right?
Because we're doing dealer frame here, frame to free.
Like so when we actually free, that old is frame, we also need to, you
know, Advanced this pointer because I believe frames or threaded,
right?
If I remember correctly, how we decided to make that work.
Whereas whoops frame.
Dude, dude, you can see we've got our next there.
So whenever we forget, we got to make the oldest frame point to the
next one over, but other than that, right?
It's totally frame.
Now there is one sort of a caveat here that I'll point out, which is
that it's in theory possible that the most recent frame was also, what
the oldest frame was.
So we also need to do a thing here, we say, well, if the debug State
most recent frame equals the frame,
Free then that also needs to be.
Well, I mean technically it needs to do this right.
What that will presumably always be zero because there shouldn't be
anything after the most recent frame.
Make sense.
So that's really it.
That's the entirety of it in terms of how that stuff is going to go.
Now, we have to make a free frame actually be pre declared, right?
That's got to be up here because we're calling it, restart collation.
I believe it's gone.
So that's all.
I'm so the last thing we need to do is actually just make a macro for
this so that people can call it with sort of the convenience of push
struct, which they're used to.
So here, it's like instead, it's going to be, you know, debug push
direct or something like that.
And what that's going to do is going to call this,
And that's it, that's really all we need to do, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and sort of push through this a little bit
further.
Whoops, alignment offset alignment offset.
Yeah, that's unfortunate.
So I have to call that twice, which is annoying.
All right.
Well.
That's fine fine, it's totally fine.
Don't worry about it.
You know, don't care.
Don't care.
All right, so sighs initialize.
That's a good point.
Thank you for catching that mr.
Compiler, this one is as well.
Why did it not?
Complain about that one.
Was Arena has room for a never called it's just because it's never
called it would have come but don't worry would have complained about
that and you get concerned compiler wasn't sleeping on the job.
It was doing its job it just probably never called that because we
haven't actually called debug push truck yet.
Okay.
So then we can just presumably just go through here and replace push
truck with debug push struct.
Right.
And then we'll just have to change the parameters to it, to be debug
State instead of the Arena.
So I believe like all of these are fine.
Right?
What happened there?
What's going on?
Okay, there we go.
Struct struct push struct.
And that's it.
So now all those should give me a compile error and they should give
me a compile error because remember, we needed it this to actually
pass in some different stuff.
So, in here, instead of passing the arena, this is actually the debug
state, right?
So that's got to go in there and otherwise everything else is kosher
so I believe all we will have to do to resolve any of these compile
errors is just get rid of that sort of.
You know, Finding of the Arena that we were doing.
Right.
Again really really straightforward.
I'm doing here.
Nothing particularly interesting at all.
Oh oh we've got a push copy.
Mmm, we've gotta push copy people.
That's unfortunate because that
And we would have to sort of also have debug push copy, which is not
the greatest right?
And you can see why like I was saying you can see why there's some
argument for building this into the arena because then now it's like
okay we wanted to use push copy and then you have to have a copy of
push copy as well, which is kind of annoying.
Right?
So that you know, that that makes me reconsider.
That, that makes me think.
Well, maybe I should just take that take this guy right here.
Here and put it in, I don't know, I don't know.
It's got some Merit, not gonna lie, definitely does so.
Yeah, let's let's let's just think about that for tomorrow, just keep
that in mind and I don't know, maybe we'll talk about in the Q&A a
little bit.
So yeah, Okay, so we've got to push copy when push copy comes to
shove, so we've got a debug push copy.
And debug push struct.
Yeah.
See how we're doing here?
Debug state.
Undeclared identifier, is that?
So, yeah, that is actually so
There we go.
And hopefully that's the last one.
Yeah, see happen again.
Right.
So that that actually does that does kind of make me want to to build
it in.
Just looking at how many times we were using that that that just does
that that really does make me kind of go like okay, you know, that's
that's
troubling.
Is it just Graphics calls?
Debug push struct.
See push wrecked Dubai.
Push struct.
do my push struct VAR, struct your books, copy
struct array.
Font so yeah.
So I think that argues, that argues pretty strongly for it.
I guess is what I'd say because I don't think we want to be in the
business of duplicating all of these.
It's just not you know that's just not a useful thing for us to be
doing and you know there could be plenty more of that down the road
right?
There's no reason to think that it would intentionally proliferate so
yeah so I don't love that but there we go you know that's that's all
we really
To do regardless.
And so now in theory, we should get to a point where we actually yeah.
There we go.
Should get to a point where we run out of memory and we try to free
variable group and we get to are not implemented.
So that's what we wanted and that's what we got and that's good but I
think what we want to do is just you know, put it to do here.
It's like move this into the Arena's proper so that everything doesn't
have to be duplicated.
so that all the
Macros and utilities don't have to be duplicated.
And so there's like I said, there's a few downsides to that, right?
It's not all positive but maybe we'll address that tomorrow.
All right, that's about it for now, we're out of time.
So let's go ahead and go to the questions and answers, right?
let's just just Cuban a
If anyone has a question of what I was talking about today, and we'll
see.
Let's see.
Have you heard of the dtrace tool?
It allows Dynamic tracing on running binaries and also Colonel not
available on Windows though.
No, I don't think I have.
I mean I'm mostly developed on windows so I don't tend to know much
about the Linux utilities, to be honest.
Alvin you mentioned in the pre stream, a dynamic memory and how does
that actually work?
Since we allocate memory, only once what happens when the arena is
full.
So all you do is you just make it so that you allocate in chunks.
So you allocate like I said you know 256 MB time or something or or 64
Meg's at a time or however much you want at a time and you just go
back to the operating system and get more memory if you want a dynamic
Arena, right?
There's nothing pretty much everything we've done.
You can actually do
With that with dynamic memory, allocation as well.
All you have to do is just take the Arenas and when they run out of
memory, they just ask the operating system for more, right?
So I was just trying to point out that like at some point I may show
how to do that because it's very simple and it, you know, people get
confused sometimes about the static allocation nature of things and
it's just like there's no the code actually all the code.
We've written doesn't actually have to change at all.
It can, it can actually work exactly the same with almost no
modification.
And so that was just
Nothing.
I was mentioning.
Mojo 123 x, you mentioned, the term Coalition.
This episode in several previous episodes.
Where exactly do you mean we use that term?
What I mean is that we the way the debug system is set up right now is
all of the game and engine code rights debug events into a
For and those debug answer totally raw.
They're like I entered a timing region and I exited a timing region,
right?
But at no point, does anyone know how long we actually spent in that
region?
So then after the fact, the collate, the collation part is going back
through that buffer and going, oh, I see a start and an end event.
I'm going to like pair those up together.
Take the difference between their clock values and produce like the
actual amount of time that was spent.
Out there.
That's like it's like collating like this putting the things in order
and understanding what they mean or whatever.
Right.
What keyboard do you use this keyboard?
Right here is a Das Keyboard three.
My current favorite keyboard is actually the Razer stealth tournament
Edition.
That's what I have on my other computer, the other room.
Could you elaborate a bit more on what memory alignment means?
Not probably right now because that was a whole, we talked about that
back in the episode where we talk about memory alignment.
Basically, it just means, you know, the memory address that you're
actually talking about, right?
You know, pointer or you know, everything stored in memory somewhere,
right?
So pointer is like an address in memory.
It's like, where stuff is stored.
Basically certain operations on certain CPUs.
Require those addresses to be aligned to a certain boundary.
So for example, if you had the address, you know, 16 the 16th B in
memory, it might be valid to do an operation on this 16th by in
memory, but it might not be valid to try to do that same operation on
the 13th, but invent in memory.
And the reason for that might be that the alignment that's required by
the processor is sixteen, byte boundaries.
Which is to say that the bound, the actual like pointers have to be
aligned every 16, right?
So, if I wanted to talk about a certain value as far as the process is
concerned, it might just be like, okay, it's got to be there at 0, 16
32.
So, you know, 48 64.
It's got to be at one of those locations.
It can't be in between, it can't be like off of that alignment, that's
what memory alignment is.
But that's a very brief explanation that we talked about that a bunch
an earlier episode.
So you'd want to
you want to go back and
look at that.
Elvin but wouldn't ask him to us from Ur, me expose more flavor points
and that's against the hmh memory philosophy.
Since the whole point of our scheme was that we're sure once we run
the game, we can't crash.
Well, yeah, like I said, I don't expect that we will necessarily do
that.
Meaning, I don't know that we will use Dynamic arenas.
Or the actual game storage, but a lot of people ask questions about it
and it's really trivial to show how to do and it's conceivable that
you could ship the game with it that way.
And it would basically just be like, okay, if there was a dial that
the user can set for how big you want the game world to be and we're
like well we let you set that to as big as doesn't crash your machine
or something, you know you could see doing that, you know.
I don't know.
I I don't think I probably will do that, but I'm just saying, you
know, we could it's theirs.
I just kind of wanted to get across the fact that
You don't have to take my memory philosophy, right?
Let's say you want your stuff to just dynamically grow and if it
crashes, it crashes.
That's what you want your thing to do.
The point is just that, that decision doesn't change the rest of the
code.
We wrote, you'd still could write it exactly the same way and I
probably would.
Right?
So the actual the, the two aspects there, the the fact that we're at,
we we the fact that we may want to allocate a
Big block of memory and then run and know that we, you know, never
would crash or run out of memory.
That fact doesn't actually change.
If we were to change that decision, it doesn't actually change the
rest of the code all the rest, the coast days, exactly the same for
the most part, and that's the important part.
K.
I'm always hesitant when using linked lists in engine code, and
gameplay code, because of their cash and friendliness, random access
memory and difficulty in debugging.
You'd have to dig down a node to find what you're looking for.
Do you think it's not that big of a deal and I'm worrying too much.
well, I guess what I would say is,
yes, you probably are worrying too much but no, you don't want to
completely unworthy about it is, I guess what I'd say.
in general, like,
Places in the code that might be hitting.
Pretty heavy, might take a significant amount of the execution time in
general you know probably don't want to be using linked lists that
much depending on the circumstance.
The sometimes you do right.
Sometimes things are the best thing, Etc.
So you don't want to design your system in such a way that you have to
use linked list somewhere or that.
The whole thing depends on it being linked lists.
Because then when you profile the game,
And find out that something is slow.
And then go oh the reason it's slow is because it's a linked list and
it's like you know to cash on.
And we need to make this an array or some kind of, you know, things
like that.
You have all this work.
You have to now do to fix that, that could be a problem.
But as long as you're using, you know, if you're just using linked
lists in a way, that's would be easily for your replace at any time
with something else.
Then I wouldn't even really be worried about that because, you know,
as long as it's free, you know, as long as it's reasonably simple for
you to just go I see there's a performance from here so I changed it
for a linked list to something more efficient.
That seems a totally fine thing, right?
On the other hand, I would also point out that the concept that linked
lists are slow.
You actually have to understand where the slowness might be coming
from or whether it actually affects you.
Because one of the reasons that people might see linked list as being
slower than they actually are, is that if in general, you're
allocating them very sparsely, then you know, you're pulling in a
different cache line every time and that, you know, can make them be.
Very slow, but if you allocate them out of an area where they're all
together already anyway, it may be that they're actually not that slow
because they're all kind of actually fairly cache coherent, right?
And the way that we do the memory Arenas, a lot of times you will be
allocating linked lists right next to each other potentially.
So there's other reasons why linked lists might not be as cash
unfriendly depending on how you actually do them.
And so that's a sort of separate issue.
But not really that related in general, I just say the takeaway is
Always be aware of what the cost will be for you to fix to change
whatever the thing is you're doing.
If it turns out to be performance problem, that's a very good way to
think about it because it lets, you know, as you're going through the
code, when you need to make performance decisions.
And so if you get to a piece of the code and you go, it would be
expensive here for me to change the type the way that I'm storing
these things.
That's a time to usually go.
Okay, I should probably stop and figure out what would be a good
performance store or into the storage mechanism and Implement that
from the start.
Rather than just doing whatever is most expedient.
But in most cases doing what's most expedient is actually probably the
best thing to do first and then come back to it later when you're
actually able to measure the performance.
And if there is a problem at that point, now you have the actual you
have actual metrics now, to work with and know what you're actually
trying to do.
Rather than guessing what you should be doing and whether a linked
list or an array, or a hash table or whatever is better there, right?
Jim 0 0 says I'm debugging on day 1 2001.
Do you use ENT instead of in 32 for any reason?
I I might have
It depends what the circumstance was.
Most of the time.
I don't use something like that.
This is going to be hard, right?
Because it's going to show me all the ants.
Yeah, this is bad.
Yes, it looking through the code here, like, for example, this this is
not.
I don't know why that's an in right?
Like that should probably be you and 32.
I would say this one would probably be you in 32.
Those are, those are probably should not be there to sign wave, that's
just some test code.
So I wouldn't really care about that too much in depth and handmade
debug, I don't know why.
Yeah, so these I don't, those are just over sites.
They we really shouldn't be using ants.
I feel like in most of these cases
Yeah.
Yeah, I don't know.
I don't know why we're using ants in these.
I would say that's just an oversight.
I don't know why we're using in those cases.
We could probably replace them and probably should eventually
and SZ lives like the stb lives that you specify a custom Malik free
function.
How would you integrate that into an arena based system?
Well, I guess it depends on what you mean by integrate into if you're
trying to say how do we actually get the memory out for them?
Well, you know what honestly I guess I'm not sure what you mean.
What do you mean by that?
Would be would be my like, what do you mean by?
How do you integrate into it?
Are you saying if the are you basically saying, if you have an arena
based system that you're using and then you are trying to call the stb
library to do something.
How do you specify malloc and free to it?
Is that what you're saying?
I guess.
Little bit.
Have you heard of VM?
No, I have not heard of He-Man.
Alvin if you want to use object pools, reusable, recyclable object,
for enemies.
For example, where would be the best place to store?
Them permanent or Transit memory?
I guess they wouldn't be in transient because the whole game shares
the same tool so I guess permanent yet.
Anything permanent and transient is just about whether or not it's
something that could be regenerated if you've got rid of it, right?
And so the transient storage is just things that if you blew it away
it could just be recreated on the next frame and it would be slower to
do that because it's where all the stuff gets cached like Britt maps
and everything.
So you don't
Want to throw it away, but if you did throw it away, it was fine.
Permanent storage is, where you store stuff, that actually is the
state of the game and can't go away, right?
Meaning if you deleted the permanent store then you lost your game
state so the you know the user just lost whatever the game was that
they were playing so the permanent store you know, that needs to stay
there.
Elvin reinterpret, static cast and dynamic cast.
Are they of any good?
Use?
Not really there.
There's I guess.
No, I mean not not really not that I can think of offhand.
They're just kind of extra verbosity for no real reason.
I mean
yeah, I would say know that they're pretty useless.
And to see, there are lives that allocating and freeing multiple
chunks of memory during runtime.
How would you specify Malik free for them in an arena based game like
handmade hero?
You can't really, I mean, basically, if you have a system that that
requires fully dynamic memory, allocation, then there's no way you can
use it in a system which is not about fully dynamic memory,
allocation.
Right.
Now, for certain circumstances you can just ignore it.
Like for example, if you know that there's a bounded amount of memory,
the thing will use, you can just get not have free do anything and you
can have Malik just be pushed size and then when you're done calling
through the library, you just get rid of all the memory, right?
You use the like temporary memory Point thing that we did.
So, you know, you can do that if you want to
But yet you can't you can't integrate those in.
It's one of the reasons I don't really like using most libraries is
they don't have a solid memory model most of the time.
So they don't really let you give them efficient ways to deal with
memory.
They always just expect fully dynamic memory, which is usually not
necessary mean if you actually look at what the library actually
needs, it doesn't usually actually need
Fully dynamic memory.
Usually needs like two stacks, 14 stuff that's going to keep and then
a temporary stack that's usually all it needs but you know what do you
do?
Jim 000.
The interviews in question, was a lot in Sim Deidre, rectangular going
to today and my version of the code is crashing on access violation
reading location, when casting pixel to m120 a tie at the start could
iterating with inverses in 32 years and no, although, that that sounds
to me like an alignment problem memory alignment problem, but I don't
actually know.
it could also be because the source memories not there,
But I don't know.
But no, that has nothing to do with interested in 32.
I would suspect
Because in thin 32 are the same thing.
So there's really no difference between typing either of those
What do you think of passed by reference and references?
I think they opposite the code, because it's harder now to see from
the calling site to find out if an object, is passed by value, or are
we actually passing an address of it to modify it?
I guess what I would say is I actually
References like everything else in C++.
We're like a harsh.
Like, they were like somebody who didn't really know how to program
like was like I should probably try to do something that fixes this
thing and then they made something that didn't really actually fix the
thing.
Right?
And what I mean by that is like, so there actually is one useful thing
about references and that is that they allow you to use
Semantics of something as if you actually had it even though it's
actually a pointer, right.
And the reason that's kind of nice is because it gets you.
It gets you to be able to do stuff like this, right?
It's like, okay,
I write some code and I'm like, you know,
I do some stuff where it's like, food at x equals, you know, Bart of X
plus, you know, something, whatever.
I don't know.
This sort of thing, right?
And then later on, I decide I'm going to pull this out into a helper
function.
So I copy the thing, but I want to I need to pass the food that its
operating on.
So now I have to change it to a pointer, right?
That sort of thing happens.
And so this gets annoying when there's like, tons of these, right?
And now, like, I copied them up in here, and it's like, ah, crap.
I gotta, like, change these all to like the thing, right?
It's just annoying.
And so, being able to do this,
Was actually kind of nice because it means that like when I call this
thing.
Now, the code is the same.
Even though I'm trying to do this like concept, I'm trying to do this.
Like I'm passing you a thing that I want you to modify so I'm not
trying to pass it by value, right?
The problem is and this is not really necessarily the thing they were
trying to solve with references either mind you.
This is why I say that like you know, original C++ design is just all
messed up.
But the thing about this is, it's actually just papering.
Over the thing you actually wanted which is, to not have Dot and arrow
in the first place.
Like, what I actually wanted to just have this code, just be the same
in both cases, right?
Because it is basically the same, you know, the compiler doesn't need
this information.
In fact, there's never such a thing as code that can compile like this
and this at the same time, so the compiler.
Always goes.
Oh it's a pointer.
It needed an arrow.
It could have just gone.
Like when it's a pointer, I use the dot as well.
And that would have been a much better use of that, right?
So yeah.
So I don't really like references.
They do have one nice aspect, I guess.
But still
All right, looks like we don't have any more questions so I will go
ahead and sort of wind it down like a little like wind-up toy that has
run out of spring if you know what I'm saying.
So thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's good to be back.
I hope you have all sort of gotten your programming sensibilities back
on track for this week of code.
I will be back here tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time again.
Hope, see you all back here on Twitch, and I guess I should also point
out the fact that it's a slightly short week.
We didn't have programming Monday, but will be programming Tuesday
through Friday, so and then will pretty much be back on a regular
schedule for the rest of the time.
I think, I don't know what we'll be doing about Thanksgiving.
That maybe will be off just Thanksgiving day.
I'm not sure.
But in general,
well, we should have a regular schedule from here till the holidays
till Christmas time.
All right, that's about it.
As always.
If you want to follow along at home, you can always
Pre-order the game on hand Mirador, get comes to the source code, and
so if you would like to actually play around with it yourself, that's
an easy way to do it.
We also have a forum site which has now been taken over by the
handmaid of guys, so it's hosted on their site and it seems to be
running pretty smoothly.
Now, you can see it's now at hero dot handmade, Dev dot org and it's
still kind of, you know, being worked on.
So there might be some some transition pains, as you can kind of see
See as it's coming imported but it seems like it's working pretty well
and and should be fully functional.
If it's not always let us know the the folks who are working out at
are pretty darn good and they managed to deal with Joomla nightmares
and all these other sorts of things pretty quickly.
So, if you report a bug, it tends to get fixed fixed presently.
We also have a patreon page.
Want to support the video series.
We have a tweetbot, the tweets, the schedule at you.
If you want to know, when this is going to be live, that's also a good
place to do it.
And we also have a convention coming up.
There's I think something like 25 tickets left.
I think at this point.
So it's almost sold out.
But if you would like to come to our convention, it's in Seattle, it's
coming up in just, what is it?
It's coming up.
It's right here.
So, it's just like, it's a little over two weeks away, two and a half
weeks away.
Let's say there's
There's still a chance to get some some tickets to it.
So if you type handmade con dot organ to your browser, you can go to
the site that that has the tickets on it and there are still some
available.
So again hope to see you guys back here tomorrow.
And of course, hope to see you at handmade Con in December until
either or both of those things have fun programming and I will see you
guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.