A clean record.
Alright.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on Twitch from scratch.
No engine.
No libraries.
No, nothing.
Just we can learn basically everything that is involved in the
complete sort of software stack of a game all the way down to the
hardware, which I think is actually really important and is becoming a
little bit more of a lost art these days.
So this product kind of attempt to bring that back to basically have
everything there from start to finish.
Anyone who wants to really study, how games work through the entire
pipeline, through the entire code base, have the opportunity to do so.
And I think it's really great to just in general for everyone to kind
of be aware of this sort of stuff.
I know.
It certainly, makes it much easier for me to do any kind of work that
I'm doing on games.
Whether it happens to be using libraries or happens to be using
engines or not, because you can always go in there and fix stuff.
You can debug so much more effectively.
You can know when something is suspicious, just when you have sort of
that that kind of, that kind of full background, so that's what we're
doing.
Doing here.
And we have basically finished sort of our prototyping layer.
We made a win32 layer the past couple weeks so that we can basically
do all of our own stuff right on top of Windows without having to use
any libraries or anything.
And it's pretty basic at this point.
It does basic sound output and basic bitmap output, but it and also it
does basic input from user devices, like keyboards and gamepads.
And that's really everything that we need to get a game up and
running.
So that's exactly what we're going to start doing here, but I felt
like
Like we had done a bunch of the hard work of like, picking through
windows and like dealing with all of its apis to do stuff.
And really, we were just doing that in order to get sound output bit
but map output and input into the thing.
And so what I thought would be nice to do tonight is to do something
fun with the windows API to kind of show.
Like, okay, when you're down there and you're doing crazy stuff, you
can actually do some cool things.
If you've done all of this yourself, and so what I wanted to show is
kind of like an
Example of something pretty cool you can do and it's going to be an
example of sort of something very useful to a game developer.
So if you are following along at home here on day 21, if you have
purchased the source code, using this handy, dandy pre-order button
here on handmade hero dot-org, you will get a link in your email, that
should have allowed you to.
Basically there's a link that comes when you pre-order the game and
that will always allow you to download the source code.
So save that link go there.
And there should
A day 20 zip file inside the source code ZIP.
If you unzip that one, that is the source code.
We're starting with.
So look for day 20 because every day we start with the previous day's
source code.
So if you unzip that into a directory, you will have exactly the same
source code that I am starting with now.
So you can follow along at home, which I know a lot of people like to
do.
So, let's go ahead in there and we have some stuff.
We have a few issues that I have my notebook that I want to address
from previous day's, but right now, I'm just going to go ahead.
This will get to them in the Q&A.
So I'm going to go ahead and jump right into like new stuff.
Sort of the fun stuff I want to do.
So.
All right.
So basically, one of the things that people often ask me, in fact,
they ask me this multiple times on the sort of about handmade hero.
They basically say, like, are you going to implement a scripting
language?
This is asked this has been asked many times.
Or more specifically, I suppose are you going to use a scripting
language?
And the answer is no, of course, we're not going to use a scripting
language, but the question of whether or not we were going to build a
scripting language.
Well that would still be making something from scratch so we could
decide to build our own scripting language if we want to but we have
to ask ourselves.
The question is building a scripting language really all that great.
I of an idea right?
And in order to know whether it's a great idea not you have to kind of
stop and ask yourself.
What do you think you're going to use this scripting language for?
And is it going to provide more benefits to you versus the downsides
of the scripting language has?
And of course, scripting languages have a lot of downsides that maybe
people don't realize right away, one of which is performance problems.
Because remember if you implement a scripting language, you are also
on the hook for ensuring that that scripting language is performant,
which may mean that you have to use just in time compilation or all
these other sorts of things that order.
If you know, if a significant amount of your game is written in the
scripting language, you're on the hook for that performance, and
that's something you have to be aware of, right?
It's
Not like see where, you know, how to optimize it and you've already
got tools to profile it in all these and optimizing compiler there to
back you up.
It's not like that.
When you're using a scripting language, you're on your own right.
And similarly with scripting languages.
You have to ask yourself.
What you going to do about debugging.
Do you have a debugger for the scripting language or you going to
write one yourself?
Are you going to use some third-party one?
And will that integrate properly with the debugger for the platform
that you're using?
Or you going to have to constantly ping-pong back and forth between
the buggers?
There's all sorts of things that could go wrong.
And so when you're talking about implementing a scripting language,
A huge number of costs that go with it.
And so you have to be very aware of those costs that doesn't
necessarily mean that you shouldn't do it, but it does mean, you have
to think very hard about whether or not it's a good decision for
handmade hero since we're doing everything from scratch.
I think it's kind of a no-brainer that it would be a bad decision.
Because we're certainly not going to want to take the time to write a
debugger, for the scripting language and an Optimizer for the
scripting language, compiler from schedule, a all blah, blah, blah
blah, blah.
All the things we have to do to do a really good job of using the
scripting language in a game.
We're not they do those things because that would take
A huge amount of time, out of learning stuff.
We want to learn, which is more about how to write the game code.
And so given that, that's the case.
I would then say well, okay, what are the reasons why people might
want a scripting language.
Like, what is a scripting language?
Good for y, or do they even think they need it?
And can we just go ahead and get those benefits without having to do
all of the work, right?
So I think one of the primary benefits of the scripting language is
that people perceive it to be easier to write things in a scripting
language.
I don't really know necessarily where that comes from so much because
I think it's actually pretty easy to write things and see if you make
the API to it.
So, I don't think we're going to have too much trouble writing, our
game code in C.
I think we're probably going to be fine with that.
But one of the other things that people often point to in scripting
languages, that's a benefit.
Is the fact that we can do things, like, edit the scripting language
while the game is running.
Now.
This is a pretty big bonus in a lot of cases, because if you can edit
the scripting language, while the game is running, you can tune
variables live on the Fly.
You don't have to try to, you know, exit recompile.
Go back into the game that sort of thing and you can also do stuff
like, well, if you're trying to debug the behavior of a boss,
Boss monster.
You can just go in there, you know, get when you get to the boss
monster and see this not working.
You can just right there.
Pop up the scripts or editing and see what the boss monster does and
change it.
Not stuff and it saves you from having to make a whole bunch of
scaffolding to allow you to like exit the game change some pasta
master code, jump back into the game, jump straight to the boss.
Monster actually deal with the stuff.
They're look see how it went.
Go.
Okay, it did work.
Jump back out, blah, blah, blah.
So there's kind of a lot of stuff there where it's like that ability
to just use to edit the code, right?
All of the game is pretty valuable.
Actually, that's a pretty big thing.
And so, there is something you can do there, right?
You can inside Dev studio, right?
If I open up Dev Studio, there's a thing called edit and continue,
right?
Which allows you to edit stuff inside, Deb through, you can set a
breakpoint.
You can edit some stuff and you can have it recompile.
And that works for some very limited cases, like unfortunately a lot
of the time and it continued doesn't really work.
Like if you're writing tons of new functions, and if you're actually
trying to really write new code edit and continue doesn't work.
It's usually
For small changes is the only thing that is really reliable for
otherwise it mostly just breaks.
So editing continue isn't really a good solution, but it's sort of
like what we would want.
Right?
What we'd like to be able to do is just kind of go like, all right,
the games running and we have the C code.
We want to just be able to edit the C code and have the game just keep
on running.
Right?
So the question is well, could we basically Implement our own version
of edit and continue, right?
Like is there some way that we could go ahead and do that where we
actually don't have to worry, you know?
We basically don't have to care about visual C++ and whether it can do
whatever it's supposed to be doing with this compilation step.
Could we actually make it so that we have what amounts to our own sort
of relatively foolproof editing continue.
And so what I'm going to do tonight is, I'm basically going to try to
implement that.
I'm going to try to implant a way where we can basically have our game
running, change the code live, and not have to restart the game to see
the results.
And just basically, let us kind of go from there and we'll see how far
we can get towards that goal, basically.
And I think that's kind of fun.
So I said tonight, Scott kind of time to do something fun rather than
spending all our time, doing stuff, just to get Windows, sort of as a
conduit working.
Let's see if we can actually use Windows to help us now to make
something pretty cool.
So the first thing that I want to do is go.
All right.
Well, what I know about the way that I've set up the game because I
think I've architected it pretty well is basically I've got this sort
of platform independent part here, right?
That's going to hold all of the game code.
It's going to hold that stuff that I want to be able to edit on the
Fly.
and then,
Gotta win 32 portion, which is separate.
So, the first thing that I'm going to want to do is I'm going to say,
well, could I in just split those two things apart?
So that we basically have one part.
That's the, the platform code that's compiled separately.
And one part that is the platform, not zip code that's compiled
separately and then maybe, you know, just merge them together and, you
know, can I do that in some way?
That doesn't Force us to unload to to kill the executable, and you've
already basically scene.
The answer to this question is yes, right?
Because you've already seen that.
We have a thing here, which is basically the load Library.
I don't know if you remember when we were talking about this kind of a
while back.
We have the ability to load code out of a library already.
Dynamically, right?
We can basically pass a file name.
That's one of these dll things, right?
That's something that that Windows is implemented.
We can load that in, we can call get proc address on it.
Right.
And get proc address will give us a pointer to a function that's in
there and
We can just call the function.
Right?
So if we want to do that, we could just do that with our own code.
So there's really no reason why I couldn't instead of compiling this
monolithically, as one translation unit.
I just compiled it as two separate translation units, one for the
platform code 14, the platform independent code, right?
And that platform independent piece of code.
I didn't just load as if it's a dll, I call into it, to do, whatever
it is, I needed to do.
And then
When when I want to refresh it, if I feel like it's needs to be
reloaded.
I can just close it.
I can just Free Library, which is the corresponding call it to load
Library.
I can just free that library and reload the new freshly compiled code
and I don't have to kill my executable.
Right?
I mean, it should just work.
So the reason that this is simple is because as you know, we're
basically passing in the game memory as a chunk.
Now, I've said a couple times at there's a lot of good reasons to do
this.
Well, this is a big one of them.
Since we're passing in all of the game memory, the game itself is not
input.
The, the get, the actual game code is never actually doing anything
with memory.
So if we just keep, if we just hold on to that game every which we've
allocated, we pass it to the dll when it needs to run.
We can unload that dll and we still have all the memory.
So if we then reload another dll, that's a new version of the game
code.
We can just call into that and pass it.
The same exact memory that the previous dll was using and poof.
It'll just go ahead and keep running in there.
Now.
There's a couple caveats of times when it doesn't.
Allow you to do that because depending on what your change in the C++
code, but for now, that's a pretty easy way to Envision a very simple
way to make this work.
So, what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to change our build up
at a very, very tiny amount, right?
Basically, instead of compiling this, this 64-bit, instead of
compiling it this way.
I'm Ashley going to compile two different things.
I'm going to compile the handmade dot CPP.
I'm going to compile that, and I'm going to compile the win32,
handmade.
Dot CPP.
Exactly like that.
So basically what happens here is inside this where we have this sort
of stuff here.
Right?
I'm effectively going to start to bifurcate these two code paths,
right?
I'm going to go ahead and take into handmade here.
O.h., I'm going to go ahead and pull the things that we actually had
pound to find out here, right?
I'm going to pull those into here like this.
So now I've basically got a should keep that at the top, so they're
not.
I've kind of got those out there.
This
Guy is still going to look at handmade .h, right?
This this guy still going to have to look at that.
It's going to need to see a couple of these things.
Right?
But now the it's no longer going to include this handmade dot CPP
anymore.
That's not going to happen.
So instead, handmade dot CPP is only going to happen inside actual
handmade dot CPP.
So it's going to be compiled separately.
We're not going to like pound include the CPP file into win32
handmade.
Right?
Does that make sense?
So then all I need to do in my building.
And there's a couple of things we're going to have to do here.
But basically all I have to do my hammer in my hand made here at I bet
it's figure out my build up that I should say.
It's I have to figure out what to pass to this seal thing to build.
One of these dlls, one of those dlls that we were loading before.
Basically the compiler has the ability to build dlls as well as well
as link with them and so on, like we were doing where we can import
libraries and doing stuff like that.
It has the ability to build dlls itself.
So, what I really want to do is just make it so that I can build that
dll as well.
And so, what I have to do there is, I believe it.
I think it's a pretty straightforward.
So actually, I believe it's just a dll switch to the Linker.
It's been a long time since I passed it, but I'm pretty sure there's
almost nothing to it.
It's like, yeah, it's just that / dll.
I believe that's a pretty much almost almost the entirety of all.
We're going to have to do so /.
Dll there, I think is all we're going to have to do and I don't think
we're really gonna have to do anything else.
We don't actually even need
Most of those other Libs there as because, because really, in fact, we
don't really need any of this stuff.
None of these common Linker flags are actually relevant to us.
I think all we actually need is the / dll.
So let's go ahead and take a look at what that does first.
Just so I can see what's going on here.
All right.
These guys are no longer internal.
Obviously.
These are actual linkage calls will have to deal with that in a second
here.
Let's see here.
So we gotta get rid of that because they're actually going to be
boarded.
This is the first time we'll ever have an exported function.
Let's take a look.
We've got those are not.
Yes, right.
These are the calls.
These are our calls back back into it.
Let's see here you go.
Platform, read entire file.
So these are no longer internal either.
Those are going to be like that and there we go.
Alright.
So now, I think besides having are unresolved externals.
I think we're in pretty good shape here.
Let's take a look at our error.
Win32 handmade as well because we were expecting, link are errors that
we're going to deal with a second, explain how to do with those.
It's like, if I just want to take a look at these.
Let's see here.
We've got right.
These are no longer internal.
These are called externally, although that's not really true.
Well, we'll see you in a second.
What we do with those, those are probably premature.
All right.
So basically, all I did was I just split the code into two compilation
units.
As you can see, there's basically places where they called each other
game, update, and render, and game set, and get sound samples.
And then the
The debug read free file memory, right?
Entire file, and, and read entire file.
These are basically the places where our two halves of our code called
each other.
And so, as you can see, now that we're compiling them separately.
We just get a bunch of liquor errors that tell us, you know, I can't
resolve the stuff anymore.
You're calling stuff.
That doesn't exist in the translation, you know, I don't know where to
find it and that's an error.
So, we have to do, is figure out ways to resolve these.
Now, the the to where the platform layer calls the game.
I just said how we can do that.
That's really straightforward for us to resolve.
We're going to treat it just like we treated xinput, where we're going
to load library and do that kind of stuff.
You can see here, where we basically have sort of these get proc
addresses, this sort of stuff.
That's all we really need to do.
So really, all we need to do here is basically do something where we
go win32, load game code, or something like this.
And all we're going to do with that is we're just going to do that.
Load library and ropes will call this handmade dot DL.
For now we can
Obviously, play with that a little bit later, handmade code or because
call this game code or game code.
Dll.
If that actually works, then we will try to do get proc addresses on
it and those get proc address calls will give us the pointers to those
exported functions that we wanted.
So basically, we're in here.
You can see, we've got game update and render and get sound samples.
All.
I'm going to do now is do the exact same trick we did.
X input.
It's going to be literally exactly the same.
It's this, this exact stuff right here.
Nothing.
Nothing else do it.
So all I'm going to do is basically say there is a game update and
render and that takes a name and it is exactly this function prototype
that we had here before.
So I'm just going to go ahead and make that like this.
Then I will make a typedef for it just like I did before and this will
be called game update.
8 and render, and then I will make a stub for it, just like I did
before.
So, this will be game update.
Oops, game update and render stub.
And of course, that doesn't need to actually return anything.
So, that's it.
That's really all I need to do there and we don't actually even need a
global variable for it.
I don't think we might do something slightly different than that.
So, I'm going to, I'm going to delete those, those do not need to be
there.
So, this is the entirety of what we
To do there and we'll get rid of that like that.
Okay.
So we're going to do that.
And then the other thing that we're going to do is we're going to do
the same thing for get sound samples.
So get sound samples.
Again, will be a game, get sound samples, and this will take a name
and then we're just going to use exact same function prototype that we
were using before for game.
Get sound samples only now, it'll do this and then I will do a typedef
of it.
Did I remember to remove the semicolon there?
No, I did not doesn't really matter, but I want to get rid of it
anyway.
Just to be cleaner.
You can have more than one semicolon at the end of the line.
It doesn't seem that anyone really cares a lot of the time, but just,
you know, just to keep it a little cleaner.
So this is game get sound samples, right?
And then I'm going to do a game, get sound samples.
Oops, get sound samples stuff.
So that's really about it.
Then what I would like to do because I don't see any reason why not?
Is I would like to then say, well,
We're going to do so, there's a couple different ways that I could
have done this.
In fact, you know what, maybe I'll do this slightly even a little bit
differently.
Instead of having stubs for these since, I don't actually really need
this stuff.
Well, yeah.
It's a little
It's a tough call.
Really is.
But you know what?
I think I'm going to.
I'm thinking to do one more.
I think I'm just going to go one more, and I'm going to do game get
functions.
Let's say called game get functions and basically game get functions
is just going to be something that basically returns its functions
else.
Do I need?
You know, I do I'm gonna have to its I'm conflicted.
You can hear it in my voice, you know, it's true, but I'm not I was
going to try a different way and I just wasn't sure.
I can't quite tell exactly which one I want but I'm gonna
Stick with the one that I was really doing.
So we're going to do it that way.
And that means that inside here.
I'm also going to go ahead and say that game get sound samples is
actually going to be one of these now, right?
So that's that.
So that will automatically Define that for us and game update and
render is also going to be one of those.
So there we go.
Like that.
And we may have a little bit of funkiness that we have to do there as
well.
That'll tell you about the second.
But yeah, so now hopefully we
Can still compiled and we can so that's good.
And now, inside here, what I do the load game code, remember?
I'm still including handmade .h just so I can see these type, these
defined types here.
Basically, what I want to be able to do now is I want to be able to
actually get proc address these things here.
So I'm going to try and load game, get sound samples want to load
that.
And that is a game.
Get sound samples pointer like that and that's going to load from our
game code.
Dll, right, so I want to do that.
And I'm going to make a little struct here which is win32 game code
and it's going to have pointers to both of these things.
It's going to have pointers to this.
Bat and pointer to this.
So that's get sound samples.
And this is game.
Well, actually don't need the board game anymore.
That's get sounds tables.
And this is update and render.
And basically, what I'm going to do here is just say that there's a
win, 3-2 game code struct.
Comes back from this, we have win32 game code.
That's the result.
And basically what happens is that right?
We will initialize to the sub functions, equals the stub there.
Salt this stuff there.
So basically get sound samples.
We will start off pointing just to stub function.
So things that don't do anything then, assuming we can actually load
it.
We will go ahead and do it this way so we can get our functions in
here.
So, get sound samples, will go there and game update and render will
go there.
Update and render like that and there we go.
Okay, so that's pretty good.
And then I will return that result back.
Okay.
So now what should be able to happen?
Just to start things off to get us sort of in position in Striking
Distance of what we want to do at least in the platform layer stuff.
I'm just going to do this sort of at the outset.
The first thing I'm going to do is just do this.
Now.
We're going to have to move this later because we want to we want to
load things on the fly.
But for now, what I'm going to do is just do this and then
Um, from then on basically I should have two errors here.
Yeah, I can just put do game code or just game update and render and
then the get sound samples right?
Can be game dot.
Get sound samples and let's see here.
So there we go.
So now our win32 platform layer compiles properly.
And basically what it's doing now is instead of actually calling
functions that were that are in its own, executables of the Linker
resolves.
I'm now what it does.
Is it leaves
Leaves those function calls.
It makes those function calls.
Go through pointers and those pointers.
We are loading inside this game code function.
So basically any time we want to, we could always just reload them,
right?
We could go ahead and fill on reload them.
And I also want to set us up for Success here to this, to the extent
possible by basically saying that, the dll itself will go up here.
And so that way we will track.
Basically, when we load it.
That we can basically free it later to load a new one, right?
That's so I just want to track that instead of it having be having it
be entirely local to this thing.
So, there we go.
Now we've got that stuff.
And what I want to do here again is also check to make sure that we
actually got these and that they're not bogus.
So, what I can do is basically have something in here which is like,
you know, is valid or something like this.
And basically, I can make is valid be equal to
to these two guys.
So in fact, you know what?
There's another thing I can do here which is, which will be cool.
So, we'll check to make sure we got both things and if we didn't get
both things, then it's invalid.
But what I can also do there as move this down here, right?
I can say if it's not valid, then set them to the sub function.
So no one fails.
So that's kind of nice and clean that'll work pretty well.
But now we at least can return to whether or not we actually think we
got the functions that we wanted to get.
So that seems like it should work.
Okay, for now and that will load that handmade.
Dll.
But now we have to deal with the reverse process, right?
How are we going to deal with that?
Because we can't get proc address back on our executable, or maybe we
could
We could load the executable in the dll.
Load a hand over that and reverse call into it, right?
We could do that, could do all sorts of fun things.
But if you think about it, really, there's no need to do that.
That would just be a waste of everyone's time.
Because if you think about it, when we pass in our structure here, we
pass in all these things.
When we call game update, and render everybody is getting the game
memory struct.
For example, we could just decide that.
That inside the game memory struct.
We also pass the pointers to the debug Services, right?
We can just just begin, just flat-out past those, right?
Because these things here don't actually have to be function calls.
They can just be pointers to function calls, right?
So we can do the exact same thing.
In the reverse only instead of having to get proc at just, then we
just pass them because we already have a pointer to the game code.
So when we call into it will just pass it.
Right.
It's it's totally simple.
It's trivial.
There's, there's no reason not to do it.
So,
Go ahead and do it.
So the debug services will just be done the exact same way.
Basically, we have debug platform, read, entire file.
And that's it for that.
We will type def that this way, right?
We just have to go ahead and no, wait, that's not right.
There.
We go, debug platform, read entire file, and that will just take this
guy here.
Okay, and then the same is true for the rest of these guys.
Debug platform.
Free file memory.
Oops.
That's no good.
That goes here.
So that will basically be the same thing again name.
Hi.
Def memory like that.
And this should be named as well.
Get those out of there.
Okay, the type deaths are good.
And the last one same thing.
So basically, instead of actually ever defining the functions in here.
This is right entire file, instead of actually doing that.
We're just going to not do that.
We're just going to Define what types they are and assume later that
someone will pass pointers of them to the game, right?
So right in
File.
There it is.
So now we have defined the types for those pointers and a macro that
defines something of that type, so that we can use that inside the
platform layer.
And basically, all we need to do now is just pass these to the game.
So I'm gonna stick them in game memory for now.
I'm just going to say inside game memory.
You actually also get basically pointers to all these things.
Debug.
Oh wait that tight.
Those are those are new.
Those are named wrong.
That is a typo.
A cap here.
This should be debugged platform, 3 file memory and debug platform,
right?
Entire file like that.
Okay.
So basically all we need to do is just actually pass pointers to each
of these things.
This
Right, that's it.
And so this will be debug platform, read, entire file, debug platform,
3 file memory.
And debug platform right entire file.
So we have those now and sort of what we've done.
Here is basically created our own little vtable.
If you think about it, it's sort of almost like making our own little
dispatch only instead of it having to be all C++ and weird.
We actually can see it and do whatever we want with it.
So now when we pass game memory.
We should just be able to call our stuff directly out of that.
What did I do?
I did something wrong here Undeclared.
Identifier, debug plant Loops.
That's no good.
Gotta pass the name.
There we go.
And then in these so anywhere we were calling those.
Now we can just we can just call them straight off of our memory,
right?
Just like that.
And that's it.
So basically,
I think that is basically all we need to do here, got to move that up
above there, because this actually calls that, that should be it for
that.
Alright, so now, all we have to do is actually initialize those in our
memory call.
So these should actually be these guys, here should actually be using
this macro because that way, if the macro change is, these will be
correct.
So, we've got free file memory and I'll rearrange the order here.
I like things to always be in the same order every
I don't know why, but I just like everything to be in the same order.
It's some kind of OCD tendency.
So anyway, we'll go ahead and do that.
So, there we go.
Debug platform, free file, memory braid, entire file will now be
defined but the macro.
So, again, this is just making it so that I don't have the same
parameter list in tons of different places, because that just makes
for more maintenance work for me, which I don't want to do.
So, there we go.
And now, if I build this, we should be good to go.
Yes, we have never actually when we created our game memory struct, we
haven't actually set the pointers in it.
So they'll all be pointing to 0.
Which means we'd crash immediately when we tried to call them.
We know, but I'd rather just not have to to go through that crash to
see that.
So what I'm going to do instead is just go ahead and initialize them
to what we would then go and do after we saw the crash.
So let's just skip that whole crash process.
If no one has any objections.
Basically, I'm just going to initialize those pointers so that when
the game gets the memory Struck it has each thing initialized
properly.
So that's it.
That's basically the end of it, right?
Don't think there's really anything else to do so.
Now we're actually compiling correctly.
But let's take a look to see if we actually got in our build
directory, what we wanted, right?
Because I don't actually know if we did or not.
So it doesn't look like we did because I passed that dll switch.
But you notice, we're still building an egg Z here and I don't want it
to build an egg Z.
That's not what it's supposed to do.
So I still, I'm not passing the correct things.
So let's let's double-check that.
I'm not doing something wrong.
So let's see here to maybe that because we're specifying other things,
that it's a problem.
I'm not entirely sure.
Let's take a look.
Let's take a look because all we really need to do now is make sure
that that's actually getting followed.
Is this something that you pass to their entry point must be defined?
That doesn't help us and if it's linked, what's going on there?
Why are we not?
Why are we not getting the dll that we asked for?
Because we asked for a dll and we're not getting one.
So, basically, all we have to do is decrypt, the magical switches and
then we will figure that out.
So it's still producing an egg's e-what.
Are my common, compiler Flags.
Let's see nothing suspicious there.
There's an output of the map file, which should probably
Be specified separately, but that's really not going to do it.
That's a separate thing entirely.
That's just, we will need those two output, two different things as
all.
But yeah, I don't see.
We're looks like we're out putting everything as you would expect.
So I'm not sure why it's disobeying, my dll call.
I do not actually know why.
It is disobeying that call.
So they're not producing the map properly, but it's still producing an
x z.
So let's double check.
Let's see here.
Module definition statement, the base and deal options together
equivalent to the library.
A dealer just going to its exports.
Yes.
I know we're going to do that in a second.
But what I want to know is why won't you build a dll from I just want
you to out.
I just want to see.
I just want to visually see the
You're outputting it CL Flags to make a dll.
So please tell me what to say.
Overflow.
Say here's your big chance to redeem yourself stackoverflow.
Be correct about something.
Let's take a look.
What is this?
This doesn't look?
This doesn't look useful.
This doesn't look useful at all.
Actually, no, no.
No, come on people.
How hard could this be?
I mean, seriously, there should just be, like, a thing.
That's like, here is how you build a deal.
Alright, I mean, how hard is this?
Normally?
What I do is I go I go open up one of my existing projects that builds
a dll and I look at what it does.
But of course, I'm trying to go through the steps.
I would have to go through if I didn't have anything.
So I can't actually do that.
So why mr.
Finicky, do you not see?
To want to do that.
It says right here, the deal option builds a dll is the main output
file.
I am passing it, but it doesn't actually seem to do anything.
Now if it's, if it's not followed by slash link, if I just do that, it
says entry point, must be defined.
So maybe what's happening?
I'm going to guess I'm going to hope this is my hope that this was
that tough passing.
It after the link thing actually makes it not work and this makes it
work because we don't specify a dll main which is
nothing, what we would actually probably need to do.
So, let's hope that this is the correct switch and we'll go add the
dll main and and then hope that that was actually doing it properly.
So I'm gonna, I'm gonna hope that that's true.
And then it's just like, if you put it after the slash link, it
doesn't work because because it doesn't.
All right.
So, basically what we need to do here is inside handmade dot CPP,
right?
We still have the problem of
We basically solved the problem that we need to make a win32 version.
So we have our win32 handmade sort of Library thing.
But we also have our win32 handmade game or something like that.
So we've got, we've based got to win32 things happening if that makes
sense.
So basically what I want to do because how should I say this,
executables have the same thing dlls have the same thing as
executables.
That's a good.
Set windows will still call us when even if we're loaded as a dll, it
will still call in to us for no real reason other than to give us a
chance to do startup stuff.
So really we don't actually need Windows to do that.
But Windows is going to do that.
So even though we're building a chunk of code that we don't actually
need it to jump into.
I don't know if there's a way to tell it, just don't bother jumping
into us.
So what we need to do is just put a little stub in there.
Now, we could do that in one of two ways.
In fact, maybe this is an easier way to do.
It, I don't know.
Like we could we could not.
This, we could just stick a stub at the bottom of handmade dot CPP,
right?
You could go in here and do something like this, but it maybe is a
little uglier, right?
We could do something like, say, okay, if it's handmade win32, right?
Then we just stick the stub in here because it isn't actually code
that anyone has to read and it could go below here.
I don't know how I feel about that.
Like I said, I like to keep the code segregated and multiple files,
but we could.
And so basically what we would need to do.
I'll do it in here and then we can kind of look at it and decide
whether we care about that and whether we want to move it out.
Basically, we've got this thing here, which is dll, Main, and dll,
Main basically is essentially the same as when main, right?
Basically, it's just a thing where this happens.
We have to include Windows .h to Define these things and that we just
go ahead and we have to process this call.
Now.
I don't actually think there's almost anything that you need to do.
I think it's all pretty route.
Let's take a look.
There's our community editions.
Do we have
Is there, there it is.
Using Dynamic link, libraries, creating a simple Dynamic link Library.
There should be just the bare minimum.
Yeah, of stuff that we would need to do in a dynamic link Library.
Let's see.
This doesn't seem to be.
This is not what I want.
I want something that just shows me the minimum set of things to do in
a dll main.
Let's see.
Here, let's see.
Here we go.
So basically this is what where Windows is going to call us back in
our dll, when that dll gets loaded into memory by another process,
which in this case is also going to be our process.
So basically these are the things that it's going to ask us to do
attach detach and so on, if basically saying okay process attached
thread attached thread to attach process detach so it'll call us at
this dll main every time a process or a thread starts using the dll or
stops using the dll we do.
To do anything because we're not going to master any resources, right?
The whole point of this platform not specific code is that it doesn't
do anything other than respond to calls from the platform layer
itself.
So really all we should have to do honestly is just return.
True.
It looks like there's absolutely nothing that we would have to do
here.
So I think we can just do that and leave it at that.
However,
Okay.
So what's the problem here?
If I actually compile this, it says entry point must be defined.
I have the dll main that you asked me for.
So why are you complaining?
This is the part where I'm not sure if the /d at Jude me, the / delos
actually working.
Of course, let's let's take a look here.
If I was to go into win32 handmade and put a
In Maine in here.
Would that compile?
And if it does yeah, we're sad so it's still not building a dll.
So Windows, why are you not building a dll?
Just tell me, you know, you don't have to be cagey.
Why not?
I really don't understand why.
Let's see.
What is the reason why?
I'm not sure.
I honestly don't know, I must be forgetting something.
It's going to be just the standard thing where you kind of slap your
head and go and feel stupid at the end of it.
But let's see here.
Let's see.
Surely.
There's just a simple DLo example or something that I can just see
what it is.
So we've done this.
That's but this is not the final example, is the source code need to
create a simple dll.
But this doesn't even require I guess.
So, is it just that we haven't exported any functions.
Is that the problem?
Well, I guess we're going to have to the anyway, so I'll talk about
that and we'll see.
We'll see if that's the case.
Alright, so basically what has to happen.
In order for a dll to export entry points.
Basically, because remember, the compiler is going to compile this
code.
It's going to Output a dll for us.
And a dll is something that's essentially executable code is
essentially the same as an x z, right, but it has table in it of
places in the code marked by strings.
So you can basically say get proc address like we did before pass it a
string, it will look at the dll and it's got a string table in there
that map strings two locations in the code so that you can basically
do linking at runtime.
I'm dynamically which is why it's called Dynamic link library.
And what we will have to do in order for this to happen is we will
have to actually have some things that are exported.
Now, one way to do things that are exported is to put decal spec dll
export in the code.
This is just some crazy syntactic stuff.
That Microsoft's compiler.
Basically uses to tell you that the thing is that is being exported
the function that it's tagged on is going to be exported, we can use
that.
But another thing we can,
Can do is we can just specify what the exports are directly.
And I don't actually remember exactly how to do those but they're
actually pretty straightforward.
If I remember correctly.
Basically, it's like yeah, it's this so you can actually just on the
link line.
If you don't want to cut up your code with Windows specific stuff,
which we'd like to minimize as much as possible.
You can use / export on the link line to basically say that a
particular piece of code is going to be / export.
Now.
There's one other, there's one caveat to that.
See you in a second, but basically / export.
I don't know where it's got the, the Define for that.
Should have it in here somewhere.
Let's see in this PC /.
Export blinkers switch.
Yeah.
Let's see here.
For its function.
My net is slow or maybe it's just a mistake and it's slow.
All right, so basically this right.
So basically what this does is you can basically say, Okay.
I want to export a particular name.
I want to export it and I can just give the name of the function
there.
But there's a caveat here that we'll see in a second basically.
Okay, I'll put it in and you could see what I mean.
So I'm going to do export entry name here.
I'm going to say that I want to export get sound samples because we
said we wanted to export that.
And I also want to export,
Game update and render, right?
So I just want to do those two things, right?
Well, okay, I guess I got to put them.
After the link line.
Like that.
Alright, so yeah, I just don't know.
I'm failing tonight.
This might be an ally of same moment because I am failing.
Just to know what the compiler switches are to do.
The thing that I actually needed to do.
I really need this thing to actually build a dll for me.
But it really doesn't seem to want to but now that I've got some
exports, it seems like it's actually doing it.
So maybe the whole time, it was really just upset about that.
I don't know, but it's still outputting an executable.
I can see that it's outputting an executable which is which is kind of
weird.
But anyway, all right, and it but it's even it's creating a lip.
Do you notice that?
So it's actually creating an import Library as if it was about to
build a deal and even an export to so, very strange, but let's just
finish what we were doing and then we'll go try to debug that some
more.
So anyway, I've got the exports here, game update render get sound
samples, but there's a rub basically, which is that we have not
actually marked up these
auctions.
To avoid having them be named mangled.
Now know, if you remember the name, mangling stuff.
I showed where C++ mangles the names in order to work with old-school.
See linkers.
There's this sort of whole process.
I talked about it in detail.
Hopefully you guys remember
So, if we look at what these functions actually get called, they ain't
called game that sound samples and game update, and rendered their
names, or something, totally different.
So in order to make sure that they don't essentially get.
That they don't get mangled in.
That way.
I can put a thing called extra and see in front of them if that makes
sense.
And what extra and see does.
And do not ask me where they came up with.
This particular syntax is very different from just about anything else
what extra and see does is it says, okay this function in particular
it needs to be following this the old-school sea convention.
Don't mangle the name, right?
And so if we take a look at what actually gets output, hopefully it
will get out, put it in the map as well so I can actually show you.
Dot map.
Let's see.
Update and render update and see.
What did I use that?
That's not what I meant to do is I used the wrong function function
their date and render.
Okay.
There we go.
So here's the simple demo of this.
So, before extern, see, game update and render, I'm going to do the
build.
I'm going to look at the map file, which remember I said, is the thing
that gets outputted that shows us where all our functions are.
And now, I look at what the names of these things are.
Well, here's the name mangled version of that, right?
It's total crazy town, right?
It's like it's not the name at all.
Okay, and so if I go in now and I add that extra in, see
See, you can see now that it will change it.
To what I actually wanted, which is just the straight name game update
and render game get sound samples, right?
So that's exactly what I wanted.
And that's it.
So, the only thing we have to do now is try to convince em SVC to
Output a DOT DL L.
Now, I suspect because it actually imported the I suspect because of
the way that it did this that we could actually load the executable
directly.
I feel like it's just naming it XZ or something.
But hold on a second.
Will actually try that and see.
So basically, if I go up here, instead of letting loading handmade dot
DL, I load, handmade .exe.
I just want to see what actually happens.
So let's go ahead and step into our code here.
When I load the game code, I want to see what happens.
Yeah, so it's opening up this, right?
It's opening up this guy and then it goes ahead and asks for game
update and render and it got it right.
So there we go.
And hey, look at that.
It's actually well.
No, actually, I think it's probably not quite working at that point
because we should have seen the we're not actually getting the game
code running.
Let's see there, but it actually got updated, render it, got an
address back for it and it got
Address back forums for sound samples as well.
So I'm not sure is valid.
Oh, right.
Typo.
Not valid then we overwrite it.
So let's take a look now.
Yeah, so who knows why we'll have to figure out why Windows is
deciding to extra to create an exe instead of a dll.
We don't know yet.
But basically doesn't matter for our current purposes.
Maybe we'll do it the Q&A because I'm sure someone on the stream has
already thought of what the problem is.
So basically what we're doing here is now we're actually loading our
own code.
Dynamically, right?
We're actually loading out of that XZ.
That was produced.
We're doing the load.
Sells this, Handmade by DX e, right.
So now what we could do, if we wanted to, we can make it so that we
can just reload that code on demand essentially rent.
So if we want to, we can say, okay, this is win32 load code.
We could also do something like this when pretty, to unload game code,
right?
Which would basically be taking this one through to game code thing
here and it will take one of these and
It just just flat-out, get rid of it.
Right?
So we've got our game code.
It's going to take a pointer to the game code and it's going to go
ahead and say
It's valid, right?
Well, actually I guess doesn't even need to do that.
It's going to go ahead and do a free library on game code dll.
Right, assuming that game code, dll was actually there we go, assuming
that it was actually there.
It's going to free it and then regardless of what it's going to do.
It'll just go ahead and set this stuff so that basically the game code
is no longer considered valid, right?
It's not valid anymore and the
It's the, everything is reset to the stuffs game.
Code update render.
Game code samples that and so that will unload our game code, right?
So let's see No Object file generated on login code on reference local
function.
Okay.
Well, that's fine because we're about to use it.
So now if we really wanted to be absurd, which I don't want to be but
I'm just going to demonstrate the fact that we could be absurd.
If we wanted to in theory we could go ahead and actually just load and
unload the
Code every time through this Loop, right?
There's absolutely no reason why we couldn't do that, right?
I can go in here and I can say, all right.
I'm going to take this game code and I'm going to load and I'm going
to unload it every time, right?
So there's the, there's the load.
Oops.
Sporadic.
Equest, there's the load.
There's the unload.
So what I'll do is, I'll go into our running thing at the top of the
loop.
I'll load the game code in.
And after we're done with our game Loop, I'll just unload it, right.
Which one of these.
Let's see here.
That's wild Global running.
So there we go.
That's the samples.
So, in theory, I think that'll actually work but it'd probably take
our frame rate, but I think it actually would work.
Let's find out.
Yeah, so it totally.
It's going to ruin things a bit for us.
But, you know, it appears to work and you can actually see it.
If you actually look in here.
If we look at our history, you can see us, unload, and load unload,
and load, unload and load all the time.
Right?
So basically, what's happening there is it's actually going to load
and unload.
This guy that stuff that we built in here all the time.
Now, what we can do is we can go in here and say now we we actually
have a problem.
I just realized
We still have a static variable in here, right?
That t sine should have gotten moved out to the game state, but it
never did.
So we need, we need to get rid of all our local persist because there
shouldn't have been any more of those.
And that's going to cause a problem because those things are in the
dll, so it gets loaded and unloaded they're going to reset every time.
So we've got a t sign here, let's go ahead and and fix that.
So that t sine actually gets initialized properly.
So in the game State, when we set the tone hurts, we're going to go
ahead and set the T sine equal to zero point zero.
And now when T sign gets used, we're actually going to use sort of the
game State T sign, right?
So
Here, game State, and all I'm doing, they're really very
straightforward.
Right?
I'm just, I had a old static variable, a local persistent variable,
and I don't want that because we don't want anything stored in the
dll.
We just want everything to come in in the standard memory like we
planned.
And so, I'm going to go ahead and do that.
And now, we just need to pass that game State.
Because presumably, this does not take that currently.
So here we go.
Game state do right up there.
So game output sound.
Now has to take the game state.
But other than that, everything is good and let's rerun it.
There we go.
Good as new and somehow that is so fast that we actually can do it
every frame.
I guess because their code is so small.
It's a little surprising, but it kind of works right now in theory and
I don't know because we're loading and unloading it so fast.
The compiler may not be able to slip in there to actually write the
file in theory.
What we should be able to do if we really want to write is while this
is running, we should now be able to do some really crazy town stuff.
Right, we should be able to come in here and say, okay.
I don't know the games running.
But if I wanted to, I could come in here and say that this was
actually going to be shifted up 16 instead, right when I compile that.
Yeah, so that's the problem is it can't ever open it for writing to
see how that's happening.
So I got to do the next of my process before we can really get to the
awesomeness.
All right, that's ok, because the next step is pretty darn trivial.
The next step is pretty darn trivial.
So all we have to do
Now, is we're loading, and unloading this code every frame, but we're
loading, and unloading it.
So fast that the compiler doesn't actually have a chance to write to
the file because it's always being opened by hours.
So, I guess one thing I could do.
Here's a, here's an easier way to do it than what I was going to do.
So let's let's actually try to verify that this works first and then
we'll go back and do it the fancier way because we're almost out of
time and so maybe the fancier way we'll have to wait till tomorrow.
So where is my load game code?
So here's my
I load game code.
So all I'm going to do is I'm going to load the game code before we
enter here, right?
But then I'm going to take the free code, the VM, the unload game
code, right?
And I'm actually just going to do at the top of the loop.
I'm going to do the unload game code and then I'm going to do the load
game code immediately after, right?
And I'm going to actually, I think what I want to do here.
Well, no, this is fine.
So we'll basically just do this, right?
So there we go.
That so
All I'm going to do here is I'm going to basically say, you know, I've
got a counter load counter and that load counter is going to be like
every 60 frames or something like that.
Right?
So every 2 seconds, maybe we'll make it a little bit more, right?
Like that.
And what I'm going to do here is basically say if the load counter is
greater than 120, then we'll reset the load counter so that we just do
it.
Every few times through the loop, if that makes sense, but that's all
we're going to do.
So we will say every time through the loop increment, the load
counter.
This will give us 120 frames.
30 frames a second is like four seconds.
That should give the compiler some time to open the file.
So that's that's that's all I did is I just said, all right, let's
let's only unload and load it that frequently if that makes sense.
So off we go.
Let's see.
Now if we can actually get the file to open at some point.
So, let's see here.
Can we do it?
No, we can't.
Well.
I wonder if that's a wonder if I'm doing something wrong in terms of
freeing the library because that could also be the case Free Library.
We are still, we are doing the Free Library.
Although this should actually do.
I should actually set this so that it's clear.
What's happening here for some reason?
That is oh well, duh.
I don't know why I thought that was going to make it any better.
Now that I think about it.
That's just dumb because basically yeah.
Basically, I still have to do one more step of the problem process
because this will still only leave it unlocked in between there just
because I'm not reloading it again.
Obviously, the dll will be locked while it's being used.
So I got to do one more step of the process.
Right?
What I gotta do is I gotta make it so that I'm not locking the thing
that the compiler is outputting to, right.
So the way that I'm going to do that is I'm just going to when I do
the reload, I'm just going to copy that file, right?
I'm just going to use the copy file call, which is a Windows call,
right?
Copy file.
Oh, and the copy file function, just basically takes two things and
does the copy.
Write, it just takes an existing file and a new file.
It copies from the existing to the new one.
That's it.
And you can pass it whether you want to fail if the new file exists or
not.
So if you want to always create a new one, which we know, so all I'm
going to do is basically like call.
There's something called.
Let's say handmade temp dot DL.
L.
And I'm going to copy handmade .exe to that handmade tap, right?
That's all I'm going to do.
Nothing for nothing.
We're there.
I'm gonna do that copy, right?
And the copy is going to allow me to lock a file.
That is not the file that the compiler is outputting to write pretty
straightforward.
So I know that'll work because now I'm not locking that file anymore.
I'm locking and unlocking a different file, and I know that I will do
the copy when I have it unlocked.
So let's take a look at this here.
Oops.
That's not good.
Looks like my copy did not work particularly.
Well, did that actually work?
Where's my copy file juror 0?
Because we're running in the data directory as well, aren't we?
Okay, so we need to do one more thing, which is a little janky.
Okay, but we can get we can get around that for the time being.
All right.
So basically the problem here though, is this stuff only works.
This is only without a path.
This is only going to work.
If this stuff is in the current directory, so what I need to do
temporarily is set the current director do that because until we do
the full thing, which I guess we'll have to again.
Wait till tomorrow to do.
We don't have, we don't know where we're looking for stuff.
We don't know where those dlls are going to be.
So we don't really want a handmade.
We don't really want to hard-code this path in there.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to actually just run it in the
build directory where everything is and that should actually work,
right?
And so now you can see if I look in here, it actually did that.
It did that?
Copy that?
I
To do and it should be doing that copy every so often, right?
Because remember I put a timer on the why didn't that lie?
Timer, it's a frame counter on there so that it will periodically do
it.
So now, when I go in here in theory, I should be able to actually
write to the file, but I don't actually know.
Let's see are going to program database handmade pdb.
Oh, but okay.
So we do have one more problem, which is that the the debugger itself
is locking.
Our
Pdb file as well, which is definitely not what we wanted it to do.
Oh debugger to bugger.
Well, alright so we can still make this happen in the short term.
Here.
We can run.
We can run our game outside of the debugger and we can do this.
I suppose.
Let's see here.
There we go.
So there you go.
This is now actually doing what we wanted it to do, which is basically
we can edit the code and have it update while we're running.
Right?
And we don't actually have to stop the executable.
And again, the state is all actually there as well.
Right?
There's no, we could get to the bus fight, change the code and see it
update in real time and without any actual without having to do
anything, right?
So, it's, it's sort of as good as having a scripting language, in some
sense.
It basically allows us if we want to to edit all the code and we can
do all sorts of weird stuff here, right?
We could decide that this was, you know, some other thing and that
would just be, you know, I don't know, whatever.
You can see whenever it updates.
We don't even know what it is, but you can play with the patterns here
and get pretty immediate feedback.
Now the feedbacks not quite instant because we're waiting for seconds
between reloads, but we'll see, we're out of time tonight.
What will see tomorrow?
Aro, when we do all the rest of the stuff that has to back this up
because we only just got it in with the wire tonight.
What we'll see tomorrow, when we do the rest of us at the back, step
is how to make that basically instantaneous.
So that as soon as we hit recompile, it will reload.
So there you go.
That was just something again.
Like I thought we deserved to do something fun because we had done so
much sort of just wrote stuff with the win32 API where we kind of just
had to play by its rules and do what it wanted us to do so that we
could get access to the stuff that we wanted to.
I thought maybe it'd be fun to do.
Something cool with the win32 API that lets us do something
interesting.
And this is not specific to win32.
You can do the same sorts of
On other platforms as well, because almost every platform supports
Dynamic linking.
So anyway, this is kind of kind of awesome.
I like this sort of thing because it just makes it feel a lot cooler
when you can code to just do that.
And then it's like, once you, once you change the thing, it I don't
know.
It just it just makes it cool.
So you can see.
Now we're only clearing like half the screen right?
Or whatever etcetera, but we've got a lot, this gets even diskettes
way cooler, so we'll do.
So much much cooler version of this, as well as some time soon.
Let's also do.
I don't know.
Let's, let's, let's let's play with the with the size of the gradient.
Maybe, it's just fun to watch it.
Go sometimes, right.
There's there's one that's sort of why writer write so on.
So, anyway, that's pretty cool.
I hope you enjoyed that little trick.
We're not done with it.
It's not nearly as cool.
It's going to be tomorrow, but we only barely got in there and also we
do not know.
I still don't know why it's outputting an egg Z.
I gotta go.
I'll go look at my other stuff and find out why?
Or, you know, I don't know because it's it's still seems to want to do
an X the export and I do not know why.
All right.
So anyway, there we go.
We've basically taken.
I mean, that was not very much work, right?
All we did.
We did it.
Extremely, you know, all the work that people put into scripting
languages and like at the end of the day, there's a lot of stuff.
You could just do and see if you just tried, right?
And so, this is an example.
Ample of how to do that.
And now you can reload all your code, not just your scripting language
code at runtime, right?
So we can reload all the engine code to if we want to which is going
to be pretty awesome.
Now, there's a problem of course, which is if the game crashes what do
you do?
But that's the thing.
We're going to take care of tomorrow.
So anyway, so for tonight, just to recap what we did, as we enter the
Q&A here.
Please make sure your questions includes senior ettore in them.
So I'll see them and try to keep them on what we did today or past.
But I'm just gonna do a quick recap here because I went pretty fast
for everything.
Basically, what we did is we took our build up at file.
We decided to build two things.
Instead of one thing.
We split the game, code into one, basically executable chunk, and the
platform code into another executable chunk.
Right?
We then have the platform executable chunk load.
And whenever it wants to it, will reload the game executable chunk.
It then calls Windows to ask it to give it the address of functions in
that junk in the trunk that loaded.
It says,
Are the, where's the sound samples function and the update and render
function because that's the two functions that I need to call.
It, gets us back from Windows, it calls them.
And when it calls them, it passes in a struct in addition to the
structure.
We already defined like the asking buffer and that sort of stuff.
In addition to those.
We also pass in any functions that we need it to call us back at,
right.
So, any calls that go back to the platform layer, which are only debug
calls at the moment.
But if we had any that we're actually real calls, we could pass those
right.
Those get passed in.
So that the game has pointers back to where the functions are in the
main executable as well.
That's all we did.
And then we just put in a simple frame counter so that every 120
frames, it tries to reload the game code.
That's all we did in the code proper at this time.
So there you go, pretty simple really straightforward.
If you architect the code correctly in the first place like we did,
this is Trivial and I hopefully you saw that was trivial.
In fact, most of the work we have to do is figuring out which
On switch to pass to cl to get it out.
Put the dll that was like, most of the time, but, yeah, but there you
go.
So I'll go to the questions now.
Okay.
So bunch of people say they think maybe /ld will tell it to Output a
deal on not an executable.
So let's try that and hope that they're right.
Because yeah, I don't we don't I mean we don't have to produce a deal
as you saw an executable works fine, but it just seems nicer to to do
a dll because that's I don't know why.
It's just that's what people do.
So let's try it LD.
Incremental link.
So one of the things we also, you know, I forgot to do this.
One of the things, we also should do on our common Linker, frags is
turn off the incremental Linker because since we build everything from
scratch, every time that's just wasting everyone's time.
Is it incremental know?
Okay.
So let's see.
I'm going to go in here to our build directory.
I'm going to delete a handmade star.
All right, so that's gone.
And then I am going to rebuild.
Let's see what we get here.
Yay.
Okay, thank you stream.
That is what we needed.
We just needed to specify some extra sauce here to just tell, I guess
the LD / eldest, which this this / DL else, which, I guess tells the
Linker doubt, put a dll but the /ld switch tells the compiler to do a
deal on this much market, so that it gets an exit name instead of a
deal.
I don't actually know the interaction of these switches.
I'm not sure it might be that we don't need this one anymore as well.
Like, once you pass this, it may automatically imply that I'm not
sure.
Let's take a look.
Yeah, so
Like we can just pass that.
So basically, I guess it's just if you happen to be calling CL which
is itself going to summon the Linker, you do /ld.
I guess is how that works.
I'm not sure.
But thank you stream for.
That's that's really all we needed to get that going.
So what we can do now is do what we want to do here, which is instead
of loading him a DOT exe.
We can load handmade dot DL l.
Okay, and I'm going to put the two dudes in here as well.
So Casey to do need to get the proper path here, right?
And to do automatic determination of when updates.
Snuggle those in there for tomorrow.
Okay.
Use a key, press to unload and keep pressed to load.
No, so we're going to do something better than a key.
Press to load/unload tomorrow.
So we should be we should be fine with that.
So we have small code right now.
How does dynamic linking and compiling to Annex e work with huge games
that are gigs.
Well, first of all, the reason most huge games are huge, is because
they are not written, right.
I know, that's kind of a strong thing to say, but basically like
Basically, this game will never get huge.
We will never have a 20 GB executable.
That's just not going to happen.
So we really don't have to worry about it.
The reason that that sort of thing happens is because of bad,
programming decisions, basically, and sometimes those, sometimes,
those bad, programming decisions aren't bad in the sense that like
they were made, because there's a thousand programmers on the project
and there's no way to actually get everyone to do the right thing.
So it was just better to have the thing be 20.
Then whatever.
And that's so I'm not trying to point the finger at people and say you
were stupid or anything.
You may well have been smart and it was the only thing that you could
do, but when you are architecting things properly, you will never
ever.
No matter how complex the game is.
You will never have a 20 GB executable.
That's just not going to happen.
So you're pretty much safe.
Let's see here.
For people suggesting find, first change notification.
Don't spoiler.
Tomorrow stream.
I'm not going to tell you what we're using.
We're going to use some stuff tomorrow.
That's for tomorrow.
No, spoilers.
Let's see here.
I always have problems with loops and how they work.
Have you in all your years of coding, learned an easy way to help with
loops.
That I do not totally understand CI 12.
I mean a loop is just very simple, a loop.
Basically is this
Write a loop is basically some point in your code.
And you do some code and then when you get to the end of it you go to
back to the to the point in the code, right?
And basically, the only thing that a loop is is a way of conveniently
writing like a while loop right where I have while you know, something
is true.
Do
Stuff, right.
Basically, a while loop.
All of these just get turned into this form.
This is just basically, if something is true go to top else.
Don't right.
So basically, this is a loop, the condition goes in here, right?
The stuff you do goes in here.
All these are and all all of see Loops are, is basically the stuff
that has to get done happens, right?
And in fact, in this case, we would skip the first one.
So while loop checks it first, so if something is true, it does the
stuff, right?
Then it goes to the, then it goes back to the top.
And if something isn't true, it just doesn't right.
So really, it's just, you can imagine it.
Just executing line by line.
I'm you can turn any Loop into just an if statement in a go to really
right.
There's not there's really nothing to it.
So, I don't know if you have a more specific question.
I could try to answer it.
But Loops you don't have to think of them as something special go to,
like jump is the only thing that actually exists.
Go to is the only thing that actually exists at the CPU.
Loops are purely syntactic sugar, that high-level language is put on
top of a go to.
That is all they are.
So yeah.
So yeah, let's take a look here.
Do you recommend playing around with creating dll files or is it?
Mainly used in specific cases?
No, I recommend playing around with them all the time.
Yeah, being able to dynamically load code is a great idea.
So play around with them.
See what you can do with them.
I mean, you saw how easy it is.
All you have to do is say, here's an entry point.
I needed exported and then you can get proc address it and off you go.
So, yeah, see what you can do with it.
I mean, go to town.
That's what I would say.
Let's see.
Can someone now create a dummy handmade dll and use it to intercept
the game update and render function to get a pointer to game?
Memory and change stuff is security.
Something you will cover in a later stream.
This is by ambiguous Panda.
So I don't know why that would be relevant.
So one of the important things so security is one of those things
where I don't feel like people really understand it.
Usually, they tend to think that something is more or less secure.
Based on a bunch of stuff that isn't actually relevant to its
security.
So, if you think about the, the threat model that you're talking
about, basically, I've got a handmade exe and I've got a handmade dll
and the only threat model that I've introduced.
Now that didn't exist previously would be, if for some reason, someone
had write privileges to handmade dll but didn't
Have write privileges to handmade exe since they were both installed
by the same user at the same time who installed the game in the same
directory.
I'm not exactly sure.
Why you would ever think it was less secure to load eggs out of two
files, executable code out of two files.
Then one.
It just really doesn't make any sense.
Right?
Because whoever overwrote handmade up dll could have just over wrote
handmade exe.
Right?
There's no reason for them to.
There's no reason for them to attack handmade dot DL because it
doesn't have any weaker security than hand me that exe had all virus
Checkers, understand that there's code in dll and x z.
So, there isn't such a thing as a place where it's like, checking one
of the other.
So basically, yeah, there's really no.
There's really no security hold there.
At least not one that I can think of.
So.
Also, I think security for games is silly, like that should just be
built in the OS.
The fact that the games have to even think about security is
ridiculous because security should Games should run in a sandbox.
They're not an application that interconnects.
So like the fact, you should be able to ship as many security holes as
you want in a game because game should always run us out.
Its Windows is entire fault that that isn't true.
That was just a colossal, a colossal boxing up.
As they say.
Let's see here.
Let's see.
I'm going to post this again because I'm sure mine got buried.
We have a tiny application right now.
So, with code that takes minutes to compile.
How do we do?
What we just did?
Okay.
So I'm going to say this again.
I already answered part of that question, but I'm an answer it again
because you asked it slightly differently this time.
You asked about taking this to compile.
If your code ever takes minutes to compile, you've done it.
Wrong code, should take less than 10 seconds to compile period.
If your code takes more than 10 seconds.
Compile.
You need to stop and figure out why you have written code that way
because that is a bad way to write code period.
And I know there's a lot of people who will disagree with that
statement, but they're wrong like I do not.
I've never encountered something.
So complicated that it could not compiled in less than 10 seconds.
So that's really all I can say.
I really don't care what it is.
Like, it's just compilers are extraordinarily fast and machines are
extraordinarily fast now and the reason that things take 10 minutes to
compile is because people decided to use all kinds of weird, template
metaprogramming nonsense and stuff that slows the compiler down
tremendously.
And if you go that route, then you basically have sacrificed all of
the benefits that you could have had, and it's just a really bad
programming.
Even so don't make that decision, never make that decision, and you
won't ever have to worry about it.
If you do, make that decision all
Rough and I really can't help you write your in a situation that you
sort of created and then you will have to do all sorts of things.
Like now you have to implement an entire scripting language and add
the butter and at Optimizer for scripting language because you made
the poor decision to write code that takes multiple minutes to
compile, right?
So yeah.
What can you do now?
What I will say is verify that you really are in that position.
Can you break your huge amount of code up into multiple dlls and only
reload the ones that changed, right?
Right, you know, can you make if you've got 20 Gigabytes of code, can
you break that into two hundred dlls and then you only rebuild one
dll, and it gets reloaded, right?
I mean, there's an option for you potentially, but there's a lot of
headaches that go around along with doing something like that.
So again, I don't know.
So, the right decision in my opinion is, if your code takes longer
than 10 seconds to compile.
You've done something wrong assume that that is true and build your
project from there.
Would you be able to load the deal though yourself using read file and
Implement get proc address as well?
Assuming there's an easy way to make the memory executable like em
map.
Yes, you totally can do that.
The reason I'm not doing that is because we would like the debugger to
understand the code.
So what you have to what you have to understand is that a debugger
runs by looking at the executable that it is debugging and loading,
corresponding debug info for
That executable when a dynamic link library is loaded.
That is a new set of code that is brought in and the debug information
for that code is not present in the debug info for the main
executable.
So, it has to go and find the debug information for that dll.
Now, the way that it does this is because loading, the dll through
Windows is standard hooks, right?
Load Library, Free Library, the debugger sees those happen and it
knows to go get the debug info when it sees those happen for the
Dlls that it's he's loading if we implement the load ourselves.
Then we get into a situation where the debugger doesn't know.
We've loaded that code.
So we can't load the debug information and we can't step through the
code that we've loaded, right?
You could go ahead and write a symbol server that the debugger
connected to and Implement your own symbol server, which made up for
this shortcoming or stuff like this potentially, which then faked the
symbols for the executable to look.
Like they were whatever the symbols were for the
Hidden code in some back-channel like you could do stuff to patch that
hole but it's a real long road if you decide to go down Route, so
basically the reason that we're using Windows to load this and the
reason that will use like other platforms as well, and we're Implement
like this on Linux will do the same thing in their way.
The reason that you do that.
Is specifically because we want the debugger to understand that we
loaded that code and to support us which it can do if we go through
the standard Channel.
Let us see.
Is this technique still possible without using the passing of a large
memory block between the dll and the X Z?
Well?
Well.
So, I believe the answer should generally be yes.
Let me, let me let me state it this way.
As long as the dll code always gets its memory from the main
executable.
You will be fine.
Now, there's multiple ways that this can happen, one way that it could
happen would be to do it the way that I'm doing it right now with the
does debug calls where when the dll gets loaded it basically gets
handed some pointers and then you call those pointers when you want
more memory.
Because that way all the memory is still allocated in the executable
and there's no issues with what happens when the dll gets unloaded.
but,
By default that is already sort of what happens in Windows because
what happens is when the dll gets loaded if you use.
Well, it's not really true if you're using static linking, I don't
know what happens if you just call new, like, or Malik directly from
the dll.
I think when you unload it it'll get freed.
If it was a statically linked C, runtime library in the dll.
Now what you can
Do is, you can change to using a dynamic C, runtime Library, which
means that both the executable and the dll that you load will share a
dll.
That is the C runtime Library.
So they both call into that.
But in order to do that, you would have to go onto the build line and
you'd have to change this - Mt to a minus MD or whatever it is.
I don't remember.
So, I mean, so the short answer is, yes, it certainly can work without
the monolithic block, but the answer is,
No, you can't just do it willy-nilly.
You have to actually think about where that memory is coming from and
make sure that it's coming from a place that won't get purged when the
dll gets unloaded, so you can definitely make it work, but just you
have to be aware that it's not free.
It does take a little bit of planning, but it's it still works.
Okay, what's next?
Does the dll prevent the compiler from inlining?
It prevents the compiler from inlining across the dll boundary, but as
you've noticed, we don't need that to happen.
Right?
We have like, basically our entire game runs inside this function,
right?
The entire game is going to be in here.
So you call game update and render and everything that happens in the
game is called off here.
So all of the in line that will have to happen in the game happens
inside the dll, we never need to in line across that boundary.
So we don't have to worry about that.
But know, if, for some reason you wanted to have lots of functions in
the dll that were small and were called from the platform layer and
you were counting on inlining, to make that fast, that is a problem
and that will not work, but you know, don't do that.
How are we going to implement dlls on Linux Mac?
They bait.
They basically have the same thing.
So they basically have shared libraries as well.
There's like
there's just they're just called different things, but that's the
same.
Let's see.
Are there vods for this series?
I just stumbled upon it and really want to catch up.
Yes, handmade, hero dot-org.
If you go to handmade hero dot or you will have everything that you
need basically news and forums, you click on that.
And then episode guide will have a bunch of stuff for you that you
need.
So that is what you want.
Let's see here.
I'm looking for a new question.
That is on top of the basic.
Are you ever going to write the platform layers for other platforms on
the stream in the far future?
Yes, at the moment.
If you just want a platform layer to use, you can go to sew and Hammer
here.or.
If you click on that news and forums thing again, there's a coating
resources page and people have already ported it to both sdl and Mac
OS native.
So if you want to just run it on other platform, that's actually
pretty trivial because people already did the hard work for you.
If you want to watch me pour it, it that won't happen for quite some
time because basically porting work is just straightforward.
Grimble work of, take the things we did in win32 and do them in Linux.
There's nothing, it's literally as uninteresting as it gets.
So now that we have one platform layer working.
I'm not going to spend any more time on platform layers until we go to
ship things.
But if you just want to get it running right now, you can go access
those resources.
Is the process roughly the same for doing the Linux equivalent with
shared libraries?
Having seen your windows version would a couple hours of Googling and
GCC clang, documentation, dignity likely to get me there or should I
be looking for something specific?
Yeah, I think so.
I don't know if David GAO is planning to do.
So, if you go again to coding resources, David guy who has done this
awesome thing called handmade penguin.
That if you go look on here, it's just it's got all sorts of stuff
that you want to know if you're doing.
Linux version of this.
In fact, it's probably I'm going to guess and I don't know, but I'm
going to guess that this is a better resource than looking at how I
will port to Linux because I'm less knowledge about Linux that he is,
I suspect.
So if he decides to do the dll loading, you may be able to just wait
for him to do it for you because he may already understand that stuff.
Really.
Well.
If not, then yes.
I do think that it shouldn't take too long to implement.
What I just did because you're just looking for three things, how to
export functions from something.
I'm in a way so that you could basically call the compiler and say,
Here's a make, a dynamic library with these functions exported.
Then you just need load library and get proc address well and free
library, right?
So you basically just have those things to do if you can find those,
that's all you need.
Right tomorrow.
We'll do some other fancier stuff.
And so you may need a couple other things, but, you know, if you just
want the basics,
The internet FTW says, you're a pound to find type of magic kind of
bugs me and that it hides, the arguments return type away from the
implementation.
How much of a win is having the signature in one place?
The answer is, it depends how many times it happens?
So for these, it's probably no big deal.
I would say, just if you don't like it, don't do it.
The the person who's asking the question is asking about these sorts
of things that I do to make it so that you never have.
Have to change what the parameters are in multiple places for a
callback.
And yeah, you you don't have to do that.
If you'd rather not do it, then you don't have to.
But there are certain cases where I would strongly advise that you do,
do it.
And those are places where you have lots of the same type of calls.
So for example, example, if you're making like an entity dispatch and
you've got 300 entity types in your system, you really want to use
this macro because if you decide to change the
Orders that go to an entity dispatch.
You really don't want to go change it.
300 times or more depending on the circumstance.
Let's see.
How does Windows manage memory in a dll?
Is there a dll process space where our variables may be?
A text or at?
How is Heap memory managed that is allocated from a dll.
So the answer is, I don't remember some of the specifics of that.
Basically, what happens is?
We had some mspaint going on here.
Yeah.
So, basically, what happens, let's take a 32-bit executable because
it's a little simpler to going to conceptualize 64-bit, such a much
bigger address space.
So basically, here's two gigabytes of memory.
And here's two gigabytes of memory here, totaling four gigabytes of
memory, which for 32 bits of address, space is all the address space.
There is right.
Four gigabytes is the maximum addressable memory for for a 32 bits
pointers, right?
So typically
What happens in Windows is you basically have the upper two gig?
So this is the 2gig with the high bit set.
The, the high 2gig is for the OS, and the low to gig is for you.
Right?
That's how that works.
So, as far as I know, what happens when you load a dll, is it just
flat-out picks a place in here and slams that dll code right on in
there.
And basically what it does is it uses a memory mapped file to
basically
map the file.
So if this is the disc, right?
If here's the disc, right?
You've got your eggs e is on disk somewhere, right?
There's the X Z.
And here's the dll is on disk somewhere.
Who knows where right?
Basically, what happens is, I shouldn't probably have drawn that quite
so soon.
Basically, what happens, right?
Is when you start up your XZ is mapped into here somewhere, right?
I'm not trying to say where I'm not trying to say that it slow.
I'm just saying somewhere in your address, space your eggs.
Is file gets mapped in and then your dlls file gets mapped in when you
load it, right?
And that is how the code gets mapped in now when you allocate memory.
Basically, there's stuff in here.
There's different ways of allocating memory, right?
If a dll were to call virtual a lock.
I don't know whether that counts towards the exit charge or the dll
charts.
So so this is why I say I don't remember the specifics well enough for
an egg Z.
If you call virtual Alec like we are, it basically takes some range of
your executable and reserves it for use as memory and you get back a
pointer to it.
So now the X Z is pointing to it.
When you leave when you when you call virtual free you can free it or
when your ex he dies, obviously that reservation.
And goes away and all of the information window stored about that page
goes away.
But with the dll, I don't know.
If it remembers virtual Alex from dlls are not my.
So my assumption is that it doesn't but I could be wrong about that.
My assumption is that you
Virtual Alec from a dll with Alec in here, in your memory space and
that it would just stay and when you unload the dll, it would still be
there and the XE could use it but I don't know if that's true.
The reason that I think that's true.
So I'll tell you why.
I think that's true, but you will have to go and verify it yourself.
So here's virtual Alec.
Right.
That's this is what it looks like and virtuality takes an address.
It says, this is where I want the memory to be.
It could be zero if you just want Windows to pick an address.
Here's how big I want it.
Here's the type of allocation I want and here's the memory protection
for it.
Right?
Well, nowhere in that code.
Did it have a module handle, right.
So when you call this Windows, doesn't actually know who's calling it.
Other than the information about the thread itself, but called.
Right, it has some way of determining, which thread called it, but
that's about it.
So, because that occurs, let's say we go ahead and do a get proc
address.
So, we load this dll and there's a procedure in here.
We do a get proc address and that procedure calls virtual Alec.
We do a get proc address in the XZ.
We now have a pointer into this code, right?
It's just a pointer.
It's just like, any other function pointer.
When we dispatch into that from the X Z and then it calls virtual
Alec.
I don't see how
How Windows would even know that the virtual Alec call was coming from
the DOL.
Does that make sense?
So, basically, my assumption is that that, like I said, you have to be
aware.
Like I was answering the person before it was saying, what happens if
you don't pass memory from the executable, yo, you have to be aware
that there's a difference of between code in the dll and code in the
XZ.
You have to be aware of it, but it doesn't mean that you have to
It doesn't mean that you can't just do all the things that you want to
do.
So here's the part that I don't know.
There are things called heaps that we aren't using right now.
Okay, and that kind of looks like herpes.
So let's try and draw that again.
So that it actually looks like heaps.
There we go.
Keeps our a different thing entirely heaps are not virtual.
Alec calls.
Heaps are basically things that have called virtual Alec in some way
and are now portioning out that virtual a lock for you as you ask for
stuff.
So they're more like a traditional memory allocator.
What, I don't know is if there's a heap created for the dll that by
default calls in the dll that are static, C, runtime Library,
allocation calls.
into it, at link time when the dll is linked, not dynamically time,
but statically Linked In, when the dlls produced, if there is a heap,
that is normally used that goes with the dll and that
Will be freed by Windows.
When the dll is unloaded.
I suspect that there is and I suspect that you would get into trouble
if you were relying on that.
So, for example, if you call new right, and the function new inside
this dll, when it was called gets compiled to calling and address
which uses a keep that is the Heap from the dll in some way.
I don't know, Wright uses a static variable.
That is the heat pointer that got allocated to dll main or God knows
what right?
Hopefully you can follow me why this is not ridiculous what I'm
saying, then it could very well be that that gets purged on exit.
So I guess what I would say is there's a lot of things that could be
going on here if you wanted to do stuff, other than what I showed you,
you should learn this stuff well, and then you should be able to do
it.
But as a rule of thumb, I would
I'd say that if you're only calling virtual a lock, I suspect, it
would never matter whether you called it from the exit, or the dll.
Because I don't think Windows knows which one you're doing.
If you use new or Malik on the other hand, those are not operating
system calls.
Those are calls that call into the CRT and so the same diagram again,
right?
Basically, you have to imagine there's a c runtime component of this,
So here's my x z and let's say that both the C runtime Library, both
my eggs e and my dll were statically linked with the c runtime
Library, not dynamically linked, right.
Then I look like this, the dll code has a see runtime library in the
XZ.
Has a certain time.
I'll bring it included in.
This is a static.
Let's say a static pointer.
To a heap that gets initialized at startup.
So there's a static heap, if there's a static Heap then that static
heat could very well be used by all the calls to Malik that happen in
this dll because remember the call to malloc exist.
Now there's there's code for Malik in both of these and both of them
can use a different static.
There's a static keep here as well, right?
So, depending on which compilation unit, you're in, you have resolved
your calls to Malik to be calling into different pieces of code at
runtime and all these calls to Malik may use this Heap and all these
clothes to Malik may use this Heap, which means, two things one, when
this dll gets unloaded all the heat goes away, that it ever Alec gone.
Poof.
Goodbye.
Right, but the other thing it means is you better be darn.
Sure.
That you never pass a pointer that you Mallet in the dll.
Over to the CRT where then would call free because now you're freeing
out of a heap.
That's not the Heap you allocated out of and the same goes vice versa.
Don't pass in a Malik here that's going to get freed on this guy's
Heap because now you got to keep mismatch.
So the solution that a lot of people use to fix that problem, which I
believe is actually a problem.
Like I said, I don't remember a lot of
Because I don't use any of it anymore, but point being.
You know, it's a thing.
Basically, what ends up happening is you've got an x z here, right?
You've got your dll, which is here.
They then have a CRT dll, so they link dynamically with the c runtime
library.
Now both of these guys call into mallik, right?
And now you're always using the same Heap because the staticky pointer
is the same for everybody.
So that is one benefit to using.
If you're doing crazy stuff like this.
What should I say crazy, but it's how most people do it?
I think it's crazy.
But if you were doing crazy stuff like that, that is one reason to use
a shared a dynamic link library for the dll because then everyone can
just malloc and free memory using standard new and delete or malloc
and free.
And it just works because they're all sharing the same.
Same code for the C runtime Library.
Okay, so we're basically done here.
We're out of time.
So let me just double check to see what we've got.
Let's see.
Let's see here.
Any Mouse doesn't Windows no.
By the instruction pointer is leading up to the virtual a lot call.
No, I mean it would have to walk the stack right in order to know who
it was because you're not passing, really anything that would identify
them.
I don't think so.
It could walk the stack and try to figure out, but, you know, or look
at the return value address, I guess.
And then you see which one that's in.
But, you know, that's, that's work that I don't think it does.
Does, I'm not sure but we'll see.
Again, I don't do any of that stuff because I don't want to rely on
operating system behavior that I don't have to.
So it's one of the reasons rather reasons.
I don't know that answer offhand is because I just don't do that
because it can only lead to portability problems in some sense.
If you start relying on stuff like that, I think.
So.
What is the?
So Gareth Lewin is saying that allocating cross-boundary is there's a
different reason for it, but I'm not sure he doesn't actually
Posted what it is.
So I'm not sure what the answer is, what he wanted me to say.
So, I don't know if there is a way he could, of course, there's a
delay.
So now he doesn't know that I'm asking him to post what he wants to
say, but let's see.
So the internet FTW, such a mess around the system, maintains a
purpose reference count for each dll.
Yes.
It does.
When the reference cap comes 0 DLC, unloaded from the virtual address
space of the process.
Yes.
It does.
The dll uses the stack.
The calling thread and the virtual address base of the calling
process.
Yes, the dll kids memory from the virtual address space of the calling
Yes.
so,
But that's what I'll just said, right?
So that sounds like, msdn is just saying what I said, is there
something that?
So I don't know.
If someone could tell me what they think is incorrect because I just
want to make sure before we end the stream that if there is something
incorrect that I could correct it or Point people to the correct
version of it, but that sounds exactly, correct.
so,
I got nothing.
So Gareth Lewin.
You you have a few more seconds here to tell me what it is.
You think is incorrect.
Otherwise, it will have to wait, I suppose till discussion on the
forums.
If someone thinks there's something incorrect about that explanation.
So I will go ahead and say that now.
So if we are basically at the end of the string, but I'm going to wait
a little bit, just to let the questions cup up.
Catch up there in case someone wants to type in what they think was
wrong about that explanation.
Based.
Only, if you go to handmade here a.org and obviously you can pre-order
The Source on here, if you'd like to if you'd like to follow along at
home, you can get the source code every night.
I push the source code every night so you can redownload it and see
where we were at.
If you'd like to follow along at home.
It makes it a lot easier, but you can also click on news and forums
and that will get you a little resource site.
Here.
It has the schedule for the week to post it on there.
It has an episode guide that you can use to catch up if you're or to
re reference older things.
It has a
Coding Resource page with has ports and stuff like that, but you can
go to do as well as other informational.
Good information, materials.
And finally, there's a Code discussion button here, which is where you
can post stuff.
Like if you think an explanation was incorrect or you just weren't
sure about something you could post on here and other people and me
read it and try to answer those questions to try and help out people
who are trying to learn.
So that's a good place to go to follow up.
So, let's see here.
Okay.
Let's see.
So, alright, Gareth Luwin says, the mistake.
Is that using Ms.
V.
CR T dot DL.
L won't solve the cross-boundary allocation issue.
So, if you could post a reference to why it doesn't, that would be
helpful because it definitely does in practice because I have worked
on projects in the past, which rely on that specific thing, if that
makes sense.
Well, the deal is loaded into the same outer space, as the
application, its own Statics are unique.
So I don't believe that's actually true.
I believe that it depends.
I believe that basically
The way that the dll gets mapped in is Statics, aren't all the same.
If that makes sense.
They can be defined as shared or not shared in.
Maybe I don't actually know exactly how that's implemented under the
hood, but I'm pretty sure M SV C, RT D LL actually does the right
thing there and we'll put like uses the same Heap for each instance of
the dll that's loaded.
At least that was the way that it used to work.
I'm like 99% sure about that.
So, yeah, but all right.
So if that's the only objection you had, I'm pretty sure that's not
actually true so we should but we can pick that up on the forums.
Now that I know what the thing is because that's a pretty small minor
thing.
So, let's go ahead and pick that up on the forums and we can see which
which which one is correct.
But other than that we are now over time by 15 minutes.
So I apologize for the slightly long string by just wanted to make
sure that was on there.
Thank you very much everyone for joining.
I hope you enjoyed this little sort of fun dive into how to make see
be editable at run time tomorrow.
We're going to do the super cool thing of making it super easy to
edit.
It run time, getting rid of sort of the, some of the hacky things.
We did just get it working today.
And so after that, we should be in a point where we can just
literally, leave the code up and running the whole time, if we want to
do.
I don't know if we should or not, but we could from now on too for the
most part except for a certain circumstances.
Well, we'll have to kind of do some reloading but well, there's some
other cool stuff tomorrow much like we did today.
I hope you enjoyed it and I will see you tomorrow at 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time when we will continue doing some some fun.
We're in 32 stuff.
All right.
Thanks everyone for joining me and I will see you tomorrow.