Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream and, you know, one of
the things I always say is, is no engines, no libraries because we're
not really allowed to use any of those, but one of the things that's
kind of annoying is that since we are programming, see, you know, we
call the C standard library for some things and that's not necessarily
something that we want to that we want to keep doing
So, you know, at some point we'd like to remove even the C runtime
Library, so we can literally be at, you know, absolutely zero
libraries except those that you know, are actually just calling him
the operating system like stuff that we literally can't not do
because, you know, if you want to run a game on Windows, well, you got
to ask Windows to open a window for you because it's Windows, right?
So we're kind of at that point where it's like, all right, you know,
maybe we got
Got to take the time soon to like, actually go replace the few see
Lauren time, Library functions.
We're actually using, which is like a couple of math functions and
like a string formatting because in our debug system, we were actually
using the string formatting to print stuff out and so you know it's
like not sure exactly what the timing of that needs to be.
So I've been thinking about it and I think what I'd like to do is
today since we're kind of in the middle of doing debug historical,
debug stuff.
I think what I'd like to do today is do a little bit of
Work with historical debug stuff and kind of get that to an
interesting place where we're kind of using it a little bit.
And then next week we might go ahead and do like actually replacing RC
runtime Library stuff.
Like we'll just go ahead and go.
All right, let's get the C runtime out, Library out of there.
Let's, let's build the utility functions that we actually need because
since the debug stuff is like kind of calling into that, as part of
the formatting, we can do, we'll do a little print formatting for
formatting our values and then we'll do, we'll just clean up the
couple.
Like, you know, I don't know what we've got in there for, like,
flooring functions and like, sine, and cosine, and maybe
Atan2.
I don't know what all the ones are we actually need but basically just
the math Library functions.
And then the string formatting and that's all, you know, we don't use
anything else from the C runtime Library.
So it's actually pretty minimal but we've got to replace it at some
point.
Hmm.
And that seems like probably a pretty good time to do that.
Alright, so let's go ahead and get started.
Today is day one, eighty and day 179.
Source code is obviously what I'm starting with today, so if you would
like to follow along, unpacked a 179, source code,
Code, that is where I am at.
So I'm going to go ahead and load this up here.
Let's go ahead and load up a handmade sln and you can see where we
left things off.
You can see that we've got a little debug, sort of a debug output
situation going on here, right?
Where were, you know, this was kind of thing we're working on.
We've got these like pretty Freecycle counters that we can drop in
there now and it tells us what's going on.
And in fact, even, you know, even just from this slight amount of
additional debug code, you can now see when like, ground chunks are
getting filled and stuff like that, right?
You can see your, we're actually seeing information that before we
wouldn't have known, right?
Like we would not have known anything about when these these ground
chunks were being.
The now we know, right?
And so, we're already kind of getting a better picture of how our
program works.
But like I said on the previous stream, it's still kind of hard to use
its, you know, it gives us a little bit more insight but it's not as
much as we would like, and we did the work yesterday of figuring out
how to keep these things tracked over time.
And in fact, what we're displaying here are actually the running
average has not the absolute you know the one on any particular frame.
So we're on our way to having sort of a much more instructive thing to
view here.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead and follow that down a
little bit, just keep going a little bit further on that and maybe
start to make use of those of those values that we can sort of see,
maybe a little bit of a
For lack of a term for like a Richard, maybe a little bit of a graph
over here or something so we could see spikes and maybe play around
with some other sorts of things that we would like to see.
So really just like, kind of start to take a look at, like, what could
we do to make this a little bit more useful.
Now that we've done the work of storing it properly, how can we
actually display it in a useful way, right?
So let's go ahead and
oops.
Open ourselves up and we made a handmade debug .h where we put this
stuff, you know, here it is.
But, you know, we kind of only have the very beginnings of something
to Output this information, right?
We update it here.
and actually,
We could do something interesting here.
We could move, we could just move this stuff out.
In fact, debug record, array counter.
That's the only one that needs to be declared there.
So we could in theory move, this guy, we could move this guy out so we
can start to actually put them in the correct place, right?
Yeah.
So what we would need to do here is we need to start including our
handmade debug dot CPP, somewhere, right?
So we need to go in here and start including that and then we can
start putting the debug code in there.
So it's not clogging up our main file and getting us confused about
what is like the debug code and what it's not, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and put that up.
Top potentially?
I don't know where that wants to be.
Will conceal what that later?
But, here we go.
So in here, this is our debug update.
We've also got some stuff where we would want to actually draw.
So, our drawing code, that should probably be separated out into the
debug stuff as well.
And that is, is all this stuff, right?
This is the stuff that we were working with debug text line and these
Global's and kanji kanji owl code points, of course, who can forget
kanji, owl code points.
And I'm just going to go ahead and grab the
stuff and move it over so we can sort of start to to talk about this
and look at it, you know, in a more concrete way.
Alright, so I'm going to grab this stuff and put it over here.
We've got this standard IO.
This is thing as talking about the earlier.
I'm like it would be nice to remove this and you can kind of see that.
You know, the reason we were using it is because we have to format
some debug information.
So I'm going to put that.
I'm going to put that up at the top here.
And you know, that's the thing that I was thinking, maybe next week we
should
We should tackle so that we don't rely on the C runtime Library.
because again,
if you're not using a libraries, you might as well go Whole Hog,
right?
Like why use the library that's built into the language?
If you're trying to use no libraries, we might as well not use any at
all.
And we can actually, we can just be even though it's the C runtime
library and it's like, sort of built-in.
It actually isn't like required to be built in.
We actually will probably be able to turn it off like even on the
build line so that it just never even gets linked into our program
which is kind of cool.
So you know,
Even though it's like in theory part of the language, it's really just
the lib that gets LinkedIn just like every other lip so you can
actually turn it off, which is pretty cool.
It's not like, you know, in some languages where it might be like.
So, so welded in there where you literally can't, I mean, you could
not call it, but it's there.
It's like in see if we don't call it, we can actually turn it off
completely.
So that's kind of nice.
All right, so let's take a look here at what we're doing right now.
I made a thing here which sort of creates the averages over time for
these things.
And you know what I'd like to do is maybe just just draw a graph of
the actual values over time, something like that.
So I'm going to, you know, right now we don't really have much in the
way of good utilities for this, but I'm going to try.
I'm just going to try pushing this through the renderer as something
where I can just draw like a bunch of
Little rectangles where the height of the rectangle maybe is the kind
of cost of that function over time something like that, right?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
So for each counter when I go through here and I do the snapshot index
and you know what else, the other thing I want to do?
I don't know that.
I like the idea of these things kind of going away.
I think I might want them always.
So I think what I'm going to do is even when something isn't being
used, you know what, I might also just go ahead.
And have that.
You know, kind of continue to print out.
So it looks like yeah, since this wants to the debug stuff, wants to
be able to access the render.
I'm going to go ahead and do that.
Oops, the asset system I should say, go ahead and put it back down the
bottom, okay?
So yeah, in here, that should mean that everything, you know, all the,
debug counters that we have.
So now we can see, like, actually all of them even when they're at
zero, they'll show up here.
And that way it'll be like stable.
And we can see the charts over time and stuff like that.
That's the only reason I'm thinking that.
All right, so if I want to do that, how would I do that?
How do I draw this information?
Well, you know, I'm trying to draw a triangle our graph here and
obviously these values kind of have wildly different sort of heights
that they have wildly different maximum values, right?
Because like, let's say I'm talking about drawing the cycle count, the
total cycle count spent in something.
Well, the total kit cycle counts,
Fenton something.
It's going to be drastically different from like if it's some core
render routine versus some like function that hardly got called at
all.
Right, and that isn't expensive.
So just having some fixed scale is not going to be really that useful.
So I think what I'll do instead write is I will take whatever the
maximum value is because remember I have the maximum of the cycle
count, right?
I have
The the maximum cycle, count for whatever counter I'm on, right?
After I do this, these snapshots, I know what that is.
So what I could do is I could say, oh, all right, you know what?
Let me run through the snapshots again.
Grab the cycle count out.
So now I know what that, what that psycho count is supposed to be.
And I could divide that by whatever the maximum cycle count is, right?
So, I could just say, oh, okay, you know, assuming the maximum cycle
count is greater than zero, then I can always take whatever the cycle
count was that we have.
I could divide it by like the, you know, the scale, right?
So the scale is going to be the inverse of the cycle cap.
Like so,
So this is just be scale times.
Right.
So, if I want to do that, I can say, all right, I have the the cycle
count I scale it, so that it will now be between 0 and 1, right?
Because even if it was the maximum cycle count ever seen throughout
all the snapshots, you know, it'll go, it would
it would only hit one.
So now I can just say, well, whatever the height is that I want the
chart to be, I can multiply this value out right by that.
So I can just do well.
And you know what?
I can just even bake that into the to the scale itself, right?
I can just have chart height / cycle count that's going to be the
scale, right?
And that'll map any value in the cycle count that we've seen to the
height.
Now, there's something that will see when I sort of get this working
with something that will see, that's possibly undesirable about what
I'm doing here, but I'd rather just kind of show it to you first and
then we can kind of decide what to do about it rather than sort of pre
solve the problem.
So okay.
And maybe we'll decide.
It's not a problem, there's also that.
So if I go through here and we do this sort of scaling operation,
right?
We now have the height that any given snapshot of the cycle count how
high that should be for our chart, right?
So this is going to be you know, you know this height.
And so what we want to do here is we want to draw a rectangle or
something, right?
We want to do a rectangle draw.
So I'm going to take a look at our render group.
We still have like
Bility to push a rectangle, right?
So, if I do a push-up, if I do a push wrecked here and yeah, I do a
push wrecked.
I should be able to just draw, you know, for every snapshot, I should
be able to draw like a little bar, right?
So it's kind of like a little bar graph going across, and I just drove
one pixel per snapshot.
And then, since there's, I think we said 120 snapshots from like that,
it has to be 120 pixels wide graph of stuff, right?
So again, really, really simple.
We have this sort of concept of debug render stuff and so what I like
to do is actually, you know, the debug text thing, right?
You know this debug text line thing.
You can quit sort of see on here that that we have a way of driving to
my chest.
I know what it does.
Is it kind of cues up into that render group.
It cues up, whatever it was that we were going to do for that
rectangle.
So I don't know.
We could do something like that or we could just go ahead and push it
directly.
I don't know which one we want to do but I suppose we probably want to
do something like this where we'd say, you know what, let's make sure
that we have both of these because if we don't ever do by Brenda
group, there's no
Went into doing any of this display stuff and write.
And then what we could do from there is
Just push rectangles directly onto that render group because we know
that render groups already in screen space and everything.
So it's going to be really, really convenient, right?
So in order to do that, we would want to probably do that after we
print the text, right?
So here's the text and then we know as well, that the text itself, if
we wanted to put it next to the text,
One problem with this is the text line is going to kind of Advance
itself down.
And so actually, I guess now, I think about it, we almost until we get
a better look.
Out system in here, which is something we probably want to do.
I guess, I want to do it kind of beforehand.
So I can sort of fake readout of the text of, I can figure out like
where this stuff actually is in terms of lines so that that align up,
right?
So wherever that that Baseline for the text is that's what I actually
want to know.
So this at why, right?
I want to know the at why.
Because the at why you know this this basically tells me this the
information that I want, right?
This is the
Stuff that's going to be relevant to this chart.
So you know the chart Min Y and the chart Max y or I guess I could
even say just the chart height the chart height should probably be the
size of a line of text, right?
And then the chart Min, why should probably be where the Baseline of
the text is or something like that.
Seems reasonable.
And get line advance for is maybe not the most reasonable thing
because you know, if you think about it the line advances is the whole
line.
I think, I probably want more like the the ascender.
Probably want something more like this.
So I suspect what I want is like the Ascender height should be the
chart height.
Something like that.
I would suspect is a little more correct.
Yeah.
The problem of course that I have is, I don't actually have the font
information at the moment, so that's something that.
Yeah, we would need to be able to, to grab out of that, debug text
line thing as well, and you can sort of start to see here.
I don't know if you get this.
Little tingling sensation but you kind of start to see here that like,
okay, you can you can imagine how this stuff is going to start to
collapse down a little like look at all this code you know there's way
too much of this nonsense going on here, right?
Like you could imagine me doing this stuff well that's tough.
All just seems a little too boilerplate e and like if we're going to
make a debug system where it's easy to print out stuff, we don't want
to be like querying the font all over the place as I've so, you know,
just kind of put that.
I mean, in fact,
I even put it to do here layout cash.
Font info etc.
For real debug display.
You know, that's something that we're going to want to sort of push
into going forwards, just to get a little bit better stuff happening
there.
Alright, so here we are down here now and we actually would have that
font info so now we, you know, we know the Ascender height and we can
figure out how high the chart should be.
So when we go to to push the rectangle on
We now have the ability to actually draw something.
I don't know.
I guess I'll draw something for the moment that is, is yellow, maybe
you know, maybe I'll even do something.
Maybe maybe I'll do something slightly different.
Maybe, I'll even do this and and then put the chart height in
Are so this proportion.
Will do grass times.
Scale.
There we go.
And this way, I have a number between 0 and 1.
That is how much of the towards the maximum this particular sample
took.
And I'll just shove that into the red Channel and that way we'll get
sort of a, you know, we'll get yellow when it's when it's at the max
and green when it's at the, you know,
When it's at the man.
Who knows, why?
Just because
And so then for setting the offset in the dimensions, the dimensions
for this thing, right?
Are going to be like, whatever the height is and why?
And I don't know how our rectangle routine.
We wrote it.
So long ago is probably a little janky, so we're going to have to play
with that a little bit and maybe actually go make sure our rectangle
chain is, is, you know, usable and is accurate enough to do, you know,
per pixel stuff.
Because it was one of the first things we wrote in probably isn't
But anyway so in order to figure out where this thing actually goes,
we need like you know whatever the chart left is plus the snapshot
Index, right?
That's going to be that's going to be the location we want to do and
why then we've got our chart Min Y and then RZ I think we don't really
need anything for and that should should in theory.
Do it assuming that's an in pixel space?
I assume.
So we need a chart left and we don't really have any idea what that
would be at the
A moment.
So I'm just going to hard code that in at the moment and we'll have to
sort of again, this is one of the things we're talking about, we talk
about layout, we probably want to start thinking about how to lay
things out.
So we can have text and charts and stuff embedded and have them sort
of all play nicely together.
But just for starters, for getting things working, let's start working
with this and get something actually usable first.
And then we can go kind of try to get a little fancier, right?
All right, so I don't know what this is going to do.
Let's see here.
Oh okay, so it looks like you know, we've kind of got like heartbeat
graphs at this point it would appear and so the dimensions are
rectangular routine.
It looks like it takes the center and goes out from there, which is
actually fine for the graph, but it also means it doesn't quite line
up with where things are, you know, what I mean?
So that's not, you know, that's not possible.
we the best that's that not necessarily the best idea, so there's that
But we could fix that pretty easily so maybe we can go ahead.
Maybe we go ahead and fix that just really quickly.
So assuming that the rectangle is being drawn at the
Better than what we would need to do is we would need to make the
dimension still stays the same, right?
But we need to offset the Min so that instead of being at the
Baseline, it's actually up by half the height, right?
Look, so
And that that's, you know, that's going to be more sane.
So now the stuff looks more like a proper bar chart, right?
And lines up a little bit more properly with, with the, with the
actual lines, to which they correspond.
Now, I don't know how accurately.
So let's go ahead and just double double check here with the kind of
use a little ruler.
Yeah.
So that, that looks right.
So I think we've got that under control
And it's all good.
So okay, so now we've got the ability to draw a little charts on the
side and what you'll notice is so the thing that there's a lot of
things to talk about now, but one thing that you'll notice is these
charts they change their scale, right?
They often times will change their scale and the reason that they
change their scale is because they're using whatever the maximum value
was for the
You know, 120 Cycles.
120 frames.
And what that means.
Is that in the case where there is some kind of a Performance Bike
like perhaps due to like the operating system, taking some time at
that particular moment in the code or something like this.
Or you know, who knows what happens?
Then?
You know, if there's a performance bike, that will reset the scale of
the graph for that, 120 frames, but as soon as that performance bike
falls out of the 120 Frame Window, the scale will jump back up again.
You know what I mean?
So, that's why I was saying there's a little bit of drinking as to how
this is done.
The problem, of course is it's not really obvious how you really want
to do this sort of thing, right?
You know I suspect that if I sat down for a long time and thought
about how to visualize the graphs as you know perfectly as possible we
come up with some rules and they might be stuff like okay, like filter
out outliers and just Mark those specially and then otherwise use the
average and blah blah blah.
But there's just
These concerns there.
Like you also can't compare the graphs to each other, the way that
they're here.
Because, you know, I can't tell because the scale is varying.
I can't tell if this, you know, versus this who's taking more time.
So there's just, you know, there's a ton of things like that that are
reasons why this is not probably the most fabulous possible thing that
you could do in the world, in terms of Visual Arts shade it.
But at least you can now see that we're, you know, properly recording
the debug data and that we can view it over time.
Okay, and we could also say that, you know, we can, we can make this
like bar with, you know, we could make it so simple.
You've got room, it could actually be like 4 pixels per or something
like that.
So if we wanted to we could make this B bar with and then we do like
the snapshot index times the bar with to move it over and we'd of
course, you know, always subtract away half the bar with because
that's the
Actually, I guess we would add half a well, you know what?
It doesn't matter.
We don't care.
Well, we would add it if we wanted to line up with the left Edge,
which we probably would want to do for layout purposes.
We'd have to add half the bar with, right?
So there are some like you know a little bit fatter right a little bit
fatter bar graphs just which are you know, maybe a little easier to
see and you know, an off you go and so then you can kind of see the
heartbeat going there and it's kind of entertaining if nothing else.
And you can totally see the you should spikes as well, right?
Look, you can see where the performance spikes are, they're pretty
clear?
So you know, like what was that right there?
Who knows?
And so, yeah, I assume I don't really know.
But I assume that that those are things that we not, we couldn't
really even track down and fix necessarily it.
That might just be the sort of the
The vagaries of trying to run something where you're on a machine
that's running like open broadcasting system in the background, not
sure.
But to say the least, it's probably not the case that in general were
actually getting the a spike that's happening because we happen to
call, you know, begin Sim in a more expensive way on one particular
time.
That's, you know, that's probably not the truth but who knows
Until we actually literally go investigate.
It's hard to say so.
All right.
That's you know, that's fairly interesting.
But what I'd like to do now is I'd like to kind of start looking at
this in a more holistic way.
You know, what Scott was kind of string to it's worth pointing out
here.
So do you see these nulls here, right?
Those nulls are anywhere where we don't, we've never actually hit the
performance counter because if you remember the only time that the
performance counter actually knows
Who actually is using that slot is if it actually gets called at least
once.
So, unfortunately, we'll never actually see the name show up here,
until it actually gets called once.
So, once I start doing some stuff right, and we actually get to, you
know, those if we ever do, if we ever do actually get to whatever that
thing was timing.
Then we can actually see what the what the performance counter there
was.
But until then we have no idea, right?
And that's just the nature of the way that we built the system.
Because since we want to be very easy to drop stuff in part of that
was that you only put code in just the one line, you know, where the
function is it says hey let's let's put the function in here, right?
And so we
Decide not to display those functions because then, you know, yeah, it
would be a little unstable as things, get added occasionally but
otherwise it would be that they'll never go away.
So what we could do is replace when we were doing our, if where we
decided, you know, whether to draw, debug out for something, in
particular, what we could do there is say all right,
Let's go ahead and test on a counter if it's got a function named then
we'll assume that it was actually filled in at least once, right?
And then that way we'll only see functions that have that we actually
have called at least one time so that their information is properly
filled.
Okay.
So again, pretty simple.
So now what I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead
And sort of take that concept.
A little bit further here.
What I'd like to do is make a sort of a stacked graph of some kind
something that kind of shows me over time who is taking you know what
time and in sort of a little more proportional way.
So what I want to do is the first first thing I'm going to do is I'm
going to go into
That, that debug sort of debug info that like, that watermarking
thing.
Remember, I made this, where the platform layer passes in sort of the,
as the stuff goes, like, what was the timing issue of, always ready?
What was the time when the input was processed?
What was the time when the game finished updating?
What was the time when the auto finish up thing?
What was the time when the frame rate was done and when did the frame
actually do loop back around to the top?
What I'd like to do is just save that as well as a separate set of
Of shots, right?
So inside handmade.
Debug .h, where we do these sort of snapshots.
What I want to do is make another one of those that's just sort of
outside, which is like frame and infos.
And that's just going to store all, you know, the same same sort of
deal, right?
It's going to store a snapshot one for every frame.
And so then what I'll do is whenever we call whenever we actually get
that, that strobe events at the end and we actually do sort of our
update
Debug update that I want to save a copy of that info, the comes in.
So the other thing that I'm going to do here right is I feel like well
I don't know I'd like to have this being here but it's pretty hard for
that to actually be true.
Well yeah, yeah yeah.
What I could do is I could just put this stuff at the bottom
Of the hammy.
Debug thing I suppose, right?
I could do something.
I suppose I could do something like this.
Now if you think this is a good idea, you might not and you might be
right, but I'm going to try it anyway.
And I'm going to come through here and grab him a debug.
I'm going to go ahead and put that here.
All right.
And then what I will do is I'll just move the stuff that we actually
kind of need to move out into the H file and there's some stuff in
there that we want to take care of separately.
Anyway, some stuff that's like some Global variables that we don't
really want to really be actually all that Global.
So yeah.
So let's see here.
Render group is Rock to render.
People just put forward to clear that no problem font ID that will
that one, that one doesn't really need to be there.
In fact, it's probably only that one that really needs to be there.
So these guys can stay here for now but we probably want to take care
of those in a slightly different way longer term.
Anyway, so debug reset would have to be actually put in
Our and debug reset.
I feel like debug reset.
Could almost happened during the strobe as well.
Well, I'm not going to fuss with it at the moment, but we maybe want
to consolidate that as well either.
There's the problem, it has to pass the buffer information in so, you
know, maybe it makes some sense to actually do it there.
But either way, I'm going to go ahead and put it out here so it can be
called and game asset structure needs to be pretty clear as well.
And lastly, overlay cycle counter.
So this I don't think we actually want to call this overlay cycle,
counters, what we actually want to call, this is, you know, over
ladybug or like debug overlay, right?
Because that's really, you know, that's really what that is.
And so, we'll call debug overlay here.
We'll put that in.
So, over ladybug account, oops.
Where is that?
Oh, yeah.
That is it overlays or counters.
So, we'll call this debug overlay and that will do all of our debug
overlay stuff and that could just leave it here and then we'll see how
we do.
Okay.
And so that should have done absolutely nothing right now.
We should just be back where we started but ready to kind of do a
little bit more with it.
All right, so if I come in to debug overlay, well, let me first, say
the information, if I come in to debug frame end, if I want to do the
snapshot capture, right?
I can go ahead.
Say, the debug state.
Now made the frame and infos that snapshot is just going to be equal
to whatever the info thing is that I got the you know, that I got
past, right?
So now we have a set of those that we can actually, you know, go back
through and draw.
So, in here,
when we do our, you know, when we do our counter display, after we do
all of the counter displays, we could then also put some in here where
we draw all of the debug info is that we've been passed so here, like
so,
There we go.
so, now we've got these frame end in foes
And that's just going to be whichever one, is the snapshot that we're
on and what I'd like to do is I'd like to draw that in sort of the
same way that I was driving anything, but because it's got multiple
pieces of information in it, right?
What I'd like to do is I'd like to make that be a little clearer and
you know what, I just realized to there's something we could do here.
That's kind of cool because I was thinking about this before.
Oh yeah, yeah.
I like this.
So I was thinking about this before and if you take a look at what
happens here, this debug frame, info frame, an info thing.
If you think about what's going to happen in terms of platform
porting, this is kind of
Specific to the win32 platform layer, right?
We kind of the order in which these go, the order in, which these sort
of strobe points go is very much specific to the win32 platform layer,
and that's not necessarily something that we want, right?
That's not necessarily
A particularly good.
Way to do things especially because it means that now like you know,
if some other platform layer doesn't do things in the same order or
doesn't do the same series of steps, this is kind of the wrong, you
know, it's the wrong abstraction for it, right?
So you know, a better thing to do here probably would be to have the
debug frame and info be something that was more like, well, maybe
something more, like,
There's a debug frame or a debug frame, timestamp.
And it's just like something like this, right?
Where it's like, what's the name of this particular time stamp?
And what's the clock at that point, right?
This is the the seconds.
And then what we could do when we pass this thing in, you know, is we
could do you 32 count, right?
And debug frame timestamp
Timestamp.
Like that.
I don't know if timestamp is timestamp or timestamp.
Does it really matter?
And so that way you just get some time stamps, you know, you just get
a certain number of them and you would know that that's how many you
have total, right?
And I suppose, one thing I could do is I could also maybe do it more
like this.
Where it does still get this piece of information, but that
information actually has these in it, right?
So I could do like,
Timestamp count and debug frame.
Timestamp, you know, timestamps something like that, I could do that.
And then just have these guys, you know, are all in there and this is
some known size thing so it doesn't have to actually it could just be
passed as a struct or it can be an address thing.
I don't know but we know we're not going to have that many of them.
Anyway, so we could just have that be fixed.
It doesn't matter that's entirely up, you know, we that we can play
with that later.
so if we did something like that,
Then this guy could just print those guys out as a stock graph, as
well.
And then, we could also have a thing in here, which was, like, for the
debug frame timestamp thing could have the timestamp count and an R32,
which is like total s.
So, like what the actual amount of time believed to have been taken on
that frame was.
And then we're all the time stamps were sort of along the along the
way, right?
And so if I did that, then what we do here is say all right,
Here is however you know big that chart thing is going to be I don't
know how big that's going to be but I want it, I think probably to be
pretty high.
So let's say it's something like 300 pixels tall or something like
that.
You know assuming that is 300 pixels tall as I go through here what
I'm going to want to do is make a set of stacked bars that kind of go
up and you know what?
Kind of layering all these things I want to do on here.
The other thing I'd like to do is I don't want to have to keep doing a
rectangle.
I don't want to have to keep doing rectangles that are about
centering.
I want to be able to do rectangles where I put the Min and Max Corner
in because that's a lot.
It's just a lot more convenient, right?
That's a lot nicer.
So we should probably make one of those as well but anyway, let me
just sketch out what I'm going to do here.
And then I'll kind of go through and fix everything that I just said
that I wanted to have happen.
That's not happening yet and since I'm the only one here, I'm going to
To be the one to do it.
So if we do this,
What I would want to do is for this info.
I want to go through the the timestamps right and I guess I've got
right.
I have that.
I have a scale and like before, and the scale is going to be the chart
height divided by the total s for that frame, right?
So for any given frame, well actually you know what, this is not even
true because this is since I want this to actually show me how long
each frame.
For real for reals.
What I'd rather do is say that the total chart height is going to be
like, you know, maybe let's say that the total charge height is
something like
60 milliseconds or something like this.
Like, suppose that, you know, are really bad frame time.
So, we've got 1,000 milliseconds, are, you know, in in a second,
right?
And so, if we were going to run at, like something really awful, like,
ten frame to S, right?
We'd have 100 milliseconds, taken up in a frame.
And so I'm going to make the chart height.
Be absolute.
So it's 100 milliseconds and so if something even someone sort somehow
we started running
That if somehow we started running even worse than that, we would
actually pop out through the top of the graph.
And in fact, maybe since, since our goal frame time since we don't
care, if we if we missed 30 frames a second we're just unhappy.
Maybe what I'll do is say instead let's just do it at 33.
So basically say like 33 milliseconds is our Target and so will
actually pop pop out of the graph if we're not actually hitting that
something like this, right?
So what I would say,
There is like okay 33 milliseconds is going to be what we want and so
in seconds right 33 milliseconds is, is that right?
It's like
That so yeah.
So that's how much time we would actually want to spend.
In order to keep hitting 30 frames/second.
And so, let's see what we need to do to do that, right?
So that's our scale that converts seconds to the Chart height.
Here is our info and now I want to draw a stock graph.
So what I want to do is say we've got, you know exactly this is
exactly the same thing happening here.
You know?
And so we would have sort of the proportions this.
Yeah.
This is the exactly the same thing and I guess again, I could do.
I could do sort of the, the proportion bit, where we, where we color
coded.
If I want to do the exact same thing, I could do that as well, right?
So that we multiply the chart hide out in here.
So I could do, literally this exact same thing.
And only this time instead of any sort of
any sort of cycle counts or anything like that.
What I'm doing is actually going through the timestamps here, right?
So, I have my timestamp index, and I'm going to go through the
timestamp index for a particular frame, which is this
And for each one of those and I really want to capitalize that Dona
Dona for each one of those.
I'm going to get out the debug frame.
Timestamp like so.
And I'm going to grab that out of the info structure.
Once I have that, I'm really just interested in this total s bit here.
Now there's something that's a little bit tricky.
And that is these things are timestamps based off of a base character,
right?
So I can't just draw What proportion, the actual time stamp would be,
I have to draw What proportion, the timestamp - whatever the previous
time stamp was, right?
So I have to know what the previous time stamp is because these are
like timestamps not not measured amounts of time.
And so, what I want to do for this sort of a situation is I want to
take the previous two.
I want to take whatever
This is like previous times that s whatever the previous time stamp
was.
So this seconds elapsed basically, is going to be the timestamps S -
whatever the previous time stamp s was and then
Yeah.
I mean that's that's really all there is to it and then the priest
timestamp s is going to be whatever this guy was.
So we're just kind of keeping a, you know, those the spans coming out.
So this seconds elapsed that's going to be gone by the scale to figure
out how it comes into the chart.
Then we're going to end under the chart height and then we're going to
do the same exact stuff here to draw it.
The only difference is now we're going to draw them stacked on top of
each other instead, right?
So
In order to do that.
Again, this this all has to be essentially the same.
So all of this is exactly the same only.
Now the chart left since this is kind of going underneath everything,
this could actually be whatever the, the actual leftmost Edge is, of
the debug stuff, which I believe we actually store in here somewhere.
Right.
Left Edge.
So we can just start at the left edge of the screen.
If you want to maybe we'll go in by 10 pixels for good measure or
something like that.
But basically otherwise the same we could then say
That our chart bottom is going to be wherever we were in at y, plus
the chart height.
Again, maybe, plus 10 pixels for good measures to move it down a
little bit.
And so, then this stuff I think should all be the same.
The bar with, I don't know if the bar was, should be maybe made Fairly
large.
I'm not sure.
That's a really good question, but we could also do bar spacing so we
could make it so that the bar is, were visibly, distinct, right?
We could do something like this.
And so if we did that, then we have bar spacing here.
We have bar width here,
And again, I'm not going to worry too much about the centering at the
moment.
Because I'd like to do something.
I'd like to change the way the way these
Angles are rendered relatively soon.
Okay, so the bar with is the bar with this height.
Is this height?
That's all right.
This proportions, fine.
And then this is chart Min y.
So whips short mean why?
Okay, so I think and this bar spacing plus the bar with its actually
that's its +5.
Yeah, I don't know what, I don't know what I was doing there.
I want to, I want to fix this stuff because I don't want to specify
these
This way.
It's all right, so that will draw the rectangles for us.
And so I think that's roughly you know, that's almost what we want.
The only problem is we're now you know we don't actually have it's
debug frame and info.
We don't actually keep track of the stuff this way, right?
And total side on maybe we don't eat till Cycles may be the last guy
kind of tells what so sexist, I don't know, doesn't really matter.
So let's see here.
So in here, now in our frame and info, we're actually going to do
something slightly different.
We're going to sort of have a little map.
I guess or something that just adds on to this.
It doesn't really even need to be a macro I suppose at some level I
could just be an inline here if it's like, you know, void take time
stamp or record time stamp, something like that.
Right?
And this thing is just going to take one of these debug and info
frame, and info things, and it'll just record whatever the time is,
right now, right?
It'll just insert a thing that records the timestamp in right now and
I'll do, you know, whatever the name is.
And so, that'll just do debug frame.
Timestamp oppressed all cert, obviously that my info timestamp count.
Is less than however, many there actually are to use.
And then I'll just say that.
The actual one I'm going to use time stamp.
Is, is that one?
I then just record the information here.
And I can put in that winter to wall clock, whatever the wall clock
thing is right win32.
I might have to make this a macro because I guess I don't know, it's
your to get wall clock.
I don't actually know introduce seconds, elapsed with her to get well
clock, I don't actually know how to do this seconds, a lap.
If I don't have what the last counter value was right, so I guess I do
want this.
Be more of a macro so that it can so that it can be placed in there
although I could just do it this way where you actually has passed the
second set.
And that's fine too.
Something like that, right?
Okay, so let's see here, when 32 Record Times,
And so in here, I would just do whatever that debug info thing is
frame and info.
I would just do the same exact thing I was doing but now I just pass
executable ready as a string, right?
Like so.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
So, let's just do that for everybody.
So there's input processed again.
Pass it in the spring string.
Save that.
Next one down.
That's going to be game updated.
Again, not doing anything interesting here, just literally doing
mechanical process of converting.
These timestamps, I hate the way I wish.
I wish I had a like, when I kill something in emacs, like I don't want
to actually lose what was in my paste buffer and there actually are
some ways to do it.
I fiddled with it and I never got the illest to work, right?
It was as making me grumpy.
Mr.
Fourth dimension, if you're out there, Alan
If you can solve that problem in your editor would be pretty sweet,
you know, it's just, I mean, you see what it is.
It's like, I I used cut and paste to remove something and then it
loses.
This thing that I wanted and I want that like I think Max has these
like register things for it.
I don't know.
It was just always kind of clumsy and I don't, I just want a nice like
easy-to-use thing, that that makes that work, okay, right, so yeah.
Okay, let's see here.
And then and a frame.
So that's the like total s would also be that value, right?
So that's going to be.
Here.
And frame.
Yeah, and I guess that I don't really need that total s there or maybe
I just don't put the marker in there.
I'm not sure, I'm not sure.
Which one of those things I should do.
Right.
It's just it's a little confusing.
I guess for.
Now, what I'll do is I just won't put the total s in there.
That's what I'll do for now.
And we'll see.
Maybe that's good, maybe it's not.
All right, we've got some issues to say the least that is not where my
chart should be showing up.
So let's go fix that.
Let's let's let's let's see if we can improve that just a little bit.
So there's my chart Min with the half this height, so that looks
Seems okay.
So what's the, oh, because that's supposed to go down by the chart
height?
That's the problem.
I went the wrong direction.
Always, you know, I'll never unlearn the fact that y goes down in
programming for some reason, you know, that's, I guess just in the old
days, I'm just so used to it that it's just, it's really hard for me
to kind of like,
it's hard for me too.
Switch into the wise up thing.
Even though that's the way Matthew.
No wants it to be and all that.
So we gotta go.
Why are we going higher?
It looks like we're going higher than our 300.
Oh, that's why.
But still looks like I'm kind of going up in there and I shouldn't be
right.
I should not be because I said that the chart I was 300.
I should only be drawing up that high.
No, I did it again.
Seriously WTF, right?
But doesn't make any sense.
Oh wait, no that, no, that, no, no, no, that was fine.
That's fine.
Because the chart Min, why?
I'm it's going to go down by that much.
So that was that was that was just me.
Being over the heart of myself.
It's fine.
It's totally fine.
So yeah, so why am I still overshooting there?
Because I feel like that's a little bit odd.
The chart Min, why should start at whatever the at why was for our
text line.
So all of our text lines are done then it moves down by whatever the
chart height was plus 10 and presumably, everyone is just doing that.
I guess maybe it were, maybe we're missing because
All this debug print out.
Maybe we're missing 30 frames a second.
I don't know.
We should probably draw.
We're 30 frames a second.
Actually is.
So let's do that as well.
Let's just go ahead and do a push wrecked on here for the 32nd bar,
right?
And so to do that, we just do chart left.
And we do chart, Min plus chart height.
So and then our bar width is, you know, the width of the, the graph
essentially it's going to be chart with plus 0.5 times.
You know, chart width and that's chart with sharp height and well
just make that the 1.0 like, the white, the white line.
And what we want to do, in fact, I guess I can put that down.
As well.
So what we want to do there is figure out what the chart with actually
is total and the chart with would just be the bar spacing times.
Ooh, hello times, however, many of these snapshots there are.
Right.
That's how that's how wide the signal end up being.
So that would at least give me words.
The Chart top of the charts supposed to be 0 and of course I probably
want to draw one.
So there that's that's it was a little overzealous with that.
So, sorry about that.
All right, so I guess it is in the right place and we're just we're
missing our frame rate by little.
It would appear, which is probably not that surprising given the fact
that we're dumping a bunch of this extra rendering onto the system.
We're not even compiling in release mode and it's, you know, got to
draw these rectangles and our rectangle drawing routine is not
optimized either.
Write our rectangle drawing routine is is actually
Incorrect.
Right is
of course, it is a little weird.
Yeah, I don't know.
So we'll have two will have to play around with this a little bit
more.
We're almost out of time for the stream.
So the next thing that you know, the other thing that I wanted to do
there was I just wanted to make it so that we could see those sort of
see the individual rectangles a little bit better.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and make it so that
they're colored distinctly and I guess the proportional stuff is not.
So interesting in this at least in this particular one.
Yeah, so I'm going to go ahead and try to color these things color
code them so that you can actually see the you know, them stacked on
top of each other.
And so in order to do that, I'm just going to do something like colors
and I'm going to have the different colors.
In here.
Just I'm just going to write them myself, right?
And so what I'm going to do is I'm just going to do like okay for now,
these are not particularly good colors.
We can we can kind of fix them later.
I guess I'll do V3 will do something like just you know, primaries
Secondaries.
Right.
And then maybe like another set that's like half with half these
Something like that.
So let's see.
So I want to do maybe 0.5 10 and then on the other side like so and
then maybe 51 and just do it here.
And I'm just putting in like some colors, right?
So we actually have just a set to work with.
So what I want to do here is say okay, whichever one of these
timestamps it is I'm going to grab that color.
So we'll do the color cure equals colors, you know, time-stamped and X
Mod array count color.
And then the color can just be, you know, V4 color one.
That makes sense.
And so, when I draw this thing out,
Hmm.
That does not look right at all.
So, I think we've got a bug in here, a little like somewhere, right?
I feel like this, this feels a little bit buggy.
This seconds, elapsed is the timestamp seconds - the proof, timestamp
seconds, and then pretest answer, you'll timestamp s.
That should be sort of taking, whatever that Delta is.
And I feel like if it's blue it's just saying we're always seeing just
the third one, are we sure that this is actually working properly.
This site equals red at this times.
This proportion, the
Jim is going to be out of 33 milliseconds.
Oh, I still haven't stacked them.
I never actually bothered to stack them.
So what we need to do here is we need to stack them up, right?
I need to do a thing where I take like, you know, stock Y and I need
to make that equal to what we were starting with, right?
Like so.
That's kind of obvious.
And then after I stack it, I've got to add on whatever our actual
height was the guy, right?
So there we go.
That's more like what you know I was thinking
And so you can kind of see actually that yeah, to no one's great
surprise.
We have one thing that's taking basically all of our time and that's
inside our game thing.
So we're going to have to do a little more work to make this more
useful, but you can sort of see what we're, what I'm starting to get
out there, right.
And eventually, what we need to do is we need to go ahead and make
this so that we can kind of
We can kind of break this up into stuff that's actually also in the
game, possibly tied into this sort of stuff, but you can sort of see,
we're starting to, we're starting to get into the realm of something
usable down there, but I'm out of time.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to just I want a space this
out a little bit more.
So I'm going to have some spacing there.
There we go.
But we're getting there, slowly.
But surely, we are getting there.
And, you know, I feel like, really the next step is to kind of unify
these two things and maybe try to figure out a way to get the, you
know, get the timestamps and the, get the timestamps in the count
blocks to be basically doing the same sort of stuff.
I'm not sure I know exactly how I want to do that yet.
It'll be interesting challenge.
All right.
Anyway, I'm going to go to the Q&A where I'm going to try to go to the
Q&A.
Anyway, let's see here.
CD.
I don't actually remember.
See, here we go.
And a.
All right.
So if you have any questions about what we did on today's stream,
Now would be a good time to ask it.
Go ahead and please put Q: in front of the question, and I will try to
answer it.
Questions.
Dollar questions.
In fact, I would actually go as so far as to say that there are zero
questions.
Hey, man.
So Friday, we can end early.
Braying Cruiser, doesn't the multi-core rendering screw up your
timing.
I don't think so.
I can't think of any reason why it would we made.
Sure our timers are multi-core safe.
So like this stuff right now, these things are not so interesting
because they just don't really time.
Anything granular enough, I want to go ahead and tie these two systems
together.
I really probably should do that, but these timers are thread safe.
As far as I know, we tried to design them to be.
So, so, basically, even though there's a bunch of threads, all running
the same stuff at the same time, in theory, all of the counters, just
some together and give us the right value.
Back in theory.
Can you briefly explain how it tracks, how long it takes the frame to
work and the render engine to work if rendering debug as part of that
work, also a suggestion, use a key to toggle, the display, to see the
game that we're not at that point yet.
So controlling, the debug view is not that separate topic for a
separate day.
It will not probably be keyboard oriented.
Maybe it might be more mousey.
Doesn't the multi-core rendering screw up your timing.
Our weight, our answer that one, can you please explain how it tracks?
How long it takes the frame to work and the render engine to work if
render the debug is part of that work.
So right now we don't have a way of eliminating the that part of the
work, right?
We can actually do that because we render the debug in a separate
pass.
So we will actually be able to figure that out to a certain extent,
right?
If you take a look here,
In fact, we can already do it this right here.
is, is the
Is the debug render group rendering, right?
So if we wanted to know how long that, that was taking,
We could do that.
So yeah.
So if you take a look here, it's like, okay.
Well, the debug rendering is taking a lot of the time because this is
inclusive, right?
This game update, and render is inclusive.
So, basically, debug rendering is taking almost all of our frame time
at the moment.
You know, what you gonna do.
So there's that part of that is again because it's probably doing the
rectangle and also, it's got a blit, all those little font things in
there.
So we're going to probably want a discount, you know, take that out of
the equation when we're actually trying to do timing stuff because
that's just, yeah.
I mean, there's not that whole much, we're gonna be able to do about
it.
I mean, we can also double check to see how bad it is if we actually
do an optimized build right now, we're not right?
So if
If I optimize some of that I don't know, but that's, it's still going
to be a problem, you know, no matter what we do.
But yeah, so you can see that right now.
The debug rendering is still taking about half the time but you can
also see that we totally hit our frame rate just fine.
So now we're like nice and locked at 30 Hertz but and and you can see
though we wouldn't make 60 hertz with a debug rendering on.
We would make 60 hertz with a debug rendering off easily, but with it
on we wouldn't at all and so it might be something where we want to
try and discount that a little bit so that we know that we're looking
at the debug, it doesn't
It doesn't skew our timing stuff too much but you know again, we'll
get there, we'll get there.
Go ahead of them.
Did you get for coders setup?
No, I'm gonna do it on stream.
So, you know, I'm going to reserve like doing the
New mapping to on stream.
So, like, when I get home early enough to do a longer, Priya madhu,
the bindings there.
So people can see.
Cute.
Chisholm.
Do you ever think it's amazing?
How hundreds of game hundreds of designers can screw up a project by
trying to be complex when Indy designers can make a better game in a
few months.
I mean, I don't know, I'm not really a game designer, so I I don't
really have too much of an opinion on that.
But I would point out that like
That's a little bit unfair.
Because if you're actually talking about Indie Games as a whole, there
are a lot of really poorly designed Indie Games as well.
I mean, there's like thousands of India games that came out this year,
90% of them are probably abhorrently awful, right?
But when you think of, when you say in D designer, make a better game
in a few months you're talking about out of all of those designs.
The few that we're good or maybe the designer was really good or they
just looked out in the game, was good.
Who knows, right?
And you're comparing those against this big Triple A game or whatever
that you're saying it was screwed up or something, right?
And it's a little bit unfair, right?
Because there's only a few AAA games.
There's not that many released every year, right?
And so it's tempting to look at any game say, oh there was like 20
indie games this year and they were all better than, you know.
No.
I don't know what Arkham City or Asylum Arkham Knight Batman runs
around, whatever.
I don't even know Metal Gear, Solid 12, The Legend of Zelda boat
riding simulation, right.
Whatever it is and you think that maybe the design was like over
complicated, or wasn't as good as this thing.
It's like well, yeah, but you know it's such a high stakes game and
there's so few of them that it's actually very
Believe that you know it's not going to come out that well just like
it's very likely that most indie games are not going to come out well
but because of the numbers game you know that's not so much what
happens plus since there's no wait.
Indie Games don't have a lot of weight to throw around.
They don't like if you want to revamp something in an indie game it's
very easy.
Often times.
You want to revamp something in AAA game.
You may be invalidating you know hundreds of millions of dollars worth
of
Of work.
You can't just change something last minute.
It doesn't work that way.
Because there's so much.
There's so much like pre, there's so much pipeline to the art
production, all these other things,
So, yeah, you know, am I going to defend AAA games?
Not necessarily but
I just want to point out that there's a lot of subtlety to that if you
actually think about it and it's not as simple as like.
Oh Triple A game designers are bad at their job.
That may also be the case sometimes, or even often, but don't don't
assume that it's always that it's not a Level Playing Field.
When you compare those two things are very different and so, you know,
it's complicated.
Griggs, you mentioned that the way you draw a Rex is not optimized,
what do you want to change?
So we you know we optimized our texture filling wreck, you know,
arbitrary scaling and rotating stuff, we optimized all that because we
had to and so that's runs really nice and fast now, but we never wrote
an optimized version of of the actual just draw rectangle without any
blip.
Just fill just filled rectangle.
Right, so it's not even doing for pixels at a time.
It's not even Cindy, right?
So we could probably speed up draw a rectangle of pretty dramatically,
right?
We could probably I would imagine speed it up quite a bit.
If we just if we just did Cindy you know, I would we get four times
faster I don't know but we could probably get quite a bit faster.
Stephen last because we're using rendering multiple threads, is it
saying that you're spending more Cycles in draw rectangle drug until
quickly than game update and render know?
So okay.
Again you have to understand like what our timers are actually timing
here, right?
So okay.
I'm sorry.
You know what?
I misunderstood your question.
I understand what you're asking now.
Yes, yes.
Is the answer.
So what happens here is game update and render is is doing one threads
worth of rendering, and then also waiting until all the other render
threads are done.
That's how that works, right?
And so the other render threads are
Actually going to sum up the total amount of time that they all spent
on their separate course.
Right?
So, if we're running on four cores at the same time or whatever, I
think we might be running on six.
Cores the same time right now.
I don't remember what we said, 28.
It's something High.
They're going to be that many more times longer because they, each of
them, you know, is counting a full that full parallel part of time.
So when you have eight things running in parallel,
Going to get eight times the amount of cycle, spent in that period of
time.
And so, if I understand what the way you're asking the question, I got
confused at first, the answer to what you're saying is, yes, that is
why
Why are you echoing to Locked Up temp in your batch file?
The reason we Echo to Locked Up temp in the batch file is for this
code reloading stuff.
Which, by the way, we have to re-enable for the debug system right
now, I'm pretty sure the debug system still doesn't actually work with
that stuff, which we can fix.
So, we should.
So what we do, when we need to reload the game,
when we need to reload the game, we use this locking mechanism because
visual C++, I seem to recall have some prop, has some issues with
loading the debug symbols or something like this.
So what we did is we made sure that when we do win32 load game code,
We check to make sure that the lock file is is not there.
If the lock files there, we won't try to do the load so we won't
Try to load something that's that.
Where the, where the debug info hasn't been written out yet because
what was happening.
If I remember correctly, is we would reload the game dll?
As soon as it was ready and the pdb, like the debug info hadn't been
finished, it wasn't finished writing like like visual sees compiler.
Haven't finished writing the debug info.
So we'd load the new dll.
Microsoft Visual Studio would go.
Oh, a new deal.
L was loaded in.
I'm going to go
The debug symbols for it, but it couldn't load the debug symbols
because they weren't written yet.
So, having that lock file there, just allows us to know, oh, the
compilation is not done yet.
Don't reload the dll, wait till it's done because otherwise Visual
Studio will will poop out.
Jeff Catalan.
So after lib Freedom week, we could reasonably easily Boot hhf
something like bare, metal loss and go all look ma, no os- sound, I
guess.
Well, I mean not really, it would depend on whether that bare, metal
OS.
Had initialization code for like the graphics subsystem, right?
Because we need, you know, we prepare the bitmaps in the sound, but we
need places to we need ways to hand that off to the hardware.
So I don't know anything about bare metal of s, but, you know, if it
didn't have those things, you have to write like the
Graphics card driver and the sound card driver yourself and stuff like
that.
So there might actually be a significant amount of work in there and
also like keyboard reading that sort of stuff.
So I don't know if bare metal OS is but
You know.
Well, he made here will be optimized for gpus, or are you sticking to
CP render?
Will that be an arduous task or pretty straightforward?
It won't be arduous, I don't know if it's straight forward, but it's
not arduous.
And I don't know, to what extent we will optimize for gpus that
remains to be seen.
If I have a simple app concept that I can't code myself because I'm a
scrub.
Is there any good way to get somebody to make an app?
For me?
That is somewhat simplistic and we split profits or even I just get
10%.
I don't care about the prophets.
I just want to help develop the app.
Well, I would say this is the wrong stream to ask that.
Obviously, this is a stream for people who want to do serious
programming themselves.
So I have no idea possibly.
but,
Yeah, pretty far out of the topic of this, this show.
Why are you not using visual studio to write your code?
It seems to be a Windows machine.
You're working on.
I don't like visual Studios editor.
So, it's the debugger.
I mean, that's, we do use the debugger, it's the best of bugger on
Windows that I know of.
So, we use that, but I don't like it as a code editor so I don't use
it.
All right.
We all good.
I think that's it folks.
I think that is it.
So I'm going to go ahead and close out of here, right?
Okay, everyone, thanks very much for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the series at home,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and it
comes to the source code, even right now.
So you can follow along, even when we're just building the engine and
we added a new feature this week that people have been requesting for
a while.
So in addition to downloading zip files of the source for every day,
we also now have a GitHub repository.
And so, if you would like to use GitHub to access the handmade hero
source code, when you pre-order, there will be an access code that you
can use and instructional text file.
So on that, send owl, you know, if you preorder, you'll get a page
That you can use to download handmade hero.
The art assets, all that stuff.
There's also a GitHub now and they'll be an access code for your good.
You can use to authorize your username on GitHub and so look for that
if you're someone who already pre-ordered the source code if you go
back to your sin dowel page, right?
And if you don't know where that is you can always do this.
You can, you can take the email address, you used for the order and
put it in this habit, resent thing, you can go back to your send out
page and there will be a new there.
You know, it will have added at the bottom a access code.
And the text file with the instructions on how to authorize yourself.
So, if GitHub is something that you've been asking for that, you want
to use to stay in sync with the source code, you can now get on those
private repositories just by putting your username into that
authorization system.
So that's another option for you, as well.
As always.
We also have a patreon if you want to support the video series, we
also have a forum site that you can go to ask questions, get people
who've done ports, to Mac and Linux is like that.
And by the way those ports, Mac and Linux are now also in the GitHub
that people are working on.
So you can you can get those either from The Forum site or probably
the GitHub is the right place to do that.
Now you can check our tweetbot which tweets the schedule.
So if you want to catch the series live and if you do want to get
stories alive, I think the next one will be Monday, probably 5 p.m.
but I don't know.
So check the tweetbot because I'm not sure what next week's schedule
is going to be the Cinerama is running a movie a movie series that has
a lot of movies that I want to go see again.
And so I may have to move
the stream may have to be moved to weird times next week.
So check the tweetbot because, you know, I'm going to try and catch a
few movies next week.
Anyway, that's it for this week and handmade hero.
We will be back next week to do some more programming.
And I don't know if we're going to do, like I said, I kind of started
getting.
I'm kind of into that little display.
We made at the bottom there.
So we may do another week of debug display coding, before we do the
lip stuff because we didn't really go further.
Onto the printing out of stuff.
Area.
So I may I may actually say, let's do one more week of just debug
print out stuff.
I mean, debug visualization stuff and then maybe we'll go do the lib
stuff.
So who knows?
We'll see.
But anyway, I hope to see you back here for that until then have a
great weekend programming and I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.