Stop recording.
Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we Cody complete game live on stream.
We don't use any engines or libraries.
This is actually a full picture of game development, all the way from
the pixels up to the AI.
Every last little thing is covered on the stream.
We have gotten to the point where we would like to do what I would
consider, you know, perhaps even really the only
hard memory management problem that we will have in handmade hero
because we talk about memory once in a while I'm handmade hero.
But usually it's to point out the fact that you really just don't have
to think about it that much.
There's a lot of people who think that they can't program without a
garbage collected language or think that it'll slow them down too much
or have all of these sort of preconceived notions about how hard it
would be for them if they didn't rely on these sort of abstract
Notions of memory where it's just kind of amorphous and weird.
Right.
But so far on handmade here.
As I hope I've demonstrated this you really just don't have to think
about it that much.
There's a couple times that you might think about it a little bit, but
on the whole, you can model most things.
As very simple Stacks.
You write it once and you really never have to think about it again.
And so that's the case for most of the time.
But this, there's two places in handmade hero, I think that we might
have to think about it.
One of them is what we're at right now, and so I want to talk about it
and one of the things that's
Kind of important to remember about this is actually, this one in
particular, is one that also can't really be solved by a garbage
collecting language.
So, this is a problem that you really have to think about, no matter
how you choose to model your memory.
If you care, if you actually care about being able to do some of the
stuff correctly, you actually have to think about it, whether you're
managing memory yourself or not, because it's less about remembering
to free stuff for collecting garbage and that sort of stuff and more
about.
How to make the optimal use of a fixed amount of storage space.
It's a caching problem, really?
So what I'd like to do today is just talk about this problem.
I don't know how much programming will do, but at what I'd like to do
is go to the Blackboard and basically try to give you some of an
overview of the problem.
We're trying to solve why.
It's very difficult ways in which you might just decide not to solve
it, which is certainly an option and then we'll make some decisions or
decide kind of what our first stab is going to be like in trying to
solve it for him a hero.
Alright, so here on day one 57 let's go ahead and talk about the
problem.
We have, which is asset memory.
Management.
Okay, so here's the thing.
All the crazy Java versus C Sharp versus C memory management.
Oh my God pointers no it's so hard.
I can't program blah blah blah like and everyone fights its cognitive
load.
They say all these are the things right.
It's this gigantic Nightmare and you never want to get to.
Those are just take it from me.
If someone starts saying stuff, like garbage collection is a cognitive
load, just let them take their cognitive load and go load it up,
right?
Like it's not even worth arguing with those people, but if you're
someone who's really actually legitimately intellectually interested
in this topic, here is a good way to think about it, right?
So there's a couple things that you care about, when you care about
memory, right?
Number
One is how much right?
Right.
So there's quantity.
And this is just how much memory do you actually need to run?
Like, like what is the actual footprint, right?
And we care about this?
Because there are times when that's actually constrained and no matter
how much anyone would like to pertain to pretend that that's not true,
it rears its ugly head again and again and again.
And again we don't have to care about memory because PCS have a lot of
memory up here.
Come consoles and they don't have a lot of memory.
Okay, finally consoles, get enough memory.
Don't worry.
Memory it's fine, we've got plenty and then all of a sudden phones
happen and now phones have no memory, right?
And then when phones get memory, all of a sudden it's going to be
something else.
It's like, oh, wearables.
I got my little wrist watch and the wristwatch has no memory, right?
It's like, it seems like throughout time no matter what happened.
We always run out of memory and you always have to care how much
memory you're using.
Because no matter what, no matter when we think we have enough either,
what we want to start using in terms of assets, gets too big or the
machine suddenly
Lee come out that we want to Target.
That are too small, right?
So quantity actually is important and we need to think about that.
Right to is when, right?
And you know when is like, you know, sort of the concept of Alec and
free right?
Where did these things happen in the code?
Because there's how much memory we need at any given time as one
question.
But how we track when we need which parts of it is?
Kind of a different thing, right?
And so, if we think about garbage collection, as a thing, right,
garbage collection is end and languages that management before you are
really entirely about this, right?
They're entirely about figuring out when you need the memory, they
have nothing to do with this, right?
So that no matter what, you've got for a language, it doesn't help you
use less memory if your code is written so that it needs that much
memory, right?
It doesn't help you at all.
So really the only
only thing that garbage collection helps you do is if you
You can't figure out how to write your code.
So that, you know, when you need memory garbage collection can help
you.
Because what garbage collection effectively is, is it's a search over
the graph of your programs ownership structure.
To see what memory is actually in use.
And when that ownership structure changes, the graph search will then
figure out.
Oh-oh there's been a piece that's now been calved off it is no longer
necessary.
So I know that it can be freed right?
And so garbage collection is
Is basically replacing you right garbage.
In fact, I could even just summarize it.
Basically all garbage collection is is garbage collection.
Means it replaces you with search, right?
That is what that is.
So instead of you having to know, when things are elected freed, it
will search to figure out what those are.
And basically all of the research around garbage collection and all of
the, you know, technology around garbage.
Collection is designed to figure out how to make this less expensive,
right?
Because if you actually think of it as a real search,
It would be impossible.
Like, it would be totally impractical because running that search.
Every time you did something would just be prohibitively expensive.
So what they do instead is well, okay, can we limit the search space
to just things that we know of changed recently?
Can we do it?
Only at certain times coming overlap, it on other threads, blaubart,
right?
And so there's all these sorts of things that try to make this less
expensive, right?
So, the reason I dismiss garbage collection is uninteresting.
Is because as you've seen so far on handmade hero when is not really a
problem for us, like we just don't have that problem.
I'm, you know, we haven't, we've literally not even come to a single
point and handmade hero so far, where when was we, when we even
thought about it, we just know, we've got some Stacks, we put stuff on
the stack, that's appropriate and that's it, right?
It doesn't matter because we know that the world exists is one thing
and we just run it and we don't really have to think about it, much
more than that.
We know when something gets destroyed.
Whatever that it's been freed.
So we don't you know it's just really there really isn't anything, a
garbage collector could do for us.
So all you would be doing would be paying for a bunch of search that
we don't need to do.
It's strictly baggage, right?
Whereas if you know either you are confused about it or maybe you have
some very wacky program where it's just this is going to be the only
way to really know for some reason and I don't really know what that
program would look like.
But you know,
Who knows?
Then you can imagine this being a thing, right?
And one place that that might happen, let's say was like some kind of
editor with really dense weird structures in it and you like delete
one of them and it's hard to tell whether some of the other related
things should go away or what you know you know maybe something like
this.
I don't know or you know in a more game context like maybe we'll see
it later.
On where we maybe we get into a situation where there's like, entities
that have sub entities.
And you know, when one of those goes away, like should other sub
entities of it, go away or, you know what I'm saying.
So that's really the only time where you can start to see like, oh,
okay, I get it like like, that's, you know, garbage collection.
Well, I'm personally not interested in it because I just Implement
something myself.
There.
You could at least see where it might be useful.
Whereas, in, handmade hero so far, we haven't had any
Thing where it would, it would be useful, right?
So, it's just kind of a, no, op.
But eventually, maybe we'll get something where it is.
And I'll point it out.
If we, if we do, if we don't try to imagine that in your head.
And that's, that's what that's doing for you.
It's preventing you from having to write code that detects what that
is because it's like a generic version of that.
Thing of the oh I deleted.
Entity are there any entities which are now irrelevant to the game and
should also be deleted.
That's like what garbage collection is supposed to solve the generic
version of that.
So you don't have to write it yourself, right?
So, there you go.
Okay, so what we have unfortunately, in the asset memory management
thing is this is not really relevant.
We don't care about this at all because when is not at all the issue
in terms of when the memory is used because what asset memory.
If you think about how this works is, right?
We have something.
That's like, you know, let's just say it's like a bazillion, right?
Assets.
However, many there are we have a huge number of them, right?
And then we have some amount of space that we have to run our game in,
right?
So let's say this is like three terabytes because who knows?
It's the world's largest game, right?
So you know, the community gets together in the make three terabytes
worth of assets for handmade hero and we're trying to run the game
with three terabytes of asset.
But guess what?
You know, we only have 4 gigabytes of RAM.
Right.
And so what we need to do is the when for memory is always, there's no
there's no time when we didn't want all these assets we wanted all of
them right?
They're all in use.
None of them will ever be garbage collected.
Now, they'll never be garbage.
We need all the asset data, it's all there.
The problem is we can't fit it all in memory.
So what we essentially have is a caching problem, right?
We have a
Problem, right here, where the amount of memory that we need is larger
than the amount of memory we have and just to underscore why this is
irrelevant.
If that wasn't the case, right?
If we had four gigabytes of assets and 4, gigabytes of RAM for the
assets, we're already done our asset system already.
Does the exactly maximally efficient thing, which is that at any given
time the assets that it predicts that
Needs are getting loaded into the 4 GB end over end over end.
You can actually see this.
I'll load up the code and show you exactly what I mean, so that it's
concrete for you and you know, exactly, which part of the code I'm
talking about when I say this, if I go into handmade code handmade
asset, right.
Then when we do that sort of load asset work stuff, right?
You can see in load bitmap what we do.
Right here is we do a push struct to push the bitmap sort of
Handle on.
And then we do a push size to push on the bitmap B, right?
And that goes into our asset Arena.
Now, the fat-ass Audrina will never fill.
So, we're got four gigabytes asset for GB Arena.
And they'll fit, if it'll never fill, we're done our asset code AS
written will do exactly the right thing.
It will it will load all the assets into memory eventually.
It will load them in the order in which we need them to be loaded and
it will do so in the background so that you don't have to wait for a
loading screen.
So it's exactly what we want.
If our asset load is lower,
then our memory footprint allows us to keep at one time.
So, the reason this turns into a caching problem is because if we have
more memory than would fit in here, right?
So it's too much.
Then what we have is essentially a VM problem, we've got a virtual
memory problem.
We have a problem where what this actually is is a cache of the assets
that only stores some small subset of them at any given time.
And what we need to do is pick out the slices of our asset pool and
map them into here as necessary, right?
And when we need to load an asset and the 4 GB has been filled up,
Need to find room by evicting, right?
We need to evict assets that are currently in their get rid of them,
temporarily to put something else in, and then when those assets are
needed again, they will be reloaded, right?
And so you can see why garbage collection doesn't help us here,
because garbage collection, doesn't solve this problem, right?
This is a inherently, a virtual memory problem.
And what we want to do is essentially say, well, we always have a
handle to all the Assets in some sense.
None of them are ever garbage.
But we only want you to have one's resident that are ones that we
believe ourselves to need in the in the in the immediate frame or in
you know, frames that are coming up within the next second or two.
Right?
But things that are going to be used in
Thirty minutes.
We don't need to have those in memory right now so you don't need to
store them, right?
Okay.
So ways we can ways we can choose out on this right?
so, what this means and again to underscore, why the garbage
Doesn't help you.
And also in fact, I'll show you why both doesn't help you.
So we have, you know, we talked about two things here.
I was like, we were we've been using Stacks.
Other people say garbage collection, woohoo, right?
Or whatever.
So why did neither of those two Loops?
Two solutions work for us.
Why don't stacks and or Garbage Collection work for us.
Right.
Well, the reason is because if we have four gigabytes of memory,
right, then what we've got in that 40 bytes of memory is some
Ooping of stuff in there, right?
We've got acid a acid be at sea ssds iesf or whatever, right?
In a garbage collected system.
We have handles into these, right?
And what we would need to do in order to make room for the new assets
to come in, is we would have to tell the garbage collector that we no
longer need.
Be right?
So we need to basically free be right?
So garbage collection doesn't help us because we have to explicitly,
tell it to get rid of that.
Otherwise, it would still just pile up.
And the same thing is through true of the stack, as the stack gets
pushed on there, right?
ABCDEF, right, or whatever, we need to tell it to free one of these
guys, right?
Would freebie.
And it would know to get rid of be right in either of these cases.
Sure.
We could then say well, okay, you know, that's good enough, right?
I mean, yes we have to do free so maybe it's not garbage collection
but now it's a heat or something right now.
It's like well, we're still could do it.
We could say freebie, or we could say, freaky free this thing or
whatever, right?
Not exactly.
The reason for that is because when we free something out of the
inside of an asset pool like this or inside of the stack, right?
We end up in a situation where it leaves a hole, it leaves a hole in
the memory.
And in order to put something else in that hole, the thing that going
going into the hole has to be smaller than it, right?
But what happens when I put something or the same size, what happens
when I put something smaller than it in?
Is that now I've left an even smaller hole that probably nothing could
go in or very few.
Things could go in, right?
And this is called fragmentation.
And fragmentation is exactly the problem that you get, when the size
of the memory that you have is, is very constrained.
So, I've got four gigabytes of memory, and I'm using 4, gigabytes of
memory, right?
Fragmentation is a big problem because what happens is over time,
you'll do stuff like, oh, I allocated this memory.
And then I freed the memory and I loaded something else in.
So I had, you know, just this part used, but I had already put
something in after it.
So now this part right,
Is the is free, right?
But this thing sticks around and now like I do some other stuff.
I like free and real like this thing and then I end up with like some
other swiss cheese in here and suddenly my total memory size starts
going down from 4 GB with these sort of holes in there, too.
Like, oh, and I've only got 3 GB because I've got all these holes in
there that are you know, sort of taking it up and
Can't free this asset because it's in use or whatever blah blah blah
blah blah, right?
So fragmentation is a huge problem where you're trying to maximally
fill this space that you've got you constantly run into these problems
where you're like, ah crap, you know, I can't
I can't just free one resource and put another resources in this
place.
If they're not the same size, I leave these little fragments and who
knows, how long it'll be before, I can actually start to do something
with those, right?
And so again, yeah, garbage collectors, don't address this at all,
neither do stacks.
But what's underneath could write?
So a garbage collector, could be built on top of a memory allocator
that does try to address this, right?
Similarly, for our usage.
We could imagine doing something similar like, building something
underneath it.
Which does handle this, right?
So let's talk about that and that's that's really what I want to talk
about today.
How much time we got here.
So 35, we're going to 15 after something like this, so 6:15.
So yeah, we got, we got plenty of time.
We got 40 minutes,
Okay 40 minutes.
Alright yeah we got 40 minutes so yeah so let's talk about this
problem.
In a world, in a world, in a world where all the assets were the same
size.
We would be very, very happy campers, right?
Because let's say, all of our assets were the same size in our memory
pool, right?
So this is our, these are active assets.
So if all the assets are the same size a,b,c,d,e, then when I need to
load a new asset, right?
I need to load asset f.
It is exactly the same size as everything else.
So what I can do is I can look and see.
Which of these assets is the oldest.
But the one that hasn't been used in the most number of frames, let's
say
and I can take that evict it, right, and stick the new one in its
place.
So we get rid of asset.
See if that's the oldest, let's say, and we put asset evidence place,
there is no fragmentation.
Everything is always used perfectly because however, much space.
There is let's say there's four gigabytes of space.
If every asset is, you know, I don't know, 256, Meg's or something?
Then I know I have space for 16 assets.
I'm always storing exactly, 16 assets.
Whenever I get a new asset, I evict the oldest of
16 and put it in its place and the memory is always guaranteed to be
used maximally and perfectly.
No problem, right?
And this is why fixed-size allocators, right?
Are really great.
Any problem that you can turn into a fixed size.
Allocation problem is really fantastic because it will allow you to,
basically do perfect management of the memory, never have any
fragmentation.
It's very, very simple and straightforward and we've seen
Before we've done it with a free list and I remember, we did free
lists where we just reuse blocks of that size to kind of just like,
you know, when we free, we just keep the old ones around and then
reuse them.
Again, that's a classic example of a nice fixed size allocator.
They're so simple, and they work.
Great, right.
So, our problem.
We kind of have two ways you can go with it, right?
What we want to do is we want to handle the solution.
We want to handle the situation where these assets are not the same
size.
So, how do we do that?
Well, the first thing that we can look at right is the fact that we
could choose to make this into a fixed size, allocation problem,
right?
That is actually an option that we do have, and the way that we would
do that, for example, is, let's say you just flat-out decided that all
Sprites are 256 by 256.
Right, let's just say you just said that if that was the case, then
all of our bitmaps would be the same size.
And at that point, it would be pretty darn easy for us to go ahead and
load the bitmaps on top of each other.
Because when we freed one, we would free exactly the same the amount
of space we would need to load the new in it, right?
So that's pretty compelling.
The problem with that is that doesn't really necessarily do a good job
of representing what we actually want, right?
It doesn't make sense for us to force.
All of our bitmaps to conform to this size because you know, some of
them are larger.
Some of them are smaller, it would be wasting space or whatever, you
know, if we did that.
And so the other thing we could do is we could say, well, okay, we
could tile things, right?
We could make it so that everything was in tiles.
So, you know, if we have the hero or something like that,
Said of the hero just being one bitmap.
That was a certain size.
We broke it up into ones that were 256 by 256, right?
So if you want a 512 by 512 hero or something like this, you break
them up in interviews expect of you styles.
It's an option, right?
You still have some wastage, right?
You still have, you know, times when it's going to be too big?
Like if the hero was only supposed to be 270 by 283, or whatever,
right?
Well, you got ton of wastage now, because you've got, you know, the
hero only taking up, you know, maybe that much of your four tiles and
there's all this empty space there, right?
But there's even stuff that we could do to try to mitigate that,
right?
And to sort of, give you an idea of one way to mitigate that.
One option that we easily could do.
It's a let's pretend the game is one gigantic Sprite sheet, right?
And all of the Sprites are like packed into the Sprite sheet.
Not by hand, but by an automated process.
And then the Sprite sheet is just broken up, you know, into 256 by 256
tiles.
Then when we say we want to load a Sprite, we just have to figure out
which set of tiles.
It needs and we load those in.
And then all of the tiles are always 256 by 256 in the, you know, in
this tiling scheme and that's like, very similar to like, you know, a
mega texture scheme, basically, right?
That's very similar to a sparse virtual texture.
And it has some Merit, right?
It's definitely has some Merit to it.
So I wouldn't necessarily dismiss out of hand.
We could do something like that, right.
But there are, there are concerns around this, right?
The biggest concern around doing things.
This way, is what you do about mipmapping.
For example, because mipmapping gets very difficult than schemes like
this for reasons that I don't really think we necessarily want to go
into detail here, but there are reasons why?
Might not do it now with a 2-D game.
It's possible that we could get away with it right.
You know 2D game is totally possible that we could get away with it
because in a 2-D game you know what the mips are ahead of time you
don't have to do like trilinear and you don't have to have a lot of
angular stuff going on, where the mid-levels going to change across a
single polygon.
So it's actually plausible in a lot of cases to do a scheme like this
for a 2-D game.
I think.
So, yeah, so I'm just going to put that out there.
So that's one thing that we could choose to do and what that does just
to be clear, is it doesn't quite get you entirely out of the business
of having your assets, be different sizes.
Because even though it now means that the actual page able asset that
you're working with is to is all the same size.
So we have a uniform size.
For the page will ask that which is a tile, what it doesn't do.
Is fix the problem with the asset tile list, right?
So we still have the case that asset.
A, if it was a 512 by 512 asset, right?
It's got four tiles in it.
But asset be that was 256 by 256 that only has one tile in it, right?
So you still have a variable size to your assets.
This one requires four indices into the tile table and this one
requires one but because 256 by
I 256 by 4, right?
The actual size of the Sprite data is well to put a fine to put not to
put too fine a point on it, right?
But 256 x, 256 is 64th, you know, K right 64 K times 4 is 64 K more
than what it takes to store an
Right.
And so what you can choose to do is just not page the tile set, right?
So the thing that stores, the asset tile list could just be loaded in
memory at startup.
It's probably pretty small you know like the okay.
So it's a 10 megabyte thing or something like this.
You just load that in once and you're done and then you're just paging
in the tiles as necessary, right?
So that's one thing we could do.
And as I'm saying it to myself, I am kind of wondering if that's not
the best solution, right?
Like, I don't know if that's a smarter solution to the problem than
then what I was going to propose here but
I'll keep God.
So, our other option, right is to do a regular alligator, right?
So if we do sort of, for lack of a better term of variable,
Allocator one, that can allocate things of variable sizes.
What we can do is say, okay, we've got our memory here, right?
So we've got our four gigabytes.
And what we would do is we would go in here.
We would allocate a chunk of memory for a resource, you know, an asset
a right and then we will go here and you know allocate 1 B and then
going here and allocate 1 C, right?
If later on we then deallocate be, lets say,
Right.
So be goes away.
And we put something else in it, so in comes a new asset D.
We've lost the ability to kind of use this space, because it's like
maybe two tiny now to really load much of an asset in there.
So this space has become fragmented, then what we can do, we have
really two choices.
Actually, one thing we can do is because our assets immune system is
already in directed because the asset table itself points into these
things and people always reference assets through the asset table.
We can then start to do some kind of compaction, like we could move,
see up to close in that space, right?
We have the ability to basically do defragmentation.
So that's one thing we can actually move stuff around in here.
But the other thing that we could do to is as stuff, gets freed, we
can do the standard stuff that you do in a very well allocator, which
is we would actually condense on free.
So when you start to free stuff when you get you know you get this
little space in here, if C then we're to get freed, we would record
the fact that these phases would be merged.
Aged so instead of thinking that there was a sea space, you know, a
see size space and a b - D size space to be used.
We would now know that we have space, that's the, you know, actually a
B minus D plus C size space to use which is a bunch more open Memory,
right?
So, yeah.
So
Probably the thing that I say that we might as well just go ahead and
do because it's possibly a good exercise to sort of go through the
steps of making a variable allocator.
So you can see how one works because at the end of the day, that is
what malloc and free, what new and delete, you know what these things
do and it's also if you're in a garbage collector language, it's what
the thing underneath, the Hood in a garbage collector has to do too,
because, remember underneath the garbage collection layer, you still
have to have something that can do.
Random size, free Alec and free, right?
Because that the lower level, the garbage collector, still needs to be
able to you know we use memory efficiently otherwise it's going to be
a really bad garbage collector, right?
So yeah, so I kind of felt like that was the right thing to do for our
asset system even though it, you know, maybe it's not the smartest way
to do, if the
You were strictly doing was like how do we make the world's best asset
system?
I feel like this may be the right thing to do in terms of the
educational aspect of it because I feel like it would be good for us
to just do one of these as part of handmade hero.
So everyone kind of has a chance to play around with it.
And you get to watch me kind of go through building one and seeing how
it goes and what happens because it really is kind of the lowest level
allocator that everything has to run on top of at some level and
So it's probably kind of useful for that.
And so what we would do for this again is we would make our system
work pretty similar to how it's working.
Now where as you go through, you know, when you call load bitmap, it
goes ahead and allocate stuff.
But what we would then do is we would put sort of a cap on its
allocation limit on its allocation size.
So when it gets up to some number of gigabytes, right?
However, much we set aside for asset storage
When it gets up to 1 GB or whatever, we said it will then have to free
enough, other stuff to basically give it space if you will, you know,
sort of give it space to ensure that it's never going to use over that
one gigabyte amount, right?
So that's it.
That's all we're talking about.
Nothing more complicated than that.
It's pretty straightforward really.
And yeah.
And so, all of the Finesse is really just in constructing.
The thing that actually does this, there's nothing particularly
conceptually Difficult about what's going on.
It's just a very finicky kind of a thing because it's about placing
things and looking through structures to see where, you know, if
there's free space and whether you can fit something in or would it be
smarter to
Put it somewhere else.
And, you know, it's just kind of this nasty if that kind of a sort of
nasty finicky code.
And so, you know, while there's nothing particularly tricky about the
high-concept, when you actually start getting down to, how do I do a
good job at this?
It can be kind of tortured and weird, right?
And to some degree, it's sort of a black art, I believe to, you know,
I don't tend to write much code that goes through variable allocators.
So, I'm actually not the best person to say, what the state of the art
is, in terms of variable occurs.
But my experience with them in the past has been roughly, that, it's
sort of a black
Cart sort of a thing where it's like, yeah, there's certain allocation
scheme seemed to be pretty good at the kinds of stuff that people do
with allocation.
Right.
And so, you know, you'll see people saying, you know, oh I used DL
Malik or whatever and it was good for this workload is the it's just
like these are just like arbitrary schemes that people kind of tuned
to be good at arbitrary workloads.
That they were testing and had good performance in terms of not taking
too long to find out where things should go and being able to use a
reason a lot of memory without too much wastage right without leaving
lots of empty space and all these sorts of other things, right?
All right, so we've got about 24 minutes something like that, 24
minutes left.
So what I wanted to do was go into the system and try to figure out a
way.
I'm not 100% certain
How we will do this, but try to figure out a good way to make it so
that we will run out of memory in our asset system, right?
So if we take a look down here a base, I want to us to assert.
So, when we say memory index size here, when we allocate the sub
Arena, that's what we're going to use for our our system here.
I'm going to, I'm just going to go ahead and tell it to allocate
something really small.
Right?
So it's like oh yeah you know, one megabyte or 2 MB or something like
this.
And I just want to get it to the point where it goes ahead and asserts
so that it doesn't, you know, it can't actually live.
Would all of the memory that it would would want, right?
There we go.
So you know, at some point here I turned the character, you know, and
it came in here and it decided, right?
And you can even see here it is with the heroes head or Cape or
whatever.
At some point, I turned the character and that was enough to like,
blow out that size, right?
So that's exactly what I want.
This is what I want some situation where we artificially constrained.
So that even with a small number of assets that were currently
Working with, we will hit that hard cap and we can start to play
around with what to do.
When we hit it, I forgot that we left the particle system on there,
that is kind of ridiculous, obviously.
Particle systems are so damn funny.
I'm for those of you who missed it on Thursday and Friday, we added a
particle system.
I just we were kind of I said, what should we do for a fun diversion
and particle system was on the list.
So we added this and you can't tell me.
That's not hilarious.
That is just, that is just hilarious.
All right, so yeah, okay.
So here's what we need to start thinking about, let's let's, let's
start this process here.
Let's recover from the humor of seeing a bunch of weird little
He had spew out of our heroes abdomen.
So we've got the asset system and the the asset system itself has this
memory Arena.
And so it's allocating things on this memory Rina.
And what we want to be able to do is we want to be able to have some
kind of an opinion.
About when we need to free memory and like, how much Headroom?
We need their, right?
So, let's take care of a few really basic things, first that we kind
of need to, to address, right?
So one thing that I was thinking about is for our assets, Lots, I
wanted to think about whether we wanted to expand the assets.
Lot set to, you know, how much memory would it take to, to expand the
assets lot set to just have
The data in itself.
And so what I'm going to do here is I'm going to go in and I'm going
to take a look at what the loaded bitmap stuff does and I'll show you
what I'm talking about here.
So if you take a look at the the loaded bitmap stuff and you can
ignore the five-minute warning because like I said, we got 15 extra
minutes on the clock today.
So we've got 20 minutes.
It was a long question day-to-day, it start.
yeah, so if you take a look here, if we just take a quick look at
What we're looking at, in terms of loaded bitmap, you can see there,
that's what the loaded bitmap looks like, with the little bit map
code.
Looks like we need to store with over height.
We need to sort of the alignment percentages for where the bitmap
should be centered.
We need to store the width and the height of the actual bitmap itself
and we needed to store the pitch.
Those are the things that we need to store.
Now my assumption and I could be very wrong about this, is that pitch
actually doesn't need to be Stewart.
My
Option is that we could just make a rule about how you compute the
pitch from the height and that from now, I'm sorry from the with, and
then from, so we could get rid of that, right?
So that could go away.
So let's try that first.
And again, what I'm trying to do here just to say it again, are what
we have in our game as we have this assets lat and we have as many of
them as we have assets.
And right now, they store their essentially, a 12 B thing.
Right?
If they were packed which is they have a 32-bit State variable which
does not in any way need to actually be 32 bits.
If you actually look at how big it is, that's totally not necessary,
right?
And then they've got pointers out to whatever the actual data.
Is that would be there, right?
And so there are 12, bytes, or something like that.
What I'm wondering is, could we just get rid of loaded bitmap?
I'm sorry, I could get
Rid of the pointers and actually put loaded bitmap and loaded sound
directly into the asset slot.
So that it's just always there.
Why do I want to do that?
I want to do that because it means that assets are only the size that
they actually are from then on.
So we don't have to constantly think about allocating.
How loaded bitmap structure 2.2 and then have that point to the
memory, right?
I'm just removing a little bit of indirection there because what you
see happen?
If we actually go to load bitmap or something like that, right?
Is you see that first we push, we do a push truck for loaded bitmap
into the arena and then we do a push size for the memory that we
actually need.
So I wanted to get it down to just the memory.
So we know that assets, take the size that they are, whatever their
size is is what they take, right?
So yeah.
So I just want to condense these structures down and see if I can put
them in there.
So let's think about that pitch.
You know do we actually need to store that?
So let's go ahead and see if we can get rid of it, right?
So what I'd like to do is just replace that with a thing that's like
get pitch, right?
Some function that we just call.
So every time the pitch is talked about, we actually just do, like,
you'd get pitch called, write something like this.
And so, I guess, you know, now that I look at it too.
I could already see what the problem is going to be.
So I wonder if we want to do one more step before we do this, which is
that are
Our when we're actually writing to stuff, those are technically loaded
bitmaps as well because we don't have a we don't distinguish between
the two of those things.
So the actual problem is going to be how we handle buffers.
We write to if that makes sense.
And so I feel like what we would almost want to do is do something
like struct like a writable bitmap, right?
And that thing has an extra pitch on it that the other ones don't have
that make sense.
I may try to do
At, let's do something simpler first though.
Since I can see that, that's going to be a little bit of problem.
So we'll try that first.
We'll try something else first.
So, first of all, width and height right now, can be 4 billion by four
billion.
So there's really no, well, two billion, they're signed, there's
really no need for that, right?
That is not at all necessary.
I don't feel like.
So one thing we could also do here is, we could choose to store this
in a much smaller way.
Now, eight bits isn't going to cut it because to Pieces by 26 is too
small but 16 bits would
Certainly be fine, right?
64000 by 64,000 is bigger than any bitmap.
We're
Haven't handmade hero, because our screen is not even that big.
So that would be kind of Overkill, in fact, our screen would most be
like 4K.
So we'd be talking about sixty four by four.
We talking about a Sprite that was 16 screens wide not going to
happen, right?
So, we could change these guys to 16 bit and we wouldn't miss it
right.
That would be totally fine, right?
And so that gets us down to two, three, four, five, and then the
pointer 67, right?
And so, we
Also of course, change the pitch, also be one of those and then I'm
not sure that we could really do much else we need these guys to be
float, right?
So yeah, we really want to get rid of the pitch because that would
leave us dangling at 16, which we don't really want to do.
So that would be for what we really want to do is get it to this.
Because then what we have is essentially two floats, one, float 2016.
So it would be like for
44 B, things or 16 bytes, and then the pointer
Right.
That would I think be
Probably what we would want, right?
So that'd be good and if we were down to that, right?
If we were down to that, that's basically just talking about for you.
That's talking about 16, bytes extra per asset.
And we could also do a little snuggling there.
We could snuggle that up a bit because if you think about what happens
with this assets lot, we have this asset stayed in there, that asset
State could probably be stuffed into here somehow in a relatively, you
know, in a relatively sort of cozy, fashion, if you will, right, in
fact, if I did it like this,
Now, the asset State could easily just be a u16 and and off you go,
right?
Of course, the only problem is, we do atomic rights to that guy.
Yeah, not sure.
You'll find out.
S, let's find out.
Okay.
So here we go.
Let's see.
I think we do.
Am I?
So that guy could be wrong.
Yeah, we do at our gross that guy, right?
So that's no good.
So, that guy has to stay as a youth order to basically will have to
have to play around with that a little bit because we we could do
stuff to make that, not be an issue.
All right, so let's go in here.
All of these.
I think we just want to do.
Oops.
We want to just do a safe truncation.
I don't know if we've got a safe truncation there.
Let's let's actually take a look and see if we do.
There's made transics trunk.
it's
I'm a platform truncate.
Here we go.
So what we want to do is something here where we can safely truncate
something from a 32 you know some kind of a 32-bit value.
I'm sorry 32-bit value down to a 16 byte value.
Just so we can ensure that you know it's not going to be that we
didn't accidentally truncate something that we actually wanted.
Right?
So we want to do something like you know we want.
What is it 65536.
My to, we want 32 768.
We want to make sure that it's greater than then 32 cents 58 and less
than 32767 because we know that we'll be able to be stored in a 16-bit
integer, so we can go ahead then and cast it down, right?
Although, I guess I think about it, if we do a safe truncate,
if we did something like safe truncate to you and 16, then really,
what we want to do is something more like this.
We want to be less than 6 5, 5 3, 6 or 5 and greater than 0 because we
want to truncated in that way, right?
So that that's a little more that's that's more what we were trying to
do there.
Okay so in this case that should be fine, we'll keep that result there
and then we can just go ahead and do these safe truncations.
So there we go.
Right.
And yeah, and you can see that that pitch is very easy to compute in
here.
So we know that we can do it for everything except for bitmaps
basically.
All right.
So why don't you ask?
No Object file generated?
Initializing conversion from you and 32 to you and 16?
That is just a typo.
Okay?
So these guys again are also safe truncations.
so,
and one more time.
Okay, so that should just be fine and of course, we should still crash
whenever it will not crash but we should assert that as soon as I use
enough bitmaps.
Okay.
And so, inside asset here, let's go ahead and just finish this off.
So for loaded sound, the same thing would be true, right?
I'm going to go ahead and say that the sample count and the channel
count.
Could be shrunk quite a bit and what I would assume is the sample
count, you know, does it really need to be a 32-bit value?
Could it be a 24-bit value?
So what I might say to do here is could we go ahead and pack these?
So that basically we have you know, sample count is 24 and channel
count
You know, is, is it even less, right?
The channel, count could be four bits, and the sample count could be
28 bits or something like that, right?
So, if we packed those guys together, again, that would keep it even
smaller.
And so, then it would be basically the same size as, as the load a bit
Maps as well, right?
Although now that I think about it, it might be at the load.
A bitmap is still a little bit bigger.
Let me take a look at that certain render group so loaded bitmap.
It's got one pointer one pointer.
Then these two guys would encounter another pointer so then you've got
the R32 which account for it.
So yeah.
So basically the loaded bitmaps, always a little bit bigger so I
suppose we don't really have to do that one because in since they're
both stored in a union, right?
Unless I could get them.
Look down to a smaller size.
It wouldn't really matter, right?
So I'll just play to do in here to do if the loaded and also, we don't
even need two pointers.
So the loaded sound, this could be shrunk to 12 B if the loaded
Bitmap ever got down that small.
Right.
So yeah, that's all I want to just mention there, we don't need to go
totally crazy with it but it's something we could probably do a little
bit more of and you know what, I'll put one into this to where I'm
like just to do
Get rid of pitch and we'll try that in a second potentially.
All right, so what I want to do now is I want to just make these guys
actually stored, right?
So instead of being pointers, they're just actually going to be stored
in there and we'll make the asset State be.
The only thing that actually determines whether you can use them or
not, which I think we already did.
Like we already did this check right to make sure that the thing was
loaded.
So I think we're totally fine on that.
So basically all we're doing here is making it so that it's going to
use it out of there directly.
And we no longer have to do a push struct on these guys, what we can
do instead is just take, whatever was in that.
Slot and use what was in the slot, right?
So yeah.
So we can go ahead and take this.
In fact, we can probably do this at the top here where we just kind of
go like asset slot, slot equals whatever the slot is like.
So I guess we don't have to do that until we actually use this thing
and then in here we can just you know we you know what, we could
probably even just do it like this because it's not invalid.
You just do the computation.
We're never going to access it, unless it actually is valid.
We can just come in here and say, okay.
You know, instead of actually doing this, we can just do it off the
slot pointer like so right.
So, now when we want to use this, and I guess I could do this here
slot unloaded.
So now
When we come in here, I can just say that the bitmap is just the slot
bitmap and there's you don't have to do anything, right?
And that means that we don't use up any additional memory and all this
stuff should just work fine, right?
So I can go and compel that I think that's really all we need to do
and this doesn't actually need to happen at all, right?
Then in here, the same is true.
We don't actually need to do that anymore but we do need to actually
pull out that slot
so here it is, then we can, you know in here take that
Use that slots now.
It's it's already been kind of pre-addressed for us.
And in here we can avoid ever doing that that allocation for the
sound.
So I'm just going to take the address of the sound that's already
there for us to fill in and use it, right?
So there we go, and while we're doing this, I think I might go ahead
and turn the music back on just, so I can hear that still loading
properly.
In case we make a false move, that makes it.
So that our music stops playing.
That would just be a good thing to keep in mind.
So, there we go.
Aha.
And of course, just loading.
The music was enough to blow out our amount of space that we said we
can use.
Let's try and change it to 3 megabytes.
So now, just by virtue of playing the music well or creating the guy,
we blow out the arena, right?
So that's good.
Okay.
So, all that's nice.
And now what we need to know
I is, we need to have some way of now determining ahead of time.
when we are going to,
Hit our load limit, right?
And this is actually trickier than you might think the reason this is
trickier than you might think.
And the reason that we're going to have to probably introduce
something somewhat fancy.
And you know, when I say fancy, it's not that fancy but and I should
probably know if I should end now, or if I should explain it, I'll
give you a little preview and then we'll do it tomorrow.
So, what needs to happen now, right?
Is we need to have some kind of a situation where when we are full and
we have something that we want to put in here, right?
We're saying we got to load an asset and it's going to take a
megabyte, right?
But we don't have a megabyte of space.
We then need to be able to start freeing stuff to fit, 1, megabytes,
worth of space.
We can't actually free anything.
at the time, when you call this,
Why?
Well, let's see when it gets cold.
and those of you who are sharp who are watching right now,
you should know what I'm going to say.
You should be able to figure it out.
So I'll give you a little couple seconds.
Where is this called?
Where we calling load sound for example, right?
Well actually you know what?
Load sounds probably the not the best example because it's we don't
load probably any sound.
So let's do little bit map instead.
Okay.
So where are we calling load bitmap, right?
Well, we're crawling little bit map inside push bitmap, right?
And game update and render is where that gets called.
Now, the problem is on this Frame, we've already called push bitmap a
bunch of times, and what happens when we actually call Push bitmap is,
if the bitmap exists, we use it.
How do we use it?
We put it on a list of things that the renderer will go and use.
So if during this load bitmap call we were to evict an existing
bitmap.
We would run the risk of Addicting, a bitmap that is currently being
used, right?
So what we would much rather do you know because we can we can try to
go the route of introducing locking code to bring that from happening.
Right.
But rather than doing that, what I'd rather do is say let's introduce
a controlled time when bitmaps are actually marked us freed
So that we don't ever free them in the middle of things, right?
And so there's two ways we can do that one is that when we call load
bitmap we can put them onto a list of things to be loaded later.
The other is that we can kick off the tasks immediately at that time,
using space, we've pre freed
Okay, we'll say those two again on the Blackboard.
We can either keep some amount of free space around in here, right?
So we keep, you know, out of our four gigabytes, we keep, you know, 16
Meg's free.
So every frame
We can kick off tasks that will write to the 16 megabytes.
And at the end of the frame, we will free back up to 16 megabytes.
So if we, if we used up some portion of the 60 megabytes of free
space, we've done will three a bunch of stuff that gets us back to 16
total mix free.
Something like that.
So we always have places to kick off our new slots tasks to write into
without having to evict things can do that.
Or we can do is when we do load bitmap calls, we actually defer them
to the end of the
frame.
So when somebody calls the bitmap, we don't kick off the task.
We just right in all of the bit.
We wanted to load ABCDEFG, whatever.
And then at the end of the frame, we say kick off, and it goes through
and it kicks off all of these to new tasks.
Right.
You do either of those two things.
I would lean towards probably doing the free space one because I'd
rather kick off the load immediately so that we have the rest of that
frames render time to get the stuff for that.
We're missing for the next frame on this, you know.
So I don't know.
Like because missing, yeah, I don't know.
There's a lot of ways we could make that trade-off on the other hand.
We always pray.
Want to be precasting.
Anyway, so this may actually be fine.
I'm not sure, but either way, I'd like to go to the Q&A because well,
we talked about a bunch of stuff today and I want to make sure people
who have questions have a chance to ask them.
So and I noticed pseudonym 73.
Sing well, it's official assets are now.
Handles, I wouldn't say they're now handles.
I would say they've been there were handles right from the very
beginning, right?
Because as soon as we introduce that
It's lap thing that was when they became handles so they've been
handled for a while now and that is exactly the way I want them
because I want the game to be able to always refer to an asset and not
have to worry if it exists or not, right?
I don't want the game code to have to think about ownership.
Will there be a benefit to using a two level cache for storing
compressed and uncompressed assets?
Mmm,
I mean, the answer is certainly that it's possible.
And I guess I don't know whether the answer would be yes.
Or no.
You'd probably it would probably depend on the
Platform.
On the PC, I strongly doubt it because you've got so much memory.
I don't know that and the hard drives are so darn fast, you know?
on the
You know, a system for that II.
Don't know, I'm sorry.
I really couldn't tell you, I feel like you'd really have to test it
but I suspect it uncompressed is probably fine.
Is there any performance reason to not use malloc and free?
You mean like if we just if we didn't want to?
Okay, I think I know chasing so you're saying if I didn't want to show
you how to write one of these, could we just call malloc and free
here?
And the answer is yes.
In fact you could even do that probably even if you didn't want to use
the C runtime Library, you could just call the platform's malloc and
free which is like in Windows like keep Alec and Heat free because
we're making so few allocations you know we're going to make like 16
allegations of frame or something like that for these asset movements
or something at that point.
It doesn't have to be super efficient.
So so yeah.
If we didn't want to look at this problem in a little more detail, you
probably could just call, whatever it doesn't even matter, what new
and delete malloc and free he palak.
Keep free.
I don't know.
You want to call virtual a lock because that's a little heavy weight,
but but certainly anything else would probably be fine.
Are there technical terms for the memory emptiness Assurance
algorithm?
Are you talking about like these two things I said here, where like
you defer to the end of the frame or you leave space to kick off the
tasks.
And the answer is I don't know the technical term for those know, I
don't think I've ever heard some of them refer to those as a specific
technical term.
Dual 1,000.
Can you talk a bit more about what new and delete actually does and
when to use them.
Sure.
So we don't need new and delete on handmade hero because we don't use
any kinds of C++ features that need them that need to use them.
But basically, what happens is, you can think about there being sort
of two steps to constructing a, you can think about two steps to using
memory, right?
There's one, there's like getting the memory.
two, there's initializing the memory
and then we might as well like those are the two steps but we could
also throw in step 3 if we want them to which is freeing the memory
Right?
Or I should say this, you know, if we're going to do that in, we might
as well do four steps.
3D initializing, the memory
And for freeing the memory.
Right.
And so the way to think about the things that you're talking, the
things you're asking about new and delete, right?
Is essentially
If you look at this process, this is Malik.
Write these two together.
Our new.
This here is free and these two together.
Or delete.
So basically what C++ tried to do is it tried to formalize steps, two
and three whereas see only really formalized steps 1 & 4.
Okay, so this is C.
This is C + + to make these a little more concrete.
Let's suppose that I have something here, struct Foo, it has an
interior bar in it.
okay, and so if I want to make one of these, that's not on the stack
that is going to be dynamically allocated from a heap
The C runtime Library provides you with steps 1 & 4, which is malloc
and free.
And what those do is they go to the Heap and they reserved something
of this size and they return it to you.
So, when you say Foo star, a equals malloc right size of
Oops.
Sighs of Foo, you are asking to do step one, which is to reserve as a
place in the computer's memory for a food, right?
And you'd have to cast it here in C++, but in see, you wouldn't cast
it because the cast is implicit from void.
So if it was see, it would be this, right?
But the memory you got back is just garbage.
It just has whatever is in there, right?
It's not this.
Step two was not done for you.
And then later, right?
You can imagine calling free on a, which is saying, I no longer need
the memory that you got here, so put it back into the heat, put it
back like let it be known that this part of memory doesn't have to be
reserved anymore that step 4.
Okay?
And that's free.
So that's what see looks like and so when you wrote C code you did
this, then you did whatever you want to do to initialize the object
like a bar equals 5.
Right?
There's the initialization.
I'm going to sizing bar 25, I use it.
And then later, if I have some D initialization to do, I do it in this
case.
I don't have any but you can imagine something more complicated there.
In fact, I guess you know what?
Let me help illustrate this a little bit better by saying, instead of
in bar.
Let's say it's file.
Star Bar.
Right.
So there's actually another thing inside it.
So an initialization time, I want to do bar equals F open some file
when I'm done with it, right?
I then need to close it.
So I need an F close here, and I need to fclose a bar before freeing
the memory, right?
So again, those are the steps, two, and three right here, step one
here, step to hear step 3 here, step 4.
And so, what new and delete tried to do in C++?
Is standardized on this step as a couple.
So instead of one, two, three, and four being
Is where one in four were facilitated by the C runtime Library & 2 & 3
were entirely up to you.
C++ makes it so that, actually, those things can be bound together.
So, if we expand this class to have a Constructor Foo, right?
And a Destructor Foo, right?
And I'm calling this truck, but remember, struct and class have our.
There's no difference between these two things.
The see, they don't, they're exactly the same.
The only difference is whether things are declared private or public
by default, that's it.
So if you
A public at the top of this thing, there'd be no difference between
calling the class instruct, so, you know, don't let that confuse you.
They're literally, they're there.
It was a meaningless keyword, it was should never have been
introduced.
It doesn't actually mean anything.
It's just a struct.
The only thing that we have in C and CE os are structs and so class
was just you know, someone's little mental.
You know, be honest roster of how to
You know, unhealthy attraction to similar or something.
Okay.
So, we introduced these Constructors and destructors.
And what they are designed to do is move the understanding of what
steps two and three are into C++ proper rather than just as something,
the programmer does.
So what we do is inside these Constructors, right here is Foose
Constructor inside the Constructor.
We actually do, you know, bar equals F open, right?
And inside the destructor for Foo, we actually do the F close.
Okay, right.
So that's what's actually happening in the case of in the case of
doing the C++ way.
So steps two and three move into the class, right?
They move they move in the responsibility for that is no longer in the
outside.
It's on the inside of the struct, right?
And so the reason that C++ had to introduce new and delete was because
now you needed a way of saying, I want to do a Malik follow.
By the initialization I wanted to do step one and step two and that is
what new means.
And similarly to be symmetric, they needed to introduce a way to say I
want to do step 3 and step 4.
And that is what delete means, right?
So the time when you have to use new and delete is really, very
simple.
Did you want the compiler to call the Constructor?
Did you want the compiler to call the destructor?
Or didn't you?
That's it.
Now, it's worth noting that sometimes you really don't have a choice
in this struct that I have here.
It would be trivial for you to balak it and just not, you don't have
to call new, even if it's got a Constructor in it, if you didn't want
the Constructor to run, you could just call malloc, right?
Doesn't matter.
But suppose you were to introduce a virtual.
Chen Heaven, help you first, you would get fired from my team but then
second what would happen is inside this this struct Foo, the compiler
would silently introduced a pointer to what's called a vtable, which
is a dispatch table.
That is how it actually implements virtual functions right now.
You have no way of initializing that virtual table yourself because
you don't even know where that you don't know anything about that.
That's a compiler detail.
Right?
And so, one of the things new also does is it initializes any hidden
information that you did not put there but the compiler did.
And so if you start using compiler features, C++ features that the
compiler needs to augment the structure of the class width and which
have important initialization that has to happen.
You must call new.
Even if you don't care about the compiler, calling your Constructor
because the compiler,
Are essentially has a Constructor that has to get called.
And it is the initialization of that V table.
Okay.
so yeah, hopefully that gives you some perspective on what new and
delete are and when you have to call them, the reason we don't need to
call them in handmade Heroes because I find them be completely
Superfluous in a relevant because if I wanted a function that both
Malik to memory and initialize my thing,
I just write the function.
I just write a function called a lock and in it and I passed the print
like new and delete are literally two of the worst ideas I've ever
seen.
I have no idea why they were written that way.
They don't make any sense to me at all.
They're really, really, really stupid right?
The correct way to have added them to the language.
If you wanted to get the features that you were going to to get there.
I think would have been to just have a way of doing a stack call.
So saying like the thing that this thing returns is a stack call is is
on the stack, you know, move semantics.
Basically as they call them nowadays probably would have been the
thing to implement because then you wouldn't ever care about these at
all.
But yeah, so I never use these because they're literally worthless in
my opinion, I don't think they ever have a point but like I said, if
you ever start doing things like virtual function calls, you don't
have a choice.
You're going to have to do them now.
Mind you
You know, this kind of gets into C++ programming which I don't care
about but like I said, you know, as much as I bagged on other
languages like Java and C++ or whatever on the stream that's just
because I don't like them, right?
But if you like them, you should use them right?
You know, there's people should program in the language that they want
to use.
So if you are someone who does like C++ in your programming in C++,
again, keep in mind.
You do have other options here.
There's a thing called a placement.
New right, which is a way of telling the compiler.
Order to generate the code that it needs to generate to initialize an
object without allocating the memory, right?
So, if you want to just do Step 2 or just do step 3, you can actually
do those.
And so, if you weren't aware of that, you know, go read about that.
That's something that is pretty important, to be able to do, if you
want to do sort of advanced memory management stuff and see, I mean
C++, it's relevant
Could you briefly comment on how viable it would be to recast?
The problem, as one as asset packing, split sounds into fixed size
chunks and dice bitmaps into fixed size tiles.
So that all the tiles are a reasonable science group related assets
together.
So that they are loaded together that sort of thing.
So, you're talking about elaborate more than what I said.
Already back when I talked about the option here, are you talking
about more students sitting in my you're talking about more than this
elaboration?
Because this is what that is.
Right.
Mega texture is basically what that is, right?
It's just you pack all of the assets into a giant bitmap effectively
and then you break it up into two phases by two basic Styles.
Then you have to figure out some way that you're going to deal with
the fact that your assets now have to list variable length tiles in
them.
But like I said, that's probably okay because you can probably fit
that all in memory and flat loaded, the beginning, kind of like we do
with our asset tags.
So that's you know, that's rough.
What that would look like and you do the same thing for sounds.
You just have a giant sound one giant sound, which is arbitrarily
long, and you'd break that into chunks of say, you know, I don't know.
Sixty-four thousand samples or something, right?
And you just what, you know, what I'd probably do.
Is I'd make it to I'd make the sound chunks.
Be 256 by 256 by 4, right?
I make it be that many bites, right?
So that everything could be swapped uniformly, right?
So I make everything, be 256k, everything would be a 256k chunk.
Is there a real philosophy difference between using smart pointers and
using garbage collection, or are smart pointers just a way to
implement garbage collection?
So, you know, first of all, let's clarify what you mean by smart
pointers because smart pointers in.
You know, sometimes you say smart pointers, people think Otto pointer
right in C++.
And so, and that's a pointer that like freeze automatically, right,
and it's worth noting that like that's not the same thing as garbage
collection.
Even at a feature level, right?
Because if you have two things that both Auto,
Enter to the same.
Then it's an error because when one gets freed, it'll delete it, and
the other one was still trying to point to it, right?
So you can't just use something like an auto pointer and get what
garbage collection gives you because garbage collection actually gives
you reference counted pointers right.
And so smart pointer, if I smart pointer, you mean a pointer which
does reference counting on the target.
Then yes, that is a way of implementing.
What is essentially garbage collection?
No.
But it's not the same as a general-purpose garbage collector because
the jumpers garbage collector, could be a lot more efficient than that
potentially, because it can know things about the usage patterns that
that pigeonhole thing that a reference kind of player does can't tell.
Right.
So I would say, philosophically speaking garbage, collection isn't
super different from reference counted pointers.
That's true.
But you know, there's also the concept of of liveness and how it
actually gets how that actually gets handled.
so,
there's kind of an island concept, right?
So, I'll just sketch it out, briefly, it's stupid.
But, so let's say, I have object, a, and object B.
Right object, a stores, a pointed object, B, be stored as a pointed
object.
A right, I've got a pointer to both A and B, okay?
So let's pretend that this situation occurs, how does it occur in
practice?
Right.
I'll actually do it sort of step by step.
Okay, step one allocate a right, I create one, right?
I want to use the word allocate.
I'll just say you know we get a new a so however that happens in your
language.
So what happens there?
Well, now there's a pointer from the outside world right into a.
So it's reference count goes up, right?
It's actually reference count is 1.
Now then I get a newbie.
Okay, so that means the world now has a pointer to a b and that
reference count goes up.
Yeah.
Step 3.
I have a point to be right.
Like so, so it's reference count goes up by one step for I have be
point to a right.
So it's reference count goes up by 1.
Now, step 5, I stopped.
You know, I stopped using a right?
So this world pointer to a goes away.
It's reference count goes down by one, so it's reference.
Count is now just one step.
Six I stopped using be.
So now this world pointer to be goes away.
Its reference count goes down by one.
Right?
So now it's just, it's just a reference, kind of one.
If these were just reference counted pointers you now have an island,
which is course the term for saying, you know.
All right, this A, and B point to each other and are mutually
supporting each other with a reference count.
Nobody gets freed.
There is no way to ever access these.
Again, they are no longer used the world, the pointers from the
outside into them are gone, but because they mutually support each
other, they will stay alive for the rest of the program and that is
effectively a memory leak, right?
So some garbage collection algorithms can detect this right?
Good garbage.
Collections collection, algorithms do Walks from the live set of
pointers things that it knows our lives out to see if things are being
mutually supported like this and realize that there's an island and
get rid of the Island.
Right?
So a good garbage collector, can do that a reference counted pointer
can't really do that.
So for certain use cases philosophically like
Feature wise, I should say again there's a difference there.
So a garbage collector is typically a more powerful thing than the
kind of pointer you're probably envisioning.
Let's see, the sizzix.
What about resource?
Acquisition is initialization.
So resource acquisition, so he said are a AI that stands for resource
acquisition
Is initialization.
For those of you who don't know what that is, what that basically.
Out early even know if I want to explain it.
it's a modern programming Trend that basically says,
If you are conceptualizing things in terms of object, because it
doesn't really make any sense, it doesn't actually have a meaning
outside of opportunity program to some degree because without the
notion of some like unit of data, it's hard to describe what it would
even mean, right?
But thinking about it in those terms, right?
If you have an object,
Then the idea is that the object should be considered initialized once
it has acquired its resources, right?
Meaning I should not have the ability for objects to exist in
partially initialized states where they have acquired some butt.
All of their resources or something along those lines, right?
So the classic example of resource acquisition is initialization is
just saying like, I mean to give up this is a pretty stupid example,
but if I had an object
You know, don't make an object, that's has to file pointers in it.
Right?
Because when I when I go to initialize, this object there's no way for
me to actually do a single initialization step that will make these
both valid.
So it's entirely possible that I got one of them and not the other
one, right?
It's not really good example because you could still at that point,
just going to just throw the exception there and trying to think of
what the best example would be for someone who's never looked at this
game before.
I mean I guess I can still describe it in terms of that.
It's what I just said, which is that if I did want to have an object
that had to file pointers, it has to only be used.
It has to only come into existence when those are both valid, right?
And so this is where you get into exception handling and all those
other sorts of things.
So, what is trying to say is like, okay, when I Define this object,
right?
And I say I've got struct Foo.
Okay.
And I've got my Foo Constructor here and then I've got these two file
Stars, right?
I've got file star, a and file star, b or whatever.
Right in this Constructor.
The idea behind resources position is initialization, is inside the
Constructor.
I need to get both A and B and if for some reason I don't get them
right.
I need to abort and the reason why I was kind of saying that if you
have two of them, you shouldn't do that.
Is because generally the reason that people care about this and the
reason why they sort of fallaciously think it's a good idea, is
because
The destructor for my thing.
Should be able to do the clean up properly, right?
And so if I make it through the Constructor for the object, then I
know that my Destructor will clean it up.
If I don't make it through, then there shouldn't have to be clean up
because if they're did have to be clean up, no one's going to be able
to do it because the destructor won't run, right?
Because if I did a and I try to F open the A and it doesn't work if I
threw an exception here, right?
I'm fine.
If I do a and it works and I do B and it doesn't work and I throw an
exception here.
Now, I'm messed up because this file handle leaked, right?
So the idea is, if you only acquire one,
Horse and you only free one resource in your objects, right?
Then you kind of know that you can always rely on the destructor to
free.
The thing that you allocated in the first place, right?
And so the way that they, you know, sort of advocate programming with
resource acquisition is initialization, is making it so that all of
your code is basically constructed in this fashion where if there was
a need for multiple things to happen, those are actually separate
objects.
Right.
So, the way they would probably Advocate that you did.
This was to say that, okay, instead of having an object that's got to
file pointers, what I do instead is I make a file object, right?
And a file object is just
File.
And then the object that I was making over here is going to be to file
objects, right?
It's going to be file object, a and file object B.
And that way, when I go into my Constructor and I've got a b, c d,
right?
They get initialized up here in the Minish Eliezer list and I'm sorry
for people who don't know C++, I don't want to explain it because it's
all stupid and a waste of time, but for the people who asked the
question.
So in here, you would start actually initializing these guys, and what
will happen?
There is, if one of them fails, it will throw an exception, which will
unwind that initialization and call the destructor codes.
Which will clean them up one at a time.
However, many of them actually got initialized, right?
So that's that's resources.
Acquisition is initialization, there's more to it.
I mean, that's not a complete explanation of kind of how it works.
But just for knowing for people who've, literally don't know anything
about it.
It's trying to say that the acquisition of something that needs to be,
why should you can begin even broader?
The notion of a resource is just something that has to have shut down,
right?
As soon as you have gotten something that needs to be shut down, that
is the end of your work.
That that that is you have now initialize up into freeing, the part
where you will free is going to take care of the symmetric operation
of freeing that.
So that you know that you're not ending up with a lot of things that
some of them might be initialized on the might not.
And how do I clean that up, right?
So, I don't like this programming model at all.
It's it's really just kind of dumb.
I don't really know why people like it.
I think it's probably for people who aren't super maybe super aren't
super versed in actually like production code or something people
who've kind of think about code more theoretically maybe, but the
reason that it's not very good is because you, you, you basically
obvious Kate the part of the system that was actually the problem in
the first place, right?
So the problem with the code that they were trying to solve because
the because with restart, the only reason you care about resource
acquisition is initialization.
Is if something goes wrong right?
Because if nothing goes wrong then
it doesn't matter how many things you
Initialized, right?
Because you could you could digitize 50 things and then shut down 50
things and it wouldn't matter, right?
So the reason to break things up into things that do a single
acquisition and then a single shutdown is so you can handle an error,
right?
If you have an error, then you know that that you were going to, you
know, unwind or whatever, right?
The problem is error, handling is usually more complicated than this,
right?
What?
Usually you want to do an error.
Handling situation is actually look at what the are actually.
Was and take corrective action and these kinds of systems are
fantastically brittle because the only thing they can do is unwind but
unwinding may not be what you wanted, right?
And so yeah the sort of inexorable binding of this to like a wrote
series of steps that have to be done symmetrically, just ruins all of
the flexibility that you had in a handling errors and be handling
shutdown, right?
Um, because now, you don't know the difference between shutting down
in a normal scenario and shutting down an error scenario, they both
have to do the same thing essentially, right because all of your stuff
was written in this way.
Whether you have these little guys who just do Alec free or whatever,
right?
And there's no way to get like more information into them because
you've constructed them in this way.
That you know you've got these guys with hundreds of little tiny
objects in them that all do these sort of symmetric operations and now
you don't have the option of doing them as a batch because the whole
point of
Of resource acquisition is initialization.
Is that they were done individually, right?
The trivial example is I want to have the choice of using this thing
where I've allocated a block of memory, but they all use versus one
were, you know, it's just a narrow piece of memory, right?
Well if these people don't know, if they're all written to like do
their malloc and free.
Well, now, it's like impossible for me to do an asymmetric version
where I, you know, allocated them in sort of this block or whatever,
right?
It just, it encourages you to write this really stupid code, which
always does exactly the same thing.
This is what the situation actually wanted you to do and that's true
for the error handling part and for the resource acquisition part
which is what this kind of is all about.
So I really don't recommend that resource acquisition is
initialization.
I don't use it myself and I strongly recommend against it but that's
what it is.
It's sort of this notion of keeping those things.
Tightly coupled symmetrically.
Let's see how about vibration affect assets, I don't think we're going
to have any vibration, effect assets, soy sauce, the kid, what is it
in between Mega texture and texture Atlas?
So, it depends a texture.
Atlas is basically the same
Bang Mega texture when I say that, it's megatexture involves other
things.
It's part of like how the query works and it it's how you do the the
texture coordinates into it.
So there are two different.
There are two different flavors of a similar thing.
Mega texture is more includes the 3D pieces of it, but but if you know
it at a texture Atlas is, that's basically what I was talking about.
Do you object-- to you to the use of explicit V tables like you would
have to use Encino?
I'm actually fine with supposed to be tables.
In fact what I what I wish C++ had done is instead of making V tables
and implicit thing is I wish that what C++ I've been about when they
decided to introduce, those concept was actually giving you the tools
to write code about V tables conveniently that would have been useful.
What they did was not useful implicit V.
Tables are almost never useful
But if they had given you good tools for making your own V tables.
Like, for example, what John blows doing in j.i., that would have been
very useful.
So,
With thinking about asset allocation in terms of maximum amount of
pixels that can be displayed on screen at one time.
Be worth it for instance, with your 16, MB safety buffer.
So you tailor the asset loading to load assets at a resolution
proportional to the distance of the camera and operate under the
assumption that only a fixed number of things.
Could physically occupy, the high risk space and so on for medium
load, Etc.
Yes, that is actually how we do it in the engine that I did for what
we're doing at Molly rocket right now.
That is not really necessary necessary for handmade hero because in
Here we don't do a lot of zooming.
Right hand made here as a 2-D game that basically takes place at the
same zoom level or close to it pretty much all the time, right?
Like a Zelda game doesn't zoom out or zoom in a lot that's just not
what it does.
So for this game we don't really need to do that but that's a totally
valid thing to do and if you have a if you're expecting a 2-D game
where the assets get zoomed in and zoomed out on a lot, that's a very
good thing to do.
Do because you want to be able to load the assets at different
resolutions.
So you would actually have, you know, sort of MIT mapped versions of
all of your assets that you would load, dynamically and stuff like
that too, right?
There's a lot of other things that you would be doing there.
If zooming was something, you were targeting heavily students, every
three.
Yeah, the thing I didn't see was grouping small related assets
together, so they fit in one allocation unit.
Yes.
So basically, what you would do,
In this scheme is you just pack all of your Sprites into one giant
bitmap, right?
So and you just pack them as closely as you can.
And so that way you can just load out of it and you just grab out the
piece that you need, right?
So that's how that works.
Is this still the same Blackboard file from day one?
Not quite, we didn't find Mischief as a black boarding tool until day
you know, 20 or 30 or something.
I don't remember.
But otherwise.
Yes.
And if you would like to view it yourself it comes with the pre-order.
Actually, if you take a look at
See here, if you take a look, if you pre-ordered the game unpack, the
source code and look in hand in the misc directory, I think oh wait,
no it's not in this directory.
It's actually just in the zip file.
It's just in that the source zip file.
It's right in the sort of that file and it's there.
It's Blackboard to Art and you can actually load it with the free
version of Mischief.
So if you want, you can load, you can go down.
The free version of mischief and zoom around the Blackboard all you
want.
So that that's actually comes with the pre-order.
All right.
let's,
Let's close this down.
No, there we go.
Okay, everyone, thank you for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the code at home,
like I just referred to with the Blackboard or other things like that.
You can always pre-order the game on handmade here a.org and it comes
with the source code.
So every night, I update the source code, and you can follow along
with the game as it is developed.
You can also go to our Forum site if you have questions and want to
ask questions or get ports to Mac and Linux that community members
have done or look at our anti depa sewed guide.
Which community members have done.
You can also, if you want support this video series pledge to our
patreon page.
We always very much.
Appreciate that.
And then we also have a tweetbot which tweets the schedule at you.
So if you want to catch the stream live, it's a great place to go.
So you kind of know when it's coming up, that's all the stuff we've
got up there.
So check that out.
If you're trying to file the video series, we will be back here
tomorrow at 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time to do a little bit more work on this asset
memory management.
So we'll do kind of the very rudimentary thing tomorrow.
So we're we're just kind of allocating and freeing and not thinking
too much about it and then we'll slowly try to make that a little bit
better.
And that's really what we'll do for this week.
I don't know exactly how long it will take, but, you know, it
shouldn't be too much of an adventure, but it will take a little bit
of work on our part.
So, you know, plan for a couple of days of us getting the assets
system memory management, correct?
Alright, so I hope to see you back here tomorrow for that until then
have fun programming and I will see you guys on the internet.