All right.
Hello everyone.
And welcome to handmade hero.
The show that we Cody complete game live on stream on Twitch.
No Engines, new libraries, just us, and we are taking a look at
absolutely everything that goes into making a game right down to
software rendering like they did in the old days, is what we're
working on right now.
And like we talked about in the pre stream.
Why are we doing this?
Because man, it is hard to find good low-level programmers.
These days if you need one for a project.
Working on, good luck, finding one.
And so on, handmade hero, what we try to do is encourage people to not
be all about.
Let me go grab some library and I have no idea how it works.
And I'm not going to try to optimize that because I don't even know,
optimization is none of that nonsense.
This is all about if something needs optimizing.
You are the guy who can go in there and no problem, right?
So with that, in mind, let us get down to some optimization.
Here we are.
Right in the middle of it.
We just, this is basically our week their first week of optimization
and we're just about to talk.
Well, not about talk but to actually go do some symbolization of some
code.
So let's go ahead and do that if you want to follow along at home and
you downloaded the source code because you preorder the game on
handmade hero to org, please make sure you've downloaded the latest
Source zip and then what you can do is unzip day 115 source code.
That's
I'm on right now.
All right.
So, this is actually going to be pretty easy because we set it up to
do yesterday.
You remember, move this over here, keyboard little more centered.
You will remember that we have our program here, draw a rectangle
hopefully quickly and what we did is we set it up.
So that basically there was a little block of code that happens for
four pixels at a time.
That's all math operations and we were going to take that as the first
thing that we need to do so that you could see I could I could show
you very simply how we turn some code into SIM decode using the Intel
suggested compiler, intrinsics that are built into base.
Any compound that you're going to use these days are built into msv.
See they're built into GCC.
They built it to llvm.
So pretty much no matter what platform you happen to be targeting.
You can actually write code basically exactly the same as what.
I'm going to write today.
The only time that you can't do this is when you have to port to like
a processor, like a neon, like a arm processor, but the concepts are
still all the same.
And so when we do look at a port, will probably try to look at a port
to arm some time in the distant future.
We will show how to deal with that but basically what it involves
doing.
Is just kind of usually just using some macros to switch from using
the Intel intrinsics to using the arm style intrinsics that it's not a
whole lot to it.
It's not like having to write a completely different piece of code and
there's a lot of stuff that just carries through.
So anyway, that's what we're doing today.
I want to do one simple thing first before we actually write those
Cindy things just so you can sort of see a little bit better.
What's going on?
There's there's something that I wanted to do now if you remember,
we've got this going here.
We have a little debug cycle counter thing.
That's telling us how many cycles are happening for our code, right?
And of course, right now, we were compiling in debug mode.
So these are all kind of crazy cycle counts.
So what I want to do is I want to just switch us back just for a
second to running in the optimized build, right?
This is this - 02 that makes us makes the compiler, not do anything,
crazy and stupid.
So basically if you if you take a look at what our
What our stuff is doing now.
Here you go.
And what you can see here is the actual cycle count has gone up pretty
dramatically, from what it used to be, right?
And the reason for that is because we've made this code a lot worse by
me, setting it up to do the Cindy, right?
We have these ridiculous for, I Loops in there now, which are, you
know, we're we've confused the compiler fairly heavily by introducing
all of this extra stuff.
So even though basically the same sort of stuff is happening, there's
You know, there's issues there and also, you know, we you know, the
compiler would have to be very smart to figure out that, okay.
This should fill matches with a bunch of other ones stuff so that we
confuse the compiler.
So it's a lot slower than it used to be, but that's fine.
Because, like I said, you know, we remember what it was, it was like,
200 something Cycles, you know, you kind of remember what we were
doing there.
It's not a big deal but what I did want to do is I wanted to do
something where we could, we could do, without doing this count time.
Block test pixel in here,
R.
We could start to time.
How many?
How many cycles per pixel?
This block actually did take over a wider range, right?
And the reason for this, the reason that I'm thinking about this is
because if you think about it, we're actually injecting like this.
Begin time, block has to call an instruction, to get the time stamp
counter and then this end block has to call instruction to get the
time stamp stamp counter, right?
That's the issue an instruction and it has issued some instructions to
update the time, stamp counter and it
To pull in whatever that time stamp, counter storage is in the cache,
right?
So if we did that on every set of four pixels, we're actually
increasing the amount of work that we have to do and potentially
polluting the cash, right?
We're ruining sort of our Loop by putting the timing into it.
So what I'd like to do is move the timer outside.
Right?
So that we have a timer right around the block here, like so where we
have a timer around, just the block that actually does all of the
filling, right?
And I could even do it.
Just so we're just around the for Loops, right?
So now we have test pixel there and what I want to do, you know, you
can see if we if we actually compile it now and run it.
What you can see is that we've got two Loops that are basically, you
know, they're more or less the same.
Here's the test pixel to me.
Here's the test pixel Loop and I should actually highlight these
values.
These are the, these are the totals.
What is actually?
You know, I'm going to actually, we haven't actually needed to do this
yet.
I'm going to do this, just so I can make it easier for myself to see,
which one is, which here.
We don't actually have names on these guys yet either.
Where is here at here?
Is my list of guys.
So we don't actually have names on these guys, so it's kind of
annoying.
To actually see which ones they are.
But well, you know, I won't do it yet.
We can actually see.
Which one's these are at the moment, but just by looking at the
numbers here, you can see later on, we'll do better debug counters.
Don't worry guys, I like to focus on one thing at a time.
So anyway, you can see here.
Number 3 would be test, pixel.
And number five would be drunk to know, hopefully quickly now test
pixel is not really good name for this anymore, so I'm going to change
this one over to Phil pixel.
it's basically, we
We are filling all the pixels now or just like, let's just even due
process pixel.
That makes a little more sense.
I'm going to delete the other guys.
Okay.
So I'm going to go ahead and do it this way.
This way across this pixel.
Okay, there we go.
This is draw a rectangle slowly.
I forgot we had these in here.
Get rid of these.
All right, so now we should have you know, basically a listing here.
So this one is we never call the other team so we only have three and
four here.
This one is processed pixel, right?
And this one is draw a rectangle slowly.
So you can kind of see that they both get called 64 times and
obviously the the total time for the routine is a little bit more
perk.
All right, a little bit more and that's just a
Cost, right?
You can see that there's a little difference between these two.
That's the set up cost and then this is just the loops.
So most of the time is spent in those Loops, right?
So, what I want to do now that I time the loop right in draw a
rectangle quickly.
Once I've timed the loop, what I'd like to do is I'd like to now go
ahead and tell it how many pixels I did because I know how many pixels
I've done, right?
I've got my y Min, my y Max.
I know I do one Loop through for each of those, right?
And
I've got my X Min and x max.
I know I do one Loop through for each of those.
So if I just multiply those two together I know how many pixels I feel
right it's just the area of that rectangle.
So what I want to do is do an end time block counted, right?
Where I just pass in what I think the time actually was and I have
that do that.
So it's X-Men plus, I'm sorry it's X-Men minus x max plus 1 right
because we're actually filling that x max.
We're actually looking at that X Max and xmax.
Why Max minus minus YN plus 1.
I believe that's how many pixels were actually filling their right.
And what I'd like to do is just go ahead and use that count.
So what I can do is I can go into handmade platform and I can take
this macro that we were using to end the time block before, right?
And I can do end time block counted where I pass in that count and
then instead of it doing a plus plus on the hit count, what it will
actually do is just add the count to the hit count.
Like so, right?
So that's that's pretty easy.
I'm going to wrap that in that seat just in case.
There's anything weird going on there.
And so, you know, now when we run it, what we should see is we should
see our our fill pixel count counted much, much more, more accurately,
okay?
And now we see that has gone back to the value that we expected to
have, which is, which is much better, right?
So, I think that the artist pixel must have gotten, the reason we were
getting that weird 900 before was not because it can probably was
getting too.
As I was, I was kind of a little shocked that that was the case.
It looks like we just misplaced the the we had still had the end in
there in some kind of errant way.
So now we're timing the whole Loop and then we're dividing by the
number of things through it.
And so now we're getting a value for cycles per pixel without having
to time, each individual pixel block, which takes a little bit of the,
in accuracy out of it.
Hopefully, because now we know that we're not injecting essentially
instructions into the stream that we are trying to time, okay?
So there's our 243 cycles per hit and now what I'd like to do is I'd
like to go ahead and show
How to write some of this Insanity.
So what we're going to do is we're just going to take one thing first
and we're going to do the simplest possible way to write it in in
Cindy, we're going to do it.
Take it one step at a time, very slowly.
Now, you remember for everything yesterday, we talked about, we're
basically talking about registers that hold for values at once, okay?
And so I'm just going to Define one of those Hoops, two underscores.
I'm just going to Define one of those registers.
And so I'm going to replace text, Alejo.
Are right with one of those.
And then all I'm going to do is I'm going to make Texel AR.
I actually I sized you up here because this is where we first actually
do it.
I'm going to make Texel AR pass through the entire thing as if it is
one of these registers, okay?
So I'm going to say Texel, a are defined up here and I'm going to get
rid of the text layer that we had.
And so then what I'm going to do is going to look in here and you can
see, here's where we loaded in and we're not actually going to write
the loading code and Cindy yet, like I said, but so we're just
Just going to take Texel AR and we're going to set one of the members
of it, right?
And the way that this works is there's actually this this part.
And fortunately, this part won't persist for very long.
This part only works on Visual Studio.
On, Microsoft's compiler for whatever reason.
Microsoft's compiler, allows you to access the members of this thing
as a as an index, whereas the llvm compiler.
Like doesn't have the same Syntax for it.
For some reason, they picked different ways you can actually do it,
but you can't do it the way that I'm doing it here, but I'm going to
do it because it's a little easier for people to see.
Well, you know what I guess, like,
I guess if I had to, I could do it the other way, like we could do it
this way, right?
We could change it to a float pointer, like so and do it this way.
So I'll, you know, I'll do it this way just for the benefit of the
people who are, who are programming GCC.
So there you go.
Okay.
So what this is doing is this is basically saying, okay, take the
address of of the of that wide value that for wide value and
And pretend it's a pointer to a float and then you set the eye of the
value of it.
Right?
Because remember these things in memory are just for values so they
can just be addressed exactly that way.
Now you don't want to do this if you're actually trying to write
optimized code.
So when we optimize this section we won't want to do this.
The reason for that is because we want to work with it in registers
and do things much more efficiently than having the compiler have to
do as memory but the compiler may actually understand this as well and
do something smarter will see either way we won't be leaving this in
but
Now we'll do that just so we can not touch the loading code, if that
makes sense.
So that will put that in there and then when we take a look at text
Texel a are here.
What I want to do is take a look at everywhere that Texel AR is used
and what you can see is that Texel AR is only used there at the top in
terms of modifications.
And then down here in the bottom, you can see that it's just gets red
when it does this, this lerp right to produce, the final Texel our
value.
So what we can do is for now we can just we can change again.
This this textile a are here, we can change this.
Use of it.
Into that same way of accessing it, that that text layer is afloat.
And then what we can do is pull just this computation outside the loop
and we can now do this.
Instead of doing it inside a loop for four values, what we can do is
we can actually just operate on it as if it was for y.
And so Texel AR, which is now four wide be.
It's just going to be a series of instructions that operate on this
thing as if it were for values already, right?
So I'm going to take one second here to actually do that and then you
will see what I'm talking about.
Okay, so this is the Cindy code that does exactly what we just wanted.
And like I said, all we're doing is instead of putting that
multiplication in there.
Mmm, mul PS just tells the compiler.
This is specifically the
Traction.
I want you to issue, I want you to issue a 4 wide multiply of these
two values.
And then I want you to another four wide value of these two right now
this is a little confusing because we need to multiply by a constant
here.
And so what we need to do is anytime that we were using a constant
before like in 50 to 55 we need to make a corresponding constant.
That is 4 wide of the same value and like we covered the other day.
We can do that very easily by just asking the compiler to generate one
of those
Things that is basically just this this single floating-point constant
broadcast to all four lanes.
It's called a broadcast sometimes.
But you know, just it's setting it in all four positions.
So now we have a wide version of are in 50 to 55, right?
And this is literally just saying, hey processor, please do a 4 wide
X, PS stands for packed singles.
Pack single floating Point values and packed means for it was a bad
choice pack.
Pack is a ambiguous statement this case but that's just what they
called it.
This is Multiplied packed and the two things that we're going to do
basically that's it if that makes sense.
Hey I don't I don't know why the compiler thinks we didn't initialize
that value.
I guess it's it's having trouble understanding what this is.
So I will go ahead and temporarily just initialize it to nothing but
that's that's kind of annoying.
Set 1 PS.
There you go.
Are you happy now compiler?
Because we don't actually want to initialize that.
All right, and when I run this, we can actually see that.
It's actually still producing the correct result or at least, you
know, as far as we can tell.
Anyway, and we're good to go.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead and turn off for just temporarily since
we're not timing.
Anything at the moment that we are looking at in terms of we're just
working through the code, I'm going to turn on debug mode so you can
actually see what's happening in there and I don't know why it never
keeps our
It never keeps.
Our render file open, right?
Oops,
it's hopefully quickly or rectangle.
Location.
Hopefully quickly.
Yeah.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to show you what happens
there so you can kind of see what's going on.
So we step down here and well actually, I guess I could show you what
happens here as well.
So we step into for, I can't.
I don't know why that didn't go because this is not a should fill.
Oh, that's why it's complaining.
Okay, it just doesn't like the fact that we're multiplying things.
That maybe we didn't fill.
That's okay.
Actually though, I mean assuming we
Have any floating-point exceptions on.
We don't care about that because we wouldn't actually use the results.
Yeah, I don't know how to tell the compiler that but it doesn't
matter.
Anyway, let's actually step to where we actually got are going to fill
stuff in.
And we can set a watch here on this text layer value, right?
And you can see, if we take a look at the text layer value in in
Visual Studio anyway, like I said, it defines this as a union, so you
can look at the actual values of it.
So, cure is the F32 component.
That's if you want it, because remember, this is just all.
This is is a 128-bit value.
And, depending, on what instructions, we use it chooses to treat it as
one of any of these things.
They, it could be signed.
He pitted teachers that are 16 wide.
It could be to unsigned 64-bit integers, blah, blah, blah, right?
So it's giving us basically a bunch of options as to how we choose to
interpret this thing because it doesn't know, right?
And so we initialize it to zero because the compiler was being whiny
about things.
So here is it initialized to zero and you can see what we're about to
do is load into the zeroth member of it.
It looks like the actual sample, a value there.
Is actually zero.
So it doesn't actually set a tiny things.
That's not very exciting.
Looks like all of them are 0, so that's, that's unfortunate.
But that's just what happened to be.
So we're not actually loading anything in there.
That's not very much fun, and this is not gonna be very much fun
either, but unfortunately, that's just the pixel that we happen to
have.
I guess I could try to see if I can get to any non zero pixels first
or I could set an if statement in there I suppose.
Oops, I mean to do that.
Let's actually do.
Fifth Texel AR.
.
Oops and one 2832, excuse me.
Oh, right, I'm not supposed to do that.
Quote star.
Yeah.
Okay.
This will allow me to set a breakpoint.
when we actually have a value in there,
So there we go.
So here's textile.
AR and now, it's got some values in there.
You can see that it has some values in there.
Now, remember we loaded out, straight out, straight up color values,
which are 0 to 255, and we just turned them into floats, right?
That's all we did.
So there's, they're not in the range of 0 to 1.
They're still in the range 0 to 255.
So, what we're about to do wide is we're going to multiply and you can
see our constant here that we loaded.
We are about to multiply this by this, and this is just one over to
55, the inverse operation, to normalize this ranges.
And what we're going to do with this multiply is
Multiply them all at once and so there you can see them all.
They all got multiplied, the same time, and then we're going to square
it to do the light linear approximation.
There you go.
And so now that we've done basically what we were doing in a loop over
four values, we just did all at once, right?
It's literally that simple.
That is the basic way that you Cindy ice code, right?
So hopefully that's pretty clear to everyone.
There's really nothing fancy going on here.
That's about it.
And so, all of this stuff,
Tough a gabaa and so on we can actually do exactly the same way.
So if you take a look here, we can also do a be in exactly the same
way.
And we can do a g in exactly the same way.
Right.
I guess I should put these in the right order there, AG in exactly the
same way.
Like, so, and we could even make this a, you know, a little bit
clearer by adding a square, macro.
We could have kept this.
We could keep this exactly the same way that it was now right by doing
a like a, you know, some kind of an M&M Square thing, right?
That would just go around this and do the squaring for us and it would
just look like, you know, Define m square, a
Would just be equal to the call to mull, PS?
Right.
Would just be that.
So you can do all the same stuff that you would have done in here.
And so I think that's a little clearer, right?
That makes sense pretty straightforward.
So we can actually make our own macros or make our own anything.
You can even make your own functions inline functions.
You can use these things anyway that you really want to.
There are some caveats that we'll get to a little bit later with
alignment.
But for now
Can think about this way.
All right.
So that's pretty much all we need to do there.
And we've got a different thing that we were doing here to Texel a,
which is we were just doing this mole PS on it.
We were not doing the square.
So we want to make sure that we handle that properly.
So there's our AAA.
And so that replaces, essentially all of this code, right?
All of this stuff that was happening in the loop can work that way,
right?
So we want to do here is convert texture from 0 to 255 srgb to linear
021 rightness.
Sprite.
So that does this and we're going to do this exact same thing.
For all of this, for all of the, for all of these guys, right, we're
going to do this exact same thing, Texel ARA gabaa.
We're going to do that for for the B version of all of our stuff too.
So we could literally just duplicate this, right?
And off, we go.
So in here, Texel a comes sex with be in here, text, a it comes text
will see and hear Texel a becomes Texel D and now you
can still see it and we could even collapse.
Further we could make a little macro to do this whole thing which
maybe we want to do but I'm going to leave stuff a little expanded
right now just so people can see it because for people who've this is
their first experience with this.
It may be a little confusing and I want them to be able to see all the
instructions.
So it's not all hidden up in any in any complex way, right?
So all right, that's that's all of these, right?
All of this stuff now can can go away, basically.
And then all we have to do is
Is is change these guys to actually be using this, this sort of float
load, but I'd rather not do that because I feel like it'd be easier
for us to actually just do this operation wide as well, right?
Because we kind of know showing how to do them now so we don't really
need to take quite such baby steps.
We could just make this whole thing be wide as well, right?
So what I could do is I can go ahead and take this guy out here.
We can start to lock these guys out and make these guys,
Is that too much?
I don't know.
I don't want to go too fast for people.
So what I could do you know here's what I could do?
I could do like just something like a simple macro to help us at the
moment where we do something like this and then all that is is just
whatever.
The thing is that we were talking about, it takes the address of it
and then accesses the eye of the value of it like so.
And and then I could do this a little
More straightforward, right?
Does that make sense?
Hopefully, that makes some sense and that would just mean that we can
take this one step at a time.
I don't want to go, I don't want to like, Cindy eyes the whole thing
and, and have everyone get lost.
So, what I want to do is make sure that I go at a speed that everyone
can follow, okay?
And see what we're doing.
Step by step, that makes sense.
And then, you know, once once everyone's kind of comfortable with
this, then we won't in the future.
Spend a lot of time doing doing things and
You know in a step-by-step fashion maybe we'll go will jump a little
further and maybe you know do a little more of like just go ahead and
do it and then we'll do bug any problems that we have step through it
kind of thing rather than taking it sort of piece by piece but the
first time out might as well go slow.
Excuse me.
All right, so what we have to do now is we have to and I'm, you know
what I want, I kind of want this to happen everywhere here.
All right.
So what I would like to do is I would like this to be there.
Like, so, and so that way, we can also convert all the rest of these.
So, if I do em, I that I can now poops
Convert all the rest of these.
So that everything in the textile set is in a proper.
M 128.
this is probably something I should have made a macro for just now,
but what you going to do
I'm having a bad typing day-to-day.
It's problem is this is a very narrow desk that I have in here.
It's just a little it's not even really a desk.
It's this cheap thing.
I bought on Amazon to hold the handmade hero thing in a off in the
side room because it's not a very big apartment.
And so, when we do handmade hero, I try not to drive my wife insane.
So I don't do handmade hero out in the, in the main room of our
apartment.
So,
II bought this little it's kind of like an artist's easel thing but
it's a drafting table that's what it is.
All right?
So where is our em?
Put that up there?
Okay.
Just need to.
That a little further down.
There we go.
And all of these guys, now have to be defined as as actual in 128 and
unfortunately, that means I have to do this.
So the compiler will because the compiler will keep complaining, which
is a 9.
But we can fix that later.
And it's totally fine for the compiler to complain.
It's technically, correct.
We have some stuff that we're going to need to do, it doesn't really
understand how the pixel setting and getting stuck like masking and
stuff works.
So, we'll deal with that, a little later on.
That's not really our primary concern right now.
Primary concern is just converting this code into stuff that operates
wide.
And then, once we're done with that, we can worry about the actual
mechanics of getting it to produce good code.
That's not too far off of what the Assembly Language should look like.
Okay, so now as you can see, we're running just fine.
Even though we have compiled in a fashion that is now doing everything
completely wide in along the for those textiles.
So now all of this stuff has been moved outside of the loop which is
great.
We're getting there, right?
So, all this stuff that used to be done in the, for I Loop is now just
done in one go / / guy that does all four of the pixels.
So we want to do now is again, we'd want to just kind of keep moving
things out here.
We want to keep making things more wide wider than than they were.
So what we want to do is continue along so I think
I'll start with with FX here as well these guys.
So let's go ahead and make those wide.
Okay, so everywhere that those are used again in this routine, we will
lock those.
We will let the macro take care of those, but then when we actually go
to use them down here, we want to make this stuff kind of again Loft
back up.
So what I want to do is I want to pull this whole thing out, right?
Like so and that is that actually, you know what?
Let's just let's just do the rest of it here.
Let's let's all
Do do that part and then this part we will can we will still do in
scalar, right?
So
There we go.
And the reason I'm stopping here is because this clamp is something
that I want to talk about a little more specifically because I don't
know if you remember, but back when we had it in there, the reason
that I didn't expand out that clamp routine into a real routine was
because I wanted to talk about how to do it in Cindy in a different
way, right?
Almost there.
Okay.
I think that's everything that needs to happen down in there.
Oops, no I missed one.
There we go.
So now those are all working.
Okay, in there.
And so now we need to do is we need to make all of this stuff at the
assembly.
So this is these guys are new, right?
All of this stuff is new.
So we need to actually Define new things to hold it.
The same is true of these.
There we go.
And now some of this is Trivial, right?
So we know this guy right here, we know to modulate the incoming
color.
This is we've already done this, this is just a, an MMO PS2, right?
So what we need is we need our color value, our color, are we need a
Forex version of that, right?
That incoming color value.
We're going to need it to be blown out because basically, anytime we
multiplied by some constant that gets passed in.
We need to now
Have a wide version of that constant so that we can multiply, you
know, all the lanes of what we're working on all four pixels at once.
So typically we just take all of those inputs.
Like, those color values we take them all and we blow them out, right.
So you can see us doing that, right?
We've got
See here.
Score 3-2.
What is color?
32 still doing there?
We don't even use that.
So we have this
Color that comes in, right?
And what we want to do again is we want to sort of prep those wider
versions of the of the things.
So we've got, you know, we've got that here.
And I'm because we know we need all these constants.
I'm going to do the other ones we need here.
Just we just need the value one, just need a second.
We're going to that will probably need the value 0 as well and now
sometimes there's ways people like to generate these in different
ways.
Like you can generate zero in a different way by, you know, X or any
register with itself or study.
This, we're not going to talk about that quite yet.
And we may never, because it's not necessarily,
The kind of operation we're doing.
But point being for now we can just create them as values.
So what we want to do is we want to take this color value that we have
here and we need each of its corresponding virgins.
We need color are 4X like so.
And by the way, the 4X prefix suffix, I'm going to drop once
everything is entirely done in this, so I was just using it to make
sure that we don't name conflict with any of the existing ones.
So, here we go.
I'm literally just preparing replicated versions of these so that we
can just multiply
Buy a replicated version of the constant x 0.
So it's the code still looks nice and simple, okay?
And so we've already done, this guy, the mole PS.
If we take a look at what's happening here again, this is exactly the
same thing.
This is a really, really straightforward thing for us to do, right?
All of these multiplications, they are just literally multiplications,
right?
So we can trivially turn them into this.
Here we go again.
I'm doing absolutely nothing here.
Other than rigidly translating, any, any times symbol that you see
into a mole PS, right?
That is now Mack Road, and then the pluses exactly the same thing, we
haven't done an ad yet, but in mmm, add PS.
Just does the why dad as well?
And what you can see is, we're summing three values here.
So I literally just going to do three add pieces, right?
Add the first two together.
Add the next one.
Right?
And then add the next one and that's it.
So, that's the complete some DS version of that.
And we can actually make it a little bit clearer.
Potentially, by doing this, you can actually still read it, right?
But, you know, I don't actually care about that.
So I'm just going to leave it this way.
So, that's really all there is and this, I guess this whole thing is
just, you know, an ABCD with the R value there.
so, I'm just going to duplicate that since it's
exact same thing happening each time RGB and a right RGB and a
r, g b and a
A gpna, right?
So that's the complete bilinear operation there does the blending all
done these guys.
Again, if you want to subtract, mmm sub PS.
So add and sub, literally nothing to it.
We've got this way, but of course, you can't use a constant here.
You have to use an actual wide value, but we have a wide value, right?
We have the constant one that I already defined.
Like so.
And so that subtracts those values from one again for wide.
And then finally we've got these guys again, pretty simple.
This is just a mole, right?
This is just a mole.
Really straightforward, right?
Okay.
Oops.
All right, so now we've converted a much larger chunk of this routine.
So, all of this stuff is now happening in Cindy, and let's see if we
made any mistakes.
Looks pretty good to me, right?
Still all pretty pretty kosher.
So, here we go.
All we have to do now is kind of push through to a few more.
You can see leaving the clamp in there.
If we, if we don't look at the clamp, if we, if we ignore the clamp,
we should be able to actually do the rest of this as well.
So, let me go ahead and grab out everything other than the clamp, put
it out here so that we just left with the clamp.
And so, all of these things, we should, you know, should be
immediately recognizable to you.
If you take a look at this, you should be able to see that, that
literally all this stuff can be done, why?
But only stuff that we already did, right?
We have an M square that we did, which is just a mole.
We have the, the in of 255 Forex version, so we can do that wide.
So, these should be liked by now, hopefully, everyone could just do
exactly what I'm doing and there's no
History to it, right?
It's literally just totally wrote transformation.
Nothing.
Interesting at.
All right, just totally basic.
Totally easy.
Okay, so there's that all happening for wide.
Again, we can do this for wide because it's the exact same stuff.
Always forget that s underscore.
This is going to be a sub, right?
It's going to be a sub of one and Texel a like so
And then these again the Blended are going to all be exactly the same
as well so we can get rid of all of these eyes.
And these are all just going to be again.
Moles.
these are moles with M Texel a
and these are just now.
Don't need to be accessed by element anymore.
They can just be done for a wide like that, so now that's all done for
wide as well.
This is done for wind and finally these guys again, really, really
simple to do for wide.
We've got a constant here that we need to do.
Excuse me.
And so then the only thing we need that we don't have yet.
Is that square root?
So we're going to leave that square root in there, just a second.
Okay.
Alright, so to srgb.
0 to 55.
Yeah.
Sorry, I'm still a little bit allergy fish.
I'm not sick.
All right, so this square root here.
We're fortunate that even though it's a little bit slow, there
actually is already a.
We can go to that Intel intrinsics guide.
And you can see right here, that we actually do have a square root.
In fact, if you search for square root, you can see all of the options
that you have for square root right now, we're going to take the
easiest option that's available which is I believe there is a mmm
squirt.
Yes, which again isn't necessarily the fastest thing we could do,
we'll have to think about a little bit more if you want to do
anything, fancier here.
But for now we'll just
A script.
Yes, they literally just does the square root for us.
So let's go ahead and put that in there and I'm squirt.
PS rip!
Yes someone right.
And so now we have to go ahead and convert some of these variables
because all of these are now wide as well.
Right.
and,
Done.
Right.
So finally
once I'm done with getting,
Accessors in here.
We should be able to run this and it should be now wide everywhere
except for the clamp.
Oops, I left a plus in there who did that?
That is not how you do it.
Go.
Make that happen.
Okay, so it looks like we forgot one constant.
And this guy needs to be accessed via the m, and then, hopefully,
That is it?
all right, so 155 oops is
Just that.
Oops, forgot my xxxx.
Okay, so if we run that now again,
We are totally blind incorrectly as far as we can tell and we've
almost 70 is everything except the load Bay.
So what we have to do here is get the clamp working.
So the clamp between 0 and 1.
If you remember, you know, we've got this math code here, right?
And we have clamp 0 to 1 and the way that was working as a basically
does a bunch of work here, right?
And so, what I want to do is I want to sort of
I want to do something where we can actually take a look at what code
that was actually generating.
When we actually do this, right?
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to try anyways to see if we
can see what that does in the optimized build.
I just want to show you what's actually happening there.
I don't know if we'll be able to or not.
I'm not sure how well, how easily I'll be able to point out what's
going on here, but so we're in the optimized build now.
And so we're going to jump in here and see if we can see if we can.
Look at all the at the, at the clamp.
Let's see.
So you see how we coming here to this clamp and here we go.
We're doing we're loading some stuff in here.
Let me, let me get up the registers window.
So we can take a look at it.
So of course, unfortunately, probably bunch of these values is 0.
Since we're, you know, we're up on the first pixel or whatever, which
is usually a 0 pixel because it's, you know, it's not inside the field
region of the Sprite.
But if you take a look here, you can see that.
We've actually got a bunch of jumps that are happening in here as
well.
And what's happening?
Yeah, I mean, it's just kind of hard to see what's going on here, but
you can see that what they're doing for the clamp is, it's actually
doing those if statements, right?
And you can kind of see, it's got xmm six, it's got it loaded with one
and it's got xmm.
Seven loaded with zero.
And what it's doing is it's actually doing just it's actually doing
jumps based on whether or not it thinks it needs to replace the values
or not.
Right?
Based on whether thinks they're out of bounds or whatever which is
not, what we would want it to generate.
Like we don't want it to generate those jumps.
There's no reason for that to happen at all.
Like we shouldn't have all of that.
They're right.
And so that whole kind of situation is not at all the way we want it.
To look what we want it to do is do something much more
straightforward and so that's what we're going to do and you can kind
of see it continuing to do more of those clamps are right?
You can see it doing them clamping by doing the jumps, right?
And so the reason it's clamping, the reason that it's doing clamps by
jumps is because that's what we actually wrote, right.
We wrote like comparisons.
So it's it's doing sort of literally the structure that we have here
it's looking to see if it needs to do this operation and if it doesn't
it jumps over it looks to see if it needs to do this operation.
If it doesn't it jumps over it, right?
And so that's much less efficient than we would like it to be.
What we can do because now we know we're operating in Cindy, what we
can do is we can use functions that there are built in the Cindy which
actually do a comparison plus a replacement in one operation that's
actually extremely fast.
As you can see from the tables throughput 1.
And so, what this instruction will do is it will take two values.
It will compare the two values, and it will keep in, in which for each
lane.
So, for wise, doing for these, at a time, it Compares each pair and
it'll keep whichever one is the minimum.
And similarly, we can look at the one here, which is the opposite,
which is the max.
It'll keep what you
One is the maximum, right?
So if we have a way to compare and keep only the minimum, that's, this
is exactly what we're doing.
We were comparing and keeping the smaller of the two values, right?
If result is, is the smaller value, right?
Then, in this case, I should say, maximum, if result was a smaller
value, we keep them in, right?
And if men was a smaller value, we keep result so doing the clamp to,
the Min just is
Is doing a Max between result in men, right?
And similarly this guy was doing am in between result and Max.
So if we just do the Min and Max we can just own we can do to very
simple instructions.
No jumps to do that clamping, right?
So all we need to do here right to do these.
Clamps move them outside, get rid of the loop, right?
So in order to do those clamps, all we have to do is first.
Make sure we clamp from 0 to 1.
And then I started first make sure we clamp to 0 and then make sure we
clamp to 1, right?
So we just do an M&M Max P sorry Max PS right.
And we say that we want to keep whichever value is larger Texel are or
0.
So if it's below zero, we keep zero.
If it's above zero, we keep Texel are and then we just say, well and
also we do am in PS, right to say will keep whichever is smaller the
value that comes out of that.
A poor one.
Does that make sense?
So we're just we're just basically using Min and Max to do that clamp
with no actual comparing or branching on the values, explicitly
because, oops, because it's actually done just as part of that Min and
Max operation that's built in the 70s.
So we can just use two instructions to do that clamp.
And that's why I say that the clamping is very cheap when you're in
Cindy that's basically two cycles to do a clamp between zero and one
very, very straightforward.
Operation.
Okay, so we got rid of all that nastiness.
It's gone now.
And here we are in.
I want you to notice something to about what's going on at the moment,
right?
So in the compiled build here, you can kind of see that our cycle
counts already going down.
Even though the only things that we've done so far we haven't even
optimize the load.
We've just made that back-end happen.
More 70 style, right?
You can see that our game is already starting to run faster in an
optimized in the optimized build that cycle count is now down to one
sits.
Low 200s down down to 175 179 cycles per pixel, right?
It's still not where we want it to be per pixel, but it's getting
lower, right?
And so, the last thing that we might have to that, we need to think
about here.
I'm not sure if we got time for it.
In fact, let me see if there's anything else we can do besides that.
I don't think there is unfortunately, let's take a look here.
Well, you know, we could do some of these guys wide.
Let's do some of these guys wide and, and yeah.
Yeah, I mean, basically, you know, I said it was going to be easy.
Hopefully you agree that was easy.
Now that you kind of know that we've got these intrinsics to do
multiplication, subtraction adding we know that and we know that they
just turn into single instructions and Sydney that are very easy to
understand.
Hopefully, you can see that programming literally what the processor
was going to do almost down to the assembly level.
We didn't quite do like register assignment or anything like that, but
where we did most of it with the intrinsics
It was very very straightforward, right?
And so the hard parts are what we have left.
I don't really know that I want to try and start tackling them now
because we only have about five minutes left.
So I think that would be a bad idea but basically what we need to do
now is we need to tackle
The thing that fills.
So, basically the thing that,
the thing that rights, you know the pixels back after they've been
Blended,
And the thing that loads right and the loads going to be the really
nasty one because it's got to do all this texture look up as well
which is inherently not Cindy, able specifically this part right here
is super not Cindy friendly.
So yeah, what I could do just in the meantime as we could simply a
little bit of this like RV to par pixel p and so on, we could do that
in preparation.
I don't really know that we even want to do that.
I have to think about that a little bit more but we could do it now.
Since we've got five minutes left and we're sort of on a bit of a
bender here we might as well go ahead and do that.
So if I was going to do these guys wide, let's first change them into
scalar equations, so we can see it.
So here's pixel PX pixel p y, right?
There's the x value and there's the Y value.
Like so.
And then if I were to do a d x d y, that would just be that correct
you see where we're at here?
That's got to be a float conversion there.
So, does this?
And there we go.
Now we have to convert these guys to to, to that as well.
So we have an inner product and we know what the inner product is
right, the inner product is just each of the components multiplied
together, right?
So, it's just that DX times x and the d y times, Y, and similarly in
here.
We would do the exact same thing, right?
And get, I'm just expanding out that inner product d.
Y times, y,
Oops, ex Sex You by x y and there's everything there done in scalar
and let's just make sure it's correct.
Looks pretty good.
Why is this running so fast?
All of a sudden, it was like a what just happened?
Our speed just doubled from me doing that.
Does that make any sense to you?
But I don't know.
Okay, what just happened there?
I am so confused by what just happened that we have?
Just, that is what we are figuring out right now.
Did I accidentally compiled somehow differently?
What on Earth did just happened?
Let me see, I would really like to know what just happened there.
Okay.
So was that literally the entirety of
So that's 178 cycles per pixel.
I switched to doing just that expanded out.
And we drop to 125.
All right, I'm not imagining anything, right people, you're
witnessing.
That this is literally the exact same code, almost in the exact, same
way.
What is the compiler doing?
Please tell me what the compiler is doing to blow 50 Cycles on the
same piece of code.
It just full-on inserted 50 cycles of nonsense.
Apparently, what's it doing?
Show me the disassembly.
Alright, so here's this branch.
I don't see anything particularly weird there, do you?
I mean,
Convert cube move.
SS sub SS.
I am not.
I have no idea what what would be causing 50 Cycles.
Of stuff there.
Well, alright, I mean I'm just going to I'm just going to do, you
know, I don't know what's happening.
So I'm just going to take this.
And I'm going to copy it into the scratch buffer for now.
So there's the slow one, right?
And now let's take the fast one.
Maybe it optimized out something below it or something, you know, it
could be the case.
Uh-oh.
oh,
do you see?
Do you guys see what happened there?
It lofted, this stuff.
outside of the loop I think,
I think it just literally folded this stuff in.
Did it change the loop condition?
I'm perplexed, but you can see that this code is completely different.
It's doing nothing even close to what it was doing before.
All right, there we go.
So you can see that it's still doing the bottom part, so it's still
Computing u and v.
But it is now no longer doing any of the other work.
It is not doing any of this.
This stuff has gone away completely and I guess so, RB P minus 80 into
xmm to
So I wonder what it's actually.
What it's actually decided to compute here.
I'm not sure move X.
Let's see, can I take a look at xmm to
I can't do that.
I was hoping I could guess I can't.
I wanted to view it as a float.
Pupae are 14d.
That's that's actually up converting convert dq2.
PS.
It's that's that's converting.
I believe the integer to the float there.
Doing the sub.
So it's doing this thing.
It's doing this.
Malaysian here.
It's the pixel p x value so I think I could be wrong because it takes
a while for me to read assembly.
I'm not the best assembly guy but it looks like what it actually did.
Was it went ahead and moved out the pixel P to not actually have to
happen.
It looks like it may be folded that.
In to the outer code and doesn't actually it and and for it couldn't
figure out for some reason.
How to do that here, I guess because of the V2, I was confusing it.
I don't know.
I mean, that's the only thing I can think of is that the v2i or the,
or the inner I suppose was compete, was confusing it,
I mean I guess without a little bit more forensics, it's hard to know
exactly what it did.
We'd have to look at the whole Loop and ducote decipher what
everything was doing.
But I guess this is just a useful lesson here.
To mention briefly before we even know what exactly the compiler did.
This is kind of what people joke about when you know people often say
that you see programmers talked about, you know, in C++ and stuff,
they're like zero-cost extractions, you know, oh it's an inline
function or I wrapped it in this class and that it's fine, doesn't
cost anything.
So hopefully you can see
What a load of bull crap that actually is that is an example of
literally just taking an inline function that was two multiplies in an
ad and another inline function that was a cast.
That's it.
Just that it was enough to confuse the compiler out of 50 cycles of
optimization in 179.
Cycle routine, like a third of the Cycles, while a quarter of the
cycles of the routine.
We're saved by simply getting rid of to inline functions that the
compiler had complete knowledge of
To coat, Fabi, and he's in when he was complaining about something
like this.
Just recently on Twitter, I think he posted tell me again about your
zero cost abstractions and then he posted some timings that showed
that some very straightforward things of putting something in like an
inline function or something ended up costing him huge on some stuff
and blowing it out.
Didn't what can I say?
That's just the way it goes right?
That's that's pretty spectacular.
I don't know that we want to go through the assembly and actually
figure out what it did.
If anyone wants to you're welcome to do.
So you've seen both good bass now but but that's pretty amazing.
So anyway sorry that was a little bit of Sidetrack I'm going to take
just five more minutes real quick.
Here will still do a Q&A but I'm
Pomerance real quick just to finish doing the same day that we were
going to do here lofting that that outside of the loop just in
preparation which actually might make a slower because it looks like,
you know, maybe I'm you know, I'm setting up for doing the final thing
that we want to do.
But but basically, what I what I wanted to, I want to set it up for
doing the rest of the Cindy stuff, so we're at 125 Cycles.
Now, we may actually get slower, but what I wanted to do is I wanted
to move these guys outside of the loop, right?
Because we can calculate all of these in Cindy as well, right?
So let's see here.
What I want to do is say okay, let's make, let's make d x and u and v
and all these guys.
Let's just make them wide, right?
So, here are some 128 for you and that's going to be a MMO PS2 X.
So that's going to be a mole PS of d-y.
That that's gonna be a mole PS.
And this is going to be a mole PS 60 and these obviously have to be
for X's, right?
These are those those axes axes.
As constants.
So we got to make those constants.
There's and 128.
And I guess what I could do here is I could make them right here and
then we can just copy them out.
So there's that that for X is just going to be a MM set, 1.
PS and an X axis .x.
We go.
So I'll put those out here.
look, so
And once we've got that, we got to do our mmm, add PS.
To add these quantities together.
Thank you Emax for that helpful.
Premature indentation.
And then this is going to be an M sub, PS.
And I'm sub PS, and this is going to be another constant.
Origin X.
And I'm set one.
That out there.
Okay.
Yeah, and we will grab this guy that up there.
Here's our origin values.
And so now all we have to do is compute these, these pixel ones, I
guess for.
Right now, I'm just going to do an M&M set 1.
PS of these guys, I'm not going to think too hard about this but will
probably want to do something a little bit smarter for
Sorry, it's not a set 1ps actually because it needs to be the Y value
is, but this guy needs to be the different values x.
I plus, I.
So what we need to do there is load in, for Pixel, p is p x, we can do
an M&M set PS.
Again, we could do something, we can do something a little smarter
here later but for now,
Let's go ahead and and do it the obvious way.
Now, like I said, I always had a check this because I get bitten by a
lot.
We want it to look like this in memory order.
So we want the the low value to bxy + 0, then the higher going up in
the registers and I think, Mmm set, PS is written backwards from what
I usually want it to be.
And it is you can see it does three, two one zero.
So
I want it.
I want it actually like that, that makes sense.
So yeah.
Did I spell those wrong and xx + x axis.
Oh, I didn't do the y axis.
We go.
Okay.
And so finally inside of our slow, part of the loop here that we have
not actually done yet, we need to access those values, the u and v
values by their eye.
And similarly, we're going to have to do any of these other guys have
to be done that way as well, who are using the U and the V.
Here we go.
But now we've got a little bit more outside the loop there.
So we're still, you know, we're creeping for words.
And there we go.
All right.
Now I'm going to bring the episode to a close here.
It's hard because I like doing this kind of stuff for some reason I
like doing these Transformations, I don't know why probably cuz I
don't do them that off any.
I don't optimize stuff in Sydney that often.
Ironically I happen to I mean, or oddly enough, I happen to be doing a
bunch of that this week for the witness but that was random, that's
not the common case.
So anyway, we've gotten it down to where we just have
Is one Loop here that is not symbolized, that's at the top and that's
where we're going to have to do a little bit of work there to load
everything in.
That's going to be a little Annoying and then we got this pack.
This will probably start on Monday with this repack here because
that's going to be easier for me to sort of explain and welcome
everyone through.
It's going to be easier than the Texel loads.
So we'll do this one.
But as you can see, we're getting much closer to having an entire
assembly as routine.
And, hey, guess what?
Looking at the cycle counts and the Speed the game already
She is now back to running in real time.
I don't know if you noticed that right, we are no longer slow, right?
And so that's pretty awesome, just in and of itself, you know, we
haven't even really done anything too serious to it.
All we've done is just the rigid Transformations.
That hopefully now that I've explained them to you.
Anyone could have done those right.
I didn't use any special processor knowledge.
I didn't use any special experience.
I literally just did a series of transformations to that code that I
think now that I'm displaying them, any of you could have done based
on just the explanation that we had yesterday.
And today there was no experience or finesse necessary, you did not
have to be some kind of optimization with to do any of those things.
You just have to go.
Okay.
I'm going to change this routine from doing one pixel at I'm doing for
Pixel at a time, just by widening, all the operations to for right.
So,
Hopefully, that was easy and comfortable and it might have been a
little scary and weird to you at first because yeah.
I mean, you've never seen any of the stuff before perhaps and that's
fine.
But, you know, now that you're looking at it, you know, does this look
that strange?
No it's just all it is is instead of putting plus and times in between
things, you seem all and plus and what you mean time so you see Mullen
dad and whatever, right?
But that's it and it's really easy to read if you understand functions
at all right, now there is one thing which is like hey, you could do
is overloaded operators or
Thing to make this easier to read the reason.
I don't do that when I'm Cindy optimizing is because I am terrified of
what the compiler will do.
And I think hopefully based on what you saw today with that simple
change.
We did up here remember saving 50 cycles and it was just a change from
using an inline function to actually writing the stuff out.
I am terrified in optimized code of the compiler doing stupid stuff
because it always does.
And so when I care about a routine being optimized, I want nothing
that
don't have to be there to be there, it's a small price to pay to just
write it out this way and then I know the compiler is not going to do
anything too dumb, although sometimes I still do some dumb things.
And so that's why I don't like overload operators for this because the
number of routines that we are going to optimize at this level is very
small, they're basically just going to be a few pixel filling routines
probably.
And we won't do probably that much more in Cindy so it's a small price
to pay to just have to do it out in this way once or twice.
And then you know the compiler is not going to ruin your life in some
bad way that you that you weren't expecting, right?
So, there we go.
So let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
there may be some things that were confusing people today, so that's
just want to give a little time for questions and we will see
How do you cover multiple CPU Technologies?
Intrinsic wise preprocessor switches on dedicated intrinsics for each
also whom to read on as mm.
I'm thinking Mike a Brash.
So Mike a Brash probably isn't super useful to read on as them anymore
because all of the stuff that he wrote was prior to wide, I don't know
if Fabien he's got some good stuff on Cindy.
I don't really know.
I'm sorry but I'm not sure.
You'd want to read someone who talks about Cindy because Cindy is very
different.
And a lot of what you have to do, doesn't have anything to do with the
stuff that Mike a Brash was talking about, which is like filling u and
v pipes and stuff on a Pentium which isn't really that relevant
anymore.
Occasionally, it's relevant but it's the its way down the line on
things.
Usually tends to be more about making sure all your stuff lines up in
lanes and stuff like this.
So, I don't know as to how do you cover multiple CPU Technologies?
Intrinsic wise?
Yes, the answer is you use.
Basically what we will do when way down the line when we get to that
is these intrinsics.
We will just Define our own versions of.
So we'll change it to something like, you know, our own mul PS or some
or own like, you know, mole for x or something and then we'll just
pound to find that to be the right thing for the compiler.
For the, for the particular,
For right?
And it's kind of a pain in the butt but you know, it's it's not that
hard to do.
HR.
You be we have come from 385 Cycles to about a hundred and twenty
three Cycles to something like the 80/20 rule.
Apply, do you think we will get down to 50 Cycles?
Yes, I do think we will get down to 50 Cycles.
Well, I don't know yet.
We haven't done our estimate.
So again, like I was saying what we need to do before we can really
say what we'll probably be able to get down to is will need to take a
look at all these and count the operations that we have here and see
what our maximum throughput would be.
And then we
We have to figure out whether or not we could hit 50 Cycles, right?
What you can see is even if we just start to count them.
Now, right.
We've got you know, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
So seven times for their I guess is like 28.
So you know looking at this here it's 28 and that's going to be about.
I mean, looking at this
I think it's pretty clear to me that we will be able to get this
routine down to 200 cycles.
And 200 Cycles is 4 4.
Pixels is 50 Cycles a pixel, right?
So really my primary question is going to be what happens right here.
So I think the answer is will we be able to get the math down to 50
cycles for Pixel?
Absolutely.
I think we're on track.
Will we be able to get the Texel?
Fetch and unpack down to under it to, you know, when L added up to be
under the 50 cycles for Pixel, that's going to be the real question.
So this is the guy and I don't know it's premature but just spot
checking the number of multiplies, I think.
The number multiply ads in here.
Will we be able to get that down below?
50.
Absolutely.
Because again, we only have to get it to 200 and we're doing for Pixel
at a time.
So getting from 200, 250 won't be.
You know, if we get 200 that means we're at 50 per pixel.
The way we use M Square, does it calculate the argument twice?
It shouldn't but we should definitely verify that.
That's a good point.
The compiler should do common sub expression.
Elimination pretty well but, you know, that's a very good point you
bring up, we should definitely check, right?
So, let's see if we can determine that from to looking at the looking
at the instructions here.
So it's going to, well, it's done.
A bunch of folding.
This.
But all right let's take a look here.
So it looks like
It looks like.
It is doing the squares.
Let's see here.
Would be nice if we could see this a little bit better as floating
Point values.
So we're doing a move.
Move in move in.
Move in move in
Excuse me.
It looks like this is loading.
255, where is so X mm3.
Where is our?
We need RM250 5 for X in here.
Or did it just leave that in a register is xmm three?
That the thing that's kind of annoying me is.
Oh right.
We can, we can view the floats down here.
I forgot we can view the floats in this weird.
Like hard to read.
Read out that it does.
So okay, a MMX mm3 is, is the 10.
So there it is, right?
And we actually have
Two copies of it, right?
Because 1 over 255.
Is this point zero zero three nine two, one fight, right?
That value.
And and so it looks like
392.
Well, that's not exactly right.
So, I'm not sure.
Where it actually is.
Let me see here.
I was just trying to figure out where our
values action.
There's the clamp
So, I'm not sure where that in 5255 was actually happening.
That's very confusing.
Because I feel like it should have been loaded, but -3.1 3.7 179.
Right is not the same.
Is not the same value.
I'm not sure what the compiler fanciness was doing here.
Right?
These are not their clothes, but they're not exactly the same.
So I'm not sure what it was doing there.
I'm a little confused.
So if we take
We take that empty to 5000.
Did it do something?
No, I don't know what what did it do there.
Do you guys know what it did there?
I'm not sure what I did there.
As opposed to figuring out what to do with the square.
I'm not sure what it actually even did with the constant, right?
Because I'm just trying to figure out where it loaded.
The actual value that I would have expected to see their right.
And, and I do not know because this is not that constant, it's a
close, but it's - and it's a, not exactly it.
So I'm not sure where it actually loaded that constant.
And so, I guess, what I might do to is, I'd like to look and see where
it actually loads, that where it actually loads that constant in if it
ever actually generator for generated some other constant.
So
let me see if it actually ever even stores, that constant
It might not have.
I've done that, right?
Yeah, so I don't know.
So the answer with the mm square is, I don't even really know what it
ends up doing with this code in terms of how it's doing the
multiplication by m 255.
I don't know what it's doing there.
It's decided to do something decidedly more advanced than what we
asked it to do.
But what that thing is I couldn't actually tell you
Maybe you need somebody, who's better at Assembly Language trickery
than I am to know what the compiler decide to do there and whether or
not it was a smart thing or a dumb thing if that makes sense.
What is a tardy p?
+ h?
Oops.
A bunch of zeros.
So, is that actually giving me the value?
Sorry, I'm sorry, I'm not talking more, but I actually do not know
what's going on.
So that is actually correctly RBP - 10 H, so it's actually loading
into xm-10 a bunch of zeros, right?
That's just what it decided to do there.
Hmm.
Yeah, so I don't know.
And I in the extended registers in the upper in the
The upper registers to, I don't see the value in here either.
Xm-10 is just a bunch of zeros.
Mo, PS, 8 and 0.
So it's multiplying.
Those two together.
What's innate?
We still don't really know what that value means, right, let's see
here.
XM m.
8, is there a way we can see xm8 as float.
God, this is so awful.
Let me see here.
How do I, please let me view the registers.
Why can't I view the registers as float?
There's got to be some way to view the registers as float.
That's the floating-point registers that doesn't help us.
I just want to view, right?
I mean, is that so wrong.
I just want to view these are these are showing me as double-doubles
which I don't want to see.
I want to see them as floats, which here we go.
This is what I'm looking for.
There it is.
Okay.
So it was just using the extended registers.
It's just using the, the top eight, okay?
That was going crazy there for a second, man.
This register view is worse than I remember.
All right, so anyway,
Here is where it loaded the value in xm8.
So what it's doing here, here is the multiplication of xm8, and it
looks like it's this is probably going to do one of those.
So it's loading xm8 in there.
It's multiplying both of these guys.
Exponent n.
And so it's doing tumults.
This is doing two of those in 1555.
Right.
It's then loading a bunch more guys in right here.
There's one of the squares that squaring of value.
So this multiplied by the inverse 255, here is a squaring the value,
so that's good.
Here's a squaring the other value.
So it did this, totally right, here's where it did the X inverse 255,
right?
It gives those a little bit of time to complete.
So it's hiding the dependency.
Okay, by inserting some moves in here, right?
Then it's doing the square right there, right?
So it doesn't compute the value twice.
Now, it's doing here's where it's doing the into 55s, for the new guys
that moved in gets those in the in the pipeline and then it's moving
some more guys in two registers and then I don't know where it's
doing.
Oh, it doesn't have to do the square for the alphas.
So it's just
moving new guys in and now we're on to other stuff.
So yeah, sorry about that.
I got confused because I forgot that I forgot about the extended the
top 16 registers to check them.
For some reason, I was like, well, it's got tons of registers down
here but yeah, obviously, it doesn't care which registers it uses.
It might as well use the higher registers, whatever.
So yeah, so an ABI wise is probably smarter for to the higher
registers anyway and that's a whole nother story anyway.
So yeah, it looks like it's doing exactly the right thing.
It's loading.
These
As in its doing the multiplies and it's hiding the latency in the X
doing other stuff.
And then putting just so, in case the processor, even if the processor
couldn't have, you know, making the window a little more favorable,
it's doing moves to hide the latency multiply and then it comes back
and does the square.
So it's doing totally exactly what we want.
No complaints there.
Even though it took me a little while to actually figure that out.
So yeah.
Check that out.
Look how fast that's running compared to how fast it was running.
Right?
I mean you can just feel the difference.
It's pretty cool.
All right.
Where do opencl and other gpgpu Frameworks fit into optimization?
It seems like a something is simply a bull.
It could just be done wider on a GPU.
Are their workloads that are better suited to the CPU and Cindy.
So the answer is really that it's usually more about transfer time and
About the degree to which things fit the pattern of what gpus do.
So to give you a little bit of a perspective on how this sort of stuff
goes
gpus are set up as you know,
These are set up as stream processors.
What they want to do is they want to be able to move stuff directly in
in a streaming fashion.
Operate on it and stream it out, right?
That's what they want to do.
Things like read modify write.
They're very bad at like they don't want to do things where you're
doing a lot of work on things in place or scattered, right?
Where you're going where you're like, writing to random parts of
memory a lot.
They hate that sort of thing.
Furthermore control flow.
They are awful at.
They don't do that very well either.
and so there's, there's
Basically CPUs are very good at general-purpose, kinds of stuff where
there, where it doesn't fit that that super concise stream in up,
stream out format and to put this in some perspective, if you take a
look at a modern GPU, and a you look at GPU general-purpose, GPU,
workloads, the Xeon Phi, for example, which is a bunch of x86.
Corazn, it died.
Apparently annihilates.
Gpus at doing general-purpose workloads like, that's what everyone
buys the Xeon Phi.
Now they don't buy a G-Force card, right?
If you're doing like actual general-purpose workloads in, so I feel
like in general, what it boils down to is, how well does the thing
you're looking at work working on look like a stream processor that
has a very known set of ins and outs.
That's very like Compact and doesn't do a lot of scattered read and
write kinds of
Operations.
How closely does it resemble that if it resembles that very closely
than a GPU, may be a good choice, if it doesn't resemble that very
closely, then a CPU or one of these special purpose cards, that's like
a Xeon Phi, kind of a thing.
That's a bunch of a lot of CPU, cores on a dedicated memory thing,
maybe looks better, right?
We have optimization still on.
Yes, optimizations are still on 02.
Why are there optimizing options in the compiler?
If one will end up typing CMD functions the answer is because that's
not really the what optimization means when you turn on optimization
in the compiler.
So what optimization in the compiler means is basically try to
generate reasonable Lee, good Assembly Language for what I typed in.
Right?
And it does not include vectorizing usually because the degree to
which the compiler has to know what your code is doing.
In order to vectorize it, well is a little Beyond compiler technology
tends to be at the moment is what it boils down to.
It's not to say that maybe someday in the future, we won't have Auto
vectorizing to the
It actually can do all of this stuff that we just did, but right now,
that's not the case.
So what optimization usually means is actually go through and try to
write good assembly code which takes longer and is harder to view in
the debugger right versus when I turn optimizations often the compiler
at saying, right?
Exactly what I wrote down and store it to the stack all the time so we
can inspect it easily and so on.
Right.
So that's really what OD + O to switch between it.
It's like whether I want you to write brain-dead literal translations
of my stuff into assembly that are easy to debug and slow or whether I
want you to really think about it and try to write good versions of
the assembly, but don't really change the like effectively what the
code is doing.
That's what odierno to mean.
If we want to do creative wide Cindy stuff, the compiler doesn't know
how to do those things yet.
Do you know of the mm set RPS, intrinsic, and PD note, the are and
said, Arlo's the values in reverse order.
IE the order that is more intuitive.
I have seen those I don't ever use them because again, it's just a
question of remembering how the order goes.
And if I remember the order, I would know which way our went, like,
I'd still not remember which one was, which probably like is our
because it says reverse order.
That makes me think it's going to load it in big-endian, but the
reverse is true.
First order actually makes it loaded in little in the end so it's it's
very confusing to me.
Girl, Linda Bloom.
When do you think we will thread the renderer?
Well, not we won't thread the renderer probably until we actually get
a single thread Optimum pixel fill working.
Well, so we got to finish getting these pixel fills working really
well first.
Possibly misguided question, is there a way to overload operators to
use Cindy instructions instead?
Yes, the problem with it, is the compiler may not understand what
you're doing, right?
Like you just saw we had a 50 cycle penalty for just using a vector
to, right?
We used a V2 instead of writing it as scalar, and it cost us 50 Cycles
in 179, psycho routine which is crazy.
Again, almost a third of the cycles and at least a quarter of the
cycles.
Just for using that.
And so I never do stuff, like, use overloaded operators with Cindy.
Because I never know if the compiler is going to get confused.
Because oftentimes, it does
It's padding, an alignment, still something you have to concern
yourself with.
I remember doing Cindy in the mid-2000s, and Cindy was essentially
worthless much of the time if your data wasn't aligned,
so I guess the answer to that is, I don't
No, when I learned some new programming like you alignment was of
Paramount importance and so I till still tend to align everything.
But I guess what I would say is even just based on what you saw today,
Cindy was clearly very worthwhile even though we haven't actually
taken time to align stuff.
So, I guess the answer must be that actually alignment, while possibly
still important is obviously not as
As is not Paramount, right?
Addendum by concern yourself.
I mean, is it something that can power now, handles more automatically
when you engage Cindy?
Ah, yes.
So I believe the compiler is now always smart enough to do stuff like
align the stack properly so that your CMD variables are not loading
unaligned.
I believe it does do that properly and so that maybe if that's what
you're talking about, I think that does happen properly now.
Yes,
Will you generate as mm for neon?
GCC seems to be pretty bad at generating.
Correct?
Code with intrinsics, from my experience on Android?
I don't know.
I have never optimized on Android.
I did optimize a neon Thing Once.
I didn't really super optimized it.
I do really, just had a code generator that I wrote output it to
Android into two PS Vita, which was, which is neon,
But I've never really had to look at it too closely so I don't know.
I'll ask Jeff and Fabien what we will need to do there, but that's a
long ways away.
How would, you know, if doing something will speed up the code,
especially when it's a fairly large change to the code base?
And when time is limited, I find myself reluctant to perform, such
optimizations in fear of introducing bugs.
Well, the answer is I try to follow that process.
That I was talking about before which is get statistics, which we did
right figure out where the code is slow, which we did.
Build a model of what the code has to do, which is what we're in the
middle of doing now.
And so pretty soon, we'll have this routine in a CMD format where we
can look at all of the instructions and know how fast it should run.
And then see how close we can get to peek, which is what we'll do
following those steps.
It's kind of hard
not to succeed at least a little bit.
I'm not scared of introducing bugs because I mean,
I don't know if you can't.
If you can't be confident that you can re write some code without
introducing bugs.
I think that's probably a concern that you should address Moorhead on.
What are these bugs that you're introducing, are they, because you're
being sloppy at coding, or are they because the code that you're
trying to fix was very poorly written?
It's hard to know what it's supposed to do.
Could you write some tests could you, could you revert to unit
testing, for example, to make some unit tests that will call the code
that you're trying to optimize and go ahead then and rely on those
unit tests to catch problems?
But you're gonna introduce like, look what can you do there, right?
And I would, I would tackle that very head on because I don't think
you should be scared to optimize your code.
That's not a good idea.
It's not a good place to be.
What do you think you'll next want to convert to Cindy in case I want
to practice over the weekend?
Well, so if you want to practice doing something simple with Cindy and
you don't want to push forward on symbolizing this stuff because I
think I haven't explained any of the tools that you'll need to do
that.
So I think if you wanted really hard assignment get this done in 70.
Get rid of this for I Loop if you want something real hard because
that will push you.
Well, beyond the things that I've taught if you want.
Wait for me to teach that.
Then what I would say is we've already done everything, you would need
to know to go Cindy optimize the thing that draws a filled rectangle,
right?
We've got that filled rectangle here routine.
Where is that guy?
Draw a rectangle.
So this routine right here, you should be able to write the CMD
version of this completely by yourself.
We've already done everything that you need, right?
And so, you should be able to do this empty version of this entirely
by yourself with the exception of one part, which you could choose out
on just like, we choose out on it here, because we haven't gotten to
it yet.
And so you could pause on that part, which is the should fill part.
Right?
We haven't shown how to do that.
We're basically doing some masks, right?
Kinds of stuff for that.
So but what if you want to practice over the weekend, which is a great
idea?
I love the fact that you're even asking that question, if you want to
practice over the weekend, take draw a rectangle and Cindy eyes the
whole thing.
Except for that mask, that ending right part.
You can choose out on if you want because we haven't covered that.
But this doesn't load any texture stuff.
It's just writes.
So, you should be able to do the whole thing Cindy just with the
exception of that.
About that last part of the film.
Could you compile it Odie and show how Cindy has helped their?
Well, we can but it's not really a useful.
Jur in od because likes over 120 Cycles right now something like that.
And if we switch to OD right you can see that it's, you know, 280
Cycles or whatever.
So it's it helps.
But it's a problem because it's still inserts a ton of cruft code in
there and so you know compiling with OD, definitely slows you down.
Would it be a good exercise?
I'll be at large when to study a simple GPU and write some soft for it
Arduino or something ancient, I wanted to learn coding for GBA for a
while.
Basically, what I would say is getting more familiar with Assembly
Language, kind of code, is always a good idea.
I don't know that you need to go overboard with it but basically what
I'd say is whatever motivates you to do some Assembly Language
programming.
And when I say something nice for
Even something that's just basically what we're doing here which is
like writing some intrinsics and seeing how they compiled and making
sure that you kind of understand roughly how that's working just that
alone is good.
And so if you want to do some stuff like that, whatever motivates you
to do, it is good.
If hacking on a Game Boy, Advance is what will motivate you to do
that.
I mean hack on Atari 2600 emulator.
And right, right?
Atari 2600, piece of code, if that's what works, anything that just
gets you in the habit of thinking about registers memory machine,
individual instructions, just that mental model of my CPU has actual
things that it does and every piece of code.
I write translates into that, in some way, anything that gets you in
the habit of doing that thinking is good, so whatever motivates you to
do that, do it, if that's ocular GBA do it, if it's Cindy optimizing
some code on visual C++ on a
Before Do It.
Whatever Gets you comfortable doing that, do that.
And you will definitely be a better programmer afterwards.
And to end your follow-up, that says, let's rephrase.
What CPU, would you advise a study that would be simple enough yet
representative enough of General stuff?
I would say it did that, that doesn't matter.
What matters is that you've connected the code that you write with the
fact that there is a real CPU with actual characteristics, executing
it because CPUs change every year, right?
So it's a, it's a constantly evolving knowledge.
It's like saying, how do I What GPU should I study?
Its it doesn't matter.
It's these things change over time and so the important thing is that
you build a mental model of the fact that there is a CPU down there.
And that you know, that when you
Have to start carrying, you know, what?
You'd go read, right?
You'd go.
Oh, you know what?
This code is too slow.
I need to optimize it.
I've never worked with the CPU before, but I know that there is this
concept of a CPU that
Cute.
Instructions and it's got memory and stuff like this.
That's where about.
Let me go read about that CPU.
You'll read about it go.
Oh, it's got a cache that moves in this way.
Okay, it's got these instructions.
Okay, it's got a wide Vector unit.
Okay, I see all these things and now I've built a mental model of that
CPU and I can optimize for it.
That's what you want to do.
So it doesn't matter what your first CPU is getting some experience
with any CPU is enough.
And then from then on, you'll always kind of be in a situation where
you have to read about the CPU that you're on and learn some new
things.
Things because they change all the time.
So there is no such thing as like a representative CPU that is going
to like be the thing that you can always think about.
That doesn't really work.
How long have you been working on this?
And when do you think we'll, you will finish.
So I generally ballpark about 6:00, which breaks down to about three,
or four months of if you were working on it full-time and we've done
about 100 12 hours or sorry, 116 hours.
So we haven't even gotten, you know, we're only a six of the way
through, so we haven't really spent that many hundred to put it in
some perspective.
We're almost
Three weeks of full time programming work in and three weeks of
programming is very little, right?
So, yeah.
Are you going to optimize gameplay code as well?
Probably not that much, because it probably won't be the bulk of the
time that's spent but we'll see.
There might be some, like, the Collision detection or something might
want to be optimized.
Have you heard of the Jay station to project from Jasmine Kessler
working with the Raspberry Pi 2B?
Plus I have not know.
Alrighty, I think we have come to the end of the stream and the
questions, so let us go ahead.
Let us go ahead and close things down.
I feel like we should be pretty proud of ourselves even though we
haven't really taken too much of a.
Look at things are debug code.
Now, runs about as fast as the assembly, is our, as the optimized
version did, and, and the 2002 version.
Now, with the CMD in, there is running is now running real time,
right?
Like, we're totally running.
I
We're running 30 frames a second.
Now, right?
So that's that's pretty great.
You got to feel pretty good about that, right?
Least I do.
So yeah, we've got a ways to go still before.
Assembly optimizing that stuff the pack and unpack and all that.
But you should feel pretty pretty good about yourselves.
We're getting, we're getting there.
All right, and that was only one week, right?
That was, that was five hours of programming.
We did or whatever, right?
Five hours of programming to go from could not even run to running
actually at frame rate.
So I don't know.
You guys should feel pretty good about that.
Anyway, thank you everyone, for joining me, for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, I hope you have enjoyed our optimization and we've got
another week of it coming up next week, where we're going to take a
look at some little, some more.
Stuff basically those that the load in the store part, and it's
basically true of almost everything you write in Cindy as you saw
today, making the math run and Cindy is almost trivial.
I think anyone can do it.
It's really easy.
Once I tell you a couple things I feel like you should just know,
right?
I mean, that was, that was pretty basic because it's like if you see a
Time symbol, you replace it with a mole PS.
That's it, right?
The hard part is that the top and the
Bottom because as you'll see next week they just they don't fit the
model of Cindy very well.
And so you're constantly doing especially on x64 which has a limited
instructions on sse2.
Anyway, the avx-512 coming down.
The pipe actually has a lot better stuff for this but in sse2, anyway,
it's really very cumbersome to do that pre and post work that we need
to do and you'll see we have to start getting into some talking about
permutations rotations and stuff inside the vector.
Inside those Vector registers and it's just a little more complicated
in, you're going to see.
It's little more annoying, but it's again, even that is not that hard.
It's just annoying.
You'll kind of see what I mean, when we get to that, but please join
me next week for that.
Because once we have that in there are routine, I think we'll be
running actually pretty quickly, and then we'll just have to take a
look at the cash loads for our textures and stuff to make sure we've
got that working relatively.
Well.
So anyway, thank you very much for joining me.
Help you?
Join me next week, starting Monday will probably be at 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard time starting on Monday next week.
I suspect.
So I hope to see you all back here for that as we continue our
optimization of the software rendering path, and in the meantime, if
you would like to play around with the source code and practicing
optimizations on your own, if you preorder the game on handmade hero
dot-org, you can go ahead and download the source code and work along
with me.
I upload it every day after we're done.
So it's always up to date.
So definitely check that out.
Also, we have a forums if you want to ask questions outside the Q&A or
you want to take a look at ports to Mac or Linux and stuff?
That's up.
There is a bunch of good resources on the forum's.
Check it out.
We have a patreon page.
If you want to subscribe to that, it's a it's a cool place to go just
in terms of supporting the video series, very much appreciated and we
also have a tweetbot that tweets, the schedule.
So if you're trying to catch a stream live, please check that out.
It always let you know when we're going to be broadcasting.
So, that's it for another week of handmade hero.
I like to give a shout out to all the moderators who hopefully, now
all have their wrist guards official.
Handmade sure.
Wrist.
Guards, that I sent out earlier this week.
I think everyone's gotten them now, so at least I hope so.
So please enjoy them and thank you very much.
For all of the hard work you do in moderating the streams.
I know monitoring the twitch chat can be very trying at times, it's
always a bit of a zoo in there.
So thank you for keeping it, relatively sane.
I know everyone appreciates very much who's trying to actually pay
attention to the stream and ask real questions.
And I know I appreciate it very much because I don't even want to know
what the stream would look like if you guys weren't there.
So, thank you very much.
And, like I said before, we also will the
The wrist guards, aren't it?
We will also be trying to do some other nice things for our
moderators.
Going forward with some of the patreon funds.
We haven't really figured out what that's going to be yet, but we're
we appreciate what the moderators do.
And so we'll definitely be trying to figure out some other good things
we can do for them.
So that their work is not thankless.
Alright everyone, take it, easy.
Hope to see you back here on Monday until then have a great coding
weekend and and I'll see you on the internet.