Hello everyone and welcome to handmade here on the show.
We could have complete game live on stream.
We stopped yesterday after rewriting a bunch of stuff and we need to
go to bucket and get it working.
Kind of a nice thing actually.
It's a lot like I know that writers or writing teachers or something,
I don't know often say stuff like when you're writing a book or
something, stop in, when you know exactly what you're going to write
next that night.
So that in the morning, it's easier to get started again or something
like this.
I have no idea point being we're in a situation where we know exactly
what we need to do and it's just a mugging work.
So hopefully.
We can just jump right in day 3, 16, you want to start with de 315
source?
Code?
That's what I'm working with right now.
Hopefully you have that same day, Thrifty 315 source to start with,
this is what was happening to us.
Speaking of assertions, on the pre stream.
This is exactly an example of one of those assertions.
This is telling us that we have output, a cliprect index that is
totally bogus.
And so we need to kind of go.
Look at all the sort of
That we made to our code and, you know, it's not really a surprise
that we mess something up, its kind of, finicky code that we were
working on.
So we need to kind of go back there and just take a look at what's
going on and try to make sure that we have our code nailed down.
Alright, so the first thing that I want to check obviously is you know
we come in here and we get a clip.
Rect index.
That's that's way out of bounds right?
16 527, not a clip rect that
Really means anything.
I wanted to see what the header is here.
It looks to me like the header is is garbage, right?
And the reason I just want to check that is because I wanted to know
whether we were in a circumstance where you know, we were where we
were looking at a wrong location or whether it was a wrong clip,
directing this.
It looks like we're looking at a wrong location.
Now I, you know, I kind of already have because, you know, we wrote
the code hastily yesterday and we didn't have a chance to really look
at it at all.
So, you know, in my mind, I've already got a bunch of ideas of
probably what's wrong, and so I'm just going to go look at those first
before I do anything more sophisticated than that.
And the first thing that I want to look at is when we push it on.
I don't know if I ever updated the code that actually sets what the
offset actually is right.
And so if we look when we do push render elements and you know, we we
work with the offsets and stuff like that.
You can see here we do, you know, whatever it is.
We're going to do.
And we come down here and we take a look at the offset stuff.
I don't know if this offset stuff is really what I want it to be.
I don't really know.
I didn't really look too carefully at that code.
So I don't know whether those offsets are valid offsets or
Whether you know what they are or what's going on, right?
So we kind of need to do a little bit of work to make sure that that
what we're doing here, makes sense.
And if I take a look at this code, it already looks stupid to me.
I think I was probably just hallucinating when I wrote it.
If you look at what's going on.
That offset is supposed to be where in the buffer we wrote the data,
right?
And we didn't like what I did is is basically compute how far there is
to the end of the buffer because I was thinking an end to buffer mode.
Yeah, but we don't want that.
We just want to know where in the buffer, it actually is.
And so, you can kind of see here that that's what this computation
would have been.
So that was just dumb.
So that's the problem to begin with.
So, let's start.
Oops.
I didn't load my project file, did I?
There we go.
Let's start with that because that's at least one problem.
Let's get that out of the way.
All right, so now we're back to looks like actually a saner situation.
Let's see how we're doing on the rest of our sorting.
So that actually looks like we're sorting properly.
Now in terms of our slices so who knows.
Maybe that was the only error.
I'm not entirely sure, but we definitely have one other problem that
you can see that.
Introduced, which is previously.
We sort of had this thing for sorting the hero structure and you can
see that.
That's all busted now.
Right.
You can see that the hero is not at all that that aggregate sort
concept that we have there, that's obviously completely trashed.
So, we need to kind of go fix that.
And we also have some weird things here, like, what's going on with
those trees and stuff like that.
So we've got a bunch of things that we need to go look at and so we
can go look at them now.
Alright, so the first thing that I want to look at is actually I'm
going to take a quick detour here because I want to sort of take it
one thing at a time inside, handmade world's mode.
When we do add standard rooms, I'm going to go back to just one room
briefly and I want to take a look at the aggregate sorting since that
was code that we kind of broke before so you can kind of see and and
you can see
There's more than just that that's wrong, right?
Because if if you look at what we had before, we didn't have all those
weird blinking tree problems, right?
So we're not quite there yet.
We still have some errors as to as to, what's happening.
So let's take a look at what's going on there and let's start to try
and solidify that a little bit more.
So one thing that's true about this is, I do want to make sure that
this offset is actually correct.
Now we know that it's not woefully
It's not crashing lie wrong but we don't know if it may be points, it
slightly the wrong thing or something like this.
So if I have my pushed by for data at a time, I pushed by four base
and I subtract those two, what I want to know is is this actually
pointing at the correct location?
Action.
I think that it is but let me just make set, make sure of that.
So in here, you know we have the put, in fact, you know what.
Now, I think about it, what we really want to do is say where the
header actually is, right?
That's what we're trying to point out anyway, so let me just do this.
I mean, that's what we actually wanted now.
I think those are the same thing, so this shouldn't change anything.
We should see the same behavior but that's what I want to start with
certainly, right.
And so so that's that's the Baseline.
So now that I know that I've got the offset pointing at least a header
that I'm actually filling in.
Right.
And you can see that I'm filling in sort of the various fields of
that.
And then I'm filling in the sort stuff as well.
What I want to do now is take a look at the group is
Hitting answer for the group is aggregating stuff.
And I say first aggregate at, you know, we have the sort entry count
here and I'm just saying if this happens to be the first one,
Then I'm going to copy in the start key and if not, then I'm going to
do the, the merge operations, right?
I'm going to do a merge operations with that, same sort key that, that
we were passed in.
So, what I want to know is, is this operating properly and I just want
to take a quick look at the actual code for this.
So when we do a begin aggregate, sort, create, we're basically saying.
The first aggregate is that wherever the sword entry count was?
That's what we're saying, right?
And that seems correct to me.
Because that's pointing at essentially, the next one that we're going
to fill in.
So then when we come here and we say, first aggregate at equals
commands sword and recount.
I'm not really sure that that makes the most sense.
I mean, really, what we want to do is take a look at whether it equals
this thing.
So I feel like the, the sort of the safer thing to do, rather than
trying to be math tricky about it.
Is, I could just, say first aggregate at equals push short entry and
just actually take the
It gets bright bound, right?
The what is that called?
The gets hard entries.
That what I could just say as well, you know, if I was going to do
gets sort of entries plus very segregated that I would want to, you
know, make it be pushed toward entry.
Now, the thing that occurs to me about that is I'm not sure why we're
actually using an index for for that, in the first place, like,
We actually need an index or can we just use a pointer?
Because if you look here, when we do our iteration, it's like we're
doing all this work bending over backwards to keep it an index.
I say we just change it to a Pointer while I'm debugging.
This I might as well change it to something that I want it to be that
way.
I'm not debugging, something that's not what I actually wanted, right?
So let's go ahead and set sort Sprite bound to be first aggregate like
that.
And then what I'll do is say, okay, when we do first aggregate,
We could also get rid of this is aggregating flag to if we wanted to
actually we could just do this first Aggregate and get rid of this
aggregating.
So then what we could say it's just like, okay, let's assert that
there isn't a first aggregate
When we come through here, we'll set the first aggregate to get Sprite
bounds, so I'd get sort entries, never gonna get that right Plus or
Dent recount so whatever.
The first aggregate is is whatever the current one is and then we'll
save that then here will assert that we've got one of those and at the
end we'll just set it to nothing.
That would be don't even is that getting flag anymore.
So then when we come through here, we can say
Instead, let's just snap a pointer to the last one.
So this is like one pass last entry and that can just be whatever.
The current sword entry county is now we know is that's the one we're
going to stop at.
So then we just say, all right, we've got to sort spray pounds, we're
going to start it at whatever the first aggregate was render group.
First aggregate.
We're going to go for each entry until we get to the one that we don't
want to process like the very last one, and then we're going to plus
plus entry.
And you can see that was a - - entry that was wrong already.
So that was a bug as well.
But I just fixed because we're going forwards now not backwards,
right?
So then we come through here and we say, okay, do the operation going
to do and then clear it out.
So that seems a lot more saying to me.
And then up here, all we have to do now is say well okay, if the first
aggregate
That were working with is the the one that we're talking about here,
then we finish it off, right?
So that seems totally sane to me that cleans that up to a, you know, I
think a better place than it was before.
And so I'm hoping that we can make that work cleanly.
Now last thing is that now since we've reversed the order, I think we
can go back to standard order on the other things that we push because
before we had actually done them in like sort of reverse wise if
That makes sense specifically so that we wouldn't have to worry about
the fact that they were reversed before so in add, you know, player or
whatever.
We'd actually reversed this order to keep torso Shadow instead of the
other way around.
And so now we can kind of go back to logical order where we're pushing
the road.
We're going to draw, which I like better, like I'm glad we could do
that.
And now I think we're good to go, right?
So now we just have to fix the head.
I believe the head is still wrong.
Let me check here, familiar, can you block me for a second?
Thank you.
Yeah.
So I feel like that is the head.
head part is
Still kind of wrong there.
Yeah.
And I'm not sure.
Where exactly, that's coming from.
So I want to take a look at that one as well.
Okay, so in handmade render group.
I'm pretty sure Reserve sort key, really has nothing to do with that
stuff we changed.
So, I'm not sure why that would be the case, what I could do actually
as well, and let me just go ahead and change this and I think about
it.
So, inside platform, I'm gonna turn on the the drawing here.
I want to see whether we're getting a cycle at that point, so we are
getting a cycle when that happens.
So I suppose it's possible.
There's just because again we're not really breaking Cycles in an
intelligent way.
Let me double-check that I can't make it happen without a cycle.
It does seem.
It sure does seem
So, it will sometimes work when there's a cycle, but, of course,
that's expected because we don't, we break Cycles randomly at the
moment, but it doesn't seem to break unless there's a cycle so far.
so that may actually just be because of Cycles hard to say,
Yeah, so that may just because of Cycles will have to think about how
we should break Cycles because I'm not really sure what you know, the
way is that we would want to break them.
I haven't really given it much thought.
So I'm not sure.
But yeah.
All right.
So that's our current situation.
Let's go ahead and crank back up the room, count and start to look at
some of the other bugs again, because that just seems like, okay good.
Yeah.
You know I'm saying?
So, add standard room.
Let's take a look.
No, I like how many rooms.
I don't know.
Maybe 4 is fine.
Let's say.
Okay, so
we're not getting a lot of those other bugs at the moment so it looks
like we fixed a bunch of those with the way that we were.
So those blinking tree bugs, were probably mostly based on the fact
that we were
Going backwards in the order, we were probably over writing sort keys
for other entities.
I wouldn't be surprised if that was the case.
So let's take a look here at how that sorting is doing.
It's looking pretty good, I guess I would say.
So that's good and yeah, everything looks actually relatively solid
right now.
So that's starting to look pretty respectable and I think you know,
we've got more stuff to do here, but it looks like the sort is less
than a concern.
Now, the cycle breaking is going to be something.
We're going to have to deal with for sure.
We'll see what happens when we put stuff in that.
Has the correct bounds as well, but that's starting to look pretty
reasonable.
So, I think now we can go back to what we were doing before, which is
getting the layer stuff working.
Because that seems okay.
All right, so yeah.
And now you know, in theory, at least anyway, we're sorting by group
now so we shouldn't have hopefully as much pressure either on the
sort.
And let's take a look at what's going on there.
So if we take a look at build Sprite graph for calling it for four
times but it is taking up a tremendous amount of time there although,
you know, one thing that's a little bit hard about that.
Lets we don't really want to look at it in the
list of
the debug system.
So let's just go ahead and quickly pause and then look back at some of
these.
Okay, so if you look back at what's happening when we're not, when we
don't have a debug system up.
So here's a frame, that doesn't have the debug system up invisible.
You can see that.
It's kind of quite a bit less than once the debug system is visible
its Giant and that's because all of these Sprites are all getting
sorted as well.
And you can still see the closest reversible as one of our worst
offenders.
Well, which is good because that's a completely an accelerated and
squared algorithm which we know how to trivially accelerate.
So that's a good one too, but that's still a lot of times Felton spent
in build spray crap again, periodically, I just kind of like to check
to see what the situation is here.
So I'm just going to check build up at really quickly.
I want to see what happens in release mode and make sure that there's
nothing particularly unusual going on there.
Let's just take a quick look.
At what's happening there.
Here's the profile and you know we can kind of see that in this
situation.
Build Sprite graph is it's still expensive, but not too bad and if I
go back to
Look at some other frames here.
So here's one where the debug system isn't up.
3% of the time isn't bad.
You know, do I love three percent of the time?
But you know, that's really not that bad considering how much work it
has to do.
And, you know, we haven't done a whole lot to optimize it yet other
than just the grid based stuff.
So, I'm okay with that, that's not going to make me to lyrics.
Not going to lose sleep over that guy.
So, I think we're okay, right?
And this is nice and Zippy this is 60 frames a second as well.
Let me unpause this guy.
There we go.
So yeah.
So this is running at 60 frames a second.
So we end we don't really have to worry too much at that point.
Because yeah I mean the actual game itself isn't going to be that much
more complicated in terms of what's happening on the screen than what
we see right here, you know.
So because this isn't a game with like thousands and thousands of
Sprites that supposed to be you know roughly how many there are on the
screen right now.
You know they'll be more effects happening but effects can kind of
Be their own thing.
I think a lot of the time hopefully.
So yeah.
All right, so that all seems good.
I don't really have any problem with that.
I think that's all pretty reasonable.
So now what we kind of have to look at is sort of what I was talking
about before of, we have a problem at the moment as far as Alpha
blending in and let me see if I can get it to a point where it's
actually happening.
a guitar do that, I'll have to go downstairs when I
Okay, so this is an example of the alpha in problem, but I
unfortunately, I can't I don't have trees that are quite on top of
each other enough.
But you could probably kind of see it happening down here a little
bit.
And that is essentially that well, you know, if we were to stack up
some stuff, let me see if I can actually get that happening somewhere.
So,
I'm just not sure how to get anything.
All that more obvious.
I mean one on the one hand maybe it's a waste of our time to even go
down this route.
But
It would be nice to show.
I guess.
One thing I could do is if I made this read that might help.
So I'm
Go ahead and do that.
So let's suppose, we went into the world mode code or actually I guess
that's an entity.
Now, when we draw the Traverse Littles, we do an occupier check, and
if someone's on and occupied Square, we change the color.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to change that to Pure red and so
here you can sort of see that happening, right?
So now what I'm going to do is I'm going to kind of come up here.
So what I want you to focus on, is this is the area where this
familiars head is floating, right?
You can kind of see it.
Now, there's no red there.
It's like, brown tan or whatever, right?
But doesn't look red.
Now, as soon as I go like this, you'll notice it becomes kind of
almost a reddish shade, right?
You start to see red in there.
It's all kind of a, almost more of a uniform color, right?
And that's because this is getting transparent.
If that makes sense, you can start to see that getting transparent.
Now for a more, let me I can think I can do an even
More obtuse or obvious version of that.
Probably, let me see here.
If I was to say shrink how big these are so suppose, I was to set this
to something thin.
So do you see how this is probably the most?
Yeah, I should have thought of before.
So do you see how you can't see this line coming through the head,
right?
You know, their heads opaque, it completely blocks out what's behind
it.
But when I start to Alpha it out all of a sudden you can see through
the head, but you're never supposed to see through the head.
We're supposed to Alpha out that whole floor as one
Coherent piece, right?
And so, that's a good example, that's probably the best example.
I can give of why we would want to Alpha out everything it and so that
it doesn't look like things are disappearing.
It looks like the whole thing is fading away rather than pieces
disappearing.
On top of other pieces, which are also disappearing independently if
that makes sense.
So hopefully that's a little bit clearer.
What's going on there?
I don't know, I hope
Hopefully, you can gain some sort of appreciation for why, I would
might care about that.
Being sort of a person who's OCD for that sort of thing.
All right, so let's go ahead and take a look at what will require to
make that happen.
Now, we already have the concept of a barrier in here now, right?
And so, we know that when we go to render things, we have the
Have things occur at barriers.
So, if we take a look at what's happening inside our sort code render.
Now, when we come out of here, when we come out of sort entries, this
sorted list of indices what it has in there obviously, are the things
that it has in, their can include information to the render.
I'm about stuff that needs to happen.
So what we want to do there potentially is have there be a way that we
can insert something.
In addition to our barrier that says like, hey we need you to do an
alpha fade on this whole thing that's coming up next.
So you have to kind of do a separate composite to it, that's just kind
of the way it goes right now.
I don't know that.
That's I think that might be pushing the system a little bit too far
at that point and so
I think we're going to probably want to do at this point is when we is
to actually have the notion of a coherent block that, that has
rendered Cape, that knows how to do some kind of certain rendering
operations, right?
So I think what we want to do is have our render command list actually
have some understanding of sort of what's in there and we probably
don't want to do something quite like that.
I mean maybe we do I don't know.
I mean maybe this is a fine architecture for it considering that we
don't really need to push it that far, but it's just, it's I don't
know.
We'll see, maybe it's fine to have those in there.
Maybe it's not, I'm not entirely sure we'll see as we go.
But for the time being, we kind of have to ping-pong back to our open
GL code, and our other render code in order to make this stuff work.
So the first thing I want to do though is I want to see if we're still
rendering, okay?
Through our other system and it looks like we are.
So this is the software renderer, that's so cool.
I love the fact that our software renderer is so accurate.
I want to fix that that half pixel offset as well, so that they're
just exact someday we got to go do that.
So anyway,
Here is the software renderer doing its thing and, and looking awesome
and all that.
So what I think we want to do is go to our software renderer and
implement this first so that everyone understands what it is that
we're actually doing.
And then we can go back and implement it in opengl, which is as always
a huge pain in the butt because open Jill and basically all
Safety is our ridiculous.
So let's go ahead and talk about what needs to happen in order for
that to occur and then we'll get started on it.
Oops.
so what we are going to be talking about here is multiple render
targets
And the phrase render Target basically means, you know, buffer of
memory.
That you draw, too.
So what you have seen throughout the course of handmade hero when we
wrote all the software renderer and all that stuff, you'll note that
we were always rendering to the same piece of memory, right?
We have this notion that there was sort of a back buffer like a screen
buffer that was holding, what we were going to display.
We render everything into it.
So that piece of memory we draw into and then when we were done, we
basically handed that buffer to Windows and said here show this
And then when we did the opengl version of the code, we did
essentially the same thing.
We just said, here's all the stuff we wanted to draw into that buffer
and then when we're done, we said swap, you know, like show it to the
to the user.
So that's how we've been thinking about things, right?
We've been thinking about things in a sense of curious like the screen
and we would thinking about like all of this stuff kind of like being
drawn onto it, right and then we display it.
So it's really like a
A back we were sort of thinking of is like the back screen and then we
were bringing it forwards, right?
Well, what we have now is the need to expand that notion.
So, what we want to do now, right?
Is we have the actual screen.
and previously we had, you know, one buffer,
We call that the back buffer but let's call it for.
Now that we're sort of spending out let's call this buffer a right and
previous what was happening as we did all of our drawing into prefer a
and then we had some way of getting buffer, a to the screen, right?
That was either via a call to Windows that says, here, take this
buffer and show it on screen or a call to opengl.
That said, we're done rendering now show the buffer that we've been
working on.
Okay.
And so previously, that's all are sort of composite phase.
Look like
But what we want to do now is we essentially want to take two buffers,
right?
Or more so we want like a buffer a and a buffer B and we want to
combine buffer a and buffer B and draw them to the
Right.
so, what we want to do,
Is we want to draw a bunch of stuff into my for p.
We want to draw a bunch of stuff into my for a and then we want to
combine them using our standard Alpha operation, write a standard
Alpha blending operation, like what we've been using that sort of
Composites.
Those two things together to produce our final screen.
And again, the reason we want to do that is so that we can apply a
uniform alpha Fade to this buffer, or well, we can choose whichever
buffer.
We want to be the one that we're fading in and out.
Out having separate pieces become in like see-through.
Hopefully, that makes sense.
So that's what we need to do.
And so if you take a look at the way that our old renderer, our
software under worked, you know, we can sort of pull that back and you
can see that the way that that was happening.
If we go to software under commands is we pass it in this output
Target, and the output targets.
The thing that was sort of doing double duty, right?
Like I said,
it's basically, it was basically buffer a
And the sort of back buffer it was basically just we didn't really
distinguish us to what it was.
So it's just a place that we drew our stuff too.
And then it was going to get displayed.
But what we want to do now is essentially have more than one of these
output targets that we choose between at the end, we'll composite
between them, right?
That's what we actually want to do.
Now we have a situation here where I thought when we passed I'm gonna
verify this.
I thought when we pass these in,
Yeah, so I we pass in a temporary ne4 to prep for render.
I'm going to I'm going to keep that that love going.
So I'm going to say that software renderer commands gets a temporary
NE the arena for doing allocations right.
So, where's that prep?
Tempt Arena.
It is so that way we can have some scratch memory, right?
So I'm going to start really, really basic just so everyone can follow
along with what I'm doing.
All I'm going to do is I'm going to introduce a totally extraneous
completely, unnecessary piece of work that we're going to do just to
show you what I mean.
So right now we have a loaded bitmap, it's called output Target.
We know that whatever we draw into output Target is what we were then
going to hand to Windows.
in the software interface and say, here, display this in your
windowsill
Um, we don't know, we didn't write windows, we don't know how you're
going to do that.
We just know we produced a beautiful looking game image for you,
please display it, right?
So that's what output Target is and if you remember what that actually
looks like, I can't remember where we Define loaded bitmap.
I think it may be in the renter group code loaded bitmap or maybe in
the asset code.
I never remember.
There it is.
So we have this loaded bitmap and we've got that sort of memory
pointer and all that nonsense, right?
And so if we wanted to, what we could do is create a separate look,
one of these loaded bitmaps that we draw two instead.
Because remember output Target is just something that we pass through
here.
You can see all of this stuff where we do software renderer commands,
you can see us doing this sort of work with the output Target, right?
And then, when we have all that stuff, it actually kicks off the, the
work and all that, you know, blah, blah, blah, blah blah, right?
So software renderer commands when it gets caught,
Old, that's what it's going to do.
And so if I wanted to, I could say call this final output Target.
I could, if I wanted to create another exact copy of it, right?
I could basically say let's say we have another output Target which is
going to be like a push struct on The Temper Inna.
So let's create another one.
I'm going to copy all of the values of the final output Target, right?
So basically all this stuff, the with over height, the width, the
height, the pitch that all, that junk.
We're going to copy exactly, but since there's two different, you
know, we don't want to draw to the same memory.
Although you know what, I could obviously, if if I leave the memory
part of the same.
Now, if I just, I'm using that one nothing would change, right?
I'm just going to do the same exact drawing that.
I was, of course.
I want to set it to actually call that renderer, so I have to switch
it every time.
So let's go ahead and say win32 rendering type equals win32.
Display opengl but render and software so that now will be rendering
to the software renderer at startup by default and there we go.
So you know, it's just doing the exact same rendering, it's using the
exact same memory pointer, right?
But now I'm going to change it to say.
Okay now, I want the output targets memory, I would like to have a
memory block.
That's the same size right as the other memory block as the
On that was getting passed into me for the final output Target, right?
So instead I'm going to now go to load a bitmap whereas little bit
mad.
Look at it, right?
So now I want to say well okay I'm going to set the pitch to whatever
I want the pitch to be.
So I'm going to set the pitch to be the width times for because I want
it back.
So I'm just going to say like okay the the output Target.
Oh well, actually you know what?
I'll leave the pitch as it is I'm going to assert temporarily that the
pitch is positive.
Is that true?
Yeah, some assert that the pitch is positive and then it's going to
say okay the memory block that we're going to render to.
Now I'm going to push a basically a block of memory on here.
That happens to be exactly as big as I want.
It wanted it to be right?
I want the pitch times, the height.
So block of memory that's basically as big as the old one was and I
want you to give me that spare block of memory and that's what we're
going to draw two now.
Now, we know that this stuff has to be aligned.
So I'm going to go ahead and ask for alignment here as well.
I'm going to look just to make sure because I'm pretty sure that we
asked for the alignment in the existing one as well.
Yeah, you can see here.
This is how we do this stuff.
Oh we virtual Alec that.
Wow.
Aren't we fancy?
My goodness?
Well.
Okay, that's, that's not how we're going to do it here but but
whatever.
So
Go back to and may not h.
Memory.
That is it.
There we go.
I just want to look at how I did alignment there.
And it looks like a line.
No.
Clear is what I probably want to do.
So I'm going to say a line.
No clear and I want you to align the 16 B boundaries so it's SSE
aligned, right?
So now I believe I can just run it and what we're doing now is we're
rendering into that block of memory.
Now you'll note you don't see anything on the screen and the reason
you don't see anything on the screen is because we didn't touch the
actual buffer that we're just
But we didn't crash because we gave it a completely new buffer that
can handle it and so it's fine.
So now what I want to do is when we get to the end I want to copy
these two.
So after we do complete all work, I want to do a thing where we
basically say like, okay let's Loop through all of the pixels and
actually copy them one by one.
Now I suppose I could just copy the whole memory you know I could just
do this.
So maybe that's the easiest thing to do first and that's again, pretty
trivial all I'd be doing they're saying well I would like to copy the
output targets pitch times, the output targets height.
Worth of memory.
I'd like to copy it from the output targets memory into the final
output targets memory.
Right.
And there we go.
So now we have meet our render or slower, certainly, because it's
doing a big old copy of the entire screen for no reason.
But we're seeing what's happening.
Opening right?
We're seeing what happens to that back, buffer.
So now we've created a situation where we are doing this.
We are basically saying okay renderer you know render into output
Target.
We are then issuing a copy.
Two final output Target.
Right.
And then we're taking that buffer and we're giving that buffer to
Windows, and that's what we're seeing on the screen to the software,
vendor side of things, right?
Okay.
So hopefully now you can see it's a pretty short step to do two
different renders, right?
If I want to, I just now need to know.
What are the two things that I'm going to render, right?
I just need.
The ability.
To shunt things into different render targets.
Now, since we already have the concept of clip, Rex, it seems to me
like it would be pretty straightforward to do the same thing for
render targets, right?
So when you specify cliprect, you can also specify
What render Target you were looking at right now.
This is not the kind of clip, rect I'm actually talking about here,
this is the clip.
Rect obviously, for the tile.
I'm talking about the other clip, rex that are specified in the actual
stream.
So,
All we really need to add to the render system, other than some kind
of an index and except break that says, which render Target to render
to is, we need some way of saying how the final composite Stage Works,
right?
That's what we need something along those lines and in order to do
that, there's a couple different things we could do.
One of them is to just actually include those things in the Stream and
that does seem like kind of a compelling way to do it in my mind.
So I think that might be the way I would like to do it and
furthermore, because we have this concept of sort of being able to
render to.
We could probably do something where we could select these as sources
as well.
I think it seems likely, right?
So let's, let's take a look at what it would take.
We'll take this one step at a time.
I
Have very much time left, unfortunately, but got about 15 minutes will
make the most of it.
So let's start by going into the render group code.
And inside the render group code, I want to sort of do exactly what I
was doing with the cliprect index stuff before, instead of just
specifying a rectangle to, I, I want to specify a render Target as
well.
So,
Here, I'm going to have like a Target index, something like that,
right?
And that Target index would allow me to say that I have more than one
render Target or who knows what.
Right.
And I again, I'm gonna, you know, I'm not going to implement a really
particularly robust system for this.
I'm just going to do a very basic one, but this would basically say,
okay for every clip rect I'm going to have a Target that Target is
Going to tell me where I'm going to render to, and I can now have more
than one render Target in play.
So, what I want to do there is I want to say,
Probably in the object transform, I'm guessing.
But let's see.
Cliprect index currents on purpose.
So, in here, I could just say current render Target index.
I suppose.
Well, actually, when we push the clip, rect that's when we would do
it, push cliprect, right?
So here in the cliprect, when we specify one of these clip Rex,
presumably what we would do is say, you know, whatever the render
Target is that you say that you're going to render to that's that
would get set here.
So, in addition to that stuff, you would say, you know, render Target
index, something like that, and the render Target index would just be,
like, okay, here when we set the wreck stuff,
Packets recorded.
Right.
What did I do?
Just called it Target index.
There we go.
Oops.
and so, now when we're actually putting clip Rex in here,
I should.
I should be able to specify multiple render targets, they just won't
do anything but I can specify them, right.
Like so.
And so invite a fault.
Obviously we do is render to render Target zero and when I do push
clip, Rex you know we've got a couple of different times that that
happens here mostly in the debug system at the moment, right?
And those I think we don't really care too much about.
But what I'll do here is say, you know, render Target or
That.
So, you know, we can set it to whatever we want it to be later if we
want to have a separate render Target for the debug system, right?
And so in that case, I just need to store that here in the
Like state.
So I would have something in here where we're like render Target and
that would just get cleared, 20, presumably when everything else gets
there to 0 and then we should be done, right?
That's all that.
That would have to happen to have that be specified.
So no big mystery there, nothing particularly exciting.
Now, what we do need to do however is in the render group when we
actually do set that information.
So when we do a push clip,
Right here.
And we actually set that information.
What we need to do is make sure that the, you know, if the group
commands render Target count, which is something we'll have to track
is not sufficient.
So if it's less than or equal to the render Target index, or I guess,
we'll call it Max render Target index.
If those are insufficient, then we will set it.
So this way, we'll track, whatever the maximum render Target index is
that you used, we will, we will remember it, right?
Okay, so let's see, cliprect count.
So, in here, with all the rest of this stuff which gets initialized we
can just say Max render Target index, like so, and that should now
always be set to whatever that value, whatever.
The highest one is that we actually used.
So, now what we can do is go back to our renderer,
Right.
And make essentially, a table for the renderer of the render targets
that we needed.
So, here we are in there.
When we do suffer render commands, what I'm going to do now is I'm
effectively going to clone out as many render buffer is, as I think we
need based on that number
okay, so what I'm going to say is render targets
Right.
EXO.
I'm going to do a push a ray.
And I'm going to say, I want a loaded bitmap render Target.
Four.
You know, it's kind of amusing.
We use the same thing for a little bit Maps as it for drawing, but I
don't really remember why we ever did that.
Did we ever draw to something and then use it as a texture?
We did.
I know what we were using that for, yeah, we use that for ground
chunks as like a new.
We must have done it for something.
That's what we did it for.
All right.
So anyway, I'm going to push in a
These guys and I'm going to push an array of Max render Target index
plus 1, right?
So that way.
And in fact I just do render Target count here.
I'll just sort of compute that
Up above so we can see what it is but there you go.
So I'm going to create an array of those and I'm going to set the
first one equal to the final output Target.
Right.
So render Target zero Zoe's just the screen and then I'm going to do a
loop over all the other ones if there are any.
Right.
So you know I'm going to go from one to the render Target count.
Men go through each of the targets.
And then I'm going to, I'm going to still do this part here.
I'm going to get a chunk of memory for each of them.
So for each case, and when I go ahead and say Target equals render
targets plus Target index, I'm going to just romp over everything with
whatever the final output targets settings are.
And I'm just going to give it new memory everything else will remain
exactly the same.
Like so.
And then in here, so for the tiling, five minute warning for the
tiling, I'm going to do the same thing, right?
I'm just going to use the final output Target for it instead.
And then all I really need to do for these output Target things here
is instead in that of that work, that sort of work array.
I don't know where that's actually defined, to be honest with you,
what is that called tile render work.
Where's tile render work?
There it is for towel render work.
Instead of output Target, I'm going to call this render targets like
so and I am going to set that to our render targets array.
So now there's like, you know, n render targets and you can render to
any of them that you want.
And so then what we will find is out here where we do this, let's see.
What is this doing?
Render commands to bitmap?
Yeah, so when we do run,
Commands to bitmap instead of this output Target thing.
Now, we actually need sort of a render targets array there.
And that's a nice old array and we pass it.
And let's see who else needs that because there's some other people
who apparently need that, let's find out who that is.
So render CrossFit map draw, rect angle that.
So that's the clear.
Let's see here, output Target those are all Apatow.
It's here we go.
Final output Target.
This is all final output Target.
Oops.
Okay.
So yeah.
It's no longer needs to be here.
And so I think that's basically it all.
We now have to do is select the actual output Target that we want from
our clip.
Rect so we have a loaded bitmap, it's our output Target.
It's going to be render targets plus whatever the clip rect is that
we're currently using.
I guess I can do it like this.
It's going to be whatever the clip rect is that we're currently using
Plus.
I'm sorry.
It's going to be the base of the Rena Target array.
Plus whichever cliprect entry were using whichever render Target.
It says that is
it says it wants.
Okay.
Here we go.
and,
So now everything is doing exactly what we want in theory.
We now have multiple render targets, we don't composite those render
targets, but let's just check to see if that's actually working now,
right?
And we can do that pretty easily, I think just by saying, let's take
the debug system and let's set the debug system so that it's code is
Going to use the default render Target, right?
So, when we call debug begin here and we set default cliprect to be
current cliprect index or whatever this is, you know, I think this is
using a custom cliprect.
Let's go ahead and set that custom cliprect because we know we have it
in here, render Target.
I think that's what it's called yet render Target, let's set render
Target equal to 1.
So it's using a
A different render Target number, right?
Poof, where did it go?
It's getting rendered to the other render Target and we can't see it,
which is exactly what we expect and exactly what we want.
So now we have more than one render Target in the actual software.
Renderer, we just don't have any way to actually say how we want those
things to be composited, but that's okay.
That's something that we can do.
Next week.
So I will go ahead and leave that in this state.
Let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
I'm sorry, I didn't mean to say next week, I meant tomorrow.
A bit unrelated to the project.
But what do you think about the rust language?
Yeah, that is a bit unrelated to the project considering the fact that
it is not written in Rust
I have not used it so I don't I don't have any opinions about it.
Build a strong.
So when do we think we will be ready for the new graphics assets?
I'm excited when we are when we have Z solidly under control and we
might want to do lighting as well.
So we kind of have a couple things we got to do their Graphics wise,
that's then that's about it.
So yeah, probably should stop doing that.
but,
Can you explain what this game is?
Yes.
Well it's it's actually an educational programming series.
The the idea behind it is to show come creating a game completely from
start to finish, not using any libraries or even.
We don't even require opengl or even Hardware acceleration, like we
even like I was just showing at the end of this stream, for example.
Wrote Our Own rasterizer.
That actually draws all the pixels one by one.
And so the the game per se is basically a reason to show how all this
stuff is done and, you know, eventually it will be just a game on its
own that you can play and have fun with.
But the point of the vast majority, certainly
Out of all of the twitch coding is a little bit different.
It's not to generate, you know publicity for the game or something
that we're not just showing like fun parts, or simple things or
whatever.
We're actually just showing how to do game programming and the goal of
the series is to have a really complete sort of video series of the
end, where you can see how every last little part of a game is made,
if that's something that you're interested in learning, and you can
look at specific Parts if you want to see how
A particular part of a game can get made.
That's that's one.
Is writing to that other currently invisible render Target much.
Any less computation expensive than also sending it to this play.
Well it's it's not probably that much more computationally expensive
to render to the Target.
It can be depends on the cache situations and various other things,
right?
Because since we have a tiled renderer if the tile sort of data stays
in the cache multiplying out how many of those tiles you have to have
I don't know to what extent that would cause problems.
It depends how often you flip between rendering to the different
targets as well.
So there's a there's a bunch of
and stuff like that, that could be there, but in general,
All the main cost that were adding, isn't that hopefully the main
costs are adding is the composite step because that's pure cost,
right?
So when we render to render targets, if we had rendered all those
things to just one render Target?
Is that a little faster?
Yes.
But is it hugely faster?
Possibly not.
What is going to be much slower, is the fact that once we have
multiple charts, we got to bring them back together, sometime somehow.
And so that's a bunch of extra bandwidth, write a bunch of entrant
grabbing all that data back from the render targets compiled causing
together and putting it into yet another render Target, right?
So that's what I would say.
With multiple render targets.
Are there other effects you can do other than the alpha blending?
Well, you know, as far as multiple render targets is concerned,
specifically, you know, usually what you're talking about for render
targets, is if you want to do stuff, like I rendered the screen and
then I like did some kind of a wipe or like a maquette like, you know,
maybe you've seen on the old Nintendo games, like they do a circle
that squishes into like and then comes back out, you know, once you
are ready,
Two separate targets.
You can have Matt's between them, or you can offset them or you can do
stuff like that.
So, you know, you can also take a rendering and put it somewhere in
the game.
So, if you wanted like a little TV screen or something, you know, you
could do stuff like that, we won't really be doing that stuff.
There's nothing in particular that I have in mind that would require
any of that.
But, you know, you can, you can easily think of a lot of reasons.
Why once you have the game render into a buffer,
Things that you could do.
Are you going to support shaders?
And if so, will you try to support multiple render Targets in the
shaders?
So know.
So I'm not sure which question you're actually asking.
We don't have any need for shaders themselves, to have multiple render
Targets in the Shader, because that's a real thing.
A Shader can actually Target more than one render Target at a time.
However, for a game such as this one, that's a 2-D game.
That would be like a fantastically bad idea.
And the reason for that is only some graphics cards can support
multiple render targets out of a single Shader and since we don't need
the extra performance.
That that the only reason you do that is if you have specific
performance reasons, why you why that's more efficient for you to do?
We can easily just run the Shader twice and run it to each Target.
If that's something that we actually needed.
Now, I don't
Even know that we have any reasons, why we would even ever have a
Shader that would write to two Targets at the same time.
Anyway, I don't think we have any situations that would be like that
so I don't even think it would even come up.
But point being we wouldn't be doing that.
Now on the, if what you were actually asking is just when we do, the
opengl version will be support because we have an opengl renderer
running as well.
When we ping pong over to that, will we add render targets were too?
That.
Yes, absolutely.
But that doesn't have anything to do with shaders shaders.
Don't even know that there's multiple render targets.
They just know that they're like until you actually start targeting
more than one render Target inside the actual Shader, you don't, it
doesn't even know because that stuff gets set outside the Shader
before the Shader gets invoked.
Are you excited to get an art 64 tool chain up and running to get this
thing to run on a Raspberry Pi 3?
Not really platform work.
Doesn't usually excite me that much.
To be honest I kind of wish we had just settled that matter from now
and had it's just a just a ship the day gpus go away will be my
happiest day of all times.
Yeah.
Lord Marshal, are you still working full-time?
Why only stream one hour night?
Yes I work on an actual like full big game project in my normal hours
of work.
SC, 24 vad.
How would you go about rendering?
Huge tile, Maps.
Some batching techniques.
Or any tips?
What is a huge tile map.
I'm not sure what that means.
The tile maps in handmade hero can be so large that you could never
really even walk across them.
So if the question is just how do you render a scene out of a giant?
Tilemap, we already do that.
If the question is you want to zoom way out and have tiny little
tiles.
The answer there is like I'll be honest.
Chances are you won't even be able to get the tile tiny enough that
you even really care.
Performance-wise.
You just can't fit that many tiles on the screen.
I mean, even if you style, was only one pixel big.
So if what you want to do was zoom out to the point where each tile
was a fraction of a pixel or something like that, then you just need
to have multiresolution.
You need to have knowledge of what you basically MIT maps of your
world map so you can say, OK for this whole region, what's the tile
that I should use?
Or what's the color that I should use?
But I'm not sure which one
Asking.
Building strong.
Would that be a good technique to use to create an overhead map?
Yeah.
Possibly I mean it could be I don't think you'd really usually need to
though.
Because remember, you can just set a cliff region and then render up
into the corner, a smaller version.
You don't really need a separate render Target for it.
Separate.
Render targets are only necessary when you actually need to combine
two things after the fact, using operations, that could not have been
done.
Just in place, right?
So Alpha and other kinds of Composites, like that are good examples of
that, right?
It's about is pretty great.
I'm loving these and so Bots.
Let's see.
All right, let's go ahead and close down.
Thank you everyone for joining me for handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along with series at home, you can
always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org and it comes with a
source code which I update nightly.
So you can play around at home and learn.
We have a forum site, you can go to ask questions a patreon page if
you'd like to support our video series, a schedule bot, you can use if
you want to have the schedule tweeted when we're going to be live and
also an episode guide for trying to catch up on past episodes.
That's it for today.
I will be back here tomorrow, I believe 8, p.m.
Pacific Daylight time, but check the Tweet.
But if you want to know for sure, until then have fun coding and I
will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.