Hello everyone, and thank you for joining me for handmade hero.
Welcome to the only show on Twitch where we coded complete game live
from scratch.
No engine, no libraries, no nothing.
We do it all here, it's like one of those weird fancy restaurants
where they like grow all the herbs in a garden on the roof, right?
You know, the kind I'm talking about and it's very strange and like
when you read the menu, you don't actually know what any of the things
are because the descriptions don't really
If anything, they're filled, both mostly with words that you've never
heard of before or that you have a vague sense of what they might be.
But you really just aren't sure.
And you kind of have to wait for the waiter to come over and when they
come over you have to be like.
So the salmon and like you kind of let your voice Trail off like that
and that lets them know that you really have no idea what you were
looking at.
That's sort of what we're doing here, you know?
I'll admit that but we do not have a garden on the roof.
I've actually never been on the roof of this building.
I suspect it's probably very dangerous.
It's actually rather tall building but we do grow all of our code
ourselves.
And all of our pixels are hand selected by us for the finest quality
and that is something that we're going to get back into today.
We have gotten to the point where we're doing our own texture mapping.
We wrote our own texture, mapped renderer and
We have a bunch of things that we kind of need to look out into now in
terms of picking, what our next step is.
So I think today is a good day for us to kind of, like, figure out
what it is.
We want to accomplish with the rest of the renderer and make a plan
for getting there.
So if you have pre-ordered, the game on handmade hero dot-org and you
would like to follow along with a source code at home today, it is day
96.
So you want to unpack day 95 source code, because that is what I am
working with today.
And so if you want to
Line up with what I'm doing that is the code to start with all right?
So you know we we had a little bit of something that we needed to
address at the end of last episode and we kind of got to think about
how we want to do that.
Exactly.
I don't remember exactly which state we left it in here but I guess we
left it in the optimized Village.
So as you can see, even with are completely unoptimized renderer where
we were now doing gamma correction everywhere and we were also
supporting scaling and texture map.
And rotating and all that stuff and we got all that working things
were very slow when we compiled our build without optimizations on,
but they're plenty fast with optimizations on.
But as I was pointing out, it makes a little hard to do a teaching
stream if we compile with optimizations on because it makes stepping
through the code, be very jumping.
It's hard for me to show you things.
I want to show you when we do that.
So what I do want to do is figure out some way that we can start to
address that and really we've got two ways that we can do that and I
feel like
There's certainly some, they're certainly.
I agree.
There's there's a certain part of me that philosophically wants to
say, let's not optimize the code ourselves right now, because if we
start optimizing the code ourselves right now, we haven't really
necessarily gotten to the point where we know everything that we want
to do with it.
And so the optimization may have to be changed or may, you know, be
sort of rendered obsolete.
When later we decide we need to do other things with the renderer.
But another part of me says well I don't know how bad that really is.
At the end of the day because we haven't introduced optimization
really at all on this stream.
We haven't talked about it at all, and so optimizing something and
then having to optimize it again.
Later is really not a big deal because maybe we kind of need to do
that just to let everyone have a chance to kind of see what goes on
there.
So I don't really know which way I should tackle that if I was doing
the code myself, I certainly wouldn't optimize it now but you know
that's you know, certain things happen differently on the stream here
just because it is a teaching stream.
So there's that.
So what I was kind of thinking we might do in terms of moving forward
on this, we've got to sort of directions we can go one is, we can add
some features to the renderer right now, meaning we can go, what are
some, what are some of the other features that we might need?
Can we get them in there?
And can we do that with letting the code be unoptimized?
We can step through it and all that.
And the features that I think that we don't have in there right now
that we might need really.
There's two.
And one of them is not so much.
Teacher.
The first one is making sure that we have a sort of a rigorous
definition of what filling a pixel means and where the texture is come
from for those pixels, right?
Because we were kind of ad hoc with it.
When we just we're getting things working, which is a good idea
because you really don't want to be too hung up on any one thing where
you just trying to get something working, so that's fine.
But before we start building a bunch of stuff on top of this, it would
be nice to know that we had really dotted the eyes and
Cross the t's, in terms of where, you know, what is our pixel fill
rule, how does it?
And how does it operate?
What is our rule for Gathering texels?
And all that sort of stuff.
So that would be nice.
The other thing that we haven't tackled because we have tinting and we
have Alpha control and we have scaling, we have rotation, which is
most of, I think what we probably will use for the game, but one thing
that we do not have is we do not have any sort.
Of lighting control in here.
Meaning that if you wanted to change the pixels of a Sprite in here,
in some way that had to do with a directional or area based light
source, we don't really have any way of doing that effectively.
So the other thing that I thought that we probably would want to
investigate before.
We start optimizing our actual texture filling routines, is to take a
look and say what can we do?
You know, we've got our little tests right here, that's rotating
Around, and it's nice.
Move and does all the things we wanted it to do.
What can we add here?
That would allow us to do some more Dynamic Lighting on this thing,
right to sort of give it a little more of that liveliness and so that
we allow our game to kind of be a little bit more fancy.
So you know I'm differing about it and to be honest, I don't really
know which one we should do.
But here's what I'm going to say I think that if I just turn off
everything else.
The game and just where to render just the tree.
Obviously, we would not have a lot of performance problems anymore, I
don't think right because having completely unoptimized code, if we're
only running it on a very small subsection, that doesn't seem like it
would be a problem.
So maybe what we should do, is turn all this stuff off just stop
rendering entirely which is Trivial for us to do only render one or
two things put in our lighting, get that working.
Get our
So sort of math.
Correct?
Like exactly the way we're going to do that.
And then button that down, say that's the renderer.
That's the features that it supports.
And now let's go ahead and optimize it seems like a pretty same path
to me.
It's very similar to the path that I would take if I was doing this
for real.
So that feels kind of good.
And so that's sort of what I'm thinking we might do.
So, let's just take a look at that.
Let's see what that would entail.
As a start to today.
So, if I open up the code here, right?
You remember that we have our render or kind of builds up groups of
things that it's going to render and then it issues them after the
fact.
So we kind of have this push buffer scheme.
It builds up a list of things that wants to do and then it renders
them.
Now, our test thing that we were working on with rotation and scaling
that we got working was in this render enter entry coordinate system
thing which is really just a test thing that allows a specified
coordinates and then it would kind of work or rectangle so that we
could learn
Do that and that all went very well but what we can do is recognize
the fact that right now, all of our fancy code is running through this
path, right.
And so the other code, which you modified it be gamma correct and
which is kind of slow now.
But that doesn't do any of the fanciness in terms of the stretching
and rotating.
And that sort of stuff is going through these other code paths, right?
So this drawbitmap code path, for example, if I were to just get rid
of it, right?
So we just we just fully get rid of it.
Oops, that's that's a good type out and V.
Like so so if I just got rid of it entirely, then when we ran the the
program we would end up with just the tree on our hideous, pink
background, right?
And of course, if I left in the outline rectangle stuff so we're still
seeing those.
But we have our hideous, pink background and we have our little guy
and of course, we can make our hideous pink background, not such
hideous, pink for the moment, certainly we can go in and change that.
So
I've got our.
Let's see.
Where was that guy?
There's are clear.
And that's the ground chunks.
So here we have our clear right here, so if we wanted to clear the
screen to black or to gray or something, in fact, I guess maybe I'll
pick a gray here.
Like so if you wanted to clear to a gray, we could do that.
And then we have a pretty open, you know, ability here to kind of to
kind of play with this and if I go ahead and take out the optimization
request to the compiler.
So we go from having that owed.
D2 that 02 to have them that OD cure is the slow version running and
that again is totally fine speed-wise, I think, right?
So I feel like, for the most part, right for the most part, this is
probably good for us and we can just work on this for a couple days,
get in the new features that we want.
And then switch over to optimization at a time when it's probably a
little bit better.
So unless anyone has some
Reservations about that.
I think that's what we're going to do.
So.
All right, let's start with first of all, we don't really need this
guy to be rotating anymore for the moment.
We can stop with all of the rotation.
So I'm going to go ahead and here and just have that rotation stopped
entirely.
So there we go and and now our tree is they're just kind of sitting
sitting upright.
So, what I want to do is kind of introduce what the
Of lighting here are we won't go to into detail about some things but
then we'll kind of start to try and figure out what it is that we want
to implement in terms of lighting, okay?
Here we go.
Where is the Blackboard?
There is the Blackboard.
Okay, so here we are on day, 96.
And we want to talk about lighting because Lighting in fact, I'll
quote Doug church here.
One of the primary, you might even say the primary person who made
Ultima underworld lighting.
Is the sound?
Of graphics.
And that is Doug Church.
The doctor is very smart and you should listen to him but I can
understand why taken out of context.
This quote, might seem a little strange.
What he was trying to say at the time and it is now absolutely classic
quote, in my opinion, what he was saying at the time, it was actually
John Carmack.
Had given a private demo of Quake before anyone had seen it in the
public.
And one of the big things that he had added, since the last time the
people in this sort of private demo had seen it was, he had added
The shadow Maps, right?
And the shadow Maps, really dramatically.
Change the look of a game.
Because when you look at something with no lighting, it just kind of
looks like this flat, but, you know, arrangement of colors on the
screen, it just doesn't have any sense of place or any sense of depth
to it.
And when you put in that sort of realistic shadowing or even not that
realistic shadowing at some level.
Just some degree of allowing your eye to kind of see that, that, that
sort of way in which the light plays off the space.
It really you know, changes dramatically
How present that spaces and how much that space feels alive and feels
real?
And it gives it a lot of dimensionality there because a lot of depth,
right?
And so, what he was saying with this quote was, he was referring to
the kind of alt well-known sort of similar sort of thing to this,
which is that if you play a game without sound, you'll be shocking at
how much worse.
It feels, even though you're not really consciously aware of it.
This
Sound.
Add so much to the look that, you know, you feel like a game just
doesn't look as good, right?
If there's no sound with it or if the sound isn't good and if the
sound is great, it makes the game look better in this weird way
because all of the actions are accentuated with these sound effects
and it really sort of brings it to life.
And so what he was saying with lighting is the sound of Graphics, he
was sort of likening lighting to sound in that way, which is,
Like you can do all this great modeling and you can have these great
art assets but if you don't like them, well you lose this.
This very important accentuation that really makes things come alive
and so it's true in a 2-D game.
It's not as big of a deal in the 3D as it is in a 3D game because the
artists do a lot of baking of the lighting into, you know, the the
Sprites that they do but we still would like to have Dynamic Lighting
in the game because there's a
A lot of accentuation that Dynamic lighting can do just to give some
simple examples of why we might care about Dynamic lighting.
We might, for example, want to have, you know, with, given our tree
example, you know, if we've got a bunch of trees in the world and
they're around, you know, a little campfire kind of thing that's
happening here, right?
We might want to have that campfire flicker against the trees.
That's just a really it sets that scene really nicely, that sort of
thing.
Similarly, if someone is is, you know, if some kind of wizard here,
you know, with, with a long kind of beard or something like this and
who's very angry because of some reason that like j.r.r.
Tolkien took, 5,000 pages to explain and that maybe still doesn't make
a whole lot of sense but you know you can ask some parents about it
and they'll
Explain to you all the backstory.
He casts some Fireball, right?
And so here is the fireball that's that's there and it's going
forwards and as that fireball move
By the trees for example right?
You want to kind of see that light playoff them and animated way.
First letting up here and here and then here and here, right?
You want to see that and that really accentuates the motion the thing.
And again, it makes it feel like they're all in the same space
together.
You can also have the absence of light tell a story and similar way.
If you have you know the shadow of something that's very large, come
over space, that's all that sort of stuff is examples of how in 2D
games you still do want to have some control flooding if you can
If you can, if you can't help it, right?
So what are the ways that we can get lighting into our game?
Let's talk about lighting in a sort of abstract sense and sort of then
we'll talk about how we can actually get our Sprites to have some of
that because again we don't have full fully 3D representations here
coming in.
So we don't have the complete information, we would need to do full
lighting.
Okay.
So, lighting is fundamentally.
A directional effect, right?
And what I mean by that is light is traveling in lines.
This is true in the real world for the most part, right?
When you think about light in the real world, we're talking about
photons that travel in straight lines.
I mean, modulo relativistic effects and all these other sorts of
things.
But traveling in straight lines, between two points bouncing off and
traveling in another straight line.
Eventually, you know these light these photons they all start at
I'm light source, right?
You know, I'm saying they all start at some light source and they
bounce off a bunch of surfaces in the world and they fundamentally
eventually come back to your eyeball, right?
That's your eyeball where you collect those photons and in the process
of collecting those photons, your eye constructs and image.
And what that means is, all of the effects that have to do with
lighting are very much about the direction
In which the light was coming from at any given time and what this
unfortunately kind of means when you extrapolate it out, far enough is
that doing lighting correctly is actually extremely difficult and I'll
try to give you a little bit of a picture of why.
Real lighting if you were to do it, completely correctly is
extraordinarily difficult.
So if you were to compute the lighting what actually happens with
lighting and let's take out everything from this equation, except the
Are Necessities.
Okay?
So all we're going to have is we're just going to have the sun here is
the sun, right?
This is the sun, we are going to have one surface.
That's it, right?
So the light comes down, it hits this surface, right?
And we're going to have just your I just just your eyeball.
There it is, right?
Light comes down it hits.
It it comes back in here and it hits your retina back here and
produces an image of your brain, right?
So let's suppose that that's what we've got.
So, even in just this situation where this is the only thing that's
happening, Computing, the lighting for this effect, no matter what
this surface is, is still incredibly difficult.
There are a few services that can make it easier.
But for the most part, it's incredibly difficult because the way that
light bounces off a surface is highly chaotic.
Most surfaces that you see in the real world, actually scatter light
in
Need directions when it hits.
So when the Sun hits this surface, right?
It bounces in all directions.
Typically?
Right?
So photons come in you know billions of photons come in from the Sun.
They strike this surface and they bounce off in all directions.
Some of them bounce off in the direction of your eye and those are the
ones you see, others don't others, bounce off in other directions and
there they go, right?
Now when it bounces off a surface right?
The photons.
They actually have a wavelength.
Okay, and so for those of you don't know anything about light, light
has wavelengths.
And wavelengths are essentially, you know, I am not a physicist.
So when I am leaving to say what wavelengths are, I'll say, what I
think of wavelengths are but I'm sure a physicist would correct,
whatever, I'm about to say.
But point being light, the photons that come in there is this whole
notion in physics of particle, wave Duality and all this stuff that I
don't even pretend to understand.
But basically what happens is you can think of the the light as
oscillating, you know, like a sine wave kind of thing.
It's
Lighting.
So, when it's coming down this line, it's actually oscillating and the
speed, which oscillates is actually changes, right in there is the
wave length, the distance between when it crosses the same point, it
changes depending on the light source.
So when the light is emitted, it has a certain wavelength.
And those wavelengths are the colors that we perceive, there's
infrared.
Which is colors.
We can't perceive down in the heat Spectrum, then it crosses into red,
right?
Goes through all of the colors in the Spectrum until it gets to
Violet.
And then ultraviolet, right?
Which we can't perceive.
So there's more wavelengths in both directions but we can't see them.
We might be able to feel them, or we might be able to see them once
they hit something and change back into visible light.
But for the most part we can't see anything on either of those two
sides.
Okay, but everywhere else in here, we actually see this light and the
way that we see this light and incidentally, this is why monitors if
you ever wonder why our monitors RGB, you know, what's the
With that, right?
Because honestly RGB isn't a thing in the real world, it's not a
thing, right?
We actually have continuous wave lengths of light that can represent
any color.
It's not a question of their being red light, green light and blue
light.
That's not, that's not a thing, right?
There's actually all of the colors are real and have their own unique
wavelength, right?
Well, the reason RGB is the thing that we use is because our I
actually only has receptors at those points, right?
So basically in your retina
Okay, in your retina, you have sensors for red, you have sensors for
green, and you have sensors for blue, okay.
And the way these sensors collect light is they collect it in, sort of
a, you know, an overlapped fashion, right?
Like this.
And so your green receptors.
Don't only catch one specific, wavelength of light, they respond more
strongly or more negatively.
I was are more strongly or less strongly depending on how far the
wavelength from light is that hits them is from Green.
So by looking at the combined activity of your red green and blue
sensors, what your brain is effectively doing is trying to figure out
where the light
Six were, you know, that actually hit.
So like something comes in here, right?
And it, you know, it's cyan or something, right?
And, you know, it sort of is, is or, you know, I don't know what color
it is.
I drew that line in a place that I'm not sure exactly what it is.
But it's registering on both the green and the blue, let's say, right?
And so, you know, it's there and there it's registering you'll
perceive that as a color that's that's, you know, a mix of green and
blue.
One of
Those colors that's in here, right?
And if you happen to have light that's coming in at multiple
wavelengths, right?
You've got you can have light coming in that Scott photons of all
sorts of different wavelengths.
That's you know you know maybe a light source is emitting lots of
different kinds of photons.
Some like this, you can have things like white where there's some
coming in here and some coming in here and some coming in here and
whatever and it's it's affecting all of these sensors evenly etc, etc,
right?
So RGB tends to be a very effective way to represent colors because
that is basically just us saying, all right?
Just output light at the three things you can perceive and we'll just
fool your eye into thinking it seeing something like yellow.
For example, by highly triggering the red and the green light with red
Wilt by Heart, by putting out, red, and green light that triggers,
those two sensors and not putting out any blue.
So your eye goes oh that must be some yellow light coming in but
surprise wasn't yellow light.
It was red and green light in the real world.
There may be such a thing as yellow light.
You may actually be seeing yellow.
When you see yellow, not a combination of red and green but you'll
never know because you can't see it.
Now, there are other animals that have more sensors in here.
And in their world, they can tell the difference.
So, if they were to look at a monitor, they would be like, your
monitor is awful.
That doesn't look anything like the world looks.
You guys don't know anything about technology.
That's what they'd say.
And we would look at the picture and go.
What are you talking about?
Looks exactly, right, it's just like, you'd like you went out and took
a photograph, right?
So
Don't talk to those animals, okay?
That's if there's any lesson that you take away from a day.
It's don't talk.
Two animals.
With more color receptors.
Or more color, wavelength.
Sensors.
Venu.
Okay.
Because frankly, it's not worth the hassle.
So I think that's the main takeaway, but let's compress on and
continue, we've got about how much we got.
We've got 35 minutes so I'm going to press on, try to get to the
actual lighting even though this is really the main takeaway, okay?
So back to our picture.
So we have wavelengths of light, wavelengths of light are coming in,
they're hitting the surface, and they're scattering in all directions.
Some of which come to your eye.
Now the problem and the reason that I said, it's such a fantastically
difficult problem is because this is true for any incoming Direction.
Okay?
So if there was light coming, if you had a second son, for example,
and there was light coming from there, maybe it's the Dark Crystal, if
you got a
Concerned.
There's coming here it would also scatter light towards your eye.
Okay?
So what you see when you look at a surface is, you actually see the
aggregate effect of all of the light sources scattering light towards
your eye.
And the reason that this is a problem, even if you only have one son,
is because everything else in the world is also reflecting all of
those photons.
A lot of them are bouncing right back to that.
Point that you saw and then scattering to your eye.
So in order to compute even the lighting the correct lighting at just
one point in the world, effectively requires Computing, what the
light, what the incoming light was for all of the directions emanating
from that point.
It is an incredibly, incredibly difficult problem.
It is why accurate lighting is probably the hardest thing to do in
computer Graphics.
Now if that wasn't
Bad enough, it actually gets even worse.
For reals.
The light doesn't actually just bounce off the surface.
The light actually travels into the surface then back out.
Okay.
If we were to talk about a real
Fast.
It is actually has some thickness to it and let's say it could be
something very complicated like Wax.
And what happens is when photons hit the surface anywhere, not just,
the point you're measuring, but anywhere the light goes into the
surface and the photons actually pass through.
They maybe don't hit anything, but then they do hit something inside
the surface, right?
They bounce, they bounce again, then they hit the exit point and
happen to scatter back to your eye.
Right.
This is called subsurface scattering.
So technically, if you really wanted to do light incorrectly, not only
do you have to know all of the light in all of the world that could
possibly come back to you, right?
You need to know all of this but you also need to know all of the
light that could have come at you from inside the object that you're
talking about now.
Fortunately, a lot of objects are so opaque that you just don't have
to care.
But if you really want to do it, right, and you want to support wax
and you want to support Waters and you want to support dr.
Pepper
Or a flashlight.
You got to handle all of this, right?
Now, what makes surfaces?
Look different.
It's good question, right?
Because you look around the world and all the surfaces.
They look different, they have different colors.
Okay?
They have different shininess.
We talk about, some are translucent transparent.
We've got all these sorts of things.
What makes surfaces look different right.
And the answer is what they do to the photons during this process,
okay?
So there are a couple primary aspects that you want to think about.
When you're thinking about lighting, the first one is for any incoming
Direction, okay?
And we can start to talk about these directions, very specifically.
I'll do the 2D version here, and I'll draw the 3D version in a second,
but for any incoming Direction.
And any outgoing direction, right?
And so maybe I'll draw that a little bit differently.
Let me draw them this way, so that they're both kind of on the same
angle system due to that way, right?
So, here is one angle in here.
Is another call that fee, will call that Theta.
So, for any two angles and one, I have we'll call this the angle of
incidence.
So this is the way the light is coming into the surface, right?
So here's the light source.
And then the angle that were viewing, right?
So here is our viewing angle.
The thing that we're actually trying to measure along so there's RI
for any two angles.
Every given surface in the world will have a different amount of light
that they tend to reflect back.
Right?
And
So if light is coming in at this angle Theta, right?
If it comes in at Theta, right?
We know that it goes out at fee for some percentage, okay?
Some percentage of the photons will go out and for every surface in
the world that percentage will be different.
And that is what controls the shape of this lighting.
If you imagine, now, we need to Define it for every one of these and
every one of these combined.
So it's effectively a function of both Theta and fee, right?
It's a 2 dimensional function, saying for every angle that I've you
and for all of those angles every angle of incidence, there's a
different percentage of light that I'm going to reflect in that
direction, okay?
And obviously, this percentage should all some up to the total amount
of light.
So it's they should also add up
Hundred percent.
So all of the light that comes in, you know, should go out.
Well, I shouldn't say that should sum up to that or less because it's
going to absorb some amount of light as well, right?
So, it's not gossip to understand, it's going to be less than that.
It can't emit more light than it takes in unless it's photo active.
In some way, which I suppose you could also simulate, right?
So this is what controls the look of that surface.
And if we extend it to the full range so that you could actually talk
about in here as well, then you're talking about
Doing what it looks like interior but you need a few more things, such
as How Stuff, scatters internally.
So you need a few more parameters to talk about how light bounces
around in here as well.
But this measured along say r g and B is what defines all the
services?
Although if you really again wanted to be absolutely precise about it.
You would actually have to say, well also the wavelength because
technically different surfaces can handle different.
Wavelengths differently.
They don't have to obey our break down into RGB that we use an
approximation, right?
So you know, people will often use things like spectral calculus and
stuff like this if they're really trying to do accurate rendering to
handle things where different wavelengths of light behave differently
when they hit, right?
So this is an incredible, incredibly difficult problem.
And again I just want to kind of impress upon you how difficult
lighting is if you wanted to do it correctly and to set the stage for
saying we will not
Not attempt anything like this because first of all you don't usually
do anything like this.
In real-time you often are going to use some approximation, but we
will be using much, much more simplified models of how the lighting
Works in order to be able to achieve results in real time.
Okay.
so,
What sorts of surfaces do we tend to actually want, right?
Because that was all of them.
Let's talk about ones that we want.
So typically what we want to have in our the ability to simulate most
of the time, right?
If we're just talking about simple artistic concerns here,
What we typically want to have is diffuse surfaces you know, I guess I
would say glossy surfaces and reflecting it surfaces you know and
these are just my terms here.
I'm not trying to introduce any standard nomenclature be saying.
These are some ways you might think about them.
And what those are, is this, a diffuse surface is something like
chalk, right?
It's something that really doesn't have a bright highlight on it,
okay?
When light comes in it, scatters in all directions evenly.
It's not biased.
So no matter where the reflection comes in, it's going to scatter in
all directions evenly, it just distributes it diffusely, right?
Glossy surfaces.
Well, let me do reflective surfaces first.
So, highly reflective, I'll call these highly reflective surfaces are
like mirrors, right?
These are like mirror surfaces and what they do is when the light
comes in, they reflect it directly back out again, it doesn't scatter.
Nothing.
Goes in this direction.
Nothing goes that way.
Nothing goes It goes right out the opposite direction, right?
And that produces a mirror.
If you think about why that is, it's actually kind of obvious, all of
the time that you look at it.
It just basically is as if there wasn't your, I sitting there looking
back at
Other direction, right?
It's very very straightforward how that how that happens, right?
So that's, you know, ends up being sort of a mirror surface and the
glossy surface is somewhere in between it's one where light comes in
and most of it, right?
A high amount of, it goes out this way, but a little bit, goes out in
the other directions, right?
And typically, so there's sort of a lobe here.
You might say, right?
So the reflectance, you know, is kind of less over here but then it
kind of gets
bigger in this direction and kind of goes like that, right?
So these are the kinds of surface that is that we tend to care about
because they are the ones that we could use artistically to get a
reasonable set of, you know, approximated effects in our games that
allow the services to look a little more realistic.
Okay.
so,
Given this, what we typically end up with, right?
Is we end up with
Approximations for those things.
That's the worst.
You know?
I'm going to write that again.
That was the worst.
There we go.
There are some awful handwriting.
So what we tend to do is we try to come up with approximations that
will let us do reasonable jobs of these things, okay?
And originally back in the old days when lighting was really, really
bad because computers were too slow to do anything.
Good, typically what you had is you have literally computation
companies that look almost exactly like the diagrams that I was
drawing only, they didn't even really have any
Of any, of much of this stuff.
They were like, basically,
The, you know, I have a point that is sending light at my Surface,
right?
And then I have a bounced out to the thing and all I'm going to do is
have some fall off that determines, you know, how sharp the low bits
here.
That's that's all I'm going to do.
So light always comes in from just one place, right?
The source of light is one point and what that ends up looking like,
is it looks like somebody shining a flashlight.
Basically on surfaces, right?
Right, and yes you can by controlling, you know, by looking at this
angle, the difference between the incoming and the outgoing, right?
I can make the services look more or less shiny by sort of controlling
whether or not the light that gets bounced bounced back falls off
sharply As you move away from that primary reflection angle, right.
So if the primary reflection is here and you know we're viewing it up
here.
If it's getting darker due to that then you know the surface will kind
of has a nice shininess as I move here, it gets brighter.
And so on and you can think about this surface, right?
Like, let's say that I was looking at a sphere, right?
We're evaluating this whole thing at every point on the sphere.
So basically, you know, if you want sort of a nice bright highlight
there and then, you know, it's dark everywhere.
Else we can do that sort of thing, that's not that big of deal, right?
But it always looks like just one light shining on a thing and it's
usually very harsh, right?
Usually has a harsh, a fairly harsh Shadow because there's no light
coming from anywhere else.
It's black on the back here unless you add in some fake light,
Right.
And all that sort of stuff, right?
So old approximations tends to be that way and they were pretty harsh.
Now we could of course live with stuff like that and what we're doing
because we already have art that's drawn that imagines that there's
all of this light coming in, right?
And so if we were to just overlay some lighting like this on top of
it, that would probably be, okay?
Right, it would basically just add in highlighting here and we let the
fact that the artist drew it, with some ambient lighting, take care of
the rest of it, right?
So you know, this would probably work for us, right?
Because we're not in 3D and we're not having to recreate the entire
scene with all of its lighting ourselves.
We do have some leeway of picking old-school, fairly broken and lousy
approximations to lighting because what we need the lighting to do is
very limited.
We don't need it to recreate the entire look of the lighting.
The artists already did a lot of that, right?
But we may be able to do something better and we'll play around with
it because modern approximations will often do things that involve
say, light probing, right?
So light probes are ways of trying to get around this problem of only
having the compute computational power to deal with single points that
say, where the light is coming from.
Because remember, what I was saying back here, when I first introduced
this, the light comes from everywhere, right?
The light comes in from everywhere.
And so when you compute things, as if there's just one or two point,
light sources, it's never going to look like the real world because
you're never in a situation, where light is only coming from two light
sources.
Because even in a room, that only has one physical light, and even if
that light was almost a single point, like was a really tiny Point
light, the light bounces all over.
And once it's bouncing, it's coming in from everywhere.
So, every surface is still getting light from
Even if there's only one actual thing that we would call light.
And so what we've done nowadays in games to try and get around that in
a lot of cases is we try to come up with some way of allowing
approximations to all of that incoming light.
Now, that would be incredibly difficult for us to do if we were trying
to solve a directly, you end up with doing things like, you know that
Racers do where you kind of try to do this stochastic sampling and
reconstruct the light field.
There actually are some
The things you can go look at, there's a thing called Brigade.
It's a real-time Ray tracing renderer that they've gotten fairly far
on.
It's not the kind of thing.
You could really use in a real game yet but, you know, it's getting
better.
So there are times when people just full-on say, all right, you know,
let's try to simulate the whole thing and maybe someday when computing
power gets gets, you know that advanced you'll actually use that in a
game but not today we're still a ways off.
If it ever does come to pass, it's going to still be a few years away.
but what we can do is use things called light probes and what light
probes are or, you know, you could you could even I'd say this more
more sort of generally say, indirect light sampling, you know,
And basically, what we're doing here, what we're talking about is can
we build some systems which compute effectively like, look up Stables
or things that we can go quickly access that would give us a fast way
to compute all of the contributions of the light that is coming into a
surface, right?
And so oftentimes what you'll see people do is for example, let's
suppose that I want to light
You know, again, I've got that sphere, right?
And I want to light this fear.
So I want to compute the lighting at all of these pixels on the sphere
and so on and so forth, right?
Well what people will often do for example is they might render a cube
map which is essentially as if you were to start at the center of the
sphere and render out in all, you know, in six directions, right?
Six.
Orthogonal directions from the sphere render out images that you can
imagine if you were, you know.
Inside a cube like so.
If you're here, what you'll do is, you'll render out and actually
render what the world looks like on.
All of the faces of the cube right.
Does that make sense?
So essentially you made a box that
Is what the sphere kind of sees when it looks out from its current
direction.
Right?
Well, what that effectively is is, it's like a condensed, lookup table
of all of the light, right?
It's like a condensed way of saying, what all the light looked like
coming into the sphere and you're like, well, that's great Casey but
who cares?
Because now I still don't know how to compute any of this stuff
because I was still have to go look at all of the pixels on these Cube
Maps.
Well yes and no.
What you then do is you might
Take this and you might start downsampling it.
So let's say you rendered these at 256 by 256 by 256.
Right?
Well it's really just doing it by 2 6 + 6 x, right?
So it's 256 by 256 by 61 for each face, right?
Suppose, I then blur these down to 128 by 128 by six, right?
And all the way down to 1 by 1 by 6.
Now, I would have a bunch of Cubes that are blurrier.
And blurrier versions of the light that's coming from around the room.
What good does that do me?
Well, it means I can now simulate the effect of all the incoming
light, right?
Like in this diagram by saying?
Well okay, if I know that my Surface is like that chalky surface and
all the light bounces evenly, then I'll just look at that most blurry
Cube because that's what it's going to look like, whatever.
The average light that comes in, that's a pretty reasonable
approximation, right?
If instead,
Said, I've got the other kind of service I should be using my other
diagram for this.
So if I've got that, I can just look at the blurry versions of the
cube and that tells me roughly what the aggregate light that comes in.
Looks like, if instead I've got points that have sort of a, you know,
a more pronounced reflection lobe there.
What I can do is sample this direction, out of one of the Heidi higher
detail, cubes and add it to a weighted version of the lower detail
Cube sample.
A nice averaged glossiness between the two, right?
So you get some reflection, you get some incoming ambient, right?
And furthermore, if I'm just doing highly reflective, I just sample
the the highest resolution Cube always and don't add in any of it,
right?
So there's ways that you can start to approximate these things, right?
And that's in 3D
So what do we do in 2D, right?
What are we going to do?
So we have two real problems in 2D, right.
Problem one, we don't know.
What the surfaces are.
In 3D, you always know what your surfaces are because they're
polygonal used.
So, you know what they shaped like.
You know what direction?
They're facing, you know.
The thing that you need to know, okay, but we have no idea in 2D
rendering what our services even our if we look at this tree all we've
got is colors, right?
And the reason that you and I see this as an actual 3D shape that we
recognize as a cartoony, little cute version of a tree is because our
brain is interpreting those colors and the value change, sort of the
brightness change of the greens,
To imply that there is sort of a tree shape there, right?
So we could go in as humans and kind of roughly know where each of
these cert what, you know, kind of made up these services.
But that's incredibly difficult for a computer to figure out, because
it doesn't even know this is supposed to be a tree.
Those are like machine.
Learning problems are incredibly difficult.
And so, the first question is, what can we do to even know what
direction or facing any of these services are?
Because remember, all of this stuff was based on reflection, right?
It was based on knowing the direction, the surface was pointing if the
surface is pointing that way it's going to reflect things a lot
different than if it's pointing this way.
Just like you throw a ball against a wall, it matters which way the
walls facing depending on, you know, how the ball is going to bounce,
right?
And so all of those reflectance functions are in terms of the
direction service.
We don't know what direction these services are pointing.
We have no idea, right?
So that's our first problem, and one solution to this is to have
normal maps for your Sprites, right?
And what a normal map is is that saying okay I've got a color map for
this, right?
This is what the colors are.
And then what I do is I augment that with a bitmap that basically has
at each location instead of storing RGB.
What it stores is XYZ of a vector that points in the direction that
the surface is pointing at that time, right?
So it's like a bunch of little tiny vectors that just say for every
pixel what direction that pixel surface was pointing.
Now, typically you don't actually need to store the x y z because it's
a normal.
So it has a length of 1.
So really only need to store the X and the y, or the Y and the Z, or
whatever, depending on what coordinate system, you want to use your
new star, two of these.
You can reconstruct the other one, but that's a totally separate
topic, right?
Point being a store of vectors in here.
So that works quite well for solving this problem.
The problem with that, where do you get them?
The artist painted the bitmap, they can't paint a normal map.
You can ask them to
Like a bump map and generate a normal map from it but then it takes
your artists a lot more time, blah, blah, blah.
There are programs that try to generate normal maps for you, who knows
if they'll work particularly well?
I could certainly try.
Passing ours through there.
We don't know, right?
So this is kind of a problem for us, but it's an art asset problem.
Not a computational problem because we can implement this and we
should so we'll go ahead and Implement normal maps, and then hope that
we'll have a way to produce some relatively useful, normal Master, our
stuff.
If we don't
Then what, you know, what can we do?
At least we tried, right?
So we'll Implement that, as a solution for the 2D problem of not
knowing where the surfaces are.
And then if we can't get our assets to have reasonable Maps, maybe
we'll do something that fix them in a really bad way and just leave it
that way, I don't know, but point being will have the computational
stuff in there to handle them.
So that's problem one.
We also have problem, too.
Problem two is we don't know what the light field is.
In 3D.
We have the luxury of being able to do this because the whole idea
behind 3D games is that they're rendered in 3D, which means you can
set the Viewpoint anywhere you want and render in any direction you
want.
So if you want to know what the light field is at any particular
location or family of locations, you can usually come up with a way of
placing the camera and rendering so that you can see what it looks
like there and then you could use that for sampling, but we can't do
that.
So we have no way of placing a camera in this scene and rendering
things in.
Instructions to see what the lighting is.
So we needed to come up with something that will allow us to produce a
light field we can sample.
Now one way we can do this is just by using Point lights, right?
This was the old scheme that I was talking about before where we just
full-on just saved.
There's light coming from point somewhere and then that's just used in
computations, right?
We can do that.
Okay.
And you know if worst comes to worst, this is all we will do.
Will just put in point lights and we'll let the point light shine onto
the surfaces, right?
But we may be able to do something better by like doing some kind of
light rendering, right?
So what you could imagine us doing is you could imagine us making a
thing that sits over the screen, a bitmap that we're going to render
before we render a pre-render pass, right?
And maybe that pretty render pass, you know, it's not 1920 by 1080,
maybe it's 192, you know, maybe it's maybe it's subsampled by 10x.
So instead of 1920 by 1080 right no it's not going to be that.
It'll be like 192 you know, by 108 or something or maybe the closest
power of 22 that.
So maybe it'll be 128, you know, 256 by 128 or something like that.
So we've got basically a map not a mat.
That's a, that's a real thing.
So a a, a sort of a
separate frame buffer, if you will a light buffer that sits on top,
when we start and we render our lights, we figure out a way to render
lights in here in some kind of useful way, right?
So, for example, what we could do is we start by rendering into this
thing, you know, anywhere that we want lights, we render a little
Splats, right?
So like here are the actual lights that we have in the world or
something, right?
And then maybe we like defuse those Splats programmatically.
So like we, you know, let those blur out, we like do some kind of
blurring on them, right?
And then we take wherever there are entities and we subtract light
from there to darken it or something, right?
I'm totally making this up, but you see where I'm going with this,
right?
Some kind of buffer that we can draw stuff into that, we can then use
when we are drawing something to sample.
As if we were looking out in the
Various directions.
So that when we grab a normal and we want to know what the light is,
we can go.
Okay.
Yeah, there's some light coming from over there, and we're going to
put it in to our lighting equation, right?
So like I said, don't know and we could do this, you know.
And so basically what this is doing is it's making little light probes
like every baby, every like eight by eight of this is kind of
considered a little light probe you know.
So when you're sampling, your just sampling, the 8x8 near you, you
know, whatever you see where
I'm going with this, right?
And again, light is a directional problem.
So it's pretty tricky because technically, like, if we have a
reflection mirror over here and a light source, all the way over here,
you should be able to see this in that.
And how do we do that?
Kind of a search, right?
It's pretty tricky.
So again don't really know what we're going to do here.
I haven't thought about it at all and I've never tried to do anything
similar to this.
It's I normally work on 3D stuff.
I don't do a lot of 2D work but point being we'll try, we'll give it
an honest go of trying to sit down and think through what are some
ways we could accelerate the lighting lookups?
What are some things we could do, maybe that would lead to some more
interesting lighting.
That had more dynamism and made the scene feel more cohesive, right?
So I think that's I'll probably wrap that up.
I think we've covered most of the lighting stuff.
We haven't talked specifically about how to compute letting that's
okay.
Just want to give you the overview today.
And so, probably what we'll do now is, you know, maybe tomorrow.
Let's, let's implement this because it's actually pretty
straightforward.
So, we'll talk about the light, the actual equation for lighting for
one bounce and we'll do our normal maps and then we'll move on to
seeing what we can do here.
Because, like I said, don't know what will be able to do.
We'll get a shot.
All right, so with that, I will go ahead and and push us over to the
Q.
And the a, if you have any questions about lighting, please put Q: in
front of them and we will tackle them or try to anyway.
Hmm.
Questions, who has questions?
Questions.
Questions questions.
I guess we don't have any questions.
Everyone was like, yep, lighting, awesome.
I totally understand all of it.
Now
So is this why Animation Studios like Pixar have super computers for
the rendering?
Yeah, so basically like you know the weird thing about lighting is
we've actually understood for a fairly long time.
I guess you might say how to do pretty good computations to compute
what the lighting is.
It's just they're so expensive to do because they're four dimensional
or worse problems.
Sampling problems that we just don't have the Computing resources to
solve them and so, yeah, if you want to produce high-quality images,
one solution you've always had is you can get significantly better by,
you know, throwing more more electricity at it and so, yeah, you know,
they can they can produce much more higher quality lighting.
The other reason that they have supercomputers is because they spam a
lot of geometry at stuff like forfor rendering and stuff.
They'll often do that and so that eats up a bunch too.
It's usually lighting lettings.
Usually what does it?
It's very hard to actually have geometry cause you to need a
supercomputer but lighting is is rough.
What about Shadows?
So the interesting thing about Shadows is Shadows, isn't really.
A thing Shadows is just when you don't get light.
And so really these techniques handle Shadows, right as well when you
think about it.
But because they are so approximated.
Sometimes if you have situations like where you want sharp Shadows
because this would, this will actually give you, you know, when
you're, when you're doing something that's, it'll give you did, you
know, sort of very
Darkening.
But if you want sharp Shadows like the sun on a Lamppost and you get
that long thing, right?
Then typically what people will do for that is what's called Shadow
mapping, right?
And what that is, is they will actually do the computation for a light
directly for its immediate contribution.
So, just its direct lighting, right, as opposed.
So none of the bounce lighting.
That's all done.
You know, using the light probe kind of thing.
But what they'll do is they'll take the direct lighting and they'll
actually render A View From the Source light, right?
The render of you directly from the source light and they'll use that
view to let them know what the source light saw.
And what it didn't and that will produce the shadow because when they
light things, they look up into the light and say, did the light see
me?
No, it didn't.
Okay.
I'm in Shadow so that shadow maps and I don't think we'll need to do
those because really
We don't have, we don't really need to.
I don't think there's anything in our game, where we're going to,
really want to get super crisp shadows.
And if we did, we could just probably take them of Sprites.
So I feel like what we're going to want to what we need Dynamic like
to do for us is not really Shadows.
That doesn't really Define the look of a 2-D game in this style.
Very much.
What we want is more that environment, lighting play that sort of if
there's green poison someone,
I want to see some green light bounce off of stuff and I want to see
things that, you know, are shadowed from the Greenlight have like a
not have it on there, but that's the extent that we want shadowing.
And so, I feel like a light propagation scheme is going to be more
what we want and Shadow Maps, would probably just be a waste of
compute for us.
I think, but it's always hard to say.
I was looking for a build design doc to follow.
If you have one, I'm not sure what a build design doc is
If you let me know what a build design, doc is, I can tell you why we
don't have one because I'm almost certain that we don't, but I don't
actually know what it is.
Do we also plan on having a day-night cycle and dynamic Shadows where
they stretch and fade depending on the position of the sun?
No, well, okay, so
Although I can appreciate why it might be nice to look at that from a
technical standpoint.
Like I say two things, I appreciate them, a special type of
standpoint.
Unfortunately, I don't like daytime for this game.
So this game takes place entirely at night, so we will not have a
day-night cycle in the game because I it's supposed to be kind of
Adventure in a forest at night, so it never turns to be day.
But that said this, the way that we're doing Shadows by having them in
a separate pass would allow you to do that.
Actually pretty easily.
So I think our Tech would just support you just fine for that and so
maybe if someone wants to make their own version, eventually that does
a day-night cycle, hopefully they wouldn't have too much to do.
Question, light Feathering example in a window or tree.
Light Feathering.
Are you are you referring to translucency can if you could be more
specific about what you're asking, I'm not totally sure.
Sort of on topic, would you consider doing a true 3D lighting or Ray
tracing discussion lesson at sometime?
I mean, I wouldn't say necessarily know, but it's, you know, that
would have to be way after handmade hero because we it's just not
something that applies to this project, you know?
How do you account for infinite Reflections?
If there is a mirror that reflects light into a mirror that reflects
light back at the first mirror?
Well, so,
There's two sides to that question.
The first question is, how would you handle that if you wanted to do
it in a synthetic environment?
And the answer there I suppose is it depends.
You're going to have to do some kind of hack that you know, eventually
terminates.
The thing after a certain number of bounces or something like this.
But if the question is, what do you do about it in the real world?
The answer is the real world has no such thing, every time a photon
bounces off a surface.
It has some per percentage chance of being absorbed or scattered in a
different direction by that surface.
And So eventually, there is no such thing as a mirror that can bounce
light and back.
Bounce light back and forth.
Infinitely eventually the light will get absorbed and that is why if
you look at mirrors that face each other like that the reflections
actually get darker eventually because it just, it can't keep sending
the light back and forth, ad infinitum, because we've, I don't think
there's such a thing as a pure, like, a totally pure reflector, I
could be wrong about that.
But I'm pretty much positive.
No one's ever invented any such thing.
Also, obviously, you have dust in the air, so you have to also be in a
vacuum because light, when it hits the air, there's things called
volumetric scattering, which isn't really talked about which is, is
basically just the case where.
So if you remember, I drew this thing where I sing, well technically,
you have to worry about what's happening inside the surface, like I
used wax as the example and really, the whole world works that way
unless you're out in space.
So if you're in a
Our atmosphere, then actually anywhere in here, the light could also
decide to take a detour because it could hit some particle in the air
and bounce.
And that's why you have things like, you know, real a scattering and
missed.
And you know, think the fact that things that are further away up here
to be more washed out, that's all because there's actually scattering
going on in the air as well.
And so with your to mirror example, you'd be hitting that as well.
Every time the light Transit between
between the two mirrors, you would end up losing some of it to
scattering that was happening.
Just bought due to air molecules.
And so in the real world, there's no such thing.
As light to bounce back and forth infinitely as far as I know,
Could you repeat that buddy mansur?
I don't know what you want me to repeat.
I have no coin.
Bray heated, debates of why we need to go through the trouble?
You're going through just use Unity Kappa, many newcomers.
So, yeah, I mean, I've said it a million times but obviously for
newcomers, they haven't ever heard it.
So this is not a programming stream, you know, this is this is not a
game development for dummies.
I won't even write that on our Blackboard.
But, you know, this, this is not.
How do I get a game up and running as quick as possible because
there's tons of that, right?
If all you want to know how to do,
It's brewed up unity and whatever Unity can do.
That's your game, right?
If that's what you want to do, you really don't need to stream
obviously because, you know, you can go just watch some tutorials in
fact, I think Unity site and I probably has pretty good tutorials on
it.
I never really watched them but I suspect that they've got good
training materials.
I mean, why wouldn't they?
That's the whole point they want people to use the engine same thing
with unreal or any of these other things, right?
Game maker.
So if all you want to do is just get a game up and running and you
don't really care about pushing any
boundaries or you don't really care about being able to zero in on
quality and that sort of stuff then.
Yeah, but this dream is different.
This stream is about learning how those things work, right?
It's about being able to extend your ability past what the engine is
capable of doing out of the box, right?
And there's two ways that this can affect you one, it can allow you to
do things that other people can't do.
Because once you know how the lighting works, you are much more
empowered to be able to.
Place it modify, it hack it.
Do whatever you need to do to get the effects that you want, right?
And that goes not just for letting but everything that we talked about
on the stream but also it means you are you're on the road if you want
to be to sort of actually be able to work on that higher level
yourself, right?
You could start making your own engine so you could start making your
own Unity plugins, you can start essentially giving yourself much much
more power, right?
Right.
And, you know, it's kind of like saying, why would I want to to learn
how to, you know, build a car when I can buy?
You know, I can go buy a Honda Civic, right?
And it's like, well yeah, I mean, if all you want to do is just drive
a car around, you should just go buy a Honda Civic.
But if you're someone who's interested in the future of cars, and
about building the next car, that does awesome performance stuff that
no one else does, or you wanted to invent the electric car because you
Your Tesla, you were Elon Musk or something, right?
That's what we're talking about in this dream.
So, this stream is supposed to be the place that you come, where you
can start getting into at a sort of starting at the ground level.
Getting into that real.
Game development where you actually learn, how to do everything.
Not just hey.
Well, if there's a button for it in unity, then I guess I can do it.
But if there isn't, I can't
It's 2D worth going for when it becomes more complex than 3D.
Well so you know I can appreciate why sometimes on the stream.
It may look like 2D is more complicated than 3D because anytime I'm
going to mention 3D is that circumstance, right?
And so every time I'm going to mention 3D, it's going to be because
I'm saying well in 2D we don't have access to this.
So this is why we're, you know, why it's a little harder for us here,
right?
What you don't see is the 8 billion things that are harder, if you're
implementing stuff in 3D because we don't have to do them right.
So 3D carries with it, just huge amounts of hard stuff that you're
just not seeing because I'm not having to teach you how to do it,
because we're in 2D and it's really good idea to start with 2D first
because that is the case.
And usually, you know, I mean, I'll give you a very simple example,
right?
Let's suppose we wanted to do this, okay?
All of this stuff that I'm talking about here.
You actually have to implement this stuff in 3D, it's incredibly
complicated.
You need to come up with surface reflectance functions, you need to
come up with approximation so service professionals have to Source
them from somewhere.
How are you going to do that, right?
You have to handle transparency in orders that you can't predict, you
have to sort the stuff in your scene, into two groups and then sort
this.
The, the transparent groups that, you know, that you can handle them
in the correct order, right?
You then have to worry about when you're doing
Part of this rendering here, right?
This this Cube map rendering how often?
And where are the cube apps going to be placed and what are the
numerical consequences of where the cube map was relative to where the
object was because they're not going to be exactly, right?
So then you have to interpolate from multiple probes in the world like
to try and try to triangulate your position and then wait a minute,
something's in the world.
If they're translucent they should allow light to pass through but
they'd have to call her that light and blah blah blah, right?
So there's like it's incredibly complicated.
If you actually want to do it in 3D as
As well.
So I don't mean to give the impression that 3D is easier anything like
this.
And also, you know, you can see this in a lot of systems like even in
when you use a licensed engine, they're only now getting to the point
where you don't have to do a ton of pre-computation like unreal for, I
think, finally has lighting down to a better sort of solution where
you can kind of do it a little more real time and actually looks good
and everything right?
And so it's been a very, very long hard Road for 3D Graphics to get to
that point as well.
And if you were to see the stuff that we would be doing, If This Were
3D handmade hero to do lighting, you would be very, very unhappy.
I promise you that because there's a ton of stuff involved there.
Not to mention, we'd have to be an HDR, which is a whole another
issue.
Is your lighting Cube idea.
The same thing as cube Maps.
So I was, I'm sorry, if I didn't say, I thought I said Cube Maps here,
I was describing Cube Maps.
That's what I was describing here when I was saying, this is how
sometimes people do it in 3D, they call them light probes and they're
typically Cube Maps or something similar rendered at various locations
throughout the world that they then interpolate between.
And you know, that's just one example of one scheme.
There are many ski
Things that one might employ to do sort of the indirect lighting part
of the indirect lighting equation.
Because really, that's what this is all about, right?
There's the direct term and the indirect term.
Right and this one's the easy one.
The direct part of the lighting is just the part where the light
bounced off the surface directly into your eye, right?
That's really simple.
So, you know, the and I when I say light, I don't mean the generic
light.
I mean, like the light source, like the sun, you know, the direct path
that the sun took off that surface directly to your eye.
The indirect part which is all the other stuff coming from everywhere
else where the sun bounced off something and hit it or whatever,
right?
That's the hard part because it's coming from every direction.
This is One Direction.
Like the band I'm sure there are fantastic, rock group or whatever it
is that they do and this is many directions and many directions as
much more difficult.
They don't sell hardly as many albums.
How to feather light through a window or tree?
So I guess I so you're trying to clarify the question for that doesn't
really clarified unfortunately but
I'll answer the question about trip as if it's about translucence,
hoping this will help you because I'm not sure what you're asking.
But here's translucence.
So, let's suppose I take the classic example of translucence.
And and we'll say, inside, Japan and outside Japan.
So the classic example, in Japan would be a Shoji screen, right?
You ever seen these things?
They're like, they're kind of cool.
They got like a lattice of wood, right?
And then inside the lattice of would there's like this, this sort of
paper, this like, you know, sort of paper and they're very
characteristic because what happens is they are just kind of, they
just kind of light up when there's light on the other side, like the
sun on the side, they just kind of our nice, a nice pleasant gray.
And if
One was standing here really close to them.
You would see their Shadow projected onto it, right, but you'll never
see them.
So it's not transparent, right?
Because not a transparent surface.
It is a translucent surface.
And if you're anywhere, besides Japan, then that's where the tree
comes in.
So, if you're to look through a leaf, right?
One of the leaves of a tree at the sun, right?
You kind of see this brightness there and if there was another leaf
that was obscuring it.
You'd see the Shadow on there, right?
So you kind of see the presence of light
On the other side but you don't see the actual objects at.
All right?
And that's translucence, I assume that's what you're talking about.
I'm not sure.
The reason is because you said feather, light through a window.
But a window is transparent, really.
All a window does is have an index of refraction which bends light,
but it doesn't tend to really absorb it or re scatter it in that way,
but so I'm going to just answer the question for translucence.
And so the answer here is translucence is really
Is really actually pretty straightforward.
It's another aspect of the indirect light transport.
So, remember how I said, okay, I'm viewing the surface right?
And here's the light.
Okay.
Right.
So, if I wanted to start and you know, I've got my indirect light
coming in from here, right?
Bouncing off.
If I want to start handling translucent Services, they are typically
thin, what you end up doing, is you just have an infinitely thin your
polygon or whatever it is, right?
And you have the light that comes from the back.
So if the sun's back here and there's indirect light coming from all
of these angles, what you start doing is you actually look at the
light that comes in here and you scan
That light through the other side, right?
So, basically, all translucence is, is indirect lighting equations
that are operating off the back of an object?
Instead of just the front, right?
Hopefully, that helps
Why don't we just have the lighting feigned on the Sprites?
The reason is because we don't know ahead of time where the light is
coming from.
So if we want the light to be able to circle around the tree and the
tree to light up differently, depending on where it is, there's no way
we can bake that into the Sprite, we need to be able to compute it
dynamically.
So the lighting that we can bake into the Sprite is the kind that you
see here where, you know, which is what we'll do, which is like sort
of a general lighting and self shadowing of the light of the, of the
Free on itself, but in terms of light, that moves around the object in
order to portray that we have to be able to compute it dynamically.
How about the second frame buffer?
You mentioned with light sources, having precomputed distance fall-off
plus Graphics objects.
Having another Channel similar to Alpha.
That indicates reflectivity that would be fast and maybe good enough
for a 2-D game.
Yeah.
And so, that's, that's sort of what I was getting at.
When I was saying, you know, we be blurring it out.
There was like, you know, that's the distance fall-off.
So the problem and this is again, this is why lighting is so hard.
This is why lighting is even more difficult than say fluid dynamics.
Or other volumetric things.
It's because lighting at least in 2D, lighting doesn't care how far
the light travels really.
So, the problem is that again, and this is something I didn't mention
because this is not supposed to be a complete course on lighting.
So, you know, I gave you the very, very simple overview of everything.
It gets a lot more complex if you go all the way down the rabbit hole.
But basically like what
One thing you might say is illumination.
Is constant.
Along a line.
And this is the big thing about lighting.
Basically, when light starts traveling in a line, it just goes in that
line forever.
And if it doesn't hit anything, it will be just as bright when it hits
the end as it was, when it started, right?
And so really, the only thing that's making light get dimmer ever is
when it hits something.
Now, unfortunately, for us are just isn't that thick.
So when you have something like in in our game, where we have a light
source over here,
And something all the way over here.
Let's say that was highly reflective like a mirror ball, right?
Well, this light should be super bright in this mirror ball and it's
all the way on the other side.
There's no fall-off like lights.
Don't have a fall off, that's really, not a thing.
The fall off of light at the scale that we're talking about is
literally non-existent.
It does not happen unless there's some real thick fog in here or
something, right?
And so, fall off really isn't quite right now.
What we may do again, like I said, because we don't have the luxury of
it is
They just end up using a false because we have to write and that might
be what we do.
Because again, you know, with games, you have to compute in real time.
You just don't have the ability to just say, well, we're going to just
simulate everything accurately.
That's not an option.
So we'll see what our approximate approximation ends up being, but
it's always worth noting that things like fall off, don't even really
happen with lights.
And so that's a bit rough, but what we could do is
Maybe like, you know again maybe we use Point lighting to get that and
then our diffuse lighting, well maybe we don't care because you
wouldn't see the diffuse lighting travel that far, right?
And so the fall off can help can happen there or something, right?
Due to the complexity of lighting, our system resources a major factor
consideration in shading engines sure.
I mean, you know, if you go look at when you, you know, can tweak a
game settings, oftentimes like Shadow detail and things like this, are
things that that get set in the game settings.
So, you know, it's definitely the case that the beefier the GPU and a
machine, the more lighting you could do on it, right?
If that's
If that's what you're asking.
I'm not totally sure.
I know what you're asking though.
if you use a 2d lighting buffer will you need to generate a g buffer
or Z buffer as well first
Well, probably not a z-buffer but we're going to need something to
control the propagation here.
So we'll G buffer is probably sort of something.
Like what we might use in the sense that we want to be able to knock
out, put to prevent light from traveling in the direction where there
are solid objects, we want to, you know, reduce the amount of light.
So we'll see how we do that.
I'm not sure how we'll do it.
What about bleeding, affects?
I do not know what that means.
Is this going to work with software rendering?
Or will it be to computationally expensive?
Well, we'll implement it in software rendering and if it turns out
that we can't get it to run fast enough, we'll just turn it off in the
software renderer.
But yeah, if so if it's too slow and we can optimize it enough then
we'll only run it on the GPU path.
But you know, will at least make it work correctly, in the software,
the software path so that we can see how to do it.
And then if we have to
I am GPU horsepower to actually render it real time for the gameplay
that's fine.
You mentioned Computing values for a single Source, receiving light
from multiple sources.
How would we in essence do this computation?
I'm assuming this is based off neighboring, pixel values.
I'm having a hard time formulating and approach.
So, again, the approach is kind of the same.
As I was talking about up here, what I'm thinking is, basically, you
know, we compute something
Which we then subsample down.
So we have our 256 by 128, you know, and we sample that down to a 128
by 64 and a 64 by 32.
And 32 by 16 is 16 by 8 and an 8 by 4 and a 4 by 2 and a 2 by 1 and a
1 by 1, right.
And then when we want to get blurrier and blurrier versions of the
light that's coming from an area, we would just sample those, right?
So yeah.
So I don't know what we're going to do.
Exactly.
We will play around with it and again, like I said, one of the things
I like to do on the stream is I like to tackle some problems on the
string that I've never talked to before, because one of the things I
like showing the stream is how to tackle problems.
And if all I ever do is show you stuff that I already know how to do.
Well, that doesn't really show you how to tackle new problems, right?
So
So, we'll play around with it, we'll see where we get.
Wouldn't it in most cases be smarter to use an existing graphic render
engine and just focus on coding the game itself, gameplay.
Well, you know,
Asking question in the abstract like that presupposes that you already
had a specific goal in mind and that goal was to make some gameplay,
right?
And so if your entire goal is that you wanted to make some gameplay
then yes it would probably be a much smarter idea not to spend your
time coding graphics.
However, I don't think it is a good idea to assume that what makes a
game or what makes a game developer.
Is just the fact that someone sat down and was only thinking about
gameplay, right?
Game development is an entire discipline.
It is not about you had some specific idea for gameplay.
And the only thing that you wanted to do was Implement some gameplay,
right?
That's sort of like saying, why would you paint a picture of a flower
when you could take a photograph of the flower, right?
And it's like, well, that presupposes, that your goal was to reproduce
a flower.
Accurately, as possible, a particular flower somewhere, right?
And so what I would like to emphasize is that game, development is a
thing that you do it is like any other artistic Endeavor.
There are many aspects to it and where you find enjoyment.
May not be the same as someone else and presupposing a singular
purpose that is I just want to get gameplay as quickly as possible
onto the screen supposes that you had a very specific goal.
All in mind and I for one never have that particular goal in mind.
and I suspect, there are many other people who don't either
and those are the people who just enjoy developing games in general,
right?
They enjoy the process of making the parts of a game which may have
nothing to do with the Gameplay at the end of the day, right?
And to emphasize how important this is to everyone that there are
people like this.
The only reason you even have the option of using an existing renderer
or some other technology or engine is because there were people who
didn't just sit around thinking well I just want to make some
gameplay, right?
And so it
It's all sort of aspects of the discipline to move the discipline
forward.
And it's very important that there are people out there who enjoy
working on all the different pieces.
And so like I said, this dream is for the people who want to know how
to build the whole game.
Not people who just want to put some gameplay on the screen because
you can just go down, get download Game Maker, if that's all you
wanted to do right?
What is the, what is the ambient occlusion?
And why my video card get late to run games with ambient occlusion,
like really lose FPS?
So I can't speak to specifically why a particular game might be
running more slowly with ambient occlusion or anything like that, but
I could give you some hypothetical answers.
I can tell you what it is so ambient occlusion, we didn't have to talk
about thankfully, and the reason for that is because it's baked into
the Sprites actually fairly well, but let's talk about what it means.
So ambient occlusion is a term that actually
It's not real, right?
It's not a real thing.
Okay.
All the stuff I talked about up there before we're real things.
Ambient occlusion is a term that actually refers to in effect of real
things.
Not some aspect of what's actually happening to the light and what
it's referring to is the fact that if you take a look at a surface,
okay, let's say I have a surface that looks like this.
Well, my light source is able to hit all of the pieces of this
surface.
So when I am rendering it, I do not have to consider the fact that
there is light getting absorbed by the surface.
When I light this surface and vice-versa A and B are completely
unrelated, okay?
However, if I were to come to consider the same light source now
operating on a different surface, right?
Let's suppose the surface looked like this, okay?
As the light kind of comes in here, what you can see is that a certain
degree of the light that should have been falling on?
This surface is not going to fall on it because other surfaces in the
area where preventing that from happening.
Right?
So the light comes from over here.
Yes, I can hit it but if the light comes from over here, I can't.
Furthermore, if it looked more like this, then I've got even more of
that happening, right?
Light from anywhere.
Here is going to Shadow this interior part, light from in here, it's
going to Shadow it and so on.
So ambient occlusion refers to the process and again.
So ambient, meaning light from all directions, not a specific
Direction and occlusion meaning to block right ambient, occlusion is a
fake and actually kind of lousy approximation to recapturing.
Some of the detail that is lost because you're not actually doing
letting calculations at the Fidelity necessary to capture these
effects.
So what happens is you take a surface
Like this, you take a look at this here.
And you say, well, I'm going to before I ever run the game before I do
anything.
I'm going to look and see how much of the Horizon can see, right?
And more specifically for a particular Texel.
So like right there, you know, like right right.
That point I'm going to cast out the Horizon.
I'm going to see that.
Okay?
It can see about that much, right.
So when I am lighting things just in general, when I'm using the
indirect lighting terms, so light coming from everywhere.
If it can only see 25% of the Horizon, I'm just going to multiply the
incoming light by 25% and call that the darkening effect right call
that ambient occlusion
and so what ends up happening is in places where objects have
crenellations or folds, you know in skews things it darkens them
so that's ambient occlusion and there's two types are typically used,
there's baked
and there's screen space.
So there's baked ambient occlusion screen size and of inclusion.
Baked ambient occlusion is when you do exactly this process offline.
So, I take my object, whatever it is, I go through it.
And I have a texture map that covers its surface, and at every text on
a texture map, I see how much of the Horizon it can see my saying
arise, I don't mean that I really mean hemisphere right?
The hemisphere around it, and I bake that into a term.
That's the ambient occlusion term.
Now it can get fancier.
Because there are ways oftentimes using things called spherical
harmonics, which we're not going to talk about.
Or other kinds of bases, there are ways of trying to encode, not just
how much of the hemisphere has seen.
But actually what sort of General region of the hemisphere you saw,
and that allows you to do more directional ambient occlusion, right?
But anyway, baked Deo computes that everywhere on the model and writes
it into a texture map.
So this comes up as a texture map /, / model, right or you know,
textures that cover
The model that say how much you can see and off you go screen space.
Inclusion is a totally different idea.
What screen space ambient occlusion is, and this, these tend to look
real bad.
But, you know, some engines do it better than others.
But what this is, is this goes ahead and says, all right, look, we all
we know we've already got a z-buffer, right?
We already rendered a z-buffer into the scene.
So we actually already know when we draw this thing, right?
We actually already know the depth value at every pixel.
So if there was a place in the scene that has
I'd like an in skews part like that and we wanted to darken it in
there because of that, what we could do is at every point on the
screen we could look at the depth values in screen space that are
nearby it and decide based on those deaf values whether we think there
were things that would be shadowing.
It that are nearby and based on the collection of those depth samples
we will then darken the incoming lighting for that point.
Okay, so that's screen space ambient occlusion again, these are not
real things.
These are hacks that are designed to increase the degree to which you
capture in skews Lighting on things because typical game lighting
can't handle doesn't do full computations there, right?
Like remember I said there's that cubemap lighting trick so if you
imagine something like that happening on an object?
Well, it's not ever casting any raise that?
It's never not ever seeing if it.
Actually reach that cubemap, it's just assuming that it can and so you
never get that self shadowing.
That's what the ambient occlusion terms trying to put back in, but
it's not a real thing.
It's just a technique.
It's like a hack to try and reproduce What would actually be
happening.
If you were Computing, the leading equation at every point for the
whole light field.
Auntie Songbird cake.
I do not prefer muffins.
Do you have any plans to implement Sprite?
Opacity, we already do Implement.
Sprite opacity Sprites can be as translucent as they want to be.
And if so, could this be taken into consideration with the lightmap
calculations?
I less opaque.
Objects block less light.
Yeah, and we could even try to make translucent objects are
transparent.
But colored objects transmit, that light color.
I don't know.
We'll see what we can do.
You know, we'll just give it a shot.
That's one of the fun things about writing your own Graphics engine.
We could come up with some techniques that no one's ever done before
maybe they look good or maybe look awful but it's a lot of fun to play
around with and so that's when things will do it.
Maybe that's what will spend next week doing just playing around.
See what we get.
Are there any books or resources you would recommend on lighting?
So, you know, I guess I've never read it myself.
But there is a book on lighting that a lot of people rep recommend.
Let me see.
It's by, I think it's by Matt far.
Yeah, this is the one
This, this book.
Yeah, I feel like this is a book that a lot of people respect.
I have not read it myself, so, you know, don't take me if it turns out
to be awful or something, but I believe, if you want to know the math
behind how light actually works and how to simulate it, I feel like
that's one of the books that people recommend for a good, you know, a
good kind of
Full overview.
Twister.
So game design, documentation, like a roadmap for the game.
No.
So we are not doing anything like that.
This is a game implementation Stream.
So the design is kind of a separate thing that we don't really work
with.
We just do programming the engine and then the gameplay as well will
be programming it.
But we're not actually talking about that part because I'm not really
a game designer.
So I don't want to try to give lessons on how to do game design
because I'm the wrong guy for that.
So yeah, so we're not dealing with any of that stuff.
In terms of design docs or anything like that.
Wouldn't a game in Pitch Darkness at the easiest lighting system to
code?
Yes, it would.
And they're almost was a game that was done in complete pitch
Darkness, you may have heard of it, it was called alone in the dark.
And my understanding was It was supposed to be entirely Audio Only but
the publisher eventually made them change it and so then they ended up
doing it as a bitmap with 2D objects over it game.
This was the original one of the dark, not the Remake, obviously, but
it was very successful anyway, but my understanding was that was
originally supposed to literally be a black screen and the game was
played entirely and audio, but they made a change that so so it didn't
happen.
That would have had very easy lighting.
Can you go back in time and start this series, 15 years ago?
I would love to be able to go back in time.
15 years.
You don't know how much I would love to do that.
If you can provide me with some sort of a device that would allow me
to do.
So I would happily start the series 15 years ago.
Course we wouldn't have twitch and YouTube and stuff so we'd have to
figure out a way that we were going to transmit it, but I'm sure we
can figure it out.
And T song bird.
It is neither cheese.
Nor mud cake.
I like the sort of cake with buttercream frosting.
Okay so we're still trying to chase down this question.
What I mean is sort of more like how to make beams of light passed
through a rendered object.
Okay so and and Garland oh Bloom tries to clarify I think they meant
God raised.
Okay.
So, God raised.
Is actually volumetric scattering.
Okay.
So the way that this works is, there's no such thing as beams of light
right there.
Just photons flying through the air and what's actually happening.
That when the reason this occurs is when the are around something is
highly particulate, right?
So it's typically bright light.
So there's a lot of photons, right?
Lots of photons and heavy are, right?
Lots of particles.
Right?
So typically about sunlight, bright sunlight, Misty are that sort of
thing and and or Dusty.
That's when you get into these heavy volumetric scattering situations
and what's happening there is you end up with stuff like, okay, I've
got a window, right?
And it has, you know, it's got
You know it's got Jesus in it, right?
And a vampire or whatever and Jesus is like about to kill the vampire
with a steak or something, right?
I don't know.
It's a stained glass window.
Is my point.
I don't know if the vampire.
Maybe it's got some bat wings or something on there.
So, there's a stained glass window, right?
And the lights on the other side of it and it's coming through.
And what you're asking about is like, well, they, the these, these
colored light rays that like pass through, right?
Or
Like this.
And the way that that happens is the light.
When it hits the stained glass window, the stained glass, the the
whole point of stained glass is it absorbs certain colors and lets
others pass through.
So, if you see red stained glass, like, you know, Jesus has
vampire-killing.
Steak is like dripping some blood or whatever.
So that's red, right.
What that means is it?
Absorbs stuff outside of that wavelength.
So basically like here's red on the wavelength Spectrum here is like a
bunch of other things.
It's absorbing all of this light into the glass and it's letting this
pass through.
So the light on this side may be whatever color but when it comes to
here it's going to be red.
What then happens is all of these photons that are streaming through
here that are read, they hit all that particle matter in the air.
All the dust that's in the that's in the spooky church or whatever,
right?
And it hits that and scatters in all directions, some of those
directions.
Back to your eye.
And so, that's what's actually happening.
It's a volumetric scattering problem.
And so, you know, if the ant if the question is, how do I Implement
that in a ray Tracer?
Well, the answer is you literally do the volumetric.
Scattering what you do is when you cast raise right, you have volumes
and they are defined as having a certain density of volumetric
particles in them and as the ray passes through them you compute a
percentage chance of it getting scattered.
And then you if it hits you scatter that Ray and you you know sample
that proportional to what you believe the incoming light field is in
an unbiased way and all this other nonsense, right?
If you're trying to figure out how to do that in a game, then you're
in hack territory, right?
Because volumetric scattering is one of those things that, you know,
you got to do an approximation to of some kind.
And so, I have to say, I don't know what the current, I'm sorry.
I don't know what the current like, you know, slickest technique is
for that.
I don't know.
For God raised I suspect that it would have something to do with, you
know, taking one of these guys and going well okay, we're going to
presuppose that we know what our services are that.
That do God Ray pass through stuff and you know, we're going to go
ahead and we're going to start off.
If they might just do it in screen space now.
Now that I think about it.
Yeah, okay, so there's probably there's probably a screen space way to
do this now, actually, because we've got so much ability to do that.
I wonder I, you what they might do is just take a look.
They might just take a look at like, render places that want to have
volumetric effects in them.
They might just use screen space for that.
I don't know.
You should look this up.
I wonder if there's some stuff because this is what I was missing.
I want if your screen space, godrej techniques now seems like that's
the way you do it and you would kind of go through the screen.
You would see if you had godrej pixels.
If you did, you would sort of set them.
You would do, maybe perhaps the raycast just right there or you do a
cube map, look up, right there.
That, that seems that might be.
So,
It might actually be that you do this in screen space nowadays.
I don't know, I'd be curious to know.
I've never implemented.
God raised in at all.
Really, I've never tried to implement godrej, so I don't know.
But that's that's what's actually happening.
I suspect that nowadays maybe screen space is how they would do that,
because it seems like that's probably probably the only way to really
handle it without doing anything crazy.
Don't You cast Rays from the eye and not the sun to reduce
calculations?
And then see if the Rays cast from the I hit the Sun.
So I'm not sure what you're actually referring to.
Has again, like in games, we don't really do a whole lot of Ray
tracing.
I mean, sometimes we do for computing, things nowadays, but you don't
really cast raised from light sources or from eyes.
If that makes sense.
You do render Shadow maps from like light sources.
So in that sense you are casting Rays from the Sun if you will.
So yeah, you don't do that way.
But if you're making a ray Tracer, the
Sir is typically that you do, you do go from the eye out in purely
Monte Carlo, right?
Racers in like in the is a purely Monte Carlo.
He forward Monte Carlo rate Racers which are fairly common.
You go from the ayat where it's but
In a whole Suite of other ones, you actually go from both.
They're called bi-directional path tracers.
So, like Metropolis ones, they go from both bi-directional rate by
directional path tracers, go from both.
So, no, I mean, the answer is, is you don't exclusively go for one or
the other.
It really depends on what you're implementing, which one you go from,
for what?
Can you use a 3D overlay to pretend say a slice of a 3D environment.
For example, the platform you're on being Z and then X is across y up
and down, so you can have a light source at x-33 y50, Z1.
So all objects, less than x 33 would be shadowed to the right objects,
greater than we show to the left.
That is sort of what I was talking about.
But again, I don't know how crazy will get with it.
In terms of three dienes.
I'm not sure if they were talking about.
But again we let's wait till we get a little bit more into trying to
play with that stuff before we talk about it more because we're not
sure exactly what we're going to try.
In early episodes.
You worked on having multiple Z levels.
Wouldn't this mean you would need to render walls in 3D?
Thus introducing some 3D into the rendering and letting calculations
possibly but I think I'll probably try to handle that again in slices.
Like I don't know that we want to try and do full 3d for that.
I think we might want to just have like, Lighting on two different
planes or whatever, right?
Or maybe just one plane, whatever.
The plane you're on, has Lighting in the other ones, don't stuff like
that.
How often do you stream game development every night at 5 p.m.
well, except weekends?
My Lord.
This a lot of questions.
I think I might have to end the Q&A.
Sir, my voice is getting tired and I want to have dinner.
What is your background that led to where you are is education or
important or interest more important?
And we've covered that in earlier episodes, I'd probably recommend
going back and watching earlier episodes to for more Exposition on
that.
Well, this lighting system work for blind people.
So, the important thing for blind people write is, it's very much like
deaf people.
You want to just do it really loud, right?
So, if you want the lighting system to work, well for blind people,
you need to increase the brightness to a very high level so they can
see it.
Obviously, I mean, right, that goes without saying, I'm telling you
stuff.
You already know but
Do you think we'll be able to do all this in real time?
Or we have to pre-bake some of the lighting information?
When generating the map, don't know, I really don't it's all
conjecture at this point.
Couldn't you just make a 3D game and then flatten it with a rolling
pin?
That's not a bad idea.
II.
Do agree that, that, that would be an easy way to create 2D assets out
of 3D assets, but I'm afraid they might smush out too much so that you
have to figure out how to solve that problem.
How often is Real Time radiosity used in games?
Is it easy?
And do you guys use it?
Why or why not?
Well, so real-time radiosity I wouldn't use the term radiosity because
radiosity is a specific technique, right?
Radiosity is really not, you know.
without going into too much detail, radiosity is a scheme that's about
solving for the heat transfer between lighting space between surfaces
right and
If not really that common in games, I think maybe frostbite uses a
licensed radiosity transfer engine maybe, but a lot of people just
aren't using any of that stuff anymore.
They do real-time lighting, but it's not radiosity, it's done in
different ways.
And so radiosity is a technique not in effect, right?
And so I would, I would say that real-time lighting that does include
indirect lighting, is now much more commonplace
Like I said, unreal 4 has a lot of it in there.
I believe they'll do they have?
Like, I think they have a sparse voxel, octree stuff in there.
Now for lighting where they actually do, like, you know, real time
diffusion crytek has you know, a voxel light propagation scheme so
that it's in many professional 3D engines now, but it's not
necessarily radiosity.
Radiosity is a very specific type of a technique.
DGM TV.
I saw a game that uses normal maps on Sprites.
There are many games I want to say, there are many games that use
normal maps on Sprites.
It's still not actually that common like a lot of sprite games don't
use normal Maps but it's definitely not super rare.
Like there are plenty of games that have shipped with normal maps for
Sprites.
The question is usually, just how do you generate them, right?
If you render your art assets from 3D down to 2D it's trivial.
But if they're hand-painted, like ours are, it's a question of who.
Hates them and how right?
Isn't lights.
Fall off inverse Square As you move farther from the light source,
each Ray is further from its neighbors.
So know your there's there's two separate things right and this is
kind of crucial.
Again, this is not a complete lighting course.
So, you know, I don't go into detail about everything but the inverse
Square law is actually only affects part of your light.
So, let me, let me give you a little, I'll try to explain a little bit
how that works.
So basically remember I said there's the
Direct indirect light, right?
And so, if you think about how the light works, if I have incoming
light and outgoing light.
Like so,
Then the inverse Square law.
Really does not affect a single Photon path, coming from a light
source and bouncing off, right?
And so if I'm trying to figure out how bright are reflected lights,
light source is in a mirror, there is no inverse Square law
calculation.
The only thing that affects that the inverse Square law affects is how
big the light appears to be in the mirror.
Does that make sense?
So basically the inverse Square law, if I had a mirrored sphere, the
only thing the inverse Square law says is as the light gets further
away, it will be bigger or smaller like as as it gets further away,
like here's if it's closed right?
And here's how big it would be if it was far so the inverse Square
law.
That's what what happens there, right?
And that's because again, the light obviously like you were saying, if
I have a constant density of things that are showing out, you know,
along this, whatever the solid angle.
Is right then the further away, I get the more spread out, those
photons are going to be right, but for a given one, it doesn't matter.
So the size of the light source projected onto the object, does fall
off with inverse Square law, but it's brightness, does not, okay.
So, what that means is that, yes, you will have a inverse-square law
affect in terms of how much light in total May reach an object based
on how far away the light source is because the bouncing around from
different angles will get more sparse as you get further away.
But for the pure reflected part,
It's actually just the size of the reflects that changes but the
brightness is intact and I know that's a little counterintuitive but
that's just the truth.
And so there is no inverse Square law for brightness.
It's not really a thing.
That's, I mean, I'm sorry I should say for the pure reflective part,
that's more for the diffuse, bouncing around part, if anything right.
Would you consider voxel izing the scene like LittleBigPlanet 2 does?
Yeah, so I mean, honestly, that's what I was sort of talking about
here, right?
Literally, that is sort of what I was thinking in my head was that
kind of a scheme, right?
You put in the light sources, you defuse them and then you have like
you you you know where your objects are.
So you block you kind of remove the light from there like a voxel kind
of scheme, right?
Only we're not we're too deep because we don't you know so we don't
have voxels per se.
And so yeah, like to a large extent that is exactly the sort of thing
like LittleBigPlanet style.
Lighting is exactly the sort of thing I was thinking of
Let's just see if there's any more good questions here.
There's probably, there's just so many questions.
I'm not going to get to the mall, so I'm just going to see if there's
any other ones that like, I really think we should answer.
Had to log in so hopefully this isn't too late.
Wouldn't there be fall off with a point source when integrating across
the surface since the Rays spread out away from the source?
Okay, so I think we just covered that.
And so the answer is that's that is for ambient lighting terms.
As for the indirect, lighting terms will do that.
But not the direct lighting terms and it's a common misconception to
about that, right?
Like how that works.
Exactly is the inverse Square law.
Doesn't affect light along a line, light is constant along the line.
So, only, once you start talking about areas, do you care about that?
So it depends on which part of the reflectance, you're trying to
compute whether or not the inverse Square law, affects the size of it
or the brightness of it, right?
And so yeah, you can't just say that light falls off with inverse
Square law because that's not actually true.
The brightness of light is constant along a ray.
It's about what the the actual effect is that's happening.
On the other side, whether the spread of those Rays, end up causing a
diminishing brightness effect, which is the case for purely scattered
light or a smaller size.
Which is the case.
With a reflectance.
Why is it easier to represent light as photons and not particles in 3D
programs?
I don't think it is like, you're not first of all photons are kind of
particles, right?
I'm sorry, I don't think I understand the question.
I guess I'll say about that one.
Rendering light in environments and events, approaching the speed of
light.
How to do it?
Haha, I don't know.
Good luck to you.
I'm sure that's a whole relative.
That that sounds like something, Mark ten Bosch would do.
PBR lightning.
I don't know what PBR lightning is, quick rundown on how it works.
I'm afraid.
I cannot give you an hour or so.
I don't even know what PBR lightning is.
You mean like lightning from the sky lightning?
I'm not sure.
All right, think we've come to the end.
We have come to the end but I understand that John is streaming.
Now, some people are saying that John streaming so if you want to
watch some more stuff right now, you should go check out his stream.
Naysayer 88 on Twitch.
I may well be going to check out history as well.
So yeah.
Alright let's go ahead and wrap this up tomorrow.
We will start working probably with normal maps that
Be the first part of the stuff that we do.
So, I hope to see you back here tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
right here, same time, same place on Twitch, it's been a crazy q a
day.
I don't know what happened there.
Maybe we're on the twitch FrontPage again, or something like that, but
glad to see new people ask questions in there.
A lot of good questions to, which is pretty awesome.
Again, thank you for joining me for an episode of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, I will.
I will.
Hopefully see you
Guys, again, tomorrow, or on John stream, after this?
In the meantime, if you would like to preorder the game to get the
source code, you can do that on handmade hero dot-org and it comes to
the source.
So you can play around with the techniques that we're talking about
here on the stream and see how they work.
You can also subscribe to our patreon if you want to support the video
series, it's always about you.
Shadid we also have forums we can ask questions and there's also ports
to Mac and Linux and stuff like that on their Community contributed
stuff and anti depa, sewed, guides all good stuff.
So I highly recommend checking that out and if you want to be able to
catch the stream live, we have a tweet, but you can subscribe to that
tweets the schedule at you.
So I highly recommend checking that out.
If you're trying to catch us live, it's the best way to stay
up-to-date.
So, thanks again for joining us and I will see you, hopefully
tomorrow, take it easy, everyone.