Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
Show recode a complete game live on stream today.
I actually decided because this has come up many, many times that I
think today, we're going to do a handmade chat, not a handmade hero
because I would like to really clarify this and it's the sort of thing
that comes up really frequently.
And
Guess you know, if I had done a complete introduction to see series
ever which I've never really done, which you know, someday would
probably be nice.
We would have covered all this sort of stuff but since handmade here
is really only about how to do game programming and it kind of assumes
that you already know how to do non-game programming of some kind.
There's a lot of kind of gaps in the understanding potentially about
what's going on.
In terms of how see is doing things, how the CPU is doing things and
so on.
And we dive
Into it.
at appropriate times on handmade hero but we sort of leave it, you
know, as just understood a lot of the times, if I'm not specifically
addressing it,
And so, what I want to do is just maybe take some time to kind of go
over some things in a little more detail today and I do apologize for
people who already know these, but I feel like once in a while, it's
good to kind of just do a chat where we kind of address, some things
in detail, that people who aren't familiar with sort of lower level
programming, have a hard time wrapping their head around and we may
have said them on and made here but we don't necessarily dedicate a
whole lot of time into looking into them, other than just stating
what's going on and you know moving on.
So this was more to be motivated by yesterday.
I'm going to go ahead and bring up this email here.
I asked one of the people on the chat who had been asking some
questions on the the chat to write in and sort of more completely
describe.
Sort of the problems of understanding they were having with pickle
thing.
They had been asking about on the chat and I was like, just send me a
thing and we'll we'll kind of go over it because I get this
specifically asked about this.
Ticular thing actually, often, this is not in any way.
The only time I've been asked about this and I think that for whatever
reason, it's a uniquely confusing aspect of perhaps, C C++, or
actually also just perhaps low level programming in general.
So I just kind of want to go over it here.
So I'm going to go ahead and read this.
That's not very long.
And then I'm going to sort of break it apart and start talking about
how these things work, and try to really like cement how this stuff
happens.
So that when these questions are asking the future, we have an episode
of point or like here is an episode that explains completely from
start to finish, everything you need to know about this.
So the email goes well, okay, see, I'm Nico 314 from your stream and
Leave their on the stream today as well.
Who asked question about type testing of functions.
I'm trying to follow along with your file IO code.
First establish, an episode 15 then completed in 24 and 25, not 100%
sure.
But you're far, Lyoko definitely changes from the 15th episode.
You use the following lines of your platform layer and it has what we
are all sort of familiar with.
Now, is the way that I typically do function pointers if they're going
to be defined in multiple places, which is I make a pound to find for
the function signature that I make a typedef.
If using that pounded fine, again, I'm going to go over these in a
little more detail later, but that's not the real meat of the
question.
I think this creates a type called debug platform, read entire file,
that returns a debug read file result and takes a thread context
pointer and a care pointer.
And that is a correct thing to think this will allow us to declare a
function of this signature as a type.
And that's a function pointer.
Another place in Winter three-layer, you define a function that
matches the signature of the typedef that will actually load a file in
Windows as
Here it is.
I believe the macro changes mr.
Reed, and then puts that there and he is again.
Correct writing it.
This means you can declare the following debug platform read entire
file star, a equals.
Debug that from the entire file.
I inserted the star there because it seems it can only be used when we
have a pointer correct.
I tried to make it, not a pointer and test program and a function
can't be initialized.
The left hand side of the Declaration is what you're declaring in the
game.
Memory struct and assigning it to the same function in the winter to
layer.
When you initialize the gamer instructed assign members were going to
use the term.
I was wrong.
I'm not from the Cs world.
As of writing this, I'm getting the vibe that there is no way.
For a CPP file to communicate with another CPP file.
Without the use of function pointers.
I think that's what a callback is.
I have to think about this more before I say anything further, I also
have some header file problems to where one is referenced in another
that is causing further.
Confusion on another note to me, understanding pointers doesn't really
tell me about how to utilize a function pointer.
I get that a pointer, isn't Addison memory.
That stores another address in memory, that stores a value.
Depending on the type, or more generally reads, a certain number of
bytes starting at that memory address based on the type, it was
declared
Or cast it to.
I made function pointers in a test program and it behaves slightly
different from an integer pointer.
If I have a function pointer called see and I watch see and star see,
they reported the same, it gives me a memory address.
Then saves the says, the signature of the function in parentheses, if
C was an integer pointer, see would return the memory as to the
integer and starseed return the integer value itself.
None of this helps me, understand implementation.
It's like saying, f equals the derivative of p with respect to time.
Now, I should be able to solve every Newtonian mechanics.
Oblem, I'm new to C++, C and C++ and I've learned everything.
I know about it from watching your stream.
My degree is in physics and I started coding with C sharp eight years
ago for work purposes.
So all my experience is based on what I'd call pattern recognition.
I found out about handmade hero around two years after you started.
I've been watching every episode, sometimes, more than once and
chugging along on episode 52.
Currently, I found them in Caskey different.
Some fascinating as I've never seen an application of it.
I only know Mankowski from space-time relativity, diagrams.
I watch your my rocket video from 2006 on Mankowski.
Jake albums as well.
I can't thank you enough for the work.
You put in a streaming and educating its best $15 ever spent sorry for
the long scar.
Me an email, I spent several hours running it and I'm really tired
right now.
First of all, thank you for writing in.
This is very complete and gives me everything.
I need to understand, sort of where your confusions, probably are with
some of this stuff.
And let me first finish my bubble tea here and I will kind of go into
more detail here.
Okay.
Wait, there's still there's still some tapioca left in my bubble tea.
I got to get those those out here.
Never leave a boba behind.
That's my my feeling ability, right?
Okay, so first of all, let me say that I don't think you are alone in
your feeling that function pointers and calling functions in general,
is a little bit impenetrable in terms of understanding how it works.
And see it's one of those things.
That see kind of dances around a little bit and maybe doesn't end up
doing a particularly good job at making be orthogonal and logical.
You know, programming languages, all have things that they do well and
things that they don't do so well and they're always edge cases stuff
like that.
See, I don't think really ever reached maturity with respect to the
relationship between code and data.
It's just not something that really happened in.
See,
It's a problem and it does carry forward to today and not only does it
create problems with respect to what we can do in C and what we would
like to be able to do and see.
But it also creates problems of the form you're experiencing which is
to say that and actually I would say that I actually disagree with
your analogy of f equals DP over DT.
Now she will solve every Newtonian mechanics from that's actually
being more generous to see than it deserves because
F equals DP over.
DT is actually at least consistent with every Newtonian mechanics
problem and there are no gotchas in there.
As far as I'm aware sees function, pointer stuff actually is not at
all consistent with the way, the other pointers to things work in a
lot of ways.
And so in some sense, it's not even as good as saying f equals the
derivative of position over time.
Go solve every Newtonian mechanics problem.
You're actually at a more severe disadvantage if you will, in trying
to come
Matt sees use of functions and pointers and try to understand them.
Just from understanding how regular pointers work and extrapolating
from there.
So let me start out with a few.
Basic things that I think we should get straight.
That have never really been addressed on handmade here, very much,
because they're not really relevant to the way we do development on
handmade hero.
And that really has to do with translation units.
What they are, how source code is linked and so on.
I'd like to start with that and then build up to the function pointer
part of things as we go.
Okay?
So let's let's do some of that.
So
so what I want to point out in a kind of go back and this should be
probably more familiar to the the person who is writing in then,
probably a lot of the other people are watching because the person is
writing in started recently at the beginning of the series, everyone
else maybe has forgotten.
We did to be a serious but obviously, you know that we in our code we
have a thing called build up, bat here and build up at is just a batch
file.
That does our build now, why do I use a batch file to do our build?
Well, the reason I use a batch
Of durability is because, you know, maybe five six years ago or so I
found that build systems, took more time to maintain and use, then
they actually saved in practice and that most code, even code.
That's 200,000, 300,000 lines of worth of source which are the kinds
of sized projects that I typically deal with are, are just not, it's
not necessary to use.
Use a build tool.
Now, when you get into heinous monstrosities that are like, libraries
on top of libraries, on top of libraries, on top of libraries, on top
of Java, on top of emscripten and top of JavaScript and like, piles
and piles.
I guess that you couldn't really do that quite that.
You can't put any script on top of JavaScript, but you know what?
I mean, if you if you have these monstrosity is that are kind of the
way that people build some of these modern projects, which I won't
touch the 10-foot pole.
Then you can understand why people may be still need to use build
systems because these
Things take hours potentially to build from scratch, but in our case
we're talking about a game code base that's written by hand and is
relatively clean.
These things can be several hundreds of thousands of lines which is is
sufficient for any game that I've ever seen.
Really if you're actually being coherent about it, you just don't need
them.
So that's why I use a build up at to build it.
And the way that I do that is I
I call a single or in this case two different calls to the compiler
and in those lines it implicitly invokes the Linker it's a compile and
Link command.
I only call it twice and I only produce to executable portions ones,
an executable and ones that deal.
L that is how we build handmade hero implicit in.
That is a bunch of stuff that is relevant to the understanding of what
a function pointer even is.
How they come about and where you how you can start to understand
things such as the question that was asked in the email about how one
CPP file talks to another.
So what I'd like to do is depart just briefly from the build bat that
we were using so that we can talk about what the compiler actually
does, what the Linker actually does.
Look at both of those and start to talk about what a CPP file even.
Is what an H file is, and all of those sorts of things, so that you
can really get a coherent understanding of exactly what's going on
here.
And then we'll move up to the, to the code level.
The assembly level itself and watch exactly how these things are
working on a number of fronts, Okay?
So,
Let me start.
By making something out here in the temp directory let's say and or
not temp directory but I'm going to call this.
What was the name that was on here?
Okay so I'm going to call this nacre 314.
It's a deadly.
I should mention that that if those of you who are with me on the
freestream, know that I was eating a meat pie for lunch and the place
where I got the meat pie was actually is called 314 pie.
So I feel like this is serendipitous and
Anyway, so here I am in a clean directory.
And what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to make a file in here.
I don't know what it's going to be temp.
Dot CPP, let's say, or maybe I'll call this main.cpp.
And then I'm going to open it in for coder.
Here it is.
I don't actually need that there.
But what we're going to do here, is I'm going to make something that
the C compiler can compile, right?
I'm just going to make a very, very simple thing.
Like, you've seen many times before and I'm not going to decorate it
in any way.
I'm just going to have a void function here.
I'm going to, you know, make something where I take an inch in and
that's it, right?
And maybe I'll make it a little bit more interesting here by saying
that I
I'm going to generate a result.
I'm going to multiply whatever the input is that I receive.
I'm going to multiply it by 2, right?
So that's the the entirety of what I've what I've created, right.
So we all know intuitively what this is now, right?
We all know intuitively what we're looking at here, but how often do
we really talked about, you know, in on handmade hero we don't.
How often do we really talk about exactly what's going on in here,
right?
So this means that CBP is just a text file on a drive, right?
And it's really crucial to emphasize this point.
In certain sense because there are languages out there where files
have more meaning but in C++ and C and C and C++.
It's important to understand that files on a drive, literally have no
meaning until we invoke the compiler.
And it sort of is instructed as to how to interpret those files files.
Don't have a one-to-one correspondence with anything in particular in
C.
And so it's important to stand all we have done now.
Again, it may seem
But just going to hammer it home.
All we have done is type some text into a file and it has no meaning
whatsoever, right?
Not yet.
Anyway.
Okay, so now if I'm out here, I have the ability to invoke a compiler.
In my case, it's Microsoft C compiler.
So I type c l.
If you were on another platform maybe you would be typing clang or Cc
or something.
If you run Linux or on Mac OS X or something like this, but point
being I have some way to invoke a compiler and
There's two different ways that I might ask the compiler to deal with
this file.
One is traditionally called compilation and the other is traditionally
called linking.
And we don't super distinguish, those two and handmade hero, but I
want to distinguish them now.
So, what I'm going to do first is I'm going to take this main.cpp
file, right?
And I'm just going to call CL on it.
And I want you to see what happens, right?
So when I just call CL
With main.cpp.
What you can see here is actually two steps have occurred.
The first step is it is, if it is invoked the compiler, which you can
see here on main.cpp and what you'll note is, there were no errors.
Now I could have had an error.
Like maybe I accidentally typed.
Why here?
Right then it would have stopped it would have invoked the compiler
and stopped, okay, but instead if you take a look at what happens with
what I have here, when there's no errors it, then progress.
Is on to a second stage where it's actually invoking the Linker.
Now the Linker is not CL, the Linker is actually a separate command
called link which you can see if I actually type that separately.
But what happens is that CL as a command will impact, will invoke both
the compiler and the Linker if told to do nothing else and that is the
way that it's currently working on handmade hero, right?
So what you'll note here is that you'll see, it says entry point, must
be defined now.
What is happening?
Okay, right, even just right now.
I can already start discussing.
What is going on in terms of functions and how they work and how text
files are related to them and all this sort of stuff.
So let's break down exactly what we're seeing here.
Before we even go one step further and actually do Define an entry
point.
Okay.
So what has happened here is actually a two-stage process.
Where the first thing that happened is this main.cpp.
I was fed to the compiler, it started interpreting it because of its
extension, there's an automatic detection, right?
That occurs here, where it's going to look at the extension.
It's going to see a DOT CPP and Microsoft's compiler.
Will just intuitively treat that as a C++ file.
Meaning it will start to interpret the text that it sees as if it is
C++ text, okay.
That is not an absolute requirement.
For example, let's suppose I did something.
Here, that was exclusively the domain of C++, right?
That does not exist in C.
Here's a bunch of things which should not compiled in a c program, and
when I hit CL main.cpp, you'll notice that it does not complain.
However, if I look at the command line arguments to the compiler, what
I can actually see and of course there's so many of them now that it's
kind of hard to actually find, but if you find, if you can manage to
find it, you can see that you get information in here that actually
tells you what kind of of input file the compiler.
going to expect and let me see if I can actually scroll back up to
this here and see if I can and have some kind of a
And understanding that it should be doing.
See compilation and not C++ compilation which actually maybe I can use
less here to help us find that.
So here, we'll get the help type it to less and then see if I can get
just see as opposed to C++ through here.
Take a look at this.
No, no, there we go.
So you can see right here, this,
You compile all files as dot C, right?
And so what I'm going to do here is I'm going to say you know / TC and
now I'm going to pass it mean, dot CPP.
And what you can see is that now it immediately starts to complain
about these constructs here because it doesn't understand what they
are.
It sees class and assumes, well that must be something.
I don't know what it is yet.
Then I see, this is my class in like, well I can't have an Undeclared,
identifier, followed by another Undeclared identifier something's
wrong.
So you're going to have to, you're going to have to fix this for me,
right?
So again, just to be clear on this, there is no real understanding of
what a file contains until we tell the compiler.
What is looking at and the compiler in this case is operating very
much like a stream processor.
It is taking in the text, it expects that text to be compiled to a
certain language specification by default.
If that came from a CPP file it will assume that it is CPP.
If we tell it otherwise it will not
Not make that assumption.
If it came from a C file, it would assume it.
See again, we could override that if we
To write, but it is acting entirely as a stream processor here and
what that means is that I can just do whatever I want in here and just
the text will just get money together.
So for example, if I have another file as we often do in handmade
hero, I'm going to copy this to like main to dot CPP.
Let's say write what I can do here is I can load main to dot CPP and
put something else in here, right?
Something completely
Other than that, where I say, you know, in bar, in y, and maybe this
has a result, and it is y times y, so it's squared, and I'm going to
return that result, you know, in here, if I were to call this.
So I were to say, okay, the result is actually that I crawl bar of 2
times x like so you can now see that I'm calling the main two dot CPP
file from the main.c file.
If I were to merely call the compilation step on this.
Now what you will see is that the compiler is taking,
A text file in, its doing the compilation on it.
It does not see, right?
It is not see bar anywhere.
So when it gets to the, the request to call Bar, it's like I don't
know what you're talking about right now.
There's a number of ways that I can fix that problem.
And problem is the wrong thing to say here, because what, I'm trying
to adjust show how the stream processing works and start just to
motivate our discussion of functions and how they work.
So it's not really a problem, but there's multiple ways I can.
Get bar into the visibility of the compiler in this step.
One of them is I could just include the CPP file.
Now, again, this may seem counterintuitive especially to people who
are, you know, indoctrinated perhaps to think that, the only thing you
include her dot h files.
Not true C is compiler, is simply a stream processor.
It does not care where the code comes from.
It does not even look at what the files are or what they are called.
Unless again, it's to do some kind of auto-detection to override.
Detection Auto detection in the case where you have not specified what
language are using so we'll assume C plus plus.
And so on, it's only going to do that on the main file, right?
It's only going to do that on the main file.
So, let me go ahead and motivate this, a little further, for example,
So let's say in this case actually I'm going to I'm going to change
gears slightly here back away a little bit.
From one of the things I just said I'm going to instead of Maine to
.cp, I'm going to call it main 2.c, right?
I would've done this initially.
I thought of it didn't think of it, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and include main 2.c, okay?
And now I'm going to go ahead and do my build again.
Right now you can see the compilation step works.
Okay.
Why does compilation step works?
Is because this include all this directive does.
Is it takes the contents of Maine to see and it sticks.
Those contents in the place of
Include it is literally required to do exactly that.
So, this is not like telling the compiler to import something in the
way that other languages might reference a package, or a file that has
things in it and say, I am going to call Things From This understand
that it's a separate file.
But, you know, I'm going to call Things From it.
C does not make that distinction.
When you do a pound include, it is a direct textual include and so it
has to be considered more like if you're
In other languages.
Things that literally import text directly into the stream of
compilation, right?
So what you'll notice here is that if I went over to main.c mean, 2.c
ripe,
Gun and load that here again just to hammer this home.
Let's put that class thing in there.
Right, let's put that class thing in there.
I can pile.
I don't get any errors.
If I compile main.cpp, even though main to is a DOT C file, again, the
only time that the compiler does Auto detection, is on the initial
file that it is past the pound include is not considered a
re-examination of any files.
It's just taking the file and inserting it verbatim as if you had just
cut and pasted it.
So it is never going to look at what this name.
The only thing that's going to do is use that to load it from the
drive it's never going to think about what that name is.
It's never going to ask if the .h r dot C is difficult to ask.
If it's not C or a Dusty P.
It is literally just a cut and paste.
That's all it is.
I can prove it prove it to you.
If I were to try to compile main 2.c, it would Auto detect that it's a
DOT C file and again, issue the error, because now it's compiling in
see mode, because the time when that auto-detection happens is on the
initial compile, right?
When you initially pass that file, anything that is included in the
file, right?
Is just glommed in.
Okay, we can take this a step further and say, well, I actually can
pass multiple things on the command line, right?
I can tell it in this case that I want to pass Maine and Maine to
write, I can I can ask for both of them.
Now, here's the part where we really depart from.
A lot of the stuff we do in handmade hero.
We're starting to consider multiple file compilation again.
Made hero because it is much more optimal in terms of compile speed.
We compile everything as one big file with just a main base file that
impound includes all the other files because again like I said see
doesn't care about files really in any specific sense, the C compiler.
All its intending to do is to take a big ol stream of text that it
assumes as in either C or C++ form which ever one you tell it and turn
that into its output and we're going to talk a lot about the outputs.
I'm
potentially not going a deeper than that but that's all it's intending
to do.
It can do that.
Times or it can do it one time so if I want to be most Optimum just
going to invoke it once I'm going to have a main.cpp which pound
includes everything else I want and like the actual code not H files
but everything I want H is cpp's all the code into one giant textual
glob that the compiler digest all at once and spits out a single
result, right?
That's for efficiency sake.
But instead like you see here, I can choose to pass things
independently on the command line, and it will compile them in turn
and what you can see Happening.
Here is specifically, it's actually invoking two separate compilation
steps.
One for main 2.c, 14 main.cpp and the main to see one has errors.
The main.cpp.
One does not have any errors other than it does not know what to make
of this call to bar, right?
Okay.
So, I'm going to take a second just to let that sink in.
Okay?
Because again, we're departing from the way that handmade hero things
are built.
So let's dive into this sort of idea, of a multi file build so that we
can start to understand what that means.
Right?
Now again I really want to emphasize a multi file build, really
doesn't have anything to do with the concept that there are multiple
files.
What we're really talking about here.
Is the fact that we're asking the compiler to consider multiple chunks
of text independently, we have chosen to break that up.
Such that one of them is one file and one of them is another but we
could easily not do that.
And so just to underscore that, I'm going to create one more file,
main three dot CPP.
Oops.
All right, I'm going to load that file in.
I'm going to have the definition of bar in there and I'm going to go
to Maine to see.
And the only thing that's going to be in Maine to dot C is my class
declaration.
Okay, now what will happen in this case if I try to compile them all
together, right?
Main 2.c main, three dot CPP main.cpp, what we will see
Is that I get only the unknown, you know, I get the Uhn Uhn found
bark.
It doesn't know where to go.
What to make a bar right in my main, still main three compiles, just
fine because it's just the one definition of bar and Main to still has
the problem because it's thinking of main 2.c as a C file.
So now, what I'm going to do is I'm just going to say, okay, in my
main.cpp I'm going to include main 2.c, right?
I'm going to include that file and then I'm going to remove it from
the command line.
Right.
So now I'm going to say let's compile these files.
And here we go.
So what I've done there again, I'm just trying to underscore the fact
that the number of C or CPP files that you have has nothing
To do with what the language will actually.
Look at the language is going to look at what you eventually produce
as streams to the compiler.
These are called typically translation units and they're called that
instead of file specifically because a single translation unit is
actually made up of a file that you launched on the command line like
CL main.cpp and all of the files it might include.
It could include hundreds of files, it can include no files, include H
file.
I'll CBS does it matter?
No one's going to look at what those files were called, where they are
or anything other than just what their contents were.
And those contents are going to be inserted directly into the stream.
That is how it's going to work.
So just what I've tried to get at here is just the step one which is
to understand the fact that we are going to control and we are always
in control of what our translation units are.
And a translation unit is a set of text pass to the compiler, to be
considered as a unit.
And the way that we do that in most compilers is by specifying
individual files on the command line, Each of which
And comprises a translation unit.
By aggregating, however many files it has included in it.
So pound include will pull all sorts of other physical files in to
this one translation unit.
All right?
So when we say CL main three dot CPP and main.cpp we are talking about
two separate translation units.
One of those translation units is strictly main three dot CPP.
So in the main 32GB case, we have one translation unit corresponding
with a single file in the other case of main.cpp, we have one
translation unit that is consisting of two separate files, right?
It's main.cpp but also main to dot C, which is pound included.
So again, very important, understand translation, units have nothing
to do with how many files you have, because you are
Control of how many files will end up being pulled in to that
translation unit via the pound include directive.
So hopefully that's very clear and there's no mystery there.
Again, we have not talked anything about how these functions are
actually getting built, how they're getting linked, how they're
finding each other any of that stuff.
I'm only trying to establish the Baseline understanding of what is a
translation unit and how do you control it, okay?
All right.
So now let's move on to step 2.
When I hit return, you'll notice that I do not have a properly
completing compilation step even here specifically for my main.cpp and
the reason that that can't cause remember it's invoked twice.
Here's my to
Listen units, right?
This one.
Succeeded it was able to process this translation unit with no issues
when it got to processing this translation unit main.cpp.
It was unable to complete the processing of that translation unit
because it could not find bar.
Now, why couldn't find bar right?
And furthermore, what would happen if I was to force this function to
be compiled in C form, for example, right?
Because I
I think I don't know.
Let me actually see if this is the case.
Oh it's it's got this kind of Clips.
I'm a turn this off temporarily just I can see ya.
So I want to I want to show you what happens here.
If I do this compilation again I had to unlearn include this because
I'm not this is a C++ constructor we can't have an A/C program when I
switch to see.
I told it.
Hey dumain, three dots, dot CPP and main.cpp I want you to treat them
as C files.
Not sleepy files, right?
What you'll notice.
Is the complaint about bar goes away, right?
You'll notice.
I am not getting an error.
That's complaining about bar.
However, when I switch back to complaint to compiling a CPP, I do get
an error about bar.
Right.
So what's going on there?
That takes us to the next stage of sort of, the understanding of how
translation units work and how multi file stuff works right.
Which we again have to understand before we can get to the
understanding of linkage of functions and function pointers.
Okay.
So
the problem here is that in see, in the original, see, the way that
compilation worked was that when you called a function,
Remember there's no such thing as operator overloading in.
See that was not a thing that she had.
I'm sorry operative.
There was nothing is function overloading in C.
There is also nothing like, you know, polymorphic types that had ways
of like casting between them automatically, like, complicit
Constructors, all these sorts of things that you see in C++.
So the rule in original, see, was that if the compiler saw a call to a
function that it did not recognize.
So in this case, we have bar and I'm not even including main.c to,
that's the anymore.
So this is the entirety of the translation unit.
Now is Justice in Foo.
It sees a spider.
It's like you've never told me what bar is
The C compiler would just go.
Well it looks like you're passing it into your.
I'm going to assume that bar is a function that takes an integer.
And we'll deal with it later.
I'm just going to create the code that in this case, would call a
function that looked like that.
And I'm just going to assume that later on.
During linking which we haven't talked about yet.
We'll take care of this, right?
C++ on the other hand tightened up.
That requirement considerably.
What C++ said was, I always need to know what a function is like what
the definition of a function is before you call it.
You know, if for no other reason than the fact that hey, there might
be multiple overloaded version of this function, one that takes an
input.
One that takes a float, whatever.
I don't necessarily know, even what
Calling if I haven't been told what all the possible versions of this
function are, so it always wants to see the function before it
actually accepts the call to the function, right?
So it's not like the C compiler going to allow me to call a function
that I have never told it anything about.
Now, one way to solve this, obviously, is to define the entire
function.
But as you might imagine, especially if the functions call each other.
There may be, you know, if I have one function that calls, you know,
if I if food calls bar, but bar calls Foo in some kind of circuitous
way, I can't possibly structure it so that they both occur before each
other, right?
One of the function bodies has to happen.
First one of the function B has to happen second.
So obviously, one of the constructs that even see had
Because you may want to do so just for your own era checking.
But that C++ requires is that you define or I should say declare a
function before you use it, you do not actually have to Define what
the function does.
You only have to provide what its signature is so that it's clear how
it would be called.
So in this case, it is sufficient for me to use.
Just the Declaration of the function not its definition over here.
That includes the body just the
Declaration, which is the same as the the, you know, preamble to the
definition.
But that does not have to include the body.
That is sufficient to tell the C++ compiler, what that function
actually is and to allow it to call it, right, okay?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to include that in here.
I'm going to include that function declaration and now I'm going to
try compiling again, right?
And now what you can see is, we're back to good.
We are no longer getting a complaint that bar is not defined because
I'm the bar is what did he call it Undeclared I believe.
Or unrecognized identifier not found is all it said right?
Which is true.
It doesn't have any idea because it doesn't really even know what it
is at that point, right?
And so in this case now we have gotten ourselves back to, okay?
We now have told the compiler when it is processing, the main.cpp
translation unit, it now has the information it needs to do
compilation, right?
Okay.
So, let's get a little bit more.
Aggressive here and move on to the concept of linking, okay?
And this starts to get at the central sort of thing.
That one of the, the sort of phrases that the the person who wrote in
asked about which was, how do CPP files talk to each other, right?
Because this is kind of an interesting question in the abstract sense.
I've got these files, how can they call each other?
What's going on?
I don't know, right.
And then you got function pointers on top of this.
And how do I take a function pointer between two files is what's going
on etcetera, etcetera?
Right?
So taking a look at this.
What the point that I kind of want to get across here?
Is that nowhere at all?
Is there any verification that?
This bar function actually exists anywhere, right?
And I can underscore that point by removing bar entirely from the
compilers consider it consideration.
Remember bar is defined in main three dot CPP, but I could choose to
only compile name, right?
Only compiling main.cpp at this point, right?
So at that point, when I'm only compiling main, I end up in a
situation where now things get pushed to the next step, which is the
linking step.
And that's the part that I want to look at now.
So first of all, you know what's going on here, right?
And we're kind of going to get to it.
We're going to ping pong back and talk about object files in a second.
You can actually see that they're getting created.
He remained a Dobbs, main three that optional talk about what those
are in a second but I want to talk about the Linker first and then
sort of loop back around, all right.
So implicit in everything that we just said and now we're going to
have to actually address.
It is.
What does compilation mean versus linking, right?
What is this mean?
Why are these two things eat?
What do they even have to do with each other?
You know, maybe you have your more familiar with the language, it
doesn't even have these things.
There's no such thing as two distinct sets steps of processing your
code.
Right?
Well, the way that c and C++ and I guess really this comes from see
traditionally handled the concept that compilation.
Or rather processing of your program, might take a long time.
Is that it allowed that compilation to be done in sort of parts,
right?
So if you had a hundred thousand line program which, you know, let's
say Back in 1970, would have been extraordinary perhaps in terms of
its largeness, in terms of how long that it could be, it would take to
process this or even if the compiler would even have enough memory to
process it, who knows, you know, I don't
Say that that's the correct size to be large in those days and
obviously would depend on the machine.
You were using it so on
but one of the things that was introduced,
As an optimization in that case, was the idea that if you were going
to end introduced in C, this is by no means specific to see.
It's not like, they invented, this idea.
This is, this is a common idea is that there's two phases of work that
have to be done in order to translate the textual content of your code
into something that the computer can actually execute.
The first pass is the
Elation past traditionally come called the compiler, that is
responsible for taking the actual code that you've written and turning
it into, you know, essentially machine code, right?
Assembly Language code, but a bunch of the things at that point that
need to be known in order to finalize that code are left unfine
alized.
So for example, in this case here, where I have this function, I have
all the information I need in order to produce the machine code.
For this function self-contained, it's an NT, it returns an ENT, it
takes an INT it computes to x value.
It calls the function bar, it then takes that result and returns it.
I have everything I need to reduce the machine code except for one
thing, which is the address of the function bar, right?
So if you imagine what this code is going to look like, it's going to
look like, oh I'm going to have some machine code that sets up the
stack and then we have a call instruction and that call
all instruction is going to have to have an address of where to call
and it is that address that the compiler does not have yet because all
its got is a definition, right.
I'm sorry declaration that says here is the signature here, is how you
call bar.
So I've given it enough information to know how to generate the
machine code to call bar but I haven't told it.
What bar is it has no idea what the address of bar might be right.
None whatsoever.
So that is where the Second Step the linkage step comes from.
It is the job of the Linker and the Linker has grown to in Crete to
Encompass other jobs, including code generation sometimes for
optimization purposes.
But traditionally it was more about compilation, pretty much generates
the machine code linking.
Just pulls that machine code together and replaces the addresses.
But, you know, like I said, it's grown over time so that the Linker
now Doug can do more cogent to do optimization and stuff like this but
The linking phase its job is to take the output of the compiler, which
may be many different sort of pieces if I especially if I have.
You know, if I have 30 or 40 CPP files, all of which I'm compiling as
separate translation units.
So ever May translation notes.
I have I have that many outputs.
The Linker is going to take all of those and it's going to compile
that, well, not good pilot.
Its core to link them into the executable that I can actually run.
And it's going to do that by looking at all of the names of all of the
functions that have been defined as well as things like Global
variables, which also have to have addresses associated with them.
And it's now going to take that machine code and patch in all of the
places where the addresses were previously missing because they
weren't known with the actual resolved.
Addresses that says where these things are in the final executable,
Okay.
So, that is what the Linker is doing.
Now let's start with what we're seeing as Linker output here.
I'm asking you to compile main.cpp.
So I've removed one of my translation units, main three but let's say
I left main three in there just for the sake of an argument and we can
see what's going on here.
So I call main three.
That's the API call main.cpp, we're getting compilation, the
compilation here has succeeded.
There's been no errors in the compilation.
What does that mean?
It means that each of those two translation units, main three dot CPP
main.cpp again,
Not files translation units because one of them includes main 2.c.
So we actually have three files that were involved in compilation, but
two of them got funded to one translation unit, one of them into the
other, right?
The compiler did the work of analyzing the source code that was input.
And it generated what is called object code?
Which is compiled like, you know, machine instructions basically for
doing the work of the source code implied but it left out the step of
fixing up those addresses because they weren't known.
Now, if we look at the actual Drive, even though we never asked the
compiler to do this, it did it automatically because it needs to in
order to support the multi-stage compilation, you can see that
actually it out.
For each translation unit and you see it pairs directly with the
translation unit main to see did not get one.
Why it is not a translation unit main three dot CPP was the
translation unit and mean may not see through the translation unit and
main.cpp included main to dot C.
So all of the main two dot C code, if there was any went into Maine
DOT obj, the result of that translation, right?
So what we can see here is it wrote out that machine code, right?
Main dot objects, and main three Dobbs.
Actually are the results of the compilation step which did not fail.
So, it's successfully output those to obj files.
I didn't get an executable because the Linker failed, but I did get
obj files because the compiler succeeded, right?
So now let's take a look here.
At these, I think I can.
I don't know if I can look at these or not.
Yes.
Okay,
It's been a long time since I've done any of these.
Can I can I get
I'm sorry, I'm just going to.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I make sure it's been a long time since I've done this sort of
stuff so bear with me here, but it turns out it is it is exactly as I
remember, so what can we now?
Do to verify that, that sort of, and, and cement, what I'm trying to
tell you here.
So that, you know that I'm not, you know, making this up in and sort
of floating floating around in the the stratosphere, telling you,
ridiculous things.
Well, so let's actually take a second to
By that.
What I'm saying, is actually, what's going on here.
And just to get you familiar with, actually, how these things work in
practice, get your hands dirty, get under the car.
So to speak and like, look, you know, I don't know how cars work so I
have no idea under the hood, who knows?
I don't know how to use cars.
I don't even own a car.
So what, who knows?
But I imagine, this is the kind of thing that people who rebuild their
engines know, in the car sense.
So, here we go.
There is a utility on the Microsoft compiler and there's, you know,
equivalents for your platform as well.
If you're not using Microsoft stuff, maybe someone can post in the
forums at some point, some guides on how to do this if you're on Linux
or Mac or so on.
But there is a utility called dumped in that comes with the Microsoft
Visual Studio compiler, which is what we use on handmade here.
And it is a tool whose
Job is to take the output of the compiler, or the Linker and sort of
reverse engineer what its contents are, right?
So it's supposed to take it and go, okay, here's an obj, here's an
executable whatever.
Tell me what you can about that by looking at the the way that the
compiler wrote it out and and spit out something human-readable right.
It's got a number of ways.
I can analyze this sort of stuff.
The one that I am using right now is called Des, azzam the dis ass
Um, switch is basically saying, hey, you produce this obj file.
I know that an obj file is the result of translating, some of my
source code into machine code that the computer can execute, but with
the addresses left on processed, right?
So what I'd like you to do is give me the disassembly of that machine
code, show me what it is and so here is that line dumped in / Des
azzam Main obj
And that obj.
Is that translation unit?
That includes write this in Foo and in fact, I'm going to go ahead and
and load it up on this side so that we can see a little more clearly
so you can look at them both the same time.
So here it is in Foo index into result equals bar 2 times x and here
is the result.
Okay?
Now here is what the compiler produced.
It produced a label, right?
That's what this is here.
And again this is this obj file is essentially sort of a
A pack file, kind of like the kind that we have in hand made here for
art assets where it's taken.
You know, if we have multiple functions and you know what, let me just
throw on in here.
It'll be distinct.
The floating-point version of Foo right, there we go.
So now let's compile so you can see two of two of them.
Where's my dump bin?
There it is.
Okay.
So, let's take a look at what we got.
Right, again, it looks a lot like a Pac file.
And what we're seeing here again, is a textual display, the actual
binary format of this file.
It's telling us right here.
That it's a cough object cough.
I think, is the common object, file format or something.
Like, I don't even remember what it stands for.
Let's find out what it stands for answer, something like that.
Common object file format.
Yep.
It's basically a binary specification that says, here's how we produce
packages that sort of list.
Here's a bunch of functions and Global variable data, and so on, that
does not quite yet.
Have the addresses bound, right?
That's what it specifies as well.
As I think it provides maybe debug ways to include debug data.
I don't really know fit a long time.
So I looked at it but it's got a bunch of that stuff in it, right?
So it is a binary file format.
Here is a textual listing of what is
Chained in that file.
There's a label, which says, here is the function Foo, right?
And we'll talk about what this is in a second.
But here is the function Foo.
Here is the code for that function.
Foo, then here is a function called baz, and here is the code for that
function, right?
And so what you can see here, is this done, exactly what we would have
expected.
It's going to go ahead and have the preamble to the function, right?
You can see that it shows to implement the x 2 as a shift left by one.
Which is kind of amusing, right?
It's already doing some optimizations there.
Rather than issuing, an I'm all it just doesn't shl even though we
weren't asking for anything specific, but did that it's pushing that
in to a particular register, right?
Which is for the call, I believe that the convention probably says
that that should go in ECX.
So, what it's doing here is setting that up.
And I guess maybe I should be a little more clear.
What happens?
There just haven't talked about that yet but I just want to finish
this and we can talk a bit more about that in a second.
It's then calling again a function that it doesn't know.
So you notice there's no address here, you can see a lot of these
things have a dressy looking things on them.
They're hard coded to locations relative to registers.
You can see a lot of this stuff here, stock manipulation and that sort
of stuff.
This is not that way.
This is actually a symbol, the symbol is question.
Mark bar at y, EA H at Z
She will talk about why it's looks like that in a second but that's
the call with without a known address and then it's going to take that
value.
That comes back and put it into the return register, which is eax and
then it's going to fix.
The stock and return, right?
We then have a bunch of in threes in The Dead Zone which is just
there.
I believe to make sure that anyone who jumps to this area accidentally
issues a fault.
I think this is typically padded so that if this function grows you
have to understand, there's incremental stuff, I think it tends to
leave padding so that if, if it wants to expand a function that it
doesn't have to recompile things that's for incremental, things like
that, I believe that's typically what that's for, but I'm not entirely
sure.
You'd have to ask a pod.
Like these entities are not necessary, right?
Right in three is a thing that's that breaks into the bugger.
It's an interrupt and so it's basically just dead.
It's dead code, its code.
That's never supposed to be executed at all but it's there.
Presumably as padding, you can then see.
We have our other function, write this function here is about as
that's a second ones floating point.
You can see it does exactly the same stuff, it uses the xmm registers
because that's where you do floating Point math nowadays, it does a
mauve to load in whatever the input was it does a mul to to, you know,
basically
Apply two times.
The value.
In this case,
I guess.
Wait how exactly are we doing this here?
Move us.
Sx-70 Dura pointer as Fates say it's saving them register, which makes
sense.
Move us, sxm, 02, reporter real out of four.
So actually What's Happening Here?
It looks like here is the here is the mole that actually does the two
times.
This it must have put the constant 2 into this data segment here which
is going to have a 2.0 as a constant and that's what it's loading out
there.
Actually
Going to actually take this and move it into the return register and
return, right?
So again, I know this is all for a beginner.
This is going to be overwhelming to try and understand all the
Assembly Language.
I just briefly said what it was, you'd understand.
You don't have to quite get familiar with that just yet.
All I really want you to pay attention.
To again, is these things here, these are labels, which say, here's
some code.
Here, it is a call to a symbol that has been defined.
Here is some code and, you know, if there's any other calls
One doesn't have a call, right.
Only that one does
Okay, so hopefully you understand what's going on there.
Now what you can see, if we dump out main three dot object is we have
the corresponding symbol.
So this is the obj file produced in the main.cpp translation unit
which again includes Maine to see as well.
So against not file specific when it goes to call this function.
Now, imagine what the Linker has to do, the Linker is trying to
produce an executable whenever it goes through and pulls all these
things together.
It's going to look.
Look and see that it has an address here, it's looking for something
called question, mark bar at at.
Why a h at Z, right?
That's what it is looking for.
And you can see that in this other obj file here, it has that symbol
question.
Mark bar at at why a h at Z, right?
So that's how the Linker, no.
Was how to connect things up.
The code, the actual Assembly Language code or machine code.
I should say in the cough file that the compiler executes has names
which exactly match the names in other translation units and the
linkers job is to line.
All those up, assign everybody a position in the file the executable
file that's getting output and then you know make all those addresses
lineup.
Ace call, you know something let's just call and then some symbol that
we don't know what it is replace that with an actual call to an actual
address.
Right?
Okay, so let's go one step further.
Now let's let's let's really try to start to sort of tie all these
things together, what you'll notice and I think this is the part that
I was really trying to motivate is that if I call this in either way,
right?
I can call CL main.cpp or CL, mean 3.
Dot CP, n main.cpp in neither case, does it complain about bar?
Miss being missing.
Now that makes sense in this case because I gave it a translation unit
that actually has bar in it.
And in this case, I
I didn't, why is in this case?
It not complaining well,
What we need to understand is that the Linker is under no obligation
to complain about a missing symbol.
If it doesn't need the symbol.
So the way Microsoft's Linker works is it actually starts at What's
called the entry point and it crawls its way outward from there,
pulling in the symbols that it needs based on what the entry point
actually calls.
This is a good way to do dead code elimination because it means that
you're never going to link a function into executable that nobody ever
calls.
Because why would you want to link in a function that nobody ever
calls?
That doesn't help you in any way because no one can ever call.
It's just wasted space, right?
So what's happening here?
Is a very logical and very understandable process because here is the
key.
All of these translation units that I have in any project that I have,
all of them can have tons of symbols and all of those symbols can, you
know, point to each other, and blah, blah, blah.
But there's one step that's missing.
How do I actually start executing my program, right?
Because all of these files, and all of these functions have all
they're doing is pointing back at each other right there.
No, the operating system Microsoft Windows, which is actually going to
run my program.
I'm not linking with its source code, right?
So it can't call me.
How does it call me?
Right?
And so what you have to understand is the next step of the process,
right?
Which is that link time?
What's going to happen is we are going to be using knowledge, right?
The Linker is going to be using knowledge of the platform for which it
is exporting an executable, and it's going to utilize
Why's a priori knowledge of how that operating system loads
executables.
So what happens when people make an operating system?
Is they rigorously defined how they will load a piece of data off of
disk and start execution at it.
Right?
And then it is the linkers job to make sure that It prepares an
executable in such a way so that it conforms with that standard
Right.
Now, what I would like to do for the next step is going to take a
little while so you're going to have to bear with me here as we try to
get through it.
Right?
So first what I'll do is I'll show you the not particularly helpful
thing that's about to happen and then we'll sort of go a little bit
further.
So let's say, I actually use the standard for
For C programs and I put in here the standard sort of Maine that you
would expect, right?
Oops, I didn't mean to do that.
So I'm going to go ahead and do a compile now of Cl Maine.
And what you can see, if I add this sort of this boilerplate code,
that is everyone's seen for the, you know, how a C file is to put how
execution supposed to start.
And it C program.
What you can see is that if I do that, I know immediately get the
unresolved external symbols
Or if I'm only compiling that one translation unit that I would have
expected to get before.
Why am I getting it now?
Well, I'm getting it now, because I've actually defined a starting
point somewhere.
And so when I Define that actual starting point, the compiler, now
starts to look at other things that are in that translation unit.
Now it can choose not to look at them because I haven't actually
called them, right.
So the fact that it's complaining about missing bar refuge in
function, Foo is purely advisory really because it's underneath
Obligation to even really do that.
Because since I haven't called Foo, that's not actually necessary.
But I'm going to actually call Foo here anyway.
Just to make sure that if you are on a compiler, that's even more
aggressive.
It would work, right?
So point being at some point, when we actually start to use this, we
will now get our unresolved externals, because now it knows that we're
actually trying to use these files in these functions.
And so on, we're starting to actually use the stuff that's in these
translation units, right?
So that means I do
To have everything to find.
But once I have everything to find, what you'll notice is now the
linking step actually works and I get my main three dot exe.
Why is it called mean to .exe?
Because that happens to be the first thing that was specified on the
command line.
The definition of how Microsoft C compiler CL command works.
Is it will just call it the first thing it saw?
It will call it that .exe.
We can control that using like a directive like the output directive
to tell it to produce some other file, but
It's fine by me and if I want it to be the other way around, I could
just switch it like this too.
And then the automatic naming would produce a main w.
Right.
So I'm going to delete the main 31 and leave it like that.
So there's main dot exe, right again, we have not really covered how
well the Lincoln stuff works yet.
So we're getting there, but I've just got to take it one step at a
time.
Okay?
Now what you'll notice is a, some ridiculous stuff has now occurred,
okay, bad, bad, bad things have happened, the train is gone completely
off the rails.
And how do I know this has happened?
And why did I say that?
We're going to take a bunch of steps up few minutes ago.
You
you'll notice I said the next thing I'll show you going to take a lot
of steps you'll have to bear with me.
Well what what do you see in front of you right now?
What do you see when I take this directory?
Well you can see that main three that obj took 795 B to encode as an
object file and main.cpp and Maine to see the other translation unit
took 1409 B to encode right now.
You know, I'm no mathematician as I said at the beginning of the in
the, in the
Stream.
Actually we're talking about math but that's, you know, just just a
little over two k right in terms of size.
So that's how much machine code we asked the compiler to make, that's
how much it took to represent the source code, we gave it so why on
Earth is it an 80 K executable that popped out?
Like what happened here?
Right.
What is going on?
It's nuts, right?
I mean stuff has gone completely as going completely off the rails.
The answer here is a bunch of implicit stuff, a bunch of implicit
stuff that the compiler just does and which we are now going to have
to turn all of it off to try to get down to the understanding that I'm
trying to give you, which is about exactly what happened.
So bear with me.
As I talk about all the stuff that the compiler just basically pooped
on us in a little like, poop sauce Sunday.
All right, so where does this problem come from?
Well, it comes from the fact that if you think about what's supposed
to happen,
if you pop open a copy of kernighan and Ritchie C or something like
this or the definition of C, Is it supposed to be that if I want to
write a c program, I can have in Maine NRC Karis our RV and the
execution of my program will start there, right?
That is what's supposed to happen.
That's the definition of how a c program supposed to work.
It's in the standard.
That's just what happens, right?
Well unfortunately that has almost nothing to do with how windows.
Is actually runs executables at all.
Windows is not defined to conform to the C standard.
Window does his own operating system that has nothing to do with c and
in fact Pascal was probably a very common thing that Windows was
targeting originally.
If I remember correctly, in fact a lot of the really early Windows
stuff I think was Pascal targeted.
but neither here, nor there point being -
Such as an operating system, is a program that's running on the
computer.
It's the thing that needs to load and execute our executable.
Again, we'll talk about that a little bit later on when we get to
that, when we finally get to that point, but it has no interest in
specifying what ENT Main in our see.
Kara starts our RV has to do with anything, or how you call it or any
of that stuff.
So, actually, what happens is between the specification that Windows
lays down for our executables are supposed to run and the
Actual see specification of how compilation I'm sorry in, how
execution, and program starts as a supposed to start in between there,
there is a giant Golf and that Gulf is filled with code, from the C
standard Library, which Microsoft's compiler in order to make it
appear to be working when you just do in Maine in RTC and have the
program actually work, which it would in this case, right?
That Gulf is filled with runtime code that Microsoft's
Pilar will just plain stick in.
Okay.
So let's use dump bin, just to verify that this is going on again.
Remember I can do dis as mm, like I did before I can say main dot exe
and just ask it to give me the disassembly of that code.
Now what you will notice is it is massive, right?
All of this code, it just goes on and on and on and on and on and on
and on and on and all of that stuff is based on the
Fact again that Microsoft's compiler interprets your decision to try
and compile C code as an implicit request for the C runtime libraries
Preamble stuff, that allows you to get to Maine for that to be
included.
And that is all the code that you're seeing scrolling across three
right now.
It is the machine code that you are looking at, which has been
included for you.
That is all the C runtime, libraries set up stuff and
Preparation and thread will stuff and everything.
All that stuff is just getting welded in there for you, right?
You can't see it.
But that's actually what's happening and it's actually coming from dot
lib files which are files that the compiler has in its lib directory.
You can actually see in fact if we go back up here, you can see that
we've got this lib path here and there's all these sort of and lib
stuff where we've got these different path variables right.
Where
Microsoft is going to look at include and I think include in LeBar,
the two.
I think these two here.
It's going to look at these four pound include files automatically for
them.
It's also going to look for Libs automatically in here, right.
And what we can see if we want to, I believe I can sort of motivate
this a little bit better as you can see.
Well, okay, if I do this compile it succeeds, it's getting all this
code from somewhere.
We can tell that's true because we look at the file there's all this
code in there.
Where is it coming from?
Well, if
I want to, I can look at that, set lib and I see what that says there.
If I want to I could do like old lib equals lib, just get another, and
then set lib equal to nothing.
So now lib is just clear, right?
And I believe, now if I do the CL you'll see what I'm talking about.
So now I've done a CL here of Maine and Maine three that's to BP and
what you'll notice is the link failed this time.
Why did the link fail?
Well, the reason the linked fail is because now it
Can't find the code that it needed to insert because we took that
environment variable away that it was actually using, implicitly
didn't tell us anything about it but it was implicitly using that as a
search path to look for the C standard.
Libraries dot lib file, right?
But we don't want any of that now.
Right so now you can see if I take away at search path so the compiler
doesn't know where to find the libs.
It's like, hey I can't link my dude you know I can't find the
Runtime Library code and I need that code.
I implicitly link with it.
That's how I get to Maine DOT to Maine in RC car, starts our RV.
So, you know, you know, help me out here, right?
So the first step that we want to take because we're trying to
investigate this from first principles is we need to stop the compiler
from inserting a bunch of code that it wants to insert into our code.
And instead, tell the compiler to Just Produce an executable with only
our code right?
As close as possible.
Just take the object files that we gave you and produce just our code.
That's all we want, right?
So, the first thing that I think we can do here and I
It's always a bit of an archaeological process to get rid of the
default library, but let's go ahead and just try it.
We can always look it up.
See here, if I can find anything in here, ignore the default Salerno.
That's not what we want.
Omit default Library name, no enable, try gasps, no off by default.
No, Richard bugging fishing.
No send report.
No, no and no.
So unfortunately, in here, we don't have what we want.
So we're just going to have to wing it.
I believe it's no default lib.
Yeah, so when we actually get now we're going to we kind of have to
start talking about the different stages here, but that's okay because
this is act what I want to do.
So what I want to do now is I want to create a new basically, a new
build up at file where we're actually going to control the compilation
a little bit more succinctly here.
Right?
And so, you know what I'll do to is let me let me just go ahead and
make a like a dummy file here.
Bill.
Dot bat.
okay, and so this build up bat file,
What I'm doing going to do here is I'm going to sort of motivate this
by just showing how to do these steps individually and control each of
them individually.
So that again, because that's another thing I want to get do so on our
way to removing it.
Here's what I want to do.
Previously, we're specifying everything on one line and I was sort of
saying, well what's happening is through sneeze obj files and it's
calling the Linker let's do that manually now so we can see each
individual step and control each individual step, right?
So what I want to do in this case is I want to only
Output.
The C file.
I don't want to link, right?
I just want to say take in take an input translation, unit and produce
an obj from it, right?
That's the only thing that I want to do and I should be able to do
that by like a there's there's usually a switch for this again.
I never remember what these switches are because you do them once and
you put them in your ear.
Batch file menu, forget what they are.
So let's see.
Let me see if I can
Here.
For link?
No, there it is.
So it's I thought it was /c, but they look the such / lowercase C.
So you can see compile only no link.
So, if I want to, I can make in any one of these cases, I can say, oh,
compile main.cpp.
But what I want you to do is I want you to only I want you to only
produce the obj file.
So you can see that all it does in this case, it's reduce that one obj
file.
So in fact, if
If I delete all the obj's here, right?
So all my obj's are gone and now I do CL / C main.cpp.
You can see that, the only thing it did was reduce the obj.
So now we are in a position to actually be able to manually control
each step of the process and see it.
So we can say, all right, what I want you to do is produce, you know,
that obj.
I want you to produce this.obj, right?
And so if I do this, and I do a build, it does each of those red, it
produces both obj's.
And now what I can do is I can specify a link line, right?
So I'm actually going to invoke the Linker myself rather than letting
CL do it for me, right?
And what I can pass to the link line, is my to obj's, I can say, I
want you to link those two obj's.
And now we've gotten back right to the place we were before where I'm
like, I link these two obj's and it's like, I can't find my default
library because I nuked, it, slid path.
It can't find them, right?
It has no idea where they are.
Okay, so we now know that no default lib can be specified to the
Linker and to tell it to stop actually providing the C runtime Library
as something that it's going to link to right.
So now if I do my build I should get
Well, if you do exactly what I expected to do which is give me errors
based on stuff that it doesn't know how to do because it doesn't have
the C runtime Library more, right?
And that's okay.
So now we're down to a situation where we only have to deal with our
own code, but we have some issues.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to eliminate our
floating-point code because there's this thing called float used,
which is a way I don't really want to get into what this is right now.
This is a separate issue that has to do with just removing the C
runtime Library.
Basically, what it is is it's a way of the C runtime Library
The way for the compiler to signal that floating Point operations were
used in the course of compilation, it's has nothing to do with the
stuff that we're talking about.
Now, it's really better left for the subject of how to compile without
the C runtime Library, which is not what I want to get into.
So all I'm going to do is just leave that out for now and focus just
on the parts we actually care about right?
Because if you don't use floating point, you don't have that problem.
So we can talk about that some other, some on, some of the stream.
So, what you can see now is we've got our build
Working.
And I also wonder if I can maybe quiet down the compiler a little bit
here, in the case of keeps doing our this sort of over over, you know,
overly aggressive Preamble of printing out and stuff and I think you
kind of all get the point by now and let's see quiet, you know.
Let's see.
How do I get you to stop printing out the version?
Look like I really I know that I can you know what, let's take a look
at quickly at the build-up at and handmade mirror because I know that
I look this up before no logo, that's what we're looking for.
All right, so I'm also going to stick no logo in there.
Guess I'll also use this format.
Well I'll use a slash that's really the more Windows command line.
Way to do things.
All right.
Okay, so here we can see the steps occurring.
Here's the main.cpp compilation, here's the main three dot CPP
compilation, which again, this main.cpp, one includes main to.
So this is the translation unit.
No transition at those two.
Now we have the link line.
It can't find main CRT startup and now we're at the part that I
actually wanted to talk about next, which again, is that executable
loading and Running part of things, okay?
So what Windows is going to do is it is going to, you know, it's the
thing that runs the code, right?
It's the it's the thing that's running on the operating system that
booted that you booted into, it's the code that's running right now.
So in order to load and run an executable, it, what it has to do first
is it has to map that executable into memory somehow
Again, we don't really care how that's not really the point of this
particular investigation.
So we just care that it gets into memory somehow which it will and
then it needs to know where to start, right?
It needs to know how do I start executing the code in this executable,
right?
It needs a place.
And so what's going to happen with the Linker?
Is the Windows executable file format, right?
Because windows again, defines the file format for an x z how the
codes laid out stuff that Windows XP file format contains in it
information about how to know where to start.
So what's going to happen is Windows, is going to load the executable.
It's going to look at the information that's in the executable that
window.
Specifically defined to be in there.
It's going to pull out of that table.
Where am I supposed to start?
And it's going to point the exit the execution pointer.
Of the processor at that line of code and go right?
That's what's going to happen.
So what that means is, the Linker has to be able to produce that part
of the code, which says, here is you know, that that part of the
executable, which says, here's the address, here's the location, the
executable that you're supposed to start at windows, so start there
and the the convention that they've used for that is to say, well,
main CRT start-up is the name.
We will look for if we are not
Not told otherwise in order to start up, right?
And what you can see hopefully somewhere here.
Let's see, is the function signature for it?
Although I don't actually see the function signature for it.
Can you please msdn?
Tell me the fuck I just want to see the function signature.
But of course, it doesn't seem to tell me.
I just want the function signature just want the function signature.
Well, alright.
Hey.
Oh Windows.
Well I don't know where the function signature for this is but I don't
really care because I can easily find out, right?
All I really have to do if I want the function signature is I can just
look at what the C runtime Library defines the function signature, and
I can go from there.
So let's take a look at where is our simple?
We have like a test project right here, it is.
Here we go.
So here's our.
This is a test project that we had in handmade hero.
I'm just going to look at Main CRT startup.
What is it called?
And see if we can find it.
Probably I would have to change the type of project.
In this case, I guess I might have to even do a new one.
Let's see here.
Actually, you know what, I could do to?
I could just search for that in the C runtime Library.
So if I go through here and say, I don't need that folder, if I just
say, all right in program files, wherever this stuff ended up.
Let's see.
I can hear visual studio time Library.
So this is the source directory for the runtime Library.
It's going to say, tell me where that is.
All right.
So now in theory, I should be able to find this what the function
signature for main CRT startup is.
I just want positive confirmation of what it expects that thing to
look like.
And of course, we could just blindly guess, but let's see.
So here is mean CRT startup.
And looks like it.
Just does nothing, right?
It looks like there's no function.
Signature of there are no parameters passed to it, right?
That's what it looks like.
So I'm going to go with
That for now because we have a bunch of other stuff to talk about.
Okay, so here is our function, signature, I assume, although it
doesn't say what it returns as well.
Let's, let's actually take a look at that.
Here to means here to start up, and take a look and see what it
actually returns to me.
Answer it returns an integer.
So I'm going to turn it into juror as well.
Means here at you start up, okay?
Okay, so what we've done now is we've just conformed to the standard
or we haven't quite conform to certain, but we're close to conform to
the standard will still show.
There's one more thing involved here.
We've conform to the standard of what the Linker is looking for, as
the default entry point to the program, which it's going to look for
by name in the obj's, that it gets on the link line, it's going to
look for a main CRT startup function defined and if it finds one, it
will use that as the
Thing it puts in the executable that tells Windows here is where
execution will start right now.
Unfortunately, for us, that's really not going to quite comply and
that gets into the part of the obj's that I sort of said we're going
to talk about in a second and so now is the time that we will talk
about it.
So if I actually call the build here, what you can see is it still
says that the entry point must be defined and it's like well I thought
we defined the entry point.
I don't understand like what's going on here, right?
Something weird is happening.
Well the problem that we run into, if we look at what's defined in our
file is, if we look at these entry points we've got our 20 BJ's.
Let's take a look at what our end ostensibly.
The thing that defined main CRT startup what it actually.
Pain in the main dot obj, right?
Here's the disassembly for it.
Now, what you'll notice is actually the symbol main CRT startup has
not been defined anywhere.
The symbol we defined was question mark main CRT startup at at y HX Z,
right?
So now we have to ask the question, how do we Define an actual symbol
May answer to Startup?
And why the heck is what is this, right?
I glossed over it before.
What is this?
So now let's talk about what that is.
This is called C++ name mangling colloquially.
And what this is, is, remember early on, I sort of said, well in see
we didn't have function overloading.
Well, C++ does have function overloading and what that means is that
since
See, never allowed you to have more than one function with the same
name.
It's Linker was set up to just say, here's the name of a function.
And you call that function by name.
I can bind those two together, but when C++ came along that was no
longer sufficient, I can have many different versions of the same
function.
Foo one that takes an integer.
One that takes to care Stars.
One that takes a float.
One that takes a struct one that takes this but pop, right?
So what C++ did to continue backwards compatibility with existing see
linkers?
What's the just mangle the names of functions so that the name of the
function included markup that told you what its function signature
was?
So, this right here is a way of saying that it takes an integer,
right?
This right here is a way of saying it takes a void and that's what
that name mangling does.
What that means is that if an external program is trying to look at an
obj file in find a specific name.
If that name is compiled with C++ name mangling, it will not be found
because the name that it will actually be put under is some mangled
name that includes a bunch of stuff from the calling convention in the
type specification and all this other stuff.
so what we need to do is let the compiler, no, not the Linker, but the
compiler, that this particular function needs to be compiled compliant
with the sea
There's two ways we can do that.
One is we can put it in an extern, see block which tells it to just
use that, right?
And you can see what happens.
Now when I do it right there is my main CR to start up the other way
is we can tell it to do that just as a property of the function name
itself which I believe is just that right?
Nope.
Oh I know.
No.
Sorry, it's still extern.
See, that's just the calling convention.
It's that
Right.
And now we've actually got a main CRT startup that is actually defined
directly in the code, right?
Okay, so now we're in a good position to actually try to get these two
things to connect up.
And again, the only problem that we're going to face here is the
inability to find the correct what?
This should be correctly, defined as and I don't actually know because
again, I couldn't actually find that specifically, so let's just
double check.
Care when I tell it, we don't want that.
You notice we're getting an entry point.
Must be defined are now as opposed to a main CRT startup is not
defined.
So, in that particular in, let me, let me go ahead and here and just
take a look here.
We should find.
I think we need one additional thing here for their entry point is not
to find because I just want to again.
This is sort of a this sort of a compiler Linker sort of snafu here I
believe if we did this
And let's see here, / link.
No, default rib.
how do I do the
Never under I this this is the this is the part that always slows
everything down because we got to remember all the vagaries of this
particular compilers fun.
It's / lowercase.
Link /, lowercase link.
No default lip.
There we go.
Okay.
So again, at this point, now we're in the position of I just want to
make sure that this was, this was all happening correctly here.
So now we have to figure out how we're going to get the compiler to.
I'm sorry the Linker to recognize this as the entry point, which means
that the endpoint has to match.
Exactly.
It has to be named the right thing, and it has to take the right
variables as well.
So now we have to figure out how exactly were going to do that and
there's two parts to this.
So, the
first part is again you know lining up the thing correctly, but the
other part is which thing it's actually looking for so on Windows
there's
Two separate ways that it might look for the startup of the start of
the code.
The first way is, if you're trying to build an actual Windows
application, where it actually opens windows and stuff like this, the
second way is if you're building a console application and the Linker
actually has to specify, which of these two things you're doing in the
actual executable itself, and windows will load them differently,
based on which one you specify.
This is why I don't know if you've ever noticed this, this is a common
complaint of programmers and Microsoft has never fixed it to the semi
knowledge unless they finally did in Windows 10.
I don't know, I'm not familiar, very familiar with Windows 10, but at
least up through Windows 7.
There is no way to make an application, which when launched from an
icon in Windows in regular in the shell in the graphical user
interface does not pop
Up a console window.
And also, when run from a console window is able to Output text to
that console window via standard out.
There is no way to do it.
The reason is because this actually occurs in the actual executable as
a thing that windows will do differently depending on which one you
have, if you specify that, you are a console application, then when
you are run from the gooey, you will get a console window.
It will create one and you'll have it if you don't specify that and
your run from the console.
Will not get standard out, and there's nothing you can do about it.
So, people have tried to fake it by like, oh, finding your console
window and hiding it.
So you don't ever see the fact that it got created in stuff like this.
So they try to look approximate it, but there is no way to really do
it for real.
Unfortunately.
All right, so moving on from that.
How is that?
How is that specified?
Right?
What kind of these two, which of these two things?
Are we going to have?
Well, there's basically a thing called subsystem it's a switch to the
Linker and it tells the it what to put in the
executable to make that happen.
So you can see right here, here's the subsystems that are supported.
In our case, we only care about the ones for app level stuff, which is
console Windows, potentially, posix, we don't care about things like
EFI applications or boot applications things that are specific to
Hardware stuff.
And in our case, we could do windows or console
So what we could do here is say, well, you know, subsystem maybe is
Windows, right?
Maybe we want to make a regular Windows application.
Let's say that's what handmade hero does.
And so, let's see what happens when we when we do a build and what you
can see, is it now thinks that there's an unresolved external symbol
wind main CRT startup, right?
That's what it's looking for.
If we tell it, that's the subsystem if I switch the subsystem to
console now, it's actually works, right?
Why does it actually work?
Well, it actually works because now he knows
Knows what the default entry point should be.
And that default entry point is main crtc start-up.
If we hadn't have defined this,
Right.
It would complain about that instead so we need that subsystem line in
there to tell it which sort of startup code we wanted right.
Which kind of executable to Mark us as
And then we need to define the corresponding startup, but now that
we've defined all of that, we will actually get a working executable
and lo and behold are working.
Executable is now 1/40, the size that it was when it was shoving, the
C runtime library in that we didn't want.
And if we now look at what this looks like,
Under dis as mmm, it's quite proper, right?
You can see here, that this is our entire executable.
The, this is the, the entire package, the entire executable package of
it, you can see here that we've got three separate sort of functions
if you will.
And I want to kind of put these side by side so you can see how they
work and how that translation occurred.
So, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
Dump in our executable.
I'm going to dump in that executable out to Maine.
Exe dot as mm.
And then I'm going to dump our obj's.
So our main, our main obj, I'm going to just ask them that out and
then I'm going to also do our other translation unit out as well.
So here is the main three obj dot as mm.
Okay.
And so now what I'm going to do is I'm going to load those up so you
can see them.
M.
So cure I'm going to load, just me.
Here I'm going to load in all of those as in files.
So here is the executables as I'm file and you can see again this is
all of the information here.
That's the all of the code that's in there.
And then I'm going to load in here, the main obj dot, add some file,
and you know, here it is, right, and we'll look at that and then I'm
also going to load in that main 30 be treated as mmm.
So let's start with bar right here.
You can see the code for bar, and it's pretty obvious where this ended
up in our executable.
So, if we take a look down here, you can see that this code is pretty
much occurs verbatim, right?
Here's the RS.
P, + 8.
Here's the RSP 18h, right?
Here's the to RSP 20 HS.
Here's the d word pointer part, here's the eax, here's the RSV change,
here's the red.
Now that code exists verbatim.
Now why does that code exists for Batum?
Again, it
No, unresolved symbols.
So the only thing the Linker had to do when it saw this code, it just
had to find a place to put it in the executable, and cure is where it
put it, right?
So this is in our executable where it's stuck, the actual code, right?
That's just where to put it.
So now let's flip over to main, which has the rest of our azzam and
take a look at what happened there.
Here's our main CRT startup, we start up with an RSP 20.
Uh, you can see that that code is right here.
And now here's where things start to get.
Interesting, notice what happened to the call here is the call, right?
This is an instructor, this is an instruction of the processor to
Branch a way to separate piece of the code to execute it, and then,
come back.
This call is called the question.
Mark.
Fouad at why?
A h at Z, right?
And remember that is this code up here, right?
That is what that code is, right?
It's calling this code.
So it is going to have to put that code into the executable somewhere
and you can see that it did exactly that it put that code right here.
And so when the Linker smushed, these together and put the executable
together into one piece, you can see what it did is it.
Placed this symbol name, which is not useful to the processor because
CPUs have no idea what symbols are, they don't care.
They just want to see addresses it provided the address in the
executable where that code could be found and that is where this code
went.
You can also see that when this code wanted to call bar again a symbol
that was not known at the time of compilation, it replaced it with the
address of the of the code that was in a different compilation unit.
Remember,
Which is right here.
Okay.
So hopefully now you can see the complete process of assembly that
goes from compilation where you take translation units which are some
collection of files as matter what they are.
Some collection of files that can be interpreted as C code or C++ code
go from that source code to an obj file.
This is what an obj file looks like it's object code.
It's basically like machine machine instructions, where a bunch of
things have been left undetermined and just have names and their
places, right?
If then all of those
Is object files, are then synthesize together to produce a single
executable, which can be loaded by the operating system that
executable has all of the addresses resolved internally, right?
Okay, so hopefully everyone is comfortable with what's happening
there.
Now, there's a bunch of stuff in here.
That you probably don't understand very well.
All of this Preamble code and stuff.
Like this is maybe very unfamiliar to you because you don't program
Assembly Language.
You don't know what it is.
Hey no surprise there, I don't program in Assembly Language either.
So you know again it's definitely not the sort of thing that we're
used to reading but we're going to have to get a little bit more
familiar with it to complete the cycle here, hopefully everyone's on
board with the so far, hopefully nothing that I've said.
Ed so far is super mysterious.
Now that we've gone through every step of the process, you can see how
compilation goes from text files, on your hard drive to object code to
an executable.
Now, we just have to talk about what actually happens when the
executables actually run and how it might be partitioned into multiple
pieces that can get dynamically linked, so that we can finish
answering the questions posed by the email that I originally received
again.
Most of those questions we can now answer that we actually have
Look at exactly what's happening in the code and understand literally.
What's going on?
Not in some figurative, kind of language way, that is detached from
reality.
We can actually look at the reality of what's happening in the
processor.
Okay.
So now let's get to function pointers.
Right, let's get to actual function pointers because that is the place
that we kind of started this discussion, from where we, what we want
to discuss and all of this stuff was kind of necessary to discuss
those things.
We have two separate ways that we need to talk about function pointers
because one of them is completely Dynamic and one of them is slightly
less, so right?
And so we need to talk about those in a little bit more detail.
The first thing we need to talk about is just function pointers inside
regular code and that's the one we'll do first because the easiest to
talk about because we don't need to start involving windows in our
business.
The second one is the one that's a little more advanced which is what
happens when we're actually dealing with multiple executable.
Sort of entities like xzs dlls Windows system, libraries itself, those
are two things.
What happens at that point, when we're talking about different
executable modules, essentially calling each other run,
What's happening there?
So, let's leave that for the second part of the inquiry.
And we'll just focus on what happens in an individual program.
What goes on when we are actually calling functions right by pointer.
Okay, so hopefully, this point, everyone is comfortable with what
happens when you call things.
Not by a function pointer, right?
When you're just calling things by a function name in see, you have
seen exactly what happens.
So there is no mystery anymore.
It just puts the symbol into the
It file.
And then later the Linker resolves, that symbol to it hard coded
address.
That is related to where it is in the executable.
Now, there is a little bit of hand waving there because when that
executable is loaded into memory, this address is relative to where
the executable was loaded.
So it is worth noting that there is a little bit of fun there.
Where either the processor itself has to have the understanding of a
relative call where when you load in an executable you can call
relative to
Location.
So, it doesn't matter where in memory, you loaded it or the executable
has to always be loaded in a known Base address.
So that the hard coded addresses are the actual addresses that are in
memory, or when the executable is loaded, it has to patch the call
sites.
So that all of the call sites that are absolute are shifted based on
the loaded Base address of the executable.
And that requires a fix-up table.
That requires that, the executable having a fix-up table that says,
well, they all are
Right?
So there is actually a step that you have to consider that is about
how those addresses are translated into actual memory, addresses
later.
But you can understand how there's many ways that that could be
approached depending on the option and that's operating system and CPU
dependent, how those will work.
Right?
But you can understand the compilation process.
Now pointers are taken out of the equation to a certain extent and
we're literally hard-coding addresses, or we just like this is the
location to jump to.
Now, write for this call.
So what happens we want to investigate now is what happens in code
when we stop talking about jump to a specific function and we start
talking about a jump to a pointer which could be pointing to, to any
you know, number of functions potentially
So, let's get started.
Going back to actually I guess I'm reading my text editor.
I'm used to seeing this.
I'm in the bunker must be in the bunker.
No, you're not mad about her.
You're looking at this as in files.
So if I come back here to my main.cpp, my translation unit here, what
I want to do now is I want to start looking at the potential for what
I can do with function pointers.
Right.
And so what I want to do is I want to have the ability to call more
than one function or something like this and so I want to start
talking about how do I, how do I what happens in the compiler when I
have these function pointers?
So the first thing I need to do is be able to take the address of a
function.
But you know what, I don't really even need to do very much to do
that, right?
If I want to, I could say, let's create a void Star, right?
Because here, I got my call to fou, right?
Let's create a void star, I'm going to call that.
Star function pointer, right?
And I'm going to take as the value of function pointer, I'm just going
to take food, right?
That's what I'm going to do and I want to compile it.
Now what you'll notice is that actually worked right.
There was no errors involved there.
That actually worked and if I want to, I can take a look at what the
disassembly is of that particular.
Module.
Now here it is and what you can see happening is literally that exact
same that exact operation is occurring, right?
So let's take a look at what's going on here.
Here is the call to Foo, right?
And what you'll notice, is that call to Foo is using the symbol,
remember, right?
The it's, it doesn't know where that is yet.
It's using the symbol for food.
Now, granted when I say it doesn't know where that is, yet it does
know.
Out food because through is defined in this translation unit.
What it doesn't know is where the Linker it's going to put Foo right
because the linkers allowed to move this around and put it anywhere it
wants in the ending executable.
So it can't put in a hard coded address here because it doesn't know
where it's going to put it, right?
So it just puts in the symbol and says, hey when you mr.
Linker, when you decide where you're going to put Foo, you know, go
ahead and and patching that address here because I need to call it
right.
What you can see happening immediately after that is the the leaa
instruction which is a load-bearing
Basically is going to move to our ax.
There's a register in the processor, it's going to move in the that
same address.
Exactly where it was going to call.
It's going to move in that address to our ax, right?
Ed minutes, going to store.
It's going to turn around and store that to RS b.
+ 20 H.
Now RSP is the stack pointer.
So RFP plus 20 H is just the location of this function pointer Star,
right?
This it doesn't appear in here by name because it's a symbol that
nobody is referring to.
Right.
The compiler in general doesn't output names to the Linker, that would
just be extraneous.
So if nobody ever
Needs to refer to function pointer outside.
The scope of the function, that's being compiled, they don't get
names, they'll in the debug information, they'll get names because the
debugger needs to be able to inspect, by those names.
But the Linker doesn't need to see any of that other than in the debug
info, right?
So that's just not placed in there.
Now, what we could see though is, if we moved this function out to a
global variable, now, it does have a name
Right.
It does have a name because people can refer to that Global variable,
right?
If I was to do that now,
And I may need to decorate that a little bit to make sure, but I don't
think so.
Yeah.
If we would do that now, it becomes even more explicit.
Now you can see what it's saying to.
The Linker is, hey, call this function Foo, I don't know where it's
going to end up.
Just make sure wherever you put it, you're going to tell me what the
address is.
Okay, that's this line here, right?
Then I've got okay go load that address, you know what put that in a
register then store the contents of that.
So whatever.
Whatever this address is this now in our ax store that out to This
Global variable function pointer blah blah blah.
Right?
I don't know where that's going to be because again, the linkers free
to decide where the global variables go, when it's defining the sort
of the layout of the running executable, but wherever that's going to
be, that's where you need to put it, right.
So you can see Now function pointers in this initial sense are no
different than any other pointer in this initial sense.
All that's going to happen when you refer to a function by its name in
a context where it
Needs to know that address.
As if it was a pointer is you will literally just get the pointer.
It's just a pointer like any other pointer, right?
It points to some memory that memory happens to be in the mapped
memory where the executable code itself, resides and off you go,
right?
So that is exactly what will happen in this case.
And so in that way, a function pointer is no different than any other
pointer.
It's the same as a tent pointer.
It's the same as anything else and one of the things that
The person who wrote the email referred to was the fact that it was
confusing.
When you look in the debugger, he found that he was not actually able
to inspect the value of the function pointer.
And in that way, it was different, that integer that is strictly a
function of the fact that the debugger is is not showing you.
It right.
Actually, you could do that.
You can dereference a function pointer and see what's actually there.
Let's
Ruben right, let's prove that it's no different.
Now, what I'm going to do is I'm going to load this code, okay?
And I need to do a little bit first because I'm we're going to need
debug info.
So I'm going to go here to build that bat and I'm going to try and get
some debug info here.
I believe /zi is the thing that would direct it to produce debug info
for us, but I'm not entirely sure.
So I'm just going to hope that that's the case.
Let's take a look at that mean to object.
Again, you can see this code.
Here is the main Dobbs.
I'm going to invoke developer Studio here on our main dot exe and hope
that I have some debug information again.
I don't know that I do, we'll see I might need to tell the Linker
about it so I don't actually have the debug of well you know what
though?
Why do we care?
We're looking at the assembly.
I don't even care.
I don't even need to preserve do again for a forget.
It doesn't matter.
It's not important.
Alright, so here we are at the start of our code.
I'm in the debugger.
We're at the start of our coat and by now, even though you probably
don't know, Assembly Language, maybe you have no idea what assembly
languages at all really, but you can sort of see from what I'm talking
about.
You, at least have the pattern matching.
As I think the person originally wrote in called it, you have the
patterns, you know, this is the code, right?
We're looking at it right here.
Here's a code.
Even though I have no idea what these things mean, I can see it's the
same code, right?
And the only difference is the place where food was actually talked
about, right?
It's here.
It is, right?
It's been inserted that address has been inserted in place of the
symbol Foo.
I've have the address, right?
And so what I want to sort of underscore here.
So a couple things we can look at that are pretty interesting.
Actually, let you know.
Let me make a brief digression here.
Just to point out here is my main dot exe and one of the things that
you'll notice about this mean dot exe is you can see that actually the
thing that I was talking about before that relative addressing is
kicking in here where it's been relocated.
You can see that the actual addresses where we have been loaded, are
not the addresses that were filled in here.
It's slightly different, right?
You can see, this is 13 FF.
It's not 1,400 or whatever, right?
It is not the same addresses.
Let's let's load this one more time, right?
Notice anything suspicious suspicious?
I'm going to load this many times.
You see what's happening here, right?
These addresses change every run of the program.
Why do these addresses change every run of the program?
Well, there's the thing in Windows address.
Space layout, randomization my zation.
There we go.
A SLR address space layout.
Randomization is a technique.
That is designed to try to improve Security on your computer
basically, by making sure that hackers can't know the locations of
things in executables when they are running.
So if you imagine what would happen,
Right?
And this is true of older all older operating systems for the most
part and, you know, then windows and a bunch of Linux and stuff.
They start implementing address space layout.
Randomization as a sort of exploit mitigation tool originally, it was
generally the case that most of the time, if you load an executable,
you were going to get it loading at the same place.
It always loads like an executable just loads at a particular location
and the actual might even have been optimized to load at that location
by having all of the addresses hard-coded into
It or something like this, right?
Without even a fix-up table to fix them or maybe all the call
instructions were relative.
So it didn't have to hard code addresses.
It just hard coded offsets and so at that point it was fine, who
knows, right?
Well, what ends up happening in here without us for space layout.
Randomization is every time Windows loads or executable it picks a new
location in memory to load it.
At, because remember, virtual memory is such that Windows pretty much
picks, your address range for you, it can just say Here's Where in the
virtual address space, your executable going to be loaded, you have
potentially no saying that so it can move it all around, right?
And so every time we run we get different addresses.
So really the only thing that we know is that the actual effective
Address of all of our functions will be filled in in all of the
places, either by patching or because they were relative, the
instructions were encoded to be relative calls, you know, this is like
I said some processors support relative branching of certain sizes.
Some don't, it has to have it.
Bubba Bubba, Bubba, regardless of what that mechanism is all we know
is that will actually get the address of wherever it is in this run of
the program that may not be the same location in every run of the
program because of address.
Space layout randomization.
Okay.
So what we can see here, when we're coming through, here is the code,
we know exactly what code that is.
Like I said, we it's kind of cool.
We don't need the debug information because we just know what code
we're looking at.
We're looking at this code right here, right?
And so, what we can see when we step through this code is the
processor is doing exactly what I said I was going to do it's taking
the address of the function Foo, right?
Which has been filled in in this place right here and you can see it
loading it into the are eax register.
If I look at the registers here's our ax, it's a 64-bit register.
It's going to load that in and lo and behold there is the address of
Foo right there, and now it's going to move it out to the stack at
this location, right?
It's going to move our X2, I'm sorry.
A stock.
It's going to move it to our Global variable, which is this right here
that remember, I switched it.
I almost forgot that I switched it.
Oops.
To This Global variable function pointer, right?
And so I'm going to go to go do that.
And so now at that memory location, there is now a pointer that's
holding that that address that RX address.
That's what's happening.
Right now.
What I wanted to show you is you were saying that oh this this pointer
seems different than in pointer that's strictly because the debugger
Know how to show you a function if you dereference an integer, it
knows how to show you the integer, the debugger for whatever reason in
the watch, window doesn't think to show you disassembly, that's what
it should do, right?
It should show you the instruction at that point, if you try to
dereference a function pointer, it should show you the function, the
first line of code potentially at that point, right?
But I can prove to you that they're still the same kind of function
pointer because let's see exactly what happens.
Here's the address, right?
This is the address right here.
I'm going to look in a memory window and I'm going to paste that
address in.
In right?
And here we go.
This is I'm sorry.
Paste pick the wrong one.
That's the address of our function pointer.
This is the actual address that was loaded into the function pointer
which is the one that we want to look at, right?
So this is where that function pointer is actually pointing, right?
It's pointing here.
And we know that this should be the contents of food, right?
And if we take a look back at our disassembly, where is our food?
Let's see.
Don't bend this as them.
It should be the one at the top there, but I just want to make sure
that we've got it.
Here it is.
This is this is what food is supposed to look like, right?
It's supposed to look like, you know, this instruction, this
instruction, this instruction, this instruction, right?
So is our pointer is our function pointer that, we just snapped.
Is it actually pointing to?
This is it pointing is it just pointing to this memory which is like I
said, it should be exactly like an integer pointer.
It should just be pointing at some memory and the contents of that
memory should be a bunch of bytes that encode the function.
Well, how would we know if that was the case?
Well, it just so happens that disassemblies helpfully include the code
B in the corner.
These are the B 8, 9 4, C 2408.
That encode, this move instruction.
That is the Intel x64.
Well, I guess it should say MDX is before us and say to find the exit
divorced and
But it's partially the x86 standard obviously there you know it's the
extended xa6 for x86 instruction set for 64-bit so it's AMD Intel you
might say those are the code B that correspond to this move
instruction.
These are the code B that correspond to this move instruction blah
blah blah blah.
All the way down to here where we haven't really encoded the B because
we don't know what we should put here.
We know what the symbol is, but we don't yet know what the bites are.
So we would expect them to differ right here.
Because instead of having a symbol fix up, what we would expect to see
here is the actual address.
So, is that what we have?
89 for a see 2408 894 su-24.
Alright, 483 EC3 84-88, right?
Blah, blah blah blah, blah.
All the way down to the 8bc 88, where are we a PC 8th, right?
And now instead of all zeros, what we expect to see is the actual
address of something to call and we do for B 0 0, 0, 0 8, I Bubba,
right,
So again, function pointer in.
As far as she is concerned is the same as any other pointer in terms
of what the processor is actually going to do with that piece of
memory write, whenever you're referring to a function pointer, it's
just a piece of memory that will store an address.
That address is the first bite of the code encoding in x64 machine,
code of the stuff to do, right?
And
we can even take this one step further just to make sure that that
let's just go nuts.
Just in case, you don't believe anything that I said and you can't
really tie it back.
If you're just like, I don't know what you're talking about.
Like I did, this is, I don't get it.
I just don't understand, right?
Let's just make this 100% explicit.
Just how interchangeable these things are.
Okay, so now what I'm going to do is going to back up a little bit,
hopefully, all the stuff.
Up translation units and all that sort of stuff has sunken.
I'm just going to stop mentioning that stuff anymore and we're just
going to work in this one file, right?
And I suppose I should have left that include in because we got rid of
it there.
My bad.
So I suppose, what I can do here, just say let's let's sort of clean
this this away now, right?
And let's make something a little bit more straightforward.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to have just in our one
translation unit.
I'm going to put a couple going to put two different things in there,
right?
So I'll leave that stuff in place so that we can talk about it later
if you want to.
But I'm going to, I'm going to create a very simple thing.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to create
A piece of code here that will produce some value.
And let me, let me feel figure out how I want to make this work in the
in the sanest way possible.
So here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to create a piece of code that just returns a constant
value.
That's it right?
That's all it does.
I'm gonna call it five.
and the only piece of code in five,
Is return five.
That's it, right?
Then what I'm going to do is I'm going to have a global integer here.
I'm going to have a global integer and I'm going to have a little
bunch of jerk.
All'd number
and delete this for now.
And I'm going to set number.
In fact, I guess I don't really need it to be global.
No, leave it global.
Equal to the result of calling five.
That's I'm going to do right, simple enough.
And now I'm going to step into that code.
And here we are.
Well this is the entirety of our program.
It's not particularly exciting.
Is it all we're doing set up the stack frame initially again,
Sub R SP that you see all over the place.
All that's doing is giving yourself 28 hex.
So 0, x, 28 worth of Stack space.
You're just moving the stack pointer down by that much.
It's not relevant to what we're doing right now.
This its stack frame stuff, we haven't really talked about yet and I
don't know that we really want to get into that yet, then we're going
to call this function right.
And that function is 5 and we can again let's just just so everyone
could see it.
Let's let's do the this awesome again.
Here's the dis Azam you can see our startup code again.
Sets up that stack frame, it calls.
The five function here is the five function up there.
We're going to do our mob right in our mom's going to take whatever
five returned.
And again, the reason that this is the return of five here is because
the definition in x64 What's called the a bi or application binary
interface.
It's the way that function signatures are expected to work the return
value.
If it will fit in in RX e, ax.
That is where it goes.
It stays in a register so it doesn't put it
Stack, the return value?
Just comes back in a register.
So what's going to happen is we're going to call five, were expecting
five to put 5 into a register or threatening to put in eax.
So when it comes back, we're going to copy whatever.
It was that that return five, right?
We're going to put it into number three.
Aha here.
Which is that Global variable?
We're going to move it in there.
Okay, that's all we're doing.
Hopefully everyone's on board with that.
Here we go set up the stack frame going to call here's our function.
That's the function.
It just puts five in eax and returns.
That's all it does, right?
So there we go, put five NEX return and now we're going to move the
resulting X and we can see in the registers.
There's ETA X.
ETA X is the bottom.
Half of our e^x e^x is 3 is the 32 bit.
Register name the wait until registers work is you have 16-bit 32-bit.
64-bit sort of registers that grow.
So if I want to I think you can refer to B.
So it's got like each individual one of them.
So if I want to refer to just the bottom half in this case an inch is
32 bits.
Eax is what it's called if I wanted to I could I can even ask it for
that in the watch window and you can see it Returns the bottom half of
that, right?
And it's fine.
So anyway, we're putting that into our X.
You can see that they're in the bottom half.
There's the five that we moved in there, right?
It's all good.
And then we're going to move that out to This Global variable here,
which is that Global variable?
And I can, I can watch that Global variable even without debug info.
I can just tell it.
Hey, by the way, that's an integer right at that location.
So why don't you go ahead and why can't I paste?
Cut paste.
There we go.
So, I can just go ahead and say, by the way, that's an integer.
And if we look at what's in the integer, you'll notice at startup.
It's nothing, right?
But after I execute this mob instruction, it has moved that five in
there.
And so now we're we have correctly, put five in there, which is what
we'd expect.
Alright, that is all hopefully everything that we
Today, all of the work we've done today should lead up to this point.
You should be completely comfortable with what happened there.
Except for this one sub stack bit here because we haven't talked about
the stack, but hopefully this part the call, right?
The getting the five I put in there.
It should not be very mysterious at this point, right?
Okay.
So, just to prove to you that the function pointer is literally just
that it's just that function pointer.
Now, we will go ahead and actually do some Shenanigans with it.
So you can see that it really is just a pointer to a block of memory.
Okay, so what do we need to do first?
Well, implicit in all of this, as you can see, is the fact that c
needs to understand how to call a function, and there's a lot of
aspects to how to call a function, the first aspect you've seen, and
it's the only one we're dealing with here.
I wanted to keep it simple is.
Where does the return value end up?
And what is that, return value, right?
In this case, it's just an integer.
So it knows that the return value would go in eax.
How does it know that?
It knows it because of the Avi, right?
And an Avi station, binary interface and ABI you can look up its this
this thing right here.
What an ABI is is it's a thing where people get together in this a.
All right, look
We've got the operating system, we've got user mode code, we've got
multiple compilers, we've got multiple languages.
All of this stuff has to call each other.
Maybe someone wrote A C library and it's got a call python, maybe
python has to call Pearl.
Maybe Pearl has to call in to the operating system and maybe the
operating system has to call back to some C code.
All of these people need to have an understanding if they're going to
work together about how functions are called and how return values
come back, right?
This is just a fundamental aspect of programming and it needs to be
obeyed because if it didn't you couldn't have anyone call anyone else.
Any given compiler could call code that it wrote itself, because it
knows how it's going to do stuff like, where it's going to put
parameters, and where the return values come back.
Remember that stuff is not specified at the processor.
Level.
A processor is just a machine that has registers and memory accesses.
It doesn't specify anything about how a function is called other than,
perhaps, some slight bias towards.
For example, the call instruction may be automatically, pushes the
location where things were executing previously on to the stack first,
so that a ret instruction will automatically pull them off or
something like this.
And we're going to look at that in a little bit.
But that's it.
So, all the other stuff about like, oh, where does the first float go
that you pass?
And where does the first ant go and what if I pass a structure where
do all the members go?
What if I pass a pointer to a structure?
What happens, right?
All of that stuff is defined in the ABI.
So once you understand the ABI you understand how functions are
called.
So fortunately for us, we don't really need to understand very much
about the Avi unless we're actually
Using machine code which were not really doing here in most cases in
handmade hero, certainly we're not.
But when we look at the assembly, it's important to understand that
the assembly we're looking at is generated that way because it is
complying with the ABI it is using the stack it is using the registers
and is using them in a way that complies with someone specific
definition of how code was supposed to call other code on this
platform.
This operating system and everyone is supposed to obey it, right?
Right?
So Linux lays down the law for Linux.
It says, anybody who's operating in our ecosystem.
This is how you're going to call stuff.
Just get it straight, right?
Or something.
And again, they have to do it for each processor type, they support as
well because the processors differ so whether you use a register or
stack or memory or whatever, right?
That stuff has to be defined per processor because the process differ.
But for all x 64 processors, for example.
Here's a bi and everyone has to obey.
Okay, so,
We know that the Linker is going to obey the ABI so we know that no
matter what we tell it to do in C, it's going to figure out a way to
do that properly in machine code.
That's great.
We don't have to worry much about that, but we do have to worry about,
is the compiler itself.
When it's actually going to go, like, process our code, it needs to
know what to, you know, basically how to do the code gen to conform to
the ABI for whatever function call we're doing, which is why it needs
to see a function signature, it needs to see the function signature so
it knows.
How to set up the call stack and the return value information so that
it can properly call the function, right?
It needs to know that information.
So, that is where we get to the weird typedef, part of C, right?
So let's say that I do avoid star.
Function.
Equals 5.
We know this works.
We know this takes the address of five and puts it into void star
function, right?
And now I want to call it
Well, I can't write and the reason I can't is specifically, I get a
compile error.
The reason I can't is for no other reason than it, simply does not
understand how to conform to an ABI.
When it doesn't know a function signature, it doesn't know what it's
supposed to return.
It doesn't know what arguments that supposed to pass, or what they
look like.
So, there's nothing it can really do.
If it just has a void star, it can't call a function because it
doesn't know what that function signature would be right.
So what we need to do is tell it
What the parameters are.
And what the return value is because this syntax in C is telling it to
treat this as a pointer to a function and we'll put the arguments in
here.
This syntax is function called syntax when it sees something with open
close parenthesis, that's a function call.
Could do this, it could call this location that part.
It knows what it doesn't know.
Is what's coming back?
How do I create code that obeys?
The ABI maybe I can infer because this is closed with nothing in it
that there's no arguments.
Okay.
But I don't know what it returns.
I know you're assigning it to an integer, but maybe it returns a short
and a short to an integer conversion would be okay.
Here maybe it returns a whole struct and this is an error.
I don't know.
I really don't know what to do.
Do so what we need to do is we need to give it enough information so
that it can properly generate the code that conforms to the ABI.
And furthermore again, since we're in C++, some of the information
we're giving, it isn't strictly for composite complying with the ABI.
It's actually also there to do error checking.
So that we don't try to call a function in a completely incorrect way,
right?
Okay.
So that's where the typedef stuff comes in.
The typedef stuff comes in to give us a function signature in a way
that we can use, so that we can do stuff like
Calling functions.
So if I say into, you know, number function,
What I've done here is, I've typed F the function signature so that I
can now use it to say.
This is the kind of function that I have, right?
This is the kind of function that I'm pointing to.
And again, nothing has changed in the code at all.
At this point on this line, I am still just moving in address into
this, this function pointer.
That's all I'm doing.
The only difference is I have now given the compiler at compile time.
The information it needs to know how to generate code conformant to
the ABI, to generate the preamble to the call instruction, that will
successfully set up the stack frame and the return stuff about
processing for this function, right?
Okay, so now we can pile and we get code that actually should work.
We can step in here again.
I'll show you the dis azzam here, just as we've been doing, you can
see it exactly as it goes before we do a call here.
And now, the only change has been we load in the address first and
then we store that address to a place on the stack, right?
And this again is just because the code is not optimized, we would
probably just call straight out or something similar.
Although maybe we wouldn't because we you know RX is going to get
destroyed by their turn.
So maybe it wouldn't who knows point being what the code does here?
Is this loading the address of the function to call its then storing
that to the stack at the location?
This is the space on the stack that was created to store our local
variable.
It's a space that was created to store function, right?
So this is function, it's then going to call it.
And again I can continue my trend of putting these AS Global
variables.
So they become name so you can see that, right?
If I compile now, oops.
If I can pile now and then do this step, you can see exactly what's
Happening.
Here I load in to eat too.
Ax the location of the function.
I store that location out to my function pointer.
I am going to call through my function pointer right which will call
out to here.
It will put 5 in eax.
I will then move that into X into my number my Global variable and I
am done right?
And again we can look at the at that happening in the debugger one
step at a time.
Right here we go.
I'm going to load in that address.
I'm going to move that.
Address out to the location on the stack.
That is
Corresponding to that Global variable function pointer, I'm going to
call through that function pointer.
And you can see now that I've arrived there, right?
And you'll notice this is the function pointers location.
So I'm calling through that pointer that's what this bracket syntax
this keyword pointer bracket syntax means it means look up.
What's the address at this address?
Don't Branch to this actual address so it's going to get this that we
stored there.
It's going to use that and Branch through it, right.
The until x64 is crazy, sis constructions that can do stuff like go
fetch a piece of memory.
And call in one instruction, right?
That's just Intel's encoding for you.
It's a cyst style encoding.
So anyway, we're going to Branch up there.
You can see we do we move into eax, exactly as you expect, there's
that eax.
We hit the ret, here we come down here and we do them off to put into
our Global variable the value.
And now, if we were to look at this value as we did before we would
see.
Oops, again, we would see that it was
Five as we expected, right?
No big mystery here.
All I have done is shown how to call through that function pointer.
Again, it's exactly the same as if we adjust inserted 5 here.
Except now, instead of calling having that call site, be patched
during the link phase to actually point to a specific location in the
executable instead, what it's doing is it's creating code that's
taking that same past address.
It is still patching hours.
Instead of patching.
The address at the call site it's taking that address the Linker is
putting that
To code that loads it into a global variable and then it's calling
through the global variable.
Hopefully you saw that happen.
Nothing, no, nothing weird, right?
It all makes pretty good sense to you, right?
Okay.
Again, let me show you
Yet one more way, just how unmiss terius this really is, let's
suppose.
We just want to make our own function.
I don't even have this anymore.
It's gone.
Okay.
I want to do that.
And if I wanted to do that, I need something here.
I don't know.
I need some kind of thing for my function, right?
So how would I go about doing that?
Well, we have the compiled version of this function, right?
I mean we've got it.
So let's suppose I step here and I go, well, this is the code for for
that function, right?
I mean, this is the code, it's be 80.
5000 C3.
That's the code.
Right?
But that that's it.
I mean, I can look at this location in memory in the memory watch
window, right?
I don't have to believe the disassembler and here it is.
So that's the code for five that just just, that's just the code
period.
There's nothing else to say about it.
That's the code.
So this is literally, and I'm going to just cut and paste it out.
Here this function 5 literally compiles to this byte sequence.
Okay, this is literally the code for this function.
That's the code.
That is what exists in memory at the time.
It's executed when we call it, that is what the processor literally
sees.
Right?
So what that means is once I've got it, what do I need this for?
It's not necessary, right?
Because I now have the compiled code 45.
I'm not even going to bother passing it to compiler, right?
Screw it.
Forget it.
So now when I compile it's like well I don't have this function 5 I'm
like I don't care just use this.
I just want you to Branch to that.
And it's like, well, I can transfer that.
It's not a function.
And I'm like, well you know what?
Pretend it is just trust me on this one pretend it's going to be and
of course this this doesn't okay, fine.
You know, if you don't want me to do that, let's just say point to the
beginning of it, right?
So I'm just saying look that first that very first and in fact, I
could, I could probably do this a little bit cleaner.
If I didn't Point you're there.
But anyway, the pointer to the first bite of this thing.
Just pretend that's a function pointer, right?
That's all.
I told it to do, I'm just, like, trust me, it's a function pointer.
Right.
So then I'm like, okay, let's see what happens.
And there might be some caveats here, but we'll kind of get to those
later.
So let's see what happens if I look at my disassembly here.
You'll be like, you'll kind of take a look at what's going on now.
We're like, hey, you know, this is a little bit weird, right?
Because you can see now when we're kind of looking at this, we have
code, 45 code.
45 isn't defined anywhere though, right?
So, when I look at this, I'm like, where is
The code 45 code.
And the answer is that basically we've only been looking at the code
section of an exit.
But as you saw before, when I kind of like brushed it aside because I
don't want to talk about it yet.
When we had that 2.0 times something I was like, oh it put that float
in some in the data segment, this executable this, I'm sorry, this
object file, in addition, to specifying code, which is what it's
dumping here in dis as mmm.
It also
It has data and so there's different sections.
Like I said this cough object format is kind of like a pack file.
It puts in or sorry I should say the object file for
Is kind of a pack file, doesn't have to be cough object file format.
Where it can put data in there as well.
And of course, you can understand why this might be the case.
It's not uncommon for code to have a bunch of tables in it and
constant values, the string, constants, and all that stuff that stuff
all has to flow through the whole process because the executable, when
it loads has to have all that data, because it's referenced, right?
So, in addition to having the code segments, which is what we see when
we do a dis a them, we can also ask it.
And again, this is going to tax my memory on how do this.
We can also ask it to see
parts of, of the
Of the data that are that are purely data.
It may charting part of the object file that are purely data-oriented
in nature.
And I don't know how to do that.
Exactly.
There's the raw denim.
Not tell it to actually print it out.
Is the problem show me how to print it out let's see.
Directors dependence.
Well, I don't know what if I set all what?
All help.
Probably not.
Hey yeah it did.
Yeah it does.
So you can see if I do all.
Now I'm getting a lot more stuff, right?
I'm getting all kinds.
The things that maybe I wasn't getting for before and what you can see
now is we've got a bunch more information.
Here's the symbols, here's all the symbols, we have code 45, is there,
right?
You can see it's relative offsets and all this stuff.
Here's a bunch of raw data and what we can see this be 80, 500, you
know, somewhere in here.
That's going to be right.
And I think we probably can find it.
Let's see if we can find it somewhere.
Um where I should probably just load this in and search but we should
have again some information about exactly where it is.
When we actually, look, let me let me go ahead and do a less here and
see if it if I could find it.
So let me look for B8.
No, we didn't get it.
So I don't know.
Maybe maybe all still doesn't actually tell me all of the data because
you can see like it's got this here and I don't know where it's
actually put it.
I'm not sure I want to spend the time trying to tell dump in how to
It but just trust me.
It's all going to be in this object file.
You can and you can presumably coerced dumpin to show it to you at the
very least, if I wanted to, right.
I could also just ask that list on here.
Yeah, I could presumably also asked to just show me the obj file and
in a hex editor, we could just come in here and actually find it right
because somewhere in here is going to be code 45 and we can find out
where that
it actually is and I can search for it, right?
So if I want to, I can look at for that, be 8, and here it is.
So, there's that code, the be a 05 code, right?
Be 80.
5000 C3, which is this code right here.
So, there it is in the executable right, Augusta?
And somehow, we could, if we had more time to play with dump in, we
could probably find a way to more clean, the do it.
And of course, it says here, what, the offsets are so we could have
known presumably as well wear and may not obj, it was right, but
anyway, point being now I produce an executable, which is going to
call that specifically.
And so if I look at the, the dump in here,
Here for my main.
There it is.
What you can see is now, we're loading the code, 45 address, right?
We're loading that in, which is just our array of data that we put in
there.
We're for whatever reason doing this array indexing.
And so you know I think this is just because we haven't specified that
the compiler should do any optimizations.
It's actually doing this 0 part here so you can see what it's doing.
Is it's saying like Okay
Let's go 0 far into here, right?
Let's go 0 far into this array.
It's like all right, I'll go 04 on the right, which is a still exact
same place and then it's actually loading that into the function
pointer and then it's calling that function pointer.
But fundamentally all it's doing is calling code 45, right?
That's all it's doing and presumably, I don't know.
I don't know if I can make that less obtuse.
I don't think I can make an initializer list in any other way.
I want to do it.
I would like to do it so that it wouldn't do that.
But you can see how it wants to.
It really wants to make me convince it that it's a pointer because
it's thinking of this as an array, right?
And you know I mean we could sort of fake it out by having it do.
Something like this.
Maybe I'll do it the other way around.
You know, I'm not going to do it, it's too much.
You'll just have to bear with me or believe me when I say that.
That's what that code does because again go ahead and
Because this is still going to be the simplest way I think is just to
show it, right?
So you can see here.
It's loading in the address, it's not
When it does this Advance by zero, that's not going to do anything,
right?
It's pretty much entirely.
Sorry allergy season.
It's pretty much just going to load that in its going to advance it by
0 and then it
Load that in and call through it right.
That's all it's doing.
So it's not particularly interesting, it's not it's really just
calling directly to that address.
So let's take a look at what actually happens when we do that, right.
When we actually do that, we come through here, right?
We end up with that function pointer and we're going to make a call
into this here and lo and behold when we make a call and we're here in
our data segment.
What do we find the exact code that we expected happening?
Right here is the code that moves 5 into eax, right?
And of course, this is the caveat that I said I was going to have to
deal with and then we're going to return
Right.
That's exactly what we want to do.
Now, what you'll notice is even though this was totally valid code, I
get an exception here right, access violation, executing location.
Why are we getting that, right?
Why are we getting that?
Well, the reason that we're getting that is because we're technically
not allowed to execute data that we haven't pre told the operating
system is executable.
Okay, why is this?
Well, it's the same as the address space layout, randomization
problem.
The problem is that security people get kind of overzealous or maybe
you would say just zealous because they're not necessary overzealous,
they are trying to prevent real hacking problems.
One of the things that
Gpus added recently was the concept that in addition to memory Pages
being marked readable or writable, they could also be marked
executable.
And if a page with not considered executable stuff in it couldn't be
executed.
Now, why would you ever need this because you never do.
Well, the answer is because hacking, right?
No reason.
Will programmer ever really needs this?
Because if you wanted to things, start executing some where you wanted
to start, excuse summer, but
But to prevent against hacks.
It's obviously interesting and useful to be able to say only things
that the operating system has previously, said can be executed, should
be executed.
So if somebody manages to slip some kind of a hack in that should that
that you know, tries to call into a data segment somehow that will be
prevented right?
And it prevents like stacking because stack is data, right?
And so if you can get some code on the stack and then try to Branch to
it, the operating system will immediately fault you because that page
was not marked as executable its stack, its memory
Right?
And so that's what's going on here.
So how do we prevent the operating system from from doing this?
And, you know, get our code actually marked as executable.
That unfortunately is a little bit harder, certainly, but we can
certainly try, right?
And this is where things become a little harder to read, but we'll do
our best.
So what happens here is, basically, we need to sort of let
The compiler know that this data that we've got here needs to be
executable.
And the way that you do that in Windows is via the virtual protect
call.
You can see here the list of memory protection contexts.
I'm sorry, Constance, that Windows, accepts page.
Execute is the one we need.
So what we really want is, is sort of to tell Windows.
Hey, I need you to allow me to, you know, to execute some memory that
I'm going to specify, right?
So let's just do it.
Let's just do it and take it all the way.
So here's a virtual, a lock and a virtual protect.
I'm going to call both of them, right?
And this will actually set us up for the final thing I want to talk
about anyway, which is how the operating system and you agree on
locations of things, right.
And first, I'm going to blow my nose again because allergies are
awesome.
So first, we need to get some memory and then we need to Virtual
protect it.
Although actually, I suppose, I could probably try to just virtual
protect the page.
I don't miss any to allocate it, I could just say, let's virtual
protect the code 45 page.
I just don't know if it's smart enough to take the base of that
address describe, the starting page of the region whose access
protection as we change all pages, in The specified region must be
within the same Reserve region, Al-Qaeda members Irv
They can't span adjacent Reserve region.
So the problem here, the reason I can't really use Virtual protected
because I don't know where the base of the allocated ranges.
So I'm basically going to have to do something like this.
I'm going to have to call the operating system and get a page of
memory.
I'm then going to have to protect that memory, as being legal to
execute, I'm going to have to copy the code, 45 code into their,
right?
And then I can jump to it.
So let's do that.
Here's Mike are unsigned code, 45.
I'm going to get it from virtual a lock, right?
That's not the way this actually works but you know, that's basically
we're going to do right.
Then what I'm going to do is I'm going to Virtual protect that page
and then what I'm going to do is I'm going to copy the bytes that I
actually need in there.
Okay.
So I'm going to do this.
Okay, so let's look up the function calls, I need.
So here's virtual a lock.
And here's the prototype for that.
I'm going to cut and paste that in here.
Just so we can see it.
So, we have a void.
Virtual lock.
Have a void star LP address.
I'm just translating the
for lack of, I don't know.
The the correct term.
I'm translating the
Hungarian notation, if you will.
into saying types, temporarily
Here's the virtual Alec.
All right, that we actually need.
There we go.
And then we also need that virtual protect call.
Oh wait.
No.
We don't, you know why?
Because we can actually pass the protection to it directly.
So we only need virtuality.
That's all we would need.
And then,
We should be good to go.
So size T in this case we need the definition of.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to cheat again and use the
previous wind project here.
Sure we'll save that go ahead.
Let's go ahead and look that up when through and project.
So we need to know what is size t.
Go to definition.
And so there it is.
So it's really just one of these underscore underscore in 64 is the
unsigned.
So let's go ahead and put that in there.
There we go.
And so now we have the function prototype for virtual Alec, I'm going
to call it, I don't need a base address.
I the size can just be one page.
Let's say in fact we really only need 64 bytes but it'll round it up.
So you know I don't know it's really going to allocate the page anyway
might as well put one in there the out.
patient type in this case,
We're going to need to remember allocation allocate pages and we need,
we want to actually commit.
So we want these pages to actually be used for us.
So we need this constant, right?
So there it is.
And then finally, we want the correct memory protection.
We don't need any of that stuff.
So, we just need my protection constants here, page.
We just want everything, right?
We want to be able to read, write and execute.
So we want everything.
I don't know if that's a, if they have a convenient, one of those,
let's see.
Read.
Write read only no access execute, right?
Copy execute, read, right.
Execute read-only or read, write access to the committed region.
So this is the one that we want, I believe.
Let's go ahead and paste that in there.
Alright, so now I'm going to compile, we don't need this anymore, it's
gone.
And what you can see here is we pretty much are good to go in every
respect, except for one slight problem.
And that is that we don't currently have the the
The way to link with the virtual lock.
All right, so that's what we
Have to figure out.
Well, I guess, you know what?
We probably even do.
Let me just see if we do.
We should actually
Yeah, I think I think we actually can I take it all back?
So in theory, we probably can and I'll explain this in one second.
I apologize for
This is the stuff I want to get into, but I don't opes.
Let's see referenced in functions main sewer to start up unresolved
Sterno.
So it does actually need to specify Colonel pretty too.
So I will.
And so let me just and again, I apologize for getting a little bit
ahead but I want to finish talking about the execution part and then
we'll move on to all the stuff that I just did in a second.
So let's go ahead and get ourselves.
The one other thing we need and I'm going to again, keep us to only
stuff that's actually in our directory so that we're never going out.
Out of it so we can look at literally everything that there is.
So, let's go ahead and grab that out of here.
Let me see if I can find in here.
I don't know that it's in here.
I want the platform SDK.
Let's see it in here.
All right, I think that's sufficient for our purposes.
Let's copy this.
fell out and in to
All right.
Okay, so again, you'll have to bear with me for one second because I
want to tackle this part separately.
So we're going to talk about Libs and so on.
All right, so now in theory, if I jump back here and again, like I
said, I'll explain all of that.
I just don't want.
I want to show you the executed code.
First part to finish off that last part we were doing.
So let's go ahead and take a look at what this code does now.
And unfortunately, it gets a lot more complicated like I said, but we
have no choice because I don't really know if there's any way to
specify two maybe there.
Is a way to specify to the loader that you want execution prevention.
Turn protection.
Turned off, they're probably somewhere.
But this is the fastest way I could think of, on stream to do it.
So we can see down here where we actually do our function.
Call all of this right here is the code again unoptimized code, but
code nonetheless, to just move to do the construction of the the code
in memory.
So let's watch it happen, right here, right here is our call to
Virtual a lock and that call is going to return in our ax the pointer
that we got.
So here is in
Theory that pointer, right?
And now we're going to actually start moving stuff in there and we
should be able to actually look at it.
Right?
And I if I was smart, I would have saved that but we know it's our SP
+ 0, x 20, right?
According to this.
So it should be, at least it should be in there, right?
Let me actually
Let me get that out in a little bit more, same fashion.
All right, so let's try that one more time so I can make it easier on
myself.
So, here's our call.
Again, should be our call, our first call out to Virtual Alec, right?
So in here, where we are on the stack right now, if we look, we're in
kernel32 inside virtual a lock, right?
So I'm going to jump out of that.
That's after the virtual Alec has completed our X.
Now, the register itself has in theory.
Anyway, the pointer to the page that got allocated.
So now if I take a look and I do a car unsigned and I look at that
location, right?
So there's looking at this location and I look at, you know, say the
first 16 bytes of it, that's the first, that's the page that Windows
allocated for us.
Now, what I'm going to do is Step through the code that literally all
it's doing is filling this out with the code, so you can see it doing
that here.
Is our B 805 C3, right?
And that's the end of it.
So, it stops there.
This is just untouched right now.
We're going to call into that memory.
And this time when we get there again, it will look exactly the same
as it does before but now notes and things.
First of all, you can see that this time when we step it works, right?
We've done nothing differently.
Now the only thing is instead of it being in memory, That was supposed
to be part of our data segment which will
Those does not set the execution bid on when it loads it into memory
as part of our executable this time.
We did it in memory that we allocated.
And when we allocated it, we told Windows specifically, hey, this is
going to be executed, so allow that set the memory protection on this
page so that you will allow that the processor will not throw an
exception when it happens, right?
We executed it, it did exactly what we wanted to do, right?
And now we're doing a return call.
We get back here.
We finally complete the thing that we wanted to do which was actually
setting our Global variable equal to 5.
And remember we can actually now look and verify that, that is the
case.
And lo and behold, there is our five.
So, what we have done now, literally,
Is we actually made essentially our own compiler, right?
We made something that can do.
Exactly one thing, which is create a function that can return five.
So it's not a very good compiler.
It's not really compiler.
I suppose it's a code generator.
Let's say they can generate exactly one piece of code and that piece
of code is something that returns five but wait.
There's more.
Is it really something that can only return five?
Well, not really, right?
Because we kind of know that this 05 right here is the constant that's
getting returned.
The Intel encoding happens to encode that that return as an immediate
which means that the instruction itself, encodes the value that will
be moved to the register.
So really what we've done is a compiler that can generate a return of
any bite.
That you want?
Right?
And furthermore, it's really more than a bite.
Because this one, two, three, four.
Here is really 500.
This is the 32-bit value in coded as an immediate into the
instruction, that is getting returned.
so, if we wanted to,
We could produce a piece of code that returns any value by patching
that location equal to the thing.
We wanted to return.
Let's prove it right here.
Is an in Star.
I'm going to say that this location cure this code for 51.
I want to treat it as an in Star and I'm going to put the 5 in there,
okay?
So now let's dip in and see what happens to that particular piece of
code, right here, we come down.
And let's take a look at what we get.
You can see our in our hexadecimal display here, be 85 C3, right?
So that's the old style, let's go ahead and change that now to some
other variable.
Let's say 15 and let's do the same thing we come through here.
We take a look at what we get
Oh, you know what?
I got to remember since address base layer is randomization.
Every time I call this, it's going to every time I call virtual Alec,
it could give me back something different.
There it gave me back that address.
For example, instead of gotta, I gotta look at the right address every
time, right?
So here we go and we fill it out B8 and now you can see we put 15 in
here, right?
Instead, there's the 15 and now what we're going to do when we call
into our function you can see Hey look, it's no longer a move five,
it's a move 15.
So when it returns, it's going to return 15 instead of 5.
And when it moves out into our Global variable, now, the result of our
code is going to be something different entirely.
So here we go.
Looking at that code.
There's our 15.
So now we really do have a real code generator.
In a sense, we can generate something that returns any 32-bit value,
right?
So as long as you wanted to implement a language, that's only feature
that it could do is return a value.
And that value has to be a 32-bit number.
You've written the compiler for it essentially already, right?
That's what we've
Okay, it's pretty cool when you think about it because it's really no
more complicated than that to do on the Fly code generation.
This is an on-the-fly code generator it.
In fact, can generate any code that you want, if you started giving it
some ability to Output more, than just this simple set of
instructions, you can now build any x64 code, you want.
There's nothing.
You can't do anything.
You want to do in here you could do right?
Now, I don't know if I've lost everyone at this point or if everyone
is still on board, I'm hoping that everyone still on board.
Let's go ahead and push it a little bit further and just sort of take
it to its logical conclusions.
Before talking about the virtual a lock part of this and how the
operating system and dlls and that sort of stuff, get bound together,
right?
So in here, I have my code 45, right?
One of the things that's interesting about this code, 45 is I'm
generating some code in here.
Could that code call my code, right?
What if I needed that code to call something itself?
You know what I'm saying?
How would that work, right?
So let's go ahead and get our five back in here.
Okay.
And let's go ahead and take a look right here.
At what happens if we want to call five at say, this point in our
program, right?
So right here, we want to call five.
We want to get the result of five back or whatever.
Actually, let's see, how would we want to do this?
So I want to
Oh, and you know what?
This doesn't have to happen this way anymore, does it?
Yeah, so I'm just trying to think of how I want to do this.
So let's say what we wanted to do.
Oh you know what, I just realized, this is what we'll do, this is
totally what we'll do.
So let's say that I wanted to return, whatever, I get back from five.
Okay, so there we go, right?
So let's take a look at what actually happens in that code right
there.
Okay.
So now I'm going to step into this code.
I'm going to come down here.
You can see when I'm doing this sort of operation stuff.
You can, you can see the move, our ax, you can see the move, this is
the call to the function 5, right here is the call to that function,
right?
And it's a little bit complicated if you take a look at it, right,
because What's Happening Here is is really kind of confusing, right?
And let's try to break down, why?
It's why it's confusing.
What's Happening Here is we're calling essentially relative.
How do I know that we're calling your essentially relative?
Well, if you take a look at what's Happening Here, the bites for this
call in no way in code, this address, right?
So here's the address that we're calling.
And here's the code B for the instruction.
I would expect to see this in there and it ain't in there.
Now, what I do see instead is an FF FF FF 7 8.
That looks suspiciously like a negative number in two's complement,
right?
It sure does to me.
Anyway and furthermore, since this is little-endian it's really going
to look like this, right?
Because the smallest bite comes first which is the 78, then the FF and
the fsma I've have.
So it's really this value, right?
And it's that value I suspect.
As an integer, which is a negative 136.
Now, if we look at where we're at 13, f59 10, B, 3, right?
If I look at that, hexadecimal value,
Here it is.
Right.
If I look at that hexadecimal value and I want to subtract 136 from
it, right?
I would get a different hexadecimal value.
What hexadecimal value do?
I get I get 13f 5910 to be write something like this.
I think, right?
Is that what I get?
I don't know.
Did I type that incorrectly?
13 f59, 10 B 3, right?
Okay, yeah.
So I know that I'm calling this address, right?
And so if I look at it here, oops.
And I look at the location.
And I subtract the two of these.
There we go.
You can kind of see that.
It's almost what I would expect, right?
It's like, okay, so I have a negative 136 and the difference between
the thing that this is saying I'm jumping to and the instruction that
I'm currently on is - 131.
So it's almost right but not quite but so I
Sort of see how it's doing this encoding, I guess, right.
But not quite.
So, just from looking at it.
It's a little bit hard to reverse engineer, but it's pretty clear that
it's some kind of a relative jump, right?
It's like, hey, I know that I'm jumping to here.
This is where the instruction is, it really looks pretty darn close.
So why is it wrong?
And the answer is like, well the difference between these 13 6131.
Oh hey.
Look it
Happens to be 5 b, right?
So, it just so happens that the instruction is encoded based on after
the 5 b hits, right after I suck up those five, bytes, then I get that
encoding right then, I get the value.
So this is a relative call that calls relative to the instruction
pointer, right?
So, if we wanted to generate code ourselves and we know that we have
to write that code into a memory page somewhere.
Obviously, we can't use this call instruction.
Because of this call instruction is going to have to embed a relative
call in it.
And we don't know where our virtual page will be relative to this
page.
So we can't very well do anything about it.
Now we could hope that when we allocate the virtual page we will end
up being able to put them you know, close enough together.
Something like this that we could still use a relative call but
obviously it's a little dicey, right?
So what we'd much rather do is we'd probably rather have something
that can call sort of more absolutely but unfortunately it's pretty
hard to get something like that to work.
Sorry I get likes.
Get the compiler to output something like that so that we can look at
it because in all these cases it's going to be calling something
that's going to be pretty local in this case.
However we do have some guidance.
I suppose I can't set a breakpoint there.
Okay, there we go.
We know that this is going to call virtual a lock, right?
So here's a jump into into the virtual outcome, what you can see is
really, this is just a secondary jump which comes out here and then we
get another jump which is going to be to an address which is encoded
sort of more directly in here.
I suspect although still and I know this this this may still be a
relative jump 77 95d 328.
H, which is not the same here, right?
So, here we go.
Into another one.
Are we actually met?
And now we're actually in kernel-based.
So this is the code.
We actually wanted to call to here, which is 7 F EF like blah, blah
blah blah blah, right?
That's that's the actual
address that we were trying to call their that one.
Go ahead and switch that tax, a decimal View and if I step back out
here and I look at how that call was structured, unfortunately that
stepped out twice, I guess I shouldn't have done it that way.
Let me step in one more time.
There we go.
So there's the jump again.
The initial jump in the table and again we're going to talk about a
little bit of this little bit more.
Here's a secondary jump.
Here is the actual code that's going to be doing the virtual Alex
stuff and it does a secondary call in here, but it comes down to this
Rhett.
It's at the same location in both cases, 7fe FDA for 190.
So we know that that's the correct address still.
And so if we take a look at where that call is happening, oh I guess I
see what happened.
It returned there because those are the things we're jumps.
Not calls.
So they didn't modify the return address, but I found out the piece of
information I needed.
Which is that that particular location doesn't get modified with
about.
It doesn't get moved around.
So if we take a look at what's happening here, we're doing a jump to
this location.
Ation which again is not this.
Then we're doing a jump to this location.
That's basically reading out of this pointer.
It's here and that pointer has the location of virtual a lock, right?
The reason for the double indirection has to do with how dlls or
LinkedIn, we can talk about that again a little bit later.
So if I take a look at this, what's at this location?
What I should see again is a pointer to that virtual a lock function.
So if I take a look in here, see if I don't actually want that to be a
void star.
To be a void star star.
There we go.
So if I look at that void star star, I'm saying, what's at this
location?
And the answer is what's at this location?
Is this pointer to this function which is where I'm actually going to
Branch to, right?
So what it's doing here at the moment, I guess this table we were in,
is in the address space for a kernel32.dll, which is what we're
jumping into.
And again, it's sort of a
A redirection table that's going to move us out to the actual virtual
alochol.
So the question is still none of these have really given us what we
would need which is something that allows us to more easily crib off
the compiler something that we could call so that we can call like a
location where freely maybe.
Yeah.
Nothing.
I don't know.
I can't really think of anything that would allow us to do that.
So
I guess what I would say here is given the only thing that we're going
to be able to do is do a relative function.
Call in this case, I feel like what we need to do is just Embrace that
and go.
All right, let's figure out how to call some of our code directly by
using that same indirection style, right?
So what are we going to need?
Well we're going to need that sequence.
That uses a relative call, right?
So for example this thing right here this call keyword pointer.
Here is an address
And that address is saying, go there, read 64, bytes and Branch to
that, right?
So this is the sequence for doing that call.
This is the sequence that does that.
So let's grab those bites, right?
Let's just grab those out and look at how they correspond.
Okay, so in this case, we've got again that jump, in fact, maybe let's
use one, that's a little bit.
Do we have one?
That's that's that's not going to be so onerous, maybe a call
It's a little bit.
So here's here's a call that's going to be a little bit less finicky.
Perhaps so right here.
So this is the call that goes to to to our actual data, right?
And so let's take a look at how that's encoded.
So again, here is our hero, our B, right?
This is, this is the location of the code.
This is the pointer to the code.
This is the location that we are loading from.
I would like to load from.
So, this is the point.
This is where the data actually, is where that pointer is.
We know there are one, two, three, four, five, six, bytes in the call,
right?
So technically, we want to add 6 to this value, which is the one that
we'd be starting with, right?
And so then let's take a look at if we subtract that away.
So if we say, where would we have to go to get there?
Take a look here, right?
And then, let's see what we're actually.
A passing in here as the actual values.
Again, I'm not sure I quite did that correctly in the reverse
engineering there, so I'm going to have to be a little bit more
careful here when I'm looking at it.
Yeah, because just looking at it.
Maybe it's going forward.
I don't know exactly where it's trying to get that deer pointer, so
308, so it's going forward, right?
So that's why this number isn't - right.
So, we're expecting to see this to be a positive number.
It is, we look at the hexadecimal, it's 1 F.
5B is the actual value.
There is the one f5b.
So that's the 32-bit offset.
I believe that we are interested in.
So what this gives us right here is a sequence that would call
With a 32-bit offset, something relative to our current location,
right?
Okay, so let's go ahead and put that in there.
So instead what we want our function to do is rather than include the
code 45 that we're actually putting here, we want to actually put the
call to code 45 in the generated code.
Then we'll just return.
We know that c 3 does the return.
So we'll just do that.
Right?
So we'll call and then we'll return not particularly good code
regenerating here, but that's what we're going to do.
And like I said,
The five b1f part, that's the actual offset.
So off we go.
All right, so how will we do this?
Well, the way we'll do this is first by saying, all right, the code 45
needs the Preamble for the call, that's the FF and the 15, right?
We then know that the five b1f part
Right here, five b1f, right.
And you can see that's five b1f.
The 5 becomes first because again, because it's little-endian Phi b, 1
F 0, 0, 0 0.
That's the part, that's an in Star.
So this time we're looking at here, and we're looking at that integer,
this is our offset.
We don't know what that offset is yet.
That's going to be two, three, four and five.
Then we get to six and that's our rent, right?
So now what we need to do is we need to have some location somewhere
that's going to store the jump.
Okay ssion, right?
And again, this jump location can now be absolute because the relative
encoding is in the instruction that says, go look at this location,
pull out the pointer and jump there.
Right?
So let's go ahead and do that.
What we need to do is now store in code, 45 somewhere.
Let's say up after our return instruction, we're just going to put in
here the actual N64 address that we need which you know, in this case
would just be a void Star.
Right, we need to treat this address as if it's going to be a pointer
to something and we're going to put in to it the the function 5,
Okay, so let's go ahead and compile that.
Everything works except for the fact that we need this location.
We now know what this location is.
We just need to know the offset from where we are that that seven,
that that code for 57 is well, we know, we're going to end this
instruction at code for 55, right?
Or I should say it code, four, five, six.
That's where it's going to end after its when it's executing, so all
we need to know is where code 457 is relative for code to, you know,
to code, four, five, six,
Because the CPU will have consumed up to code 45.
I've code four, five, six code, 45 is a bad name.
Let me just call this code.
Or maybe just code.
Just call it code.
Just to get me out of that.
That was just hard to say.
Okay, so what we need to tell it is what's the difference right
between the address of where we're going to end, we're going to
destruction and where I need you to read the pointer from which is
right here, right?
And let's go ahead and compile that.
All right, so now let's look at what we've done.
Let's go in here and take a look at this monstrosity that we have
created.
So we're going to come through here again.
This is our call to Virtual a lock virtual Alec will return into our
ax the pointer that we now have allocated for our code generation.
I am going to go ahead and look at it as a car on the science, which
look at the B.
Here are the B now, we're going to go ahead and quote-unquote,
generate our code, which just involves a stuffing, the b n so you can
see uh, stuffing the b in here.
There's the
FF in the 15th and remember that FF in the 15 are just being hard set.
Now, what we're doing is going to insert the offset necessary to call
to get to this part of the of the code, right to this part of, it is
just a piece of data, we're sticking in there, but just that part of
the allocated memory, right?
So we need to do is fill that out.
And that should happen right here.
Or somewhere soon.
There it is.
Okay.
And that's correct actually it's only one bite now that I think about
it.
That's what it should be.
So we went away then we're going to stuff in The Return part, right?
And now at the end,
To the code.
So this is all of our code.
This is the call instruction plus the offset which is 1.
Byte the offset to look at the so it knows where to load the pointer,
right then the return instruction and now right here which is where
we've told it to look.
We sorry right here, where we've told to look, we need to put the
eight byte address of the function and that's what this code is going
to do right here, right?
And there it is.
So that's the actual address of the function.
Let's see if it actually did that correctly because we should actually
be able to find five, it should be right here.
So what we should be seeing is 310 8 C f8 13 right?
310 8 C f8.
Oops.
310.
Sorry.
See 8 or 8?
C?
Yes, f8.
Fa.
I'm just reading that wrong but yes, that's exactly right by my
reading comprehension, those are not great.
So we've loaded the location of this function 5 that the compiler
generated, we loaded it into our code page, right?
That we created and that's where relative addressing we told it to go
get the result when it does the call, right?
So, now, here comes the moment of truth.
Did we do it right?
I don't know, right?
That was pretty fast and loose that I was playing there.
Certainly
So we're going to have a load here of RX into this thing is like, this
is, that's this right here where we're loading in the function and
then we're going to call through there, okay?
So this is the Moment of Truth.
This is the call.
We're calling through it.
Here's our generated code.
It's beautiful.
Isn't it?
Look at the code we generated, aren't you?
Proud of yourself?
You should be.
If you've made it this far, here we are doing our load.
I'm sorry doing our call that loads the address to jump to out of this
location.
This location was encoded relatively right here by saying, one bite
after the end of this instruction, that is where we're going to go.
Okay?
That's exactly where we put it.
We put it right here so we're hoping it loads properly.
What you'll notice is the disassembler doesn't know, that's what we
made.
It still thinks it's code after the ret, we stuff data in there.
We didn't tell it, right.
So it's going to go ahead.
Disassemble.
That so it's thinks we stuck in an X or mob ad ad ad ad ad, right?
That's that we did, but it doesn't know the disassembler.
Just disassembles what's in memory assuming that it's code, right?
But instead what we're going to do is we're going to Branch out to the
location found at this place.
Let's see whether that actually.
Is if we actually encoded that properly.
So let's say that's a that's a pointer to a void.
Here it is and Hey look it's got the 13 f8c 10:30 in there.
Hopefully, the I think that was the right address, right?
So we're loading the address.
We're going to Branch boom.
There we are back at 5:00, right?
It's a great day to be alive for programming.
Everything worked just great here.
We are at the actual call site of five.
This is where we would have got the calls 85, but the place you jumped
you go to when you call five, just as if the compiler called it but we
called it.
We generated the code to call it right here we are.
It's going to return and it's going to
Have place in eax, the value of five.
So that's their right when we ret back out, we come to our Rhett.
We are not going to touch that, so that's fine.
It's going to leave that return value in there and lo and behold
through our own code that jumped into the code, the compiler
generated.
We got that value, 5 out and cure.
It is.
Ladies and gentlemen, it has been written out to our Global variable
just as we would have wanted.
And if we look at that Global variable and see what it contains,
Ins.
Like so.
Oops, that is if I can type.
There's the five, right?
so hopefully that demystify some of that stuff
the code that the compiler generates is just B.
Those bites when they are initially compiled may have empty spaces in
them that are just mentioned as a symbol is going to go here.
When you link the Linker fills in all of those symbols that are known
at link time although there may be some of the operations massive deal
with.
And that's the part we're going to get into now but mostly that's what
happens.
All of that code B that were generated.
They get loaded into memory when the operating system executes your
program and you can look at them, a function pointer just points into
those bites.
That's all it does.
And you can do anything you want with function pointers all the way
down to what I just showed you, where you can just make up the code
yourself.
Tell, see what kind of code you made and it will dispatch to your code
just like,
It would dispatch to its code.
No difference.
Furthermore, you can actually snap a pointer to code.
The compiler made, feed it into code that you make, and actually call
that.
So you can call into your code and then call back out again, it's none
of it's a mystery.
It's just bytes in memory and function pointers are just those
pointers and all that any of this other stuff does is it just informs
the compiler at the call site?
What does it have to do to dispatch to
That address.
That's all the function.
Signature really tells it, right?
Okay, time to finish up the understanding of what's going on with
these function pointers now to answer the last part of the question.
That was posed by the, the email that I received.
How do things work if you have two separate actual executable pieces
that are produced at the end because hopefully now you've seen there
should be no questions in your mind about how an individual program
works.
In terms of function pointers, right?
You can see that the code that's generated is just call instructions.
It's just going to get the pointers from wherever it needed to.
In terms of like, either those symbols were specified by the compiler,
initially when it generated piece of code or that that can be made by
us where we allocate memory and tell it to call it.
So it's just getting a pointer from somewhere reasonable and off you
go, it's all under your control and you have the ability to specify,
how it's going to happen and the Linker follows very specific rules
that we have now investigated and
Should have no trouble understanding how that's working.
You can even use tools like dumpin to inform you.
If you are confused about what the Linker is doing.
Okay, so
Now, the question becomes what happens with stuff like this call.
This virtual alochol.
We never defined that, right?
And you saw me have to do a bunch of mumbo-jumbo here.
I added you insert kernel32.dll, lib on to the end of our link line in
order to be able to call virtual a lock, okay.
And the question is like, how does that work?
Because virtual Alec is defined nowhere in any translation unit that
we have.
And in order to get access to it, I had to do a kernel32 lib.
Does the code live in there and if the code does live in there?
Well, the allocation is something that the operating system has to do,
right?
So how does it tell the operating system that it needs to do in a
like, what's happening?
How does any of this stuff work?
Right?
Okay.
Well
So let's start at the very very beginning.
Initially there was no such thing as the stuff that I'm about to tell
you earlier, computer programming, like under MS-DOS and stuff like
this or going further back, let's say in the Amiga days might be a
good example.
When you wrote a program, you have the option of writing a program
that would be the only program that was running on the system.
So there wasn't really an operating system per se in a lot of cases.
There was your code and whenever
Your code needed, something to happen that related to the actual
Hardware.
What you did was invoke an actual bios interrupt.
Now, what this means is, you were actually telling the processor.
I need you to jump into code.
That's actually stored in ROM in the computer, hard-coded, into the
hardware.
And that is the place where anything that I didn't right occurs.
So you're literally talking about like the firmware that's in the ROM,
that's mapped somehow.
Memory, who knows, what's going on depending on the system
architecture.
Blah, blah, blah.
The only things that you would be calling quote-unquote, that weren't
your code.
We're Hardware operations.
Okay.
But as the understanding of operating system ecosystem, sort of
matures over time, and this is not like contemporary contemporaneous
with a Meegan MS-DOS.
We're also systems like vax and so on where this had already occurred.
So it's, you know, it wasn't like it happened.
Only as Windows NT happened or something.
But anyway, as operating systems mature, they tend to end up at a
point where now, everything that your code does, if it's a user kind
of program.
So not the
Operating system.
But user mode code, it no longer directly interfaces with the
hardware.
The reason for that is because the operating system is required to
mitigate concerns that happen between programs.
What do I mean by this?
Well, if I am trying to allocate memory in a program, I wrote, but
it's a multitasking operating system.
So, somebody else's program is also trying to allocate memory.
Well, if we both talk directly to the hardware and said, here's the
memory, I want to use, right?
We might pick the
the same mapping in memory and overwrite each other's changes or who
knows what or one of us would update the memory mapping on the CPU
without being aware that the other person updated it and clobber their
change.
Who knows what happens, right?
So the operating system has to step in here and provide a set of API
calls, which will mitigate this sort of, like, sort of solve the
collective action problem.
It's sort of acting like the government does, where you got private
citizens, who want to do various things in the government, has to say.
Okay, let's arbitrate, who's going to do what?
We're
And who owns what property and so on, right?
It's for it's doing that same thing.
Nowadays the operating system is
Okay, so in this case, what we have is a modern-day operating system
provides usually, a very large surface of API functions.
And the way that this works is that when your code is initially
starting when your executable is loaded, there is a secondary link
phase so very much like the obj files that we had where we can, we
have the compiler produce obj's, which had
Symbols in them that were kind of missing, right?
They were sort of saying, well I know I need to call bar here but I
don't really know where that's going to be.
So just when you find out, when it's going to be later on down the
pipe, put in the address here so that this code will work, right?
So what the operating system does is it basically does that same thing
to your code.
In another link step that only happens when the executables actually
loaded.
That's what's actually going on, right?
And so, if we take a look at what's happening, we can now start to
speak.
Can start to inspect that process.
Let's take a look at this virtual AA, call.
For example, I can go ahead and do a dump bin like we were doing
before.
On our code in Maine obj.
And what I can see up with the virtual alochol, you can see right here
that the same sort of thing happened.
That was happening to our stuff before.
Do you see that input virtual Alec there?
Now, in Virtual a lock, is nowhere to be found, write our code, simply
does not have an imp virtual a lock.
So the question becomes, where is imp virtual a lock?
What is imp virtual a lock?
It's a symbol that's getting inserted into our code that
No one has defined.
And that is how we get to, what that lib was that I placed on the link
line, and that starts to inform how the dynamic link linking process
on Windows, actually works.
And how things are connected up to each other, right?
So if we go and look at how this works, that that link line, you can
see that I had to put kernel32.dll a bond there.
Well, what is kernel32.dll?
Abib kernel32.dll ID is this file that I copied in because like I
said, I wanted everything to be in here.
Oops, I want it to be lowercase as well, because I like things to look
lower case.
There we go.
Let's pretend that I had done that originally, and let's do another
directory.
There you go.
So looking at this here kernel32 lib what is that file?
Well a DOT.
Lib file is really nothing.
Mysterious a DOT lid.
File is really basically the same thing as an obj file for all intents
and purposes.
It's a pre bundles set of obj's, basically that you can link to so
that you don't have to have all the obj's that actually created it
lying around.
So it's sort of like instead of producing an actual executable that
you're going to ship to somebody and say here run this code if a
developer wants to ship something to another developer.
Say hey here's a bunch of code that I pre packaged together.
You can call it and link it into your executable on your link line.
A lib is just a way of bundling, a bunch of obj's together and
providing them to you to call.
So that's exactly what this is.
And what that means is we can look at it with dump in just like we
would look at an obj file actually.
So if I want to take a disassembled of kernel32, not live, I can write
now unfortunately, what you can see here is since this is a import
Library, we don't get very much information out of it, right?
Right.
It's not willing to give us a dis as mm of this up because it's in a
specific format.
Let's see if I can do this with a slash all.
It's an acidic format.
That's really only job is to provide a dispatch table for a dll and so
I'll kind of get into what that means.
But you can see it all is kind of scrolling by here.
Probably not super necessary.
Here you can see.
Yeah.
let me get this into something I can actually,
Here we go.
All right.
Alright, so here is kernel32 text, which is the dump bin of kernel32
and what you can see here is what we have in this library and it was
my bad for trying to diss azimut.
You can't just
Man import library and import libraries, slightly different from
regular Library again just because it's made to specifically instruct
a Windows, the Linker, how to create a permanent going to bind to
Windows, but it's still basically the exact same thing.
It's just a series of name symbols and those symbols are there to tell
the Linker how to patch up information.
And what you can see about this library, is that this Library?
All it has in, it is a bunch of basically names which are
Imp.
And then the function and it also has that function.
And all of these functions core are all the functions that exist in
Windows kernel Services right now.
I don't know if I installed depends on this machine.
I hope that I did.
I'm not sure how to find out if I did.
Do I have it?
I hope that I do.
Depends anyone?
Here it is.
Yes depends is a program that we can use to inspect dlls and basically
what it is, is it something that takes the dll and shows us what's
contained in there, right?
And so, let's talk a little bit of what, what a DL DL is to begin with
and how it relates to the import Library.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to the windows system32
directory, a hilarious name considering that fact that it's actually
64-bit now.
But, hey, Legacy.
And this is the actual even though it's called
32.
And it's in the system trajectory, it's actually a 64-bit dll for
backwards compatibility reasons, they kept the names of same, instead
of curling it colonel 64.
Yeah.
Anyway, I'm going to open up kernel32.dll and what you can see in
kernel32.dll in this program depends you can see here all of the
functions that kernel32 actually exports.
And so what is a dll and why do we care?
And what is this?
Actually giving us that anyone needs to actually know.
Well, alright, so what you can see first of all is like, for example,
let's take.
Well let's take a virtual I like because that's the call.
We actually needed.
That was the only call that we're actually using in our in our code,
right?
Here's virtual a lock you can see right here.
It says we're virtual Alec is in the in the dll.
It has some other information are like ordinal which is a way to bind
things that by name by numbers instead of names.
Not really important to us now but there's that virtual alochol.
And the other thing that we can see is if we look inside the, the lib,
you can see that we've got those same exact things you can see like I
said these correspond exactly.
You can see them here, virtual Aqua TX free, right?
This import library that we dumped has the exact same structure as the
dll in terms of what's in it, right?
They're not the same but they correspond quite directly right?
So what this is is actually a way of describing code, a dll is a way
of sort of, bundling up a bunch of code.
So a dll and an executable are almost exactly the same.
They contain almost exactly the same stuff.
The only difference is the dll is basically not stand alone.
It's designed to be code that people call in, to, rather than
executable which kind of launches and does its own thing.
Right?
And so a dll, which stands, for course, Dynamic link.
Library is a library that's of code.
Code that's been pre compiled that you can just run.
It's not a lib.
It's not a library.
Like, in the linking sense of the word like we were talking about, its
actual code completed code.
With all the symbols resolved and it just has a bunch of entry points
in it, that you can call into that, do something specific.
So in our case, kernel32.dll has the code for virtual alloc init.
That's what it has.
What windows will do when it loads your executable is, it will map
into your processes memory space, these dll code.
So when our program is loaded,
it knows that it needs to map kernel32.dll in and it knows that we
need the code from kernel32.dll to complete our execution.
Specifically, we need virtual a lock right now.
How does it know that?
That's where the import Library comes from?
An import library, is specifically what you pass on the command line
to the Linker that says, here is a dll, right inside.
Kernel32 out, lib it basically says there is a dll
Kernel32.dll.
Here are all the entry points that that dll has.
And so, if someone wants a symbol like virtual a lock, I've got it,
here's where it.
And the way that you're going to resolve, that symbol is in the
executable.
What you output it, you're going to put in a line that says I need
kernel32.dll and I need virtual Alec from it.
I need you to patch that value in right here.
Okay.
So let's take that a little bit further here is my Depends.
Like are saying I'm going to load, depends allows me to look at
basically what sin, you know.
I've been saying all this time, it puts this thing in the executable
that you can lewd.
Depends is basically something which takes an executable file either a
dll or an exact.
Because, like I said, they're basically the same,
It takes one of those and it goes, what is in that specific section
that thing I keep talking about?
That's like, here's the thing that tells Windows what to do when I
load this and it dumps it for us.
So what that means is I can take our program, main dot exe and say,
look at that, and lo and behold what you can see is it tells us
exactly what we need to load.
Made idac, we only have one dependency.
It's
Colonel 32, dll and if we click on it it will show us exactly what we
call in that dll.
It's virtual Alec, right?
Again that is actually specified in the executable itself so you can
actually see depends let you actually see that in a GUI manner.
Now we could get a different way.
I believe dump bin / can I get Imports?
Imports we go
What we can see if we run dumpin in a less, pretty fashion is if we
run dumping on our executable again, what that's going to do is it's
going to take that executable file, and it's going to look at it and
grab that section that tells Windows what to do and tell us what's in
there.
And it says, here are the Imports kernel32.dll is required and the
symbol that comes out of it.
It's virtual a lock, right?
So again, this is just basically the exact same thing that the Linker
does at link time.
The dynamic Linker hence the name dynamic because happens at run time.
The dynamic Linker in Windows does at runtime so when our executable
comes in it performs the exact same function which is patching in
missing symbol addresses and it does that by mapping in the various
Dynamic libraries we need and wiring up.
So
Watching in those call sites to point to the correct location in
memory where that function actually exists.
Okay.
So we can see this happen directly if we step into our code right
here.
For example, is that call keyword pointer and this called goes to
Virtual a lock, right?
You can see it happening right here and here we end up in the code for
virtual a lock, right?
But if we actually look what's in our executable, it doesn't look like
that, right?
If we do a dis azzam of the executable main dot exe, you will notice
that we actually see no such thing.
Instead what we see when we look at this call to the this, this is the
location that we just step through that location here.
Four thousand two thousand H, right?
Is actually we can we get that?
I don't know if we can actually get that.
We can't actually look at the depends piece of information.
Can we, how can I, well,
This is the actual piece of information here.
I'm trying to think if I can get dumped into show us.
I know we can definitely do this.
I just don't know how this won't help us at all some while I'm typing
it in
Because we don't have any of that in there.
Well, I guess here's what I could do.
Okay, so let's just look at what the executable contains literally
before it is loaded.
Okay, here is the executable in a hex editor.
You can see the MZ prefix which is actually the tag, the header tag
that actually says that this is a Windows executable, you can actually
see if we actually look.
Where is my web browser?
There it is.
This is actually what they're called, they're called MZ executables,
right?
And what you'll notice is this is MS-DOS executable.
It says, this MZ.
Executable is actually the Preamble.
You can see that it says, this is this program cannot be run in DOS
mode.
What this is, is, this is actually a Das program and MS, DOS program,
that Windows still for legacy purposes, inserts at the front of a
linked executable.
Not making this up.
Such that if you were still to run it on MS-DOS, it would give you an
error that says, that this cannot be run in DOS mode.
So that, you know, you have to run it in Windows, right?
Again, this was when they initially made the transition, they spec,
the Windows File, executable format, to have the Das executable at the
beginning of it.
So that it would print that error message properly.
If someone tried to load the exe from da Smo.
It was a backwards compatibility feature.
So that's what that's doing there, right?
You can also see the rich G here.
I don't know the story behind that, I don't know who Rich G was.
Let's find out.
It, does it say?
I don't know, I'm not sure what the rich G comes from someone, from
Microsoft, can maybe fill us in on that anyway.
Maybe that means, maybe that's someone's name.
Maybe that means Rich graphic, I don't know.
Who knows point being that part of the MZ executable, that part of
this video format is just the dose Preamble, that's a piece of code
that's designed to cause MS.
DOS programs had no Dynamic linking.
They
Started at the first byte of the file, there's loaded it in point, the
Rest by the file and go.
Right.
And so that MZ X q0 to start the beginning in a just that's what's in
there, right?
As far as I know, and what know that's, that's a lie.
That's not, that's, that's totally not true.
The MZ part is loaded in, actually, check properly, it doesn't have a
dynamic linking.
It starts further in, obviously, it can't start executing it mzi.
So I think that what I just said is completely wrong, but you can see
that there's hardly anything in here and that's because again, no
Dynamic, limiting has to occur.
As far as I know for this to happen, it can just do a straight for it
interrupts to print.
Stuff to the console.
So I don't think there's anything in particular happening there.
Other than just the code starting somewhere in here again, has been a
long time, sentencing Das wise.
So don't quote me on that.
The PE here is where the executable actually starts for Windows in a
In Earnest.
And so you can see, it's called a PE portable executable format.
That's where this actually starts.
This is the windows part here.
These are the segments that are dated, a tepee data and so on.
And here is actually all of our code existing in here.
Right?
What that means?
Is that in this file, we can see what our code actually looks.
Like before the windows Linker, does anything to patch it up, right?
So, if we take a look, if we step in here,
Go ahead here.
Here we go.
So if we step in here and we see this, this jump, what we can see is
that jump there
That jump there.
You can see it's getting the, the the address from this location,
right?
13 fe0 2008, right?
That is something that's in our executable, that we have stored, and
it's doing very much like we did where it's getting a 64-bit, I
believe jump out of that.
So, if we take a look at what's in there, let me do this.
No not 9x.
There we go.
So if we assume that this thing right here is a pointer to a 64-bit
value.
Then we can see what that value actually is, and it's 778 d5c 40.
That's where it is, right?
It's at that location.
And what we can furthermore, tell is this address, right?
Where is that relative to the start of our code?
So here's where the code starts.
Right.
This is where a code starts, right here.
Where is this relative?
I just want to know where that is, right?
I just want to find out where that is relative to it.
Oops.
Here we go.
So that's 4,000.
That's 40-32 away.
So it's down here somewhere, right?
It's down in this 13, feo 2000, right?
So let's, let's go down there.
You can see that it is doo-doo-doo, doo-doo-doo-doo-doo-doo
doo-doo-doo-doo-doo.
There it is.
All right, so you can see where that is.
It's right here.
And this is getting disassembled as actual code but it's not right.
This is the same trick we used.
So the disassembler things is code, it's not really code.
It's actually the address.
It's actually this
Address.
Right.
Why did you do that?
To me?
I went all the way down there for a reason to bugger.
There we go.
You can actually see that that that address 7.
So it's 45, cd45 C8 D 77.
This is the same trick we used, where it just stored, the pointer that
it needed to jump to its stored that out here in in sort of the, the
part of the code where addresses, for, for dynamic, linking are going
to live.
Okay.
So what we
To know now is was that ever in the actual code, was that ever was
that in our executable that that address hardbound and the answer in
this case should be no, although this is taxing my knowledge of
whether Colonel gets gets special linkage because it's Colonel, but
assuming that it's not what actually presumably happened was that the
dynamic Linker patch this up from some other address that wasn't
actually there to begin with.
And what we do know is we know that
Know that it's from the start of our code, we do know how far away it
is.
Like I said, it's 40-32 away.
So what we might be able to do here is take a look at Main dot exe and
figure out if we can locate our actual code.
So ff15 a 3-0 f for example is code.
That should just exist in here somewhere and I'm going to search for
it.
Ff15 a 3-0 F.
Here we go.
And let's see if we've actually found our code.
So here is FL
15 a 3-0 F, right.
0 0 is Right.
48, 49.
So this is our code in our a, this is on disk or code, right?
And so, from the start of this segment here, that we looked at, which
was, which was actually here and furthermore, we could just look at
1000 because 1000 is probably where this actually started to a certain
extent, right?
It was probably loaded into this page.
This is probably nonsense here.
We probably got loaded there.
Right.
So, if we take a look at this, this code page, right?
At some point, we would assume that we'd get down to the location
where we would have been loading that pointer from, and that pointer
should actually have a different piece of information in it.
Now, you can see, we can even see just right here that this is the
table.
That tells us what we needed to load, because you can actually see it
right here.
It's kernel32.dll, virtual Alec, right?
So here's the table, that tells the windows Linker, what to patch
But the question now is where is the actual value that got patched?
And what was it, right?
And that's going to be a little harder to find because it's probably
just again zeroed out or something in here.
So I'm not sure.
Anyway, what I'd love to be able to do is actually,
See before the windows Linker actually does its patching but I don't
know any I don't really know any way to do that.
Like I don't know how to stop Windows from how to inspect code before
the windows Linker gets to do it.
So what I'm going to do instead is I'm going to try here, some things
that are not super advisable.
I'm going to try some some amusing things to do if that makes sense.
So I'm going to, I'm going to, I'm going to try and look at this,
musing some, some more hand-wavy stuff right in the actual file.
Although, I guess, you know, the other thing that I probably could do,
I could probably use dumped into kind base.
So let me actually try that instead because that would be less
ridiculous than what I was about to do, which I don't think we should
do.
Okay?
So let me go ahead and try here.
How do I get to my desktop?
There we go.
That up.
It's coming here.
I'm going to go ahead and call dump in, and I'm going to take a look
at the Imports remain dot exe, and I'm just going to see if I can get
it to tell me.
So you can see here, right?
These are the two pieces of information, that tell me, where, in the
code in the absolute addressing of the code before, it's had address
space layout, randomization applied to it.
But in sort of the canonical addressing of the code, where these two
things are,
Which correspond actually fairly reasonably.
Oops.
To where we're seeing them here, right?
You can kind of see the import address table is at this location and
the import name table is just just a little bit ahead of it.
So you can see here.
Here is, the name table, right?
Is here.
And it's only 50, B, assuming actually, I guess this is probably in
HEX, so it's 0 x.
50 B back is where the actual pointer table is, right where the actual
import address table is.
And so in this stuff right here,
Should be where that is stored.
That's my guess.
Now I don't know if I can get it to tell me any better than that, like
where it actually is in the output file.
Let me see if I can get it to give me something a little bit better
and again, I apologize.
I'm kind of rough at this sort of stuff.
See here.
So, okay, so this is pretty good.
This actually gives us the raw data which is exactly what what I want.
Okay, so, that's perfect, right.
Okay?
So in this case, right, we can see two pieces of information.
Here's this this raw data number four and this rotated.
Number one are not the interesting part.
It's this raw data.
Number two, how do
I know that this this rotted a number 2.
Well, the reason I know is because when I looked up with the Imports
where you can see that, it said the import address table was at this
location logical location and the import name tells that this logical
location out.
Again, these are not the locations are acting to be encode.
These are because of address, space layout.
Randomization, these are sort of the recommended Base address, so I
guess, one thing that I never quite mentioned was whenever the
compiler compiles, something, I'm sorry, whatever.
The Linker links, something it links it with an understanding of what
the Base address.
Probably will be
Be it picked looks like 140, 000 000, right?
And you can see that everything that it generated is based off of That
Base address.
So when it does a dump bin, it's just saying hey this is where I
expect this thing to be loaded in memory but of course windows will
randomize where it actually gets loaded.
So now that new lower corresponds used to be that majority of the time
in Windows when you run it ran a program.
What you got in dump bin was exactly where it would have ended up not
true anymore so you can
It's slightly off and that's because of that address, space layout,
randomization, okay?
But putting that aside.
So now we know that the address import table is at this location.
Here is the address import table.
This is this is it right?
We also know that the import name table starts here.
So here that is right this is the import name table.
And so, what's happening?
Is this value here, right?
And we should now be able to figure this out because we can, we can
now, do sort of a Delta ink from the B that we see in the code here in
the Raw data and where they are here, we should be able to, actually
do sort of a Delta there to figure out what, where it actually is
relative in the code, right?
So let's actually see if I can do that to a certain extent.
I'm going to look for the 894 see 2408, right?
That's what I'ma look for in here.
See if I can find it.
And maybe I can maybe I can't or actually, you know what?
I could probably do it the other way around.
Let's look for the ff15 part of things here.
So here it is.
A 30f.
So that is this piece of code right here.
Right.
And so working backwards from there, if I just kind of go backwards in
in code B, I should get back at some point to the first actual
instruction that I see here in this page, which is at the 40 part,
which is right here.
So that's 40.
80, 3, EC 38.
That's that piece of code.
Okay?
So if I take a look at where that loaded, so this is the location that
that piece of code loaded at.
I know that this is the place where I'm at.
In where the the Linker just guessed if the Base address started,
where it thought it was going to start at the 14 million or whatever.
Sorry, 140 million hex.
It's not you know 0x 1400 1000.
What I can do now is look at the Delta between these two and figure
out where that you know, where it corresponds to in this universe,
right?
So let's go ahead and look at where we're calling here.
We're calling at 2,000, right?
That's the location that we're looking at and again.
So if I was to take this location, which I did, originally the 1040
there, the start of the code and
Act.
It it's 4,000 32 away I want that in HEX.
Again, that's fc0 right.
And so what I want to do here is I want to know.
Well, if I was to start from here, right?
14 X, 14 000.
1040.
If I was to start from there and go that far forward, right?
Go fc0 forward.
Where would I end up?
And I'd end up right there, right?
That is literally the start right here.
So now we know definitively in our executable.
This is the address 60, 20 000, 000 000.
000 is actually.
What was there?
Right, but that's not what's there anymore, if that makes sense.
When we actually look at what was there, we find something totally
else altogether, which is what Windows has patched in.
So we know that Windows is now, over writing, that value, by using
this table, that's specified starting here, encoded in whatever
format.
So couldn't, we could actually go look up this encoding and actually
decrypt that, but this has been an incredibly long stream.
I think I want to say,
Heard of the stream at 2:30 potentially, maybe to 15, I think this has
been probably one of the longest dreams I've ever done.
So I won't belabor that point, but that's exactly what is happening
here, right?
It's using this table, which is information that actually has strings.
It's matching those strings to the actual dlls, it's patching in the
address so that it can jump into the dll.
And that is what's happening, right?
And so somewhere in between when it gets loaded, and when we actually
Actually get to start in the debugger that patch up occurred, which is
why?
When we go, and we look at where we jump, we jump to this value here.
Even though that value was nowhere to be found in here, right there is
that, that is not encoded anywhere, in our, executable Windows is
patching that in using this table, okay?
so now that we've done that, we now have a complete understanding
of exactly what is going on in all of the, handmade hero stuff.
Okay, from what I've given you today, you can go and apply it
completely to handmade hero.
How well, here you go.
We know in handmade hero.
We produce two things.
We produce one executable,
And one, dll?
Right?
The executable is the win32 platform code.
The dll is the game code we use.
Windows has Dynamic, loading capabilities to load the dynamic dll in,
right?
That's what we do.
And when we load that dynamic, dll in, we know that we have to get
some location of code to jump to
and how we can do that.
And the answer is, we use the exact same process that Windows uses to
figure out where to jump into our executable.
Right.
It's this these tables, right?
These tables are written into our executable and say stuff like where
the entry points are or if we have named functions like virtual Allah
like the dll does in
Like kernel32.dll, has it knows that there's specific name entry
points.
So, what is that?
It's get proc address.
If you go back and look at the win32 stuff, get proc addresses, a
thing that says, hey Windows, using the, all the mechanisms that you
use for dynamic, linking tell me, where does this name exists?
What, what entry point?
What function pointer, what I need?
If I wanted to start executing at this named entry point in this dll,
and it will return back using exactly the same tables that were
looking at.
Our it will return back here is where that is, right?
When we do that, we are then able to jump to that function, right?
As a function pointer just like we were doing before.
So it's just gives us back and address of that dll.
Furthermore, when we calmed that deal on handmade hero, we passed it
function pointers that point into our code again, no difference here.
All we're doing is passing those function pointers into that code so
it can call those function Point itself using exactly the same stuff
techniques that we showed today, that code is just code in memory, the
pointers just point at the location.
Memory.
We wanted to be able to provide them to the execute to the game code.
Dll, we did that by bundling them up in memory, and just passing it a
pointer to that memory, and that's it, right?
So let's take a look at that in a little bit more detail.
Let's go into the handmade hero directory.
Right.
Oops.
Build directory, actually.
And here is the code that we build for handmade hero here at all is,
right?
And let's take a look at the win32.
Handmade stuff using dumped in, right?
So if I actually take a look here, I don't know that I want to just
ask them.
That's because it's kind of wrong.
Way too much stuff at me.
Yeah, this is going to throw away too much stuff on me as well.
Stop stop, stop, stop, stop bad.
No stop, please.
Oh my God.
Just no.
Well, ladies and gentlemen, here's a nice print out, and me hitting
control syrupy.
But you're not getting any ability to stop it.
How about we just close this window?
That seems like a good compromise.
All right, try that one more time.
It's out of here.
Go go into the handmade directory.
Sorry, build directory.
And let's do a more modest.
Look at the Imports of handmade.
Through to handmade gotta see.
And so, to start out with, you can see the win32, handmade links to a
bunch of things user 32, GDI 3-2 win, mmm, opengl 32 kernel32, right?
And you can see all of the entry points we use.
Now, you can see, this is much more involved than the one, we looked
at before.
Why?
Because handmade hero calls the operating system in a bunch more entry
points, right?
So, it needs to map all of these dlls.
Into its address space.
At start up, windows will map all of the code for those into our
address space.
So we have, you know, our code.
We have GDI 32s code.
When M&M's code opengl 32, s-code all of that gets mapped in there.
And then all of these names, get resolved.
So it all gets wired up.
So everywhere there was a function pointer to say get device caps, it
is now replaced with an actual, the actual address of get device caps,
so that it can jump.
It can execute that call properly, right, but that's all that's
happening.
There's that's getting wired up, okay?
So then we can look and also look at our handmade that dll.
What does it import?
So what you can see from the Imports of the, handmade dll is basically
the stuff that's there is just the necessary stuff for dll.
The C, runtime libraries, dll stuff, right?
So this is all part of that.
This is all called from the C runtime Library cuz we don't call any of
this stuff, right?
When we remove the C runtime Library, eventually all of this will go
away and they're actually won't be anything here.
So the more important part for us to look at it, handmade dll is the
exports part.
And you can see here is what we export again.
These are the tables that windows
Into the DLR, the Lincoln Rode into the dll that windows can read, and
when we call get proc address, it will look at these to figure out
where in the act, this dll in the executable code of this, dll, these
things start so that they can patch up things that link to directly.
But we don't actually do that.
What we do is we call get proc address, kept proc I dress just looks
at this table and returns where these actually are, right?
Okay, so all that's happening when we do our load library on handmade,
Dll in win32 code, it's being mapped into the address space of the
win32 handmade executable.
We are then calling get proc address which searches the table in the
dll for that name that we're looking for.
For example, get sent game, get sound samples, or game update and
render returns back a function pointer, which again is just an address
that says
Here in this, you know, it mapped it into our process.
So, at some point loaded handmade dll, put into our address space,
where in our addresses, is the actual code off, it goes right.
That is all this happening.
Now, hopefully you're very comfortable function pointers all that
chefs and seemed very non mysterious.
The only thing we haven't covered is how those tables are actually
stored again.
Those actually can be described in here if you want to see them.
There's a whole bunch of information in here about how relocations
work you can see in here you've got import table specifications and
stuff like this.
You can actually see that stuff is all rigorous rigorously defined, we
I do.
I know the best place for it if there's a speck for this out here
somewhere, here it is.
So you can look at these and in the spec it would tell you exactly how
that was laid up laid out for example.
And go from there.
Also, probably the map, Patrick article.
I suspect this probably is a good tutorial on it as well.
Oh, and here you go.
So, Matt, Patrick writes pretty good articles about the sorts of
things.
Like one of the windows internals guys, right?
I believe.
Yeah, he's the one who's Charles got.
So if you want a something that's less dry, his articles would
probably tell you all about how that stuff is encoded in there, right?
But again, it's really academic.
All you really need to know is that there's some kind of binary
encoding, just like the kinds, we develop on him, a hero for storing,
art assets.
They just encoded in binary something that says, hey, here's I open
the file.
I got to look at the file and go.
Okay, where's the table?
So, I need some header.
That tells me where the table is, I go.
Look at the table, the table says, how many entries, it has in it for
each entry?
It has like here's how long the name is.
It has the name and where it is, right?
It's that kind of stuff.
So it's just the same things we're doing on him a hero.
The windows Dynamic Linker is exact same thing.
So,
A beautiful file reading that file into memory, right?
And and looking at the tables to figure out what it has to wire up,
it's nothing mysterious.
It's stuff that it's exact same code, we've already done in handmade
hero so
Once you've got that right, once you've got that happening, the only
real thing that I wanted to point out that underlies all of this.
And that we've never really talked about explicitly on handmade hero
is the notion that the CPU is executing code somewhere and the notion
that there's a stack.
And I don't want to go into those too much detail.
Because this has been a huge amount of information to cover in one
session, but hopefully it was a complete enough explanation that Now
function pointers are.
To a certain extent.
Anyway, I just want to cover one brief discussion of how that works to
ground.
It a little bit for you and maybe some other time we can go into more
detail about what these things mean.
So, what I want to do is show you now
Looking at this code.
First of all, I want to explain what it means to say that the
processor is executing code somewhere, right?
And what it means to say that a call is relative to our location,
right?
Those are kind of like nebulous words.
Well, what I want you to do is look at the register window in the
bugger and pay attention to this R.I.P, okay?
This is one of the registers in the processor r.i.p.
and what hopefully you can see is that the address in our IP is the
address we are at.
And when we executed instruction r.i.p., advances to the next
instruction.
This is actually.
How the processor is tracking, where it is, executing, right?
Quite literally, if I say, what is the value of r?
I p, it is always the address of the instruction that I am currently
executing literally.
If I were to change the contents of this register, I want to go back
and instruction so I cut and pasted into here the address like so I
move the instruction pointer literally.
You can see that.
I just did it, right?
Let's move it back further.
I don't know, let's move it there.
I don't even think that's legal.
What I just did, but that's what happens, right?
I just moved it to some totally nonsense location and that's just what
goes on, right?
So when I say we are X, the processors executing at a particular
location.
What that means is actually very concrete.
It's not abstract.
There is literally a register in the processor that register literally
contains the virtual byte address.
Again, this is in the processes address space.
So it goes through the virtual table, it's not a physical memory
addresses of virtual memory address, so it still goes to the mapping
table to virtual memory it, but it holds the virtual address at which
code is being executed at that time.
And if the value in that register changes, it is executing at a
different place period.
The definition of an executing, an instruction is to read what is at
that location and execute it?
According to the rules of x64 instruction encoding and to advance
r.i.p.
by the number of bytes it consumed.
Every time that is all we are doing, right?
So when I say that this call in coded, the location relative to the
current place.
What I mean to say is that after it consumes the bites of this call,
our IP will have advanced by that many bites and is now at a
particular value, the value that you put in here is quite
specifically, or sorry, I shouldn't say that value put in here.
This is the translation of it.
The value that you put right here in the actual instruction, encoding
the value that you put right there is literally the
The Delta between what RIPD the the register equals after the
instruction has been decoded and where you would like it to go, it's
the Delta, right?
This is actually called, Rip relative addressing I believe
Jimmy because it is addressing relative to our IP.
And what it means is that when you have instructions that support rep
relative addressing, you can encode instead of an absolute offset and
offset relative to the instruction pointer at that time, okay?
Also same thing with the stack, the stack which we always talk about
what is this talking to set up the stack of just a stack blah blah,
the stack is just by convention.
There's nothing really magic about the stack other than I believe push
and pop calls have built into them and
Ending of the fact that there's a particular register that stores the
stack.
But other than that, the stack is meaningless.
The stock is just a convention that's obeyed by when code is generated
point being our SP, the register is just the pointer to the, the
program stack, the code stack, right?
So all the time, when you see things address on the stack, it's just
our SP plus some number, right?
So it's saying, here's here's where the stack pointer is at and I'm
going to reference off of that all the time.
So, again, the
And the instruction pointer the stack pointer partner.
I actually just registers that are just there there's nothing magical
about them either.
They're just numbers that store where in the virtual address space
stuff is, that's it.
So none of this is mysterious at all, there's nothing weird about the
relative to where we are, or what we are means.
It's, it's very concrete the r.i.p.
registers stores where we are and when we say, we're going to be
Relative to where we are.
We just mean our IP plus some number
Okay, let's go ahead and just and go to a brief Q&A here.
I hope I've covered everything that you might want to know, but I'll
take some questions in case there were things that that kind of
slipped by.
So so let's go ahead and do that.
I think H MH D butter whatever is dead so I can't.
So it's not dead in the handmade hero chat but it is dead in the
Twitch chat, I guess, for whatever reason.
So, pseudonym 73.
Also
Also known as our resident math.
Expert is
Is saying that www II see si.com Linker is worth a plug and if he says
so he's probably correct but I don't know what that is.
Oh it's a linkers and loaders Thing by John Levine so let's try and
get that up on the screen there because that probably
Pretty good thing to know, www.is, EC.com Linker here you go.
Here's the chapters of that book that talks about all this stuff.
Look at that.
That's great.
So this would be a great thing for marine that go into a lot more
depth than I would
But why not?
One says technically you need to call flush instruction cache.
When you generate code, I don't think that's actually true, is it you
only need to call flush instruction cache?
If the instruction cache could have had those instructions in it,
which if you've never executed the code before, it can't write.
So is that actually true?
I suppose, maybe it's true because virtual Alec could have given you
back a thing that was Matt, well, but
So that's a good question.
I don't really know.
Maybe you do, maybe you don't, I don't really know.
That's a really good question.
Well, let's talk about what that means.
It probably is true that you should call it because if it, if it, if
it may have had that piece of memory in previously for another reason,
well I'm going to say what this is and we'll leave whether or not this
in this particular case you actually have to call it as an exercise
for the reader because I'll be honest I really don't know if you do or
don't I would suspect that you don't in this case need to call it, but
that may not be true because it may be the case that
Well yeah, I mean the instruction prefetch.
Maybe could hit it before you got there or something, and then be
wrong.
I don't know if that's how that works.
My knowledge of the Ecstasy for CPU is simply not good enough to say.
So, I'll just simply say what this is talking about and why you may
need to call it or may not.
So we all know from talking about it, on handmade here, obviously,
that data always goes through a cash, right?
In the processor, there's this cash sitting there and the reason for
that is because typically speaking when a processor touches the piece
of data, it's probably going to touch it more than once.
So usually when the processor goes and does some
Operation, on memory nowadays, it goes through a cache.
The cache is designed to be a smaller version of memory, that's faster
to operate on.
So things, move into the cache much like they move into registers
which are even faster.
It's kind of like this tiered system of things come from memory to L3,
cache to L2 cache, L1 cache, two registers back out to L1, L2, L3, and
so on, right?
How that works.
Well, the same thing is true for instructions.
Instructions actually go into a cash as well.
And the interesting thing about this cash is this cash may actually
not store the actual contents of the instructions.
What this cash actually stores potentially are the Micro Ops of the
instructions.
So there's actually different kinds of caches, there's caching the
actual bytes of data that form the instructions.
And that's one way that the instructions might be cached.
But there's another thing called a Trace
Cash which oppressor can have, which is the thing that actually
stores?
A more specific decomposed version.
That the processors already looked at and potentially stored in an
even more decomposed form than the assembly language.
Do something that's more specific to the processor and how it's going
to execute it.
So there's actually multiple ways in which code can be cashing.
The cash just in terms of caching the memory, but it can also be
cashed in a way that that has actually sort of dis disaggregated the
code into smaller pieces, like Micro Ops that the op that
A processor actually wants to operate on.
So there's multiple ways in which codes can be cached, and if the
processor is not smart enough in a particular circumstance to know
that you have modified a piece of code and that it needs to invalidate
its cash.
You can tell it.
So that's what this function is.
It's flush instruction cache and basically what it does is it says I'm
going to give you a pointer and a size and I want you to take
everything that's in there and assume that you're going to have to
reek.
Refresh your caches of that if they happen to be there for it for
execution, right?
And so, if we want to do that, what we would do is after we generated
the code, we would call flush instruction cache with the actual.
I should put that pure as well, because this is another
One of these.
We've this is a symptom signed don't quote me on that.
This is a handle, this is a LP void and this is another one of those
size tease.
Okay, so there's our flush instruction cache and we're going to have
to deal with this definition of handle in a second here.
But then we're going to have to do is we're going to have to pass
flushing destruction cast, something for that handle but then we're
just going to be able to do exactly what we did for our virtual Alec
so we can pass that and the code size.
So what we really want to do here is just say how big is our code
page.
So we'll say code page size and we'll just say 4096 and then we'll
say, Okay, past that here pass that
There and that will flush the instruction cache.
Now, the handle
in this case 4-H process again, we sort of have this problem of where
we going to get that from.
And furthermore, we need a way to get our actual process.
I believe I showed this on handmade hero but the get
Handle function actually will do that for us.
I don't know.
Can we pass 04 that I should have double-checked?
I don't know if we can.
I don't think so.
Although sometimes you can and they don't say so I don't actually know
but I'll go ahead and do the full version anyway.
Get module handle gets the process handle and windows of the
particular process and you can pass zero for the module handle name
there.
So, in this case, I've got this
Like so.
Long prayer to a string module name.
There we go.
And so I'm going to go ahead and just pass get module handle.
Zero here.
And so the only thing that we really need now is a definition for
these two things of of handle and of H module, which we don't
currently have.
But again, I can do the exact same thing I did before to get those
definitions into our program here.
And if you're wondering why I'm doing this sort of just lb including
windows .h, it's because I wanted to keep it so that we are completely
in control the process.
And we are, we are providing all of the code that's actually getting
compiled because that's kind of the you know, low-level sir.
That we were doing so here.
If I do get module handle, right?
And I ask for the definition of that, you can see here that with it
goes to ask you version there, and let's take a look at the H.
Module definition, go to definition.
You can see that there's a bunch of typedefs here.
It's actually an H.
Instance, is what that is and declare handle is used for that.
We need to go to declare
Andal.
And you can see that basically it's just an anonymous struct with an
intent in it, right?
That's about all that's happening here.
And so if we want to create one of those, we can pretty simply by just
saying, okay really all we're talking about here for a handle is this
and I believe it doesn't matter at all.
These are just things that get it seems they're just dummies trucks
dummy, ways of talking about it, right?
So I believe we should be fine here.
Oops, gotta have that semicolon there.
And now our get module handle unresolved.
Eternal symbol.
Is that really true?
Right?
It's because we need the ASCII version of that, maybe it doesn't
really matter which one we have there.
There we go.
So now we can call flush instruction cache as well which again I don't
really know that in this case we absolutely needed to do but it's a
good point to bring up regardless.
So if I come back here to our code here, we should now be able to call
both of those functions.
So, here's the virtual AA call, right?
That's calling through here.
Then we're going to generate all the code, so here's all the code gen
etc, etc, etc.
Then we're going to call, I guess, after all the koujun, we have to
call get module handle, a, and we have to call flush instruction
cache.
So let's take a look here.
There we go.
I believe that's the get module handle, although we should actually
cut the dump in to verify that I believe this is the flesh instruction
cache cache.
And actually correct.
Let's take it.
Let's look at the done.
I don't want to say that because I have to look at that a little bit.
I have to look at that a little more closely before I would be able to
say that, that was true.
Cannot open input file, that's because we're not in the right
directory.
All right, let me actually.
Okay, so yeah, you can see, here's the call, get module handle a right
there and there's the flush instruction cache.
So if I actually come back here and take a look at it and kind of
scroll down past all the code flowing out there after the leaa
There we go.
So there's the Ellie, and then there's the call to get module handle.
So there it is.
The call right here.
And what you can actually see here is that it's again, there's that
the Linker has patched it, right?
You can see that the patching happened there because before there
wasn't anything here.
And now there is a 73, right?
So there's the patch that the Linker did and then similarly, here's
the patch again and you can see that these were indirect patches.
So the Linker, probably patch this one.
And then the dynamic Linker, patched this one
Right, it patched this right here.
So it's kind of a double indirection, right?
And in fact, that's when you've got a bunch of these you can see how
it decide to do that.
So instead of welding that call indirectly, it did a double disc
interaction there but there you go.
Let's see insofar as says, I think something like / section, colon dot
data.
/ RW e.
+ /n, x compat:.
No, to link XE might work for the non-virtual.
Protect code in a real thing.
So, yeah, like I said, I don't really know.
You might be right?
in theory, the executable has
It.
Here are my data sections here, my code sections.
Here's how I need you to Mark those when you load them mr.
Windows.
Right.
And I guess the thing about that is just that yeah, there's probably a
magic incantation that lets you say.
I want my data segment to be executable please but I didn't want to
try and figure out what that was so that may be, right?
I have no idea but they're almost certainly is some way to do it.
an acre 314, who is the person who originally asked the question,
maybe this episode belongs to the intro to see week as episode six,
Maybe
Is there 549 may be the smallest CRT ever and it's a link to
something.
Let's see here.
Feel Adele ski says, is there a little reason?
You don't like virtual functions?
My understanding of them is that they're basically just function
pointers in a table.
That is dereferenced.
Yes, there actually is a low-level reason.
I don't like virtual functions and that is that they are uncie
realizable.
So, one of my main complaints with and and furthermore, I can't patch
them.
Right.
One of my main complaints with the way, C++ does virtual function
calls is.
It's an opaque system, so you're not allowed to specify how it's
working.
You can't say, for example, that what you want to have inside your
structs or classes is just an integer that says, what class it is.
And then that integer looks up into a dispatch table somewhere else,
or something like that, which would be serializable.
For example, so low level wise virtual functions are just not very
good, right?
They don't give you the control that you need that you have if you
actually build your own function pointer.
Tables.
As you can do anything you want there, you can have them be double
dispatch, single dispatch.
You can have them dispatch off an integer that you control that
serializable.
You can put it anywhere.
You want in the struct, you can get rid of it in the struct if you
don't need it because you can infer it for something else.
So yeah.
Like like I don't really like anything about virtual functions right
there.
They're a bad feature because they take control away from the program
that they actually need.
There's a good way.
They could have done that and C++, they didn't do it because they
chose not to give you the control that you need in order to write.
Code, that's flexible and interesting.
They chose to go with the really procrustean version that takes a lot
of away Along the power that you get if you're actually using function
pointers yourself.
Engineering says, first of all, thank you so much for this stream.
You are very welcome at the beginning.
You mentioned you hadn't done some of these things for a while.
My question is in, what context did you originally?
Learn and apply.
All this information.
It seems like spending time at work exploring.
This may be considered time
Taken away from actually being quote, unquote, productive is it just
something you have to learn on your own time.
I guess I would say that it depends on the place that you work for.
You know, if you work for a company that values low-level programming
skills and people who can debug very difficult problems and also
create, you know, creative Technical Solutions to things they should
value this quite highly.
I cannot imagine the situation where, you know, Jeff would have come
into my office at
Add and found me.
Looking at how something was happening in a link loader, and telling
me that I was wasting my time, you probably would have been delighted
and probably would have helped explain it to me because he's a very
talented level programmer.
And so that's just the nature of where you work.
If you work at a company whose like main job is to, like stack python
on top of JavaScript, on top of, you know, 12, you know, piles of
libraries 10 high to get sort of a, some weird thing working on top of
the Google.
Maps API.
Yeah, they probably have no interest in you learning stuff because
when would it ever come up and it has nothing to do with you know,
getting the next round of venture capital or whatever.
It just depends on the attitude of the company I work for and what
their priorities are.
I can tell you that, we very rare for you to go to engine development
company for games and have somebody tell you that learning this stuff
is not a good use of your time at the company because this is
definitely a good use of your time, right?
But if you're at a
Higher level than that, I can easily see them saying that because it's
not relevant to what you do there, right?
And so, it's all dependent on what your job function is and what
you're doing.
Furthermore, I would say that in the web development context, I think
this would also not be wasting your time, if you're somebody who's
job, it is.
Let's say at Facebook to do like, back-end stuff where you have to
optimize like some crazy huge amounts of PHP code that's coming in and
you're trying to write this, like, compiler thing that's going to make
your stuff perform better.
Because you've got all this Legacy code that needs executor whatever.
You know, even if you're doing web development, there are places in
web development where the metal or what do they say?
The rubber hits the road, if you will and those people need to know
all these things.
So you know the people who are powering the Google search back end you
know base level stuff and the people who are working on optimizing,
you know Facebook's file IO stuff or whatever.
We all need to know this stuff.
And I don't think those divisions, even though they're in companies
that are piling libraries on top of libraries, in our libraries,
that's one part of company.
There's usually going to be a part of a company that cares a lot about
little programming.
Those people would not consider this a waste of your time.
So I think that's, it doesn't look like we have any more questions.
So I think I will just wrap it up there.
That was an incredibly long handmade hero stream to say, the very
least, but it covered just about everything that I wanted to cover and
hopefully it answered the original question.
Well enough to say that basically now like all of the parts of it are
demystified hopefully and there isn't any sort of like hand wavy weird
thing happening.
Where you're not really sure about what's really going on, right?
So anyway, hopefully that is, that is everything there is to say about
that.
In terms of an introduction, obviously there's loads more, you can
explore on your own, I do appreciate that link from from pseudonym 73,
which I bet is a great place to investigate more about that.
If you want to learn more about Dynamic linking or static linking and
all those sorts of things that we talked about.
So please do
That out if you're interested in more or post on the forums, and
that's about it.
So, thanks for joining me for another episode of handmade hero chat.
This time, if you have questions about the sort of stuff we covered,
you can ask it on the farm site and that is about it for this week.
Next week, we will be back to do regular game coding again until then
have fun, programming and exploring some hopefully low-level code
stuff on your own.
And I'll see everyone on the internet.
So take it easy everybody.