Start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on stream occasionally
after eating way too many of the little candy egg things that I was
eating on the free stream.
It is true that I tend to eat those to excess.
That is why it's pretty good that they're only available in the United
States during Christmas and Easter used to only be available during
Easter.
Now they're available during both Christmas and Easter and as a
Results.
That means I get twice as fat as I used to get but what are you gonna
do?
That's just the reality of the situation and after all this is America
where we are very fat and unhealthy.
So I feel like at the end of the day I'm just doing my part to
maintain our high average rate as a country that said today, on
handmade hero, we're going to go ahead and finish our memory handling
for
Our debug code, which we pretty much got into position of almost
finishing yesterday.
We did the first part of it, but yesterday, I talked a bunch about
stuff and so we didn't have that much programming time.
So today, I want to go ahead and finish that up and then we can start
to move on to cleaning up the UI for our debug stuff as well.
Because then I think we just have our debug system running fairly
fairly cleanly at that point behind the scenes.
And so we just have to start cleaning up the actual way.
It's displayed also Martin's Mosaic.
Oh, I don't know how to pronounce
Is his name, I have never known but you may know him as the person who
answers, like literally all of your questions on the handmade hero
forums.
He also pointed out that the version of Visual Studio that we're
using, which is visual studio 2013, I guess doesn't actually create
thread safe code for.
Static static variables 2015 does but 2013 does not.
And so we also have to decide what we may want to do about that
because we did want to use static variables, we
Don't use static variables in any of our actual game code, but we do
use it in the debug code to try and avoid doing lookups all the time.
And so that code is something that we may have to consider as well.
That's sort of a separate issue that we may want to look at as just in
terms of how things work.
Now, we may not care because at the end of the day it's just the debug
code.
So if we have some kind of a weird race condition where a debug
variable gets added twice or something like this happens, we may just
decide that that's not really that big of a deal and we don't care,
but we should at least make the decision that we don't care.
We shouldn't just
Art of Let It language.
So that's also something we should probably take a look at at some
point.
Now, I will remind you today is day to 17 so if you are following
along at home and you are someone who has pre-order the game on a
meter, a tour and you want a phone source code day, 216 source code.
That is a source code that you want to be following along with today.
Now, if I remember correctly, where we left off yesterday was just
that we will hit our assertion about not being able.
To actually do any of the freeing of the memory.
Wanted to do it so you can see the game kind of running here.
It starts to fill up the debug before the debug buffer gets filled and
then we get our assertion fires right here.
When when it actually tries to go get the memory.
So for those of you who may have forgotten what was supposed to be
happening here, what's going on, is just as the debug buffer, fills
up.
When it tries to first time, it tries to allocate memory, that would
overflow that debug buffer.
So it goes to the overdose, I need this much memory and the above
offer doesn't have that much memory in it at that point.
Then what happens is we try to free stuff?
And so this is our little routine here that was supposed to free
variable groups.
It does not currently free variable groups, it just asserts and that
is why.
Sir fired, right?
So let's go ahead and push through that.
So here is our free variable group situation.
It's not in that file.
Here's our free variable group, and if we take a look at how debug
variable group actually is implemented, we should be be able to see
fairly immediately how that is supposed to occur.
Now, like I said, it's a little bit janky.
What I, you know, I'm a little bit torn, I kind of feel like, maybe we
I want to just actually kind of rewrite, a little bit of this stuff or
rather clean this stuff up a little bit, as we do it.
Instead of writing the free, then changing it.
And then rewriting the free basically.
Because what I was saying yesterday, is that really these debug
variable groups?
That part of it is really a standing structure and its really the
debug events themselves that are the part that needs to get freed
overtime, right?
And so really that part of it is kind of why I was sort of saying, you
know, I think maybe we want to sort of
Do that part because free variable group honestly isn't something
that's ever really probably going to happen.
Free variable group is not it.
It's going to be freeing these debug event pieces.
Of information is really what's actually going to be getting Freed at
the end of the day.
So I'm just trying to think about how exactly want to do that, how we
want to sort of move towards that kind of a structure for things and
and so, I don't know.
So maybe you know what we'll do is just do that.
Part of it.
First, we'll jump ahead a little bit and then jump back instead of
kind of finishing this up, which is what I was kind of thinking.
Now that I'm looking at it, I'm like, well, you know, probably we
don't really want to do that.
We want to finish this part up first and then finish the other part
up.
All right, so what I was saying before you remember, this was kind of
a little bit, I'm going to call an epiphany because it was just
working through an architectural problem in the way that you do.
But the realization was that linking sort of considering the structure
of things to be baked into the frame was stupid.
What we actually want is the structure of things too.
Be a persistent concept that's built up in understood globally in the
debug system.
And then On Any Given frame, we just have the data for the values that
those things took on at that time, right?
That's what we actually want to have happen.
And so that's what we're trying.
Make work here.
And so that means really this stuff is all totally fine.
And it's really just this part that has to change.
And then the main difference is just going to be that in here when we
had debug frame, right?
And you know in here we've got kind of have the super frame thing
instead of the root grouping and here it's really just a question of
kind of pulling back a little bit and and putting it back in the debug
state which is actually where it used to be right.
Just putting it back in there and going.
All right this route group that we had in here before.
In fact you can still see the variable was still there writing though.
I don't think it's actually
So being used for anything at the moment.
If we just make the route group exists in there, permanently then that
takes care of the hierarchy, part of things.
And we never actually free the hierarchy, the hierarchy, just grows to
the point where it contains all the possible debug points that exist
in the program, which is not that many right?
It's a finite number of them that are just existing, you know, in the,
in the code where we've said, please give us some debug coverage here.
And after we do that, right?
Then what we want to do is have some way.
So we've got that debug hierarchy.
What we want to do is have some way of having these debug events, sort
of Stack up in one of those, right?
So if we have, you know, we almost have like sort of this this concept
like I said of the of a debug element, which is really just like.
Okay, I've got some number of events in here and like I said, I don't
really
You know exactly how we want this to work per se but you know, just if
you imagine the simplest possible thing, you could imagine us,
literally just chaining these events together and then sort of pulling
them out as we start to free things, we'd pull them out.
That's the simplest possible thing.
You could also Imagine keeping a race here.
I'm not sure what the, you know, the what the best way to do that is
I'm not sure which is the way that we want to do.
It but we do know what we actually want to have happen.
So what we want to have happen is when we go to free memory, you know.
Because so let's say we have one of these devotee book variable links
here, right?
And that's the standing structure that contains the UI.
It's, you know, it's so so these are like this, the sort of the UI
pieces that are floating around that are that are viewing things or
doing whatever else, right?
You can imagine that we're saying okay, it's viewing some element and
an element has some number of events in it that all belong to this
element, right?
Or whatever the data is that needs to be in here, right?
So you can you can take one of those debug events or something.
And you can imagine, let's say that we were just doing a more
hard-coded kind of a system, right?
One that wasn't you know, designed to be flexible or anything that you
can imagine something like this where you're just like, oh, in even we
could even just hard code.
It you said like oh, there's eight events per debug element, they just
kind of come in and then they fall out when they fall out or, you
know, whatever, right.
You can imagine something like that being the hardcore.
But if we want these things to just sort of Stack up until we run out
of memory, then my question is just okay, it's easy to have them stack
up because as the events come in and we collate them, we find the
debug element to which they correspond and we stick them in there,
right?
That's pretty easy to do.
But what we don't know, is when we need to reclaim memory, what event
do we free?
See I'm saying that's the part that's not immediately clear and so you
can imagine these being double threaded, I don't know.
You know how that sounds kind of crazy.
I'm not sure, that's really something we would want to do, but you can
imagine like, okay, we're going to free a frame.
We need to kind of go through all the debug elements that exist and we
need for every debug element.
We need to free like one event off of them, right?
So if we take
look in the actual debug interface where we have a debug event here,
you can kind of see that this at the moment doesn't have any room.
For anything in it really extra, right?
Because these are going into the log and we don't want to blow that
out at all.
So really, what we would have here is we have like a debug if, you
know, debug stored event or something like that.
And we would put debug events in here.
And then we would, you know, point to the the next one or whatever,
something like this.
You know I'm saying?
And and this right here would probably have something where we would
go oh you know what?
There's
There's there's a debug stored event.
And it's the first event or something like that.
Right?
And you know, like I said you can imagine, I don't know how we want to
do this exactly.
But I'm just saying this is the simplest thing that that would capture
what we actually need it to do, like what we actually need to have
occur, is this?
So in here we would just say okay and you know this would probably be
you know again just something that we would chain very simply and so
if we want to do something like this we would have these debug
elements.
The debug elements would store basically just a chain of events.
And any one of the UI systems and thing could point to one of those
and be displaying it basically, right?
So
if we were to do that, then what we would need is some way of walking,
all of the debug elements that exist and pulling.
Again, the first thing off of there, debug event chain, every time we
wanted to sort of like free memory, we just kind of go through there
and gank you know some guys and and toss them and free them.
So, that would be relatively easy for us to do again.
There's a little bit of sort of Oddity there because if you imagine
that not on, it's not true that on every
Frame that we would actually have a debug events for every element
that exists.
And so we also don't really know which frame we're talking about.
So it's almost like to, you would also want something like this,
right?
Where every time we free a frame we go through.
And any, you know, we look through the events that we have, and we're
only going to free frames that match that frame Index, right?
And if the frame index that we see is actually,
Lee greater than the frame index that we're trying, you know, where
we're trying to make the cut off, then we don't free it.
So that's, you know, again not saying this is anything particularly
brilliant.
I'm not saying this is a really necessarily a good idea.
I'm just trying to figure out like what would sort of roughly
accomplish the thing that we would need to accomplish?
That seems like we would need something like that.
Okay, so if we push forward on that a little bit, then what we would
need to do again, is we need to have this, you know, storing.
These things is pretty straightforward.
But what is less straightforward potentially is how we iterate over
them, when we need to free them.
And I suppose, the way we could do that is we could just use the route
group and iterate over it like walking it like a hierarchy, just sort
of the standard way that we would iterate over anything else and in
fact, you know, we've kind of already
I have a way to iterate over it.
Right?
Where is that code?
We've got that in here somewhere.
Yeah, so in here, where we've got this kind of like iteration code.
Like so that's an example of what we could do.
We could iterate over everything and do the freeing as part of that,
iteration pass, right?
As part of the sweep through what we were doing.
We could do that, right?
It's just a thought.
That's one way we could do it.
One thing I do not actually remember about our code is why we were
actually doing it.
I don't remember why we were saying like, oh, we shouldn't do it with
recursion.
There was something where it's like, oh, will write it without
recursion maybe just to write it without.
I don't even remember, there's some weirdness going on there.
So we may also want to make this a little less.
Obtuse while we're at it because I think I was just like, out to lunch
that day.
In fact, I even think I said, I was felt like, I was out to lunch that
day, but that's separate issue.
Anyway.
So, yeah, if we want to do that, that's really all we would need is
some way to kind of get through here.
So I'm going to go ahead and give this a shot and to see kind of what
comes out of it, right?
So if you take a look at what's going on here, if we have this, like,
I don't really remember again, which of these because we kind of, sort
of gut it, a bunch of that stuff.
I don't necessarily remember which ones of these were doing what or,
or why, or when, or how, or anything like that.
so, what we would need to do,
Is first for every frame that we might have.
We're going to need some kind of an index for that frame, right.
We're gonna have to take these debug frames and we're going to
presumably keep all this stuff.
I don't really want the region stuff anymore because you know so let's
get rid of that as well.
We'll sort of cut that part out but we need something here.
That's like the frame Index.
This is like the canonical frame index and that's again the thing that
in here would tell us which one were sort of doing there and then when
we create a new frame, right?
When we create one of these,
Is and we set like stuff like the begin clock value and stuff like
that.
So here we are a new frame, right?
Then, what we need to do, every time we do a new frame, is we need to
actually create inside there.
A frame Index, this canonical.
So we need to do like, debug State frame, you know, like total frame
count or something like that.
And so then here where we've got, you know, the frame cat which is
probably going to be something more.
Like how many frames are in here or whatever?
We've got a total frame count, to be honest.
I don't even know if that's actually necessary.
Tomorrow, but we've got a total frame count, which is going to be a
number that has increments As We Run the game.
Now normally, that would mean that we have a limit of 4 billion
frames, right?
Because otherwise then it will wrap around.
And if you think about what that implies in terms of, I guess I can
use emacs cualquier.
I was forget, if you think about what that means, if you were to say,
okay, we've got, you know, for x, 1024 x, 1024 x 1024.
Right?
And that's how many frames, you know, the that in that unsigned
integer will go from 0 to 4 billion, right?
As that goes up,
how many frames is that?
Well, if we were doing 60 frames a second, right?
Then that's how many seconds it would be if that makes sense.
And so, if that's how many seconds and then we want to know like how
many minutes that would be like another 60 seconds, right?
In a sorry, it's 60 frames per second and then 60 seconds in a minute,
right?
And then we've got what 60 minutes in an hour.
And then like 24 hours in a day or something like this, right?
I think that did I get that, right?
Don't know why.
That just and so that would run for like, what two years is that
correct?
Let's let's double check how many seconds in a day, right.
Seconds in a day to do it.
To do it.
So basically, we know we've got, we've got this x 60 frames per
second.
And so that's how many actual frames we would go through in one day,
right?
And so if we wanted to know, when we would wrap,
This is the calculation.
That's how many frames we can Count versus how many frames in a day.
That's how many days.
So yeah, we did it right 828.
So, you know, realistically is anyone going to be capturing debug info
for two and two and a half years or whatever that is?
No.
So we don't really have to worry about this wrapping.
So I think we're totally fine there.
And so then every time we do a new frame, all we have to do is just
assign a new index to it.
And those index indices will sort of just grow over time
monotonically, right?
I'm going to go ahead and nuke the region index stuff here.
Just go ahead and get rid of it.
Temporarily.
And then we can start to focus on this other part of the debug code
that we need to fix.
Which again, is that sort of concept of where does the stuff go, as we
sort of pull it, out of the debug stream and put it into something, we
need to put it into these, like, debug start events.
So let's make that actually happen.
So okay.
Looks like this is just capturing.
Yeah.
So what's happening here is this is that violent interaction.
This is just if you were trying to interact with one of the debug
values, right?
Then what you were doing is you're passing one of these links and
before the link pet pointed directly to the event that was interacting
with now, it's not going to anymore.
You're going to have to kind of come down to an element and so on.
And what's interesting about this is probably I would also say inside
the debug element, we'd probably want to know like the
Stan last of, of the series because this is like the most recent, and
this is like the oldest, right?
So it's actually like the oldest event and the most recent event,
right?
And each one of those, you know, we kind of have those sort of change
over time, like I said,
So yeah, so if you want to interact with one of those guys then you're
in a situation where you have to have something again where you know,
you're going to have to, you're going to have to sort of grab ass out
of here.
So this would have our link interaction would have to be something
where I guess, you know, we would look here and say if the there is an
actual event present in the thing, then you can do it because
otherwise, you couldn't do it.
Like there might be no.
At all in whatever this particular thing is that you're trying to
interact with and that would make it so that you can interact with it.
Right?
So presumably you have something like this, where you're like, okay,
whatever the links element is.
It's got a most recent event, whatever that is.
That's the one, you would presumably be interacting with right and and
on here you'd say like, okay,
Because again, if you're interacting with something, it's it's a
little dicey.
To because now I think about it, there's there's additional things.
You might even want to do here, which are even more complicated than
this, which is like if you're trying to interact with a particular
frame index, then this would want to sort of look through that linked
list and say, do we have one for this particular frame, right?
Which is even more kind of crazy if you think about it.
So yes, I don't know.
It also even maybe sort of suggests to me like as I kind of think
about it in my head, like do you want to just be throwing all these
things into
Sort of a hash somewhere where you're just kind of like dumping events
into the hash and then, you know, they come in or come out or whatever
like something like this, I don't know.
Again, that's something that to be thought of, if we ever want to
optimize the debug system which you know, probably we may be never
would even do.
So anyway, if we have something like this then we can interact with
the event.
That way we can just say all right you know we'll go out and grab it.
Yeah.
Matt's I think mostly
We would really be talking about.
So in here, when we're grabbing events out, I think the same thing is
true, right?
For events.
I don't know how the events get used in here or if they get used
exactly how they occur.
So, yeah, there's the like event type stuff that we're switching off
of.
So really, what we would want to do here is check to make sure that
the event actually exists, right?
I think we would want to do something like this.
Oops.
And then we would kind of come through here and bracket around that.
So assuming that the event actually exists, that way we can do, again
the same thing.
And you know, what I'll do since since people are going to be pulling
this out, I want to make an actual utility function out of that, so
that we can maybe potentially make it do different things in the
future as well.
So, if we just said, okay, there's this concept that you can get the
debug event pointer back from a particular link.
So you can be like, get event.
From link or something.
And I don't mean link, like the character in Legend of Zelda, right?
So anyway, here's the debug variable link.
And it's going to just be this.
So exactly the same thing that I was doing yours result.
So the result equals this guy
And then we return him.
So, that way, if in the future, we do want to do something where it
looks at like some active frame selection, sort of a situation or I
don't really know what we want to do, but that would give us maybe a
way of going.
Like, when we just want to know, whatever the, like current thing to
print is
We know it's going through get event from link, so we can do some kind
of fancy jazz in there.
If we need to
All.
So that also means this can go away, doesn't have to check any more.
It can just sort of do its thing where it's like, oh yeah, get it from
that, and everyone's happy, and, and smiling, and it's just great, and
everyone loves it, and it's fantastic.
And it's just the best thing ever.
And that's great.
Okay, so that's all good.
Oops, except I didn't put in the right name for it.
And so here is our debug event.
Like I said, this is just like get event from link and then we can
just do that and we're good functions.
Not take our head.
That's true.
It takes a debug State as well.
So, all these verlan contractions, are presumably going to be that
way.
So they've got a pet, take the debug State now as well.
Yeah.
Region count.
So add region is just going to be a task 0.4 now because I don't even
know that we're going to have that anymore.
All right, so we've got events.
So we do add very little group here at the debug event and we're
adding the debug event.
So this thing, you know, again, this is not actually correct anymore
because this thing that's that's building up variable groups.
Those are actually going to be permanent things now.
And so what we actually need is when we're building up those
hierarchies we now
Way of, like, sort of permanently placing things in a debug hierarchy
because that hierarchy is going to exist, essentially forever.
So when we say add variable to group and again, like the other thing
that's a little bit weird about that is we we have the choice and I
don't know what we want to necessarily do about it, but when you think
about what's going to go on here, there's two kinds of hierarchies as
well.
That we might talk about.
There's the hierarchy of the data coming in from the debug system and,
you know, maybe
Don't even necessarily considered that exactly a hierarchy.
Anyways, it's just we have a certain set of possible debug locations,
right?
We've got those and then we also have, you know, some sort of a
hierarchy for the UI.
and that hierarchy is more fluid and
implies a bunch of different stuff because the user maybe wants to
drag things around and that sort of thing.
So I'm not sure exactly again, how we want to handle that stuff.
It's kind of a little bit odd and it's again, it's we sort of had we
have the ability to deal with this stuff before by by using the
counter variables.
Now, we don't have those anymore, but we're synthetically creating
those, remember we?
Inside debug interface.
What we did there is we just did a like
Where is?
It?
No, no, it's not that it is.
Where's the code?
It's not Atomic, add you 64.
It's not cool events rain but I know it's none of these things.
Yeah.
So they're supposed to be
I thought we did a thing where this calls into the debug system and
says, hey I want you to allocate a new one.
We had like a static.
We had like static variables and all that stuff.
Yeah here it is.
Here it is.
I was like this is the whole thing where I was talking about the
beginning.
Yeah.
This is the stuff that I'm talking about.
So in here when we have the sort of static values that have to get
initialized and all
Kind of nonsense.
This whole thing here, debug initialize value where we have sort of
this recording of a thing that we record once, and then we get back, I
guess a permanent pointer to it, that sort of thing.
So what exactly?
I just want to refresh my memory as to what we're getting back with
that.
So I can plan out how these things would work.
Let's see here.
So when we do one of these, we do a record debug event with
Debug type, Mark debug value.
And then we don't actually do anything with that.
What, wait what?
What?
Allah S cord?
Debug event.
What's going on here?
So it just gets one of these events back, but how does that?
How does that help?
How does that help anybody?
We get back one from the global.
We just get what you know this is just getting back.
All this is doing right.
Is getting back a entry into the debug event table.
So how does that help us with our static initialization of these guys
here?
What is that?
Actually,
Oh, we passes.
We pass it forwards.
Well then, all right.
So you can see what happens here, right?
So essentially, we don't actually know in the debug system we pass.
We do a local persist here.
And and that local persist is the debug event gets passed into the
debug system.
The debug system records, the fact that there is a debug event.
Now, sitting on the stack of this, you know,
Of the caller and that is well, it's not.
S Clark because it's a static variable so it's actually in the Heap
but point being the the caller's scope has that in there and we use
that as the permanent location of this thing.
So the reason that that's kind of a little disappointing is because
again it means that we don't have any kind of a real table entry or
anything in particular for the, you know, we don't have anything that
we build up in here, that's already correspondent.
We would have to do something like use the address of that variable.
You know where or who knows what exactly.
And so yeah, I'm not 100% certain how I feel about that, but I suppose
just a hash table that hashed on that location, wouldn't necessarily
be a bad thing for any particular reason.
I mean, I can't think of anything at least is what?
Guess what I would say.
And at some level I also do think that if all we really need is an ID
That's Unique, if we were just going to always use like a hash table
or something like that.
Then having a static variable.
Might actually be all we need.
So riddle, me this Batman.
Here's what I'm, here's what I'm thinking.
So, what I want out here, right?
Because I want to be able to do something.
In fact, you know, if we, if we look at what we had here, we've got
these debug stored elements or whatever these debug elements, or
whatever they are.
Right.
And we've got this sort of stuff with the tree.
That's like how we would might display in the UI, but then we actually
have the values that we're going to store and those
In here.
And so we need some way of like as we see things, we need a way of
like corresponding them out to these to these debug elements, right?
And you can imagine if we just had a big old thing of these debug
elements, you know, cure whatever.
You know whatever we want to do there.
If we just had a big old thing of these debug elements, we need to
then be able to find the debug element that corresponds to something
and before we were using counters for that you know so that we could
know exactly which one we were talking about but we kind of we're
saying that that's maybe not the best thing in the world to do because
that force is that whole weird thing with the translation units
needing to be defined and it sort of was adding all this complexity
and we didn't really want to have to deal with it.
And so what I'm thinking is like okay if we did have some kind of just
a hash table sort of a situation where we looked up things in the hash
table.
I
Look what we could do is use the static variables address, right?
We could use the address of this guy as the thing that would tell us
what what I you know a unique ID so basically it gives us sort of the
equivalent of counter in that they're unique but it's not quite as
good as counter because they're not like linearly laid out in a
perfect array fashion, which is what we would, you know, prefer to
have.
We could since we can't have that, it would give us
Is it would effectively give us what we wanted, right?
We could also do something a little bit, a little bit more.
For sort of wish we could use sort of a thing that increments a
variable as well to get a linearized version.
Hmm, she was like yesterday right on schedule, I'm still.
So jet-lagged.
I've been going to bed at like 8:30 at night, so it's like, you know,
I get off handmade here on, there's like an hour or two before I'm in.
I'm just asleep.
So anyway, looking at this.
I'm just trying to think of like what the right way is to correspond
out to those debug elements and I'm not sure exactly what it is.
What the best way to do that would be and you know hash table seems
like maybe it's as good as anything else for that.
Seems like a fair thing and we could probably we've already got the
Sensitive hashing, these things in the view hash week, I guess that,
but that's dependent on the piece of UI that were talking about so
that that probably wouldn't really help us out much.
So we would need a different hash, which is again, kind of annoying,
but I don't know, seems reasonable.
It seems like a reasonable way to get it.
Those things, I don't know.
I don't know.
I don't have a strong opinion about it one way or the other, to be
honest with you.
Do you guys have a strong opinion about it?
I don't know how you're feeling about it.
I think I'm just going to say, like okay, maybe maybe we just do have
a hash so we've got something like here's the element hash or
whatever.
And we just stick stick.
We stick stuff in there as we go, something like that, it's in theory,
it's plausible.
I could believe it, you know, I could, I could believe it.
So at that point, we also have the sort of values group.
You think these are you?
I things, right?
And in fact, I think these would probably go away to some degree.
And we would just have a tree.
A particular debug tree that we consider to be the tree that we that
we build up initially.
That like the is the route you.
I tree something like this.
So we wouldn't actually have these.
I don't know if values group is used anymore.
I suspect, it's probably not but I'll double-check, let's see here
values group.
Yes, / values group is just the sort of thing.
Thing we were using for our sort of debug hacky like.
So the values there is Route group getting used other than in the
frame as well would be the other question.
I have so route group create freely in the frame.
Not really either.
So it's only being used in there, so yeah.
So
I feel like that's the that's the transformation that we want to make.
I feel like that's a transformation we want to make.
So we'd have to have looks like this, right?
We have the view hash which is basically the thing that stores the how
the UI itself is wants to sort of view things like how, what the
status of things is in the UI, we have the debug element hash which
basically says, for anything that we're getting data about, we have a
place where we dump sort of its state over time, which is fine.
And and yeah.
And that seems maybe like it's reasonable enough for now.
I don't know.
So, let's see if I want to do that, right?
And, and I guess the other thing too, is that, like I said, we have
these, the sort of debug UI trees and the debug UI trees, could be
whatever the user wants to build as the user is, like, kind of making
stuff, you know, that they might want to use to view things, or
whatever else are doing, who knows, you could imagine them doing this.
So, as the user, it's like doing that process.
they're creating trees, but
we would also presumably have one canonical tree.
That would work sort of, as the, you know, as this stuff goes, right?
So we've got ground chunks underscore checkerboards and that was, we
were sort of saying we wanted that to mean, like, okay, there's a
ground chunks, like there's a, you know, hierarchical item ground
chunks.
And then underneath the higher Echo, element, ground, chunks.
There is an entry checkerboards, and that's a Boolean that you can
switch on and off.
Right.
So, if you imagine that
Being a thing, then that thing needs to exist somewhere.
As sort of the canonical you I that you can play with right?
A UI that you're not
Editing that you can't screw around with potentially that sort of just
the canonical one that gets built up.
And so what that suggests to me to is like okay there's there's a tree
Sentinel or whatever that has like debug treats in it but then we
probably also have a debug tree that sort of a separate one which is
just like the root tree or I don't know something like that.
Where we would have this this one tree whereas things come in when we
see a new thing we find a place.
Where it should go in the tree, by doing the name matching as we go.
And you know, it gets the thing gets stuck in there.
So I feel like we would also need that because in addition to the
element hash which is just the thing that actually stores the stuff
that we have, we would also sort of have to have this concept of the
tree of the root tree which is sort of the the UI version of that.
So the element hash the sort of the weird thing about this too is the
element hash we probably don't want that.
Has to be particularly large would be my guest as well.
And the reason I say that is because I feel like the element hash is
going to have to be iterated over all the time.
Anyway, because remember anytime we want to free memory we've got to
go through that element.
Hashed find some stuff in it that we're going to free and free it.
So we don't want to be stepping over a huge number of things.
And since there's not going to be that many places in the code
necessarily that have this that have debug points in them, you know,
we're talking about, you know, and
Some kind of a relatively small number.
So when we do that, looping over those variables to do the reclaiming
of memory space.
I feel like that's probably what we would want.
Is a relatively small number of things to Loop over.
Now, there's probably a smarter way again, like I said, to sort of,
To look at this stuff.
But again, I don't want to like make the world's most optimized debug
system that can sort of be an exercise left for the reader of how you
would sort of start to take these Concepts in, like maybe turn the
crank on them a little bit because the, again, the end-user will never
run this code.
So it's strictly like going to be there for for our benefit, which
means if it runs fast enough to be usable in a debugging scenario than
it's fast enough.
So okay, so let's say we did something like that.
Then what would, what that would imply is when we do free frame, then
what we would do is free variable group would not actually be what
would happen, right?
We would free the frame, but we would also then have a thing which
would go through here.
And it would just say like, okay, you know, for all in the debug state
for all of the entries in the hash table of the element, hash
then for all of those Jimmy,
For all of those things, the element hash what?
And want to do is we want to look at the chain as whatever that hash
chain is, right?
Because we've got sort of debug elements here.
Oops.
Debug element.
So in here, where we've got these d block elements, and we've got
these events and then we presumably also have the dual enrollment like
you know, next in hash or whatever if they're in the hash.
So in here we would have to go okay for each debug element in the
chain, right?
So here's the element debug State element.
Hash
I want hash index for each element in the chain.
We want to take a look and for all of the events that have been stored
for this particular element, right?
So, for any event that got attributed to it, we know that we've got
from oldest to most recent, we want to free any of them.
That are before the frame that we're trying to free map, right?
So we're trying to free a particular frame, so anything with that
frame index or earlier should be flushed and so that's a pretty simple
while loop, right?
It's just going to say, while the oldest event.
Whatever that is has.
I guess we should say, first of all, while there is an oldest event
and that oldest events frame index.
Is less than or equal to whatever our frame index is that we're
freeing.
We want to free it, right?
So, we would want to say, okay, this particular, debug stored event.
And you know what?
We wrote.
We already wrote this code, to we wrote this here.
We want to do a free list, deallocate on these
So come through say like, alright for everything in the element hash
if the if the oldest event, if there is an event in there and is
famous is less, then we know that we want to take that guy.
Whatever the oldest event is this is debug what is it called, debug
stored event.
So, this is what we're going to free.
Right.
And we want to
We want to then free it and update the pointers, right?
So we want to say the element.
Oldest event equals the free event next, and then we also want to say
that the oldest event most recent I'm sorry, the element most recent
event if that is equal to the event being freed.
Then we know that you know it's also going to be that but that that
actually means it should also be null, right?
So this dish is really should always just be 0, but whatever we could
even is sort of that
This.
So assuming that we do that, then we want to deallocate here at the
free list pointer would be just in the debug State.
We just have a pool of these guys that just gets recycled.
So that would just be first three stored event.
And this guy is just the element, sorry the the free event.
That's what I meant, right?
So that's it.
That's how we would free a frame.
So we basically free all of the elements in that frame that are no.
All of the elements that exist, currently all of their stored events,
that would have been on, or before that frame, they go away.
And you know, we could be more specific and and do that and just say
it look whatever.
But I feel like I kind of want it to catch all like let's say we free
a frame and then somehow we get an event that comes in late and gets
added you know in there somehow I feel like we want to do something
where we just would make sure that, you know, eventually it would get
cleaned up.
It's probably not necessary but it's just, I'm just kind of saying why
not right?
And so while that's true we just kind of loop through and we just
Pull off and free all of those, right?
And that's and that's all there is.
So that would be how we would free a frame.
There's also in here.
Now, we would, we would have a debug stored Events, first free stored
event,
And whenever we would, you know, after we would for your frame,
whenever we would be coding, debug records.
Now when we would sort of be putting these things into place, then we
would sort of do this, this notion of taking a vent off of the free
list and using it for storage, right?
So there you go.
That's what that is.
So now we need to kind of like press forward a little bit and finish
up the rest of the stuff.
Oops.
And so, again like I said, the question here is we sort of have these
these trees and things and I, you know, I'm wondering, is the tree was
there?
Anything in particular?
Why did we still need the tree?
Can we get rid of the trees and just use variable groups for that?
Is there anything with does a tree?
Do anything that we care about at all?
Is it just because it stores?
Like where it was?
Is that like all we need it for and I think that's, it does appear.
That that's the case.
So really a debug tree like is almost nothing relevant anyway so yeah.
Anyway let's so let's let's go ahead and get rid of all this stuff.
I'm just going to say that this stuff goes away entirely at the moment
and that's fine.
And so let's go ahead and
To compile this.
So now we're talking about the stuff where we have to actually start
to fix up the collation.
And, and I feel like we've got rid right of the, handmade variable
stuff yet, right of debug variable, that's tough slog on, right?
Yeah.
Because then we remember, we previously had a file that had a bunch of
other stuff in there.
So we have this sort of like variable group stuff and I think we
previously were calling them collate and and now we're not anymore.
Yeah.
So all that stuff already got
And up and that's good.
But this stuff is still not really correct, right?
Like this stuff is now kind of still doing doing it the old school way
which is not what we actually wanted to do.
So for example when we do this thing that's called create variable
care where we actually want to be doing now is we want to be doing a
thing where whenever we see something new we're going to be placing it
into this element.
Hash based on some kind of information that we get about it, right?
And so we want to do things here where we're you know this this whole
Situation is now not really correct, right?
So let's take a look at where that's actually happening because it
should only be happening in one place I believe.
Now if I'm not entirely mistaken, where does create variable actually
occur, okay?
It never occurs is that what you're telling me, shouldn't that have
been, okay, cuz it just.
All right, I take it back before the reason that it never happens.
Is because right?
We got rid of the concept that you ever actually create those things
out of mine.
Okay, that's fine.
That's one more thing we don't have to do.
I guess.
So anyway, what that means is now all we have to do right here is this
is this is where everything would happen.
This is where an event comes in that.
Some kind of a type that just means we're seeing event.
That's data that we need stored, right?
It's not something like this where we're seeing a begin block, end
block, although even this right here, instead of creating these
regions, I think this probably is something again that we would want
to create sort of those standing structures for.
So that's actually something that I feel like we probably would want
to have happen as well.
So really, I think this code should probably in here instead of
creating a region.
Like I said, get rid of that concept that region concept entirely.
We can actually make that just be something that gets stored like
everything else is being stored.
So we have the begin block and blocks all again.
Go straight into that that, that key element that the element hash,
right.
I'm actually starting to be pretty happy with this.
I think this is going to come together really.
Nicely takes a long time to get to the right thing, but I think this
is starting to this starting to be like, actually like a little bit
more started to starting.
I feel like it's arriving at a good place to me, and that's nice.
It's like you can tell, I don't know.
It's just I don't know if this is just like having worked on so many
architectural problems in the past.
You never know when you've arrived at like the perfect architecture
necessarily because you never know what you might be missing or what
could be better.
Like, it's hard to always know like what the future could be.
But there's definitely at least from my experience at this point.
There's definitely a feeling that I get when I know, I haven't gotten
to the architecture that I should be doing at the moment.
Like, I haven't gotten to an adequate architecture, right.
I definitely know that.
And before until like, we started thinking about the concept of like,
oh I see there's like these three different things.
There's like the events buffer.
There's the concept of like a static sort of naming of the different
points of the debug.
And then there's the UI hierarchies, and these things are like, you
know, that's sort of the way that they're coming out until that sort
of that locked into place.
I was not.
Getting that feeling of of coalescing, right?
It was just everything was still kind of a little bit.
Like, I don't really know what.
Exactly, I feel like something's a little wrong here.
There's too much stuff.
That's not quite clear about what it should be doing.
And so I like the fact that we, I feel like we've gotten past that
now.
And now, it's just a question of like, okay.
What's a, what's a passable implementation of that thing?
Okay, so again, open data block, closed data block.
These things are.
I believe the only real thing that we care about their is for doing,
like, hierarchical listings of stuff, right?
Like that was all those are really getting used for if I'm not
mistaken.
Like you can see here, we just do like, okay, we open debug block and
that that deep up lock like tells us who like the parent was for our
stuff and all that thing, right?
But I believe that if we have anything else, then like the rest of the
stuff that we're getting is going to be sort of debug marked debug
information, right?
Am I right about that?
Let me see what we're getting here.
I guess at the moment now, I think about it, we're really not even
getting that because at the moment do we even what's the what's the
actual, what's the actual?
Oops, I want to be here.
What's the actual set of things react?
Get so we get Mark debug value.
Does that come through every frame?
They take a look.
Mark, debug value.
To to, to do.
It doesn't so.
So it seems like
it seems to me.
Like, we don't actually.
Okay, so it looks to me right?
Like we don't actually ever get the debug variable stuff here.
We those never come through
Yeah, those never come through multiple face.
Those are strictly, right?
Only, those are ones that basically come from the debug system to the
program, and they never go back the other way.
So, it's debug value is the only one that actually ever goes the other
direction.
And I just wanted to look and see, what does that come through as when
we do a debug value.
So it's an open close data block on the bracketing and then, okay.
And then it's just the type of
Thing is just whatever.
The type of the data was that, it was sending, right?
So it's just going to come through.
Is that?
So in here we are basically getting
That's basically a cacio and it's not.
So that's basically getting Mark.
Debug value is getting handled here, right?
So here are ones that are that are that we handle specially, right?
And then out here, here are the data.
Here is the data stuff that we receive, that's actually just like
feed-forward data, right?
And so, the feed forward data,
I guess we don't have a whole lot of ways to Hash that pointer wise.
Do we or well, you know, we probably actually do.
So, I guess, I'm just trying to figure out what is the unique?
What is the way to identify one of these uniquely?
I guess, you know, file name line, number right?
That sort of thing we could certainly use.
I'm trying to think if we have anything else, when we use debug
variable, I'm sorry.
Debug value to output something, right?
And it looks like, you know, when we do that, we do record debug event
here.
I don't know that we ever actually put anything else in there that we
could use.
We don't create a static variable, which probably, you know, is for
the best.
I don't think we want to constantly be polluting everything with
static variables that you know, it should be as right, only as
possible and that sense.
So I'm not sure what we want to do there.
We could certainly create something a little bit more.
Dramatic there, what I'm thinking.
Is if you look at how debug value works.
So let's let's just say, right, let's say we were to do something.
Where we unique a fight it by using the file line.
We could use like file counter.
Just file encounter would work, right?
So picture this normally, you know, in the other code, we could, uh,
we have the ability to use the address as the hash thing, but in the
case of the value, we don't have that option, but we could do, right?
Pretty easily is in this record, debug event thing, we're passing the
file name here,
But instead we could pass something which was a little bit more
descriptive, right?
Like we could do something that would be guaranteed to be unique for
example.
File plus counter would always be unique.
So you could imagine something that would be like this, right ID or
whatever.
Or, you know, you know, unique ID with, or something, right.
It's grid would be like, oh, whatever the file is, as
String, and then you can imagine whatever a counter was you know, as a
string.
that would be an example and of course we'd have to do the sort of the
stupid macro trick to get that into you know to get that into a
Usable format.
But but that would be a string value and that string value would
always be unique because there is no way to generate the same.
You know, the counter will never be the same value and the file always
unique if eyes it.
So that even if it was a different translation unit it would be fine.
I guess now.
I think about it, if it maybe if it was looking an inline function,
that might break or something like this, but I feel like that's not
something we would really care about too much.
At least not that I can think about so and and for that matter if it
wasn't an inline function then the static value version wouldn't work
either because the address of that static variables will be the same
since the inline function presumably would get you know would get the
same static.
I don't know maybe maybe not.
So I could see doing that which something like you know, unique file
counter string or something.
Like this would just be like that sort of a thing.
And again, we have to do that stupid nonsense that we do every time
which really is annoying.
That we talked about before and that would just be this.
And so, what we do is say okay, we need the unique file counter
string.
Oops, there's any file counter string.
We take the file and we
The counter and we're done.
and I think that would be sufficient and then you'd have the grid and
once you have the grid, you also presumably don't need if you don't
want to
We could stop sending the file on line number just to reduce that
traffic a little bit as well, right?
We could do something like this if we wanted to
Where we do file line counter.
and if we did file line, counter,
Then what we do is we say, all right, when we produce the string, now
that we know that it's file line, counter, we could do like, okay.
We know that the string will have the file name in it and now we want
to basically create something that's going to be a readable like a
readable string.
So it would be the file name, parentheses the line number, right?
And then maybe we just put a dot in there and then the counter, right?
So it's like the nth one of these on that line.
So, in case someone stacked up,
More than one debug variable on the same line, it would still work in
theory.
I think that would work.
Who knows?
So if we did it that way, then everything would have a good in it so
we'd be fine from then on and we don't need any of this stuff anymore
like that stuff can just go away the block name.
I suppose maybe we want to still keep it just because we're using that
for other things but this way we don't actually take up any more
space.
In fact, we took up less space and the grid is actually the thing that
also would allow us to, you know, unique if I things
And so from, then on, we could just use the event great.
And that's what we'd use in the hash table.
Right.
So, in here, we would just do, you know, like hash this event kind of
a thing?
But at this point, we're out of time.
And so, I'll just leave, I'll leave things because I'm such a nice
guy.
I'll leave things in a, in a building state by turning off handmade
internal for now, but we will undo that.
So I'm going to go to a brief Q&A just beforehand.
But yeah, I think we're in good shape.
We just need a little more programming time, which is hard to come by.
And meet here because I only get an hour at night, which is not very
much.
So if you have any questions about what we're doing so far, go ahead
and hit me up with those now, but keep in mind, I kind of have to do
another hour tomorrow to kind of get everything, sort of finished up
with the hashing, but I think we're good.
Otherwise,
No questions.
Elvin for you.
I programming.
What do you think of the model view controller pattern?
so, I guess what I would say is,
I think it's close to being the right way to look at you.
I things or a a right way, a good way.
Let's say to look at you I things but it's a little bit off.
like, you know,
I like to think of things you I wise, in terms of I have definitely
the view part right of MVC.
So there's a thing that's going to create, you know, a sort of a
rendering of some kind of whatever the stuff is that we're working
with right and the model part makes some sense because you know,
whatever that thing is that's producing the viewable you know, the
view of things you need to have something that it's actually sort of.
That it's a nice, have some database.
Some some structure that it's you know, that it's actually rendering
out of so we know we also have some kind of backing model that were
editing.
So the model and view part are pretty obviously reasonable ways of
looking at things, the controller part.
The thing that I have a little bit of a problem with in MVC is a lot
of times when it's described, that part is not.
Really expanded upon to the degree that I think it needs to be in
order to actually have a functioning system.
Like controller is, is partially in the view and partially in some
other code.
Usually, it's usually controller is really two things.
One of, which is usually welded to the view in a number of ways,
right?
And so,
Is really like more like model view manipulator.
Interfere like input processor is really is really the actual thing
and model-view-controller.
It makes it seem like controller is actually separate from view
entirely but the truth is it's not if that makes sense.
So it's close like considering how old model view controller is, it's
actually pretty darn good in terms of like how it thinks about things.
It's just people's
You have to be careful about what you actually mean when you say it
because it's easy to put two potentially like Miss the important parts
of it as guess what I'd say.
SSS McGrath you can never have too many s's in McGrath.
Could you talk a bit about other debug systeme stuff, you've done
before I've done all sorts of debug systems, not much like what you're
doing now, and I'm curious what other stuff you may have done.
Just high-level description, one sentence, descriptions are fine.
So I've done a lot of different debug system things before they range
from, they're all over the map.
I don't know if I'm supposed to really talk about mustache which is
the custom which is the most recent one I did and that was it rad.
That one is pretty baller and so we'll let that once.
For a minute, I've done one.
So granny, had a pretty interesting one.
And I think it eventually got removed after my my tenure there.
I'm not sure anyone.
Even knew it was there besides me.
But basically the way, the debug system worked in granny was pretty
funny, the dll itself had some debug infrastructure in it.
And what it would do is you could actually make a call in to the dll.
And say, give me the root pointer back to the debug system.
And then there was a tray application.
You could run that was like granny debug View and that tray
application.
It was lookin anytime, the granny dll was running, it would call into
it, and it would get that debug information out of it.
So you could in the tray app, look at any running granny applications
that were there and go show me all of the stuff that's in them, right?
And that was kind of fun because
As it's a, just a nice way of like being able to kind of like, have a,
an outboard thing that inspects the debug information inside a running
application.
As it's running, it's just kind of interesting.
So that was a bit of a fun one.
I've definitely done ones that are kind of like the way that I'm doing
it now on the event side of things, there was a new streaming event
models like that.
But they they the other the collation side of things, it doesn't I've
never done one.
That's like, does sort of the stuff that we're doing in there now, but
I've done ones that do like, sort of
Just writing it debug events to a log, kind of a thing.
And I'm kind of in the middle of one of those right now for our code
base at Molly rocket, that hasn't quite reached maturity yet and it's
a little bit different because the way that it's meant to be one that
works sort of in an expandable buffer way and like it's, it's kind of
got different goals as to what it does.
So that one's a little bit different than this one and I'm not sure
there's anything particularly relevant to say about it other than it's
like,
Like it's it's meant to be a little more system Z.
It's meant to be a little more kernel log style, kind of a thing than
it is like this, which is meant for just dumping a bunch of sort of
data into it or that sort of thing.
And then mustache is the one that has most the most crazy stuff in it.
That one has stuff.
That's like, literally it seems like magic when you actually if you
just use it.
But then if you think about it, you're like, oh wait, no, right,
that's not magic.
You can just do that if you want.
and that one does stuff that's like, oh,
That one, basically, supports back Tracy, sorts of things for a lot
for lack of better term.
That one does stuff like, oh, here's a pixel on the screen, tell me
like how it got there, right?
And it's so, it's sort of like, you know, like like pics or one of
those debugging systems that they have imagined having a system like
that, but just for your general code base, right?
And that's, that's what it, it sort of did.
Chris 0.
Can you explain what the macro nastiness?
Exactly.
Does.
Why do you have to underscore levels?
We covered this a couple episodes ago so you're going to want to go
back and look at that.
I gave a complete exercise basically, just because the preprocessor
treats variables that are passed into it or that are intrinsic to it
differently, then, variables that have been passed in more than
It's right.
So like every time you use a variable just to give the capsule
definition.
So if I was to do this
That up.
Sorry this that would not give me a
That was the line number.
It would give me the string underscore underscore a line underscore
underscore, right?
So the first time you pass it in your trying to pass it in so that you
actually get it into a variable right?
The next time.
But but if I did it here, I would actually get the parameter be like
the comes through.
I think it's, I can't remember.
Zack.
What is so you need to pass it in a second time.
In order to then turn it into an actual different variable than the
actual word.
The score underscore line.
It's just C++ preprocessor, Ridiculousness, and I never remember the
rules for this.
I should go read them some time, and then just know, I never remember
the rules for it, so it may be that you don't actually need another
one, right.
It's probably not necessary to have this one, but I never bother to
actually remember exactly how the replacement rules work.
So, I just put in, I usually
And one extra one for no, no good reason.
Let's see.
Sizzle 182 would you say that your engine makes it easy for a new
programmer to come in and add functionality?
I don't know that.
Not really something I care about if that makes sense because there
are no other programmers on this project.
So it's not really a goal if that makes sense.
So I would say that it's easy for me to
Come in and add functionality, which is what I care about.
Elvin, I was employing, Shadow mapping in opengl.
It seems that there's a lot of issues and artifacts and to work around
those.
You end up with something more comics expensive.
I kind of find it hard to kind of find it hard that games that
defendant graph so hard to believe that games are decent Graphics.
Do this technique, do you know of any other good way to implement
Shadows?
Or we just have to work around its limitations.
So, yeah, I mean, it depends what kind of Shadows are talking about.
So if you're talking about Shadow mapping, your presumably talking
about hard-edged Shadows or relatively hard and shadows as opposed to
General light occlusion, where you be talking about something more
like, you know, a, you know, radiosity ish, right?
Like you're talking about, you talk about direct lighting, not
multiple bounce, is I assume what you're talking about?
And what I would say about that is I agree with your sort of your gut,
take on the shadow mapping, I've never liked it.
You do have to do a lot of ridiculousness, like Cascade Shadow maps
are for example, a very common thing now, which is obviously more,
Complicated than Shadow mapping and you're doing all these things to
try and improve the resolution from the vantage point of the viewer
and all this other nonsense.
And it is kind of lame.
As for what the alternatives are, no, there's not a lot of
Alternatives, you know, one of the things that people are actually
starting to do.
Now is actually doing some, some Ray tracing of stuff and other things
like this because they've got the extra horsepower to do it.
And so if you think about it I feel like in the future it's entirely
possible that direct lighting will be more Ray Tracy just because that
eliminates all of those resolution artifacts and you're starting to
have enough horsepower to do that.
Like right now, if
Wanted to retrace shadows in a game.
I think you just could you probably have enough horsepower to do that,
you know, and so, you know, really when you talk about the fact that
we don't can't really do rate racing games, what we mean is we can't
really do ray tracing of indirect Lighting in the kinds of stuff that
you might want to do, right?
But you could absolutely do direct lighting ray-tracing I think at
this point and so, you know, maybe that will be a way that we can get
out of that in the future.
But
You know, the the thing to remember is Ray tracing quickly is a real
pain in the butt as well.
And so, you know, unless you're talking about like voxel Ray tracing,
which is again, another kind of technique that's starting to look like
maybe it's useful or whatever, unless you're digging my Seng voxel,
Ray, tracing where the ray tracing really can happen entirely on the
3D card.
You've got this nasty problem of, and when I say happening,
On three credit cards that wider me.
We're talking about voxel, refacing, you're talking about something
that can happen entirely in a forward mapping sense.
Meaning, you feed triangles into it, it rasterizes the triangles into
the voxel grid and then it traces them back through there, if you're
not sorry, messing with that.
Then you have this sort of problem of you've got to do stuff like
building KD trees or other accelerated structures for doing the ray
tracing.
And so you're ending up creating again, a very complex system.
To do the Shadows.
So, even though you now don't have to implement a complex Shadow
mapping thing, you do have to implement a complex, spatial query
thing.
And so I don't really know what's going to shake out there and I don't
stay that up on those things these days because I not doing a 3D, I'm
not doing a 3D sort of lighting kind of thing like that for our game
at Molly.
So I haven't looked at what the latest stuff is that.
People tend to do, that's good.
So I don't know but all I would say is that yeah it's kind of a nasty
problem because the the reason that shadow maps are valuable, the
reason that they work well is there forward mapping?
You dump a bunch of triangles into them the same way that you dump
triangles into the renderer right?
You just you don't
I have to have a bunch of code that does spatial partitioning or other
things, too that you just run the same sort of stuff you would run.
If you rendered, you can, you can use that for shadowing and that's a
pretty compelling use case, right?
Whereas most other things involved sort of these, these more
complicated structures and that point you're back to having a complex
thing you have to do.
And so that's again, one of the reasons why the voxel stuff is kind of
interesting.
Seeing as it's going currently because it's still a very feed-forward
sort of a thing.
There's no commune ever, compare triangles with other triangles or
things like that.
You're always just dumping things into a very straightforward.
Rasterization looking Pipeline and outcomes, some stuff, right?
So I don't know.
Let's see.
Brutal excesses the mobile platform, limit to Android only excluding
iOS for any particular reason.
Yes, so handmade hero is I am not ever going to allow it to be on
platforms that are closed.
So if you can't, if an end user is not allowed to just load the the
handmade hero directly onto their device, then we will not be
In that platform.
And so iOS, of course does not allow that.
The only way that you can do that on iOS is, if you jailbreak, you
have to basically use something that Apple doesn't approve to like
jailbreak the phone, and in fact, that was illegal up until recently
until the until the Library of Congress passed an exemption for it.
So it was actually even illegal to do it.
If you can believe that.
And so yeah, so until Apple changes
They're really what I would consider pretty much anti developer
policy.
We will not support them in any way on any platform.
K.
What if we just blur the edges of the Shadows gaussian blur?
So, that's not the problem with shadows.
That's not the best, not what you're seeing when you look at shadows
and see problems.
It's not because the edges are don't have enough resolution.
It's because of the depth doesn't have enough resolution.
So blurring, it doesn't help because it just means that you'll get
blurry, Flickr instead of solid
Flicker, right?
And and the problem is the flicker, not the fact that it's hard,
right?
It was just the fact that the edge is hard then.
Yeah.
K.
Do you think namespace is actually solve the problem of many
collisions or there's no need for them in the usual, see style system
named functions of Isis.
Well, namespaces have a bonus Over the Sea style system name
underscore function because you can use the using declaration to pull
them in and not have to do the underscore.
So they do have a little bit of a benefit, right?
Is it enough of a benefit for me to ever really care about it?
No, but it's not completely useless, right?
Jeepers, Caleb, yes.
But how is Windows?
Any different.
Don't need to compile Windows programs.
On Windows.
I'm not here about compiling them.
I'm talking about being able to run them, so on an iOS device.
If I build a executable right, I can't send it to you and have you put
it on your device?
You need to be apple developer, you need to pay $90 and you need to
get a signing certificate to put it on your device, right?
And so, as a developer, if I pay my $90, I have the ability to sign an
executable and put it on some number.
I don't remember.
The number is 100, something like that, and if you want to put it on,
more than that,
To go through the app store, right?
Or blah, blah blah blah, blah.
It's all just a complete.
It's ridiculous.
It's completely Draconian and I don't approve of that at all on
Windows.
That's not the case at all on Windows.
I can build this executable and I can send it to you and you can run
it, you can build this executable, nobody had to pay Microsoft right
now on the Windows store side of things.
So if you wanted to use Windows RT, the new programming environment.
All the standard Apple stuff applies again.
And that's why we don't support that.
So we will not be supporting the Windows store, either.
The Windows store can can go die in a discussed in a horribly
disfiguring, fire.
And all of the people who are responsible for, it can also be welcome
to be in that fire.
And if they need a little push into that fire, I'm happy to be the
foot that it does that.
Because again, I hate anti developed for stuff because I am a
developer
I've lived for 30 years in an environment where you were able to
develop stuff.
And not have to go through these things.
And I think that it's it's just basically pure greed.
And and sort of, I don't know what you want to call it despotism and,
and I am.
I cannot tell you how angry it makes me.
It's, it is not a case of capitalism.
It's not a case of Economics.
It's a case of like just fundamental rights for me.
and the concept that you can sell a computer, these days that a
programmer is not allowed to write programs for, without your
permission is like if I were in charge of the world, that would be
Punishable by death.
It'd be like you are just marched into a room and like we are never
heard from again.
If you do that it's like it's the worst offense, you can do, right?
It's kind of like, in my mind.
It's equivalent to like quite literally.
It's equivalent to like what, you know, the old sort of 1984 style
regimes do.
It's the it's the equivalent of like the media sensor lock down like
we control, what you
You can think and say thing, like that sigh, those, I put them in the
same category, like the worst kind.
They're the worst kind of systemic like oppressors, right in my mind.
And the reason for that is very simple, right?
I've been in development since I was seven years old, there's, if you
tell me I can't publish a book, I am less upset about that.
Than, if you tell me, I can't publish a program, right?
And so,
Like in general, I feel like to me the right to publish a program is a
fundamental right.
And it's unconscionable to me that you are not allowed to do that.
It should be like.
That should just be a fundamental thing that you are allowed to do.
And, and so yeah, again, it makes me it makes me absolutely Furious
and it's just completely like, you know, that that would be, that
would be
Be the one like thing.
You're never that you can't do like with there's no possible way for
clemency if you if you ship a hardware platform that people aren't
allowed to develop.
For then you can't.
There's literally no defense for it in court, right?
In the court of mirror Tori, you are just permanently sentenced to
death and you're gone, right?
You're just we'd never hear from get everything else.
There's plenty of, you know, there's, there's plenty of Mercy for you.
We were happy to hear your explanation for why you did it.
We will try to
Take you as a person.
We will we will, you know, look upon you with with, with
understanding.
But if you ship a hardware platform that you don't allow people to
program for do to your sort of like your avarice and greed or whatever
it is, then than that.
Sorry.
There's there are no defenses for it and then we're going to grind you
up for sausage to feed to feed hungry people.
Apple.
All right.
Looks like we are done with the q's.
I'm going to close down.
Yes.
And yes, there we go.
Well, thank you for joining for another episode of handmade here.
It's my pleasure coding with you.
As always, we're not quite finished with the thing that we want to do
today.
So we'll pick that up again tomorrow 5 p.m.
service center time.
Hope to see you all here and looking forward to wrapping up the debug
system to.
I hope it's good in the end.
I think we kind of went through a number like I said, it's it's
actually one of the most serious architectural things we've done so
far.
And I feel like it's kind of important to sort of look back at it and
understand how we went through each individual part of the process and
how to push through it.
So I hope it ends up being pretty good in the end and I'm happy with
sort of how we came through everything and eventually work towards a,
what I think is a fairly good solution will solidify, but we need a
few more days to actually see it through to completion.
And so that will be what we're doing.
And hopefully maybe we can get it done in time for their handmade
cons.
So after handmade con, that'll be your like are
Point where we'll go to, whatever our next thing is, maybe some
lighting.
Who knows what we'll do?
Actually, maybe there's a different thing we might do.
But yeah.
Eventually we'll have to do letting either way.
So anyway, hope to join me for that tomorrow.
Back here again, 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time.
If you want to follow along the source code at home as always handmade
here at dot org, you can pre-order the game becomes the source code so
you can play around with it and learn from it.
We also have Forum site, you can discuss the code or if you're having
problems, you can ask people for help that sort of thing.
We also
Have an antidepressant guide up there, which will probably start
licking to.
It's been going through some revisions and stuff, but we'll probably
start linking to that pretty soon here.
On the main page, we haven't quite gotten there yet, so it's linked to
on the forums page.
Was that a patreon page want to support the video series?
And the tweetbot that tells you what the schedule is, you want to
catch it the show live.
That is the place to go for that.
We also have our convention coming up, you can get tickets here.
It's December, fifth.
Like I said, I think there's about 20 tickets left, something like
that.
Handmade conduct org has the information on it.
And you can get the tickets right here.
So that's going to be pretty awesome Hamid.
Khan is, I also should mention as kind of a last note, I am probably
going to be wanting if you are somebody out there who has a camera
that could record video of handmade con like a good camera.
Like if you're one of those people who has like, you know, a 5D Mark
to Canon camera or something with a decent length.
Is on it like something, if you're a high-end camera guy and you would
not and you are coming to handmade con.
If you have any interest in setting up a camera to record handmade
con, I will be setting up some recording stuff myself.
But I feel like if we got multiple cameras more than just one to
record it, that would be good because we never know, one could die in
the middle of it.
Or we might want multiple angles to, you know, sort of cut together.
After the fact to make sort of a better video of the thing, all kinds
of stuff like that.
I think we could do.
So I would be interested in hearing from people.
You can post on the forums or send me an email.
Of course, my email address is public.
You can just go on my Twitter handle.
In fact, if you want to get it or you can actually just use on this
page.
If you go to the about page or you can actually see, I think on here,
do we have this?
We have this yet.
You can see me right here.
On the, if you click in case me, try and go down to the bottom, you've
got my kind of calm, my contact info stuff.
So if you are somebody who wants to help out with that, please let me
know.
Because I think having more cameras is going to be better than having
less cameras.
And so if you're somebody who knows what they're doing with in terms
of recording video, I would love to have your help keeping some
redundant records of handmade con.
Just in case something goes wrong with the main ones that were going
to set up.
That is about it until tomorrow.
Take it easy.
Everyone have fun programming and I'll see you guys on the internet.