Okay, hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream on Twitch.
No library's new engine.
It's all our own code right down to the individual little tiny baby
little pixels on the screen.
Every single one of those, we put them there by hand and it's been
pretty glorious.
I have to tell you yesterday, we implemented asset streaming in the
background because I for some reason just decided to do it.
It was not at all planned.
Just what happened.
But we didn't have a chance because we, again only program for an hour
on it, we didn't really have a chance to do all of the things that we
might want to do with asset streaming.
So it's still a little bit primitive at the moment and it's not
something that you would actually want to call done because it has a
number of issues.
Mostly the biggest one just has to do with how it uses memory at the
moment.
It does not really have any strategy for what would happen if the, if
the total number of assets that
You were going to use in the game.
Did not actually fit in memory now, it's entirely possible that for
our game, all of the assets will fit in memory because machines have a
lot of memory these days.
And so we could, you know, choose to ignore that problem if we wanted
to.
But I would rather not do that because I would like the game much
like, how we've been trying to make all of the programming, be very
industrial strength here on inmate hero.
I would like to make sure that our engine could handle the situation.
Where are you have vastly more art resources than can fit in the
memory of the machine at any given time?
So in the case where, you know, you have a user who has 4 gigabytes of
memory in the machine, it should be able to handle a situation where
the uncompressed asset load for the game was 32 megabytes or
something, right?
That we'd like that, to be true.
So we're going to go ahead and push forward on that and see if we
can't bring our background streaming up to a higher quality level
where we can sort of start to do.
Some more of those things that we would want in sort of an industrial
strength solution.
Okay.
Before I get started today is day 133.
So if you would like to follow along at home, you can unzip day 132
source code and that is the source code that I'll be programming with.
Today.
So if you pre-ordered the game, I hammer here at org, download the
source, and then unzipped a 132.
So, that's what I've got.
And that is what if you, if you start with that source code, you're
exactly where I am right now.
All right.
So let's take a look at what we've done so far, so that we can explain
what we're going to need to do and so that we can go do it.
So, we've got our background loading in there.
And so now we can see that when we start the game, when it loads in
Instantly it also nothing is there yet and it just kind of pages in
the background, which is exactly what we wanted.
And
So what are the things that this is not doing yet?
And what do we want to start making sure that it does?
Well, first of all, you can also see that our guy is like floating and
things are in the wrong place.
So one thing that we do have to do which is just pure clean up, is we
have to go back and put in that concept of having the displacement
because we took that out of there just as we were finishing up this
case we have to put that back in there.
That really doesn't have anything to do with the system though.
That's just a minor thing.
So I have to do that but the the more important things really have to
do with memory
Me and you can kind of see what I'm talking about if we just take a
look at some circumstances here.
Here's the load asset work, all right, the load asset work called.
Obviously, you can tell
From the load asset work call.
That we have this sort of process where we're loading a bitmap and
then at the end when we've loaded the bitmap, we go ahead and set that
pointer here equal to the bitmap that we loaded.
And this is the pointer that the rest of the game can pick up and use.
Now the problem with this system
We have two problems.
Really one is that this debug load bitmap call the debug bitmap called
doesn't in any way.
Guarantee of any kind of a bounded memory footprint, right?
Basically what will happen is As We Run the game, every time we call
debug load bitmap, it will load more memory into the system and so
we'll just keep allocating more and more and more and more memory ad
infinitum, until we run out of virtual paging in the operating system
and then the game will just flat-out, stop working, right?
I'll just crash or
or encounter an operating system are where it puts up with those
dialog boxes.
Like your system is running low on virtual memory, right?
So, it's really bad to do that.
I don't really want to do that.
Like I said, it'd be fine.
If you knew that you only had as many art assets as would fit in Ram
and you didn't care, then you don't have to worry about it, but I'd
rather do something a little better there.
So, what we have to do here is understand the concept, kind of like,
if you've ever seen Arrested Development, you know, there's a one in
one out policy in the military, right?
And
What I want to talk about here is the concept of you, no one in one
out.
Which is basically to say that what I would rather do is I'd rather
say how big of a memory footprint.
Do we actually want the artist to take art assets to take, right?
So let's say we say that it's going to be 2 gigabytes.
So that's like, what we want.
Our backing store to be for art assets at any given time is 2 GB.
Okay?
And again this is an arbitrary number.
We just would pick it based on what we think.
The minimum spec of a machine for running handmade Heroes should be
okay, maybe it'd be
Much larger than that.
Maybe be much smaller than that.
It just depends on the circumstance, right?
So let's say we have that and we have that chunk of memory.
Allocated out of the transit pool and then we have, you know, on disk
somewhere we've got and who knows?
We don't know how big it actually is on the drive.
But you know, because it might be impressed or something like this but
decompressed, you know, we've got 32 GB of art assets or something.
So some giant set here, right?
And maybe that's pretty small on disk you know, maybe it's only six
gigabytes on disk or something but you know it decompresses out to
something much larger than that, or who knows what right?
So who knows what the situation here is.
But we know that this is how much we would actually have.
So what I would rather do is I'd rather say, well, okay, at any given
time we have 2 gigabytes worth of art assets loaded and when we
encounter an asset that we do not have loaded but that we need, what
we would like to do is take something from here that was previously
being used and that we haven't touched in a while and I'd like to
evict that, right?
I'd like to get rid of it.
So that we no longer are storing that our asset, and then I would like
to load in whatever the one is, you know, that we're actually going to
use and put that in its place.
Okay.
So that's what I'd rather do.
I'd rather have something that works like this.
And the reason that I'd rather have something that works like this is
because then we know that as long as at startup, we get our initial
memory footprint that we asked for.
We know that we will never run out of memory and crash or anything.
Like this will always be able to operate in the size of memory that we
are given, and we know that the art asset loading won't ever do
anything, you know stupid, right?
So that's what I'd rather do.
So that's one thing we want to get to and the other thing that we have
to get to that's actually considerably easier than this is just making
sure that nobody tries to load the same or an asset twice.
Okay?
So right now what happens is on a particular frame, if we go in here
and we say like, you know, so you know only load once
Right?
So, what happens currently is on a particular frame.
If we come in here, and we say, oh, you know what, I need you to load
the shadow, right?
And then somebody else comes along on the same frame and says load
Shadow, right?
Well, the background task for loading, the shadow probably hasn't
completed yet.
So both of these guys are going to do this, right?
The first guys going to kick off that load thread.
The second guys, also going to kick off the load thread, when all we
really wanted it to do was kick off a single load thread and the
second guy should not have kicked off a load thread because it's just
the same thread, right?
This, you know, it's just it's completely wasted work and it'll be
wasted memory to because we'd lose, you know, that allocation in
there, right?
It would be a memory leak essentially.
So what we want to do is make sure that we also do that, we talked
about that a little bit.
End of the previous stream so we want to do both those things.
This one is harder.
This one is definitely the easier of the two things to achieve.
It's really just about being a little more, careful about how we label
things.
So that's that's really it, right?
That's what you want to do.
So I'm going to take these in order of easiness, which is to say that
first, I'm going to go ahead and put in the line X top down a line
stuff.
Get that back in there since we act, you know, we kind of lost it.
it, it was supposed to be in there, and then we
We sort of lost it when we were quickly getting things working
yesterday so we got to put that back in.
Then I'm going to do the only load once and then we'll start in on the
the more difficult problem of making sure that we always use a fixed
resource for print.
Now granted, that's actually not that difficult of a problem.
If all your resources are the same size but when we don't know what
the size of the resources are we kind of have some decisions to make
in terms of how we handle that right in terms of how we deal with
that?
Okay.
So, here we go.
Here we go, indeed.
So in order to do this here, with the line X and the top down a line
Y, right?
I can essentially just, you know, again, not replacing the bitmap,
debug load call yet, even though that you know, might be something
that we want to do.
Eventually I'm going to go ahead and make it so that we essentially do
you know a little bit about just a branch here and call the original
functions exactly how
Have them before.
Probably we could clean this up a little bit and make this be a little
more smarter in the way it passes through.
But that's certainly something we can address a little bit down the
line if that makes sense.
So in this particular circumstance, what I want to do is I want to
store in that load asset work.
I want to store these two things that we have here that we were using
before, so that I can put them in there.
I don't actually remember what types those were.
Let me go take a look and see, they were in 32, so that's good.
And then I'll just stir a bull 32 as well which is like has alignment
or something like this and then I can, you know, put that
Here at something to check.
So if it has an alignment, it'll use the alignment, if it doesn't have
the alignment, it won't use the alignment and again, that's something
that I'd rather clean up.
But you know we can push that down to one.
We're looking at RSS little more it really didn't have anything to do
with this routine whatsoever.
So
In here, I'll just go ahead and assume that it doesn't have alignment.
And then later what we can do is anybody who does have an alignment
can set that.
So, has alignment equals true, right?
What are these guys top down a line Y, and a line X.
Right.
There we go.
So if I want to go ahead and insert these in here, I should be able to
do so.
Then I can just cut and paste.
The old values that we had in there into the work order.
And now, the work order will have the information.
It needs to accurately reflect the stuff that used to be happening
single-threaded.
So that we're back to like the feature parity of the thing that we
started with, which obviously is what we want.
So anyway, there we go.
And now our guys are aligned properly which is good, and everything is
fine.
So now let's tackle that other problem of making
Make sure the things only load once.
Now, you can see that we sort of talked about this again a little bit
where we said, oh, because someone asked about it on the last day when
I was like, okay, we're well eventually we need to sort of upgrade
this to have a notion of what's going on so that we can Mark things as
being in progress so they won't get queued twice.
Right.
And the way I was proposing to do that was to actually make, you know,
an asset thing here, I'm going to call this an asset slot and then I'm
just going to change this right here.
This bitmap spit to actually be bitmap slots essentially.
So yeah, so if we do that, then what I would look for is, I basically
say, okay, we've got this result here when we're going to return this
result what I've actually like to do is say, okay, you know, when,
when it looks at the actual result, it's fine for it to go ahead
probably and just get the bitmap right from the pointer.
That's probably.
Okay.
And we'll make sure we always make that be authoritative in terms of
whether you can actually
Use it or not.
But what we would like to do
is on the load, right?
So when we do load asset, when we're about to kick off the asset, what
we would like to do is actually ensure that well a that it needs to be
loaded and be that it hasn't already been cute.
So what I'd like to do is basically do something here where we're
going to check
Like so.
We're going to check to see whether or not the asset in question needs
to be loaded or whether it's already been cute.
So what you can see here, what I'm doing is I'm going to check that
state, right?
And I'm going to see whether it's unloaded.
If it's unloaded, then we'll go ahead and do it.
Otherwise, we won't.
Now there is something that we need to be aware of here that this
doesn't want to be written.
Exactly.
This way.
And the reason is because multi-thread
It would make it so that two threads could potentially see this
unloaded State at the same time.
And we want a fair bit of flexibility with loading assets on separate
threads potentially depending on how we're going to do it.
And so, I would just like to say this probably is not.
We want to do what we would like to do is we would like to do again.
One of those locked compare exchange, right?
Like so maybe I'll call it Atomic compare exchange, right?
What I'd like to do is atomic compare exchange of an integer here.
Right, I guess this is technically you want 32 right?
I'd like to do an atomic a exchange of that you in 32 and what I want
to do is say Okay I want to Atomic compare exchange this with that and
set it to queued, right?
So I basically want to take this guy, I want to make sure
These unloaded and assuming that he is unloaded, I want to then set
him to queued and then when I could do is just check the return result
to make sure that what I actually got back was unloaded because if
that's true that means no other thread could have seen the unloaded
because it would have been replaced with cued by the time that they
did right.
And so what I want to do is make sure that that state again is always
going through that Atomic compare exchange.
So that we know that we're not going to have any kind of nasty
contention there.
Right.
So there we go.
Alright, so that's pretty much it for for doing that.
What we do have to do, of course in the intrinsics is, we have to
actually make these and unfortunately again these are ones that are
dependent on the particular compiler, in question.
So they will be things that people pointing to other platforms.
You're going to have to deal with.
You're going to have to specify what they should be that makes.
and so in here, what we've got to do is we've got Atomic compare
exchange, you went 32, I should probably actually delete this because
that way people to do case you need GCC llvm equivalents
So anyway, we do atomic compare exchange.
Oh, and we even have complete previous rights before future rights in
here.
How come I didn't just use that because we're supposed to have this
fence in here.
Good now we've got that fence, so if we have Atomic compare exchange
you in 32, what that's going to do is it's going to take, you know, a
pointer to a un 32.
This is the the, you know, the sort of the value change, right?
And then we have the expected value and the new value.
Right?
And what that's going to do is that's actually going to call right
into the interlocked compare Exchange.
Function which I don't actually remember exactly what intrinsic it
actually is.
But here we go.
New and then we have the result, which we need to return.
Okay.
So let's see what that has introduc.
Compare exchange cannot convert argument one from volatile too long.
That's totally fine.
Because those are the same thing.
There's your cast.
Let's see here.
Okay?
And that's it.
Well, no time.
I compare exchange, telling it through to cannot convert.
One from asset state to you at 32.
So, we have to do this one as well, so there we go.
And this guy here, it just needs to be talking about the bitmap
explicitly.
And once it does that, of course, it also has to go ahead and set the
state to the correct State value, which is loaded, right?
That's why I think that should be good.
So that way we get the bitmap pointer in there.
We've set it to loaded so we know what's going on and then we can
retire that thread.
So I think that should be fine.
I suppose it's also possible for us to do that slowly differently.
But I'm going to go ahead and and leave it like that for now.
All right.
Oops I don't know why I said stamp
So I think that should give us what we want and now we should have
some protection from the case of calling this multiple times.
Of course, again, we don't have a whole lot of debugging visualization
stuff in here yet.
So it's pretty hard for us to actually know that it's working
properly, but that is something we'll have to address a little later
on when we can maybe visualize a few more things.
So that's good.
And that's roughly what we have to do to make that lockout.
But now we've got sort
Have some some some other little bit of nastiness to deal with, right?
So,
if you remember, we do have a problem with our code, which is that
Phil ground chunk when we call Phil ground chunk.
But that actually does, is that just builds the push buffer stuff.
And and then it goes ahead and and and you know, puts a puts a work, a
work order in, right?
And you know, there's a there's an issue with this which is that if
the thing that is being composited, doesn't exist, yet the bitmap that
was going to be used doesn't exist yet.
Then when this goes to do, its rendering, the rendering will be
incorrect, right?
Because it will be missing one of the stamps.
It should have stamped in and we'll just get an incorrect ground
chunk.
That's might be fine when we're talking about the actual frame buffer,
when we're rendering actual frames in the game because at worst case
it's a flicker but more often, I'll
Happened because we're streaming far enough out that things left.
Time to page in before they actually move on to the screen, but we
don't have any such guarantees here.
And once we met, if we even have one failure in here, that gets baked
into ground chuck, you're going to see a lot.
That could be a pretty bad error that I don't want to have.
So we have a couple of different ways that we can approach this.
And I'm not sure which one is the best one, but one way to do it is to
make sure that all of the stuff that's used in ground.
Chunks is always resident and cannot be evicted, right?
That's one way.
Another way to do it is to only allow the ground chunk to be filled in
the case where it actually got all of the things that it actually
needed, right?
And the final thing.
Would be to make it so that it just stalls out and weights on loading
until the loading is done, right?
I don't know if that makes sense.
I don't know which of those is best.
Certainly the simplest one for right now is just to make sure that it
you know, to basically not Mark, the ground chunk, as actually having
been filled until you actually know that everything is fine with it.
So the way to do that, for example, would be something like this.
I don't know if this makes any sense, but hopefully it will.
Let's say, I do all this work here, right?
I can then say, if all bit
Apps valid on the render group then go for it, right?
And so what I can do is go into my render group here and and say, all
right, there's a call called all bitmaps valid.
What all bitmaps valid does is it checks to see whether or not you've
ever had a cache Miss in that case, so all bitmaps valid render group
on the group, right?
And if all the bitmaps are valid than it can render, right?
So, there's that.
There's one additional piece to it, so, we'll see.
Again, like I said, I don't really know if this is good way to do it,
it might be that we want to just always Force ground, chunk, members
to be resident.
But, you know, I again, it's an educational stream.
I want to show options and I want to show things I consider doing.
So I'm just going to put this in here and see, you know, what happens
bitmap, missing bitmap
Out, right?
Or we could even just say missing resource caps.
So when you allocate a render group,
Okay, when you come in here when you start off it'll just assume that
the missing resource count is 0.
And then leader, when it goes, if it has to issue a load asset called,
what it will do is it will link the missing resource count so that
everyone knows that there are resources, missing.
And then at the end, when you say, like, I guess we should say, all
resources present might be a better way to say it all resources
present.
what we can do there is
If all the resources are present, it will return true, right?
So it's just group missing resource, count equals zero and then you
return.
So that's one thing we could do, right, all resources present.
Now, we know that will never actually fill a ground.
Chunk will abort if it turns into a circumstance, where the stuff that
it had wasn't there, right?
So we can do that.
There's a problem with this still, even if we do it that which is that
technically.
So one thing that we can do with the main renderer is, we can make it
so that during the time, when stuff is going to be rendered, we can
guarantee that nothing is going to get evicted from the resource cash,
right?
Because we could just make sure that resource eviction happens at a
known time.
And that time is not during the rendering.
So that would be fine, right?
But with ground chunks, ground chunks happen, on a separate thread.
So what could happen here is we could go ahead and pull all these in
right then be about to render them and have one of them, get evicted.
So the reason that and that's really bad, because actually, what that
would do is that would potentially even crash because when it goes to
use one of those bitmaps, it will find that.
There's just, it's a good, be a garbage pointer or a zero pointer or
just it's other memory probably, wouldn't crash what
Really do actually is is probably just split the wrong sizes and the
wrong data completely, it would be bad, right?
And it could crash if the sizes got corrupted to be things that were
large enough, right?
So it's a bad situation.
And so the question is, you know, what do we want to do about that,
you know, is there anything in particular that we want to do to try to
combat that, right?
And there's a couple things we could do.
So one is, you can just cross your fingers, right?
One is a finger Crossing and that would be probably not such a great
idea.
I think and the reason you can cross your fingers is that depending on
how you implement, your least, recently used scheme, you can probably
be sure that if you just went through and asked for all these bitmaps
and they were there, they've all been sort of marked hot and will not
be a
Did any time soon, right?
It'll be many frames from now that they would ever be evicted if
they're going to be evicted, right?
So you could cross your fingers and just hope
not actually fabulous, but it would probably work, right?
You certain will certainly wouldn't Kraut crash any more frequently
than anyone else is games that get shipped, but, you know, it would be
Nice to be able to do something.
That was at least going to be theoretically correct.
And so the other things we could do is temporarily lock those
resources in by every time that we actually use one in the renderer,
we do some kind of a state change on that resource to make sure that
it changes to a state that is basically a used State.
And then when we're done we clean up the used state, right?
And I don't really know what to say.
About that.
I mean.
It's the correct way to do it.
Probably I would say.
It's not hard to implement.
The only thing that's a little bit problematic about it is that it
does involve reiterating over the buffer.
So, you know, I don't know, I don't know what to say about that, but
You know, it's it's an option.
So you know what?
Maybe I'll just write it and we'll see how it is.
But basically what that boils down to is when you go and do an
allocate
When you're in the render group, right?
And you do and allocate render group, then what you would need to do
at that point afterwards is, you would need to go and have a sort of
clean up, right?
We would actually need to have clean up, which is annoying.
I hate clean up because it's something that someone might forget to do
or that.
You know, might take longer than it should.
Because you can't just go ahead and straight up or use the memory.
You've got to actually do that.
Step of cleaning things up, but you know, who knows.
So we'll go ahead and say, you know, here's the group and then we can
say like cleanup render group or something like this.
And what that would do is that would just step through these guys,
right?
It would do nothing other than stepping through this list exactly the
same way that it that the other people are doing it only this time.
What would happen is each time through any, any of these guys which
actually had something in it that need to get free.
Three, which would basically be the bitmap one loops and do that.
That would basically be the pit map going here.
That one would have to Market stuff as not being used anymore, right?
So yeah, so you'd have something like this and again this is one of
those things that
Looking at this, if we're going to have two people who iterate over
it, it feels like we would probably want to pull that out into
something.
That's going to be a little more easily shareable and harder to screw
up.
The only problem with it is since it is a rendering thing.
I'm a little hesitant to do that.
I don't love that idea but, you know, we'll see how it goes again.
Like I said, most of the time, it's exactly sort of that, you know,
it's that we'll see how it goes, kind of a thing.
So yeah, so in here, if we do the cleanup render group call, what we
would need to do is assuming that it was actually a bitmap that we
were using.
We would need to be able to release it, right?
So we need to basically like release resource and
In here, the the loaded good map for necessary, the little bit map.
The actual thing that that does it would have its game asset ID in
here, right?
Like so and yeah we wouldn't probably need the loaded bitmap pointer
anymore for that matter.
We would just record the asset ID and that would be it, right?
So it would probably something more like this where the bitmap
actually comes in here.
Although I don't know, it may be that we need that bitmap pointer a
little earlier on to get like the dimensions of it.
Let's, let's take a look because I don't actually know, I don't
remember.
So let's take a look at what happens there.
Yeah.
So as you can see, we actually use that bitmap information so it means
we do need to have the pointer a little earlier on.
So we do need to actually still store it, if that makes sense.
So what I'm going to do here is just say, okay, you know if the entry
bitmap actually was valid then I've got that game asset ID.
I'm going to have to release a set or something like that release
asset something like this or unlock asset.
And that would just be whatever the entry ID is and this is the group
The assets, you know, for the group, right?
This game asset ID, where is that?
Actually, there it is.
Okay, so, where am I?
Yeah, so this actually wants to be up there again, and this is render
group, right?
So this is going to unlock that asset.
And then we need to do down here, right?
Is when we actually do the push bitmap, call we need to lock the
asset, right?
So we need to do a lock asset call.
Like so,
and assuming that that succeeded then we should be able to, you know,
Dispense with this check.
And in fact I guess we can dispense with the check up above as well
because since we have to get the bitmap in, we don't actually need to
do and if bitmap anymore because that's just never thing, right?
We always know that we had one because otherwise we wouldn't have
pushed the call.
So yeah, so that should be that should be exactly that.
So yeah.
So that would really be all we would do we have the lock asset in the
unlock asset?
If that makes sense.
And, you know, again, this is why I say it's kind of ugly and I don't
super love this.
I would probably say that based on how much I'm seeing here, I would
say that.
The better thing to do is just leave ground chunk bitmaps resident at
all times.
So they cannot be evicted.
It's like only victim oil if that makes sense.
Because the number of things that are going to be participating them
as far as so small, they
Still be streamed in.
They just can't ever be kicked streamed out, right.
But we'll see.
We'll see.
So the way that that would work is in here, we've got, you know, our
asset state right?
And and in there we basically need a lock count which would tell us.
You know, how often, you know how many people were using this thing.
Now, if we wanted to we could also say, oh, you know actually this
This lockout could just be one thing could just have a single variable
and, you know, you you just kind of like increment on it or something
like that.
And yeah, I'm not sure.
I really like that.
So yeah, it would be something like this where you just do a lockout
and then inside lock asset, it would be a locked increment and
Outsider would be a lakh decrement.
You know what?
I just having seen all that.
I'm just like,
I cannot believe that would ever be worth the trade-off.
It just doesn't seem like it would ever be worth the trade-off to me.
I can't see that being a good idea to me.
It just seems like it would be inviting trouble in so many places,
right?
So, I think what I would rather do is just say that those assets.
Get locked.
That's just how they work.
I'm there, they're just always in place, right?
Right?
So I think that's what I would do, I think that's what I what I would
prefer.
So, I'm going to go ahead and back that out.
I just really don't like that.
That was giving me a really bad it just it, required so much more
stuff for such a small for really just such a small piece of the code
because everybody else doesn't need that feature.
And so like putting it in there just for background loading of ground
chunks.
Just seems so bad, right?
So that's
That's my call on that.
I'm saying I'm saying it's not going in, that is not happening.
Okay, so that's out.
That is out.
Oops, I went too far.
My bad.
Sorry.
That's still fine.
There we go.
Okay, so
see.
All right.
Just making sure everything's kosher there.
So yeah.
So I don't think that's a good idea.
I don't like that at all.
So what I would rather do is say that there's a concept of a locked
resource, and lock resources are not allowed to get streamed out.
That makes sense.
So I'd much rather say something like asset State locked and a lock
tree sorts can never get streamed out.
Ever once it's loaded, its
It for good, right?
And the way that I would do that is inside load asset.
When we do this stuff here, at the end of this work, when it's get
set.
So that it says that the asset state is loaded, what I'd rather do is
say final State like so and that way we can have the luxury of marking
anything, we want to be locked and then that thing can never be
streamed out ever again.
So
That seems better to me right, there we go asset State, final State.
And so, in this case, right, we don't have any of these are can all be
streamed out there, not a problem, but when we add things later that
have to be in the ground, chunk Arena, I shouldn't use the word Arena,
but in the ground chunk usage case, then does those have to be locked
because anything that happens for the rendering of the other thread
has to stay locked.
And we'll see how that goes.
If we decide that it's too much, or too onerous for us to do that.
Like there's too much stuff that gets has to stay in memory.
In that case, we can know he's back pedal on that.
But that seems like a pretty reasonable compromise because it means
that there's a hell of a lot less code to deal with.
All right?
So there we go.
That's it is
Basically it for all that stuff, we still have to do some of the
structural things.
But at this point, I think we should probably start to talk about
eviction right since it's a you know, since it's a thing, we should
talk about this stuff the winning to announce stuff.
So what we want to do here is when we load an asset currently, what
we're doing is I think, you know, the debug load bitmap nonsense
What's actually happening here?
Is it just reads the entire file.
And then it pretty much.
I think it just does its work in place.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
Yeah, Source desk.
So you can kind of see here, right?
When we load these, these bitmaps in the bitmaps, are just getting
loaded.
They're getting allocated by the, by the platform layer and we just
always use that memory in place, right?
So really, we don't even have the option here of doing anything smart
about this when we actually load this guy into into memory.
So I I guess maybe it's premature.
Now, I think about it to do this quite yet it may be.
That what we would rather do is actually tackle this other part first
which is like the bitmap structural stuff.
Because what I'm seeing when I look at
this and I suppose, I could move this back down to where we had it for
now, like so,
What I'm seeing when I look at this is it's looking to me like will
want to start working with a table of what are all the things are that
we have in the game.
And if we're working in that space I feel like that's where we want to
start to do stuff like have a general table that stores all of our
bitmap information and this sort of stuff.
So I kind of feel like that's where we should actually be headed.
So I think I'm going to push that direction first finish up that part
of the asset stuff, which isn't really have anything to do with
background screaming.
That's just starting to put ourselves in a more complete position.
In terms of just our asset Concept in general,
I think I'd rather do that and then come back to the to the sort of
memory management aspect of it.
And again we're under a really no pressure to do that because we don't
have hardly that many asset resources.
I don't even know if in the end we'll have that many asset resources.
I suspect, we will though like are uncompressed compressed asset load.
Could very easily be well above, say four gigabytes or something, that
might be a reasonable footprint for a game.
Unlike the lower spec machines or something, although
I don't know if that's actually true because on the lower start
machines, you probably wouldn't be loading the highest risk, all
right?
So you could do other stuff but yeah, but yeah.
Suffice to say, it could happen.
So anyway what I want to do here is start to tackle some of these
other problems.
So we have these irate assets here and I'd like to start to tackle The
Irate assets as something that we want to deal with right.
And so we have a game asset ID here.
What I'd like to do is expand the notion of a game asset ID to talk
about things that maybe don't really have anything to do with specific
bitmaps and that are rather a more General concept of what is going
on.
Right.
So we've got two types of things there that we would expect, we have
grass stone, tough stuff, which is like an array of things.
So we have like grass and there's some array of them.
And then we also have things like hero bitmaps where the hero bitmaps
have like a facing Direction and then there's like some of them
they're like kind of paired together.
So we kind of have two sets of things that were talking about.
Two two types of structure that we want to address directly, right?
So what I'd like to do with this one here is I say well, okay, we've
got these grass arrays.
What I'd like to do is introduce sort of the concept that we have.
You know, I don't know what you want to call it a game asset.
I don't know, maybe a game, let's say asset bitmap label or something
like this or something.
I'm not sure what exactly would be called.
But what I want to do is basically something that describes this
particular thing, right?
And so loaded bitmap, you know, is basically what that was before.
All we would use is in the render group we'd have loaded bitmap and
you can see exactly what it has on there.
It's got a line percentage with over height with high pitch and
memory, right?
It's got that stuff.
What?
I'm more interested now is the part of these things that we
Might want to save as a descriptor of this thing, right?
We don't care about the pitch of the memory that's like stuff that's
loaded.
I guess we can call up it mapinfo.
And these are some, some properties that we know we had, but in
addition to that, maybe we also have like a couple Properties or tags
of this thing.
That can be on there, right?
So maybe we have something like an asset tag, right?
And that asset tag is like the tag and the value or something like
this, right?
And there's something in cure of the form, you know, tag count and,
and or something like, you know, first
Index and tag count something like that.
I don't know.
You get the idea, right?
So I'd like to do is sort of talk about like can we make something
that allows us to start to sort of start to create a table of these
assets where the code could read the table and know something about
what?
It was getting right?
And so for example, in the case of like the grasses or the stones,
right?
Is there some way that we could make a way of marking up the art
assets to
That here are the things that ground chunk construction are concerned
with, and here are some that represent like a Stony surface.
And here are some that represent a grassy surface.
And for the ones that represent a graph, these grassy surface here is
like this and that and whatever, right?
So I'm just wondering if we can maybe do something like this.
I don't know if that's a good particular way that I've got it in there
right now but that's sort of the thing that I am going to sort of look
towards.
So what I want to do here is
Is right?
The usage code first, I want to write the usage code so that we can
See how it would actually play out in practice and so I'm going to go
over to fill ground chunk, right?
And infill, ground chunk.
You can see that it's sort of does this random seed stuff here, right?
It's doing a random seed thing.
It's a little hard without having more World, building code to know
exactly how this would work.
But you can kind of see and hear when it picks stuff.
Wait sorry that random seed is for inner Flame, the series.
Sorry.
I was back bill.
It's it's a random choice, right?
It's randomly choosing between these things.
It randomly chooses between one of two different things and then it
randomly chooses, in here, out of whether it's going to put down stone
or grass or whatever, right?
This sort of stuff.
And, and in the, in the decoration case does base of the same thing at
picks one of the random Tufts that it has there, or whatever.
So if we think about what that's doing, you could imagine if we were
trying to fill a ground chuck, where we have specific information
about what we're supposed to go in this ground chunk, you could
imagine first of all, us wanting to make this choice not necessarily
randomly.
Like, for example, we would say whether it was grass or stone would be
based on some input as to the region that we were placed at the
current like location, right?
And the other thing that we would want to do is in here where we're
doing things like random
choices.
We may want to pick choices that make more sense for the area.
So, for example, if this is an area with taller grasses, then maybe
we're airing on the side of tall grasses, more often than other
grasses.
Whereas, if we are in an area of Short Grass, then we wouldn't pick
the tall grasses, right?
So that's just, that's just what I'm thinking.
I'm trying to think whether I can really emulate that with the art
assets that we have in here right now.
Oh, I can, you know what?
I could just scale them and pretend that but but let's take a look.
As I don't actually remember, it's been a long time since we actually
took a look at any of these, what they actually are in the tuft case.
So there's the Tufts, I don't really have much in here.
I probably should have put in some more art assets, sometime soon.
So we can start playing with them the Rocks.
However I guess are a good example.
You can see there's like a Flat Rock as well as some more bulbous
rocks and that would be an example.
But yeah, I don't know that.
We really have anything we can super test with.
So maybe I'll have to go dig around and put some more ass at it, art
Assets in there that we could use for this.
But suffice to say the way that we would do this, presumably is it
would basically rank the ones are in there.
I don't know if it would be a little too long to rank and each
individual one but yeah, that's sort of what I'm thinking, right?
That's sort of what I'm thinking.
So how to do this efficiently?
So here is one way, right?
Let's say you have these tags, right?
Let's say I have something like asset or or you know in to pick best,
right?
And I was going to go over some array of these Assets in fact bitmap
infos, right?
So, I had something like this, and I was going to e.r.
iterate over these.
So I have, you know, an info count and I go over them and I, you know,
Do this.
And I oops, that's not what I do at all.
Sorry, I do this.
And inside here, I'm just going to Loop over however many there
actually are, right?
And when I do this, what I have to do now is ranked the tags of this
guy, right?
So I would I would essentially go, you know, tag and x equals First
tag index.
And then I would do tug index is less than.
In fact, this is probably one passed last tag index.
So I would do something like that tag and x 60.
So, I would go in through this table and I would read out what all the
things,
Is were in there, right?
And when I did that,
I would be able to to grab whatever the tag was.
So I'd have an asset tag tag and I would see which one it actually was
okay.
And I'd probably also have a big in here that was like
Match Vector, right?
And so, what I would do is, I'd say, all right, the tags list, right?
Whichever tag Index.
This is, I'd go ahead and take, you know, the difference or something.
I could also do the wait, you know, something like this match, vector,
and a weight vector.
What I do is I say all right the difference here is whatever the
weight Vector is for this tag ID or whatever, right?
For this tag Ivy times, whatever the match Vector is for this tag ID,
write the absolute value.
Value.
Of that and whatever the value of the actual tag is, right?
Like so I should probably maybe do it like this so you can see it a
little more clearly.
So I have the difference which is just the difference between the tag
value and what I would want to get and then I would have you know,
something that sort of does awaited difference, right?
Waited
Like so and then I would sum those or something.
so I'd say total GIF or total weighted death 10 total weighted, if
plus equals waited
and then I would say, okay, whichever one
was best.
This would be the best F here.
Best gift would be real 32 maximum.
I've come through here and say, if the best, if is greater than the
total weighted death, then the best is equals, the total weighted diff
and it also have the best index here.
And I'd say best index equals info index
So this is the super slow way, right?
So basically, what could happen is here someone who had a particular
idea of something that they wanted to grab, right?
And these all of these disciples will be marked up by tags.
That were basically, some set of ID's.
Just I don't care how many there are and I don't care what they mean,
but we just agree.
That, you know, any particular piece of code is using some set of ID's
that the art assets has to be marked up by and those IDs have some
value associate with them.
These could be stuff like tallness and then this value would be like
how tall the thing is, right or whatever.
This thing that does pick best with then actually just do that.
It would go through these things and, you know, you'd pass in a match
vector and a weight Vector.
The weight Vector is how much you care about, you know, from 0 to 1,
how much you care about each of these traits.
And this is what the value of each of the traits is that you're trying
to match.
You would then go through and for each one of them you would see how
far away you are from the desired value and multiply that by whatever
the wait was for that.
And then you'd see.
Who came up with the best score.
That would basically allow you to select out of a pool of assets that
you've never seen before and had no idea what they were.
It would allow you to select the one that best matches the criteria
that you're trying to get for whatever the thing is that you're trying
to draw, right?
And so, you know, that's one example of how we could do it, right?
And so when we load in the asset pact with the asset Packwood having
it is would have these bitmaps.
They
Would be tagged we would then have at load time all those tags loaded
in so we would know what bitmap we were looking for in a given time by
looking at the how the tax matched out, for whatever it is that we're
trying to do at that time, right?
So we can do that, right?
We could straight up do that and
What can I say?
I can't think of a whole lot of reasons not to do it that way.
Seems pretty flexible.
And then what we could have on top of that, is just some set of fixed
Arena.
So that this search doesn't take too long, where we would essentially
say that, you know, each one of these bitmap infos has something in it
or probably even that they come in bulk groups, right?
So we have like an asset bitmap group or something like this.
I or just an asset group and that asset group itself has an ID.
That's like, what are these?
Oh, this is hero bitmaps or something like this, right?
And so maybe they can be matched, kind of like a little bit more,
hierarchical e, you know, or could we could even do it this way,
right?
Where an asset group has a set of tags on it.
And so you can sort of pull out particular asset groups that go with
certain things that you're trying to do and then you don't have to
search all the bit
Between them, right.
Something like this.
So yeah, I think I'm going to leave it there for now.
because I think at least at the moment and I'm going to put this
I'm gonna make this compile, I think we want to explore this a little
bit more before committing to anything since we're kind of getting to
the end of the stream here, I just want to leave it at that and we can
talk about it, some more tomorrow.
For now we can go to the Q&A because it is Q and A Time as you know.
So if anyone has any questions, please go ahead and ask them now.
Put Q: in front of them so that I can see them and please try to keep
them to the stuff that we are.
Working on so that it can be on topic.
Robot chocolate Dino in pick best.
Would you want other types of fall-off and Computing?
The difference?
Probably.
You wouldn't care but you could certainly have that, right?
When compiling for 64-bit shouldn't you be using interlocked compare
exchange 64?
I'm not sure.
Are you saying that for like a performance reason or something?
The value that we're exchanging is only 32 bits.
So I don't know why.
I don't I'm not sure why we would do a little luck, a exchange 64.
In this particular case,
In your example of having 32 GB of assets uncompressed and two
gigabytes of space for them.
Are there techniques you can use to tell whether you will need more
than 2 gigabytes at one time?
Well obviously you can do this by playing the game and monitoring it
and you can also make reasonably conservative estimates like for our
game.
For example, we know that we're a 2-D game, we know there's only so
much overdraw and so many different Graphics that we're going to have.
We can probably put a pretty conservative bound on it, but no.
There is no way, I mean, without having some kind of a crazy sort of
like, static code, analyzing solver or nightmare thing to actually be
able to prove exactly what the maximum you would.
The minimum you would need to guarantee that you can always load
everything you might need for any given frame.
The game could possibly draw.
But usually, you can make sure that you're so far above what that
could possibly be.
Anyway, that's not that big of a deal.
To summarize what you've done from the artists perspective.
Did you add a light obligation to the contract between the programmer
and the artist?
I'm sorry, I'm not a sure I understand.
That question.
I mean it is Gang scene is a contractor.
She's not an employee if that's what you mean but I mean she's under
no obligation to keep working on the game if she wants to stop working
on it she can just like an employee could quit at any time.
I don't think it's common for contracts to have obligations that
somebody like an artist stay on till the end of a project.
I think that's very rare sometimes.
Our payment contingencies like, you know, maybe you get some bonus, if
you stay to completion, or if there's like royalties involved, you
only get the royalties.
If you certainly, there's things like that sometimes, but that's the
only thing I could think of.
So, I'm sorry, I'm not sure.
I really understand what the question is.
Trying to ask.
If you can't evict luck resources, what would be the point of
streaming them?
Over just loading them up front and doesn't it put a restraint on the
diversity of the environments?
You can have.
So I don't think it really puts a restraint on the diversity of the
environment you have because we're only talking about ground chunks.
So the number of things that will make up a ground texture.
I mean, even if you had to lock half a gigabytes worth of bitmaps or
something, the streaming was still work.
Fine, right?
And that's so much ground.
Texture to work with, like I can't imagine that ever being a problem
and chances are we're talking more like 256k or something like this.
Oh G.
Well, probably not that we probably talked about something like 64.
MB of locked worst.
Right.
So I'm not sure I care about it too much.
Like I said, it looked like the code overhead was just going to be
annoying.
So I don't think it would be a good idea to do it that way, but we'll
revisit that, if it turns out, we somehow have 10 gigabytes of ground
texture then,
You know, we'd revisit that but I suspect that it will be a very, very
small portion of the footprint as to why you still stream them.
The reason is so you never have a loading screen.
Like, I always liked games to run immediately, right?
And so I don't want to have a loading screen, it's like hey, why don't
you sit here?
And wait, while I load up all of the ground chunk data, even though
we're not going to draw half of it even, or even 10% of it for a long
time, till you get to like the ice area or whatever.
We don't need the ice bitmaps, right?
So I don't like to waste the users time.
Waiting for things that aren't necessary.
So that's why I want everything to be streamed even if some things
never stream out because it makes it easier to make sure the code will
be correct.
Shouldn't you fill work completely before calling platform at entry
for load asset work?
Yes, I should.
Did I miss something?
So,
Bonus at work.
We have assets file name ID should I put these in the right order?
Not that it matters.
But task bitmap has alignment Ally next.
Top down.
Line wife up.
Yeah, so there are all.
They are all filled.
Oh no.
How did this get there?
Ah,
thank you for catching that.
That was definitely not supposed to be.
I did not think that was what was happening?
That is totally wrong.
Totally, totally wrong.
That's supposed to be down here.
Yeah.
Sorry about that.
Thank you for catching that.
I have no idea why that was there.
I must have like cut and pasted something and and totally flubbed it.
Yeah, but no, that was not supposed to be the case.
So yes, you absolutely should.
I may have missed this but do you have the ability to set a hard limit
on memory usage yet?
So, you know, you can support lower memory machines.
So right now, when we start up, we only do the one allocation and
that's it.
So, we already only run in whatever memory we have, but that's not
really very meaningful because we just don't have any art assets yet.
So obviously, we're never going to hit that because art assets is what
will take up all that memory.
So, really the point where we'll be able to say we can set a
memory usage limit is when we actually go and finish the streaming
stuff to have eviction
in a prior episode, you implemented by linear filtering.
Are you going to take it a step further?
And Implement mipmapping and trilinear filtering?
So trilinear filtering is never necessary obviously because we're 2D
flat projected.
So there isn't really isn't any.
You would never try linear that, right?
You're just literally a me unless I'm
I guess unless I'm not thinking about it properly, you you never
actually need trilinear filtering because you just make sure that your
bit, your mitt Maps would always be bilinear downed versions of the
higher res stuff so that you never have to do trilinear, right?
But the reason I say are going to take a step further, I would say no,
we're not going to get further because it's unlikely that we're really
going to be scaling things by that much more than 2X.
The direction.
So I don't feel like mipmapping would really benefit us in any
particular way, I feel like it would just waste memory but to be
clear, we don't have to do any work to implement it mipmapping would
be free on architecture, currently all
To do is switch which bitmap we were using based on the size, that's
it.
So, we would not have to rewrite the render at all.
We already effectively support.
Mipmapping in that sense.
So yet, so the answer is no, we would not modify the renderer in any
way.
If for some reason we find that mipmapping is going to be important.
Meaning, we see that we are doing a lot of that scaling and things are
not looking good to us.
Then what we would do is we would just have at the head end when you
do a push bitmap call it would
Look at how big you are trying to draw it.
And pick the bitmap scaled versions with a bitmap based on that.
That'd be the only change and then it and then we'd have the full
quality that you would get.
If you turned on mipmapping and trilinear in a hardware.
Renderer
Well, the assets loaded in from a file be stored in evicted in the
same way as the ground chunks.
I don't know because our ground chunks game is kind of hacked right
now that the eviction scheme was just something we threw in there.
So I suppose, we'll probably think a little bit harder about it, but I
don't know.
Questions questions, are there questions on the string?
Maybe there are, but maybe the lag is keeping them from being asked.
But there may not be any more questions, everyone might be totally on
it.
Then see why only BMP.
So the answer is we will not the answer should not even be why only
BMP I tried the question shouldn't be why only be a the question
should be why anything?
And the answer is because it's temporary we will not be loading any
type of Art in the game later.
Any type of standard file will be loading from a pack file, that's our
own devising.
So that's why we only load be empty at the moment.
It just happens to be an easy format to load and so when I was
implementing it to show people how to get that working, I just picked
the MP and did it because it's really easy to load but yeah in the
future there will be no such thing as loading a BMP basically they'll
just be a giant pack file.
The PAC file will have a bitmap format that we have devised that we
are comfortable with and that we load directly, it will probably be
compressed with something like you know in lzma
A or something, who knows?
And we will just have that will be our format in the PAC file.
So there won't even be BMP.
Loading in the in the actual version.
Once we finish shipping it,
Soy sauce.
The kid the eviction stuff you're doing is it basically garbage
collection know so it's not garbage collection.
It's sort of more like
How should I put this?
So the way that garbage collection works is garbage collection waits
to see if something isn't used anymore and when it isn't used anymore,
it gets rid of it, right?
But what this is is not that all of these things are things that we're
using, right?
Meaning.
All the Assets in the game, are things that we're using, but we just
can't fit them all in memory.
Like, we'd love to have all 32 gigabytes of addresses or whatever just
in memory.
And then we not to care about any of this, but the truth is, we don't
have that much space.
So what we do is we page in whatever is being most recently used.
So this is not akin to garbage collection.
It's akin to virtual memory if that makes sense, right?
We're sort of
Our own virtual memory.
So what we do is we have 32 gigabytes of virtual bitmap space, and
then two gigabytes of physical bitmap space.
And we're just moving in, whatever the two gigabytes you know.
We're trying to keep that 2 gigabytes of physical map to whatever the
most useful ones are at the time.
Right?
So hopefully that makes sense.
So it really has nothing to do with garbage.
Collection, garbage collections, about seeing what's used in, what's
not used.
This is not that this is about trying to
Keep in ask in a fixed amount of space, the things that are most
likely to be used soon if that makes sense.
Will we be using AMD hair physics?
Obviously, how could you even ship a game that doesn't have a hair
physics in it?
That's ridiculous.
Probably what we'll do and obviously this is hush-hush.
So don't tell anyone about this like this stays just between me and
the you know a couple hundred people are ever who are watching the
entire game will be constructed entirely out of hair.
So basically like the main character.
There will be all care that one that's in there.
Now, just a stand-in, it's just going to be like a hairball.
And then like all the ground is going to be hair.
That's kind of like mad and out.
And then the trees will be hair and the Monsters will be hair, but
like a different color.
So, for example, like maybe the main character will be will have dark
hair and I'll be fighting against like blond-haired things, right?
It's kind of like a statement on racism, if that makes sense.
You know, you know, I don't want to go too deep here but, you know, I
don't want to bring Ferguson into it, right?
But
Like, that's that's basically what we're going for.
So that's why we need the Ambi hair physics and that's why that will
be going in soon.
It'll be all about AMD hair physics and like I said, that's not
cosmetic.
That's a that's like about theme and so the AMD hair for this will be
letting us address racism in a much deeper.
Way then we could have if like the rest of the game was made out of
real stuff instead of hair.
If you turn a bit matte black and white by altering the pixel, then
would you have two copies of the bitmap?
Would you delete one if you have to
Yeah.
I mean I'm not sure I totally understand the question.
but I guess what I would say is the
the idea is a bitmap is sort of a cash in some ways, right?
Like you could imagine saying, Well what we'll do is, we'll
procedurally generate all the graphics with some complicated routine
that like take sanctions brain and breaks it down into a neural
network and then tells it to paint the hero and it Paints the here or
whatever.
Like right.
But what a bitmap is is it's sort of like a Memento it's like here was
a process that was expensive to do.
It took human effort even right to produce what this thing should look
like.
And it's what we're going to do is, we're going to load that and lift
that, right?
You can think about that as being true for like all bitmaps.
Essentially, any bitmap is just a cache of some process that was
potentially expensive and so what you have to think about in terms of
your game, is anytime there's bitmaps that I could be generating.
So like in your case, you're saying, there's a procedural modification
to the bitmap, like I'm turning some of the pixels to a different
color, right?
If there are procedural modifications, you can make, you have to ask
the same question, are those procedural?
Modifications fast enough so that they could happen during the frame
When we render if so then it's probably more efficient to do it that
way but if they're expensive then it's probably more efficient to cash
them in bitmaps and make new bitmaps and that's like what we do with
the ground chunks, for example, right?
So you yeah, to give it a totally concrete example.
In fact, look at the way we deal with the hero versus how we deal with
the ground chunks because the ground chunks are going to have a lot
more logic to them and a lot more splatting I chose to cash them.
The hero is just three Sprites on top of each other that we'll just
kind of bounced.
So I chose to Creak and posit them every frame.
And that's just a decision that you have to be comfortable with
making.
Sometimes you have to make with a profile and actually timing it if
you're uncomfortable, knowing which one is going to be correct, but
it's always about that.
It's about what can I do dynamically versus what do I have to cash,
right?
Why do people care so much about garbage collection?
I have no idea.
As far as I'm concerned is completely useless concept.
Why use a pack file instead of bmps?
What makes it better.
So basically there's two reasons, well, three reasons really, one of
them silly.
The silly reason is that I hate games spamming my hard drive with
eight thousand files.
I just want an executable and a data file, like that's it.
It's nice and clean.
I can copy it around, it's not a nightmare, it's all good.
Right.
So there's a little person acting as their but that's the silly
reason.
And the good.
R1 you don't pollute the OS handle pool, and you're not opening files
all the time, right?
With a Pac file.
You just open one file handle to the OS.
It knows.
You're always going to be looking at that file, right?
The file is now locked.
So no one's going to delete it out from under you, or do anything
else.
Ridiculous.
The OS is expecting you to have it in there.
It's warm in the in the cash.
Everything's good.
And so it's going to be able to pull those in as full pages and all
these other good things.
And then all I'm doing is pulling parts out of it, right?
It also allows me to issue background reads really easily.
There's all these sorts of things, you'll see a little when we get to
pack file, how much better it is than individual files.
It's way better but that's that's the majority of it, right?
And the other part that's great about it is also the the indexing so
the the Manifest of all the stuff that's in there and I don't mean
like a Windows manifest.
I mean like our whatever our table is that tells us about what's in
there.
Could all use offsets into the file which is just a simple probably 32
bit number.
And that way we don't have to use strings and have strings in there
that point tell you like what file to go load and all that garbage.
So pack files are like, it's not even like a subtly better thing.
Pack files in practice are like so much better than individual files
that it's like it's not even a contest.
Earlier, someone asked why we Implement virtual memory on top of the
OS is virtual memory?
Are we doing this?
Just so we can have more virtual space.
The reason is because relying on the OS is virtual memory is extremely
tenuous.
You have no idea what it's going to do.
You have no idea when it's going to page in, you have no idea who
which thread is going to hit the paging.
It's just, it's just very dicey and so typically you do not want to
rely on the OS is virtual memory for something as critical as asset
streaming.
It just tends to be a pretty bad idea, right?
Furthermore, you don't even know if the
System has that much virtual memory.
It's entirely possible that the machine is not configured to have 32
gigabytes of virtual memory and in that case, you will just fail.
So those are, those are not really good options.
Yeah, it's not fabulous.
You could try using a memory mapped file instead, which would solve
that problem.
But then you have the problem with the fact that that's actually not
the thing that you're cashing, that's probably compressed.
So you would need a second memory mapped file which was your sponsor
yet.
it's just there's a lot more complexity there, it's not as simple as
just saying, let the OS, do the virtual memory for you, it's really
not that simple because the paging process involves decompression and
all these other sorts of things that are, you know, that the OS
doesn't do
Are the ground trucks.
Going to be peaking positive when using the GPU, I would assume.
So, yeah, I don't see any reason why not to, and it'll be much faster
that way than trying to have the CPU, do them and then upload them,
which when we could just have the GPU to them directly.
Is there a reason why you split the character three B is, yes.
So it can have some nice bounce to it, some squash and stretch.
Is the rendering going to be eventually done on the GPU.
Yeah I mean at this point it's unclear whether we'll ever really need
it but we would want to ship it that way.
Because in fact, I was talking to Danielle, bemberg read about that.
This just earlier today, it's more power efficient to use a GPU in
most contact still like on laptops, for example, even if our software
renderer turns out to be so good that we could showed leadership with
it.
And it's not an issue, it will be much more power hungry.
Even using a GPU for the same workload.
I would suspect.
And so for example, on a laptop that was using Intel integrated
Graphics, I can pretty much guarantee that if we go through the GPU,
it will not burn the battery nearly as fast as if we spun up the whole
CPU to do that rendering if that makes sense.
But that's just my assumption.
Our game saves going to be part of that asset pack file or their own
pack file know.
The game saves cannot be part of the pack file.
The reason they can't be part of the pack file among other things is
because they are writable.
So the pack file will be read only and potentially installed on the
user's machine in a place that cannot be written to.
We don't know whether it can or not.
And so the same game saves have to go in like a Windows directory,
that's allowed to have writing Privileges and all these other sorts of
things.
So we want to make sure that we write say files.
Totally different location or at least can because there's a bunch of
compliance reasons why that will have to be true.
So, in general, you want the save Palace to be separate anyway.
So people could like copy them around or do anything they want, right?
So generally, you want to save files, to be separate for other reasons
to probably, but even if you wanted them to be part of the pack file,
I would probably advise against it because of platform compliance
reasons.
On Windows and on elsewhere and also for cloud.
Save, right?
If you have a save game and you're using, like, let's say we shipped
the game on Steam and we want this saves to be cloud-enabled.
That's a perfect example of where you couldn't be part of the pack
file because the pack the whole pack file is not going to be recent
every time.
So we need the it to be like a sort of separate file that that's just
for saved game data.
All right.
Have you come to the end of the q's and the A's?
Q's and A's using a skews cues and A's.
just putting the rendering Tree on the GPU mean, you have to write a
renderer completely separate to the CPU on or is it is most of the
groundwork done by having the CPU render or done, it's usually
completely separate because everything that the GPU renderer does is,
you know, all the
Is that our CPU render or does the GPU render has like different calls
and stuff for, right?
So, probably like the render group that CPP file has two would be
like, you know, replaced by a separate one for the GPU.
And GPU rendering is pretty complicated actually, especially if we do
Vulcan.
There's a lot of setup in a lot of management fencing and all these
other sorts of things, right?
So for doing like a mantle Vulcan d3d 12 kind of a thing, those are,
you know, much more low level and they involve a lot of work that has
nothing to do with what the CPU renderer is doing.
Its totally separate.
It's about setting up things for Hardware, right?
And so if we
End up going that route which you know I think we probably will
because by the time we get to that you know either d3d 12 or Vulcan
will be a viable thing.
I'm quite sure for us to use.
I suspect you know because since the software under turned out to be
so good, we aren't in any rush, we can choose to wait till the very
end of the project to put in the GPU render.
So, you know, for talking a year from now or you're in a half from now
when the project is getting in you know into ship mode or
Ever.
I feel like we'll be able to use one of those and there's a lot of
work in there.
I thought you hated both DRM and cloud-based stuff based off of Jeff
and crazy show.
Yeah, I do, well, I wouldn't say that.
I hate all cloud-based stuff obviously.
I like the idea of backing things up to a server or things like this.
I mean you source code control stuff like that.
I hate DRM which is why handmade here, hasn't any DRM.
But I'm also don't have a problem with putting handmade Hero on
something like steam that might have DRM on.
As long as people have the choice of buying it somewhere where it
doesn't have DRM, right?
Because if people want to use Steam and they don't care about digital
Rights Management, then, you know, I want people to be able to, to
get, I mean, in fact, the reason I don't like dear Emma specifically
because I want people to get things the way that they want them,
right?
And DRM is about preventing you from being able to get the game, the
way you want and store it, the way you want and run it the way that
you want.
And so I certainly wouldn't prohibit people.
From getting the game on a platform that they liked such as Steam just
because it happens to be dare end.
And also, I'm pretty sure and I could be wrong about this.
That steam doesn't require the DRM.
So when I put it on Steam, I could also, I believe turn off any sorts
of DRM features on Steam so that when you when it downloaded the game
to you, you could then copy those files to a different machine of
yours and Run the game.
And that would be fine.
So yeah.
Just be clear on that.
All right.
I think, creepy Uncle cases going to go get some Ramen now.
So let's go ahead and wind things down so they don't see any more
questions.
Let's go ahead and close this.
Close it down.
Alright.
Oops.
Try to close down.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade here.
It's my pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along with the source code at
home, you could always pre-order the game on him, made here a DOT org
and it comes all the source code.
The handy dandy pre-order button allows you to get a link in email and
then you can download the source code any time.
After I finish every night, I upload the changes.
So you're always current if you want to just support the video series,
we do have a patreon page, which we very much appreciate subscriptions
to we
Have a forum site where you can ask questions and you can also take a
look at Community ports there.
People have done some reporting to Mac and Linux, if you want to try
that and you need some help.
We also have annotate episode guide, which you can look at their,
which helps to catch up on old things, old episodes.
You may have missed.
And finally, if you're trying to catch the show live, we do have a
tweak bought.
The Tweet bot will treat the schedule at you.
So if you want to know when it streams going to be live any given day,
that's the place to check.
And it should always be able to
to tell you that's about it.
I think for today.
Thank you everyone for joining me.
And I will see you back here tomorrow, when we will go ahead and push
forwards on our asset storage format, which probably means we'll also
do some pack file stuff.
I feel like now that we're in there, you might as well just finish up
asset stuff.
Like I said, it's not super complicated so you might as well.
Just try to get that finished up in a reasonable state, so we can just
check that off our list and be done with it.
So, thank you very much for joining me.
I hope to see you here.
Tomorrow, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time until then Happy coding everyone.