Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream in the pre stream.
We had a question and I thought it was a question that probably a lot
of people ask a lot.
I see it's kind of talked about it on the internet and it's something
that I feel like probably should be addressed it and it's actually
fairly topical I suppose at this point in time.
So I figured I would actually put the answer on the stream for reals
and the question was
I'll just read it again.
Exactly.
As it was written.
The question was, I'm a student struggling with imposter syndrome?
I feel like I can't do anything and everyone is better than me.
Your thoughts on this phenomenon and I guess there's a lot of things
to think about in that sort of wrapped up in this question, I'll start
with the fact that impostor syndrome was something that I had never
heard about until a few years ago, actually, when I was growing up and
when I was starting out in the game industry,
Stree.
And for most of my career in the game industry, I never heard that
term.
So it's only fairly recently that I think that you know, that the
general programming population was aware of this as a thing to give a
name to write, which is not the same as saying that it's a recent
phenomenon, right?
The phenomenon has probably been going on in terms of the feelings
that people have surrounding, this has maybe gone on forever, who
knows?
But
It wasn't like I never heard anyone discuss it or even like know, you
know, didn't like have a name for that and you may not have liked
associated with like a group of people who have this or known that you
had it or even thought to yourself.
Do I have this thing right?
And so you know I feel like part of probably a little bit of of the
the benefit to having gone, you know, grown up during that time period
is I will say before I say anything else about it.
Imposter syndrome, I will say that.
Once someone puts the thought in your head that this is a thing, you
may be more likely to get, you know, hung up on it too, right?
It's like, if you've never heard about problem X and maybe you have
problem X, you might be just okay?
Ignoring it because you never really thought of it and you don't, you
know, have concrete thoughts about it or whatever like that.
So, you know, I think maybe we got some benefit in never having anyone
talk about this thing, you know, it might make it easier,
Move past, but either, or I think the feelings are definitely genuine
and probably have happened throughout programming history and probably
throughout anything history.
And I think there's a couple things to think about when you think
about impostor syndrome, right?
So first of all, there is actually a legitimate question for everyone,
which is Mia, any good at this thing, right?
It is important to try and figure that out to a certain degree, right?
It is important to be aware of the fact that you can just be very bad
at something.
Right?
And, you know, I certainly have things at least that I've experienced
in my life where I like, I'm pretty sure that like, whatever this
thing is, you know, I'm doing this thing.
I'm like, I can kind of tell that I'm probably always going to be
really bad at this thing, right?
For example, if my goal in life was to be a long distance Runner, I
can pretty much tell you that there would be
Problem with imposter syndrome, it would just be regular.
I'm really bad at this syndrome because I am going to be really bad at
it, right?
And no matter how hard I worked at being a long distance.
Runner, I'm never going to be one of the top long-distance Runners,
like that's just not going to happen, right?
And probably, I won't even be one of the like, okay, long distance
Runners.
I'm probably just going to be bad, like, period, like just pretty much
bad even if I was in best condition for me, right?
It's just, it's not, maybe my genetics to be good at this thing.
It's me.
Be not, you know, my lifestyle, or how I conduct myself, you know, in
terms of physical fitness, who knows?
Right.
I have no idea, but it's pretty clear that it's not going to happen.
And so it is definitely true.
That it a certain level, you do want to be aware, you want to be
self-aware and go Mi pursuing a course that is definitely going to be
too difficult for me to ever achieve the level of proficiency that I
want, right.
And it's important to put it into those terms right?
Because if I just wanted to do long distance running for fun and I
didn't really care how good I was at it.
I just wanted to do it then it doesn't matter so much, right?
In other words, it always has to be about
Particular goal because, you know, if your goal isn't to be great at
something, if your goal is just to have fun, then why are you even
talking about a positive as the goal is to have fun, right?
And the same can be said of something like programming.
If your goal is to just you enjoy programming and you're, you know,
you just want to do it for a living and you don't care.
If you're one of the worst people at it, as long as you still can just
main keep a job, right?
That's a much lower bar, then I want to excel at programming, right?
Furthermore, you could just be a programming
A hobbyist.
I just want to do this as a hobby for fun, right?
And then the bar is lower, still, it doesn't matter if your program
has ever even work.
As long as you're enjoying it, that's okay, right?
And so certainly, it's worth recognizing that as well.
But assuming that it's something that you're saying, you know, this is
something I want to spend a significant amount my life on.
I care whether I am good at it or not, so you've already made that
decision, right?
And again it's important to actually get there, don't just assume that
because do you really know that's the important thing in your life,
right?
Do you have you actually sat down and
Right.
Is it important to me that I am a good programmer, right?
Because it may not be right.
That is that is it is not, you know, it's easy to fall into the Trap.
You know, on the internet where everyone's yelling about
How great they are templates or whatever is going on over there.
And did you get in the IPO?
And who knows what's happening, right?
It's easy to think that your self-worth is going to be tied up in how
good of a programmer you are or something like that, right?
But don't let that happen to you without actually establishing that
yourself like you should actually get there yourself and decide, I do
care about being a good programmer, it's not just a psychological
thing.
That's happened to me that I let the world kind of push on me, that
that was
Important.
I actually got to put where it's important to me, right?
Because if you don't get there, you're if you're not there then you
again shouldn't care about imposter syndrome at all.
If it really isn't important to you, like like inside that you are a
good programmer, then you shouldn't care at all.
The only thing you care about is, is, you know, am I getting hired for
a job?
So, I can support myself, right?
That's the only bar, you have to clear and it doesn't matter if you're
awful at it or whether you feel like you're off lot at.
None of that matters.
If you, if you don't care, then all you have to do.
Just don't worry about it.
You're it's just a job, right?
It's like going to any other job.
If you didn't care about whatever it was, you were doing you don't
care how good you are, as long as the boss is happy, right?
So you got to get there yourself, and if you get there yourself,
you're like, it's important to me that I'm good at this thing, right?
Then we get into the question of sort of more The Imposter syndrome
stuff, right?
And for those of you who aren't familiar with this phrase, I'm
assuming like, everyone is at this point, but like I said, it was kind
of a new word.
To me, what is essentially describes as far as I am understanding it
from the way.
I see it used is, it's the feeling that you get when you are in a
position where you're expected to do something, whatever that thing is
and you feel like you are not good enough to do that thing and
everyone around, you just doesn't like know that yet or that they are
good at this thing and you're not and you're going to be like found
out.
It's like literally
Imposter part.
It's like you believe you are just fronting the fact that you are good
at programming.
But actually you're bad at programming and it's just a matter of time
perhaps till everyone finds out, right?
It's literally, like, you know, kind of Taken literally, I am not a
pop psychologist.
So, you know, don't listen to me for a textbook definition of this
phrase.
That's just my understanding of kind of like how people tend to use it
and the kinds of things I describe when they attach it to that term.
So the question is, let's say, you are in a position where you care
about being good.
Programmer, you want to do programming for living, and your self-worth
is tied to this.
In some way, you care about.
Whether you excel at this.
It's a self-esteem issue for you, right?
Which is totally fair.
You know, I definitely want to be good at programming.
I do it all the time.
I don't want to feel like I'm bad at programming, right?
That's not a thing that I want to feel etcetera, etcetera, right?
so, if you've gotten to that point then,
I think there's some things that you have to, you know, start to
internalize and it's kind of difficult, but it gets to part of the
reason why I do handmade hero as well, right?
And that is you have to understand first of all that most programmers
are not as good at programming, as you probably think they are right.
People who are looking outward and having these thoughts about like, a
my, you know, I'm not really good at this.
And everyone else is good at this or something.
You are probably over perceiving like or overvaluing, I don't know
what's wrong.
You're probably looking at other programmers and evaluating their
skills higher than you should right.
And again that's one of the reasons that I do handmade hero the way I
do it because one way that I could have done, handmade here is do a
lot of preparation for it and then do a stream where I didn't really
make any mistakes and everything came out, really perfect.
And you know there,
Bugs and stuff, right?
That would have been one way to do it and that would be an interesting
way to do it if what you're trying to do is just show typing in,
correct?
Code, or something, right?
But I don't think that's particularly useful, especially not to people
who are just learning.
And the reason for that is because it is very much tied into the
Imposter syndrome thing.
I never think about imposter syndrome because like I said, that was it
something that I grew up with as a thing?
But I just do.
I do think that the way we've traditionally taught programming where
it's in books with pre-written code that's been like, pre-tested, you
know, and worked on.
And then, we just saw the results, we write blog posts that are like,
here are the results of this law.
Process.
And here's where we ended up, right?
I think what those things do is they accidentally, right?
They're not trying to do this, but they accidentally make it appear as
if great programmers, just have the answer and they just stick it into
the like editor and then, there it is, right.
But having worked with plenty of great programmers.
I can tell you for a fact that that is nothing to do with it, right?
It is nowhere like that at all.
I don't care.
Which
Programmer you care to name, trust me?
That's not how it worked.
And so what I wanted to show on handmade hero was an example of
somebody who does program for a living and gets paid to do it.
Right.
So, you know that they're, you know, someone who you could go do this
thing, if you want to do this thing, and you would be reasonably
successful if you did it like they did it.
Showing me programming and making tons of mistakes, right?
And having to go through lots of iterations, right?
So, even if you're not talking about mistakes changing your mind, a
bunch having to re move code around, change the way I do things.
Get stuck on bugs, right?
The reason I do that is very specifically because I want younger
programmers, who don't?
I have the experience of working with people like I did, right?
Because, like I said, working with great programmers, lets you see
that they have these problems, I wanted them to see
That people who work in this industry day-to-day on code that ships
and lots of games have all of these same problems that they're having,
right?
Because that is crucial in my opinion to understanding the development
process, right?
Even if imposter syndrome and worrying about the psychological effect
of that isn't the primary question that we were asking.
Like that is the question that I'm addressing now but even if it
wasn't it's just a question of being
Good developer, right?
A good developer has to internalize the fact that this is the way
development works, there isn't such a thing as someone who can just
come in and write the perfect code for you.
The first time, the only time that you can ever do that is if you've
already written exactly that code before and occasionally, you'll see
that on handmade hero.
Sometimes, I write something you'll see me do it on handmade here and
it comes out.
It's like, how did he do that so quickly or something?
I've heard people ask me this about certain parts.
When I've done them and the answer is always the same.
The reason, the only reason you will ever see me, do something
flawlessly on handmade hero is because it's something I've done so
many times before, right?
And anything that I haven't done enough times before or don't have a
good solution for yet that I've been satisfied with in the past it
goes through all those same problems, right?
I have all of those same problems that a beginner programmer would
have and maybe I have better attack skills because I have so much more
experience than being a programmer but
Of the same problems, apply I get bugs that I didn't, you know, c4c, I
have mistakes that I make and how I architected something that means I
have to sort of change it around again.
I have to do some exploration right?
Because I'm not sure I think maybe this is the right thing, but then
it turns out to not be.
I make a mistake that cost some performance and only through the
profiling.
Do I determine that?
I've made an error somewhere and I have to go change the way I was
storing.
Something all of those same things.
Apply.
You know, and I've been programming for 30 years, right.
So I think it's critical that people see that and they see that
programmer programming is about having is about that process.
And very recently, actually back onto the Imposter syndrome part, I
was talking with a programmer, who's, you know, unquestionably a great
programmer, right?
There's just no question about this and I won't say who it was because
this was in a private conversation by, so I can someone who was
unquestionably, like from my perspective, a great programmer, right?
And they
We are in the midst of a project that they were just feeling really
bad about the state of the project because, you know, they felt like
they had kind of bitten off more than they could chew.
And then it was making, you know, creating problematic costs for their
company and what they were doing and like, they just, you know, they
wanted to do a really good job on it, but the cost of doing the really
good job, or just a lot, right?
And all these sorts of things.
And it's like,
It is literally the case that no matter how long you program.
If you're trying to do something new or you're trying to do something
difficult and your trunk, you know if you're trying to go beyond where
you are right now, it doesn't matter how good of a programmer you are.
It is just, that is the process.
The process is about going through those things and making the
mistakes and keeping at it and at the end of the day, what typically
differentiates, you know, the programmers, who make it from the
programmers, who don't in these when you're
Talking about difficulties.
That is, it's really about that perseverance, right?
It's about how you recover from the mistakes, how you move past, you
know, your shortcomings, how you kind of get past that not about never
having them because programming is so complicated that I've just never
seen anyone ever get to the point where they're not wrestling with all
of those issues.
So, I think when you're first starting out,
You should absolutely expect to have all of those sorts of problems
because, you know, that even people who are much more experienced than
you are, and who are shipping high-profile games, and all these are
sites are having those problems to write.
And so, it really doesn't matter.
Where on the Spectrum you fall in less, you aren't challenging
yourself, like, unless you're intentionally picking code of a size and
a nature.
That is beneath your skill level at this point.
You will go through these same problems, right?
So that's and I think that's very important to internalize is that not
only do great programmers, make mistakes, they make horrible mistakes,
they make really bad decisions about their projects, they get things
pretty deep into the hole right and eventually they will pull
themselves back out of that but it's a definitely a fallacy to assume
that just because it's some famous person that you look up to that.
That person doesn't have that those exact same
Mmmmm days where they're thinking to themselves, oh my God, like I
can't do this, I've screwed everything up, what am I going to do?
This is never going to work, right?
That's just part of the psychology.
Okay, so I'd say, keep keep that in mind for the rest of the session.
So the next thing I would say is well, okay.
It is generally true though that I do find, there are people who have
an aptitude for programming and people who don't
It is true that that you have a spectrum, right?
It's not the case.
I don't necessarily think that every person is like a great programmer
waiting to happen or something like that but I don't really know one
way or the other.
All I can tell you is that just in terms of having worked with
programmers, before you definitely can see.
Some programmers are just a lot better than other programmers.
Write that is actually true.
Now, why they are aren't?
I have no idea.
Like, I don't
I know that there's like the programming Gene kind of like there's,
you know, genetics for body types or something like this, where it's
like, hey, like I said before, probably never going to be a long
distance Runner.
If you just look at the way I'm built, that's probably never going to
happen, right?
But I don't know that that's true because we don't know very much
about human and you know, mental development and stuff like this.
So it could actually be that everyone could be a great programmer and
it's more about training and and how you know what growing up was like
for you and whether
Learn the right things at the right time, right?
Like we have no idea where well before the point where we would have
any idea.
Whether this is something that's about how your brain has been
conditioned or whether it's about how your, you know, chemistry Works
internally or who knows what I have no idea.
None whatsoever, but it is definitely true that there.
There's a range of programming, sort of aptitude out there, it does
seem.
And so, I think the question is for any individual who is concerned
about their situation and goes okay, you know, first for as far as the
Imposter goes first, make sure you internalize the thing about
programming being difficult.
About even great programmers, having these problems, make sure you've
actually internalize that.
So actually do understand that these problems are here, take a minute,
to watch some handmade hero.
And remember, after 30 years, look at how much work I have to still do
to, like get things into the right.
Place to experiment with things to to find bugs like to do blah blah
blah blah, right?
Like think about that and think about how long I've been programming
and there's still
These problems, right?
So keep that in mind and then keep in mind.
The same thing is true for great.
Programmers, you admire, right?
Because I like I said, I've worked with plenty of great programmers
and they have these same things, right?
In fact, you can go watch some of streams of great programmers
programming, and you will see exactly those same things happen, right?
So, you know that even after you've done all of that work and gotten
to a place where, you know, you you're
Ordered respected or whatever it is you're not you haven't gotten rid
of those, it doesn't mean you've attained some kind of of superbetter
development process.
You've actually just
Gotten better at the same thing with all the problems that it had,
right?
And you will still have the same psychological problems.
You will still think from day to day.
Oh man, that went really poorly, right?
It's not like I'm sitting here going like every episode of handmade
hero.
We did great or it work.
I'm not always thinking like, well I wrote Amazing code today.
That is not, you know, that's not happening, right?
Part of being a programmer that engineering mindset, is always looking
for the problems with things as well.
So more often than not, I'm like,
There's all these problems in this code that I wrote, right?
So if you've actually internalize that and found some people who you
look up to who have streams or whatever and watch them, and seen just
how much of a struggle it still is for them even though you know
they've had way more experience than you.
Right?
Internalize that and then you look and go.
Okay now do I think that maybe I'm questioning whether I'm going to be
good at this?
Heading up that right?
I factor that out.
I factored out the, the high probability, I would say that I'm being
too harsh on myself because I'm not looking at the, the flaws in these
other people, I'm not letting myself.
See just how hard it is for them even after they've had decades more
experience than I have, right?
So even factoring that out in.
Now if you're starting to look and say well I just don't know.
I want to know if I'm going to get this.
It seems like I'm having more trouble with this then than I should and
I'm concerned that maybe I'm just not good enough at it right.
Then I guess what I think you have to ask yourself is
Is there some ways are there?
Some steps you could take to verify that a little bit more
objectively, right?
Or to take a more objective assessment of what you are doing and why
you are failing at it or perceiving that you are failing at it, right?
Because one of the things that's that's true about anything, right?
Is that you need to have some metrics for success and failure.
You need to have some way of analyzing why you did or didn't hit those
metrics if you want to factor out just your subjective opinion, right?
Because if you're talking about something like imposter syndrome, this
is a psychological effect.
You may very well just be unable to see that you are doing something
reasonably well or the potential that you have.
You may just not be able to see it, right?
You may be and there could be all sorts of reasons for that.
For example, let's say that you're actually a very good programmer,
but you're going to a school that teaches object-oriented programming.
Well, obviously, in your programming, like, by its nature is not good,
right?
Or at least if you take my word for it.
So you maybe being taught something that fundamentally
Doesn't gel in your brain because it's a fundamentally flawed way of
programming in the first place and your brains actually good at
programming, right?
And if someone was to just tell you, oh, here is a way of programming
that more better aligns with your Natural Instincts.
It turns out you're really good, right?
So certainly, you have to start from a premise of what is the metric
that I'm actually using?
If it's just that I'm, like, not doing as good on these School
assignments as other people are.
Or if it's just that like I didn't pass this job interview at Google.
Or something like this, right?
You don't you haven't really learned anything by that because those
metrics may be set up by people who are not good, programmers write
and if they are set up a good programmers, that doesn't necessarily
mean that those programmers were good at making metrics for disturbing
compare numbers.
I've certainly known more than one, good programmer, who was very bad
at interviewing other programmers, and deciding, which ones of them
were good, right?
So, it's also not the case that you can just rely on
Some external measure to tell you whether you're a good programmer or
not because that may not be true.
So I think you have to look and say what is a way that I could create
some things for me to try where I could then more objectively measure
whether I can do this or whether I can't write.
And I think there are a lot of factors that go into making a good
programmer and
And, you know, some of them are like being able to kind of work
through math, okay?
Right.
Not in the like math class way, but in the, like kind of handmade hero
Blackboard way, you know, just being able to understand like roughly
what's going on and being able to solve the equations, you need to
solve in the way you need to solve them, right?
There's that there's perseverance, you know, being willing to sit in
front of a computer for many hours a day, trying things and you know
debugging things and all those sorts of things right?
There's being able to keep systems in your head in ways that allow you
to sort of figure out whether they're whether there's things you could
do to help improve them and whether or not they could be working more
efficiently, each other.
There's understanding hardware and understanding how it works.
So that you can have a rough mental model of it and make reasonable
decisions that don't result in really poor.
Operating code and all that sort of stuff, right?
So it's all these sorts of things there.
So I think before you should be willing to sort of adopt an opinion,
like maybe I'm not that good at this.
I think you have to come up with some things you can do to try to see
whether you actually are not in a more objective way.
So one example like I said before is pick a very simple thing to write
asteroids like for game development right?
Asteroids is my favorite one for that because it's very, very simple.
But still is a complete game, right?
You know, doing
Thing like developing asteroids from scratch on Windows or something
like this using opengl let's say or something like that.
Setting out some tasks like this for yourself where you pick something
and you see how far you can get in it, right?
I think are much more reasonable ways of going about determining
whether or not you can or can't do it.
And the reason for that is I think that
With programming.
A lot of times, the proof is very much in the pudding.
The difference between a programmer who can ship asteroids and a
programmer who can't is that the program who can ship asteroids shift,
asteroids,
Right?
And so at some level I think you have to pick some goals like that.
See how you do, right?
And if for some reason you are unable to get an Asteroids game working
eventually in something, you know, in it exercise.
Such as this figure out what it was that prevented you from doing it,
lots of people, the thing that will prevent them from doing it, is
they just didn't spend the time they gave up after a couple weeks of
doing
Right?
They just, they just don't do it.
So, it wasn't that they couldn't do it.
It wasn't that they can't figure it out.
It's that they just don't spend enough time to actually get a working
asteroids together, right?
That is what prevents 90% of programmers from being any good at
programming, right?
That's what prevents some people who actually know a ton about
programming and know a lot about computer science from ever doing
anything useful in programming, right?
Because a lot of programming is
Just doing the programming.
So, if that was the case, let's say that what you do is, you sit down
and say, I'm going to write asteroids over the next few months and
what you find is that you never finish.
Asteroids, you never just, you just never it, never even works at all.
Like you never get it up and running, no matter how bad it is.
You now have one answer to whether you are good at programming and
that is you do not have the perseverance.
Right now, you have a useful thing, you can actually act on.
If it is important to you, that you become a good programmer.
Now, you know, if you want to know whether you'll be good or not, it's
can you overcome your problem with perseverance?
Can you actually sit and code for longer than you have been in order
to get to the point where you can actually ship stuff, right?
And that is an objective thing.
If you can't, you now know it was an impostor syndrome, you were
actually allows you at it, right?
Mind you.
I put a big caveat on there.
Plenty of people who are gainfully employed, making lots of money, at
lots of places right now.
Also have that problem.
So before you actually consider yourself, bad at programming relative
to the rest of the world.
You also kind of have to internalize the fact that I'm talking about,
actually good programming not getting a job.
Programmer so don't despair.
Even if that's the case, you may come to the conclusion that you're
never going to be a great programmer, that doesn't mean you shouldn't
go get a programming job.
There's plenty of places, especially at web companies that will take
you, and you will never really have to be responsible for doing all
that much code.
Anyway, so
That caveat aside that is an actual actionable thing.
You can work on right and not only is it actionable in the sense that
it's a good decision thing.
Am I going to be good?
Perm or not?
It's something you can work to improve right?
If the thing that's stopping you from getting, Astra is done is
perseverance, work on your perseverance.
Make a rule that you have to program for an hour a day non-stop.
No distractions next week, two hours a day.
Next week, three hours a day.
Next week, four hours a day, right?
Once you have 24 hours a day,
You should be able to make Asteroids for hours a day.
Might take a while, but a lot of programmers.
No matter, even good programmers.
Don't get more than four hours a day to program.
A lot of times there's other stuff they have to be doing meetings or
talking with other people about stuff, or going to things or whatever
blah blah, blah dealing with, right.
So if you can get yourself up to four hours, a day of straight
programming, not reading the internet, not searching stack Overflow,
but four hours a day of typing in code, and running it.
You can make asteroids.
So, take that out of the equation.
Next question is, is your Asteroids game?
Just not working?
Are you spending all your time to bugging?
Do not know why it's crashing, whatever right?
If that's the thing, that's stopping you from getting there.
Now that you're programming for our is a day, ask yourself.
Why am I not able to do these?
Why am I not able to debugging can tie concretely, practice my
debugging skills to get me to the point where I know how to do it.
We show a lot of ways to debug stuff on handmade hero.
Can you watch that?
Can you learn from
That can you write keep a log of the bugs that you're having once you
have found them after 6 hours or however long it took?
You can you then go back and go?
How could I have found this bug faster?
What are the reasons why this bug got into my code base?
And took me a long time to find, right?
Again, a concrete thing.
You can evaluate yourself on.
If you don't think you could ever get better at it.
You've tried and tried and tried, you're not getting any better.
Okay?
Imposter syndrome validated you're not a good programmer, right?
Right.
Chances are no, you could get better at it and if you work at that and
you put in the time to work at it, you will get better, find those
bugs, and then you will be good at that, right?
And on and on and on and on.
Not right.
So I feel like if you had to boil it down,
Unless you know, like I said, maybe there's some genetic component to
it and you can just be born with a brain.
That's never going to be good at programming, okay?
If that's the case, whatever there's nothing we can do, right?
We know that's true for some physical things.
Like I said, I don't think I'm ever going to win, you know, the
Olympic long-distance running thing it's never gonna happen, right?
So maybe there is, I don't know, but assuming that, there isn't then
you might boil down.
All of what I just said.
Even to one very simple thing which is are you willing to work at
being a good programmer?
And if you are and you really will, you won't just go read Facebook
all day, or whatever it is right.
Instead of actually programming, if you are actually willing to work
at it, unplug your ethernet cable.
So, you can no longer contact the internet and program for 4 hours a
day.
If you are willing to do that and concentrate on it, I really think
that most people who have any affinity for programming at all, can get
to the point where they are reasonable, that it and imposter syndrome
simply wouldn't be warranted.
I think what actually happens more often than not is.
If people are bad at program, it's because they aren't willing to take
the time to do those things.
They would rather go read Facebook, or do whatever else it is answer
emails or go whatever.
Getting a flame war on a forum and then just say that they're not
better programming or feel, you know, let the Imposter syndrome take
its toll on them.
But in reality, I don't know that it was because of something inherent
in them that made them a bad programmer.
I think it's quite possible that the only thing making them a bad
programmer whether inherent or not, is the unwillingness to actually
do that work, right?
So that's my relatively complete answer on imposter syndrome and just
in general how to approach getting to be a better programmer.
And again I would just re-emphasize the fact that
You know, a lot of the people that a lot of the people that you see
who, maybe you think are good.
Programmers.
Keep in mind that they may also not have been great programmers, when
they first started, right?
So in a lot of situations, there's people who are pretty fast out of
the gate at something, but, you know, maybe they're curved kind of
looks, you know, like this sort of thing.
There are other people whose curves look more like that, right?
So just because you may not be good at something, right away.
And this is usually the case with me, by the way, I don't tend to be
good at things like right away.
Necessarily in programming, it typically takes me a long ramp up time
but once I've had that ramp up time then I tend to get very efficient
at the leader or whatever.
Right.
And so if you're a type of person like that, don't be discouraged when
you're first starting out.
If the people around you in school or whatever are better than you at
this that
It mean they're always going to be right.
And typically if you stick with it and like I said, you're very
serious about getting better.
I feel like you should let, give yourself that time and give your hand
and try to challenge yourself, to see whether you really are bad at
this, or whether it's just
Question of you just need more experience because you have more of a
curve that looks more like that, right?
And one more thing I'll say about that is that I often find that the
people who, you know, take the longest to get something sometimes,
maybe the ones who understand it the best at the end.
So sometimes it takes a lot longer to really understand something at a
deep level, it may appear that this person isn't really as Snappy as
their peers but later they end up doing things their peers couldn't
do.
And the reason for that is their learning process is deeper.
It takes longer, but it's more complete, right?
And more facile at the end.
And so again, don't assume just because you've taken a few sample
points relative to some other people doing the same things.
You're doing.
Don't assume that that that, you know what, the real curves look.
Like you may not be at the point where you can really make that
assessment yet, right?
So I would say that that is a really sort of broad answer to the
Imposter syndrome question and I don't know that I have any specific
opinions about it Beyond, you know, specific opinions about The
Imposter syndrome part of it as a separate.
Kind of Peace again because I I didn't grow up with it.
I didn't.
Grow up with.
I don't mean I didn't grow up thinking that way.
I mean I didn't grow up with that as a term.
So the part of my history that this would have really been more
related to is so far back in my head now that I can't remember if
these were things that I thought or not, you know, like, I can't
remember if I ever had something that would have been imposter
syndrome back at that time because it's you know, you know, I would
have been so young.
Young right.
So that part, I really couldn't speak to, but the rest of it, I think
hopefully, I've kind of laid out what I think in terms of the like.
Am I good programmer or not question that you may be asking yourself
and how do I, you know, maybe assess that a little bit more
realistically?
I think that's the only sensible approach to something like, imposter
syndrome because I just, I don't think that your emotional reaction to
a question like that.
Is going to ever really be unbiased enough to go with, right?
I feel like there's probably no question that there's plenty of people
out there who feel no impostor syndrome at all who are actually awful
at what they do, right.
And I'm equally sure that there's plenty of people out there who feel
a lot of imposter syndrome themselves, but are actually very good at
what they do, right?
So,
I don't think you can take those feelings at face value.
And I do think that it's important.
If it's something you care about to take it more seriously, and and
try to do some objective, some well, unless there's anyone can ever be
more objective exercises to really work through that and figure out,
whether you can take some more realistic measurements of this and
figure out whether you have what it takes to be a good programmer or
not.
And
I think that if nothing else going through that process will itself
make you a better programmer.
Even if for some reason psychologically, you're never really able to
convince yourself to get out of the Imposter syndrome mindset, you
know.
It certainly can't hurt to do exercises like that and if nothing else
it proves to you, that you can ship stuff and can do stuff that is,
you know, that is at least done, right?
Because that yeah at the end.
Of the day just getting code.
That's done and works.
Puts you in a category of programmers.
That's a pretty good already right because there's plenty of people
who just get nothing done, most of the time and you're already ahead
of them, right?
So yeah, I think that's mostly what I would say.
I don't know at this point, it's probably at this at this point in the
Stream.
I guess what I would say is, we're so far in we only have 20 minutes
left.
I would say maybe we'll just switch this to a chat and if I could, I
guess I'll maybe take questions and answers on this topic if people
have them.
If anything that I said, wasn't reasonable or you would disagree with
it.
You could put that in the chat now too, so I could maybe address it
and I guess I would also say if anyone has any follow-up questions to
that, where it's like, if there were parts of that, if there were
parts of that answer, that didn't go into enough detail in a section
that you cared about I would be happy to address those as well.
So, if you want to go ahead and go to the chat stream, just put a q:
in front of it.
I will address any questions about the Imposter.
Something that people might have.
In summary again, I would just say important things are one get to a
place where you know what matters to you and what doesn't right
because don't don't spend your life thinking.
You have to be a good programmer or a good, anything else if that's
not what actually matters to you, right?
I mean so figure out the matters what matters to you and what doesn't
then figure out if it does matter to you and you don't feel confident
in it, figure out what objective steps you could take that could start
to
Help you see for real, whether you are or not, rather than a
subjective feeling that is probably wrong or at the very least
inconclusive.
And then as a result of that go, what have I?
Learn from this.
Does it tell me things that I could work on to improve?
Because maybe it's not that.
I'm a bad programmer, maybe it's that.
I just have specific flaws that if I address those flaws.
I would be a good programmer, right?
And that's just a question of practice and experience that you can
overcome.
And so, it's, I think it's very important.
Like I said to really kind of work through that and don't let your
subjective impression of how good you have a programmer.
You are be the thing that holds you back.
Back because it is probably not so well.
Founded.
So, let's see whether or not there were any questions.
To do do.
This drunk Dane, how to battle the urge to have 100 different, small
projects around and stay focused on a single project.
That is an excellent question.
So, I guess what I would say about that is it is a constant struggle.
So I can speak from personal experience and say that, you know, if
you're anything like me, you always want to fix everything, right?
You're always like this seems broken.
I could fix it, right?
But in reality you don't have time, right?
You may not think that but you don't write even at this point.
Like I said, programming, for 30 years, I am still always doing
stupid.
Stuff like going this thing's broken, I'm gonna go fix it.
Not realizing that, you know, that is not feasible in my schedule or
whatever it is, right?
So I would say if you can, and
If you're lucky, you'll be better than me at this.
So this is in no way speaking of imposter syndrome, this is in no way
me trying to say, eventually you'll get to be able to do this well
because I can't, and I don't know, very many people who can so, you
know, I'm more saying aspirational fantasy, right?
Because you do kind of get a little better at over time but, you know,
aspirational fantasy
Is as much as you can think of any particular programming problem as
taking an unbounded amount of time, and it sounds a little bit weird,
but an unbounded amount of time.
Meaning.
Whatever the program is you were going to write.
I'm fairly certain you could spend the rest of your life writing that
program.
The.
I say that is because okay, you write the program.
How efficient is the program?
Could it be more efficient?
Could it be more portable?
Probably, it could.
Probably it could write, is it written as concisely as possible?
Probably not is the language.
It's written in, not capable of expressing how concise it should be
possibly.
Maybe you need to rewrite the language to do that.
Right is the architecture is the is the, you know, is the machine, the
operating system letting it be as efficient as possible.
Well, maybe not, maybe you need to rewrite that right, Bubba, right.
In order to completely solve any programming problem, you will spend
the rest of your life and possibly not solve it, right?
So the first thing to understand is there is no such thing as like,
figuring out how long it takes to Mesa, make a piece of code.
There's only a question of how long it will take you to make a certain
piece of code at a certain level of quality, right?
So what that means very directly with no, it's I feel like this is an
objective statement at this point.
If you accept that premise, that may be subjective, maybe not.
But if you have to accept that premise, the next thing is objective
and that is everything you decide to do.
Makes whatever other things you were doing worse.
.
because however much time you spend on whatever the next that the
other project or adding to your list is that is how much worse the
project you were working on will get
And that's at a minimum because it doesn't count any task switching
overhead, right?
So even if we assume zero, task-switching overhead, if you have a
project a and you're like oh well I could just do Project B, you have
now subtracted, the quality that amount of quality from your other
project
And that's just the truth.
It's a zero-sum game, right?
It's like, every time you choose to take on a new project, you are
making another project worse.
And I of all people have it at tremendously difficult, time dealing
with this.
Because I always want to know, I'm sorry, I always want to go do
something.
That's, like, I could fix this, right?
And when you look at something, it even gets worse, as you get better
at programming.
Because chances, are you look at something, you know, you could do a
better job.
You know, you could and you're not even wrong, like you may be totally
right, that you could do a different, a better job.
The problem is however, long.
It's going to take you to do that better job.
However, long.
It's gonna take you to exceed that quality bar is now quality that's
coming out of your other project, right?
And so, you really, really do have to understand that trade-off and I
think that if you can actually internalize that, it is something that
helps you make those decisions.
Those hard decisions.
I want to
Do X.
I just saw this thing and I want to go do that right now, right?
You have to
Wait, that will make my whatever thing out game I'm working on now
that much worse, right?
So, the first thing I'd say is try to internalize that.
The second thing I would try to say is if you are starting to lose
interest in a project finish the project, make it be a goal that you
always finish the project, right?
Even if it's bad, just finish it.
Because a lot of times it's before starting the new one because a lot
of times it's simply it's enough to get you over the infatuation.
You have with whatever the new product is.
You were going to start to force yourself to finish the old one,
because a lot of times what happens is, you'll get to a point in a
project where there's
Hard work to be done and it's just more fun to go.
Try.
Some other thing don't do that, right?
Make yourself finish the thing that you were working on.
So that you can, you know, at least call it done and chance already
come back to that, you may forget about how exciting that other thing
was for a while because maybe it really isn't that exciting after all.
And when you go start that project you would hit the exact same point
in that project at some point, right?
So I would say try to think about those things, more helicity if you
can and it might help.
I don't know for a fact that there isn't some value in having more
than one project though and the reason for that is that there may be a
sweet spot that's not one The Sweet Spot maybe say to.
And the reason for that is that it may be possible to just be too
burned out on one project and you kind of need one to ping-pong back
and forth between and so I don't want to say that.
I know that there's an answer there because I don't know that we know
for sure.
I do think, for example, I believe you know, you'd have to ask John
but I believe Jonathan.
Blow would probably say that it helps to have two projects because
sometimes you just need to be able to switch back and forth between
them in order to keep yourself motivated.
If one of them is very big, right?
Like if the witness is your main project, you may need jii as a side
project because without it you just you can't do seven years of work.
Thing without switching back and forth little bit on it, right?
So it may be that.
At some point you will find your optimal productivity is to have two
things.
Not one right?
It's probably not to have ten though but what I would say about that
is again, can you take an objective approach to it?
Can you look and see?
Am I making better progress when I have two things when I enter leave?
Or if I just stick with one try to actually measure the progress to
some degree and make an informed decision.
Ian about it, don't just assume that adding more products is better
because it feels better to do or whatever right try to actually make
that decision.
And once you know, that should be a good argument for you as to what
to do, if you know your faster when you're always focusing on one
project stopped taking on other projects right, that's the best thing
for you.
That's the best thing for shipping.
Quality piece of software and being proud of it.
At the end of the day, is doing it that way, right?
Allen asks, this is slightly related to one thing.
You said I have been getting the feeling that programmers in general
are bad at taking objective measurements of things.
Like how good am I with maybe the exception of how long a chunk of
code takes?
Would you agree that the assessment?
Would you agree with that assessment and do you think we suffer a lot
because of it?
I do.
100% agree with that assessment.
And I do also 100% agree that we suffer a lot because of it.
I would say that the number of things that I have found through when
I've been programming, in terms of like, successes that I can say,
like, where I've been like oh, you know, this some things went really
well here.
Many, many times, the reason the things that led to those successes
are exactly that thing you're talking about of figuring out, a way to
take a more objective approach to something.
It was just dogmatic before, right?
You know, even like the build-up, bat way that we build things on,
handmade hero is a very good example of just being objective about
things, right?
It's like, what is the simplest thing?
We can do here, that produces the fastest turnaround, for building
this game, that creates the least problems when you actually look at
it objectively like that.
You find that A build-up at file is so much better than every make
system that anyone's ever made like in the history of time, right?
Right?
So the question is, well why you know what?
How do we end up in a situation where we aren't?
We're all doing this already and it's just because well there's we
don't constantly measure those things, like nobody is measuring those
things.
So sure, way back when there is probably some reason to have a make
because compiling took longer and, you know, Bubba blonde, there was
reasons to track these things maybe, and we had two separate things
for various reasons, they didn't, you couldn't concatenate all the
files together and compile them, because there was enough memory on
the machine even
To do this, right?
And so you have to remember that there may be very sane objective
reasons for things way back in the past.
But what you're doing now is a product of that long chain of
reasoning.
That was right at the time, but not be right now.
And so I absolutely do think the more you can force yourself to go, is
there a metric here?
I can look at, can I look at build times?
Can I look at number of amount of hours spent on the build system that
I'm actually spending maintaining the build system.
Can I look at?
You know, how maintainable this thing was for me?
Can I look at metrics like this that even if they're not pure
objective or at least more objective than
I read on.
Some internet message board that cmake is better than some than good
new make.
So I'm using it or whatever or ninja is important to making builds
better and so I did it.
If you can find some more ways to a objective evaluate things, those
things are going to lead you often times too much better results
because often in many stories of programming, no one has actually done
that.
Active measurement, right?
We're very good as programmers.
For some reason, we're very good at objectively measuring, what the
hardware does.
So, optimizing things has been a discipline that many people have been
very good at what, we're not so good at is objectively measuring us.
And so, programming practices inherently.
We are not very good at optimizing and it's important to get better
because the better that, you know, getting better at those pays
dividends everywhere, right?
It means better code.
In less time with less people at less cost, which is always kind of a
good thing.
Somewhat related, a final update on the TA.
We talked about his talk on raytracer efficiency.
When he got to the GPU side of things, basically broke down into use
op, 2x GPU, programming is hard, so I don't even know to him.
Yes.
Oh, so that's a
That was someone who had talked to me about, they had a TA who had
told them that their raytracer would be better if it had virtual
functions in it.
No, other explanation.
Just it would have better if it was a fun time.
Like I couldn't tell you any rate Racers that got better because of
virtual functions, they can only really make a ray Tracer worse.
I think most of the time but you know, whatever.
And so yeah, I mean this kind of gets back to the Imposter syndrome
thing like you can find plenty.
Your people who, you know, might be a professor at a university who
actually has no idea how to program effectively at, all right.
So maybe, you know, wrapping the whole discussion in just one big
thing that says, no matter how bad you are at programming, there
probably is a prominent person who's actually just as bad.
So maybe don't again, don't write yourself off prematurely because
there are a lot of really bad programmers out there, right?
It's, it's, it is not a field.
Is marked by Excellence, like, so many fields.
The average case is really bad and so, you know,
Don't don't, don't be harder on yourself.
Then you would be on some prominent people about their right.
Like
Burger love.
Let's say you are someone who is really drawn to starting and growing
your own projects in a tough.
Mister you like this while.
Some people are getting experience at big studios.
You're fighting through the details of smaller projects.
Do you think in the long run?
It could really hurt you because of how you look on paper.
I guess, I don't know.
I would say that.
I don't think it would really hurt you.
If you've done a good job and did actually learn a lot from those
projects, I think it's pretty clear most of the time when you've
gotten good enough at programming to be useful to it, to a game
studio.
So, I don't know that, that would really be the case.
However, I would agree that, maybe, if you don't get that good at it,
let's say you weren't going to get that good.
In either case, then you do have the problem of.
Well, if I had gone to a bigger company and you know,
I didn't really get very good necessarily.
But now I've got a bit of a resume behind me, that may make it easier
for you to get better jobs, right?
That's just a potential nature of our way that our systems work in
terms of hiring and how we assign value to individuals that they're
not purely based on the individuals, aptitude right?
And so yeah, I couldn't say for sure, I couldn't say for sure.
I would also say that I wouldn't discount working at a big company in
terms of a learning experience separate from that because working with
other good programmers is a very important part of becoming a good
programmer I think.
And so working at a company where there aren't any good programmers at
all.
Maybe that's not so useful.
But most companies might have at least one or two people who
Going to be better than you when you're just starting out certainly
and being able to work with them.
A little bit, is going to be a valuable experience for you.
And so what I would say is, you know,
It's not as cut and dry as maybe your question sort of purports it to
be.
Because at some level I do think that being a part of a team.
Unless you really are just always the best person in the room or
something.
Which again, when you're just starting out, is it that realistic
probably not.
I mean, maybe you're a prodigy or something but then so sure.
But you know, I think the average case won't be true.
There are people you can learn from
And that's valuable in and of itself.
So I would say there's more to that question potentially, if that
makes sense.
We're largest restoration currently, is that large sections of my code
currently?
Get rejected or Rewritten in review.
Is there anything I can do proactively to help myself, right?
More efficient code IE teach myself how to approach some problems
better.
A lot of the patterns I used regularly are turning out to be
suboptimal.
well, I guess that's a tough one for me to answer because I don't know
I had since I can't see what an example of code is that you've
submitted that then gets rejected or something and it's like, you
know,
I can't speak to anything specifically about that.
But what I would say is it sounds like let's let's assume that the
people rejecting and rewriting the code or reviewing the code, who are
we write it in reviewer.
Whatever our are actually good.
So let's assume that they're doing a good job.
Well, then you should have a very clear path towards Improvement,
right?
You should study those changes.
So what you do is say, here is the code I submitted and I should I can
write down.
Let me write, let me write down.
Next to it.
My thought process that went into why I wrote the code this way do
that before you submit it when you submit it now you have the changes
that they made and the parts that they rewrote now ask yourself what
was it in my thought process that did not allow me to get to this
solution that I think is better.
If you don't think the solution is better, maybe it's not.
So you have to first verify that the people who are rewriting, the
code are better than you and are doing a better job, right?
But assuming that they are
That should give you exactly the feedback loop.
You need, you should be able to see, here's what they did.
Where was the error in my thought process?
What wasn't I considering, and you should start to see some patterns
emerge there about what you're not considering, maybe it's that you
don't have a strong enough background in data, structures and
algorithms.
So, you're just not aware of some of the techniques you could use,
maybe you're not thinking about the hardware enough, so you're making
decisions based on something that isn't really related to how the
machines going to use the code and so you're making bad decisions
because of the cash or
Something else that was not in your model, right?
Figure out where your mental process went wrong and that will give you
the path to success, that will show you what do I need to start
studying and practicing in order to stop having these people get code?
That's better than the code that I'm writing.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
Just drunk tame by to it.
By the way, I thought the my rocket I was didn't have internet.
You are correct.
It did not and we just got it installed.
That is why the handmade hero machine moved over here, finally,
because we were required by a contract to have a static IP address.
So we had to get one.
We still did not plug any of the Molly rocket machines into the
internet, so it is just the handmade hero machine that is on it.
And then, we will plug in the, you know, one machine that's used for
that contract will plug-in eventually, but that is, you know, the
limits of what we will be doing there, if that makes sense.
So there won't be any actual
We still don't plug any of the actual development stations into the
internet.
And since I don't really like having the internet on at work, that is
the way it would remain.
Certainly if someone you know in particular individually wanted it,
they're welcome to it but I would not
I don't have it on my machine or won't have it on my machine.
Let's see.
Empire Tycoon.
Hey, Casey, I'm new to programming.
Have been studying information system for two years.
My problem is I can't start projects at all.
I always get stuck and by the end of the day, I get nothing done, all
that I wanted was to start something to improve my skills.
Would fall asleep for a while?
What should I do?
so, my recommendation there,
I guess what I'd say is, can you be more specific about what you mean
by?
I get stuck by the end of the day, I get nothing done.
What is can you say more specifically?
What does get stuck mean, right?
Like Define get stuck does get stuck mean.
You don't know how to do something in the code that you needed to do.
Like I wanted to, you know, print out.
Value.
But I didn't know how to print it out and I got stuck or is it more
like I just don't know what to do next.
Like I'm not sure whether I should be printing out a value at all like
I didn't it wasn't like I knew what to do and didn't know how to do
it.
It's that I just don't even know what I should really be doing.
I'm just kind of staring at a blank editor going.
I don't know.
So what does get stuck mean in this particular sense?
I guess while I wait for that one, I'll look at the other Q here.
What is the thought process behind?
Not having the internet, is it just for staying on task?
Avoiding distraction or for some other reason, how do you look up
documentation and things of that nature?
It's just for staying on task.
I find that if the internet's there you know you get I don't like
being distracted and I find that, you know, rather than try to teach
myself self discipline about that sort of thing.
I find that the easiest way is to just
Have it because there is no need for the internet when you're
programming.
It doesn't really help you in any way in my opinion.
So,
I just find that.
All it does is create distractions.
That's not to say that.
I don't like reading things on the internet that are related to
programming or, like, to look things up.
It's just those things can be done offline or not offline after
programming.
So, what I'll do typically it's like
Okay, you know, I'm working on this thing that's involves like
multi-threaded, you know, file handling, you know, file handling on
win32.
The night before that, I'll just read a bunch of stuff on it and save
off articles and whatever I want on to a drive, right?
And I bring that with me to work and then when I'm working I have all
my research there, right?
And that allows me to compare compartmentalize the two things which I
think is very important because if you're always in a research mode,
if you're always like I'm going to look up on the internet.
I feel like what you end up doing is you just end up reading on the
internet way more than you actually needed to read to solve the
I'm right, you're just kind of like spending time reading cuz it's
always easier to read than to do work right.
So I try to compartmentalize things, right?
If I let you know and then anything I during the day where i'm like I,
you know, during the day I'm like I got a I got something here that I
didn't anticipate and I need more information about it.
I just write that down and then I go on to something else and then
I'll come back to it the next day, because in the interesting evening,
I can look it up.
If I really am at a place where I 100% need the internet right now to
do something, which happens very rarely.
But, once in a while it happens, then I always just have like, before
we had internet at the office.
Like, now I would just take a laptop over plug-in.
Go look up.
The one thing and go back.
If I really need it to write, and I like having that requirement
there.
So, it's clear that I'm doing that and I have to actually make a
mental switch to do it.
I would prefer it be more than that.
But what can I say, we had to do it for the contract before that there
was internet in the lobby where we are in the building we're in.
So I would just go down there and look it up and then come back,
right?
And I like having that really dramatic I have to completely switch
gears so that I know I have to make a mental decision.
This yes, this is important enough to waste this time to go get it.
Okay, I'll do it and most of the time I find, I just don't need that
because most of programming is not looking things.
Up.
Like, if I'm looking things up, it means I don't really understand
what I'm doing.
And in my mind, that's better a better thing to be doing during study
time.
So like I said, you know, let's say, I want to do, you know, some work
with compression or something like this, right?
You know where I'm just like, okay, I don't know very much about
compression and I need to write some compression stuff, right?
Well, you know, that's like a research thing and I need to spend
several nights like, reading about this thing.
Internalizing it getting some papers, like, right.
And that's, I'm going to build up this like, directory somewhere on my
machine.
It's like all of my compression research and then I'm going to go
start writing some code.
I'm not going to just start writing the code and try to like cut and
Hey.
Some stuff from stack, Overflow or whatever, right?
So the idea that I need the Internet like interleaved with typing in
my editor, it just doesn't square with my experience of how I write
code.
That doesn't mean that other people, maybe don't have different ways
of doing it, but it's definitely the case for me, that like, that is
not how I write code.
I have to like either are either.
I'm trying to understand something in which case, yes, the internet,
very important.
I got to have papers.
I want download the papers I want to scroll through everything, read
people's blogs, about it, whatever.
I want to consolidate all that and then digest it and then start
programming.
I don't want to like be ping-ponging back and forth between those
that's not how I like to do it.
Huh.
Show?
Do you think web programmers simply don't aspire to be better?
Programmers.
Don't know what good programming is or simply don't care.
What should we do to entertain their minds from this evil?
All right.
Well, first of all, I would say
I think that there's a bit of a systemic problem there.
Certainly, I don't think I don't think anyone doesn't aspire to be a
good programmer, right?
I think it's just a question of understanding what that means.
And one of the things is that game programmers have in some sense, a
luxury that that web programmers nowadays do not have, which is that
game?
Programmers are oftentimes writing fairly close to the code?
That's actually
Executed on the machine, right?
They are writing in x64 Assembly Language if they want to their
writing and see that gets compiled to that in a way that they
understand.
You know, sometimes they're writing GPU Shader code that they can see
how to a certain extent, it's going to be executed.
Well, there's tons of stuff in between there and what actually
happens, don't get me wrong, but it's you have a very close
relationship to what's actually happening computer.
So you know what's possible.
And what's not to a certain degree, people that came up to the web
programming world have never had that luxury, really, right.
I mean by the nature of the best they can possibly do is things are
going to run on a browser and the browser is so much big of a, you
know, sort of jump above all of
At that it's unclear that most web programmers.
If they didn't come from, a different discipline ever have the
opportunity to know really what the best possible version of their
program would be because their first of all may never have had the
experience of writing the low-level stuff to know, but also even if
they did well what are they going to do about it right?
So you know, it definitely, I think being
Ying.
So,
Are removed from being able to actually control the hardware and not
having any any real prospects for ever doing.
So I think definitely creates a sort of a culture that is not about
performance and is not about trying to figure out what would be the
optimal thing to do there.
So I think in some sense you might say, the real fault, may not even
really be with the programmers there.
It's in the platform, right?
The problem was the platform.
If this platform had been about making something that you could be,
right, very portable things that were fairly native in some way, and
that was the standard.
I think maybe you wouldn't, you would see people kind of go down that
route.
So there's that and then on the other side, I would say almost the
exact same logic applies.
If you have to spin up an AWS amorphous,
Esther, that's a virtual machine kind of a thing that you're not
really sure.
Even if it's a real machine or part of an existing machine, that's
doing some stuff in a network, that's I don't know where it is and I
don't really know how long it takes packets to get there and blah blah
blah.
If you're dealing with all of this, you know kind of uncertainty it's
very hard to develop a culture of really caring about how fast the
response time is to a user thing, right?
Or whatever because you don't even know you have
I've no idea how long it will even take your virtual cluster to even
be up, or whether it's up or how that even happens, you may have no
idea how their load balancer doing anything, right?
So you're so far for moved from it that I think that again on either
side but the front end and the back end, the culture has been removed
so far at this point that an individual program are coming from, it
could probably hardly be blamed for not knowing or even caring about
these things because they're in no position to ever have learned or
ever affect right?
These things that people who program games at a low level would take
for granted.
And just be like, of course, you have to know these things.
And of course, you can assure 60 frames a second and blah, blah blah,
right?
That said, do I think there's a fair bit of shared delusion, they're
certainly and the reason that I say that is because oftentimes I have
asked web programmers.
I'm like, why is this thing?
So slow and they're like, well, you know, the round trip of packets is
like 200 milliseconds or something.
So, you know, it doesn't really matter.
You know, if I take an extra 100 milliseconds to do something that
could have taken, one millisecond, doesn't matter.
And, you know, I've had the experience actually, very recently of
having some say, I mean I was like, actually,
We if I ping like Google server for example from my machine it's a 1
ms, ping time.
So I'm like actually if you took less than 15 milliseconds to process
whatever I was doing.
This would be a 60 frames per second app, right?
And this was like a real Revelation to this person when I said it, you
can see that their brain kind of went like, whoa, wait a minute,
right?
And I think that, so yet at the same time, even though the it's super
crafty
I think there also is sort of a shared delusion that's been brought
into this point.
That somehow they believe that there is no way to make these things
fast when actually the network is no longer a problem like to a large
number of people's homes.
You could actually deliver 60 frames a second web apps that were still
running off of a server client model.
And the reason that you're not is because
Nobody in the chain cared about doing that but the could have its it
ain't the link layer anymore like it just isn't right.
And so I think one thing that would be nice to your quite point of
like, what can be done?
Is it would be nice at some point to start getting out there and
saying, hey, look web apps actually can run at 60 frames a second,
even the Ping, because a lot of places, there's one millisecond ping
times, right?
And sure there will be people who have 200 millisecond ping times but
that's okay, that's no excuse.
Having all the people who don't have a bad experience.
Internalizing that might be a good first step in going.
What do we need to do?
To all the rest of this stuff to get it to the point where it's
actually realizing that goal?
Empire Tycoon.
Okay, so I'm at.
This is going to be the, the last question.
I'll take since the Q&A is technically over because this is the
follow-up to the one where I asked for more clarification.
So on the person who said they were getting stuck and I asked, what
does that mean?
Here is the explanation.
For example, one day, I decide to write a small game in an engine but
instead of doing that, I spent the whole day reading through the
engine documentation and video tutorials by the end of the day, I got
nothing.
Accomplished and got burned out on it.
Okay, so two possible reasons for this and I will give them to you,
right?
One.
Is that you aren't good at programming, right?
Always the possibility, right?
Like I said, we have no idea, right?
It's possibility.
One
But we have no idea if that's true yet.
So I'd say, put that one aside.
Possibility to is you are picking things that are too big a scope for
what you should be working on right now.
And typically you know with what you just said, I would say that that
is almost always the problem.
So
A game engine or a game either or are two very big and difficult
problems.
Right.
Nobody who isn't very competent at programming, and has had a lot of
experience should really be doing either of those two things.
Now, if you are going to go download, you know, Unity or something,
and build a game in that and your game doesn't have very much game
code to it.
You may be able to just muddle through, right?
It's entirely possible.
But if you are trying to do something that has any code complexity
whatsoever to it, often times, you'll get exactly the situation that
you're just saying.
You're like, I don't know, I read all the documentation and it was
like I don't understand at all and there's too much and I got worried
about these things, they were talking about, don't do this and do do
that.
And I don't know how to connect these.
Two things out Bubba bomber, right?
It is almost always the case that if you're having that kind of
experience, you just need to step back and start with smaller things,
right?
Because your brain may not be ready yet to integrate all of that
information about the existing engine and understand how you would
proceed, right?
So again, I would say, can you pick a very small much more achievable
task and accomplish it, an example.
B.
You want to write a game in a game engine?
That's the end goal, right?
You don't want to write the engine.
You just want to write a game in that engine.
It sounded like what you're talking about.
You try doing that whole hog and you just you got it was too diffused
and it just didn't happen, right?
So, start with something much smaller.
Today's goal is figure out how to render a sphere in this engine
create a sphere and render the sphere.
That is all the goal for today is at the end of the day.
I download Unity or whatever it is you were using.
I download Unity.
I read as only as much of a tutorial as is necessary to create one
sphere and produce the execute Unity executable, that shows the
sphere.
This fear does not have to be shaded, it does not have to move, it
does not have to do anything other than be a sphere on the screen.
Okay.
D to make the sphere go from one place to another.
Just move like that right D3, make the sphere.
Have a material like a color.
D4.
Make the sphere have a light.
Those things may sound silly.
When you think of them.
But that is how you actually get better at these problems.
You add and add and add, and add and add from small achievable goals.
Because if you try to take something that's too big for, what your
mind currently is facile with working with that is where you get that
diffusion in that burnout, where you just like, I don't know what to
do.
I'm sitting here looking at this thing, but I don't know what to do,
right?
And there's too much stuff coming in.
I'm too confused.
I'm worried about this and worry about that.
You sit down one day.
Like I'm going to make a game in this game engine and somehow by the
end of the day, you're what you're worrying about is how you will
convince YouTube streamers to stream the game, so that it people will
know about it and play it because otherwise it won't be successful,
right?
Somehow you've gotten your mind there and you don't even have like a
project open and unity yet or something, right?
So you can't, you you have to disengage that part of your brain that's
thinking about the long-term picture, you need to turn that off
because what you're doing right now is you're learning, you're not
executing your learning and learning is about picking small concrete
goals that you can do in a finite amount of time.
And know that you have finished make a game in an engine is completely
undefined.
Do you mean Assassin's Creed 4 metal of the Ancients or do you mean
Tetris, right?
Do you mean high quality Graphics or single little pixel art?
Right?
Is there music in this game?
Are there images in this?
Like, who knows?
Right.
That is not a learning experience.
A learning experience is concrete.
I am going to make asteroids it will look exactly.
Like the original asteroids in order to make the original asteroids.
I know that.
The first thing I will need to do is to be able to display an
asteroid.
Okay.
Project for day one is, how do I display a square on the screen
project for day two?
How do I make that square?
Show the shape of an asteroid.
Right party for day three, move the asteroid.
But if your day for two, asteroids products for day, 5 and asteroids,
right?
That is how it works.
And nobody, you know, just sat down day one without ever having done
anything before and made a great game, whether they downloaded an
engine or not, right?
And all of that goes, double triple quadruple times 10, whatever.
If you're making the engine yourself, because we're making the engine
yourself.
You're now in a whole other class of technical competence that takes a
lifetime to master.
And so by the time you're going to think about making a game engine
entirely by yourself.
you need to have done a lot of work, and
I know that that is a really important thing to you to want to do,
right?
So hopefully that answers the question, if that makes sense.
And as strange as that might seem
I would also like to point out, as if that seems overly pedantic even
or not overly pedantic, but overly, like educational, even to you, I
would even point out.
The fact that look at what we do on handmade hero, when I go to make a
change in the code base, notice I do the same thing, right?
How many times have you heard me?
Say, I'm taking this one step at a time and I will take a change.
And this isn't make a game.
This is I'm just making one change to the code base.
I'll say here's the steps.
I'm going to take to make it.
Why?
Because the more concrete and individualized and achievable, each step
is that you make at any level of development, the easier it is to stay
motivated.
Ensure that it works.
Do a good job, know that you completed and keep your project moving
forward, right?
And invariably anytime I ever get myself into a situation where I feel
like I'm not making progress, the solution always turns out to be and
I wish sometimes I even come at it to it way later than I really
should have after 30 years, right.
Is wait, you're spinning your wheels on this?
Break it into smaller problems.
What can you ship out of this, right?
You've got this big thing, the asset system and you've trying stuff
and it's not working.
It's not coming out.
What?
Okay, stop.
What are some things?
You know, this will have to do ship those first.
Okay?
Now, they're taking out of the problem and now you have more
visibility about what the rest of the solution has to look like,
right.
Grab
Nothing to hold onto and ship it to grab the next thing and ship it,
right?
And that is how you make progress on those kinds of
on those kinds of problems that are too big for you right now.
And by the way, kind of like I just tried to elude to too big for you.
Right now is something you will never outgrow, no matter how good you
get it programming.
There will always be a problem that's a little bit bigger than that.
And when you go to attack that problem, this skill will come in.
So handy learning to divide and conquer a problem.
Never goes out of style, right?
I
Do it every day still, it is part of my development process and more
often than not.
When I am done with a section of code, one thing I will think to
myself is that would have gone faster.
If I had divided it up more sooner, I'm almost never say boy.
I wish I had done those two parts together at the same time, right?
Like that.
Not a thing that happens in my world, right?
And there are some techniques that you have to learn to employ
architectural, e, to make sure that things fit together.
That's the compression oriented program stuff.
We talked about in the also, the writing usage code, first kinds of
stuff there are techniques that make things fit together better.
Those come with time and you do have to learn those when you want to
start making like really good architecture stuff like that, but even
before, you know, those you will still be more successful shipping
things if you break them.
Two pieces.
It's just the pieces won't fit together as well as they should right.
But you will still be more successful at getting stuff done.
Even with that.
Oops.
I like wrote the renderer and it doesn't quite work, right?
Because I didn't think about this binding, oh well, but you'll get em
next time, right?
And then over time, you'll learn the techniques.
You need to try and minimize the degree to which you have that
problem, right?
So
All right.
Hopefully that is a pretty yeah, we're right at 6:30 so I'm going to
sign off.
That is a ridiculously long discussion of imposter syndrome and
related issues.
Hopefully it's useful to somebody if I was to have imposter syndrome
right now I would say something like I don't know if this dream will
be useful in anybody.
Maybe I'm just talking randomly and none of this information is any
good, but if we were trying to be more positive about me, like I'm
I'm sure it'll help someone somewhere.
Okay, that's about it.
Thank you for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
I guess this wasn't really a.
Handmade hero was technically a handmade chat so we will branded as
such I guess on.
When I upload the video I will be back here tomorrow at 8 p.m.
it's an eight pm stream tomorrow.
Hope to see you guys here for that until then everyone have fun
programming and I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.