As I had explained to you all my great monetization ideas, hopefully
this won't be too bad, with the drop frames.
If not, you can catch it on the YouTube, I guess.
All right, ladies and gentlemen, welcome to handmade here of the show
where we code an entire game live on Twitch.
No libraries, no engine, just us and code, and awesomeness, honestly,
you know, I'm feeling pretty good about it, where it's at these days
because we've been working on our engine
Peck stuff and we just I feel like had a really big breakthrough
yesterday where we were like ah here is a good way.
We can make a lot of the code nice and simplified and still do all the
things that we want.
And it was pretty exciting, but we only did half of the sort of
restructuring work yesterday.
I want to go do the other half now and get right back into it.
So I'm not even going to spend any time on the Preamble.
I'm just going to say, if you have pre-ordered, the game on handmade
hero dot-org and made hero dot-org.
If you preorder the game using a little Peter button, you should have
gotten any Link in your email and that link allows you to download the
source code to the game every night.
If you download it, you should have gotten a zip file and inside that
zip file.
There's lots of little Zips day 363 since we're on day, 60 for
unzipped a 63 zip file.
That is the one that I am basically on right now.
And so you'll be exactly where I am if you want to follow along at
home.
So that's what you want to do if you're into that so
Let's take a look here at the situation as it stands.
We got a bunch of stuff to do, so let's do it.
So basically, I made the change yesterday where I decided we were
going to break things down into simulation regions.
There are sort of these things, you can create any time that
Encompass, some area of the game world, and then you can simulate it
and then you can write it back.
So it basically like lost it up into a simulated will form.
Does the simulation and chunks of back out again, right?
Now I thought of something yesterday after we'd started as well, but
we didn't actually quite get to it.
Yes, I was like I also feel like there's something we can do now that
will sort of make it easier for us to get to where we want to go.
Programming wise and that is since low entity and high entity aren't
really what we wanted to use.
Anyway, I'll explain this a little bit more detail if I open up the
same region file here, we've got the same entity and that's what we
were working on, right?
And then it had we were still referencing the low entities stuff
because while we're working on the similarity, we have to go back and
get this other data.
Now that's not actually the way I envisioned it working.
When we're actually done with the entity system, what I actually
wanted to do and I sort of alluded to this yesterday.
Was I wanted to make it so that the the storage version of The Entity
is like the most minimal compressed set of information that stores
what that entity needs to remember.
But then, the high entity.
Just has all.
Stuff blown out.
And so what I thought we could do
Before we get to the point where we've actually done that work to make
that sort of forward and backward, Tappan instead of constantly
referring to the two entities, what I was thinking would actually be
much better is we just essentially have one entity type and we just
move it between the two.
We just block copy it basically, right?
So what I was thinking is we just say, okay, basically we've got you
know, the extra stuff that's on the Sim entity will just stick the low
entity just flat-out in here, right?
Like that, like it's just there, right?
And furthermore we could even do something a little more aggressive.
Like we could actually just stick this guy in here.
We could actually make a Sim entity, you know, have all the same
members as this guy does and then just have the low entity like look
do it.
The other way around.
In fact, I think I like that better for now because like I said we
don't care at all about the storage space yet because this is not the
way we're going to do it at the very end, we just want something
that's easy for us to do prototyping, wise in that sense.
Um, so I think I might do it exactly the opposite.
Way basically go like this.
So everything's in the same entity and then what happens is, the low
entity is just a Sim entity storage, right?
This is the stored version of that, right?
If that makes sense.
And so, we'll actually have at some point.
We'll go ahead and start making the low entity be something actually
real.
But for now, it'll just be a thing that stores, everything that was in
the same entity to begin.
With.
Does that make sense that way it gets us out of the business of having
to deal with that dichotomy because we don't actually want that
dichotomy ever.
We just were just going to treat especially due to this new change.
We're always just going to treat the low entities as like a packed,
some kind of thing, where we crammed down the blown-out Simonetti
stuff.
Into a smaller space that we don't pay a huge memory footprint for
having things be giant or, you know, that sort of stuff.
All right.
So I think that's the way I want to do it.
And so, what that means is that I don't want to see low entity in here
at all, basically?
Right.
I don't want to see this at all.
So we're going to go through here just before we finish doing the
porting work, and I'm going to go ahead and get rid of that that
entire concept, right?
So basically let's see here.
So when we do the NCAA,
And the stored entity here.
When we grab that store identity, all we're really going to do on
that.
Yeah, so like change entity location, for example, all of that sort of
stuff will now no longer actually look directly at one of these guys
anymore.
Yeah, because changing the location was still working on those guys.
So what we do is we grab the stored entity out, right?
We'd basically make the stored entities Sim entity.
What did I actually call that?
They're the stored version, right.
So, this is called a SIM for now.
It's just going to be equal to
Entity, right?
So basically to block copy it into the store identity and then the
other thing we have to do is we have to update that low position,
right?
And that low position I guess is the one thing that we wouldn't want
in here, right?
Because that's something that only exists for the low entity, right?
Like so so basically we just have all of this stuff is legitimate
things that we had in here for our Sim entities.
Yeah.
But then this
This world position P.
Obviously, only exists for the low entity, that's not a thing that we
ever talked about in some space.
So there we go, that's fine.
And then this would still work I guess.
So we could still use the change any location thing and in fact I
guess all of this stuff pretty much still works exactly that way.
There really isn't actually a guess anything else that we would have
to change because the only places that we were talking about it in
here, where the place is where we decompress it essentially.
So when we go to do a density,
I guess all we would do is say now.
Yeah, instead of instead of
Here.
Hmm, instead of just copying the position in like we were doing here,
we would actually just copy the rest of it so we'd basically say
everything that's in our Sim region entity.
There we would go ahead and just overwrite basically all of this
except for the storage index although that we can even over at the
storage index because technically that's coming from the other guy as
well.
Right?
And normally, the way I would do this is I would make
I would pull out these members that work.
So the storage index only existence them, and in the same entity,
normally, I would pull these guys out so that these guys are in their
own struct that we talk about separately.
But since I know that eventually, this is not how it's going to
actually be stored.
I'm not going to bother doing that because I don't care about the fact
Hoops.
That were storing that additional you went in there?
Yeah.
So basically I'm just going to go ahead and copy it out wholesale just
He that Sim out entirely and later on, we'll do the compression there
and I feel like did we ever actually set?
I don't know.
If we ever actually set the storage index to the storage index has to
be set properly, but I don't think we ever did.
So actually add entity.
What add into T should be doing when we call it here, right?
Identity should be taking where it should store it back.
So that low entity index should actually be there and that was just a
mistake.
We hadn't finished porting yesterday so we probably didn't get to
everything that we should have been doing.
So let's go ahead and make sure that that's true.
So when we do that, ad entity will go ahead and pass the low entity
index here low entity, I'm not in a good typing alignment.
Things sweetie is off or something.
There, the feng shui is
People move this.
There we go.
Okay, much better.
So I'm going to pass that low into the index and that way, I can store
it in here.
So after we're up this guy, we will go ahead and put a storage index
in there like that.
And actually, what I could do to, let's move Loft that up.
Even one more, I guess, the reason we can't quite do that it's because
we overwrite everybody here.
Mmm.
Yeah.
That's that's unfortunate.
So I guess what a dignity would want to do too is want to take one of
these like so so that it could do this.
There we go.
And we'll have to think about, I guess.
I guess all of this will be sorted when we actually do the compression
decompression stuff, because then we won't be using kind of, a Cheesy
little romp romp over thing that we're doing there.
All right?
So any this ad entity,
After we go ahead and get the entity instead of clearing it now, we're
not going to actually do that.
Clear what we're going to do is do the decompression.
And so I'll say here to do this should really be a decompression.
Step not a copy but we don't have that part yet.
So we've got our entity, we have our source, I guess I'll still call
The Source, and we're going to grab that and copy it over.
And then we also want to make sure that
Our storage index is going to be that low into the index, and I guess
I'll change it to storage index as well.
There we go.
So now that we've got that straightened away, this is just passing
those on to the next guy.
And then it also happens to have already computed its position.
And so it'll actually just go ahead and overwrite the position there.
Yeah.
Again, this will be more, this would be more meaningful if we weren't
actually still storing the position out as well, but you could imagine
again once we can press it, we wouldn't be storing that position.
So we kind of should leave that in there since that's the path that
will actually have to get taken.
All right, so that's
Fine.
And now we need to go ahead and move.
Our our entity stuff here, out of handmade dot h.
So, we want to grab that out.
Let's take a look at what else we've got here.
We need our hit points.
So there's our hit points, that may be it, for the things that we
actually use actually have in here, looks that way, alright?
And so when we do an end Sim this, right?
Okay, so now we've got to do, we got to do the entity mapping, hash
table.
We talked about that, I guess we might,
Just jump in and do it.
So basically, what's going to happen?
We talked about this yesterday, we'll talk about it again, when we
left everything up into a Sim region, we basically are creating a
secondary array of these sort of cement Keys, which are all going to
be processed.
No, as part of the simulation.
But since we have entities stored often in, we have the permanent
storage of all the entities in the world, that's in a different place.
May be compressed.
May be stored like like what we're saying?
The position changes.
When you go from one to the other, that sort of thing, we need to be
able to persist references to entities.
So basically an entity is going to want to talk about when it's
talking about say, the fact that it's going on, here we go.
When it's talking about another entity, it's going to use its index,
probably into the low entity array, right?
Because that's a stable index that you could always use,
Your index into the array of the other kinds of entities.
The same entities, right?
This array is not stable that your index in that array is just depends
only dependent on where what SIM region is being talked about at a
given time, right?
So if in here we have something like for example what the sword was
right?
Because we remember we use this to point to the sword was right.
If we have something like that, we need that to be able to persist and
so a sword.
Index.
We need to be able to get from that to the actual sword.
And the problem with that is we don't actually know how to do that in
our current system.
We love things up into the Sim and we don't really have any way of
actually dealing with.
We don't have any way of actually dealing with the fact that we need
to reference or do cross-referencing.
So what we need to do is we need to have some way of doing that
cross-referencing and so what I thought I would do is again I can just
make like a hash table in here for example,
And hash table would just tell me for any low entity index, it would
tell me where the high entity index was like, basically where the Sim
entity was in this array, it's not an operation.
We'd probably do that often, so I don't really care too much about
making it be particularly fast or anything, but that's basically it.
And so what we'd want to do, right?
Is we'd want to be able to change this into
Essentially a Sim entity pointer, right like, so we'd want to be able
to change that into a cement to the pointer so that we could just get
it, the sword whenever we wanted to and then when it gets stored back,
that is when we would actually go and turn it into a low, you know,
into a low index, right?
That's what we'd want to do.
Ideally
So that's what I'm thinking about, right?
That's what I was thinking about and what we could do.
In fact, this kind of seems like maybe it's worth doing already, just
because it kind of points towards the direction we want to go.
What we could do is make a little Union here, right, where we
basically have a low index and a Sim entity pointer, right?
Like this.
so, if
Wanted to we could do like index and pointer.
I guess something like that.
I don't know what we could do is say that this is actually like an
entity reference like so I'm having trouble typing today and any
reference and this is like, you know, an entity references.
The thing that references the sword,
And so it'll happen is when these things get loaded right references,
get pulled in and when they go away, they get converted back to index
indexes, right.
And that seems like a pretty reasonable thing to me.
I don't know.
We'll see again, like, this is our experimentation period.
So, we are allowed to sort of figure out what sorts of stuff we want
to do by trying.
So that's what I would say.
I'd say, that's what we want to do, and then for the entity references
are in here basically, we map them in and map them out, in that exact
same way that we used to do.
So, you can imagine in here when we actually do our storage operation,
right?
When we do our stored Sim entity, this block copies, that entity into
the Sim version.
Well, we want to go ahead and change that sword.
We want to go and chat with me.
Go ahead and change that sword pointer into a an index.
So we essentially want to do this.
In fact, I guess we could just make a function for it, which is like,
you know, I don't know.
We don't have a good, I guess we could call it store entity reference.
Like so and then we would just pass it that address and it turns out
that we really don't have to do anything to make that happen, right?
It's really, really simple.
If we want to convert into a reference from its pointer into to me.
Into a permanent index.
We have a really easy way of doing that.
I guess we don't want to call that sword.
Probably, huh.
And actually get this as a Sim entity.
This is actually an interesting reference like so, all right, and so
what we would do there is say, first of all, if the ref pointer is not
equal to 0, right?
If the ref pointer is equal to 0, then hey, the index would also be 0,
right?
Because it's zero and zero so we don't have to do anything, but if the
ref pointer is not equal to 0, then what we would do is we just say
well whatever its pointing
That it's just that guy's storage Index.
Right?
Is what we want to actually store, right?
Really, really straightforward.
Not particularly difficult at.
All right.
So what we would do there is we just say the index equals the storage
index and then we're done.
And so, that's really easy.
When we do the NCM, that's a really easy thing to do and that would
pack our that would, you know, translate our stuff back into storage
and everything's fine.
But the part that I was more concerned about in the my reason I say we
need to Hash table is the
Opposite.
So, when we actually bring an
The in, right?
That's the point where we have to actually start to care about that
that hash table some way of mapping.
because what's going to happen is,
When we have one of our low entities come in right.
And I suppose we should assert here that not supposed to add an
entity.
That doesn't have a source at the moment.
Maybe in the future will allow that.
Yes, we could allow that.
Yeah.
All right.
Never mind.
I'll do that yet.
So when we actually go in here, what I'll do is lock, say if source,
so assuming that there was a source entity, right then what we want to
do is now we want to map
Like things like this sword, we want to map that in and so much.
Like I had the store version store in view reference, right?
I want to have a load as well, right?
I want to have a way to do a load entity reference and that's just a
lot harder.
Because what do we do, right?
All we have is, well, we have the same start, I guess, which is to say
if it's not equal to 0 we have to do something about it.
But what exactly is it that we're going to?
And the answer is, I don't actually know.
Hash table was my first hash table was my first instinct.
Right?
What I want to be able to do is I want to be able to say something
like, okay the ref.
Oops.
That's that's around much.
Sorry.
We only have that we only have the index, right?
So what I want to be able to do is say okay the pointer equals like
get SIM entity from Index, right?
I want to be able to say that and pass whatever that index actually is
and get
I could pointer to an entity that's in the same region, right?
And so, the reason that the reason I was thinking of hash table is
because I have an index, I want a pointer, I could just have a, it's
just a straightforward map.
It's just a mapping from pointer to index and that seems like the
easiest thing to do, right?
That just seems like the easiest way to go and then that will go ahead
and give me that that'll translate that reference and that'll be the
end of it, right?
What I could actually do here to just to double-check
I might want to do something like getting this.
And asserting that the pointer was actually valid because there should
never be a case where you're referencing something and it's not in
there.
And in fact, what we should do is we should all, I think we actually
want to have a policy where we actually pull in.
We probably want to pull things in because thinking about this a
little bit more when you go for a simulation region, anything that
other people were using, you presumably want to pull those things in
as well, right?
That's kind of interesting.
Thing.
So much fun.
I love.
I love programming complex systems because there's so many interesting
things to think about, but if you think about
That right?
Like if I go ahead and do a region query, if I'm referencing somebody
presumably, I'd want to pull them in as well and maybe not anything
that they're referencing because they won't get simulated, perhaps
themselves but we because we already have that notion of simulated,
not simulated that we're going to put in, right?
But just in terms of whether they're referenceable, so that's kind of
interesting.
I don't know.
And I don't know how far we want to crawl out.
We may want to crawl out through all the references.
We may not, I don't know, that's kind of interesting.
Question.
And it depends on how complicated our game logic gets what we want
that answer to be and I'm not exactly sure.
So that'll be interesting.
That'll be very interesting.
So I'm going to leave that there for now actually and that should go
that a search should fire for the sword.
Specifically actually probably I'm thinking.
And so I'm going to go ahead and just let that be for now.
And then we're going to come back and take a look at that in a minute.
But anyway, that's the that's the current situation.
So what I want to do is every time that I add an entity, what I want
to do is basically add that entity and I guess when you add into,
you've got to give it a storage index, that's kind of requirement at
the moment.
I suspect I can't think of any reason why we would allow a zero
storage index.
Those are the entities that don't get written back there.
Only, they only exist inside the same region that doesn't seem logical
to me.
So for now I'm going to go ahead and assert that the storage index is
always something ballad and if we can think of a case,
Later where we did want to change that, that's fine.
But for now I don't think I'm gonna allow that.
So go ahead and do this.
Then, what we want to do is say, all right, for that storage index.
What we want to do is remember that, this is that that's where this
entity is.
So I want to do basically, to store it in that hash table.
So I want to do something like
Map storage index to entity or something like this, right?
And then I passed the same region which will store the hash table, and
I will go ahead and end and pass that storage index.
So then from then on and I guess the end of the pointer right now.
So there's storage under their CD player.
So then from then, on anyone else who asked about the storage index
will get this entity back and so they basically just have that nice
mapping done, right?
So that's pretty trivial.
I don't think that'd be very difficult to write.
So we'll just go ahead and write those two right here, right?
Like so, so we've got a one that returns an entity and takes an index.
Like so that's going to have to take the same region as well, right?
Because it needs to be able to look it up in there.
We could just make this a general entity mapping pointer.
I don't know if we want to do that.
What we'll see.
We can always pull the code out later.
And this one returns nothing.
This one is just a thing that is in charge of yeah, of bringing.
Upsetting it, right?
So it doesn't actually return any values, it just sets it.
And so, same thing.
I'm going to do exactly the same thing I did before with the tile
chunk.
I think I'm going to make a hash table, I feel like that's the easiest
thing.
We want to do a quick look up.
That seems totally fine.
And so, what I want to do is just set my hash table to be some fairly
large thing.
For fast look ups.
And I want it to make sure it would store at least the max entity
count, you know, for this, for this, for this Sim region, right?
So, I guess what I do here is say that we've got I guess a Sim entity
hash
Something like that, same empty cache.
And that's just going to store the index and it's going to store the
the pointer, right?
So essentially, it's actually just one of these but instead of having
it as a union, it's actually both of them.
Right, that makes sense.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead and say all right I've
got some number of these in the hash table.
There's the hash table, I guess for now, I'll go ahead and hard-code
this size but I'm not sure.
That I want that to be the case for Evers, if that makes sense.
So we'll go ahead and see and this, this is something that may be
problematic, just because of the clear 20 nature of it.
A little little bit nervous about it because the reason I'm a little
nervous about it, is it probably will end up being better to do some
kind of a
because there's so few lookups like a tree or something that's more
compact.
Might be a more logical way to do it.
Something that requires less clearing.
I don't actually know.
It's just something to think about, but we'll see.
In fact, I can put it to do there to Casey.
Do I really want a hash for this?
Who knows, right?
So,
Okay, when we add these guys in their chances are, I guess we're
probably adding them relatively sequentially.
I think, I don't know.
We might just go ahead and directly use the index into the hash table
for now, because I don't think we need to do anything fancier than
that, so we'll see.
But anyway, when we go ahead and do our begin Sim what I would like to
do is just go ahead and zero that hash out.
I don't know if we actually ever made a function for zeroing things.
It would be nice but I don't know if we ever actually did so we'll
see.
Yeah I don't think we actually ever did.
We did not, I don't think yeah.
So I don't know.
I don't actually know if you can do.
I don't think there's any real good way to do zeroing on this guy.
So I'm going to go ahead and have to write a 0 in function.
So
Excuse me.
Yeah, so when I go ahead and get this guy, I think I'm going to use
internal probing this time, you're embar, we talked about external and
internal training, I should say of our hash table.
I don't know if you guys remember this.
What day are we?
Where's our where's our?
Let's get some Blank Space here.
There we go.
Here's day 64.
So I don't know if you remember this but last time we did a hash
table, we kind of went through it and we said like all right we're
going to fill in a slot of the hash table and then if the another
thing wants to be in that same slot because their hash key is the
same, then what we'll do is we'll just make another sort of one out
here and point to it.
I don't think they do that this time.
I think I'm going to use internal training which basically means that
if it's not found in
This slot, then it will basically go.
It'll step through the hash table.
Looking for an empty space sequentially, right?
So we'll just kind of do this sort of thing and we can go just by
stepping by one if we wanted to.
He's a better thing to do.
Sometimes it step by prime numbers.
There's all kinds of theory to Hash table stuff again, right now,
that's all performance stuff.
We don't really care about that right now.
So for now we're just going to do the simplest possible thing and then
later will actually try to figure out it won't.
If we even determine that, we do want to Hash here, we'll actually go
ahead and figure out what to do performance wise for
All right, so what we want to do is we're going to look up our index.
So let's say we have a hash value for right now.
We're going to make it equal to the index so that's fine.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and step
through like so and look in the hash to try and find one of these guys
to try and find a match.
And also again index can't really be equal to 0 here, right?
Because we're not allowing the we always say that.
At low end of the index is, like, the storage index is 0 means null.
So you shouldn't ever be looking up a know, what we could do to make
things easier, I guess is if, if we wanted to, we could also say that
this, this gets them into D from index, always just automatically
returns a 0 in the case where it was Zero, you know, we do this
basically, right?
And maybe that's a better way to go.
So basically, this function just becomes that write something like
this.
Yeah, that kind of thing.
I'm not actually going to overwrite directly there because I'd rather
since it's a union, I'd rather be able to still see what the index is
when we're in the debugger.
So I'm going to leave it like that for now.
But yeah.
So this gets immunity from index.
Will handle the case where index is 0, if an x is 0, it will just
return a null pointer.
So that way, we still have the ability to pass nose through directly,
which I like so, we'll go ahead and get the hash value will call, just
call that the index for now.
And then we'll go ahead and say our probe
Is going to be equal to the hash value or actually, are I guess we'll
call this our offset.
I'll call that zero.
I'll step through the entire array essentially, right?
Whatever that hash is worth of offsets stepping through.
And then the the place that we're going to look up in the hash is just
going to be the hash Value Plus the offset.
And then we're going to go ahead and and off that mask.
So like just just wrap it into the table.
Put it into the table properly, right?
And again, that just stands with that array count.
- 1.
This is all stuff we've done before, but just in case just to refresh
your memory again.
Basically, what I'm doing here is I'm saying, all right, I'm going to
look up into this hash table, right?
And I want to look up.
I want to basically search through the hash table.
So, most of the time I'm hoping that I hit it the first time, so this
Loop won't really loop at all right.
It'll just hit the first time and then return.
But in case it doesn't, it has to look through sequential values and
again, we could make it probe
Something other here, like a prime number or something like that.
Like I said, is there's more hash table Theory stuff.
Maybe we'll get into a little bit later, but for right now, we'll
just, we'll just probe by one's looking through the hash table to see
if we can find what we're, what we're looking for.
In order to do that, I need to search the whole hash table, right?
So, I need to make sure that I would check every individual item in
the whole hash table.
If for some reason, the hash table got totally filled which is a
catastrophic case that we don't ever want to happen.
So we'd always make sure I have tables too big to ever have that
happen but point being that's the correct way to write it.
So after we figure out where we're probing, we're starting at some
place in the array, right?
And when we get to the end of the array, we want to wrap back around
the beginning of the re because we didn't start at the beginning of
the race and we need to check their.
So we're going to do is we're going to mask off the sort of just the
those High bits.
And we're only going to use the bits, that would actually map into the
array.
And so, right now, like, for example, I put a thing here too.
It just says must be a power of 2.
Because we're using that ending off trick obviously, if we're just
using and enough to wrap into the table that only works for the power
of to size, because we're going to check all of the values that those
bottom B could possibly be set to which obviously means it's power of
2.
And so what we want to do here is just generate that that simple Mass
from the power of to 4096 - one is 4095 that's the bottom 11 bits set.
I believe right?
And and then we're going to not that because
We want to wait.
No, we don't need to not that.
Never mind.
That's the way it should go, right?
We want to subtract one from that because that will set the bottom B.
And that's the only bits that we want.
So we don't actually want the not there.
That was my bad, shouldn't had enough.
So I don't think so.
Hard to say, I make mistakes on stream all the time, so yeah, it
happens.
Anyway, so what I'm going to do here is I'm going to pull out
This Sim entity hash right now.
So this is the hash value or let's try.
This is the entry I should say.
So I'm going to grab that entry and going to grab it like this.
I'm going to look at the entry and I'm going to see if the entry index
equals the index that we're looking for, assuming it does.
I'm going to set the result equal to whatever the pointer is and I'm
going to break out of the loop.
Otherwise I'm going to assert that the entry index is not equal to 0.
Because if the entry index was equal to 0, that means that we've hit
an empty, hash lot.
And
At the moment that is not supposed to be allowed, right?
Like we're actually not supposed to, we're always supposed to be able
to find it here.
So, yeah.
So basically what we want to do is this is the place and we'll put up
to do there, right?
This is the place where we would add, oh well, you know what?
Let's just go ahead and do that.
Let's just go ahead and add it.
So if at this point, the enteric the EM entry index is zero meaning,
we've hit an empty slot.
Meaning that this hasn't been stored before.
We'll just go ahead and store it.
Right.
That will be the case where we actually add the entity in.
So do you want to do there is kind of a little tricky, right?
What we'd want to do there is we would want to be able to call this
directly from their, right.
We'd want to be able to call this call where we just do the identity
right here.
We'd want to do entry.
Index equals index entry pointer equals, you know, identity and then
results equals entry pointer break.
So we just make a new one right there.
And what we want to do here is we want to be able to pass.
I guess these are actually technically storage index as well.
What we'd want to do here is we want to actually be able to pass
Those storage indexes and the source entity into this.
So like or rather a way to get the source entity.
So that in this particular case, when it comes back and it didn't
actually exist, it would get pulled in in the process of actually
going to get the entity right.
Maybe that's a little bit too much to do in that call.
So the other way I could do it is make this guy, this gets em entity
from index that could actually just return the same entity.
The cement entity hash lot that it found that actually seems like a,
that actually seems like a pretty good way to do that as well
actually.
Now that I think about it.
Yeah, that's that's not bad.
Right.
So basically if there's a similarity, hash
Slot there, then that's going to.
Yeah, I like this better.
I think there was too much stuff going on in this routine because it
what you wanted to do inside here would probably depend on who was
actually looking up the thing and it just seemed like I was getting a
little bit too, too much stuff packed in there.
So what I'd rather do is say, alright let's go ahead and say that this
gets back the hash lot itself and then the person on the outside can
decide what they want to do with that hash lat.
So in this case, if the hash equals
Then what I would do is I just break out right on there and the result
again equals the entry directly like so right.
So I guess what we could say is if it's 0 or it's the storage Index,
right?
If either of those two things are true, then the probe is done bail
And that seems pretty good to me.
Yeah, yeah.
So I could even get rid of this as well because this would just work
the first empty index would return it.
And so maybe I'm going to go back to my original thinking and say that
storage index has to be something and then that other stuff gets
handled out here.
Okay, I like that.
So,
So when we call gets him into the get SIM entity from index, what we
want to do now is we want to be able to pull those things in
recursively, basically, right?
So what we want to do is we want to have more things in here.
When we're doing our identity call, we want to be able to do more
stuff in here.
Right now.
Of course what I will do is let me before I go and handle some more of
that.
Let me go ahead and just put some stuff together here that's like
Sort of a destination hash.
So when we're storing somebody, we want to go ahead and do this,
right?
Where we do the same thing again.
And this is probably in aptly named at this point.
This is actually get, you know hash from Storage index.
That's actually what it is.
So we'll call the get the hash from Storage index.
That gets us back the hash entry that we're looking for.
And then, what we want to do is we want to make sure we want to
basically assert that if someone's telling us to map the storage entry
in and maybe, you know what, maybe we don't even care.
So all we have to do is basically say, all right, if they've stored it
before, that's fine.
So let's assert that the, the index that's in the, the entry equals
our storage index or it's null, right?
So either, there was nothing in this hash lot before the one that
we're trying to set or
It's equal to the one that we're trying to put in there, right?
And that'll just allow us to overset entities, right?
It allows to overset Hash slots which seems fine to me as well.
So what I basically do is
No, at that point will initialize it.
Like so like that.
Oops.
And so that actually will put an entry into our hash table and say now
whenever whenever anyone asks where this storage index is entity
pointer wise will give him this back and off we go, right?
So that seems pretty easy.
And now that this is the, the trickier part like I was saying, store,
any references?
Easy load entity reference is going to be the hard one.
Basically, what we want to do here again.
Same thing we were doing before we're basically we grab out.
That ref index but now let's actually check.
Let's make sure that ref index is actually something we care about
now.
So assuming that ref index actually is indexing into an entity.
We're going to get out.
Its hash lat.
And then we're going to see, okay, we're going to, we're going to
basically assume that either.
I'm trying to think of how exactly we want to do this.
It's a little fuzzy in my head right now either.
It's already there because it's already been loaded or, it's not there
yet, and we would like to load it, right?
That makes sense.
So, this is going to create.
A little bit of a recursion here, I'm not sure if I'm thrilled about
that recursion and I'm not sure if maybe we should change it into
something a little less recursive.
But for now, we'll leave it recursive and we'll see how that goes, I
guess, I guess.
So, if I want to load an entity reference
Basically, what that would do is it'll get out that entry if the entry
pointer is null, then we need to load a new entity into their right?
But if it's not then we're pretty much good to go.
And I could also say, okay, so basically the ref pointer equals the
entry pointer, right?
So basically, the case that I have to worry about is the case where
the entry pointer equals no, which means we tried to reference entity
like the sort, but the sword wasn't in there yet.
Excuse me.
So, what I want to do in that case, right?
Because I want to go ahead and pull that sword in any way.
So I want to basically say here.
All right.
Well then, we're going to keep calling down will call down into their
right.
With the storage index of of this guy, right?
The ref index and I want the low entity that corresponds to that
Index, right?
Which I can get, I think we have a get low and do we have Get Low
entity?
Yeah, what we want to do is basically do this call, right?
And so this call
which we've actually,
We actually want to put in the H file so we can call it from other
places that make sense.
So that would go in here for now.
I guess, so what I want to do here is I want to get that low entity
that the one that corresponds to this index.
There we go.
So yeah off we go.
So I'm going to go ahead and get that.
I need the world's or I guess I need the game State there and I really
wanted these to be I really would have preferred
And again, that they were stored in the world but they're not stored
in the world yet, so I guess that's just the way it's going to have to
go, which is fine.
It just means that basically, these guys will have to take the game
State instead of just taking the the world.
That's something I want to get rid of, but we got so many things that
we have to do to do this full thing correctly just to put everything
into the right places and have it work correctly.
I just don't want to deal with it at the moment, one thing at a time.
So anyway, all right, so I added the entity.
So now when we do that reference mapping which we're going to do in
here, right?
So we do that copy in we have to do map storage unit that saves this
particular guy.
In fact I guess this should be done immediately upon entry so as soon
as we map it as soon as we have it we map it like so on.
Yeah that looks good to me.
So anyway
What we'd want to do is after we do that romping, we now want to
translate that sort Index, right?
So we want to do a load entity reference to load the sword index,
translate it from the olds from the old kind of reference from the
index into a pointer, right?
So we're going to go ahead and do that.
Like so,
Oops not source.
So this is entity sword like that and when we do that, we have to pass
it this stuff.
Now unfortunately, that's just the way that goes.
So now what this does is this will call at entity recursively
basically to pull in any other references that we find.
So we're kind of spidering outwards grabbing new things into the
simulation set as we go.
And I probably forgot a bunch of things there because we've landed a
bunch of things at once.
But that is just, that's just the way it goes sometimes.
So let's see.
Hash Value Plus offset and array count - one less.
What is the problem?
Oh, sorry we go.
It's got a print size that put see here, ref is not a member of sim
region.
I agree with that.
So what we need here is the game State, I think, and Annie
Not take three arguments, that's true.
It takes game state that we had to pass their this is as well.
Same thing, same entity.
Story to dereference store, entity reference.
There we go.
That's not supposed to be an arrow.
These are basically just a little typos that we have to clean up that
they're particularly interested in going on here.
And then finally.
Okay, so now we're actually in a position to do this properly as well.
Right.
We've got a Sim entity.
And what we want to do here is we want to go ahead and actually do we,
where we have our load entity reference, right?
But we'd also like to do, instead of the load we'd like to have a
similar version of this, right?
Which is basically like, you know, check entity reference or something
like this or or like get entity by index or something like that by
storage in.
X, something like that.
Where we can basically call do a check, just to see if it's in there,
if that makes any sense, just seeing purely if it happens to exist in
the set.
And so, basically, what that would do is, we'd say, alright, you pass
the same region, you pass the storage index and all it does, is it
straight up?
Does the check, it grabs the entry out and just returns you whatever
the entries pointer.
Was it?
Doesn't actually matter.
Whether it's null or not because you're going to Chuck, right?
That makes sense.
So now we can actually go ahead and Implement that here.
The camera following entity is just get ND by storage index and we
just go ahead and ask it like so for the camera following entity
Index, right?
So if that ended, if the entity that we are, following happens to be
in the same region, then we'll do the update for it.
If it doesn't then
You don't and we don't really have to do anything more specific than
that that just works.
I think.
Yeah I think there's really nothing else to it.
So all we have to do is say all right, the camera following entity, we
grabbed it out, this doesn't actually have to happen on every Index.
Right?
In fact, you know what, we don't even have, this is actually easier
really.
All we have to do is do this check.
This is stupid.
I don't even know why.
I just wrote that call, we don't maybe don't even need that.
Call will see really
All we have to do is just go.
Oh, is the entity that we just wrote out, right?
Is this guy's storage index equal to the camera the one that we're
following, that's it.
Why are we even looking the hash table?
We don't need to write if it is then what we want to do is move the
camera, right?
So entity or I guess stored right?
Where's that piece toward P?
Dot chunk Z and then it just goes
Head and does that, right?
That's it.
That's really simple kind.
Nice to.
That's kind of cool.
How that worked out, that's it.
Nothing else to it out.
Think.
Yeah, so set camera, set camera doesn't we don't even need such camera
anymore, right?
Because we've done everything now, all we need to do is just remember
that the camera is at a different location, but that's it.
The set camera call was there to do all of this mapping stuff, but
now, we're just doing that during the same stuff.
So, as far as I know set camera is just not, do we already delete it?
Yes, probably just gone, right?
So that's totally fine.
So we can get rid of
Is that camera that camera just gone?
Nobody cares about that camera at all.
We don't care about any of this stuff that's just that just goes away.
Although I didn't actually couldn't read that because by my head let
me actually read it.
Mapping tiles and stairs into the entity set.
Yeah, well, we'll know to do that when we actually go to implement
them, we don't really need to do there.
All right, so that just does all that.
And that's, that's just, that's just fine.
It's just done done.
So I think this is mostly just going to be mapping to the Sim the fact
that
Scott that Sim pointer now.
Right.
But I'm thinking that probably the way that will do this is we might
actually just add stuff in the same entity eventually as well.
But again, one thing at a time.
So really all this stuff is just some dot, right.
In fact we could almost say that low Arrow just becomes low Arrow, Sim
dot for most things, right?
I think that just works.
So off we go.
To to do blah blah blah look so that sword thing will have to change.
Obviously these are all this, this is this is going to get a lot
simpler than it was, so that's all good.
That doesn't have to change.
Although the move entity stuff does have to get updated so just check
that, right?
These are things.
These These are going to all change.
Totally.
They're going to get vastly simplified probably tomorrow tomorrow
morning.
In fact.
Um, yes, we're not to worry too much about those so change that.
All right.
So now what we have here is our sword dot index.
So, that's what we want to do there.
And how is this happening?
Now, when the add player, we add our sword.
Yeah, so when we add things now, when we get our ad low entity
results, you got it back that looks like just, we just need to set it
because we have that ref type now nothing particularly interesting
going on.
On there.
So now our move entity call that really has to get ported out to the
Sim, right?
Because that supposed to be something that happens in the Sim.
So let's go ahead and get that in there.
So here's our simulation stuff begins, immense M, and so probably I'll
put that down at the bottom for now.
So when we do move entity, what that's going to do that's going to be
on the same region now, right?
And
it's going to take just an entity pointer and
And that's going to be the entity who is getting moved.
We still want the moves back and his acceleration that all seems good.
We have the world like so this is all easy to deal with what else we
got.
That's immunity em, entity, the move specs.
Where do those moves specs come from?
We didn't we didn't ever Loft those out into an h-file which we should
have.
So there we go.
So
of specs or something that I'm going to put in the same region as
well.
Just put them out here for now think about them a little bit later and
now entity da Hai is always just just just entity, right?
We don't have any more of the stock High nonsense that all goes away
into just entity.
And this is nice.
Because, again, this is starting to now collapse down into code that
just looks like if you wrote something without ever having to think
about the fact that there's all this complexity in terms of
Managing large entity sets and you know, not simulate everything,
every frame which is what we'd like right.
Ideally, we'd like the code to not most of our code to never look like
there's anything special going on because then that means every time
someone adds something to it, they don't have to think about it too
hard, right?
Before it was definitely in this place where you had to think a lot
about it when you added stuff and we don't want that.
So it's really good seeing this stuff collapse that way because
that's, you know what I was hoping for right.
And so again Dot Low
Also, and I guess .lo Arrow Sim just goes away entirely, right?
That just becomes straight up accessors and this right here, the test.
Hi entity index where we're this is going to Loop over all the stuff
in our Sim region which is again.
You know, something we want?
This is something we're going to want spatial partition for eventually
spatial partition here, right but for now
We're totally fine.
So we have our entity count.
We're going to Loop over.
Our Region's entity count, like, so should probably call that a Sim
region instead of region.
I don't know why I'm calling it region in some places.
So, I kind of want that to be called same region.
And so that's going to Loop over those like, so, and test High entity
index is not what we want to do.
Here is basically say that the entity pointers are not the same,
probably, right.
Oh,
Man, I was just getting into that.
I hate having to stop on the our boundaries, man.
That's just not the way.
It should go.
Well, you know what can you do?
That's the rules.
Only an hour, a night.
You don't get to just keep going just cause you want to unfortunately,
that's that's the way it goes.
So yeah.
So we'll just do Envy is not equal to test entity like so and then
this just just
it goes.
No, more of that.
No, more of this, no more of that, no more of any of this.
That is just now, a nice, little simple thing just looks like what you
would normally write without having to think about anything and it's
fine.
Same thing, but hit High, Catlow that stuff all goes away, pretty much
because we can now just do entity star hit right entity.
And Let's do.
Let's take a look at where that happens, right?
So,
Hit entity.
Now just equals test entity that get rid of all that food.
So and then down here, you don't have to do any of that.
You just have hit entity and later we can do stuff with it.
All right.
Almost done Andy.
Test wall.
Yeah, test wall should probably moved in here.
All right.
I said I was going to stop I'm just I'm kind of into it right now so
you know sometimes you go just a couple minutes extra and I started 5
minutes late.
I want to point out the fact to you but I did start five minutes late
so I technically I feel like you owe me an extra five minutes, you
know I'm saying.
That's what I think.
So, anyway.
All right, we no longer have to do this, that's done and we know if
longer have to do either of these.
So that's good too.
So that just moves The Entity and now, everything in there is just
nice and clean and it's totally none of this.
I don't even know.
I don't even know what this stuff was even here for this is some old.
Yeah that was some rain shucking stuff.
Let's get rid of that entirely.
Yeah.
Starting to look nicer started.
Look nicer.
All right.
Yeah, I guess that's a good place and any from high index.
I don't know what that was there for.
That's gone.
Goodbye.
Yeah.
So we still have a bunch of work to do.
Obviously, to finish our Port, plenty and plenty, and plenty of work
to do.
But tomorrow morning, could we could finish, we could fit system
possibility, it is a possibility.
Trust Friday, right?
Friday morning.
It's possible.
I don't know, not gonna promise anything but it's possible.
And then we would be in really good shape.
I think that would be some good so be some good clean up work that we
did there.
Good architectural shift.
So I think that's mostly what we want to do.
We're going to have, I'm going to leave a couple notes in here for
ourselves.
We begin Sim to do Casey important, clear?
The hash table.
Otherwise we're going to be very sad, pandas about that.
And then we also have another thing to do which is notion of
active versus inactive entities for the apron.
About yesterday.
So just so, I don't forget those.
Okay?
Now, we can go to the Q&A, we can go to the Q&A.
If you would, please put Q: before your questions.
So I can see them.
And in addition to that, please keep the questions to stuff that we've
actually coded so far.
If you want to talk about off-topic things or like speculation.
About what we're going to do, you know, that sort of stuff that's
totally fine for before the stream but not after the Stream.
So if you want to ask those questions, come about 15 minutes before a
scheduled start time and we always do off-topic questions again
stream.
So,
Alright, okay, let me see.
Can I start the Q&A?
I don't actually know if I can or not.
Don't know if I can do it Q&A.
I don't think I can.
I think the bot totally ignores me the boss just like, yeah, we don't
care about you.
Why are you even?
Why are you putting exclamation point things?
Yeah, I can't.
So sad.
All right.
Well, I tried I tried.
Yeah, I have not been whitelisted yet on the bot.
I'm blacklisted on the handmade hero, but I guess,
Not sure though.
I tried to start the Q&A.
Just didn't happen.
Okay, why don't you upload chat Logs with videos?
Somehow?
I just don't really think of those as being part of the
serious.
It's basically just supposed to be video series with me going over
stuff.
So if something is important enough, it should be asked in the Q&A,
but if someone else wants to have a chat log, that's totally fine,
right?
You can feel free to capture them and post them somewhere.
As far as, I know, they're essentially public domain, right?
Like, no one owns the chat log.
So, you know, anyone who wanted to have a site that basically
replicates the chat log, totally fine by me.
Doesn't look like there's any questions.
It's question, free, probably, because the scream was acting up or, at
least something about streaming was tough today.
Right?
Like, look at that.
It's really having trouble but I don't know why, right?
I don't know what the problem is.
It's very confusing.
So it's very confusing like this is way worse than we usually have
ever, but I don't think there's an internet problem at the moment, so
don't know if it's just twitch or something else.
It's kind of hard to say I suppose.
One thing we could do to is just take a look at like you know, this
kind of thing.
Right.
I mean.
It ain't a problem with the internet far as I can tell.
It looks like a problem with the old Witchiepoo but we'll leave that
running.
There's a bug in your random number table.
The numbers are limited to a range.
Yeah, that's fine, though.
We're not going to use the random number table.
I just put that in there because I didn't want to go over the the
random number how to do a random number generation, right?
I don't know if there are bugs in that rain or whatever.
We just always went to random.org and got random numbers from them.
But again, we don't we don't care at all and that isn't a bug that
would affect us pretty much at all anyway, because we always mob them.
So the fact that they're limited to arrange isn't a problem at the
moment.
Anyway.
But yeah, you really don't want to use a random number table like that
either.
Like there's really no reason to.
So if you are using that for some reason, I would highly recommend not
doing that.
It's literally in there just because I didn't want to have to teach
random number generation yet and I want to save it for when we go and
start doing World World Generation stuff.
So yeah, random number two, random number table, not something you
want to use, just something that's in there.
As a placeholder till we actually cover how to generate a random
number.
You mentioned not wanting off-topic questions so I apologize if this
counts not off to a good start there but could you explain your naming
conventions or explanations behind using them?
I've never seen a style similar to yours.
It seems inverted data types versus variable names, and it's very
interesting to me data types versus variable names.
oh, are you talking about the case you're talking about, like camel
case versus underscore lowercase with underscores
If you're talking about, just just the capitalization scheme.
This is actually pretty standard in certain circles, but really I
picked it up from Chris Tucker.
I used to be all
Lower case with underscores always like there was no I never had
uppercase, could I don't think I ever even had uppercase letters in my
coach ever till I was like 18.
And then I picked up from Chris Hecker, doing it this way.
And I don't really have a strong feeling about it one way, they're
just how I do it now.
And basically, so types are always lower cases, underscores, and
functions and variables are always camel case.
The reasoning behind that is it takes longer to type underscore
versions than camelcase versions because there's an extra character in
them.
So you leave them on the thing, you type less frequently that was
that's like the entire reasoning behind it far as I know, I don't
think it's only.
I feel like there's not really a reason to or not to have a naming as
long as your code can be read like and it's not all really confusing
than that's fine.
Let's see.
Do you want the store data T's to move like normal ones or simulate
them?
Like you mentioned stuff moving around with slower updates off-screen.
Yeah.
So basically what I decided to do with the same region stuff is not go
that route basically I want to try at least at first and we'll see how
this goes.
I want to try everyone.
Always runs the same simulation code, it just some people get less
time stamp steps.
So basically like when you're far away from the player, your region
will get updated.
You know, once
Every ten frames, and it'll get updated for 300 milliseconds, instead
of being updated once for 30 milliseconds, right?
Let's every frame for 30 milliseconds, but everyone will run the same
code and that, that my goal there is to just make it easier to code
for when you add things to the system because I'm afraid that if I
make it so that you have to write two versions of every entities
logic.
And every piece of logic, it's going to be very hard to keep that bug
free, right?
So I want to try and do some things to help that what we don't know.
Yet, it's Ray too early to know what's going to actually happen there.
But that's what I'm driving towards and hopefully it'll work out.
We don't know yet though.
Maybe if you change your Twitch server, I don't know how to do that.
I mean, I know, sort of how to do that, but yeah, just I think we've
pretty much verified that my internet connection is fine and might,
which is messed up, because there was one lost packet that entire time
And that was probably the one that I control seed, right?
Is it always say one lost?
No, so I guess it did technically lose one, I don't know, maybe there
is something to it, but I think it probably shouldn't be quite so bad.
I don't know how to change my twitch server.
So if you want to send me an email,
I'm Casey at Molly.
Rocket.com it's on my Twitter, if you want to send me an email and
tell me about it, or you can post on the forums about how to change to
its servers or what would happen there.
What is the point of high and low entity when it makes sense to just
have one?
Well, I think you'll see as we go, if you were, if you watch previous
streams, we talk in some detail about why there are two.
Now, the reason that there are two is more speculative, it's because
eventually, I think we're going to do some stuff with the high
entities.
With what I should say, sim entities now I think they're going to be
much larger than we're going to want to store.
That's just a hunch but we'll see what happens going down the line.
So at the moment, we don't we at the moment, we actually don't really
have two types of entities.
Like you saw how I did it where we actually just use the same data for
both.
So at the moment we don't necessarily need it but I think we're going
to possibly want it down the road so we'll see.
Can entities reference each other?
Do you need to check for cyclic references?
So we don't really need to check for sick.
The references thankfully, I guess that was kind of something that I
just knew and didn't really mention.
Which is if you notice when we have cyclic references, what will
happen is load entity reference.
When it gets to the first one, it'll go get Hashem storage index.
It'll find the pointer zero.
So it'll do the identity, right?
And by the way, we actually should store this.
Well, I'm here, right?
We need to do this.
Like so otherwise it would never get filled which would be bad.
And similarly we probably want to put that that index in.
Right.
Glad we did.
That would have been annoying.
We have to go to bug that so I'm glad we actually found that.
Yay.
So what will happen here is when this gets the hash when this gets the
hash back, it'll find its 0 and it'll add that the entity in it when
it adds that entity, if there's a cyclic reference pointing back to
this entity, that's actually fine.
Because when it does the
Add.
It'll find that the next time through load entity reference.
When it's when it's doing it, it'll actually find the one that's
already been added.
So it won't trigger another call to a density.
So they can't won't loop around right?
And you'll notice that's why I put map storage and X2 entity at the
top of this, so that it would immediately.
As soon as entering here, it would immediately store it in the hash
table.
So that anyone who was trying to resolve some big cyclical, entity
chain would not cause it to Loop forever.
It would instead
Turn out cleanly, right?
So that was how that was supposed to work.
When is a ground up rewrite warranted.
How often do you just burn everything down and start fresh?
You almost never do that.
I mean unless yeah you don't really ever do that.
You pretty much always just change code in place.
I feel like like you saw a lot of time, stuff goes away entirely like
set camera.
Now, doesn't have to exist anymore because we like changed the meaning
of how things work such that it's not necessary.
So, in that sense, code gets deleted, but I don't really burn anything
to the ground.
I like to mutate code towards good.
I mean here's one way I could say it.
And this might be kind of clear.
So here's the theory for you.
This is this is
I'm going to spell this wrong.
My spelling that right.
Let's see if I'm spelling it right.
Liya poon of my, a poon of.
Yes, I am.
Sorry, I do not speak Russian, so I don't know.
Russian spelling very well.
So basically, there's a concept called live Pune of stability, which I
think about from time to time, which admittedly really is not have
anything to do with what I'm about to say, but it's just they occupied
Spain, mental space in my head.
So I'm just going to point it out.
Ignoring all of the actual math Venus of Life who now stability and
skipping, right to sort of a very, very simplistic reductionist view
of what it means.
If you were to imagine a vector field and for those of you don't know
what a vector field is think of something very simple, like a bunch of
water or you know what a divot like you know like if you were looking
at like a driveway and there was a pothole in the driveway, right?
And at any point, if I was to put something on the driveway, right?
And it's like like a marble or something.
If it was near the divot might like roll into the divot and end up in
the bottom, right?
And so, if you think about what that kind of means is like you can
think about everywhere around the divot, right?
If this was the center of the divot and here's like the radius of the
divot, right everywhere around the divot.
Our arrows are like, gravity is pointing into the divot, right?
And out here, Gravity is not pointing anywhere in particular, right?
It's not going to move the ball, maybe, but if you put the ball
anywhere like here or here or here,
Are here.
It's going to go right into their right.
This is one form of.
Like this is one type of vector field, you could think of where
basically stuff, no matter where it starts out is going to end up at
the same place.
And once it's there it's very hard to get it out of there.
You have to move it all the way to this boundary to have any chance of
it.
Not just rolling right back in there again, right?
So, that's the case of like, here's my driveway and there's oops.
Here's my driveway, and there's like a divot, right?
This is the driveway and here's the divot.
If the balls out here, it's okay anywhere in here.
It's just going to go right back down to the bottom, right.
Now, there's another kind of vector field though, right?
You can imagine and think of that as corresponding to the opposite,
kind of thing.
It's a, it's a lump in the driveway, right?
So it's up instead of down, okay?
Well now if you think about what that div, it looks like up here.
It's the opposite.
All of the vectors for Gravity are like pointing out, right there
pointing away from this thing.
So, if I was to put something on there, right?
Like here, it's going to roll off and it's going to, it's going to
leave.
It's very hard for me to get things up onto here, right?
Because they're always going to want to come off of it, but there's
still a point where the ball will stay here.
There was a point where the ball would stay and it was almost
impossible to get the ball off of there, right?
It's like it'll always just go right back down into it here.
There's still a point where the ball will stay.
It's right.
Right at the very top where all of the arrows, stop pointing away and
it's like, right, it's just perched right up on top.
They're right.
But any little perturbation like any Breeze that, so much as blows the
ball a little bit off and it goes right back down again, right?
So this is a very stable system you might say and this is very
unstable, right?
If I want to purchase something in these two, I want to put something
in here.
It's very stable to put something in here, and it's very unstable to
try and to get to stay in here because it'll just leave immediately.
Its whereas, this one actually has a very wide range where I could
even have it go to and it will come,
Back down.
That's how stable that is, right?
And so I tend to think of code bases this way, right?
This is a lousy code base or I shouldn't even say codebase this is a
lousy programming model.
Okay, and this is a good programming model.
And what I mean by that is every day when you do work, you are trying
to make your work, do this sort of a thing, you're trying to make it
so that you are always, the code, is always converging towards a good
better stable place than what it was.
Right and such that when you put
Is into it even if they weren't quite right there, they're going to
move towards good, right?
This is the opposite.
This is a programming methodology where you everything has to be just
so and if anything goes wrong at all, forget it we're done.
Like it's like bug City and things are lousy and whatever.
It's all kinds of terrible, right?
And so, the reason that I brought this up with your question is as
long as you're following a good programming model.
You almost never you almost never burn, right?
You almost never burn things to the ground because you can always just
move things incrementally towards good and things are getting better
all the time.
The longer you code, the better things are getting, you're replacing
like old pieces with new pieces, and you're changing old pieces.
Two new pieces in incremental ways that move you towards good.
If you're following a
Was he programming model?
Then that's when you need to burn.
When you get yourself into a code base, where everything is awful, and
no matter what you do, it becomes terrible, that's the time when you
would need to burn.
But the only thing that you can do, if you're going to burn, you'd
better burn and go back and go to something here.
If you don't know how to do this, then burning here isn't going to get
you anywhere because you're just going to go right back to this
garbage and create another code base.
That sucks.
And by the way, that's what I see, most people do when they burn, they
usually have a bad code base or like, starting over.
We need to start fresh.
They start fresh, and they end up with an awful thing again, because
it was the programming model that was bad.
Not the code.
And usually that's true.
Usually, the code is not the thing that was good or bad.
It's the programming style.
It was, what was, how you went to work every day, and the fact that
you had too many programmers going to work every day working like
this?
I meant that it didn't matter.
It's all it's all over.
You can start fresh and you're still going to get an awful code out
the end, right?
Whereas, if you have programmers that are working with a good
programming model, you can always March forward and just replace
things in the get better and better, right?
So that's the way I usually like to think about that and there's a lot
of aspects to this.
I try to teach a lot of them.
You know, but a lot of its experience to, you know, a lot of it's a
lot of its having done this before.
And now, you know, why it's bad, right?
So something to think about
Let's see.
Doesn't look like any more on topic questions to me.
So, I think we may be done.
You may be done.
You may be gone.
Yes.
Looks like we may be done.
All right.
Well, that is very good news.
It's kind of fun to zoom out and see the days Happening Here.
I think this is kind of fun having like a having a thing that
that allows you to zoom in and zoom out like that.
I'm kind of like, in the way mischiefs working out.
We take a look here.
I've got one more question.
What are your opinions of scrum and agile methods?
So I don't really know like I've never done scrum.
and like,
I mean, programming methodologies of that format, are probably the
kinds of things that
how should I say this?
I guess what I would say is I don't have any experience with scrum.
I've never done it myself.
I only vaguely even know what it is.
Like I have vague Notions of people like taking cards off of white
over on Note border something like this.
I don't really know.
So scrum.
I can't really talk.
I can't really say one way or the other.
Agile methods, I remember long ago, I think when I first saw them
appear in like the C++ report or something like this, I mean, it was
kind of like, I was like, yeah, that's how you should probably
program, but I don't know that I ever read any of the like agile,
programming literature to know whether what they think of as fast and
flexible programming or whatever you want to call Agile.
Programming is what I think of it as and so I can't really say
Yes or no to it in any definitive sense.
I think because I really just don't know so I'm afraid I can't give a
very good answer to that question because I'm just not familiar enough
with them to know if they line up with what I think is what you should
do.
But you know,
that, you know it might be
Let's see.
All right, so I think we're done.
So I'm going to go ahead and save this off.
Minimize close.
This, we're getting pretty close.
I'm pretty happy with how that's going there.
Still a couple things that I'm like, not super sure how we're going to
do.
In terms of that Sim stuff, but I think it's pretty cool the way that
it's going now and it'll be interesting to see how well it scales and
how well it performs.
We start timing it and there's just a lot of interesting things there,
but there's a couple things still that I'm not sure.
We're going to handle and it's going to be interesting to see like,
the, the, how you do the like, apron how you simulate in a region with
the not having it go forever in like a cascading marbles sort of way,
I don't know.
It's gonna be interesting too because we I mean it's easy to write it
so it doesn't do that.
But the question is, will it work?
You know in practice does it?
That are there problems with entity simulation that you don't think of
that come into play there?
And I don't know, but again, that's one of the reasons to why I like
doing this sort of stuff.
I like trying new systems and not doing things and trying to push the
boundaries a little bit and saying, what if we, what if we had to make
a system that could scale to this many of these?
What if we had to make a thing where, you know, we know that we're
going to be bigger than a float.
What if we, what if we had to do this?
What if you had that I like doing those things?
Because it kind of shows me how new stuff and it's like it's like
exploring new areas.
And, you know, I really like that sort of thing.
It's like, it's challenging and keeps programming fun instead of just
Oh, you know, the same old thing, I got a roomful entities and we just
simulate the room and that's it and you know whatever.
So I'm pretty happy about where it's going.
But I think there's still some challenges left ahead and I'm looking
forward to tackling them but they'll have to wait till we're done with
our current port and some more stuff so hopefully you will join me for
I think what may be the conclusion tomorrow although who knows how
long did bugging will take, we made a bunch of changes, so we have to
do a bunch of debugging, but the very least, I think we should be
BB recompiling and running tomorrow with our Sim region stuff which is
kind of cool.
So hopefully you'll join me for that tomorrow.
I believe tomorrow is at 9 a.m.
I'm going to be tired, it's going to be some breakfast programming.
But basically before I go to work, we will be doing some handmade
hero.
So I hope you'll join me for that.
I'd love to see you back here.
If not I understand sometimes I would like to sleep in to it's true.
But anyway, if not, then we will post the schedule as well for next
week and you can check that.
And come back and see how we're doing next week.
Anyway, if you would like to follow along at home with the source
code, if you preorder the game, you get the source code with it,
basically get a link in your email that allows you to go anytime you
want and download the latest source code.
So if you want to do that you can do that.
Check it out here at handmade here at dot org.
You can also, if you want to support this video series, we have a way
to do that.
There's the patreon uses.
You can subscribe to which you very much appreciate.
And if you want to be updated,
Added as to like, when it airs every night and the schedule for the
week, we have a tweet pot, but tweets out the schedule every day and
also a one hour warning.
So, like little tweet out and say, you know, go out goes live in an
hour.
So that's a pretty handy little guy.
You can get to him on this tweets button here and we also have a news
and Forum site, which I highly recommend checking out.
It's got some good stuff on there.
It's got like ports to Mac and Linux if you want to follow along on
other platforms.
Like your murga does illustrations to go.
Which the episodes and some other folks do time-coded episode guide.
So if you go on there and go to the episode guide page, you can get to
all that stuff.
It's pretty cool.
And there's also a forum that you can ask questions on.
So if you're trying to learn from the stream and you want to talk with
other people who watch the series, that's a great place to do it.
I highly recommend checking it out.
So yeah, thanks everyone for joining me and I hope to see you next
week.
Take it easy everyone.
Nope, I guess not next week.
Tomorrow tomorrow morning.
And then next week.
All right, take it easy, everyone.