Okay.
Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The only show available on planet Earth on the whole, perhaps even in
the whole universe.
We do not know how far these radio waves may be traveling right now
across the galaxies.
The only place where aliens on Mars, should they exist can tune in in
some sense if they had some magical way of doing, so to the the place
where a entire game is coded from scratch using
No engines, no libraries.
They said that, that was absolutely crazy.
But how crazy really is it at the end of the day?
I think we've totally proven that.
It's possible.
It's not only possible, but it actually, has some pretty awesome
benefits to it.
One of them being that we get to kind of muck around in, in all of the
sort of crazy, underlying stuff and do cool things, like the looped
Live code editing and that sort of stuff that really, you know, you
would never get a chance to play with.
It's too much fun.
But I don't know.
That's just me.
Maybe everyone else thinks is crazy, but I still think it's a good
idea and I think the martians on Mars, probably agree with me when the
rover finds them.
They're going to be like, I'm so glad somebody finally did a series.
It wasn't using an engine.
That's probably what they're going to say.
At least I'm fairly certain.
but,
Not everything can be for Martian.
So sometimes we got to talk about other stuff which is stuff.
You got to think about whether you're doing an engine or anything
else.
And so that's what we got to do today.
Now, I want to quickly take one moment to say but here we are on day
51.
If you have pre-ordered the game you can unzip day 50s Source zip.
You should have gotten a link in your email.
And if you go to that link, you can download both the test assets that
we've been using and a zip file that has everyday source code in its
own little private zip.
Unzip day 50, and you will be where I am.
Day so that you can follow along at home if that is something that you
want to do, and I highly recommend it because following along at home
is the best way to learn.
I would say, and tinkering with stuff is certainly a very good way to
learn and so that's a very good way to do that.
Anyway, so let's talk about some of those things that the Martians
have been waiting for me to talk about.
Basically, we are at the point where we sort of implemented a
rudimentary Collision detector.
That does some of the things that we need, you know, it can glide
along walls and that sort of stuff and we can move our guy around.
But we have at this point.
We kind of have to open up into a new area of development.
Because like I said, right now, what we're doing is, we're sort of
getting basic pieces, all the basic pieces in place and seeing how
they work, so that we can go start writing about, full like shippable
Quality Engine versions of each one.
Until we actually have one of everything in place.
I'd typically don't like to do that.
I like I said, we want to explore the code first.
I want to know how everything fits together, and then I go start
writing, sort of the industrial-strength version of things, but the
problem is now I'm not sure what the next best thing to do would be to
do at this point.
My there's really two separate.
Areas that I want to tackle and they're sort of independent.
One area is animation.
Like I said, I really want to animate this guy, right?
I want him to hop along when he when he moves and that sort of stuff.
So, I want to sort of put in an animation system because that's a big
key component that I want to have in there so we can see how it works.
So we know what it's requirements are and that sort of thing for when
we build the final version, but the other thing is multiple entities.
Now we have obviously I think I still have the the controller over
here.
We
We have the ability to drop more than one dude in here.
Right?
So we've got another dude, but they don't actually interact in any
way, right?
So they don't Collide and we really don't have any notion of an entity
system or anything like that.
Right?
We've got, we've got nothing of that form whatsoever.
And so basically what I want to do is say, okay, what exactly are we
going to do here in terms of of
Of getting multiple entities and that sort of stuff because that's,
that's kind of a big part of the, of the whole shebang.
And there was also a, you know, a sort of thing that came up the other
night that I was saying, where I really want to get to the point where
we don't have to deal with coordinates all the time that are in the
sort of tilemap Center.
Offset format.
I really wanted it to mostly be the case that entities got packed away
in that format when they were no longer useful from moment to moment.
And that most of the time what was happening is that entities were
actually all
Any entities that were involved in the screen that we were on or near
by?
We're always just in float space.
So that's like a pretty big thing that I'd like to, to tackle as well.
And I just don't know which of these is the most important to tackle.
What?
I don't want to do is keep going with the Collision Vector, because I
think the Collision detector is, you know, it's, it's pretty janky.
There's no question about that, but there's not a whole lot more that
we need to do to know what it has to do.
And so I feel like going any further down the Collision detector path,
like trying to make it actually be robust and nice and good.
And all that sort of stuff, and support, more different types of
objects in.
Those sorts of things are all stuff.
That can pretty much be put off till when we actually write the final
version.
I don't think there's anything that's necessarily going to stop us too
much.
So that's that.
So just thinking that through really the point that I'm at right now
is just trying to figure out what do I really want to start doing?
Now?
What is the most useful thing to start doing?
And so I'm thinking that probably what it is is I think it probably is
the sort of multiple entity kind of more.
Like let's get the gamey sort of stuff running like an example would
be maybe we have a guy and a little monster that attacks the guy and
there's like health and the health goes down and you know, the monster
can be off screen or walk on screen these sorts of things and then you
know monsters that are far away or not getting stimulated at the same
rate, those sorts of things trying to start putting those in.
In seems like, maybe the better.
And the reason for that is because like I said, I would like to get
away from that co-ordinate system thing where we're sort of constantly
using these coordinates that I really kind of only intended for
packing and also, you know, we don't really know exactly how we're
storing other stuff like World stuff too.
So, I don't know, there just seems like there's a lot of stuff that
probably wants to get sorted out there, and maybe that's more
important than animation right now.
And also animation might How We Do animation might be somewhat
informed, by that.
Because if everything is operating in that float space, that may have
some
Vacations for how the animation system works and it may make it
easier.
Develop the animation system if we've already cleaned that cruft out.
I don't know.
So that's what I'm thinking.
That's just off the top of my head.
so,
I think that's probably the best thing to do.
So, hopefully everyone's at least someone on board with that as a
concept.
And from there.
I think I'm just going to go ahead and start playing with that and and
see where we get with it.
Right?
I think that's probably the most logical thing to do.
So we'll just spend a couple days getting that sort of part up and
ready and then we can sort of also have a little bit of a, you know,
we kind of see, we walk through the world and there's there's people
in it and that sort of thing.
And we can kind of start to see roughly how that's going to
So let's just say that that's something that we want to do.
And let's take stock of where we're at and see what it's going to take
to get us to a point where that sort of stuff starts to happen.
So obviously we've got a tile map system here.
That's that's basically just meant to virtualize a giant map where
there are only exist tiles in some locations, right?
That's essentially what we wrote here and we decided that we didn't
want it to wrap because we thought rapping was probably not a good
idea.
So we're probably going to get rid of the concept of wrapping for now
though.
We'll see how that goes because it seemed like that was just gonna
introduce bugs and there was no real reason to do it because the world
was so large.
No one could really ever walk from one end of the end for from one end
to the other.
Anyway, that was kind of one of the design ideas behind the fact that
it was going to be as far as Tom app.
Was that there would be no way you could ever make a world that there
be no way.
Ever want to make a world larger than what it could support.
So if we ever did want the world to appear to be rapping, what we
would do is actually just virtualize, sort of like say when you hit
these tiles, you wrap around to another set of tiles or something like
this.
So, given that I have that I guess the sort of the idea that I was
that I was toying with and that I sort of think is the way I would
like to go with.
It is instead of always actually doing computations on these tilemap
things and having everyone be represented with these, tilemap
positions that are basically, you know, sort of overkill for most of
the operations we're doing because they're only there to allow us to
have these huge Maps but in
Any given section, we could do all of the operations at float, which
is what I want because that's much faster than having deal.
These time a positions and dealing with wrap the sort of the wrapping
from
One town to the next like the, you know, the sort of moving from town
of Thailand renormalizing, the offsets and all that stuff.
So, thinking about that, what I'm what I'm sort of in my head
envisioning is sort of this concept that what we have is sort of two
sets of entities, basically, right?
There'd be one set of entities where the entities were actually like
active and they were actually moving around with full floating Point
precision.
Ian in the world where we are and then there'd be sort of like I don't
really want them to necessarily be dormant entities because I want
them to still potentially have behaviors but they'd be entities who
exist pretty much solely in tilemap space and are updated at a much
lower frequency.
And so what I'm thinking is like let's say we build a world, you know,
and in Crete I could sort of do a little diagram of a little rough
diagram of sort of what I'm thinking about here, which is that suppose
that this
You know, sort of situation here, right?
This is like the screen, right?
This is what we actually see.
And then there's like an apron around it of stuff that wants to be
simulated, potentially at Full Resolution may be, right.
I mean, I don't know, but let's say that there is.
So basically, everything inside here is like full resolution Sim.
This is full of risks him, right?
But then everything in the rest of the world.
So everything that's not in that, you know.
Apron area, everything else.
I want to basically be, you know, low-res Sim.
So that basically, we could have, you know, if we wanted to have
10,000 entities out here that weren't really doing anything too
important in terms of their like, s to S stuff, but we still want to
simulate the maybe they're on routes.
They're going places and picking up stuff for, you know, doing some
kind of planning about what they want to do.
Those sorts of things.
They're still doing things, but they're not necessarily doing them
with the same, kind of resolution as these, where they're actually
doing like, you know, full path, finding, and trying to walk around
and look, realistic, as they do it or attack the player.
And those sorts of things, right?
So I'm thinking that that sort of sort of the thing here, and I don't
know what this number is, right?
I don't really realistically know what this number is.
So one of the things that I don't know if I've really talked about you
much in the series, I do it a lot.
I don't know how useful they are, but I'm going to say what now
because it's what I would do here.
There's a thing called a back of the envelope or boat, right?
And it's back of the envelope calculation, right?
And what it basically is, is, I don't know why they call back of the
envelope.
I have no idea where that actually comes from.
I don't know if they're talking about envelope.
Like, you know, like a in the sense of like a performance envelope or
whether they're talking about like this sort of thing.
And like I use the back of an envelope to write down a calculation on
that.
I didn't particularly care too much about, I have no idea but point
being what it is is its kind of Ball parking, some computation to some
To give you a sense of what might be possible or to kind of guide your
judgment, but that, you know, is not accurate to any real, like, you
couldn't use this calculation for any real purpose, because it's, you
know, it's kind of just very fudgy and it's a fudge Factor kind of
thing.
And so what I'm kind of wondering it's like, okay, how many entities
might we have?
Like, I don't know what that number is, right, how many entities?
And so the way I like to do this sort of thing is I'll say, okay.
Well, let's say that realistically speaking since this is a generated
game.
You know, I feel like 8 hours is probably like pretty darn long for a
gameplay session.
Like I feel like, you know, I feel like eight hours is
Longer than you might ever probably want to play a generated guck.
Java generated game games or like four or five hours, but, you know, I
mean, if we were to go crazy, you could imagine 6A someone for some
reason and I have no idea why wants to generate a 60-hour experience
and play like, you know, like a final fantasy length, kind of thing or
whatever.
And then also, you could think the more typical playtime is maybe two
hours, right?
One to two hours.
Like I just want to, I want to generate a little game.
I want to play it.
I want to have some fun.
I don't want it to take all weekend.
And right.
And so, I feel like that's a pretty reasonable range of things.
Like, you know, that's the min max.
This is probably the most typical.
This is probably less typical on.
This is probably, I don't know that we ever even care, but it's
something to think about to see what that kind of Maximum bound is
like, is anyone ever going to play 60 hours of one game of handmade
hero knowing that I could die at any time and be done and not, and
have to start a whole new one.
I don't know.
But point being
So if I think about that and I say well, okay, you know realistically
speaking how many enemies do you encounter typically per minute?
Because you know, if we if we look at these right?
What is that?
That's thirty six hundred minutes or something like this that the
person's playing for and in this case, right?
It's what 1480 minutes.
I don't know.
Bad with mental math.
These are probably all wrong hundred twenty eight twenty minutes,
right?
So we're looking at like, you know something that's between
A hundred and twenty and thirty six hundred minutes of playtime,
right?
That's what we're looking at here.
And so, if you're talking about how many enemies these, this, this
player will encounter, you know, let's even if they were encountering,
some very high rate of monsters for this type of game.
It's like as LD kind of walk around game, you're talking four, five,
six enemies.
On a screen at a time is already getting a little chaotic for the
player to deal with.
Really if there's enemies that are all meaningful and aren't just kind
of, you know, throw away.
So, you know, even if we're talking about something like 10 monsters
for screen, which is really high, right.
So if we said something like 10 monsters per screen where we were
talking about, you know, that's a pretty pretty heavy rate and we
Talking about, you know, maybe even two screens a minute.
So figure, 20 monsters a minute at 20 monsters a minute, you're
already, you know, encountering them.
You're already talking about really less than this.
This number I already was talking about here, right?
That's like 72.
Oh no, it's a little more.
Never mind.
That's a little more 72,000.
Is that correct?
Right.
You add the zero and x 2.
So 70,000.
So, so there
You go.
72,000 would be if we're going to play 60 hours, encounter, 20,
monsters, a minute.
I think I did that, right.
So 72,000 entities right would be, would be roughly what that is.
And you know, that's, that's kind of a pretty massive number of
entities.
And so let's think about that number a little bit, right?
If we had 72,000 entities and we're talking about this 20 per minute
thing.
Well, how many screens really are?
They're going to be here, you know, if there's nine even if there was
something like, even if you're talking
Maybe Thirty hot screens, you're talking about in that working set of
entities.
You're talking about, maybe 600 entities tops, but we're probably
talking about a lot less than that.
Right?
I mean, we're probably talking about something more in the range of
like 100 to 200 entities that are in the in that hot range.
So we're talking about simulating, maybe 100 to 200 entities per frame
at the full resolution, which seems like a totally doable number,
right?
Isn't that doesn't seem to particularly difficult there at all, and
that's a feels pretty.
Hi, but even if it was 600, that doesn't seem like too bad, right?
Especially because a lot of her off scene.
So we don't even have to draw them.
We just have to know what they were doing.
So that seems totally doable not really a big deal.
Write this number.
However, in terms of how many are stored externally is a bit of a big
deal because, you know, if you sort of think about how we might want
to how we might deal with that if you were actually simulating 72,000
guys for frame.
Well, one thing that you can do pretty easily.
Again, this is sort of that back-of-the-envelope compute computation
stuff.
If I whip open the calculator here and I say OK on a 3 gigahertz
machine.
That's three times 1000 times, 1000 times 1000, right?
That's how many cycles I've got and I'm running at 60 frames a second,
right?
So that's per second.
So per frame, if I was running at 60 frames a second.
Let's say I would have what is that about?
50 million?
50,
In cycles that sound about, right?
So I'd have 50 million Cycles is the total number of cycles that I'd
actually have right.
So I'd have 50 million cycles per frame to do.
All the work that I need to do.
Right?
And so if you think about taking the 72,000, right?
And I divide my, my number of Cycles by the number of entities, you're
down to a really tiny like seven.
Rinse cycles per entity.
It just not going to happen.
Right?
It's just totally out of the question because seven hundred Cycles.
I mean, that's only a couple memory, a couple memory fetches, a
couple, a couple things out of the cache and you're already at seven
hundred Cycles, right?
So we pretty much know that that number is never going to happen.
So if you want to scale to that number of entities, we need to have
asked, we need to have something in mind, that's going to handle this.
And so what I expect to do, what I think is the easiest thing to do,
right?
Is to just update these guys at a much lower latency, a much lower
frequency rather than everything else.
So once people move out of The Hot Zone, what I want to do then is
say, okay from then on once people are out.
Of that Hot Zone.
What I want to do is say they are now going to update, you know, at,
you know, some kind of a, let's say, let's say 1,000 a frame or
something like that or potentially even less because at 1000 of frame,
it would roughly be one.
Second.
I'd update every entity like once a second, right?
And once the second seems like enough for enemies who are just kind of
doing things with with each other, you know, they're basically just
doing stuff outside of the world.
And you know, some portion of these entities might be able to go to
sleep completely if their entities that don't do anything.
Like their enemies that don't have any evolving behavior, that could
make them do something that we care about then we don't have to worry
about them at.
All.
Right.
So really, this is just, you know, sort of a ballpark number.
Now.
The other thing we have to think about here is storage for these guys.
Right at this at this rate.
Basically, this is 72,000 entities, right?
So 72k, so, you know, it's probably really not that big a deal, but if
we actually were starting to think about well,
I want to be able to sort of save the game or stuff like this.
It becomes a little tricky because, at 72,000, well, how big is each
of those?
If each of one was say, one kilobyte large, you'd be at 72 megabytes
of memory just for the entities that are not in, you know, that are
just kind of sitting there which on today's machines is nothing.
Like I said, that's totally meaningless, so we could totally do it.
It's not a problem.
But we do have to think about it a little bit for like saving the
game.
Do we want the save game file to be 72 bags?
Right?
And I mean, like I said, I don't know that we're supporting saved
games per se, but we might support like closing the app and reopen it
again.
And so you're starting to wonder if that's maybe such a good idea.
I don't know, it probably doesn't matter, but point being something to
think about.
So, sort of what I'm thinking here is saying, okay.
What I want to do is I want to I want to say we're going to have these
two things.
This is how I've been thinking about it in my head, what we've kind of
got out here.
So what I want to do is I want to say that we've got sort of one set.
That's a relatively small set and then one set that's a pretty big
set.
And these are basically these are the low frequency entities, right?
And these are the high frequency.
These.
And what I want to do is as the player moves around the world.
What I would like to do is essentially move right entities from the
low frequency set into the high frequency set, right?
So, they kind of they come this way as they become on screen, right?
Or I shouldn't say on-screen, I should say like as they move in range.
So because I'll, you know, I'll probably start simulating them a
little bit further out and that's just for stuff.
Like if you want to be able to
To hear things in the Next Room that are happening.
Right?
Or stuff like that.
You know, maybe we want them to be simulated, a little higher Acuity,
right?
So there's the high frequency set and they move in when they come out
of in range.
And then things will similarly, get moved, you know, out to the low
frequency set when they are out of range, right?
So that's really all I really want to be able to do.
Now, I wanted to talk a little bit about addressing here because this
is kind of something that's relatively important.
What I wanted to say was so
Entities can have behaviors, that are about that, revolve around or
need to think about other entities, right?
Pretty obvious.
Like, for example,
If one entity has decided to attack another entity, then typically you
need some way.
You basically need some kind of a pointer, right?
That is from and one entity to another entity.
How do I remember?
You know, the The Entity I was talking about, right?
Another example would be like a familiar.
Like if someone's following the player like a Aid, a support player, a
support entity.
How does it know who it's following?
Because like I said, we're just kind of supporting multiple players.
We don't know if we'll have
Both players in the game eventually, but you know, we want to do it.
Right.
And similarly.
Maybe the same thing that happened were monsters, like, maybe monsters
gonna have familiars to, right?
So, we want to be able to support kind of a generic concept of, like,
I am following this guy.
Well, in order to follow somebody, right?
I obviously need a way of saying, who the person is that.
I'm following.
And so, we have this need to, basically do a dressing of some kind.
We're inside these structures.
We have the ability to discuss other entities, right?
So what I'd like to do is I'd like to have some stable addressing
scheme because you can see why this gets a little confusing if I have
high frequency and low frequency entities, right?
Then one thing I definitely don't want to do is have to Loop over this
entire low-frequency set, right?
Every frame just to find which ones are high frequency, right?
And similarly.
I may not even want to store because like I said, that seventy two
Meg's is looking a little bit dicey there.
I don't know if I want to store all 72, MB of that.
So, if I if the
Tool information, necessary to process a guy at high frequency
happens, to be very detailed and has like his animation State and all
this sort of stuff.
I don't necessarily want to store all that in here, either.
Right?
So, I've kind of got this situation where I have a number of competing
concerns that I need to work out and it would probably be best for
performance and just in general for space efficiency as well.
If we could have entities exist in either place and be able to address
them correctly.
Ali, no matter which one they're in.
So, basically be able to say I am pointing to an entity somehow.
I am following entity blah and know that I can figure out the things I
need to figure out about him without having to always search one or
the other or do anything weird.
And without forcing me to have everything in a giant index table or
anything like that.
Right?
So I'd like to have a skiing that does that.
And I think probably since the low frequency table, basically has all
the enemies in it, for the most part, I think.
Probably.
Well, it's very hard to say, right.
The real question is how we want to held your doorman entities.
But let's say that every entities always simulated for now.
We'll put this question aside temporarily, but let's say that every
editing we wanted every enemy in the game to always be active.
That's just something we're going to do in the game.
Every entity has a behavior of any and every NDS stuff that happens to
them and they're always kind of possible to be used.
If that was the case.
Then I know that basically my low frequency table, always has all the
entities in it.
So what I could do for my addressing is basically just address into
the low frequency table, always.
And then if there's a high frequency, if that person is actually in
the high frequency table, I just store something at the head of that,
that sort of says, like, oh, you know, he's in the high frequency
table and here's where he is, right?
Let's say I could do something like that.
The other thing I could do is have a separate table.
That's totally transient and isn't stored that just says, who's in
high frequency, and who's in low frequency, right?
So, you always look, there's always a 72,000 72,000 entry table, right
out here that has all the entities in it, and basically, all it is, is
just a pointer or just, you know, like a information that says,
whether it's in high frequency electricity table and where it is,
right?
And then, every time someone moves from one to the other, we update
this.
So, there's different ways that I could do that the
This is doing it this way and maybe this is the right way.
Is that we can also have dormant entities, which is to say that
entities, that are in here.
They're in neither table, right?
It's like, it would energy just doesn't even exist anymore.
Maybe it's in some like dormant table, which literally just stores
where it was.
So, the only thing that's in there is the location so that when it
moves in range, it can move, it can move from this table, into this
table, into the high frequency table, but it, like, never actually has
to have its, you know, be processed in the low frequency table, right?
So, I don't know.
That's a good question.
But the fact that I'm even thinking about it suggests to me that
probably, we would want to start with a three table scheme.
So that we know that, we could support doorman entities correctly.
And then if we find that it's not necessary, we could collapse down to
the, to the, to table scheme, but basically, like what I'm trying to
say here is I'm a little worried that baking it into this.
Table is a bit of a premature optimization and I'll be sorry later
that I did that because I want it to be more flexible in various ways
or whatever, right?
So
That's what I'm thinking right now.
That's roughly the way I'm thinking about it.
And so, this high frequency table would store everyone in float space.
It would be float.
Space, based around wherever the camera is at the moment.
And whenever the camera moved, we just update all the entities in here
to have that offset, probably or something like that.
I'm not sure exactly how we want to do that.
I'll have to think about that later, but this would basically always
be float space and these would always be in tile space.
Right?
And that would get us completely out of the business of having those
sort of annoying two-tiered coordinate systems because we still have
the court system that we worked out and it would still be working
correctly, but we would no longer have to worry about dealing with
them.
Both at the same time.
We'd always only deal with one in low frequency and only in float in
the other and they're just be one very clearly defined place where we
do that transition.
And that, you know, I think what's would make it first of all, very
bug-free, right?
Because I feel like we've already had bugs that involved, having to
deal with with those two at the same time because the canonicalization
and all that junk.
And, and so just being entirely in float, over here, would be great
and I think it would eliminate a huge source of bugs.
It would also eliminate a huge source of frustration of having to deal
with these Special coordinate systems and all that sort of stuff.
Because we would know that we would just always be in tiles here,
which are just integer Thailand disease, and we'd always be of float
over here and never the tricks chummy, right?
So that seems pretty good to me.
I feel like that's pretty reasonable.
And so I feel like that's probably what I would start with.
And then I'll have to think about, you know, what, these tables look
like.
We'll have to evolve as we decide what we want to do for any system.
But this seems like a little bit of a better approach to me.
And so similarly over in the high frequency side of things, not
necessarily in the entity table, but in addition to the end of the
table, I feel like it would also be all of the sort of stuff in the
In that area as well, right?
So all of the, you know, basically everything that we are doing, for
the game would kind of be in here.
That's in that sort of apron, would be in here.
Like where all the trees are, where the shop is, where the grasses
are, all that sort of stuff would all kind of be this thing in that
apron.
And then when we sort of go and and it gets sort of moved out, we just
yeah, we just say that's the end of it.
Okay.
So really, the only thing that I'm not still sure about exactly how I
want to do is sort of the I'm not really sure how I was.
To handle the the re offsetting part of things, right?
So there's there's a way we could cheese it, but I'm not really
interested in cheesing it.
So I want to talk about it a little bit.
So let's suppose right.
Let's suppose that I'm looking at this screen here and the hot region
that's being.
Simulated is like one screen around me on all sides.
Right?
And I don't know if diagonals are in there as well.
But you know something like this so you figured there are nine
screens.
Like I said, potentially 27,
Means if we wanted to think about vertical as well, I don't know if we
do or not.
But basically there's some number of screens that are in the hot set
here and everything outside of here.
Right?
All this is the Wasteland that's all in the low frequency table.
So when something comes from the low frequency table into the high
frequency table, right?
It's simple enough.
We just say, where is the camera looking right?
This?
You know, let's say we just moved here.
So this this tile, you know, we
Moved.
We just move one to the right, you know, we did that motion.
And so now these guys are coming into that hot set.
They were previously dormant.
So we gather all the things that are in here, right?
And we go ahead and we say, where are they relative to that camera
location, you know?
And we place them right?
So now we've got all of the things that are there and they're in float
space, right?
So what we've created, you know, is a local coordinate system where we
can do everything.
And we know that we have plenty of flow Precision because it's a very
tiny little world.
So it doesn't matter how giant our actual world is the real world that
we're simulating.
Willow.
I will if anything be smaller than most games full coordinate system.
So we'll have you in more Precision than most games have, right?
Because we're in this tiny space.
And so, you know, that all works out great.
And it allows us to have his giant to world, as we want, and never
have to worry about float, precision and still do everything in float.
So that we don't have
Many performance penalty either, which is all nice, but we do have one
performance problem.
Well, it's not a very important problem, but one performance concern.
The problem is what happens when we move again.
So when the guy moves here, right?
So this is now the new center.
Well, what do we do with all of these guys, right, all of their
floating Point positions.
If we were always going to make them be centered around the camera,
right?
They all have to be updated.
So, basically, everything in the high frequency table, essentially has
to be updated when we, when we do that move.
And so I don't know.
I mean, is that a problem?
Is that not a problem?
I mean, how many entities in here?
We have to have for that move to be an issue.
I don't know, you know if there was a thousand guys we're talking
about basically an ad, we're talking about, you know, a CMD ad where
you've got, you know, an x, a y and a z coordinate or something and
we're just full on adding and
XYZ, so we're talking about like one Cindy up, but we got to kind of
go through it all, you know, for all the guys or whatever.
And so, you know, if we have to offset a thousand of them, when we
move is that a big deal, right?
And I don't think it is.
I think we can basically do that in a very trivial number of Cycles.
You know, what, if we push that, how high would that have to be before
we care?
I don't think that much.
I'm just worried about like let's say each individual tree, you know,
in this world is being done, that way, you know, something like that.
Yeah, so I don't know.
It's something to think about is the point.
And so I'm not sure about that part.
But what it does suggest to me as well, is that that high frequency
table might want to be stored in a way where you kind of have some
sort of a notion of the X Y, the X has the wise and the Z coordinates
that are stored in a way that's very efficient to bulk process, for
addition, because that may be one of the biggest operations we do is
we move left to right or with that sort of thing.
But anyway, something to think about.
So,
About it.
I think that's that's really the only sort of snafu of the plan in my
mind where things are not 100% obvious that they're good.
That part is a little wonky, right?
That's yeah, so that's a little bit wonky.
And there's a couple other things that are not super clear about this,
right?
I'm not sure how we deal with the fact that like, so there's there's
dormant entities or not dormant, but low frequency of these out here.
So there's a question of how
how people ask about how low frequency and high frequency, entities,
see each other, you know, maybe they don't really but I mean, let's
pick.
Absolutely ridiculous example, like say that there's the concept that
whether I can see this.
There's here the sky or not and he made a sound and this guy knows
about it, but they're in different spaces, right?
So, you know, is there something that basically allows us to easily
Push simulation stuff out and in from the two different kinds of
people who are being simulated here, right?
And I don't know.
So that's that's just something again to think about.
I don't really know how we're going to deal with with that stuff too
much.
It's a little bit tricky for the stuff that's on the main screen.
Doesn't seem that much of a problem because unlikely that people will
be thinking about guys that are multiple screens away in terms of what
they're doing, exactly.
So I think that we're probably safe for all of the gameplay.
Interactions.
That actually happened but it's what happened to that apron.
That's a little bit confusing.
So again, we'll have to cross that bridge.
When we come to it.
We certainly haven't gotten to the point now where I have enough
information to really know what I would do there.
So there you go.
That's my full.
That's my full brain dump on.
Like, how I'm thinking about this stuff.
If that makes sense.
But if we kind of look at what we've got already, it's not like
there's all that much work to do to sort of get us there or at least
to sort of get us started on what's going to happen there.
So here's our
are you know our way that we're drawing entities, right.
And based on what we're doing now is we're constantly Computing that
difference.
From the camera.
So we're constantly saying, where is this relative to the camera?
And so, really, all I'm saying is that, now what we would do instead
of that, is we'd say, okay, let's actually go ahead and always just
store the entities relative the camera if they're in that set or not,
right?
So I what I want to do is kind of bifurcate these here.
I want to say that I've got, you know, maybe we'll call it a high
entity or at HF entity, or an LF entity.
I don't know, something like that.
I'm not really sure what I would call these exactly, but
But, you know, High entity and low entity am not sure if there really
isn't a particularly good naming for the my guest.
But if you imagine, we've got these right then my low-frequency
entities and my high frequency entities, my high frequency entities
would only just have a V2 for their position.
Right?
And I guess we still, we haven't really talked about what we're going
to do about Z.
I don't know if we want to kind of make this start to be a
three-dimensional Vector there.
We kind of got a thing.
About exactly how we're going to deal with three dimensional.
But for now, if we're only talking about two Dimensions, we've
essentially got this, where we've got the same stuff we had before
with the width height, 50 Direction, and all that sort of stuff.
And then we've got the low frequency entities, which basically store
the the tile map position stuff, right?
They're the ones who actually store this time at position data.
And we could start to eliminate that by saying.
We don't care about the offset any more after it goes off screen.
I'm not sure.
We'll see how that goes.
But anyway, so if we've got this, there's another part of, there's
nothing we could think about as well, which is whether we want to keep
the low frequency and of these around.
So the high-frequency entity can basically reference stuff in the low
frequency entity and that would be an interesting idea as well.
So let's say we also have the dormant entity, right?
See here.
I'm going to go ahead and call this low entity and high entity.
So if we had the doorman entity as well, like dormant entity would
definitely store the position right?
Because that's the thing that it needs to know and then the low
entity.
I don't know exactly what that would store or whether it would store
anything in addition to that necessarily.
But it might be depending on, you know, what sort of any of these you
had what kind of data it wants to remember.
And then you'd have the high energy which has more stuff yet.
And so the question is, you know, are these actually sort of do?
You actually always have all three for an entity?
That's in the high end of the space?
And always have both for the low entities.
And then sometimes only once the door - so like do these actually form
sort of a composite piece so that, for example, if the width and
height of an entity is something that actually needs to be specified,
then that's actually out in the dormant entity because it's something
that you actually always need to persist.
Whereas something like the facing direction is not.
So it's only in the high entity for example, right?
So you can see where I'm kind of thinking this through.
I don't really know yet.
And so this is a case where I'm going to write the usage code first,
like I always say, we'll find out.
But again, I'm just trying to write something here so I can start.
So that's an example.
You know, that's let's say we're doing something like that.
All right.
So at first, excuse me, at first to keep things simple, let's actually
just have three tables that all have the same, so we'll have high
entities and we'll just do the exact same number for each of them for
now.
So low entity, right?
And then doormanity.
Okay, and like I said, don't really know what's going to happen here,
so we're just kind of playing around.
So if we do that, then we can sort of say, alright?
So just High into these are the only entities that we actually want
and so all we really need to know is whether or not an entity exists
in that in that high into table, so again just doing the dumbest
possible thing will just store something here, just sort of a Flags
field or something which is just like entity some kind of and I don't
know entity and
The Residency or something like that, right?
So there we go.
And we'll say that our entity residency is just going to say,
basically, which of those tables, The Entity is in, at the moment.
So we basically have a entity residents.
Hi, you know, low or dormant, right?
Really?
Really simple.
So entity residents and I guess, since I'm not packing, everything
else in there.
I can literally just say
Say that we've got that.
So if we got the entity residents, that would tell us which one it's
in.
And so again the really inefficient way of doing this is we'll just
Loop over them all.
And actually do it and then we'll try to start splitting it out into a
slightly more efficient version and see kind of how that plays out, if
that makes sense.
So off we go.
We Loop over our entities here and obviously
When we, when we get this, we can sort of see what is the actual
residence of a particular entity.
Right?
So here's my other the index.
Here's its residents and we can just say for right now.
We're only going to deal with the high entities for the moment because
that's the only thing we actually know how to do.
We don't actually have any definitions for low or you know, what they
would be doing out there, but we'll have to sort of figure that out.
As we go.
So, here we go.
And I guess we have that exists thing, but I feel like now that we
have entity residents exists, won't necessarily be a something we need
because we could just have, like, you know, non-existent or something,
right?
We can just have some some and we could, we could reorganize this.
So basically you like don't exist your dormant, your lower, your high,
right?
And we can, so we can sort of move that concept of existence sort of
up into the actual.
Entity residents instead of having a separate Boolean for it, which
isn't really necessary.
So, assuming that it is in the residents, high table, then we can say,
okay.
Well then if it is, we want to get the high entity out of it and let's
go ahead and grab that.
So we've got our high-end fees.
So that's in game State.
I entities and we will grab it.
At the index.
There we go, like so so that will basically give us what we needed to
know, for that.
And now we're saying that basically the pee in here is exactly what we
actually wanted directly, right?
I'm out of tea, man.
II brought two tea cups and I'm out completely.
It's like how does that even happen?
Right?
Got it Morty.
All right, Jeeves.
Touch the ti need those little bells that they have in fancy British
documentaries.
All right, so if I have a high entity, what I need to do is I need to
grab out.
It's, it's information about where it is.
And what I'm saying is that now this is already relative to the
camera, right?
So this is already relative to the camera.
Or it is.
So all I have to do is draw it relative to the camera.
Now, which means I go ahead and say and and one interesting thing.
That's to think about there as if we did want to do the split screen
thing.
We'd have to do something a little fancier here because it's like
well, Rich camera, right?
So we need to have at that point.
You would need to have some note in the residents when you said it was
resident in high, you had to say which camera belong to there'd.
Be some kind of fussiness there, right?
So, that'd be a little more complicated.
I don't know if we want to deal.
That because I don't think the split screens are very good idea, but
something to put in the back of your head, if it comes down to it, we
will have to do more work there.
So, anyway, we'll get the high entity out.
And now we just need to say, all right.
All we need to do now is just take a look at that, that high into DP
and that gives us exactly what we, what we actually want.
There we go, X and I think we also need the low or try the dormant
entity portion to get the
width and the height out, right?
Yeah.
And so again, don't worry too much about what we're doing here.
I'm just playing around with it.
Obviously, there's a bunch of things that are kind of a little messy.
Like, it's like, okay, we have to do two different gathers of memory
to get it, which is not necessarily a bad idea because probably
there's enough that it would be two different cache lines anyway, so
it's not really necessarily big deal.
But again, don't think too hard about it yet.
I just want to see what we have to do.
And then we'll start worrying about massaging.
This sort of thing to make sure that we're not setting up a
performance trap for ourselves.
Later.
We have to optimize this stuff, but for now, don't worry too much
about that because it's not, it's not our primary focus.
Our primary focus right now is to see how we would structure this at
all at the start.
So yeah, so if we're going to fetch all of them, let's say right, then
it would look like this, right.
This is, this is how we would fetch all of them.
So, let's assume we fetch all of them.
It's the doorman entity that has the width, right?
And then we've got sort of anything else.
Do we have anything else on here?
I don't even know what.
Got, let's see, right.
Okay.
So this, this entity stuff.
Now, we actually have to deal with also, because when you put things
in like the get entity stuff, obviously that has to has to know who
it's fetching, whether it's fetching high in, these are low, 80's, or
so on.
In this case.
I feel like what we, what we want is get entity, right?
We want to.
This is really get high entity.
Is what it always is essentially, right?
Oh.
Oh, I'm I'm sensing a.
I'm sensing a fun necklace.
I'm sensing a fun thing.
Okay.
Yeah, I'm liking where this is going.
All right, I'm liking this a lot.
Dude.
Are you with me on this?
I don't know if you guys are with me on this.
Do you does.
Everyone already know what I'm about to do?
I think you already all do so, it's fine, but I kind of got excited
about it there.
So what I just realized,
Is actually, if I basically say that these are flags, right?
Like so then what you could say was just okay.
When I call get entity.
It returns me an entity.
And when I asked for that entity, I can just say, why don't I tell you
right?
What state I wanted the entity in.
So like I want, you know, the state of the entity I can say which
state it is.
And then when it goes to get it, it can move it into the state that it
needs to be and if it wasn't already in that state, right?
So when I call get entity, right, all I have to do is say, okay, when
you call get entity, you tell me what state you wanted, this guy to be
in.
I don't know that.
I maybe I don't actually need those to be flagged because they're I
guess there always
Are always kind of never mind.
I didn't actually need them to be flagged.
That's not true because they're always strictly in order.
So I guess I can still just say, right.
Something like this residence.
So like that.
Okay, so yes, but still everything else still applies.
I can just say, I wanted it at this level of residents and when this
guy goes to get it, if it's not at that level of residents, you can
just move it in.
So that way when we do get entity, right, let's go ahead and do this
here.
What's going on?
There we go.
You switched on me switch back.
Try it again.
Okay, I like it to have it on the right side for some reason which is
bad.
I guess when I guess because it's the the it's closer to my center
line of view.
It really means.
I should move this over here and the mini buffer over here, but it's
like, yeah, you know, it's all complicated anyway, so if I'm going to
go ahead,
And do all this.
Now I have to actually do the porting work to make that happen.
So I have an entity.
I'm going to return that entity structure.
We will then go ahead and give it all of the different portions of
that.
So, entity residents equals residents and we will say, dormant
entities, right?
Lo.
Hi, there we go with that, and that's it.
There we go.
And then I have to say that it's got to be less than the entity count,
right?
You count.
Do I ever try to get an entity?
Who hasn't actually been Inked yet?
No, I don't.
So we're good.
All right.
So then we're calling get entity here again, which residents so
players will always be in the highwomen.
Because they're always on screen or important.
So that's just a given that their goal is going to be high and that's
fine.
So we don't have to set their existence anymore because that's already
handled and now we have this.
So we've got load up P.
So
Right?
And then we've got oh wait.
No, that's dormant.
Sorry dormant .p.
Okay, so that's in the dormant, set their doormat.
I like that.
So that's in the doorman set and then there's
This is also in there set, we go.
And so now the only question is.
When I actually do that sort of.
Initialization, I guess I want to be able to kind of move him up into
that.
I want to map them into the camera space after I set up that that
whole situation.
Mmm.
This is going to be interesting because you see why this is a little
bit complicated.
Once we initialize a player.
I guess, it needs to be wherever the camera was and then that'll be
okay.
And then only be once you move.
So that's yeah, that's actually totally fine.
All right, never mind.
I thought there.
A little bit of an issue there.
So this we're going to have to think about a little bit harder exactly
how we want to do that.
I'm going to go through some more of these and oh, yeah, right.
This is a DOT.
I've messed up my dots in my arrows.
I'd never really no one really knows why see decided, but it was a
good idea to have both of those.
It seems like you always just want that.
I don't know why they did Arrow.
It was a very odd decision.
It doesn't seem sensible.
Anyway, get entity.
So okay in this one.
We're also going to see whether or not there actually was an entity
that the camera was already following and I guess we don't care which
residents that was so it could be dormant for All We Care.
Actually matter, but we just want to see whether or not it actually
existed.
So we just want to say if entity dot residents equals non-existent,
right?
So if it's not existent than we want to start following the first
player, I guess, is what we decided to do.
So, that's fine.
So what we need to do now is we need to map this guy, properly into
that space.
So really, in some sense that's
That's this.
And then after we actually initialize it, we could say, map entity or
set entity residence or something like this right change entity
residents, might be a good name for it, where I basically just passed
that entity and it will go ahead and change it to something that it
isn't already.
So it'll map it from that dormant too high and that will do the
mapping to where the camera, actually, is, right?
So that seems fine.
Let's see.
Identity doesn't really have to do anything other than clear out all
of the state, right?
That was really all, we said that Adam Stephen did was add into T.
Just clears everybody.
So really, we could just say, okay?
If you're going to add an entity, you can you can basically add the
entity as a dormant entity.
So that's just going to be dormant.
These entity index equals nothing low entities and high empties, right
equals.
Nothing like so and then we paste it just set that table.
Our resident stable entity residents, that's going to be equal to.
Oops, that's going to be equal to dormant.
I guess that's how everything gets added probably, right?
And you're done.
So that seems reasonable that totally seems fine so far.
I don't know that we care about any of the rest of this.
Let's see, change.
Yes, we haven't written that yet.
And that's fine.
We want to assert that.
Basically, we are not out of the array range of any of these.
That up.
So it's not underneath my head, change into your residence DP K.
So this will basically just do.
Yeah, it's still going to do what we had before with this.
This could probably pass by value.
Maybe it's quite a few pointers.
I don't know how you want to do that.
But probably we do something like this, right?
So we'd say that entity.
Hi.
So everywhere, we did entity Arrow would now be like probably entity.
Arrow like so and so on.
Yeah, of course.
None of this.
Yeah, none of this is actually really necessary anymore.
Right?
Because, well, first of all, this stuff can just go away.
We don't need any of that anymore because we're not doing things that
way anymore.
And now we also really don't have to do this stuff anymore.
Either.
This is going to be interesting change.
This is going to take a while because we can get rid of a lot of cruft
here.
This will probably have to be a
loop through to tomorrow kind of a change because there's there's a
another easily another whole hours worth of work in here with all the
stuff.
We can change this.
We don't the Collision detector doesn't have to actually do any of
this stuff with the tiles anymore, either because that stuff will get
mapped in to the working set.
Basically.
Yeah, so I'm going to go ahead and, and get rid of this stuff entirely
for the moment.
So that will just basically be old player P.
Hi P there.
Go.
We don't need that at all.
This will just.
So this will just literally be the entity High p is the old player P
and then the DPS and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Yes, everything is.
So I'm just, I'm just eliminating, the tile map position stuff
basically and so the new player P, all that's going to be, is the old
player P.
Plus the player, Delta 0 and we're down to the Q&A.
No.
Oh man.
I was just getting started to well, you know, how it is.
You know how it is.
Sometimes.
You, you run out of time.
You just you run out of time when you're trying to program.
So let's go ahead and sort of clean things up just a little bit.
So we've got change entity residents here.
Right?
Which is going to take that game State and it's going to take an empty
to change D.
And I guess really that's just going to take a an entity index because
that, that one's well, yeah.
So that's like an empty there.
Yes, we'll change it to the residents.
That will go ahead and do that.
And now I just need to see which actually wants to do implement this.
There we go.
And
clean up some of these last little things here.
I would like to get it compiling before we stop if possible, because
that's usually nice.
So this has to be a high entity obviously.
Basically only thing we were working with before where entities that
were would have been high.
We didn't have any doorman entities at all, right?
What's this asking about cannot convert?
Right, put that in the right place.
Glad to again.
See type checking, so good, catch us so many errors, and that will be
like that if the residents equals
not equals assistant.
There we go.
Then I think that's all correct.
Well looks good camera.
Following entity gets gotten this way.
And I guess we don't really care about which one it is, but it should
be high.
I guess we do care because it should always be high at the cameras,
following it.
So, if residents equals non-existence, I want to make an actual check
for that.
I feel like there should just be if exists.
Basically, that seems like a thing that's coming up pretty often.
Let's see, does not have an overloaded member operator.
That's true.
It doesn't.
So that's just a high p.
And the Abbe style Z 0.
Right.
So that's actually dormant the, and this is also a dormant P.
But let's see.
So really this, you know what?
I'm going to if this zero out as well because this can all be done
differently to because now this will all be in the right space to do
fix this to work in camera space.
We won't have to work with tiles there, either.
Yeah.
This is going to be a nice change.
I think this is what I want had been wanting to do, but
I said you kind of got to go in waves that you know that you're not
doing things.
Totally dumb, dumb lie.
Let's see here.
So entity residents, that's this.
Torment entity.
Let's see here.
Dormant into the width and height dormant of T is not 0 because I
spelled it wrong.
Doormat entity.
Well, if we ever have a doormat entity that would be an appropriate
name for it.
Right?
We could have a doormat, something that the player steps on when they
go, you know to house or something like that.
Okay, and let's see.
So that's going to be high in to be facing Direction.
Okay, so that's not going to now.
We've totally regressed.
Our game is totally busted at this point.
So, you know, what can we do?
That's just the way it goes, but at least we're running and that's
fine.
So tomorrow we will go through.
Finish this entire sweep, and I think our code will be in a much
better place there.
It'll be really much simpler to work with now that we've finally done
the change.
That sort of.
I've been saying we should do for a while, but never quite got around
to doing.
So let's go ahead and start the Q&A.
Since we're a little bit over time.
Not too much though only about three minutes.
So that's good.
So, please, if you could prefix your colons with your colons prefix,
your question.
Ins or your colons prefix, your questions with Q: so I can see them.
And if you could
But two things that we've done in today's streamer on previous
streams.
If you have questions that are off topic, save those for free stream,
which just come 15 minutes before the stream starts on any given day.
And I'm here answering all kinds of wacky questions.
How about hot cold and Frozen instead of hi-low dormant?
I don't think Kyle.
Oh, and dormant is great when they're high frequency, low frequency.
And dormant is pretty good.
I think and hot cold, Frozen is if anything worse, I would say.
But that's not to say that I think high-low doorman is great, but I'm
not, I'm not in love with hot cold Frozen.
Are We spelled non-existent incorrectly.
Is that true?
You're right, we did well, you know.
I feel like the key there is, is that
Really you want to make sure that whatever it is.
It can be assigned to a variable.
If there is a variable in, you know, if a variable should ever exist
and stop being non-existent.
It would be important to say the least.
Ah, yes, Tarzan, Charizard's reminded me of something that I asked
specifically on the forums for someone to remind me to do and he
reminded me, whereas its own intrinsics.
So, one of the things that I've been doing periodically, just, we have
imported our code yet to another platform, but other people have, and
I try to make life a little easier for them when we can.
And so what I wanted to do was go ahead and wrap the the
Which these do not exist on other compilers, I guess sometimes,
depending on the platform.
I wanted to go ahead and wrap the rotates instructions because, like
these other instructions are pretty standard C runtime, Library
instruction.
So other people who are pointing to other platforms will have access
to these typically but they won't have say the b can forward on that
we put in here.
And so what I want to do was I'd forgot the done that for the raw and
people were having trouble compiling on.
Other platforms.
I just wanted to go ahead and do that in here.
So
So we don't care what this is at the moment because basically, you
want to actually compile this out to a tour, rotate certainly.
So we'll sort of do a to do Casey.
Find out actually Port this to other compiler platforms.
So, that we actually do get a rotate since anything with x64 should
give us a rotate, right?
That should be there.
I don't know if arm has it or not, but basically anything x64 should
have it so we want to actually go find out what it actually is, but
basically all we have to do now is say well, okay, you know, if the
Mount.
There's there's a couple of weird ways you can do this.
I think you can do like a dual shift that an or kind of a thing, but
I'm just going to do it the straightforward way and we'll see if the
compiler generates hopefully during something smart.
But basically, if the amount is zero, then we'll do.
I'm sorry if the amount is less than 0, because this is
Rotate left, which should rotate, which would move values to the left,
right?
So I guess I should phrase it this way.
If the amount is greater than zero then I believe we want to shift it
up.
Right?
And if the amount is let is not, then we want to shift it down.
I believe that would be the textbook, definition of rotate left.
And in the case of the other way, round.
We just convert them.
So I think that should be correct.
Now, what I will try here, so there's our image.
What I will try here is, I will pound to find compiler msv.
See to be 0, right?
And we will see.
No.
All right, so I'll clearly I did not Implement that quite right.
Let's take a look at that.
Again.
That's pretty funny.
I did say rotate left should rotate up by amount when it's positive.
Should it not?
Is that not right?
Hold on a second.
Oh, you know what though?
Also, I don't know.
Do we ever test our B can forward?
Because I suppose that could be wrong as well.
I don't actually know if that's true.
If want to test result is test.
Let me just let me just verify first before I go to bug those
routines.
Let's actually verify Loops that this isn't broken.
Okay, so that's correct.
So these are not correct it go so I guess my brain is a bit fried.
So if a match is greater than 0 then we should shift it left by the
amount.
I believe otherwise we should shift it right by that amount if it was
- oh, yeah.
Whoops not so much.
Yeah, so obviously if
Amount is - we don't want to try and tell it to do it - shift, which
it can't do.
So we have to negate the amount first.
That's just yeah, that was just dumb.
Yeah, so there we go.
Happy day.
Okay, thank you for reminding me.
We'll get that posted.
So that people won't have trouble compiling anymore.
And, and, yeah, hopefully, that'll make it easier for them to to port
to other platforms without trouble.
Is it a good idea to update the low entities in a separate thread?
I don't know.
I mean, it depends on the target platform.
I don't think so largely because I don't think we're going to be doing
enough, entity work on platforms that have spare threads running
around, to make it necessary.
So, like,
I guess what I would say is.
It depends how many extra threads we have sitting around, not doing
anything.
And I have a feeling that on the kinds of processors that.
Like quad-core or whatever, they're probably so fast that we won't
really need to if that makes sense, but I don't know.
So I assume, we could probably enter, leave it.
And that actually have to do that.
But we could one of the things that we might do is just update, you
know, use threads to update the high entities as well.
Each one can update like chunks of them or whatever.
We could, we could do lots of different stuff.
So we'll see what we do, but it's really not something we need to
think about now.
Have you ever done any big projects in a dynamically?
Typed language?
If?
Yes, how did you handle the refractor without the compiler help?
So I can tell you that actually, it's really a huge pain.
Like I haven't done any really large projects and I know the type of
language, but I did write a pretty big web thing in PHP one time.
And if I remember correctly, there's some typing in that language and
then there's a lot of non typing things like and it was not all just
typing but it was also stuff like things can just come into existence
without like there isn't like a hard notion of whether a variable was
actually declared and stuff as well.
You know, there's a lot of that and it's awful like it really is I
don't have really any good suggestions my
Justin is don't use a dynamically typed language for that reason.
Like Dynamic typing is not necessarily a bad idea its own, but but you
always want to, at least have static typing too.
And so I'm, you know, there's definitely room for dynamic typing and
it can be useful dietary.
So, a useful concept, but man is for doing for doing real programming.
Not having sex height, not having static type, checking to help you
refactor things.
Like the way we're doing here.
Like you said is, is it Sam?
It's a massive speed hit for me and I suspect it is for everybody.
I don't think there's much you can do around it.
So static typing is really, really good for these types of things.
I've noticed some games physics and things break, when the FPS is
increased.
How does that kind of thing happen?
If you don't tie the game takes to frame rate.
What do you tie them to?
So typically, if you have, if you have physics, that is time step
dependent, meaning that it doesn't scale well to larger time steps
then, typically, what?
Well, obviously what some people do is nothing and that's where you
get the breakage that you're talking about.
But what a lot of people will do is they'll
Their physics at a constant time, step always.
So the physics will always run say 60 frames a second or 120 frames
per second.
They'll always do that.
And then all they do is if they have to do a larger frame update, they
will still run the physics multiple times, but they'll just only draw.
Result of having done it multiple times, right?
So that's that's how people usually do it.
I don't love physics as a gameplay thing.
So I tend to not have to worry too much about that sort of sort of
thing.
So I try as much as possible to write things that are capable of
scaling to relatively large time steps.
So, you know, if they can get, they need to go down to 15 frames a
second.
They can.
But I also try to not have frame.
Might be that variable.
So I don't know.
I realize that it becomes a very intractable problem for certain types
of games.
Like big open world 3D free.
Look, moddable, blah, blah, blah.
Like, there's all these things that make it, then you start having to
give up your performance constraints and so on.
But you know, I don't really care that much about those kinds of
games.
So I don't tend to program things looking for that, you know, so yeah,
so I try to just avoid that whole problem, but I don't envy the people
who have to deal with it because it is, it's a heart, it's a
legitimately hard problem.
It's not like the people are just crappy programmers.
It's like, it's legitimately hard.
You have to do a lot of kind of extra work there to make sure that
that sort of stuff doesn't fail physics.
Physics is hard like real physics is
Hard problem.
It's really nasty.
You're just shifting not rotating.
If that's true.
I feel like we name these improperly because we don't actually care
about the rotate.
All we actually care about is the shift by a bio - like being able to
shift by a variable amount.
So we could actually named this something entirely different if we
wanted to, but I'm not sure what we should name it.
Like we don't actually need to rotate if that makes sense, but I could
do I could do the or trick.
If we actually wanted to implement an or here.
I'm if we actually wanted to implement a rotate here, right?
The or trick is escapes me now, but it's like you shift in both
directions and you or it together or something like this, right?
What is the trick?
You know, you don't talk about people out there who are b, b, twiddly,
kind of things, rotate, two shifts.
And and or her can you type something like that into Google?
No, apparently not.
Oh well.
You know what?
I'm talking about there, right?
Hopefully people who know exactly.
Yeah, we could let me I guess I could try to work it out.
You're on the stream.
I'm not the right person for this sort of, this is more of a Jeff
Roberts question, sort of the old bit Shifty tricks.
But okay.
So what do we need to do here?
If we actually want to implement a rotate, which we don't need but you
know, we just said we're going to do it for some reason, right?
Then what we've got is we have some values here, right?
A BB CC DD or something like this and we now want to be able to go
role in either direction.
Right?
And we want the stuff that comes out the top to come back on the
bottom, right?
So, assuming that the number was originally positive, right?
Assuming that we were talking about a positive number.
So let's say we were shifting up by a positive number, right?
Then what we need to do is we would need to say, okay.
Obviously, we just shift this thing up by whatever the positive number
is, right.
So let's say we did it this way BBC.
See I don't know why I'm even why am I even having that many things in
there.
Get rid of that?
A b, c.
D.
E, f.
Yeah.
All right.
So if I shift it up, let's say I shift it up by 2.
So then I have C D E F and I've got two blank spots, right?
And so what I need to do, if I shift it up by 2 is I need to basically
recapture the to top things so that they end up down at the bottom.
So what I need to do is I need to shift this guy.
I need to shift him down so that he lines up here, right?
And obviously that's just however, many bits there were
Which in the case of what we were inputting their with 32, right?
That's how many bits there were - the number here.
So, it's just - this shift.
It's the number of bits - to shift.
It would shift it down and and line up there.
Right?
So if I wanted to actually do the rotate, but I would have to do is
say, okay.
I'm going to shift the value up by the amount and I'm going to or it
with the value shifted down by 32 minus the amount.
I believe that's the
Actual correct version, right?
That's, that's what you would do to, to produce the thing.
Now.
The only thing I don't know about is, do I still need to check for?
What's the what will actually happen if that number is negative?
When we do the shift if the shift is negative.
Then, what happens to this value?
Is my only question.
Because of the shift is negative, then this value will that will shift
out to nothing.
So yes, I don't know that that still works at all.
If the shift value were - because this would shift down by an amount.
That was too high.
Right.
So I feel like we kind of still have to do the check, but maybe I'm
wrong about that.
Anyway, so there's that version and then here's the other version,
right?
This one would shift it down.
On by - the amount and then presumably we would want to do the exact
same thing.
Let's go put this pen down.
So if the amount we're - then we're just shifting down by - the amount
and shifting up by 32, plus the amount, right?
I would assume you like, that's, that's roughly, correct.
And then this other one is just the exact same thing with with
everything reversed.
Right?
That makes sense.
So, so there we go.
Oh, that's going to be that's going to be down and it up and up and
down.
And then I got to actually go test this because I kind of just pulled
that out of nowhere.
So I want to actually see if that that actually does what I expected
to do.
So in order to do that, I'm just going to go ahead and write at the
beginning of handmade dot CPP here.
When we enter the code.
I'm just going to go ahead and call it.
So, structured art for the
In, I'll do a zero.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, right?
We go.
And then I'll do a rotate left left.
We will rotate a and we'll rotate it by, let's say five.
Well, let's just do an even multiple.
So we'll do for and then we'll also do negative 4.
Or just so we can see if that works at all for rotten egg for and then
we'll do the same with, right.
Okay.
So now I'll just step in and see whether the rotation actually works
again.
I don't really know why we're doing this other than for amusement sake
because I guess we named it rotate.
We might as well rotate.
So there's a rotate, the thing we're rotating.
Right.
And let's see if this works at all.
So when we run left, we should get.
Something that slid up and put the, let's see if we rotate left by 4.
Then we should see the top number shift into the bottom and everything
else should shift up.
And that's what happened.
Let's see what happens when we do our Rock left negged for, that
should be the opposite effect, and it is, so that's good.
And then, the rot left for the see.
These should basically be the same, but they should be opposite.
So those should be the same.
Yes, and then rod
For should be the same as the top one.
And it is.
So that looks about, right.
I think, of course, we probably don't handle arbitrarily High values
there because if the values got more than one full rotation, we would
support it.
But that's okay because I suspect that the processor probably would
get mad at us for that as well too.
So, there we go.
We've implanted some rotations.
I'm not sure.
Think that I was wondering is I don't actually know what happens when
you rotate.
I'm just interested to know shift by.
- I don't know what.
I don't know what happens.
If I if I shift by negative 1, I don't know.
Okay, so you basically just it basically, just doesn't even let you
compile it.
I guess undefined Behavior because I don't actually know what would
happen if we actually did that.
So yeah, so we can't actually allow a - go in there.
So I guess that means we have to do and I'm out because we can't pass
a negative value to it.
So unless there's some kind of trick you can use to get around that.
All right.
There we go.
Let's see.
Is there any gameplay reason why we want to keep entities live even
when they are off the screen?
Yes.
So kind of the way I think thinking about this game is I want there to
be a lot of stuff happening around potentially like, oh, you know,
there's a little dude who like goes from place to place.
And so when you happen upon him, he's actually going somewhere.
And not you know, he just was waiting there, dormant the entire time.
So I kind of wanted to minimize the number of dormant entities and say
It's going to be lots of entities that have an agenda or an agency in
the game, just for fun.
Largely.
I don't know that that's necessarily good game design, but it's just
more like it's more programming work that we have to do because it's
way simpler to just sleep.
All the entities all the time when they're not on the screen, and I
wanted to do something harder than that.
Like I said, my goal is to make the game engine for the actual core
gameplay, be way better than most games.
I see, rather than making it less complicated.
I want to make it more complicated so I can show how to handle that
complexity because I think that's interesting for educational.
Mrs.
Is there any reason to do it?
Gameplay-wise not my position to say?
Let's see.
So people on the stream are basically agreeing with me that you cannot
shift by a negative value.
But they were saying that you could do amount equals amount and 31 in
skip conditional and use only amount greater than 0 code.
Is that actually true?
I don't know if I believe that.
because wouldn't that be a very large number if you do amount and 31
that would basically be
Oh, I see what you're saying.
No, that doesn't make good sense, I guess.
They were saying, basically, if I could do this.
Right, then that would basically eliminate.
All of the values that were going to be greater.
Like so we know that we can only rotate within that range.
So then we know that we would only be doing rotations that actually
work though.
I don't know.
I don't know if I I don't super understand that yet.
I'm trying to think of whether that's, let's see what happens.
Let's go back to the white board.
This was basically to people on the street were talking about how to
avoid.
Because memorize asking just moments ago.
How do you avoid the conditional?
Right?
And I sing, I think there was a trick for up.
I wasn't sure.
So what they were saying is well, what you could
Do is you could and with 31, right?
And what 31 is right, is that the five bottom bits are set, right?
So that's that's these bits are set.
And then all the rest are not right.
So that would be anything up to 32 not inclusive would basically be
represented in there.
And so if it was a negative number, right, then you would end up with
these being.
It would it would since its two's complement.
It would still be all of these would be set if it was negative 30.
One, right?
And if any of them weren't set would decrease downwards to - right 29
- 28 and so on.
So that's kind of cool.
I think I kind of like that.
Right?
So basically, this knocks out the part that wouldn't work and it turns
it into a properly unsigned number that actually does the shift that
we want it to do because of the fact that we're doing both shifts
anyway, so in theory,
See here in theory.
I think we could do something like this.
If I understand, if I understand their suggestion correctly, so let's
take a look.
Pound Define to Pilar MSC and there we go.
Okay.
First of all, do we even run?
Yes, we do.
So now let's go ahead and step in and verify that that actually still
works.
Okay.
Lovely.
Well, that's very nice.
Okay.
Thank you stream.
That is a good.
That is a good trick.
All right, so I think that's about it.
I'm going to go ahead and delete this test code for our rotate there.
This as well.
So, we're back to actually using the actual rotate instruction down.
Okay.
All right.
I think we're just about out of time, as well.
It's 9:27.
I guess we have time for probably one more question.
If there is another question on the stream, looks,
Everything is is pretty much.
Like I said, it's where a little bit broken because we had to remove
some features and we're going to have to go ahead and put the back in
tomorrow because obviously, we ran out of time to do all the cleanup
that I wanted to do, but we'll do it tomorrow and it'll be good.
And and so yeah, we'll leave it like that but doesn't look like
there's any more questions as far as I can tell.
Anyone questions, no questions.
All right, then I guess we're done.
I guess the stream has ended, and I will go ahead and close it down.
There we go, and we'll sort of prepare ourselves for success by
clearing carita.
Here we go.
And okay.
All right.
Well, if there are no other questions, and I think there aren't
519 lat.
Yes, the Jesus asked me if the Anthony one thing will work for
negative values.
Yes.
That's exactly what it is for basically.
All that does is just knock out the actual - part of the negative
number and turn it into a small number between 0 and 30.
One that happens to invert properly if it was a negative number
originally so that the shifts do the right thing kind of a wacky idea
basically, but you know, that's how those kind of bit twiddling
things.
Tend to be I got to remember to fix this because it ends a minute
early, right?
So everything's one minute early right now because it's a yeah, it's a
little premature.
I got to go fix that.
But anyway, thank you very much for joining me for another edition of
handmade hero.
I'm glad we started to do some cleanup work today, on our entity
architecture.
I think that's going to be really nice to kind of be in a place where
we know that, we're either in float, or in tile space.
And we can kind of compartmentalize those two and not have to deal
with it anymore.
So that'll be kind of nice.
But still have all of the niceness of being able to have a giant
world.
I think that's, you know, going to be a good trade-off and I said
there's a couple weirdnesses there.
Specifically what happens when you're talking about people who are
looking at other entities that maybe aren't actually in the high space
and so on.
So there's, there's some weirdness is that I got to think about
exactly how we want to deal with.
But hopefully they'll all kind of work themselves out relatively
cleanly, so hopefully you'll join me tomorrow, same time.
Same place 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time.
Right here on Twitch.
When we will finish that.
Up and get things running very nice and smooth.
I hope if you would like to follow along at home.
You can pre-order the game comes with the source code so you can
download it every night after I finish.
I upload the latest source code to send out and you can use the link
to get your email to download it every day.
That's a great way to follow along at home and kind of just play
around the code in.
It's just it's a lot of fun and it's easy.
It's pretty easy.
Once you get it set up to just kind of grab the changes every night
and play around with them.
if you'd like to support the series, we do have a patreon, you can
subscribe to and if you're trying to learn and follow along with
Serious day-to-day, we have a news and Forum site.
That's pretty handy.
It's got the schedule for the week.
Posted every Monday.
It's got an episode guide so you can catch up on old episodes.
It's got a coding resources page where people have done ports to like
mac and Linux.
It's got code discussion where you can go and post.
It's like a forum.
You can go and post questions and talk with our people and so it's
just it's pretty handy.
I highly recommend checking it out if you try to learn from the
stream, so thanks everyone and hopefully I will see you tomorrow.
Have an excellent Tuesday.
If for some reason I do not
Not take it easy, everyone.