Pat is the person who I have the most notes for and I pretty much
looked at.
I just like, we're never going to get through all this.
So we'll do our best.
But we really do need all of the time.
And so on handmade here, one of the things that I get asked all the
time, like, all the time is about Network programming and people are
like, are we gonna do networking ever going to networking?
And my answer is always no, we're not going to networking because I am
like the last person you should ask about Network programming.
Like I've literally never shift a piece of code in anything that does
networking.
Like my my experience and everything is like in
Colonel tools only and I shudder to think what would have happened to
these tools?
If they had been deployed in the wild, I'm sure they would break like
immediately.
And so what I wanted to do for this session was to sort of get the
person who I thought knew absolutely the most about game networking to
sort of fill that in in, whatever we can do in an hour to sort of
answer those questions where it's like, everyone wants to know more
about this.
So maybe I felt like we could get a perspective on.
So Pat Wyatt is somebody who's
Look, I think I said this on the actual diagram, he is the person I
think of who had the only Network game that like, shipped with like,
no problem somehow, like, it was like, perfect and that was Guild
Wars.
And it was just this, it was this, like, amazing feat of engineering
that it actually had the launch that it did and, and because,
basically everything else at that time were just like, oh yeah, the
day that they launch the game, like World of Warcraft, and the server
immediately goes down or whatever else happened.
And so I was like, he had plenty of experience with it working on
previous titles on Warcraft.
Don Diablo and then when he went to do Guild Wars that was kind of
like the nth generation of his Network coding.
So I was hoping I could sort of get at some of that knowledge and have
him.
Give us an overview of like what does it take to ship these games that
are played by like you know literally millions of people and how do
you go about designing it?
So please give a warm welcome to mr.
Pat Wyatt.
All right, so give people some context here because this was something
that that I was kind of curious about as well.
Like the first Network game you worked on, was it Warcraft?
No, actually, it was there one before the battle chess.
So I poured it down your chest.
From there's a Dawson Amiga version and I did Windows 3.0 version.
I was on modem, of course.
Okay.
So this is a modem version of battle.
Chess was your first experience with network programming, that's
right.
Okay.
So Warcraft was actually like, a second-generation thing.
In some sense, you'd already have some experience and this was
For the internet, for the most part was used in gaming, I believe,
right is very local network only.
So, tell me a little bit about that development process.
Like, what was it?
Like, you know, how did you guys go about doing that, that Network
development?
So because I can't I don't even know like what was involved at that
time.
Yeah.
Well, so because the internet didn't exist, I sort of had to invent
the whole idea of how this would be done whole cloth.
And one of the first, you know, immediately obvious things was we had
about, I think 600 units that were going to be running around in the
game.
And when I saw,
Third working out the math of like.
Well, if every unit
Sending its orders of what it's doing all the time.
There were just going to totally saturate, our 2400 baud, modem 2400
baud modem.
That's right.
Okay.
And so it was immediately obvious.
It was an impractical solution to try and send what each unit was
doing.
And so like, I'm not sure exactly how I came up with it but I figured
out what I would do is instead just send the process user input.
So when the user clicked on a map like then I would send while he
clicked here and you know, had these units selected, go tell those
units to do that and so both.
Both computers would work in lockstep with each other, so that you
only had to send the process input which is very, very tiny.
In fact, you can fit, you know, like 300 baud modem or something.
We do the job.
And so for those synchronous models, right?
Obviously, the latency becomes a bit of an issue potentially?
No.
I mean, like so, so how did you guys?
I mean, work obviously being a real time strategy game isn't the most,
which oriented but it's still real time response.
So how did that play out in the cold?
So actually, it's really interesting.
So RTS is by and large are not very Twitchy because
Happens is you're busy giving so many different orders at the same
time that you don't really need to see the action take effect
instantaneously.
So in the single-player version, there's actually no delay.
You click on unit and immediately it starts executing the action.
But in the multiplayer version we have like a, I mean, it's a tunable
parameter for some of the earlier games, and we just set it to a
hard-coded value in later versions.
But basically you say, you go to this and it's like, yes, my liege.
And then it starts going, right?
And it's because like, what happens is you send the order out and you
have several packets in flight and, you know, everybody's got these
packets and flight all the time.
And so it takes a while for that to get to the other side.
And then you're, you know, you might get the packet early but you
don't start processing that packet until it's time for that packet to
happen.
And so they're sort of like this long queue of like I think 400
milliseconds before your actions need to take effect.
And if it doesn't get there by then then the game will it will still
allow you to to
You know click buttons and do things but really the simulation has
stalled out in the units.
Stop moving internet.
So like, you know, you start getting packets again from all the
players.
So, sort of the architecture of that original Warcraft.
Networking model was something like I have a queue of user input
basically.
And they might just be doing a bunch of stuff and it's getting stacked
up and it really, I start sending it out until I get confirmation back
that the next sort of, like, step has occurred.
I can't actually pull anything, you know, I can't actually consider
one of these
UI options executed.
So I'm just kind of trying to buy time until that happens.
Is that right?
That's where just wait until I get package from every single player in
the game and it's, you know, scales naturally 2228, players and
Warcraft 2.
Yeah, and Starcraft and as soon as you've got everybody's packet, then
you can execute the turn.
Although you generally wait until it's like, you know, enough time has
elapsed.
So I think we're doing like four turns for Network turns per second in
Warcraft one.
So basically what happens is all of the people send sort of
I guess what I'm what I'm what I'm hearing you say there.
Which is not sort of the way I was picturing it when you first set it.
So there's basically
We like fixed slices of time these 400 milliseconds, like you said, it
was a tunable parameter, there's fixed slices of time.
And basically, everyone is going to get to make a move in that time.
And that move, maybe I didn't make a move, but everyone's going to get
to send what their move was.
And if I don't hear from anybody, we just keep running out the clock.
If we don't hear from everybody in that time or that's right, for the
next couple seconds.
Like I'll still take input on your local client side and then after
like if I haven't heard from anybody from, I'm just going to guess
like five seconds then.
I actually gray out the screen so you can't do anything because
clearly we now have a central issue and so people get the idea that oh
I'm not an able to do anything.
So that's pretty interesting that I guess in that sense that's a
pretty clean division of the networking code from everything else to.
It's like it can almost exist in a vacuum because as long as you
really the only thing I guess that you need from the game at that
point is the ability to not, you know, the ability to just not execute
something, but that should be pretty easy.
Because if the user is not doing anything, it doesn't execute
something.
That's right.
Okay, so that's that's actually kind of cool.
So, and I would say like, it would be really nice.
Yes.
It could be so easily isolated and everything.
But if you're doing the code, you go like, where is it?
It's everywhere.
It's spread out.
Oh, really?
Yeah, the first Warcraft was a mess.
Okay, okay, so was that, is that, but that would be something that is
fixable meaning.
The, the integration into it isn't necessary at, just how it happened,
organically occurs.
That's right.
I was ganic is a good word for that, okay?
But you know, it was my first like original development project, so I
had to learn along the way.
Yeah.
Okay.
So moving forward.
I guess then for like Warcraft 2, for example, same sort of thing.
Yeah, like really not a whole lot had to change.
You know, there are a lot of data structures that just assume two
players and so they're just be Boolean values for them and then it's
like well we're going to date players.
Now what we can pack eight players into one bite because just one bit
flag for each entry.
And so it was really more, a failure of vision that Warcraft to
Warcraft.
One didn't have more players in it.
It's like, okay, do two players.
Oh my gosh, that's a lot.
You know, we could have done more but we're thinking about modem clay,
I say I see and then by that time into kind of gotten a little bit
better in terms of what it could support.
And how many people I guess with Warcraft?
You learn what people might want to do, which is play a player games
or other things like this.
That's right.
Okay, so from there, the next title is sort of drastically different.
I guess is my understanding.
So you then did the networking layer for Diablo which is you did the
part where it's the actual in-game networking layer, right?
I guess someone else was friends with a Battlenet back.
Back and sort of system.
That's right.
So Diablo is not synchronous in this way.
Is that correct, right?
So Diablo is actually developed by another company that was acquired
by Blizzard.
Entertainment was a bunch of guys, Condor and they had this great idea
like Diablo is their idea.
And when we heard about it, we're like, this is awesome.
We need to be doing this game with them, but they were making a single
player, Single Character game and we convinced them that they should
do multiplayer.
Oh, and eventually, when we come in to do the multiplayer, they're
like we want it to be turn-based multiplayer.
No, no.
It's got to be real time, okay?
So we, you know, when we convinced him to do that, it's like, okay, so
go do that.
And then like they really needed some help to get it done.
And so, I actually flew up there with a plan to go and figure out how
to help them.
It was going to be a synchronous Network model like similar to
Warcraft.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Because I'd only done that and it would prevent cheating.
And, you know, I look at the code.
It's like, you know, it's going to be really hard to back in a
synchronous system into a game.
That's already been written.
And like, doesn't really have like the data constructs where it's
thing.
About like, let's keep the server stuff over here, you know, like the
simulation stuff over here and the game stuff over here is all just
intermixed and this is, what did you see out the window and wrote a
different network model.
So when you say that you kind of mean that my representation for a
particular object in the world in something like Warcraft is a little
more split in terms of like explain a little bit more.
What you mean by, you looked at the code and found something you
didn't expect in terms of that welding.
Sure.
So if you're doing a network simulation, you want to ideally have all
your network data structure separate because they're going to get mud.
I'd only when packets show up that should be affecting that data and
your simulation data.
I mean, I'm sorry your user interface data is probably going to be
separate because like you know, I'm tweaking things.
I have a status bar updates for these units, there's lots of stuff
that the network code and the client code are going to have that are
different because of the time that that changes, right?
The simulation can only change one packet show up and the client did a
contingent Centennial soon as I click the mouse and a keyboard and
things.
And so in something like Warcraft,
To where you'd already had some experience with it.
You guys had sort of gotten to the point where you were already
dividing the codebase up into this way, I guess it's sort of thing,
but when you went to their code base that's you know it was all still
kind of intermixed.
Yeah.
Also the other factor is when you're doing synchronous lockstep games,
the problem is you cannot have any coding errors because if you if
you've played one game already and you've initialized your some of
your internal State variables slightly differently than mine.
I'm playing my first game then, you know, you do a command and it
doesn't behave exactly the same on your system as
On my system and the games desynchronize and we always disconnect
because we don't know what else to do.
So basically there's a Divergence there because of some state that was
not cleanly initialized, that's right.
And so you have to exceptionally careful and it's just ridiculous how
hard this is.
Right.
Like you know accidental pointer use of after the point has been freed
or uninitialized variables or you know, static variables that don't
get reinitialized, right?
Lots of things can really impact this and so it takes a long time to
find these bugs to, and, like, Diablo was written in haste, and it
just
We have the same level of like carefulness with with respect to
variables and so there was just no way to do a synchronous lockstep
game with that.
And so, what was your approach then?
So you decide to change things up, you're like, we're gonna have to do
something different.
What was that thought process?
Like?
Because you said, you came up with their other plan and now the plan
is gone, right?
Right.
So I came up with a plan in like a day and it's what I call like
asynchronous Loosely coupled game.
Okay, so we're all playing sort of the same game but not exactly.
Okay.
So you happen to be the first person to get onto like level one of the
game and so you're not
Master for that level and when I come to the game, come down to that
level of the game.
So for people haven't played Diablo like you to 16 level dungeon and
you know, there's a master for each level.
Okay?
So I get in the master is whoever happens to load up that level first
some way.
How do we know that because it's Network?
So, I don't know who loaded first.
Well, like, you created the game, okay?
And then I join into your game, okay?
And so, like, you have the authority to like, you know, you're the
first person on like level 0, the town level, okay?
And then you go down to level one.
No.
And then when I join your game you see that I go down to level 2 first
and so you're like okay you're the master for level 2 and as long as
I'm in the game, I'm the master.
I was a Dropout then, there'd be no master or argument you can say
like, you know, any of them could pick up the master position.
So let's just drill down that for one second.
So that's sounds like sort of a consensus problem across these
clients, though.
Because like, when I say, I see that you drop down to level of to
First, how do I know like how do I know that?
I've seen that, at the
Time or how does another client know, like, is there some kind of
centralized like the person who owned level 0 is the person who
decides who owns level 1 or how does that?
Like because I mean in networking, things can come in at any time and
you never really know who said what Wet Brush.
Right?
So the, like the person who created the game is, sort of like the
Arbiter of who is the level Master for each lot.
Okay.
And then if that player drops out, then the next player who came into
the game was, you know, and like they just increasing sequence.
I see numbers.
Okay, so basically the person who started the game, they are the
master and
They will be periodically.
Sending out a list of who's in the game, in your order in that, where
they are first and the next person, second third is like the order
will go through to keep trying to play this game.
If something bad happens kind of a thing.
That's right.
Okay, so you are the master of the game, I go to level 2 and your and
you tell me, okay, your level Master for to until a great.
I get to initialize everything myself and tell people what's going on
on that level.
I see.
And then after that point, so now I've taken over ownership of level 2
and I'm like, you know, I'm picking up things and dropping them and
I'm telling all the other players.
Yeah, I picked up this item, drop this item.
So if I drop
The game.
And then we need a new level to master than somebody else.
Can pick it up and I can sort of apply all the knowledge of what
happened there.
Previously, like there's dead monsters here and this this Treasurer
and has been, this Treasure Chest has been broken open, then they can
reapply all those rules so that the world seems consistent, I see it.
So they kind of keep a buffer of.
Here's all the stuff I've been told about level 2, even though I
myself am not actually keeping a representation of level to you.
That's right.
So at that time, if we do need to do like basically a failover or
something like this or if
I come on to level 2, I guess would be another case where I just am
starting to look at level 2.
I'm going to go in and take this buffer that I've been recording of
everything that I've been told about level 2.
And I'm going to replay it that's in order to get my level 2 to that
state.
That's right.
And there are lists may not match up exactly because of, you know,
hacking or things like that.
And so it's that's why I call it Loosely coupled because we're really
playing two games that are nearly identical, but it's obviously very,
very cheap table.
And so what happens now, as the game is being played, two of us are
both on the same level and we're doing stuff.
What is that?
Networking process?
Like one person is the master for the level and then we have n number
of other people who are sort of getting you know information about it.
But what does that actually look like?
Yeah.
So we're all broadcasting messages to all the other players saying you
know, this is what happened.
So like I pick up, you know, sword and I start, you know, I tell all
the other players have that sort of now gone.
And so you can have a race condition for that.
Yeah.
And we just sort of arbitrate it like you know the level Master gets
to make the determination of who actually got that.
So
Basically, two people, you know, in their separate, copies of this
game, they both go to pick up the sword, right?
And they both think that they've picked up the sword, so they send out
the packet.
I picked up the sword.
Well, more like I am attempting to pick up the sword.
Okay, so there's actually a like a two-stage process.
I'm attempting to pick up the sword to packets come in.
You know, we can't really tell who maybe was doing it first or
whatever.
So, the level Master goes, I see two people trying to pick up the
sword and I decided to break this tie.
However, I decided to break it.
Any particular Nuance of that?
Or it's like there's really no, it's pretty straightforward.
It's whoever got it first.
And of course, if you can
Master you're always going to be faster because it's not.
Okay and so that and that is that roughly the way that most things in
the game works.
So if I try to attack somebody, is it a similar two-stage process?
I'm trying to attack this person and then the level Master
acknowledges it and only once you've knowledge is it, do I actually
see the attacker?
Or is it more asynchronous than that, in that?
I see the attack occurred, either way, but maybe the damage goes back
up later.
If it turns out, it didn't acknowledge, like, you know what I'm
saying?
Like, in terms of like,
Like, how does that work out when when we're actually doing other
sorts of things besides something as discreet as picking up the sword,
right?
So it's really loose.
So like you go and attack a monster on your system and you kill him
and you decide that he's dead.
And then you let me know that he's dead, okay?
I'm the level master and I go.
Okay, great.
Okay.
Yeah so I mean it's really possible to cheat very easily right now you
can just kill anything as fast as you want and that isn't really.
But I mean, ignoring the cheating part of it, in terms of actually
keeping the stuff working.
The actual game, it's not really necessary to do anything beyond that.
Meaning, if a bunch of people who are all trying to play the game,
legitimately not hacking it, not trying to do anything weird.
Then Simply Having the clients announce when they did something.
And if two people say that they killed, the monster doesn't matter
because like the state just goes to Dead.
And so it's fine that country where the only area of contention is in
picking up things off the ground, okay?
Or like breaking open a chest like you know, even that doesn't because
chest is broken open.
Both players might have done it at the same time but it
it leads to like things popping out on the ground that you can pick up
that are the areas that you fight over.
So the only because and is that because things like damage are just
numbers that go down.
So if I get to people who say they did damage, I just apply them both
or like, like what's the is that?
Just because picking up is the one thing where it's like there was
only one item and we need to know who had it kind of a thing.
Exactly.
Okay.
All right.
So I think that's pretty good.
Fundamentals of trying to think if I missed anything of the sort of
you miss one thing, don't do a game like this, okay?
Why not?
Because people will cheat.
And in fact, the thing that happened was, you know, Diablo came out
and people really love the game.
And a lot of clear players had fun is particularly when they played
with their own friends, but as soon as you played out there in the
larger universe, there are just lots of people who were griefing and
in fact, you know, it was really startling to me because, you know,
I'd played muds before and things like that and occasionally there's
Griffin.
But usually you had like a GM's, it would oversee things like
volunteer GM's, it's sort of like make sure that people weren't
complete asshole, right?
But so, like a couple days after we shipped Diablo, like there's
As a friend of the company who came in and he was playing in an office
adjacent, me I got him Yash and he's just like, going Dungeons and
he's killing people because he's a much higher level than them.
There's nothing that they could do about it.
And like, so, you know, all their armor and swords and everything pop
off on the ground.
And then they get real reincarnated in town and they come down and
dungeon naked and try and recover the stuff.
He kills again and again, in this was at your own company, taunts
them.
Well, he was actually just a friend of somebody work.
Okay, just a friend.
Okay.
And I was like, I watched him, you know?
And I realized that this was a microcosm of stuff.
Going to happen, right?
So like I didn't see all the features a like you shouldn't do this or
anything like that.
Instead of like let me understand this and that's really my first
serious experience with Griefers.
And I mean, it was shocking at that time and now, like every game I've
ever designed since, you know, I have to think about like, how are
people going to hack this and how are people going to, you know,
especially abuse others which is in some ways even worse than hacking.
Yeah well okay so that's actually kind of fascinating so moving
forward I guess the next one you did was Guild Wars.
Yes source of tin in goers.
Okay so you
The network on Starcraft as well.
Yeah, it was.
A lot of the same stuff.
Was that asynchronous?
Or is that synchronous.
Was that more like?
The warcraft - like Warcraft.
Okay.
Just like Warcraft it.
So after Starcraft, you go to start Guild Wars and I remember Guild
Wars was particularly impressive to me because like, I remember like
the download to download Guild Wars was like this little tiny thing.
Right there was some kind of like little tiny executable and it just
like took care of everything from there and all this sort of sorts of
stuff.
That's pretty was a 200k executor K.
And so the challenge was it was so small that people
Click on it and download and it would go so fast.
It'd be like, did that work?
So I think we should make it bigger.
We had a padded out just to make sure they can see the progress bar.
It's right.
So Guild Wars is in some ways a lot more ambitious than Diablo.
Because this now is sort of designed up front to have a lot of the
permanence may be backed up by where authenticated sorts of things.
I guess this comes out of your experience with the griefing on Diablo.
I guess is that without fear and also
the desire to have an online economy.
Okay.
Okay, so this one, I guess I got kind of a list of things to drill
down in here.
But before I may be asked any of those questions?
Can you give me B people?
A brief understanding of what was involved in making Guild Wars happen
because it's both.
It's got about the persistence day and it's got a peer-to-peer thing
happening.
And those things interact.
And there's just, I remember you sent me an email where you're like,
here's all the servers we wrote for Guild Wars and there was like 12
or something.
List.
So can you just give a brief just high-level explanation of what was
involved in?
Just, just the basic architecture of this shirt.
So first, it was not a peer-to-peer game at all.
It was a client-server only.
So, so even when people are playing inside their own, when they would
kind of Spawn off the dungeon, that was still always round trip
through a separate server.
That's right.
Okay.
Sorry.
Fully server hosted.
So the very first thing you do is you connect to the server and say
hi.
I'm Gilbert version zero because you've got this 200k stuff and it's
like oh you need version 53.
Here you go.
Download you reboot the game engine.
Hey, I'm version 53, which one to get?
Okay, great, you're up to date.
Here's the manifests, for every single piece of data in the whole
world.
Okay?
You know, and you download that file and then you say, well, I want to
go to login screen.
Give me all the files.
I need for that and you download those and you know, progressively you
start accumulating all the files you need.
So that you never actually have to download the entire roughly at that
point.
3 gigabytes of data you could just download the the tiny portion that
you need.
This was actually sort of like an on demand package manager.
You basically had it.
We have a dependency system, we know everything in the world and what
it depends on.
So when the game starts up, it just kind of asks for some kind of like
a root object for was trying to do.
Like I'm trying to go into this dungeon so I need you know I asked for
that and then it starts pulling in things we're like okay.
Now I'm going to ask for this and that pulls in more things.
These get downloaded into sort of a cash on the drive.
That's right, okay?
And those are marked in some way to tell whether they're stale in case
they're updated or does that ever happen.
Every file effectively is an ID number
So there's both the the identity for it and the version number okay
and so you can you can know whether you're up to date on the file and
so if it turns out that you're out of date, you can say I have version
17 of the warrior armor and it goes.
Oh, and if you look at it manifest, it's like, oh, I need version 19.
So you say to the file server, you know what 19 have 17 and it loads
up with those files, Delta compresses them seriously ill actually
Delta's them, then it compresses them and sends you down that small
chunk because this was 2005, when we're doing this actually 2002 when
we are writing
Code for it.
And you know like bandwidth was much lower than it is today.
So we had to make everything as small as possible.
Otherwise we've been hours and hours and hours before you can get in
the game.
That's awesome.
Okay.
Soso you on-demand Delta compressed, the difference between the
version they have and the version they need and send only the Delta
Down, correct?
That's like better than most internet infrastructure.
Probably.
It's everywhere in the world right now.
But okay, so going back to sort of the that sort of process of dancing
is right?
You said the ID number and the
It's both the ID anniversary.
You mean they're they're together or the ID is somehow intermixed with
the versus just two separate pieces of data ID and version or right?
So okay yeah.
So every file has a base ID, which is the very first file number that
was assigned to it when the asset was created.
So, you know, I create a texture.
It's like, well, you just have an even number three, right?
And so, and I can forever more.
I can refer to that texture as three, but now it has different version
numbers.
So like, you know, it's also file 17 and filed 28, you know, every
time the artist changes it, that texture gets a nice a number of with
it and so I always
Food made by the base idea and I look in the Manifest for it.
And looks like for the Bayside III.
The current version is 781.
I say I need 781 and I have three or 17 or whatever the previous
version.
And so sorry, this is just kind of fascinating science is not
technically that was a my life so I don't know.
Okay, so and just one other question about that, I guess because we
sort of talked about this with when we're talking about Super Meat Boy
as well and what Tommy was doing and it's just kind of fresh in my
head.
Like, how do you assign this?
These IDs to things that artists make because but, you know, by
definition, an artist is not, somebody who goes and knows what am a
CID necessarily is.
So how does that process work?
I'm somebody who needs to add, you know, a texture to Guild Wars.
Is there a server that you query or there too?
Like what just give me just a quick idea of what that looks like?
So we're easing / forces are revision control system so they check the
file into perforce and then there'd be some way that that file was
referenced.
So perhaps there is a model file, okay?
And the model file, you know, using 3ds Max refers to this texture
file by name, okay?
And so
And in that model file is reference Center.
Level file.
Okay.
I mean it's a it's a tree since that seems to be the model for today
and then the you know, the level file contains a bunch of different
Assets in it.
And then the level file is actually referenced in some source code
like this is level 13 of the game or this is like the Lion's Arch
Outpost, okay?
And so what happens is, there's a tool FS bill that goes through and
it picks up all the code references to assets, and it's like, okay,
let me load this little file.
And then, we look at the dependencies, it says, oh, it's got a model
file in it.
Let me let the modify a little bit.
Look at all the dependencies.
Oh, it's
A texture file only load that textures don't have any dependencies.
Okay, so now I can process that file that file is now file ID 3
because it's the third file.
It was never processed, okay?
And that whole stack gets processed up into the piece of data that's
actually referenced.
That's right.
So the textures aren't represent reference separately or they are they
can be referenced separately.
That's right, so it processes and saves file 83 in this big giant, you
know, data?
Well you can think of as a database of files that's like more or less
every every
Version of a file back, say 90 days or something.
Okay?
And so when you're doing that, how can you tell that that, you know,
I'm an artist.
I made a new version of this texture.
How did the does it correlate?
Those is it just use the path, the full file path in perforce as the
thing that it knows it seen this before.
So like, you know, that thing kind of tracks those and can associate
the IDS internally with that that perforce path or that's right?
So FS Bill loads up all the assets and creates
His graph of everything.
And then, like he goes, oh well, that file hasn't changed, I don't
have to do anything for it.
Right?
So it because it has lots of metadata associated with the whole
process, so it knows when files were last touched and and, you know,
if something breaks it can like knows which artist check that file in.
Maybe that's not the reason why it broke right?
Because it be the programmer change some code, which caused the all
their files to break.
Okay.
All right.
Sorry, that was a bit of a rattle.
I just was kind of cured.
I wanted to know how to about that system, because it's pretty
interesting.
Okay.
So, going back to the networking part.
Things.
So, essentially you've got this system where it sounds like there's
already kind of one server that we've already sort of talked about
what it is which is like we need something that's sitting there
running that has every version of every asset that we've ever shipped
on it, which can answer this question, right?
And presumably, we need more than one of these because everyone's
getting the data from this.
So how does how does talk a little bit about how that one?
Sure.
So we have lots of these file servers all over the world.
So Guild Wars is kind of unique in its era for being a game that had
no monthly fee.
And so we couldn't have lat.
Of servers to do all the stuff we need to be extremely efficient in
the way that we did everything.
So we wrote everything from scratch because there weren't tools that
would do like this, Delta compression Zone.
But so we have lots of file servers out there and they're spread out
all over the world and it's kind of interesting.
Why if you connect to a really long distance TCP server, what happens
is there's this thing called the TCP window and so I send you a few
messages and you send me back a bunch of stuff.
But you're as a server you're like I'm not going to send you more than
64k of data because I don't want to flood out the internet and
Tool that 64k of data gets acknowledged.
I'm not going to send you more stuff so you can only have at most 64 K
beta outstanding and when you say server, who do you mean, because
you're going to roll it in this case, the file server, okay?
So it only sends 64k of data, you've set that up.
You put the so the TCP stack just be said, like the window size is 64
K.
And so until we negotiate a bigger window size, that's as much as
it'll send in Windows of that era like you had really limited ability
to control TCP parameters so you couldn't especially on the game
client, right?
Because, you know, you can't go and hack people's registry.
I see you nowadays.
I guess you can possibly set those options dynamically in code but
then you could.
Yeah.
But even then like it, like Windows XP.
You have to reboot really?
Yeah.
Okay.
All right, so keep going.
So you're about to say there is problems with this, right?
So what you want to do is instead of instead of trying to get stuff
from a really long distance away server where like 64k, you know, you
send it and then there's a long pause before the acknowledgement comes
back and so you're not constantly filling yes the Stream.
So you want to have the file server, really close to people so that
you can send a lot of data more quickly.
So, the instead of the delay being the limiting factor instead, it's
the size of the channel being the limiting factor and we stand with,
you can send is that like work around, double meaning like let's say I
actually only had one file server, it sounds like that's / TCP
connection.
So in theory, could a client, be written to open multiple TCP
connection to the server, so that it can start multiple 64k chunks in
parallel.
But you decided
I did not to do that.
I guess that's right.
You certainly could do that, but what we did is we just distributed
servers all over the world like we had them in Japan, Taiwan Korea to
data centers in the US and a data center in Europe, okay?
That was enough to do the job.
Okay.
How about Missouri's race?
I mean, Australian uses had to suffer but we just couldn't afford it.
But service there.
Okay, fair.
Yeah.
And so we just had lots of those servers which creates another
interesting problem which is whenever you want to do a build you have
to make sure that every server has all the data before you can really
say that the build is truly live.
So it's a distributed.
Database.
Commit problem.
How did you handle that?
It's actually fairly straightforward.
It's like, okay, everybody got the data, everybody.
Everybody ready, ready?
Go.
And then afterwards, you're like, okay, did anybody get it?
Okay, we're good.
Right?
And then if one of them didn't get it then you keep crying again.
And again just like get it, get it, get it and eventually he wakes up.
Yeah but you wait until everybody's got all the data and then you try
and commit the metadata on all the systems simultaneously and there's
only like twice in five years that ever failed.
And
Wow.
Okay.
And that's so my failed in a way that require human intervention.
These are database.
When you say database, are you talking literally about something that
you guys wrote or you talking about?
Okay, so basically it's not like we installed my SQL or something.
It's like we wrote this thing from scratch to do exactly this job of
serving the art assets.
That's right.
Okay, yeah.
And in fact, like it's embedded in the Guild Wars client.
When you see the g w dot dot file, it sort of the database file
format.
We use for everything and what kind of load were these servers under
Like what what were they designed to serve, basically, how many people
updating and how much traffic we do?
You have any kind of just to give people a ballpark?
There weren't that many of you said six or seven?
Something it sounded like there were six data centers six days.
But like within each data center, there were lots of these file
servers, okay?
So you just duplicate the file servers.
Many times you needed to, for the load in that area.
That's right.
How much would one typically handle?
Do you think or is it?
So each one would saturate like it's Uplink at about 400 MB, okay?
And they just run like 400 MB sustained load during Peak.
I'm so the majority of your actual the thing that actually prevented
you from serving more stuff on a particular server was actually just
the outflow pipe.
It was actually a combination of factors so it's file.
Servers are actually really fascinating is like really easy to do
things wrong but there are some things there's like, how much the
network card could push onto the network?
We're using blade servers and so blade servers unlike you know,
individual pizza box, servers blade, servers have a shared network or
in that?
They had like a shared network like infrastructure for the entire row
of 14 blade servers.
Okay?
So you could saturate, that would be a problem if you had to spread
your file servers out.
So they can all be in the same rack, they had to be different racks.
My God, the other thing is that the amount of data that we're sending
is very large.
And so these servers all had only two and a half gigs of memory, you
know.
Okay.
You've got a subtract out some for the operating system and stuff like
that so you could have about a gig and a half of cash which you've got
to have enough space left over for like load file a load file.
Be
B, Delta compress them now you've got file a file B and the delta in
memory all at the same time.
And then you want to keep that in memory as long as you can because
presumably other users want that.
But if you keep it in memory too long then you run out of memory in
Crash and so that's no good.
I see.
So it's this constant thing of like trying not to run out of cash
Bates and trying to avoid virtual memory fragmentation because these
servers are supposed to run for years at a time.
And so like memory fragmentation is a big issue so we had to use a
Fibonacci Heap, are you serious?
Various different sizes of heat buffers in order to make sure that
there's always like a nice
Available for the file that you want to load up.
That's kind of amazing.
Yeah, so a lot of engineering just wanted that one server by itself.
Yeah.
The build process to make people process really fast because like if
any one thing you can do in your games, you want to make your
iteration speed as fast as you possibly can, because that's going to
determine the quality of your game.
If you can only get one build done per day, then when people try and
put something in the game and they have to wait to get user feedback,
like they just don't get that feedback right away, we did so over the
course of Guild Wars, we did an average of 20 builds a day for four
years, it was roughly 10 day in the beginning and
Close to the 30 to 40 day, okay?
The project so we're just turning builds like roughly every five
minutes during you know, the ordinary course of business and then data
builds took a bit longer and so we spent a lot of engineering effort
when I say we I mean me, myself and I but I mean there are other
people who worked on like texture compressors and like you know like
loaders and things like that.
But but FS bill was my baby and like I had to make it fast because
that was the core of the of the build time for things.
And so every time I can make that faster I can make it more efficient
for like the entire
Rest of the, you know, 60-person Dev team to get their stuff in and
see it.
And so they that was kind of a live process because they wanted to be
able to, it was that I'm just not sure.
I totally understand, because obviously iteration you can iterate
internal to the company but this sounds like something that you're
iterating external to the company.
Well, it's really both like you work, all the people on your team to
be able to see stuff instantaneously.
But we start on an alpha program in roughly April 2001 where he
invited, you know, a few friends and family and that grew within a
relatively short period of time to 500 to 2,000 people.
We kept
The entire Alpha process.
And when we, you know, when some people would leave or get tired or,
you know, our numbers were not high enough because of exhaustion of
the game, then we just bring in more people.
Okay?
And so, like our Dev build was actually going out to two thousand
people every single time that we did it.
So basically FS build was both the server for your internal
essentially, essentially your internal testing and the actual game.
No difference really made no difference between devs and Alpha's,
okay?
So let me just ask one other question that I had about the about the
the server.
Although I
Suppose there are a lot of questions I could ask, but I want to make
sure we get sort of coverage is different areas.
So when you said like keeping the the cash you were like I got a load
these two files up.
I'll do the Delta and then I'll try to keep the two files in the delta
in, you know, presumably flush the two files.
I just keep the Delta with a tag on it or something that says this was
the Delta between these two files.
So if someone wants that Delta, it'll hit the cash and I'll send it
out.
The idea is presumably that we want that second level of caching
because probably most people are up to date.
So probably when somebody wanted this Delta
one right after them is going to call for the same, Delta kind of
thing.
Okay.
All right, so, let's move from file serving down to sort of the next.
So this is now, my client can actually get all of the data that I need
to play Guild Wars and it's self updating and sounds pretty awesome.
In terms of like keeping everyone on the same sort of set of data.
Now, I need to start talking about how to actually play the game like
how that server infrastructure works.
So there's a bunch of things involved there.
Once you give a little overview of how that works and then we can kind
of drill down to.
So, the next server Utah,
Is the lobby server and that's one that handles authentication and
presence.
So again for people who don't have familiar with the Guild Wars it's
not like in a traditional MMO where you join one map and you stay
there for a really long period of time.
Instead you join a particular game and you play there for a brief
while and then you join another game.
So I might go to an outpost where there's like, 100, 150 people
running around and the hey, let's go play in an instance map and then
you and I get our own private copy of a two player or for player a
player world.
We play there for a while and we finished that and we go play a
tournament game, which is, you know, five teams of eight people and
then we play
A an arena map, which is two games, two teams of eight people.
So we're playing lots of different maps and so because you don't have
a persistent connection, we don't have a way to send you messages all
the time.
Okay?
So what we do is, instead you connect to the lobby server first and
your lobby server connections, persistent.
And so when you get Whispers from your friends, or when we need to
send you any notifications that can all go through that persistent
connection through the lobby.
So the lobby, you know, you authenticate yourself, you get your
friends list, you get like your guild information, because it's called
goers, right?
And like all the other information, you need to maintain a persistent
State and also we established like some encryption keys because all
the data is encrypted back and forth and is that process?
So I guess this is pressing, probably should be brought up now, just
to can be mentioned in different parts of it.
So like TCP versus UDP was a big thing.
You put in the in the emails, actually, the first thing you said.
So, do you want to mention briefly, like sort of what these different
systems are that we're talking about where they TCP were the UDP, and
why it sounds like the file server was TCP?
Because you mentioned the
Window, the send window.
What is all, what is the lobby server TCP, as well, if we go towards
everything is TCP, okay?
So everything in the game is TCP.
No UDP.
That's right, all right.
And so an instantly, the reason for that was like we're going to use
TCP and then we're going to decide later on.
If we needed to use UDP for the server to client protocol, we thought
we would need to but it turned out.
It just wasn't a big issue for the type of game that we were doing
okay but like it was expedient for us to write tcp-based game, okay?
And so,
Keep going with that.
So I got to connect to the connect to the lobby server.
So I TCP to the lobby server and I get my information back from that
and presumably, this is also going to involve, you said you don't ever
do peer-to-peer.
So presumably, I'm going to have to Route the packets for the rest of
the game to the people.
I'm playing with through somebody is that also a lobbyist over?
How does that's right?
How does that process or so sure.
So like briefly the lobby server talks the database server and you
know post on all your data.
And then after that talks to us,
The server, which is it's called site serve, but it's like a
matchmaking server and it says player Pat was last in Lion's Arch.
And so, you know, find a lion's Arch server.
And so the matchmaking Server doesn't have any of those yet, right?
Because it's a brand new build or, you know, like everything crashing
into the owner.
You know, the whole thing was they wanted the game, whatever.
Okay.
And so, it has a whole bunch of game Services have connected up to the
matchmaking server and said hi.
I'm available to host games, you know, I have excess capacity and so
the matchmaking server says, you were going to host the game.
Go create a lion's, Arch will call it District 1 and then the server
and create that sent back a token to the match over to Matt saracens
about to Lobby server.
Lobby server to the client plants.
Got this token, which is like a token that says I'm allowed to join
this game and the address of that game.
Okay.
So then I joined that game and I say hi I'm Pat, here's my token,
let's encrypt this communication then the game server then goes to the
database cache server says Get me the past record oh he's not loaded
yet.
Database cache server goes to the database server, get me the record.
Here is your entire record which has all your inventory, like the
parts of the map that you've explored, how much gold you have
everything interesting about your character.
So there's a ton of servers in there that you've just mentioned.
Just for them, just the basics, just for the basic.
So, okay, so the first question is I guess before I ask any more
specifics about those, why are there so many servers?
So why was this a load balancing thing?
Was this just a cleanliness thing or a testability thing?
Like why do we have that many servers involved in?
Just this one process.
Sure.
So it's really good when you have a lot of complexity to try and
simplify your program because if you're trying to do too many things
at once, and if one of them crashes, it takes down everything else,
okay?
So, like isolation components, also, you know, just from an
understanding, something standpoint.
If you can't understand something, it's really hard to modify.
So, the smaller something is the better.
It fits into the like seven plus or minus two items in your brain,
right?
And each one of those, you know, like things can be separated, right.
Separation.
Of concerns is the is the Cs terminology for that.
So basically your philosophical your approach to this basically would
be if we can define a, you know, a set of operations that clearly
form.
Something that can all be done with the same set of data, we're going
to make that into a separate server if we can even if that's going to
run on the same machine as some other server we'd rather have it be
like its own sort of self-contained thing.
That's right.
Rather than merging these two things together.
And then also, you know, another really compelling
And to do that.
It is like you can keep buying bigger and bigger services but the cost
for the server goes up instead of being a linear cost at Scales
exponentially.
So you know, if you want to for processor server, it's more than twice
as expensive as a two processors and a process has more than four
times as expensive as a to prices.
Sure.
So, if you can have the ability to distribute these things across,
lots of Cheaper machines.
It's a win there as well.
That's right.
And then also like, when you design your stuff to be, it's called
horizontally scalable, you know, like vertically, scalable is by a
bigger server, right?
But you can only get so big before you run out of like there.
Isn't a 256 core server that you can just go out and buy or at least
you couldn't in 2000 and searched for era.
Probably not even close.
But yeah, we're not spending like multimillion-dollar.
Yeah.
And yeah, so you want to scale horizontally and that causes you to
re-architect the way that you write your software and also then you
know like oh well one of our officers blew up right big deal.
Okay.
Because you just have lots of all servers running.
That's right and it's totally fine.
Okay, so going back to sort of the that that server break down then.
So if my philosophy is like lots of little servers each that does a
specific job.
I contribute.
The mirror I want and I like programming it that way because then I
have a much more well-defined sort of, you know, problem, space and
solution to the problem.
What about sort of the extra interconnect that this generates?
Meaning, the fact that now, these things have to talk to each other.
Don't I sort of introduced a new failure point or a new thing.
I've got to get right every time these two servers can't just call a
function, they've got to actually now have the packet protocol.
How did you approach that?
Because that seems
Seems like that would then be something you maybe want to stay matte
eyes or something.
I mean that's right.
Tell me tell me how you thought about that.
Yeah, absolutely.
So the server is speak a different protocol and it's like, you know,
an RPC protocol.
It happened to be a custom one, although like, there's lots of
different versions that.
So today, like today, you'd use protobuf sore Thrift or a message
pack, or something like, okay, because like lots of people have
studied this problem, figured out like her thing to do or, you know,
another new one is Captain Frodo, and you think these are good,
meaning like you've looked at them.
And absolutely, these would be these.
We could have used these and they would have been okay.
If they existed in that time.
It's yeah, absolutely.
So, you know, you just need some standardized RPC protocol that, in
particular, has the capability to do versioning because, you know, day
one, you do something.
And then like three weeks later, you're like, oh, we should have added
this parameter, we have a new feature.
So, you need to think about how you would add additional features
without having to like, take down all of your servers and do
maintenance period.
One of the other rather unique things about Guild Wars was that we
tried never to do maintenance like we ran 24/7 365, okay?
No maintenance periods, which is extremely unusual.
Yeah.
That the sensor
And so like what you had to do was like rolling upgrades of your
servers like you'd upgrade one, it had to continue to work like new
version and old version.
All you know, rather new protocol and old protocol had to continue to
work but now that you've got a new server running, it can speak the
new protocol and new you know, it can do additional functionality so
you take down the servers like okay the server is going to go out of
service everybody get off it, okay?
It's it's empty kill restart with new version, okay?
So remember to you know get all the users office was it is that some
kind of a
So that sort of scale down, meaning I've got a flush everything off,
this is a thing that had to be built in to all the servers.
I assumed was the concept that like, you have to go down for
maintenance now and we built that in from day one the class with you
can go down for maintenance.
You get everyone off and they go to some other servers and then we can
do whatever kinds of upgrade for going to do to you.
That's right.
And this was built into every server or do you kind of like so when
you talk about having somebody servers and I can I can't remember the
number but you had listed so many servers there on that line.
When you sent me the email, there's I mean there had to be there was
over ten.
Let's put it that way.
Yeah I think there's 1818 servers
Did you develop that with a particular?
I don't want to say framework because, you know, that's kind of maybe
a loaded term.
But did you essentially have some code that is shared between all
these servers which is like, okay, we kind of get this now, maybe a
little bit into it, how we want these service to work.
So we kind of built a standard lot.
Our standard server Library, absolutely.
What does that look like?
Well, so another interesting is that like the core of all the server's
was one set of code that could do like file handling memory management
and socket and hot reloading okay like Ma.
All's okay?
So a module would be like the file server module, or the matchmaking
server or the lobby server module could actually be dropped and
reloaded dynamically.
So in a sense, a server instance may be thought of as the lobby
server, but really, it's sort of the generic server.
Like top thing, whatever this is with only, the lobby server, loaded
up and running.
But for technically, if we'd wanted to, we could have also had it load
up a matchmaking server.
That's right.
So like the you know they were the way to look at it is really
Reena serve, which is the loader module is an executable and
everything else is a dll.
And so like on a developer system you would actually load up every
single dll so you can have the entire stack of 18 servers running.
I seen one and test them, just right there and see how they trade.
That's pretty fascinating.
Okay, so I guess we had to create a protocol to talk everything,
right?
And so, that protocol library, then became part of, you know, could
have been part of the core.
But because we wanted the capability to update, it really frequently,
every single server, use the same code but it had it loaded into the
dll.
So I
Could be updated, okay, so called like serve socket.
So basically when you load a dll, it also includes linked into it.
It's version of whatever the protocol was because it may be different
than the one that you know.
Some other thing that might be loaded on it or whatever or when we
want to have it too.
Even for only loading one.
When we want to go away and come back, we don't want to, then have to
go like, oh, right, he's going away.
And he's changing his version.
So now I have to like switch out the version of my protocol that I'm
using I think so it's like, no, it's all just welded into that one.
Dll, it knows which protocol was using but that
Did come from a shared library that we use internally so that everyone
just links to that and knows that can use it correctly.
Okay.
Wow.
You know, stuff.
All right, so we don't have we don't have nearly as much time left.
As I would like, of course, but I guess I just want to quickly kind of
go through some of these things here and get a little bit of a guess
of your perspective on them.
So talk a little bit about the TCP versus UDP thing because you'd
mention that likes it on the top of thing.
Just said, Guild Wars used all TCP, which is kind of
Rising to me.
We actually have this discussion with some friends recently where I
was like lamenting the fact that like I you can actually download a
file in a browser like downloading a file in the browser is like an
unsolved problem, half the time, it just like stops and new.
Nobody knows why right?
And so like Guild Wars I don't think ever had these sorts of problems.
So you know I guess it does.
That sort of say that like well you know, can you give me a little bit
of background TCP versus UDP and how do you if you're going to do TCP,
how did you do it right versus doing it wrong?
Because
Oh, I see so many things where it's obviously done wrong.
Does that make sense?
As a question?
Yeah.
So the first thing is TCP versus UDP.
So TCP is a reliable ordered protocol, which means like even if you
receive data out of order, then you'll wait for the piece that we
supposed to come before and insert that.
So that everything shows up in a nice stream it's like reading a file
except that, you know, sometimes the file like, handle gets broken and
you can't read anymore from it.
Whereas UDP, you can send lots of packets.
They arrived in any order, that is unguaranteed.
And some of them don't ever arrive at all.
Yeah.
And so, you know, obviously TCP and UDP are built on the same
underlying Primitives and TCP just has a lot of mechanisms to ensure
that the reliable order guarantee actually happens and you know that
maybe not what you want for your game because if you're doing a first
person shooter like you're sending like position and angle like a
regular position, velocity, something like that so that, you know, at
any moment in time when I receive a packet, I know exactly where you
are and where you're headed.
But if I lose one of those, I don't care because I'll get the
Next one, which is your new position and in fact it would be bad to
receive an old stale packet because now you're going to pop backwards
in time.
So TCP would be a terrible protocol for that.
But for an MMO, it actually works really well.
Because almost every single message that you would send is something
that you would have wanted to know correctly, right?
Like I picked up this, right?
That is not a message that you can lose, because if you did, then
like, multiple people could pick up the same item and so reliable
ordered protocol works really well.
The downside to Reliable ordered is
Like on some devices like in mobile devices, for example, you lose
those connections all the time, right?
You're on the bus you go through a tunnel and TCP doesn't survive that
trip to the tunnel.
Where's UDP, you know, the phone can keep going, no, really try again.
I'm here, I'm here, I'm here.
And so UDP works great for mobile devices.
If you need like a high bandwidth connection, if you're going to do
something low bandwidth like you just use a simple restful, interface,
like HTTP.
But what happens?
So TCP connections are not necessarily reliable either, so presumably
the game kind of has to deal.
With that state as well.
And is that, like I said, kind of using the straw man of the the
browser that can't swim download a file for some reason.
Is that just basically about, okay, the game just has to be smart
about checking the connections know if I haven't received anything in
a certain amount of time kill it.
Start another one.
Like how much logic would you say you have to put into making a TCP
connection work?
The way it needs to, for a game versus the way it needs to apparently
for a file browser or web browser?
Yeah, I mean if you were to look at the socket library for all of our
servers and
Fine.
It's all like the same kind of stuff.
There's probably 1,000 lines for Windows 95 and 1,000 lines for nt,
Okay?
So it's not a huge amount of code.
I think it's more of a conceptual model that you have when working
with sockets, okay?
That you just have to assume that it could break at any moment in
time, okay?
And plan for breaking.
So we had sort of a coding standard in written at which was like,
don't have functions return failure.
So don't return Boolean values.
Like, I failed something went wrong except for a couple of cases.
One of them is sockets and the other one is files.
Look like if
If you open a file like obviously it can fail.
Yes.
But like for memory allocation it is succeeds or your program blows
up, okay?
You can set a flag saying you know I'd like to know if this would fail
and then you can I collect robe you don't return null and say well I'm
sorry I can allocate that Marina and but that code is obviously
prepared to deal with that failure case.
The idea is like if you try and load a model file and it doesn't load
up with the heck are you going to do?
Okay.
Well you know you can crash the game but that's not very
user-friendly.
So we just show a white box like a six foot square box.
So you basically
He's had a case where it's like when we do something that we know we
can fail, we decode is designed around the fact that that's actually
just a legal operating condition.
Like I'll either get this model for I won't.
It's not it's not an imperative basically right?
Well, so I'll for the model file always get a model file.
I can ask if it's valid after.
Oh okay, I see.
But for a socket you just have to look at it and go like any moment
this thing can fail.
And so what's my you know failure resolution for that?
And of course, a lot of testing doesn't hurt either.
Yeah, okay.
And so so you never really had any misgivings about
Using TCP, then you felt like that was totally fine as long as you
architect around the fact that you expect it to maybe go down, go back
up that certain.
Yes, although like in practice the thing that really affected us the
most was you know at any moment in time like somebody's doing
maintenance on their gear somewhere, okay.
And so like you know your packets are taking one path like they're
hopping through 18, different routers to get from your house to the
servers and you know Gamers play at night maintenance periods or
tonight.
And so like the routes change and the or like the, you know, the
It's publishing our game decides that they're going to do maintenance
in their Data Center and switch their devices and you would think like
I mean you know this is in 2005 right?
Like Cisco had been making routers since the 1980s just that they
would have had solved this problem.
All right?
But there's this thing, it's called, you know, route convergence.
And like what happens is your router takes like 30 seconds before like
you have a, okay, an active/passive set of router's, right?
And this the active gets taken down either by, you know, manual
control or like it just fails.
And, yeah, the other was supposed to pick up
And it takes such a long time that your TCP connections, all get torn
down.
Okay?
And, you know, so you talked to the folks in data center, that's a oh
yeah, routes are converging the fuck.
Does that mean, right?
What it means is that like, you know, seventy thousand players, just
lost their connection, like half of our users, just lost their
connection.
It does sound like something that in a sci-fi film could be about a
bunch of you.
Litigate the great convergence is half, its upon us, some some routes
are getting right, we're going to use UDP then you know you have much
more control over that process because you
You can just keep trying and eventually routes will converge and, you
know, your packets will start getting through again.
And so why didn't you guys decide to do something?
Like, for example, use your own, you know, reliable stuff on top of
UDP or something that just never became that much of an issue or yeah,
the game worked well enough and like we had plenty of technical
challenges to solve that weren't that after launch.
Okay?
You know, because that problem that really crop up until after launch,
okay?
When you know, we started seeing maintenance periods from our
publisher, I say really can you guys not do that that
Rex don't change stuff because changing things makes them.
So, and one more question on that was you were talking about like
first person shooter versus non or whatever.
Guild Wars still is kind of an action e game in the sense that I do.
See people like walking around and doing these sorts of things.
Why do I not want that sort of UDP likeness for that portion of it?
Where I'm just sort of sending where guys are and I don't really want
to know where they were, you know, 30 seconds ago, if that packet got
dropped.
I don't care anymore.
What like was that just not that important or was
Reasons why for Guild Wars that's not true in the same way.
Well, so we could have designed the game differently.
So it was more first person shooter action e but we wanted to make a
game that was less twitch focused.
Okay, and so like all these things feed into each other and we had
lots of different business rationales and gameplay rationales on
technical rationales that we merge together to form our game and like
they all sort of overlap with each other.
So like yeah, we could have done Arrow combat, where are you firing
our own?
You have to be aiming the right direction but we decided that was not
what what the spirit of the game that we were trying to do.
It was so when you fire an arrow like, you know, you're actually over
there because you've been running this way and so I don't know that
yet because of network latency.
So I fire the arrow and the arrow like it doesn't really do, you know,
doesn't really curve in space but like conceptually.
That's what it's do.
Even if you can't see it, right?
Because on my system, you're standing over there, I fire it hits you
but really you're standing over there.
So you know, you see me in a different place, the musical thing on
your system, it looks one way.
And my system looks another, the same resolution happens right at the
point.
The arrows fired, we decide whether it's going to hit or not has
nothing to do with motion and as
Was that's a good.
Let's see.
We like I said we're super low in time, unfortunately, but so I
suppose that's a good thing to tie it back to the earlier games as
well.
So we haven't talked much about how the architecture works for the
actual gameplay inside, Guild Wars.
So it sounds like this is maybe sort of a hybrid of the two.
In some sense meaning it's like a little bit of lockstep because we're
going through a server now.
So obviously everything's getting resolved in one place, which is a
little bit more like a lox that sort of thing.
But it's also very asynchronous in the sense that what the clients see
These is sort of just trying to represent what it got from the server
in some way.
So can you talk a little bit about how you decide to do that and was
that informed a lot by sort of experience with Warcraft, Diablo
Starcraft, right?
So you know in Guild Wars, what happens is.
The server is authoritative for any important decisions, like where
players are actually located who owns, Which items but clients do
their best to model that in a way that seems seamless to users.
So if I start walking, I don't have to go and ask the server.
It, is it okay?
If I walk over here, I already know all the Collision
That's local to my system, I know where all the players are and I know
where all the objects in the world are.
And so I can effectively, you know, perform pathfinding around those
things, you know.
And like if I bump into a wall, my local client will tell me, you
know, back up a little bit or, you know, you can't interpenetrate that
wall and, you know, I'm telling the server the whole time while I'm
doing this and the server's telling me what is actually true, so it
can provide modifications.
So, if there are a bunch of people standing in my way, you know, and I
didn't quite know that that was true.
It because they all sort of formed a wall right before the quick clasp
through.
Then you know in my system I might actually have to teleport back a
little bit but by and large the rate of communication that you have
with the server is high enough that you don't see those artifacts,
okay?
But if you did and the server just says, nope.
I'm telling the truth, you have to move back.
Okay, so basically you sort of have a model where the the client side
is effectively running the game as much as it can, run the game and
it's getting it.
What are amount to Corrections from the server as to like, hey, yeah,
you
There and I understand you drew that but that was wrong.
So you know, move the guy back and like correct the sort of state that
sort of thing.
That's right or you know if you want to pick up an item then what
happens is you initiate the pickup request and now you have an
animation sequence that like takes a while to get it done.
So that the likelihood is that the round-trip to the server has
already elapsed.
So, you know, it's not like you pick up something instantaneously and
it disappears in this like, oh wait, you didn't get it.
It takes a while and like, it could disappear before you pick up the
object and how does that sort of thing like
What's it like programming?
With that understanding in general, like do you find that?
There's do you find that that's a completely new process every time?
Or is there a certain systemic nature to that program?
You like do I have to think about it?
When I write the code to pick up the object?
Or is there more of a system that I did?
Like how can you give a little bit of a perfect, but how that works
when I'm writing the code that's different from if I wasn't doing that
working?
Yeah, so there's two things that I think are really helpful.
One is to model everything as if it takes a minute to do each action,
okay?
But, you know, like like a ridiculous amount of round trip.
Or an hour, right?
Because you start to think about the problem differently, right?
It's like, I have to ask the server something.
Well, every time I do that, it takes a minute round-trip.
And you start thinking about like, oh well, there's a lot of failure
cases in there, so many could pick it up in that interval of time.
So what am I going to do about that?
And, and so, it helps think about problems differently.
The other is that you should inject simulated latency in your servers.
And in fact, you should not run servers locally, you know, in your
office like since most people doing cloud-based games these days,
that's not so much an issue.
But even then like look at your service far away or if you have a code
budget for it, then
Go put in simulated latency so that and especially simulated Jitter
resiliency changes over time like some of this really quick, sometimes
it's really long.
That's right.
So a minimum of 200 milliseconds, like, for the last time we worked on
we were using 200 and 250 to 500 milliseconds.
Okay.
So there was a lot of Jitter in there, okay.
And that really helped like because you could feel like when the
problem showed up, I say like, you know, if you click on a button and
then nothing happens.
I think I need to, you know, the dialogue, the user interaction.
First off, has to change.
Like, when I click a button, something should happen on the local
system that indicates that I've accomplished that action, and then,
you know, and like many of the dialogue changes now, like, I'm trying
to do something else and that way, you know, you don't have the stall
where their client feels unresponsive.
So you would say that pretty much all of the code that's gameplay, you
know, user-facing and kinds of code at that point, pretty much.
All gets written with the network.
In mind, it's not really a separate thing where, you know, like, for
example in the warcraft one where you could almost imagine it being
separate two, separate systems that don't really have to think that
hard about each other.
In this case, it's like know if you're a gameplay coder on this thing,
you need to think about how that works and that's just part of your
day-to-day writing the code.
Absolutely.
Okay.
So let's, let's see here.
Yeah man.
We need, we need like another hour so I guess I'll just just quickly
mention some of these things that you
Sort of said before, and you can see if maybe you can give a little
bit of background.
So, some of the things that you talked about, like, in the email that
that you sent me, was, like, things we could talk about, you, sort of
talked about stuff, like, hacking, and encryption, and these sorts of
things and peer-to-peer versus server as like sort of.
And then there was like, you know, OS choice for for, you know, where
you're going to be Linux or Windows for hosting the server and all
these things.
So, I guess my, my sort of broad question on that stuff is there's a
tremendous amount of new things.
You kind of have to think about if you want to do one of these games.
Is there a particular resource?
Like, I don't know if maybe, like you said, you did a talk on one of
these at one point but like, has anyone compiled sort of like things,
you should think about your network game, from some experts, they kind
of just go through.
Like, you know, it's not trying to tell you how everything needs to
do, but it's bringing up all of the points.
So, you know, you should think about all these things because there
were things on that list I'd never even heard of before, right?
Yeah.
What, where would you start point you to a specific blog or or a book,
but they do exist out there.
Okay?
You just have to look for like Game Network programming and other
issues to get raised.
Okay, I mean, I think the biggest thing to be aware of is that
whatever you create will be hacked, because some people really enjoy
the process of hacking.
And so, their game is, you know, different from what you think you're
selling, right, right.
You know, like, some people like to grief, like if you don't take
griefing into account in your game and it can be griefing your players
or can be, you know, griefing you the the game operator, right?
Like when they take down your database?
Yeah, for fun.
Yeah.
So like you have to think about rate-limiting so that people can't try
and do too much stuff at one time you have to think about like the
interaction model so that I can't get my guilt together and we can all
like attack you at one time.
With whisper messages in like push you off the internet, I say you
know like you don't want to expose other players IP addresses because
you know in the old days like I could send you the Ping of death and
kill your computer ping of death, the Ping of death.
I would send you an icmp packet that would cause your computer your
Windows computer to crash.
Good stuff.
How many, how many players can you do that to you today?
Yeah, you know, like for example, we had a bug in Guild Wars chat
system at one point where we had these color codes that you could send
along but it wasn't perfectly validated.
And so there's a color code that you could use that would if you sent
that color code, it would cause clients to crash.
Okay?
And so, all the sudden we started seeing like this, like, weird
effects in our concurrency graph and we would get alerts like, you
know, something's going wrong.
Like, lots of players are disconnecting, like our concurrency isn't
stable.
And we're
Also getting lots of crash reports, you have really good crash
reporting for your pregame, right?
So we'd see stack dumps of what was going on.
We were able to immediately look at it and go Oh look The text
processor is crashing and so like oh we're you know we were able to
figure out really quickly so many sending data that's not valid patch.
The game, five minutes later we have a new build of the game out in
the problems fixed.
Okay, right.
So that's again where iteration speed is really important, but like,
in literally everything you do you have to think about the griefing
and hacking aspects of it because that's something that happens with
Network games.
Really just doesn't happen anywhere else because if someone wants to
Run game that they're playing single player that's just fine, right?
It's like there's no problem.
But once you do Network, you kind of open this hole.
Yeah.
And even more than that, it's the responsibility of the programmers
and designers there is no legal recourse, you have, right?
Because the players can be living overseas or right could be under
agency, can't stop, right?
So like the worst hacker we ever had in Guild Wars was like this 15
year old kid named Pablo from France and you know like Pablo from
France, we were able to identify him and like we talked to his parents
from time to time but he never stopped.
How does that phone call go?
Yeah.
It was really really, like little Pablo to stop taking down the Guild
Wars or almost she was making too damn much money.
So you know, like he could sell items online but the thing is, we
started watching really closely and watching what his interactions
with the game work, we're able to identify bugs before he could really
take advantage of them in a big way.
Okay.
So I think we're just about out of time.
So I before we finish, I want
Other leave time for.
You told me you walked up here, right before you were going to start
talking.
And you said, you want to say something about, how do I get a job in
the game industry?
Because I had asked Mike about that.
Is you had something you want to say.
So we've got time.
Sure, what did you want that?
So, I mean, it's the number one question I get asked.
So I figured rather than like everybody rushing down here, like
afterwards and hitting up all of us about how to get a job.
I'd talk about what I think are the right things to do.
You know, number one, I mean, I think the game is free is great
because I worked here for so many years but I think
Like the one thing that people really need to have is demonstrable
passion and so, passion is an excitement for stuff.
I mean, it sort of relates to the Curiosity that Microsoft about, but
demonstrable means that you have something that you can show and it
doesn't have to be a game.
But if we, like here's some code that I wrote that wasn't just for a
class project or something, or if your designer, like, here's this
level I designed in, you know, whatever, Half-Life 2 like my own level
that I did that, nobody else participated at all.
And look at all these cool things I did and I could talk about and
it's great stuff that you can bring to you and talk about in the
interview.
Shows that, you know, you haven't us, just on your schoolwork.
I've interviewed tons of people and they always, say, not, not all
them, like a bunch of people say, well, you know, I was so busy with
school.
I just didn't have time to do extracurricular activities, like writing
code bullshit, you know, we always say my hours in the day and we just
choose what we want to do and it can be watching TV or hanging out
with friends or whatever.
But if you're really passionate and you want to be successful at
something, you know, when you're early in your career,
all right, then, you know, you have to find a way to demonstrate that.
So I think that really helps a lot and you can also contribute to
other people's projects, but I think that that's, it's harder to
demonstrate like.
Well, this is what I did.
And, you know, like looking at hiring like, you know, a lot of people
have tried programming tests, and whiteboard tests and things, but
unlike the financial industry, past performance is a predictor of
future success, okay?
And so, the best way to hire is to look back,
Somebody's done in the past because that is the best predictor of what
they will do in the future Beyond any other thing that you can do,
okay?
So demonstrate that you've done something, I also like coding
interviews are really hard like just about any company you go to like,
any bigger company, is going to have a really hard coding test.
They're going to grill you all day long.
There's a great book for this.
It's called cracking the coding interview.
And if you can just solve every problem in that book, you'll get a job
anywhere you want.
And so like, it's funny.
But like people go to college for, you know, for years or something
like that.
And then there,
Like well I maybe I'll study little bit for the interview know like
the interview is the most critical thing you can do to get a job at
the place that you want.
So treat it like it's a college course and put like a month into that
book and solve every single problem in the book, right?
Then and then you get a job anywhere I guess I didn't know that there
is a such a these would these be applicable to game companies even
though I mean absolutely, really, okay.
All the stuff is the kind of questions that Amazon, Google Facebook.
Okay, soft.
Ask ask, but what about companies?
You know, for example companies, I've worked at to like reading that I
wrote the code.
In test there and it's because, you know, some of the problems are
very similar similar.
So you think it kind of does map well, even across the board?
Yeah, like, you know, the kind of stuff we need to reverse a linked
list in place singly linked list in place right now.
Stuff like that is really common.
Okay.
Well I think that's it.
Thank you so much for talking with us about.
That was that was fantastic.
I would be