There we go.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on Twitch.
You know, we don't use any libraries or engines because that is just
the way that we roll and we roll pretty strong here on him here.
I don't mean to, I don't mean to brag or anything, but our render is
pretty darn sweet which is actually kind of surprising.
It's surprised everyone including me because I was not expecting it to
be this fast without a lot more work and it turns out that computers
are
Very fast these days.
If you actually just take some time to program them, you don't even
have to be, that clever, as it turns out.
Who knew we really haven't done anything.
Super finesse oriented to our render, and it's already extremely fast.
So I don't know what to think about that.
I guess we're just very lucky and so that's a good thing.
But that said we do have some work to do here because we're not out of
the woods yet.
In terms of rendering stuff, we might want to do today is day 128 and
so if you want to follow along at home and you have pre-ordered the
game on
And made hero dot-org.
You should unpack day 127 source code because that is what I'm
starting with today.
So, if you want to follow along with where I'm at, that is how you
would do that.
So, let's open things up here.
We are back in our debug build compile, if I don't, if I'm not
mistaken.
So we are not compiling for performance anymore because things are
pretty fast.
Now that we did the multi-threading so we can actually run the game.
It doesn't quite run as fast as we would like it to, but we can
actually
Run the game in a completely debug compile.
It still runs at a totally reasonable frame rate, so that's pretty
fun.
So that's all good.
So we've got some more stuff that we have to work out.
I want to put in here some just a little bit in terms of notes before
we go any further.
Because inside the renderer, there's some stuff that we haven't done
that.
We might want to consider doing that could have some ramifications.
So I just want to put some to dues in here.
For things for us to think about.
So to do Casey, and we don't have to do these anytime soon because
we've already kind of put things in a situation where we're relatively
well, isolated, and we could work on this all day long if we wanted
to, and it wouldn't really affect the outside code, so that's like a
good thing, right?
That's that's where we want to be.
So, here are some to dues one is, make sure that tiles.
Are all cash aligned so like what we're doing right now?
Oh, and this actually reminds me something I'll mention on the
Blackboard because someone asked about it and I had no idea what the
term was that they were using because I'd never heard it before.
But I actually looked it up and I was like oh that thing.
Okay so I can actually mention it here because it's relevant.
So, in terms of what that means and with tiles, all being cash
aligned, right?
Is that if you want the tiles to be, if we if we break up the screen
into tiles and our whole
Purpose of this right?
Is to try and make it so that we're rendering quickly, what we want to
do is we want to make it that, you know, the whole reason of breaking
it up into those tiles is to make sure that we can run them on
separate threads.
So we can have, you know, core zero takes this one and core one takes
us one and, you know, whatever we want to do something like this.
And what that means is that two tiles next to each other, you know, we
want to be able to support that a very, very easily support that being
in a situation where thread korzy
Errol is writing to one.
You know, some core is writing to 1 and some core is writing, that's a
different core is writing to the one right next to it, right?
And we don't have any problems with that now, because we made sure
that we were always seem to be aligned.
So we're always 16, byte aligned and so that's always good, right?
And that means that we never have any sharing across this Edge.
So we can always just load up a block of four pixels operate on them
and write them back and we never have any contention between these two
tiles, right?
In terms of our thread code, but
Even though we don't have any contention that we can see in our thread
code and we don't have any bugs at that boundary that are due to
contention.
They're actually can be some silent contention happening at this
boundary.
So I want to magnify when do a little magnify here.
Let's take a look at this boundary.
Okay, so we've got all these pixels in here, right, coming through
here.
And we're operating on, you know, these four pixels here on core 0 and
we're operating on these four pixels here.
Oops, that's the only three pixels.
These four pixels here.
Encore one.
Let's say right.
Well as we know and we haven't talked about this too much but there's
something called a cache line and maybe this is a good time to be.
More explicit about.
That is a cache line is the unit at which the cash cash is memory.
So, you know, if your cache lines were four, bytes long, right?
Let's say in the hypothetical cash.
That would mean that every time you looked at a memory location,
right?
It would be looking
To see if you hit somewhere inside a 4, byte long region.
That is the place that that is, you know, stored in the cache.
And if you weren't, if you're outside of what the things that are
stored in the cache, right?
And you know who knows how many we have of these.
Right, let's say the cash has one megabyte of data or something.
Well let's that's a little too big.
Let's say it's 32k, right?
If the cache is 32k, that means it has, you know 32k / for cache lines
in it and each one of them has four bytes, right?
And so it's going to look and see is, you know, anywhere in the cache
does it have the piece of memory that I'm trying to access if it does
it goes.
Okay great.
And it tries to remember the fact that it used that recently so it
doesn't evict it, if it doesn't, it goes.
Okay.
Try to evict someone from this cash.
Take one of those 4 B lines and put it back.
Out to memory.
If it's if it's been modified and then load in, you know, from memory,
grab in from memory, the four bytes that are actually being asked for
and now they're in the cash and they can start being worked on the
cash, right?
So a cache line is just like how big that chunk is in the cache.
Cache line is one, you know, one of those those chunks and four bytes
is way too small.
I made that number up, you know, you're talking about something much
more like you know, 128 bytes or something like this, right?
So depending on your processor, you have
you have a cache line that is some size, right?
And it's that is the you the unit of granularity which memory will be
pulled in.
So the reason we care about this is that cache lines are the things
that actually get arbitrated.
Remember when we talked about messy, right?
Modified exclusive shared invalid cache lines are actually the thing
that that preserve memory coherence between multiple cores when
multiple cores are working on things.
And so as long as the cache lines ended right at the tile boundary, we
would never have any contention for cache lines between
In the cores, right?
We never have anything going on there.
They would always like, this would be one cache line, right?
That ends right here going and this would be another cache line,
right?
And these two cores could just party on it and they never have any
contention.
But if we did not happen to end right on a cache line, then that means
there is a cache line that likes spans these things.
So let's say that the cache line, you know, spans these things.
So here is a cache line.
Well, yes, we don't have a bug in terms of contention because the
processor will always take care of it for us, but what will actually
happen when we're working on these things, is, when we go to load this
cash, this this piece of data, right?
When we go to load that,
It's going to pull it into court, zeros, cash and core 0 is Cash is
going to be marked as shared or something like this, right?
Then you know, core ones going to hit it and he's going to pull it in
and it's going to be marked and share a shared in his caste or
something like this, right?
But then zeros going to try to write to it.
And when 0 goes to write to it, it's going to Market is invalid, in
this guy's cash, right?
And it's going to mark it as modified in this guy's cash, eventually.
So now what happens is when one wants to write back his results, he
then has to go re pull that data into the cache again because his copy
is now invalid and he knows that he can't actually write to it without
first.
Grabbing it from whoever had modified it.
So it's got to go, Snoop it out of zeros cash, and then it's going to
invalidate it in his cash because this guy's going to modify it.
And so it's bet this cache line is like bouncing back.
Forth between the chorus potentially, who knows what's going on,
right?
And so we actually want to make sure that we don't have, you know,
this happened.
We want to make this happen.
We want to make sure that these guys are not actually going through a
bunch of contention internal to the processor even though we are not
seeing it external because that could have performance ramifications
for us that we don't want it will lead to us having more memory
traffic or more cash.
You know people talking to each other.
In terms of on the CPU and that could lead to slower performance than
if one CPU core knows.
It can always just fully monopolize that cache line, right?
So I'm not saying that's a performance concern right now, I'm just
saying that we don't know that it isn't and it could be.
And so, one of the things that we want it, we want to test later is
making sure that we cash align things and see whether that improves
our performance because that may be important.
So there's that.
The next one is, can we get hyper threads?
Synced, so they do interleaved.
Oops, interleave lines.
Because right now, we're not using hyper threads at all.
Really in any particular way.
We're not trying to account for that and it would be nice if we did
something with Hyper threads where we could do it early Alliance.
The reason I haven't done yet is this not immediately?
Obvious to me how to synchronize things.
So that people pulling, you know, hyper threads, we'll both pull the
same work unit out or something like this and just do even an odd
pairs of that work unit.
So I don't actually
Know how to do something clever like that.
And so I might talk to some friends and see if there's any way to
really do that or it might be the best, just a bad idea and that was
stupid and I shouldn't try to do that and in which case we don't have
to but I wanted to mention those two things and then finally we want
to know like how big should the tiles be for performance, right?
Because how big the tiles are affects how much of the render Target
stays in the cash?
And we may
Be doing some read modify.
Write to that render Target often, you know, multiple times, like if
for layering things on top of each other or who knows what
And so in that circumstance we have to consider how big the tiles are
makes a difference in terms of performance.
Making them smaller means that more of it fits in the cache but more
work has to be done in set up, right?
Because remember every one of those tiles has to do work to like
figure out where all the blocks are relative to it and clip them and
all that stuff.
So there's work being done in D queuing the thing and all that stuff.
There's work.
So it's not free to make the tile smaller, but there may be benefits
in terms of
formance in the renderer to making the smaller.
So we want to see if we can figure out where that performance
trade-off leads us.
In terms of what is a good tile size to pick.
So there's that.
So I just wanted to kind of put those in there now and maybe some time
when we're feeling like Goosey doing some more performance, we should
play with that because that that's basically what we have to do in
terms of doing some, some check on the performance.
And then we also want to do a couple other things here.
We want to do like actually ballpark the memory bandwidth for our
render routine for our draw a rectangle quickly.
So, you want to do that actual ballpark there, and we also want to
retest some of our instruction choices.
Once we actually have now that we've got multiple threads working and
stuff like that, we would want to go actually do a little bit of
playing with the actual observation of that routine.
Once we now, you know, can sort of see, here's the actual fully
hyper-threaded use case, once we decide to do that.
So, we've got some of those things.
You in there.
Okay, so
I don't really want to tackle that stuff today.
What I'd rather do is start to clean out the render a little bit more
in terms of some of the sort of things that we left as Loose Ends.
So before we actually start to tighten the ratchet down on this now
that we've got it running, I think what I want to do is just go a
little bit further in terms of getting the renderer into sort of a
more complete feature set, if that makes sense.
So that we don't optimize stuff that's that in in absence of knowing
exactly.
What everything should be doing.
So what I want to do in that effect and I guess we can pop over to The
To Do List here.
So what we want to do is finish straightening out all the coordinate
systems which we kind of did.
We actually did a bunch of optimization as well, it's kind of cool.
We're actually running very fast so we want to straighten out these
coordinate system so I want to go through and do that pass.
I want to get back and sort of finish up that lighting.
Right.
And then we'll do the final optimization and then we can kind of cross
rendering off the list.
What I might want to do as well in here is some particle systems
because I feel like particle systems might want some consideration in
the render as well because they tend to be a little bit different from
other things.
So I want, what else I like to do?
A particle systems a brief little particle systems thing in there.
Perhaps before we do lighting for perhaps after not sure where that
should go.
I don't really know.
But then we'll have to do that.
Final optimization pass.
Then we can kind of call the renderer essentially done for all intents
and purposes.
So I think that's a reasonable idea that seems good to me and I'm
going to take a quick look here to see what we have to do in terms of
other stuff.
So I feel like we probably want to move.
Audio up here as well.
And I think we want animation up here as well to probably, maybe not.
All right, so I think this is basically going to be mostly sort of
game stuff, right?
This is sort of, in fact, I feel like this stuff is kind of getting
straight into game stuff.
Most most of this stuff here.
So
This stuff here is kind of stuff we can make and put away.
So I want to sort of concentrate on getting this stuff finished up
because this is basically, you know, the low-level engine stuff that
once we have it done, we can probably call it, you know, pretty,
pretty.
Pretty much done.
So, yeah, so I want to try and get through some of this.
And maybe look towards trying to get the renderer actually ship
sometime soon so that we can we can check it off our list of things
that need to get done before before the game can ship.
So let's take a look at how we were doing with our coordinate systems
here, right?
We had our render group and we're pushing things onto the list and we
kind of have things that are a little janky here because we were just
sort of pushing things on sort of willy-nilly and not really thinking
too hard about how
Stuff wants to work.
And so what I think I don't like about some of the stuff is this
render entity basis stuff and these sorts of things, I feel like
there's a little bit too much going on there.
That isn't necessarily stuff that we need to have happen.
And similarly, I feel like we are playing it a little fast and loose
in terms of how we're actually dealing with our camera stuff, right?
So I kind of want to take a look at this and maybe make it a little
closer to how you would typically do it in a 3D.
A pipeline so that I can be a little more comfortable about how it's
all actually working, right?
So, let's go, let's go back and take a look here, right, at at how
this stuff is actually playing out.
You can see, we've got this this basis function, that's get render
entity basis.
And what this does is this basically does our our 3D transform,
because even though we're in 2D, we're actually doing, you know, most
of our stuff in 3D, and you can kind of see us going ahead and doing
that here, right?
And so what I'd like to do is is go ahead.
And make this a little bit more formalized because what we, what we
have a sort of a problem with at the moment is we don't actually have
any a way of saying we that we don't want to do any sort of 3D stuff.
Right?
And that kind of reared, its ugly head at us because what ended up
happening when we want to build the ground chunks is, there's no way
to actually go and disable this situation where we are doing these 3D
transforms, right?
And that is a problem because we can't.
Ground chuck seamless like we were doing.
If we don't know that we're actually operating in proper pixel space
and that sort of stuff.
So I think that this is mostly what we want to focus on here is
actually like you know doing doing some work here where we can where
we can make this a little more, a little more solid I guess that's
what I would say.
So what I want to do is make it so that we have a way to do both a
An orthographic transform of standard transform.
Like we were doing originally where we just can pick place.
Things pixelize.
I want to be able to do that and also I want to be able to do the
perspective transform in both cases.
So the way that I want to approach that is I want to stop doing these
delayed and I want to start doing them right in line.
And what that's going to require is.
If you remember the way that we were doing this, we had it so that
when we went through, our our entity simulation which was happening in
here, right?
We would simulate the entities first by, you know, by executing, what
was ever in there, switch statements here.
And then we would
Sort of put on whatever we wanted the bitmaps to be, that they were
going to have that, were related to them, right?
And then after we were all done, we would do this thing where we would
simulate The Entity and the entity would move to wherever it needed to
move or whatever that sort of stuff, right?
And this created a problem because it meant that we couldn't actually
know where anything was until after we already finished, our
simulation switch statement and that was just really annoying and
that's what caused us to have to have the delayed render entity basis
to like that.
So in general, I don't really think I like that idea.
And I do
Really want to do that anymore, right?
And so what I'd rather do is I'd rather have it.
So the entity gets moved and then the rendering for the entity happens
and we can really do that in one of two ways and I'm going to do the
simplest way right now, but we may do something a little bit
different, a little later on.
So all I'm really going to do here is, I'm just going to copy the
switch statement, right?
And I'm just going to have half of it be and render half of it.
Like out here.
I want to be the render part, right?
So this is like you know render an entity.
And the other part up here, I want to be simulating entity.
And I think eventually, I don't know, eventually we may still be able
to do these together because we may have the way movement Works, be a
little bit different, but I feel like in some sense, I maybe don't
even want to call it simulate an entity or moving.
And see, I think what I probably want to call it is more like pre.
Physics Sim entity work, maybe would be a better idea and and post,
right.
And so, you know, we might not we might even do stuff that is actually
not just rendering in this back end here, right?
And so, you know, I just kind of want to, I want to make make it clear
that simulation could happen in here and so what I'm going to do for
the moment is I'm just going to do again.
The simplest possible thing.
I'm going to just go ahead and kind of make this make this stuff work
to the
Scent of just splitting it in half.
And that's it.
And then what I'm going to do is go up here and remove the, you know,
remove that code.
So that's gone now.
Walls don't need any Sims.
Stairwells don't need any Sim here.
Store does.
And then we've got our familiar and are familiar does have SIM, but
then it stops here and the monstar has no shame at the moment and
let's see, space has no sin either.
So we're only sending a couple entities at the moment in terms of
stuff that they actually do and then we do all the rendering here.
And so what I think can
Ben now is we can go ahead and actually just put things at the
location where they actually should be, right?
And so now instead of having to do this stuff delayed we can just do
it right in line.
So when things get pushed, they will just get pushed properly, right?
So let's take a look at that here.
What I want to do is say this default basis thing, I'm going to
actually make that
Be something.
That's just kind of set directly in the render group and used as sort
of a, you know, a thing that kind of gets gets overwritten and stuff
like this.
So I'm going to have a default basis there.
And I think what I would like to do
How do I want to do this?
I think what I want to do is I want to look and see what we're
actually using in here out of that the basis.
So let's see empty basis so we use the p screen dim.
Screened in probably also wants to be something that's sort of in
there as well.
It looks to me like so I feel like we're going to want to do that.
Monitor half-demon, M, sort of situation.
I'm going to want to pull that out as well.
I think almost certainly.
Then we've got.
Let's see.
So, the cameras distance above Target and the let's see in the focal
length.
And it looks like that.
About it to me.
Yeah.
of course you got the new clip playing as well, but that that looks
like basically it
Yeah, so I'm going to go ahead and just again do the simplest possible
thing here to to pull this out.
I'm going to I'm going to sort of, do we use m 2 pixels in here as
well?
L 2 pixels, we do.
So we have M to pixels as well.
So I'm going to go ahead and sort of pull these out into the that
render basis, right?
Which I guess will actually, you know, I might just call it this.
Here we go.
And this render group camera.
I'm actually going to call this just a render group transform for now.
And I'm going to use this render group transform and I'm going to say
that we basically have one of those.
Right?
Like so and I'm going to get rid of this concept of game can Burr and
render camera in here, right?
And I'm going to have that be something that's actually done outside,
right?
So we're going to have that be done outside.
So here is our transform.
This is our current transform and it is going to contain all of the
stuff that we need for this.
And so this routine get and render entity basis.
P is actually just going to kind of collapse away into the thing that
actually does the push.
So I'm going to put that this entity basis P result thing.
I'm actually going to sort of get rid of that that concept a little
bit, right?
And we're going to we're going to kind of move it down.
To where things are getting pushed.
So here, where things are getting pushed, I'm going to have that.
Be the place where this stuff happens.
And so, when we actually were doing that appear, like when we were
actually doing the get render entity basis P, what I want to do is I
want to do that all at push time.
So instead of having that be some delayed thing, that transforms
things after the fact, I want to make this actually something that
happens at a
at the time, when you actually submit it,
Okay.
So at the time when you submit it, I'm actually going to call this.
So we're going to have this guy.
Down here.
So when you call, you know, draw a rectangle or push Vector, any of
these sorts of things, right?
So we do push bitmap.
For example, what this is going to do is its first going to actually
do that transform, right?
And then it's going to see if that the transformative it can actually
be seen.
And so what will happen is the nice thing about this will be if this
thing was like behind the camera or something, it won't even ever get
pushed onto the render stack.
So just gets thrown away immediately which is kind of
Eyes, right?
So we'll do that for this guy right here.
I guess the same thing.
Just does the is that how these guys work before with the with the
rectangle as well?
Yes.
So these guys work the same way.
So similarly, like I can do the exact same thing when you push a
rectangle, right?
We can say if the basis is valid
There we go.
If the base is valid, then we would do push.
Otherwise we just won't ever do the push.
Push wrecked outline.
It's just exactly the same thing clear.
And then our coordinate system needs to do the same thing as well.
Write it needs to do this as well.
So, all these guys basically just have to do this this system here,
right?
And this is now going to be something that might return a 0.
That makes sense.
And so anyone outside who calls it without the right now, this is our
test call anyway, so I'm not super concerned about that but just to be
safe when we actually do coordinate system here, I'm going to do a
thing that says, you know, if C.
So actually, we have a reference see anywhere.
At all.
SI pero weed out.
All right, so that doesn't actually even matter.
Never mind, never mind, nobody cares.
Nobody cares at all.
So we'll just go ahead and get rid of that.
like so, in fact, we could if we wanted to just get rid of this
entirely,
Okay.
So yeah, so if you can see sort of what I'm doing here, I'm just sort
of pushing this work into a different location and I'm pushing it to a
place where it can be done, you know, right at the time.
And I like that a little bit better because then we're not wasting
this time of like going back and retouching things to recompute them
and storing more data than we need to
So, all right, so when we come through here, and we're going to look
at our render entry bitmap, we got to make sure that that now stores
the correct stuff with it.
So I want to just take a look at what that's got render group entry
bitmap.
So we have our loaded bitmap and our entity basis can now go away.
And we only need to know, basically whatever the the P.
These two things were so we just need like
Story the p and the scale that would get used.
It looks like that's about it and so that's fine.
Now I guess I don't understand exactly entry sighs.
Why is there a size and a scale?
Yeah, does anyone know why we still have a size and the scale?
Does that make any sense?
I don't know.
I'm going to say that it doesn't make any sense and so I'm going to go
ahead and say that this would just be like that because since the
scale is not actually used anywhere, it just doesn't seem relevant to
me.
Now, it could be that since we normalize them in the other routine
that we should store a scale Plus or a deep renormalized, but I don't
know.
I'm just I'm just gonna go with this for now.
It just seems silly to have more so inside the rendering,
The bitmap information.
You know, all we would have is that 2D position and then and then a
size we may eventually want to store the full 3d position for lighting
purposes or you know, something like this.
So I don't actually know if we want to.
We may want to double later but for now I'm just going to store only
what we're actually using rather than try to like guess and and see
what we would use later.
So we would need to store the the P there and we would need to
Were the size prescale there, and that's fine.
So that all looks good.
So the same would go for these guys.
The Ender, Ender entity, rectangle would now do that.
Plus I guess the the dim there would now be pre scaled, so we wouldn't
have to call scale on it.
And so I think that was just all there because we're doing the
transforms in line.
I think we can basically just get rid of all that.
Now
So this stuff, we now totally got rid of, I guess we're not even
calling it anymore because we are having been testing with it.
So I'm going to go ahead and compile that
And see where we're at.
So pixels 2 m, where does that actually get used that gets passed into
these guys.
So, draw a rectangle quickly.
Let me take a look at what's Happening Here.
Those I guess are just used for are positional lighting stuff.
I assume is the only thing that that's actually used for looking up
into that reflection bitmap so I guess that can change is the only
Problem, right for the lighting that can actually very.
So I feel like we need to store that with with the
With any particular render entry as well because it's part of the
lighting equation.
At least that seems like what would be the case to me?
That's what I feel like.
So let me take a look here.
Also at screen dim.
What's happening with screen dim?
So screen dims only getting passed in here so that we won't need
either.
So that can just go away actually that can go away entirely and so
that's good.
All right, so it's really just this guy here pixels to m is actually
something that's
Going to have to be stored.
It doesn't have to actually be stored for things that don't have
lighting like the render entry bitmap, which doesn't have lighting
doesn't actually need to be stored, but it would need to be stored for
other people.
Like, for example, the coordinate system would need to store m 2
pixels in it to do the lighting.
So when we think about that, we'll have to think of it.
Think about how you want to do that.
Need to store this for lighting.
Let's see like that.
Okay, so we come through here and we do our rectangle drawing.
We do our draw rectangle, slowly, and our draw rectangle quickly now
can both work.
Okay, pixels to M, for draw rectangle.
It's weird that dark tunnel, slowly.
I was taking a different spot.
So dark tan quickly and draw a rectangle slowly.
They don't actually need those quite yet.
What the heck?
I guess, I'll go ahead and put them in there.
Because eventually I guess our well I'm really torn because we're
going to want a drawbitmap that doesn't use lighting, so I'm not going
to do that.
So I'm gonna I'm gonna put like null pixels to meters or something,
right?
And I'm just going to have no pixels to m is just one.
There's no transform.
Okay, so that should be fine.
Let's take a look here, the entry render entry rectangle.
Oops, I didn't actually add that in there.
Kind of want these sorted like that.
Probably, don't.
I feel like I do.
Okay.
And this doesn't need a render entity basis anymore.
In fact, nobody needs one of those in fact, render entity basis can
actually just go away.
And let's take a look here.
So now what we need to do is we need to initialize some of these
things.
Like our default basis is gone but we do have the concept of that
transform and the transform.
Is going to have to have some of the stuff, right?
So what we want to do in our transform, we probably want to have again
that scale and we want to have an offset in there, right?
So we'll leave that like that and
Yeah, I think that's all.
So in here in the transform we need to initialize all this stuff.
So it's doing a push struct of a render basis.
I guess it doesn't need to do that anymore because the render group
now just contains it directly.
So actually it doesn't actually need to do that.
It can just do render and to transform directly without ever having to
do that, but it needs to be able to put m 2 pixels in there, right?
And it needs to be able to
You want to actually initialize any of those?
M, 2 pixels needs to be in there and monitor half-demon M needs to be
in there.
The focal length needs to be in there.
And the distance above Target needs to be in there.
Set p and the scale.
All right.
And what we probably want to do, I'm just guessing is to start with
essentially an invalid transform.
I'm guessing, I don't really know.
I'm just guessing.
Well, I guess we could set it to something sort of reasonable here.
Let's take a look.
So in here, will say, okay, we've got, we've got the monitor
half-demon M, we net, we know what that is.
It's right here, right?
We were to Computing it.
We've got M to pixels.
It's right here.
So, that's good.
Let's see.
We've got a to do in their Justice based on Buffer size, so that's
something we'll have to do.
That's still not being done.
So, we've got focal length and let's go ahead and copy that down.
All right, we've got distance above Target.
And we've got with the monitor is just something that needs to be
dealt with a little bit more specifically later.
Offset p is going to be nothing and the scale will just be 1.0.
Is global Alpha used anymore you still using that?
Yeah we still are using that.
That's what we're using for do that.
That silly fade thing.
Yeah.
Okay fine.
So I think that's everything that needs to happen there so that all
gets initialized properly, right?
So, that's good.
And I think
I think, now when we call get render entity basis P, let me see what
render group actually.
Oops.
That's not, that's all what I wanted.
Yeah, let me see what we actually call.
What?
We actually get out of render group.
Do we get anything?
So, we need the focal length.
But that's okay because that's now in our transform, right?
So we need the focal length.
We need M to pixels which we have right and we have distance above
Target, right?
And then we also have screen center.
So screen center is just transform monitor.
That's that's
Monitor half-demon m is not actually who actually is using that
monitor half-demon.
M, get camera rectal.
Okay?
So that that is actually a mistake that that I didn't mean to pull out
that actually stays in here.
So that's monitor half-demon.
M, that's a different thing.
Got a little overzealous there.
So that actually wants to stay up here.
So here we go.
No Casey default transform.
And so, what we want to do here is just have screen center like so so
we want screen Center.
And we want screen center, I assume we'll just be this.
For now.
Right.
So we'll leave that like that but of course we can always modify it
later.
So the transfer has got that in there now and so if we pass them
transform here,
and,
Render.
Let's call that just render transform.
I don't think we need to be rendered group transform.
So if we said what the transfer was here, right?
Like that, then really all that has to happen is we just need to to
take in that the p-value there, right?
Because entity basis, oops, entity basis was only used to get that
that p-value, right?
So there's the offset x y.
Hmm.
Yeah, I mean, this is just a 3D position now, right?
So entity based p is this value, right?
And then entity base p is never actually used again.
So we really just have a p-value, right?
There's nothing wacky about it, so we should just be able to do this.
Right.
We should just be able to go ahead and get the the p-value indirectly.
And if there's some kind of Z offset that someone wants to do, they
just wouldn't pass it in here.
I assume, right?
They wouldn't they wouldn't consider it part of the get rendering
databases part of things.
So I think that's fine and we can just say, okay,
You know, this is just peasy.
Right, and this is just p x y.
Like so.
That seems good to me.
I don't actually know why raw X Y gets constructed as that value of,
okay?
Because we wanted to see what the actual scale was.
So that makes sense.
So I think that's all good.
That looks pretty reasonable to me.
Let's reorganize this a little bit here.
Screen center is now part of the transform, so that's that.
Looks like this and now we've reorganized this routine to a reasonably
good, you know, a reasonably good situation.
So we compute everything off of just the transform and off we go.
So, that seems pretty pretty reasonable.
What that means is though, this actually has to have screen center in
it, not monitor half dim in meters, that was just wrong.
And then when we do the entity basis P result, right?
When we have that happening,
what that's going to do is we're going to pass that now different
stuff.
We're going to pass it the group transform, right?
And it's going to use that.
And then what we want to do is we want to take the sort of the
position of this thing.
We want to take that in as as like a p-value here.
Now, the question is, do we want an offset in addition to the P value?
Because there we could have an offset that gets passed in.
That's not part of it, right?
I don't know if we want to do that anymore.
I think we were
Kind of up in the air as to whether we were under that or not, but you
can see where we would kind of do it in here if we want to.
But, but anyway, so
We're going to go ahead and put that in here like this.
I guess you know what?
I also have to do, which I forgot about is this P value here.
This P value has to be adjusted based on the transform, right?
Because the transform has an offset in it, right?
And we're not actually using that right now.
So this is like a pea or it, you know, original pee.
And so we do actually still want to do that sort of stuff where we go,
original p+ transform, offset P, so that allows us to move everything
around with the Transformer if we want to.
Um, let's see.
Let us see here.
All right.
So that's all good.
I think for the most part,
Let's take a look pixels to M pixels to meters.
Where did my pixels to M?
Go to, I accidentally deleted it.
Didn't I?
Horrible.
Why did I do that?
Alright.
Well,
meters to pixels.
Go pixels to meters.
And there we go.
Okay, I guess I could also do a safe ratio one here.
Just to make sure in case some weird totally bogus values.
Got passed in.
And let's see.
So transform does not have an overloaded.
You're right.
It does not have an overloaded Arrow operator, because it's right in
there.
There we go.
And we've got, let's see, offset P needs to be all zeros in a vector.
It's not a scalar value and
Oops.
In fact, it's oh, although it should be.
I don't know why.
It wasn't a vector3, you should be able to offset stuff, however, you
want really.
All right, so that seems fine, push bitmap entry bitmap.
That was just a, that was Scott.
I think a cutting cut and paste error, there that should be up here,
right?
That was that should have been this.
I think, I don't know why.
I accidentally cut and paste the whole thing.
So we come in here, we do push bitmap, we see whether it's valid.
If it is, we come through here we need the size again like our size
now needs to be scaled.
So we have that that basis, that comes back.
It's got the scale in it so we can go ahead and and, and multiply
that.
And then when we store the actual p-value, right?
Offset minus V3 a line.
Okay?
So we need to do this stuff.
We go.
So we need to do this computation up here and then this is our actual
P value that we're using, right?
Here's our p-value that we're using and I guess this is technically
offset.
All right, so we need to do that alignment of the bitmap which is
fine, right?
Looks like we're just trying to align the bitmap there.
So you do that alignment and then that's the thing that we're actually
going to transform.
So we transform it.
And then, we actually just store that p-value now instead of instead,
of doing anything fancy, right?
And we don't need the scale anymore because the scale will just be
baked in to the size and the size.
Besides wants to be multiplied after the transform.
So I think that's all correct.
Now that will just basically do exactly what we did before, but it
does it right now instead of waiting, right?
So, here we have the same situation group, we've got the group
transform.
And then we pass the offset that does all of our camera work for us.
We then go ahead and say shooting
Hmm.
So I guess we actually want to do this first, right?
Yeah, so you want this to go ahead and happen.
First, we want to say here is our P.
This was the p-value that we're going to use like so and then we want
to actually instead of.
So we don't want to store this in here.
We just want to store, not know why this is called peace.
Seems kind of dumb is that
So, we want to go ahead and record the scale and the result there, and
this is going to take in that value.
So, I think that's all good that again.
Should we're just trying to reproduce what we had before but do
everything in line.
So here's the push bitmap, we don't store the basis anymore so we can
just get rid of that entirely.
Let's go ahead and see that.
Coordinate system.
So coordinate system, we're not really doing any more, we'll deal with
that when we get to it, but I think we have 10 minutes left on the
clock.
If I remember, we started 10 minutes late.
So I'm going to go through so I can finish up these code changes.
Okay, so when we do this stuff like on project, so unprojected now do
it with whatever the whatever the transform is that the group is using
right?
It should unprojected with the current transform.
So that's just going to be doing this week.
So,
Oh well, hmm.
Hmm.
So this is where this is why we have the debug one, the debug camera
and the regular camera in the renderer.
So I kind of I got rid of that, but I wonder if we still want to do it
because if that's the way I wonder if we want to do it this way where
we, where we still do the to transforms and when we push them on, we
change things, I'm not
I'm not sure if we want to do that or not.
It's a little dicey, right?
Because
Is as we are editing those adding in sort of that distance above
Target.
It's really the distance of a Target is and the offset of the only
things we would changing.
So I think we I think I want to do that slightly differently.
I think I want to do that slightly differently so I'm going to I'm
going to leave it like this for now and we're going to re-enable that
later.
So we're going to we're going to leave it like this for now.
So let's go ahead and keep going here.
We've got the transform that needs to be accessed here.
And then we've got the render basis.
See, so we don't need to do this anymore, right?
This stuff is actually not that necessary.
So when we push on these render basis, what we can do now, instead of
having to do this, we can just actually pass these values in as the
actual things that we want to use, right?
Because they're not, they're not necessary at all anymore.
I don't think so.
Where is the, the default basis equals basis?
Where is the actual?
It's just pushing a random one on and putting them at Delta so we can
I think we can literally now just do this.
Just write for these guys.
Like so and not have to do any of this stuff that stuff can just go
away, which is good but we will need to set up so we'll need to do a
thing here where we actually set up the camera, more more
appropriately but I think that's that's basically it.
Okay, so let's see, we got the render basis stuff happening here and
going 200, again, that none of that actually needs to happen anymore.
That can just be cleared out.
So that's good.
And none of this stuff needs to happen.
Either that
Go away and then here so really all that this is doing is doing that
that that transferring to put things into the correct position.
So all we would really have to do here is go ahead and set the render
group, right?
Set the transforms P offset key to be whatever the ground points
location is right.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Now we probably missed a bunch of things up and that's totally fine.
Oops, Sadat.
What is the saying?
What is wrong with my render group transform must have a class?
What did I do?
I want to access transform from my render group.
Left of transform must have a class or cream and type as render group
star.
Oh, so it was a, it was a pointer.
I guess it was only complaining about this one, my bad.
So I don't suspect that this is going to work at all.
Well,
How is it possible that every time I think there's no way something is
going to work and we make a ton of code changes.
It totally works.
That's just weird.
Okay, well, I guess it worked.
All of those changes and it worked right the first time.
Okay.
I think there's still something wrong though, because you see there's
that orange.
I don't know why that orange thing is there.
So I'm not sure what's going on with that.
Exactly.
So there might be something strange happening there.
I don't know, that's probably just offset stuff.
Anyway, I am shocked at that worked.
We should have at least had something serious go wrong in there.
We didn't.
That's good, I guess.
But that is.
Yes, very strange.
So what I was going to say before is I was thinking that perhaps what
I should do is I should make the render transform stuff, work a little
bit differently for the debug where it would just take distance above
Target and if it was in a debug scenario would add to it.
I'm not sure if I like that or not but I'm trying to think of a way.
I want people to be able to work with the transforms and
You know, be able to work with them directly and they only get
modified in a debug scenario.
Like after the fact
So I'm not totally sure what I want to do there.
I'm not, I'm just not totally sure, but I'll I think you know what I
was thinking is something like taking this distance above Target and
saying, you know, okay?
You know, distance above Target equals that right?
And then this could be picked out of a different location, right?
So distance above Target could actually be modified in some way.
You know, if debug camera
Distance above Target, you know, you just were much higher than we
would normally be or something like that, you know, stuff like that.
I don't know if that's a good idea or not.
I'm not I'm not sold on it but you know, that would be one way of
getting our debug camera back.
Right?
So,
Yeah.
So that's all fine.
It's kind of funny watching a little dude, walk around in here.
This is going to be a pretty sweet game engine.
I gotta say since it does everything without like much in the way of
the limits
It's going to be kind of fun.
I wonder if anyone will ever actually play a world.
That's huge.
I see, I suspect, I mean, I don't know.
I'm just thinking this is probably true.
I don't really know.
But I suspect that if we make it so that you can say, I want you to
generate me a world that will take me six months to complete somebody
at some point.
We'll do it like one dude or something.
But yeah, okay.
So I'm going to put a little to do in here.
But we want to keep that.
Keep that going.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A.
I think we're right.
A little maybe two minutes early, but that's fine.
I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A.
And and take any questions.
I think.
We've got everything organized relatively well.
Now,
And so that's good.
That'll allow me to kind of go ahead and now go through and finish up
the rest of the coordinate system stuff and and it'll be pretty in
line with what we would want to do for for Hardware rendering as well.
Please remember to prefix your questions with Q: so I can see them by
the way.
No questions today.
surgery, everything works the first time because you think out loud
we've been in but
Not everything works.
The first time, that's the thing.
Oftentimes stuff doesn't work the first time on the stream but they're
not.
The things that I think are not going to work the first time, right?
And then when I do think, something's not going to work the first time
it does which is odd.
I guess I've just because my brain is is thinking something's
complicated.
So it's paying more attention to it and is less likely to screw it up.
Then in the case where it, you know, well, I don't know.
Let's see.
Here does the Yellow Part represent the loaded bitmaps?
Well, so yellow was just what we were writing in there because we were
before ground.
Purposes.
I can turn those back on.
Actually, in fact, we're tomorrow, we can turn this back on
permanently I think because we will
We will no longer have the problem of having to turn them off, for
testing purposes.
But they're, they're basically this Phil ground chunk thing.
That's what the yellow is.
It was just showing where those things were not happening at the
moment, right?
And so these, These Guys, these things
Right.
So so we are kind of in a position where we need to.
They were sort of the big there.
The big thing that's left in the engine, not the ground chunk
specifically but like the sorting and the depth stuff and how we deal
with those Z's and how that all ties into lighting is like the big.
Is this the only real giant thing left in our in our to dues?
If that makes sense
So yeah, so I need to fix the the 2D.
So I did break something when we went to it, which is that?
I, I'm treating the, the Z, offsets all the same now, which I guess we
don't want to do, right?
Because you can see the head as it floats up and down.
It actually is moving, you know, it's moving, laterally, as well.
Which I think we were saying we didn't want to do, but I don't know.
Back and forth on it.
I never really know what we want to do, what we don't want to do, but
we'll take a look at it tomorrow.
These guys are placeholders for a stairwell.
So yeah, but we wanted these things to be.
I think to stay on top of each other with the idea.
So, yeah, so I'm not sure what we're going to do with that.
It's going to be dicey.
But I really love the scaling.
I love the scaling so much that we're going to figure out a way to
make it work with the art.
I don't know what we'll have to do but we'll figure it out because I
really want to be able to walk up and down a stairwell and have stuff
get bigger like that.
It's just too darn cool to not have.
So I feel like we have to have it.
What does it mean to invalidate cache?
So
You'll have to take this explanation with a bit of a grain of salt
because I am not really that knowledgeable about CPU, Hardware.
These days, I really just don't know very much about how it works
internally.
So I can only kind of give you a sort of rough overview of what
probably happens.
And if you really want to know the exact specifics of any of it, you
will have to do additional reading.
I'm afraid or ask someone who didn't tell for a good explanation.
So,
What happens if the cash, right?
Let's say we have core zeros, cashier.
Right?
And I'm not going to draw L1 and L2 and L3.
I'm just going to say that we have, you know, two caches of some kind
for these cores.
Well, I'm just trying to give, like I said, I don't know the specifics
well enough to make explaining it at that level of detail worth
anything, because it would just be, it would still be more just more
hand-waving, right?
So, here's the CPU.
And here's a register, right?
So typically what we're going to do is we're going to issue something
like a move instruction and the move instruction is going to grab
something from the cash, and it's going to bring it into the register
of the CPU.
It's going to be worked on here and then it's going to go back out,
right?
So, what happens in this in this actual scenario is that main memory
is what actually stores the definitive contents, right of stuff that
is not in the cache.
So there's a lot more here.
This is, you know, this is 16 gigabytes or something, right?
And this cash is maybe only 256 k or something, right?
So this is very tiny, right?
And here's another 256k.
These are very tiny compared to this thing.
Okay, and so here's I shouldn't say CPU, I should say.
In fact, I don't really know why I drew it this way.
This is a dumb, the dumb drawing.
Dumb drawing.
All right.
Try that again.
So here's core zero register.
And here's core one register.
so, what happens is you go out there and there are some location in
memory and let's call that location a
So, at some point, the CPU says, I want to move location a into this
register, right?
Core zero says that.
So it goes out to the cash and it asks, the cash for location a.
It's like, I need to load location a and with the cash says, is, it's
like, oh, I don't have location a, right?
So it goes out to memory and it grabs location, a, and it brings it
back in here and sticks it in here.
And now the contents of location a living here, okay?
It marks it with some Flags, it knows that this is a value that's
potentially shared, right?
Or something.
Let's say maybe someone else has it.
I'm not sure.
It could be marked as exclusive when I bring it in because nobody else
has it.
I don't know, right?
So something happens here.
It's Mark with those flags.
These are the meze flags that's talking about.
So it's Mark with some Flags when it first gets loaded in, we have
location a and then says, okay, now I
You location a and we put it into the register.
Now what happens is core.
One also wants to do that load.
So it goes out to its cash and it says, hey man, like I need location
a and it doesn't have it either.
So it goes out and gets it from here, right?
Actually, that's not true.
It first does a snoop to see if anyone else has that in.
I suppose without going to main memory and it finds that cache 0 has,
it is what actually would happen, and presumably it would get it from
there.
It get it from core zeros cash.
It would stick it in here and now these guys would both be marked as
sharing this cache line, right?
So they're both sharing it.
And what that means is they can both operated on it, just fine,
everyone's reading from it, they read from it, lots of times.
They move it into a register.
They do some stuff.
They move it in to register again leader, who knows what they do?
But then what happens is somebody rights to it, okay?
So core zero goes, I need to move something to location a.
So instead of moving from location a, I'm moving to it.
I'm not moving from it.
I'm moving to it.
What happens then is the cash goes up.
Okay well unfortunately I'm sharing cache line.
A I'm sharing memory location a with a cache line, in Core 1.
So what I first need to do is I need to announce essentially that I'm
going to write to it.
So what happens is?
I change it to exclusive and I let everyone know that I haven't made
it exclusive so they now get marked invalid.
Okay.
That is what is meant by invalidating the cache line?
It's saying this cache line this thing that I've got stored here, no
longer accurately reflects what the location, the value of location a
is as far as the CPUs are concerned in this machine.
This cord then go ahead and rights to it, which changes it from E2 M,
which is modified, right?
So out comes the value.
The new value gets placed in here and then the next time core one goes
to read from this.
It goes.
Hey, give me that cache line and it goes sorry.
My friend cache line is not in there.
I gotta go get it again.
So it's snoops the cache again, gets the new modified value puts it
in.
Here is shared this guy comes back to shared and we're all good.
I believe that's roughly what happens, like I said.
Don't know, messy worth a darn.
So basically, you will have to go read about it if you want the actual
set of steps that goes in there, but it's something along those lines.
So invalidating the cash is that step where you had a value, you could
have used, but then it became invalid because somebody else wrote to
the line behind your back, right?
Could you summarize?
What you did tonight?
And a little hard to follow along.
Yeah so what we did tonight was really really straightforward.
It just involved a lot of typing
Previously, what we were doing is here is our render buffer.
Previously, what we were doing is we're saying, okay, we're going to
push in, you know, essentially a transform.
We call this The Entity basis.
And then we're going to pass in, you know, bitmaps bitmap records.
And these are just records that say, you know, what's the bitmap to
draw and whatever.
And these guys would refer to some basis, right?
Then when we actually went to render, we would combine these two at
render time and say, okay, at render time, figure out where the bitmap
is by using the basis we pushed on before, which is like a transform
thing and the actual offset and stuff that we stored in the bitmap.
And produce, you know, an actual position in an actual rectangle in
space, on the screen.
You know, it's like here, this is where the bitmap actually happens,
right?
That's what we were doing.
What we change to doing is saying, let's not do that anymore, let's
have the render group.
So here's the render group store, a transform in it.
That's whatever the current Transformers at the time and then the
render buffer the the sort of the push buffer, right?
Instead of ever pushing on these bases, it just pushes on bitmaps and
at the time when the bitmap is pushed on it does this operation here
that the actual like whatever you want to call this operation, where
we
Transform.
It does it right at the push time and then just stores the result of
this instead of storing, the all of the data needed to reconstruct it.
So I just wanted to get that done for efficiency purposes.
I wanted all the transforms to happen there so that's all we did is is
change from Adelaide transform to a push time, transform, that's it.
Can you explain what is meant?
When one says, something is done, see, really sure.
See really means that things have to happen in order, right in.
They have to wait for each other, right?
So if I have here, are my steps
I have a b c and d Kira, the ways I could do that cereal.
Would be a b c d, and these would happen at various times.
This is x equals 0 x equals 1 x equals to x equals 3, right?
They happen.
Parallel.
Is the other way not cereal.
And what happens there is, I have time equals 0, ABC, and D.
If they were happening in, parallel can all happen at the same time?
Now, maybe they don't all complete at the same time, you know?
Maybe some take longer than others but the point is, they can all
start at the same time, they have to wait for each other, right?
Whereas here and I probably should say time equals 0 x equals a time
equals a plus b.
Time equals a plus b plus C, right.
Meaning D won't start until all of a finished, all of be finished and
all of CSUN if see finished in order.
So a can't start up.
So a starts, then B has to wait for a to finish before it can start
then Siesta wait for be to finish which means it also had to wait for
a to finish because a be couldn't start to lay finished and blah blah
blah.
So this takes a lot longer because each
Thing has to wait for each other.
Whereas parallel.
One way to say it is cereal takes the time of all the things added up
right?
Where as parallel takes the maximum of whatever the times were right.
So whichever one takes the longest is the is the amount of time that a
parallel thing would take, right?
I missed a bit of the stream after you removed scale.
Didn't you use that for scaling by Z?
So, yeah, we just didn't need to store it anymore.
So we do we preserved.
It pseudonym.
We preserved it in.
Where is it in here?
So the render transform sets the scale and then never get stored in
the actual render buffer ever.
What happens is at the push time, we compute what the scale is at push
time, and then just store the dimensions, pre scaled.
So that we don't have to keep scale anywhere.
So, when we compute this scale like you can see in here
when we do a push bitmap, we do the scale right in here, right?
And we and everything does get Scaled P, get Scaled as well, but like
we store the pee, right?
So we just don't store the scale anymore because we don't need it
anymore after we've pushed the value.
We just bake everything in
What's happening between staircase passing in the bitmaps.
It is simple scaling based on the Z axis.
Yes.
So I think what I did here and I have to again, we go back and forth
on this so many times and it's just, it's the 2D art thing.
It's always hard to really know what the right thing to do is but get
entity basis p.
Where's that get tea?
Render entity base speed.
So, when we were doing this, right?
And we pass in that offset.
I think the thing is the, the P value actually shouldn't offset this
Z, right?
I think is what we want.
So, like original P, if that makes sense, original peas, Z offset
should only be taken into account to move the X Y to move, the Y of
the guy or something absurd like this.
So I think, you know what, we wanted, if this makes sense is this.
Right to knock out that Z value.
And then after the P transform happens right after the P transform
happens, we would take the scale, I guess.
And we would add the scale in
So in addition to the projected X Y, right?
We would add additional, why based on that p-value.
So it's, you know, I want to say, it's something like this result
thought scale x times.
Original P .z, right?
So it's going to go up.
I don't know if that's correct, but I feel like that's so.
So you can kind of see like how that's working now, right?
So I think that's, that's more what we want, potentially.
So yeah, so the problem with that is when we do that obviously, you
know, stuff Z value, the Z value for the offset isn't really baked in
so I don't know.
I mean, we got to kind of think about this.
This is, this is like, this is the offset Z, right?
And so I think what we probably want to do is just do it this way and
for now set the offset z20 and then we'll have to play around with how
we want to push that.
Maybe we'll do that tomorrow.
So basically what we want at the moment is to kind of do this.
Just I think just like, yeah, just as we were doing it where we don't
really
Why am I still?
I'm still getting.
Why am I still getting?
Some, I feel like I'm still getting some roll offset there.
Don't you think?
Felt like I was still getting some roll-off set there.
Now, that may be fine.
All right, well, we can think about it later.
How many FPS is this running at?
We're running at 60 right now.
Locked, if I, if I actually compiler ourselves and optimize mode,
So it's pretty sweet.
Actually our ground chunk rebuilding is not on a separate thread yet
although we could do that pretty soon.
So we do have some, some hiccups like if I move to a new location, see
the hiccup there.
So we have to fix a couple things but but we're pretty good.
To make the 3D appearance of the staircase where you have to make
render technique to draw the walls of the staircase to start from the
bottom floor and end at the top floor, creating a cool peroxide.
I don't know, like I said, I don't know what we're going to do, will
do something.
When do you consider Consulting other programmers?
Where's the threshold?
I usually consult.
Other programmers.
If I know somebody is an expert in something that I'm curious about,
right?
That's usually when I don't usually consult, other programmers to,
just talk about some programming thing because I'm usually find to
just program it myself.
But when I'm like, doing some multi-threading code and maybe I don't
feel like I'm an expert in this particular thing about multi-threading
or whatever, because I don't do it that much.
I might ask someone who I know, does a lot of multi-threaded program?
Who's a good?
Grammar and say, like, you know, what do you do about this, or how do
you tend to think about these problems, you know?
So I can gain some insight there.
I'll do that.
Even if I'm not working on it though.
Like I also just will tend to ask people how they do stuff in general.
If I know that they're good at something because it's, you know, then
I'll just know for later.
What happens if you want to apply different transforms or lighting to
different parts of the scene that's that, were already set up for that
basically all you do is, as you go through things.
Well, well, in fact, we already are applying different transforms,
we're applying a different transform to every entity actually already,
so you can trivially do it to different parts of the scenes if you
wanted to like right now.
So you can see transform that pea right now.
We're setting the offset to wherever the entity is for every entity.
But
A trivially do anything you want.
Who could set the focal length differently for every entity or
anything else you wanted, right?
So that we already allow all that
What do you expect will be the Boost using opengl D3?
D4 bleeding?
Well, I mean, there's just more, there's a lot more Hardware on there,
for copying memory around, and, and it's set up for that, right?
So, it should be able to do our texture stuff faster than we are.
So I'm not sure what you mean or do you mean for just living our
bitmap to the screen?
If you mean just bidding our bitmap, the screen.
I don't know.
They probably just be a little smoother because we're not going
through a weird path or
Thing.
But I don't know.
Is there a concept of local space model, space camera, space clip,
space in the render that is analogous to the kind of transformations
in API service opengl d3d would want so opengl and direct3d don't have
any of those actually.
They only have clip space.
They don't have local space model, space or camera space.
Opengl and direct3d are now, they allow you to do all of your
transforms and stuff like that in the shaders.
So you are in complete control of all of that.
So the only thing they really care about is clip space and clip space,
we don't really have and then we sort of have it in the sense that
when we do the entity get basis B thing.
We have it, it's right here, right.
But we aren't ever
That we actually Computing things that could face because we don't
have to wear as opengl.
Direct3d need to put things into clip space first.
But local space model facing camera.
Space are not things that opengl and direct3d ever care about or do
anything with.
Those are all things that get pre multiplied together into some values
that you will submit to your Shader and opengl and direct3d don't care
about any of them or even think about them.
This isn't really the stream.
I found a video where you can explore, explain quaternion double
cover, but there is no intro to quaternions and I could really use a
good one.
Would you consider doing that in the recent future?
No, probably not.
I haven't worked with questioning in a long time and so I don't feel
like I'm probably the right person to give an explanation of them now,
especially since there's been a bunch of things that have happened
since when I originally did all the work but turning into, they were
very new when I did work with them.
Well, new to computer Graphics.
They were not new.
I mean, Hamilton had them under control a long time ago, so they were
not new in mathematical sense.
So yeah, the the
The landscape has changed.
There's they do dual quaternion stuff now and other things and I don't
really know anything about that.
I've never studied it.
I feel like a good introduction is probably also include some
geometric algebra stuff, and I don't really study that either so it's
not really my thing.
Alright, let's let's finish it up, folks.
Let's finish it up.
I'm going to go ahead and close this down.
Save that.
Takes a long time to save Mischief.
Now how big is it?
Sure handmade.
I guess it's archived.
Where is that Blackboard?
Gays.
Six megabytes.
That's a lot of drawing.
We've done.
We've done six megabytes of drawings folks.
Alright enough about that.
Thank you, everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home and you want to
copy the source code, you can go ahead and pre-order the game at hand
made here at org and it comes with the source code so you can check
out all the days source and follow along and all that sort of stuff
and you can download it every night, I uploaded after I finish
programming here.
So you can always be up to date as well if you're just
For this video series, we do have a patreon.
You can subscribe to, it's always much appreciated.
We also have a forum site that you can go to and ask questions or get
ports to Mac and Linux look at an antidepressant guide, good stuff
like that.
We have tweetbot the Tweet has the schedule, it basically schedule
every weekend and it tweets.
The schedule like, sort of a coming up soon kind of announcements on
on every day that the stream is there.
So if you're trying to follow the stream live, it's a good way to
always know when it's going to be.
And finally, we have the
Live Now button which will actually show a countdown timer to the days
stream.
If there's a stream on that day.
So you can also use that, you know, if you're trying to figure out how
long it's going to be.
All right.
So thanks for joining me.
I'll see you back here tomorrow.
Same time.
Same place.
And we will sort of go and maybe start to clean up our pixel Texel
coordinates that needs to happen.
So we'll probably go ahead and do that tomorrow or try to do that
tomorrow.
So thanks everyone for joining us and I will see you tomorrow.