Start.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show recoded complete game live on stream.
We are well it's New Years.
Actually it is New Year's Day, no New Year's Eve day the day before
the year changes.
However, you properly say that.
And so I thought we would spend the day taking a look at some stuff
here in the issues drawer because I feel like
like for 2017, we'll start with 3D stuff, probably I'm guessing.
So we have some stuff to do.
I figured I'd try some of these and then we also have the, the the
fact that our, our room detection stuff, wasn't quite done, yet, we
had just implement it.
We didn't have a chance to debug it last time.
So that's something we got to do, too.
So you have plenty of stuff to do here, to try and finish 2016.
With, with everything tidied up, some of them are easier than others.
For example, entering being misspelled in the timer app.
Certainly seems like something that's easy to fix.
So we might as well just go ahead and do it.
So, let's jump in there today is day, 3 55.
So please used a Thrifty Force source code.
If you are trying to follow along,
Home.
So let's take a look here at the timer stuff.
I think that that should be pretty straightforward to say the least.
So entering.
There it is.
I think, I think all we need to do there is make sure that it only has
that once
Looks like that was the only place where it so hopefully that is
sufficient for that and off we go.
So if I come over here to the timer, well I'll have to recompile it
when we're when we're done.
So I'm going to leave that here.
I'm going to say we fixed the string.
I will have to recompile it once we stop the screen.
Obviously, I can't recompile it now because we're in the middle of
actually running it.
I mean, I could recompile it, but I couldn't actually switch to it.
So I'll need to switch to it at that point.
All right, so let's take a look here.
We've got a couple of different things.
Let's take the easier when still first as Abner was pointing out and I
think I fixed this basically everywhere else.
Already, I went through all of the places on the website in the
tweetbot and so on, that used to post old links to before handmade
Network started up and provided a place for the forums and the episode
guide and stuff like this.
But inside handmade hero there was still like a readme.txt sort of a
thing that's there for like people who are coming to it the first time
which is this guy right here.
And so these
Still using that sort of old-style forms, handmade hero, dot-org bit.
And so this day, one link, we want to switch that over to like the
place where the episode guide is now.
So I'm going to jump over there and see what those links are.
So I believe it's just asking about setting up the windows build,
right?
It's that one.
So I think we just want this is the correct one in terms of like how
it worked to this day, 0, 0, 1, so that should be correct.
So I believe that,
That link should be this link, right?
And then let's take a look here and see if we've got forums.
Yeah, got the forums here, forums that handmade hero.
Dot-org is no longer the correct place for the forum's either.
So we've got to change that to be here.
Oops, didn't mean to open that, that way.
So that's the correct link for the forms.
Now, which is nice, that's a better link than that one, ugly one.
So that should be that I think so.
Let's see.
Here if there's any more links I don't think there are looks like that
was all of them.
So hopefully that updates those links properly and now everything
should be up to Snuff.
I think
Okay.
Looks good to me, so let's call that good.
You should be fixed, ma'am.
Close comment.
All right.
So let's take a look at some of these other ones here because we have
a couple more.
So, obviously like I said, this one we got to work on this one.
Here is an interesting one.
It started because Abner was talking about trying to get Visual Studio
2015, to work out of the box.
Which again, I have not installed Visual Studio 2015 because the the
cardinal rule of game development, then unfortunately not many people
follow, and sometimes they're forced to
Follow it, which is unfortunate.
But the best advice I could possibly give for game development.
And I know that sounds weird and it's not something I probably would
have said, 15 years ago.
But based on the state of software today cardinal rule of game
development.
Is you never upgrade anything during the development of the game, you
will want to because they'll be some feature that supposedly in the
next version of this thing like Photoshop or Visual Studio, or 3D
Studio, Max or Maya.
Or Unity or whatever.
You never ever, ever upgrade anything in the middle of development.
Why?
Because you can guarantee that in that update, they have introduced
literally like thousands of new bugs that you will then have to work
around.
That break existing stuff you do or that make it.
So you can't build your stuff anymore or that change how things are
working and Bubba, Bubba blah.
So generally speaking, once you start a project I usually say the
tools are locked at that point they don't change and if for some
reason you feel like you actually need to change Tools in my opinion,
that's like a major decision.
That's like a, should we sell our company level decision?
Everyone should get together and like, hash it out for a day.
And if everyone is not completely on board with
with it at the end of that and like, quite certain that, it's an
absolutely essential thing to do.
You do not change tools, so, that is why I have not upgraded to visual
studio 2015 and never will until this project is done.
But that said, if people are coming to this project and they have
Visual Studio 2015, the stalled, and they don't want to have to roll
back to a previous version to get it to work.
That doesn't mean we shouldn't go ahead and fix things in the
Base that Visual Studio 2015 doesn't like to try and help those people
out.
So they have a smoother experience.
So
I was asking.
These folks to tell me what the actual problems were and Martin's sent
in a really nice in that Martin's way that he always does everything
to the nth degree sent in like a complete listing of like, of all the
things we need to do.
So I felt like at that point, it behooves us to actually follow them
because
If someone going through that level of trouble to give us that
specific level specificity, we should definitely go ahead and fix
them.
So, let's start at the top.
The first one is that in simple preprocessor.
Everywhere percent .s is used, the lengths are going to need to have a
type into not size.
T spec requires the type for length, this can be fixed either in code
or disabled with the WD warning, that seems like something we could
fix in the code relatively.
Well, we could just cast those
Ence if we wanted to among other things we could do.
So let's just take a look at that and see.
Inside simple, Professor percent .s start us so you can see us us
looking at it here, right?
So everywhere that we're doing that,
I guess the problem is that text length.
Here is defined as a size T.
And so what we could do since we really don't ever need it to not be a
size, T we could use
We could probably make it so that that wasn't a size T because we're
never going to be pressing 4 GB of text so and they're a single token
would never occupy that much space either so we could if we wanted to
just change that to be an integer for more.
It's just printing, it feels a little wrong to take code that used to
be capable of handling everything though, and change it just for the
printf.
So, so I'm not sure what the right thing to do is at the same time, it
seems kind of a little bit wrong here to kind of go ahead and and and
cast everywhere.
Yeah, I don't know but I think that's probably honestly the right
thing to do.
I mean because I really don't think like, breaking the code
functionality is the right thing to do.
So I think this is probably what we would want to do, and let's see if
that's all of them.
One, two, three, four, five.
So there's a 6 here, let's get that one.
And that one will just do as a prophylaxis in case anyone wants to put
it in there.
So, all right, I think we've got that one.
And handmade intrinsics, absolute value should use Fabs because
Festival.
That's true.
I didn't know we were still calling that.
Let's go take a look at that and I'll talk a little bit about that in
a second here.
I must have been a nap.
Okay.
So this is a sort of a mistake that I guess I just did inadvertently
because I didn't do it here and just to give you a little bit of
background here
What's going on here is that in the C runtime Library, which we don't
really use much of.
So I haven't had any occasion to really talk about it.
And I've often said multiple times at the end, we'll probably replace
it with our own Library as well.
So that's double reason I've talked about it but just so that you're
aware of it because sometimes you will decide to program using the C
runtime library in which case it's good to know, they're math routines
oftentimes have two different versions, they have one version that
takes a double and returns a double and that's the kind that doesn't
have an F on the
so, that would take a double and return a double
And then a version that does have an F on the end and that takes a
float and returns a float.
And so if you take a look at what we were doing here with f ABS, we
were going to be passing F ABS a double.
Sorry.
We were going to be passing, F, ABS a float and since F, AB, suspect
is taking a double, it would have up converted that to a double no
harm there.
But then it would return us a double.
And since we were stuffing that into a regular float, a 32-bit float
that would trigger
Compiler wearing it says, hey, I'm like down converting this value.
Like I'm taking it by that with 64-bit string.
21 32 bits.
Are you sure you want to lose that precision?
And so that's that's all that's happening there.
So if we change that, that that's just a, that's just a typo.
There's no reason we wanted to call the regular F ABS so that's just
should be fixed regardless because there's no reason to call the
double version of apps.
It's not really going to matter because it's a single absolute value.
But, you know, that in general, we don't
Two calls 64-bit absolute value.
Anyway, if we don't need to because, you know, maybe the compiler can
do something Faster by doing four of them.
A Time who knows what it could do.
But point being letting it know that we're not trying to do that as
important anyway.
In the future will be trained to that to Intrinsic probably and so on
anyway, aligned pao2 macro, complains about zero, extending a 32-bit
value to memory index for the size.
Changes it to this fixes the warning.
Aligned pao2.
Let's take a look at where that is C line.
Pattu actually lined out to thank you Alan for the search.
Okay.
Here we go.
And so let's see here.
I'm just going to take a look at what he was saying and look at these
two side-by-side and aah.
I see.
So I'm assuming that the problem here is just a deals with the, the
size variance of these things basically.
So when we do a line pao2,
The problem here is that the alignment value could be anything, right?
The value is the thing that we're trying to align.
So, typically that's like a pointer or account, and if that count was
32 bits, we probably wouldn't have a problem because the intron
integral promotion and see the way it works, is things will generally
end up as in says they go.
And so this thing would just all work out to an end.
It would do this some expression over here that would become an ant it
would do this when this would become an ENT and you would and to
instigator and everyone's happy, right?
It's all good.
But assuming that the thing we were trying to align was a pointer.
Then what can often happen is the pointer is going to be 64 bits, but
the alignment value will probably just be an end of some kind, right?
Like for right, which by default on this compiler is, you know,
because compilers are free to Define in to be whatever they want it to
be in terms of size, right?
And it could be 16 bits could be 32 bits on this platform and it is 32
bits.
Integral promotion means that this expression will stay in ENT, right?
So not
I'm at -1 will stay in ants and then over here, we'll get Value Plus
alignment - one that will become a 64-bit value and it will do an and
of the 64-bit value with the 32-bit value.
And I don't really know what will happen in terms of the fact that
this is now a pointer my guess is that since this is now a pointer and
you're trying to end a pointer with a 32-bit non pointer, I don't
know, I'm just assuming that something bad happens here in terms of
the
The compilers guesses, I'm not super good with with C++ has rules
about what can and cannot be converted to what.
So, I can't say specifically what triggers the problem.
But as you can see what Martin said, fixed it on 2015 is just telling
this expression to convert to 64 bits first before we did anything
with it.
And so I
Take his word for that, that works and off we go, right?
And again, this um, m is specified to be the sum integer the size of
memory, an unsigned integer, the size of memory.
And so even in 32-bit mode that would still be okay.
It's not going to try and convert it to 64-bit and 32-bit mode.
So this will just make sure it stays the size of a pointer which is
probably what we want.
Although that said I guess I don't really know if that's true.
Either the reason that I don't know if that's true is because if you
imagine what would happen if we were trying to align the 32-bit value,
is this would automatically turn it into a 64-bit value on 64-bit
architectures, right?
Because what will happen here, is this will become 32-bit, and this
will become 64-bit.
And if this was still a 32-bit value, whatever it was the whole thing
would get converted to 64 bits for no reason.
So that's a little bit of a problem.
I want to read this again.
Align pao2 macro complaints about 0, extending a u-32 value for the
tilde, operator to memory index of Greater sighs.
Yeah, so that's that's exactly what that what that is right.
It's trying to so I guess it's that.
It's just because when it's going to do this, not
It doesn't like the fact that it has to figure out how long it has to
be.
I guess, I'm not sure exactly what the problem is there.
Hmm.
So, I'm not sure how to write this in a way.
I'm trying to think about how to write this in a way that it ends up
being the correct.
Ttttt.
The correct size here.
I mean one way to do it might be to just have a dummy thing in there
that forces the size to be correct.
I don't know, I'm trying to think like for example, could you do
something ridiculous like
That.
Where you're basically taking something that's Anon Anon value like a
0 and you're inserting it into the term so that it knows that this
however big this was, it will have to up convert this to that same bit
size.
So, I don't know about that one Martins.
I'm going to say let's, let's assume.
That that's that, that's a good idea.
When I say good idea, I don't really mean good.
I mean in that way, that I hate the fact that that Inc have to even
think about things like that because there should be ways of just
telling the compiler, what you wanted to do, instead of having to come
at it sideways.
But yeah.
So let's let's just let's just put that in there for now.
And then I'll talk to Martin separately when he takes a look at this
and it will let me know if that fixes the problem in a way.
Way that's going to work.
I'm just kind of like trying to figure out how to get the power to do
something reasonable there, that will work in all cases.
So, let's see, do a penalty function.
It doesn't like this cast, it wants this way.
Oh, cast to the um, first, okay, that's fine.
So, let's take a look at debug pick entity.
It's still a party.
Sorry I was looking at the wrong thing so it is this debug pointer ID.
So it is, this is just one of those pointer cast things where I'm up
converting something to a pointer.
And it wants me to First convert it to 64 bits, then converted to a
pointer, it was on 64-bit architectures.
It kind of a useless thing, but okay.
In with your hair - EVP, this should be changed to this.
Okay, so the global back, buffer, width and height just have to be
cast into you 32s first.
So let's take a look at that.
That's an easy enough has to add.
Yeah.
And let's see a lot of warning Declaration of XYZ hides function
parameter or declarations, you hides previous local decorative
declaration.
They could be potential bugs because if you try to use x, y, z, value
variable somewhere below and will think that you're using one, but
probably the second temporary fix would be blah.
Here's a full list of locations where it happens.
So since we have the full list of locations, we - Go - well go check
them out and verify that
They're okay.
And that nothing weird has to happen there.
I wish I could change.
I don't know how to change make this buffer editable.
It would be cool if I could make it editable, because if I could make
it editable, then I could jump to these directly.
But oh well although maybe not because they don't have the source
location in them.
But anyway, so I'm going to go ahead and go to the scratch buffer
here, put this in here and then
We can take a look at where these guys are.
So, let's go to 194 and take a look at Declaration of count, hides,
the function parameter.
That's true.
So we can just name this something else I suppose.
Let's let's see where count is used here.
So I think what I'd like to do here is maybe call this like the entry
count, for example, just to make it clear.
What?
We're looking at here.
I think that's just a better idea.
And that way, you know, that local count can still just say count
because otherwise you've inside here, you might accidentally refer to
count differently.
So I think that's, that's a better choice there.
Oops.
Let's see, definition P render group.
Let's see.
Yeah, we've got a, we've got the p-value here that's being passed to
this and
I don't know what we want to call this exactly.
You can call this a modified P or something like that.
Okay?
And then here, the P value that we actually passed down, will be call
that.
So, that's a totally reasonable thing.
Let's take a look at asset.
So in 270 acid index hides a function parameter.
Let's see.
So asset index is getting passed down here, and then we've got another
asset index in here.
So that does also seem confusing.
Let's take a look at where that's actually being used.
So really the only place that that's getting used is down at the
bottom.
So I feel like what we want to do there,
Is maybe call that the new asset index.
So we do a choir asset memory.
We just kind of do that on it, right?
Let's just make sure that we're not violating anything there.
Okay.
All right, so I think we've done all of these might as well just get
rid of them and now let's take a look at where we are on these asset
ones.
So we have asset it looks like asset.
It's getting used more than once I guess but I'm not sure.
Yes, you can see we're just kind of dereferencing asset here for
convenience.
And I'm not sure.
I'm not sure that we really
Need that second declaration.
Seems like it's just that
and since the header asset index,
This is inside a lock.
So I'm not really sure what this is doing because asset equals assets
assets, plus header asset Index, right?
And then we look to see if that's all good and you know we don't
change anything here.
And then we immediately go grab that asset index out of the header
asset index and then do the offset again.
But we've already got it up here.
So it kind of seems like that's just unnecessary, right?
It seems like that's just that's just that
And I think that was probably just, you know, one of those like stream
sort of nonsense typo situations, doesn't really make any sense.
So, I'm just gonna go ahead and say that.
Now, our line numbers will be off a little bit here because we just
edited them a little bit, but I presume we will be able to figure it
out, okay?
So you can see again.
So this is this is exactly the same situation here, right?
We're changing the state on this asset and then for some reason we're
grabbing it again like we've already got it and the ID
You is not going to be changing here, right?
Because the ID value is a local thing.
So we don't need to re get this asset.
It's just it's it's the same asset so it doesn't need to be access
that way.
As far as I know, and same again, is true cure.
So I don't, I don't think those are actually irrelevant.
So a lot of those are just, you know, redundant lookups, they were the
exact same value, and just make sure that it's not the last one.
Yeah.
Far as I can tell those are all non.
Those are all non things.
All right, let's verify that.
That's still working properly that I haven't broken.
Anything.
Looks like I haven't
And now, let's take a look again at what's going on with some of these
other ones.
So, handmade dot CPP, if we go to 282, I data, block hides previous,
local Declaration of data block.
So that was kind of by Design is the only problem.
That's a macro problem.
So I'm not sure there's a whole lot, we're really going to be able to
do about that for the time being.
I guess what we can do is not Nest them.
You know, the other thing we could do is just lean on the debug
system, right?
We could do this, we could do it this way.
But the only other option would be to go change the macro to actually
have like a an auto-generated name that uses counter or something to
avoid conflicting.
But for now I guess that's just the easiest way to do it to do.
Casey had to move this out into its own block, to avoid an spcc 2015
warning.
Probably should eventually fixed the macros to generate unique names
to avoid
Clothes blocks.
Complaining of reused block.
All right.
Oops, to go back there.
I've got it in the scratch buffer.
Okay?
So hopefully, that'll fix that problem, but I don't know again.
Someone with Ms, V CC 2015.
We'll have to test it.
If we jump over here, to debug you why, it says that info is re
declared.
So apparently, there's something else called info here.
Yes, it's the font info.
So,
Let's take a look at where these things are used in general.
And see, those infos being used in multiple places.
So, I think I'll just call this bitmap info.
And we'll leave it at that.
Let's see, we've got people got CPP it 762 and let's see.
Text buffer.
So the text buffer, previously was this thing?
And then we had the tooltip version, so maybe I'll just call this the
tooltip buffer.
Seems like a reasonable idea.
And let's see.
We have handmade sort.
Deckard.
Can't hide switching parameter.
Oh, that was just because it got included again.
So we've already fixed.
That one.
Opengl
Decoration of a price previous.
Oh, you're right, it does.
So let's see.
So I think probably all I would really want to do there is since at is
not used again.
I think I would probably just wrap this up.
In fact, I think I could do this.
If I was so inclined.
Right.
So basically just put that inside the loop.
So that now it's got kind of a
a natural enclosure since that is not used outside and that keeps it
more symmetric with the way.
These are written anyway.
So that seems good and we got a lot of things called entry.
So we must have used entry up here.
I see.
So that's probably the wrong thing.
So this is actually like the offset
Right.
This is actually entry offset.
So let's see.
Is there anywhere else that that's used?
I don't think so.
Nope.
So that's all good.
So, all of those should be fine.
And then we're kind of almost done here, which is nice.
Let's see, we've got X and Y, but those are stepped over here.
So let's see X and Y.
Those x's and y's are used in a bunch of places, some kind of
interested to know what would happen if I was to do like step backs.
Step.
Why?
Or something like that.
All right, so that's here here.
And here.
Oops.
Seems reasonable.
And while I'm at it, just for completeness in here, I feel like since
these are texture exes, you know, maybe I'd call this something like
that.
Just make it clear.
What it actually was.
That way we don't have x's and y's floating around.
When really there's multiple x's and y's, in that sense.
Seems reasonable.
All right.
So think.
Would be okay, let's take a look at where is 42.
Oops.
So I think I fixed both of those.
I'm not sure though we'll have to get a check again, from somebody
else.
So let's take a look at that one 1520.
And this is the exact same thing.
So this is just I'm going to switch it the same way.
I switched the other one to be entry offset.
It just is just the loop in the regular render instead of the opengl
renderer and that should fix all of these and then we're down to our
very last one.
There we go.
1209.
So, by thread discuss declared again for no apparent reason other than
probably cut and paste.
We don't care about that, we're never using it anyway.
So off we go.
All right, so I think that's all of them that I can think of that were
listed there anyway.
So let's go ahead and take a look at this.
I think we've got all of these.
Let's say, Okay Martin's I think we've changed all these if you want
to test it again and reopen this issue with
New bugs.
If there are any
Guess I should say Ms.
VC 2015, income to abilities about spelling please.
That was some great spelling there.
All right.
So hopefully that will all be done.
I guess I should say changed all these.
In De 355.
Yeah, so hopefully that's that's all good.
I don't know if it is or not because someone with msec, 2015 will have
the test that first and let us know if we actually fix them or if we
broke them.
So now we're down to just a few last things.
Like I said, this one, we fixed but we just have to actually recompile
and test it.
The software.
Renderer, the mouse move in the the GL scissors.
Are the only ones we have left?
Clang compatibility.
If I am not mistaken, we're down to just this, this is the only thing
that we that we have and let me just double-check
Because I feel like no one's ever sent in how we would fix it for
clang, and I don't build on Clan currently because we're only on
windows at the moment.
So,
Yeah.
Okay.
So yeah, so taking a look at that.
Yeah, I think we're, is there a way to mark this, as like waiting.
Like how does this work here?
There we go.
So that way, we kind of know that this one is waiting for somebody to
tell us what Hooves on clang.
He wants figure it out.
They can do that.
These are enhancements.
These are just feature requests.
So now we're just down to these four in this one.
We are waiting on, on finishing the stream.
So we're really just down to these three.
Okay, so let's start with this one because it's kind of interesting
one that I hadn't really thought about since we don't do mouse moves.
Processing in this game.
But basically, what this what this is about is it's sort of a
performance concern.
I don't know that we can actually demonstrate the performance concern
at all.
It's not something that probably would ever cause a problem.
But I felt like it was worth mentioning on the stream because it is
kind of an interesting esoteric property of Windows.
That it seems like we would want to to talk about.
So people are at least aware of it so it seemed like a good
opportunity to do so.
So if we take a look in win32, handmade dot CPP, we can see inside.
There's a
Here it is.
If you kind of cast your mind, back to when we originally doing the
win32 code, you can remember that.
We sort of had this notion that we need to occasionally, pull Windows
to see what events had has put in our message queue.
And of course, Windows is kind of a nightmare as far as message.
Queues are concerned.
It's real bad.
Basically.
if you think about,
How one might want an operating system architected from the standpoint
of a message Cube?
It makes a fair bit of sense right.
I have an application, the application needs to be able to process
things that the operating system
Is notified me about, but the operating system doesn't know how long
it takes me to respond to them.
When I want to respond to them, how to respond to them.
So miss excuse, make a fair bit of sense.
A message queue is basically a thing that substitutes effectively for
something like a call back, or a function call that the operations
might want to make.
But instead of the operating system having to make it right away, it
can instead just shove it into this q.
And that way the application as it's running, could feel the thing.
McHugh when it can.
And if it gets something from the queue that it can't feels right
away, you could always like prostate a little bit later or do
whatever.
It's very flexible and nice.
So message queues are actually a pretty nice thing.
They make a lot of sense in inter, inter code design right in?
So you can again you can just think of it as any time you would have
directly called a function or something.
Instead, you just make messages that encapsulate what the function
call was and then the other person on their side receives it.
Why do you do this again?
Because if you're trying to write two things that are completely
separate and you don't know anything about either of them, it makes
sense to allow them to be processed in a more asynchronous way.
Having some kind of a direct binding.
You could have done direct binding, like, with dll linkage and stuff,
it could have been the operating system, just calls you directly, but,
but cues are a lot more flexible.
And so, you can see why you might want that sort of thing to be the
way that inter-process communication is happening.
Rather, again, the direct function calls all the direct function.
Calls also happened as well, right?
So, so that's the the nice part about it.
The bad part about it is that the way that Windows ended up going
about, this was in a very haphazard fashion, and this is probably
because, you know, Windows is a, is a architecture.
That's never really had sort of a high-level architect, you know,
looking at it and trying to force it towards a well working system.
There's definitely been times like, when the, when the the Cutler
folks and stuff came and did the first version of Windows and T where
there were people who kind of like try
To do some good stuff with it.
It's not that there haven't been people who knew what they were doing
touched it at some point.
But most of the people who have added stuff for made modifications,
the win32 API weren't really system architecture.
Kinds of people who really thought these kind of things through very
much and mostly the way that things tend to get added as far as I
could tell, it was in a very haphazard fashion with no real sort of
overarching philosophy behind it and not a lot of testing and not a
lot of end-user sort of clarity just
It's just kind of like a big old mess in there.
So as a result, the windows message queue doesn't really operate.
Anything like an actual message queue.
So, all of the good things that you might have wanted from the fact
that there does appear to be this message queue and windows.
They're actually all not there.
So it just ends up being a pain in the butt.
For example, not all messages in the message, queue will actually go
through the message queue.
Some of them short circuit and try to call their Handler directly.
So right there,
Whole point of the asynchronous cueing behavior is out the window,
it's no longer, their Windows, actually just calls, you directly back
at, like, your window process or things like that.
I'm your window procedure and stuff instead of going through the
queue, like, it's supposed to.
So this nice concept of a queue out the window already.
Second thing, it's threaded wrong.
The message queue and windows can only be processed by the thread that
created that message queue in the first place.
And so, you end up not having one of the central reasons for having a
queue in an operating system.
Mm, which is to allow multiple threads to process things coming in on
the queue in a sane way that is out the window as well, because only
one thread can ever look at the messages in the queue.
So that's out the window.
And then finally, the thing that's also out the window like basically
if you took everything that there was about a cue and you threw them
out, one by one Windows actually has done that.
So, the last thing that we have in a queue is the concept that things
go into the queue.
But that's not actually what happens in Windows.
So what happens in Windows instead, is that sometimes things that go
into the queue actually go into the queue, but other times
Things that look like they should be going into the queue.
Actually don't go into the queue instead.
They get generated spontaneously by the act of looking at the Q sort
of like a Quantum Q.
If you will
And so what happens here is when you call Peak message, right?
Peak message as a call is saying hey go look at the queue and give me
back a message.
If there is one if there isn't one.
Just give me back nothing.
So that I know that there wasn't one right.
This makes a lot of sense for games.
Because in games, what we want to do is process all the messages that
are in the windows q.
But once we press on the message, we don't want to like sit there and
wait for more messages, because we've got rendering to go.
Do we've got sound to go, do we've got stuff to do.
So we only want to get the messages that are actually in our queue.
And it looks like from a far enough away perspective, that that's
what's happening, right?
We call this peak message function and, you know, we get back to
things of the queue and then eventually we stopped getting things back
and we figure, we've processed all the things from that.
We knows how to give us but that's not what's actually going on under
the hood, under the hood.
What's going on?
Is that Peak message will do that first?
So, the first few things that we'll do when we call it is getting us
the message from the windows message queue and
Giving it back to us, right?
So it's taking thing off of Q, giving it back to us taking it off a q,
giving it back to us.
But eventually it will run out of things to give it back to us.
And at that point in our mental model, what we
I think is happening, is that God message will return false.
At that point, right?
It will, it will, this will become false.
So Peak message will, you know, our gottman's Peak message will return
false and we'll go.
Okay, it's out of messages but that's not what it actually does.
Internally instead, what it does internally as goes, oh
There's nothing left in the queue but I got a call to Peak message.
So let me look and see if there are any messages of a type that I
could generate right now to fill this queue so that it has something
to get back, right?
And those messages that fall into that category and I don't know what
all of them are offhand.
I want to see if there's a list but WM paint and WM mousemove are two
of them.
So if your window could be repainted or if the mouse had moved at all
in between the time when you last got a mass move message and now Peak
message will spontaneously generate.
Those right now, right?
At this point,
Does that make sense?
So,
As you might imagine in a theoretical scenario and I don't know if
this is actually fully theoretically possible because I've never
actually tried to get it to actually happen and I'm not sure you would
have to probably write your own Mouse driver to make it happen.
I don't know and it might not really be possible.
I couldn't tell you.
But in theory, I believe you might be able to get yourself into a
situation where mousemove and paint messages were coming in so quickly
and you are processing them, slowly enough that you just stayed in
this Loop forever, right?
Like I don't really know if that's possible but just the vague kind of
idea of it is sort of possible, Right?
Like meaning because windows can generate WM paint and WM mousemove
messages in response to the movement of the mouse.
And the painting all the time, right?
As often as it wants to, whenever there's no messages in the queue, in
theory, every time we called Peak message, it could just return a
mouse move forever, right?
So the question becomes, is there some way that we can structure this
a little more carefully so that we don't have that happen?
Right.
now, adding insult to injury is the fact that if you look
We never used of your mouse move.
See really?
We never use WM paint right?
Like all we have is like a dolt as like a dummy Handler for it.
We don't care about those at all.
We do our own Mouse polling.
And we do our own paint.
So really we just don't care about these, we literally do not care.
That they're happening at all.
And so one thing we could do
Is in our Peak message.
One of the things that Peak message allows us to do is pigeonhole what
functions we actually care about getting.
And so if you take a look at Peak message,
Due to do.
There we go.
You can see that it allows us specify a range where we can say, what
the like, minimum, and maximum messages that we might want to get,
right?
And so, what we could do here is like, we could just say, hey, let's
skip the, the ones that we don't actually want, right?
And so you could imagine something like this.
We're in place of these.
We said, okay, filter Min filter, Max, right?
Which are these these two here.
This is the window handle which we don't care about, because we're
getting messages from any window we could say from zero to like, you
know, WM whatever, minus 1.
So, we whatever this one.
This first one is whether it's paint or Mouse move, right?
And then we could say from that one,
To the last one, right?
And I don't know, I don't know if we can pass a zero for that one.
Let me see here.
I don't know if we can pass a zero so we may have to do like the
maximum possible message value.
So we could just do
Write something like that.
And we'll see.
So, what I want to do here is I just want to figure out and I don't
know if you remember this trick that I did before, I have this dummy
win32 project, we created that's a nice way to quickly search the
documentation.
So we don't have to do it ourselves if I want to, I could just say,
oh, I know that WM mousemove and WM paint are the two things that I
really don't want you to be doing.
I don't care about them.
So, stop it, right?
What I can do is go and see what they are.
So, WM mousemove is
Oh X200, right?
And then if I go back to here, WM paint is 0xf.
So paint clearly comes first.
So what I could do is say hey give me everything.
Up to WM paint.
And then here I want you to do just skip over it and go go to to the
rest of them.
That would skip over paint.
And then again, I probably have to do one more here because then I
want to skip over one more.
I would say.
All right, WM mousemove minus 1.
WM mousemove plus 1.
And now, we've basically notched out just those values, right?
So, basically saying, like, Okay, we're skipping WM paint because
we're going right up to it and then we're going skipping it and going,
right?
One after it.
And then we're going right up to mousemove, skipping it and going one
after it, right?
And so this would be UPS.
Switch back to my old project.
So this would be what that looks like, right?
And now we're not pressing those messages.
So now you know, our game is running and we're never getting a mouse
move or a WM paint, which is sort of just saying like, hey, I don't
care to ever receive these.
We don't need to process these.
So I'm never going to actually look at them.
And so that's an interesting idea.
Like I said, I don't really know how necessary that is, because I
don't know that we could ever really get in a situation where that was
causing us any real problems.
but,
It's kind of worth noting.
And today is day.
355.
Yeah.
So yeah.
So again not really sure that this matters particularly much but yeah.
And we'll let people test out a little bit to see whether that causes
any additional problems but hopefully, that should be right.
So we're basically just looking said, okay?
We're going to do got message going to look to see if anything up to W
and paint comes in if nothing came in.
Then we'll try again to get something from paint to Mouse move.
If that didn't come in either then we'll we'll try one more time.
Right.
That's it.
Okay, so we're getting down to it here.
Let's see.
We've got this done.
So we've got these two left to do.
Let's take a look at push, clip, rect and GL scissor.
I think I know what's being talked about here, but I don't quite
remember the exact thing.
So let me just reread it.
Again, the bounds for push, cliprect are in World coordinates, and
these are passed directly to jail scissor.
These should be converted to screen space first.
The effect of this, but can be seen the debug profile if running the
game at a lower resolution.
Okay, so this is just a case of us not actually translating.
Our push cliprect coordinates first to the screen resolution, so since
Kim saying that we could reproduce this bug easily by switching to a
lower resolution.
Let's go ahead and head and switch your lower solution because the
best way to fix something, as if you can see it break, right?
And right now we can't see it break so we could try to fix this, but
we wouldn't really know if we
It properly.
So I'm going to go ahead and comment that out and see if I can observe
the bug at practice and that way we'll fix it.
So that okay, so right off the bat, we're in bad shape, right?
Because that that's clipped wrong to begin with.
So let's see if that is in fact, clipping or related or not, because I
guess we don't really technically know that it is.
In fact, I'm kind of curious.
That actually looks like.
It's not scaling the screen in the first place.
This looks like we might have bugs other than that in here, honestly.
and also I don't know why we're still calling this win32, resize dib
section since
Yeah, since that's not exactly what it, what it does exclusively now.
But anyway, point being
Let's try and fix all that.
All right.
I don't really like this thing.
I'm eating, I'll be honest with you.
I really like pound cake.
Like those dents.
You know, butter cake sorts of things.
But for some reason,
They always put like lemon in them.
They're always lemon pound cake.
I don't like lemon flavor.
Like that.
All right.
I like, lemons, just fine.
I just don't like them in desert.
So it's this weird thing of like you can't ever get a pound cake
without the lemon in it anymore for some reason.
And that's a lemon one.
I don't know.
Sometimes, I'm just happy to have food.
That's probably how it should be, right?
I mean, you know, if you can have food, you should be happy.
And so I was kind of just happy to have a pound cake at all.
And there you go.
Anyway.
Human beings especially in the developed World.
Probably don't have very much real like depreciation for.
The incredible scarcity that food used to come at.
I mean, it used to pretty much dictate everything that Society did was
like, how you were going to get food and nowadays, there's whole
portions of the globe somehow, Seattle, obviously, being one of them
where they just have food like everywhere.
And you can still be in a situation that like, you know, capitalism
dictates that you don't get to have the food, which is a questionable
practice to begin with.
But the bottom line is that there is plenty of food and that wasn't
really the case.
Even as as
Even as recently as like a hundred years ago or so, you know, major
developed nations were still not sure how they were going to feed
their populace has, you know, it's like it wasn't just a question of
like you know, how do you feed everybody?
It was the question of, how do you feed people at all?
and so,
Yeah.
Just kind of an interesting perspective.
You know, we're living at the sort of point in history where like you
can think of it as there are places on the globe which have an
abundance of food.
And that was not, that was not true, really?
I mean, except in very small circumstances a long time ago, and so
it's pretty weird.
I don't know why I'm getting off on this tangent.
Unlike Food Supplies and feeling lucky that you have food even in a
developed Nation, because it seems like kind of ridiculous this point,
but it's true.
That's all I can say.
It's true even in a developed Nation, even for like, you know,
Places like you know, Seattle or something.
The concept that you could feed as many people as are in Seattle right
now who are getting fed every day with like all this food is totally
ridiculous.
Like that's you know that's a it's a very strange time that we live in
that that sort of thing can happen at all.
Anyway, moving on, we have to figure out how to deal with this scaling
stuff here at the moment.
And I just want to go into figuring
her out when we initialize opened.
One of the things that I don't really know at this point is how we're
setting that up.
Exactly.
So it looks like we're passing in when we do buying frame buffer, you
know what?
Let me check one thing real quick first as well.
I want to use the software render for a second here.
So let's see global suffering.
I want to, I want to see how much of this is an opengl problem and how
much of this isn't?
Let's take a look here.
So here's our software renderer and so you can see our software
renderer is still working correctly.
So
it's like this is largely a problem I guess with, with our Hardware
renderer
Yeah.
so it looks like we want to fix that so that our Hardware renderer
Is doing things correctly, because our software render, it does appear
to be.
So, let's take a look at that for a second here.
And see why that's happening.
So when we do cliprect pushing, we've got, that's let's see that's
down here in our render Loop.
Offset offset.
So when we're pulling stuff off of our render queue here, well, we're
not like pulling stuff off as we're walking our render queue.
We get into this circumstance where we take a look to see whether we
need to push a clip rect.
And if we do, we do push the clip.
Rect right.
And so you can see here like the code, on the GL, side is a little
more complicated and the reason it's a little more complicated because
it needs to use those Dynamic frame buffers.
Whereas of course,
In the software.
Renderer, we kind of have more control over that sort of stuff so we
don't have to worry about it as much.
We don't have to prepare resources and junk like that we just set a
pointer and go.
Wouldn't that be nice someday when we have programmable gpus someday?
Assuming that day ever comes.
Anyway.
So in here in when we're dealing with the opengl version you can kind
of see what's happening here.
We've got the opengl by and frame buffer stuff, which is going to go
ahead and do sort of the same thing we're doing here.
Presumably the intersect operation still occurs, does it still occur?
We don't have a base cliprect I guess so we don't have to do that now.
I think about because it's not trunk run.
Again, this is for the tile to rendering and we don't have to do that
here.
So we're just looking at the G else is
your call.
Which is this part right here.
Now, the GL scissor part I guess is essentially just happening with
the clip rect bit here.
So I'm curious.
I'm curious to know.
Why that one is working in this case.
The other one isn't this?
Must be a separate bug.
Let's see.
Hold on a second.
Let's see what happens with the debug system.
Profile code course.
Create something that's too big in the first place.
So it's hard to see.
Hold on one second.
So yeah, if I was to do one let's say that was like can I do one with
bigger?
I don't know if this will work.
So it sure looks like.
This works properly.
Is this the only place I know of that's using the clip region.
In that way, it sure.
Looks like that works properly at the moment.
so I'm not sure if that's really the bug, it looks like maybe the bug
is more, just the fact that the
Yeah it looks like the the bug must be something slightly said there
because in this case, we are still using the clip.
Rect coordinates directly for clipping.
In this case where we just used that that clip.
Rect and so presumably if that works in software renderer we should be
able to make it work in the GL render as well.
And so, I guess, part of that problem may be just gl's.
Interpretation of GL scissor is not in the same in screen space.
It's in viewport space potentially, so we should take a look at that.
I do remember there being something weird with GL scissor in that way.
So, I have to think about that in a second, but first, let's take a
look.
So when we do our cliprect ear, we do an offset of the cliprect when
we're not using render targets.
Were the target is zero.
We do an offset of the clip.
Rect
So this is just to make sure we line ourselves up when we're just
driving the screen to line ourselves up so that we're off setted a
little bit and we do like a black bars kind of a thing if we don't
occupy the entire screen size, I think that's all that's doing right?
And I think, did we have a windowed mode at some point?
I think we did.
Let's let's let's take a look at that.
If we have a way to do that here,
So, if I change the size of this, right?
You can see that that all still appears to work correctly.
As far as I can tell,
So now if I turn software rendering to false so we're doing Hardware
rendering.
Hardware, rendering can see.
Now does exhibit the bug
There you go.
Now, for some reason, Hardware rendering is not
Does not exhibit the problem of changing the screen resolution causing
a prop.
So so basically it's not for whatever reason doing our scaling.
This way does not pose a problem.
Get changing this from 1920 by 1080 does, so is that?
Because we hard-coded that somewhere when we were doing the opengl
stuff or something, I'm not sure.
Why, that would why that was happening?
So I think we've basically got two bugs here.
One is, we've got the the scissor is not properly aligned, right?
You can see that happening here.
Very clearly, right?
And then the other one is that if we don't start out at 1920 by 1080,
we're getting this sort of other problem in only the hardware
renderer.
Again, both of these cases, it's only the hardware renderer.
The software, renderer just seems to work.
Exactly.
And off you go, which by the way, tends to be the case with software
rendering software, rendering is so nice because you control
everything and it just tends to work anyway.
But anyway, so let's take a look at how that goes.
I think it's big like anything else.
If you wrote it, you understand how it all works.
You're less likely to have weird things where you're like, oh, do you
know this particular call?
I forgot that it doesn't
That thing or this that or the other thing.
So anyway, let's take a look at why that's happening.
So first things first, so the scissor being misaligned, I'm going to
take a quick look at the documentation for Jill, says they're just so
we are correctly interpreting what those parameters are supposed to
mean, like what space are supposed to be in?
Right.
So here's a GL scissor call and we've got the width and the height
presumably, and the X and the Y.
You know, we're Computing those correctly in some space, right?
Because we're doing Max minus Min.
So we are doing X, Y, width, and height, we're definitely sending that
down.
But the question is, what's the space and it says it defines a
rectangle in window coordinates.
Okay.
The first two arguments X & Y specify, the lower left corner of the
box with Isis, the width of the box to enable the civil service test,
blah, blah blah, right.
So it says that those are specified in window coordinates, right?
So now let's take a look at GL viewport, which is the other call that
we have that has to do with this situation.
Oh, did somebody say docks?
G l or something?
There it is.
So, let's take a look at Jill viewport.
Here's Jill.
Viewport.
So I assume that our problem here is that our GL viewport call, right?
So when we do, when we do open gel bind frame buffer, oops.
There we go.
so, I'm very
It's that season where I'm very stuffy opengl bind frame buffer.
In this case, you can see that what we do here is we say like, well
how big is this drawer region supposed to be, right?
And the draw region again, is something that we that sort of comes in
up here, I believe, right?
So here's the draw region.
And you can kind of see that we're doing a couple different things
here at the draw region is how big the entire thing is that we're
supposed to draw to, right?
And we're passing down to the in the drawer region, we're saying that
rgl viewport is going to be whatever that size is, right?
And you can see that we've got a couple different ways that we're
doing that.
So in the case where we're drawing to a frame buffer, we're just going
to use the we're just going to draw it aligned right?
But in the case, where we're drawing to the final screen, we're going
to use the the Min X and them in Y for the viewport when we pass it
down and again the reason that we're doing that is just because we're
trying to when we're trying to the screen, we're trying.
Put it in the right place for the viewer to see it.
Whereas when we're trying to a texture, we're just going to use that
texture and some other way.
So we don't need to have it be aligned in that way.
So here, when we call our GL viewport call, and we're passing the
window within the window height, I feel like that all, should that
looks roughly correct to me like I don't see any reason why that would
be unusual.
Now, when we come in here though, you can see what's happening that
the clip rect comes from a different place.
So the the window within the window height and then the clip rect the
cliprect itself has not actually been transformed in any way.
A, that is relative to the window width and window height, right?
So really I suppose that is where our problem lies.
And this is probably what Kim was talking about when he said World
coordinates, right?
So the clip rect in this case and the window within the window height
the clip rect is going to be something specified.
In terms of that viewport I suppose, but it's not going to be
interpreted in terms of the viewport.
Which, of course, means I'm not sure exactly how we want this to be
interpreted, but so when we actually set this GL scissor, and we've
got the min max and the Min, why here.
I think we would first need to know and let's take a, let's take a
quick look in here.
so,
You can see here that when we do our transform, we've got this screen
area a bit.
And when we're doing pixel widths and pixel, heights were doing
everything in terms of the screen area and the screen area.
When we set it, see if we can find it here,
Our game render commands, let's see where screen area actually is
because that comes from here, I would assume it just comes from within
height, right?
In-game render commands me just double check that all.
That's true.
So whenever we call begin render group, that's where we pass the pixel
within the pixel height in here.
Right.
And you can see that getting done right here, right?
And it passes in the width and the height that it got from it a
command.
So that is where that comes from.
We could we could make this a lot cleaner.
If we wanted to probably somebody we do want it.
So it's taking the global back buffer within the global back bumper
height and those are the things that are coming in as part of this
part of that screen area, right?
so when we do a push clip, rect like we have in here,
Let's see, we've got it.
Like, like, for example, one of these things,
When we do a push clip, rect for one of these things and we're setting
it up, you can see that we just scored a specify X Y, width and
height.
And we don't really in any way transform those like, if we were doing
any of these guys, let me, let me just double check here, which ones
we're doing.
So in these cases, let's see backing transform.
So it looks like we are going through the object transform, it looks
like we're going through
This call.
Yes.
So we do go through the full pipeline here, which means that when we
transform these guys, they are getting transformed by whatever the
basis is here and scaled out and all those other good sorts of things,
right?
And then they're just getting recorded after that is done and place in
here.
So, when it goes through this, this transform,
At that point.
We would expect it to have been transformed out by however, big the
screen was, right?
Because that piece of information gets taken into account during the
entity basis P, right?
You've got M to pixels that comes in here, you've got the screen
center and so on.
Now, I guess,
Though at that point it doesn't take into account.
Yeah, so it does therein.
They're in our concept of the screen coordinates at that point, but
they're not it's not in any way related to where the window actually
is because it's not being offset by anything in addition to that like
it's not being offset by anything which is why that additional offset
has to be there in the opengl path, right?
That's why this offset has to be there, right?
so,
Again, looking at this one though, there isn't anything special done
to handle it in the case of the software renderer which is weird,
right?
I, you would have expected it either to both, have to do it or
neither.
So the fact that we're able to just use all of these because it looks
like and it does look like the screen.
Information, like how big the screen is is sort of baked in to all the
transforms that happen there.
So when we take a look at the clip wreck stuff here, it's a little
confusing to me why we're sort of seeing that difference there where
we have to
account for that.
It's just a little puzzling.
Wouldn't you say?
because in theory,
yeah, I just don't understand why that's a problem because in theory
these should be in the same coordinate space if they are working
correctly inside the software renderer which is really the bizarre
part, right?
And it's not obvious to me, why you would have anything weird or
happen there, because it should happen exactly the same way.
And furthermore, I don't see why we're getting strange results when we
set the size of the buffer differently,
In that case either, right?
Hmm.
Yeah, I don't I don't I really just don't understand that.
I'm very confused by that to say the least because I can't figure out
why we would have a disparity between those two things.
And I feel like I should be able to figure that out because if one of
them has the problem in one of them doesn't right,
There should be a solid explanation, for why that's the case,
something that they're doing differently, that would explain.
That fact, right?
So, you know, there's the hardware renderer, there's the software
renderer and they both agree here.
But, but when I go to look at the profile, for example, they won't
agree.
Is that is the implication, right?
So there's right hardware and software,
You can see again, totally, totally incorrect there.
And so, you can see that the clip rect in this case,
Sort of converges to the correct answer as well as I guess you get
bigger.
Like, if I do that suddenly, it's right.
And again this seems to have to do.
It's just very, very strange.
It seems to have to do with the total, with the difference between the
size of the screen and
And the original size, the expected size, the 1920, by 1080.
Which again, makes it very, very little sense to me.
Right.
And you can see that it's scaled wrong as well.
So it definitely it, definitely the scaling problem because you can
see, I don't know if you can see this, but the motion of this line
Doesn't go linearly with emotion of this line.
So the size of the clip, rect is getting increased in a way that is is
not one to one.
It's like a, it's a factor of two or something, right?
Well, it's probably a factor of, however, Bix big, the screen sizes
versus the total screen size.
So again, I'm really not sure how that's why that's happening.
Yeah, that really doesn't make a lot of sense to me.
Okay, so I think I'm just missing.
Let's let's just dig in one more time here.
Because again, these are both supposed to be in window coordinates,
right?
Because it says deal viewport, specifies, the affine transformation of
X and Y from normalized device coordinates to window coordinates as
doing this.
So they're both in the same space.
So I guess what I would infer from this is that this transform the GL
viewport transform is going to happen on everything that we put in
except the GL scissor.
Right.
And so I'm guessing that it must just be thinking that through that,
that is the problem there GL viewport.
in this case, this transform,
Right here is going to happen to our positions, but it's not going to
happen to LG L 2 H, GL scissor positions.
Right.
And so,
I guess that is the primary problem that we're going to face.
So, let's take a look here with rgl scissor down here.
And we can see what we're doing here.
So we have, like, zero zero window with window height.
So all of our X and y's that come through here, are going to be
X half the width, right?
And then have the offset added to them.
Right, so that's what's going to happen.
And rgl scissor like our cliprect presumably is, I guess we're saying
is should be in that same space.
Right, because everyone else is going to have to be.
So that would imply that we would have to take normalized device
coordinates, right?
Which is the clip.
Rect
Value, divided by whatever the the window with actually is, right,
because we've got, we've got a normalize, the coordinates first and
normalized device coordinates.
Right, is saying that we've turned this.
You know, that entire area where drawing to, we've turned it into, you
know, 0 to 1 or negative 1 to 1.
I think GL uses negative 1 to 1
And then we're going to multiply it.
Well, you can tell right here in the equation.
That's negative 1 to 1 because you can see it's multiplying by the
with over to if it was 0 to 1, it would multiply the width.
If it's negative 1 to 1, it multiplies by the width / 2 and then the
offset.
Comes in there.
So let's take a look I guess in Milton at this for a second.
We should be able to work this out.
Let's see, Milton.
Where are you?
Milton?
There you are.
Okay, so what we know here is that the normalized device coordinates
for this thing.
So I'm just going to go ahead and copy this equation down.
So essentially what we're saying is that the actual coordinates we're
going to use is going to be the input coordinate, plus 1 over W over
2, right?
Half the width plus the center of the screen, right?
At least I assume it's a yeah, it's right.
This plus the 08 plus the lower left corner.
Call that left.
So yeah, so you can see what the plus 1 is here, right?
Because this x of n is going to go from negative 1 to 1, right?
And remember, let's just talk about what normalized device coordinates
are here.
We've talked about this before so an opengl, it assumes a system where
the center is 0 0, right?
In terms of normalized device coordinates negative 1 to 1, right goes
horizontally, right - 121 goes vertically like so on.
And so the center lines are always zero and the far ends are negative
one or one on either.
In either case, you know.
Now, another way to do normalized device coordinates would have been
like, you know,
Ro 0 is here and 11 is here, but that's not what we're doing in GL, GL
uses negative 1 to 1.
So each axis goes negative 1 to 1, right?
So this would be negative 1, negative 1 and this is 1 1, right?
This is 0 0.
This is one troops -1 and this is negative 11.
So the plus one is to just to turn this into a 0 to 2 because it's
coming in as negative 1 to 1 this value is and we're trying to turn in
2022, so that we can multiply by the width over to cancel the 2s and
actually just get, what would have essentially been zero to one
mapping goes to a 02 width mapping, right?
That's what we're trying to do.
and then,
When we do this plus X1 here, that's just to offset if the but if the
base corner of the window, is not supposed to be in the lower left
corner than this is our offset there.
Right?
So there's our equation that we're using to try and line this up.
And so, in this case, what we need to do is just figure out how to
take care of this transform part and then do this offset, right?
So let's take a look at how this is coming in.
What we need to figure out is what are are normalized device
coordinates for our clip.
Rect right.
Well our clip, rect in this case, go back here are cliprect in this
case is not based on the draw region, right?
It's based on whatever that that commands with and commands height
are, right?
So what we want to do is say our our clip value are clipped
coordinates that come in, we want to do is normalize them first by
making them be relative to that width, the width of of whatever, the
the basic render region is, right.
So, whatever that commands with is, we wanted to First normalize them
to that because we know they're in this space.
So we normalize them too.
First.
And then we would know that we would have them already ranging from 0
to 1 because we're not using negative 1 to 1 space.
Here, we know that we were ranging in the Christ's face there and then
we want to multiply them to get them back to this.
With this, here is the drawer region with this, is whatever we were
using for the viewport, right?
So that's that, that window with window, height situation here, right?
So then we would do with the window.
So what we really need here is we need this ratio.
The reason that are normalized device coordinates are wrong.
In this case is because we're not using this ratio, we need the window
width over the window.
We need the the window with over the command with, right?
We essentially need
Jimmy.
we need commands with over whatever the like draw a region with
We need to multiply by this to get that ratio to be correct, right?
In order to transform our GL scissor.
The way that we think we should transfer module Caesar and then we
also need to handle the offset at that point.
But we're already handling the offset in this Clause right here,
right?
So I think the only thing that we really have to do here is we have to
say, okay,
Our clip.
Rect first has to be scaled by that scale value.
So our cliprect Min x x equals scale X.
And we know what this has to.
Because again we have our drawer region within our drawer region
height.
So we know just make sure we've got that up here somewhere.
There we go.
So we've got our dry region with an, I draw region height here.
And we want to do that scale.
so, again, to do this commands with
To ensure that our commands with is actually going to be valid.
We need to make sure that it's nonzero because we're going to have to
divide by it.
So at some point here we really should be testing that.
I don't know if we test that anywhere else where we might need to do a
divide.
I don't know for actually doing any divides here.
It looks like we're actually not other than bitmap sizes which we know
to be correct.
So I think what I'll have to do here is create some kind of a ratio
A safe ratio system.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to say, all right, when this
thing comes in and we have the command, we have this, like command
with the command height, I'm going to do like in command with those
1.0 over to man's wit.
And in command height goes, one point over a man's height because I'm
going to have to divide by these.
And what I want to do is we have if you remember
We have our safe ratio, I want to be able to make it so that this will
work, no matter what.
So I'm going to actually call Safe ratio carrier.
So in case commands with happens, to be 0
I still want it to work.
So, my scale is going to be the width.
And the height of the draw region that were specifying here.
I want to use that scale.
And then I want to say the width and height of the drawer region.
Oops.
scaled by whatever that inverse
command with a height chart to get that ratio proper
Right.
So, I think that would give us the correct values.
Of course, that is, if I actually type that in right?
to adjust for that that transform, that you'll view ports, doing
I believe that would give us the correct values.
Now, the only thing that I'm not certain about here is when we're
calling this, the drawer region get with here.
If we weren't using render targets, then we will not have called glv
port.
And so, in that case, the draw region is just going to be the overall
draw region, but I guess does
Draw a region ever.
Actually change.
So that doesn't actually change.
So, it looks like these scale X scale, y values, actually would never
be different, right?
They could be computed at the beginning.
And just saved.
I think.
Right.
So, in theory, that's something that I could do.
Right here.
And then the safe ratio actually is just
is actually just of these values, right?
We can actually dispense with this whole thing and just say like okay
whatever the drawer region within the drawer region hide are you know
knock yourself out.
And those are just be.
Oops.
What we use?
Let's see.
This needs to be an F32 as well.
From F 3 to 2 in 3200.
Interesting.
So the clip rect here is a 2 I so when we do this scale we're going to
have to do another rounding of it.
I suppose unfortunately.
So we're actually going to have
Do a round real 3032.
232 here.
Because these have to be pixel values at the end.
Okay.
But that was not a good at a job.
Okay, Butterfinger e.
So yeah, so now we actually are doing that transform and now we have
to go.
Make sure that we've actually got a correct.
So that will transform the scale of those properly and I think also do
the offset properly.
Of course, we don't actually know if that's true.
So let's actually start to work this through now.
And see if we've gotten any better.
So again here's let's open up.
Something that actually is using the clip.
Rect so here are the clip.
Rex again let's switch between the two software, rendering Hardware
rendering and so it looks like now we've got those scaled properly, so
there we go and we can sort of double check that that's true.
Does appear to be true.
Good.
So now we've got that scale and again, that's just applying.
That's just remembering that the GL scissor is in
No space.
Just like Jill viewport is and so gr viewport was applying a scale
transform that we were not compensating for and now we are.
Now the thing that I don't know is did that fix our other problem can
go back to software rendering being off by default.
So, now we fixed that sort of window, oops, window version here.
Right.
So that all looks good.
But what happens with our switch?
Oh, I accidentally destroyed my little half version here.
Let's put that back.
What happens if we say that we want the back buffer to be 960 by 540?
How does that affect things?
Now, right?
So, it looks like thankfully, that was the same problem, just not
applying that.
So now we're in a situation where we can also count on on that to work
in the hardware render as well.
All right, so scale bug resolved as far as we can tell.
Today is day 3, ft 5, right?
Yeah.
So taking a look here, now, let's see.
We've still got some time left, and it looks like we only have one bug
left which is the software.
Renderer a drawer.
Tony's could bask in draw, a rectangle of the fill wrecked is less
than four blocks wide.
Only the start that mass will be used, ignoring the end of the best
thing to wide, rectangles if it's less than four weeks twice to our
capacity to B, anded the end clip, Mass pre pre Loop.
That makes some sense.
We don't use fill wrecked a whole heck of a lot.
We never really tested it.
We just kind of threw it in there and so I feel like that's very
likely to be wrong.
Indirect and quickly, there shouldn't be a need for the clip masks.
The Fill wrecked still needs to be rounded up down as the UV 0.
1 comparison should make it redundant.
I think that's a very good point.
That's a very, very good point.
So I think both of those things are probably true.
Let's take a look.
So here's draw a rectangle and we're in the fast case here, which is
this case.
So there is the start and end the Basques.
You can see them there.
And we're just looking up, which one of them are going to do.
Right, we say, okay.
Let's go ahead and and see whether we need to do either of them.
Take the star clip.
Mask will take the end clip mask and off we go and then we come in
here, we start with the start clipping mask and we always use it and
then we only switch to the end clip mask at the end here.
So yeah if we if we have a wider rectangle, if we have a narrow
rectangle that wouldn't work.
So yeah, I think what we want to do here is say
If we know that we're not going to fill enough pixels, we need to add
them together.
Nice.
And that's not particularly difficult, right?
All we're talking about here is like start clip mask.
And the end clip mask.
We're just talking about that, right?
Where we and these two together.
And so, the only question if because again, that'll make sure that it
will only use what's available in both the start and end clip Master,
they're actually work together.
but the problem here is, we need
Made to determine when that actually needs to happen, right?
And the case for that needs to happen is if the fill wrecked Max x
minus the full erect in X, right?
If that is going to be less than or equal to 4, I believe, right?
So if if the total total number of pixels that we're doing is, you
know, is 0 1, 2 or 3
And I guess for wouldn't matter because the start would be full.
So I guess it's really just three right at the total number of pixels
that we're going to be doing is less than or equal to 3.
Then we know that we're inside a single the entire rectangle fits
inside a single vertical column of four pixels.
We need to make sure that we use both the start and and clip masks in
that case, believe that's the case.
Now, I don't know that we're actually using any of those rectangles
that would actually fall into this category, unfortunately.
So yeah.
I'm not sure we can really test this in any useful way.
I suppose if I turned off some things, we could see what the sides of
that rectangle was when it was being drawn like right now, you can see
that there's kind of a little weirdness to it.
I think that must be incorrect.
Although I don't know if that's just because of Z fighting because we
can't actually tell when we're still drawing stuff here.
What if I turned off?
Anything that wasn't pushed wrecked there.
So we weren't getting any of those.
What I could do is just say like okay in render group push wrecked.
Let's see.
Well, the problem is that push for outline actually uses that I
suppose.
What I could do here is just do like this sort of thing.
This is, this is not going to be.
I will do it a slightly different way.
So I'm going to go into entity, I'm just going to turn off.
Places where I am drawing that.
So that's in traversable.
I'm just going to go ahead and say don't do that.
So, there we go.
And now we should be able to test these a little bit better.
so yeah, you can kind of see their like
Definitely not correct.
So, let's take a look at that.
so yeah, if the fill wrecked
One thing I do want to do is I want to see if zero here.
Let me take this out and let me take a look at config as well.
I'm going to set this true.
What was the 30-ish?
Here we go.
So that's just how that's working at the moment.
so, essentially what we need to do is make sure that we're actually
doing this test correctly
Because maybe we weren't.
So, let's see how that was working.
So the fill wrecked.
So the this fill wrecked is not the rounded version, right?
Somewhere.
We must round this up to 4 pixels at a time, although I don't know
where that actually is happening.
So let's take a look at that.
Let's see.
Min max and Min why?
And we do plus equals four.
So I'm not sure where that's actually happening.
Interesting.
So I guess we never actually bother rounding this.
At all.
Am I right?
Hmm.
Something is very confusing here.
I don't really understand.
I'm going to have to double-check this here because I'm missing
something crucial.
So when we start out and we just grab this here,
here's our row pointer, and here's our Min X Min y, right?
And what I don't super understand is I don't see where this is getting
aligned to, you know, where Min X is getting a line to 24.
Oh, there it is.
I see there.
It is, right there.
So this expands Min X Out 24 and this expands Max, except for okay,
good good, good.
I don't know why I was looking looked right past it, so this does the
rounding to like broaden the thing out so that were properly looking
at the right number of values.
And when we look at those two, I guess the problem here, right?
Is that since this is post expansion, it will always actually be
greater than that.
So because remember, if we expand once it's expanded it will always
occupy at least one row of pixels there, right?
If it's going to draw anything at all.
So we actually need to do here is we need to make sure that if we
ended up.
So when I did the less for that was incorrect.
It's really just if we end up with exactly four,
Exhales to fill.
So we're just doing one column, then they need to be added together
and I think that's the only thing, right?
That should have been the only thing anyway.
And yet.
Does not appear to be so.
Why not?
Well.
I want to step in been a long time since I wrote that code.
It's going on here.
Are we in?
Well, we're in a debug build, why?
Why do I not seem to have a compiled version?
Draw a rectangle.
Oh, duh, that's in the platform layer.
It doesn't get hot Reloaded.
There we go.
Much nicer.
All right.
Yes.
We have to fix that Jitter at some point.
Drives me nuts.
So that's much much nicer.
Now it draws the right size rectangle, so that's good.
Everyone's happy.
I think that's good to go.
And then the other one is a lot more subtle but I don't think it's but
it's pretty easy to do.
So if we go ahead and hear it, let's hear is our our draw a rectangle
quickly routine which, of course is not actually, it's actually draws
a textured rectangle.
The in aptly named the point that he was making about this, one is a
good point and that's essentially that hey, you know, we've got this
start and end clip masks here.
We're doing some work not much work but we're doing some work to set
up but if you look at what happens with them, the right mask should
always be taken care of them, right?
And the reason why I thought I needed these clip masks in here was
because hey, you know, we've got a clipping region that comes in from
the outer code that we need to obey, right?
but,
We always want that to be aligned anyway, right?
We never want to be drawing something when we do our like are tiled
rendering, we would never want those tiles not to be clipped properly
to a 4 byte boundary, right?
So I mean for my boundary, a for Pixel boundary which is 16 bytes
because that's how our that's our right granularity and so we kind of
need that to be happening anyway.
And so, in fact, we probably want them a cache line boundary aligned,
right?
We probably want them 64 byte aligned so that the different tiles
aren't sharing part of a cache line on the overlap as well.
So there's a lot of stuff that we probably want to do there.
So what that means is that we don't really need these start and unclip
mass because since we're never worried about,
Since we know that our clip region will always be aligned to those
those four by four is right?
Oh,
No but you know what?
There is one reason why we still have to do it.
Those start in and clip masks we do need because otherwise they
wouldn't work with stuff like this.
this guy, remember this, clipping that guy needs clipping to a
rectangle in addition, which is not going to be pixel aligned
All right.
So I think that's that's that and hey, guess what?
We are literally just in time.
For the Q&A.
So I think we have successfully done all of our issues and we can end
the new year with, with nothing on the actual issue list except this
one, which is done.
I just have to actually recompile and switch to it, but that's good.
Unfortunately, we still haven't done the fix the room testing thing.
But that wasn't on our issue is so that's okay.
I'm not gonna complain about that one, but I'll
The Q&A here a little a little bit early to minutes early, since
there's nothing else to do.
And happy New Year k'nuckles.
I guess.
Are you in?
Where are you in?
You're not in Moscow, are you?
I thought maybe you were.
I can't remember.
Jim says, in the compression code, there is an assert literal count
equals 0.
It seems to fire on some files, should the literal buffer be flushed
after the loop in case it didn't end.
On a run.
So, let's see.
Well.
So really there must be a bug in that case.
I mean, you can see how it's meant to work anyway, and you know, we
wrote this code kind of fast and whatever.
So, you know, I'm not going to pretend that there's not lots of
possibilities for four nuts stuff in here.
But so what's supposed to happen is in equals in, end is supposed to
mean, we got to the end of the buffer and so at that point, right?
At the at the end of the buffer, it's supposed to flush.
It supposed to go in here and flush.
Right, I guess the problem here is that in equals in and break will
trigger first.
So the problem, I think the whole problem is really just
This probably has to happen.
Here.
And yeah.
Let's just check that a little bit.
I think you can also do test now as well, right?
Matt succeeded or think.
Six is seated.
Anyway.
All right.
We should probably add that here.
Hopefully, that helps.
Yeah, the size that are you going to consider resize and debug display
for a lower display resolutions?
Or would that not really be worthwhile since it's not part of the
final game.
Yeah, the latter, I would say again stuff like that kind of depends in
terms of like a real project where, you know, you're not dealing with
constraints of like a, it's an educational stream and we have to, you
know, make certain concessions to how we do things and stuff like
that.
Basically, what happens is, you have to think about what your end goal
is for the code.
And so, in some circumstances I would say you should in some
circumstances.
I would say you shouldn't in the case of him a hero I think that would
probably just be a waste of time, right?
Because we've gone over how to do stuff like that.
But you know we we it's not a mystery like I hopefully anyone who's
followed the series can go go do that if that's what they want to do.
But in other circumstances, it might make sense to think of that as a
more higher priority item and the case that's more higher programs
like let if you were trying to build like an engine or something that
you're going to use on multiple projects and there's a long lifetime
for it and things like that, then it makes sense to pay attention to
human factors, sorts of things.
When you're, you know, when you're just talking about debug code or
utility code,
right?
So the way that I would think about that is just how often do you do
you envision this code being used, you know, try to spend the time
proportional to how much you think will actually be happening there.
So for example,
You know, let's say we're building a product like Unity or something
like this, right?
Where we're trying to ship like an engine that lots of people are
going to use, then it makes a lot of sense to go.
Oh, hey, we should make sure look, our debug code is aware of the
screen size and has multiple things like this and all that sorts of
stuff, right?
And so I think that's like the, their way to think about it is just is
this part of the end product or not.
And just saying part of the end product is, is like I said, it's kind
of a little bit of a deeper question because it doesn't just mean
like, oh, if no player is ever going to see this and don't do it, it
could be that if lots of developers are going to use it, you know,
more than just the one who's sitting here and knows what machine
they're working on.
So, if I was a team of like, you know, on team of
Any people I might take more time even if we're not show me as an
engine, I might take more time to worry about human factors stuff in
there because I know it's x 20, how many people are going to have to
deal with this?
Then it starts to make a little more sense, right?
and so, you always have to
Fry.
I mean, every exercise in programming is about trying to make sure
that you're spending your time in ways that are going to be useful on
handmade hero.
That tends to be an odd decision because what's useful tends to be, is
there something educational to be shown here?
But in a project that has nothing to do with that, the product that
just about shipping a game or shipping an engine or shipping whatever,
then the calculus is still the same, but the goal changes.
And so then it becomes about well or
Right.
I still want to be making the exact same kind of a mental trade-off
model where I'm saying, where is the most useful place for my time but
the metric is, how much time will this save other people?
How good will this make the end product for the people who eventually
buy this thing?
You know, is this something that's going to be used in the future?
How much time will?
I save my future self on future projects.
All of those things have to start to come into it.
Then at that point because now your metrics of what makes
In terms of where to spend your time change.
So on handmade hero, what I spend the time do I know?
There's no reason for it, I'm not teaching anything useful at that
point, obviously, we don't eat it because we're always on a 1920 by
1080 display.
So it would just be a waste of time but in another circumstance it may
very well not be worth the time.
And so it's important to distinguish between what's a waste of time to
us is not a waste of time to somebody else.
And all of that is just a part of being aware of the circumstances.
Programming who is being affected by it and whether or not those
decisions make sense in the greater context.
We bit off topic but have you ever considered setting up a green
screen chroma key for your stream?
No, I haven't again just because I don't really care much about
production values because I feel like that's just a rat hole that you
can go down and the stream is just here to provide programming
information for people who want it.
And you know, I intentionally never have gone out of my way to try and
encourage.
Rich people to come.
Watch it.
It's just here for people who want to come watch it.
We don't advertise.
We don't have high production values.
We don't we don't really do anything other than just coding.
And so you know, doing anything that fusses with trying to make the
camera better or something like that is is just in time.
Better spent making programming resources for the goals of this
stream.
What are your 2017 resolutions for handmade hero?
None?
Really like I said, just try to
Out.
Useful coding.
Stuff right.
MTS box.
Shouldn't the clip?
Rect only be rescaled at the same point that the offset is done.
Only the main buffer should have it.
Well no, I don't think so.
Let me just double-check
No.
So if you take a look at what happens here, opengl buying frame
buffer, always uses the window within the window height in all cases,
right?
So whenever it does bind frame buffer, it's going to it's going to set
up.
That scaling transform the only thing that changes between the two is
Is the offset.
So so I believe the answer to that is no the scaling always occurs.
I know high production value stream looks good and there's a frame
around the scare cam and a nice little fade in time or that seems like
more effort than a lot of what I see.
Well, yeah, I mean, I probably says more about the low production
values elsewhere, but that the timer is actually just adapted from an
MP3 player I wrote.
And so I didn't write any of that code new.
I just copied it and we needed a timer to make sure that we
Schedule.
So, the only thing I added there was the bare minimum necessary again,
for the stream.
And the reason that there's a window around me was because we found
when we were doing the streams that I wouldn't know when I was
programming that the that I was programming in the area where my head
was and people couldn't see it.
So again that was entirely based on necessity, not on production
values.
We weren't trying to make it look good when I first started doing the
stream, there wasn't one there, but we found it was a problem.
So again, any time
Time, the thing get, is it important for the educational purpose?
I do it, but if it's not, I tend not to do it.
Zack to said that black box is a window, not just an overlay in OBS.
Yes.
Correct.
So that is not an aspect of OBS.
That's a thing that's actually on my actual screen and it's there as a
blocker to prevent me from from basically.
It's there to make sure that anything you can't see.
I can't see so that I know, like when I come down here and I start
Thing on this line I know that when I get to where my head is I can
see exactly where it is and I won't do that, right?
And yeah, I don't really know I would you know, OBS is I mean it's
free software whatever.
So you know, I'm glad it's there at all but definitely the I don't
understand why streaming programs wouldn't have it built-in that those
things would be, you know, sort of
Blocked out so that the streamer knows that it's there.
It seems like that would be a pretty basic feature that you would
want.
Jesse are Meyer, please consider demonstrating videos, command list
extension as a way of thinking about modern Graphics Dev.
I guess what I would say is I feel like that's a little bit too far
down the 3D rendering specificity rabbit hole at the moment.
So I don't know that.
That's something that's really going to be within the scope of what we
do on the Stream.
So I don't know that that's ever going to actually happen in in the
sort of handmade hero.
That's kind of like advanced advanced 3D because in order to talk
about why you even want that or need that you have to get to a certain
point in terms of mead
That is that we're just not going to get to.
so,
Yeah.
So all right stretch
Let's close it down.
Alright everybody.
Thank you very much for joining me for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home you can always pure to
the game on handmade hero dot-org and it comes to the source code.
If you want to play around with it, we also have a forum site.
You can go to.
If you want to discuss what you saw on the video or anything about
handmade hero.
We have a patreon page, you want to support the series, we have a
schedule, but if you want to know, when we're going to be live, and
I fixed it over Christmas break.
So the schedule about in theory, should be working and it does appear
to be working, at least I think.
Yeah, looks pretty good to me, I think that's right.
12 hours ago, four hours ago and one hour join us.
So one hour to three hours, that's correct, I guess roughly.
Yeah, and it was 7-Eleven so good news, the Tweet, but I believe has
been restored to proper functioning
I wish this said, I kind of want to check this.
When did it say it?
Yeah, 94.
So 10 a.m.
the stream.
Was started 11 a.m.
So that's about the right time.
That's all good.
Thank you.
Great, Amazon deal.
Yeah, fantastic.
So anyway, that's a, that's a all set up there as well.
And we also, of course, have an episode guide.
If you want to catch up with old episodes of the series, you can go
check that out as well.
That's about it for today.
And we
We'll be off tomorrow, on account of the fact that it's New Year's
Day.
So probably most people won't even be up in time to watch the stream,
but we'll be back to our regular regular schedule of Saturdays and
Sundays.
In January where we're going to do some upgrades for the renderer to
do a 3D and then we're going to start on the gameplay code.
So we've got to sort of fun things coming down the pipe and yeah, I
guess.
2017 will be the year of gameplay.
Coding, and handmade hero, which, of course, is not really something
that I'm super looking forward to because to be completely honest, I
don't really like gameplay coding, that's why I'm in engine program or
not a gameplay programmer, but what you going to do programming,
unfortunately is oftentimes about programming things.
You don't want to program as well as things you do want to burn
because not everything is going to be something you want to program.
And if you want to be able to Do complete projects by,
You're going to have to do that.
Maybe you can always get on a team where someone else does it for you.
But usually, you're not going to be that lucky.
Usually gonna have to do some programming things that are not your
favorite.
All right.
So anyway, that's that's it for today.
Thank you, everyone for joining me.
Let me just close this stuff down here.
There we go.
And I will see you all next week.
Take it easy, everybody.