In, there we go.
Okay.
Hello everyone.
Welcome to handmade hero.
This is day 5 of programming, and I was very excited to see everyone
here.
We have done a tremendous amount of work this week actually despite
only having an hour a night.
We now have our very own animated graphics on the screen in Windows
that we wrote in tireli our self, which kind of opens the door for us,
doing absolutely anything we want to do.
So, for those of you joining us, who may be new, this is handmade
hero.
This is the
The weeknight series, you can go to handmade hero dot org and see this
is a weeknight Series.
Where we code a complete game from scratch.
No libraries.
No engine, just us.
And we see how absolutely everything works, which has been a lot of
fun and I am looking forward to doing even more of it.
So you can go up here and handmade here at dot org to find more
information about it if you would like to.
And if you have questions or anything for me, there's an email a
question button.
And if you would like the source code, you can always pre-order the
game and it comes with the source code that
we upload every night.
Alright, so let's get started.
Today is a Friday.
So we are going to be doing some recap about the things that happened
this week.
And basically we spent the first day Monday was not a very, very
interesting day.
We basically just set up our development environment and Tuesday
through Thursday.
We got animated graphics on the screen, which was pretty cool.
And so let's open up that file here.
We basically put it all in one file.
And one thing I'd like to point out is there is not very much code
here it
Really pretty straightforward which I think is pretty great.
Because one of the things that often intimidates people as they think
that, if they write everything from scratch, it's going to just be a
huge, huge, huge amount of work, but it's not, there is very little
code here and we have done it in three nights with, mostly me
explaining things.
So if you were to do this yourself, I think it would take you 10 20
minutes to put in some code like this.
It is really not much code.
What I'd like to do tonight is I'd like to kind of Step through this
and just really emphasize how every last little thing works.
So everyone can be on board with that and maybe we'll try
I to start questioning answers a little bit early if we do have time
for that so people can get drilled down to the things that they want.
But before I get started, I wanted to clear up just a few things from
emails during the week.
So first of all, I wanted to thank some.
I don't even know how to pronounce your name.
I'm sorry.
It's something like Kurt cartel, to pay for writing in because we did
not need to order a capture card.
At the end of the day.
It turned out that really all we needed to do was change OBS from
monitor capture.
To the secret other monitor capture option and I tested this and it
turns out that.
Yeah, if you if you switch it into this other mode, where instead of
capturing monitor, it's capturing a game but you select the monitor as
the game suddenly everything works and I didn't have any more
problems.
Like I was having like the disaster that happened last dream.
So thank you very much for solving that problem for us.
That is way better than getting capture card because the capture cards
was looking like they were a bit of a nightmare and had a bunch of
Backside and want to deal with.
So this is perfect.
We are running smoothly and I think everything will go well from now
on.
Hopefully, anyway, I also wanted to thank Martin vladek from, for
writing in again.
Don't know how to pronounce your name sometimes.
Because I wrote a thing here, which, which was saying, let's check if
H, redraw the redraw and own DC still matter.
And if you remember from the original part of the stream, we were
filling out a wind class structure here.
And if you go back to the documentation and you look at the wind class
structure, although we deleted
Because we were just seeing if it would do anything in here.
You can see that there is a style field and the style field.
We had put some stuff in it.
We had put in up.
That's a lowercase style.
Not a capital.
We had put this in there and basically they were a bunch of styles.
We ordered them together to set them all and I was sort of
hypothesizing is like, what exactly do.
We need these 4-H redraw.
It's basically saying that says redraw the window when you when you
size it horizontally and this is redraw the window and you sides
vertically and this is whether
You have your own DC.
We pretty much determine.
We don't eat our own d.c.
Because we didn't really amount to anything that we would need to do,
but it turns out that H, redraw and V, redraw are actually pretty good
Martin's a decoding and tested them for us, just to verify.
But basically what they what it does is it's really just a flag that
says, I need to repaint the whole window when I resize it.
Not just the section, that's new.
So, if I make the window a little bit bigger, instead of just painting
the new section, I want you to have to repaint the whole thing.
And what he pointed out was just like
Well, if we're going to be stretching our image to fit the window or
anything like that, we're going to have to redraw the whole thing.
So we probably do want those in there and you test it to make sure
they work.
That was great work.
Thank you for doing that exploration.
And I think you are totally right on the money.
So I'm going to consider that matter clothes and say that we do want
these two flags.
So we are going to leave them in there.
All right.
That is it for my thank yous.
Now.
I want to address just a quick, a quick little optimization thing, and
maybe a little bit early to talk about this, but I'm going to talk
about
It.
Anyway, one of the things that I did, when I wrote this function win32
update window is I I passed a pointer.
So, basically, we had a clot.
We had a rectangle.
When we called win32 update window, and if you see, if you go look at
where we actually called that, you can see that I got the rectangle.
It was on the stack here inside the WM paint message.
And I went ahead and passed a pointer to it.
Now.
The reason I pass a pointer to it was a bit of a habit.
Usually I tend to pass Porter's two things if the structure is get
large and this is a four-element structure, so maybe.
It's not that large.
So it's a little bit weird that I did it.
But, you know, for us, I have it sometimes, old habits, die hard, and
one of the things that someone pointed out when they wrote in and it's
a good point is that typically one of the things that you want to try
to avoid is passing pointers to things that are on the stack.
If you can't avoid it because the compiler now, no longer really knows
what's going on here.
Because, basically what happens is, if the compiler see, something
like this, where it's going to get the whole rectangle, the whole
thing will be passed fresh to the to.
Action.
That is going to use it.
There's a bunch of assumptions that can make it can it can start to
assume that nobody else is going to need to touch that thing.
It can assume basically that it is just a private copy.
That this thing is going to use itself.
There is no possibility for aliasing.
There's no possibility for anything.
What aliasing is basically something we'll get to a little bit later
and it's something you probably don't need to worry about too much
right now.
But basically it's just saying whether I have two pointers that might
point to the same memory.
And the reason that is important is because when the compiler is
compiling your code, you can imagine
If I have something like this where I've got a two pointers, let's
say, right?
A and B, if I was and these are pointing to something, this is
pointing to memory.
Both of these are pointing somewhere in memory, and we don't actually
know where they are.
Let's say, and neither does the compiler.
They're just some pointers.
Maybe they were passed into this function.
We don't know where they came from.
So if we add these pointers and I'll take them out of the function
just so we're not thinking about it in this cost function.
We're just saying somewhere somewhere in our code.
We end up with pointers and be well, one of the things that can happen
is I may want to write to a I may want to go ahead and write something
to a
Right.
And similarly.
I may want to read something from be right.
I may say that, you know, I don't know.
Some other thing here in Texas, Equal star b, or into y, equals star
be right now.
If you take a look at this code for a minute, it looks pretty obvious.
What's going on?
I'm going to.
Well, you know, I should probably even read out the values that they
are, but I think I can upcast to ensure that's fine, too.
Anyway, I'm going to read out of here.
Eight bits and shove it into these 32 bits of why it's going to look
at whatever is in the location Rhett pointed to by B.
That's going to put it in.
Why?
And then I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to write five out, just
the 8 Bits that represent five.
I'm going to write those out to wherever a is pointing to.
And then I'm going to reread be right?
Just going to reread the same thing.
So at the end of this, we are all looking at it and we say well,
obviously, right?
Y and X are the same, right?
Because here is here is the pointer to be?
We're reading it twice.
It should be the same.
So, duh.
The compiler should just load it once, right.
Just turn that into this so it doesn't have to go out to memory two
times to find out what that is.
It should be efficient.
Right?
Well, the answer is.
It cannot do that?
And the reason it cannot do that is because we have not given the
compiler enough information to know that a does not point to the same
location as be.
So it could be that this right to a right here, this right of 5 over
wrote the previous value, that was in Star B.
Because if the pointer, I mean, if somewhere outside of here, before
we got here, before we got to hear, if someone had done
A equals B.
Well, then this code just reads and writes from the same location.
So this will equal 5, right?
But this will equal.
Whatever was actually there, before we wrote the five, right?
Make sense everyone on board with that.
I hope so.
That is called aliasing.
It is a situation.
Well, is one type of aliasing.
There are actually a lot of types of aliasing, but that is pointer
aliasing.
That is what happens.
When you have two pointers that could point to the same thing and the
compiler does not know.
So there are ways you can actually mark up your code.
Now, the compiler things about the fact that there is no aliasing and
its various stuff like this.
But one of the easiest way to do it is to just not use any pointers.
So if you can get pointers out of the equation entirely, sometimes
that's more effective.
And one of the things that you'll notice about this function is, it is
small.
It is a very small function.
It is a classic candidate for what's called in lining, which is where
the compiler will go.
Hey, there is not much work being done here, maybe instead of actually
generating a whole function for it.
I will just go to the place that it's called and I will just shove the
code, right?
Actually, in
There.
And if it's going to do that, that's pretty handy.
It can go ahead and look at this and know that it's not.
It can inline it and know that it's not actually a problem to go ahead
and assume that this client wreck stuff is all the same and you may be
asking
It's totally illegitimate Casey if it's going to do that.
If I just have a star here, why isn't the compiler smart enough to
figure out that?
Hey, it's just a pointer.
We're not changing the pointer.
There aren't two pointers.
What's going on?
Why do you think there's aliasing there?
Well, the answer and you should definitely defer to to people who work
on compilers for this sort of thing.
The answer is that actually what the compiler ends up seeing at the
end of the day, isn't something quite this simple.
Oftentimes, oftentimes the optimizer happens at the end of a bunch of
things that occur inside a compiler.
It basically turns things into stuff like bytecode or pseudocode
different things called IRS intermediate, representations.
The code goes through.
A bunch of Transformations.
Comes out the other side and the optimizer gets this big goopy mess.
That's just the way the compilers work.
There's a number of reasons for it, you might argue.
It's a bad idea or or you may say that it's a good idea, but either.
Way that is, what's going on a lot of compilers.
And so at the end of the day, this will probably not actually look so
clean to the optimizer.
It'll look like a bunch of different things.
It'll actually look like four different memory, locations left top,
right and bottom that all came in here at the top of this code, and it
has to sort of go back and do memory partitioning to go.
Oh, that's what's going on.
There's a whole bunch of stuff that happens.
So, I don't want to belabor that point too much largely, because I am
not an expert on optimizing compilers by any stretch of the
imagination and Iowa, probably going to explain them poorly.
If I try to give you specifics,
X.
But point being one thing you can do to help the compiler out is if
you are passing relatively small things and you can pass them by value
nowadays.
It is probably a good idea to do that.
Whereas in the old days of probably wasn't because there wasn't as
much compiler.
Optimization stuff going on nowadays, there is so probably we should
have just done that someone wrote in to suggest that we do that.
And I think that's probably a good suggestion.
I oftentimes past things by value, a lot of times and that is probably
a good one.
So I say, we go ahead and make that.
But one thing that we could do in the future, as we could look at the
code to see,
What the difference was in this case?
It's not performance-critical.
So I don't think we really need to do that.
But it's just something to consider.
Okay.
Now that we've gotten rid of that.
Sorry, go ahead and do that.
Now that we've gotten gotten that out of the way.
I have one more email that I thought was good to go over it something
someone sent in.
Basically what they were asking, they were following along at home,
which is awesome.
The number of people following this areas along at home has been
surprisingly.
Charge.
And that is awesome to all of you out there who are typing while I am
typing, that is just totally cool.
And I love all the stuff.
You guys have been trying and sending me questions.
It's been awesome.
Anyway, what they mentioned is they said, hey when I was following
along I accidentally put this definition, the MSG, the message
structure.
I put it out here instead of putting it inside the, the actual run
loop.
I put it out here and what he was asking is essentially what is the
difference like we're what what difference does it?
Make to the actual code that gets generated where I put this.
And again, that is an awesome thing to ask.
That is exactly the kind of thing that I hope people are thinking
about, because that is the kind of minutiae that you want to learn.
Because once you learn it, you know, it forever and now, you just have
so much better idea of what kind of code is getting generated and
nowadays, people are very detached from the actual stuff.
The CPU is doing.
And again, one of things I really want to hammer home is, it's great
to stop that to actually go and reach down and really figure out
what's going on.
It makes you such a much better program or just to know.
Anyway.
The difference is essentially nothing.
You will be heartened to know that most compilers, as far as I'm aware
are pretty smart about, how they lay out things on the stack.
Now, basically what happens is when we come into this function again,
if you saw the intro to see stream, there is a stack and the stack is
basically something that is a block of memory that is reserved for our
program as it runs and it grows on the top and shrinks every time we
call and return from a function.
So we call into a function, it pushes.
Onto the stack, it basically puts on the values that we pass the
function and it puts on the values that that function needs for its
local variables.
So when we declare something like a local variable, like this wind
class here, like these integers and like that message structure is
basically just growing the stack out to make room to store that.
So instead of actually doing an allocation.
Remember we did a virtual Alec up there to Alec a block of memory
instead of doing an allocation, which is something that will sit
around for a while.
It's just putting it on that stack the stack kind of grows and shrinks
and it's just memory that ends up being reused.
You can think of it almost
You know, like a watermark, you know, it's like a we've got, we've got
this pool.
You know, we got this big old swimming pool and it's empty.
When we start the program in the water level rises and the water will
strengthen the water level rises again, and we're just using that big
empty space.
We're using the same space over and over again.
So when you call into a function, it uses space on the stack store,
the local variables, throw the parameters that it uses that sort of
thing.
When you return from that function, it backs up the stack to the
point, you know, it no longer is using that area, but then the very
next function you call Will reuse.
That same area that was used by the previous function, right?
So it's constantly getting reuse the stuff on the stack.
So the question of what happens when I declare a new thing.
Like, this is basically that it's largely for your convenience where
you put it when you put something inside a while loop, what that means
is nobody can reference it outside the while loop.
So the reason that I put it there was because basically, I didn't want
people out here.
I don't want people, maybe who are going to be.
Let's say, let's say someone right here.
I didn't want them touching this.
I didn't want them doing stuff to message in here.
That's no good.
Because messages is is
Supposed to be something that's used as a result.
Basically.
The only reason we have in the first place is to get a result from
Peak message.
So I certainly don't want them using it out there and I definitely
don't want them using it down here, which they could also do because
it was declared up here.
Remember, it is in this outer scope, the scope right here.
So anyone in that block could use it.
And so basically what I'm doing, when I put things inside particular,
blocks and functions is really, I'm just trying to make sure that they
are sort of lexically scoped.
Meaning the people who can refer to them, lexically scoped, as
narrowly as possible.
To avoid people, accidentally referring to things that they should not
be.
And while it seems like, that's an odd thing to protect against.
It actually is kind of useful because oftentimes code gets moved
around and cut and paste it.
In various ways, inside a function and you may accidentally leave
something that kind of moves to some place, it shouldn't, and you've
got a bug.
So it's just helpful to kind of put that in there.
Helps compiler.
Catch a few mistakes for you.
No.
Big deal.
If not, a lot of people who program and Street see put all their
variable declarations at the top because that, you know, C does not
have declare anywhere until C90.
That's a habit, some people got into and so on so forth and that's
totally fine.
So you can certainly be a very productive programmer without doing
that, but it's something to consider.
So when you put it anywhere doesn't matter where you put it.
Basically all that's going to happen is the compiler at its discretion
at some point during the execution of this function.
Whether it's at the beginning or right?
When it sees it, or any time like that is going to enlarge the stack
to hold it.
That is the only real requirement as far as I'm aware.
That the compiler has to adhere to, it has to be able to do that, but
it can do basically anything it wants to do to optimize it, so you
don't have to put it out here to prevent it from like basically
growing and shrinking.
Stack all the time in here.
An optimizing compiler.
I should think would be plenty smart enough to make sure that it can
always just do that allocation knowing that it's always going to have
to happen.
Do that stack grow up at the top and and and make it nice and
efficient so you can put it in there and I don't think there's really
any penalty now, it's worth noting that in C++.
If you are going crazy with your C++ - there is another thing to watch
out for.
And what that thing is, is that individual structures classes, those
sorts of things.
They can have Constructors and destructors and what?
Instructors and D structures.
Are things that happen when something comes into existence and when
something goes out of existence, they're basically function calls that
are triggered on those boundaries.
And if you had something in here like the message structure, if that
had a Constructor a Destructor, the definition of what the compiler
has to do, is it has to call the Constructor when it is created and it
has to call the destructor when it is eliminated.
So in that case, there would be something additional think about
putting it inside this while loop means that every time through the
while loop, it would call The Constructor right here.
And it would call the destructor right here at the end of the scope.
That is the compilers responsibility.
It does not have the flexibility to do anything else, unless it can
determine that.
It can safely, defer that destruction in some way it pretty much has
to do it.
That is the specification.
And so there is a real difference, potentially, even performance-wise.
Between that and this if there was a Constructor call because that
Constructor called could be expensive and the compiler is now doing
something else in the loop.
It is not just a case of it having to reserve space for this somewhere
up here, and just using it when it gets down here is not just lexical
scoping.
That is actually creating real program Behavior.
So that's something to be aware of.
We will almost never be using anything like that in this stream, but a
lot of programmers do use those sorts of things.
So be aware of it.
Okay.
Hopefully, that answer that question pretty well and we are done with
the questions from
Um, the email.
Now one more thing for those of you who are following along in my DOT
e Max file, if you look in my daddy, Max file in here, we've got dot e
Max in the Mist, directory.
I set my font to Liberation mono.
That is that is the font that I load and it turns out that that is not
a font that is often on machines by default.
So if you would like to get it, if you're, if you're trying to follow
along with my emacs file directly, you want to type Liberation mono
into your
We'll search and you can go on here to the red hat page and you can
download it that will prevent you from getting an error in the dot e,
Max file.
So, I would redistribute the font, but I don't know if that's
technically allowed.
I want everything in this package to be distributable in the public
domain.
So I am not going to include it, but you can go get it yourself.
All righty, all that said, that is the entire cleanup for the week
that I can remember.
So now is the time for us to kind of look at this code and go a little
more in-depth from what we were able to do when we were actually
implementing.
So first thing I want to do is I want to look at these Global
variables.
These Global variables are not something that I really like to have
around, like I was saying the reason for that is they kind of get a
little it gets a little confusing to know who and when and where and
so on, they're being accessed and you can do that, you know, if you
want to you can work around that.
Actually, if you have Global variables and you like to use them, there
are ways to work around that you
You things like coming here?
If you have a cleanly compiling program, you can add some random
character to the end of a variable and hit compile.
Again, and that will show you all of the places that it was used
because you will generate errors in all the functions that reference
that.
So that is one way.
You can figure that out.
But I would rather go ahead and bundle these things up into a
something that's a little bit more concise.
Again.
This is not for performance or anything like that.
This is strictly because I would like to keep the code in something in
a way.
That's a little more clean way.
That's a little
It'll more manageable so that we can see easily, no matter who is
looking at the code exactly what had to happen for these bitmaps.
For this off-screen buffer that we created that were drawing the
screen every time to exist.
And so, basically, what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to open a
struct and I'm going to go ahead and put the stuff in there.
All the stuff that we actually needed.
So we knew we needed a bit map info to describe our bitmap.
We know we needed a pointer to the actual bits of that bitmap.
We know that we needed the width and the height.
And I'm going to go ahead and remove bitmap from these because since
they're in a structure now,
we've got to know that so I'm going to go ahead and remove bitmap from
those.
We're going to have the width and the height there and
Also going to have the bytes per pixel and one of the things that's
nice about this, you can see bundle this all up together.
And now we know that anyone needs to operate on this bitmap.
We can just pass this structure and we're going to call this our
off-screen win32 off-screen buffer for now because I don't have a
better idea for a name.
So that's what we're going to use.
So basically if I just bundle those things up, now anyone who have to
use this can just get a pointer to one of these off-screen buffers or
pass by value, as the case may be, and they're not going to modify it
and then they can go to
town and they know they have all the information, they need, the
width, the height, the bytes per pixel and so on.
So I'm going to go ahead and change our functions here to actually
work on that.
And you can notice this surrender, weird gradient.
It will now take an off-screen buffer and it knows to write to it and
you can see that we're kind of Levering up.
We've got a little bit more power here.
The reason that we have a little bit more power is actually because
now we can have multiple off-screen buffers before we don't we have
those global variables.
Well, if you did render read gradient, it was always going to go in
and saying buffer, right?
Same buffer.
You could never have multiple buffers, but maybe we wanted multiple
buffers for some reason.
Who knows.
Now we have the flexibility to do that, because every time you call
render weird gradient, we're going to pass at the buffer to use and we
could have tons of different buffers if we wanted to.
So again, that's a lot of the reason for pulling things out, a global
variables for pulling things together.
It makes it clearer, and it also makes it more flexible.
So, the width and the height here, I'm just going to dereference into
that buffer.
And again, I don't know.
This is a pretty giant guy.
I don't actually know if I want to pass.
This guy by value.
We could pass them by Bali because we're not really going to change
him.
So we could actually do it this way.
And I don't know, which one's better.
You know, what, let's do this.
Let's actually go ahead and do that since the nineties, an exploration
screen.
Let's see what the optimizer does.
Let's actually
Take a look and see what the optimizer does.
If you pass this by value to see whether or not it does the right
thing in either case.
Okay, so I'm gonna go ahead and pass that buffer in here at the buffer
that supposed to write to and I will go ahead and change all of these
things that have to happen.
Bytes per pixel, also coming out of the buffer.
Now, the memory also coming out of the buffer and that looks like just
about everything.
Let's see here.
Yes, that is now clean.
Looks like it's doing it now.
The pitch was computed.
And this thing is operating off.
That one thing that we could do here is the side that the pitch is
also variable.
So we can have a little bit more flexibility with how we actually
allocate that.
So we I'm going to go ahead and put that in there.
And then I'm going to move the pitch computation down into here
because we're going to need that in a second.
All right.
So here is our off-screen buffer.
We're going to render our weird gradient to it.
And it looks like that's pretty clean.
Let me compile.
That should compile that cleanly.
Oops.
Nope.
Gotta get that out of the buffer as well.
There's really no reason to for me too, dear.
Reference those buffer, widths and Heights here for referencing by
value.
We can just go ahead and do that.
So that should be fine as well.
And so that looks like a totally reasonable compiled.
Yes.
So that is nice and clean.
Now, takes the win32 off-screen buffer and drawers to it.
Now, win32.
Resize, dip section.
That is going to take our win32 off-screen, buffer as well.
But this
Kind of interesting and something to note what we have to do here
since we are changing this thing in place.
We have two options, ladies and gentlemen, to options that we can do.
If we were to pass this by value, that basically means that we have
our own private copy of it.
Yes.
It means that when this function is called, we are getting a copy of
an entire buffer that someone else was doing not the buffer memory
itself.
Because remember that as just a pointer that's inside here and a
pointer is just 32 or 64 bits depending on how we're compiling, but we
get a copy at least of this entire structure.
So that means, excuse me.
I'm still sick today.
That means basically, any changes that we make will not stick.
So you notice we're changing a bunch of things.
We're
Change a bunch of things in the buffer here, right?
We are writing to all sorts of things.
In this buffer.
We are changing the width.
We are changing the height.
We are changing the bit map info structure.
We are changing the memory that it points to.
And we are Computing.
The pitch, we are doing all kinds of stuff.
Right?
And since that is the case, that means that when this buffer comes
into us and we get a copy if we go change that copy.
Well, the person who called us is never going to see those changes.
They're just gonna disappear because this is a local variable that's
on our stack now.
Basically, it's a parameter to us.
So what we could do is we could if we were in functional programming
style, we could return basically a new buffer to them, so we could
just return buffer here.
So that's a local variable and we could return it and they would have
to capture that return.
That's a little bit error prone.
So this is not a particularly performance sensitive function.
So, even if the compiler was going to have an easier time, optimizing
something like this.
I don't think I would prefer that.
What I would prefer is a situation where basically it gets a pointer
to a buffer and just modifies that buffer in place.
That is much much more.
What?
I would prefer now really what we want to do is We Wish Chandler qarth
was watching this stream and he could tell us if that was a terrible
idea or not.
We basically need some optimizing compiler author to come in here and
tell us how bad it is that we're doing stuff like this.
But at the end of the day, like I said, this function is called so
infrequently.
That we really just don't have to think about the performance
implications of this because it is called once whenever you resize the
window and that is also, it is not even called every frame of our
game.
It is not going to be on the critical path in any way.
So I'm a little more comfortable running that way.
I'm going to write it that way for now.
But yes, if some day for some reason Chandler ever does, watch this
stream, please tell us if we are being stupid, because that would be
excellent information to have.
So I'm going to go ahead and change these dots to the arrow reference.
We have a pointer to a buffer, not an actual buffer.
So I'm going to do that.
And the other thing that I will note is we actually store the width
and height in here.
So if we were being super conscious about space, we would get rid of
these.
I don't think that's necessary.
Because again, we've got so much memory to play with this point, and
that is a tiny, little tiny little bit of that concern.
So I'm going to go ahead and just finish up the porting here.
We got to go ahead and free the memory out of that.
We have to allocate the memory out of that.
Yes, indeed.
All of that is good and we have
Have.
Oh, right.
We change that just to.
So I'm going to go ahead and change.
Do you know what?
Everyone loves this so much in the streaming to do it again?
Kill rectangle.
I do not know why they like that.
So much, ladies and gentlemen, but they do.
So we need to do it.
You have to give the people what they want.
That's my opinion on that.
It's got to actually change that buffer as well.
And here we go, buffer width, buffer Heights again.
I am doing absolutely nothing to the code right now.
I'm just changing it to read out of that structure and that is a
little bit of an artist process.
I probably should have used a search and replace for this if I was
smart.
But what can you do you think of things after they would have been
good?
Sometimes the programming it happens.
All right.
So now we've got our resize set and it will take a buffer to resize as
well.
And now we're going to go down here to win, win through the update
window and that as well should now, basically be instead of update
window.
I think we're going to call that win32 copy buffer to window, because
that is what it is actually doing, or maybe you had will say display
buffer in window, something like that.
I don't know, whatever you like to call it.
Is your code if
Are typing in at home.
And you have a, the control, you have all the control over.
What is going to go on?
Do not let me brainwash you into typing in the names that I like.
All right.
So this guy again, we're not going to change the buffer so we could go
ahead and pass by value there.
So maybe we'll go ahead and do that.
And let's go ahead and change the width and height to come out of the
buffer.
Let's change the memory and the info that looks good to me.
Me and that should be everything except the calls themselves.
Yes, does look like that is the case.
All right.
So now we are not going to get rid of our Global variables entirely
just yet.
Maybe we will later.
But what I'm going to do is I am going to actually just declare now a
global version of this thing just to go ahead and quickly replace
those places where we call it and then we'll think about whether we
want to replace it.
We're going to call this the back buffer.
The global black buffer for now.
Let's say because we are only going to have one
I'm so it doesn't seem like a particularly important thing to actually
have that be any local to anyone.
Let's take a look here.
Okay.
I don't remember what order I even said that those things were in a
didn't mean to actually create a new file.
They're not my intention.
Sometimes the emacs keyboard shortcuts get away from you.
It is totally true.
Alright, so this is the new function prototype that I made.
We've got the device context.
We've got the client wrecked.
We have got the buffer.
Now.
This is global back buffer.
We have got the
Parameters that used to be there.
And that is everything.
And the last one is render weird gradient.
That just had to take the global back buffer as well.
So, let's take a look at that and just make sure that everything is
copacetic with our code.
Oops, change the name of that display, buffer window.
Good to go.
All right.
So now here is the part where we see whether I was correct about the
fact that the capture in OBS should be working correctly.
Now if I hit F5, let's see.
Do.
Oh my goodness.
That is not a good situation as well.
That is a good.
That is definitely good.
This is our first access violation.
One of the things I did when I pulled that off, was obviously a
complete mistake.
Probably something that was pretty simple.
But instead of going fishing right now.
I just want to talk a little bit about what just happened.
In fact, let's run the code again so you can see it.
All right.
So whenever you remember when I talked about virtual memory, a lot,
when I talk about virtual address spaces, I said that by default we do
not actually have any pages in our virtual memory space reserved or
committed.
And so, basically, what happens is, if we go touch some memory, if we,
if we have a pointer basically that we try to write to and that
pointer points to an invalid page.
Then we know that the that the operating system will will basically
get that exception you will basically cause the CPU to go.
Hey, wait a minute.
That page is not something I
It should not actually be touched by anyone.
So, it'll go ahead and raise a flag to the operating system the
operating system ago.
Oops, and it will say, hey, you are, you are touching invalid, memory.
You are trying to write in this case, right?
It could be read as well.
You're trying to write to a page that I have not actually put in
physical memory and that I do not think is supposed to actually be
ready for writing.
Now, it could be when those exceptions are raised that they're totally
normal.
Could be like remember I saying you can basically Reserve memory and
then it will only actually get committed to physical memory when you
actually.
To use it.
So it could be the operating system wakes up and goes.
Oh, he is supposed to be able to write to that memory.
So I'm going to go ahead and actually back it into physical memory now
and that's going to be good.
But that's not what happened in this case.
So we got what's called a segmentation fault Linux.
Sometimes Sig Sig V.
You'll see sometimes signal segmentation violation basically or on
Windows.
It's called an unhandled access UAE.
I don't actually know what they call themselves - but anyway, it'll
give you a basic something that looks like this where it says access
violation.
Writing location and then this is the pointer that you tried to write
to.
Now if you notice this pointer is awfully suspicious.
It's all zeros.
And basically what that means is we were trying to write to a pointer
that we never initialize.
So I probably just mess something up real quickly when I was changing
the code to be using the buffer and so we can go in and see now.
It's pretty obvious.
What happened here.
We're in the pixel at the pixel pointer was Zero.
Well, that means that our buffer pointer was probably zero because
there's no other way.
The fact that happened.
So let's take a look and see.
Yes, the memory is set to 0 0 0.
So what happened there?
Why did we?
We not initialize that the way we thought that we did.
So let's take a look.
We come here to win32 resize dip section.
Here.
We are back out.
This is the WM / call.
It's passing a pointer to the global back buffer, which at this point
should have absolutely nothing in, and it should be completely
uninitialized and it is.
So, let's go ahead and, and step into this code.
We're going to Virtual free, but we didn't have to, because the memory
was empty.
We're going to set our header.
That's all the stuff that we actually wanted to do.
That's all perfectly good.
We're going to try and allocate memory here.
The bitmap memory size.
Oh,
well, there it is.
Ladies and gentlemen, there is the problem.
There that that bytes per pixel, huh?
Awesome.
Well, I hope you guys caught that that was a pretty simple mistake,
but just to be completely clear on what happens, remember, I had B 4
pixel in here and I moved it out and I did not actually set it to
anything.
So that's a, that's our problem.
We got to said by special equals equals for their.
This would probably be a good time to talk a little bit about
assertions.
I'd want to put them off a little bit till later, but the so I have
not been putting them in the code at all.
Assertions are things that probably would have caught that Air Force.
But at the end of the day, one of the things you have to remember,
it's not that important to catch all errors.
Basically, that is an error that will manifest itself.
Very cleanly, if we have an allocation failure.
We will immediately have an access violation.
So, those are not the kinds of errors that we really need to guard
against that much.
Basically, there's two kinds of Errors.
There are areas that are very Insidious and difficult to find.
There are errors that don't manifest themselves very often and there
are ones that will happen.
Every time you run the program.
If you have an error that happens, every time you run the program,
that is not an error.
You have to be
Not at all.
You do not have to worry about preventing that kind of an error
because you will always find it before you ship.
The kind of error that you do have to worry about, is the kind of
error that does not happen on every run through the program so that
you may not find it until you ship and that is bad news.
And so this is probably not the kind that you should be too concerned
about.
But even so that is the kind of thing that if I was putting assertions
in this code probably would have found it.
And so that is something that we will probably cover it is 8:30.
Right now, there's more stuff I want to do.
So we're going to leave assertions until about two or three weeks.
Now, but so I will not quite do that, yet point being, that was the
problem.
If you didn't catch it.
What happened is?
We used to have B 4 pixel in here set to 4 and then I change it to
being in the buffer, but I neglected to initialize it before, that was
just a stupid stupid thing to do on my part.
And so, what ended up happening is when we went in here to compute the
size of the bitmap.
Well, we multiply the width times the height and got the number of
pixels that we needed.
And then we wanted to see how much memory we need for all those
pixels.
We multiplied it by zero, being guess what?
You don't need any memory to store pixels, that have no sir.
I so it ended up generating a zero, which past 02 virtual Alec and
when you pass 02 virtual allocate passage is 0 right back because hey,
it does not have to reserve any pages to store nothing.
Not a surprise.
So we should be back in good working order unless I made another
stupid mistake.
Let's go ahead and double check that.
Excuse me.
Again.
I apologize.
Hopefully, I'll my sore throat will be gone by next week.
That is a much better looking size.
We are in much better shape.
Now.
I think we should be good to go.
So I'm gonna go ahead and remove that break point, and there is our
beautiful pattern.
Now, you will notice how silky smooth that is tonight.
Hopefully, it's silky smooth on stream.
It's silky smooth for me.
And again, that is thanks to Kurt.
Thank you for writing in.
We would have been in
Dire Straits without you my friend.
Okay.
So now that that is working, that is basically a very, very simple
thing that you can do that.
I have shown, which is basically just taking something that was a
bunch of little variables.
Pulling them into a structure and now you have code that operates on
that structure, which means you can have as many of those
As you want to and you also have a much easier time, reading things
because everything that you need is in one place, so that's always a
good thing.
Now.
If you want to take this one step further, we could even get rid of
this Global variable.
There really isn't much reason to do that because even though it makes
it a little bit cleaner sometimes to do stuff like that.
You don't want to go crazy and start doing things that you don't
really need to do because doing things that you make the code cleaner
and some conceptual sense, but that don't actually have any real
payoff for you is just making busy work and that is a bad idea.
There's a lot of that that goes on in programming, a lot of people who
do things because conceptually they believe something is cleaner, but
really at the end of the day, it's just what produces good bug-free
code in the least possible amount of programmer time.
That is what you're looking to do.
Oh, and it should be performing obviously that goes without saying.
So if you are doing something that is strictly for some kind of
conceptual cleanliness, you are actually doing something wrong because
if that claim this doesn't ever does not pay off for you if it's
purely conceptual and not practical, that is a waste of time.
And time is of the essence, especially here on the stream because we
only get an hour, a night.
Ladies and gentlemen.
All right, where to now, what I would like to do.
I think this program is relatively good so far.
I don't have a lot of complaints about it, to be honest with you.
But there's one more thing I wanted to pull out and that is that we do
this.
Get client wreck thing a lot.
I was thinking maybe I would go in here and do something that that
basically made this a little bit easier for us.
So I'm going to go ahead and make a little helper function.
It's very simple.
It is just going to be called.
To window dimensions.
That's all it's going to do.
It's going to return a width and a height, just a very simple pair and
you will notice the reason that I'm doing that is you see this in a
number of places, get client rekt, get client wrecked.
And then it has to do stuff with the width and height that sort of
thing right there.
So what I'd like to do is just get rid of that redundant code a little
bit because it's kind of looking a little ugly and I don't love it.
I don't love calling doing the same thing multiple times like that.
So I am just going to make a very simple call just for
my own sanity and convenience that is called get window Dimension, and
it'll take that window handle and give that back to us.
So there it is.
That is the entirety of what we actually want to do.
So, I'm just going to Claire.
One of these.
This is going to be the result and it is just going to instead of
creating local variables with the height.
It's going to write that result and then it is going to return it.
That is it.
That is all I wanted to do.
And so now I can go down to the places that we did get client wrecked.
And instead of doing that.
I can do win32 window dimension.
I can ask for the dimension, get window Dimension and I can pass that
window now that will clean up nicely.
And here, we can just go ahead and pass those Dimensions to our resize
call.
That looks good to me.
We can come down here to the same thing that was happening and and
actually do the exact same thing and I'm going to change this display
buffer in window call because instead of taking a client rekt, I would
prefer that it actually took the window Dimension because that is what
it actually needed.
So I'm
To actually pass the window.
And the window height here, so that it doesn't have to deal with those
wrecks structures.
And that makes that code go through the exact same path as the
previous code, which is always good.
So, it's good to have the less code pass.
The better if you can avoid having multiple ways of doing the same
thing for no reason, just means it's easier to change later.
And more likely to find bugs.
Because if there's bugs in each individual place, you do something.
Well, if you find and fix one.
Now, you gotta go and remember, to find a fix all the others.
All right.
So what I basically did there is, I said that when we're going,
Back to the screen and start taking that client record.
It's going to take a window within a window height and you can see
that all that had happened.
There is actually I move that window width and height computation that
used to happen into here.
So that's going to go away as well.
So now we have it all done in exactly one place.
That is pretty awesome.
And I love it.
When code comes together like that.
You really can't argue with it course.
This is this is child's.
Play with training wheels here.
Obviously, we're just cleaning up some really simple clothes so I
wouldn't get too excited about it necessarily, but honestly, you know,
what can I say?
It makes you happy, it makes you happy.
Know what?
I forgot to prefix.
That thing.
Why do I keep hitting that hotkey?
Is that is a hotkey that I should not be hitting.
OK.
What I want to do is just add that win32 there because I was, I was
kind of following that convention, and I'd like to do that.
Just so we know that things that are in our win32 platform layer.
Have a win32 in the front.
I'm just makes it a little nicer, makes it a little easier for me to
see.
So we are going to go ahead and get the window Dimension, here of that
window.
We are going to go ahead and delete this.
And then we can pass the past the dimension like that.
There we go.
Okay.
Yeah.
Well, you know what, I call the full Dimension there.
Let's let's let's be consistent for desistance sake.
It is the hobgoblin of small minds, they say.
But you know what?
Maybe our mind is small tonight?
You know what, that could just be the case.
All right, we are done with that.
If I just can clean up the fun up.
That's right.
Casey.
Nice.
Gotta love the typos.
Okay, and here we go.
Dimension with
With and dimension .height.
Okay.
Now you may ask why I'm cleaning that up.
Why do I keep passing Dimension, width and height instead of just
passing the dimension itself?
And the reason is because one thing that you want to make sure that
you do is you don't go overboard with your type rapping.
So the reason that I created that structure, the reason I created this
structure right here is because I can't return to values from AC
function.
You can only return 1.
And so when I want to return to, I go ahead and make a structure that
bundles, those two together.
That's why this is here.
Otherwise, I just returned to integers and there's languages that
support that kind of thing.
And if you're using one of those, that is what you should do, there's
no need to actually name this it is not important, but
When I actually start passing things, if I was to go down here and
let's say, change this to taking you to mention or change this ticket
to mention.
What I have basically done is I have forced everyone who is ever going
to call these functions in the future to bundle those things two
together.
Again, they are now forced to create one of those structures in order
to call.
Function even if they already had the width and height from something
else and that is not something that I want to do.
Because basically, when I make a function, I want the most number of
people to be able to call it in the most number of circumstances
because that is what gives me leverage.
And that is what allows me to reuse code, the most often.
So you don't want to get carried away with wrapping up your types.
The only time you really want to force people to pass types of
something, is when those types literally have to all go together.
Now, for example, in this Austrian buffer, that is a good cake, making
a good case for that.
Because all of
These things are related, the pitch, the height, the width, the bytes
per pixel, the memory in the info all go together and they cannot be
used separately because there are all interdependent.
Basically, this memory has to be a size that's dependent on the width
and the pitch in the height and the bytes per pixel.
And this info is set up to be specifically this layout.
You cannot arbitrarily combine these things together, but win32,
window Dimension is just an arbitrary width and a height that could
have come from anywhere.
It could have been from any window.
You may have gotten it not from calling this and so I don't want to
force people to pack things into some structure.
Just to do it.
So, I didn't.
Let's double-check to make sure that we have not introduced any
heinous Errors By typos.
We have not, that looks pretty good.
Our resize is still working.
So that's good as well.
And that is all good.
Now.
I think that probably, at this point, what I would like to do is go
ahead and see, you know what?
I might make one more thing before we drill down in the queue a little
bit because we've got about 17 minutes left.
So there is one more thing that I think I'd like.
Try.
Maybe.
This is a bad idea at the at this point in the Stream, but I'm gonna
try it.
Anyway, what I would like to do is I would like to start using our
stretch flick called to actually stretch our bitmap.
I want to basically allocate this bitmap instead of allocating in the
WM size command.
I am going to stop doing that entirely.
I'm just going to go ahead and say we're not doing that anymore.
Instead.
We are going to resize our bitmap right here.
We're basically just going to go ahead and say that when we start up,
we are going to make our bitmap, a particular size.
We are going to make our bitmap.
Let's say 1280 by 720 that is going to be the size of
of our back buffer.
That is the way that I want that to work.
And so now when we go in and we do resize dip section, we will do
that.
Just once we will not do it on the double size and that bump back
buffer will just sit around and get updated by us.
Now, when we actually call Winter display buffer in window that will
stretch it for us, because remember, we're passing the buffer width
and height with will now be always be the same.
They won't be changing, but we will be passing a different window with
and different window height.
So if we go in here and run this you will now see
That basically, as we, as we stretch, oh, that does not look good at
all.
Well, when I said, you will now see, as you will now, see a bug is
what you will see.
So that means, we are passing some incorrect things here.
What did we do wrong?
Oh, that's fantastic.
I I just assumed I know that the bug is here because I feel like I
remember, I feel like we've typed the wrong things in there, even
though we read the manual, ladies and gentlemen, we've read the
manual.
But we must have ignored it because I am pretty sure those are in the
wrong order.
Let's take a
It is the destination first.
Well, guess what?
People?
That is not the destination.
The buffer is our source.
The window is the destination.
Those are in the wrong order.
That is no good.
That has been a bug.
That's been lurking in there before they were both the same so it did
not matter and that is true.
But now we have fixed it.
And there we go.
So there we are.
We're stretching, and that's totally fine.
That's what we wanted to have happen.
But I would point out that, that is not a particularly good stretch.
Ladies and gentlemen, that is not a fantastic stretch.
It is certainly not doing a lot of filtering and help us out there.
So that's something to be a little bit concerned about something to
think about.
So we'll have to play with that a little bit for the time being
though.
That means we do have a back buffer that size the same and that is
something that I want to start out with.
And we will have to think about how we're going to deal with some of
those things because stretch stretch TI B, may not be enough.
When I mean, not be industrial-strength enough for us, but we'll think
about that as we go.
It's totally fine for now.
So one of the thing that's going to happen here is if we stretch in
some kind of way that that actually does something bad.
They're right.
We're stretching like this.
We're stretching like that we end up basically distorting the aspect
ratio of our image, right?
We are drastically.
The aspect ratio.
So if this was our little handmade hero, he would be squashed, you
would be squashed horizontally or he would be squashed vertically.
So what I want to do here is, I want to just take a second to go ahead
and actually correct the aspect ratio when we do the split.
Because I want to show you a little bit of math for that.
It's very simple math.
Nothing really too too much.
So basically what we're going to do here is we're going to try and
figure out basically how.
All right I got think about this carefully, 15 minutes left.
These are the kind of decisions that are hard to make.
You know, what?
No, we're going to say the aspect ratio for later.
The reason why I stayed the aspect ratio for later is because it's
probably true that we will want to do this.
In floating Point.
Maybe not, maybe we want to do it, integer.
I don't know.
It's such a tough decision.
Sometimes the decisions I face on the stream.
When the time is, when the clock hits the clock that makes a decision
difficult.
I don't always know whether we should go for it or not.
Well.
The answer is no we're not going to go for it.
So I'm just gonna drop it to do in there.
I'm going to say aspect ratio correction, and we will have a thing
where we actually make sure we do that early in the Stream so we can
take the time to talk about how we're going to do it and do it 100%
correctly.
So for now we're going to get a squash and that is totally fine.
But otherwise we are totally good to go.
Alright, so last thing I wanted to do before the Q&A is we are going
to go ahead and step through our code and make sure we understand what
all of it does.
So that everyone who followed us for this week.
Can make sure they really solidify their understanding of how the code
goes.
So, let's go ahead down here and let's just set a breakpoint.
Again.
That's F9.
Ladies and gentleman.
Let's set a breakpoint right at the beginning.
This is the first time that it enters our code.
Now.
Remember, we are not the first thing that happened.
The C runtime library has already done a bunch of stuff, but there's
not much we can do about that at the moment.
There are ways to compile without it, but I don't know if we
necessarily want to go there.
We may try to some point and when we are feeling brave, anyway, we go
through.
here, and we are basically
Going to start by putting this window class initialize, it to 0 that
again, is going to initialize the window class.
20 basically, because we have not put anything in the little brackets.
That is the clue to the compiler to initialize it to zero.
And where is that going to go?
Where is any of this stuff?
Go, all of this stuff goes on the stack, all the stuff goes on the
stack, these parameters.
Go on the stack, the window class, one on the stack, and just to
reinforce that lets go ahead and take a look at that memory window.
Shall we?
Here is the memory window?
This is the memory in the computer.
And actually, you know what, I get.
I think I want that in different places.
I'm going to go ahead and just drag the memory window and I'm going to
go ahead and drag it down here so that it ends up down in here.
That is not what I wanted.
Ladies and gentlemen, I need to be a little more precise with my drop.
There we go.
Okay, that is the memory window.
That is what I wanted.
I'm going to go to the watch window and I'm going to take the address
of that window class and so I can see where it is.
So I'm going to take that address.
There is the address right there.
You can see it.
It is a 64-bit address because we're in 64-bit mode.
So we have big memory space.
I'm gonna go ahead and paste that in here and hit return.
So this is where that window class.
As you can see, it.
It is not all zeros right now.
It is got stuff in it.
Right?
And I'm going to go ahead and hit F5 to step over.
I'm sorry to hit F10, to step over this line.
And you can see that it all got cleared 20 down there, right?
So that is what's happening.
This is the stack right here.
And I just want to point out that if you look at where that is to c f
5 F 0, right?
To see F 5 F 0.
Where did you go?
Right there?
Let's take a look at those parameters, instance, prevent students.
And command line just so we can see where they live as well.
There you go.
You can see that they are.
All right next to each other, which is what we would have expected.
Because it looks like compiler has pushed them onto the stack and push
them on the stack.
Sequentially.
We can see what order it put them on in the stack as well.
Right?
You can see they go in order here, 30, 38, 40, and 48.
And if we go ahead and look at where that is, we can see there at to
CF7.
They are a little bit further down.
I will widen this out.
So basically here is the one that we were talking about before 5, F 0.
It is right there.
That is that one and the sevens were over here.
If I remember correctly.
Yes, they were.
Okay.
And so what that leads me to believe, although I do not actually know
that would suggest that it is pushing these.
That the stack is growing downwards.
I don't actually know if that's true, that may not be true.
It seems odd that it would push them in that order.
So I'm not sure what order the stack is growing in.
So
Let's go ahead and see if we can figure that out.
Let's take jump up.
The call stack one.
I just want to know where the stock is going up or down because
honestly, it's been so long said, look at anything like that.
I have no idea on x64, which is what we're doing.
Now.
I have no idea at this track gets bigger off, the bottom of the stack
or off the top of Stack.
Let's find out.
All right, so see here's a here's a variable in it Rhett.
Let's see where that is.
Oh, it was optimized away.
All right.
Well, alright so much for that.
Let's call into one of our functions then and
See where it is.
So let's go down here real quick.
Actually.
You know, what?
No, we can do.
I do that.
We can actually do that right here.
Now that we're allocating our back buffer.
All right, let's take a look window class.
That is where window class was placed on the stack.
That is this location in memory, 1 FF C a0 and all I want to know is
whether it's that grows downward or upward meaning, when you push new
things on the stack, do they go at higher addresses or do they go at
lower addresses?
That's all.
I wanted to know.
Just wanted to get that out in the open.
So let's take a look.
At where some of this stuff goes.
So here, we are bitmap memory size.
That is a local variable.
It should be on the stack here.
Let's see where it is.
And so one, FF C a0 and we have one FF bf0.
That looks a lot to me.
Like we are growing downwards, ladies and Gentlemen.
Let's just verify that that's true.
That does not necessarily surprised me, but I just want to make sure
that that is true.
That is the wrong way to go.
So this is the value that is lower.
This is the one that's further down in the function, basically.
In the depth of the function.
This was the one bitmap memory size.
And so this was a function that we called the most, the deepest nested
function.
And here's the one from the function that called it hit return.
It is 176.
Yes.
So our stack is growing downwards with that means, is that every time
something new is pushed on the stack.
It goes at lower and lower memory addresses, which is a little odd
because normally you think of things is growing and getting higher and
higher but it looks like the stack is going downwards.
Just something is good to know, does not really affect anything in any
particular way, but just something interesting too.
Think about also, I guess that means, and those of you who are
hardcore assembly guys, correct me if I'm wrong on this.
I don't want to speak out of turn.
But I guess that means that if this is the value that the stack is
that now that's the entirety of the stack size.
We actually get.
So basically we can only add about 2 megabytes to the stack before we
would get to the null page best.
So it can't be any more than that.
Our stack must be less than 2, MB.
I don't know if that's actually true.
But that's what that would seem to suggest to me.
Do you understand that?
Do you guys
Stand that at all.
Basically, what I'm saying is if I've got a local variable in this
function right here and I say, where is that, right?
I say, where is it tells me?
It's right here.
Well, that's where in memory.
The stack is at.
And every time we go ahead and push things on the stack, the stack is
usually continuous continuous rather.
It does not use disparate addresses in memory.
It uses contiguous addresses memory.
If we are subtracting from the stock every time, if those numbers are
getting lower than that, number certainly can't go any lower than zero
because we know that 0 is a null pointer.
And that would cause a an access violation and that whole page,
Age would be an access violation at least 4096.
So somewhere down, there is access violation territory, which means
that this pointer basically represents the max amount of stuff we can
push on the stack that value is the maximum number of stuff that we
could push on the stack.
I hope that makes some sense to people and I'm not just rambling.
But that basically means to me that says, you know, if you go ahead
here and said, well that divided by 1024, that is to, that is, that is
KB.
And if I went ahead and did 1024 x times.
24.
Just looking at at how many megabytes and it's only one megabyte.
It's a little more like it's almost 2 megabytes.
Basically, if I if I actually did this, in floating Point math, I'd
see a little bit more but that is kind of scary.
All right, so you have a 2 MB back to work with I guess that's just
how much you get by default.
Now, there are things that control how big the stack is.
Certainly you can change the stack size if you think you need more
than that, but that's just something to understand that.
Basically as you are calling functions, when you call functions, if
you were to put gigantic things on here, you might in run into
To a problem just because we are being kind of strange tonight.
I guess we could sort of see how big that default stack size actually
is.
Let's go ahead and just be, just be a little rascal, just be someone
who's who's just screwing around for fun because it is Friday.
And that is our prerogative.
Let's go ahead and see what happens at the five-minute warning.
No less if we just told this thing to allocate a bunch of memory, big
old block of memory, right?
On the stack.
I don't know how it will fare, but I'm going to
Go ahead and say go ahead and allocate 2 megabytes right on the stack.
What do you think about that?
Mr.
Compiler?
What are you going to do?
Well, it worked fine.
So I don't know what happened there.
This is a little puzzling.
This must be one of those things where I'm going to look at the stream
afterwards and you guys are going to say you're an idiot and that may
be true.
Ladies and gentlemen, I may well be an idiot.
So, let's take a look at big old block of memory, where that points
to.
There we go.
It is, uh, noops.
What did I do?
It is undefined.
Oh, well, the optimizer optimized it out.
I guess I didn't think we were compiling an optimized mode.
So I'm surprised at that.
Is that really true?
Well, see if we go ahead and clear that maybe let's see what happens
if we clear that and then maybe we'll do something ridiculous.
Since the optimizers not on.
Is that going to work?
I don't know what's going to work.
I don't know how we're going to get it to do that.
Ladies and Gentlemen.
Let's take a look.
There it is.
That's what I was looking for stackoverflow.
Thank you.
Ladies and gentlemen, we have done exactly what we tried to do.
That is great.
That is what I was hoping for now that it has not been optimized out.
Maybe I just didn't recompile.
Maybe that's what happened.
I don't really no point being basically.
What I did is I forced the compiler to make a 2 MB thing on the stack.
And since I noticed that, that particular time to the program, it had
given us an address, that was less than 2 MB away from the bottom of
memory.
I figured that the default stack size couldn't be any more than that.
Now remember in Windows first to security concerns.
Our stack will be at randomized locations.
So
It will not always be there but just noticing that I figured well,
that means that if it has to allocate stack for us to run, it could
not have been trying.
It.
It's there's obviously no way that the default stack size could have
been any bigger than that because it obviously thought it was okay to
give us, give us the memory down that low.
So what I did is I just made something to megabytes large to see,
whether it would just roll over and die.
And the answer is it did.
Now you could take a look at that error.
It basically is the same kind of thing.
We got when we were writing to invalid memory.
But this time instead of access violation.
It is a stack.
Overflow.
And that.
Exactly.
What we did.
We overflowed the stack.
We asked it to put too much stuff on there and we got this error and
that was what I was hoping to show you because I just wanted to
underscore the point that memory is not free.
It does not come from some sort of little magical memory pixie dust
Fairy Who sprinkles it on us and gives us as much as we need.
That is not what happens.
Even the stack, which is managed for us automatically by the compiler.
And by windows in some sense does not actually give us carte blanche.
We still have to be totally aware of.
How much of it we have and every time we call a function, we have to
know.
Know how much stack space were using so that we do not get too out of
control.
Now, we should never really be using something that's going to
allocate to Meg, suspect space, but you may be surprised if you were
to do something that's called a recursive function, which is a
function that calls itself and uses the stack is temporary memory,
something that we might do in the future.
Just to illustrate the point.
You can easily get in a situation where maybe you call yourself 40
times and all of a sudden each one of those things if it's just using
maybe 50 k of memory, let's say on the stack which is still a huge
amount or maybe you know, 10 K of memory that
Up to half a megabyte right there.
And that's a pretty big step a commitment.
When you know, it's less than 2 MB.
I guess.
One thing we could do is we could be a little bit more investigative
here.
And just start, instead of just looking, you know, we could always
just go look up how big the stack is right?
But what fun is that?
Why not?
Just go ahead and figure out how big it is by trial and error, right?
Okay, so we're down to two.
Let's let's go to a half, half a megabyte.
Let's see how that does half a megabyte work just fine.
Fine, so maybe we'll go up a little bit higher.
I don't know what to do here.
Maybe, something like that.
Let's see.
How that does.
We are still.
Okay, so I don't know how close we can get to one megabyte of stock in
our first function before we cause a problem, looks like we can get
real darn close to it.
Huh?
Really.
Darn close.
So let's go a little bit closer and still not stack overflowing yet.
This is going to be interesting is going to be tight.
Are you as excited as I am to find this out?
Where are we at?
All righty.
We have stack overflowed.
So we're real close.
And when I say stackoverflow, I mean the interesting kind not, the
website that has weird answers to questions that are sometimes wrong.
All right, there we go.
We are almost there.
Will binary search this down a little bit closer.
A little bit closer.
That is real real close right now.
There we go.
Okay, so we know we are basically like something like this.
Something like this.
We are really close something like,
Thousand 1000 K.
Okay.
Alright, so we know that it's somewhere between 999 and 1000 K or
maybe not what's going on there.
He'll exception during user call back.
Wait a minute.
Oh ha ha, that's pretty funny.
So we have actually started stock faulting down somewhere else because
we gave just enough stack for us to exist.
But as soon as we start calling down into
We first Windows to fault.
That is excellent.
So, we know.
Yeah, we know we have something like a megabyte of snack.
That was kind of fun.
We know, we have something like a megabyte of stock.
When we enter our first function.
If we don't tell the compiler to give us more, I think there is a flag
that basically tells the compiler to give us more.
If we were to go in here and look at that, we could search for stack
and we would probably find something.
Let's see.
Let's see, Forest parameters.
That's xi's /f numb and I said assume that.
Basically, if we did a /f we could allocate.
We could have our cake and eat it too.
Remember, we cannot make something this big we tried to make something
that big.
It was two megabytes.
Let's go ahead and run that and that totally faulted.
So now let's ask for a giant stack, ladies and gentlemen, let us just
see what we can get away with.
Let's do ten, twenty four, four times, ten.
What is going on?
That is no good.
I'm in the wrong mode all together.
There we go.
Four times.
1024 x 1024, we will just copy.
That value will get a nice 4.
MB stack in theory will go back in here and we'll go to the build
build dot bat Bill, Dot bat.
And we will do what this thing said to do.
Where was that again?
Starts ffffff.
Where was that?
Where are you?
Mr.
F f numb, so just slash F and then that value.
Okay, let's do that.
- F and that value.
And let's see if that gives us a bigger stack.
Look at that.
We can have all the step size.
We want ladies and gentleman.
That is a very very generous stack indeed.
Hopefully we will not be anything like that.
So I'm gonna go ahead and delete that but just for the sake of
completeness, I want to show you that.
We had control over it.
All right, I'm gonna go into the Q&A a little bit today, just because
I want to step through these things and this is basically an entire
day, essentially up to you a maybe, let the Q&A run a little bit long
if we have to.
All right.
Here we are.
We basically clear these things on the stack.
We are going to go ahead and initialize our Global buffer back by 4.
So we're going to claw back in here.
We're going to pass it a pointer.
Now.
Where is this thing?
Where is This Global buffer?
Will?
That's basically something that was created at the initialization of
the program.
So that's just memory and that's not on the stack.
That's memory.
That's permanent.
We do not have to worry about.
You.
See that's in a totally different location.
Nowhere near the stock, right?
If you look at where the window class is, that's very low.
And if we look at where this back buffer is that's that's very high in
memory by comparison.
So there are nowhere near each other.
Oh, and that is kind of what you'd expect because this is not on the
stack.
This is, this is data memory of our program static data memory.
That was basically created.
When we launched, the executable said that.
We basically said, we needed that memory to run all of our Global
variables, go into it.
All right.
So we going to resize dip section.
We are going to allow this call to be called as many times as we want
to.
So what we do first is we check to see whether we already allocated
memory for our buffer and if we did we will get rid of it.
If we didn't.
We basically just fill out a bunch of fields that we will need to
remember.
In height, in the bits per pixel would bite for Pixel, which is
things, we want to know.
And then we are going to go ahead and fill out that that information
that Windows needed basically, to do the blind later on.
And you'll notice we have to pass that later on.
So that's basically just basically description to Windows.
That says, we are going to pass you a bunch of memory and here is how
you interpret it.
Now.
Remember, we had this negative here.
In fact, you know what?
I'm going to go ahead and add a comment to that because a little
confusing to people who don't know what's going on.
I'm just going to add a comment there that basically says,
Note when the bi height field is - this is the clue to Windows to
treat this bitmap as top-down not bottom-up.
Meaning that the first bite of the image, is the top left, right?
So, I guess, I should say, the first three bytes of the image are the
color for the top left pixel.
In the bitmap, not the bottom left, right?
Make sense.
Okay, so that is all that is and I just want to get that out there.
All right, we compile that have really changed any code.
So, we come back down in here.
We basically compute how big we need, because we are going to ask for
a permanent chunk of memory.
And you may ask, well, why didn't we just do what we did up here?
Why don't we just declare the chunk of memory up here and we could
have done that.
That is totally valid.
The reason I didn't want to do that is because I wanted to make the
size of this bitmap bi parametric meaning.
We could change it at any time.
Time in the code.
And if we had put it up here, it would have to be known at compile
time.
We could not change it.
We could still do it up there by just doing the one that was so big
that we knew it was always as big as the biggest one we could possibly
ever need.
We could totally do that.
Maybe we will do that eventually, but for now, I want to show you how
to use Virtual lock as well.
So we went ahead and did virtual Alec which, of course, ask the
operating system to reserve memory Pages for us.
It asks us to reserve this many basically, however, many memory Pages
it needs to take this much to hold this much data to hold.
Many bytes, and the thing that you have to remember is this will
allocate in increments of the page size.
The page size.
I believe, on Windows is normally 4096.
If you are not using large pages, in which case it is 64k, what that
means is we probably will not use exactly the right amount of memory.
Here.
We will get back more memory than we needed, just a little bit more
than we needed.
So if you look here, this is the actual size we're asking for, if I am
to go ahead and divide that by 4096 and then multiply it back by 4:00.
1096.
Let's see what we get there.
Well, that looks like it actually lifted up my eyes.
It out.
Looks like we are actually right on a page boundary, if that is
actually true.
Let's double-check that just to make sure it's not doing something
fancy thing here.
So, excuse me, apologize, again for the cold.
Okay.
This is the size we had.
This is the page size that I believe Windows using.
There's a way to get that page size and we could do that a little bit
later too.
Maybe we'll do that right now.
If that's the page size.
Then we know we are asking for at least nine, hundred Pages, possibly
more and I just want to see
See if 900 Pages basically time.
Page size comes out exact and it turns out it does.
So it turns out we are asking for exactly an even number page sizes.
So we are not wasting any memory ladies and gentlemen, how about that?
Totally accidental?
Normally, what happens with virtual Alec is you will waste a little
bit memory at the end of it.
And so the thing that you typically use Virtual a look for is not to
allocate little chunks of memory used virtual allocate.
I like to get a bunch of memory that you then subdivide and that is
exactly what we'll be doing with it.
But right now we only have one allocation, our entire program.
So there's really no way we can do anything more optimal there.
So we just go ahead and call it.
It anyway, we store the bytes per pixel back here.
And when we multiply the width times, the height for Pixel to
basically get the pitch or the stride depending on what you want to
call that and basically what that is is how many bytes pointer has to
move to go from one row to the next row.
And of course, that is the width.
The number of pixels across that the bitmap is times, the bytes per
pixel because we need to remember that each pixel itself is actually 4
B.
Since each pixel is 4.
Bytes.
That means that we could not just go.
With number of bytes, we have to go with times for number of bytes
because we have to skip the RG.
The are the G, the B, and the pad for each individual one.
All right.
So when we finish, we then fill out our window class remember window
class is just something we register with windows, that tells it where
to call back when a window needs to do to actually feel the message.
We fill out an instance because Windows needs to know who to call as
well.
So if you imagine basically, when I talked about the fact that we have
a virtual,
No memory.
We have a virtual memory address space for our program, right?
Well that virtual memory address space contains our code as well.
So if you want to call us back, you have to know which virtual address
space.
You are calling back, right?
Windows needs to know which process is actually holding the function
because if I just say, here is the address of a function.
Well, that address is in my processes virtual memory space.
If you didn't know which process you are calling back.
You wouldn't know what that address actually refers to, because every
address space.
Every process is different.
So in a pointer does not uniquely identify memory in the system, it
uniquely identifies memory in one process.
And so, without the process handle Windows would have no idea who it
was even calling.
So basically, what this is, is that handle, this is the instance that
says this is the actual process that contains this pointers memory.
So interpret this pointer in its address space and then it can do the
disa dispatch.
We give our window classic.
A meaningless name because we need to do that because we are going to
pass that name to create window EXO.
It knows what window class our window is using.
Of course, we only have one so it's a real waste of time.
But that's just something I have to do.
We register the class with Windows by passing a pointer to this stack
variable that we have here.
Now, we don't have to worry about that ever going out of scope because
we won't exit this function, but we don't have to worry about it.
Going a scope period because windows will actually snap a copy of it.
It does not rely on our copy.
So we don't have to keep we don't have to make sure that that copy
stays around for as long as we use anything.
It is just going to use it to read them.
It out and then it is going to return.
And we don't have to worry about keeping it around anymore.
You need to remember that.
Sometimes you do, sometimes when you pass an address into Windows, you
have to make sure that the thing you pass the address to stays around
for the lifetime of the things that might use it.
This is not that case.
So you don't have to worry about it.
Here.
We then go ahead and do a create window e^x.
And basically, all we do is pass the window class that we wanted.
And that's so that our window knows.
So that Windows knows that our window is going to call this call back.
Anytime it gets an event.
We told that we want to be visible right away so that it shows up on
Startup and that it was a WS overlapped window, which is basically
just a
It set of flags composite set of bits in this bit field.
This is just a 32-bit value.
That's got a bunch of bit set.
That windows will look at each individual bit to determine a bunch of
things about the window.
It is basically just a composite that says, it has things like a title
bar and a closed box, and things like that, or resizable frame.
And we also pass the answer to this as well because again, Windows
wants to know what instance is calling it.
I think those are probably somewhat inaccurate Mystic these days.
I don't actually know if you actually really need to pass those to I
mean, I think you do need to pass my windows will be upset with you,
but I don't know how much they need because they know which instance
is actually calling it.
So I'm not sure how important that is.
I think those may be somewhat anachronistic but ignore that for now,
we create our window.
Our window is created, assuming that we got back a handle that was
valid.
We assume that we are ready to run, we go ahead and enter a loop.
That is infinite.
It will not exit until running a set.
False by someone else in the program running again is a global
variable and maybe one of the things I will do is change that to have
a prefix Global just so everyone knows it's Global.
I don't often prefix things.
But for Global's I often will will change that rule just because I
think it's important to be able to see when something is global.
So that's a good habit to get into.
I think something that's worth thinking about.
If you are thinking about code Styles something that's not bad to do.
Yes.
So anyway, we go ahead and enter our Loop.
We create some space on the stack for Windows to store its message
because it needs a place to write it.
We call Peak message.
And again, what Peak message will do is it will look at our Windows
window Q for our process.
It will see if there are any messages in there for us.
And if there are because we pass p.m.
Remove it, we'll go ahead and give it back to us.
Now.
I passed all zeros here, which means it will filter the messages.
It will not do anything.
Like only give us ones for a certain window or only give us ones that
fall into a certain message range.
It will then see whether or not or rather.
We will then check whether or not it was WM quit message.
Just in case Windows sent us one.
Now.
It should never send this one.
I don't think, but just in case it did, we will go ahead and set
running to false.
There.
We will.
Then ask Windows to translate message and translate message canceling
that just translates key codes.
I don't actually know how much we actually really care about that, but
it's a something that you typically do, and then we dispatch message
which will again call our window class as necessary.
Now remember Windows call our window call back anytime.
It does not need to only do it in this past message.
That's a little bit of a gotcha, you would think.
But that is not the case.
So we have to be ready.
Actually, anytime.
We call the windows call.
Just keep in mind, it could call you back.
Now after we Loop through there and pull off all the messages that
Windows has for us to pull off we go.
Head and call render weird gradient and render weird, gradient goes
through and it snaps the pointer to the beginning of our back buffer.
If then steps through every row of that back buffer and grabs a
pointer to the beginning of the row.
Remember, we are advancing row.
Each time.
We advance it by pitch each time through this outer loop to get to the
next row.
Because when we said the pitch was the thing that moves us from one
row to the next.
We then grab an individual pixel pointer by basically saying, okay,
let's take a look at row.
Now remember the pitch isn't B.
We said the pitch was going to be in B, how do we know the pitches
invites?
Well, if we look at where we computed it, you'll notice that we
multiplied it by bytes per pixel.
Right?
So we are we are looking at a value that is in B.
So when we add to the row, the row had better, be a pointer to B,
which it is.
Otherwise c will do that silent multiplication for us and we will add
too much ladies and gentleman if this preparing to a un 32, we would
actually move four times.
The amount we were supposed to
And that would be bad.
So just that's why that's a, uh, very important.
There.
We are, then going to go by pixels here.
So we cast to a un 32.
Again.
These are the same pointer.
Now, we've just copied it in here, but then, we're going to advance
this pointer for each individual pixel.
So we come in, here we go for each pixel in a row.
We basically used a little faux value here to just say, hey, we'll
assign the X&Y just to give us a little bit of a gradient so that X
increments here and it will wrap remember.
This is a un 8.
So, it means that when the, when the x value gets plus, whatever, the
It is that we passed in to make an animate, but that'll be 0.
The first time through these will both be zero and they'll just kind
of increment to make us get that animation.
But basically every time we overflow 8-bit, so every time we get to
255, when we add one, we will go back to zero because we've only got
you an 8 here and that's what creates that 256 by 256 block pattern
that you see in our gradient.
It's those it's those eight bits wrapping rolling over every time.
We then go ahead and write that out to fix the pointer.
We use a nice little notation here, which is basically very concise.
That is C shorthand.
I'll just say it again because I think everyone should probably know
by now, but I've never really explained on the stream.
So we will make it clear star.
Pixel means.
I am trying to write to the location of pixel that dereferences.
Pixel, basically says, okay, pixel is a pointer, but I now want to
talk about the thing.
That's at that pointer, right?
So if I put it on the left-hand side, I am writing to it.
If I was to put it on the right hand side.
I am reading from it in a sense.
You could think of it that way.
If I was going to write to it, I could write to the pixel here, right?
Some value into it.
And so that is what the star does.
The plus plus is the post increment operator.
It says, after this line.
After this statement, I should say after this statement.
I want you to increment this value by 1, right.
I want you to increment it once.
So basically, this is the same as saying star, pixel, equals
something, plus plus pixel, right?
Or pixel equals pixel plus 1.
Right now.
It's a little deceptive again because it is a un 32 pointer.
So really what will happen here is that is the compiler will silently
do that.
So it will really add 4 to it.
But that is exactly what we want, what it increments pixel because
each
So is 4, bytes long?
So that is exactly what we want.
And see is just save me some time there.
That is what it is doing.
Now, in here.
We need to pack our pixel.
As we know, inside our registers.
We have a thing that looks like x x RR.
GG BB in memory order.
That is V VG.
R RX X.
So in order to pack these into the register, we go ahead and do a blue
in the bottom B, because we know that that is the least significant
byte and we pack green one above it.
We
Don't have any red.
We don't have any pad to, right.
So those stay 0 that produces our new pixel value.
And when the CPU, remember, again, that's in there.
It's in our register looking like x x RR, GG BB right.
When that goes to be written out since Intel is little-endian.
It will reverse, the order.
It will write the BB to the lowest one.
It will write the GG to the next one.
So that will basically do that reversal into memory to make the memory
or to go like this first bite.
Second bite, third bite, fourth bite.
Just something to remember.
Okay, that is a little endian at work.
This basically produces our gradient, that lovely thing on the screen
that animates for us and that is the way that works.
Okay.
That is the end of our helper functions.
What is going on here?
Why can I not on set that break point?
F9 is not behaving tonight.
Ladies and gentlemen, I do not know why there it goes.
Okay, that's good.
Anyway, let's go ahead and recompile that now, there we go.
One thing you should be aware of is that if you have a program stopped
in the debugger, like this, and you go,
Can you try to compile something it will say this cannot open win32
handmade .exe for writing.
And that is because the debugger actually holds it open.
So basically, well, it's not really the butter.
Holds it open.
It's that it's running.
So Windows is kind of holding it open.
You could think that is a downside to Windows.
It does not happen on Linux machines.
Unix uses a different system.
It's got inodes and they get reference.
So you do not have to worry about that on units, but on Windows you
do.
I'm assuming on Mac you don't either because it's Unix under the hood,
but I don't actually know if that's true because I don't use Macintosh
very often, but at least on Windows.
You do have to worry about it.
So, always make sure you hit shift F5 to kill that debug before you
come back here and hit alt M to build, if you are building an external
editor.
All right, so we come back in here, read your are weird.
Gradient.
Oops, didn't mean to do that.
There we go.
Render, our render, our word gradient.
We get a handle to the window, which is basically just a way of us
asking Windows.
We're trying to do some drawing now.
Can you please give us back handle?
That allows us to issue draw calls purely, artificial construct.
Windows just wants to bound those because those Save State
Actually, you can later on.
Well, not later on.
Probably if you did your own investigation, you would see that you can
do things with Device context like draw lines and stuff like this.
And you can select things into them like brushes and patterns and
stuff.
So they're they're a whole state tracking mechanism.
Basically that we don't really need, but all drawing stuff has to go
through it when we're on this path.
So, that's the case.
We use the helper function that we called to basically get the width
and height of a window.
We did that by asking win Windows to give us back a client wreck,
which is the writable region of a window.
In Windows space.
So basically left and top are always zero and right.
And bottom are always the actual width and height, but just in case
they should change that someday.
We actually went through and we're a little more diligent and subtract
the left and top.
But pretty much always, every time you go through there.
As far as I know, that is redundant.
As you can see, the left and top is always zero, so that subtraction
basically does nothing the right?
And bottom is basically the width and the height, just right there.
Okay, when we step out of that, we've got it.
We asked Windows to display it by calling.
SGI B, which is just a function, which stretches a are off-screen
buffer up into or down into the windows side.
So we pass it.
The window size and we pass it, our buffer size.
We also passed it that bitmap description that it needed.
So it knows how to copy.
It, knows what it's looking at.
And we pass it, the memory.
We also gave it some Flags to tell us how to do the copy.
Nothing big.
They're just says, wasn't palletized.
So it doesn't look up a color palette or anything like that.
It's just they're straight RGB values right in the pixels and we
passed its source copy, which tells it don't do any
The best bits just copy them.
That's about it.
Alright, so we come back out here.
We release the DC because this is a getting release mechanism.
When we get one, we have to give it back.
And so then we increment our our gradient offset, which allows it to
look like.
It is animating because we update it and we will just come back
through here and this Loop will happen in at infinitum, pull off the
messages re-render, the gradient, pull off the messages rear-ended,
the gradient, and that is our program.
It will not stop until we get a window message.
And the window message is the the close message at which point we will
stop.
So if we are running and we closed that we hit here now that will set
Global writing false break out of that Loop down at the bottom of the
program because you can see that it only goes as long as Global
running is true and it won't be true anymore.
So it will exit.
That is what that will do.
Now.
There is one of the things that our program does we have this window
call back, but besides just Fielding the clothes message and the
destroy message and so on, and some of these other ones, we can get
rid of that one now.
And this one, we're going to handle it later.
Basically, we have this WM painting here.
And what WM paint is remember, basically, one of the things that we're
doing is we are forced, painting, the window to make an anime.
So we're just flat-out going.
Anytime.
We are done processing messages as fast as we can, using all available
CPU resources, just blit pass, the message blit, plus the message.
We're just gonna, you know, we're like a little we're a Chihuahua on
speed.
Here.
We are just bleeding and bleeding, and bleeding, and bleeding, and
bleeding and bleeding, and that is fine.
But Windows also, sometimes will call us back.
And though, time is it.
Cause back is when it suspends the running of our process.
Basically, it blocks the running or a process to do a size.
So, basically, when we go into this, when we go into this, you'll
notice we are no longer running.
We are blocked in that message, queue, Windows, is not letting us
continue that as something that happens when you resize a window like
that.
And so while that is happening, Windows is actually telling us to
repaint and so we are actually Fielding that message in here.
And so if you if you look at what's
Down here.
We are just going ahead and we are asking it to do.
The same blit was doing outside, but we're doing it inside the paint.
Now, one thing that you might notice is this begin paint and paint?
That is basically something you need to do in the WM paint message to
tell windows that you have updated.
The dirty region that it is asking you to repaint.
Some people ask me about validate region or validate wrecked.
They were reading the documentation and they said, don't I have to
call validate Rex?
So, Windows knows, I finished painting in the answer is no, you don't
and paint automatically tells windows, that the
Ain't that you asked it to do that.
It asked you to do was done.
So that is really all you need.
Is that in pain?
You don't have to do anything else and paint, implicitly will validate
the region.
And if you're wondering what validating regions are, you can go read
the docs to, or give you the quick capsule summary, and that is
basically that Windows remembers where on your window has it needs to
repaint.
So basically, if you actually run the program here, if I run this and
I do something like move it off, so it gets obscured and then move it
back on, Windows, remembers that area that
Scared and calls you back with, WM paint, asking you to paint that
area.
And it wants you to tell it at some point that you actually repainted
it, so that it knows that can stop asking you to repaint it.
If you don't, it'll keep sending UWM paint messages until you do, and
that will flood your message queue with extraneous.
WM paint messages.
And you don't want that.
So, you always want to make sure you do something either.
Begin paint and paint or validate the wreck yourself, but I would
recommend doing this way.
This is the right way to do it.
I think, basically, to make sure that Windows knows what happened now,
anytime.
We got a message.
That we didn't handle.
That's a default case of our switch statement.
We just let Windows handle it for us by calling the default window
procedure, which is basically just a catch-all.
It's a thing to find by Windows.
It just does the right thing by default for any message that we don't
want to handle.
And ladies and gentlemen, I think we have come to the end of our
program.
It was a good program.
I've seen a lot of people email me, who said they had a lot of fun
playing around with this buffer.
Making weird patterns, doing all sorts of stuff like that.
And I am absolutely delighted about that because this is really the
joy of programming right here.
Once you can actually start poking, right?
In the B and seeing that happen in your.
Basically, it's you and the CPU and it's just, you're just having a
ball that is really some of the that's that's programming being fun.
Again.
You don't have to worry about 800,000 libraries that you're using.
And they're not working in only Linker, Arabs, and try to go to stack,
Overflow to find the compiler switch, that makes it.
So does none of that.
It's just a simple build file and everything is under your control.
And that is what I love.
It.
Makes programming fun.
Again.
It's like booting up an old Apple to and and hitting that control
breaker, whatever it was.
I got it's been so long.
I can't remember but you could go.
In there and just start typing in basic code and doing all kinds of
weird stuff.
It's that kind of fun again.
All right, ladies and gentlemen, we have come to the end of handmade
hero for the day, but I didn't want to take up all the Q&A time.
So I am still going to do a bunch of QA.
Maybe we will go a little bit longer because I had to take a little
extra time there just to essentially do Q&A, which is to go through
and really try to solidify a bunch of stuff that people might be
asking about, but you may still have some questions.
So let's go ahead and go to the stream, the twitch chat.
Would it be a good or bad idea to get one device context of the
beginning of the program and use that for every iteration of the main
Loop?
So interestingly enough that is not really allowed.
I do not believe
By Windows, usually unless you ask for it specifically and that is
actually ironically enough specifically what this flag that I said,
we'd probably don't need does.
And if we say CS own to see DC basically that, that means that every
window in this window class will get its own device context, that it
no longer needs to return.
And so you could argue that maybe that is a good idea.
I mean, you know, because why not and
What we would do is we would just specify that own DC.
And then I'm quite, I'm pretty sure that it's completely legal at that
point to just say, as soon as I get the window, I'm just going to snap
the DC and then I never have to give it back again.
Right?
And I'm pretty sure that that just works.
I could be wrong about that.
If someone at Microsoft right now is having an absolute conniption
because I am telling people to do things that are going to make their
life harder.
I do apologize for that.
But that is just, that is just my understanding.
Of how the DC system works.
Now, of course, there are other times when we use a device context,
but I think they're pretty much only in the paint.
And since Windows is already giving us back, the device, kind of sit
wants to use.
I don't think that's a problem.
So, I think this would be totally fine.
I'm going to go ahead and say note Casey, since we specified CS own
DC, we can just get one device context and use it forever, because we
are not sharing.
With anyone.
Yeah.
Let's see.
Do do, do do.
Can we please add a Chihuahua on speed as a sidekick or enemy monster?
Yes, we can choa.
On speed will definitely be written down in the notes.
That becomes.
Why do you tell Windows you handle messages?
You don't really handle and default is good.
And default is good.
I don't know what the an default is.
Good means.
Hmm.
Well, so I guess the first part of that which is why do we tell
windows?
We handle messages, which we don't really handle and the answer to
that is the concept of of handling, a message is a little bit fuzzy.
What it means to handle a message is really whether or not you want
Windows to do anything at all in response to that message.
And so, basically, you know, yeah, I can
Delete that WM size and nothing really is going to change in the
program.
Right?
It's going to be basically exactly the same and so that's fine.
The reason for that is that there really isn't anything by default
Windows needs to do in response to those messages now, destroy and
close.
There are things that might do in response to their default and I
don't want it to do them.
So I'm not letting it have a chance to do that activate app.
Same thing.
I actually have stuff that I want to do there.
Now, you can usually check inside the WM the documentation for
whatever thing.
That you want to see whether it recommends that you still call
Windows, even if you don't do it.
Anything.
If you don't do certain things, it'll say like you have to do these
things response to the message.
But usually there isn't a return value if an opt-in process image, it
should return 0, so, it doesn't, it doesn't.
If the if the windows message isn't documented as requiring certain
things to occur, and there's nothing that we want to occur, then it is
equivalent essentially, to having a case or calling death window.
Proctor's no difference, but there are
Window messages in response to which you do have to do things.
And so if we were going to feel those messages,
And we did something like this, where we didn't actually do the things
that were required, that would be bad.
So, really, the only thing you're trying to avoid by having this
default here, is that, for those windows messages that require
mandatory work on your part.
You have to call them.
Now.
I can give you an example of one of those right off the bat because we
already said it, WM pain.
If you don't do a begin paint and paint inside, WM paint, your dirty
region will never get validated.
That means windows will continue to think it's dirty and it will flood
you with WM paint messages.
So if we were going to do something like this, that would be bad.
You don't want to do that.
You would want to delete the case entirely and make sure that you're
calling deaf window proc because that will do a basically a null paint
right there for you and make sure that it up considers the region
validated and there will be no further problems.
Let's see.
I believe set stretch, blind mode will allow you to get better quality
stretching.
I believe you want half tone.
Yes, I think there are some settings we can set.
We will look at that little later.
What I really want is filtering.
We may not get that so we may read our own filtering code, but I will
add a note in here or to do I should say when we do that aspect ratio
correction, we can play with stretch modes.
Yeah.
Let's see.
Okay.
Hi Casey.
Can you please explain pointer aliasing again?
I didn't understand how passing by reference would cause a problem.
And someone else asked when you're talking about passing by value
versus passing by reference.
You mentioned there are modern observations.
Okay.
So let me, let me handle these two stream has ended.
Don't look at that.
Ladies and gentlemen, do do not look at the little thing that this
dream has ended.
We will go a little bit longer tonight because I
I was kind of in the mood to talk about stuff.
So we'll go a little bit longer here on Friday, will be all be up late
at night, partying.
Anyway, I am sure.
So, there is no harm done.
So what?
What, basically happens here?
I'll try to give an example.
And basically, I want you to take this example with a grain of salt
because like I said, I am not a compiler author and because I am not
compiler author.
My examples may be wrong in ways that are actually important.
So, what I would highly recommend, you do, is go watch some lectures
by Chandler Caruth.
I believe his name is spelled Chandler para like that.
He's one of the guys who does optimizations on llvm, which is a
really, really good compiler compared to all the other compilers out.
At the moment, I would go watch some lectures by him and watch him,
explain some stuff because it is true.
I found about out about him through Fabien, at rigorous him on
Twitter.
It's a friend of mine works at rad.
Really, really awesome coder.
I think I mentioned this feeling before and he had been posting some
links to some of these lectures cetera like maybe a year ago or more.
And basically, they're just really, really good down to earth.
Like here's what happens in the optimizer when I were trying to
optimize your code, so please
Stan these things.
All right.
So here's basically what happens.
Aliasing.
There are multiple kinds of aliasing.
There's basically aliasing that happens.
There's there's cash aliasing.
I think there's tlb aliasing.
There's all kinds of aliasing that happened.
Most of them have to do with the CPU and most of them have to do with
optimization.
So, when you're talking about aliasing, you're usually talking about a
CPU performance problem, that occurs, because you have had some
unfortunate coincidences with the, with the actual addresses, where
things are.
In memory, okay.
So when you see aliasing, that's usually what that means.
But in this case when we talk about aliasing, we're actually talking
about something totally different.
So I understand why can be confusing because the word aliasing gets
used a lot of context, and those are not the context that we mean.
What we're talking about is we're talking about very specifically,
pointer aliasing.
Which is a language problem.
It isn't as nothing to do with the CPU at all.
It is completely unrelated to the CPU in this case.
Although I mean you could talk about things that happen in the CPU
that might be relevant to thing.
You know, that might have similar things like this, but we're actually
talking about strictly during the compilation of your program pointer
aliasing.
So what that means is when you define a function
You need to think in terms of what the compiler actually sees.
So let's say the compiler sees a function called do the stuff, right?
And it is going to take a pointer that you call in star from, right.
And it's going to take another one that you call in Star 2.
And now because you're one of these C++ Fanatics, who likes to put
const everywhere in your code.
You even tried your best to tell the compiler.
That from is const.
It's constant.
I'm not having a talk about what cost means really, because I never
use it, but let's say you even were somebody who is, who is really,
really into const.
So you put constant everywhere in the code.
All right.
So you've got this, you're saying I'm going to read a from and then
your code does some stuff.
Now, the example I gave in fact, it's called do this stuff.
Right?
The example I gave was let's say that we did something like, you know,
star star to equal star from right like this.
That's what that does.
Let's say, I do that a few times, right?
So I, you know, add some values here.
These pointers, I'm moving them around.
However, I want to that sort of stuff.
Whatever.
Dot dot dot, you know, stuff happens, right?
So here's my function.
So basically what what's going to happen here is when the compiler is
actually generating code and this is not really the best example.
I really need, I really need one other thing here that's going to
happen.
You know what this this is better.
This is better than that.
There you go.
So what's going to happen here?
When the compiler sees this code is the car is going to go?
Okay, the first thing I need to do, right?
When I'm actually compiling this code.
I'm going to actually try to put her right out.
The compilers thought process here, right?
I have to load from the memory pointed to by from, right?
It's got to go get that right.
It's got to actually fetch it.
So it's got a generate instruction that says go load this memory.
Then it has to write that fetch.
Into the memory pointed to by 2, right?
That's what we told it to do.
We told to load out of this and right into this.
That's all we're trying to do right now.
You tell the compiler basically.
Wait, did I do this wrong?
Yes, I did this wrong.
Sorry.
There we go.
Like I said, not a compiler Optimizer.
So I don't think about these things very often.
Now.
We're going to say, let's go ahead and load.
Well even even that's not right.
This is such a simple example.
You think I'd be able to do it by now, but some reason, when I'm
trying to explain things, it's hard for me to think in my head,
exactly how the things are going.
Yes.
It's so, it's always, it's always a bit of a nightmare.
Ladies and gentlemen.
Oh, no.
No, I'm right.
I'm right.
Okay.
Okay, good.
Yeah.
Bit of a brain fart.
It's getting late.
What can I say?
Okay, so now we're going to go ahead and say advance.
The pointer to buy how much and you should all know this.
My now it's not to write it.
Actually, two times the size of an integer, right?
So it's actually going to advance it by eight, right?
And then it's going to say, okay.
I have to load from the memory pointed to buy from.
And then I have to write that fetch into the memory pointed to by and
at this point will start to introduce maybe a little compiler.
Stuff here.
This is really not to anymore.
In some sense.
The compiler thinks of these things that separate values because we
moved it, right?
So it really thinks of it more like a new thing.
It basically says to, to write a second to becomes the pointer to +8,
right?
And so then it's going to write the fetch in the memory pointed to by
22, right?
So we've got to, this is an extremely simple function.
And what is happening is we write into two different memory locations.
That is what the compiler sees.
It thinks.
There are two total rights 1 to 2 and 1/2 to 2.
And that's a bad thing.
One two, let's call other.
Or first and second and be.
There we go.
That's that's that's good.
Just to avoid it, getting completely out of control.
Okay, so it's going to load the memory planner to buy from.
It's going to write what it loaded into a.
It's going to make a new pointer called be conceptually.
It's not really doing these things.
It's just this is what thinks it has to do and it's a new pointer
called be that is a plus 8.
Bytes.
It's going to load the memory point of to buy from again and it's
going to write whatever it loaded into what's for you to buy be right.
Does that all make good sense to people?
Hopefully, that is true.
Hopefully people are following me so far, pretty simple.
Now, what you want the optimizer to do here, right?
That is sort of like if we just think of these as instructions, you
know, that is five instructions, right?
I mean, you know, who knows exactly what they translate into depending
on the circumstances, but, you know, there's five logical things that
have to happen here at us.
Load a right that's to do an increment.
Another load and then a right.
Now, what you want an Optimizer to do, and the whole point of an
Optimizer is to look for things.
Oops.
That did a very odd thing.
Look for things like These Guys, these two guys right here, right?
Do you see how both of these are the same thing?
They are both loading.
The memory pointed to by from and since from hasn't changed.
What's the contents of that memory has not changed, right?
And so basically, what happens in circumstances like this is you want
the optimizer to go.
Well, the second load I can just eliminate because I know what the
value of from actually was right?
I know what it was so I can just rewrite I can replace this by saying
right?
The previous fetch the one from up here into the memory.
To buy B.
And now I have saved one instruction, essentially one conceptual
instruction.
At least possibly even more instructions in the actual CPU, depending
on how many it would need to do that thing.
It has now saved those instructions.
That is an optimization.
That is what the optimizer does.
It takes the literal thing that has to happen in your code and turns
it into something more compact that does the same thing.
Now, the compiler can't do that to this function.
And again, when I say that, what I really mean is, this is a simple
example designed to show the kinds of ways that that can happen.
And maybe the compiler actually can do it to this function.
And like I said, you want to go talk to a real Kappa expert to
Are you the real intricate ways that this all plays out?
But this is basically the idea the reason it can't do that is because
it doesn't know if from into might point to the same place.
So let's suppose that the shenanigans outside of this that we're
calling the function.
Right.
Had an integer star blah, right?
Let's say it did that.
Let's say it goes ahead and passes the same pointer to do this stuff
for both of these, right?
Well now what's going to happen is when it when it over rights to it's
actually over writing from right?
Does that make sense?
Now in this particular case, you're still okay, I believe because
since you read read and wrote from
The exact same location.
You're probably fine.
But you have to imagine the compiler doesn't actually know like let's
say this continues on, right?
It continues on and goes for four more cycle, to keeps going and
incrementing further.
So, basically, you do something like that, right?
So that it, in this case.
Like I said, it wouldn't matter if it was, literally just doing it
one, because this would be the same value, as it was going to
overwrite, it would overwrite itself, the same value, but let's say it
was just
One ahead of itself, right?
So it was reading or to write.
So it was reading and writing right ahead of itself.
So it's going to overwrite the value.
It was about to read and just to make that a little bit more explicit.
I realized I kind of pulled a fast one on you there.
I will actually do it 100% accurate here for you that the full on real
case.
Again.
There's probably a simpler case, but I'm just, I'm having trouble
thinking it through because I don't think about these things very
often from the compilers perspective.
So some and when I'm talking out loud, it's kind of hard for me to
actually do them all 100.
Correctly.
Okay.
So basically I'm going to do this, right.
Like that, I am then going to go ahead and increment.
Let's say to like this and then I'm going to increment from like this
and then I'm going to go ahead and do the same copy again.
I think this would do it.
Right.
Let's double-check that that's true.
So now let's say I come in here and this is the memory that I actually
have.
This is blah.
Block is pointing to something like 10, 20, right?
And I don't even need, why did I even bother with the to get rid of
that?
We can make it even simpler.
All right, there we are.
So basically what I'm doing now, if you can see
is I am creating something.
That's basically, let's say I have a pointer to a pointer blog here
and block is pointing.
You know, it's pointing for whatever reason at this point in the
program to two integers, right?
The first integer is 10.
The second integer is 20.
Let's just say that's what happens, right?
So, let's see what happens when we actually run this and hopefully I
did it correctly.
When I do the first star to star from will, what is Star from start
from is 0 and and we want this way, right?
Is that correct?
So complicated.
Why am I?
This is this is, this is this is basically the problem with the with
streaming live is man.
You don't get a chance to think about these beforehand, you're trying
to talk it through at the same time.
So I'm going to read from a value in that.
I want to overwrite that.
Will you write?
This is.
This is actually the way to do it.
Okay.
Yeah, we're written.
Yeah, so it's like, you know what?
This has been a disaster, ladies and gentleman.
This is the worst example that I've ever given.
Basically.
This should be a really, really thing, really, really easy.
Thing to demonstrate how the pointers Alias.
And for some reason it is like impossible for me to construct a simple
case because every time I try to simplify it, I realized that I write
something that technically should still execute properly because the
copied value is actually going to be the same.
So again, my Penance for this is I really pretty much just have to
stay here.
And actually give you a valid case.
So bear with me for a second while I unclog my brain and actually try
to write something that's going to be valid.
So I'm going to try writing something called move.
Let's say and move is going to take two pointers.
It's going to take an into a and it be well, I guess I'll just stick
with my from in my to even though it was going so poorly.
We'll do it that way.
And we'll say one of them was was const and so what this is going to
do is it's just going to literally do the copy, right?
So it's going to do yeah, it's going to do this.
It's going to do basically this it's just a copy function.
So let's say it does this and let's say it copies for
Integers.
So it copies, it reads an integer rights.
It reads, an integer rights.
It does something like this and maybe when it does that, it writes the
same.
So it's kind of like a thing that yeah, something like this.
It's kind of a thing that actually duplicates the value out.
In fact, I'll do this a little make this a little clearer.
We'll do it that way.
Let's see if this can actually work.
So basically I am kind of over writing the values there.
That is what I expect to happen.
Have happen.
So I will overwrite that and I'll
Mint from Once, I think this will be enough to do it.
But maybe I just did the exact same stupid mistake.
Again.
We'll find out.
So now I have my pointer and it's got one, two, three, four in it.
Let's say some pointer in memory.
That's pointing to these things.
So, in blah points to those integers and memory, right?
And then I call move and I'm going to call move with blah.
So I pass blah and blah.
And what I want to do here is I want it to eventually over right from
Sophie.
From is going to be.
Let's see.
It's going to write to it's going to write two one.
That's right to to then it's going to write, two three.
Yes.
Oh, so I'm going to say that it is going to point to blah plus 1 and
let's see what this does.
If I have finally actually done it.
You know what, I just realized to this is definitely an owl of Shame
moment.
That should have been a really easy thing for me to write and the fact
that it isn't just shows that the
Of Shame needs to make an appearance to let everyone know that this is
not something that should have taken this long.
This should have been like a five-minute thing.
And that is just basically, yeah.
The shame Owl makes its first appearance and I strongly suspect, there
will be a lot more shame else coming out in the future.
As we get more and more complicated code.
It will only be harder for me to think it through live like this.
Yeah.
I hope you will stick with relays and gentlemen, I do apologize for
the delay anyway.
Off we go.
What will actually do here is to is currently pointing to blah the
first element of blah.
So if we look in here after this instruction, right, this instruction
is going to read from from from as pointing to the to.
So this reads A to and writes out a 2.
So that's going to be two to three four, right?
Let's see what this does.
This is going to read.
Let's see.
See from from again.
Oh, you know what?
Let's do that.
I'm gonna pass both the same ones.
Okay.
So this reads, a one and writes a one.
No, this isn't.
It still doesn't work.
I'm trying to think of the appropriate punishment for not being able
to write.
Simple point to ice.
Keep putting wanted to do it with a copy, but I can't seem to do it
with the copy.
So, you know what?
Maybe we just need to not do that case.
So that I guess maybe whatever my blade.
Why don't?
Why does my brain even think that that would happen?
Because it should always actually work.
I don't know.
I'm just being stupid today.
We'll try it one more way.
And if we can't figure it out, then we will just call it for the night
and we will say that someday, somebody who is thinking a little more
clearly.
Well or R actually will just be me.
I'll sit down for 10 seconds after the stream is over.
I'll be
Oh, right, duh.
That is how that works.
Anyway, let's say that we go ahead and do something with
Pointer is maybe something like that.
And we say something like Star a equals star, B Star C equals star, be
that kind of thing.
So, we're going to write two things in there.
And then maybe some interceding thing will just get some more pointer
reads in here so that we can we can check it out.
So, star D equals 5, the funny thing is
As I think my example that I gave earlier in the Stream by just typed
out in the middle of like the hyperness.
I think just worked.
So it's kind of hilarious that of having this much trouble with
something that really should not have been a problem.
But anyway, so this.
Yeah.
And looking at this, this just works.
Why did I over complicate things so much?
I don't know, ladies and gentlemen, you are free to basically Point
your own Al of Shame at me if you have one at home because this is
simple and I believe this one just works.
So it's kind of ridiculous that it took me that long to explain it.
Here we go.
We've got four pointers here.
We are reading out of be twice.
So this is load be right?
A this is load five, right d which you can probably do with the
immediate.
So it's probably just write D and this is going to be load, be rights.
Right.
Right to load from like that, right?
So that's all good.
That's all well and good.
And the only thing, this is the only thing you need to understand,
poetry aliasing.
And yet I spent probably 15 minutes of your valuable time trying to
make a stupid copy.
Do it for no apparent reason, other than for some reason I really
wanted to write it as copy.
So.
Yep.
Well, you know, there you go.
It takes five seconds to write the right thing and 15 minutes to write
the wrong thing.
I don't know how to explain that, but here you go.
If now we have
In memory, we're going to call this move function, right?
And we have some things that we can point to.
So, we have a int X into y, + NZ, and an NT W, and I will just set
these two one, two, three, and four.
Okay, hopefully, that is pretty understandable.
Nothing particularly odd going on there.
And so, I am going to go ahead and pass this function, x y z w, right.
And it will should work 100% properly.
There's nothing odd about that.
It will go ahead and do the right thing, right?
It will, if you look at what will happen to this program, it'll load
from B, which is set to Y.
So, it'll load a to out of there.
Right?
And it will write the two back to what is basically X.
So X will become 2.
It will write to me, straight up.
It will write 52w, which is fine and then it will write to see, it
will write C.
It will write whatever.
Was in B, which is 2.
So you'll end up doing all that and it will work totally properly.
Now, in that circumstance, you could also see that if I wanted to I
could just load.
Be once because the value that you load from B is always going to be
to correct.
It's always going to be up to.
So when it loads from be, it gets to get loads.
From be.
It will get to it.
Could just fold those out and say right to see the same value you
wrote to a right?
That is basically what the optimizer is going to do.
The optimizer is going to say.
Hey look, all I need you to do is load from be once because since
you're loading from be twice and the value isn't going to change.
It's just be the whole time, right?
I can just save that, and that is the optimization that it wants to
make.
Now, the point is, it cannot make that optimization.
The reason, it cannot make that optimization is because there's other
pointers here.
Right?
And that is a problem.
What it doesn't know is whether two of these pointers Alias, and if
two pointers point to the same memory, they are called aliasing.
So, let's say, I go up here, right?
And because I am being mean I set B, and D to point to the same place.
Well, now, when you read out of be here, right?
You will get a 2 but when you read out of be here, you should have
gotten the 5 because the interceding, right?
2D wrote a 5 into the location that used to contain a to.
So the compiler cannot optimize this away.
It cannot write to see the same value at wrote to a it has to.
It must always load from be it must and then right to see so pointer
aliasing.
Right pointer aliasing is basically a pointer aliasing is when two
pointers.
point to the same memory or rather two pointers could
Point to the same memory and the compiler doesn't know if a right to
one of those pointers might affect a read from the other pointer,
right?
That is the key.
It doesn't know whether it can optimize out that second load from be
because it doesn't know if you might have just written a 5 in there.
So really there's two ways to interpret this code depending on whether
the pointers Alias one is that you can load from be once and
It twice.
And one is that you can load from be twice or rather load from be once
and then write a five because you would know that, the only thing the
optimizer would know.
The only thing that could happen was the five, but it doesn't even
know how to make a determination.
But he doesn't have to actually compare the pointers and that would be
slower than just probably just doing it than just actually doing the
load potentially because it still has to do the load.
Well, maybe not, I don't know, could do that.
It was really smart.
I'm not sure, probably possibly not.
But anyway, you get the idea there, right?
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
So basically what you need to understand is any time you pass
pointers.
The compiler, can't really do any optimizations with those pointers.
If you write to them, if you only ever read from them.
You're usually fine because it's only the writing that creates
something that could happen if this right.
2D weren't here then no other there's no other reason that be could
get changed now in a threaded environment.
You may see things like this where people put volatile on something
and that's a way of telling it that some other thread could be
modifying stuff.
But assuming that you're working with code, that is guaranteed to be
single-threaded, which is what you're doing when you don't put
volatile, when you're just telling the compiler.
Hey, these are just regular variables that only might.
Thread touches or I know that all the threads are locked from.
Not touching those variables at this point in time.
Then it goes ahead and assumes it can optimize those out so long as it
can tell the missing out.
So basically in this circumstance, what you want to do right?
Is you you want to pass be by value so that you can tell the compiler.
Very clearly look.
You don't have to worry about reading from be as an address.
I'm telling you what the value of B is upfront and so, you know that
it can't be changed by this interview.
Interesting.
Right to D because there's no way to get an address to this parameter,
right?
That's not possible.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully that makes some sense.
I apologize for the long winded and completely useless copy example,
that I was trying to construct for you that I thought was gonna be
more fun.
It was just a world of hurt, but that is basically all we're talking
about here.
There is really nothing more to it than that.
It is extremely extremely basic.
Now, basically, the kinds of optimizations that happen are obviously
much more complicated than this and the kinds of pointer Ellison that
happens can be.
Much more complicated this.
So this is a very, very simple example, but that sort of thing can
happen all the time.
As you're passing pointers around the compiler constantly has to be
aware of what could happen there.
And so that's a very important thing to understand when you're
actually trying to optimization.
So, I'm sorry that took so long.
That should not taken that long, but that's just the way it goes
sometimes.
So it looks like we are done with questions.
So that is good.
We are down here at the end of The Stream So that is pretty cool.
Let's see here.
And there's anything else.
Yes, and I'm terribly.
Sorry for that.
Such a long word, exhalation.
Again, like I said, you gotta bear with me on this dream.
Sometimes it's also a learning process for me, in terms of trying to
keep my train of thought, correct and talk at the same time.
It's actually really pretty difficult because talking and coding kind
of use the same part of your brain.
So it's a little bit difficult.
So sometimes my explanations go a little bit long-winded.
I will stick them out every damn time.
So I just ask that.
Maybe you stick them out with me.
I realized a little frustrating because way better if someone can just
give you at real concise example, and not have to muddle through it,
which we have done number.
Times on the stream.
So we've been getting better at it is totally true, but we got a long
ways to go because that was pretty rough.
That should not have taken 10 minutes or whatever.
It took that should have been a quick quick one.
Let's see here.
Is anyone posting notes from these casts?
Yes, we will be putting up a website very shortly with notes from the
casts.
And so I hope that you will take a look at that.
I will be announcing on the livestream.
As soon as it is ready is not quite ready yet.
So hopefully we will have some of that going.
I was under the impression that the stack always grows downwards on
Lily and little-endian.
Is that not true?
I thought that it did as well.
That was my assumption.
But to be honest with you, I have done very little.
I have never written a single Assembly Language only program in x64,
which is what we're compiling in like an x86.
I believe it always grew downward, but an x 64 for all.
I know they could have changed it.
I mean, I had no idea.
So, I figured well, I might as well check.
I'm, yeah, I've never had
To actually think about that.
And so, I just felt like it was kind of fun check.
So, yes, I think it always does grow downward and it continues to grow
downward in x64.
So that is good.
You don't have to remember that it switches or anything like that, but
I wanted to verify that.
Let's see.
Can you post interesting emails to get to the site?
Yes, I will try to.
I don't, I don't necessarily want to post emails exactly because
people probably don't want their emails posted.
If they haven't actually said that are okay with that.
But what I will do is I will comb back through the entry males.
I have received and make sort of a fact from them that sort of
discusses things that people have asked me what I've answered.
Clemens bound, the compiler is allowed to, and actually does assume
that two pointers two different types never Alias.
Unless one of the types of care or unsigned care.
That is correct.
Basically, there are modes that you can put the compiler in.
And so there are there are optimization modes.
You can put the compiler, any that make it assume a bunch of things
about aliasing, and I find affect a lot of people.
In fact, I think even rad does this now, by default turn those modes
off and the reason is because they are bugs, waiting to happen.
Compilers are now assuming more and more stuff about aliasing
sometimes in situations where you really, really don't want them to
and so assume no aliasing.
A really bad thing in compilers and I think we want to kind of get rid
of it.
What you'd much rather do is Mark up your stuff to say when things
don't Alias.
Honestly, I think that should have been the default.
Unfortunately, the language support for it is a bit spotty, but there
are things like the restrict keyword and the assumed keyword that you
can use.
And so that is kind of a it's kind of a bit of a messy messy
situation, and we will definitely probably deal with that a little bit
later.
Win32, displayed by friend window is taking for unused for a WMA is
the only part where we pass those, but we never used them.
Will that change?
You know, I'll be honest with you.
I don't know if we really need to worry about jury wrecked, updating.
It seems like kind.
Waste of time.
So we could easily just go ahead and say that we are not going to do
that.
We could basically say that we just don't care about what the dirty
rectangle is because for the most part, since we're going to have to
update the whole screen every frame.
Anyway, we must be able to do that quickly.
So we could easily just say this is the new thing for the program and
that would be fine.
I think.
So, let's go ahead and double check that.
That's all good.
So I think that's probably fine.
Those are just
just we had passed those because WM paint does actually give us back
the rectangle that we need to refresh.
So you could save a little time by only refreshing that region.
But since we know, we have to put the whole screen 30 frames a second
to make a game feel good.
Anyway, we can pretty much assume that we don't need to do that and
simplify that code because obviously, we don't need to just worry
about it.
Small wrecked on paint.
If every frame, we have to repaint the whole thing.
Anyway, yeah, so that's why it's good point.
And the answer is no, you don't have to worry about those.
Wouldn't it be better to keep comments in the code about the
explorations?
You do sometimes?
Yes, sometimes not.
I'd rather maybe pull those out to the forum's because, honestly, if
the code gets too cluttered up with comments that are explanations and
especially if those explanations are no longer pertaining.
Exactly the thing because we change the code a little bit, that's
going to get annoying.
So, I'm going to try not to do that, probably.
All right.
It is 10 p.m.
Here.
Ladies and gentlemen, so let's go ahead and wrap this up.
Let's do one last code question.
Why have B 4 pixel as a variable?
Do you expect it to have different values?
Why not put it as
Acosta, fine, or even replace it with BMI header, dot bi bit.
Count divided by 8.
Those are all good suggestions.
I totally, I would be okay with all of that.
Every last one of those is totally viable.
I just found that it was kind of a nicer thing to put there because
it's kind of all the stuff that actually you need to know about the
on-screen buffer.
So I just felt it was kind of a nice thing to put there so I don't see
any real reason to remove it, but we could, we could
Could just change that back to a local variable.
So, you know, we could totally do it this way.
We could say this, right?
Go back to the way that we have before and just say that it's always
that because really we're not going to handle anything else.
So that might be the right way to go.
I do not know we could totally do that.
We could totally do that.
Let's think about it.
Yeah, let's go ahead and do that.
Let's just go ahead and say for now because we can always change our
mind.
Let's just always say,
Pixels are always 32 bits wide.
Little endian.
Like that.
Although maybe I'll say memory order BB G RX X.
Alright everyone.
Thank you for joining me.
That cleared up everything that we were doing.
Let's see here.
Yeah, that looks good to the person who said, ugh, make it const
though.
Maybe we should take one more thing.
Someone was grumpy that it wasn't const.
I never like to use const.
Constant is a is basically, the only thing constant is does is it
basically allows the programmer to potentially not make mistakes if
they were to assign to it.
So basically, if you type in constant, just means that you can't type
B 4 pixels.
Equals eight here, right?
It will give you an error.
It'll say that you can't assign to a const variable.
I don't find that to be useful at all.
I have never had a bug in the 15 years since I stopped using const.
I have literally never had a single bug that would have been caught by
it.
So it is just a waste of typing for me.
It may not be a waste of typing for you if you make that mistake off
and otherwise, it is completely useless in the reason that it is
completely useless except for a small number of cases where you're
defining Global variables and need to say and you don't want to use a
pound to find for example, the
This completely useless is because the compiler cannot actually assume
that.
Something that is called constant is actually const.
In any case, constant is actually, so meaningless, that constant has
not even exist in the optimizer.
In fact, if you don't believe me, Chandler, Caruth, who I mentioned
before, go watch one of his lectures, you will find him.
Explain the fact that Constance completely useless and does not even
exist in the optimizer.
It does not even use cost.
And the reason for that is because in C++, they allowed you to Cast
Away constant, which means
means that something that is constant does not actually have to be
constant at all.
And so basically what happens is you get into situations that looks
something like this.
Basically, you have somebody who's doing, you know do the stuff right.
And it's got in constant A and N star B, and it could just as well be
the case just because you said that these were constant well for all
it knows be could also point to a right.
It's that aliasing thing all over again.
So the fact that this is called cost is meaningless because the
optimizer has no idea.
Whether it be actually secretly does point to a and, you know, so if
there's a right to be here, that could be mutating a so constant
literally useless.
It has absolutely no use whatsoever to the compiler and if you don't
believe me, go ask Chandler, go ask someone who works on Optimizer.
It does not help, it cannot be propagated down.
So, constant is useless.
But if you find it, useful for your own coding practices, you can go
ahead and use it that
Is fine, but just don't think you're making better code by adding
kant's because that is not true.
It does not help you.
All right, guys, that is the end of the stream.
Thank you all for joining us.
It was a bit of a man during Friday, but I wanted to go through all
this stuff with you, make sure everyone was comfortable with
everything we did during the week.
Next week.
We'll be starting again on Monday at 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time.
Next week.
We will try to move Friday to an early time so that people in other
time zones can watch.
So we will do Monday through Thursday at 8 p.m.
As usual and then on Friday, we will try to do something perhaps in
the morning or something that will be at a time when other people in
other time zones can tune in live because a lot of people been asking
about that.
So we will go ahead and do that.
I will try to post a schedule for you and hopefully, we'll have that
website up to.
So I can have a place where the schedule always.
Is and you can find out ahead of time when this will be aired.
So thank you all for joining us next week.
We will tackle input and sound assuming that we can get through them.
Both.
We will try to tackle sound first and if that takes all week, then we
will do input the week after it is Thanksgiving week, but I still plan
to be streaming.
So I hope you guys can tune in and join me.
If not have an excellent Thanksgiving, those of you who are in the
u.s., I guess.
I don't know all the countries that celebrate Thanksgiving, but we
celebrate it here.
Obviously, it's kind of an American holiday.
Day, so it probably isn't celebrated much outside of America.
But for those of you in the US, have a Happy Thanksgiving next week.
If I don't see on the stream, if I do Willie took you together and
program, sound on Windows.
Thanks everyone for joining us and I will catch you next week.