Start recording.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show recoded complete game live on stream.
We are in the midst of adding, a couple features to our memory Arena
here.
Yesterday, we did the basic step after I explained kind of the concept
of it of allowing our memory Arenas to expand dynamically as necessary
in case that as a feature that you want to use.
But although that works just fine, we have not allowed that to, we
basically have it implemented support for two other features that we
have to work concurrently with it.
The first one being temporary memory usage.
So basically, when you, you know, take a memory in and say, I'm going
to do some work in this Arena and I don't want you to save what I have
to do.
So I'm going to do about your allocations but then I want you to kind
of undo all those allocations as a block later we're not supporting
Correctly right now.
Technically it would work occasionally, but anytime you were to cross
one of those Dynamic allocation boundaries, it would fail.
And the other thing that we are not currently doing in a way that
would necessarily work correctly, is the dynamic that sort of loop
Live code editing stuff where you can sort of the live coding part
will work fine, but the, the looped part, the part where you can,
like, return to a previous state of the program.
Am that is not currently possible anymore with this system either
because the memory Arenas that are set to dynamically grow will not
restore properly at the moment, right?
And the reason for that is because they are not currently being
tracked in any way.
So, when that system goes to save out memory and restore memory, it
doesn't know about those extra Arenas.
So obviously, it's not going to be able to make them function
properly.
Right.
So that's what we have to do at the moment and this first one is
pretty easy to do.
So that one will definitely do today, depending on how smooth that
goes.
We can start on the second with the second.
One's going to be a little bit more involved.
It's not particularly difficult to make dynamically growing Arenas
work with Loop live coding, but it is more code.
And the reason for that is because inside the loop, you that's being
done for the Live code editing, you may have a situation.
And we're summer memory, Arenas have expanded.
And so, when that happens, you have to be aware of that.
And when you go back to sort of the original state of the program, you
have to be aware that those things happen and free those, assuming
that you don't want to leak memory.
During the loop.
Right.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Today is day 342.
If you want to follow along at home, if you're trying to
Following the source code yourself, you'll want to use day 341 source
code, that is what I'm starting with.
Right now, let's go ahead and boot this up here.
You can see that we're still actually, even though we haven't
implemented those features, we are still running properly.
We're not noticing an error of any kind at the moment and that's
because we're not actually doing we're not actually marking any of
those Arenas.
Those
The the ones that are actually involved in temporary memory use, we're
just not happening to hit those because we only set one member one of
our memory Arenas to, it be a dynamic Arena.
So we're not actually seeing any obvious bugs at the moment and even
if we did Loop left coating, we might not right, you know, it still
works.
And the reason that it still works is because again the only Arena
that we actually marked as Dynamic was one from the
Bug system.
And so the fact that that Arena isn't getting restored properly isn't
causing any obvious bugs, right?
So the whole program is working currently, but it's not actually
technically supporting the feet, the arena stuff, it just, it just
happens to be that we aren't calling.
We aren't using the dynamic Arena support in any place where it would
have actually caused an actual bug, right?
So that's the reason why we're not getting that.
Why we're not seeing any deleterious effects here, but we should be
able to provoke some of these deleterious effects.
Like the temporary memory, one by taking a look.
Actually, we could start here and just say, when we say begin
temporary memory, you can see right here, we do this.
Begin temporary memory.
If we were to go find an arena where that was happening, right?
So, for example, here is one in handmade in World mode, right?
And you can see temporary memory doing this on the the
Arena here.
So if we were to do it on this Sim memory guy, we could probably
provoke a bug here, right?
And the way we would do that is this transient Arena?
If we went ahead and said that the transient Arena instead of having
been a big block that was allocated out of stuff.
We could instead go ahead and make that be an arena that was
dynamically growing like our other one.
And if we did that, we should be able to provoke an error here or
something.
You know, a crash pad.
Behavior of something bad happening by forcing it through that path.
Okay?
So let's just try, let's see what happens if we do that.
There's also something that I would like to take a look at possibly,
as well, which is that right now.
We have this concept that Arenas, you can say, how much room there is
left in them.
Let me see where that actually is get Arena size remaining and people
have been using that kind of to figure out.
Out.
You can do for submarine has, right?
And you can kind of see that happening like here.
Now, not there here.
You can see that happening when we create the world, and we get an
arena, that's our parent Arena.
We go ahead and say, whatever is left in there.
We're going to use, right?
And again, that's something that we probably want to stop doing if we
start using dynamically sized arenas for stuff, we can't really do
that anymore, because if you ask a dynamic Arena, how much sizes
remaining?
It could answer anything.
It's just about
The block that happens to be in, so it's not a good thing to use
because it could I answer like four bytes, right?
I mean, who knows how close it is to the end of its particular block
that it was using.
And so when we do stuff like create world or something like that and
we say, parent Arena.
All we would really want to do there.
If we're doing submarine has off of things is we'd want the submarine
has to be things which were tied to the parent Arena.
So when the parent Arena got cleared the sub Arena would get cleared
that's about.
The only thing we would
Actually want to do their right but we wouldn't want to keep doing
that get Arena size.
Remaining stuff that's not particularly helpful for us.
Fortunately it looks like that's really the only place that were using
it is inside that sort of mode World thing and those are not in the
transient Arena.
So for the moment we can actually leave that and not have that do
anything in particular.
But now I'm going to go ahead and I'll do some sort of surgery here on
this code and I'll go ahead.
Ed and eliminate that transient memory pool that we were using before
and we'll switch that to a dynamic Arena as well, right?
And so here we are with transient storage and will say okay, the
transient storage type stuff, let's get rid of that and just say,
actually, what there is, is there just one of those transient States?
Let me see where that is and made that CPP transient state.
So we can just have one of these transient State thing
And again, instead of a is initialized, we'll just say that we store a
pointer to that state, right?
So in the game memory structure will say, hey, we know you're going to
want some transient States truck, we don't care what it is.
You define it yourself.
We don't the platform part of the game, doesn't care what it is at
all, but we know you might want to do that separately or something
like this.
So, we'll have the pointer in here.
And actually, honestly we wouldn't, we probably can collapse these
down.
Eventually, to once we have, we can just have one structure, which is
just like the games, you know, the actual game struck, which could
contain the transient and non-transient.
Because now that we allow the
Previously, we had only push forward for memory now that we're going
to say, there's no more push forward from memory, the app can request
memory.
It is something the app can request.
Then, you know, we don't have to do that anymore.
The only reason everything past forwards is just in the case where you
don't want the app ever allocating any memory, you don't want to
support that call back, right?
Which is a totally valid thing to do again, like I said, but once you
say I can support growing Arenas, then that means you have to have an
allocate and deallocate call back.
So once you have those, there's no reason anymore.
Not to just have the app do those initially.
So now the app even if the application wants to run in a completely
restricted memory space where it's only going to use a certain amount,
it would still just at start up.
The app will do the allocation of
Two gigabytes of memory or however, much it decides.
It's going to be, it's space.
It would make that call rather than you the platform layer making that
and passing it forwards.
So yeah.
So basically this would just go away here, right?
And now we would just have a thing that was the transient State and
then we'd have to basically do the work here of making sure that that
transient state was always access.
That way.
I don't know, debug get main generation ID.
Debug, get game assets, really want to get rid of main generation ID.
Yeah, we probably do.
But hey, you know, we haven't yet.
But that's okay.
Because that means this transient State call again is it's really just
This now, and it's kind of nice because it means that we no longer
have to do any of this stuff, right?
We can sort of just access this directly and it's actually kind of
cleaner than what we had before, even which is, which is nice, right?
So then here, when we're doing transient initialization, again, the
exact same things going to happen here that we, you know, that we
We're doing before.
So in the debug state, if you remember how we did this, we sort of did
the memory Arena Little Shuffle right.
Do do do we did this sort of idea that you create a memory Arena, you
push on the struct?
You actually wanted and then you sort of record to back to the
structure that you had whatever the state of the Arena was right?
And so, that's such a common thing that we want to do on Startup that
we can probably make it into some sort of a, you know, some sort of a
reasonable utility function.
It's a little bit squirrely just because see
Is really bad at these sorts of things.
See really doesn't like you to use pointers to things that don't
exist, yet.
It just the syntax just isn't as amenable to it as you would like even
though it's a very straightforward thing to do but you can imagine
what we're talking about here is so let's suppose that I have a
function
That looks like this bootstrap.
Push struct, right?
And we'll call that actually push size because we're going to have a
macro.
Like we have a macro for push struct.
So if we do bootstrap push sighs, what we need to do is say all right,
we know that there's some kind of a sighs, did I?
And I thought I added this right nowadays.
So I don't have to use memory index anymore.
I should probably replace them.
You next.
I like these are more concise fruit in my opinion.
I did add those right.
Yeah.
So when I do bootstrap push sighs, what I need to know is like okay
how big was the thing that you wanted to push on their right?
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to create a new Arena from Whole
cloth, but then I'm going to push on something that's going to contain
the arena.
So the other thing that I need, right is the offset.
So I basically need an offset to Arena inside the main struct.
Right, so however, far over that is.
And so then when I can do is, I can say, alright, I knew I need a new
memory Arena, right?
And it's basically now just this code.
I know I need a new memory Arena.
So I'm going to create one, I'm going to bootstrap it by pushing on
whatever the size is that you actually told me to push on.
Right.
Or this is the struct pointer basically, right?
This is what I, this is what I pushed on and then I want to do this
exact operation here, right?
I want to say that the thing the memory Reno that's inside the struct,
I just created in the memory itself.
I want to put the the memory Rena in there.
I want that to be the thing that attracts it, but I can't just write
that because I don't know what the structure actually is, right?
So what I have to do is just say well, okay, pretend we
Had a memory Arena pointer, right?
If we had a memory Arena pointer where would it be?
Well, it just be whatever the struct pointer was, plus, whatever the
offset is that you told me, that's where it would be because you just
told me that's how far over it is so pretend.
That's a Marina and write it in there, right?
Then of course, return the structure to the person who actually wanted
in the first place.
So, it's not very complicated, right?
It's pretty simple code.
It's just a little bit squirrely because of the syntax and then again,
for, for the bootstrap,
And this of it alone, you know, I should also allow you to align that
if you want to or do other things like clear.
So in that case, we do want the arena push params in here.
So I want to be able to pass
Prams and those will just get passed through to the size.
Right?
So now we can do a bootstrap push struct.
And a bootstrap push size, call as a result.
And now we have the ability to do the this inside, like say the debug
system as well, right?
So now, we can just do.
Okay, instead of all of this nonsense here, I can just say debug state
is going to be bootstrap.
Push struct of the exact.
Same thing that I called before, right?
And so the only thing I have to do now is actually get an offset of
and I feel like we have an offset of, right?
Yeah, we do.
So I just need the debug States debugger Arena.
That's how far over I want.
That's where inside the debug state struct it goes, right?
And that's it.
So yeah, so the same thing, what happened here?
The transient State structure, right?
Which is going to get written back into that into the game memory
structure there.
Excuse me.
Okay.
What I want to do here is say alright, let's take the transient state
that that I wanted to write and will store the transient State here as
well inside the memory structure.
So that it's persistent across frames.
What I want to do again is do a bootstrap push struct, right?
The bootstrap push truck will just pass one of these.
We'll just do one of these guys, right?
And we want the transient Arena on there as well.
So, we want to do an offset of
The transient Arena, right?
And again, we only actually want to do this operation if we have to
write.
So if the transient State already existed, right?
We wouldn't need to do this.
So you know, really this kind of thing.
This part actually kind of goes down here.
It's like the trance State up here.
Actually, we could
The trance State equals the transient State on the memory structure.
If that is not valid then we will initialize it otherwise we pass
through right?
So it's just very simple that's about it.
We do the bootstrap and then we off we go.
We don't need to do any of this initialization stuff at all.
Because now we just have an arena, right?
And that's it.
So the only other things that we probably want to do here is when we
do the bootstrapping initially, we probably want to have the
bootstrap, push size, unlike everything else.
We probably want this to be like there to be some additional
information here.
So there'd be like a struct size but there'd also be and maybe the,
you know, that Audrina but then they're probably also be the minimum
block size bit, because when we do the bootstrap, we'd probably want
to.
Set the minimum block size as well.
And that can just be set to 0 by default, but then if somebody wants
to, they can set that minimum block.
Eyes to something else, right?
And these should be set to default params as well, so that's about it.
I think that's it.
Now, we just have to clean up some of the other things that well that
need to be cleaned up.
Oops, what's the problem here syntax error?
What is the syntax error will you tell me?
Size of type.
It's a reason.
I just forgot to get rid of the arena there, so the bootstrap, push
trucks, actually still needs.
The offset bit.
I suppose we could just make it since we know that we're going to do
an offset we could just do it that way, right?
So that you actually just pass in the member that you're talking about
and so that would just be like, okay, we're going to do a bootstrap
push size of the type and the offset.
Of the thing from that type.
And that's the only part that we need.
The macro for the rest, can just be, there are eggs that are passed
along
So I think that's it.
Bootstrap push size.
Don't know why I put a
Probably because we want to maybe also keep one of the do we actually
need that to be an underscore for a particular reason?
Why did we do that?
Is there a push size macro?
Oh, yeah.
Because we probably want to pass debug data sometimes, so we probably
should keep that convention in place and do it that way.
All right, so, transient storage when we do get sound samples and a
place like that again, is just going to be able to do it exactly the
way that it was.
So nothing really happening there.
That's
This guy just now has to conform to the original way.
We were doing things.
Transient storage size.
No longer needs to do anything at all.
Let's take a look here.
Permanent storage has tranny start.
So now this again gets a little bit simpler.
Off we go.
And transient storage doesn't have to happen.
I think that's basically it, nothing else to it than that.
So, let's now take a look at what we've got.
Presumably.
And yeah, okay, so this was what we were sort of hoping for.
Although I don't actually know that this is, we may have introduced
another bug, but like I said, begin temporary memory and temporary
memory, where the things that we were trying to provoke a bug in.
And so hopefully, that is actually what we did.
I don't actually know, though, because we have not actually,
Verify that.
That's what we're looking at yet.
So, let's take a look.
So Arena uses temp men.
Used.
So yeah, I assume this would be pretty much exactly what we would have
expected to see, right?
We come in here and the memory Arena has gone through some kind of a
allocation event.
And now you're trying to unwind.
But you can't unwind properly because this Arena has actually changed
its base pointer, and it's state because it allocated a new block.
And so this assertion is firing and say, hey, wait a minute, what's
going on?
You're trying to rewind something.
That wasn't even that far to begin with, you know, what's the deal?
Okay.
So that's good.
That's what we wanted to see.
But now the question of course, is what are we actually going to do
about it, right?
So I provoked the bug that I said that I wanted to provoke but we're
going to have to come up with a solution because we obviously can't,
you know, we obviously can't leave it in such a fashion as to as to,
you know, not have our temporary memory stuff working.
So let me just briefly, explain what we're going to do again, like I
said before.
Actually, very simple.
Oops.
So this is like temp, mmmm.
For dynamic.
Marinas.
So, if you followed let yesterday's stream, then you know that how we
implemented this is we take our normal Arena that we had before it has
its base pointer.
The base pointer has like a used count that comes up.
So we move that sort of logically down until we get to the end and
we'll try to push something on the end that would overflow instead of
just asserting, which is the all we had in there before when we had
fixed size blocks.
Now, what we do is we allocate a new block and the new block right?
We can then
To the beginning of it and use it again.
So the question is, how would we Implement temp memory?
Well, if we want to implement 10th memory, then obviously, one thing
we would have to do here is we would have to have a way of knowing
that this had happened, because if the temp memory, gets locked right
here.
So it says, hey I'm going to begin a temp memory thing.
Then we do some stuff and we push a new one on and we end like here,
right?
So we filled up all of this with temp memory.
Then what we need to do is we need to eliminate this blocks.
We need to free this block back to the system.
And we need to jump back here.
Right?
And so, what we need to do is we need some recollection in our system
that this situation occurred so that we have something we can do about
it, right?
We don't at the moment, we don't have enough information to really do
anything about it and that's a problem.
Well what we can do right is use a very simple chaining scheme.
If we want to we can just say well
all right, if we took these memory blocks for example, and we just
said at the end of the memory block,
When we allocate one, we're just going to put a pointer right back to
the previous memory block.
Then if we wanted to, we would be able to know when we said and
temporary memory.
We'd be able to know that there was a situation that we might need to
be aware of where there's a previous Block in the mix.
Potentially multiple of them.
Write these could keep going.
So, then we can do is say, well, whatever the pointer is, right?
That we were trying to rewind.
To is it inside our block.
If it is inside our blog, we just do exactly the same thing we did
before and restore the used pointer.
If it's not free, the block were on.
And set our memory Arena to the previous block, then try again.
Right.
That's really all we need to do because eventually that will walk back
to the very first block and, you know, find somewhere along the way or
at that very first block, the actual original temp pointer, and when
it does, then it will stop.
That's it.
So like I said, very, very simple.
Actually there's just a little finicky Enos with it and it has to do
with how you actually specify where things are in the block, how you
put the footer on and that sort of thing.
But let me go ahead and show you what I mean.
So, if we say memory block, footer, and we take a look at what this
is.
All we really need to know here for the memory block footer.
Is okay?
We need to be able to restore the previous memory Arena if we freed
this block.
So the things we don't know about them is we don't know what the size
was, right?
We don't know what the used count was and we don't know what the base
pointer is, right?
We just don't know what those values are.
So if we just stuck these things into the footer,
Like so then we could fully restore the information that we needed, if
that makes sense.
That's all there is to it really.
So now,
We just have to make sure we put this thing.
I'm going to by the way make this memory block footer.
I'm going to make it exactly 32 bytes just because just because so
anyway here's our memory block footer that's going to kind of just you
know be something that's stuck on the end there.
If we wanted to we could sort of compress this down a little bit.
We could make it only 64 bytes because we wanted to, we could say that
we were only going to track, you know, four gigabytes of size per
block
Right?
Because, you know, presumably were not going to be out getting chunks
that are bigger than
Matt we're always going to be allocating things that are smaller than
that.
So who knows?
Right.
But if you go ahead and see memory block footer, right?
There's our one here we can just say all right doesn't matter it's how
we're big.
It is whatever blah blah blah, I'm not gonna bother padding it.
I take change my mind.
Anyway so we have that memory block footer, what we need to do now is
be able to actually stick that memory lock footer on to the end of
things, right?
And so when we go ahead and do our sort of fail down
Procedure.
So, like, when we do a push size here, what we want to do is say,
alright when we allocate one of these new blocks, we need to be able
to stick the footer onto the end of it, right?
And so when we take a look at what the size is that we're actually
going to allocate, we don't want to use that as the actual size,
right?
What we want to do instead is say the size, plus the size of the
footer,
Because that is the minimum.
When we you know, when we allocate a block to store whatever the new
push is, either we're going to do the minimum block size, which we
know will have room for our footer.
Because we know that a megabyte is bigger than however our footer
bever big, our footer is but if someone asks for a size that's bigger
than a megabyte so we need to allocate a block just to store this one
thing because it's huge.
Then what we want to do is make sure we could fit the footer on the
end and still, give back the person who's requesting it.
We can, we want to still be able to give them back the size that they
asked for, right?
So now we know we have enough room for our footer, right?
And we know, furthermore where the foot is going to be.
Now when we then set the size of the Arena, we don't want to include
the size of the footer, because the footer is reserved.
It can't be used with as an allocation as a thing for allocation.
So we needed then
You know, the the memory giveth and the memory taketh away here,
right?
We gotta add room for the footer.
And then we have to pretend we didn't have room for the footer when
we're done.
Okay, so then once we're done, where is the footer?
Well we know where the footer is so we can just make a thing that gets
us back to footer, right?
If we have memory block footer,
If we were to pass a memory Arena and say, where is the footer?
We know where the footer is because, however, big the size is of the
Arena.
If we went that far off the base pointer, we're at the memory block
footer, right?
Because we know we set the size to be however big the the block was
less the size of that of that footer.
So we know that the footer is here and so we can get that footer.
Right?
So you can see what I'm doing.
I'm just taking the base part of the arena and so that gives me back
the memory block footer for the block that I'm currently on, right,
whatever that block is.
So then what I can do is say all right I need to set up this footer to
allow me to back up.
So what I want to do is say given
You back the footer.
Here's me getting my footer back, right?
Get footer.
So, there we go.
And then, inside the footer, I want to record the information that I
was going to lose, right?
So I need to be able to say here in my, where is my footer here.
Here we go.
So in my memory block footer,
And I suppose the other day I could sort of do this as a pointer
thing, I could do this sort of separately.
I'm not sure how I really want to do it.
I'm gonna do it this way.
So I'm just going to say, alright, let's save all the information from
our Arena.
And then we'll just do.
Right.
So that'll take all of that information and it will save it to the
footer in this new block that we've allocated right now in theory.
Oops.
In theory, that should just work, right?
Force of habit.
All right, so in theory, that will just work, right?
We will just stick that information in there.
So now every time we allocate a new block, it will put that
information into the memory block footer and we're good to go, right?
But there is one caveat here, which is that if we were in an arena
that did not allow for dynamic allocation, right.
Its initial block would not have had this property, right?
So we wouldn't be able to get the footer out of that block that first
block, that was there.
So if we want to technically be you know, I don't know how you would
look at this, but if you wanted to be a little safer here, what you'd
want to do is say well, a sir, I mean, I guess it won't matter because
it'll just crash or something.
But basically, what I'm saying is we could add a safety check here.
That says, when you get into this part of the code, you
I want something that says hey assert that this Arena actually does
dynamically grow, you know, because otherwise, you're going to get
errors potentially.
Well.
Maybe not because you'll never look at the footer.
Yeah.
All right.
Forget I said anything.
Forget I said that.
So when we compile this in theory we should run just fine right up to
the same place that we had our assertion before because we haven't
actually changed anything and we do so that's good but now when we
look at our begin temporary memory and temporary memory.
Now, we should be able to do a better job, right?
So, if you
Look here when we do begin temporary memory.
You can see us doing our thing.
If you look, the thing that we're we're keeping now is not sufficient
information for us to be able to restore.
Now there's two ways that we could do this, and it depends on whether
we care.
How much space we take up on the stack, right?
I don't think we probably do so we'll probably just take the easier
way and say, well, save the base pointer as well.
Right, because we save the base pointer and the used, then we have no
problem as you'll see in a second.
But bear in mind, you wouldn't actually have to save all that.
You could if you wanted to just save one thing, which is the pointer
where you're at right now, and then that will give you all the
information.
You actually need either one, six, six of one half dozen of the other.
So anyway, when we do begin temporary memory.
What we do now is say, Okay, store the base as well.
Right.
Totally find there.
And then what we do is say when we do an end temporary memory.
Now we have an additional piece of information so what we could do is
now that we have our Arena we can do a while loop to hunt back for the
base pointer that we actually wanted.
So we can say, oh okay, take a look at the arena and see if it's base
pointer equals the base pointer.
We were expecting, if it doesn't, then we know we're in the wrong
block, right?
We're not in the correct block, I'm sorry.
So if it doesn't, you know, if they don't match we gotta go back a
block.
So now we can say, well, get the memory footer, right?
From our Arena.
And now we want to essentially unwind like we want to pop back a
block, right?
And in fact, what we could do is actually make a function here called
pop block,
That actually does exactly this operation, right?
So we could say, all right, if we had a memory Arena and we told it to
pop a block,
Then what we do is just we just keep popping until you know until we
were done right?
And maybe I'll call it free last block or something just to be clear
on what it's doing.
So that's going to get the footer right.
It's going to take a look at that base pointer that we currently have
and that's you know whatever the base pointer is that we currently
have, that's the thing we want to free, right?
So we're going to take a look at our current base pointer.
We're going to take a look at the footer and then we're going to say
all right the footer is going to overwrite all the values in our
Arena.
Makes sense and that's all we're going to do, right?
So now, the question is, just how do we get rid of the old base
pointers memory that we were using?
Well, that's not particularly difficult after.
We do this over, right.
So we know that we've used all the stuff in the footer that we need
the footer is now invalid if we free it but that's I mean if we once
we free it's going to be invalid.
So we have to pull the information out first but once we do pull the
first we can do a deal allocate memory call and just pass that pointer
and that will eliminate the block.
Right?
Okay, so will this will just walk us backwards and hopefully it will
just walk us backwards to the place.
We want it to be then we can proceed exactly as we would have because
we know we're actually in the same block that we originally took our
temp memory, sort of snapshot of, right?
And so now we should be at the point where we're totally running
exactly as we were before.
Right?
So now we can go across Dynamic allocations, and still rewind, our
temporary memory just as we were and so just to
Quick spot.
Check.
We want to make sure that we're not leaking anything here because we
might be but let's take a look.
You know what I this is not
This, this is not what I want to see though, where I need more
information.
Isn't there virtual memory bytes?
I don't want the working set.
I want the entire pool that all right, tell you what?
Let's just go to perfect mom.
We'll just go to perform on, why not?
I don't know if I've ever used perfmon on the stream before.
Perfmon is well perfmon is perfmon perfmon is a little utility that
ships with Windows and it allows you to access the performance
counters in the colonel.
Among other places.
And so what you can do is you can run it.
You just like I said, control Escape, perfect, you know.
Well how are you run programs type in perfmon and you get this guy and
it comes up with a view, that's not particularly useful, it's percent
processor time, but I don't care about that.
So I can get rid of it just by hitting the x button and it'll
eliminate what's in there.
I can then do an ad use the add button and say, I want to look at a
particular process and you can go down to wherever that is
There it is process and you can look at stuff like virtual B, how many
bytes of memory has it allocated total or whatever.
Right.
And I can also similarly, look at the working set B, whereas the
working set B, there it is.
Right?
So I can look at both of those and then I can select in this, in this
instance has thing I can select our application win32 handmade right
and I can say add and then I can get those.
Oops.
Need the total.
Again, and so now I have both of those.
For my application, right?
And you can see those listed down here.
Now, if I just click on them, I can see exactly how much memory I am
taking and I can watch it doing its thing, right?
And so you can see minimum maximum, right?
And I can see that it's stable which is what I want to see.
Like I want to see it not changing and it's not.
So that's good, right?
I want to see those numbers not going up so I know not leaking
anything.
Now, what you'll notice is
We're not getting a graph up here because this thing was made so long
ago, if you actually use the kind of amount of memory, that a modern
application would typically take for like a game or something at the
scale set.
Totally wrong.
And so you have to kind of bring it down to a level, right?
So that you can actually take a look at
There we go.
So there's the working set, there's the virtual B, right?
And and that it's kind of cool.
Like you can, you can actually save the setting sir, but you can see
that it'll just graph these for you and it'll stay up and running and
collecting those reports all for all the time and you can just kind of
like minimize it and go back and look at it whenever you want.
So it's pretty handy actually.
It's a pretty nice little utility to use.
Anyway, so I just wanted to verify that.
Okay?
So that's all well and good.
Let's just take one more leap while we're at it and turn our entire
game over to just dynamic memory, right?
So now we'll actually go ahead and go full full bore.
We will not have any more see here.
Yeah.
Well, not have any more block allocations at the at startup at all for
the game code, right?
So it's just be
What do we call that permanent State?
What's it called?
Just game state.
And even remember it's been so long.
Game state.
We'll get rid of these entirely and we're just going to do exactly the
same thing I did before, right?
So we go to the permanent storage size is initialized kind of stuff
and we just change the way that works.
So now we get rid of that, right?
And we say, all right here's the the game State stuff and we look
again to see, is it initialized?
If it's not initialized, we bootstrap it.
What's the arena called here?
Total Arena.
So we've got total Arena.
I don't know if total arena is totally going to ever even used total
arena is not ever used.
It's just these other Arenas that are used.
So we're not even going to do that one, I guess.
So we'll just say, is there I guess?
It never saves that Arena.
There's just an
Arena and a mode Arena, are the only two things.
I don't really know why that is.
But it is.
All right.
Anyway.
Either way, I'm going to initialize the the game arena this way.
Like that.
And I'm going to get rid of all of this and then instead of doing
submarine has, I'm just going to do.
I'm just going to let those guys since this will get cleared.
I'm just going to let those guys be dynamic as well, right?
Makes sense.
So now everything in our game is running through Dynamic allocation,
right?
And again I just wanted to kind of emphasize this
Well, I guess not we sought to do this, probably a sub Arena call
somewhere.
Is there?
Yes.
So, there is a sub Arena call right here.
So we'll have two will have to deal with that.
Well, not really I guess.
Lorena.
Memory Arena.
This one, I guess.
There you go.
So we still need to do something with this guy.
We can't have the World Arena also be similar.
If we would just have to have it, be cleaned up, right?
It would have to actually clean itself up.
All right, so we'll talk about this in a second.
But what I wanted to point out here was just that as you can see, most
like 99% of your code that uses Arena doesn't really change at all.
If you're using a fixed size versus Dynamic allocation, in terms of
your Arenas, right?
It just isn't a particularly it's not particularly important thing in
terms of knowledge in most of the code.
So it's really all of the same principles that
I have been applying just they just work for the most part, pretty
much throughout except for things where you ask the parent Arena, how
much size it has and then use that much size, right?
That's the only thing and we're seeing that here in this sub Arena,
right?
So what we want to do here is say well, okay, when we do create world,
what we probably want to do here is again, we could just make this be
also, a dynamic thing and allow these Arenas to be dynamic as well.
What we do need to again, appreciate is if we do that.
So if we use submarine has that would have had to get cleaned up,
right?
We have to be aware of that.
So we'll we'll take a minute to go do that.
How much time do I have here?
I've got 15 minutes, okay.
That should be plenty.
All right, so temporarily what we'll do here is we'll just say, like,
okay the World Arena also is a thing that can just be kept as Dynamic,
right?
So if we wanted to make the World Arena, be be dynamic.
All we have to do there is say, like, okay, don't don't bother
actually pushing that thing on at.
All right?
Just, just leave it as clear because this will clear it and then it
will be a dynamic arena with the default size, okay?
So the only problem we would then have is that we don't
Clean up that particular memory, right?
That memory is never going to actually get cleaned because when we do
when that Arena gets pushed, you know, essentially gets pushed on
here.
There's never anything to tell that Arena to clean up.
If we were to unwind this structure now, I don't actually know exactly
how we were doing this in the past.
I'm not sure what we did.
Oops.
What we were doing about that.
So, like, for example, when we are in handmade dot CPP when we launch
a game mode here, how do we actually do that?
Because somebody's got to deal with this somewhere.
I don't know where.
Should be here somewhere.
Play world so you can see set game mode.
Where is set game mode.
There it is.
So this is, this is our problem, right?
This is our problem right here.
So basically what happens is, if you try to do SUB Arenas like that
and you then go to clear out one of your Arenas, those sub Arenas
aren't going to get cleared right?
They're never going to actually get cleaned up.
And so what we actually need to do there is we need a system whereby,
we don't rely either.
We don't rely on that or we baked knowledge of the fact that their
Arenas spawned off of other Arenas.
We bake that into
a memory system.
Now, at the moment, it's probably just not necessary because we don't
have that many memory Arenas, right?
There's just not that many of them.
Let's see here.
These are all pointers.
1 2 3, 4 5.
Six.
78.
Right.
So there's only eight of these things total.
So at that point, right?
It's kind of, like, do we really even want to bother with that?
And some of them are in systems that don't, Matt don't have any of
these properties.
Like, the task with memory bit where it's just not relevant, right?
It's not a relevant thing.
I don't like, dude.
Just task with memory.
Do we actually even use that by the way?
I don't even remember if that's actually used.
Now, I'm curious to know.
Is it?
Let's see.
I want to move over here so I can not be behind my own head.
Yeah, so this is just a game state.
And this is all goes away.
Right.
But that's it.
All right.
/ Marina.
Where is that coming from?
Just want to take a look at this.
Ah yeah.
Just for the record when you do a bootstrap and you want to create a
new struct, it helps you know, don't want to be pushy about everything
but it would help if you would actually record.
The thing you actually created just, you know, just good to know.
all right, so we do have some problems here though, that we have to
vote that we have to take a look at more specifically and that is that
again that submarine apart isn't going to work so well, I guess since
we might
We started here.
I will go ahead and finish getting this guy going but then we'll take
a look at the submarine stuff so this is fine through the audio state
is an asset.
oh, and
we have to record that in the memory structure as well.
There we go.
So in theory, we should bottom out now because we're not handling that
sub Arena call but I guess it's okay.
I just wanted to see if that would work because it's still, it will
still use the rest of the MB part that it had.
So yeah, suffice to say.
Let's take a look.
So if I go into world, if I go back into Worlds mode or sorry world,
where do the submarine a call?
Or at least I thought we were doing.
So we're going to call
There we go.
Let's see.
So these are tasks Arenas out of the transient State and again, I
don't think we actually care about that at all.
So in theory when we do this task memory here, when we go through
these tasks, each task is going to have been cleared to 0.
So these would also all just work, right?
Yeah.
And I think that's it, right?
So now really our problem that we have at this point is strictly that
are clears wouldn't work anymore, right?
So even for like these tasks right now, we just the tasks have Arenas
that will dynamically allocate for them and that's all well and good.
But when they go to clear, like are clear call will never actually
work.
Right.
So for example, this clearing of the motor Rina will not actually
clear all the memory for the motor Arena and is that the only time we
ever clear?
Do tasks not clear their memory.
I guess.
Do they just use temp memory?
Maybe they do.
So here's where we do.
Begin test with memory and tempered, memory, memory flush.
And yeah,
so, actually the
They just clean themselves up.
Exactly that way.
Alright, so that's pretty easy as well.
So yeah, okay, so I guess that's all well and good.
So are clear.
Now, I guess the point I was trying to make before though is our clear
which we do need for certain circumstances.
Are clear doesn't work, right?
Because if you look at what clear does clear, all it does is Wipe Out
the state but wiping out the state isn't what we want to do here
because we may have allocated a bunch of blocks.
And we don't want those blocks.
To stick around.
Right.
So what we want to do when we say clear is we want to be able to do
essentially free last block all the way up to the original block,
right?
We want to basically clear out everything
All the way to the original block.
Now I don't know if initializer Rena here, I don't know who's calling
this at the moment.
But what you'll notice on this guy is that basically, when we do, when
we do this initial call here, in fact, does anyone call this, let's
just find out
Hey look, let's make this our first Global Arena.
Well, we didn't do that.
Oops.
It is now.
There we go.
So basically nobody uses that form of initialize Arena, right?
Except for our clear call which we just had to be don't want so that's
good because now we can basically say let's just get rid of that,
right?
Let's just say we just don't have that anymore.
So the only time you would say initialize arena is if you wanted to
set the minimum block size for it, right?
And so what I might do is just say let's just say that instead.
What we have is just a set minimum block size
Like so.
And that way, you can just search for that going on and that's it.
And no one's actually even doing that at the moment, right?
So we probably don't even really need that.
So, okay, so now everything's working there.
The problem is just we need some way of actually doing the clear and
what I'd like to do with the clear is I'd like to say, okay if we're
going to clear this thing, then what we want to do is we want to
essentially rewind back to some point where we
No.
We've gotten to the, to all of the memory that we may have allocated
has been cleared, right?
That's what we
And so we can do this relatively easily just by tracking one
additional parameter, right?
And that parameter is just a that parameter is just how many of these
things have we allocated?
So far.
So in our memory Rina, right, all I have to do is like block count.
Right?
No way.
That's an s 32 but okay, or you think they should say.
So, if I just track how many allocations I have made, then I know when
I got back to my original block count, when I got back to my, to my
first one, that would allow me.
Even in the case, where I put on a block that someone else had
allocated, or sub, allocated out of someone else's block, I could
still just not increment the block count at the
I mean for that case and that would allow me to always clear back to
anything that I had allocated, right?
So in clear all I would have to do is do while the Arena's block count
is greater than zero, you know, free to last block
and then, in here, what I would do is say, okay, when I have done
that,
Just decrement that block out.
So now I know how many of these things deep I am.
I know.
I can always free back to the beginning and so all I have to do is
increment that anytime I actually did an allocation of some kind.
So, the Arena's block count will always go up.
Whenever I've made a new one.
Makes sense.
So now our clear actually works just fine but again we still have one
more problem.
Like in theory we should we should still run, okay, but we still have
one more problem and that is any Arenas that we were previously
thinking of as kind of ganged to other Arenas aren't going to work.
And so what I'd like to do is just let's just not do that, right?
It's easiest easy enough for us not to do that.
So we might as well just not right.
So if you take a look at the places where we actually care about that,
they are pretty few and far between.
Mostly we just have a Rena's that just stay around all the time.
And so we actually do need to clear something, right?
We know that that's a very rare actually.
So we do this clear of the motor Rina and so really what we want to do
is say well that motor Rena bit where we did sort of the world's
allocation stuff.
What we could do there is the world really doesn't need?
Probably its own sub arena for modes like that, right?
We could just have it used this Arena.
So if you take a look at what happens in the world and it's got this,
this
Us extra Arena here.
What we could just say is like, hey just use the arena that the person
passed you.
There's no reason why you need to be a separate Arena.
Just have the person tell you what arena you were going to use and
then be done with it, right?
I can't see anything.
That is not helpful.
I need to add a mode to for coder, that's like stream mode which tries
to keep things in the center of the screen.
So now it's just going to use that Arena all the time.
And so now, when that's cleared, right?
We should get a crash immediately because it's just pointing to 0,
right?
So, all we have to do now is just say, when we actually create a
world, just pointing at the arena were given, don't try to sub
allocate out of it, right?
Because why not?
So if we do that, see here, I don't know why we weren't doing that to
begin with, to be honest, even in the other case, I'm not sure why
that would have been.
But yeah, so somewhere we do world where we initialize the world,
create worlds
There we go.
And so now that should be getting cleaned up.
So if we're doing modes here where we swap back and forth like here's
the title mode thing and this is the thing that will like play the
cutscenes or whatever else periodically and that sort of thing.
Or not.
We're what happened to our cutscene?
Our poor cutscene is gone.
Is that when we change the camera code?
I thought we looked at that.
When we change the camera code,
We'll have to add that to the to-do list.
Well, anyway, now we're running entirely on the dynamic memory and so
if we take a look at how much memory were actually using, now it
should be significantly less as well, because we're not actually
allocating space for stuff that we don't need at this point now,
right?
So, you can take a look over those lines went right?
They dropped quite a bit further down.
So if you take a look at how many bytes were using were using under a
gigabyte now, because
We're not actually doing any of that load.
Now, the other thing we can do is I believe we're actually doing in
the asset system.
I believe it manages its own memory, right?
And so it does sort of a thing where it just doesn't.
Big old allocation.
So that part where we passed the size here which is, I think 256 MB or
something like that.
That's still getting a pretty big chunk of memory taken out for it and
various other things as well.
So we could probably stand to start doing a little bit of a memory
profile at this point, but maybe we'll save that for next week.
Anyway, that's the first part of our memory upgrade.
And like I said, now it's all working relatively well, but the main
thing that we have to do besides sort of going in there and
Fixing some of those now that there's now that we have this ability
and we can make it a little cleaner, we can probably reduce the need
to have like multiple arenas for any particular reason now.
Like, we don't need a separate audio Arena, probably, or maybe we do,
but it would again be, it's completely separate Arena.
Potentially, if I do Loop Live code editing, you'll notice that
nothing happens, right?
And the reason for that is just because we now no longer
Have a way to track any of those Arena blocks we allocated.
So they're not actually getting written.
So let's go ahead and do here.
Cutscenes.
Now malfunctioning.
So I guess we'll just do.
We got to do a debugging day so they can do these guys.
so we probably need that and like a clean up where Arenas are used and
how
But that's about it.
So we'll go to the Q&A here.
I don't want to go too far over time there so we'll go to the Q&A.
But now I believe,
We're at least fully dynamic in all the ways that are not related to
bugging.
So the loop live coding is obviously a debugging feature for our
purposes.
So we need we want to support that just for ourselves but it's not a
user facing feature.
So we've already done the memory Arena stuff that's actually necessary
for us to ship right to actually, if you want to ship a game with
dynamic memory, allocation.
We've already done that part, right?
And so, yeah,
so, the risk
Have you ever tried?
Reserving a very large amount of memory and then committing memory as
needed.
So the arena can grow without the base pointer changing.
Well, I mean, yes, I have done that, but I've never shipped that in
anything.
So if you can guarantee that you're running a 64-bit only, if you're
running a 32-bit, only that won't work, right?
And the reason that won't work is you'll never be able to reserve a
big enough region of memory in 32-bit to allow all your Arenas to have
enough size to grow.
If you don't know ahead of time, how big they have to grow, right?
If but if your honesty verba system, that you probably can so that on
64-bit code, that only has to work on 64-bit, that might be feasible,
right?
It largely depends on how the operating system plays well with you.
Dude, and basement thoughts on placing the footer at the beginning of
the memory Rina.
So bad co-workers, don't overwrite it because it is at the end.
Currently,
Well, if you know, the co-worker is would right off the end of the
memory block and crash potentially, if, as if you moved it to
beginning, but sure.
Yeah, you can, if you want to move it to the beginning, the reason
that I don't like moving it to the beginning, is it?
Because it means that you're first.
So it means that your initial thing that you're pointing to is
actually not at the base of the memory block, if that makes sense,
which I don't always like because you may want that to be aligned to
64k boundary or other things like this for usefulness pointer wise or
who knows what else.
So I usually put them at the end but yeah, you can put it at the
beginning if you want to
There's no real fundamental difference between those two things.
As I'm saying that, now I'm thinking wait is there though?
I mean, basically, here's all I'd say.
So let's say you needed to be aligned to something large.
So let's say, you know, you're using,
Christine, you're on like a modern really modern machine.
So you're using 61 16 wide same day or whatever, right?
So you're like 64, you're like, one whole cache line is the alignment
boundary.
You were looking for, right?
What it means is that you'd have to basically take 64 bytes at the
beginning of your thing, for the, for the header.
Because if you didn't, then the memory the first
First piece of memory wouldn't be aligned to that so you're going to
blow 64 bytes worth of space, the beginning of your buffer regardless.
Now if you don't mind that, then that's fine.
But if you do, then you're kind of you kind of have to put it at the
end because putting it at the end is the only way you can ensure that
hate because it only needs like 16 bytes, or 32, bytes or something,
it's the only way you can ensure that you're not using more than you
actually need it.
Other than that, I don't think there's any real reason.
But maybe there is, I don't know.
I have to think about maybe there's a isn't
and when L you spend so much time on memory management.
We do if programming games for Windows Linux, would it be better to
use malloc and then create custom application for hot parts?
We don't spend any time on memory management, do we?
This is one of the first rooms we've had in.
I don't even know when where we even touch the memory.
Let's see.
Casey, how strict are you on minimizing the amount of memory that is
used by the game at the moment?
Not, not really like right now is not really a particularly useful
time to minimize the amount of memory used by the game in my opinion
because you kind of are wasting your time if you try to prematurely
optimize memory usage.
So we don't do anything, you know, I wouldn't do something that I
thought would.
Be impossible to optimize later, right?
But as long as it's something reasonable that I'm not too scared
about.
We just do it and don't care too much about it here because I'm
assuming that we will do much like performance optimization.
We will do those more towards the end of the project than the
beginning and then at the end of the project, we may do some things
where like this is using too much memory.
We need to change how we're doing it and then that will be the time
for that.
And yes, John McGrath the event tracing for Windows API is like the
worst API ever made.
I mean, that's why I said that it just keeps getting worse, the more
you want to do with it.
Keep in mind also at least if I remember correctly.
The API Badness that I talked about was the API Baptist, you'd
encounter to get anything out of it, right?
But if you wanted to get everything out of it like if you actually
wanted to go get all of the things that was capable of getting.
There's like a whole other set of disasters.
You are in for right that I never even tried to work with.
People who says, when we're dynamically allocating, we could
potentially end up allocating every last drop of memory available to
us, right?
Are there situations in which we'd want to make sure we allocate some
amount less than the Max and if so, how would we best do that?
So
I guess what I'd say about that is I don't really know of any good way
you can do that without just doing it the way we originally did it,
right?
like,
When we just allocate memory at startup and only use that memory.
That's the only way I know of that.
You can actually guarantee that you'll run properly, if you don't do
it that way, then you never know whether some other tasks in the
operating system, it's like a race condition kind of a thing.
No matter what you try to do, you can never know ahead of time how
much memory you might have later, right?
So, the only thing you can really do is allocate.
And then when you fail the allocation, then that's it, right?
And it's usually pretty
Infeasible to try and make a well, working application that actually
handles and out of memory error, anywhere in it correctly, which is
why I try not to do that.
And I tend to Dupree allocating upfront, kinds of stuff for any
situation where I'm actually concerned about it.
So yet there really isn't I mean there really isn't a way to be able
to predict whether you're going to run out of memory or not other than
just allocating what you want up front.
And then using that, that's, that's really it.
And, you know,
Yeah, I've never some people think like, you know, by putting in a
bunch of exception, handling and smart pointers and all sorts of stuff
that they will properly handle out of memory errors.
I've literally never seen a single time when that worked.
These are the only way that I ever know that actually works is
allocate up front and don't use more than what you were able to get at
the outset.
Long Boolean.
So currently you can only free memory in the last memory blocks.
If you wanted to free, stuff to the beginning of the arena and keep
the stuff at the end, you would need to do things differently.
Yes.
Obviously, these are arenas that are, they're really not technically,
a Rena's per se because I think
I guess that what I would say is Arenas are are used to describe a
different type of memory pattern as well, which is when you just do
regular variable allocations and could free anything you want inside
them as well, but then there's just a flush command to freeze
everything.
These support that but not freeing out of the middle.
So they do support the the get rid of everything but they don't
support like sub freeing.
So really these are more like Stacks.
I mean they're really more like memory Stacks, you know.
And so if you want the ability to dynamically free arbitrary stuff out
of the middle of one of these Arenas.
Yes, you need to then have a general-purpose alligator, right?
What you can Implement.
It's not like
Hard to put one on top of this.
But it's not, it's no longer a straightforward like just push the
pointer forward thing.
So if you are planning on large worlds, are you planning then?
I'm compressing and decompressing from the Mandela on the Fly.
No.
So keep in mind that we already could support out of core trivially.
If we wanted to, I don't know that we need to ever because the chances
that we could create a world large enough to not fit in physical
memory on, today's machines, seems low, but bear in mind that this
stuff right here, this itself could is where we would put the inside.
The world thing is where we would put the streaming to
uuuuuugh.
So we would not implement the streaming in the memory system, we would
implement the streaming in the world struct.
So basically, when you do sort of these chunk access stuff when you,
when you stream in and out of chunks, that would be where we would put
the out of course stuff.
Well Henry here, use texture compression and opengl probably not
because it would only result in degraded visual quality.
Right?
The reason you turn texture compression on is either because you need
more texture bandwidth to through the card.
Or you need to save texture memory space on the card.
But handmade hero since we know what we're looking at and we have a
dynamic paging system for textures.
Should never need those things.
So all it would do if we turned on text regression open job just make
all of our textures.
Look uglier like, right?
So it basically that would be a button that was called like make my
artwork look worse, which, you know, we wouldn't want to do so.
So no, I suspect we would never turn on texture compression for
handmade here because it seems like it would be a strictly a lose for
us.
And yes, like I was saying, earlier pseudonym 73 was was posting about
the term Arena.
So like I was saying earlier, the reason why I say that these are more
like, memory Stacks than Arenas is just because Arena doesn't
Arena is not a word for exactly the structure that we have here Arena
just refers to the fact that memory allocations were being tracked as
a group so that they could be freed as a group, it does not imply that
you can't free individual ones, right?
All right, so I think that's about it.
I'm going to close up.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here.or.
It comes with a source code so that you can experiment with it.
We also have Forum site.
You can go to.
If you want to ask questions a patreon page, you can go to.
If you want support the video series, 8 schedule, bot that tweets the
schedule all the time.
So that, you know, when we're going to be live and an episode guide,
if you want to catch up on old episodes, that's it for this week.
We will be back next week for more
So the handmade hero for the schedule, do check the schedule.
But until then,
Have fun programming and I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy everyone.