You ready to go?
Okay, I think it's 10:30 so I'd like to get started because we really
just don't have any time for breaks and I apologize for that but I
just felt like we should take as much time as possible to talk to
people are coming here because honestly like I'm super excited to talk
to them.
I hope you are too but you know at the end of the day I get I'm going
to ask the question.
So I want to I want to keep all our 15 minutes to myself.
Thank you very much for coming to hand make on.
I am absolutely, like, shocked to see so many people here and there
was like a meat.
Last night at the Seven Stars pepper and there's a couple other ones
that people are organizing online and I went there and we took like a
brief show of hands.
It was like, how many people traveled to get here?
And it was like, everyone and people were like, yeah, I flew 22 hours
to get here unless I just like I do not know what to say other than
thank you so much for that.
I mean this is this is a $35 conference and I don't even want to know
how much it must have cost to get here from some of those places.
And so, we will be doing our absolute best.
To make it worth your while.
So I don't want to take very much time with introduction.
So I'm just going to say really quickly.
We are trying to record it.
So hopefully there will be video afterwards and we're trying to record
both, what's on the screen and what's coming, you know, what's
happening up here.
So hopefully that'll work out well and we'll have stuff afterwards.
The streams are what we could do with what we had.
So they may go down, they may not if you're watching at home up there
on the stream, I apologize.
If it's a little spotty that was it was the best we could do, but
hopefully you'll be able to see everything.
The fact at the very least and here's how this is basically going to
work, I'm going to talk to each programmer and we're going to go
through all of the stuff that I want to know about the things that
they're working with and just kind of go in detail about like what
they're working on what they have worked on like you know what their
perspectives are on things.
How they approach coding all that sorts of stuff and I don't think
we're going to be able to do time for questions during we might but I
have a feeling we're going to like fill up all the time.
So what I'd like to do is just say anyone who has a question
Kitchen that they think of that they would like answered, I will take
all the questions on Twitter so you can do at senior ettore and just
tweet the question at me, I will gather them all up tomorrow and then
I will actually email everyone who we spoke to and if they have time
to answer some of them, I will, I will go back on stream, but I might
filter, I might filter.
So try to keep it, just a programming questions, you know, not
designed questions or those sorts of things because we try to keep it
mostly to program him here.
So that's it for the, for the, for the boilerplate.
So, you know, I just like get started.
The first person we have is, well, everyone knows his game.
Everyone's played Super Meat Boy, so I that needs no introduction, but
you may never have seen him in person.
Tommy reference, ladies and gentlemen.
And we're going to talk a bunch about the controller stuff, but but
before we get to that, I kind of wanted to start off by saying, I
don't even know.
Really much of the history of pre Meat Boy.
So I had a bunch of questions.
I want to ask about that, boy and the first thing I wanted to find out
was how do you, how do we get to me by?
Like where are you in your life at the time when you're like hey what
is, you know, we're going to do this project together, right?
Okay so I've got sick so well, not sick, but cough, cough, just is me.
I know I'm gonna I'm gonna make sure everybody's got something to take
on.
Want to aerosol that?
Yeah.
So back in 1999 2000.
There was a site called new grounds, and I think most people know
about Newgrounds.
I think and on Newgrounds, I made terrible.
Terrible.
Flash games and terrible flash animations.
And so did Edmund and we sort of met up.
And then we both went our separate ways like before.
Like I went and got into web development, stuff PHP.
MySQL.
I wrote real estate databases, which sounds really boring, but it was
a lot of fun.
Yeah.
So, you know like okay, you know, Zillow?
And how they show everybody's listings.
Yeah, that's actually called broker reciprocity.
Okay, so that's the thing where every agent can grab the listings and
so other agent stuff, and they get like, percentages, blah, blah, all
that stuff, but the complicated fund problem with that is all MLS
systems are stupid and know.
None of them are centralized.
So, my first actual job, aside from Little contract jobs here and
there was writing real estate database software that took like five
different databases in Western North Carolina and integrated them into
one searchable thing.
That was my job, that was like, when I was 20 and that was super fun.
That's crazy.
I had no idea.
Yeah.
And it was, yeah, it was, it was just the in Western North Carolina,
they had just entered,
State and I was this new programmer.
The only programmer at this little web place that was managed by this
moron.
And oh, man, this is being recorded, you know, he's a moron and he
knows he's a moron.
I'm not going to say is I won't say his name, I could say his name.
No, it's not human, his name's Blake Butler, you're never gonna find
him.
Okay.
But yeah.
So that was my job and that was sort of, you know, MySQL PHP stuff and
during that whole time
I'm I always was trying to make my little game engine and never really
I had flash.
So that was mainly what I was making stuff in and trying to make like
a game engines.
Were two things and Flash, just sort of tinkering around.
But my day job was always just, you know, web stuff this and that and
then after that job, I moved to Charlotte.
I wasn't Asheville.
I moved to Charlotte and got a job at a place that was doing
educational like almost games, but they were like an educational
portal.
And that was just dealing with hundreds of thousands of users.
So mainly my life was all database stuff and building applications for
people like teachers and stuff.
So how do you get from that?
Touka Super Meat.
Boy is all written like in C++.
Yeah, it's so how do you get from that as what you were doing to?
Like, I'm going to build a whole game engine myself using.
None of these things not using Flash not using yeah, it right.
What what did that process look like?
Does that mean?
So how that happened was?
As I was doing all that work, I was doing bunch of contract work and I
was doing stuff for like Duraflame in NASCAR like just and I would
just spend all my time doing all this work.
That was fun for my brain, but not for the creative fun, part of my
brain.
And one day I was reading an e GM and electronic gaming monthly.
I don't even know if they exist anymore, but they did an interview
with the guy that was
Coating.
The fishing minigame in Twilight, Princess and check and he was doing
it actually wasn't an interview with him.
It was an interview about Twilight Princess, but they had this little
thing and the reason there was a fishing minigame in Twilight.
Princess is because this one programmer loved fishing.
And in his off time, he made the fishing minigame, okay?
And I read that and I went, I make shit for Duraflame.
I don't want to do this anymore, so around that time, was this all?
So because of your shared, passion of fishing, I have fish.
Yes, of fishing and my hatred of Durham.
Yes, understood.
They have a weird slogan, by the way.
Duraflame, what is their slow car?
Is that the log?
Yeah.
Yeah, you put in the fireplace when you like the log on fire.
Yeah, that's like really a log.
It's like compressed post-process materials.
And yeah, it's really stinky like gasoline log, as what it is, but it
works.
It burns for a long time, but their slogan when I saw it over
Thanksgiving.
It's something like, tonight's the night.
It's something really weird like okay so amazing.
Yeah.
So okay after my friend had gotten a good jobs more romantic than a
giant.
Hey baby.
Yeah, hey baby.
Let's pop that Duraflame and let's make some Sparks.
Yeah, that's how I met my wife.
It's over a Duraflame log.
Yeah, it works.
Yeah.
So my friend had got a job at a company.
In Amsterdam was also managed by morons.
This is a weird,
Friend for me, that's management.
And they needed a network programmer.
And I am done, much sleep loss.
Plus an old long time like little bits here and there and I did an
interview with them and I convinced them that I knew C++, well enough
to get the job.
All right?
And so I learned a lot of C++ on the plane to Amsterdam and then I got
there and learned more and more and more and was able to learn fast
enough that they couldn't.
They couldn't catch me.
Okay.
Yeah.
And and from there, I was like Network program and then I worked up to
like lead engine programmer because I just it was I wasn't, we weren't
building our own engine.
We were basically taking the unreal 2x engine and porting it to 360
which 2x was terrible because it was a it was a hack on unreal to and
then to take that the 360 was crazy but I was doing all these like was
a command buffer optimizations and all this stuff to make.
It like actually they oh my God.
They had their artists have no concept of what card we're can do.
Okay?
So this was an Xbox 360 and they had models with fingernails that were
Model geometry and textures that were for it was like for 4096 by for
like 4,000 96-well for their face.
Okay.
There's no way to get the emotions.
Yeah.
Without the yeah, you've seen the video.
Yeah, you need the fingernails are part of the acting.
The the best part though, is the characters were never more than this
big on the screen.
Well, you and I had constant my emotions in there, even if you can't
see it.
It's yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So like IGN's, like was a great game especially the finger at this.
Oh my God.
Those were great.
Fingernail cannot a.
Did they add a new fingernails rating?
I did a whole fingernail Shader.
It was amazing.
Yeah.
But I that's where I was like
Like I was all into like the optimization stuff.
I was actually had a lot of time where you were doing.
See this engine work.
Oh yeah.
It was yeah like that.
That was like my whole job was.
Make sure this shitty game called hoop world, that eventually came
out, but not on 360, make sure, but make sure it runs at 60 frames a
second.
And that was my job.
And that was like, I was doing all sorts of fun stuff.
Like, I was trying to figure out a way to
Make animation textures, where it would encode, the matrices in the
texture and use that in, like instead of having like, all the Shader
constants and everything because there's a really super slow going
through.
I'm like, well, if we just use this and it didn't work, but but it was
what I wanted a shot.
Yeah, it was fun to do.
And it was like, I was, that's how I was like learning about like
optimizations and how like, you know, how all this stuff sort of works
together.
And that was my job for about 10 months until the company kind of
went terrible.
And so this is that's also 360 practice.
Yeah, that was 360 practice.
So I was like, super familiar with 360 Hardware, then quit that job
and a friend of mine.
Aubree Aubree has children.
He's a good guy.
We started a game together.
He was the lead designer on hoop world.
I was program.
We started a game together where his game called goo which came out
the same time as world of coup.
Which that?
Yeah, but yeah, it was a very good game, okay?
World of Google, not not my game.
Okay, no world.
It was amazing.
My game was terrible.
Okay, but it was super physics stuff.
It was multi-threaded physics craziness and that was my hey, let's
have multi-threaded fun.
Okay, the kind of time and that's when I learned a whole bunch about
threading and my game, kind of went nowhere, and then around that
time, I was looking at igf winners because goo had
Got into the igf and I'm like, oh, cool.
I look through winners.
And I see gesh.
And I'm like, oh, because I have this thing where I have to like, see
everything who made this, who made this and been made that I'm like,
oh, I'm like, I wonder if I still have them on instant messenger and
like I did when we started talking and then, you know, I went to Santa
Cruz because we were going to do Gish to for 360, but that fell
through, okay.
And then meatboy sort of happened.
And by that time I had the goo engine and then
I was like, well, I'm going to revamp this because I always revamp
stuff, so I'm like, well, revamp this for Meat Boy.
And then, yeah, from that made the tile engine made the tile editor
made all of those thingies for, that's kind of Interest, like I never
knew that Baxter actually.
So yeah, actually it, that is kind of like almost a training montage,
that whole thing, pretty much made up to Super Meat Boy, yes.
All the things they were like, you know, all the hardships.
Yeah.
Turns out to be really useful.
Yeah, for the bigot.
So let me ask about the Super Meat Boy than actually.
Gotta keep, I gotta keep.
Checking the clock.
So I know what times were at, oh, yeah.
So let's talk a little bit about that the, the whole tile editor
stuff.
I kind of want to ask a little about that especially, because this is
something that, that, that always is in my brain for some reason,
right?
Which is okay, so especially on something like Super Meat Boy, right?
You've got a situation where you guys weren't even in the same
location.
No, no.
I was in North Carolina because you're separated.
Yeah.
So how did you guys go about figuring out that art process?
Because you had like, again, you got your own custom engine, right?
He works in whatever tools.
He works in a glass.
Yeah, normally use this, right?
Yeah.
And so, for date day one, okay.
We should probably also turn off.
I didn't say, silence your cell phones?
Because I normally don't actually care about that, but I should not
say, yeah, right next to the Sea.
Now, you know why they say it?
Yeah, point being, yeah.
You sit down and you're like me, you know, need to start building this
game and maybe there were some decisions.
I guess you made from the previous game in terms of how art would come
in, but like, you're
Work with Edmund.
He needs to put all this content in.
How did you select work through that process?
Was it iterative or did you know upfront, what you need to like, give
me some, give me some sort of insight into if I'm in that situation.
You just drop me in in place of you.
What, what is like?
What are all the things to think about?
And how you got an efficient way of like implementing the, you know,
did you do importers or exporters or how, you know, give me that whole
thing.
So my kind of philosophy about that and about working with any artist
is you the way
You get the best workout of people is by giving them the easiest way
to give you the best work.
So when it came to Edmund oh some Applause of people who approve.
Okay.
Well so with Edmund he works in Flash and I was familiar with flash
and my thinking was because at one point before like right before and
I'm like I was trying to make some particle effects for goo and I'm
like yeah, you know, I can make a thing and I'm just like well
I'm basically just making Flash keyframing interface, but without all
the stuff flash because Flash for his terrible.
It is, as it is, it's decent in animation.
Okay.
So with Ed, he only works in Flash, okay?
And I was like, you know, why fight it?
So Kyle gabler World of Goo had told me about because I came up in a
conversation or something about how they did the art for World of Goo.
And Kyle gabler uses Flash and he's like, well, they flash has this
extendable GS FL thing.
It's like little Java files that can run in the idea and just automate
a bunch of process.
I'm like, okay, okay.
So this is actually like a scripting system that's inside.
Yeah, it's called J SF.
L, it's still around.
This is a JavaScript thing that you you, right?
So it's basically like the same as the actionscript stuff.
You write it in there?
Yeah, it's like if it's weird, you would think they would have just
made it action script but it's a weird version.
Version of java like a weird version of JavaScript JavaScript.
Yeah.
And then you can integrate that into like the Java C libraries.
So you can make like, dlls that load into the interface.
It's really crazy.
You can do it ton with.
So, so inside the flash, JavaScript, you can actually load a CDL that
yeah, external.
Yeah.
And then you can call functions to it.
You can call functions to.
Yeah.
So, so, all right.
So what I did and you can, can you pass data?
Somebody as well.
Yeah so you can actually sort of Curry.
Get get the flash information.
Yeah.
Pipe it out using this JavaScript.
Shim sort of okay sort of okay so that's this is where this is where
the craziness comes in.
So I I wanted to have well what Kyle, gabler think that is it just
basically took every symbol because in Flash everything is a symbol.
Okay.
And you know, the it just took as just separate png's and I'm like,
that's cool but you know,
No, with a lot of the meat boy stuff.
It's tiny and small.
I don't need a tiny PNG.
Okay.
I'm like, I need to make a good texture Atlas, so what I did.
So hold on a second for people don't know all of that stuff.
So what you're saying is basically in the World of Goo pipeline, what
they did is they literally took everything that the artist had made in
Flash and the output, like each frame, or whatever of every and
something like that.
Well, I don't think it was H frame because the animations themselves
are like he frame.
There's like motion tweens and everything but like the actual symbols
like
He drew a little goo ball and it needed to move.
They would export the goo ball and the animation animation.
Yes.
Everything's okay.
Yeah.
And then you want to do a texture Atlas.
I want to do a texture Atlas and Export the animations.
Because the detail that we had in the things that we had in the amount
of assets we had it was better to have, you know, 10 texture Atlas has
than 1,000 images or well.
Okay.
So you want to take all the symbols you want to pack them into?
Yeah.
A big texture.
Atlas yeah but you can look up into or something.
Yeah.
And then you want some metadata.
That tells you where everything was
Was, and that's exactly what I did.
So with.
So and you can't just like, you can't just pass that to see.
You actually have to use the JSF, I'll stuff to rearrange.
This is what I did everything, the Edward draw, it goes into the
library, I would take and the JSF Al creates a new Flash document, it
then takes everything out of the library and places it on the stage,
then it rotates and moves stuff so that they all fit into the smallest
texture possible.
Okay.
Then I have all of the positions recorded that goes into an index
file.
Boom, that's my texture Atlas.
Now I go through each one of the symbols and then I go and take all of
the animation data, like sound calls everything and I have that in a
separate file that gets piped out and then written to a file.
So in meatboy, there were am files.
That was all the animation data there ITX which was the texture.
Atlas index stuff.
Okay.
And then there was just the PNG
So, every animation, every art asset.
Is those three things?
Like all the cutscenes everything go in there.
Yeah.
So, and that was an exporter that would run in the IDE, which was
super inefficient for.
It was great for like, level stuff, but cutscenes, it would take
forever.
Because it's literally, the IDE is like, okay, put this here, put this
year export This and like the and that's running in interpreted
JavaScript.
Yeah, it's like the slowest pop.
It's the slowest possible thing doing.
The most possible work right?
Yeah, okay.
And so yeah, that's how everything like the very end cinematic would
take about 14 minutes to export which was a pain in the ass.
I feel like that's almost time to compile maybe a few of the files
from the Unreal Engine.
Yeah basically.
Yeah.
Just a few not too many.
So here's a question for you, your you said that when you when you're
putting out these, you're making your texture Atlas.
Yeah you actually sort of suggests you're jittering.
Them to get a tighter packing than if they were just rectangles.
Basically.
Yeah, I would and I would only do 90 degree because that's what you're
trying to do more than this is the 73 degree angle.
I got ya know you don't want to do that but also I don't think that
would be very efficient so did you feel was what again was that
something that you?
Why did you feel like you need to do that right?
Did you tell did you use just the standard rectangle kind of packing?
Why did you feel like you needed better packing?
This is like, I just want it or was there a time when you were like,
no?
This isn't working because we have to
SSO.
I'm a sick person and based on the drawing, based on the drawing well
that you can't prove.
That was no, we can't.
You can't prove that.
I think it was streamed.
Yeah, so when a but like the first one I did use.
Yeah.
All these little rectangles.
I'm like that's cool but there's a lot of white space and I'm like I
can definitely in my head because at my learning station job, I made a
calendar program.
Okay, that you could cut like have
Have little appointments and it would fill them in and Lego them
together and I'm like I can just do that again and make it all like
smash together and as efficient as possible.
And yeah, we didn't really need it, but it was fun to do and it worked
out.
So yeah, that was kind of why I was like okay well we definitely need
to be able to move this like 90 degree 90 degrees puzzle, Tetris them
all into this thing so that was purely just to set.
By your own OCD.
Oh, yeah, no, I supposed face is driving me nuts.
I posted pictures of it because I was super proud of it, because it
looks like it looks like it's definitely a computer, did it?
And that's what looks so cool about.
So, let's, let's jump a little bit forward in that process.
Then so after we've got all this stuff exported and we have you
noticed these sort of files that ink that encode whatever The Flash
animation.
Yeah.
Mark up for the texture.
Atlas we've got that.
So now, you know, we've got to build a game.
Yeah.
Right.
And so Flash doesn't really allow us to probably do enough stuff that
we need to do for that.
So you said, you bought the letter itself, talk about how did you guys
figure out how that piece was going to work?
Like, how did you figure out how you're going to like assemble the
game out of flash pieces?
Because there's always a bunch of things?
Like how much do we do in the the in Flash versus how much do we do in
the level editor?
Like yeah.
Was that an iterative process?
Give me a little bit of just of the overcrowding that go and was it
just we did the first thing and we just use it or did we have to
iterate?
Like how did that go?
It was actually kind of, we did the first thing in the news did.
So what?
Ben was in my thinking.
I was like Ed's going to do all the animations in Flash, everything
animation, why's everything, cutscene everything menu that's going to
be somehow in Flash and I'm going to hook all that stuff to my engine
code.
So when it came to like the level editor, I wrote The Fly.
I wrote a basic tile editor.
First, you know, click here.
Here's a tile.
Blah, blah, blah.
Okay.
At that point that's like done, you know, that's your Collision.
That's the, because the tiles themselves were just
Geez that had made and okay.
Photoshop.
That was the only thing use Photoshop for was just making the little
Arc for the tiles and then actually strictly tiles.
Are they always little square?
Yeah they're always a little swell.
There's little square little triangles and stuff.
A little tiny Square, the international, the international symbol, for
the whole triangle.
But yeah we had all those little shapes and I made the editor to just
be able to place shapes and have a collision and have basically a PNG
of meat boy, just Bop around.
Then I made the animation stuff.
The animation exporter.
And then, I spent some time making sure that integrated n because
everything was from flash.
So, like the saw is the saws were animated in Flash to spin around
because at animated him and flashed spin around.
So they might as well, spend around the same way that he animates him
in Flash and the editor.
So, everything outside of tiles and was Flash with the exception of
the editor, had a way to do, wait,
Points.
So like if you had like a missile turret, you wanted to move up here
and here he couldn't do that in Flash.
But you know, you could say here and this time be here at this time be
here and then loop back.
So that was the only like animation stuff that was in the editor,
which a lot of people with the super Meet World stuff, made some
pretty crude stuff with that, which is pretty funny.
So, what do like when you say, Collision?
Mmm, so you've got two different types of things in there.
You got the flash objects.
Yeah.
And you've got the PNG is coming fridge with our tiles.
Yeah, right.
Is that just like are you doing?
How are you doing?
Cuz there is a tiles just like a solid rectangle Collision or is it
like actually the bitmap Collision or like what did and objects?
What was the Collision there?
Like how did that stuff?
So the collision and the Flash objects I made?
I had in all of EDS libraries, I had bounding Circle and bounding
square and if he would put those in what the editor or was it the
editor?
The exporter one of them would basically Market as this is abounding
square and it's it would use the width.
Of the containing movie clip as the, you know, the diameter of the
circle or the width of the square.
So like if I okay, it would be a circle.
Actually, place the square in the circle.
He just said this is no, no, he placed them and then and then would
move them to the correct.
And then the engine would take those and be like, oh well, don't
render this and make a bounding Circle there and tie it to this.
Okay?
So and then that gave him the power to be like, oh this, you know,
this saw it's a little too big or
Something.
I'm like, well, fix it.
I don't care if you fix it, like, you shrink it, I don't need to
shrink it.
So and that that offloaded, you know, the little nitpicky work on him
because he can change it easier and faster and test it than I can
change it.
Give it to him.
Test it, you know, that we just cut out the middleman there and let
him place all of that kind of.
So he only because your meat boy is basically squares and circles,
squares, and circles for the objects and then tiles, just your basic
tile Collision
Tiles are like they're always a rectangle.
Yeah they're a rectangle or whatever the tile shape is so they're
rectangle like half rectangle or there was a because it was you have
the tile which is the image and then you have the actual model which
is either the square or the triangle and then from there then it would
it would treat it as a triangle and as we actually have the underlying
shapes.
Yeah that would then.
And so then all these things come into possession session and then
they just flow through naturally.
Yahweh and the editor is basically a thing either.
It came from Flash and was marked up there, or the editor said,
This tile is a triangle shape.
Ya, I got ya.
So, how did you deal with?
Like the, you know, I guess the binding between these things.
So you have all these flash files and that sort of stuff.
And I want to make one of these like, you know, like you said, the
sort of the spinning saw blade or yeah.
And I want to put that in there.
So what does that look like for Edmund?
You know he's doing a level or something like that, like how?
Yeah.
And what's the iteration?
Like as you said like you had to go back to flash, maybe change a
collision sizes.
Like how did, how did all that work out?
So it was a good was it was a trick, you know, know that actually
Worked out pretty well because that was a because you had, you know,
you have the forest, you have the hospital to have the Salt Factory.
Each one of those was a set of like a flash file, for our flash file,
for all the objects, flash file, for all the like set pieces that have
like, your trees, your waterfalls flash file for little animals, like
the squirrels and stuff.
So, all those would be placed in a file.
I just called a pallet and he would, it would be like, oh object is
this Diane file?
Okay, set pieces this and it kind of went down through all that.
So all he would do bird.
The am file name.
Like the file name?
Yeah.
Is it would just load that.
Yeah, it would just load that and because he would like in the editor
who would be like, all right, I want to make a forest level.
So he would load up Forest dot LP which was level palette.
He would load that up, that would take and grab his objects.
His tile sheet, his basically everything he would need for that level.
So then, like if he did have to go back and change a saw, adjuster if
you wanted to add a set-piece, he would go to like set piece the FAA,
put it in re-export, then he would just load up the levels scroll
through and there's his new thing and is that like wait so did the
files ever contain more than one placeable object at a time then?
The meaning.
Meaning like so I have these flash files and they're coming up in this
palette.
Oh, I reach into the flash file export, the exported flash file, huh?
Do I reach in there and grab out a particular element of it?
So that there's like a double binding?
There's the we have to remember.
Like okay, there's a file name that it corresponds to and like a sub
name inside.
Yeah.
How is based on an ID?
So okay.
So if he was and it was all done with mouse wheel so he would have
like a like he would go through the steps.
He would just like, scroll through those would have unique IDs, place
them and they were according to how they were layered in the FL a
file.
So, he would have to place new stuff at the top, so that.
Yeah, and that worked out well.
Like, when the index of his mess up, I he was a it's not working on
me, you place it at the top he's like, no way.
Yeah.
And then I got he would place it at the top and then re-export and it
would be fine because the level the actual level files had all the
indexes in there.
I see.
And then it would just like load the index.
Is from the animation thing, okay?
So it's straight up like a file name.
Plus a number five,
Plus a number equal better, line up Edmund.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, because he had two different, you had the animation file, which
had the IDS of the animations and you had the index file.
So if he because I made it, so he could do either a full export, which
would take forever or just a texture export.
So if he wanted to change how this tree looked, instead of exporting,
everything he could just export the texture.
But if you exported the texture and not the animation file happened to
add something that
Everything is just wrong.
This caused a lot of problems and development.
I'm not that bad.
No, no, like one or two times, I mean he's like oh because it was easy
because it was all in the flash ID form he would just literally like
it was in the drop-down for commands in Flash so he would just done
done.
Okay.
So yeah, I made it may be pretty easy on him so let's I'm all that
stuff is caveman stuff now compared to what I have.
Okay.
So
Yeah, what I made me so okay.
So so you felt like that was not that was stupid.
I hated the exporter so much.
All right.
So what did you change?
I made it just read swf files like it, renders vectored, swf files
animations reads.
All of the sounds from the swf files.
So all you have is an swf file.
So what did you do?
Like, did you?
I always things that, are you go get like a flash, I downloaded the,
The Flash, the swf file,
Spec from Adobe and I read it.
No, yes, that's what I did.
That's right.
And yeah.
And that was super fun because now I can make anything like it's so
it's so insane because it went from God, we got it spin like 14
minutes exporting this to.
Oh, well just here's the swf and it just renders and it's fine.
And it's all like,
Like, it's all Vector, so it can be any size, any, you know?
It's great.
So, I guess let me ask the question.
That's kind of interesting about interested about how you're doing the
layout before.
So, now that you've moved to an swf file, you're reading it directly
again.
How do you deal with the whole?
Like, I've got these in-game tools.
They need to reference the stuff from the swf and the artist just, you
know, output it a bunch of swf files.
How are you doing that?
Binding of you change.
The way you're doing, it is still named an index.
It's so now what it is is now instead of a level palette and
All those things.
Now, it's just the swf and inside the swf, you have Clips on the main
stage.
So you have a clip called set pieces.
You have a clip called objects, you have a clip called Parallax.
And what it does with the editor does, is it takes the swf looks for
those specific things and then just makes a big giant database and
then you have your indices to like, if this is a set piece, you know,
you you hit this movie clip and then you render this index from inside
that the Sip
Peace.
Hold on in
The set piece.
There's a drawing.
Yeah, the draw inside the set piece.
Yeah.
Also draw this guy.
And if you push down that one, you can scroll, okay?
So if you need more space.
Yeah, you do.
My draw, a dick like immediately.
So let's say we like the degree of lewd drawings that we're going to
happen on handmade here.
I guess we just get them all out, right?
You were in yours.
You weren't at my wedding, my wedding, our guest book was draw your
best dick.
And there are some amazing ones there.
You probably had a lot of good artists.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
Okay.
Ben that's going to be that's going to be like a collect.
That's gonna be the Smithsonian someday.
Yeah.
No.
I certainly hope so.
You know, collection after the bombs, drop addicted.
Yeah.
After all, the bombs dropped, and we're going through the Commonwealth
and there's like, they go into this thing and there's just this, this
in this house.
There's just picture of these two dicks kissing.
Yeah, we can rebuild Society.
Now we know what, we know what, we know what it was like before the
bombs.
All right?
Yeah.
So
You can see why I'm not an artist because that's the best Square.
I can make it's beautiful.
Yeah.
So let's say, oh boy,
Why is it?
It's no, it's that this this button.
Oh, that's me, I'm like, fat fingering it.
We got it.
We got to work on your art skills.
Many, gotta know how to use a Wacom tablet.
Okay, I didn't mean to draw a face that I did.
So let's say this is, this is that so, for obstacle, I'm still drawing
a face.
This is, this is S4 set pieces and this is P for Parallax.
Now, this is our swf
Okay, okay, that loads into the engine, through this little arrow
here.
Okay, in what Universe was that an era?
I don't know.
I can't, it's weird.
I needed to be flat.
Like hello.
We are the beings that only have lots of, so that gets that gets
loaded.
Wonderful.
Yeah, I know this is great, so that gets loaded in and basically, if
you want to think about these as these are all little databases
Okay, and each one inside of each.
What are they keyed on each end inside of each one?
If you look in the FL a that you have your layers of for people that
are familiar with flash and like this would be like a tree like the
just that but man you just can't push the button tree but let's say
you have Tree in this and that those are just like it doesn't base it
off names or anything it's literally based off where it is in the like
Drawing hierarchy in the foia file.
So if the tree is at the very top, that's like that's like the last
index.
The very bottom is 0, and this is n.
Okay?
Okay, so and this is literally just the draw order.
Meaning, what they set up as like the overlap.
Yeah.
Yeah because if you're doing, if you're doing
Flash correctly and you don't have everything all piled on one layer.
Okay, you have everything on separate layers and that, that naturally
just forms a database.
So that's kind of the structure of, let's say Parallax or whatever.
And then when the engine loads in this clip and we say Parallax you
mean the background, we had like little little background things that
you can and it doesn't matter because it's z-axis.
Okay, I know 2D people are afraid of Z axis but it's helpful.
Okay?
So
So when you, when you load those in at the engine just basically goes
through and it's just loads all of these clips because it doesn't care
and it doesn't know what's on the layers.
It just knows this is, this is I, this is child one in Parallax that
this is child to Child 3 child for.
So inside the engine, when I load in this Parallax thing I go okay
these are all my Parallax things.
This is these are there their indices.
So and actually, I don't even load the things themselves because they
load when they're only.
Needed.
So there's on-demand.
Yeah so when when the when the level of like you basically Parts like
the header of it or something, I parse?
Yeah of course everything because in the engine that's how the swf
files work is, I don't want to actively tessellate everything right
then and there, because the tessellations so quick, I can do it at
load time and nobody knows because it's just there.
So when I go through and I load these, I have like just an internal
database and when, when he scrolling through the mouse or when the
artist is scroll,
Through the mouse and they like, see a little Parallax they want and
they place it then the level.
That's a level good love.
Ya know.
It's really a girl.
Decorate.
It like that.
That's what Cliff.
There's a tree.
Yeah.
So when he clicks and places this tree right here, like that's let's,
let's just say that's that's number 0, and it also has a sub ID
because it needs to tell it that it's a lack.
So it's got a sub idealist, a parallax is 3 because I actually think
Is 3.
So now those are hard coded in the engine.
I assume like parallaxes 3.
Yeah.
Parallax is 3.
This one.
Those are by name in the swf.
So meaning the engine first looks at the swf.
Yeah engine look, here's my my obstacle layers.
My, what do you what do you say?
The S?
Was that set pieces?
Like I, let me see my set-piece clip my object clip, and my Parallax
click.
OK.
And then everything inside those clips are all the objects, all the
Parallax, all everything got it.
And so does this, this would then have the same problem.
You just need one words, if they change the order of things yet in
that folder.
So you're still going to tell Edmund.
He got to be that the top.
Yeah.
However, because it doesn't take 14 minutes, he just moves it and hits
publish and then two seconds later.
He he has so rude.
Why aren't those by name instead of by number?
Is it because the names the artist don't want to set names?
Or what was like?
Like, tell me a little bit because you you went by name for, you know,
for for this guy up here, my thinking is yeah.
But this guy down.
Not my thinking is because these are all hard-coded into the engine.
You're not going to have anything extra because these are going to be
your objects, your set-pieces your Parallax, you're special okay like
bandage girl or your Band-Aids or stuff like that.
You're only going to have these set things and these are going to be
things that I actively want to see because it's not an editor like
Unity where he can actively go.
I want to load in sunshine clip and then sunshine clip comes in and
that's a whole different thing because the levels are themselves are
structured like any level.
For any Tile game, you're going to have tiles, you're going to have
okay?
You know obstacles you can have enemies like those are all the things
you're going to have and then adding those actually to the editor is
just as easy as like, okay look for this clip, this is this clip, this
is the sub ID when you and then with the editor now you can bind a
button to mode and then be able to place whatever you want.
So it's like the thinking was these are always going to remain static.
These are always going to be
And them because they're not.
He's going to like add 10 different trees or five Ministries like him,
naming them, 30 31.
32 wouldn't do any good because I say well have to go through and like
I would actually have to know the names at that point, because I run
everything based on numbers, like little like the indexes and
everything and it makes more sense for me to just go.
Okay, here.
This, this tree, I don't care that it's a tree.
I just care that it's
Index zero for clip or clip database three well.
So I'm assuming though I'm just and sorry to belabor this because I'm
curious now cool.
So I am assuming that here, you know, we could draw a way better
squares of - I'm classically trained.
I went to square school.
I went to this, I'm sorry.
I went to the square Conservatory.
Wow, where we studied we Square studied squares.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
My hit.
My hands to shake a little bit because there's very strict teachers.
So I we could introduce here like you know, if this if this is our swf
file right we could introduce a table here that's like okay, the last
time is imported this thing like index 0 was like the tree or
something and index one was whatever and it stores the string, right?
Yeah.
And so then the next time you load it in it would look at the names
and go oh tree moved.
It's like it's down here now, but I find it and I remapped it.
But you, you don't seem interested.
Even I would say in these strings and so I
Just want to just know specifically like do you think it's just not
worth the time?
Do you think the a just don't name them anyway or?
Well, that's how does that, that's the thing.
So I never thought of it as like I want them to name because the the
Integrity of this database needs to always be consistent because it
doesn't because it's easy to fix, okay?
So, and, and with flashes being able because it's literally like out
of trees here, and it's supposed to be there, you just drag and drop
publish done, okay?
And for me to do this,
Part that introduces like a level of complexity where it's like, okay,
well now for some reason trees up here and this was Zero, but it was
this back before and it just okay.
That's really interesting.
Yeah.
So for me, it's just like, I don't care what's in here as long as I
give it to the artist and if he's like, I want to add a billion things
and if he knows to Adam at the top, he can add a billion things in
like 20 minutes and then they're just in the editor.
Whereas if he had to go through a name them and all this stuff then
it's like and then yeah artists don't name it.
At least Ed doesn't he would name stuff and it was so irritating and
Meat Boy.
He would name stuff, xxxxx xxxxx one, well, that's to the and that was
a tree but that's how you know, the difference between that and XXX
XXXX.
Yeah.
And then and then e, then it was it was an ex anymore.
It was that was the name of it and I'm like, this is useless, this is
totally useless.
So like to take like it doesn't need to have a name because it's just
it's these things and
Like when you think about the end end product, if you want to say
yeah, the in product of this level, that's always going to be a tree
until he goes into the editor and change it I guess or unless he
messes up the order here.
But is it messed up the ordering fixes super quick.
So, would one way to state that be like, you come down on the side of
look, they either have to get a bunch of names.
Yeah.
Collide with each other or they have to keep the indices in order.
I don't really think there's a bonus to this one.
So why not remove that from the prop?
Basically yeah because they're all going to be in order.
So I actually yeah I actually think it's easier to just be like the
rule be at the top at the top.
Yeah.
You know instead of name it name.
That's really fascinating.
Actually.
And it made me feel like it works.
Yeah.
I like it.
All right, so I think that's, that's pretty good for our pipeline
stuff.
Okay.
That that was actually really interesting, but I wanted to talk a
little bit about the controller stuff and so I'm just keeping an eye
on time here.
So I think I wanted to switch over to that if that's cool.
Yeah, so I want to talk about the control stuff for Super Meat, Boy, a
because it's like way far out of anything I ever do.
Like I've never worked on controller code for, you know, for an action
game or anything like that.
Yeah.
And also because you know, it's pretty universally accepted as a very
good example, of doing the controls, right?
And so I kind of wanted to get like, you know, just start off with
what was the process like for doing that, right?
Like, did you was it where the controls great from day one?
Did you iterate constantly?
Was there playtesting?
Like if
Me a little overview before I start asking questions at the actual.
So, the way, the way I approach is, I'm very bitchy OG when it comes
to controls.
I hate bad controls.
They ruin everything, okay?
It's terrible.
So before I made art Pipeline, and after I made playstyles, okay, I
worked on movement.
And the way I did that is, I knew because the flash version does not
have good controls, and I would I threw that.
I didn't look at it.
Me that out.
Okay, I knew he had to jump and while jump and that's what I that's
what I went by.
So for about three months because that was the first controller game I
made to.
I didn't do anything and hoop world for controls.
Goo was just basically a mouse game that was the first time like good,
good control.
Actually, you could use a controller and go but it was like it was
different.
You just move a thing around, you know, you're not actively.
Yeah, so what I, what I did for that.
That was I made, I made a simple tile editor, level editor thing,
where I could just Place some tiles and my little Meat Boy Square
because he was still just a square.
At that point, the little red square could just run around and like
wall jump and stuff.
And what I did for about three months is I tweaked it and the way I
tweaked it was, I would play through it and I would make specific
situations where it would be.
This is a one tile block and this is a one tile block.
I want to be able to wall jump from this.
Tile block and land on top of this block got it.
So what I, what I did and it was two prongs, so it was a lot of
iteration.
But I also made there are no physics formulas in me boy, it's called
just garbage, so it's completely hand coated, every formula.
I mean, there's gravity, right?
But there's this thing called air friction, okay?
You know, there's real friction in the air.
Yeah, but are looks like there's your stairs are turn, friction.
They haven't found all the fundamental.
That's the truth, Sarah, you do.
No.
What could this is high-level Quantum shit.
We're talking about.
Okay, so I had all these variables because like, as I was playing
through and this is how like a thing like air friction would come up,
it would be like, okay, I can jump, but I don't like how if I want to
go back this way if I'm just doing it Force base and I'm just going
like oh just add to the force just until he goes back.
I don't like that.
So I would be like well, I want like a multiplier.
If I'm going back this way in the air.
And that became air friction.
And then I made a form like in game where I could change values in
game and then test it.
So Meat Boy is a common, a like Meat.
Boy, controls are a combination of garbage formulas.
Okay, that don't make any physical sense, okay.
And garbage variables that have no bearing in reality, okay?
So it's just knobs.
So in some sense, the process was create an obstacle course.
Yes, right.
In other words, various obstacles are able to do
Yeah, well yeah.
Right.
And then sort of start with some formulas because I guess you met.
So how did you pick the initial set?
I mean, you just like because this is an iterative process.
Yeah somewhere.
Yeah.
It was a, it was just, you know, velocity, he runs jumps and then
gravity.
And then, you know, run you don't really have to change run, you just
change the speed run but it was all about like jump and air control
was the, the crazy thing.
Let's change the speed to run.
I mean it's got some acceleration.
Like Meat Boy, doesn't immediately he has I think he has to
I was like, it's insane.
Because okay.
And I remember, I actually remember that during the process.
I'm like, if there's a saw firing down at me, I need to get out of the
way.
I don't want to.
And since he's got air friction and all this crap, why can't he just
instantly coloring?
So that was, that was kind of how that went.
It was just, it was just like have some basic movement and then, like
you said, like obstacle course and everything and with that sort of
iteration it made,
Once once those controls got like perfect where I can make basically
anything I wanted and and in some way like figure out how to get up
there or over there once I could do that then was like these are the
controls that took about three months.
That's an impressively.
Like that's a I guess I say is looking at the final game.
Yeah, that's kind of interesting to hear because that to get to those
controls, you really did have to do the work.
Like it was nothing.
Like, I don't know that.
Well, I mean it was it was a lot of like dartboard.
Yeah.
In like oh cool.
Yeah because I don't know what the units for are tourney friction
right, right.
Yeah.
From for meat.
What's the meat are tearing friction?
Yeah.
So I don't know the units for that but with the interesting part of
that though, was once those controls got in place and Ed started
building levels, we found more stuff we could do through the levels of
like there's something called an S jump.
And the way the S jump works is really kind of crazy because you can
jump and do this and actually
we get slightly higher than if you were to jump and do that.
Okay but it feels correct because of how weird you control in the air.
Okay.
So you can s jump and go into these little tiny crevice things where
you couldn't possibly go over.
If you were to just wall jump out and that was all attributed to just
air control, air friction and you didn't tune for the S.
Jump the estimates, just came in, because you made all these weird
formulas.
There are certain like holes like are definitely holes but like
Optimal places in the formulas where if you just do the right thing?
Yeah I think you can get a little extra.
You can you can like you can like maneuver into these things.
Yeah.
Okay.
And that's and those those became like super special and they they are
totally wrong, but they feel super correct because of how everything
sort of flows anything there.
It's not oh coded.
So you can do an estimate because that would be a very this thing.
It's a, you know, it's more natural and because of that, it feels it
just
Feels like it is part of the controls like it was meant to be that way
and so how like what are what's an example?
And it's probably something that's hard to remember exactly what it
was.
But like so the fundamental quantities that you're tracking from frame
to frame for the control scheme, what do those look like?
Right?
Like you know, you said velocity position?
Are there more like are there things, you know and how are you looking
at the stick?
Like what's the what does the the sort of like State?
The input space?
Look, like, kind of as we're going.
As we're going through this?
Yeah.
Well trying to.
So I don't remember exactly.
We like everything that I I know, I like kept the velocity and this
jump height and everything because there was a thing where if you tap
jump, he'll jump one tile.
Even if you let go because it feels weird to jump and only do like
that, right?
It feels better to jump do like that or if you hold it jump and go
like that.
So there's some threshold and there's a jump less than this amount.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And that made it for it.
Just feels more consistent that way because your mind and your finger,
they don't always we always
He's at the same.
Yeah, same speed as far as like, looking at the controller and
everything.
Yeah.
I was just, I don't know.
Well, this drawings just got a lot better.
Well, uh, do you - like?
Yeah, keep talking.
I'll take a look at just make sure we didn't lose any plugs.
So yeah.
As far as like, looking at the controls,
And I don't even really really no I mean it was such a weird like the
way I built the controls in was a everything in the engine is
abstracted because I come from unreal town, where they abstract, they
abstract everything like to crazier degree than I do.
So like when I built the engine, I built something that could be
ported and like that's that's what it's, that's what I pried it on is
like I ported I may I pour Danny Boy in a weekend PS3 like
Okay, you know, that's in it's because of how I structured everything.
So, like with the controller, it's all, you know, it's X input for
this.
It's this video.
So you have your X input, your excellent put talks to like an input
layer, which I just recently changed, because I didn't like the name
of it because that's what you do.
Just the name.
Yeah, well, my name was, the only thing I didn't like, I didn't like
the name and I didn't like how it was set up, so I changed all of it,
but it's better now.
So that talks to like the input layer.
That is like,
Like that just basically gives you.
I have a thing in the engine where you can use like the left and right
stick as d-pads, which is the easiest thing in the world.
Because it's just, you know, if you're more this way and then this way
you're going left, if you're more this way, this way you're going up.
So it's actually digital.
Yeah, these are the controls for meat by digital.
Oh yes.
Okay so actually all of the analog Miss comes from, you know, how long
you've pushed you never?
How hard you push?
Yeah, no no no on every platform.
Okay yeah, yeah, yeah.
So what sort of quantities you track their?
So you've got you it sounds like you've got d-pad in so you've got,
you've got basically like a directional left right up down left,
right?
Yeah, and you've got the buttons.
Yeah, I got buttons.
And so at that point at that stage, I guess what?
I'm trying to ask is from frame to frame our the, you know, you've got
a bunch of sort of pseudo physics formulas that you've been working on
that you tweaked.
Yeah, yeah.
Or is there?
Carryover Beyond just some quantities, like velocity.
Position, are there other things that needed to get tracked?
Like oh, how long has he been holding down the button and we do some
stuff with.
Well, there was that.
How did you remember any interesting things about that though?
Actually yes, wouldn't be the first thing you'd think of.
Yeah, that that's actually a really good one.
And it's the best part, because it's the part nobody realizes, but
they all do it.
Okay?
And it was something I discovered during the three months of craziness
wall, jump has a 200 millisecond leeway.
Okay.
Of.
If you press, if you're on a wall and you press off the wall, it's not
going to immediately take them off the wall because in your brain when
you first play Meat Boy, you want to jump off the wall and go the
direction, okay?
But a lot of the times you'll either do Direction first, okay?
Or you'll do it at the same time, okay?
And if you do it at the same time, he detaches from the wall and then
he just falls into camera so that 200 milliseconds, makes it so
anybody can like your, it's long enough that it's like, Oh, I pushed
to the left and I jump to the
And it feels right but it's short enough that it's not like I'm trying
to get off the wall.
I can't get off the wall.
So he actually sticks to the wall, he doesn't come off the wall, but
you still allow them to jump for Toonami.
Actually sticks for 200.
Yeah, I had a thing like that and I hated it because it felt weird and
it was just bug prone.
So I'm just like, well, just stick for just a tiny amount of time.
Okay.
So if you start pushing Off the Wall there's actually like a counter.
Yeah.
It's going to start incrementing at that point or decrementing or
however you did in there.
Yeah something's going to count up 200 milliseconds over the frames.
Yeah.
And if you let go, you know, at some point there, he'll just do the
standard falling or whatever, but if you push the button during that
time table.
Yeah.
And then he jumps up, was there anything else like that?
Like how about Edge roll off?
Like as I'm going towards an edge and I'm going to do a jump, do you
get some time after or exactly never never been a fan of that.
Okay.
And and no meat boy, doesn't have that.
I had that in a prototype.
I was making for a different type of game and I didn't find it all
that useful.
Oh really?
Like
I don't know, I don't know if that's in other games, but I always felt
like in meatboy maybe it maybe it has to do more with the game because
even though there are, you know there's this Gap right here and you in
order to make the jump you have to literally jump in here.
But those situations in the game aren't that common?
Because it's not like a life-or-death thing.
You can jump and then maybe hit the wall and jump off.
So you can like compensate for yourself.
So maybe that's why I never.
It just wasn't designed to make.
Right at the edge jumping.
The.
Yeah.
Anything.
So it wasn't like a Mega Man thing where you have to pixels and either
you make it or you doubt.
And because in that thing and that's, you know, with with Mega Man,
you would jump and you would hit this wall.
But in meatboy, you hit the wall and then you can just jump off and
let's jump and go right back on top.
So I think that's that's why I didn't actually use anything like that
in there because it just seemed unnecessary.
So at the end of this three months, you've got, you've got the wall
sticking.
I'm assuming that's part of the three months process.
Was the Second Waltz.
That you've got the fake physics formulas reference physics.
Yeah reference model ref tone.
Ian Wright.
Yes tripodi in the dynamic.
Yeah so we got rough Tony and Dynamics in there.
How much do those change over?
The course of the game?
Did you literally stay with what exactly as it was in the three months
or was there tuning that happened after as you know, get through the
game more.
Well, they stayed that way the entire exactly.
So and there's basically exactly the same as the end of the three
months.
Yeah.
The the controls, at the end of the
Three months for the same as the ones that were in the final game.
And the reason is because at the end of the three months, had started
making levels and when he started making levels, like the the thing
that makes Meat Boy.
Great is the controls compliment, the level design, level design,
complements the controls.
Okay, so if the level design was terrible and the controls were good,
the game would still be terrible if the level design was amazing and
the controls was terrible.
The game would be terrible.
Okay?
But because Ed worked in the limitations of those controls, he made
levels
Complimented those controls, okay.
And that's why they never change because to change them would mean to
effective changes all the other levels because okay.
So basically part of the philosophy for the game almost was that like
we kind of have to fix these controls at this because everything we
design from here on is going to be based on exactly what this is, not
just sort of what this.
Yeah.
And that's when I was when I was doing the control stuff, I'm like,
well if we have to change these, this is going to suck because it's
just totally get because in the goo game beforehand.
And I had to change controls all the time because you're controlling.
That's what Google was.
It was just controlling these big Globs of stuff and you tried to
envelop other Globs of stuff and that is a control scheme on a
controller is terrible.
So a lot of the time I had to try to redesign controls and every time
I did I'm like, yeah, this is a little better but I don't like it.
So when meat boy I'm like, well, this is pretty cut and dry.
He has to wall jump, he has to jump.
Yes, to run these need to be right first and then we can build on
that.
And then,
As long as the levels are good, the controls will remain good.
So just want to ask, I think we've got time and I want to make sure
I'm not ready.
Okay, we've got we got a few more minutes.
Okay, so one, one final question on the controls is, so the controls
you said we're digital.
Why not analog?
Why not?
I didn't like the way it felt so, you did try.
Yeah, I had a thing where, well, it didn't make much sense for the
game because meet boys like he's either
Well, I mean you have the Run button but that was the point.
You have the Run button, you're usually always running, you're only
going these two speeds.
There's only like a few places where you have to walk you know there's
like I think one level in Cotton alley where you absolutely.
Okay.
Watch every other time you can run.
So I lost my train of thought again.
What did you try analog or digital?
That's Reggie.
Why did you decide digital was the because it's option or the, the
analog because I never
I never took and played the game in a way where I was thinking, oh, I
want to be able to lightly move like I want to be able to, I want to
have this range of speeds.
Like it was always either want to walk our own around and that's okay.
10 you know so like and and when I had like this I had a sort of thing
where like he would accelerate and he would you could adjust the the
control to make him like move a little bit faster.
A little bit slower than his top speed and it felt
Weird.
Okay.
And it didn't work in the are either because that also felt it felt
strange to have something that needed to be fast.
Paced to actually have this sort of artificial ramp up for no reason.
So in some sense you would say that the sort of the feel of Meat Boy.
Well supposed to be instant on instant off its that that's like I'm
firing the Thruster or I'm not you and I we it's not about like
getting this subtle sort of like I just get a little more lunar,
lander e?
Or yeah.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's all about just stop and go.
But it was something that you played around with at some point.
Yeah, very early, I think, I think I scrapped in the first week.
I'm like, yeah, three months.
One week was an like, are like, no one week was like, like this?
This isn't any good.
So, all right, so we got a few minutes left, just a few minutes left.
So I guess I'll close by saying, what do you have anything you want to
tell us about what you're doing these days?
Not necessarily not necessarily game stuff since that's probably Under
Wraps but like you for example told us that you rewrote how you were.
All your imported stuff, like any programming stuff.
I wouldn't know about because I don't know what you're working on.
You at that.
You might want to talk about or just mentioned based on sort of what
we've talked about so far.
So I am making a testing tool because that's the jewel.
Yeah, I had a terrible experience when Meat Boy launched on PC.
Okay.
And I wanted to make sure I never had that again.
So I'm making like this weird crowdsource testing to really thing.
I've been working on it for a while, I have it.
So tell me about so the meatball experience on PC.
It was just that so many platforms and graphic artist and kind of
testing strips or tell me a little bit about what you mean the.
So when we were doing meatboy Meat Boy was going to be we and xBox
wasn't going to be PC, okay?
Because the whole time I'm thinking like a PC and not not in the but
in the that's a lot of that's a huge range of like, oh yes this
graphics card this graphics card this you know, I oh man when when it
came out on Steam there was this off
Them bug, that sometimes it would just Flickr for people, I'd be like,
oh, you need these think they put on v singing, though.
It was a program called Lux, that would adjust the gamma thing, and it
would make him stutter.
And I'm like, what did you do?
Why just how okay, I know the program talking about like adjust the
screen settings to your outside like, yeah, mister something.
We ask something weird like that.
And it happened to like five or six people and I was like, Gamers,
never
Outside.
Why would they need utility this?
What is this utility running on their machines for it's ridiculous.
Yeah.
So I was just check for that app at startup and don't ya you don't
deserve to play you are sir.
Yeah yeah.
So when it so it was just going to be on Xbox and we because
everybody's Xbox the same, everybody's weeds the same and I'm one
dude.
And I'm like I don't want to deal with all this stuff but around that
time steam was also like when we first started Meat Boy starting team
was like are going to come on cool.
So Surf and I was like that's neat and then nothing else but then
around mid-2010 they're like oh hey we're awesome and we're better
than everybody else.
So it's so after like around July of 2010, we're like our, it has to
come out on PC.
So so it came out on Xbox and then a month later comes out on Steam
and I bought like a whole bunch of computers and I tested it.
I'm like, okay, this is about the specs and then it comes out.
And steaming it breaks for everybody, like, how did this happen?
And it was, and it was three, three or four days.
No, it was three days and I issued 18, patches, and three days and all
for system-config.
Yeah, yeah.
All for these like little things and it was it was stupid stuff
because, like, it was, it was whenever you have problems like that.
It's always assumption.
It's always, oh, this is definitely going to do this.
And on consoles, you can assume
Umm, all kinds of stuff, right?
But on PCS, you can't assume it's because the one you tested on is
roughly the same as the one that's my ship on.
So, although yesterday that gets less true over time, they're like,
yeah, the dashboard might have a Fritos integration for you that you
do you want to buy them out of the three in the middle of this jump?
Yeah.
But yes, for the most part, you can kind of count on them to be like
this Hardware is the same as the hardware.
Yeah.
For the most part, or whatever.
And, and in my own experience in my ignorance, I was like, well, I
can, I can assume that this, the graphics cards definitely like
everybody's
Be able to run this every isn't real, right?
And no so after that happened, I'm like this could have easily been
prevented because I've also found throughout the years that fans are
the people that want to test the most and will generally be the best
testers, like, we hired.
And we paid out, I think through Microsoft, I think we paid out, like,
50 grand for testing for Xbox.
And it was required by the elements, whatever, but they miss stuff, it
was because they were just paid to do it.
Yeah.
Yeah, like there were some definite fans and I've met some testers
that actually did test Meat Boy that were like super fans but in at
the end of the day, they go home at 5:00.
You know, they come in at 8:00, they go home at 5 and they, you know,
they test all day and they can miss stuff, and they did tend to miss a
lot of stuff and we didn't actually have any testers for the PC
version which would have helped do some of the stuff.
So, my thinking was there's a bunch of fans.
I can make something that I can just send out builds to people and
they can test it.
And then I can get all their information and I can issue stuff to
specific people if they have problems.
So it sounds awesome.
Yeah.
And I've integrated that into because I rewrote Super Meat World
because I want it on PlayStation and Vita.
That was the little level portal thing that again.
I'm dumb and I'm naive, I don't know if it's dumb.
It's naive.
Everyone's got to learn some.
I mean exactly what ship something you can't.
No.
Oh, yeah, we're gonna go.
So, what I did is I made this Meet World level portals
Thing and I just had it hooked to a mySQL database because I'm like
it's free.
Nobody's going to fuck with it, right?
And what happens?
Christmas Eve they like they take it and they fill it in with dumb
developer.
I'm like, yeah, I'm dumb.
I am dumb to not trust the internet, not to be assholes so so that
like know what the internet's for.
Yeah.
It is, it's like a search engine the dude, one of the dude even like
he mailed me beforehand and I'm like, just don't mess with it.
Please just don't mess with like an asshole.
So anyway, I couldn't fix it because I was at my parents house for
Christmas.
I didn't have a phone, I gonna do.
So, when I got like I was able to like, log into telnet on my like or
SSH into the server through my dad's computer and like lock down the
database so nobody can write to it and restore a backup.
But it was like, it was so traumatizing because I'm, like, I hate
this.
I and it upset me like I can imagine.
Oh man, I was because
That's very personal thing when you ship a product especially when
you're like one or two people who make it.
It's not.
Yeah, that's like a big fan.
I have credit card numbers or anything.
You're not.
I mean you taught me a lesson but that's a lesson.
You could have taught me without fucking up my Christmas.
Yeah, so Merry Christmas Merry Christmas.
So yeah, that was that was like terrible and I had 7500 levels and 300
custom chapters in it.
Like and it was, it was up for about 10 months before somebody like
So that but yeah.
So anyway I Rewritten that because I wanted my everything and I've
integrated it into the new Meat Boy code.
So it's actually in little beta testers right now and they're like,
it's getting all the data name like Rama Nike Rama.
Yeah, what does that mean?
Kyle Pulver, gave it to me.
It's some lovecraftian zombify in essence and it just sounds awesome.
So because originally, I thought it was going to be like a seti at
home kind.
And of thing.
Okay, well I could just anonymously like that and I'm like, wait a
minute.
This might be Skynet eventually.
So let's not do that.
Everyone's got to avoid.
Making the Terminator.
Yeah, but they're gonna survive, but the names.
Cool.
So I kept the name.
Well I think we're just about out of time.
Cool, thank you so much for talking with me.
It's yeah this is fun and I'm sure everyone out there.
Pretty yeah.