Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could have complete game live on stream yesterday.
We actually did all the work necessary to make a rotating camera, but
we didn't have a chance to actually put in the final piece of the
implementation, which is that, we need to have some way of sort of
passing that information into the system, the render system and we
don't really have that yet.
So we need to kind of go in there and just make a little conduit so
that we
Have a good way for code.
That wants to control the cameras orientation to be able to do so,
whoo, as I spill things.
All over the place.
Sorry about that.
This is why it's very bad for.
Those of you who are wondering, it's always very bad to forget your
water bottle because my water bottle has that nice seal on top of it.
That doesn't let me spell things.
Sorry about that.
No components ruined as far as I know.
But I guess we'll find out.
All right, so that's really all we're trying to do today as we just
want to put that rotating camera in.
And again the reason for the rotating camera is not so much for any
particular game design reason we don't necessarily think that we're
going to have to rotate the camera in the game at all, but I do want
to be able to rotate the camera for debugging purposes.
Because as we basically next weekend, will pretty much be all this as
we move all of the code that uses the renderer now that the render
understands 3D.
As we move all the
Would that was previously just sending on 2D Sprites to be able to
start sending down information about three-dimensional Sprites.
We're going to want to be able to see where we're messing things up
because it's easy to have a bug in 3D that doesn't look like a bug in
2D necessarily.
Well it will look like a bug but you won't be able to tell what the
bug is because all you can see is the 2D projection of it and being
able to rotate around is very important because it allows you to see
more information and you'll spend time less time to bugging if you
have better information.
Formation.
That's just generally the way it goes.
The more you can visualize the less time you'll have to debug.
So let's go ahead and remind ourselves where we are.
Right now, we're running.
We look the same as we normally do again.
Sorting is disabled right now.
So we get the flashing but otherwise everything is in the right place
and that is with the 3D transform going through opengl now, rather
than going through our code, which it used to, before we started this
changeover and then if we go into render group, there's a part where
we do set
Transform.
You can see it here where we pass in the information like whether or
not it's supposed to be with the graphic with the focal length was and
what the camera p is and what you can see about this function is
really, this is where we would like to start putting that information.
Where we've got sort of the push cliprect and the camera transform,
our sort of separate things and really what we're doing here, very
much.
So is we're collapsing these things down.
Now as you remember from yesterday, we made it so that you could pass
an entire Matrix down with the clip rect.
So really the clip, rect is actually really the camera in a sense
right now, it not only encapsulate what render Target you're
targeting.
What the rectangle is that were clipping to but it also
So encapsulate, see how the all of the information that's going down.
It's going to get transformed.
So we don't have to rename this right now.
I mean we know that but this is definitely something.
Where we want to rename it to something other than cliprect, because
it's doing a lot more work than that.
Now, it's sort of like the render setup and it's going to be something
that if it was called cliprect all the time.
If someone was trying to read this code later might skip over it,
thinking it only had to do with clipping, but actually now it's a lot
more than that.
So you can see here, we've got the full 4x4 projection.
And remember because that's a 4 by 4 Matrix, not only can it do the
actual projection but it can actually do everything necessary to put
things into camera space as well because it's a complete transform.
So that's pretty nice.
And what that means is that with our render entry cliprect, we should
now be able to make it so that push cliff brecht and set camera.
Transform are basically the same thing and really, they're just
accessing different parts of that piece of information.
So that's kind of what I want to get us to here.
And so, what I'm going to do is
Going to go up to push clip rect and I'm going to try to pull that
information down or rather push this information up.
Might be a better way to say it so that we have a more coherent way of
working with this.
So I'm going to slide begin render group and render group down,
because those are kind of Primal and those have to set up an initial
camera transform which is just whatever it is.
If you don't set anything unclear, whether we really want that, you
know, we could make it so that you're always supposed to actually set
something but for the time being we'll leave it that way.
Going to grab these push clip Rex out of here so that we can see them
all at the same time.
And I'm going to come down to the rendering code here and I'm just
going to put them all in this one place.
So we can take a look at them.
I'm also going to switch to the other window.
So it my head's not in the way while we're looking at there.
Alright, so you can see what's going on here.
We've got a couple different things that are happening.
Basically, we've got to push clip recalls, that do nothing.
Other than prep for the other.
Push, rip rekt call like this, is the push cliprect call here that
actually does the work.
These two are just ways of specifying, the cliprect in some other way.
And so this one is just a light way of saying, Hey I want to pass a
rectangle to with the Z coordinate.
This one is saying, alright I've got a full 3d offset and then a
dimension and object transform and I want to transfer over the object
transform, right?
And then finally, you get to this one which is actually the one that
does the work and that's just taking integer coordinates.
What the render Target isn't, what the focal length is and you can see
that playing out here, right?
Okay.
So, what we want to do now is we want to take a look.
And how people are using these because we're going to have to
fundamentally change that a little bit.
I think because what we want to be able to do is when we push a new
clip, rect on, we may want it to be in reference to an old clip rect
and we may want to copy stuff out of it.
And here's why I say that because there's two ways that people might
want to be using this function, one way that people might want to be
using this function, is just to create a new clipping wrecked or
adjust to create a new camera transform and they may not be trying to
change.
Clipping rectangle or the camera transform.
So we kind of want a way of storing.
What the last camera or the last clip.
Rect was so that when people want to just modify one or the other,
they don't have to necessarily remember what the other one was.
Right.
So that's kind of one thing that that I'd like to be able to do here
and so we need to start making it more aware of that in general.
That's got to have to be something that we're taking a little more
seriously.
Furthermore we're probably going to pull out this projection creation
call and we'll probably make it so that both perspective and
orthographic we can stop probably looking at these all together, the
false true, you know, dichotomy where we're passing those down and all
that sort of stuff.
And just make a matrix because we can do an orthographic projection
with a matrix.
Just like we can do a perspective, projection of the Matrix.
So this will really unify a lot of our code and make it so that we
don't have as much special casing which is really nice as well, right?
It's just kind of cleaning everything up and again the more we sort of
push towards a standard 3D pipeline the more it cleans things up
because the 3D Pipeline and something that's been refined for
Generations.
Now by people who have been trying to make it more and more consistent
cleaner, and whatever, so typically, the 3D pipeline tends to be a
very clean way to do things primarily just
People have spent so much time getting it, right?
You know, if we had not had the whole history of 3D transforms behind
us, we probably wouldn't have thought of using a 4 by 4 Matrix with a
homogeneous coordinates to do you know there's all this stuff that we
Nest wouldn't necessarily just thought of the first time out, right?
So we're really leaning on past design in a sense here because there's
a living, a lot of people who've worked out a lot of good ideas there
and we're just being able to use them.
So that is a nice aspect of the 3D pipeline.
It was never really tore true of a the 2D pipeline.
2D pipelines were always just a lot more ad hoc
and so that there is that anyway,
So I'm going to go ahead and take a look at push cliprect here.
I'm a look at where it happens.
So these are all inside render group.
So if you look the only there's really only two places we do it.
There's the push cliprect here.
And then we've got push clip rect here.
In the debug code.
And again here.
And if I look at this, you can see that really, these are just
orthographic push clip for X right there.
Just trying to restrict to a part of the screen.
That's you know what they expect.
So the only non orthographic one is here, you can see it where it's
trying to specify a new Alpha floor rekt.
It's not actually doing anything with the
Will clipping, right?
So really, this is more of just setting the render.
Target is all this is and so again you can kind of see that each of
these is really doing its own thing.
These are really pushed up Rex.
This is really pushed render Target, and so, that's why I say, you
know, we kind of want to start to disaggregate those.
Because again, now we're also going to have the people who call
perspective and orthographic.
They're also pushing clip rex on, but they're pushing them on for the
purposes.
Of camera, transform.
All right, so what we can see here is this push to practice just to
push render Target and so I think what I'd like to do is actually just
make it be that explicitly and not have it set the clip, rect at all.
So this is more of a push render Target.
And here we have the, the render Group which we need.
None of this stuff.
Would we actually need?
We would only need the alpha floor render Target.
And furthermore, if we were to do that compilation step, I don't know
that we would now need like, for example, the draw buffer, it may be
that that was the only reason.
Yeah.
And you can see that again this is just a nice way to start pulling
out some of that code complexity that just shouldn't have been there.
And I think I mentioned this back when we were doing
As well.
I'd started try and clean some of those out and you can see that if we
just get rid of that, the only reason that we ever even had to pass
this into this routine, the only reason update and render entities was
aware of the draw buffer at all.
Was just because, when it was pushing the render Target down, it
needed to know that, right?
But it never really cared what the cliprect was as far as it was
concerned.
You could have just inherited the cliprect from whoever set it up
beforehand and it was just forced to know what it was because it had
to pass.
Us that down in addition to the render Target, which is what it was
actually trying to set.
So I'd like to again.
That's why I'm trying to move to that sort of system that way when we
call update and render entities, here we can get rid of the drop
buffer, the drawbar for doesn't have to be there anymore.
And if we take a look back that that again that that change has a
positive Cascade effect all the way back because you can look at
simulate.
Now simulate doesn't need to take the draw buffer anymore so that's
nice right?
And so yet it's just one more piece of complexity that that nicely
Falls away and that's really nice.
So if we want to add that in here so that's another aspect of this
sausage.
Gentlemen, where it's going to be.
Let's see here.
That's a u-32 that's going to get back.
Where it doesn't push render Target and there we go.
Don't actually know what the render Target in.
This is, you 32,
So there we've got to push render Target.
This is not implemented yet, so we're going to have to do something
about that in a moment, but that's our push render Target call.
If I can pile here.
We're in good shape.
And so then let's take a look at some of these other ones.
So, in push cliprect, now what I'd like to do is in these other
functions where we're passing it, I'd like to get rid of the render
Target because the render Target is now no longer relevant all,
similarly, the focal length, and those sorts of things, shouldn't
really be relevant.
So I'm just going to temporarily remove those, right?
We're going to say, you know, let's pretend we had that as well, kind
of a thing.
And similarly, you know, here we would get rid of that.
To because we wouldn't be passing it to function doesn't need it.
So that this way, these would go back to being actual push clip.
Rect and this would be something more like push camera or something
like this are pushed render setup.
I don't really know what what we want to call that.
I don't know that there's a really good name for that bundle which is
the cliprect the render Target and
And the camera transform, but I guess I'll call it.
Push set up for now.
So when we do a push set up, what I want to do is have this take, I
guess everything.
So it would take the clip rectangle that you're going to use it, take
the render Target index, it would also then need the Matrix that we're
going to use.
So this would be the projection Matrix and it would just copy that in
there.
So,
Stuff here, where we're creating this projection, where we have the
safe ratio in the focal length, and that sort of stuff that stuff
wants to come out.
And that would be going into these camera transforms.
More explicitly here.
We'll deal with that in a second but then in here where we're doing
the wrecked, what we want to do is we want to go ahead and just
capture that projection Matrix, whatever we are being given and leave
it at that, right?
So now in the push setup, call the primary thing that we need to be
able to do is get that information as we go.
And I'm not sure exactly how we want to do that.
We might think about that a little bit.
We do have this concept of the camera transform.
You can see the camera transformed here, where it's got orthographic
focal length, camera p.
And I think, really what we want to do there with that camera transfer
and potentially is the camera transfer met just now want to be a 4 by
4, right?
We may not really want camera transform to be an actual thing that
people think about anymore.
I'm not sure but that's probably the case.
So what we would be storing for now,
Is like last projection or something like this, right?
And we'd have last render Target.
And the reason that I have that is just because I'm going to use it as
sort of an accumulation as a holdover, like a rolling sort of
situation where we just say, hey, every time you set, one of these
will just keep that as the current one.
So that if you set something else, it's just assumed to have a little
state in there and you don't always want to do stuff like that because
sometimes you can forget or it gets kind of hairy what's what?
And when but in this particular case, I just would rather do it that
way for now.
Because typically the way that our render stuff is set up as we set a
state and we do a bunch of stuff with it.
It just turns out to be a nice way to compress the amount of
information that you're sending down.
Alright, so here's the render Target index.
I want to say last render Target.
Like so and cure this would just be last projection.
And that way when we're doing that, you know, off it goes when we
whenever we call one of these push set up calls again, since I don't
anticipate this being called frequently, I'm not super concerned about
the efficiency here which is why I'm okay copying giant matrices
around.
If I was concerned about the efficiency, I might want to be a little
bit more careful here if I thought we were going to be pushing setups
a lot.
And so it is worth noting that that is just, you know, it's something
to be aware of if that makes sense.
So, what I want to do here is to say, all right, the render Target
index.
I want to snap that out to the last render Target.
And similarly, the last projection.
I want to snap that and I'm also going to want to snap the rectangle
to here.
So I want to do last clip x equals X.
This sort of thing.
And that's about it, right?
so given that then when other people do transforms,
they don't have to do anything like looking at the screen dim or pixel
height or any of this stuff, they can just use whatever the last clip.
Rect was, right?
So if you want to push a clip, rect you can push a clip, rect and then
you can also set the camera transform, if that's what you want.
But you can also just set the camera transform.
If all you're trying to do is set the camera transform, you can do
that as well, and you don't have to worry about it, right?
So similarly, on here, you know, I can say, current cliprect index, I
can do a push cliprect, what I want to do the render Target, and when
I
all that I can just say like okay the render group last Quebec's
Let's Go.
Fly w.
That's the page and then I don't have to deal with any of that.
And I can say the projection Matrix is whatever the last projection
Matrix was.
So the only thing I'm really doing here is passing down that render
Target Index, right?
That's the only thing I actually want to do.
What are you complaining about?
I was that actually passing.
Okay, well, that's something we can.
We can deal with this and we can deal with that in a moment.
It's too much stuff here.
All right.
So that needs a semicolon.
And okay.
Here we go.
So let's see, push set up that all looks fine to me.
Push cliprect pushes the clip rect as we want it to, and that's all
good and set camera transform.
So, let's take a look at these two routines now.
So set camera, transfer band push render Target.
Push render.
Target is basically done now.
Set camera Transformers.
Not so, set camera, transform.
I'm going to stop that from you from doing anything with the screen
dimensions since
doesn't actually need to do that for any particular reason at the
moment, so we can get rid of those
And it really just needs to take a look at these.
For doing those aspect ratio correction.
So here's that creation of the projection Matrix here, we are setting
information about the camera and what we really now don't need to do
is remember this stuff specifically, right.
So basically, like we don't need that.
We just pass in the focal length and use it is all.
We are really doing here when we're saying whether or not it's
supposed to be orthographic or not.
That's just going to be an
Operation that has to do with.
How we're going to create our projection Matrix.
So I can do an orthographic instead and I can still pass down that
same ratio that were using for aspect ratio correction because we're
going to want to do that.
And then we can make a routine that will create an orthographic
projection and use that.
Looks like we're doing that way.
Okay so we've got orthographic and that's all good.
We've got projection and that's good but now we have to deal with the
part.
That's actually the thing that we wanted anyway.
Which is that when we do a set camera transform here, rather than just
having a camera P.
We've now got this way like we saw in the math routines, we've got
this way of creating a camera
Throw him out of axes and a location.
What I'd rather do is just say, what's the actual camera transform?
Right.
Just tell me what the camera transform is the whole thing rotation and
position.
Instead of just giving me position, then when I come through here and
create the projection Matrix, what I can do is I can take the camera
transform and say, hey, apply the camera, transform first to the
points, right?
And then apply the projection Matrix for the orthographic Matrix,
right?
Right.
And so perhaps more properly we could do it this way and say we have a
name for y, for which is r.
Our projection only, right?
And our projection only
Get set to one or the other.
And then I just take whichever one, we actually picked.
There we go, whichever one we actually picked and then I multiply it
by the camera transform.
And again, remember transforms because of the way, the math reads out
and we did ours in math.
Order is the rightmost, transform occurs first, which is what we want.
We want to put everything into the space of the camera first.
And then we want to apply the
And not the other way around, for obvious reasons because the
projection would be totally wrong.
If we were applying it before moving the world to be centered around
the camera.
So that's really it for what we wanted to do.
Now, we just have to actually push the clip rect on so here's that
push clipped call and basically what we're doing here is again passing
all old information except for one thing which in this case.
Case is going to be our projection.
There we go.
So that's all well and good.
But now we have to clean up sort of the fact that we push this to the
outside the code that's calling us is going to.
Now have to be aware of that and do the right thing.
So now we can see when we
All get render entity basis p.
One of the interesting things about this is now we actually have in
this get render entity basis P.
All of this code is kind of now not necessary, right?
Like this code is actually sort of meaningless for us.
So when we call get render entity basis P, we're just doing a
transform on P and most of this stuff just simply isn't necessary.
All of the stuff is happening in the projection Matrix.
We certainly don't need to do really any of, yeah, pretty much.
None of this stuff is really all that necessary.
And so a lot of this, this this function may actually go away entirely
pretty soon.
I'm going to leave it on there.
You can see the camera transform.
Coming in here.
And that camera transform.
Now, you can see that it's just using the position out of it, the X
and Y, and the Z, and we don't want any of that anymore, right?
We don't want any of that anymore because we're already accounting for
that inside.
Our regular transform.
So we don't need any of that and really just don't need to do it,
right?
So we want to go ahead and take all of this stuff out and start to
collapse this function down even more.
Probably get rid of it eventually.
Early right.
So it looks like that now does not actually need any of this
information when we look at the orthographic thing, we're going to
have to again have that be a little bit more clear, but that's going
to happen almost entirely in the matrices anyway, so we should be good
there.
And so here we now no longer have to pass any of that.
We don't need to access what the camera transform was because that's
not relevant anymore, okay?
All right, so then when we get to things like gun, projection on
projection is going to be a little bit trickier for us.
Now, the reason that it's a little bit trickier for us is because we
have a actual projection Matrix that were using, right?
And because we're using an actual projection Matrix, with that means
is we need the ability to invert our projection Matrix, right?
We need the some way of being able to undo the effects of the
projection Matrix when we want to
On Project, right?
So this part is still going to be roughly the same, right?
This part where we do our unprojected in terms of correcting for
aspect ratio and that sort of stuff we're still mostly going to be
doing that.
Although not exactly right because of the order of the operations.
So I guess I would probably say let's push this on to the
Let's push this on because this is kind of going to be a topic in and
of itself.
So, what I'd rather do here is just say, alright, let's just patch
this temporarily to not be a problem, but then afterwards, we will
have to do the real work there.
So all I've done is just remove it.
This is not correct anymore, right?
It's just it's completely wrong but that's okay.
And let's go ahead and
that one there as well.
Who knows?
All right.
So here we are in push clip rect.
And at this point again, we shouldn't have to pass that down.
Presumably that can just be used straight and what is the problem
here?
Ah we need to pass that as an address, that's all good.
We don't have orthographic yet as a thing to make but that's okay for
the time being push cliprect.
In this case, we need to pass
The address of the Matrix again, that's going to be true down here as
well.
And seven arguments.
It's per set up.
That's why
I renamed it.
All right, so set camera transform in both cases.
Now is not really, I don't even know that we really need that because
now you just pass the camera, transform directly.
And, you know, you don't even need to pass the ortho or not.
Now that I think about it in some sense.
Well, I guess you still sort of do.
I mean, what we could do is have this past the entire thing, but I
guess I'll leave it this way for now.
For now, we'll see.
So when we call orthographic or perspective really, those could just
be calling the other function now because they don't really need to do
anything.
They really want to create a whole camera transform.
Probably.
So what I would say is what is get rid of those, let those error out
higher up the chain and deal with it.
There, we do need to have that ability to do
A.
Tonight, an orthographic projection.
So we will have to make that happen but for now we can ignore that
temporarily.
So here's our push set up call.
So when we're doing and push that up in the case, where we are trying
to set, sort of a default case, we can also pass an identity Matrix
here.
Which does no transform for the camera, which is presumably what we
would want at initial setup.
And it looks like I missed an argument there.
All right, really, starting to not like the fact that my head is in
their way.
Let's see, so we've got group 00.
That's X Y, width and height.
We've got the render Target and we don't need the focal length
anymore.
Obviously, because that's rolled into the camera projection, which
we're saying is nothing right now at.
All right.
Yeah.
And no one should really ever be using this anyway.
So, in theory, I don't know.
Maybe the right thing to do is actually to push something that doesn't
render anything.
I don't know.
Because everyone's supposed to set up a camera, even the orthographic
stuff before it's used.
All right, so in update and render entities, here it is trying to get
the camera P out of the camera transform.
I'm not sure what that's being used for, looks like that's just so
that's a hack already.
Actually can see that being a hack right there.
And that's just again for that fog that Alpha and fog sort of split up
if that makes sense.
And again, I don't think we really want any of that anymore.
In fact,
All of this can go because now that we're passing actual 3D stuff down
to the renderer, the renderer can just split things in half at as at a
particular Z and make that Alpha in.
So yeah, this is this is all pretty much not necessary anymore and we
want to get rid of it all basically it's unfortunate that this is such
a big change because of course, it means our debugging time is going
to go up but that's okay.
At least.
It makes things cleaner.
So if you take a look at all this stuff and typical fluoride all that
stuff, we don't really need any of that anymore, that that can all go.
So what we can do is we can just delete all of this stuff and we can,
I mean, we can literally just get rid of all this stuff.
It none of this is even remotely necessary anymore because since we
have Z in the back end, all we have to do now is just look at the Z in
the back end and color what we want and clip what we want, based on
that Z.
And so that's not going to be particularly
particularly difficult.
And again, it just cleans up a lot of stuff.
This is why I like the 3D pipeline better, but, you know,
Times.
It's important to kind of go through an exercise like we did with the
2D pipeline to see how hard is it to do this way versus, you know,
doing it, the standard 3D way and now I know.
So anyway, inside the render group if here, this is just getting
different clip, Rex for these guys, which we don't really need at the
moment.
Again, the render Target.
I think stuff can actually just be done can be handled inside the
renderer entirely.
So all of that
Stuff is probably fine and absolute Z layer.
I think all that stuff is just not necessary.
Let me go ahead and see where that actually gets used again.
I don't think, let's see, camera relative ground Z.
So getting the ground point is going to be something that we probably
would need to know I guess.
That really shouldn't be something that was done here.
I think this should just go away as well.
So I think the particle systems they were actually having to use this
information, which again is just really ugly.
So, that's great, that that goes away.
And in fact, the chunk can also go away.
I think, let's take a look at that.
So when this gets a bitmap push on the transform, it needed the chunk.
See in the floor, Z that's gone.
Out, right?
So those don't need to be there anymore and that's that's pretty
pretty good, I think.
All right, so let's see if we don't need those anymore, that's pretty
fantastic.
So, we can get rid of all those and just not need them anymore.
And inside, those transforms fact, I'll just get rid of those here.
We don't need the Sorting or the floor Z or the chunk Z anymore.
So, let's get rid of that.
And we'll get rid of this.
And that.
and I don't know that entities Z layer is something that even needs to
be there anymore either, but
I think that's just not necessary.
Yeah, that's just not necessary.
It's not using simulation, that was only a rendering step so this is
all fine.
And while we're in here, right?
We don't need sort Barry erring or any of that.
We don't need the layer index.
Yeah, we don't need any of this because this will all be just
transformed.
This will all be stuff.
That's color.
Fits all colored based on
where you are in actual Z.
So then we can safely Nerf that for now.
In fact, even the color stuff we can therefore now because again
that's just not a place, we really want to put that anymore.
Now that we have so many other options
and none of this stuff is necessary.
All right.
So, that's all good.
Let's see what else we got.
Here of stuff that I need to clip out.
So this is transform floor, Z doesn't need to happen anymore.
And with the graphic.
Junk Z.
We're going to have to do some stuff here.
We're going to have to figure out some ways that we want to have the
orthographic stuff work for the debug system, but we'll get to that
when we sort of re flesh that out.
There we go.
Okay, so this is still the same.
It just doesn't need to take the render Target anymore.
And similarly, I don't know if that render Target is even necessary
anymore, because I think the only reason it was there with just for
that one reason.
So that
Away.
And now we've got just us calling the orthographic or the perspective
stuff and now we have to fix that.
So when we call perspective here, what we need to do is create a
camera, transform that and that camera transformed, then has to be
passed as a 4x4 up to the render group itself.
So here's that set camera transform call, which is what I'm going to
be calling.
Now, also similarly, we would want to set the clip rect although the
clip rect will be set by
Fought to the whole screen, so we probably don't really need to modify
it.
So when we call set camera, transform here, and we have the camera
focal length that's going to stay the same.
It will not be an orthographic projection and we will want to create
the camera 4 by 4
Like so.
So in this case, the camera transfer from here, we don't have any of
those axes yet that we were looking for.
We don't know what the x axis is or the y axis, or the Z axis, for any
kind of rotated camera.
So first, we're just going to pass in basically an identity, but we
are going to have that
offset to maintain.
So the position is correct and we are going to pass that down for to
the camera transform, then inside.
Whoops, when I did set camera transform, it looks like I that should
be a pointer.
I don't want to copy all those on the stack necessarily although you
know, maybe that's okay, depends haven't measured it.
Yeah.
Okay, for our layered scene, we don't need to move the camera or
anything.
So in this case, it would just be the identity Matrix again.
And so I can just say
Past that and called.
Camera transform.
And again, that's going to be prospective, not orthographic.
So then we just have one last person here, who needs to set the camera
transform.
And this one does need to be orthographic and so we just need a way of
dealing with that for.
Now again, I'm going to not do anything, particularly clever here.
Because we haven't really gotten around to dealing with any of that
yet.
So now the only thing we don't,
Have is a thing that doesn't actual orthographic projection.
And again, that's not something that I want to focus on at the moment
because it's only for the debug code, which we do want to enable.
But at the moment, we are going to have to live without
and when we take a look at the perspective, call,
Which is.
Should I just call it projection?
Ah, that's dumb.
It's a perspective projection.
So yeah.
So for our orthographic projection, which is different.
Really, what you can see here is we don't really need to do anything
with the focal length, right?
We don't care what the focal length is at all.
So really, all we have is the aspect with over height.
We're not trying to put anything remember.
This is the thing that moved something into the W coordinate so that
when the Divide happened it would normalize itself out
In this case, we don't really want to do anything here at all and we
don't really necessarily know what we want in the W coordinate.
So for now I'm just going to put one there and so we'll just sort of
leave this B and we may want to do a little bit more with that later,
right?
Because we may we may want our orthographic projection to do other
stuff there to terms of sizing the world.
However it's going to size it but beyond just aspect correction.
I'm just going to say,
look at orthographic.
Re-enable, I'll look fix on projectors, already on there.
All right.
so,
Our orthographic projection will be good enough for the time being
just as a stand-in.
But again we are going to want to maybe take a look at how we're doing
that and what we actually want that Matrix to do Beyond just not the
perspective divide.
Like all I did was essentially like Nerf the perspective divide to
make sure that it didn't happen, but that's it.
All right.
So we've made massive changes everywhere.
So probably none of this is going to work, that's okay.
We're just sort of getting things into position and we'll step through
this now and
art to try and clean out what needs to happen and what, you know what
needs to get fixed in order for us to see stuff on the screen again.
But we're definitely getting closer.
To having the pipeline be reasonable.
So if I go back to
let's see here.
Handmade World mode.
I just want to set a break poem.
Here we go.
So here I call camera transform.
I just want to take a look that this stuff is actually somewhat
reasonable.
That makes sense.
And don't forget, we are actually calling get camera rectangle at
Target here and that may be broken because we didn't fix unprojected
stuff yet.
So there is that and we'll check that out as well.
But for I just want to, before we go any further, I want to take a
brief look at this code to make sure that it looks at all.
Reasonable to me before we go any further.
So, here we are inside our push set up call.
I want to make sure that all the stuff in the group got set properly.
It does look that way, here's our screen.
That is the size of the screen at the moment so that's good.
Here's that projection Matrix.
Let's take a look at what that looks like.
I'm going to slide this over a little so we can see more explicitly.
Here's that Matrix 1s down the diagonal except zero here.
Is the aspect ratio correction factor on the Y, which is what we want.
I guess the inverse of what you'd expect, because we're going to the
unit cube not away from the unit cube.
And then we've got our divide
Our perspective, divide quantity here multiplying in, but multiplying
the Z and that's really all we need.
So that all looks clean when we set it all up.
Let's see.
And make sure that it gets into the rectangle that we actually created
should be set to all those things as well.
Just want to make sure again looks good.
Looks like what we want.
So we're at least pushing that information on properly.
We're getting that.
To the current cliprect so that all looks reasonable to me and I think
that's fine for the camera transform.
Now, when we do get camera rectangle, at Target,
This is probably broken because again we're not doing that projection
correctly but the result is not awful, it's just not good.
It's it's not going to be very large, right?
And so I don't know how much that will affect us here.
The world camera wrecked to the screen bounds are here.
Yeah.
So, I don't know to what extent that will.
Create a problem for us.
Testing this weather, we're going to need to actually fix that
function first before we debug any further that may be the case.
But I'm just going to go ahead and take a look the same region and see
it does look like it, grab 400 entities, so something's getting
grabbed.
So in theory, we should be able to debug it.
So since this came up in the middle and you know how much everyone who
watched stream knows how much I love modern software and how great it
is.
Like I love the notion that somebody thought it was okay, to pop this
up in the middle of like a user's daily work but that was good.
But I want to show you the other really great part about this, which
is, it's like, hey yeah, you know it sounds great I'd love to upgrade.
Let's do that.
Let's get that new driver.
I'm excited.
I can't wait for it.
Hit me up a MD with the new driver.
Pretty great, huh.
Like they routinely interrupt my workflow to tell me if there's a new
driver and when I try to install the new driver, if they tell me that
it doesn't have anything to install its great.
Fantastic.
All right.
So here we go, check for joining new players, that's not relevant to
us obviously and simulate is not really what we want, but we have to
get into it, because it's where we do our update and render, which is
what I actually need to access.
So, here we are in update and render entities, we're going through
here and I just want to again, take a brief look at the render
activity here, just to see if we ever actually call anyone because
it's in, it's possible that that Sim region made it.
So
Nobody is actually active and that they're all kind of outside of the
active range.
Because that same region is wrong because the because the unprojected
is not implemented.
So let's see where we actually pushing our bitmaps here.
That's going to be down here, right?
Do we ever actually get there?
We do.
Okay good.
So here we go with the push bitmap, call in the push bitmap call,
we're just going to verify that we actually got one.
Okay, so we got to wait till we actually get to a push bitmap.
There we go.
So I'll come in here.
Take a look at when we get the bitmap dimensions, that's going to give
us back our coordinates.
And this is what I'm primarily concerned about here, that that Z, you
can see that in there, right?
And so, what I'm curious about now is I would like to know is that Z
compatible with what we ended up setting in our render group, right?
So our group last project, here's what I've got set.
And what you can see there is, I'm not getting any displacement,
right?
You remember these coordinates here, those coordinates are the
cameras, the inverse, the the undoing of the cameras location.
So we're not rotating the camera yet, so we would expect them to be
straight and negatives of the camera position.
But instead, I'm just getting all zeros there
And now, I think about it when I step through that that is what was
happening.
Does that mean that the camera offset was Zero?
It does look like it was.
So that's not a useful camera all set.
So, let's see.
Was that just because frame 0 it hasn't gotten set yet because it
hasn't had a frame to actually pick up the change if that's the case,
I'd like to see it.
Yeah.
So there we go.
That's better.
Z equals 8.
That's what we want.
So now, when we set the camera transform, now let's go through and
take a look at that.
Push bitmap call.
Oops, gotta actually reset that break point.
There we go.
And so inside here now I should see and there's that's what I wanted,
right?
I wanted that negative 8 in there, right?
Because that's if the camera is 88 up on the z-axis, then that means
during transforms everything else should get pushed 8 away, right?
If you get pushed 8 down the Z axis, the other direction towards
further away from the camera, right?
And that's exactly what we want.
So that is what I wanted to see, that's good.
I'm going to step into the get bitmap, Tim call here, just so I can
see what's going on there.
It's the entity basis P function that I would like to take a look at
again, distance above Target and floor Z, this is all zeroed out now
and that's only in in render debug mode that we have that and we can
roll that into the projection Matrix to.
So we'll be able to get rid of that the hide off.
Or Rosie Ortho.
Let's take a look at any of this stuff here.
To look that result.
So the result of Z equals 0 is a good result, that's a reasonable
result.
These X and y's are way off in pretty far to the left and down, but
the, the Z is at least in the right place.
So, that's good to see you as well, just in terms of things that can
be wrong, and then we push the renderer element on there.
We should expect everything to be clean there.
on this render entry, I guess we can't see the header unfortunately,
but I guess I could try to
What's the name of that function?
I'm sorry structure.
Render group entry header.
That's what I wanted.
So I just want to double-check if I look at the render group entry
header.
So I know that this entry is here
So, in theory, if I just take that location and call that a render
group entry header, that won't be anything meaningful because I'm
looking at this data, but I know that the red re-entry enter hit the
render entry.
Header is just sitting right above it.
So I should be able to do a negative one on that and get the actual
one, right?
And here it is.
Type 0 is a is a bitmap.
Oops no don't change that.
Type 0 is a bitmap so that is what I expect cliprect one is also what
I would expect so that's good.
That's what I wanted to see.
And I just want to make sure that is actually the last clip back that
was pushed on.
Verify, that that's true.
Yes.
So, that's all good as well.
So all of that is good.
Let's see here.
so,
It looks like here where we're doing store color.
I should also just double-check that we didn't tweet because we nerfed
those colors.
I should also check that are pre multiply color is not meaningless, so
that's good.
111 is what I wanted.
So that's all good too because otherwise, you know, we could have
something that was Alpha out.
All of ours of our Graphics or something like that.
So I want to make sure that that's stable as well.
Alright, so we're pushing all of that stuff on there and all of those
bitmaps are coming down, but for some reason, I'm still not seeing
them on the screen.
So I'm going to jump over to the opengl side here.
And see if I can get a better picture.
Perhaps, what is incorrect there?
It's going to come down here.
We're looking at the first clip.
Rect index.
just clip and clip entry into x 0, who
got pushed.
With the 0 clip.
Rect
I wonder.
Oh, it's just the cliprect itself, okay.
That's a waste of time.
We should probably short-circuit.
The, you know, if the entry itself is a clip, rect then you don't have
to care.
That's yeah, that's a good point.
I go ahead and put that in there.
Never thought about that before.
But now that we do have the clip, rect coming through here when we do
this.
Check.
We probably want to check that the header type.
Window group entry type.
There we go.
So this is just saying hey if this is a clip rect then we don't need
to set up the clip.
Rect for a clip rect because it doesn't draw anything.
So we want to make sure that the header type is not a clip rect and
then it's all fine.
All right, so let's try that one more time.
I'm not sure why that
if the header type is not one of those.
That should not have really had any effect.
At all, really.
Right.
Oh, I put that in the wrong place.
That's where actually one of that.
There we go.
Sorry about that, mental mistake.
I was only trying to get rid of this Clause.
Not this one.
All right, much better.
So now I just want to go ahead and stop in here and I should see the
first one should be cliprect index 1.
Yeah.
Because that's the, you know, when should be pushing anything on clip
break zero, that would be a mistake.
So here we go.
We get out the clip.
Rect and again this clip rect should look like the one we inspected
before it should be that one.
So here's a projection Matrix which is what we expect and here's the
screen region.
So we need to transpose this first before we load it, but otherwise,
that's fine.
So just going to flip this around and it's going to load it up.
I guess I should verify that it actually does look that way.
And yep, that looks like a nice flip to me.
I will say.
Wait, why are we getting a negative?
X.
Here though.
That seems odd to me because that should have been zeroed out.
So that's a little weird.
I would be interested to know how that happened.
How did that happen?
I think we should go inspect that a little bit further, just to make
sure we know what's going on.
Is that what we would expect to have happen there?
Let's see how that occurred.
I'd like to take a look a little closer.
Look at that.
I didn't pay attention that before.
So let's just make sure that that math were checks out.
Before, before I continue down the path, I was about to continue down.
I would like to see what's going on there.
So let's see.
Here's our set camera, transform call, and we'll have something to go
through once.
So we're at the right camera.
So here's our set camera.
Transform call our camera.
Transform itself.
Should look like what we expected to look like, 1s down the diagonal
and just a position that is what it looks like.
And so our perspective projection
Make sure that looks like what we think that is what we think.
And so let's go into this, the multiply and make sure that the
multiply looks right to us.
so, here is US creating the
The individual columns, we can actually watch these happen, right?
This is it producing the 00 element here.
It is producing the 01 element, continue on.
And so here's a producing the final element of the row, right?
Go, go, go, go, go.
Doing it slow multiplication.
We should probably put these on here.
All right.
So, here we are on our 33, right?
And so, what we would expect to see here, let's just figure out what
we would expect to see here, first, and then
If I that it's actually what we think it should be.
So we're multiplying a times B and remember.
That means that a is the one that's appearing on the left, and B is
the one that's appearing on the right above.
And we're trying to multiply this.
So it'd be this row times this column, right?
So I guess I do actually believe that that that does look true, right?
The -8 should multiply the 3 Point 33, 33, 33 2.5 here, right?
And that's where we're getting that term from its from here.
So that is actually correct.
I guess.
Yeah, and I think about that's fine because the W coordinate their
what's going to happen in the W coordinate of the Matrix down at the
bottom, there is, you know, this this the 33 element that's
essentially going to be an offset to the W which is what this is.
Right.
We're saying that the camera gets pushed back that much.
So we do need the W to be offset by that much.
So that the Divide is that much more
So, I am okay with that.
That seems reasonable.
And off we go.
So let me go back to what I was doing.
Just want to make sure that that was right.
let's go ahead and
take a look at one of our actual bitmap calls.
There we go.
So I just want to take a look at what these values actually are down
here to make sure that they look the same to me.
That's all I'm doing right now.
And yeah.
So, here's our, here's the values, we're actually sending down x-axis
y-axis mean p, the x axis and the y axis.
In this case.
Look totally reasonable.
They're just scaled, but they, that's all they, you know, there's
nothing weird about them, the minimum P.
It's kind of all off.
To the left and down.
And let me just
see if in general.
Is that where everything is?
So, you can kind of see that everything that we're drawing is far to
the left of us.
There we go.
Now we're getting some stuff that there was a few things that were
close to us there.
so now, we're drawing things that are to the right of
As well.
Still below us.
There's now some stuff that's well we still haven't quite seen
anything.
That's right on target.
I'm just curious.
I'm just checking to see if there's any sort of so that looked pretty
reasonable.
So these numbers look pretty reasonable, though.
so I'll be honest, I don't immediately see
Any problem there.
So I do Wonder.
I do Wonder a little bit if we have to look at the near and far clip
playing now as
as culprits.
So let's talk about that because we haven't done anything to process
the Z coordinate and that may be a problem.
So let's take a look.
So what you can see here in our perspective projection, which we've
been working on, is that we set up our divide to do the divide that we
wanted to do to produce the X and Y coordinates, that we thought we
were going to produce.
That would match what we were previously producing.
However,
At the moment, we don't do anything with the Z coordinate, we just
pass through, whatever the Z coordinate actually was what I'm
concerned about is that the clipping that happens in opengl to the
near and far clipping planes may be causing us a problem.
I believe that happens with the z-coordinate although I could be wrong
about that.
We could go double-check the pipeline stuff so I'm just curious to
know if the Z coordinate is a problem there.
I'm just going to check it.
Real quick.
Okay, all that would do is knock out the Z coordinate, right?
So that it wouldn't actually push anything into the Z coordinate, if
that makes sense.
So, I just want to double check what was actually happening there.
All right, so let's talk about the near and far clipping planes and
let's just go try to verify whether or not we're doing anything
particularly wrong with how opengl wants us to produce points that
conform to what it's going to clip to.
Because remember, we've got that notion I kind of went
A couple weeks ago about the clip space and the unit cube and all that
sort of stuff.
We have to make sure that we're playing exactly by the the gpus rules
here.
Which again is not necessarily what we had been doing when we created
the rules ourselves, when we made the pipeline, for the software side,
we didn't have to play by the gpus rules, we didn't have to even know
how the GPU conceptualizes things like clipping.
Now we do and we have to keep in mind as well, that in addition to
clipping off the Left, Right top.
Bottom of the screen.
Opengl will also clip things that are far away and things that are too
close.
So, it's a full clip in all three dimensions.
And so, if we're producing coordinates that are not Kosher in any way,
then we will have a problem.
So I want to again, I have to eliminate these things, one at a time in
order to find out what the problem is, with our transform process,
right?
Excuse me.
So let's just double-check how opengl wants those matrices set.
Hoping I could find one, that's got a reasonable drawing of it, that's
not it.
That's not either.
This, this is what I want.
But man, it's not formatted right at all.
I just want one.
That's formatted.
Well,
Good enough.
So here you can see right where we're getting this.
This is this is what the GL utility Library.
The one that comes with up in jail.
This is how it sets things up and you can see how they do it.
It's not that much different from ours but it does a couple things
slightly differently.
So in the top two ports here at they basically do what we do but they
do things slightly differently.
So rather than use focal length, they use field of view and why which
is basically an angle measure.
It's saying how you know why?
Do you want the field of view to be, but they have the aspect ratio
correction.
They also did the aspect ratio opposite, from what we do?
They do the aspect ratio of the width, the height in the X, right?
So, where is our?
Yeah, and we were doing that in the why?
I wonder if that means that's weird.
Do we I thought we worked out which way that should be going and this
looks a little bit backwards formats which is the ratio of x to y.
And you can see the aspect ratio here.
Oh, because it's one over.
They must be missing a 1 there.
Yeah.
You can see, they're missing the one.
I'm like, they've got it backwards.
They don't have it backwards.
They just there's a supposed to be a one there and there isn't.
Right?
So they do it exactly the same way we do, right?
Except we put it into a why correction and they put it into an ex
correction.
So that's why they had to invert.
There's and we didn't have to invert ours because they put it on the
other.
ER side, right?
Field of view and why we're not using we were using focal length.
So we don't actually
Do that the same way?
That makes sense.
But so we but, you know, field of view and why is a reasonable way to
do it?
I don't know that we want to do it that way.
So I'm going to stick to not messing with that part of it but we can
leave that for later.
So anyway,
I think.
Yeah, I think everything else is fairly similar one over the focal.
Length goes down into to get our W.
Divided to be what we wanted it to be, right?
And I'm pretty sure we check that math to line up with the math that
we were using previously.
And so that is similar to what they're doing.
Although they don't actually change that coordinate at all.
So they take Z, they take the Z directly, if that makes sense, they
they
Sickly say, hey, whatever the Z comes in.
We're not going to change it at all.
We don't modify it by the focal length.
We just have it.
Might you know, we just directly set that value, right?
I guess.
The way to think about that.
And I guess I don't know that I have
Any particular, so here's what I'm going to say.
I think this probably wasn't a one here.
I think this was probably an F if I'm just guessing because I think
what they basically did, was they put the multiplier in here for f
rather than putting it down here, right?
Because what we did is we stuffed the focal length, which is
equivalent to the field of view.
It's not the same value, it's not the same way of setting the value,
but it's it's a similar computation, right?
That value that controls the field of view, which the focal length,
does it just in a different way of specifying it?
We put that so that, that, that would go into the computation of the
denominator of the Divide, but they left it in the numerator of the
Divide.
Right, so we could do that as well.
If we wanted to write all we would have to do is multiply it into
here, right?
And that would would do it.
I don't know if there's some reason why we have to do that in order to
maintain clip space properly for how they want it lined up, right?
Because looking at their Matrix here, it may be that because
Yeah, if you take a look at housing near and Z far are operating here
for, we really need to find out one of these.
It's got all the values in it.
I feel like that's a good.
I just want a good drawing of it.
Is this?
This
On how to Godin.
Write to us out of a good one.
No.
Does, nobody just have just the actual because the thing is, in the
book, in the open job book, it's just got the drawing and you can
actually see what they wanted, the perspective stuff set to, but it
seems like everybody has does not actually reproduce that diagram in a
way that's easy to read, which is unfortunate.
What's this?
No.
Do you have our?
Do you have a drawn out?
That is an actual Matrix form.
There it is.
Okay, this is the same Matrix that we were trying to look at before.
But they've copied out the diagram properly with the actual ones
place.
So see there you go.
That was what I was expecting, right?
So they put the focal length which in their case is a field of view
computation, but it's the same idea.
They put that in the numerator because this will multiply into the X
and Y coordinates before divided.
We were putting it into the denominator by putting
Over it over here.
I don't know if that will create a problem for opengl.
I'm not sure it's worth worth noting.
But here's the part that's actually more relevant in terms of
Foreigner clip planes which we have to get right as well.
Now I knocked out the Z value entirely which means that I don't think
we're having a problem with clipping.
I don't suspect that that's actually the problem here but I just want
to go through because I knew we had to do this.
I just want to go through and get that correct as we go.
So there's two things that could be causing us possible problems here.
Although I don't think the clip playing part of its problem, although
this part could have been a problem.
and that is just simply the part the aspect of this, which is
Computing the near and far, clipping plane values.
It's not really doing that.
It's putting Z into the correct range from near and far clipping
planes.
But then also the part where, you know, maybe it's required that we
not put that in the denominator, maybe it's required that we put in
the numerator because remember opengl is going to do something.
When we go through this transform opengl is going to do clipping
before it does the Divide.
So, even though the way we were building, the Matrix will produce the
same result.
Whether we put it in the numerator or the denominator, it will only
produce the same result after the divided.
So if it needs those values to be in a particular range beforehand,
and we've done the
And in an order that still results in the same divide that may not be
sufficient.
So again, just want to bring up the fact that we have to play by their
rules entirely and put it into the spaces that they want.
We can't just make something that we know will produce the correct X Y
values at the end or something.
It's not that simple.
All right, so that's easy enough for us to do.
So maybe we should just do that.
We've got one over focal length here.
Really all we have to do is put the focal length up here and so you
can kind of see the way that's happening, right?
We've got our terms, all we would have to do is we would just multiply
by that and instead of one over focal length, we just pass in focal
length.
Right.
That's all that we would actually have to do to make that substantive
change.
I don't think that's a particularly interesting change necessarily.
But that's okay.
What is a bit weird to me?
Is that this is passed in as a negative 1, right?
So the fact that that's passed in as a negative, one suggests that the
Z values are going in the opposite direction, right?
And I'm interested to know if that's actually the case.
Let's see.
This is all doing exactly what we did.
I'm just wondering why it's a negative Z.
So, a negative Z flips the Z Direction around.
And I wonder if that's just because that's what they wanted to have
happen or whether there's some reason why we would need the Z to run -
like this open Jill's screen space for some reason have Z going the
wrong direction.
Well, you know what, know, now that I think about it.
I guess that is true, because when it's going to do the divide, it
doesn't do a negation after the fact of the Z.
So, even though it defines e-even though, opengl normally uses a
right-handed coordinate system, it's not going to negate the Z that we
pass in.
So we would have to negate the Z ourselves to make sure that when we
do the divide it does get negated.
Hmm.
My say.
Alright, let's take a look at this.
First of all, I'm going to go ahead and make it so that you don't have
to pass in one over the focal length.
So I'm going to go take a look at the perspective projection call.
And I'm going to go ahead and just past the focal length down.
So, that should be it.
Okay, I guess I don't know why I'm running that because we haven't we
won't see.
I won't be able to verify that the changes right since we were not at
a workable state to begin with but that's okay.
So yeah if I want to put the the focal length in here that's all good.
And then down here again I got to figure out that math.
I don't like the idea that I'm not sure.
About the negation.
More specifically.
I'm not sure why the negation work the first time, I guess, the reason
the negation work the first time is because we were doing the
subtraction ourselves.
And in fact, I guess this may be the entire problem we were having
because here's the thing, I forgot the fact that we implicitly up when
we were doing get render entity basis P, we were implicitly negating
the Z coordinate ourselves, right?
This stuff's all gone.
Now, like hide off floor and all this sort of stuff, this stuff's all
gone.
That's a zero.
Distance above Target is also zero.
So all that stuff is is gone and doesn't do anything right.
And we now are putting the camera transform, which we used to be doing
inside, get renters, Graduate Institute, render entity basis P.
We're now doing that in our perspective, projection what that means
is, we are no longer subtracting the Z away and so, therefore, we
would have to flip the order in which it goes.
So I guess I just never thought about the fact that we had already
baked that in when we were doing it here, but we did, right?
And just to like,
Go to that in a little more detail so it's clearer.
Let me go ahead and
talk about that real quick.
There we go.
All right, so let's talk about that real quick because I think I see.
Now what I accidentally did when I was modifying these
So in my mind, right the way that we had our coordinate system setup
is, we have an X Y plane.
Oops.
That's the why.
And Z is coming up, right?
That means that Z gets higher.
As it gets closer.
To the camera to get closer to the camera.
We want a smaller value.
But that's not going to be true as he gets higher now, because we were
previously writing our own code for the projection, that wasn't a
problem because all we did was we actually took and we did the
subtraction this way.
We said hey let's take where the whatever the point is, right?
And let's subtract the location of the camera that gave us a thing.
That was - downsy, right?
And was getting not - down so you that was getting
Higher.
As you went down - Z and that's what I was stuffing into the Z
coordinate.
So obviously when we built our projection Matrix to match that we
could just put the Z coordinate directly into W, it would work.
But now, when we're passing down just raw, you know, now that we're
having open to the whole transform, we're just passing down these Rock
coordinates.
What that means, is, we need some way of flipping the Z around so that
as the Z gets higher,
Things get further away.
We need that to happen or our entire transform isn't going to work,
right?
Things would be getting bigger as they got further away and smaller as
they got closer, which makes no sense at all.
Right.
So you can see why we would need to do this or I'm going to ignore
again, busy temporarily, but you can see why we need to flip the Z
around at that point.
Because in order to do that divided, we need to flip the Z value.
So that
Will change the way it's characters that will get bigger as it things
get further away instead of getting closer when we do that, obviously
the Z value when it comes through and, and does that divide here will,
then always be positive because it will get clipped, presumably, if it
was going to be negative because it will be shifted forward by opengl.
I would assume but we'll have to double check that as well again.
This is all about making sure that we understand what opengl is doing,
because we're supposed to be preparing coordinates for opengl.
So there we go.
So that it was actually the problem.
There is that I when I clipped out all that code, I forgot the fact
that we had actually been negating RC and now that opengl is getting
this raw it has a negated.
See, okay.
We still do have to handle the near and far clipping.
In mind you, but that's a separate issue.
So that's all well and good.
And that's, you know, that's fine.
And that's good because that means we're now at the place where we are
actually able to start doing some more stuff here, because now we are
actually passing down Z coordinates for everything, right?
And that's good.
You can see there, there's our screen rectangle to, you can see, the
unprojected is not implemented right yet, right?
You can.
And you can see that very clearly because that's, that's the rectangle
that should line up with the screen.
And instead, it's just this little tiny meaningless rectangle.
So you can see, we've got to get that fixed as well, but we're
starting to get a little closer to reasonable here, right?
So again getting better.
Excuse Me, Slowly putting the focal length out here into the numerator
again that probably had nothing to do with that.
We probably could still leave it in the denominator if we wanted to.
I assume let's just check to see if that's true.
I don't actually know if it is or not because again like I said we
have to play by open jails rules.
Not our rules here.
So I'm going to put the focal length into the denominator here, just
to see what happens if I do.
Yeah, so that was not the problem.
We are allowed to do that.
I suppose that doesn't mean we should, it may still be that it's
better behaved if you do it the way that opengl expects.
But again, so it was just the fact that I had forgotten, we were
implicitly flipping disease.
We stopped flipping disease and started passing the directly.
And we had to account for that, when we made our protection, we had to
account for flipping those, these
All right.
So let's try to finish up today.
We still got some time left, you got about half an hour left.
Let's still finish what we were going to do today before getting into
the the near and far clipping plane.
Because like I said, I kind of wanted to put push those off until we
were ready to actually do z-buffering because the near and far
clipping plane is really have, inter it sort of intimately related if
you will to doing that sort of Zeebo.
Ring, where you care about what the Z ranges are.
And so I would like to talk about those together and rather than doing
them now.
So, I'm glad that that was not something that we had to deal with.
All right.
So, let's put that off for temporarily, and we'll deal with that next
week when we start doing z-buffering.
And right now, that's just finished the Camera Part, which is the only
other thing that I really had wanted to do.
And inside the
World mode.
We're actually setting the camera.
You can see that we're passing some axes down here.
All I really want to do right now is just kind of, I want to make it
so that we can do some arbitrary rotation.
Stuff.
So what I'm going to do to start out with that, I'm just going to make
like a camera.
P.
I'm going to, I'm going to call this camera placement and this camera.
I so maybe maybe camera forward and Camera inverse in some sense
because this is like the or maybe camera object and camera camera or
something like that.
Because this is the object.
I want to create the object transform for the camera, like where the
camera is in the world, basically.
And then this is really the inversion of that, right?
It's the thing that takes things and Maps it into the camera space.
So I just want to kind of call those two different things.
So, I'm just going to say that we've got a rotate.
I think it's like, let's say around the x axis X rotation, I'm going
to get an extra tation.
I want to tilt the camera this way.
And so, if we rotate about the x axis tilting, the camera.
If you, if you imagine the right-hand rule, remember I said things
the, you know, align your right, take your right hand, align your
thumb along the axis and rotation, you know, is going to go
counterclockwise around.
Right.
You know this intuitively from the unit circle when we draw right.
Here's our
Standard xy-plane write z is coming out towards us, right?
So if you imagine putting your hand there with your thumb, pointing
along the z-axis and you curl your fingers, right, it goes in the same
direction as the unit circle goes, the unit, circle goes
counterclockwise, when we conceptualize it, right?
So all of our rotations that we built, they go counterclockwise around
the axle of the rotation.
If the axles pointing
Out at us, right?
So if I want to pitch the camera so that we're looking down on the
world, it's pitched back a little bit, right?
Well, that's actually the opposite, if I'm rotating around the x-axis,
right?
I'm going to rotate the world sort of toward me this way with a
positive.
So I want to do a little bit of a negative rotation along that axis.
So I'm going to take
I think we have a value for pi here.
Somewhere.
There it is.
So I'm going to take a value for pi here and I'm just going to say,
Hey, you know, Pi would be 180 degrees.
I want to rotate this very small fraction of that.
Maybe, you know, a third of pie, maybe, maybe probably even less than
that a tenth of pie, maybe.
I don't know how much we want to do, but very, very little of a
rotation, right?
Pie being pie being 180 degrees, right?
Towels,
Is 360 Degrees.
I want to do a very small fraction of that.
So if I take that, what I should be able to do is just get column
now.
And pull those out of The Matrix.
Where I have camera.
Oh,
so,
so now I can build any kind of rotation I want.
And and then my camera transform should make that work.
And again that uses that worldspace offset of the camera and what
we're not really doing yet.
Is I'm not placing the camera, rotate it around yet.
So this is literally putting a tilt in in the tilts.
Not going to quite be correct because of that.
But that's ok.
We'll we'll deal with that in a moment.
There we go.
So yeah.
So now our world is is tilted.
That's not the Tilt.
I was expecting though.
Why did I get that tilt?
so, the rotation
Oh duh.
Because this is the rotation of the camera itself.
So I am was thinking about how I wanted to rotate the world which is
completely wrong.
So let me think about that one more time.
So cure is
My why here's my ex the world is laid out on it.
Right here is my Z, my camera is here.
So what I want to do is I want to tilt the camera so that I'm looking
this way, is what I was trying to do, right?
I was thinking about tilting the world but that's not what I'm doing,
right?
I'm spreading.
We are trying to make it so that our camera is actually like a
physical object we can think about.
So I wrote All That code to assume that we were doing, you know, we
were going to take the camera as an object that we want to view things
from.
So yeah, so that rotation is going positive around X so, that's okay.
I was like got nervous there.
I never like to negate things.
Like if I have something to gated and I expected to do something, if
it does the opposite, that's like an alarm, that's like a huge like
bad situation for me.
I'm like, wait, what if I expected this?
And I got the opposite, I assume I've got a problem in my pipeline
summer and I want to be absolutely sure that I
I know what the reason is for that before I switch it.
I know it's a subtle thing but it's like yeah if you're wondering why
I didn't just immediately take the - off and as soon as I was like I
want to know that I just was thinking about some little thing wrong in
that it really should be positive not negative because the other
possibility is that there's a problem somewhere in the math that we
did before and I don't want that to be wrong and be sitting there in
correct the entire time, right?
That would be bad.
It could create other problems later that that are not.
So fixable as just removing a - right?
So, that's okay.
So the other problem we have here is in addition to, you know, doing
that rotation of the camera, which we just did, right?
So there you go.
In addition to doing that rotation of the camera which we just did.
I also that is pitching the camera up without adjusting where the
cameras looking, right?
So all we did was take the cameras location and look up from their
right.
That's all we did.
We did not try to move the camera in any other particular way if that
makes sense.
Yeah.
So this is assuming that the camera offset is in the world at that
location, and that it's looking this way, what I believe that means.
And again, I just want to take some time to double check some of this
year.
It should mean that.
By the time we rotate to 90 degrees.
We are looking straight away from like we're looking totally away from
the world and that is correct.
Like there it is.
There's quite a bit of eccentricity here.
I'm not sure if that means our focal length needs to be set
differently.
But hold on a second.
Let's take a look at that.
So that's what we wanted.
This is exactly what we wanted here.
And I want to be able to, in addition to that extra Tatian.
I want to be able to rotate about
The Z axis as well, so that we can orbit the world if that makes
sense.
So we're looking down on it and I want to be able to to orbit around
as well.
So in addition, I would like to be able to do some of this sort of
thing.
Right.
And I'm just I'm I'm not loving how I'm not loving with that focal
length.
Is it looks like the focal length is maybe a little too eccentric.
It kind of makes me feel like that focal.
Length should be
More.
I don't really know, just curious to see.
That looks a little more sane to me in terms of the degree of stretch,
right?
But we can cross that bridge later.
Take a look at that.
So anyway,
The other thing that I could do here is now we could actually have the
the mouse input correspond to that, but we'll get to that in a second.
So, what I was saying about that, is when we're doing this orbiting
and stuff like that, the problem here is that we don't actually have
any way of
Of looking back.
Making sure we're focused on the world's actual focal point.
So when we look at this world camera offset bit, what I want to do is
I want to rotate
That around with the world as I rotate as well.
So you know, if you imagine how this is, like I said, the camera is
out here somewhere.
What I want to do is not just pitch the camera up, but when I pitched
the camera up and look in this direction, I want to counter rotate its
position.
So that it is looking at the center point, it's still looking at the
same Center Point, right?
Does that make sense?
So, when I rotate the world this way, I want to counter, rotate the
position of the world in the in the other way, right?
But those are actually the same way if you think about it, like
If I'm rotating up this up, that's the same.
You know, that's going to rotate a position down, right?
If that makes sense because the position is coming out the other end
of the of the directional pointing right now, sir, I'm explaining that
right,
So if this is our Z, right?
And here's the x axis coming out here, remember the cameras axis is
pointing backwards along Z, right?
That's where it's actually pointing, that makes sense.
So if I'm rotating it this way, you know, it's looking back this
direction, if I'm rotating it this way, everything wants to rotate by
that rotation because, you know, it's going to make it point that way,
which is actually pointing back this way and its position.
Also wanted to rotate
That way.
So I should be able to take this right here.
The camera offset.
I should be able to take that and multiply that in, right?
If that makes sense.
Or not.
When I say I should be able to do that and then I clearly can't.
So I should be able to do that.
I should be able to rotate it out and I would assume
Yeah, I assume that that should be correct because that is what we do
want to do that, right?
I didn't do anything weird there.
We want to be able to rotate.
The cameras offset by the camera.
Just try this one more time.
And we can knock out one term of this for debugging purposes.
Just so we can see
There we go.
So, here's our expectation.
We have our camera.
It's pointing like this.
Right?
That's the cameras axes and the cameras position is somewhere out here
along Z, right?
So it's, you know, I don't know what was with something like eight, I
think.
So it's eight along Z.
So now what happens when we do our camera rotation?
Is we're going to rotate everything.
This way, right?
So we're going to rotate the position down here.
Please.
That's our hope.
And similarly, we're going to rotate all the axes down there as well.
That's what we hope to do.
But unfortunately we're just kind of getting a collapse here.
Like you can see, we're still drawing singing but it's kind of
flattened out in a weird way.
I'm not sure exactly what that corresponds to because of our
multiplication here.
I want to pull this out because I would like to be able to inspect
these separately.
So I'm just going to make a synthetic term there.
And the other thing that's interesting is this should just be
basically canceling out the work that camera transform actually does
itself.
So there really shouldn't have been much mystery there so I want to go
in there and make sure that we don't have any bugs because it feels
like we probably do.
All right, so let's hop over to World mode.
Assuming I can actually find their teeth.
There it is.
Okay.
So here is our camera.
Oh, here is our camera OT.
And that.
Is this is this when the offset still zero?
Okay, so I got to come back through the second time
There we go.
All right.
So now let's take a look at what our camera offset actually is here.
So we're rotating 90 degrees.
Oh,
Well, I'm an idiot.
We're rotating 90 degrees.
We should be seeing the world flat.
We can't rotate 90 degrees, and and point at the straight.
Yeah.
Okay, wow.
So no, we don't have a bug.
We just forgot.
We had.
Rotate it all the way down to 90.
Nice work.
Casey imagining bugs where there are none?
So, yeah, so we should be able to now do sort of that X flattening
rotation, which is what we want and still be pointed at the
Which again, is what we want.
So that's all good.
And now what we want to do is we want to be able to hook these up to
the mouse so I can spin it around because that's what I want again for
debugging purposes.
So those two parameters I want to
Able to control if that makes sense.
And so let's just take a look at how we might do that.
So inside update and render world, I'm going to need an accumulator
somehow.
I'm going to need to be able to specify this.
So I'm going to just do again, something pretty stupid.
I'm just going to do like
Debug camera pitch and debug camera orbit here.
And I'm going to grab those values and put them into this equation.
So rather than us, having some arbitrary value that we put here, I'm
going to go ahead and make the Z rotation, be debug camera orbit, and
the X rotation, debug camera pitch.
And then when we have these Mouse stuff coming in here,
I don't remember very much about how we capture debug input.
I don't remember if we had any debug Keys available.
If we don't, we're going to need some, because we're going to need
some way of saying that I want to access the camera now, and I would
like that to be quick.
So I want to be able to just hit a like a accelerator key and have
that come in.
So, let's take a look.
We can see here.
We've got game controller inputs, which stopped we care about Mouse
button.
So there we go.
We've got shift.
Alt and control, which should be good.
So, I'll just use the ALT key for this and say, if you know input
Alt down.
And input Mouse buttons.
I don't know how I get an is down for the mouse button.
Is down because it's a game button States, right?
So I can just say, is down Mouse buttons left.
Let's say.
So assuming that that's true, then I can just take my mouse Delta
here.
Do we have a last mousex?
I think we do.
I don't think we do.
So I'll save that as well.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say that we keep it last Mouse P, I
guess.
And store that.
So now I can get the Delta which is all I really wanted, right?
So when we produce this, we then have a deal.
SP, which is just whatever.
The last Master P was
Subtract it away.
So it's like, where did we go?
And then in here, I can say what I want to have happen with the
accumulators.
So, my world mode about camera orbit.
And my world mode.
Debug camera pitch.
I want those to be proportional to the mouse input.
I don't really know what the ratio should be, so I guess I want to
have a rotation speed then here.
Those are going to be in pixels.
So forever, every pixel, I don't know.
You know what percentage of Pi really want to go.
I'm going to tune that to something reasonable, whatever feels right
for that motion and
Oops.
I am at that.
Okay.
Game mode.
World's World mode.
Last maspeedy, it's debug.
I guess I'll call it.
Last must be that.
So, in theory, now we should be able to sort of do this and you can
see that we can now do this, but I have to tune that and also get the
directionality.
Right.
I guess.
I don't depends on how I want to orbit the world here.
I guess I want that.
I probably want the, why inverted?
I don't know.
That's hard to say.
It's always a preference issue.
But I definitely want slower.
There we go.
no, I think I like the why the way it was
And again that focal length.
Feels a little weird to me.
So I'm just going to play with that a little bit, just to see what the
difference is if we if we change that focal length a little bit
That feels a little, that feels a little better to me in terms of
what's going on there.
I'm going to take a look at some focal lengths, just to see what
happens there.
So, let's say we change it to two.
Did you see how much more eccentricity there is?
Like, there's so much more like sort of
Warping there and I like it better with less I think as my opinion,
right?
I just like that looks a little that looks more same to me in terms of
Of how much of the world is getting getting fit in there, right?
All right, so that's really all I wanted.
Out of that anyway.
And the reason for that is like, right next weekend.
What we're going to do is we're going to come through and you can see,
everything is rendering in a flat plane here.
And that flat plane is not really how we want things.
Because in order to start z-buffering, we need these objects to
actually be kind of floating up in the air, a little bit depending on
the circumstances.
But the other thing that we need is we need for them to be.
Oriented to the camera properly and we need them to have Z values set
so that they will properly include each other and all sorts of other
stuff like that.
So in order to see what we have actually specified in those terms, I
need to be able to like set a debug camera here that can rotate
around.
And so we probably will need to do what we did before with the debug
offset where we can zoom in and out.
Right.
We want to do something like that with a debug camera.
Where
The game will be looking at the camera and thinking it's one thing so
that it's setting all of its Sprites based on that.
But then we will then go and use also a debug camera offset which we
can set separately that does the this sort of offsetting so we can
look that way.
All the Sprites will still aligned themselves to the other camera
where the where the game supposed to be viewed from and then we can
use this debug right.
And in fact, since I have about six or seven minutes yet if that makes
sense.
I probably at this point we'll go and just add that that notion of the
debug Camera Part in, I think
yeah, so what I want to do there is to say like okay the debug camera
inside the render group,
Whenever we're doing that setting, we need sort of a way of the, of
the user thinking, the cameras, one thing, but us thinking the
cameras, something else.
And so what we want to do there is say, yeah, when we do this push,
right?
And we and we sort of do like last froch there, right?
We also want to store like last
Traffic a how we would say this.
So we want in addition to last projection, we also want sort of the
notion that people can get the camera that they're actually using last
user prods and like last actual project, something like that.
If that yeah if that makes sense.
And then we can put in that sort of debug camera
I'm not sure how we want to do this, I'll be honest.
Maybe I won't do this today.
Maybe I'll do this.
Once we actually have that in there.
Because I feel like we need.
Yeah, I am not going to do it yet.
I think, what I'll do instead is, we'll just make it.
So that here we can also do a thing where it's like,
This way, we can have the ability to zoom in and out as well.
It seems good.
So that would not be in proportion to pie for any particular reason
obviously.
And there's some stuff that we probably would want to do here as well.
This is one of those.
This is one of the differential equations situations.
That won't quite work.
We'll talk about this a bit later.
Alright, so what I want to do here is I guess I won't try to correct
for the the speed stuff, but what I want to do here is have a way to
like bring the camera closer or further from where it's supposed to
be.
So you can see that we've got that debug camera offset value that
we're using here.
And what I want to do is I want to have a way of interacting with that
basically, to to move it further.
Or closer.
So we want camera offset to be.
That value.
But then we want
the ability to take camera off set and add to it.
A debug value for dollying in and out.
I'm going to move this up to the top because this is actually the
value that I wanted to work with.
So I'm going to actually also do something here and I'll talk to you
about what that is in a second.
It's kind of like a poor man's differential equation here and we can
talk about that in a moment.
So let's go ahead and go over to
the place where this stuff was stored and add ourselves, a debug
camera dolly in place there and let's get
In there.
There we go.
And I think
that should be all we need.
So, I think now, yeah, I can zoom, right?
I can rotate around, which is what I wanted and, you know, we can zoom
in and see stuff clearly.
And yeah, that's all we really need their so, that's all good.
And that's nice because we can zoom in and see what we want to see and
all that other goodness.
I suppose that's probably a little bit backwards as well, because we
want to get closer as the mouse goes up.
All right?
So in this case, I want to talk about this here just really quickly.
Like I said apartment, differential equation, so suppose that I did
this, the same way I was doing rotation, right?
So here is me doing it the same as doing rotation, where we've got
just the zoom, you know, and I can zoom in here.
And what you can see is like as I move the mouse in here, like okay,
it's tuned.
Okay for that, right?
But as I get further away, you can see that.
I'm moving the camera.
I'm like the same Mouse amount is like hardly moving the camera at
all.
You know what I'm saying?
The reason for that is fairly obvious.
The further away, I moved from something.
The less the same amount of movement will the less effect.
The same amount of movement will have, you know, this is true because
Cuz for example if I am standing somewhere and I'm looking at
something right in front of me this monitor for example and I take one
step backwards.
It gets much smaller in my field of view.
If I instead look out the window at a building like way in the
distance, off in Seattle somewhere and I take a step backwards its
size doesn't change at all right.
But since I happen to know in the game where I'm looking I know the
focal point is a particular point nations--and, the focal point.
I know the
Location we're looking at, right?
Where we're aiming the camera at I'm rotating around that.
I know how far away it is.
What I usually like to do to make camera controls more usable, is to
make the amount that I move be proportional to how far away I am.
So, once I get further away, I just will move more.
So at the amount of Zoom appears, relatively constant to the user,
even though we're moving the camera by drastically different amounts.
So what I do is I just multiplied by the distance away.
And then when I run it, now, you can see it's fairly uniform through
the whole degree, right?
And even when you get close in, it's not touchy, right?
It's still the same nice amount and if it's a little too much, you can
always just tune it down like maybe
Is a little better but that tuning constant now is is, is clean and
works through the whole range.
So you don't have to have it really sort of ugly.
This used to really make me grumpy in 3D packages like Max and Maya.
They didn't do that.
And so, you'd end up zooming in on something and you'd be here and you
want to zoom in a little more and rather than it being nice like this,
it would jump, it would just zoom to nothing you'd be like, go right
inside the object because you even just one pixel was this.
Huge increment in Z, right?
But as long as you always use the distance to the thing, you're
looking at to modify it you get a really nice clean zoom and that's
the way I think you should do it.
The reason I called it a poor man's differential equation is because
if you think about what's happening here, we're taking a value which
is the the distance away from the camera and we're modifying it using
itself.
Write the equation for the change in the dolly uses the
Value for the dolly in that equation.
Right here it is.
And so what happens is this is only instantaneously correct and the
fact that we're not
The fact that we're not sort of doing an actual differential equation.
There means that for one pixel of movement, we get one result for two
pixels of movement.
We will get a different result, then we would have gotten if we did to
one pixel movements of the mouse, right?
Which is kind of incorrect.
That's not probably what we want.
So what we really should do here is work out the differential
equation.
We're not going to do that with zero time left, and we probably don't
need to do that for a little bit until a little bit later.
Anyway, but that is just an
To folks out there, this should be an equation in e0 that would
produce the correct results.
No matter what mouse you did but that's a separate.
Okay, a slim Seer posts, a very good question and even though he posts
a very good question, he said he's preface it with sorry for being a
dummy.
However, I this you are in no way being a dummy.
This is a very good question.
It says, in the camera transform in 3D games.
As far as I've been watching tutorials, there's something called an up
Vector.
What is the purpose of it?
And do we have it in handmade hero since it's a
2D game.
I guess it's different.
Your explanations have been wonderful.
And I would love it if you could explain it, and also thanks for doing
EU friendly streams Kappa.
Since I read it in HEX.
Check, it's funny.
I always see Kappa written out instead of having the little face.
Anyway, no, that's a great question and the answer.
There is we absolutely do now have it in handmade hero because we are
using a fully 3D camera.
Even though our game is 2D just because I decided I wanted the full 3d
flexibility there and so we absolutely do have a thing that isn't up
Vector.
We're just not using it prescriptively and I'll explain exactly what
that means.
The reason that we didn't cover it when we were doing this, this
modification pasch is because we kind of already have enough, Vector
defined implicitly and I chose to use a rotational definition for
the camera is and so will will will sort of go through the other side
of that now.
So you can get the perspective on what that means.
Why would I care?
What an up Vector is?
What is you know, what's the deal there, right?
Okay, so when we need to define a camera in 3D, the answer to your
question is in some sense that you already understand what an up
Vector is?
We just didn't call it that, right?
You've already seen it laced.
Through all of the stuff we've been doing, we just never called it
out.
And so, all we really need to do now is to call it out and show which
part of this whole process it was and then you won't have to worry
wonder where that effector is coming in.
Right.
So remember what we said was we've got a camera transform.
In fact you know what, let me try to do this in the same word I did it
before.
I think I did it like this.
So remember, this, we have sort of this space where everything is
aligned to something, right?
And you know maybe we've got like I suppose, I was saying we have a
specifying a triangle or something, or maybe this is a camera or
whatever else.
Right?
But we have objects and they have a native coordinate system that
we're thinking about them being defined in.
And then we have some idea of them being placed out in the world
somewhere in some other way.
Right, their origin is displaced.
This is 000 cure, but here is some position that they have, right?
And so you know, this is how we might think of this, right?
And we talked about the object, transform is the thing that goes from
some rest space, where things are defined out into the world where we
have placed it, or into any coordinate system we want.
But we've described its placement in that coordinate system by a
transform, right?
And in our case that's typically the
But, you know, you could imagine having subspaces or intermediate
spaces or whatever you are in charge of how you define your own
spaces, you just have to describe describe transforms in those phases,
right?
And so, in our case, we've got a world space.
So we describe these X Y and Z axes in the world space, we describe
this point relative to the origin of the world space and, and there it
is.
Right?
And and more specifically, I guess we don't really even
Process.
We use Sims face, right?
That local, simulation region, where everything centered around.
The Simulation Center is really our space.
It's not World space for say, because World face would be the whole
game.
We actually don't use that coordinate system, right?
Because we map everything into a simulation region and do the
simulation there.
But anyway, that's the object, transform places things into some
space.
We care about the camera transforms, the opposite takes things, and
puts them back into a camera space.
Where we know that we are looking down the negative Z axis.
Taxes.
Right?
So curious where everything is that.
We can see anything that's back behind here.
We can't see right?
There's a clip playing an ear clip playing somewhere like you know,
maybe right here a little bit slightly, you know, 0.2 - down the Z
Axis or something.
There's a clip playing there.
We can't see anything in front of it.
There's a far clip.
Playing way out in the distance, we can't see past or something.
So there's a little bit of that but otherwise everything back behind
that XY plane.
We can see right
And that's our camera transform.
So now the question becomes what is the up Vector?
Well, the answer is that the up Vector, is this Vector right here, in
the case of the camera transform, right?
Why is that?
Because when we construct the camera transform, what we do is we
provide a world space, placement Matrix basically right for the camera
and we're sort of inverting that to get the camera transform.
So we have the cameras placement which is where it is in the world.
We have the cameras axes in the world.
Z.
The, oops, that should have been an X, the X, the Y, and the Z, right?
And then we're making a transform that takes everything in the world.
So all the stuff that was out here, and we're moving it, so that it's
all right here, right?
We're kind of like, transforming everything back in the cameras face
and to do that, we need those axes, those axes correspond to real
things.
In the cameras, conceptualization of the world, the Z axis is the
depth axis, right?
And it's the viewing Direction.
It's the direction we're viewing in is as
Z axis.
So you could call this like the view direction if you wanted to write.
We have a right Vector, that's the x-axis, right?
Because that maps to this, that maps to write in screen space.
So this is the right vector and furthermore, we have a vector that
maps to what is up in screen space.
That is the y axis.
That is the up Vector, right?
For the camera.
So conceptually speaking.
We actually already sort of know what the up Vector is.
It is the y axis of the camera, right?
That camera object.
Its y-axis is the up Vector, right?
And we use that effector to create the inverse transform by stuffing
the up Vector into the second row of the camera, transform right into
the wairau.
Not the column because that would be an odd transform.
The wairau.
That is where we stuff that up Vector, and that
That dot product with that Vector transforms things into the correct
space.
So that now, this Vector is the
Actual Cardinal Y axis which is what we need for that projection,
right?
So this is the up Vector.
But that's not the complete story.
The reason that's not the complete story is because you then would
very naturally.
Ask well, why are people talking about that in 3D?
What do they really mean by up Vector?
Why is that coming up?
Pun intended I suppose and the answer is because of how you might
construct, a camera transform, if you don't already have the camera
object itself, right?
And let me tell you what I mean by that, this picture of the world is
very sensible, right?
It's saying I've got an object somewhere in the world, right?
And I've got a camera somewhere in the world, that's a set of axes
that look like this.
Right?
And I know that I'm viewing down the negative Z axis of this object
and I know it's got an origin.
So if I have this already I know I can make the camera transform that
views, the world, whatever these other objects in the world, are all
the objects that are there.
Whatever they are.
I don't care right?
I can view all of them at this camera transform.
And I know what the up Vector is already implicitly because it's all
defined for me.
I have all this stuff already, ready.
Right?
But where people start to talk about the up Vector, more explicitly
in.
Where I'm sure you've been seeing it is because what if I didn't have
that, what if I just had a point in the world that I wanted to view
from and I didn't know anything else, right?
I had no idea what where the axes were, what the axes were right.
So imagine instead of this nice picture where everything is clean
here.
Suppose I don't have any of these access.
All I have is pee, right?
That's all I've got.
And I'm trying to view the world using that knowledge, right?
How would I construct this camera transform?
Well, I know I need a bunch of things.
Okay, I need to be able to produce three axes from nothing, right?
So the question is what is the something I can have?
That will allow me to produce those axes.
The point where the camera is is known.
So, oftentimes when people say is well, okay,
I need something to look at.
So give me a Target, right?
And I mean, I'll just write that is T.
So give me a Target point.
Now I know the vector to the Target point, right?
What does that?
Give me?
Well, that gives me my Z axis, right, because I know the Z axis is
what I'm looking down.
So, all I need to do to find my Z axis.
In this construction, is say the Z axis, right?
Is just going to be
Direction.
I was viewing in, right?
I want it to go backwards because again, I'm looking down the negative
Z so I really want P.
Minus t, which gives me this Vector here, right?
And that's almost a z axis but it's not unit length, right?
I want to be unit length, so I need P.
Minus t and I just need to divide by the length of P minus t, right?
So it's normalized, that's the Z axis.
Good, right.
That's good.
Off to a good start.
Problem is where my other two axes going to come from, right?
Where am I?
Other 2x is going to come from.
Once I have the Z axis, I do know the plane in which the other two
axes must be, right?
Because the other two axes have to fall into this plane, right?
The the dot product of those two other vectors with Z must be 0,
right?
Because it is orthogonal this camera Matrix, right?
Remember from back, when it's orthogonal, what does that mean, right?
It means that when I draw these out, when I'm looking at these
There's right angles between every last one of them, right?
Every last one of these guys,
Is orthogonal to the other.
No, I'm saying.
So that means that, if I know the Z axis, I know the plane in which
the X and y-axis exist, but what I don't know.
Is there spin?
Okay, so I know they have to be in this plane but they could look like
that.
You know, they could look like this.
They could look like that, right.
I know they're at right angles to each other.
So once I knew one of them I could find the other one.
But if I don't know, either of them, there's an angle that I don't
know.
I just don't know how they're spun.
So I can make up an X and Y axis, but it would be any random skew of
that.
And if I'm trying to define a camera, I don't want it to be.
Tilted.
Because think about what that angle is.
What's that angle, right?
I've got the Z, I'm looking down the Z.
I got my X and Y axis.
What is that?
Angle its role, right?
So, if I don't pick the right role for my camera, I'm going to be
viewing the world in some totally random way.
And of course, role is an actual parameter.
We want to control, sometimes you want to view the world rotated.
So, what that means is, we need one extra piece of information to
Define.
Fine.
What the X and y-axes look like relative to the Z axis.
And that is where the up Vector comes in.
There's more than one way you can define an up Vector.
But it's basically a way of specifying what those other two axes
should be, once we can find the Z axis because we can always find the
Z axis.
If we've got a Target, the only time you can't find a tax rate of
fire, is it?
Sitting right on top of the target, but hey guess what?
You can't.
Look at something if you're infinitely close to it, right?
If you're right on top of it.
So that's usually, okay, write that degeneracy should never actually
occur in any practical scenario because it means you're doing
something, you fundamentally can't do.
So you could just if around that and just set the camera to some, you
know, known identity configuration or something.
So what people often say when they say effector is, they could mean
multiple things, one thing they might mean about an up, Vector is just
some vector.
Which says a sense of up which can be used to generate the X and
y-axes that's one thing they can mean by it.
So it can be a sense of up Vector.
And I'll tell you what that means in a second.
The other thing, they might mean is just no, I actually need the
y-axis, right?
So if they say we actually are specifying the y axis as the up to the
camera, all that's doing is saying, hey.
All right, I'm going to tell you what that y Vector is.
So now that you know that you
Trivially produce the x-axis, how you can produce it with the cross
product.
I don't remember if we've covered that on handmade hero we could cover
that will cover that maybe later.
I don't want to talk right now, because we're a bit, we're out of
time.
But with the cross product, the cross product lets you do is produce a
vector, that's orthogonal to two other vectors, right?
So basically, if I say the x axis, cross, the y-axis equals the Z
axis, right?
This cross product here.
What that does is it says, if you take two vectors and cross them, you
get the vector that comes out of their plane, in the order of the
Cross, via the right-hand rule.
So, if I read in this order, if I say x, cross y, I am imagining
rolling my fingers from X to Y and seeing, what direction?
The thumb comes out.
That's the Z axis, right?
So the cross product, will find those for you, which means that if I
know that X cross y, equals z i can
Also do the same thing if I specify a z and a why I know that y cross
Z will equal x y because I roll my fingers from y to Z thumb points,
out the x axis.
So y cross Z equals x, right?
So if you were to specify the up, Vector, and that is actually why,
then I know why cross equals x?
I now have all my axes, I found the Z with this equation.
I found the X with this equation and the why was specified.
So I
Ever needed to find it at all, right, so that's one way, another way
of doing it is has a adds an additional degeneracy, but it makes it a
lot easier to use.
Remember, in this case, what that means is the user whoever's using
this camera code has to track the up Vector the entire time.
So, as they move the Target around, if they pair pitching down on the
Target that y vector,
Has to be pitched properly to match the pitch of the target.
So it's placing extra work on them, so it doesn't really necessarily
help.
Give you the whole cloth version of just give me a point, give me a
Target and that's all I want.
Generate the camera out of it.
So, another way people, use the term up actor is to talk about a sense
of up Vector, what a sense of up Vector is it's just saying what
direction is up in general, but in the general case, what do I mean?
When I say up, right?
And so in
Are in our world, that's the Z axis, right?
Our general sense of up as world.
Z-axis, it's 0, 0, 1.
That's our sense of up, Vector.
How does that help us in this case?
Well, the reason that it helps us in this case is because our sense of
up Vector gives us another Vector.
We can use to cross to produce the x-axis, and then the y-axis.
All right, how does that work again?
I'm sorry, we're a little short on time here, so sexplanations little
bit truncated.
Hopefully it's helping.
So, what happens here, when we take a look,
How were viewing things?
Right is I have a point in the world and I'm viewing towards a Target
in the world, right?
And my Z axis is coming out this way, which I know I can find question
is, how do I find the other axes?
Well, I know that, the the right Vector must be pointing out here
somewhere.
The question is, how do I find with that, right?
Vector is well, if you imagine the world,
Space looking like this.
Let's say.
I guess that's not really our world, is it?
That's more like our older.
Maybe that's more like our old.
So if you imagine the world looking like this, right?
And I'm trying to look down on something here and so I end up in a
situation where, you know, I'm looking down on something like this.
So I'm up here, here's my camera position.
Here's the Target, right?
And I'm looking down on it.
Well, I want to be able to find what my x-axis is here for the camera.
And I don't know the y axis, I don't really know anything, right?
I don't know anything other than this one Z axis here that I can
compute.
Well, if I was to have an idea of what should be up, right?
So we're basically saying there's a there's a standard way that the
user tends to want to view the world and they want up to
Like up.
So in general I don't want to roll my view at.
All right, I want to produce a view where up is up.
And so no matter how I'm viewing things, I'm always still going to
keep my orientation as upward as possible, right?
So I'm never going to intentionally do this when I'm creating these
these views, right?
Then what I can do is say well if I've got a general sense of up
Vector which in this case is z i can
Imagine taking.
A cross product of that up, Vector, right?
With the Z axis, that will give me my ex for the camera.
Right?
Why?
Because those two are in a plane with each other.
Remember, the tilt of the camera is just how high, however, high up.
I'm going to look down on something.
If I take a vector that's pointed upwards, and I'll have my Vector,
that's tilted when I cross those two, I'm going to get something.
Thing that goes out to the right.
Based on my view direction, right, with no role because those are both
in a plane and I'm producing the vector, the comes out of that plane,
right?
So what I do is I take my up Vector
And I cross it with my Z.
And that gives you my ex right now, I have a z and an X Direction.
So, I can just do the process one more time to get my y, right?
Because I know again, from looking at the diagram
If I wanted to produce the y-axis, I could simply take Z cross X.
Remember, curl, your hands from the Z axis, to the x axis, and the Y
should come out the thumb, right.
I can just do Z cross X and that will give me my y so that gives me
the complete equation.
Right?
I compute Z first, then I compute X get using the up Vector and then I
compute y, given the the Z Vector.
I'm sorry.
Given the X Factor I just solved.
Now the cross product is not normalized.
It's actually proportional to the sine of the angle between the
vectors.
So technically this is not actually the case.
The X Vector is actually up cross Z over the length of up cross Z
Right?
Just like this one.
So these two have to be renormalized.
That makes sense.
But that gives us the complete set of equations for generating.
The the look at this is typically called a look at Matrix.
Or a look at camera that gives us the complete set of equations for a
look at there they are, right?
The Z is p minus t over over the length of P.
Minus t.
The x is up cross Z over length of up cross Z.
So, just normalize again and then Y is z cross X.
And of course, those two are already normal vectors.
So given that their normal vectors, you don't have to renormalize
them.
because this
There or they're orthogonal to each other and their unit length.
So, the equation for the cross product apis come out to length one
anyway, but they go so sorry for the relatively compressed
explanation.
Again is trying to finish up.
Does that make sense?
to whoever asked,
Ace Flames here.
Okay.
Sounds like that was good.
All right, so I don't have time for any other questions.
I'll just quickly, scan to make sure that there are no other questions
that are like super important questions that need to be answered right
now.
Would it be weird to change the focal length as the pitch changes or
should the focal?
Length always stay constant?
The focal length should always stay constant.
If the focal length doesn't stay constant.
You get this effect
This is what happens when you change the focal length.
So if you want that effect you can definitely change the focal length.
That's called a dolly zoom in cinematography.
But basically what it is is when you change the focal length of the
lens, while the camera is moving, if you match the two, you get that
sort of background compression change, but if you do it during pitch,
it would make the world stretch out as you pitched it would look like
that.
And if you want that effect,
Maybe you do, but it's probably going to be noticeable User.
It's not going to be something they wouldn't notice.
I don't think unless it was a very small pitch change perhaps but, you
know, maybe maybe you want that out now,
Alright, and then minor point, you called your variables pitch, an
orbit should probably be pitch and yaw.
Well, you know, I don't really like it to be y'all usually because
y'all makes me think of going like that, not like that.
So that's why I typically call it orbit.
I really want better terms for those.
I want it to be like
A word for orbital pitch and orbital yaw, which maybe, maybe the term
should be orbital pitching Arbol you, I don't know.
But that's why I never really liked the names of those if that makes
sense.
Anyway, all right, so let's go ahead and wrap it up.
Thank you everybody for joining me for this episode of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org and it comes to the source
code so you can experiment with it yourself.
We also have a forum site, you can go to if you want to ask questions
a patreon page, if you want to support the video series, schedule bot.
If you would like to know when we're going to be live and an episode
guide that you can use to catch up on past episodes, that's it for
this week.
I'll be back next weekend with more.
Handmade hero.
We will go ahead.
Start to try and use our Z buffer.
That we worked so hard to enable in our 3D pipeline now so we can
start to have sorting without actually having to have sorting so
that's about it.
Hope to see you back here for that until then have fun programming and
I'll see y'all on the internet.
Take it easy everyone.