Of All Times.
There we go.
And then we'll get this party started here.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero day.
32 of the show where we create an entire game from scratch using
absolutely nothing but our own bear typing fingers.
So far.
We have basically created a win32 platform layer and we are in the
midst of Designing our engine architecture.
We're doing that by writing some exploratory, code on how we want to
create sort of our tilemap.
Delayed system.
And then we're going to be dealing with how we want to kind of do
animations and rendering in that sort of stuff.
So we're kind of an exploratory phase right now, and we've got a bunch
of stuff to do.
So, I'm going to try and dive into that relatively quickly.
But first, let me say the obligatory, if you pre-ordered the game and
are trying to follow along at home with the source code.
You will note that today is today 32.
So you want to unzip day, 31 source, code out of that giant zip file,
that has all the days in it.
So go ahead and unzip day, 31, and then you will have the source code
that is exactly the same.
Let's go that I have and then starting with now.
Now, if you're anything like me, then basically you thought last
night's stream was absolutely unproductive and Meandering.
I was basically talking about all the stuff that we had to do and I
did not actually really get to do anything and I don't know about you
guys, but that always kind of leaves a bitter taste in my mouth.
And so hopefully tonight we will be able to actually do some of the
stuff that we were talking about so we won't have to go to bed feeling
like a loser.
ER, because that's never fun as you know, anyway.
Let's take a look at what we were doing.
Essentially we had gotten to the point on Friday, actually, where I
was sort of exploring how to do these tilemap things, and we ended up
in a place where we had this sort of concept of a canonical position
that a tile Map X and a Tom app, why that looked up into a set of tile
maps and then a tile X and a tile.
Why?
That we're tile like the tile indices inside those tile maps.
And then finally there was a relative offset and what I was thinking
over the
And then what I explained yesterday was that, really?
This is kind of just too much work.
There's really no need for both of these because we don't need 64 bits
of tile addressing here.
Like we've got really what we could do is use a single 32-bit integer
to store the tile X and Tau Y.
And just assume that the tilemap part is some portion of that integer,
the High bits of that integer.
And so, what I really wanted to do is I really wanted to turn these,
you know, both of those sort of into this sort of thing where they
were.
So, instead of having all of these, I wanted to get rid of these guys
up here and I wanted to switch to just using one unsigned version for
both the tile X on the tile Y and then this relative stuff would just
be relative to whatever the tile was.
Now, I'm not 100% sure about this.
I'm pretty sure about this part.
Although there are some some trade-offs, but I'm not sure about what
these should be real.
You summon someone on the stream.
Yesterday actually was talking about the fact that could we make them
relative to the tile Pages themselves.
The things that are sort of going to store the tiles in them in chunks
and I think there could be good reasons why we might want to do that.
However, I don't really know offhand.
What the right thing to do here is and so I'm going to proceed
assuming that these are relative to the tile and we'll just kind of go
from there.
And if it turns out that as we kind of get a little further that it
looks like maybe it would be smarter to make them relative to the tile
page then we will.
And again that's exactly why we're doing this code.
We're trying to explore and see what the right design decisions are
rather than making a bunch of design, decisions up front and then
finding out that they're wrong later.
So we're trying to go, you know, sort of a nice.
Low build from the ground up kind of approach.
That makes everything work properly instead of a sort of make
decisions and then Implement a ton of stuff and then only later find
out that it's busted.
So, what I want to do is I want to drive towards this because I just
felt this was a little too excessive.
But of course, we have to kind of figure out how we would actually
make this work.
Now if we go back and look, in fact, I can sort of, I can sort of say,
you know, make these into something here, that won't compile it all.
You can sort of see that we've got lots of places, right?
Where we are using these
There's just tons and tons and tons and tons of places that were, you
know, sort of rely on this stuff because we wrote the code necessary
to sort of, do all the tile map positioning and stuff.
So, what we would like to do essentially is sort of see what how we if
we can sort of move that code over into something that would that
would be working with a new way of doing things where you're always
talking about these canonical positions.
Now what I want to point out here, this is the first time we've kind
of done.
This is this is a uh,
Large step.
So, typically when you're doing architecture work like this, you've
got small steps and you've got large steps and most of the steps that
we did before.
We're like compression steps.
They were they were small steps of like taking something that worked
and just sort of making, you know, pulling out some common code and
reusing it right?
But what we're doing here is we're reconsidering one of the ways to do
something because we think we found a more efficient way.
And so this is a little bit of a larger step in the code base, right?
It's, it's very much sort of a lateral movement rather than
In something where we're just kind of going to do a trivial pull out
of something.
And so this is a little bit of a larger step and they are a little bit
harder to make, but you shouldn't be afraid of making them.
That's why we made this code, really simple, really flexible, really
easy and basic is because we want to have the freedom to change it
around like this, and we don't want a lot of stuff baked in, so it's
okay.
And we haven't spent a lot of time to bugging things.
We haven't spent a lot of time optimizing anything.
So it's okay to go in and delete some of that code, because
This was just code to play around with and that's okay.
And what you would ideally like to do as much as possible is always
try to.
Make as many large moves as you can when the code is sort of like
early.
And that not that much time has been spent on it because then you're
not losing that much work.
So that's that's this is exactly the kind of time when we want to make
these kind of moves, okay?
So, if I take a look here at the stuff that we've gotten, we have that
get canonical position thing, right?
And the thing about get canonical position, was that essentially we
were using it in a lot of places because we had backed ourselves into
a corner using pixels for everything.
Right?
We're constantly in this this sort of situation where we have a, we
have just pixels coming in and like for the player.
For example, if we look at out at how we restoring the player,
We are constantly having this problem of storing, like okay, there's a
tile Map X and a Tom app, Y and then there's the offset relative, the
tile map and all that sort of stuff.
But if we were to actually sort of move, if you know, could we sort of
start to trim out this code by just moving to storing these canonical
positions directly, right?
And so one question that I have maybe right off the bat is, could I do
that step first without actually changing to the 32-bit thing.
Could I maybe do that step first as an easy?
Step towards moving towards the 32-bit thing, like move, everything
over to using the canonical positions first.
So what would happen if I did that?
What would happen if I went in here and said, all right.
And as you can see, we have it to do here that I even said, could this
be using canonical position?
So, if I have canonical position, that's just, you know, player key or
something, you know, where's the player, right?
If I have that?
What would I do here?
What could I do?
What would the code look like?
If it always was working with that instead.
So instead of initializing.
In the player X in the player.
Why directly?
Now, we've got a player P and it's one of these canonical positions.
So the canonical position has it at the tile Map X.
We know that's just going to, we were just starting him off on that
initial.
Tilemap that one up in the corner, right?
So Tom maps, map X tilemap.
Why?
And and then the the tile X and the tile, why?
We're in here as well.
Is this?
So the tie relative exito who we were, or we had already done it so
that it was relative to the corner of the tile.
I guess.
So, that's kind of handy.
So, basically, what we can say there is all right.
The tile relative X, you know, is maybe something something sort of
trivial.
I don't know.
Just, let's, we'll talk about that.
And in one second later since we haven't really touched that much, but
let's say that this is, I don't know it's five because this is all
still in pixels.
We haven't actually fixed fix things.
Yet, remember I talked yesterday about wine?
Fixing the not be in pixels.
We haven't actually done that yet.
All right, so, you know, maybe we set it to the tile X and Tau Y is 3
3.
I don't actually know what's in 33.
Let's see.
That's 0 0, that's 1 1, that's 2 to that's 33.
Well, it should be open.
So that seems like a reasonable place to stick our player down for
now.
So I'm going to go ahead and compile that and that should initialized
properly, I think.
So then when we do the get tilemap, now, we're just talking about
player p.
Tilemap x and player P.
Tilemap.
Why?
In battle get the tile map out of the world and let's see what else
we've got here.
This is basically just adding.
Yeah.
So this is fine.
This is saying player X is not a member of game State.
That's fine because we now have the tile relative X and the tile
relative.
Why of the player we can add the
T.
So basically we have this motion Vector that before we were adding to
just the players offset from the corner of a tile map.
Now, we're just going to add it to the offset of them in the tile,
right?
That's all we're going to do.
And now we don't have to create raw positions anymore because we just
we already have a canonical position.
Right?
And what we can do is say, Okay, so the canonical position that's
going to be player left, for example is going to be equal to game
State player P and similarly the tile relative X.
There we go.
The tile relative there as well.
So, basically, all I'm doing is converting everything over to using
those canonical positions.
Right now.
I've got the game State player P there as well.
So now, I basically construct a canonical positions.
But of course, they're not really all that canonical at this point
because the player left, and the player right in and the player
position for that matter.
Have had basically movement done to them.
So their tile relative X in there Tower relative.
Why we may now be outside the
boundaries of the tile that they should have been on, right?
And so I've got two ways that I could handle.
That one is that I could call a function that re canonicalize has
them, right?
And the other is, I could go ahead and just make a function that does
the Delta.
So that from then, on basically, instead of just cold adding stuff to
it.
I could go ahead and do these as by calling function.
That would automatically re canonicalize.
I think I probably want both of them if that makes sense.
So I'm going to
Start with the re canonicalized one.
So the so basically get canonical position.
This guy here, the get canonical position.
I think that will basically become that will basically come a function
that just re canonicalize has things.
Because since everything will now be in canonical positions.
We don't really need to pass a raw position anymore.
We can just pass a canonical position and the whole job of this
function will basically just be to turn a canonical position to turn
something that's been
When mutated that's had its relative X relative.
Why messed with it?
Will basically turn it into something that's canonical again, right?
So just to make clear what I'm doing here is, we're storing stuff
right now.
We're storing it to the corner.
I think, I want to change the story it to the center.
But that's a separate issue.
Again.
Just things that things that I think about.
As I'm going through, we're storing things on a tile.
This is an individual tile, not a tile map tile map is you know is
there's tiles, you know, tiles tiles tiles.
We have my particular.
Thailand.
We say that the player is on this tile, we are storing their relative
position based on where the corner is and based on what I'm saying
here is, well, if we mutate that at all, if we change, if we make
additions, or subtractions to that offset from the upper corner of the
tile, if we offset it too much, like we offset it.
So that it's in pointing all the way out here.
Or if it's pointing back here, or if it was up here right now, the
tile X and tile.
Why for that canonical position are wrong, right?
So what we want to be able to do is say, okay.
We'd like,
Like to be able to make a just a random adjustment to this to this
vector.
And then say, hey, could you now re canonicalize it, make it back into
a proper chemical position where the tile X and Y, actually reflect
the tile X and Y, that you're in, and the tile relative X and Y are
going to be less than the boundary of one tile, right?
So I just need a function that's going to do that before.
What we were doing is we're calling a raw position, something that had
mechanical as yet.
I just want to always work with these canonical positions.
And then, in fact, we can even get rid of the name canonical, we can
just call the world positions.
So we're just
How to move towards that state Again by again, we're just trying to
slowly sort of work our way up to something that we think is, is right
and good.
So what I want to do here is say all right.
I've got the tile Map X, tilemap, why?
Those are going to copy across.
In fact, what I can do is just say the result equals the pose
immediately.
I don't have to do this flooring anymore essentially because I can, I
can sort of take a look at.
Well, I will want to do a flooring of some kind, just not.
Not anything like this.
So what I want to do here is I want to say, okay.
In fact, this is kind of neat.
Let me talk about this for a second.
To, you'll notice that in here.
We had baked in the world upper left in the world, upper the upper
left X in the upper left.
Y.
And that was because we were trying to turn pixel locations back into
World locations by storing everything such that they're in World
locations in the first place right by storing the player relative to a
tile.
We no longer have to worry about what the offset was on the screen.
And so, we're almost in doing this mutation that we're doing to the
code right now and doing this, this
Step.
We're actually getting for free.
Something that we were saying we had to do, which is start to get away
from pixels.
We're already taking one step towards that, so it's kind of another
sign that we're on the right track, right?
When these things start to fall out.
So the fact that we're getting rid of that entirely is pretty good
there, right?
So basically do they
Okay.
So basically what we can look at here is we can sort of start to say.
All right, what?
Actually is the problem with a canonical position that has become
uncanonical eyes, right?
The rail, X and the rail, why will not be within a tile boundary base
plate.
So if I say pose tile relex, I get, I know in my world definition
here.
I essentially have a tile size in pixels, right?
And that tile size and
Whistles.
I'm basically saying that my tile relative EX.
For my guy should be between 0 and tile side and pixels.
If it's not, then I need to make sure that it is.
And I need to basically break it up into whatever the part that would
have been within the boundary and then some offset to the tile X and
the tile why to move the actual index of the tiles.
Again, this is just saying we have a tile ex-anti.
Wow, that tells us which Tower in.
So if we are, you know, less than zero or if we are greater than one
tile.
We have to start moving the tile X or the tile y in the direction, you
know, however many steps it would need to to make it so that we're on
the right tile again.
So in order to do that, basically what I want to do is I want to take
I want to take the tile, the, the tile relative X for the position and
I want to divide it by the tile side in pixels, right?
That would tell me if that number is a number between 0 and 1, then
we're all good.
Then we know that we haven't gone more than one tile in a direction.
If that number is less than 0, right?
Then that would mean that I have gone, you know, back out the the,
the, the back of the tile and if
That tile was greater than 1.
Then that means that I went too far outside the tile in the positive
direction, right?
So those are the two cases for me exiting outside of the tile.
So what I'd like to do is figure out how many tiles I went, right?
So basically I can say here.
All right, let's let's take this.
This post.
I'll relics and there's a couple things.
I don't want to spend too much time thinking about this because again,
we're going to make two more mutations here.
First of all, we're going to move out of pixels and then I might want
to change like I said to Center relative addressing so I'm just going
to go ahead and make this one mutation.
Ation here.
I'm going to make it in as dumb away as possible basically.
And I think the way that I want to do that is, I essentially want to
make a function that's going to do the canonicalization, sort of, in,
for one coordinate system because they're sort of separate, right?
So I want to do like canonicalize coordinate, right?
And I'm going to pass it, the pose.
Where is my canonical post here?
I'm going to pass it.
The the tile.
Where are we here?
I'm going to pass it.
The tile X and the tile.
Why?
Right?
Oh, this is yeah, you know what?
This is going to be unfortunate to.
I wonder if we should just try to make these two steps together foof.
It's rough.
But if you think about it, I don't really feel like doing that whole
tilemap X thing either, right?
Because that's going to be a whole thing.
That's
To go away.
It's basically writing a bunch of code that we don't have to write
just to stay working with this thing in.
Well, you know, I'm going to stick with the plan.
I'll do it.
I'll do it the way that I said I was going to do it first.
And we'll just we'll go from there.
All right, so I'm going to pass it.
Basically these these fourth, the world and the three exes.
And then I'm going to have one that does the same thing with the three
wise, right?
And then I've got my canonic last chord here, which is essentially
going to do whatever it needs to do for that.
And so I think that means that I'm not gonna be able to get rid of as
much of the stuff.
I won't have to use this one, but I'm going to have to essentially
keep a lot of the stuff here that we had.
Unfortunately.
Let's see.
So
And this stuff again, we don't have to worry too much about this, I
guess because again, we're replacing it all.
But yeah, just looking at it here.
It's like, wow, what a mess.
What a mess people.
This is exactly why I say, we want to keep working on this because
it's just, there's just too much work being done for not enough pay
off.
And so it'll be kind of nice to get to the point where that's no
longer the case.
All right.
Anyway, so we're economically as the position.
We basically need to re canonicalize those coordinates.
Let's go ahead and make that beer.
Economically has coordinates.
They don't take anything and let's go ahead and grab out what this
takes.
So it takes a pointer to the world.
It takes a pointer to the tile Map X.
So that's a 32.
It takes a pointer to the tile X.
And again, it's taking pointers just because I need to modify them.
Right?
So it needs a pointer to the actual one so I can modify it.
That's all that's happening there.
Nothing.
Particularly, nothing particularly fancy.
I'm still going to work with them just as regular but
Okay.
Well, so if we're still doing it that way and we're doing the re
canonicalization, then basically, I'm going to have to stick with the
same algorithm.
We were doing before.
Just in terms of getting things working.
Thankfully we can get rid of the x's and y's part of thing here.
And instead, I can just go just using the, the tile map the tile and
the relative, right?
Okay.
So again, this is going to be basically the same all of this stuff
should be roughly the same, except I got to have to pass the World
Council.
As well.
So let's take a look here because I don't actually know which one it
will be.
Right.
Yeah, you can see.
Yeah, you can totally see that, right?
Because I've got the world count, X.
We're allowed to have different context.
And can't why?
That's another thing that we'll be able to fix is having our tile Maps
be square.
Even though this the way that we're visit viewing them isn't which
again, will be kind of nice.
Alright, so we also have to have the count, the the the tile count
basically.
And that's going to have to go in here.
Okay, so
There we go.
When I get rid of all of this stuff, we should basically be able to
Yeah, we should be able to get this down to something simpler and then
hopefully yeah, hopefully this will set us up for doing much nicer
stuff than what we were doing.
But yeah, perhaps it's a little too early to tell.
All right.
So now we want to keep our assertions in here.
That's totally fine.
These are the tile relative want to basically assert that.
The thing the the offset is going to still be in range.
At the end of the day, the tile, it was there.
So we've got the tile times the world side and pixels, got the X.
And so now we just have to kind of reconstruct these things here,
which are going to, which is going to be kind of annoying.
All right?
Okay, so I've kind of massage everything out.
All right, so we still have our floor in here that we're doing and we
have the X.
So this is flooring US based on where we are on the town map, which is
not going to be
Be particularly useful.
What we would rather do is just take a look at flooring, the tile rail
itself.
Right?
What we want to do is floor the tile rail itself.
So, basically, we're going to divide, like I was saying before by the
tile side and pixels.
We're going to floor of the tower a land that were.
Tell us how far essentially we have gone past where our tile X was
before.
And so essentially this is going to be it's not going to beat Alex.
This is going to be our X.
Offset essentially or our our, our overflow underflow.
If you will from where the tile should be, whatever that floor is
because basically if that floor, you know, 01234.
However much it is that's how far off.
That's how far from our Bay style.
We ended up being due to our tile relative offset.
Okay.
So all we really need to do then.
At that point, is we need to go ahead, It's gotta change.
Those, we need to go ahead and take whatever that offset is and we
need to add that in here.
Right?
So, whatever the offset is, we're going to offset our tile index by
that offset, right?
And then what we need to do is we need to figure out essentially,
Whatever It, Whatever the remainder was.
And we can do that again, they'll be faster ways for us to do this in
the future obviously, but yeah, we can do that again by basically
saying, okay, whatever the tile relative thing was, it's essentially
going to be, we're going to subtract out of
The tile relative that we had.
We're going to subtract out whatever the base of the tile actually
was, right.
And you can see sort of how I'm doing that here.
Don't let this fool you, right.
That is just referencing the tile that we're on.
And so all we're trying to do here is say, all right, we have a tile
relative position.
We hope that it is between 0 and the tile sided pixels, but we know
that we may have offset it so that it's outside of that range.
We want to do the floor.
So we know essentially
A number - 1 - 2 1 2 3 however, far in tiles.
We have to go that that offset, whatever, however much that offset
implies that we would have to go to get to the, to the right tile.
We're to compute that offset, add it to our tile index.
So, that now we're on the right tile, but now we have to reset our
tile relative offset so that our tile relative offset is within the
new tile that we were on.
And in order to do that.
I just want to subtract away, right?
Whatever the
The.
Oh, well, I can't quite do that.
It's actually the offset.
That's wrong.
Whatever.
The offset amount was that we computed.
We want to get rid of that from the tile from the towel relative
position, right?
Because we are already accounted for that by moving.
We move that many tiles over so we can subtract a way that many tiles
worth of pixels.
Right?
As I'm explaining all of that again, like hopefully don't have too
many bugs in their.
This is one of those routines that I wish I could concentrate on
complete.
It's just over the level of where you should be talking when you're
doing it.
But yeah, what you gonna do?
That's just how handmade hero goes.
I gotta explain it or there's no point in doing this.
Okay.
So reconnect last chords, right?
I've got a pass the tile count X here in the top count.
Why?
Like I said before oops, it's not what it is.
It's like count, count X and count wire or something like this, right?
Tilemap.
Count X.
There we go.
Tile map.
App can taste I almost there we go.
And so get canonical position.
So is world's Point empty is now just going to take a canonical
position.
Right?
And so it won't ever have to actually call that it'll just say Israel
Point empty.
It'll pass the position.
The position will just work at that point because it's already in can
pose.
So that's just fine.
We just eliminate that entirely and in fact, we can just eliminate raw
position entirely good.
So let's keep going here.
We know that we have to re canonicalize all of our positions now
because the game State player pee, right is is going to have to be re
canonicalized.
As are these guys player left equals R economically efficient.
And you can see why I say, you know, I mentioned earlier I was like, I
think I'm going to want both functions.
You can see this kind of annoying you have to remember to do this re
canonicalize after you do these offsets.
So what I'm saying is
Better if we just make a function that does the offset and does the
reconnect lies for you.
So we know we can just call that and it does the right thing.
So and I could put it to do in there as well.
To do Delta function that auto re canonicalize has
Okay, and we'll see that in a second.
But what do we do, re canonical position?
Did I actually say re canonical?
Re canonical position.
That's that's not, that's not English.
What is going on here?
It should be be canonicalize position, right?
Although that's not really probably English either re canonical
position.
It canonicalize position.
All right.
All right function does not take, is that really true?
Is that really true takes a world and a position?
Okay.
Takes a world.
Which I have and a physician.
There we go.
And there we go.
Player pose Undeclared identifier.
Well, if it's an Undeclared identifier that I guess I will have to
agree with compiler.
It is true.
It was player pose.
So we don't have to do this again.
In fact, this is already essentially all done for us.
No, duh.
Okay, and this is actually, we don't actually need to do this the way
we were doing it here, either, right?
Because we want to do canonical position.
We're doing a test for the session.
So this is a new player P and that just equals game State player P.
So we're going to do that in a test position first.
Right.
And that's just tile rail X, plus equals.
And this is a new player P towel rail, y plus Z equals, and that's
what we're doing our offset there.
And then we recant canonicalize, the new player P.
That's what we wanted.
And so then if we can actually go there, we don't have to do any of
this anymore.
Now, we can just say, all right, let's go ahead and set the game State
player P equal to the new player piece.
So we're basically going to accept the move there and that's already
getting a little cleaner.
It's not nearly as clean as
We wanted to be.
So we're, you know, we've got a ways to go.
I've listed many things, we have to do now, but, you know, we're
getting there again.
Lots of baby steps.
Great programs, get written by lots of baby steps.
That's just the way it goes.
Sometimes make a big step.
Sometimes baby steps.
Usually it's a lot of baby steps.
All right, so game state.
So now we just have to figure out where the player is.
And that's should be relatively straightforward for right.
Now.
We can assume he's on the screen that were actually looking at,
because we always view that screen.
So all we really have to do is move him by the tile amount, right?
That is in the game, State player pee, right?
So there's the tile relative offset.
There's the tile rail X of the guy and the tile rail, why of the guy?
So we want to add that in there.
We then want to, we have the Taro test.
We now need to know his his tile ex and his tile.
Why.
And those need to get added in but they need to get added in with a
couple things in mind.
We need to know the offset of the world, right?
The upper.
An upper upper left X in the upper left y of the world because that's
the basis of the coordinate system for drawing.
That's where the tile start for the Tom at that's on the screen.
Then we need to add the game State.
You can see why I say they're so.
So long to go right?
Because this this will all you will see how clean this ends up being
but along the way things can get pretty messy.
It's true anyway,
Yeah, of course.
I'm saying that from kind of knowing what things should look like.
I guess it's kind of a little bit Grim if you've never programmed
before and you're going to lift up and going, oh my god, when, will it
ever be clean?
Or how can I possibly manage all this stuff?
But don't worry, you always can get there.
You just have to not give up.
Hope you have to know that there is a good solution out there.
You just have to, you have to find it.
Anyway, what was I doing?
Oh, I don't need to do another player P.
We already have the player be there.
All I need to do is say world the tile side and pixels right tile
size.
In pixels x that tile X and that is going to give us how far over in
pixels, we have to do to account for the tiled.
The player is on.
Right?
So, there we go.
All right.
So, where to now world is not an arrow.
That's right.
Not in this function is not
Alright, so we've done a bunch of code changes.
There's no way this is going to work because we have surely forgotten
something somewhere.
But let's go ahead and run it and see where we're actually at.
Well, okay when I said there's no way it was actually going to work.
Okay.
See there we go.
At least we can watch.
I was like, I was like, I know there should be no way that this could
possibly work.
Let's be honest with ourselves.
It should be totally impossible and it was all right.
So what we want to do now is we want to go ahead and start debugging.
That one thing that is good to know.
It's like our player drawing is working properly.
Right, that is roughly.
Where I think.
We thought that they should be.
But I guess we don't know for sure, unless we actually test it.
So, now that we know what we need to do, is go take a look at our
canonicalization code, get rid of the bugs in it, and then we should
be pretty much good to go and we can continue on with our next
changes.
All right.
So when I do the canonicalization here, basically, I'm, I want to make
sure that this is the, this is roughly, correct.
I get the new player P started.
I offset it by however, much, we want them to move.
I then asked to re canonicalize that
Do that.
I go ahead and I get the, the player left and the player, right?
Which at this point.
These are kind of irrelevant.
We don't even have to think about them because the players Center
should be.
Oh, that's a, that's a typo there.
Don't think that anything probably has anything to do with it.
But point being we do on tests that so basically is World Point, empty
is definitely not working, right?
And presumably since it's doing the same thing that it was doing
before.
What that means is we definitely have a bug in our
economic Eliezer.
So what we should be able to do now is we should be able to go ahead
and put the guy somewhere that we know is is not at all the correct.
For him.
So we know you know that he shouldn't be able to go in there.
And now I can just go set a breakpoint and see what was happening.
Why are canonicalization doesn't seem to be producing the right
because I'm assuming, what's happening is the canonical?
Answer is not actually canonicalizing.
It's not producing the right tile accent.
I'll why?
For the guy.
It's just leaving the the other parts, the same.
So, let's see what new player P is.
Yeah, so that's exactly what I thought, right?
The tile X in the tile wires out.
What they were even though we've clearly gone more than one tile in
various directions.
So, basically, that's, that's fine.
So we just know that we've got a bug in our re canonicalize position.
Let's take a real quick, look at it just to see if we could spot the
problem here.
Okay.
Oh.
Oh man.
That's a good.
That's a good start there.
Oh, I tell you, I don't I don't think that's the entirety of our bugs,
but that's that's, that's just being dumb.
So anyway,
Yeah, things that only happen on the stream, what you going to do?
That's awful.
Anyway, point being what we want to do here is we want to basically
say, okay is this is this part going to work properly?
I passed these guys up here to this thing here.
I do the Xs and the Y's I passed the result properly now instead of
the input which is ridiculous.
And yeah, that's I'm telling you it is hard on this.
I make so many mistakes in the Stream that I've literally never seen
myself, make before, like, that's crazy passing the pose instead
there.
It's like, it's like, it's, yeah, I wonder if we're going to have to
start doing some things guard wise, like, I don't know.
Like I never use comps for example, but kant's would catch that.
I never ever have any concept bugs, but that's totally a concept.
Ugh.
And so, I wonder if I'll have to start doing things on the stream that
I would never actually have to do.
Do in real life just because I can't catch those things.
When I'm talking, it could be well, we'll see how bad.
We'll see if we have a bad one.
If we have a bad one, at some point, that isn't trivial to find, then
I'll consider it.
I'd hate to have to start costing up all my code and making it
disgusting.
But, you know, if you have to, you have to program for the bugs,
you're going to have for the circus for the situation that you're in.
And so if you find yourself making a certain type of bug on the
stream, you gotta guard against that type of bug.
So what I would say you got to be, you got to be practical.
All right.
Anyway, let me go ahead and step on in there and see what happens
here.
So yeah, what happened there?
That's not good.
That, that was bad.
Whatever, just happened.
What's going on there?
That basically we moved into it and it locked us into it, locked us
into place.
You can't feel it because you can't see what I'm typing on the
keyboard.
But yeah, so tilak's is for tile wise, one.
Did we just basically?
So I think what happened is, did we just did, we just accept a move
that we couldn't get out of recognized with new player P.
A plea, we were not supposed to ever be accepting.
Moves that were invalid.
So I wonder what happened there.
Exactly.
Something fishy is going on here.
What am I missing?
So you cannot new player.
P equals game State player.
P.
We do our tile relative X and Y Deltas.
We then re canonicalize that position.
Which is fine.
We take the player left, we clone it.
Oh, that's that's a that's a incorrect thing as well.
This is not the bug that I was just looking at but these guys are
should actually be testing off the new player position as well.
Right?
Because we're trying to test the player left from the new place.
He will be standing not the old place where he was.
So that's also supposed to be that way.
Okay, so,
We owe and in fact, you know what, that actually is the bug because
that never mind that actually is the bug because basically what will
happen there is it would allow us to do the move.
But then the next time we try to test the player left in the right,
they'll be wrong, right?
The, the they won't be wrong.
They say, we tried to press the player left in the playwright.
They'll be inside something, and we can't go anywhere.
So yeah, that actually that actually was the book, I believe.
So, let's take a look here.
Yeah, so now we're back to working albeit not pretty.
You know, it's not pretty, it's true, but we are working again, and
that's all we really wanted for now.
So let's plow for Words.
I'd like to get a bunch of this stuff done on this string if possible.
So, let's plow forwards.
So, what I'd like to do now is say, okay.
Can we go ahead and change things?
Perhaps to being not in pixels anymore.
Right?
Like, can we get rid?
Of the whole pixel situation.
And so I think what I could do at least for the players motion, right,
you know, and so so let's say, you know, the players motion is going
to be in meters from now on and I don't know how fast the players
should really move, you know plate.
I feel like players typically run pretty fast.
I don't know if two meters.
A second is a good running speed for somebody.
How fast is the?
In how fast is the fastest human?
44.7 2 km.
So twelve point four, two meters per second.
Wow, that's fast.
Don't you think 12 meters a second?
All right, Usain Bolt.
Well, we probably aren't as fast as Usain Bolt, but it's for a game
character.
We could move 10 meters per second.
Right?
So let's say we do 10 meters per second here and I believe although
where is our time step.
Actually multiplied by the time step anywhere here.
Do we get rid of that or something?
I thought we were doing that, which was if you remember correctly, I
passed it in here.
I remember passing it in here in handmade platform.
We have a thing in our input Duty for frame.
Are we actually using Ard teacher frame?
Yes, we are.
Okay, so there it is.
So basically, we have our duty for frame.
So these are in meters per second, if
We switch to the player to actually being.
Excuse me, if we switch all of the player coordinates out of pixels,
right?
And so if we switch all the player coordinates out of pixels, we'd
have player with and player height, you know, to be honest.
I don't really know how big of the player with the player height
should be.
I think we said something like 1.4 F was going to be was going to be
the height of the of the kid, right?
I don't know.
I mean, like I said, these are all kind of fungible.
So if the players height was one point for f in me.
Is something like this.
Then their width might be, I don't know 7.5 of that.
I mean, I don't know what people what, you know, these are cartoony
kind of characters.
So we're gonna have to play with these again.
It's it's kind of fun to do.
We want them to be sort of close if you will.
We wanted to be, you know, in the ballpark of real units, but they're
not real.
They're not it's not photorealistic rendering that we're after here.
So if you see our guy now, he's super tiny right here.
Moves super slowly.
And he's super, super small.
What happened there?
Tile relative is less than World tile, huh?
So this are canonicalization.
Assert fired.
Let's find out.
Why tile real?
So it's right on it.
So what did offset produce?
Offset produced negative 1.
And so this must have been a case where it was right on the border and
the floor produced exactly the value, right?
Hmm.
I don't know what we want to do in that case.
That's that's a pretty interesting case.
So, let's see if we can.
Let's take a look back out and see exactly what happened here.
Right?
So, we have our new player P, which has not been modified yet, and it
looks like this.
And you can see that the tile relative X.
In fact, I don't think we've ever seen this before on the stream.
So, I'll point it out.
Now, basically, the tile relative X is a number.
That's actually represented in scientific notation here because it's
so tiny.
I don't know if, you know scientific notation.
But basically I don't know if we can get Google to show us.
Sort of it expanded out in zeros.
Let's hope that it that it does.
Okay.
It doesn't, can you get it to?
Well point being?
If you don't know, scientific notation, basically, the E is sort of
just telling you how to how to, to shift that decimal point, right?
So basically it's going seven but it's going 7 this way.
So it's getting uh sorry so seven this way.
So it's getting smaller.
It's going, it's going out this way.
So it's like .005 - .030 5.
A super, super, super tiny number.
Since it's a super, super super, super tiny number at that point, when
we do our floor F, which I think I can call a floor, F in here, can't
I can, I don't know if I can or not new player P dot.
Tell ya, so if we call our floor function, our floor function
properly, gives us the negative one that we expected.
Right?
Because we're calling this the
These math function.
We know that it's been, totally, bulletproof rights, given us the
negative 1, which is correct, because this is a tiny negative number,
right?
But then what happens is, if we take our negative 1 and we multiply it
by the tile.
By the tile size that the pixels on a side, right?
Because let's go back and look at, let me, let me show you the the
function itself here, right?
We have the tile side and pixels.
We're multiplying that offset by the tile side and pixels, right?
And so the tile side and pixels tile side in pixels is, oops.
What's the problem?
Expression must have pointer type?
But it does.
It's the world.
What was wrong with that?
Tha side and pixels is 60.
So it doesn't actually matter.
We don't need that.
Right.
So basically - 60 is what we would be adding to this, to this value,
right here, right?
We would be adding, we would be, we would be subtracting, 60.
No, sorry, we would be.
Doing 60, because we subtract a negative 1 times 60.
So we add 62 it, right?
And as you can see here, this is the number that we should be getting
fifty.
Nine point.
Nine.
Nine nine, nine nine, nine blah, right.
That's the number that we actually want to get but unfortunately, we
don't actually get that number and the reason that we don't actually
get that number is because we can't actually store it in the Precision
that we actually have for our float that
that's presumably doing this in doubles and I assume that if we
actually take and do this entirely and float, that we would not get
that value.
Course.
I don't actually know how to make it.
Do a cast to float.
Yeah.
So if you take a look at what happens if we try to store it in a
32-bit floating point value, instead of 64 bit floating point value,
you'll notice it just goes to 60.
Now the problem with it going to 60, right?
Is that that's actually technically back on the other tile, right?
So what do we do here?
Right.
What do you know?
What's what's our solution to this problem?
If we want to be robust in, in that particular case.
And so there's a couple things here.
I mean, first of all, I think, I think I want to kind of move this
over into the new scheme first before, I worry too much about getting
all of the numerical stuff, correct.
So I'm tempted to try to just say, let's leave that for now, but
What we do need to do is we need to think about that.
That problem will always exist for us.
If we if we don't have a way to solve it, if that makes sense.
Right?
We always are going to need some way of figuring out how to solve that
particular problem.
So we need to think about when we actually do the math here to re
canonicalize our numbers.
Now, first of all, they'll always be positive.
So we do have that on our side.
Presumably, well.
Okay, I shouldn't actually say that.
The that's not actually true.
They won't always be positive.
So we will have to deal with the negative because you can be outside
the tile to the negative side.
So, anyway, we won't really have much to go on.
What will have to basically do is figure out a good, floating-point,
way to make sure that we can always extract out the whole number part
and move it.
Now.
I'm thinking that maybe, you know, we can do eventually is use like a
fracked like you something that extracts the fractional part of
something.
And, you know, like something like
I don't actually know if what is it.
Like Frac AB, I don't remember what it is.
There's a couple different things that we can do that are that are C
runtime Library functions or things that we can actually call in SEC
as well that we might be able to use to make it cleaner that.
But I don't know if those who still suffer from that problem.
So this will be something that will basically have to deal with.
I don't I don't know offhand exactly the best way because I don't
really want to add.
I don't feel like the right thing to do here would be to add a bunch
of finicky.
Where we like check again to see if it ended up being rounded or
whatever because I feel like we should be able to basically just
extract the fractional part of the floating-point number directly,
which you can do.
Like I said, I don't remember the the mnemonics for and stuff but we
should be able to do something where we do something that's not going
to maybe doesn't involve the divide or you know, we just do an F mod
of the thing.
Instead of actually doing a divide.
I feel like there's something clean but we would be able to do there.
Where if we actually think it through we won't have to do a bunch of
Finicky stuff here, right?
So, I'm going to put a to do here and say need to handle the.
Okay?
Need to do something that doesn't use the divide multiply method for
re canonicalizing, because this can end up rounding back onto the
tile.
You just came from.
Right?
And there's reasons to do that too.
Again, like went, like I said, we're going to make this one.
We're going to make this better.
The other thing that I don't like is like this stuff here.
Like well, I guess we'll be getting rid of this.
I gotta say this only moves like one tile count in the other direction
and stuff like that.
But I guess that's that's will be getting rid of that in a second
anyway, so it's we'll just leave it at that but point being that's
that's something that I don't really like about this at all.
That's just not good.
So
The other thing that I would say here is probably ads ad bounds
checking to prevent wrapping might be a good thing to do just for
security sake.
All right, so just I just want to make sure everyone kind of knew what
was going on there.
So that I could you know, when we come back to it will have to handle
those things.
I just want to take since we had it happening.
I want to take a minute to sort of explain what was going on there.
All right.
So now that we're starting to move things.
Let me finish what I was doing.
And then when we go back to,
That we can also think about all the other stuff we need to do to the
tilemap stuff.
So the first thing I want to do is say, okay, what we need to do here,
if the tile relative stuff, if all the tile relative stuff, is now
actually just in sort of actual meter units, right?
Then everywhere that we use a tile relative X at this point.
Has to take that into account, right?
They all have to sort of be aware of that fact, which means that these
guys,
Now will no longer be using tile side and pixels, they will to
determine whether you move from a toddler a tile.
They'll all from now on be using tile side in meters.
Right?
So no more pixels.
Pixels is gone.
It'll entirely be Tau sided M all the time, right?
And so that's fine.
Now when we come down here and we do our testing, the testing should
work properly because it's still using.
It's all it's really that was the only thing that had to happen for
that to be a m.
When we come down here, we will have to go.
Okay.
Now, this relative X isn't something that we can just add in this
relative X relative.
Why?
Because it is in meters, but we need it to be in pixels.
And so what we need is essentially something that does a m, 2 pixels
transform, right?
You basically need something that can do m, 2 pixels, right?
Where we do something like that, where we can where we can, where we
can multiply by that value.
To get us what we should actually get.
In pixel, since we want to know where to draw the player we have where
they are and M offset from the tile but we want it in pixels.
So we need something that that we do m 2 pixels.
And so how do we actually compute that right?
So we need M to pixels right again, I always talk about DeMint
dimensional analysis.
Right?
And this is another case for dimensional analysis.
One of the most useful things practically useful things.
I learned in chemistry class dimensional analysis.
I don't use chemistry class much.
Every day, but we learned that in chemistry class dimensional analysis
and you know, it always comes up.
So we compute m 2 pixels.
I want something that has M on the top.
I'm sorry pixels on the top and M on the bottom, right?
Because what I want to do dimensional analysis wise
I'm going to actually do that.
Yeah, I want to be able to do something that ends up in pixels, but I
have something that is in meters right at the moment.
So, what I need to do is I need a times that thing, right by something
that will produce pixels and cancel out meters, right?
So I need something that's pixels per meter.
Right?
How many pixels are there per meter?
Make sense.
So if I had something that was measured both in pixels and M.
I could put its pixel measurement on the top and it's m measurement on
the bottom.
And that would give me the ratio that I wanted.
Right?
And it just so happens that we have exactly that.
We have the tile side and pixels.
Right?
And we have the tile side and M, so I can just do this division here.
And now, I've got a ratio that will always transform one to the other
make sense.
Really, really straightforward.
Never Gonna never going to remember that.
That's a world world.there.
All right.
So in theory, when I run this now, well, that's not very good.
That that.
I don't know if you can see that.
Is that so funny?
Huh?
The guy is so tiny.
We didn't who we didn't ever change his.
I'm sorry, we didn't ever change this width and height to be, is this
little he's moving around at the fast speed, but he's super tiny.
Okay.
All right.
Sorry, we didn't ever change his player width and height.
Okay, I get a little bit too much fun, all that.
That's pretty funny.
So the player with and height we height, we change to be in meters.
So those who obviously have to be done with m 2 pixels, as well, as
you can see there.
So there's our guy and off he goes.
All right, so we are currently still a little janky here.
I don't know.
We're moving, we're moving awfully fast, but I suspect that may
actually be the correct run speed because we boosted his run speed
quite a bit by switching to there.
And we remember we aren't doing our proper.
Detection yet.
So we have, we still have the super awful quick injection in there.
I don't know why he's able to Tunnel right through those.
I don't even have no idea.
I certainly don't want to know.
So we've broken a bunch of stuff.
So I have to go fix all that.
I'm not sure what's going on.
There is a tall that's crazy town.
But anyway, I suspect that we just have the tile X and Y wrong.
So, what I want to do now.
Now this is sort of working a little bit more.
What I want to do now is you'll notice that I can't really tell
L like my first thought is okay.
We're going to make a few more changes to this.
I have to keep debugging these things as I as I do.
My sort of steps to get the code better.
One of the things that is unclear to me is, I don't know what, tile,
the game thinks the players in.
So, what I'd like to do is just add a piece of code really quickly.
That would like, highlight that so that I don't have to keep like
stepping into the bugger to figure it out.
Right?
So what I want to do in here is sort of say like okay, you know, maybe
when we do,
Just test.
I'm going to turn the tile like black or something.
So I'll turn the grey for the tile black.
If the row equals the players row, right?
So if game State player P dot dot y, equals the row and the column
equals game State player p.x.
Then that would let me see which row and column it thinks the dudes
on, right?
And that, that
Helps me sort of debug that, that that part of the problem.
So, that style X tile why, right?
So, let's see here.
So you can see that that's like he's offset.
He is not properly, you know, it's it's actually the tile part is
working properly to some degree, but it's offset from where the guy
should be.
So we basically have we have a bug that and I hope that you can see
how easy it was for.
Me, too.
Of like, see what's going on now by adding that debug code, one of the
things that is generally true and you'll see this over and over again,
as we get into more complicated stuff on the stream things that could
be hard to see or realize are happening.
If you don't draw them become very easy to see what's happening when
you do draw them.
And so, this is pretty easy for us to see like, oh, okay.
That's totally not correct.
So first, we have to figure out which is wrong, is it?
Is it where we're drawing the guy that's wrong?
Or is it the computation for what tile?
He's in.
That is wrong.
And so that's the first thing that we got to figure out.
So let's go take a look.
Let's see where we're drawing the guy.
So we're drawing the guy at the upper left X, plus the pixel said,
that's the tile at which the guy is.
So what I'm going to do actually is 0 - the player with and the player
height, right?
We got to actually get those that there you go.
There's the bug.
There's a bug right there for starters.
So there's our guy now.
He is at least man, I gotta I gotta kind of slow.
Got a slow him down.
He's he moves so fast now.
I can't even get him.
Hussein bolt is too.
Darn.
Quick is the problem.
I'm going to slow him down considerably.
I'm sorry.
It was saying you're going to have a lesser world record, but I need
to be able to see as I move out.
I just want to verify so that to me.
Looks like it's correct.
As far as which tile is being.
He's being tested.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Yes.
Okay, so that looks pretty good to me.
So, it looks like we just had a drawing bug again because we have a
lot of units here.
So as we're cleaning these things up, it kind of, you know, gets it
gets hairy sometimes.
Well as you're trying to clean up, you know, you don't you don't just
get clean code for free.
You got to you got to pay your dues.
All right, so that looks pretty much, right?
And then that's got the question of.
Can we get out?
Can we move to the next tile map?
It doesn't look like we can at the moment for some reason.
So why is that?
What's wrong there?
I'm not sure what is wrong there.
So why can't we move to our next tile map?
Did we leave the code in for the tile map?
We did.
Right reconnect.
Last chord.
Can still move someone to the next tile map, but I guess for some
reason it was not working properly so that
It would be, let's take let's let's go ahead and set a breakpoint
there.
Okay, we're almost out of time while we are out of time technically.
So let's go ahead and test set a breakpoint there and see re
canonicalize coordinate when we move out of the tile map.
Worldcat.
Oh, another bug.
Should not be World count X.
It should be towel count.
Yeah, it was checking the wrong one.
Again, when we did the extraction there.
I messed it up.
All right, so I think that should probably be what is going on here.
Hello.
Yeah, that broke something.
What did I do?
I'm confused.
if star tile,
hmm.
There we go.
If that is greater than tile count.
How is tile count to?
Are?
We passing bogus number to this guy?
Tom app context.
Oh, even better.
So we've got two bugs in here.
It's not Tom up context.
It's we want how many there are in each?
Yeah.
So these are just again.
This is just
This is that that that was just silly.
We want that.
That's how many tile Maps there are cross.
Again.
You can see why I keep saying.
I want to clean all this up because you just don't want
You don't want to have this many different things all in flight at the
same time, right?
So I really want to get to the point where everything is much more
condensed and we have a reliable set of small numbers of things that
work in a particular way.
Because before whether it's like the tile maps in the tiles and three
different indices it just you start making it just a lot of mistakes.
And so that's why I really want to start condensing everything down to
less stuff because that just, it's much easier.
To not make errors.
Alright.
So here we go.
Now our guy is moving along, nicely and happily we're using only
canonicalize Physicians.
So that's good.
He's I slowed him down a bit because the Usain Bolt thing was he was
bolting a little bit too fast.
And that's just no good.
So now he's kind of slowly Meandering along, we can see a little more
carefully, what he's doing and it seems to work properly for all our
previous cases.
All right, so that's that's good.
That's not great.
Progress.
But it's yes, ma'am.
Pretty happy with that.
I'm pretty happy with that.
We've got one step down, which is removed the raw, and we're right on
the cusp.
We also went ahead and we changed the players coordinates to a
Resolute resolution independent.
Once we got rid of this to do right here, right?
So that's nice.
These guys would be one thing.
I might say is, I'd still leave it to doing here, which is should
these be from the center of
a tile.
And I'm not sure exactly the right way to make that determination.
But but that, that I do want to check out.
All right, so we got rid of that to do.
So, that's nice.
We've got it down to only one.
Excuse me.
We've got it down to only one type of coordinate and we are within
Striking Distance of also packing these guys down which will finally
let us get rid of the town map stuff and have a nice kind of sparse
representation for our town map that we can always look up into.
So I think we're in pretty good shape.
I think tomorrow I'll be able to do that stuff and then we'll be ready
to start tackling some of these other issues.
So alright, that's not bad.
That's not too bad for one day's work.
Not too bad.
Alright, let's go ahead and go off.
To the Q&A.
If you could please put Q: before your questions so I can see them.
That would be very handy.
And please keep your questions to stuff.
We've actually coded so far either today or on a previous stream.
If you want to ask questions about off-topic stuff.
You can come to the stream early come about 15 minutes before the
scheduled start time, and that's when we talk about that sort of
stuff.
So plenty of chances to do that every day.
There's another 15 minutes to do that.
So let's go.
To the Q.
A
Isn't this a good time for some on-screen text to make watching the
values for the player position easier having to check the watch window
as you step through is such a pain for this.
I totally agree with you.
But unfortunately, if you think about what would be required for us to
put some text on the screen, we'd have to have a renderer.
And so until I really need to do that.
I'm not going to because I want to get a little bit further with just
How play with the play code so that I can write the renderer nicely
and not have to worry about about how kind of ping-ponging back and
forth if it becomes a little bit dire, then yes, I would do that.
But that's the reason I haven't put any text on the screen.
That's because we don't have a text renderer, but we will eventually
it just, you know, cart before the horse and so on.
What is the variable called gray?
So basically what this is is this is the color.
This draws the tile map.
On the screen are a little debug.
This is the thing that draws the rectangles to show us what the what
parts of the top map are occupied in not.
So basically what happens is for each tile in the tile map.
It assumes that it's going to be gray.
And then if the tile is occupied, it changes it to White.
And if the player is on the tile, it changed it to Black.
And that is what you saw here.
Where the these are the white ones.
And these are the gray ones.
That's the black one, right?
So that's what that is.
How does the difficulty of conceptualizing, this type of code?
Compared to say?
Coating the back end to a web application.
Um, well, I mean, I guess what I would say is it all depends on the
web application.
I mean, like for example, there are certain web applications, for
example back ends, that could be very complicated because they might
be very multi threaded and be doing a lot of stuff with multi-threaded
performance and stuff like that.
So it all depends like the difficulty is usually not about
Necessarily what type of application it is, but more how well
engineered it ends up being because there's probably web application
back ends that are just super trivial and dumb.
And there's probably web back ends that are very, very complicated and
have a lot of performance because strength to them, depending on the
company, you know, who who was writing it and what they were doing.
The window title bar has a nice place to spit out some text.
It's true.
We could cheese it out.
Look, I guess what I would say is that you guys gotta just, you gotta
be patient.
It would be nice.
It's true.
But one of the things about making stuff by hand is you got to kind of
go in waves.
And when we get there, we will have some crazy, awesome, debug overlay
stuff.
I promise you that, but it is going to take us a little while to get
there because we're going to render a first
This is in regards to the input recording code, but I don't think we
ever use the 03 play buffer in the win32 state since the code assumes
that 04 input recording.
Index means that we recording the first element never gets used.
Yes, you are.
Probably correct about that.
So that's in back here in the replay buffers because 0 means we're not
recording if I remember correctly.
So basically
Where are we here?
That's that's in here.
Yes, so I think for the replay buffers, that is true.
I'm not sure what the fix is that you'd want to do there.
So there's a couple different ways.
We could solve that problem.
I'm not sure what the best way to solve that problem is I thought of
something and I haven't gone back and change it.
I realized after we did all this work.
That actually none of it was necessary.
Sometimes that happens, the reason that I've is necessary is because I
realized that the transient storage.
Actually split into two halves and only one half actually has to get
stored and the half-ass get stored is very small.
So all of that crazy stuff we did like playing with it, trying to make
it faster.
I think we actually didn't need to do any of which is kind of sad, but
What are you going to do?
I just didn't think of it at the time.
I had I wasn't really considering what parts actually need to get
sword, which parts didn't.
So we're going to have to do some work here.
In fact, I can put
I could do their, transient storage needs to be broken up into game,
transient and cash, transient.
And only, the former need be saved for State playback.
So, yeah, so that was the mess up on my part and did cause a lot of
aggravation that didn't actually need to get caused.
But what you going to do?
I didn't really want it to wrap my to do there.
Thank you e, Max, but that would put thanks, but no.
Thanks.
So yeah, so that was not necessary and that was a mistake.
That said, if we want to fix this problem because I believe what our
convention was is that zero means that we're not recording.
So if we want to fix that, what we could do is we could, we could just
say that we always use one, extra replay buffer and the first replay
buffer is fallow.
I mean, I suppose we could do something like that, right?
I don't remember exactly how many of those
We actually use our how we actually use those.
Let's take a look.
Replay buffers.
So the index comes in here so we could just say assert index is
greater than 0.
We could just do that.
Right?
Yeah.
So if you want to you could do that.
I think that would probably work fine for now.
But like I said, we should probably take a look at that in a different
way.
Yeah.
Yes.
I know.
Thank you.
How do we
We're going to have to deal with this guy sooner or later because this
assertion is going to is going to cause issues.
I guess we could Nerf the assertion but I don't really like that idea
either.
I mean, it is theoretically possible that we could just allow that
assertion to exist but or check for Epsilon, check for Epsilon away,
if that makes sense, but I just those are the kinds of things that,
you know, are going to
They're usually just signs that you did the floating Point math wrong.
And so I usually
And if I actually sit down, you know, and kind of do it a little more
carefully.
So like for example, we could just do that and say to do fixed
floating Point math, so this can be that instead.
But yeah, for now since we don't want to be asserting all over the
place, that may be something that we're just going to have to live
with a less than optimal.
Sort of assertion.
Anyway, so checking the loop Point here.
I'll go ahead and
And make sure that that's still working.
Yeah.
So yeah, so we can do that.
I don't know if that helps for now.
But yeah, really that replay stuff.
I should probably go.
We should split the game out into something more reasonable because I
realized all that work we did was not at all.
Necessary is so
So yeah, sorry about that.
Trevor Taps is, when do you decide to add visual cues to help the
debugging?
So the answer is right now, not that often because I don't have a
renderer.
Once we actually get the renderer up and running something that can
actually put a lot of different graphics on the screen for real, you
know, lines and overlay text and stuff like this.
I will often add visual cues to debugging because
I think in fact, it was John Carmack who originally said time spent
visualizing is never wasted.
Not sometimes not often.
He was like never wasted.
So he you know, he was of the opinion that you should always draw
things out and I'm inclined to agree with that perspective.
Basically, I think that any time I've ever pretty much whenever I take
the time to display stuff.
I always learn something.
And so, once we actually have the ability to display things, you will
see me doing a lot of it and we will build little systems that make it
easy to make displays of stuff that.
So as we go, we don't have to do a lot of work to add visualization.
What are your thoughts on the progress you make daily?
Would you say it becomes tedious coding so often or is your love for
coding?
So great.
I see a burning passion in you to try and create Excellence.
That's a very odd way to face that question.
I feel like the progress that we've been making on handmade hero is
decent.
I mean, only one hour, a day of coding.
Plus I have to explain things.
So I'm not thinking as clearly.
As I should be and it takes longer means that there's not that much we
can do in a day and even so I feel like we've gotten pretty far.
I mean,
I think this will start looking like a game, you know, within the next
two months or so.
I mean, it'll be really zygote ish.
Right?
But it's like it's getting there very steadily and so, you know, I
think the renderer will take us a lot of time and so it's going to be
a big stall as that kind of comes together.
And so that will be definitely something that delays the game becoming
a game for quite some time because we want to do a bunch of rendering
things.
But you know in the next month or two, like I said, we'll have sort of
our baby like
Thing working.
And it'll kind of look gamey.
And then like the fact that we'll be getting there so quickly at only
an hour a day.
And it's not even a real hour.
I've been pretty happy with that.
So, I don't know if that was your question.
But you know, I've been pretty happy with how things have been going
so far.
Does the code actually handle skipping a tile map if there are three
Tom apps going from first to third.
So the code right now is not really doing anything intelligent
tilemap.
So depending on what you mean by that, possibly know like this one.
This code part wouldn't handle it but we're getting rid of that
entirely and we're going to basically a virtual addressing scheme for
the tiles, which is what we'll be doing.
Tomorrow.
We set ourselves up to do it today, by all the changes we made.
And we've got one more big change to make, which is getting rid of the
time.
I BEC stop.
Mopwai, and at that point we will basically be totally free from any
concept of a tile map at all.
We'll just be able to you'll be able to do whatever you want basically
and and you could do smooth scrolling with it as well if you wanted
to.
Yeah, which some people expressed interest in.
Can the player go diagonally through the to wall tiles?
Kitty-corner to each other with the current Collision code?
Yes, they well.
So, probably not, but only because of those Edge checks, but the
plate, but the current Collision code is totally placeholder, and you
could do something related, which is, if you just had enough speed,
you could tile straight through a block tile, right?
Because we only check the start and the end so you can tunnel through
things that even if they're not kitty-corner.
The reason you probably can't tunnel through kitty corner is because
we're checking the edges of the tiles.
And so it'd be really hard.
Hard to move far enough to to not do it.
So you probably actually can't.
But it's only because sort of, by accident.
The real answer is the current Collision code is not code you would
ever use in a shipping game.
It's just so that we can sort of get our bearings.
Basically.
What we'll be doing is again, we're trying to spec out our engine
here.
So these are sort of the things that we're going to want this.
Right here will become an engine spec.
It's saying that we need to move something from one place to another
and know whether it collided in between and the engine will have a
real Collision function that actually doesn't allow things like
tunneling to occur if that makes sense.
Why am I so fond of in line?
So, in line is basically just a note to myself.
So, one thing that's important to remember about in line is, in line
is more or less meaningless.
Like, if you put in line in the code, doesn't really mean anything.
There is a real in line.
It's called force in line.
Let me show it to you.
I think it has one underscore at the beginning.
I don't know if it's got one or two.
So this this guy is the actual in line, right?
This guy says, you have to inline this function, like anywhere that
you see a use of this function, inline it right?
If that makes sense.
This in line doesn't really do anything other than suggest for
whatever that's worth to the compiler.
That it might want to inline it.
But in line in C++ is just weak sauce.
It doesn't actually in line the function.
It just says the compiler, maybe you should think about inlining it,
but the compiler is always free to inline or not in line.
Anything it wants to, it doesn't have to listen to me.
So really these in lines when I'm putting them in here, are notes to
myself that.
I
This function is probably one.
I want to bake down to a size that could be inserted without actually
having a call.
Right?
So basically this in line is like a note to Casey, which is look at
these functions and see if they should become things that are in line
of.
All right.
It's not actually telling the compiler, to inline it because the
compiler doesn't really care as far as I know.
Good compilers.
Nowadays probably don't hardly care at all about what you say.
You should in line, I think.
They make their own decisions, but I could be wrong about that.
So anyway, that's basically what that is.
It's basically a note now we're compiling in debug mode.
So that means it doesn't do anything at.
All.
Right, we have inlining turned off at the moment.
So these are not getting in line.
Anyway, so really, that's just a note to myself, if that makes sense.
Are we going to have input envelopes for feel like acceleration in
friction?
Absolutely.
Will have very good player movement code.
Our player movement code will feel excellent because I want to go
through all of the math.
That's necessary to make that work.
And so when we get to that point, we'll be doing all of those things.
Can you explain what you meant by canonicalization in some simpler
terms?
Yes, or I can try.
I'll do my best.
So, we are driving towards a to a two-tier coordinate system.
Right?
What I'm trying to get to is I'm trying to get to, you know, like I
said, on Monday was trying to get to is something where this is going
to be.
Let's see here.
These are tiles.
Each each one of these things is a tile, okay.
So on the screen, you know, I've got my tiles and some of them are
filled, right, you know, like this sort of thing and whatever.
So here's my tile map and I want to talk about a location on this tile
map.
Well, if I want to talk about a look, the location of a tile, it's
pretty easy.
I can just make a grid and say what the location of something is by
using the numbers that are on the grid by first using the Row first,
using the column and then using the row, which we usually tells you no
index.
And a, why?
For example, we can say, if I want to talk about this tile right here.
Then I know I can say for comma 3 tells me where we are in the tile
map, right?
That is tile.
That is tile for three.
Okay.
But we have people moving around this tilemap who are actually not
constrained to lie exactly on the tile.
So this person doesn't have to be standing directly on the tile or
anything.
They can be standing anywhere on this tile map.
That can be standing like there.
They can be standing over here.
And so, what I want to do is I want to have a way of specifying where
they are relative to the tile that they're in as well, so that there's
two coordinates.
There's the tile coordinate.
Which is where you are in the tile map and then there's also basically
the offset from that tile, right?
Which is a floating Point number can be anywhere in here and at that's
given in meters, right?
So this is in tiles.
This is in meters.
When I say canonicalize or re canonicalize, I was just using the word
canonical to basically mean what we are considering a proper.
Set of coordinates.
And what that means is, this offset should not Point outside the tile
if I say tile 43, right, but then my offset Points, Way the heck back
here.
So actually the guy whose coordinate said he was in tile for three is
actually entitled to one because of this huge offset that he's got
right that could cause all kinds of problems for things where I'm
checking tiles in some way.
right, because if
Look and see.
Oh, he's in this tile.
What do I know about this tile?
Because I'm going to apply tile-based effects to him or something.
Well, he's not in that tile.
He's actually over here.
So the user sees him over here, but he's says, his style is his
position, says he's here.
That's no good because now he's getting affection this tile, but the
user sees them over here is like why is he getting like the water
effect on him when there's no water over here at the waters over here,
right?
So when I say re canonicalize what I'm saying is take that off set.
Right?
That's in the position.
Look to see if it is falling outside the tile and if it is reset the
tile coordinates so that it's the actual tile there in and then re
compute what the offset is to still put them in the same place.
So to give you an example of what would happen.
Let's say the tile was 56, so he's here, right?
So I start off and I've got five comma.
Six is my tile location, but my offset looks like that.
Well, what happens after canonicalization is.
I've got you know, 56 and some large offset.
Then I after canonicalizing, I will get 66 right and a new offset that
still points to the exact same location.
But now it's a different offset.
It's an offset from this corner instead of this corner, right?
That's canonicalization.
And so what we want to do is we want to be able to always re
canonicalize our coordinates so that we're always in the same space.
Now, the reason that we
To do this instead of just having one floating Point.
Coordinate, that tells us where we are is because I want to have giant
tile maps and floating Point, Precision doesn't actually allow us to
do that.
We could use doubles instead.
So everything would be 64 bit floating point, but there's platforms
are doing, so, you have seen before.
I don't even know the Raspberry Pi does 64-bit, floating-point.
It might not.
So euphoric floating point is slower.
So I often times might want to do stuff where we put things into a
floating Point spacers.
There's a lot of reasons why I think we want to go within for tile and
then floating-point offset.
But you know, who knows?
Maybe it's a bad decision.
You don't always make all the right decisions and so we won't really
know until the end of the day when it's all, when it all shakes out.
With this kind of code, be a good fit for unit tests.
Fuzz test to make sure strange Corner cases.
Don't creep around.
Yes.
Probably.
It depends on how well we can test to see what we actually want to
see.
But yes, like at least like for when we go to do like our flooring
functions and all that sort of stuff.
That's a excellent case.
For when we could do unit testing, where we could just test lots of
stuff to make sure our floor works and that sort of thing.
So, I don't know exactly.
If we where the line is drawn for that, but but yes, I mean some of
these functions are small enough and well-defined enough that we could
make unit tests for them and and might do that.
But we don't want a unit test.
These because again, these are our play functions.
We want to test it once and we actually have the engine official
functions were like, this is the one that we
Ship, that's the one you test.
Are there reasons why programmers of older adventure games?
Chose to move the character around a map and not vice versa.
It does.
This have something to do with memory usage or render performance.
You know, it's a little bit before my time, so I don't know.
I suspect that it did have something to do with it.
But a lot of those old systems did have ways that allow you to scroll
a tile map.
The reason we started off at ah, maps in the first place is because
Hardware could display them specifically.
Like, you could basically have the hardware have a set of tile lookups
where you would put like a number in the tile map, like three.
And it would know that corresponding to a certain 8 by 8, pixel thing
or something.
And so because processors back then we're
Not nearly fast enough for you to actually draw your own actual tile
map.
That was totally not on the table.
So they typically had in the old days.
They had Sprites and tile Maps were actually part of the hardware.
Like a hardware, could do some number of sprite overlays and it had a
way of taking a map in memory that had indices and turning that into a
tile map on the screen.
So that's
where those conventions came from.
So I'm keeping some of those conventions.
For our game, but I'm sort of relaxing the graphic one so that we can
have a more modern looking game.
But I like some of the aspects of tile Maps, because I think Tom apps
are just interesting.
In terms of people players, being able to understand what's possible
on a tile map and being able to understand like Puzzles or doorways
and stuff when things are totally, not when things are not aligned to
a grid at all.
It's much harder for the player to conceptualize what's possible and
for puzzles to work.
Well, because
As you end up with these kind of Lucy physics, puzzles that don't feel
very good and are typically very interesting.
And so, you know, that's mostly where where we're going with it.
Earlier, you said using const was ugly.
Is that just a visual thing or is it ugly and some other way like
performance coding style.
So I like I said, I never have const bugs when I'm programming
normally, so I never use const.
But I was just noticing that this was a book that I had a bug here.
I mean, I don't know if you'd want to call it a console, but it was a
bug that like if you know, if you had kant's here.
You wouldn't have been able to make the mistake, right?
So I was thinking well, I don't know.
Do I have to revisit that?
Because am I going to be starting a my because of the way when I'm
talking and stuff and I don't have my full attention will I start
making constant bugs ones?
That one didn't take any time to find but you could imagine if it was
subtler bug, that would have cost a lot more.
Maybe cost would have saved been worth it in the long run.
The reason I said, it's ugly is because C++ makes constituting pretty
owners.
You end up with a lot of these problems of like kant's poisoning and
all this other sorts of stuff.
And it's just it's just an annoying thing to that you would never.
There's no point in ever typing costs.
You would never do that.
You would never use const unless you thought you were going to save
bugs by typing it.
And so since I never saved bugs in my day-to-day, I don't ever type
it.
And so the only reason that I brought it up at all was just because I
was thinking.
Well, alright, but programming on the stream is different than
programming off the stream.
So, you know.
Do I have to adopt some coding practices that are different from the
kinds that I would do normally day-to-day because, you know, I'm going
to make different kinds of bugs.
I already see myself, making a lot of typos bugs that I probably
wouldn't be making in normal day.
They coating as well.
And so, you know, that's, that's sort of how that goes.
Let's see.
Think so.
I guess we're out of time.
Actually.
Let me just see if there's any other questions that we should answer
right now.
Let's see.
What's your preferred 2D coordinate system y going down or why going
up?
We talked about this yesterday a little bit.
I actually would like to keep why going up.
And so that's another change that we want to do.
In fact, I should say, I forgot to leave the math friendly, comment in
there.
So I should put that more specifically so that we do this.
Why should go up.
Because we're going to make that change as well.
That's when we actually go to the other.
Tilemap.
I want to make it so that y goes up so that we're sort of in line with
math.
Let's see.
Sorry, I'm just scanning to see if there's anything else.
So now that there's no raw at all.
Can we rename canonical position to position and me canonicalize to
fix a rebase?
Yes, and I'll put it to you in to that effect.
This.
This now can
Be this can become World position for something similar will think
about what we want to call that a little later on.
But yes, because now we've just got one.
We've done what we wanted to do.
Let's see.
Will we be using the tile map for pathfinding or some other way to get
smoother at movement, will probably use the tile map for pathfinding,
because that will be the fastest way to generate the base path.
But after we generate a base path through the tile map.
We could make it smoother if we were unhappy with people.
If we didn't want people kind of walking on the tile map, really Jank
Ali.
If that makes sense.
Well, I released my version control system.
It is the older version.
That's kind of janky is still available.
This is like a really old version of it, but it was pretty much still
there.
Yeah, Molly rocket.com 736.
If you go to win32 Source, you can download a zip file and this was
the old one that me and Sean Barrett had.
Well, I made a version of it and then Shawn Barrett liked it and
started using it.
So he poured it to his standard library because it had some stuff that
he wanted to use and so now it
B1 file.
Now, it's too.
I think that's still probably a pretty good version.
It's not great.
I've got a more updated one, but I mostly, yeah, I've been doing some,
it's a long story.
I don't want to get into it, but point being, there is a version of
the old one that's still available.
It's like the simplest version control system because that's what I
really wanted.
So it is there if people want to play with it.
And again, it's an old version.
But it is it is something I did release that on time ago.
All right, I think that is basically it for today.
Thank you very much.
Everyone for joining me for another day of handmade hero coating.
It has been a pleasure coding with you, as always, if you would like
to get a copy of the source code.
You can pre-order the game here on handmade hero to org and you will
get your own very own links.
You can download the source code every night after I am done
programming with.
It's a good way to follow along at home and it's got the source code
for all the days.
So you could
So you go start all the way back at the very first video and it's got
the source code from each day.
And it's, you can follow along with that, too, which is kind of fun.
If you're new to the stream.
If you just want to spread the video series.
We do have a patreon now that you can subscribe to their and we have a
pretty awesome site where people gather on the news and forums.
You can click on, it's got all kind of stuff.
It has 2 schedules for the week.
It's got an episode guide for catching up with old episodes.
Great stuff on it.
Cody resources where people have done ports to other operating systems
already long before we ever going to get there.
They did Linux and Mac ports.
And someone did a port to Swift.
It's crazy.
And then there's also a forums if you can ask questions on and stuff
like that.
So please check it out.
If you're looking to learn from the series.
It's got a lot of great resources for you that I think you will really
enjoy.
So, thank you very much for joining me.
Tomorrow is New Year's Eve, so we are going to do an early stream
tomorrow.
We are going to be on holiday hours.
So 10:00 a.m.
Tomorrow.
Pacific Standard Time.
If you are up bright and early, please join me for some early-morning
coding.
And if not, I'll catch you on YouTube.
Alright, everyone.
Thank you very much for joining me, and, and I hope to see you
tomorrow.