Okay.
Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade hero show.
Recoded, complete game live on stream.
I this is, this is a tough.
This is a tough episode.
Basic wave.
What I would like to say is we just finished last week doing some
finishing up texture downloads but we didn't actually get a chance to
finish them up.
And the reason for that is because there's still a fair bit of
ambiguity about what the right way is to actually download textures.
And this is sort of an ongoing saga.
And honestly, to be really honest with you, it's kind of what I would
prefer to have happen on stream as well.
Because one of the big things about handmade here is, I kind of wanted
to show how programming actually happens as opposed to showing
something.
After the fact, where you've already finished all the programming to
say, here's what we ended up with, this is very typical in my
experience with anything, that involves any kind of Graphics
programming, you can go look at what the recommended ways are to do
something.
Whatever nvidia's latest published thing is or anything like that but
then when you actually go to implement it, you find out that that's
totally not true or that doesn't work in some places for that.
What they said was wrong or not the right way anymore and just nobody
bothered to publish what the actual right way was and blah blah blah
and so right now we're kind of in a little bit of limbo regarding
texture downloads and the reason for that is because although I did
correspond a little bit with Nvidia about it.
I have not gotten a definitive answer back from them yet.
About what the actual proper way is to download textures overlapped on
their card.
Now, some people are of the impression and I don't actually know if
they're right or not, because none of them was particularly
authoritative on this topic and certainly no one had any actual data
to show me, but some people were of the opinion that CPU like they
equated overlapping CPU work with overlapping GPU work and we
Talked about this last week, those aren't the same thing.
There's two copies that have to happen in order for textures to get to
from the disc to the GPU.
One of them or two I should say to required.
You could have infinitely, many more non-required copies, but there's
two ones that are acquired one is it has to go off of the disc right
into memory that the GPU can see.
And then what is it has to go from memory that you can see on to the
actual resident memory of the GPU?
So those two copies are have to happen, even if you use direct GPU
mapping, which you can actually do, I should mention this, it's kind
of an amusing thing, like you can, you can see here.
So there's even such things as direct GPU mapping where.
For example, you can have the
like,
You can have the GPU, put something into system, memory, sort of
directly.
And then the the network card can read it out of memory directly
without necessarily having to go through any kind of intermediary.
It doesn't have to be like moved around to into two different map
memories, if that makes sense.
But even if you're doing something like that, obviously it has to come
off the disk into system memory.
And then from system memory into GPU, there's no such thing as
GPU reading directly from the disk as far as I know and so you're
always going to have at least those two copies and so yes there's
plenty of ways in opengl that we could if we wanted to get rid of that
first copy.
So when we load from disk into memory right now when we're calling GL
text image 2D it's copying it from our memory into memory.
That's visible to the GPU.
So a range of memory on the host
You that's visible to the GPS that you can transfer it.
That is not the part that we were talking about, right?
That is that is what everyone else sees you talking about.
That is not the part, we're actually talking about.
The part we're talking about is, how do you tell the driver?
To start transferring that texture.
using the asynchronous texture, using the asynchronous memory transfer
capabilities that the card has
And so the way we did, that was the last way I saw published on
nvidia's website since I figured that would be the most recent, which
is that you have to create a secondary opengl context to do it.
They don't currently have published as far as I know some other way of
telling them the driver to do that asynchronous transfer.
now, until we hear back from Nvidia,
We're never going to know, right?
I just don't know because they're the only ones who know we could try
to do a bunch of experiments about it if we wanted to.
But we may not even really have any knowledge of what things to even
experiment with because we don't know how their driver Works
internally.
We don't have the source code to it and so we can't even really
predict what sorts of activities we could do.
That would convince the driver to do, exactly that.
It may be a very simple thing that we can do it.
Maybe very complicated thing, but we have no idea.
So that is where the texture transfer stuff stands at the moment.
And so I think what we should do at least temporarily is to wait to
see if Nvidia gets back to us and gives us some better information
about what they think the best way for us to transform be and then
when we get that information we can go back and modify how we're doing
it to conform to that because it certainly seems like the way they
suggested to do it before is not actually the way that you would
think.
Now that said there is one piece of the transfer
/ that we don't do in handmade hero that was recommended by them in
the original thing.
And
That was to fence the download on either side and the reason that we
didn't finish the download on either side was simply because we don't
actually care if the download gets fenced but maybe we'll find out.
When they write us back hopefully they'll write us back, maybe we'll
find out that if you don't put the fence in the driver doesn't realize
that it needs to do the operation or something.
I'm not sure.
So I really don't know, I think I would rather just take a
wait-and-see approach.
I don't really want to try mucking around.
And with it because I feel like it's not a super constructive use of
our time to try and try and play with that any further, especially
because if we really wanted to we could always just continue to
download the textures on a single thread and that's not really the end
of the world.
It's not going to kill kill us to do that.
It's only the GPU overlap part that we were trying to make sure with
set up properly.
And so if it turns out, we don't get that, we don't get that, we can
certainly go do some stuff with our buffer objects.
Or pixel buffer is or whatever to eliminate the first copy.
If we felt we want to do that, that seems pretty straightforward.
So we still have other options for optimizing texture downloads.
If we find that we need to do that.
So yeah.
So I would like to know I would I'm hope they will sort of get back to
us and tell us what the preferred method is for that.
So we can make sure the code is architected properly.
So that when we want to optimize our texture downloads and make sure
they're very fast sometime in the future.
We are in a good place to do that until then I
I say just leave it.
All right, so where does that leave us?
Well,
I believe I was taking a look at the to do file.
I think I may have forgotten to save it.
That may have been a slight mistake on my part, but we didn't really
do too much to it, so it's not really that big of a deal.
Anyway, let's take a look at that.
Oops made proj, let's take a look at that to do here.
It is just so we can kind of see what the story is.
So it looks like I did save it.
Actually so so I think we're all good.
So this is where we were at and we have a couple different things that
we can do.
Like I said, we can sort of push forward on the rendering stuff, we
can fix the debug code, and then we've got sort of a, some audio to
bugging that we could choose to do as well, but,
Like I was saying on last, on last week stream of this kind of
thinking about it.
I'm like, I don't know what the most interesting thing to do next is
it's hard to say.
It might be too kind of wrangle, our debug code to shape.
It might be to, to go finish the rendering stuff.
I think what I'd like to do is go finish the debug code because it's
kind of nasty in there and it'd be nice to just kind of go through
and, and spend some time cleaning it out and putting getting it so
that it's running the features that we actually care about relatively
reliably and that would be like a profile that we can use.
Reliably.
And some may be some control over like variables and things.
That like in terms of being able to dump data in a sort of coherent
way.
Because right now we don't have a lot of ways of inspecting stuff or
diagramming stuff and we would like to be able to do a little bit more
of that.
All right, so let's take a little bit of a look at what we've got
there.
I'll just jump back over into it.
Well, I might as well I guess I might compile first.
There we go.
And on this machine, since this is an AMD machine, the problems that I
was just talking about with the texture downloads, don't actually seem
to to have, they don't, they don't happen, right?
So it's kind of, you'll just have to take my word for it.
That people were reporting problems with that.
And, you know, it doesn't happen on this machine.
So you can't actually see the problem, but, but it was there.
And they also were the folks who were able to repo.
The problem said that if they did it a GL flush after to force the
texture, download to happen on the separate thread.
That was another way they could make that happen.
So they did something like this.
That make sense which we could leave in there for now.
Since we don't really care until Nvidia tells us the secret answers,
we don't really care what that code looks like for.
Now we're just waiting anyway, so we could leave that on there.
If that helps people who are running on video
Cards use this without having to worry too much.
So there's that.
All right.
So where we were at before with the debug code is we kind of did a
bunch of work to see how far we could get on having things.
Be easily, recordable and easily usable, but we never quite got to the
point where everything was copacetic, right.
And that may have been because we tried to do a little too much with
it, you know, we experimented with a bunch of stuff and sometimes you,
you know, you may get to the point which arguably, the debug code may
have.
Until we're just like you know, if we want to finish this in a
reasonable amount of time, we may want to pair it down from what it
can do to what we actually only specifically need just in the interest
of not having it be a huge project.
If you know, you decide that debug code is the most important thing.
And you want to go ahead and just spend a ton of time making great
debug system.
That's certainly a good idea.
And if it's a reusable debug system that you can, you know, use on a
lot of different projects that could be a very good idea.
But we may want to sort of like say, all right, we're not going to do.
Do maybe we might not go as far as we possibly can with everything.
We may keep it a little bit, you know, more more streamlined than that
potentially.
All right, so with first thing I like to do is I want to take a look
at the debug interface stuff because that's sort of where we left
things.
And what I'd like to do is since, you know, we kind of want to think
of this as like a finishing pass for the debug stuff.
I think what I want to do is sort of come at it from a
Different places where we go.
Here's what we want to be able to do.
Let's make sure there's a good way for us to do it, right?
And so for example we had a case and let's just try to work on just
that one case and get it in and so that we can sort of, like, make
sure it's integrated there.
And finished, we had an example case, where like here,
There's some functions like Global pause and Global use software
rendering.
And although we have Live code editing for everything in the game, the
platform layer is the one thing that we don't have any Live code
editing on, right?
So right now we don't actually have any way of actually, you know, of
ever doing that.
We don't have any way.
Of toggling that variable at runtime because although normally we
could just go ahead and toggle it using some kind of Live code editing
trick which we have, we can't actually do that here.
So, one thing that I would like to be able to do is make, you know,
something like this easy to edit.
So that would be easy for us to say this variable is a variable that I
want to edit, right?
This is variables and variable that I want to be able to you know
I want to see a little interface of it up up here, right?
So in our startup time is awful.
Now that we launched opengl that that AMD context creation is super
expensive.
So yeah.
So here is our, I mean, am I wrong about that?
Look at that.
Look at how long that takes.
That's all opengl initialization right there.
It's just brutal.
I almost want to render running software just to not have to deal with
that, right?
But anyway, so that's an example that, like, and even the show cursor
would be an interesting one, but Global you saw for entering and
Global paws, are some examples of things that I would like to have a
way of controlling in a nice interface potentially.
Right?
I would like that to be something we could do.
So, let's think about how we might
Want to have that happen now, the best possible way if we were in a
sort of meta programming, kind of a mood would be if we just marked it
right here, right?
And we could do that in a completely zero cost way.
We just do something like, you know, met a program, you know, whatever
you want to do here is like editable variable.
You could imagine, you can make up anything you wanted.
And if there was the pre pass that went through here, it could sort of
grab that and then do something with it.
But I feel like we want to keep things relatively
Simple for this, if we're trying to sort of finish off the debug
system, we don't want to introduce too much extraneous stuff.
So the next best thing I think would be to just have in the code
somewhere.
A place where we announced.
Variables s things that we want to edit and we just put them in there
when we want them, right?
And so to do that, I would take these two that I actually want which
is global pause and Global use software rendering and I'll just put
them down somewhere where they would actually be relevant, right?
So you know inside our Loop here where we are doing our while running
right here.
What I could do is while we're doing our Global running.
Oops.
That's not
Actually, that's that's a test loop.
We're actually looking at this one while we're doing this, this Global
running bit here.
Then what I might want to do is say, oh okay.
Let's announce these variables, maybe I want to keep that inside that
block.
Well, it's not really a cute little fish.
So I'll put it up here.
So what I want to do here, right is I want to be able to announce
these variables and we sort of had a way that we were going to do that
in in the handmade debug interface code that was debug VAR.
Right.
So we have this sort of method where we could sort of say debug
variable and when we said to you but variable we could say type path
and variable and I can actually scroll this up into view.
Can I not think for a coder?
Has a way to do that?
Well I could do this.
There we go.
So, debug variable is a way of saying we have a variable, we want it
to be editable, right?
And it looks like that basically defines that variable in a particular
location, right?
There's the, there's the, the variable type that it is and it's doing
this sort of global constants thing.
So, all of the stuff has to be it has to be kind of out in those in
those
Well constants.
Now I don't know if that's such a good idea, that was how we were
doing it, but I don't actually know if we want it to work that way,
right?
So like I said, this may have been a case where we just went a little
bit too far and I feel like what we probably want is something a
little bit more straightforward like something where we can just say
like, you know, maybe like this is debug editable or something like
this.
Something where we can just say, all right, we'll announce when things
are due by editable.
And and maybe we give up some of the the stuff we were trying to go
for in the other cases but you know, something where we can just say,
I want to be able to debug edit these things.
Now, I like the path part of things.
I like the fact that we could have a path and because the reason that
I like that path part of things was because I like having a way of
categorizing these things in the interface so that the interface
doesn't get too clogged, right because
cuz you know, if you have like a hundred debug variables in there, if
you don't have some way of keeping that under,
Troll.
It can be a little bit janky to get to, right?
It can be a little bit a little bit ownerís, right?
So in this case, I guess what I'll say is like, okay, when we come
through here will say to you by get it.
And here's this this thing and I'll just say where I want that to be
placed in the path as a string, like kind of like we were doing
before.
And so, where do we want the global pause to be?
Maybe we want that to be in like, you know, platform know if we really
need the leading /.
Do we need a leading /?
I don't know.
Probably not.
We may be.
We want that to be inside.
Arm like, you know, paused or something like that.
And this will be in platform software rendering something like this,
maybe, I'm not sure.
So, you know, that would be sort of analogous to what we were doing
before but maybe just a little bit saner and we're not trying to do
anything particularly fancy.
We're just saying edit a global variable and that's really the the
feature that it would have, right?
So in this case,
Like what we've got the debug if and that sort of stuff, we could
also, you know, this just allows us to simplify this down to the point
where those variables are still defined in our code and the only
alternative that again without any metaprogramming context, there is
that we would have to do sort of the way we were doing it before where
there's a config, right?
And this config file has all the stuff in it.
Now I just don't know if that makes a whole lot of sense and the
reason that I think that that's a little bit trickier it's just
because
It's just as we were going down that path.
It just doesn't feel that good to have this giant file with all of
these things named in, this particular way, you know.
It just seems a little overwrought and maybe, you know, maybe I'm
missing it.
Maybe this is actually a good way to do it.
I don't really know but it just seems like it's a little bit.
It just seems a little bit off is all.
I could be wrong.
Maybe I'm doing a stupid thing by getting rid of it.
Maybe we should try to continue to use it that way.
I mean, one nice thing about this, right?
Is that it does, I guess, allow you to sort of
more easily, sort of grabbed whole sets of settings, right?
If they're all in kind of one file like that, I suppose that's
something worth looking at maybe.
I don't know, I wish I had a stronger opinion about it.
I just feel like going through that Loop of having the config file
seem to be causing us kind of some problems where we, when we would do
when we would add one of the code, we would have to go in and add it
to the config.
Maybe that's not such a bad idea, though, either?
I mean, you could imagine,
The end of the day, going back and doing that.
I don't know.
I can't say that I have a strong opinion, either way, I think just
what I would like to do is make it so that it's maybe just not.
So
I'd like to make it not so complicated.
So I'm just going to try and take a little bit of that complexity out
of it.
It's all.
So I think I'd like to try that and all this is saying is that hey
there's a variable here, it's called Global pause.
I want to kind of bind it to this editing point in the debug system
and it's assumed that I am going to take care of that.
I've defined the pool.
So it's, you know, the onus is on me and we'll just keep it that way.
It's not as perhaps efficacious as
Other way where the debug system is thinking about a little bit more.
But maybe that's the way that that's going to go.
And so in here when we've got these, you know, when I and I think
debug value is that was debug value.
The Way We Were specifying that maybe not do by variable was debug
value.
The way we were doing that before because I think we kind of have this
concept.
Where was the thing that was getting?
Yeah, I think debug value is it so we can probably even say that maybe
this is, you know.
A way that that could work, maybe we can sort of say, let's take a
look at debug value as potentially a way to do that and maybe we can
even sort of piggyback on this and just get rid of that concept of the
debug variables entirely.
So, let me take a look and see.
Let me see how we were doing that.
I think we were doing it this way, right?
We just say, hey, here's beginning to blockers and day to block and
the begin and data block, I guess the way that we did that we see
here, debug begin block.
Yeah, name and ID.
I don't really know how the ID differed there.
I think it was just to give it a grid that it could always use to
remember.
I'm going to take a look at where we were using that before, which was
in the the place where we printed out the entities if you remember
correctly.
So we had a begin data block.
I believe in there it is.
And yeah, I think it's just like that's just some ID that's sort of
associated with it.
I don't know if we required that or not but we'll see.
So this was let's just say this is platform and this debug ID, I don't
know if we actually
Have one and not let's call it zero for now we'll see if that's a
problem, right?
And Aunt there is no septal conversion is
Turn nasty bug, ID comma, and debug operator equals.
So that debug ID, I guess has to be transmitted a long time.
Some touch this code, that debug ID actually has
Be a real thing.
Yeah.
There it is, kind of see it here.
So if we want to make this one of these it's pretty trivial to make a
debug ID and that debug ID would just be like something that we could
point to some kind of stable pointer in the system, which is not
particularly tricky, right?
You know, since we could just use anything, we could use, you know, of
any pointer from here, that's going to be unique would be sufficient
to make a unique ID for it.
So, let's just see what happens there.
This turnaround.
Time is awful.
My Lord.
So, yeah.
So, in this case,
Unhandled and data block.
What?
What are you talking about?
This is this.
Not the correct way to do this.
Did I do something wrong and made?
World mode.
Okay.
It has to begin data block.
And an end date of block, which is the correct way to do it, right?
So that would be the way we would capture that, right?
I don't think there's anything particularly odd there.
Seems like that should have worked.
I wonder if that's just an artifact of the fact that we didn't quite
finish the debug because stuff, I'm going to take a look at at what
happens in here.
I feel like we don't like the debug stuff doesn't print out.
In this mode.
Right.
I don't actually see the debug there.
So it's here if we're back in here, but if we actually go into the
game, we don't get the debug output anymore, which is lame.
So that's something we have to debug as well because you can kind of
see.
I guess, unless the trees are on top of it somehow, because we
wouldn't really see much against the white, right?
This is just white text.
So if it was back there, we wouldn't actually see it, but presumably
it's on top of everything.
So, the fact that we don't see it there, it's kind of odd because
correct me if I'm wrong.
But before we stopped working on the debug stuff, we moved it into its
own sort of place in the in the platform Loop, right?
I mean, here it is, if I'm if I'm not mistaken,
Right here.
So debug frame end that should in theory have added the debug calls
right there.
so,
I thought.
Is I wonder if this means that we are sorting like that.
Those the basically the sort values of those strings are not
sufficient to put them on top somehow.
But I wouldn't even think that, that would be possible either.
So I want to take a look and see why we're not getting why we're not
getting those because I don't really understand why I'm going to
actually.
I think what I would do.
I think what I'd like to do is, first of all, see whether they're
being drawn.
And the way that I think that I can do that relatively effectively is
just make it.
So that the game World mode doesn't actually render.
It never gets a chance to actually render itself.
I think that's probably the easiest thing to do so.
Like an update and render World update and render World takes
As an input the render group.
And if I was to just give zero this out and so that it doesn't have
any way to actually render anything.
It's not going to do anything.
Go back up here, dude.
Here we go.
Let me see.
What result is actually meant to do.
In this case, not a particularly good name.
So result always returns false, that's pretty funny.
All right, so it looks like that's just completely useless.
So what I'd like to do is prevent the from rendering.
So now, when we switch into that mode, there won't be anything else in
the way, so I can just see whether this is still drawn or not, right?
That's all I really want to see.
Looks like it actually still is, I should probably include a clear so
we can be a little more.
Like I could just move the if zero down just a bit.
So now it is actually still clearing the screen and and that way, I
can see if it's still drawn, because that'll tell me if it's a sorting
problem or not.
Which is what I need to know.
Okay, so as I suspected, it's just that this stuff is getting sorted
in such a way that it's below what's in the actual game world.
So, I need a way of making it so that those things sort in front and
cannot be put behind stuff that's actually in the game.
Because I never want that to actually be the, you know, to actually
occur.
So the question is how to do that most effectively?
The sort key that I give to fonts or that I give to two elements,
right?
I actually have a fair bit of control over, what?
That sort key is because we just make it up.
And so what I could do is make it so that when we do like, a, debug
text line when we actually do any kind of text out.
So, you know, I guess in this case, I've got, let's see here, debug
text up.
Is that the only place we actually do that?
Let me see where actually do a push bitmaps.
Yeah, so I do want to hear and I do one there.
So this is the only place we ever draw fonts in this whole system,
right?
So if I have this push bitmap thing here, when I'm sending this down,
I could have some way for pushed bitmap to sort of override.
What that Z value was in a way that only changes its order.
you know, I'm saying so for example,
In hand and read a group that age.
Well actually guess in this case would be dot CPP in the push bitmap
routine.
You can kind of see here that it's going to go through, push render
elements to, you know, to do, whatever he's got to do and it's going
to call this dim basis sort key, or I'm going to call it's going to
use the result of that bitmap, Tim call.
It's going to use the result that it put in the sort key in order to
determine how to sort.
But we could we're free to pass anything else we want here, right?
So we could trivially just do
Some completely other thing by we could completely biased thesaurus in
any way we the sort.
Anyway, we want by just adding some kind of like a sort bias here,
right?
We can add something in here, that's just like, oh, is there a sort of
bias, you know, whatever it is, by default is nothing.
But if you want to, you can bias the sort value in any way that you
want.
And that would be pretty trivial now.
I don't remember.
It's our sort key, I guess our sort key is at the moment floating
point.
So it would be
An R32 there.
So that's when we do it and if we did it that way, then when we do our
push that map here, I don't super know what we're still using the C
line value for, but I believe it's just for sort of vestigial remain
at this point in get render entity basis p.
It's the thing that multiplies the alignment value, right?
So,
no, it's not in there so I guess it's only in
Get bitmapped in.
So, there's the C line, right?
Are so essentially, that's if we don't want to, if we don't want to
use the alignment information, then we use that value, right?
To adjust it, and I don't really know who sent who's actually still
using that we can check pretty easily by actually just doing this if
we want to.
And now it'll give us an error.
Oops it'll give us an error everywhere in the code where anyone's
calling that version of the function and so we can go ahead and step
through that.
So let's see where that actually is.
Oh, shut up.
Forgot.
There's two versions of this.
Although it looks like that means this version.
Definitely never has that happen.
Right.
So everyone is calling through this actual one, which makes sense
because they're only going to put call through the bitmap ID version.
So I really didn't need to test that one at all, that was just kind of
a waste of everyone's time and energy.
What I meant to do, or should have done?
I should say, is this
All right, so if I come in here and look for that, it seems like
there's really only one place and it's here.
And so this is literally, it's just for the debug system, the debug
system, displaying a bitmap on the screen so that it can do it without
its, it can basically do a debug display, the bitmap is the only case
where we ever used that kind of means we probably shouldn't be passing
that, and that should be a more special purpose thing.
But yeah,
So that's something to be aware of that.
It's something to be aware of, to be sure.
So I'm going to go ahead and switch back to render group a group got
seniority.
So in here, if I then want to I can I'll reinstate that obviously for
the time being
and what I'd like to do here is take that sort bias and actually make
that be a real thing for the moment.
So there's our sort bias and so now someone can pass the sort of bias
in when we call Push bitmap, wheel pass the sort bias, and when we do
that sort bias, it will affect how the Sorting progresses.
So now, inside the debug system, if we want to make everything always
be on top as terms of our fonts, then in our push bitmap, call,
What we could do is at the end here, we would just pass some kind of a
sort bias.
Now we want the sort we want to be closer to us and Z comes at us, I
believe in our coordinate system.
So we want this to just be some relatively large number here, right?
We want this to be something big now, I don't know.
I guess.
It's technically, we could just set it to the maximum.
Don't know that that's actually necessary in this case, but we, you
know, we could we could say it's the maximum value.
I hope that doesn't break anything.
I have to think about if there's anything floating Point wise that
that would break, but I assumed that it would just clamp out the
value.
So, there we go.
Now we've gotten our debug values back and that's all good.
Of course, you can also see that we can really see them very well,
right?
They don't really show up particularly well, and the reason for that,
of course, is that, you know, if the background like, in this case
happens to be bright white, the text is bright white.
We can't see them.
We may want for our debug code to do something, where we actually sort
of draw to draw a little bit of additional drop shadowing on to them,
so that we can see them even in circumstances.
Santa's where they might be harder to see and there's a number of
different ways.
We can do that one way.
Would be to just have the push bitmap call happen twice right?
Like you can imagine doing this and this this two different times if
that makes sense, where you know the bitmap offset here, we could just
go ahead and make that be offset by just a little bit.
I believe we're in pixel space here.
So you know, something like this I guess we'd want to be down and why.
So it really be look like that.
And then when we when we do the color we would just have it be black.
And so
We could do something like this which, you know, I think we I put
those in the wrong order.
Of course.
So that's, you know, my bad but
Now, you can see, we can at least read them in sort of all
circumstances.
It's not the world's prettiest debug display certainly, but it at
least allows us to see even against really unfortunate, you know, kind
of backdrops, it lets us kind of see what's, what, what the, what the
text says we can do better, but that's probably good enough for now.
Now, since we have the ability to sort, I suppose, this is the case
where now we would probably want to say, let's not do float backs, you
know, in this case
We'd say, oh we want that one to be on top.
So, you know, we'll we'll have two of these and we'll just make this
one sort higher because now we can just play with the sort key,
however, we want.
So we know we always want the white leading text on top and the black
backdrop, we want underneath.
So we can guarantee that that always happens in the renderer by just
setting the sort keys.
Of course, in a, in the corresponding way, if that makes sense.
So, alright, that's, you know, that's all fine.
That's what that's, that's great.
But we still have to get back to sort of what we were originally
doing, which is we want some way here to start to edit these values.
And like I said, I don't really know what the deal is with these,
these edit blocks.
I also don't really know how this stuff if this stuff is supposed ill
working where we selected.
So I think it is, so there it is.
So, alright, so I didn't do anything wrong.
This is the part that I wanted to test.
You can see that ended up data blocked.
Doesn't have a printout thing for it.
That was probably just a thing.
We did that was stupid.
When we were, when we were putting this stuff in there and so I didn't
do anything wrong with my begin and end in this, in this other case,
right?
So that seems fine and all this stuff still does seem to be working.
Okay?
So I think we're actually in relatively good shape.
So, what I probably want to do now is I just want to make it so that
these
Can be edited, and then I think we'd be okay.
Now, what I don't really know is, I don't understand how we ended up
in exactly this situation here with the readout because I feel like
this should sort of be underneath something a little bit more
specifically, so I feel like the indentation didn't work properly.
So, let's just go take a look at that, really quickly, as well.
Before we start in on anything, they're just to try and figure out
what was going on with that.
Alright, so here's our debug begin, our debug and and in this case, I
guess the platform bit, I'm not sure how this was meant to work.
So I'm going to go ahead and and and again, look at the world mode
code there and just see what it was doing when it did the debug
values.
And I guess it's just like simulation underscore entity, that's sort
of the block name.
So this would be like
No platform controls.
I don't know what it would be.
And then I guess the idea is we hadn't really, maybe we hadn't done
printing out of the actual block names yet.
I'm not sure that could make that could make sense and yeah, that
appears to be exactly what it was.
So it looks like the way that we're printing out blocks is really just
kind of haphazard and stupid.
So maybe that part is you know kind of Unfinished code in there that
we have to go in and take a look at, let's take it.
Let me jump back in the game here so we can get the simulation
And again as well yeah and you can see that's what it's doing.
It's basically saying here is the Block, it's simulation entity, and
then it gets to the end and it's got this unhandled thing.
It doesn't know what to do with.
So I think what we probably want to do, I'm sorry rather the end data
block 1.
So I think we probably want to do here is we probably want to just
start going in there and cleaning up this code because it looks like
if we clean up this code and just make this a little bit nicer then we
can just use that for everything and we don't have to worry about the
other code with the you know, the if
Trolls.
I think we can just get rid of that code and just that would be a nice
way to pair things down.
So basically like the
See here, this debug interface code.
Where is it?
This looks like the debug if and the debug variable code, I think I'm
just going to say like we're just not going to, we're just not
To do this anymore.
That was like, it was an experiment.
I think it's just adds too much complexity, and we should try to focus
on minimizing that complexity down a little bit because we already
have we know we want the ability to sort of do those little data
dumps.
Let's just put everything through that and make sure that works.
Okay.
And not try to have another system that maintains the H file and all
that stuff.
I think that's just too much, right?
So, let's get rid of those, let's just cut those out entirely.
And see how we would replace them if they just simply weren't there,
right?
So, basically, these these exist in the code, as you see in them here,
and I want to make them go away.
so,
Essentially what this means is just that we have to do a little bit of
work to pull these out into Global's ourselves, right?
And this is why I say it's not the ultimate be all and end all of the
thing that you might want.
But again this is just me making that decision that I want to try and
keep the complexity of the of the debug system down a little bit more.
I didn't like quite how far it had gotten in terms of how much time we
probably want to spend on the total.
So I think in, it's just a good.
Time to kind of pair it down a little bit so what we need if we want
these to continue happening is we just need to have these be variables
that are accessible somewhere.
You know, Global variables that can be sort of accessed, right?
They can be announced and they can be accessed.
And so I think probably the easiest way to do that again would be to
just take the ones that we have now and put those put
You know, put those into some centralized location where we just
announced them and that'll that'll be sufficient.
I think that's fine for our purposes.
Alright, so let's take a look at where that would actually go.
I feel like probably if those just lived kind of in like handmade dot
h or something, that would probably be reasonable.
You can see we sort of started to have a little bit, something like
that here.
So maybe I'll just go ahead and take can make config and you know just
drop these guys.
I mean, I guess we could even just leave them in and make it big.
Now, I think about it like, you know, we could literally just do this.
Right.
We could just do this and say, well, these are all boolean's.
Now, write their Global variables, I probably should have added that
while I was thinking of it, but I didn't.
No, big deal.
And, you know, they can all be set to the variables.
They actually were set to originally
so,
I don't know that we need this to be quite so verbose, right because
the reason that we named them that way was because we needed for the
path to be sort of baked in there.
And so these don't actually need to be as verbose as they are.
Certainly you know the other thing that I need to do obviously here is
I need to remove the code.
We had that does the writing to handmade config because we also don't
want to overwrite that anymore potentially.
So I need to make sure that that's not happening.
It looks like we got rid of that so that's fine.
I just want to make sure
We weren't going to do that and ruin our lives.
So, let's take a look here.
So, where is handmade hammock if they actually being used?
Let me see here, I guess it must be in handmade .h.
The very top, maybe it's in handmade platform.
So there's handmade config.
It's at the very, very top.
And so it's before we even Define any of these other, like, even our
types and that's not probably good, right?
I mean we want to be able to use our types.
So I feel like this kind of wants to be definitely down a little bit
more and I feel like it also probably wants to be inside handmade dot
CPP.
Now,
Or rather handmade that H.
I don't think we want it to be part of the platform stuff because the
platform could do its own, and we don't really need to do that, right?
So let's see.
That's supposed to be an R32 and that's with to have an equal sign.
So, I think now we should be in good shape.
And now, instead of like this, debug if stuff it's just wood, it would
just be if, right?
And we don't really need this anymore because those can be, you know,
we can put those when we when we announced all of them that will
happen automatically.
So let's see, that's an Undeclared.
Identifier housing on the curtain of our is handmade .h somehow not.
Wouldn't handmade.
Config have it in there?
It's the global constants part.
So I guess I probably want to leave that in there.
So I think for now I guess I'll until I want to actually maybe do
something more more, extensive
I probably want to at least leave the word Global in there.
That would be my that would be my preference.
So I think I'm going to go ahead and just do
Constance place of global.
There we go.
Okay.
And I could even, you know, I
I'm just going to leave with little.
All right, so let's start with that.
So this is global under camera debug distance for now.
This is another, if Constance.
What are you complaining about?
I don't even know what that was complaining that we'll check in a
second.
There we go.
Yeah, so this is just a rope modification.
Let's go ahead and I don't know why the compiler is so confused about
that if I guess because because it doesn't know how to interpret debug
if I suppose, I can understand that.
There we go.
Let's see.
What else we got?
So this is entirely wrote nothing interesting Happening Here.
Whatsoever.
And go.
So that didn't seem to like show lighting samples, why not?
Global renderer show.
Lighting samples.
So for some reason handmade render dot CPP
handmade vendor dot CPP, for whatever reason, does not seem to
actually have that included, that could be because
It's in the platform layer because I believe we moved it in there
after we sort of had to do the, the, to tear the, the two top tier
system.
So let me take a quick look at that.
Yeah, so these guys don't have that config file present and that's
actually fine because like I said, I just going to put these in
various places.
I might eventually get rid of him a config
It's all together and put these things in the files to which they
belong.
But for now I can just move that out and say okay will show letting
samples is just going to be something that has to do with this
particular file.
And isn't something that ever actually gets looked at any other way,
right?
So here's a global render you software.
This one now is I believe something that we want entirely new platform
where layer as well.
So that's this one.
And I'm going to get rid of that and I'm going to put that into the
win32.
Handmade part exactly like it was before.
So in the win32 handmade Parts, we've got the the global variables.
So now we've got render use software.
And you software rendering not not really the way you would want to
name things.
So I think we should go ahead and take care of that as well.
So really what we're talking about here is two different things.
Win32 display buffer and window this is whether or not we're using
opengl at all, you can sort of see this.
So what this is actually it's not render you suffer.
This is global like, you know, display with
Opengl or I guess I should say.
This is whether we're using software rendering.
Regardless of whether we're using Hardware to display it or not.
I think that's what I was actually trying to say.
Yeah.
So, this should be Global render like render game via or render.
I don't really know how to how to differentiate between the two.
One is like do display using opengl and what is the render using
opengl?
So I guess it's like
Let me flip these cases in will just say render if render everything?
I don't know.
Having trouble coming up with the name.
This is because it's not, you suffer a rendering, I guess there's you
suffer rendering and use GDI to display and they're really to, they're
really not all the permutations don't actually exist there.
You can't have Global use software.
Rendering be true or false and Global use your data to display also be
true and false.
So really, it's more like enum
you know, renderer rendering type and there's really a couple
different ones, you know, there's
To render.
Type software and GDI, there's win32 render type software and opengl.
And there's been through to render type opengl.
Right.
And another way to say this would be like soft render or render some
Render software display GDI, there's render software display.
Opengl and then there's render opengl display opengl, that's really
the only cases that we support.
We don't support the fourth case, which is render opengl and display
with GDI.
That's not the thing.
We actually support, nor do I, imagine we would ever want to and I'm
going to sort these such that by default 0 is the one we would
normally do, right?
So in this case, we've got win32 rendering type and I've got sort of a
global.
Variable here.
Of that type.
And
That I think makes a little more sense to me.
So now we get rid of this and now it's clear what's going on?
And it's not confusing.
So now I can say, all right, if we are doing rendering with opengl and
displaying with opengl, then that's one case.
So that is our Global rendering type equals that, right?
And that is actually the bottom case.
So that's the first case that we would have and that's the case where
everything
is just
going through opengl and there's no interaction with GTI whatsoever.
I mean what we call swap buffers, so that's everything going through
opengl.
Then if we're not doing that path then we need to switch here.
And say which one of these do we want to do?
Right?
So if we have a little rendering type, we want that to be render
software, display GTI, then we go down One path.
I guess it's actually the way this happens to be set up.
Actually looks more like this.
and so, this one
Is.
Right.
This one is rendering software and display with opengl and there it
is.
And then finally, we have the last one which is rendering software and
display with GDI.
And so here, I can also do an assertion where I'm like, hey, by the
way, in this case, it had better equal the one remaining,
You type that we know we have because otherwise there's some kind of
bug where the value of global rendering type that set to something
bad.
So and like again the reason that I ordered them this way was just
because I want the zero value to be the default value because that way
it's just like automatically initiate.
I always like things that initialized to 0, that's always the best.
If you can have everything initialized by just clearing the buffer,
that's always my favorite because it's the least fussing.
So I always try to make, always the default value to be 0, wherever
possible.
So anyway, that's pretty much it for that.
And compile this.
There we go.
And now we're announcing it.
We have to it's going to bring up a kind of an interesting point that
will get to probably tomorrow, but when we're actually announcing it,
I need to put the global read and type in here, Global rendering type
And that is that it won't display in a way that's particularly useful
to us, right?
It'll display it as an actual number value, as opposed to one of those
symbolic constants, and there's ways that we can get around that,
which we could look at as well.
So anyway, this is what I think we actually want to do.
And so I think we're about a time.
So I'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&A here and what we'll do is
tomorrow, we will hook these up for editing.
And maybe clean up some of these things.
And then that gets us a little closer to being in a place where these
are good.
All right?
So, yeah, I think that's good.
I think getting rid of those, it just like I said, it just gets rid of
a little complexity and I think that's a good, that's just a good
thing to do, because we want to kind of focus in on now, making the
debug system, like, sort of usable and defining exactly what it does
and then not going any further.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and go ahead and go to the Q&A.
So if anyone has questions about what we did, please preface it with
Q: so I can see it and I will answer it.
Well, we can certainly end the stream through pretty quickly if it
turns out there are no Q cones.
Oh, no way keeper.
Killer do you got accepted to college?
Congratulations.
That's excellent news.
I'm really glad to hear that.
For those of you who don't know, kb3 is a very regular viewer on
handmade hero.
He is here all the time.
Do you know 27 1988 Casey At what point is it bad to separate
everything into multiple files and when is it good?
Well.
I mean, I sort of answer answered this question before but I can
answer it again.
It's not really calm.
Very complicated, mostly.
The answer is that files are there.
Let me take this in two parts, assuming that you have control over the
project files, are there for your organizational benefit.
So the answer as to when it is good or bad to slip something into
multiple files is entirely based on your brain.
If you find that having everything in one file versus having things in
multiple files is better for you and you just had one gigantic file,
that would be fine.
There's nothing wrong.
With doing that.
So to a certain extent, the answer is largely dependent on what you
find most efficient for editing.
Like, I like to have an h-file in a CPP file, as you can see for
generally General regions of my code so that I can look at them
side-by-side in the editor.
And it just so happens that the editors that I use like emacs are much
better at doing that than in trying to keep multiple views into the
same buffer.
And so that's just the way I got used to separating my code.
Now if I had used an editor that wasn't like that or that maybe had
better support for like browse info kinds of stuff I maybe I wouldn't
divide my files that way right?
And so the way you divide files is almost universally, it's the case
that you want to divide it, the way that you that helps you program
most effectively.
Now that said
In a circumstance where you're not programming.
Like, we're programming a handmade here, like and handmade here.
We have one translation unit essentially for the entire game.
So everything just gets slammed into one transition and off.
It goes compile time for super fast blah blah blah.
Now if you're on a project that is not that way.
And it's one of these nightmare things, like, oh, I don't know.
It's like, like, maybe the Unreal Engine these days where it's like,
8,000 files, that it takes seven years.
To run a compiled, right?
At that point, you may have a real real, real hard.
Technical reason for splitting something up into multiple files.
And the reason is, because anytime you change a file, it and all of
its dependencies have to be recompiled.
And if that costs a lot, then you have to think about those costs when
making decisions about how to split things into files.
So, if I was programming in an environment where I had to worry about
that, I might make very different decisions about how my things are
split into files because now there's a real reason to and not to split
or not split things into files, right?
And when I'm working with a code base like that I have to be aware of
that.
So so you kind of have to be aware about the build process of the
project that you're working on and
That may have constraints on how you separate things to file.
Such that what I said in the first part, which is you should organize
files, the way that makes it most easy for you to keep in your head
and work with.
You may not have the luxury of doing that, depending on the
circumstances, as you sort of move into certain products that don't
have a reasonable compile time that don't have a reasonable build
process, similarly,
If you are working on a team with lock-based source code control, so
some source code Control Systems, right?
Like get or CVS SVN like the sort of the traditional unix-style source
code.
Controls are locked lists, I mean, sometimes they have optional
locking, but for the most part, all the edits are locked list, which
means that when you are editing your code, you can edit whatever you
want.
And then the time that you deal with making changes that overlap with
someone else's,
Just is when you go to like check you know the to merge those things
together.
But other source code control systems like perforce for example by
default operate in a locked mode which means that you actually say
that you're going to edit a file and you're like I'm going to edit
this file now and no one else can edit that file while you're editing
the file.
And so if you're in a lock based setting like that
Again, I would never don't use this order to a system like that, it's
really bad if you are on teams so you really don't want that at rad.
It was fine to use perforce because it's usually one person, one
project and so perforce and a and of course this is sort of a separate
story.
When we were trying to find a source code show utility use there were
very few.
There's a lot more of them available now than there were today.
Then there there were a lot more available today than there were then.
So we didn't
Much of a choice.
Perforce wasn't like the only reasonable source code control you could
use.
It was like either that or CVS and the all the other options
Release awful things nowadays, you don't have to worry about that.
You wouldn't pick perforce.
You do something else but you could use SVN, for example.
So anyway, that's a whole nother story, but point being I would never
use a lock one today.
If you could avoid it, unless it's only you using it, which case it
doesn't matter so much.
But if you should find yourself in that situation and it's beyond your
control because you're just on a team and they'd use that, right?
You get a job somewhere and you have to do it.
You don't have the option of saying, hey guys, it's stupid, use a
locking.
So let's go control system.
How about everyone just change that right now?
That's not going to happen, right?
And so at that point you kind of have to be in a in of the other
standing well, whatever the grant, whatever the size of the files are
that I choose and how I choose to break them up, that's the
granularity of the Locking now.
And so again,
You have this external imposition on file, you know, kind of file
setups having something that has nothing to do with what you might
want to do and it's more about what the tools are forcing you to do,
right?
So so yeah.
That's what I would say.
Do you try 7 1988?
Okay.
So basically personal preference compile time and external positions,
thank you very much for your answer.
No problem.
Rohit and does texture download on this stream mean GL text image 2D.
Well not really I guess what I would say is
so,
At the moment we wanted the texture, download code to be relatively
correct structurally, right.
So we haven't done anything to aggressive there, but we did make it so
that the asset background threads can call GL text image, 2D on them
to submit the textures to the graphics card.
That is happening, but we found that that was unreliable on Nvidia.
So we are waiting for them to tell us what they think.
The best way for us to do that would be, should we never try to call
on a separate thread because they, it was their materials originally.
That made me think they would prefer us to do that.
That makes sense.
So, on the stream right now, text or download, I think has been said
to just refer to the fact that getting the texture down to the card.
Anything in involved in that.
And right now the only thing we really have to do for that is GL text
image 2D because at the moment we're not trying to do any other kind
of optimization of that path in the future.
The process of getting the texture down to the card.
Might involve other steps like writing into graphics card memory
directly off the load for example.
Hopefully, that answers the question.
So the phrase texture download is just kind of nebulous at this point.
It doesn't mean anything in particular.
It just means getting the the texture data down to the graphics card
so I can use it.
People often call that texture upload as well.
We talked about this on the stream, probably the better way for me to
have set it the whole time.
If I was trying to think very specifically about the best monoculture,
would actually call it a texture transfer.
But because whether it's a downloader and upload, it's like,
Depends on Whose perspective.
Are you talking about the GPU?
Are you talking about the CPU?
Whose side is the, right?
So it's X, your transfer is really what it is.
Dude, in basement.
Have you ever used pragma section and group memory into sections and
read the map file or have you always used to stop metaprogramming?
Yeah, I've never done that.
No, I usually use to pass metaprogramming.
I don't I don't ever try to do back red metaprogramming.
Kubrick Caleb off topic.
If you want to extend the hot code, reloading to work with structure
changes.
Wouldn't you have to store metadata about each struct along with the
information and every allocation so that you could walk the data,
adjust the data and move around and fix pointers, yes, but it is
easier than that.
Makes it sound sort of that's that's one thing.
And the other thing that I would say is I think we talked about this
on the stream because I believe Elvin had a question about that.
And I kind of walked through how that process works.
So on the stream somewhere is is me talking about that but I'm afraid
I don't know exactly where, but yes you you basically just have to
have what is essentially the same as the struct that see.
You know, the information see store is for a struct to know how its
laid out.
You are keeping that same thing but that's not that hard because
Cuz I mean a c compiler is not that complicated, right?
That?
That that part of it so you can power is very simple.
So it's not like it's not a huge onerous burden to do this.
It's, you know, it's a couple days of work but it's not some crazy,
ownerís weird thing, that makes sense.
Guitar.
Maybe seven, do you specifically have to say in line for functions to
be inlined or does the compiler?
Do that automagically?
If it finds one or several to fit?
It's both so within lining, it's certainly a hint.
So it doesn't really do anything.
It's just telling the compiler.
In case you weren't going to consider this for inlining, do consider
this for inlining, but the compiler.
In have to do it and also a function that's not marked in line, the
compiler doesn't have to the compiler.
Doesn't have to leave that out of line.
It can inline that as well.
So the compiler is given pretty much complete latitude to, in line,
whatever it wants, whenever it wants and to the degree the degree to,
which it takes your suggestions into account is entirely up to it.
There are there's a directive in Ms.
V, C to force inlining.
A directive not to force in lining
Or to force non inlining.
I don't know if either of those are required, but I think they're
almost always followed.
So, unlike in line, which could often not be followed, if the compiler
didn't want to, I think force in lines almost always followed if the
compiler actually can, but there may be parts of the compiler just
doesn't.
It's like the compiler doesn't do that or whatever and like it doesn't
want to do that for some very hard reason.
Like it doesn't have code to do it properly or something like that.
Things that would require too many times or it doesn't know how to, I
don't know.
So, I think for certain lines pretty reliable and forced, not in
lines, also pretty reliable, in terms of, you know, would be rare for
them, not to do it, whereas the inline keyword, I don't get the sense
that that's that strong.
I think that's like, if the compiler agrees with you, it'll do it, if
not, it won't.
But I don't know.
It tends not to be that big of a concern like unless your code is
super object-oriented nastiness where it's got all these like, you
know, little tiny functions that don't do much just to get it things.
Then, you know, most of the time, you know, you're just in lining,
your operations and, you know, either the compiler desert doesn't,
it's not a huge deal.
The couple places where you've got real Workhorse code happening,
where you care a lot about what's happening.
Are things you tend to optimize a little bit by hand anyway, and
you're not
Going to, you know, you're not going to be worrying about that, you're
going to look at that.
Code just did the compiler in line suffered in it if it didn't you
could manually in line if you have two or turn into a macro.
So you know it's it's really not a huge deal.
I wouldn't spend a lot of time really worrying about inlining.
It's really not that that big a deal.
Would you try to fix the memory in place or when you copy it to a new
memory Arena, you hat, you have to it has to be new Arena.
And the reason for that is because the size is can change and they can
change in a way that you can't fix.
So, for example, if a struck got bigger, you can't necessarily change
it in place because there's data that comes after it.
You're going to overwrite it, right?
So when you're doing a remapping, it has to be two new memory.
Typically it's not super plausible to write a system that would use
the same memory space so during
Remapping you would make a new Arena and you would copy from one room
to the other.
Programming style.
Why do you have the function return on the proceeding line?
Oh, you're talking about this.
This was a habit.
I got into that.
I just sort of like, which is I like having the name of the function.
Be the first thing on the line.
The way I originally started as amusing, although I don't ever use
them anymore, I used to use like templates a lot when I programmed
when I used to be more
I used to be much more C + + e.
Kind of back in like, in 1998 1999 and I found that template
specifiers were so long that I ended up having to break my function.
Definitions up into two lines anyway like that my function
declarations or definitions in this case.
And so I just even after I stopped using the templates, I still kind
of liked it that way so that's just how I do it.
Strange Zack.
Yeah I don't know what the deal was when I asked about inlining last
night it blew up everywhere.
Yeah.
I mean,
I really just don't think about inlining hardly at all.
I just, I call functions in line more, as a note to myself.
I think I've said this before at than anything else I put in line
before something it's like, me sort of saying either, I think this
should should never be something that actually gets called.
It should probably be saying that just weld it in because it's
something that wants to be optimized away, right?
you know, like,
you know, you get a function like this and I'm just, like I just want
this to get inserted so you can optimize it away and you can see it so
that the compiler will look at those terms in the context of
optimizing, the thing that they get inserted into.
It's either that or I just, this is something I think only gets called
once.
So I just want to smooth.
All these things together, right?
Because they don't need to be broken up, but I really am.
Not like I'm not sitting around agonizing over it because
If I'm doing performance optimization then I need to start like
measuring things and I can't these days, there's no way to just know
if it was smarter to inline something than not.
I mean it's just it's just simply not plausible.
And so I feel like for the most part
I just don't care that much about whether the compiler will or won't
inline it.
Because when it actually gets to be important further down the line,
I'm going to have to start timing those things anyway to know whether
I should have been lined it or not, if it was something that was
really that, you know, on the edge
Gary Johansen.
I was messing around with Loop unrolling by hand, and got massive
speed UPS.
Any idea why that would be well in order to know why?
That would be?
I'd probably have to look at the code that you were unrolling and then
maybe I could give you some guesses.
However, I would say, as you've seen me do on the show before you can
look at the Assembly Language that was generated and you should be
able to maybe make some guesses, take a look at what it looks like
with and without enrolling in and figure out what was the big change.
They're right.
All right, I think that maybe all the questions for today.
I think that'll be it for today.
Alright, I'm going to go ahead and close it down.
There we go.
Thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot-org and it comes with all the
source code, so that you can play around with it in the comfort of
your own computer.
We also have Forum site, if you want to ask questions about the
series, as you work through the programming, or if you have other
programming questions, we have a patreon page if you want to support
the video series because
Subscribe to that.
It is always very much appreciated.
We also have a
Pot, the tweets, the schedule at you.
So if you want to know, when this is going to be live, you can hit
that and the answer to that will it will be live tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
So check that out.
If you would like to see some more programming.
The other thing that I try to mention is the editor that we use was
actually created by someone who watches the stream, it's called for
coder.
If you type for coder into Google, you'll get this page and you can
become a patron of
of his development progress, at which point you can pick from a number
of different reward tiers previously.
I had mentioned that if you do the $10 tier, you get the handmade hero
config that we use here on the stream, Alan asked me to just give that
away for free and it's his money.
So if that's what he would like it will just come with handmade hero
from now on.
So, what I can do is the the for coder here.
That we were using, I guess, it's, for code or Casey.
Somewhere on here.
Where is it?
It's again, it's it's for coder Casey for coder, Casey that Fork Road
or Casey file.
I'm just going to put it in the handmade directory and as of today,
it'll just be in there.
So anyone who has who has handmade hero can can just use it so that
I'll put that in the, the Miss directory, I guess, because it's not
really
Part of our code.
So it'll just go in there.
So there it is and I will try to keep that up to date, as I make
changes to it.
So you can grab it from there.
That's it for today.
I hope to see you guys tomorrow.
Until then have fun programming and I will see you all on the
internet.
Take it easy, everybody.