Flirting.
Here we go.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete professional quality game from
scratch using nothing.
No libraries, no engines.
Just so we can learn about absolutely everything that's in a game
everything that happens all the way right down to what like gpus do
and stuff like that.
So we're actually going to implement absolutely everything including
our own software renderer so we can see how absolutely everything
works.
And really gain that understanding that's necessary in order to be
able to, you know, basically be someone who can build their own
engine.
Build their own libraries, if they want to.
But also, if you're using stuff like that, you'll know exactly what
they are doing underneath and how that sort of stuff works.
So, if you need to drop down and fix something, you can, if you need
to make good decisions about what to use or how to use it, you can,
you basically just have that complete understanding that lets you be
like a really effective game programmer, every level that you choose
to, to go to.
So that is what we have been doing.
We are almost done, fussing with the win32 side of things.
We have basically been working towards
Excuse me here.
We've been 20 days into it which basically 20 hours into development.
We've been building our own win32 platform layer that allows us to do
things, like play sounds and render graphics and get input from the
GamePad and the keyboard allocate memory.
Take tiny results.
And we've done a tremendous amount of stuff in 20 days actually, and
we've done it all by hand.
So it's going actually quite well.
And I'm delighted a bit about it yesterday.
Unfortunately, we found out that the sound card and this machine is
pretty latent.
Takes about 33 milliseconds to get sound.
From when we output it to when it comes out is the best that seems
like we can do.
So that's kind of a little rough.
But today we're going to, you know, basically go back in there and hit
that and see what we can do to try to make it.
Try to get as far as we can towards getting our audio down to where we
want it to be, before we move on to other stuff.
Anyway, if you have gone to handmade here a.org and pre-ordered the
game.
Using this little handy dandy button.
You got a link in your email that lets you go ahead and download
handmade hero, the source code every night.
I update it.
So you can always follow along if you're following along at home.
This is day 20.
So when you download the source code, they'll actually be Zips in
there one for each day.
You just unzip day 19 and you will be exactly at the same state that I
am when I start today.
So you can follow along home.
Exactly.
Whenever you watch this video, Even if you watch it many, many days
down the road.
Now, I also believe I change this from saying weekly builds, to all
bills.
There we go, because some people were getting confused since it's
actually nightly that you can download the stuff.
So I change it to all builds because you get access to absolutely
everything every time I push something and we push something basically
every night.
All right, that said let us go and and get started here.
Someone on the chat was mentioning that we had an off by one error
now.
We've got we've
I only have a couple bugs in what we were writing yesterday because we
didn't really finish.
We didn't get to the point where we really actually
Lift it up.
We only just barely threw it in there.
We threw in some rendering code.
They were saying there was an off by one error with with the, with the
debug time marker.
I'm not sure exactly what they meant by that.
Actually on the chat, if they want to go ahead and point out exactly
what it actually is, then we can go ahead and and look at it
explicitly, but I'll take a quick look just to see if I see what they
were talking about.
We have debug time marker.
Here we advance it.
I don't see an off by one error in the recording of it.
It looks like it's going to record one each time.
So that's good.
Basically, we go in here.
We use.
Whatever the current value of debug time.
Marker.
Index is we increment it by 1, which is fine in the case, where we hid
the array.
Ah, there we go.
That's what we're looking for.
This should actually
They be like that that actually needs to be checking for whether we
hit the actual end of the array.
So that was thank you for that.
That is again, one of those nasty little things.
I don't usually make mistakes like that.
I have to think that probably it is.
I will admit my programming does degrade when I have to talk and
explain stuff as we go.
I think it takes up part of my brain and it's a little harder for me
to write bug-free code, which at the end of the day is okay, because I
I suspect a lot of people watching this stream are beginner C,
programmers, or intermediate, C, programmers.
Perhaps and so possibly, it's better for me to have to debug more
stuff just so we can go through it.
So, let's see there.
That that would lead to a gap once in a while, but we weren't seeing
too many gaps before.
So it's looking pretty stable here.
Anyway, this is roughly.
What we were expecting to see before so we're good.
Yeah, so all that is all good for now.
Basically, what we need to do today is just decide how we're going to
handle, what we're going to, what decisions were going to make based
on the audio latency.
So I'm going to go to the diagram for a minute and just talk about
what we basically found yesterday.
I should probably, you know, double mention I guess perhaps what that,
what that bug was just in case, people weren't clear.
So before I accidentally had typed that whenever the debug time marker
index is greater than the array count.
And
See what happens is.
Remember, these are zero based arrays.
So if I look if I have an array, so if I've got debug time markers and
I refer to the 0th element, that's the first entry in it because
essentially what the syntax means in C and also it gets translated
down to assembly relatively directly.
Basically, what this means is I'm going to take the pointer to the
beginning of the array which is debug time markers, and I'm going to
add 0 to it, right?
So what that means is the first one
Is.
Zero and the last one is actually whatever the count is minus 1,
right?
Because if we actually added all the count to it, we would be past.
The last one will be pointing to One path.
That's we actually pointing to one bite after the very last bite, that
was reserved for this array.
What that means is that when we get to the end, we're actually at
array count when we get to the end.
I don't really need this greater than here.
It's not really necessary.
Really?
What we're talking about is when it's equal to
array count.
That's just kind of being paranoid and saying.
Well, if someone came in here and muck with this value, in some really
bad way, but of course, we'd still have a bug even if that happens.
So really, we can do this and what we probably should do is say this.
We should probably say, let's assert that we are never going to access
outside that array here just so we can double check and make sure that
we don't.
So that's really all we're talking about.
Nothing, but nothing really too too bizarre, but
So, that was just a stupid bug and now it is fixed.
And we can take a look.
A little bit more, okay.
So I'm going to go ahead and open up the infamous.
Microsoft paint paint part number of Champions.
And we talked a little bit about what we learned yesterday, much to
our Chagrin, I should say.
So we decided basically, to start off with trying to hit 30 frames a
second, right?
And 30 frames a second translates into, right?
You've got 1,000 milliseconds, per frame for in one frame, right?
That makes sense.
And so, if we're doing 30 frames per second, 30 frames per second.
Right.
Basically, what we're expecting here is if we actually want to know
how many milliseconds were actually going to have in every frame, we
would divide by 30, right?
And so what ends up happening is we're expecting to see about
thirty-three point three milliseconds, every frame.
That's how long we expect this to take 33.3.
Well, it s like that, that makes
Unfortunately, for us what we end up with is we end up with a, we have
a sound card in the machine, that's going to Output our audio.
And what we would like to be able to do is we'd like to be able to
Output the audio and the video synchronously.
So what we'd like to be able to do is inside any given frame boundary.
We're Computing the next frame.
So if we are in here, if we're somewhere in here, you know, basically
we're showing
Owing.
Some frame.
And this is the next frame.
Basically.
We're Computing a graphic, right?
You know, we're Computing a little graphic here.
We're trying to compute something that we're going to show right at
this boundary.
So this is where we're going to start displaying this to the monitor.
So we're Computing it, you know, sometime in here and we're going to
try and show it here.
So ideally what we would like to do is also compute the sound that
goes with this Frame and and have it line up.
Exactly.
That's what we would like to do.
Unfortunately, what we found out is that the audio latency on this
particular computer.
Anyway, it's obviously going to vary when going through
Sound.
We don't know.
It might, it might be lower.
If we were to try X audio.
We haven't tried that yet.
But you know, we have no way of knowing until we actually try
basically the audio latency is on the order of 33 milliseconds itself.
We took a look at the difference between the What's called the play
cursor, and the right cursor and direct sound.
And we found that basically we could expect somewhere around that 30
milliseconds of latency, which is our entire frame time, which means
that assuming we're inside a frame and we're displaying something or
Computing the next
81.
We can't expect our audio to show up until somewhere like in here
basically, somewhere.
That's like, wherever we start writing it, if we if we write the audio
here, we couldn't expect it reasonably to show up at the earliest
until somewhere out here, which means there's no way for us to
actually compute the audio that goes with a particular frame and
actually have it show up on that frame.
That's just there's really nothing we can do about it.
That's just the truth.
So we've got a couple options here and I can tell you about what they
are.
But none of them are great.
What we may have to do is just regress to a very basic sound Loop and
just accept the latency and accept that it's never going to be
synchronized.
Or we can try to do something that is synchronized on a machine.
That's faster.
And we'll just test it somewhere there.
And I don't mean faster like CPU, I mean less audio latency, but
basically if you think about what happens inside of a frame, we do
have some other options that we could try to pursue and I'll just
discuss with they are briefly and it may lead to US changing the way
we do audio in our
From there, just a little bit.
So basically what happens is, if we break down the time, there's
there's inside of a given frame.
Let's say we're taking this Frame and we want to kind of blow this out
into what is actually happening inside the frame.
So we're going to divide up this time.
This is our 33 milliseconds.
We're gonna divide up this time into the what we're actually doing.
Right.
What we're actually trying to do what we're going to do.
Here is the first thing we're going to do.
That doesn't really take a lot of time is
are going to gather input, right?
We're going to gather input.
Okay, so we're going to get the keyboard.
We're going to get the mouse if we wanted it.
We're not really using that in the game.
But we may use a few big purposes.
We're going to get the keyboard, which we are using for the input with
gamepads that sort of stuff.
We're then going to update the game, right?
So that's this.
We then have some amount of time that we have to do update the game
and make a render list.
So, we have to update
And and like do render prep basically, right?
And you'll see what that is kind of as we go through.
But we're going to update and do render prep in here.
Right?
Then we're going to actually have to do rendering, which is the
massively.
The majority, especially in this type of game where our physics, we're
not doing like a 3D game.
So our full 3d physics and collision detection, that sort of stuff
would normally take more time.
But since it's a 2-D game, will probably be able to keep that code.
Pretty optimal when we write, if we write it properly.
So we're not expecting this to grow that huge.
It'll be complex because I'd like to make it for the compliment, but I
don't know that.
It'll grow that huge.
It might, if we start doing some things, like fluid effects and stuff
like that.
So we can't guarantee that.
But chances are especially during when we have the software renderer.
This is going to be a huge amount of time when we start using GPU.
It might go down quite a bit because gpus especially if it's a fast
GPU will just romp through a 2-D game.
But you know, you never know.
We could run in a huge, we can run a 1920 by 1080 all the time and at
full multi sample and stuff and suck downwards.
You pu X stuff like that.
So you never know, point being that takes a bunch of time.
And then any time that's left over.
We're just waiting, right?
We're just going to wait until the flip, right?
And then here, we actually display the frame, right?
And this can actually be pipeline to some degree.
So, depending on how deep the pipeline is a pipeline, is basically
something.
You're going to push more frames down, have frames.
Be computed overlapped!
So we could start right after we finish rendering this, or even if we
were multi-threaded, we could start doing gather input and updating
before we even do the rendering right?
There's a bunch of ways we could overlap this, but if we're just doing
it synchronously on One processor, no overlap.
Then this is what that's going to look like and then we flip.
Right?
And certainly back in the old days.
This is what it looked like because there weren't multi-core things.
There wasn't a GP
EU.
So you were and you sir, you're just talking about this, this exact
process gather?
Input update, render.
Wait flip right.
Now.
The question then is where do we insert sound in all of this?
Right?
The answer obviously would be if we are trying to minimize our audio
latency and hit this time right here.
Then if we have a 33, Ms.
Sound delay.
If we have something that's close to the frame thing.
Then we'd actually have to start outputting the sound for the next
frame.
We have to Output it like back here.
Right.
Does that make sense?
We'd actually have to Output the sound before we even gather the input
for this Frame, which means that it's sort of somewhat impossible for
us to do.
But if you think about what was actually happening, if we though, if
we go ahead and Tack on basically another frame to it and look at the
same thing.
So, basically just copy what we just drew, you know, over here.
What?
This period back here.
That was that was before the thing.
Well, this was the wait, period, right?
And then before, that was the rendering period, right?
So actually all the way back to almost the beginning of this other
frame.
Let's say this right here is only taking 10 milliseconds and this
right here was taking 23 milliseconds, right?
So we divide the frame time up in basically, The Gather input and that
update step is maybe only 10 milliseconds and then we spent a lot of
time weighted rendering and waiting process.
Probably mostly rendering.
Well, that means all the way back here.
If we look at what the time was it right?
When we actually after we did the update where we could have known,
what the sound was going to be right for the for the next frame.
If we go all the way back here, and look at that.
If we were to sort of output the sound right here on the previous
frame, we could have been only one frame behind, right?
If we did everything, exactly right.
We could have been only one frame behind and
More.
If we actually take this weight period, or if we take this render
period and overlapped and started the update for the next frame here,
right?
So, this is where the gather input happens.
So we basically overlap, The Gather input and update for the next
frame with the rendering of the previous frame.
If we actually overlap those on, you know, to course, we could
actually hit the constraint of being, you know, 40 milliseconds or
something ahead.
Ahead of where we wanted to write that audio and actually get our
audio synced, but there's a cost.
The cost is now we have pushed input Gathering back a little bit
further.
So we introduced basically 23 milliseconds, somewhere around at
maximum 23 milliseconds of input lag.
Right, that would be the cost.
So, if you think about that, is that a good trade?
Probably not for a game.
Like this one's audio sync.
Is not that important because we're not.
None of the gameplay really revolves around.
Hitting a sound directly.
We will probably have audio cues in the game that try to help the
player understand what's going on, recharge times, whatever enemy
attacks, that sort of thing.
So, you know, audio is important in every game.
I certainly don't want to suggest that.
It isn't because it very much is, but how tightly the audio sync is as
a priority versus how tightly the input is synced.
In this game.
I'm going to say that the input lag would be way worse if we did that.
So I think we really want to push our gather input as far forwards as
we can and we don't want to introduce that extra.
Lag.
So given that we don't really have any options, realistically given
that for hitting our audio sync on a
Frame, what I'm going to suggest is that I backpedal a little bit from
what I was hoping to do, which is keep the audio and video synced to
frames and basically say, all right, we're gonna go fall back to a
little bit stupider.
Right?
And and what we're going to do is just say, all right, we're Computing
our stuff and somewhere in here after the update and input has
happened somewhere in here.
We're going to try to right the audio and we're just going to accept
the fact that it's not going to be on a frame.
Hurry, it's going to be basically somewhere in the middle of next
frame and we're going to accept the fact that there's basically 15
milliseconds or so on this card of audio latency, and it's going to
write right into the middle.
We will lie to the game.
So we will tell the game that it is, outputting this frames audio.
So it doesn't the game doesn't have to try and account for that.
15.
Most I cancel a gig.
We won't complicate the game's code by forcing it to do that.
But what we will do, is Will basically
Well, basically say all right, you go ahead and output for the for the
frame.
You're actually going to be lagged by a little bit and this is kind of
a very standard audio Loop and it's unsynchronized.
It's a bit sloppy, but it's better than the alternative, which is
pushing it out to this Frame.
And having one whole frame of lag or buffering a whole frame ahead and
introducing input lag.
So what I'm going to try to do is basically right.
It go change our audio code so that, that is what we do.
In the case, where the
A audio latency is greater than what we think we can achieve.
In the case where it was less.
Like let's say we look and the audio cards got like five milliseconds
of latency.
It's like awesome.
Maybe we're on a console or something and we can get that then what we
will do in that case is we will try to make it so that it is offset.
And basically we will write the audio, we will write the audio with
some buffer.
So that the audio for a frame, does line up with the frame.
So basically we're going to have basically a conditional sort of
output there will basically.
Be one path for latent and one path for non latent audio and they
won't really be paths.
They'll just be our computation about where we're trying to hit will
basically be sort of thresholded.
So so when we look at that lag, assuming that it's more than the than
the get them the, you know, some conservative estimate about where we
can update our audio.
Let's say that, we assume that we're going to be able to update our
Our audio, you know, 16 milliseconds into the frame or something
halfway through, then we're going to say, well, if that difference
here, if the if the audio latency is 16 milliseconds or more, then
we're basically going to have to just be writing as soon as we can if
it's less than that.
Let's push it up to that 60 milliseconds to try and and keep it right
about here and we can even measure what our average update time is in
here to try and keep that as close as possible if that makes sense.
So yeah, we can do we can do a bunch of stuff like that.
Do try.
We'll try to do the best we can and we'll go from there.
So that's about all we've got and I'm going to go ahead and do that.
I think I mentioned on Twitter for those you're following.
I feel like today maybe a long session.
I'm going to go ahead and do this.
It'll take us a little while to do because this kind of code, is
always very finicky.
Very error-prone.
You saw how many mistakes are already made in it and will make more,
I'm sure.
So it's going to take us a while to kind of go through that.
But if we finish that in a reasonable amount of time, I made double
the length of this stream and basically due to h plus the Q&A instead
of one hour, plus the Q and A because there's some other stuff that I
might want to do and I feel like it's a Friday.
It's the middle of the day.
I don't have any particular time.
I might just do a stream.
That's a little longer will see.
We will see where we get.
Alrighty, so basically what we've got here is we have said that we are
going to have frames of audio latency and I'm basically going to get
rid of that notion all together.
So I'm going to get rid of frames of audio latency.
We've got a monitor refresh rate.
We've got our game update hurts here.
And basically, what we, what we're going to do eventually is change
these into.
Let's take a look at these.
We've got our two to do is hear what we want to do.
Eventually is change those to run bike to query window.
For the refresh rate, which we think we can sort of do and just assume
60 in the case where we don't get it.
But anyway, so what we're going to do here is actually delete this to
do.
That says let's think about running non frame contacts for audio
latency.
That is what I just said, we will decide to do and let's use the right
curse or Delta for the play cursor.
Just a Target.
Audio latency.
That is also what we were going to do.
So basically what we're going to do is every time we take a look at at
our get current position right now, so we come in here and we take a
look at get current position to play.
Sr and the right cursor.
The difference between those two things is sort of the minimum audio
latency we could ever expect to have right.
The right cursor says where it's safe for us to right to right now,
the play cursor says, where the audio is playing as far as we know.
So, if we look at those two, the number of samples in between them is
the lowest audio latency.
We can realistically expect to to count on Direct sound giving us in
terms of what it's actually playing, right?
So we've sort of got a value here.
Right.
We've got a right cursor - play cursor.
Excuse me.
We've got a value here, which is basically B between mmm.
we're going to do right cursor - play cursor and that will sort of
give us what we expect our our, our
Our Delta B.
Now, we've got a problem, which is that again.
This is a circular buffer.
Right?
So since this is circularbuffer, whenever right cursor, actually
happens to be ahead of play cursor in the buffer.
This would work.
But unfortunately, if the right Chris are actually happens to be
behind the play cursor, that means that the it is the right cursor has
wrapped around the buffer and come back to the beginning, but the play
cursor hasn't yet.
Then this would not be correct.
Right.
So what we need to do is we need to account for that and
And of say the blights between cursors is going to have an if in it
right.
It's going to be one or the other of these two things and we have to
compute them separately.
So basically we have to say well actually we don't even have to really
do it.
That way.
We can be a little we can be a little fancier so we can do something
like d word unwrapped, right cursor.
If you will, we can basically say
The unwrapped right?
Cursor is equal to the right cursor.
But if for some reason, the right cursor is less than the play cursor,
right?
Then we just do the and I'll just say unwrapped here.
Then we just add the size of the buffer, and so buffer sound buffer.
There's some parameter, we did that was like, the total size, right?
So, basically all I'm saying, here is like, okay, we'll take, we'll
get the right cursor.
We know that we can just subtract.
T', wherever wherever the right cursor is from the play cursor because
it's always going to be after it.
But in the case, where the right cursor has wrapped around so that
it's now before the play cursor technically will just add in the
buffer size, which is where it would be if the buffer wasn't circular
right?
And we'll subtract those two and that should always give us a constant
value.
And so that's going to be basically a Delta that's going to be our
latency, essentially our latency and B.
So B between cursors, right?
Our, I'm going to go ahead and compute that and just guarantee that,
that's true.
We're going to go ahead and change this value in a second.
So the latency sample count.
We're going to go ahead and neuter.
So, in the second here.
We're going to say, get rid of latency sample count because we are not
going to use that anymore.
And what is, what did I do?
Here is not a member of game.
Oh, right.
Well, where's our?
We need our actual, our actual sound output.
Put ER, there we go, too many names for too many buffers.
And so I just want to take a look at that for a second.
There we go.
I want to take a look at that.
And here's our Delta.
So that's looking nice and stable.
You can kind of see even we can we can spot check the case that I was
concerned about.
We can see the play cursor in the right cursor.
Here's the case that I was trying to handle the right cursor is behind
the play cursor here.
So if we had subtracted, these we would have gotten a number that we
were unhappy with.
So, basically, we've
Fixed that.
And we're constantly Computing, the Delta between them now that 5760
number that is essentially our audio latency in B.
There we go.
We are basic Computing, our audio latency and B there.
And that is all we needed to compute.
Now.
There's a variety of ways.
We could have.
Computed that.
That's just the one that I thought was, was the most easy to
understand the, easiest to look at the code.
So I think that's a good one.
And from there, we should now be able to say that that value in terms
of samples.
That's sort of going to tell us basically a number.
We can use to reason about our audio latency.
So in some sense you could think of, we now have our audio latency s,
right?
Is going to be however, many bites there were between cursors.
That's the B /, the bytes per se.
Is how many samples, right?
The how many samples there are in our audio latency, right?
How many samples of audio latency?
We also have our samples per second right in our samples per second.
Basically, is a divisor that tells us if we take samples and / samples
per second.
We're going to end up with s, which is exactly what we want.
Again, dimensional analysis.
You always want to think about that for a second.
If you, if you know what I'm talking about.
Basically, this is this, is that dimension.
This is coming in again.
I I do it in my head a lot.
So it's hard for me to always remember that everyone.
I'm not might not be familiar with it.
But if you look at what we did there were basically saying B between
cursors.
So we basically have a value that's in B, right first.
So that's this value right here B between cursors.
We're dividing by sound output bytes per sample, right?
So bytes per sample.
We're dividing.
By bytes per sample and dividing by something over something else is
the same as multiplying by by swapping those two, right?
So we're dividing because we basically want to X instead of bytes per
sample.
We want to multiply by sample over B, right?
That cancels, the B value and leaves us with samples, which is what we
want in the top.
We then are dividing dividing by samples, right?
Second.
And again, that just swap these two.
So that s over samples, right?
And this becomes a multiply right that swaps.
Those to cross out the samples.
And we're just left with s, right?
And S is the what we were trying to compute.
So, again, just dimensional analysis, really simple.
It's a way to work out the ratios in your head until you're just do
them by wrote which I tend to do.
So anyway, that's that's all that is, right.
So B between cursors, / B per sample.
Is the number of actual samples and then divided by the samples per
second.
We could also have if we wanted to save ourselves.
Some time.
We could have put bytes per second in there, which is probably a good
idea.
In fact, you know, maybe when we're doing some cleanup here, to do,
Casey math, gets simpler if we add a b/s field because we could just
use that which has this sort of baked into it.
So anyway, something to think about, but that will basically give us
Our latency in float, but remember it won't know to convert to float.
It'll, it'll look at all these.
It'll look at these three.
See Will and say, they're all integer.
So this would do the divide an integer.
Now that first divide we can do in terms of I'd if we wanted to
because it's going to be an even multiple b b between curses and even
multiple, but I don't really need it to do that.
I'm going to, I'm going to tell it to do everything in float anyway,
so I'm just going to cast those up to floats because we want the final
thing.
In floats.
So at that point we actually do have our value in s so I could print
out that as well.
What the Delta is in seconds and just you know, why not audio?
Latency seconds just to make sure you can never really make be too
sure with the number of crazy things that happens in programming.
You can never be too sure.
And so there you go.
You can see that.
That's exactly the number that we were suspecting right around 33
milliseconds, which is what that number is.
So we're basically looking at
30 milliseconds slightly less than the frame time.
Is is what we've got.
So that is our audio latency s, that is the best that we're ever going
to be able to do.
So, looking at that value.
Basically, what we want to say is, when we do our computation of what
to write, we're going to take a look at this audio, s audio latency, s
value, and are in fact, B between cursor.
This should be audio latency B, really, right?
So, audio latency B, and that basically is going to be right here.
So, what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to save these values for
now.
These are going to be actual values that go with our sound is valid
thing, and maybe now might be a good time to
Are pulling these out, but I'm basically going to put those in there
like that.
Audio latency s where it's audio latency.
S.
There we go.
So I'm going to compute those so that we can basically use those later
when the sound is valid and we're Computing where we're going to write
to because you remember we kind of did a thing where we said that we
wanted to make the sound be valid sort of the next time around.
So here's our sound is valid again.
Flights between cursors, body Alexy, B.
There we go.
All right.
So basically, that's that's just going to leave those values up here
for us to be able to reason about when we go to actually output the
sound.
So, let's take a look here at where that happens.
So that
It's right here.
Basically, what we were doing is we're Computing where we want to
generally end up in terms of where to write to, you know, we're sort
of in the, the running sample index.
We want to write to.
So, we know that we've set, our running sample index.
If we look, when we first start up, we're going to set that to be
equal to wherever the right cursor.
Was that is where our running sample index is.
And I'd also say, for math purposes to do should running sample index
be
Invites as well because a lot of times we're mapping in and out of
samples, but I wonder if that's really all that useful because
remember, the running sample index is really only used up here for
this particular thing.
And we could just go ahead and keep that in B, which might be a little
smarter, save some math and possibly reduce some errors.
So that's all we're doing there.
We're basically saying we're going to write.
This is the last place we wrote to.
And we now need to know, since we're going to lock from there.
Where is our Target cursor, right?
Where is that actually going to be at?
And so before we were using the last play cursor, but now I think
probably what we want to do is we want to basically say whatever the
last right, cursor was.
So the last play cursor will actually keep the last right cursor as
well.
See here, and this should make some people happy because they were
nervous about the way I was doing it before.
And, you know, they're right to be nervous.
It's always good to be nervous.
I'm an experiment e, kind of dude.
I go in to code often times.
Oops.
Why did I delete that?
I just wanted to add this one.
I want to leave the other one.
I'm just going to save.
I'm just going to save both of them here so we can take a look at both
of them.
We're doing computation and printouts and so on.
I like to go in and you can tell this code is very, this code is very
fluid.
Right?
I'm just kind of hacking the stuff in here as I experiment around with
it.
And then you'll notice, I've also never decided to pull this code out
and tried to clean it up into a little encapsulating thing.
And the reason for that is it's just not right yet.
Like, we're playing with it.
I'm not happy with it.
I
Is not to pull stuff out.
Until I'm happy with how it works.
And that is what's going on here.
Right?
I'm just, I'm just basically in there mucking with the code trying to
see what seems like a good way to have it work.
And that's a very intentional, that's a very specific way that I tend
to program.
And I think it's a good way to program.
Basically.
I think that it's important not to try to make good clean readable,
lovely code right away.
Because you burn a lot of time when you're in this state, like we are
now we're kind of pushing things around where things are kind of
fungible and we're trying to massage them into a place that we're
happy with it.
We don't know very much about the hardware.
We learned a lot about the hardware yesterday.
All that sort of stuff and so we're kind of pushing towards that point
and while we're in that state.
I like to kind of keep things pretty pretty sort of messy and fluid.
I find it saves more time in the long run to do it.
That way.
You don't want it too horrible.
Because you don't want to introduce bugs by how horrible it is.
So we want to try and keep it a little bit cleaner.
But, you know, we do what we can plus, I gotta admit, I can cheat a
little bit because on this stream, there are so many people who watch
this program.
I get kind of Lucky they catch errors for me too.
So so I get a bonus.
It's almost like I've got a pair of programmer with me programming all
the time.
Catching stupid mistakes.
That I make.
That's, that's kind of awesome.
You got to admit.
There's some fringe benefits to doing this stream, to me.
It's it's actually kind of pays off a little bit.
Just in terms of extra eyes on the problem and you would be surprised
how much that helps because when you're programming, you miss stuff
all the time and having people who are just doing nothing but take a
look at your code and going.
Hey, wait a minute.
Does that work?
And then going, he missed, something is pretty great.
It's yeah, it's like
Whole a whole Suite of pair programmers but standing behind you just
like catching catching problems.
All right.
So anyway, we've got those values now.
So what we need to do is we need to think about when we're going to do
our computation of where we want to write to basically we know what
our audio latency is.
We know what the right cursor was, right?
And so, really, all we have to determine is how much past the right
cursor?
We actually want to write in terms of the the sample count.
So, basically, what's going to happen here, going back to the diagram
is we're in a situation where we're we've just flipped, right?
We just flipped.
And when we, when we did the flip, we're at this point in time.
In fact, you know, I can just I can show you where we are in the code.
This happens, right?
We did our sleep.
And by the way, that reminds me, I wanted to change this to.
This is not really supposed to stay in here.
So log miss here.
So this should actually not be an assertion because this will happen.
I don't like assertions for things that actually we know are going to
happen.
So we need to log a Miss there.
It's not.
It's not really.
This is a Mist sleep, just sleep.
So, okay.
Sorry about that.
Just need.
I just I remember
A things sometimes, when I'm thinking about them.
I remember things and I'm like, I want to change that because I don't
ever like a certain things that are actually going to happen.
That's fine.
I assert things that are going to happen when I'm testing code, but I
don't like to leave those in there.
The game should never assert when you're running it.
That's always just a bad thing.
All right.
So basically, what's going to happen is right here.
We did our flip win32 display by from we do, and then we asked what
the current position was.
So basically, we did our flip here.
We asked what the current position is, and we kind of know that the
price
The play cursor is going to be like, like so we're right here.
We're here right?
At the flip time.
We asked for the play cursor is, and we kind of know on this machine.
It's going to be like, right there, right?
It's going to
Pretty darn close to where we were, at least what we're expecting.
Right?
And so the right cursor is actually going to be here.
The right cursor is actually going to be somewhere out in the, you
know, the frame like here.
This is where the right Chris is going to be if that makes sense.
Now, it could really be anywhere.
I mean, we don't know that.
I'm just saying, you know, it's going to the play cursor is going to
be somewhere behind where we are in theory or close to if we
A really good, it be close to where we are or I guess you could even
think of it as the play cursor might even be in front of us.
So it's going to be it's going to be somewhere right around where we
are.
Hopefully, if our audio sync isn't awful.
It's going to be somewhere in here.
Then we basically got the right cursor and the right cursor could be
anywhere out here.
Right?
So we're hoping that the right cursor is somewhere kind of back in
here.
Possible.
We're hoping that we're not a whole frame ahead.
But you know, whatever it's going to be somewhere.
So then what we have to determine right is from,
That right cursor.
How much do we have to write ahead in order to make it so that the
next time that we come back around our audio, latency hasn't caught up
with us, right?
So we're going to do a right and we know we're going to wait 33
milliseconds.
So we have to do at least 33 milliseconds worth of writing because we
know that however far you know, whatever our sink was.
We're going to basically have to try to do roughly 33 milliseconds of
writing, but we also need to account and if these these clocks were
perfectly in sync, it would always be that 33 milliseconds of writing
that we want after the right cursor.
We also have to figure.
Well, we've got.
We've got this audio latency in here to account for now.
I guess if you think about it, if the audio latency, this is the part
that I was talking about with two conditions.
If we know that the audio latency is larger than the frame.
So basically I kind of needed a better diagram here because this stuff
is kind of confusing and I want to make sure that I've drawn it out
just right, okay.
So let's take a look at that.
Very first frame.
All right.
So we basically have our thing going on here.
We're going to do.
Our first frame is silent.
Basically when we're because we're not actually displaying anything,
our first phase silent.
We go to do the flip.
This is the first time.
Anything actually shows up on the screen.
So we flip here and then we asked essentially, we've got our sound
buffer, our sound buffer is here.
This is our sound buffer, right here.
We ask where things are and we find out that the play cursor is here.
We find out that the right.
Cursor is somewhere around here.
So there's the play Chris, or in the right cursor.
We figured this out at this particular flip, right?
So that's where that is.
Now.
Basically, what we have to do is we have to start writing to here.
This is where we're actually going to write and so how much
Sound, are we actually going to want to write?
Well, it seems like we just want to write at that point.
We definitely would just want to write one frames worth because we
know that this this is already accounted for.
So the play cursor is going to have to go the distance of the audio
latency, which is our actual latency, right?
It's going to have to go the distance of our audio latency and then
start playing and it's got a full 33 milliseconds to go, right?
So, that's totally that's totally we want and then this is just our
30.
Ms of audio latency that there's really not much.
We can do anything about now if we wanted to then this is where it
gets even in Harrier, right?
You could imagine us actually waiting on that we could or doing that
that guess right about here.
The first time out.
We could imagine doing that guessed right about here and that would
reduce our initial audio latency, right?
If we ask here instead of at the flip, so what we could consider doing
and saying
Well, yeah, let's move it.
Let's move it back.
Instead of doing it.
The way we are, let's say we ask for it here, right?
Then.
We know that we basically are going to wait this amount of time.
So there's however much time between when we asked.
And when we expect to do the flip, right?
That's going to be the elapsed time here, right?
And the total time here of the frame, the total frame time.
It's going to be the difference between those.
It's going to be total minus.
The elapsed is this time, right?
So, our total minus the elapsed time is how much, how much of the play
cursor, right?
Cursor thing.
We expect to eat up before we actually start playing right, if that
makes sense.
So we kind of could query that here go.
Where is the soonest?
We could write to if that number is less than this time.
If this difference between the right cursor and the play cursor is
less than this time, right?
Then we are at that point, then we are at the point.
Where we need to delay and push it out further.
So we're going to right after the right cursor, basically, right, and
line it up like that, if it's later than we're just going to write at
the right cursor and we're going to write that 33 milliseconds, right?
So that's kind of complicated to think about.
I'm could complicating it.
Even myself in my head.
I'm like, oh man, this kind of complicated.
So, basically, what we're doing here.
Is whether that audio latency threshold is hit or not.
We're going to have to do a different sort of thing.
We're either going to have to intentionally sort of push our audio out
in the case, where we have a super fast sound card or we're going to
have to just write directly to the right to the audio right cursor.
When we look at where the right cursor actually, is.
We're going to write 33 milliseconds out from it in the case, where it
is, where it is too late, right, but
What?
So thinking about this a little bit further.
Basically, basically, I think that's all it boils down to so we look
at the right cry.
Think even though it's very complicated.
Think about, it's a lot of mental, gyrations here.
I think all that means is what we should do is when we go to write to
the audio, we look at where the right cursor is.
We say that we need to be ahead of that, right, cursor by the frame
time.
So we're going to write one frames worth of audio past the right
cursor.
But in the case, where the right cursor is actually far enough ahead
that we don't expect to get there in time.
We write that much less audio, right?
So basically, if we go ahead and we query these things and the right
cursor is actually inside our frame boundary.
It's actually it's actually earlier, right?
The right cursor is somewhere inside before where the flip is, then
when we write the audio out.
Out.
Instead of writing, instead of writing the full 33 milliseconds, We
could decide essentially to kind of push that out.
Push that out a little.
How would that work?
Exactly the first time through?
We would we would add a little bit of time to it.
That see the confusing thing is we always have to write from where we
left off.
So the next time I'm gonna have to actually do this out, just to make
sure
That we're doing, I'm going to actually do two frames, right?
So the first one I'm going to do, I'm going to actually work out, the
case is 100% just so I have both a good explanation and in my head a
good way.
So let's do first, this is audio low latency.
So very low latency.
Audio Happening Here.
Something that's going to be extremely low, audio latency on the sound
card.
So we ask here.
This is our ask and it turns out when we look at how much time the
audio is going.
Take, we expect it to basically the right cursor will be here.
Right?
So what we would want to do there is we want to move the right cursor
forward on that first frame so that it lines up with this.
So we're actually going to start our right here, and we're going to
write just one frame of audio, right?
That's all we're going to write is one frame of audio.
So that's what would happen here.
We then asked again here, right?
And we assume the audio latency is still very low.
So we would get the fact that
Right cursor is here and we would be here writing to it to this Frame
here and we would want to write one more frame.
So in this case, we would basically always just be writing just the 33
milliseconds and we would never want to write anything else, right?
But there's the audio clock problem where we want to make sure that
we're not going to just constantly fill the buffer.
Like let's say we were slightly off so we were always slightly.
Lee, we were always slightly writing too many bytes because wall clock
and the audio clock diverged.
The audio clock is a little slower or something like that.
That's the part that makes things really complicated.
So we can't always right exactly 33 milliseconds.
We have to write 32 milliseconds adjusted by however much the clock
consumed.
So what we need to see is how far did the right cursor move between
those two times on average?
Right?
So what we're going to do is say the average instead.
Ed of saying 33 milliseconds, we're going to say, whatever the
average.
Right cursor movement was over, you know, some some number of frames,
right?
So, we're basically going to say, however, much we think 33
milliseconds is in audio clock time.
That's how far we would right ahead.
Right?
So hopefully that makes some sense.
So, when we look at the right cursor, we'd say, if it's going to be
within here, will actually push it out to where we think it should be.
And then we'd always right that average, every
That's what we would want to have happen.
So basically just to summarize, what would happen here.
We're going to
if if we're inside frame for the right cursor, then we always write
the average right cursor, motion amount.
Right, so that's that's what we would do here.
And I think that gives us the least audio latency versus the frame
because basically the sound would show up early if we just wrote to
the right cursor and we don't actually want that.
So we basically want to wait we want to we want to do on that first
one.
We want to try the line them up.
And then from then on we always trying to want to line them up again.
Now, could we do this in a better way?
Could is there some way to look at the right cursor?
And
Do it without having to track that average because that would be nice.
It was just a more stable computation if that makes sense.
How would we do that?
So if we wake up here and we basically find out that the right cursor,
the difference between the right cursor and the play cursor.
Is it?
So we would expect the play cursor to be here in all, you know, if
we're assuming the low-latency car, we expect this like Russia to
here.
We find out that the right cursor is here.
So we know the Delta between these two is that and we can sort of say,
well.
Alright, in that case, how far do we want to write?
Well, we want to write from the right cursor forwards to our sample
index.
We're assuming that the sample index fell on a
A frame boundary.
Gosh, how do you even can you even do that computation?
How would we do this computation using only the right?
During the play cursor because they're the things that are in that
clock space.
Is there a way to do that?
Yeah, I don't I can't think of it.
To be honest with you.
I just I can't think of it.
We know how far forward the right cursor.
We know how far forward our estimated number of samples per frame is
but we don't really know.
Yeah, we don't really know anything else.
That's something to think about.
I don't know if anyone out there on the stream can think of a better
way to do this.
It seems pretty tricky to me to do anything other than just track that
average right to track.
You can see what I'm having trouble figuring out if there's a way to
do basically we're this is all this is a wall clock thing that we're
doing here.
We're using query performance counter, but the audio clock may not be
perfectly synced with the wall clock, it maybe like a sampler to off.
Something who knows, right and you can ignore the five-minute warning.
Like I said, long stream today, so we're good to go.
Basically the wall clock.
This is what the wall clock is thinking, but the audio clock may be
off, so I can't just use the wall clock to determine how much too,
right?
I can't just cold right out the samples.
So what I need is a way of saying, you know, if I'm estimating where
this is going to be, if I ask in the right cursors, here the play
cursors back here.
And I'm estimating.
Okay, if the play cursor is here, where is the play cursor going to
be?
When the time has elapsed, I can estimate where the play cursor would
be.
I can estimate where the right cursor would be and I can basically
say, okay.
I'm going to make sure that we write at least past where that right
cursor is at least one frame past it.
I guess maybe.
That's maybe that's the way to do it.
Okay.
How about this?
Here's a proposal.
Here's a proposal for you.
Tell me how the stream likes this.
Let's say we do a thing where we go.
We wake up, we ask where the right cursor.
Is.
We forecast forward where we think it will be.
Right.
Basically we say, all right.
We have a wall clock estimate for where we think the right cursor will
be.
We push that forwards.
We then say, we want to write at least up to the next frame boundary
from
Are right?
And that is the sample index that we write to.
So it's always based off this.
So, in the case where the right cursor and we do that only when the
right cursor is behind basically, right?
If the so yeah that okay.
I like that.
We basically say Round Up to frame boundary from
The right cursor is projected because that basically gives us the
thing that we wanted, which is, which is we always just fill the next
frame and we're synched.
We're synched to it properly at that point.
If the right Chris are always, is kind of behind.
I like that.
A lot.
That is feeling much better to me.
I think we're getting there people.
It's as anyone else love this stuff.
That's the weird thing about it, too.
I feel like, there's probably a lot of people watching.
God.
There's just so much finicky stuff in here, but it's like,
there's something so satisfying about banging your head against
something for a little while and then making a little breakthrough.
It's kind of like playing a great puzzle game, right?
It's like it was confusing.
It was it was confusing, right?
And then you start to see little little sort of breakthroughs there
and we're getting much better than we would have had.
If we just through audio out, the sound card.
If you just throw it out, the sound card.
You have no idea how it synced.
So, even if someone makes a really low latency sound card, and gives
you this great Hardware, your game, just threw it all away.
So you weren't synced at all.
You now, your audio was early instead of late.
But if we actually take the time to work this out, just this one time,
we then have an audio layer that can actually
We respond to that, and be pretty cool.
So, yeah, so I think we're making good progress here in this.
I don't know.
This is what I like about programming and that, and then you get to
write that great article someday, right?
That's like how to do audio output right and everyone can benefit from
it.
Right?
So I feel like it's good.
It's just good to work this out.
So I feel like that's that's that's it.
I'm going to, I'm going to re draw this here and make sure that I
think that it's good.
So we got two cases.
This is going to be the low latency case.
Ace and then we'll work out what the high latency case is in a second.
Okay.
So basically what happens is we wake up.
We need to write audio.
So this is our wake up.
We find out where the right cursor is.
We find out that the right cursor is basically less, you know, we
figured that it's inside the frame boundary, right?
So the right cursor is inside the frame, that means that we will be
able to actually be audio.
Synced.
We know that on this, we have a card that is
It's enough that we will be audio sync.
So that's a card that had like 10 milliseconds of audio latency 5,
milliseconds of audio latency.
Some kind of pro grade audio.
Stuff coming down the pipe here.
That's what we got.
Maybe you're running on an as asio driver, its professional grade.
Who knows?
Or you're on a console and things are direct.
So, basically, what we do in that case, well, what we do in any case
is first, we project the right cursor forwards.
So we take the right cursor, right?
We take the right cursor, plus frames the set, the frame samples.
However, many frames.
Samples, we want that makes sense.
So we take the right cursor, press the number of samples for frame.
We look at where that is.
It's here.
We basically say, okay, we're going to want to write up to wherever
the frame is.
So then our Target
Is basically the next frame, the next expected frame boundary, right?
So, wherever that's going to be in time next frame bonding time.
That's where we?
That's where we write 2.
So, we write up to here, right?
We come there and we then say, all right, we woke up.
Here, we ask for the right cursor.
Is it's like here, roughly, where we thought it was going to be, we
project.
It forwards.
We truncate up.
We look up words.
We say that's right.
As to be, we write forwards, right?
So this is basically what we are trying to do.
Okay.
Now, let's take a look at the case where we have a high latency card.
So we wake up here and here's our frames again.
Same frames.
We wake up here.
This is where we wake, right, same time because we're basically
assuming that basically, you know, the, the game updates sort of not
based on the sound card latency.
So we sort of waking up as a bad term.
It sounds weird sleeping, we get
It's with the stuff here.
We look at where we need to write our audio.
We find out that the right cursor is actually going to be, you know,
out here somewhere, right?
Excuse me.
Okay, the right Chris is going to be out here somewhere.
So we're like yikes.
All right, so the right cursor is actually like past the where the,
where the actual frame boundary is so we know we're going to be super
latent.
Basically what that means is that where we need to write to is going
to actually be just up to the next frame boundary at all.
Is that correct?
If the right cursors?
There, then the next time we wake would be here.
No, so so
Typically its exact same.
The code is still totally exactly.
Right.
The only difference is the when we write up, when we write up here.
We could choose not to round up to the next frame boundary.
We could choose just to add a different amount in here.
So so we could add however much.
We think our audio latency safety margin would be basically is what we
could do.
So, we could do this right here.
The target is rounded up to the next frame in this case.
And the other one, we do the same thing.
We do the wc+ frame samples.
But instead now, the target is just that the target is that plus a
safety margin, right?
So we won't round up to the next frame.
We'll just have a little safety.
Margin, whatever we think we can get away with their the lowest thing.
We think we could get away with
In terms of our safety margin and the safety margin would basically
be.
I mean, it's basically going to probably be just a few samples.
I mean it's because basically, we're writing
Like where the right cursor tells us to be at that point.
So so the safety margin could be as little as like one millisecond or
something.
Right?
I think that would probably be fine.
It's however much we think there might be very variability in this if
that makes sense.
So that safety margin can actually be quite a bit less than the Delta
that we were pushing up, right.
So these are the two things here.
So now, the only thing we have to deal with is at startup, we don't
actually know the the concept of where the right cursor is.
Is not particularly understandable, right?
If that makes sense, because we don't actually know where the right
cursor is inside our frame.
Inside our kind of concept of a frame, if that makes sense, like
saying, where the right cursor is versus the, I guess, I guess we do.
It's just the play cursor is where we are now, right?
The play cursor is where we are now, and the right cursor is where we
where we will be.
That's like, it's as good as we can sort of do at that.
First initial startup.
Does that make sense?
I think that makes sense.
So, basically, we look at the Delta between the right cursor in the
play cursor.
That's what we're going to get.
Now.
There's a problem.
The thing with that as well, mapping that in there.
That's that's makes things even harder.
So this, this seems like the right computation, but the one thing we
have to remember is this play counter thing is very latent in terms of
how often it updates.
If you remember.
Basically that jump.
Let's take a look at that for a second.
Here II.
Left that Loop in for a very good reason that jump that happens.
Let's see here, doodoo turn that back on.
So remember I did a little thing you're so we could see how frequently
the audio updates at all like basically just you know, just just
taking a look at at what the jump is by of these two things.
So, if I take a look here, that's the B, the minimum B that it ever
goes up by.
So, for a 9920 - 48000, that's how many bytes it goes up by / that we
get 480 samples.
So, again, 480, samples pretty big.
Oops, love that shake thing.
I wish it wouldn't do that.
I should turn that off 480.
Is the granularity of that of the 480 samples?
So 480 samples, if we actually divide that by the total number of
samples per second, that's 10, millisecond granularity.
So basically what that means, if we go back to the, to the drawing,
this is why I'm getting so nervous about this because this is what we
actually want to do if we could map these into time, but if you think
about where these actually are, it's going to report this
With an error of plus or minus 10 milliseconds, right?
We don't actually know when we ask
This is it could, well, it's I guess it's not plus or minus in some
sense.
We know that it's it's it's plus or minus 5, I guess, technically,
right.
It's when we ask, where this is.
It could have been anywhere.
Sort of in this Zone, a 5, millisecond, forwards, 5, milliseconds,
backwards, and some sense.
We don't know where it is because it updates So lately.
So,
Where met correlating are two buffers, we have up to 5 milliseconds of
slop in there as well.
That's just makes it even harder.
So you see why this is so complicated.
It really does make it pretty tricky for us to figure out how we could
actually try.
If we wanted to how we could actually try to hit this thing.
We look at where we are.
We look at what the the play cursor is.
We just don't know the play.
Sir is only updating every 10.
So for all we know the play cursor could be 10 milliseconds, a header
10 mil.
I'm sorry, five more seconds ahead of five-month Ms.
Behind in terms of wall clock time.
So we have to figure that every time we wake up this this is going to
be this kind of nasty thing that shifts back and forth by five
milliseconds and five.
Milliseconds is enough that we could end up if we looked at where the
right cursor is and we said, oh it's inside.
Based on that estimate, what if that's wrong?
Because of the five milliseconds that it's and it's going to jump
forwards very soon.
Soon.
Thereafter, we could assume that's always a minimum bound and do it.
That way.
Try think if there's any downside to doing that, I assume.
It's always conservative.
So, I think, I think we're probably still.
Okay.
I think we're probably still.
Yeah, so, I guess, what we can do is
Use the play cursor to determine where we are in the buffer, right?
So basically here's our sound buffer.
We basically wake up, we say, where is the play cursor in the sound
buffer?
Right?
We Mark where that is.
That's, that's where we are in the play cursor, right?
It at this time.
We then know we have a certain amount of time left to go so that we
map in the samples.
We say.
Okay, here is where the frame boundary would be in samples.
Right?
We say it's this many samples ahead of the play cursor.
We look at
The right cursor and we say, where is the right cursor relative to
that?
Right?
That's stable.
No matter what?
I guess.
Because, hey, it's a little late and whatever.
We look at the right Chris.
Or if the right cursor is behind that, then we're in this case.
If the right cursor is ahead of that.
Then we're in the other case.
I'm happy.
I'm pretty happy with that.
Basically.
This is the same as a normal sound output Loop, which would basically
just be doing this, right?
But we've now identified this other case where in
In, if we were given really low latency sound output.
I think we now could actually literally hit.
Our sound sink.
Exactly.
The more as the audio card, converges to Accurate.
We will converge towards outputting sound.
That is right on that frame, flip?
Right on it.
If that makes sense.
I'm pretty happy about that.
Maybe there's a mistake in our logic somewhere, but I'm pretty happy
about what we just worked out.
I wish we had a little thing that was like, a little happiness flag.
I feel like maybe the owl of shame.
I don't know.
Maybe the outer shame shouldn't be analysis.
A.
Maybe we shouldn't reinforce.
Our owls are shame.
Maybe we should reinforce our victories.
I don't know.
What do you think?
Should it be an owl of Victory or an owl of shame, or do I just need
to get to owls?
I guess I'll leave that to the stream and maybe even in the forums
will have to have a thread that's basically out of shame or owl of
Victory.
Which one do we want?
And I don't know.
Of course, we can't hold it up yet because we don't know if this
actually works and we have to go actually do it because there might be
a hole in our logic, but I like this.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm going to write a little comment here
down at the sound output code that sort of says how this works and
will when we extract this out and cleaned up a little bit.
We're basing to leave that comment in there just so it says how this
works.
So, because that was pretty important.
It took us a while to figure out, so I'd like to kind of just notate
it.
It so that it's very clear.
How's sound output computation works?
So what we're going to say is we're going to say in the case.
So when we wake up to right audio, basically, we will look.
And see what the play cursor position is.
And we will forecast ahead where we think the play cursor will be
after.
Sorry, we will forecast ahead where we think the play cursor will be
on the next frame boundary, right?
We will then look to see if the right cursor is before that if it is,
we will write up to the next frame.
Boundary from the right cursor.
And then one frame further which should give us basically exactly what
we want.
We will write up to the next.
So one frame boundary if it's before the frame battery, right up to
the frame boundary and then one frame further giving us perfect.
Audio sync, in the case of a card.
Has low enough latency, right?
So basically, we will write right?
We will, we will write up to.
I don't know how to say this, right?
So we will look to see if the right cursor is before that.
If it is the, I guess we'll say the, the target fill level or whatever
Target fill position, is that frame boundary plus 1.
Frame, right?
This gives us perfect audio sync in the case of a sound card that has
low enough audio latency, right?
If the right cursor is after the next frame boundary, then we assume
we can never sync the audio perfectly.
So we will write one frames worth.
Of Audio Plus a guard.
Plus some number of guard samples.
So, you know, one millisecond or something determined to be safe.
Right?
So we can actually say this is whatever, this is.
Maybe it's half the frame time, it's whatever we think the
variability, whatever.
We think the variability of our
Frame computation is right.
So we could set that all the way up to one whole frame ahead if we
were nervous, but basically that's that's really all we need to do and
this is the same basically what we need to say, if the right cursor is
before that.
It's really but before that buy-in by our safe by our safe amount,
right?
So we basically have a safe amount.
We should try to Define this.
Here.
We will say, we Define a safety value.
That is the number of milliseconds or the number of samples.
We think our game update Loop may vary by, right and so however much
that
Is let's say we assume that our game update can vary by, you know, up
to 2 milliseconds.
Let's say up to 2 milliseconds or something like this.
So we'll say that if the game update varies by up to 2 milliseconds,
then when we wake up with the audio we look and see it's a cursor, is
we look to see if the right cursor is before that, by the safety value
by the safety value, or by at least our safety value.
And if it is the Target Field position is the frame boundary plus 1
frame.
This gives us perfect.
Audio sync case card is loan of it and see if the right cursor is
after that, say,
The margin then.
We assume we can never sync the audio perfectly.
So we'll write one frames worth of audio, plus some number of guard
samples.
So this I think at you plus the safety margins worth of guard samples.
So basically, this does exactly the threshold in that I set out to do
initially, which is to say, we always write one frame, plus whatever
the guard amount is.
In the case.
Where we can't get audio sync to work, right?
Because the cards too slow, if we magically were to able to get some
Hardware that was fast enough, some really low latency Hardware, then
it would correctly, do a sort of the the forward prediction to line it
up with when we expect to flip, right?
So that's why I'm pretty comfortable with that.
How do you guys feel about that on the stream?
How do we feel?
I don't know.
Don't know what you guys are doing out there exactly.
But but hopefully people are following that, but that's what we
basically want to do.
So what we do here is we take a look, we always have to basically
right from from from so, you know, what, we're going to always look at
the, we don't have to save this kind of nice.
We don't have to save this stuff anymore, at 4-4 around the bend.
We don't actually have to do that because we can actually the last
right curse.
Our last play, Chris or thing.
We don't actually have to to save anymore.
So that's kind of nice.
We can go down here and basically get rid of that and say that from
now on, we're actually just going to use this stuff and we don't have
to save sound as valid as well.
We're pretty much good to go on that as well.
So sound is valid, can actually now be moved.
He moved back down to here.
Where we actually can do it.
So sound is valid doesn't have to Loop.
This is this is going to be nice.
This is going to clean up a bunch of stuff.
I'm going to leave this code in here for now because this is
basically, let's see here, right?
Kristen play Chris or I'm going to actually leave this code in in the
de bugging pass here so that we can actually inside that that internal
thing.
I still want to record those markers at this point because I think
that's actually going to be useful.
And so what I'm going to do is I'm just going to move the the sound
Is valid stuff up to here?
So sound is valid.
We're actually going to go ahead and do that here.
Maybe I still do want to actually keep it.
That sound is valid Global now that I think about it because we need
to still handle the case where we're starting up.
So I'm going to leave that.
I'm going to leave that going and so what we're going to do is I am
going to do the get current position to do that.
Where is the okay?
A thing.
There it is.
All right, go back a little.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and get that position.
Like we wanted.
I'm going to, basically, say, first of all, we've got a couple cases
here.
I don't actually know yet, whether we need to maintain the sound is
valid thing.
I think we do, because we need to set where we're going to write to.
So basically, if the sound isn't valid, currently we're going to
assume that the place that we're going to write.
It too.
Yeah, it's going to be roughly there.
Now we have.
So we have one little problem as well, which is that the game update
and render is happening sort of after this.
So we don't actually know this is this is a bit of a rub in the plan.
We only know the estimate for how long that's going to take.
We don't actually know exactly how that long that's going to take but
I guess that's okay because we sort of know it's expected time plus
its variability.
So that's that's the real tricky part here.
This is, it is really complicated.
If you want to try and get real audio sync, this is this is really
pretty, pretty, darn tough.
If you get right down to it, trying to manage these two clocks.
This is pretty pretty crazy.
We're going to have to actually account for the fact that in order to
ask the game to give us the the audio for this Frame.
We need to know how many bytes to ask for.
But in order to know me B ask for we have to do it before we ask the
game so we don't know.
Actually like we wanted to wake up and write the sound immediately,
but we can't.
Actually do that.
I mean we could I suppose actually do that and assume that the game
update doesn't take as long as it's going to take for the right person
to jump but we don't actually know if that's going to be true or not.
It could.
It could very easily jump.
So that's that's a little bit tricky.
That's a little bit tricky, that's going to complicate our
computation.
But all right, let's start out with start out with with it and we'll
keep on pushing through.
All right.
Okay.
So we go ahead and get that current position.
We take a look to see whether the sound is valid or not.
If the sound is not valid, then basically we're going to probably
we're probably going to defer that until after we actually do that.
So that'll still probably happen here.
So where we do our recheck.
So basically what we need to do first is we need to determine how many
samples the game.
We're going to actually ask the game for so Ike.
Okay.
I see how we can probably
We do this, I see how we can probably do this.
Yeah.
Yeah, I do I do.
I think I see how we do this.
We're going to have to do it a little bit, a little bit wet weirder,
but let's do it.
Let's let's let's let's let's reverse this a little bit.
So, okay.
So we're going to do it roughly exactly like we said, here we are
about to fill the sound buffer.
So we got the sound back from the game.
So we're just going to go ahead and do that right in.
Here.
So what we're going to do is we're going to we're going to get that
current position, right?
We're going to and we're going to print this out there.
Okay, so we're going to get that position.
We're going to look at the play cursor and the right cursor.
So we woke up there.
We're going to ignore a sound is valid for a minute because we're
going to we're going to set that sound is valid.
So we set that up here and that's just that's just a flag that we can
use to know whether it's our first time through or not.
So basically, what we're going to do is did I actually
Accidentally delete.
The, where is the running sample?
Index, update thing?
I did.
Yes, that was bad case.
You don't do that.
Why did you delete that?
Because that was code, that we still wanted.
I don't know why I deleted it probably just because I'm overzealous.
All right.
So what we want to do here is we're going to move this down and I'm
not going to leave that code.
That code is is good.
It's going to be actually want
So in here, in the case, where that happens, there we go.
That's what we wanted to see happen.
Now, we've preserved the code that we actually still need.
I don't know why.
I was feeling so so overzealous.
They're all right.
This is not going to be inside a sound valid Loop.
There we go.
So, in the case, where we get it, we check to see if the sound is
valid.
If that is not valid.
We're going to write from the right cursor.
Obviously, that's the first place we have to write.
That's where we knew start writing from if our sound is valid, if we
don't get it, then we're going to assume that
The sound is not valid and restart the process or just never write
sound.
Again.
This basically means our buffer failed or something like that.
So you look for the current position.
If a sound is valid, we got to start writing at the right curse, or
otherwise, we always write wherever we actually left off before.
That's basically what we're going to do there.
We're then going to say that b to lock, always has to be wherever we
last wrote to which, or right at the right cursor.
If we're running for the first time and that's still correct.
Then, our Target cursor, is the new thing that we're
Going to compute a little bit differently.
Basically, what we're going to assume that it is, like I said before,
is we've got two cases essentially.
We've got these two cases to deal with.
So basically we need to do an F here.
And we need to figure out that Target cursor in two different ways,
right?
And the target cursor.
Now, I believe this stuff can be moved inside this Loop.
It can be made to be direct like this.
I think so.
So, play Christian, Right?
Girls.
Are we still need to be out there?
But everything else is fine.
Good deal.
So play Christian, right cursor?
Get grabbed.
That's all good.
We're going to compute the B to lock that's relatively
straightforward.
So we do that.
We can actually even do that directly in line here.
So there we go.
We will compute the B to lock that way.
We then go ahead and
Compute the target cursor and then we compute the bites, right?
So the target cursor has two cases.
One, is that we're just going to use the right cursor, the exact sort
of thing.
We were doing before the right cursor, plus our safety.
Let's call this our safety sample, B.
Right.
So we're just going to rid of that.
Instead of sample count.
I'm going to stop using samples anywhere I can and then we'll start to
simplify this code by just using B.
Our Target cursor is just going to be a rap version of basically the
the expected bytes per frame and this is our safety B.
There we go.
Our expected bytes per frame, plus our sound are selected sound bytes
per frame.
Plus our safety bites, right?
So that's, that's basically what we need to do there.
And then this is in the case of a latent audio card.
If audio card is latent, then we will we will do that.
If it is not.
Then our Target cursor is going to be equal to the expected frame.
Boundary the expected frame boundary, right expected?
Frame, boundary b, + yeah, plus the sound output.
Yeah, just expected sound bite for frame.
That's it like that.
So the right cursor just doesn't fact it factored into it, basically.
Yeah, I think that's it.
Well the right cursor.
Yeah, it plus it sounded.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's it.
That's that's all there is to it.
I think that's that's really all there is to it.
Yeah, I don't see anything wrong with that.
We can move the this out here.
So we can say that the target cursor equals the target cursor, mod
sound crass or B.
So we know that it's always inside and then we can just get rid of
that and do this computation a little more cleanly in either case.
So we're basically just doing this.
Right.
Like that.
I think that is correct.
So now we just have to compute audio card is latent.
So audio card is latent.
That is going to be our assumption certainly because well most are two
cards probably are that makes sense.
So we're going to see if the audio card is late by saying, what did we
say up here?
We basically said if the right cursor
let's say if the right cursor plus the
Affected sound bytes per frame, right?
If that if the right cursor plus the expected sound bites per frame,
basically is
Okay.
Safe right cursor.
Let's call this.
Sorry, not the Specter right pits, right?
Chris Surplus, the safety B, right?
That's that's where we know that that's a counting sort of for the
Jitter if the safe, right cursor, right?
Plus, plus that we need to kind of know.
What are what this expected frame boundary B is.
So, we basically say, if the safe right, cursor is less than the
expected frame boundary B, right?
Then we consider the audio card to not be late.
Make some sense.
So in some sense, this is saying the audio card is latent if the safe
right cursor is greater than or equal to that.
Okay.
So we're basically saying wherever we think the frame boundary is
going to be we basically.
Yeah, I mean that's that's it.
Right?
So really it's just Computing this that we have to do.
Okay.
Do you word?
There we go.
So basically just saying,
Safe, right.
Cursor is the right cursor, plus whatever our safety.
B margin is, which is how much variability we think there is in our
output timing, right?
Determining whether the audio card is late is saying wherever that is
if that is after wherever, we think our next flip will be, then we
know that the audio card is not low latency enough for our for us to
do perfect.
Audio sync, right?
So then we're going to say, basically, whatever the that Target cursor
is.
It's just going to be computed based on either of those and then
wrapped back into the buffer and that's about it.
So this is the only computation.
We actually have to do what this actually is.
Whatever the expected Fairground.
Invite is, is basically the play cursor plus the expected bytes per
frame.
Now we have, we have a problem here, which is again that the right
cursor and the play cursor, may have wrapped.
So, what we want to do is basically say,
What we want to do here is basically make sure that they aren't
wrapped relative to each other.
We're assuming that the safe right that the right cursor, and the play
cursor are sort of in the same space.
And so, what we need to do is say, if the expected frame boundary B,
you know, we're essentially on the wrong side of whatever that safe
right?
Cursor is right.
Because, yeah, so we kind of need to take the play cursor in the right
cursor and normalize them first.
So I think what I'd like to do is just take that out of the equation
because this is complicated enough already.
Um, so let's just say we have a mapped are safe.
Right?
Cursor is going to map into the same place as the play cursor.
Yeah, that that's, I guess what I'm going to say.
So basically, what I would say is the safe right cursor equals the
right cursor.
We're going to take safe, right, cursor, and we're going to add the
safety B in like this.
So that I flipped those out to me into two, so I can make sure these
were in the same place.
So, if the safe right cursor, for some reason was behind the play
cursor, then the safe right.
Cursor is going to be normalized up to, to be ahead of it.
Right?
So we assert here, that the safe right?
Cursor is always greater than or equal to the play cursor.
All right, so that looks a bit better now to me.
Alright, so we're going to take the expected, frame, boundary B.
That's going to be the play cursor.
Plus, however, many bytes, we expect to output on a particular frame
that's going to be some kind of a value that we compute up above.
That's pretty wrote.
It's just going to be however much the milliseconds is Multiplied out
by the science sound thing.
So, basically, we've got that we then check the the safe, right?
Cursors, the right curse or if it's behind the play cursor, which
means it has wrapped.
We're going to go ahead.
Normalize it so that it's ahead.
We're going to we're not really normalize.
It unwrapped it so that it's always ahead of the play cursor so that
we can do our computation properly.
We take that safe right cursor.
We assert that, we that it's always going to be ahead of it because
that was our goal.
We then add in the safety B.
That is where we say.
It could possibly be.
We look to see if the audio card is latent.
If the audio card is Layton.
By saying is that safe, right cursor going to be before I guess we
could we could kind of reverse this audio card is low, latency might
be a bit better.
So we'll say if we can hit our thing.
Then we're going to we're going to reverse the sense of this this
test.
So we're going to say if the audio card is low latency, then we will
go ahead and compute that right there.
So, okay, there we go.
So that's how we determine this.
That determines our latency.
That's pretty good.
We go through here.
We say compute the target cursor by using just the frame boundary.
Plus, however, many bytes.
We know we write per frame, when we are low latency, when we are high
latency.
We basically just use that.
Plus the safety margin, and that's the target.
We right to the Target.
Here.
We map the target back into the
The buffer properly and then we go ahead and do the B to write.
So yeah, pretty complicated computation ladies and gentlemen, that is
pretty darn complicated.
So so there we go.
There we go.
I guess that's really Mark modulo.
The
Bugs.
That's really what we wanted to do.
So now we've got one more thing to deal with.
Well, we got two more things to do deal with really, but so, the
expected sound bytes per frame is not defined yet, right?
We got to deal with that.
So let's go ahead and deal with that.
So, we've got a Define that in a second, and then we've got that
safety B, we've got sound output, safety B.
That we've got to deal with, as well at some point, and then,
We've got, let's see.
Undeclared identifier for that.
That's fine.
So much frame.
Safety, B.
Do not a member.
Last play cursor is not actually there.
So we're going to actually have to do, just play coarser and right
cursor.
So we'll get rid of that.
Let's take a look here.
B to write bikes.
Do do, do do, do, do, do so.
These are unfortunately.
Yeah, not known anymore.
So
Is there a way I can do this?
B to lock is there?
There we go.
Okay, so plate to lock Target, cursor, B to write play cursor, right
cursor.
Audio latency B, Ru latency s.
So we're still out putting all that and that's good.
Okay.
So so our problem here, besides defining these things.
Our problem here is basically that we still need to tell the game.
How many samples it should output and that's kind of
That basically gives us another audio latency problem because where we
want to actually do, the right is right here, but the game doesn't
actually the game.
Unfortunately doesn't actually hasn't actually updated.
If we were to put this before in order to tell the game how many
samples to write then we would have to we wouldn't actually have an
accurate read on where the play cursor was going to be when we needed
to fill.
So this is what we actually want to do for our fill.
And we can assume basically that the sound buffer here.
We basically need that sound buffer to basically always be enough that
we wouldn't underflow it here.
And so what we can do there, I guess is just kind of have a thing.
Which says we're generally going to write enough.
We're we want to make sure this B to right value never under flows is
basically the problem.
And so what is the maximum value that that b to right?
It could possibly be.
I don't actually know, I guess it could be, but expected frame,
boundary B, plus the expected sound bites per frame.
So in this case, it could actually be pretty high.
Yeah.
So if we move this before here, then we have another thing.
We've got to count.
Um, yeah, you can see how tricky the spacely is.
Right?
So what we want to do is we want to if maybe well one thing we could
do is we could then ask for the audio right here for the game and mix
it on demand.
And as long as we were able to keep that to within a millisecond or
two, then that would be okay potentially, but if it was going to be
long, I don't know.
So it's pretty, it's pretty tricky.
It's pretty tricky.
Should we do that?
Should we not do that?
Are we at risk?
There is
I guess, I guess let's, let's do it.
I don't know.
I'm feeling I'm feeling experimental today.
So I say we just do it.
So basically what's going to happen here is I'm going to say that we
actually just go ahead and we get that sound straight out of here.
So we go in here and we say, all right.
What are we going to do?
We're going to say internal void game, get sound samples.
So that's a call in to the game.
And we passed that everything except the graphics and
Don't come in.
So we passed that the game memory and we passed that the sound buffer
and basically we will say that the game just does its mixed down right
there.
Right into the buffer.
So basically the game no longer gets the sound buffer at all.
And so the game has to give a sound buffers on demand like this.
So in here, we will simply say, let's go ahead.
And as soon as we know, we know how many bytes to write, we will
actually do the right right here.
And that has to be low latency, which
Is the thing that makes me nervous about it.
Obviously, that's the reason that I was kind of like, oh, sounds
dangerous.
Well, well, you know, like I said, sometimes sometimes you just got to
do stuff and then you got to fight through it and see if there's
something good on the other side.
And sometimes there isn't and it turned out to be bad.
It was a mistake and other times you come out with something really
cool.
And so sometimes you just got to do it and see.
And so this is this is basically what we're doing here is we're just
kind of fighting through it and going, can we get
Our can we get something cool out the other end and maybe there's a
few more refinements left that will have insights into and see.
But let's take a look here.
So, basically we'll get the sound samples right here and we will out
put them right here.
The other thing that we could do, which is pretty interesting.
If we wanted to is we could write directly into the sound buffer here.
Now, if we wanted to because we could change, we could change to doing
a passing, a ring buffer to the game.
We don't really, I don't think want to do that at this point, but
that's what we would do.
So, all right, we went in here and and we did that.
We now have our explanation in
Here, I might actually move this explanation kind of inside.
So basically, this is this is the explanation of what's happening in
here.
And that looks relatively clean to me at the moment.
So we get the that getting that sound samples, but I'm going to put a
note here.
I'm going to say at the moment.
This has to be
A very fast function.
It cannot be, let's say more than a millisecond or so, right?
So that's going to be important to keep our sound latency down.
All right.
So basically, we can always account for more of that by buffering up
and maybe we could measure things here.
I could say to do Casey, reduce the pressure on this functions
performance by measuring it or asking about it Etc.
We could we could think about doing some stuff there to make that a
little easier, but for now, let's actually say that that's the case.
So compiling this
We now have to go through and fix.
I left a bunch of stuff in there.
So game update and render no longer takes the sound buffer.
So that's got to happen.
So we'll fix that in a second.
We have the expected sound bites for frame.
We know what that is.
That's basically just the game update hurts which we had, right?
We've got the sound output, the total secondary buffer size.
Basically, we've got see samples per second.
We've got the samples per second times, the bytes per se.
Bowl again, to probably I'm going to go through and change some of
those.
We don't have to keep doing this multiplies.
/, the game update hurts.
That's how many sound bites we expect per frame, right?
Because we've got the bites for sample, coming out, the samples per
second.
That's going to be how many bytes per second.
And then we're going to, we're going to go ahead and see how many per
frame by dividing by the game update hurts.
So that should be stable computation.
Our safety.
B is something that we will Define kind of at the top when we first do
our sound output set up, so are and that is basically sort of like
what this latency sample count is.
So basically what we have to say, there is, how much do we think?
Well, I think we can safely probably say that the variability in our
game.
Time is probably not going to be more than half the game time, right?
So, our safety B is probably something like the samples per second
times.
The bytes per sample divided by the game update hurts, you know, / to.
I think that's a pretty safe estimate.
It's probably probably more like going to be more than like a more of
a quarter or a third I'd say because in general, I don't think we're
going to have that much variability in how
along the update takes.
So basically, I think we could probably do this a little bit lower so
to do.
Basically actually compute this variance and see what the lowest
reasonable value.
Is.
That makes sense?
Kind of get that in there.
Take a look at it.
And then I just got to add that to this thing here.
The d word.
Safety B.
There we go.
Warning treat is error game update and render, right?
So, basically, now we have to go in here and split this out.
If you remember we decided we change the definition of these
functions.
So we got to go in here and and basically
And basically split our functions into one that updates the sound and
one that updates the game memory.
So what we need to do here is we need to take this out right and get
rid of that because we don't actually have that to do anymore.
We're going to do the sound buffer output for the tone hurts.
And basically, what we need to do is we need to grab our game State.
And so, our game state is basically just again, that
Storage is how we access it.
So let's go there.
Get that out from behind my head.
Let's see.
And we need to change this to be the proper function definition.
It is this one now.
So there we go.
And go.
There we go.
Now,
Whew, man, we've got about 15 minutes before we would call this time
for Q&A.
Probably sadly.
I'm expecting that.
There's a ton of bugs in there because man that was a lot of code.
So we still have a lot of work to do.
We've still got a lot of work to do in the next 20 minutes or so.
So let's run it just to see if we just full-on fail.
Oh, well, let's let's let's turn off the infinite Loop that we that we
had their
Of all and then see where we're at.
I am at the very least.
I am shocked that that still gives us clean sound output.
Ladies and gentlemen.
And it actually feels fairly low latency.
So we didn't introduce any weird bugs, which is kind of crazy, to say
the least.
That is kind of crazy.
I am, I am absolutely stunned.
That that worked.
The first time.
I can only assume that there actually is a bug in there somewhere that
we just don't find because we don't have testing for it yet.
That is kind of crazy.
What we just did in an hour and 45 minutes of thinking and programming
and not a single bug.
That's that's wrong.
Tom, Forsythe says, must be a bug and I agree with him.
There's no way that should have worked the first time.
So, so basically what that means, we can just pretty much.
Be sure that what that means is, there's got to be a bug in there that
we just aren't seeing because we're our test cases to simple.
We don't know what we're, you know.
We're not doing enough there.
Yeah.
Basically, somebody on the stream, just says, I hate it when you
compile and it works, the first time I could not agree more because
it's it's just so suspicious.
You want to fix some bugs in it.
So you can feel like you found them because, you know, they're there.
And so now you just feel like there's bugs that are hiding.
It's never like.
Oh, I did a good job, right?
You never think that.
So yeah, yeah, so well, well, there we go.
So basically let's let's take the 15 minutes and I'm basically going
to draw.
I'm going to improve our drawing routine so we can kind of see a
little bit more.
Basically what what's going on there?
Right?
Let's go ahead and improve our drawing.
My routine a little bit more.
So what I want to do here is I want to when we draw the sound, the
sink display, what I want to do.
We start drawing some other things like when we have the play, Chris,
the Red Cross.
I want to draw where we actually did our right.
And I want to I want to pull out from there.
What?
Just the current right?
Chris are in play Chris or are so we can see those a little bit more
cleanly, if that makes sense.
Stretch time time to stretch people.
It's time to stretch.
Mmm.
Yeah.
Early morning coding here.
Well, afternoon afternoon coding, not used to it for handmade hero
after handmade hero.
Yeah.
What are you gonna do?
Alright, so that was crazy.
And this is low level stuff to.
I'm surprised that worked.
I mean, we're writing
We're essentially writing the game engine like low level stuff here
that lowest of the low.
So yeah, that was crazy.
That work the first time, I don't know what's going on.
Usually you expect stuff to work the first time.
Once you're a little higher up in the food chain thing is can work the
first time because everything is fairly logical at that point and
you've done all the finicky stuff and you've kind of baked it down
into a language that's easy for you, but I wouldn't expect when you're
doing when you're doing the hardcore stuff.
You don't expect it to work the first time you don't
All right.
So, well, what I want to do here is I want to start passing to the
sink display.
I want to say which marker is current.
I wanted to say, which is the current marker.
Right?
So we can just highlight it.
And so, basically, what I'm going to do is I'm going to say in this
thing, if marker index equals current marker Index, right?
Then I'm going to use a highlighted color, current marker index, and
if not, then not.
So I'm going to do a thing for play color, equals this and right,
color equals that sort of thing.
And then I'm going to set them equal here.
I believe the play cursor is our right.
Curse is a, is our bright one and the right cursor, right?
Color and is because that that so right color and play color that and
then I'm going to initialize those by default to something a little
bit dimmer.
Although I guess we don't, you know what I could do.
I could just change.
Ange the top and bottom actually that.
And so we basically just have to kind of rows going that that might be
smarter.
So let's say that this is pad Y, and this is pad y plus line-height
like that in line height equals, maybe 32 or 64 or something like
that.
And so, basically what we'll do is we'll just basically say, okay.
That's the top and bottom, but in the case, where the marker index 0,
and whoops, doo-doo-doo-doo-doo-doo-doo, we still want to do this,
because I think it's good to pull those out because we may want to
change the color as well or something like that.
So let's get that back in there.
Boop.
And now we go ahead and take our top and bottom will just go ahead and
plus equals those to be
Let's say, 2 times the line height or some of that, or, you know,
what, we'll do the line height plus the pad y.
So, we'll just, we'll just move it down, like that.
Yeah, and so now, we're not actually passing anything in there.
So we got to come in and say what is that?
Current marker?
And so, the current marker is whatever this was before.
So it's basically the debug, it's the previous.
It's the previous one of the debug time marker index.
So
Basically, we come in here and we say that debug time markers.
What is that value?
It's not actually this one.
It's this one back one.
But remember, we don't actually we, if we subtract 1 from it, we may
wrap.
We don't actually care for right now.
Note.
This is wrong on the zeroeth index, or I should say current is around.
We're just comparing to it.
That's fine for now.
So maybe I'll see you in there.
Fix that in a second.
Let's just see what that does.
Yeah, so that's what we, that's what we want.
You can kind of see.
Now we've got the historical ones are in there.
But but the the other ones are in there as well.
Let's go ahead and pause that for a second as well.
So we can take a look at it because I can just click on there.
Yeah, wow, so, at least this confirms what?
We were measuring to in the diagram, you can see the difference
between the play.
In the right cursor.
Is roughly the frame size, right?
Exactly what we would think.
Yeah.
All right, so that's fine.
That's all well and good.
Let's take a look here and see what else we got going.
So what I want to do now is I also want to record with our markers.
I want to record a basically change what this records to record some
additional stuff.
This is where the play cursor and the right cursor were at the, at the
time of the actual at the time of the flip.
So this is the flip play cursor.
And the flip right cursor, but we basically want to also have the
output play cursor and the output right cursor, right output, right?
For a sir, see where those were and we want to do the output location.
So that's like the output byte to lock and the output byte count.
So basically, this is the range, we actually filled.
So, basically, all I'm saying is back in here.
So, when we do this thing, when we do this, excuse me.
When we do this, this sort of save of the value, right?
When we, when we actually do this thing here, where we actually save
the value.
I want to actually do this across, I want to do this multiple times.
So basically this debug time, marker, index thing.
We're only going to increment it down at the end here.
If that makes sense.
Why did that do?
Well, because I just deleted it.
There we go.
So basically at the end of this guy, we're going to do.
You this in fact, we could actually do this, just to enforce the fact
that it's being done at the very end.
We'll do it down here in its own little block.
So we're basically going to have a little thing that there's just
increments that at the very end.
So that way, we can also write to this marker.
The same audio marker for this Frame.
We can write to it up here.
So, basically, in the case, if and main internal, basically, we will
be able to write to the same marker that will be written to down
there.
There, and that way, we can get a little more information.
In fact, I guess I've already got a handmade internal in here as well.
So there we go.
We really probably don't need to do this again, we could decide to,
but I don't think we really need to because we've already got this one
up here, so we can do this.
We could see how far it moved after the game get sound samples, but
you know, that's that's a separate thing.
All right.
So anyway, we're going to take a look at the the marker here.
We're going to go ahead and write all of these other values into it
will.
Do the output play cursor, will do the out.
Output.
Right cursor.
And those are just the things that we just write output, right cursor
and the output play cursor.
We will then do the output location and that is the B to lock, right?
And the output byte count by count and that is the B to, right?
And so now we've recorded that stuff properly.
And all we have to do now is down in the other marker where we're
writing these things.
These are
Actually, flip play cursor and flip right cursor, right?
So what I'd like to do now, so we're recording all of that
information, which is kind of handy.
So, here's the flip play cursor.
Here's the flip right, cursor.
Those are now there.
Excuse me.
Oops.
Those are now there and we should see exactly what we saw before.
Now.
It should be no change.
Oops, except there is, oh, what did I do wrong there?
Did I accidentally update that?
Oh, yeah.
Awesome.
That's good.
When we actually wrap this guy, we need to we need to actually do the
rap.
Notice how asserts save you time basically?
Anytime you can if you can assert the stuff that you know, to be true.
It definitely helps catch bugs.
Alright, so there we go.
We're kind of in, we're kind of in a vacuum where we started land and
that's good.
Everything looks about right.
So that's Happy.
Okay.
So now what we want to do is actually draw that actual information
that we had.
Right?
So we go into here to the, the thing in, this is the to do, we're
working on right now, drove over writing the sound.
So, in the case, where we have, the current marker index, I'm going to
draw some additional.
Oil information, right?
I'm going to go ahead and draw some additional stuff.
In the case where we have it.
I want to draw all the rest of this stuff.
So where do we actually have, what actual information do we have here
in there?
I've got the output play cursor.
So that's that's coming up.
Oops, output play cursor.
I've got the output right cursor, right?
And I've got,
Some more stuff here.
I've got the output location, right?
And then I've also got the output byte count.
Now the output byte count is a little bit harder to draw.
We can do it by basically doing this marker output location.
Plus this marker output byte count, but we do have one problem with
that which is that could write off the end because remember we're not
actually checking this value.
So what we should probably do here because because again, this this
there's a circular this is
A circular, right?
So the number of bytes could wrap around the buffer and we don't want
to actually overcome.
Rawr screen.
So what we could do here is just check our X if our X is greater than
equal to 0.
And our X is less than the back buffer width, right?
Then we can we can actually draw otherwise, we won't draw.
Right?
Makes sense.
And in fact, we could even do that in the actual check here, we could
do it right here, just to make sure that basically anyone who draws
this line is bounded there.
Excuse me.
Why do I still have a global back?
Buffer, typed in there?
Don't do that.
You should all be back over.
There we go.
So I'm going to go ahead and check that in there.
I'm also going to do one other thing in there, which is, we might as
well.
Also check the bottom and the top basically, if the top is less than
or equal to 0, right?
If the top is less than equal to 0, the top can just be equal to 0.
So that clips that basically Clips we're writing to and the same with
the bottom.
If the bottom is greater than
Or equal to the back buffer height, then we could clip the bottom and
say, bottom equals the back bumper height minus 1, right?
And that would that would work.
Oh, well, it's y less than bottom.
So I guess we're okay by just saying it's equal to the height like
that.
So if the bottom is, yeah, hopefully that makes some sense, right?
So that look that look reasonable to everyone.
Hopefully, that looks reasonable to everyone.
I think that should be about, right.
I'm not actually sure because what
I think this through, so basically, we're passing the bottom.
Are we ever actually writing to the bottom?
So, let's say the bottom now, we're using less than.
So.
We're not.
We're if top and bottom or equal, we would not write anything.
So if they were equal to height, we would not read anything at top,
but have to be at least less than that.
So we're okay.
That's about right.
So that's just we're going to, don't worry too much about that.
I was just putting in some some guards there to against clipping off
the screen, we're going to deal with that when we actually go, right?
The render all explain how these sorts of things work in great detail.
So this is just some
Debug code to draw lines.
And I want to make sure it would draw off the top bottom left or right
of the screen.
So that's really all I was doing here.
Anyway, so now I just need to go finish up this stuff and let's see
here.
So basically this marker needs to be snapped further up.
So that's that.
And then we also need some way of differentiating these guys.
So we're going to say
Basically that we're going to, I'm going to do this for now, which is
kind of annoying, but I'm just going to basically keep moving those
guys down as we go.
And then, let's see.
That should give us something that looks like this.
No, but that didn't?
That, that was not correct at all.
What's what?
Oh, yeah.
Well, so this assertion is no longer valid, unfortunately, because I'm
since I am actually using the output byte count thing that can.
Basically, this assertion I'm basically did the clipping.
I did the clipping that that assertion was guarding against up in
here.
So, this assertion really no longer valid that assertion is going to
assert.
Yeah, that assertion is going to assert by / definition when I do this
addition because that can wrap around the buffer.
So that assertion is, unfortunately no longer valid, which is too bad.
We could assert some of the other buffer values in here like we could
do these other guys.
Basically, these guys are all supposed to be correct, but we can't
assert it every time we do that, right?
Because it's actually it's actually kind of allowed to be wrong.
Now.
All of these things actually have to be less than the buffer size.
Nobody is allowed to be less.
But once we add those two together than that could be.
So I'll just start at those here just to make sure everything's not
wonky.
But that, yeah, that should be correct.
And this actually needs to why was this not why was this not looking
correct to me?
So we should have oh because we need one more, right?
There we go.
so,
Why are those two so, okay, we gotta change stuff here.
We've got to write Colors on this one, play color.
All right, so let's take a look at that.
It would be nice if we add labels and stuff, but let's take a look at
that.
So what do we have here?
Basically, we are looking that first one that we've got in the fact, I
guess.
While I do this.
What I should do is bring this up in the debugger so you can see what
the stuff is that we're actually looking at.
um,
all right.
So what we're looking at here is we're looking at that first one is
our play, our actual play cursor, and our output right cursor.
Is that first first row below below the Baseline.
So basically that is the white thing is where the play cursor was.
When we were going to output and the red line is where the the right
cursor was when we're going to Output, then the location that we
computed was kind of out.
You can see
Where the the white line is and the red line, that's where we were
going to output.
And then the flip location is, is basically, is the bottom, white line
is where the play cursor was when we flipped.
So you can see that that that's actually working.
Exactly.
Like we hoped would you can even see that's that's pretty good.
Like, look at what we did there.
Basically, you can kind of see
at very bottom one.
I kind of need to wait a
Pause this display.
Let's let's let's let's do away because I need a way to move, my mouse
cursor around.
So let's add a way to pause this display.
I'm going to just go ahead and full-on just throw in the way to pause
the display here.
So let's, let's, let's do that.
Let's have a pause.
Let's have some crazy Global, pause thing.
So, basically, you know, something like this.
If handmade internal.
There we go.
Pee then Global pause equals not Global pause and we'll just have.
This is just a full-on.
Debug pause function will probably want to make a pretty good.
One of these eventually eventually it's a little pause and basically
what Global pause will do is it will just stop us from actually ever
running the update.
So basically while Global running,
Will basically say inside here, when we do this sort of stuff.
Do we want to pause the input?
I'm not sure.
Probably not.
So what will basically do is say, if Global pause.
This is not Global pause, then we'll do all this stuff.
Right?
Will actually make all this stuff happen.
Otherwise, we won't.
So get 10 Dimension.
We won't do the blit.
We
Don't do any of this.
This is not none of this is going to happen.
Yeah, and so are basically, we have to not do any of this stuff.
None of this stuff is allowed to happen at all.
So we can't really do input either for the most part.
Yeah.
Looks like we can't really do anything if we wanted to actually have
it be a full pause.
So let's see here.
Let's do that.
Let's do this due to do.
So the win32 process messages still has to get called, so we can
unpause basically.
But yeah, that's that's sort of going to be buggy.
Will have to we'll have to do a better implementation of that going
forwards.
Okay.
Of course.
I also need to actually only toggle that Global.
Pause when the key actually goes down Global paws.
So we need to do if is down then Global pause.
All right, so we run that and now we can pause.
So basically what we've got here is this is where the the current.
Let's just verify this, right.
So the first thing that we drew below the Baseline, which is this
thing.
The first thing that we
To was just our output play cursor position and our output right
cursor position.
So that was where we when we woke up.
We asked where the things where that's where they were right.
We then computed where we're going to write to and we basically said
well we're going to right to right here and oh sorry, that's not
actually correct.
Is that actually correct?
What's the next thing the output location?
Okay.
Yeah.
So the next thing is the output.
Location.
So then we said, okay, the output location is going to be right here
and we're going to write this much.
Then when we actually came time to page flip be page slipped here.
And this is where the right cursor is going to be.
Although that's not super relevant.
So this is where we page flipped.
So this is our audio latency.
Our audio latency is between these two things and you can see that
that's actually much less than a frame now, which is good.
That's what we wanted.
And I suspect that.
Sometimes it will even be better than that depending on how things
work out for us.
It could even be a little bit less.
not actually entirely certain, but
Yeah, so that's that's pretty good.
I think.
That's not bad.
I'm relatively happy with that, especially because were actually doing
things so that we could do lower latency if we wanted to.
Yeah, that's not that's not awful.
I'm not unhappy with that.
I'm relatively happy with that.
All right, so that should be good blood dragon.
I just glanced at the track at this time.
To go to the question.
It says initialize the global which global you're talking about
global.
Pause this one.
I thought we covered This Global variables are initialized to Zero by
default.
And so pauses is supposed to be false by default, but
So, someone was saying I missed an assertion for one of the, one of
the things in here.
Let's take a look.
So output.
Play cursor is asserted right.
Cursor is asserted location and then well, so we could we could have
start the bike count because technically, it does have to be less.
It's not a position, but but we could certainly if it makes you more
comfortable, certainly assert it because although we don't really care
because we're wrapping that way.
We're clipping that value in the draw call.
Although we don't necessarily super care.
It is true that that does have to be less than the secondary buffer
size.
That's, that's certainly true.
So that's good.
All right, so I'm going to call that done for today.
I don't again know that, that was rather surprising that that all
worked and does seem to be relatively
Bust as well.
That that could be deceiving though.
We haven't tested it thoroughly enough to really know.
But yeah, I'm I'm pretty happy with that.
That was a good two hours of work, guys.
That was a good two hours of work.
What I'd like to do ideally if possible is I would like to at some
point go and find a low latency audio card and see if we can get it to
the point where that that frame display actually shows us that we're
getting really low latency on the audio because we want those two on a
really low latency card, we
Those two lines to line up.
So, another thing that I might do is let's draw one more thing in our
marker, which is basically the expected frame flip time.
So, basically the expected, the expected frame flip time.
This thing expected frame, boundary bite.
Let's draw that as well.
So, let's say, expected frame, boundary B.
So, that's, that's basically the expected flip cursor, right?
Where we expect, where we expect that to be when we actually computed
the value, right?
So, so let's to see whether our estimate lines up at all.
So our expected flip play cursor.
Equal to where the play cursor is, plus the expected sound bites per
frame.
Okay, see so that yeah, that already tells me that, that sort of
wrong, now that I'm thinking about that.
So we do have one incorrect thing here.
It's actually that we forgot one part of the computation that I talked
about.
We forgot to do that.
The flip is not the whole frame times worth.
It's just it's it's only actually - the time that's elapsed so far,
right?
Yeah, so we're actually not quite right.
So let's draw this out and we'll see that it's not quite right, and
then we'll make the fix and and put that incorrectly.
So that all that does is add a little audio latency.
So that's why we didn't see it as a bug, but we should be able to get
that audio latency down.
All right.
So the expected frame, boundary B will also get written here.
Marker expected foot play cursor.
Is that and now we should see that this is
Not really that close.
If we draw it, we should see that.
It's not really that close to the other line.
Right.
So let's go in here and draw that.
So, when we do our play cursor and art, right cursor, we will also
draw there or I should say when we do this.
Let's do it here.
So here's where we're writing to.
Squee.
Yeah, okay.
I'll do it here.
So this is going to be expected flip color, right?
And that's going to come out here.
Dealer expected flip Color.
Oops.
Equals 0 x.
Let's make that a nice cyan.
Shall we?
Sian would be good.
So, lets, you know who doesn't love cyan.
Oh, you know what we could do really purple, or we could do a yellow.
Let's do yellow.
I like yellow.
All right, we're going to an expected flip color and we're going to
draw.
Who did I just delete the yeah?
Suspected flip cursor.
What did I do?
What happened?
I thought I'd type this in.
I'm just, you can tell I'm getting a little loopy here.
Expected flip play cursor.
Get that in there.
There we go.
So save.
All right.
So now we should see that.
That is exactly wrong.
And let's go ahead and assert that one as well.
Goodbye count.
So that's expected flip like cursor.
That let's take a look.
So, we should see.
Oh,
Oh, that's right.
That's another one.
That also it's an it's an added value.
So that's actually allowed to be outside because that's normalized
outside.
So, there it is.
Wow, it's real close though.
Okay, so there's a case where it is not closed.
For example, right?
But it is still really darn darn close and I think that's just because
our game the milliseconds for our game update is so low that that
estimate is I guess going to be pretty close.
That's that's within reason, but you can see that often times if we're
unlucky and it's going to be a little further off there.
So let's let's try let's see if we can get that down a bit.
Let's just see.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to say well, okay.
So at some, we have an ability to query the clock, right?
And we're doing that often, right?
So we're doing stuff where we have this, this sort of flip time.
We take a look at what the flip time is right here.
So we've got kind of the the wall clock time here.
And then we could we could if we wanted to also store whatever the
actual time is right after the flip.
So basically right here, when we get this, when we get this guy,
Right, when we would, we would call that that query.
Let's just go ahead and have a thing here called flip wall clock and
we're just going to go ahead and get that.
Pull that out there and store that, right.
So let's let's just go ahead and do that.
So we're going to do our flip wall clock as there, and we're going to
go ahead and grab that every frame.
So, I've got that now and that
Wall clock.
Football.
Clock is just a large integer.
So, there we go.
There's our flip wall clock.
Boom.
Loops are flip wall clock, which is going to be, you know, basically a
total nonsense value at first.
But so, the flip wall clock is basically right from when the flip
occurred and then we're going to time the time between that flip and
where we are now, because that's what we said we were going to do.
So we're going to go ahead and say well that flip wall clock, let's do
that seconds.
Elapsed here.
Are we gonna win through to get S 2 laps that flipped wall clock?
And wherever we actually are at the time when we do
Computation for our expected.
Whereas are expected here.
Expected, expected expected.
Here we go.
So, our expected sound bytes per frame is correct, but it's when we
actually do the frame boundary B, we're not going to use the entire
expected sound bytes per frame, right?
Because we're only using a part of them.
So, what we're going to do is right there.
We're going to take a look.
So essentially right here when we do this, check will also do a thing
where we basically
If we say that, we have an audio counter, the audio counter is going
to be between here and the flip cap.
The flip wall clock, right?
I probably should call these either counter or wall clock correctly.
So clock, it will clock.
I should go through and change those wall clock.
There we go.
So, basically what we end up with is the S so far.
So the audio
The time between the beginning of the frame and so basis, basically,
from begin to audio s.
So, that's that's what we've got.
So now, what we need to do is basically subtract that out of the
expected frame time, and that is actually how many bytes forward we
want to move this.
Right.
So basically we've got sort of an expected expected thing here.
And we're going to, we're going to use only a part of it.
So.
Here we have expected, B, until flip and that is essentially going to
be the sound bytes per per frame times, whatever.
The actual proportion of a frame.
This actually is, right.
And and so, excuse me.
Whatever proportion of a frame.
We have here is what we need to multiply by, right, because we've got
the amount of time there toward the seconds per frame or expected
seconds per frame.
That is the actual value that we need to multiply this by.
In order to get it, that's the coefficient that we need in order to
get the amount of samples.
We at the amount of bytes.
We actually think we're going to use.
So the ratio of how much time we spent.
That's not quite right.
It's actually the expected seconds per frame - this, right?
It's the time left.
So we have the expected seconds, per frame.
- how many audio s?
We've actually spent so far.
It's how many seconds are left.
So there's basically seconds left until flip is this.
And so, that's this value here, right?
So the seconds left until we flip is however, many seconds we expect
to have per frame and then minus the number of seconds that we
actually already took, we go ahead and do the division to find out
what percentage of the frame that is and we multiply that by how many
bytes we expect to have in the frame.
So that's that's about it.
So then we just have to have our expected are expected seconds, per
frame value actually has to exist.
But that's pretty easy to compute.
When we take a look at our hurts Target seconds per frame.
Oh, we've already got it.
So, that's that's what it is.
It's just Target seconds per frame.
So it's Target s for French, so that's that.
Target frame, that's that.
And now let's see if I did that correctly with pause.
Let's see here.
Still a bit off.
Yeah, we're still getting that kind of because what we want to see,
right, is we want to see that value should be correlated with the
bottom value if I'm not mistaken, let's double, let's double-check.
That's, that's not, that's not what we're not seeing what we hope to
see.
So let's let's, let's go ahead here.
So, if we look at that, we should be correlating with this bottom
value here.
I think I was, I was confused before, and I was, I was looking at this
one, which is not right.
We're trying to correlate these two because this is our actual flip.
We want the yellow to basically be correlated with that.
And in fact, I guess what I should do is probably draw them, draw it
all the way down to that.
Level right.
I mean that would be sort of a better way to do it.
Let me let me draw it essentially across all those lines.
So this one that way, I don't make that mistake again, so we'll do it
this way.
Let's do that and we'll just go ahead and do it.
Oops.
Sorry.
First top first top top.
So I'm just going to go ahead and draw this all the way down.
There we go.
Yeah.
so,
What, what is going on here?
We're still not where we want to be that yellow value.
In that white value are not as correlated as I would like them to be.
Because that bottom point value, right?
That bottom white value is where the play cursor is, when we flip,
right?
That's what we were drawing.
Right?
So, this is our expected, play cursor.
Is that yellow line, right?
And oh, okay, okay.
No, no, I'm right.
So that and that bottom line.
That's that very bottom is is the actual flip cursor, right?
So basically we want the yellow line and that bottom white line.
I'm not mistaken.
Now, those should actually be lining up as closely as possible and
they do a lot of the time, but it looks like we get.
We get into certain situations like this, where they're pretty
Far away from each other.
And I don't know if that's to be expected or not.
I guess there is the fact that we can have that Jitter up to 480
samples.
So maybe what we should do is also draw in a 480, sample window to
basically say, well it could have moved by this much.
Now if it did though,
If it did, then it would be.
Yeah.
Well, okay, let's draw that in and just see.
So we knew that there was basically a 400 when we measured this card,
we knew there was a 480 sample difference there.
So I'm going to say, let's go ahead and draw that in.
Let's do that in our
Our play window will call that and we'll draw that in a.
Lovely purple is what will play right play window color.
So I just want to see basically I want to see play window color.
I want to see this Plus for an 80 times, the sound buffer, sound
output bytes per sample.
All right.
I just want to see what that will look like.
So looking at this a little more closely here, what we can see is
basically that line is where the the play cursor would be.
This is where the players are was when we measured it for the flip.
This is that for nudity, sample window.
So that's the update.
Granularity of the sound and that's where we thought we were going to.
So generally we are pretty darn close to being in between those two,
but I feel like we should always be in between those two.
And I don't like the fact that once in a while we get one.
That's a little further off than that, that feels like a bug to me,
that just feels like it's not correct.
Now, maybe that's just because there's too much variability in our
update and we're not, you know, so that's just natural.
But I would have liked to have seen those converge a little bit more
closely.
So I suspect that maybe we're still a little bit buggy.
Since this is not our final shipping code.
I'm going to say we're probably okay to move on to something else for
now, but this might be a kind of thing is when we have some extra time
or when we're doing a bonus stream or something to maybe come back,
make some better when we have a more of a renderer and we could render
the debug code a little more effectively.
I would say let's come back to this because I'm not satisfied in the
the level of quality of this.
Code yet.
I think it still has a way to go.
So I'm going to call that but Imma call that done for now.
I'm going to call that done for now because I don't want to Rat Hole
on perfect audio output for too long and want to keep it to within the
stream.
So let us go ahead and go to the Q&A now.
It has been a long stream.
That was like a two-and-a-half hour stream.
That's a that's a long one and people are saying on the stream, right?
A full-on audio visualizer.
Yes.
Well eventually we will so that's that's good.
But let's go to Q&A.
Now.
Let's take a, let's take a couple minutes of Q&A before we end the
stream.
Let's just stretch a little bit though.
Here we go.
And I will sort of a please make sure that you keep the questions to
stuff we did today.
Or in a previous day and please make sure to put Senior ettore on each
individual question.
So that I see them.
Did you try the audio without OBS?
I did, it did not change.
So OBS did not seem to affect the audio output which is what I would
expect it because it's going through the colonel mixer.
So it should be pretty free for the colonel.
Mixer to hand that audio to OBS after it's done sending it out.
So it should, I wouldn't have expected OBS to in a well working
system.
It shouldn't.
So I'm assuming that it was fine and it was
Yeah.
There's a lot of thinking today, a lot of thinking on the thinking, on
the Stream.
Not seen any questions though.
Do we have no Quest?
Maybe everyone's too tired from such a long, programming stint and I
can understand that, I could certainly understand that.
It's been a lot of code.
But hey, the good.
Is this next week's?
I think, almost exclusively fun stuff for the most part.
So we did a lot of hard work.
I across like the stuff, but I can appreciate the fact that other
people might not,
Let's take a look here.
Is it inexpensive to query for the play cursor?
In the right cursor?
Yeah, I think it's actually free is.
My my thinking.
The reason I say that is, I don't think.
When you actually do that query.
I don't think direct sound is actually doing any work.
I think it's just returning you its internal values and so it, I think
what happens is direct sound updates those on its own time.
So it's like occasionally resetting.
Those values to whenever it pushes.
New part of the buffer out, or whatever it updates, those values.
And then, when you ask for them, I think you're just getting back,
whatever its values are at that time.
So I don't actually think when you ask for it, that it actually does
any actual work.
I could be wrong about that though.
Audio seems to be the most complex part until now, which will be the
next more complicated thing.
So I don't think we'll have anything as nearly as complicated as this
audio output, until we get to the rasterization of actual of like till
we get to rendering non.
So when we do the renderer, if we just have like a rectangle, if we're
just drawing, like rectangles on the screen that are filled with
bitmaps.
We're just moving like bitmaps around the screen.
That's not that complicated.
It's pretty easy to understand when we get to because I would like to
do I would like to be able to support in our software renderer.
The ability to like deform and stretch things like skeletal animation
sort of thing.
When we write the rasterizer for that, that's going to be crazy
complicated.
They're not that hard to write, if you kind of just know everything
already.
But even even when you do, there's a ton of debugging to do.
And if you don't, if you've never done it before, it's, it's pretty
darn crazy, complicated.
And especially if we go and optimize it, which we will for Cindy.
It's going to be tough.
So this what we just did is the toughest thing we're going to do for
probably quite some time.
The other stuff.
We're like loading a bitmap is going to be a breeze compared to that
drawing the bitmap to the screen, a breeze, correcting understanding
gamma correction and stuff like that.
Maybe a little more complicated Alpha blending.
A little more complicated than that, but still way easier than what we
just did.
But then when we get to the when we get to fully deformable, rendering
that, that'd be the thing.
Oh, dear.
Hearts are a pain when debugging other things change to log messages.
Yes, I agree with that.
Tom and I wish we had a log.
Are we asserting anything though?
Now, that should that would ever fail.
I think the things were asserting are now.
The only things were asserting, Tom are things that can't fail.
Now, if they failed, you just got a full-on straight up bug.
I took out the assertion.
I took out the only assertion that was asserting on something that was
like an audio Miss.
So I think we've already got that covered.
But I agree with you.
You don't want to start stuff like, oh, I missed the frame or whatever
because that happens and then you're like,
If we had a buffer that played from start to finish, would it be a
valid syncing method to manually set audio?
Timer equals video timer?
Yes, if I understand the question correctly, I'm not sure I understand
exactly what you're asking.
But we are you basically saying could we just use the video, the
audios clock to determine when we flip?
And I think you could but the thing you have to remember is it's 480
sample granularity on this machine, right?
So, you know, just be aware that basically
That's how granular it is 10 milliseconds.
So that's a pretty high window of error for your flip time.
So so you would basically get frame stutter.
I think if you actually tried to use that.
Fully visualize waveforms and remove gradient turn entire thing into
massive audio visualizer.
So we will probably do exactly that.
When I said when we have better rendering code because when we have
better rendering code to be trivial for us to render stuff like this,
like we had to go code all that stuff ourselves.
And so I didn't want to go Hog Wild there because I'm like, we're just
redoing work that we're just going to we're doing later, right?
But once we have some good rendering code in there and we can just
call it like you would in a higher level language, where you've got a
libraries, we're going to build those things up, right?
And then we're going to be able
Program at a pretty high level, not too long in the future.
So I want to wait to do stuff.
That's like really good, debug output with labels and stuff.
I want to wait to do that until we actually have a renderer.
If we had a buffer that play for this ministry, we I did that one with
his invention.
I first got a question.
Could you please increased owners 2512 my crappy?
Laptop speakers can't output 256.
I guess I don't see why not.
That's we move that into the platform nonspecific code.
Right?
So you're asking for this and right.
Something like this that code is going to go away at some point with
something.
Better.
Okay, let's take a look here.
Turn.
Well this audio system be able to handle Music and Sound or will the
game have to mucks the audio for us.
Well, the idea is that Sound and Music are not different.
So all the sound music and sound effects, all come out through this
channel.
So basically the operating system only needs to provide us with a way
to Output audio in left and run left and right Channel.
And then the game just pushes everything through those channels.
So the music will just get mixed directly.
In there along with all the sound effects because music and sound
effects aren't actually different as far as the game is concerned in
terms of what it has to do.
How will you make sure that you don't have regressions in some parts
that are not that easy to spot right away.
Well, you can't, I mean it's part of the answer you put as much debug
visualization stuff in as you can and you put in as much assertions in
as you can, but one of the big problems with games is they're entirely
user input driven.
They're entirely based on stuff that comes back from the operating
system.
So you can't really unit test them.
Like you can't do a lot of testing of components because usually the
component style stuff.
The stuff that's easy to debug and it's the cross system user input
based like complex states of system stuff that fails.
And so you really can't do regression testing on most of the hardest
part of the stuff to test.
So that's unfortunate.
I'm sorry if I'm being slow, but I still don't truly understand why.
Exactly the audio is jumping.
I'm not sure what you mean by jumping.
It just seems like we should be able to handle it more simply.
I've been trying to put together through the storm.
Stream, but I'm just kind of lost.
So I'm not sure what you mean by jumping.
Could you be more specific starchy pancakes about starchy pancakes is
great name.
Why the audio is jumping by this question?
I mean the original problem not the current iteration.
And so I guess just tell me what you mean by jumping and original
problem so that I can I can be just just type it in and we'll ask
answer it there.
Why is the pitch of the sound changes after the game is running a
little while?
So actually, I don't think that that actually happens.
That's the controller.
So I
leave that the controller right now.
This controller has a dead zone as far as I can tell, and I haven't
played with it yet.
That's even bigger than the one specified by.
X input normally and I noticed this when I was playing games to it's
really kind of annoying.
But basically, I believe if we just took out the user input.
So this was gone, right?
We wouldn't hear that anymore.
Hmm.
Now, that's where that actually did change.
What is going on there?
I agree.
That's a bit of a bug because I think our tone hurts should now be
constant, right?
So, how are we actually getting a different sound output speed?
Because that is even difficult for us to do.
It is because we're, if we're always outputting it, basically the
exact same wave period.
That seems pretty pretty tricky.
Now, to be fair.
We're not actually accounting.
One thing we could do is we could account for the fact that the sign
sign loses its Precision, pretty quickly for our test value.
So I should double check as well that that's not happening.
Basically what happens is sign f as this T sign goes up I should guard
against that happening.
So
You know the, the T sine value should basically just wrap every time
it goes It goes through 2 pi.
Right?
So basically if T sine is greater than 2 pi, right T sine can go back
down.
By that amount basically just just normalizing it to its period if
that made sense, so,
But I don't think that should have been it.
Maybe it was.
Yeah, that's that's so for what it's worth.
That's way sooner than I would have thought sign would have lost its
floating Point Precision, but
Looks like that's it.
Looks like literally loses position that quickly and I guess that
makes sense.
Those numbers.
When you think about it.
The sine wave is oscillating.
Many times inside that set inside a second.
So that number is getting really huge and you just blow out.
That's kind of cool.
How fast that happened.
If you think about it.
Basically, you got a floating-point number here, right?
And the floating Point number.
Let's, let's let's do it this way.
I'm basically going to see if I can kind of
Late, roughly, when we hear that sound happen.
I'm going to go ahead and break break into the game at the point where
that happens.
So game output sound.
This is this is pretty cool.
I'm pretty psyched.
That was actually it.
I was wouldn't have expected that but I wanted to check and it turns
out that was it.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to drop a breakpoint into the
game basically as soon as I hear that sound as soon as I hear us at
the sound change.
That makes sense.
I'm going to drop a breakpoint right there.
Okay, so I heard the sound change a little bit.
So let's take a look.
Let's see.
What T sign is.
So there we go.
So basically what we have learned here is that when we get to 18,000
roughly 18,000 we have lost the Precision necessary for the sign to
still work properly.
So I guess one question is roughly.
Where is that on the power of to Spectrum, right?
You know, where where is where is that value?
So if you think about what kind of power of 2 we need for that that's
somewhere.
Around, you know, that somewhere around 15, B.
Let's say, like if you, I don't know.
Where's that?
Where's the pow function?
Scientific?
What do we what do we got here to be have square root?
We do have square root.
So let's see what, let's see here.
Two to the 15th.
Yeah.
Yeah, so that's somewhere around to the 15th worth of bits in there.
And then so you figure, if we have a 24-bit mantissa, right?
So we have 24 bits worth of data in our sign and we're using up, you
know, something like 15 of them, that gives us nine bits of precision,
in our sine wave, left.
Am I doing that?
Right?
Let's say something like that.
That point and so 9 bits of precision in the sound.
Wave.
What would that actually be?
So two to the ninth?
It's 512.
Oh, all right, so you can kind of see what the problem is.
So basically we're down to one we're down to five hundred and twelve
steps in our sine wave and I guess that is enough that we can actually
hear the problem.
So, yeah, we just ran out of precision.
There weren't enough bits in The Floating point value to
Really make that make that work five hundred and twelve steps.
Well times, two Pi.
So yeah, I don't know.
That's that's kind of surprising that that happened so soon, but it
gets you kind of got to figure.
It's going to there.
Just aren't that many bits in a floating point value.
They lose Precision pretty quickly.
So there we go.
I'm going to go ahead and turn the user input back on and see if we
also have a problem with the controller because I think that may be
true as well.
That sounds pretty good.
So that's that's pretty good.
So it looks like maybe it was only just losing sign Precision.
Again.
This is just test codes.
We don't have to care about that but it is nice to get it out of there
because I mean, since its test code, we want it to be consistent and
maybe like, if we'd had another bug in the sound layer, that could
have been masking it.
And we could have been thinking.
Oh, there's just a bug in, you know, in the controller output or
whatever.
And, you know, it's just getting rid of bugs.
Even if it's in code, that doesn't matter at all, is still good
because now, at least we've
Some variability there.
Let's take a look.
Sorry, I meant skipping the original audio.
Skip when we move the latency to be inside of three frames, I believe.
Oh, okay.
So the reason for that was basically just the way we were doing.
The computation was off of the play cursor.
So we were kind of being a little too optimistic, right?
Start, your pancakes here is I think what you were asking.
So basically what we were doing is we were looking at where the play
Chris or was.
So we woke up and the play cursor is somewhere like here right.
Wherever it happens to be.
And we were basically saying, okay, what we want to do is take the
play cursor and take a look at where the next I think what we were
saying something like wherever the play cursor is.
We're going to assume that the play cursor at the time of the flip.
That's what we're doing.
So the play Crusher at the time of the flip.
We were basically saying let's go a frame.
A
Ed of that, right?
Was what we wanted to do, and that's where we should actually write to
should write 2 here in the buffer.
Right?
So one frame ahead is what we would expect for it to be, and we're
going to write one frame ahead of that.
Right?
So it's basically two frames, right?
Is how much, but we would right ahead, ideally, but we then knew that
the right cursor actually was was
Is all the way out here when we started looking at it.
So if the play cursor was even just a little bit off than the right
cursor, would actually be here and we would skip right?
Even if we were lined up properly.
So we had to do is write one full whole frame ahead of even the frame.
We were writing to ensure.
That by the time the play cursor.
Got to the next one.
The right cursor, wasn't passed.
The point that we had written to because if we'd written only to their
the right cursor, will now be passed it and we'd get that Gap.
So it was really just just because we were writing, we wrote that code
optimistically assuming that the play curse.
And the right cursor looked like that, but they actually look more
like that at least on this machine.
If it's not too much of an issue, can we have line numbers on the side
when you are coding so you can get a grip of where well, so, I don't
know.
Can we get them?
I don't know if emacs has that, but I could at least put them on in
here because I think this has that and I wouldn't mind having them
here.
I'm okay with that because I don't need the screen real estate for it.
So let's see, is the text editor have line numbers.
Does it have line numbers?
Yes.
So they're at least.
Then we'll have some line numbers in the debug.
Okay.
So let's see.
Clements bound says, it's more likely to be the accumulation of a
small value onto a larger value.
That is a numerical problem.
Mantissa is not lining up.
Okay.
So basically what they were saying is that we couldn't actually
increment it by well, that's but that's basically the same thing.
I mean that's that's there.
Those are two sides of the same coin.
Basically, the fact that we can't add a small value to it is the same
as saying there isn't Precision in it to record the size of the value
that we actually need for the most part.
But yeah, I agree that maybe if you you could do the math in a way
that was a little more amenable to it.
Well, I'm not sure how you would actually do it.
Yeah, I'm not sure how you'd actually reorganize that math without
just dividing into where the sign would be.
But if you were doing that, you wouldn't have it.
You would never let it grow.
So yeah, I'm not sure.
All right.
Well, my voice is about gone.
So I think that is it for today.
This has been a marathon session.
I think we're we basically did a three hour session of handmade hero,
but I said it was gonna be long and it was long and I think we did
some good work today.
So thank you so much everyone for joining me.
If you would.
Like to get the source code, you can go to handmade hero dot-org and
pre-order the game.
It comes with the full source code, updated, every evening.
You'll get a link in your email.
You can use to download it and it's divided by day.
So you can always jump back and forth between any given day or if you
want to use source code control.
If you have a source code control system that you use, you can check
it in every day.
Even if you just start.
Now, you can basically write a little script or something and unpack
each individual one and create your own source code repository with it
basically.
So you can go ahead and do that.
If you have questions or want to discuss things the news and for
rooms link that basically has all kinds of stuff.
It has coding resources where people have ported the thing to other
platforms.
It's got
Discussion forum where you can ask questions, so it's pretty good.
Basically.
It's a good place to go just to talk to other people and find out
stuff.
Anyway.
Before I lose my voice I will sign off now and say thanks so much for
joining me for another episode of handmade here.
We will be back Monday night at 8:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard time when we will start working on some more
interesting stuff.
In terms of actually what goes on the screen will start looking at how
to
To actually get the game together.
Now that we pretty sure that we've got a reasonable platform layer.
At least for prototyping will probably do one more day of next.
Next week, will mostly be about other stuff but we'll probably do one
more day of win32 things.
There's a couple fun things that I wanted to do.
So we'll probably do a little bit more on the platform layer since it
took us two days to the audio instead of one.
So we'll basically go ahead and do one more day, but after that, we
will be on to graphics.
Doing sort of graphic stuff on the street and other stuff, sort of fun
stuff that I think will be pretty interesting.
So, hopefully, you will join us next week.
8 p.m.
PST on Monday.
Hope to see you all there.
Thank you so much for joining me.