Recording there and there we go.
Okay, everyone, welcome to day.
8 of handmade hero.
We are on holiday time today, Wednesday, Thursday.
Friday is going to be at 11 a.m.
Due to the Thanksgiving holiday here.
And I would like to to give a warm welcome to all the folks in Europe
who are joining us today for the first time because we are finally at
a time where they can easily tune in.
I think someone said it was about 8 p.m.
In Germany right now.
Not sure if that's right.
That sounds good.
Thank you.
Everyone, for joining us.
This, of course is handmade hero.
We are making a game from scratch.
And right now, we are working our way through the windows platform
layer.
If you would like to follow it home and you have pre-ordered, the
source code here.
You will want to go into the zip file that you can download from the
link that you got in your email.
You can go ahead and unpack 007 from inside that zip and that is a
source code that we are starting with today.
So if you want to follow along home, that is what you're doing.
Okay, I am going to go ahead and jump right back to where we
Left off yesterday.
I have one thing that I'll maybe talk about at the end of the stream
that came in as an email, again, dealing with direct input, but I'm
going to say that to the Q&A for.
Now.
I'm just going to jump right in here.
So I'm going to launch our trusty emacs.
A lot of people have been amusingly getting into e Max.
I think I specifically said it's too old of an Editor to start
learning.
Now, try to find something else, but people have been having Jeff
gone.
Anyway, and that's pretty, pretty hilarious TMax the editor.
That won't die people.
Anyway, I'm going to open up emacs here and we're going to take
A look at where we left off.
Basically, what we did yesterday, is we wrote this in it D, sound
function.
And you can take a look at it here.
It's very simple.
Basically, what we do is we load direct sound directly.
We get a pointer to a single function and that single function is a
function that we call to basically give us back an object.
So this is basically C++ linkage.
It's calm, which is Windows, is sort of implementation of C++ across
the dll boundary.
But basically what happens is we are just calling a function and it is
giving us back an object.
That we can use to call for other functions on that literally does
mean that we are essentially getting back an object with a vtable.
Now.
We are not really going to be covering C++ very explicitly on this
stream, but I will simply mention what this is for.
Those of you who are wondering how this all works with this little
arrow here.
I think it's worth explaining now that we've kind of got the code
working from yesterday.
It's worth explaining how this works.
So normally, if I have something like this, where I type in a struct
like that, basically, we saw
Saw in the intro to see stream and in this stream as well.
We saw that basically what that does is that tells the compiler to lay
out a particular piece of memory.
So that the the things that are in the struct basically come together,
possibly, with some padding in between them and basically, in the
order in which they occur and in the sizes that they occur.
So if I do something like this, I will end up with 32-bit x value in a
16-bit y value.
Anytime I ask for one of these.
So if later, I declare one of them, I basically get the X, and the Y
value.
Now that is, what is in memory.
But C++ allows you to do some extra things.
You can do something called a virtual function declaration, which we
will not be using in the Stream, but you can do it.
Basically.
What it is is you declare some function just like any other function
you might declare but basically what
opens is
Instead of actually just hard-coding calls to that function.
So if later, you know, we were somewhere and we had one of these few
objects, right?
We would call it as if it was a method.
We'd put the dot on there and we'd actually call it like this.
It's just like any other function call at first.
It looks the same right?
You can pass parameters to it this sort of thing.
That's exactly what happens.
But there is a catch.
If you were to just do this, there'd be no difference, really between
it and a normal.
Ocean be exactly the same.
The only difference is actually syntactic.
So basically, if I actually this is this is how I'm again.
I'm I'm going to speed through this because we're not going to be
using them.
I just want you to kind of understand what's going on.
So this is how you would declare it.
Basically, it's the exact same function, declaration that you've seen.
Everywhere else.
I should say function definition.
You've seen everywhere else, but you put this Foo colon colon prefix
on it, which basically is what's called a scoping.
It's called scoping and C++ or the scoping operator.
Basically what it says is this bar is not
Actually just a function at file scope.
It's actually a function that's declared inside this Foo object and
from in, so you can't just call it.
You can't call the function like this.
You gotta call it off of one of those one of those foods and what
actually happens is in this, the compiler implicitly actually
rewrites.
The way, the function is under the hood, you won't see it do this, but
it'll do it.
It'll basically insert a fence that synthetic parameter here called
the this pointer.
And the this pointer will be basically used as an
illicit way to reference anything that happens in the function.
So, inside this function, if I were to reference see I can just
reference.
See, if I were to clear a new variable.
I can declare a new variable.
It works just like any other function, but if I were to reference X
say, for example, C plus equals x, normally X would be undefined here.
There would be no way of the compiler.
Resolving what X-Men you would say that was undefined and it would ask
you to defy it but in our case that was not true because that this
pointer that gets implicitly past year.
This thing.
Basically it will check to see first whether it could
Could have reference something inside that this pointer.
And in this case, there is an X there.
So this gets turned by the compiler into that automatically for you.
That is the only real difference in these functions.
Basically, it allows you to sort of have this free sort of look up
that you wouldn't otherwise have and there are some other things that
I'm not going to go into their totally against syntactic and basically
features that about C++ that we won't be using.
But the thing that I wanted to talk about more explicitly in that
bears understanding or it's worth understanding in order to understand
what's happening with direct sound here and calm interfaces in general
and windows.
Again, cam is Comm.
It stands for component object model.
If you would like to look that up again, we won't really be covering
in detail here because it's not really relevant to us, but it is what
we are calling through at the moment.
Basically, what happens here is I can declare this function virtual
and what that means is that it's actually more complicated than a
regular function.
It is not just a syntactic thing where it's inserting a little fake
parameter for us.
There's more than that.
What this will cause the compiler to do this virtual function is it
will cause it to insert, basically, up here, it will insert what's
called a v table pointer.
And basically, what a vtable pointer is is outside, here.
There will basically be the compiler, will declare this globally.
It will declare a vtable for Foo.
A vtable is basically something that contains a bunch of functions.
Turner's.
It's basically got pointers to the functions that should be called
when you are using a foo and basically what happens from now on is
when you do this food bar, instead of just putting out the code for an
actual function call.
What it does is it looks up in this table.
So first, it'll do look up bar in the vtable for Foo using the
pointer.
So, using Fu's vtable, actually, literally going and looking into the
table.
So it gets the pointer out of the top of Foo, the one that the
compiler silently inserted, without telling you,
About it.
It just silently inserted that pointer.
It'll go look at foofy table.
Eat a look at the index in the vtable to which bar corresponds and it
will then jump to that address.
So if you remember, we basically did this sort of stuff up here
ourselves.
We declared our own function pointers, we made our own function
pointer and called through them for the xinput stuff xinput, get State
and, and so basically that is exactly what it's doing here.
But instead of having a global pointer, it actually has a global
Table and each, it has several Global tables one for each struct that
uses virtual functions.
Basically, what it does is it will actually look at the the structure
to find the pointer to the table.
Look up the pointer to the function, in that table.
It's this W directed thing.
And finally, it will dispatch if it sounds like a lot of extra work.
It is one of the reasons that C++ virtual functions are not fabulous
is they do hit that double in Direction, which is not a very good
thing.
It cost you some performance every time often.
It depends how good the compiler is and CPU.
Is it handling them?
Certainly?
So the cost may vary, but it is definitely a lot different than
calling just a regular function.
It is not a zero cost abstraction as they say.
Anyway, point being, that is actually what we are.
Getting back from this direct sound call.
So back here, when we ask for direct sound, create.
Basically.
We're calling direct sound create and direct sound, create is going to
give us back a
Checked with that V table in it.
So you'll notice we don't have to ask.
We don't have to use get proc address to get the rest of the
functions.
We're going to call instead.
We're just calling them off of the actual object that we got back.
And basically the vtable that is in that object is the thing.
That is actually allowing us to get to these other functions.
And just to be a little more explicit.
You might say, well, where is that vtable in memory?
Well, the vtable got mapped into memory when we loaded the dll, so the
dll itself had the vtable in it.
It when it got loaded, we are actually pointing to when we get back
our handle to the struct, or I should say, the, the direct sound
object.
Since we're, you know, whether it's a struct or class, who knows?
How they declared it.
Internally doesn't matter for our purposes at all struck.
Some classes are the same.
Anyway point being when we get back that handle to the direct sound.
It basically has a pointer to a v table that is inside the direct
sound dll.
And we will basically just be calling through that jump table.
So every time we make a call to
Up in there.
It'll grab out that thing.
And, and there, it'll go.
And, you know, we can even if you if you want to.
I got to save my file.
If you want to we can go ahead and even take a look at that happening.
If I open up the the debugger here, again, everything gets translated
to CPU, doesn't matter what language you program in the CPU, has to do
everything.
So no matter how fancy stuff looks in a language.
Basically, you are always going to end up having to have the CPU, do,
whatever work is necessary to have.
Have that happen languages make things sometimes simpler for the
programmer.
They do not make things a simpler for the CPU, that is just how that
works.
So basically, you can you could take a look at this here.
Let's see here.
So you'll notice this is the Assembly Language for this call, and you
will notice right here.
This is the part that we're looking at.
So normally normally, when we call a function, I'll just show you
another example here actually a just to make it a little clearer.
So normally if we went down here,
Let's look at a function that we were actually you know that we had
implemented ourselves, right?
This is a function that we had implemented ourselves.
So if I go ahead and I go to the disassembly here, you will notice
that basically what gets outputted is essentially a direct call to the
address of that function.
And what basically happened was the Linker when it linked us up.
It basically said, look that is where the function is.
So that is the at the address, I'm going to output and the call is
just a direct call to a constant address.
That's what happens.
There's nothing fancy going on.
And it's one thing.
When we call into it.
Then we're in the function.
That's it.
Right.
That's what happens.
Now, in C++.
Every time you use a virtual function.
You are basically incurring more overhead than that.
What you are actually doing is you are going in here and you can see
that this is the call site.
This is the place where we're actually going to call that set
Cooperative level.
And as you can see, it cannot insert an actual address.
It has to basically insert a call to an address that it loads.
and you can,
That happening right here.
Basically, you can see that it moving into our ax.
It's basically getting the vtable pointer.
It's loading in that function.
This is doing the pushes for the actual.
I think the the actual parameters and stuff and that we want, but this
is actually doing call off of our ax which got loaded up here.
So you can see that.
It's actually doing work to load something in first.
It's loading off the RSP then it's going ahead and actually loading
off of that which is the double indirection.
Like I said, it's loading a pointer.
And then loading a pointer off the pointer, excuse me.
And then finally, it's calling one more in Direction.
It's basically calling.
Yeah, I mean to be more explicit.
It's loading in the direct sound.
It's loading the V table pointer out of the direct sound.
Then it's loading the, the actual address out of that V table because
it knows this is the address.
I believe.
I'm not the best person at at Assembly Language.
I've never written a compiler that output C++ Assembly Language.
So I'm just basically assuming that this is roughly
What it has to do.
Now, maybe if we were in optimized mode, it could get this a little
simpler, something like that.
But basically that is the idea.
So you got to load the pointer to the object.
You got a little, the point of the V table.
Then you got to load the function pointer out of that.
And finally, you can go ahead and call it.
So that's what's going on there.
That makes sense.
Hopefully, that's clear to everyone.
It's not particularly complicated and you don't really have to
understand it because we are not going to be using anything like that
in our code.
But
That is what happens in C++ and that is what happens in calm as well.
So that's what's happening in here.
We're getting back.
One of those, we are basically at asking a direct sound for a handle
to the primary buffer and that primary buffer.
We are using to set the output format for our sound, which we set to
be stereo two channels, 16 bits per sample, which is good and choose
me again.
Sorry.
I'm so sick.
And, and we are also saying,
That we essentially want to be 48, khz audio, which I picked
basically, because I think one time I asked Jeff Roberts who, of
course, was the guy who maintain the mouth sound system for a very
long time.
What was the most common native format for sound output and he said 48
kilohertz, so that's what I'm going with.
But you could pick 44 one as well.
Cd-quality audio, you know, that all sound card support that as well.
Pretty much has to, I think
There's just a question whether they Read sample it or what they do to
it.
So anyway, we then open our own buffer here.
And that is what we're going to talk about right now.
We open a buffer called the secondary buffer, which is the buffer that
we can actually write into.
We can't write in the primary buffer.
Those days are over.
We have to write into the secondary buffer.
That's the way that supposed to work now.
And basically, the colonel will sort of take all the people who are
writing a secondary buffers, mix them together and output them to the
sound card.
We no longer get direct write privileges to the same card, kind of
like, we no longer have direct right privilege to the graphics card.
It all kind of gets.
Admitted, you know, kind of mitigated it all goes through windows.
I guess we use something like mantel.
Maybe you can, but assuming that you're going through the window
standard apis, you don't get direct access anymore.
It's just not how it works.
In here, what we basically want to do is we want to keep this buffer
pointer around.
This is basically the thing that we're going to use all the time to
write to the sound buffer.
So I'm going to basically Elevate that out this secondary buffer.
I'm going to elevate that out to our Global's again.
I'm not sure that that's going to stay there necessarily because like
I said, I don't like to have too many Global variables in a platform
layer.
It's usually not that big a deal actually because you're kind of
really isolated in the code here and you kind of have looked at it all
it's not that big a deal.
But at the same time, you always want to be aware of it because a
global variable is something that anyone can modify and sometimes that
creates a little bit of a stringiness in your code.
So be aware of what you make Global.
Don't do it willy-nilly.
Make sure you understand why it's Global and that it should say Global
and that there's only going to be one of them and if any of those
things aren't true, don't do it.
All right.
So we're going to actually create that that buffer globally here.
And then once we get that buffer, we will be able to output sound from
now on.
So Dillard and output sound.
Basically, I'm going to do something, extremely simple.
I am just going to ask where the right pointer is and I am going to
fill in some memory with with the sound and now sound is a little bit,
is a little bit wonky.
Certainly, it's good question.
What we're going to put in there for not loading anything yet because
I wanted to wait for, you know, I want to I'm going to show you how to
load wav files later.
We will play sound but to get something working.
First off.
I think I'm going to use a good old Square wave, something like that
so that we can just hear.
It's going to be an awful sound certainly, but if we take a look here,
you can see basically we have a square wave.
It's got a pretty reasonable graph here.
These are the basic kinds of waves that you can output that are, you
know, really simple decode.
Obviously.
There's a sine wave.
There's a square wave.
Triangle wave Sawtooth and they just look like this.
You can see square is probably the simplest to code.
All it is is just High.
High signal, High positive signal, followed by a low- signal and
nothing in between.
So it's just full on just full-on oscillation like that, and that's
about it.
So I think, I think, basically that's all I'm going to try and dumped
into this buffer.
So basically we're in our Loop here, right?
One of the things we do in our Loop is we, you know, we get the input.
Then another thing we do is we render that weird gradient.
So right here after the after the gradient, I'm going to go ahead and
try to lock that buffer.
So I'm going to go ahead.
Do direct sound output test right here, just to see if we have
anything working.
Now, in order to do that.
Basically, what we need to do is we need to lock that direct sound
buffer.
And so basically, if you remember from the help, we basically had to
use the help for direct sound 8 because the old directsound help
wasn't even there.
It's probably fine to use direct sound date for any real purposes.
Almost every modern machine I think is going to have direct sound
eight.
So I wouldn't worry about that too much.
But most of the stuff works in the older API as well.
So I was just calling the older version, which is direct sound seven,
and prior Microsoft, doesn't even have a help for those posted
anymore.
But anyway, what we need to actually do is fill up the buffer.
So we got to actually do a lock here.
Where is our lock?
There is our lock right there, where it don't they have?
I need the I need the actual help here at people.
I want to actually see the help.
There it is.
This is what we're talking about.
So this is the function that I actually wanted.
Basically it.
What it does.
If you remember, we are going to be doing circular buffer output and I
drew a diagram about this yesterday.
I'm going to draw a diagram about it today again, just to reinforce it
the page.
Really?
What's Happening Here?
Right is, we have a thing that looks like this.
It's a buffer and we are going to write our sound into the buffer like
this, right off.
It goes.
And basically, what happens here is direct sound will be playing this
buffer and when it gets to the end of the buffer, it's going to loop
back to the beginning.
So just playing it over and over.
So effectively you can think of this as a circular buffer.
It's like the beginning of it was copied to the end, right?
It just keeps going it's, you know, when it plays.
So as it plays, it's going to kiss.
Just keep going as it goes off.
The end that makes sense.
So what's going to happen here is we need to basically right into this
buffer.
And in order to write into this buffer, direct sound actually knows
that you lot of times for using these a circular buffers.
So it allows you to do is it allows you to lock a region by giving a
pointer to the beginning, basically not a pointer, but basically an
offset to say this is the place I want to start locking the buffer to
write into because remember, this is a system buffer Windows wants to
know when we're writing to it.
So we need to basically issue a
Lock call to say, we're about to write into this.
So just so, you know, you're going to have to update it.
So we locked it to right into this and it actually gives us back to
potentially regions.
So for example, when we lock this, we give it a size and maybe that
size was this big, right?
We say that's how many bytes we wanted to write into the buffer.
So it needs to lock that big but it can't lock that big because
obviously there's nothing out here, the buffer ends.
So what it does is it takes this this sort of residual here this part
And it locks the beginning of the buffer for however, much the overrun
was so it basically gives us back to Regions.
Right?
It gives us back a one region here, where that's at the actual office
that we asked for it and that goes to the end of the buffer
potentially and one that starts the beginning of the buffer and then
goes to wherever it would have been to make the buffer the size that
we wanted.
Now, that's doesn't have to happen.
It can also be that if we gave it a pointer or rather an offset to
somewhere in the buffer where it could lock the whole thing just in
one place, right?
And this is my little lock.
How's that?
Oh, it's awful.
Don't look at that.
Okay.
Anyway, it'll lock it all in one chunk.
So we may get back just one we may get back to and we have to handle
both cases basically from direct sound, it's easy to do but that's
that's basically the idea.
Hopefully that makes some sense.
Okay.
Let's put this up here.
All right.
So what we are going to try to do here?
And this is
Things, get a little complicated and I always messed up like this up.
It's confusing.
We need to write a little function, the jumps, the saw, the dumps, the
Sawtooth into into the into the buffer.
So we're going to call this lock all here.
And we are going to go ahead and call our Global secondary buffer, and
attempt to lock it.
We are going to give it the offset and that offset is going to be
something that we get from the right pointer.
So that's going to be the right pointer.
And we are going to try to write out.
I don't know, maybe maybe will basically look at
The plate cursor as well.
We'll talk about those two are in do it.
So let's say b 2 right here.
Let me see if that's actually right.
It isn't B.
Yes.
Yes it is.
Then it is going to give us back basically a series of pointer that
it's going to give us a pair of pointer and size to specify those two
regions.
So this is region 0, let's say or I guess I call it region, one of the
diagram.
So we have a pointer to region 1.
We have a size of region 1, so we have Regional.
And one size and then we're going to have this again for a second one,
and that is what we're going to pass here.
So we got region 1 region, one size, and we're going to pass the
address of both of them because it's basically returning those to us
again.
It's passing the adder.
So it can fill them out in memory and then we're going to pass the
flags.
And the flags are are pretty much self-explanatory here, I guess.
Yeah, there's not much.
Oh, okay.
So, you know what?
We can actually
Block from the right cursor directly.
All right, so we can we can even just do do that.
Although I don't we yeah, we don't really want to do it that way.
We want to actually specify it.
I'm pretty sure.
So we're going to we're going to go ahead and say that that's the
case.
All right, so
We don't really need any flags as far as I can tell.
There's nothing in there that's going to help us.
So this is basically what we're looking at for the entirety of this.
Call.
That'll lock it for us.
So now we just need, we actually need to get that right pointer and we
need to get that bite size, right pointer and we need the B to, right?
Let's see.
Okay, so we have to actually get these from somewhere.
So that's our next goal.
Once we get them, we can then fill the region with a Sawtooth
basically.
I'm going to do that in a little bit of a sort of janky way here.
Again.
This is just test code, this is going to get deleted.
So basically what I'm going to do is I'm just going to make it this
100% explicit.
I'm going to say we're going to start writing at the particular sample
Index, right.
And that sample index is or I should say.
Yeah.
Sample index.
And that sample index is actually going to be wherever this first
region actually ends up being so
So yeah, sorry.
I'm not explaining this very well.
This is the lack of coffee.
Let me say that again.
We have a sound buffer and that sound buffer contains samples.
Contain samples that look like this.
It contains samples that look like this right there interleaved.
And basically each one of these is 16 bits, right?
So it looks like this 16 bit.
It's a it's an in 16, another in 16 another, in 16 kind of AD ad
infinitum, right?
Going on and on, and on.
So, our buffer is 16 bits of the Left Channel, 16 bits for the right
channel, 16 bits To the Left Channel, 16 bits for the right channel.
So basically, I want to Loop over these
Things.
And this is what we're considering a single sample.
Because basically, they go together, right?
We can't output anything less than that.
We need to Output one of those at a time because that is the only
thing that actually makes sense.
For our stereo sound.
We couldn't output just eight bits.
It'd be like half of the left handle value.
That is make any sense.
So, we're going to Output those at a single time.
So basically region one size comes back, and it had better, be an even
multiple of the samples, because if it's not something really weird
has happened because we're only
Going to ask for an even multiple the samples, the buffer is only an
even multiple of sample, size, long.
And we're not going to ever give it a right pointer.
That isn't an even multiple.
So this would be a good place for an assert.
I haven't talked to you about those yet, but we will talk about those
maybe in the later of the stream to just to assert that that's true.
Assert that region one size.
Is valid and read the two sides as well in the case where it gets
returned.
So we'll talk about that a little bit later.
I don't want to start throwing asserts in here, until I actually have
a chance to sit down and talk with you about what they are.
So I have to schedule that some point because it's pretty important.
Anyway, sample index is 0.
It goes up to the region one size and then it, it will be finished.
Now, of course, we then have to do the same thing for for the next
region.
So we want to go up to region.
Sighs, and these sample index, these indices are relative to the
region, right?
So these are all the samples in region 1.
These are all the samples in Region 2.
And what we have to basically do is we have to fill in something now.
So we're going to have to fill in the pointer to the buffer here.
Basically, we're going to write two things, a left and a right each
time.
So the first thing we want to do is get an in 16 pointer to the
buffer.
Now, it returned us the pointer which was region 1, right?
And so this is the basically, the sample out, this is what we're going
to be writing to.
So we're going to cast that to a un to an instant steam, which is the
thing.
We're going to be writing.
And basically we're going to right here.
We're going to we're going to write as we increment along.
We're going to write our left here and are right here, right?
And then we're going to do the same exact thing down here.
So that makes sense.
Hopefully that's clear.
Alright, so basically this will do everything that we want to, we just
have to figure out what we're going to do in terms of the actual
values here.
So what we want to do is we want to go and every sample depending on
which sample we are at.
We basically want to go ahead and make a square wave.
So we want to be able to basically just do if
Sample.
Index happens to be, you know, the first n samples.
It's going to be high positive.
It's the first if it comes after that, the next and samples are going
to be low and high and low and high and low, so we're going to use the
mod operator for that.
Probably.
So basically what we're going to do here is we are going to actually
upload, you know, we could we don't even really need to use the mod.
Operator.
We could we could be a little more gentle than that.
So basically what we're going to do is go to find a variable that's
going to tell us where we are in our Sawtooth pattern.
We are basically going to call that
at I'm sorry, not Sawtooth R square wave pattern.
We're going to call that R square wave counter and basically all
that's going to do is if the square wave counter happens, to be
happens to be 0.
So we're done, you know, basically we finished one part of our Square
wave if the square wave counter happens to be 0, we are going to set
just me man.
I wish I could get healthy again.
I can't tell you how frustrating it is to be trying to talk to you and
have this stupid cold in my way.
Really annoying.
All right.
Anyway, this Square wave counter is going to basically go up to the
number of samples that we want.
Our Square wave to have high.
Before it goes, low and vice versa.
So basically what we're going to do is we're going to say well if R
square wave counter.
I don't know.
I'm going to pick a random value here and then we're going to knit
later Square wave period or something like this.
We're going to reset it.
Each time again.
This is kind of ugly.
The way I'm doing this.
Probably not the best way to do it but its first thing I thought of so
we're going to make it to that way.
And then what we're going to do is we're going to say our
Value is just going to be whether or not the square wave, counter
happened to be above half the square wave period.
Basically, that's about it.
That's that's all we're doing.
If it happens to be above that, then it will output the highest
possible value that it can well, maybe not the highest possible value.
Let's just say 16,000.
Yeah.
I don't know how loud we want this thing to be being, basically.
This is a 16-bit value.
So 32,000 is the maximum.
It could be there, you know, there to whatever it is, 65536 divided by
2.
And if the square wave period, if it's not that if it's in the other
half of the square wave period allowed, put the - that's basically all
I actually want to do here and these are basically the exact same
Loop.
So we'll probably compress these in a second down to one Loop, but
that's basically it.
That is all we wanted to do.
So, all we really need to do now is make sure that we actually fill
out all these values somewhat reasonably, I believe that's correct.
Okay, someone on the stream said, let's code a mini Moog synthesizer
and emulator instead of a game.
Umm, you know what, that is Shawn Barrett's Turf ladies and gentlemen,
I am not the person to do that for you.
But you know, I bet if you asked nothing's at nothing's at Twitter to
do a stream where he codes a Moog synthesizer for you.
I bet he would do that.
That is exactly the kind of thing that he would do and he is exactly
the kind of person who would know how to do that, a lot better than I
would.
I would just end up writing a lot of crappy code.
This that I just wrote for you because honestly, I never synthesized
sound.
Really, I always play from some kind of sample materials that get
mixed together.
So this is way out of my area of expertise to say the least but it's
definitely the easiest thing for us to write to just get things going.
Okay.
So we need some stuff here.
We have not finished because we have to Define some things.
Obviously.
We have a square wave period and that's where wave period is going to
have to be something reasonable.
We also have to make sure that we actually decorate decrement, our
Square wave counter every time we output a sample, write something
like this.
Just so that it starts to count down to zero as it should.
And and so it will repeat.
Now the square wave period, I don't really know what the average
square wave period, should be for a sound that you can hear.
Let's say, middle C.
What is the frequency of middle C?
Okay.
So middle C is in hertz.
Basically, what hurts is, if you don't know what hurts is, its cycles
per second.
Basically what that means?
If I go back over here to our amazing diagram.
Basically, what you can imagine is we have that square wave, right?
It's going like this.
And similarly, you might have a sound wave, you know, that goes like
this and basically, I believe the way they typically measure.
It is a cycle is how long it takes to go back to
Are you were so from like one Peak to the next Peak, right?
Like this or from from, you know, from here to here, basically, for
one complete copy of the pattern of the wave that is basically called
a cycle.
That is what we're considering a cycle.
And so Hertz is just cycles per second.
That's all.
So basically, if we are going to play a sound for one second or fill a
buffer, that's one second long.
Then you can imagine.
It should have 261 copies of that pattern, for middle C.
Basically that that is, that is what that means.
So if we try to back this out here, if we're trying to figure out what
R square wave period, should be, basically what the value is.
Maybe I'll go here and say, you know what the Hertz is.
So we'll try to get a hurt something like that.
So, I don't know.
Let's just say 256, should be close enough.
I want a power of two, just because I'm a programmer like that.
That'll be somewhere.
Most a middle, C in theory, I believe should be fine.
So if we have, if we're wanting to actually do 256 cycles per second,
right then the question is, how many samples do we need to fill?
Because again, this is going to be in samples here.
How many samples do we need to fill before?
We actually have that many, how many samples for a full, you know, for
one of our Loops.
So basically what we want to do is we want to say well Hertz is
samples per second, right?
So all we have to really do is say that whatever our sample rate is,
and we know what it is right here.
We set it.
So I could even say this is our samples per second, right?
That we actually asked the sound buffer for oops.
Actually asked the sound buffer for there.
It is samples per second.
If that is our samples per second.
Then we basically know that if we want to have 256 of our thing, then
each one of them should occupy.
Basically, the, the number of samples were actually going to do in 1 s
divided by the number of the things we want in one second, right?
Because that's how many chunks there would be.
That's how many samples would be per chunk.
If we've chunked up our
Set our full second into 256 slices.
So I'm going to say that's roughly R square wave period.
We're not trying to be precise here.
So I'm basically going to say that that is what we will actually fill
out.
So now this should work.
I think we can go down and see where writing that many samples.
Yes, we are.
So what we have to do here now is we have to actually turn our region
sizes into counts, right?
Because these are sizes.
These are bite sizes that are coming back and we actually need sample
sizes.
So like I said, we got to assert that
Valid.
And then I jumped into an explanation and forgot to finish what I was
trying to do.
Here.
We need region, one, sample count, right?
Because this is how many bytes, but we know that our samples are
actually 32.
So that's 4.
Bytes per, a 32-bit sample to give two 16-bit samples left and a
right.
So, basically, we have to do, is we have to divide this here, by our
B, for sample, right?
So, by our bytes per sample to actually get the region one sample
count, which is what we
To Loop over and same thing here.
We got to do the exact same thing down here.
And the reason I wanted to as do the assertion, like I saying is just
to guarantee that what it gave us back was even lie to me this evenly
divisible here, man.
I hate the winner.
I get sick every year and it is awful.
Absolutely awful.
And I think I've gotten much sleep the past few nights.
It is just absolutely miserable.
Don't ever get sick people.
If you can avoid it, just don't do it.
It's no good God.
All right.
Well anyway, the reason I made B for sample, be a variable is because
I knew it was used up here as well.
This is it right here.
So I figured we're just clean this up.
And now will actually have basically
A complete set of definitions for our sound system that we could
change.
If we wanted to just to make it a little clearer, what's going on?
So we're going to be sad with that exact parameter.
Then we're gonna go down here.
We're going to do all the work with those parameters.
And so pretty much only thing we need to do now is we need to figure
out where these guys are going to come from?
I believe we cut everything else.
I don't know.
There's a lot of code in there, and I was talking to whole time.
So there's probably some bugs, but we will debug them and it will not
be an issue.
Okay.
Hmm.
Finally, we basically need to figure out where we are going to ask
directsound to, right?
And we're going to have to figure out how many bytes we need to write
and we have some information.
We can use to do that.
Lee.
If we go back over here to our direct sound buffer, we can see there
should be a call.
Let's see if I can bring up the actual definition of the buffer
somewhere people.
There it is.
Okay.
Basically what we've got here is, we've got all the calls that we can
call on a buffer.
And what I basically want to do is I want to get back the, the clay
cursor and the right cursor.
I'll talk about what those are.
I believe it is this call right here.
Here and and this is the call that we're going to use to get that
back.
So right before we determine what we're going to do, I'm going to call
this.
We are going to assume that this succeeds, because if we can't get it,
then the sound buffer died or something bad happened and we probably
shouldn't try to output sound if we can actually get it.
So I'm just going to go ahead and wrap this here right up in that so
that we don't actually do anything.
If we can't do this, the same should be true of the lock while we're
at it.
The lock itself again returns at H result.
So, I'm just going to say let's not do anything.
If for some reason we can't lock these buffers because that's no good.
That just means direct sound is encountered.
Some kind of really bad, sort of fatal error, bad condition.
Maybe the sound card got yanked or changed out from under it or
something and we don't want to be doing anything in there.
We might end up with bad rights or some some bad stuff going on.
All right.
Now, what should happen here is basically, we should be able to ask to
direct sound for the play cursor position and the right cursor
position and I will show you what those are.
Basically, those are both going to be returned to us.
If this call succeeds, we will then have that information.
So, there we go.
And that should basically compile.
Now, I would think, oh, right now we need the, we need to call that
off the secondary buffer, like that.
And then we just need to do these.
So, there we go.
Now, what are these things?
Well, basically what's going to happen is in our diagram here.
I don't know if I can back up how far I can undo in this thing.
Look at that.
Undo didn't quite get as far enough.
All right, no big deal.
We'll just go ahead and clear that out and start drawing again.
Where's the pen tool in this thing?
There it is.
Alright.
So basically what happens here is the in that buffer again.
Oh my, why are we so tiny?
You have to use the pen.
Know?
How do I get a brush?
People?
Give me a brush.
Is that a brush?
There we go.
All right here.
Is my buffer, there it is.
Again.
Basically, what's going on here is you have to imagine that the
hardware, the actual sound card, or the kernel mixer or whoever is
basically controlling the situation.
We don't really know who that is.
But whoever it is, they are actually looking at this buffer at a
particular location and that is the play cursor.
That is the play cursor.
Wow.
That is a really bad drawing.
Play cursor right here now because of the way Hardware works and
because of the way the colonel mixing works and all those
sorts of things.
It's all asynchronous, right?
This is happening.
Whether we're running or not, it's happening.
Perhaps concurrently with us on a separate core of the processor.
We may be interrupted at any time in our code because the operating
system wants to do something etcetera, Etc.
So, these are things the hardware that that sound is going to be
playing whether we're running or not.
And so it's not safe for us to start writing directly in there.
Because by the time we finish doing whatever the right is the hardware
may actually have beaten us because we may get interrupted.
Who knows what happens?
The hardware may actually have beaten us and played garbage.
Judge something that's half written or who knows what?
So instead what happens is there's another cursor called the right
cursor and that basically leads the play cursor.
It's a cursor that somewhere else out here and basically the right
cursor tells us.
Well, we can write into a particular location and then we can move,
you know, basically from their forwards, right?
And so what we're going to do is we're basically just going to see how
far the right cursor.
Moved probably and and we'll right into that.
Now there's a little thing a little
Out here since the lock, doesn't as far as I know.
Let's take a look at this because I'm trying to remember exactly how
this system works.
I don't think the lock moves the right cursor, does it?
Let's take a look, blah, blah, blah, Returns the ring buffer stuff.
Like we said, after writing data, to the point of Return by this
method, the application was immediately call unlock.
Yes, that's true.
So we should actually do that.
We got to do that as well.
The method returns, right?
Porter's only.
Yeah, so that's, that's, that's it.
So, basically, this right cursor is just going to move a little bit
ahead of the play Chris or it's not going to move when we write.
So one of the things we're also going to have to add here is the fact
that we're going to have to track where
Were in the buffer basically and we're betting that that's really all
we're going to be able to.
Yeah, that's what we're going to have to do.
So really, the right pointer is not actually going to be something
that we need to know about.
Basically.
It's the play curse or really that we're going to have to see because
we're going to have to look to see where we can fill to basically.
All right.
So that's fine.
It's going to be a little bit more complicated math.
Like I say this code is going to be pretty janky.
Hopefully, at the end of this will actually be in relatively good
shape.
And when we actually output sound, it'll be a lot easier than this
because we'll have extracted.
This kind of weird ring, buffer stuff.
Out in a way that we don't have to deal with it.
So so it's that won't be so confusing.
Basically take almond milk, it here.
Yeah, this is probably like I said, I told you Sam is going to be
rough yesterday.
This is the kind of stuff.
I was referring to outputting to a ring.
Buffer is never fun.
So he's a little confusing as we boil the code down.
It'll get a little clearer at first.
It's always a little janky, especially, when you don't remember how
everything works, which is the case with me at this point.
But anyway, point being so basically what we want to do is we want to,
we want to actually remember where we were, how many, how many sounds
we outputted.
Which is sort of what we're doing here and we want to be able to lock
the buffer at wherever we left off.
Off essentially, so since we basically have a counter, we could we
could reuse this counter.
I don't know if we really
Do that.
Yeah, maybe we do.
So basically what we might want to do here for example is we might
want to just use a mod.
It's inefficient, but it might be a little cleaner than what we were
doing basically to actually get this value.
So let's think about it this way.
Let's say that we actually have a sample Index.
This is our, this is our sample index here that we're going to write
to
And that's going to actually Loop.
We want that to be an unsigned integer because we want it to.
Basically if it ever wraps over 4 billion.
We want to go back to zero not to a negative number.
So we're going to have a sample index here basically and that sample
index is just going to go up forever.
For now.
That's what we're going to say.
We're going to get rid of our square root of counter.
So we're going to have a sample index and that's going to go Paris
starts at zero and goes up forever.
So the first thing that we're going to do two right into the buffer
basically is when we lock the buffer.
We're actually just going to lock the
Buffer at whatever our sample, our sample index is our Global sample
index.
So this is going to be a, I don't know what we're going to call this.
Actually, I guess we, let's see.
Let's call this are running sample index.
So it's just where it just keeps going like that.
So, basically, what we're going to do here is we're going to say,
okay, we've got this running sample index and it's going to just keep
going up forever to tell us roughly where we are.
We're then going to say, okay.
We need to know where in the buffer that would because this is
basically just going to go
Forever.
And we want to map it into the circular buffer, that makes sense.
So basically we want to make a d word.
That is basically the sample index to lock.
So this is the sample index to lock is going to be the running sample
index times, the bytes per sample.
So that turns it from a sample index into a bite sample.
And so X should actually say this is the B to lock turns it into a,
we're in the B.
It was, but we now have 2 mod by the size of the buffer.
Basically, to say, if it loops
It gets to the end.
It's got to go back to the beginning because it's in this life.
It's in this circular buffer.
Right now.
The mod is basically just says remainder.
It basically says divide this number by this other number and give me
the remainder, which is exactly what we want.
Right?
We basically want it to give us something back, that's going to be
mmm.
Excuse me, that's going to be whatever, fractional portion we would
have of the of the total buffer size because that's where in the
buffer we will actually be.
So that's what we actually want here.
We want that bite to lock.
So that is where that is.
What will be asking, B to lock, right there.
Right?
And then the number of bytes to write is basically going to be
however, far, we would go to get to the play cursor because we don't
want to right past the play curse or so.
We're just going to write from wherever we are to the play cursor.
So basically here we go.
We have got our B to right.
And basically what we need to know is we need to know whether the play
cursor is in front of or Behind the B to lock.
Basically, if the bite to lock is actually in front of, right?
The play cursor if it's higher than where the plate.
Sir is because this play cursor again, is also going to be in B, I
believe let's verify that I don't actually know.
We didn't, we didn't look, let's take a look address of the variable
determines the offset in B.
That's what we want to know.
So, basically if the bite to lock is above the play cursor, that means
we have to write all the way to the end of the buffer and that for the
beginning to the play cursor.
So basically, that means that our B to right.
Which is what we're trying to compute.
Here are B to write is
Really going to be the buffer size, right?
So, this is the, I should say, secondary buffer size, is we're clear
about this.
The secondary buffer size - wherever, the B to lock is that's how big
we, that's how far we had to go again, to go back to the diagram.
Basically.
I know this sounds complicated and there's tons of finicky math in
here, but not really it's arithmetic.
Really basically, what I'm saying is, we've got two cases.
In fact, let me go ahead and clear that out so I can show the two
cases.
So basically we have case 1 and case.
To and we got to handle both of them.
So in one case this is this is our right.
This is our B to right here, right?
And here was the play cursor.
This is this is B to write not the right cursor.
The right cursor, somewhere in here, but we're ignoring the right
cursor.
We don't even care where it is.
So what I'm saying is if this is our B to, right?
And we see that the play cursor is here, then we know that it's safe
to fill this part of the buffer and this part of the buffer and this
is the region.
We don't want to touch because at basically anywhere in here, we don't
want to touch because we
Ready wrote it in the play cursor, still playing.
Still hasn't played that part yet, if that makes sense.
So based on what we're going to do is we're going to look at this and
we're going to say, okay, if the bite to write basically is is greater
than the play cursor, right?
If it's greater than it, then we need to do to chunks that chunk.
And this Chunk on the other hand, if the opposite was true, if here's
the B to write this is the arbeit to, right?
And this is our play cursor.
Then we only have one Chunk.
We only have this chunk here, right?
This is case 2.
So if case one case two,
That makes some sense.
That is what I'm trying to, right here.
So basically, this is the case, this is that case one at the top when
B to right.
Sorry, B to lock is above the play cursor.
Basically, what we need to do is we need to take the secondary buffer
size.
So the total buffer size, which is, you know, this whole thing here.
We're taking that total buffer size and we're subtracting this value
from it.
So that we're just producing that number right there, right?
And then we also need to add the, the plate, the part that part the
beginning of the buffer.
So we're basically to add
That play cursor was because we got to play from zero to that, right?
Make some sense on the other hand, if they're the other way around,
then we just have a very simple thing to do, which is say, however,
far is between those two cursors is how much we're going to write that
is how much we're going to write.
So that we go in here.
We do the lock, we do the lock with that fights to write.
And then what we do is we basically say, okay our Square wave, counter
is still in effect, but actually, I guess like I said we
Get rid of that with a mod.
I'll show you how to do that in one second.
I'll get this basically this is all about modding.
Maybe we should have a little discussion about modding in the Q&A
since we never really covered modding.
We'll talk about it.
A little more detail.
It's kind of something.
That's interesting.
No.
So basically we are going to go in here and we are going to do two
regions thing like that.
Like we wanted to.
There we go, and we will be writing our stuff as we wanted to.
And then, so, the only thing we have to do is change our sample value
to basically be this if statement, instead is just going to be on our
We're wave period, our sample are running sample.
Count our sample index rather, mod the square wave period.
Should basically be what we want to do.
Is that correct?
No, sorry / the square wave period divided by 2.
Yeah man.
This is, this is a little nuts, but I think that's it, if the running
sample index, / half the period, that's either going to be 0 or 1.
So we got
Ahmad that.
Yeah, that's that's a little.
That's a little annoying.
So I'm going to make a secondary rail for that and then I'll explain
it assuming that I did it right half.
We want the half Square wave period, a square wave period equals
square root 3 divided by 2.
There we go.
And so all I'm trying to do here is basically just say.
So if we have the, the devised that we divide this out by half the
square root period, Then basically, what we're going to get is which
half period, we're on, right?
Basically, if I have a sample index and it's going up, I divide it.
Half the period.
We're going to say.
It's going to be 0 in the first half, period, one in the next one,
then two in the next one, then three in the next one.
So basically if you imagine what I'm doing with that divide, if this
is R square wave, right?
Basically you can imagine what I'm doing is dividing by half the
period.
This is half the period, right?
This is half period here and dividing by that.
So the Pacey what that'll give me back is just an integer that counts
up, which for which half period?
I mean, they'll go 0 1, 2 3,
4 5, 6 and so on, right?
So all I have to then do is look, if the number is even right, if the
number is even, we should be high.
If it's negative.
You should be low or vice versa.
We don't care which, which phase are thing is.
So, basically, what I got to do there is I got a mod it by 2.
I gotta take the mod 2, which says basically 0 or 1.
Whatever the remainder is when you divide by 2.
That is the thing that's going to be at its this is actually just goes
back in there.
So that's what I'm trying to do here.
There you go.
And there that should be just about
The buffer size.
Again.
We got to actually put in here because that's used now.
Secondary, buffer size.
And we already again, compute that right there, secondary, buffer
size, and you'll notice that a lot of these things, kind of work
themselves out.
Again.
This is why I always say compression oriented programming is the best
way to do things.
You'll note that basically all I do when I'm trying to write code,
that's somewhat complicated like this, and that sort of finicky is, I
just keep writing, whatever.
The most obvious thing is to write at the
I don't try to overthink it and then the patterns just kind of emerge.
You can see everything here.
If I could even see where we're going to go with this eventually, you
can see how these two Loops are the same.
So we'll probably boil that down and so on.
And basically you just keep pulling stuff out.
That's common.
That is the best way to end up with nice working code that does
exactly what you want to do.
Is set a try to front load it.
Okay.
I got to blow my nose here people.
I am I have awfully sick today.
I apologize, man.
I would like to spare you from that on the stream, but there's really
not much I can do about it.
That's just the way it goes.
Hmm.
It's awful.
It is awful.
All right, let's see here.
I think we've basically done everything but let's just do a quick spot
check because there are probably some bugs in this given.
How many things happened here?
Let's just do a quick once-over.
Just, we understand everything that we're trying to do and then we'll
go debug it.
So, basically, we basically made our hurts here.
I'm going to call this our tone hurts because it's basically saying
art own samples per second.
However, in the screen that says gross, it is totally true.
It's awfully gross.
I have to live with it.
I have to live with it man.
That is the thing.
I've been living with this for like a week.
It's awful.
The cautionary tale, do not get sick people.
That is what I'm telling you do not get sick.
I'm hoping maybe I'll feel sorry feeling better later today or
tomorrow.
It's been a long time.
All right.
Anyway, this is our sound stuff here.
This is just, this was for our Graphics test.
And this is for our sound test.
They are not similar at all.
Okay, now test.
So we have our samples per second.
That's 48 kilohertz.
That's how many were playing.
We have our tone hurts and that's tones per that.
You know, this is, this is per second as well.
We might want to call this sample hurts, but I don't know.
It's six of one half-dozen.
The other, Our Town hurts is basically 256.
So, we are saying it, taking our samples per second and dividing that,
by the tone hurts.
That's how many we want.
We have a half Square wave period which is going to be whatever that
period is divided by 2, and that's because we want to know ups and
downs, so we want to build / that we have our B per sample.
Which basically tells us how many bytes we take two right.
One left, right?
Pair each at 16 bits.
That's times to 16 bits.
We have a secondary buffer size, which is however make samples per
second times, the B % sample because we know we have a 1, second
buffer.
That's basically what we Define it to be.
So we in it, direct sound with that and that should be basically
everything that we needed there.
I'm going to double check the win32 in its D sound function to make
sure that that is
Takes a second and buffer size.
That's good that that all works.
All right.
So we then come in here and now we actually do all the craziness.
We ask where the play curse in the right cursor is even though we
don't actually care where the right cursor is.
So we asked for the play cursor is essentially and let's make sure we
have those in the right order.
Yep.
Play Chris.
Our first.
So that's good.
We then get the bite to lock by taking however, many samples.
We are in, there's the thing we forgot.
I knew we forgot something.
Plus running Sam.
Index, you gotta add that every time through.
So we take our running sample index.
We multiply that, by the B 4 sample, the basically get where we are in
in the running B.
So basically an infinitely increasing until we wrap the actual value,
the actual variable and an infant increasing value of B.
So then we use the mod to map that into the secondary buffer where we
are in the actual bummer.
Cause remember it's kind of the circular buffer thing.
So we need to take this long linear thing and wrap it into an actual
buffer.
We
And say if the bite to lock was after the play cursor, then we take
two pieces.
We're basically going to do two lakhs of risk, and have to fill two
regions.
We're going to fill the secondary buffer size - the B to lock, and
then we're going to fill the play cursors worth from the beginning to
play coaster with.
Otherwise, we just feel that the distance in between them.
That seems totally reasonable.
We then go through here and we asked to lock exactly that.
So we should get back in case one will get up five minute warning,
almost there.
We should get back either.
The two chunks in this case or the one Chunk in this other case,
assuming that we do get them back.
We then go ahead and we figure out what the region sample counts.
Are.
We point to the first region here.
Let's do it this way.
Just to make that a little clearer, we point to the, to the
First region, we find out how many bytes how many samples were got the
feel for that one.
We go ahead here and we actually Loop through all of those samples.
We add to the running sample index each time.
In fact, we could even stick that right in there.
Make that a little clearer that that's only getting used just in that
one place.
There we go.
We write out both a left and right value.
They are exactly the same.
So that's good.
We go ahead and do the divided by the half Square wave period.
Check the mod with two.
And that looks pretty good.
So I don't know.
We could try to run this and I have no idea what will happen, but we
can certainly try to run it.
So let's take a look here and see.
Okay.
Oh, well, there is one more thing we have to do.
Before we can test it, that may have worked just fine.
We have to actually start the sound playing.
So that's one thing that because we never actually told the buffer, we
fill were filling the buffer, but we never actually played the sound.
So we will actually have to also do this one more thing here, which is
to actually start the buffer playing.
So we're going to go ahead and start the buffer playing and we can
basically do that at any time.
Normally we'd want to fill the buffer first before we start playing
it.
But for testing
Let's just go ahead and do it right here.
But later we'll kind of have to see maybe how to do that a little bit
better.
So Reserve we have to pass zero because all right.
I don't know why there's some reserved value.
You pass.
First the priority.
I don't think we care about that at all.
Basically, we don't we don't care about priority because we are only
playing one sound.
That is only for playing lots of sound and letting letting it mix them
or something like this.
I don't think we care about that at all.
We are going to Loop this buffer.
We want it to basically play forever.
So we're going to Loop it.
Is there any other flags that we need?
Let's see.
We don't care about that.
We don't care about any of that.
So I think we're pretty much good to go.
We will just go ahead and start that sound playing secondary, buffer,
Global secondary, buffer.
There we go, and let's see here.
Do we, wow, well, the square wave Works.
Ladies and gentlemen, that much was clear.
That was extremely loud in my ear.
I think we're going to go ahead and and maybe I don't know if I should
turn down my sound here, or if I should just go ahead and make this.
Let's make the volume of parameter.
Holy cow.
That was that was a little, a little jarring.
I don't know how loud it was for the folks at home.
But if for
It was a bit bit loud.
The good news is, it does sound like it worked?
Although, who knows we could have still have some bugs in there.
But the basic basic thing seemed to work.
I'm going to go ahead and set that to be a little bit lower.
That's where wave was Extremely Loud.
Let's just say, maybe maybe 6,000 something like that.
That seems a little bit easier on the ears.
So that does not sound quite right to me.
I think we still have a bug in there.
I can basically hear a clicking over.
Let me double check that I actually put out the tone volume correctly.
Yeah, there we go.
Let's see here.
Let me make that.
Just even a little bit quieter, still just to not blow out your drums
at all.
That is still awful loud.
I do not know.
I wonder if we have a bug that, that that is, that is actually causing
it to be louder than it should be.
That's an interesting question as well.
All right.
Well, anyway, I think we've got a bug here.
So I think mmmm.
What should we do?
I think we only have a minute left.
So I think basically what we're going to do is we're basically going
to mark this as buggy and we're going to debug it tomorrow.
Because that I think is the sanest thing to actually do would be my
would be, my guess.
What is the stream saying?
What about unlocking?
The buffer?
Yes.
That's right.
We forgot that as well.
Duh.
It's hard to remember everything when you're on the street in waves
and John and unlocking, the buffer.
We do need to do that.
I think all we pass.
Yeah, we just passed exactly what we pass before.
So maybe that is the only problem I doubt it, but I think we've got
another problem as well.
But if we
Were lucky.
It could be that it was just that we weren't unlocking the buffer and
direct sound was getting confused.
But I don't think that's it.
I think that that was definitely a bug as well.
So we definitely want to do that.
It's just, I don't think that's our only problem.
Okay.
There we go.
Well, now that actually does sound right.
All right, that's good.
We made that may have just been all.
We just what I said, we have to unlock the buffer and then didn't
unlock the buffer that may have been one of our only problems.
I don't actually know.
I'm going to say more strenuous test.
Here.
We should probably look at that buffer verify that it looks like what
we think it should look like, things like that.
But for now, it does look like we were basically able to make it to
make it actually work properly.
I think on the stream Steel.
I'm says create a new variable but then didn't set anything equal to
it.
I'm not sure what you mean by that.
I probably just dropped one in here and then didn't actually use it.
I guess.
I'm not sure where you're talking about.
But I guess we're going to go into the Q&A here.
So in a second, so maybe we can talk about that.
All right, that was actually pretty productive.
We actually have sound output.
Now.
This is basically all.
I mean, like I said, I want to test this a little more to make sure
sound is very finicky and you want to make sure you're doing
everything just so but
Actually, we've got the essentials down for actually, outputting sound
through direct sound.
This would allow us to Output, basically, anything that we wanted to
Output effectively.
We could, we could just go ahead and and output music right now.
If we wanted to, we could write a wave, you know, from a WAV file into
here and we would get full sound output.
So we have basically done everything that we need for our our sound
output.
Where is
Let's see here.
It's still super loud.
Compared to voice on the street.
Yeah, we should actually.
Now that we actually have sound, I need to go in there and adjust the
sound volume on stream will do.
That will definitely do that so that I can talk over it as necessary,
sound volume on stream.
So, that'll be good, tone volume.
Let's see.
Your steel Golem in 16.
Total volume equals.
4,000 this?
You're talking about this thing.
I don't know.
Tone volume gets used, right.
There.
It is.
It's up to 3,000 and then it gets used right here.
That's, that's what I thought.
It was supposed to be.
Yeah, there you go.
So anyway, that is the end of todays.
Handmade hero.
We will now be taking questions for 30 minutes while we.
I guess I will be taking questions.
There's no one else here to answer them.
You will be asking questions and I'll be taking them.
So we will be doing questions.
But I do know.
It's pretty productive.
That is some very finicky code to write doing the circular buffer
stuff.
I would love to go over it here in the Q&A.
Maybe we'll take a few minutes just to kind of talk about this a
little bit more detail because I kind of had to back, you know,
through it as we kind of wrote out the code and go.
Okay.
I think I'm gonna do it like this.
I'm going to do it like that.
The other thing I'm going to do here is going to say to do collapse.
These two Loops like because they're the same.
That should be pretty easy to do too next time.
So basically, yeah, we'll go ahead and do Q&A here, but for a minute,
I just want to kind of go through and just really reinforced kind of
what happened here.
That especially this this part may be right here, which we didn't
cover in too much detail.
Let me just draw, one more diagram for you.
Now that we actually have the diagrams working for some definition of
working.
I don't want to say it to strength strenuously.
So basically what we want to do right is we want to Output this wave,
right?
This is what I
I was trying to Output just a basic whole Square wave, but you can
imagine that this is going to get more complicated over time because
we're basically going to Output real waves to it.
And so basically, this this exact code is Zach, what we're going to do
to Output the music for the game, and the sounds for the game.
It's all the same.
We're just going to be putting a different way.
Instead of a square wave, going to be outputting basically the output
of our mixer, which is basically to take wav files, bring them
together and mix them together and then eventually compressed some
kind of compressed sound format, but that's much later.
Okay.
So basically if you if you imagine we're trying to
Put this, but then we've got a buffer.
Let's say this right here.
Let's say this is, you know, five seconds long, right?
It's five seconds long, but we have a buffer and our buffer, right is
only one second long, right?
So, basically, we have to fit this into this and that's obviously not
possible.
So what we're doing is we're essentially mapping.
We're going to start direct sound playing this buffer, and what we're
doing is, were essentially mapping this sound right.
The first chunk Maps directly to the buffer.
When we write it, so we write that in there, but then we have to wait
and as direct sound plays more of it like as the bricks and gets to
here.
Let's say we kind of come through, we lock the buffer and what you
know, it's got still some of the square wave in here.
It got in it ends right there.
So it's actually well.
I guess we should actually end.
I should try to draw that actually like it actually looks might be a
little clearer.
Let's try that.
So basically, if you imagine, right, it has copied this part in there
and playing that part.
Still, we now want to keep playing at this part, but we're at the end
of the buffer.
So when we have room at the beginning, when directsound finishes
playing out of this part and it's done with it, we are going to copy
this part, right?
We're going to put that in here so that the sound continues right?
Does that make sense?
So basically what we're doing is we're just mapping parts of this.
We're copying them into the right places in the buffer.
That were essentially mapping a long linear thing into a rolling
circular Thing by just putting in however, much right behind as direct
sound reads it.
We're just putting in new stuff behind there.
So, that as it as it comes back around again, it gets the new stuff.
So the mod operator, which is mod or you know, you can think of it as
taking the remainder, right?
The reason that I wanted to do that is because basically if we divide
some point, if we have some place,
Right in here.
Let's say an arbitrary point in here and we divide it by the size of
this buffer.
Right?
What we will get is the
Remainder of of that division, right?
And the division, the whole number part of the division, right?
You know, if we do that division you imagine you do that Division and
you're going to get back.
The whole number part is going to be 0 1, 2 3, depending on how many
full buffer lengths you were in.
So if you are one full buffer length in the whole part, the whole
number part of the division would be 1, right?
But the remainder part of the integer division will be how many
It's in.
You were in that region in that in that whole number region, which is
exactly what we want.
The mod gives us where we are relative to some whole number region
that is defined by the terms of the mod.
So, if we do basically, you know, some Index, this is our index.
If we do an index mod the size right, then what that gives us back is
it gives us a relative index.
It's
See, a thing that turns an absolute Index.
This is an absolute index into a relative index and that's what we
wanted.
So, hopefully, that makes some sense and, and you can understand
what's going on with that mod.
Now the mod showed up again, and it was used in exactly the same way.
Basically, we had Hoops.
That's no good.
Always resets me to being the selection rectangle.
When I clear everything, which I didn't want, anyway, basically, the
other thing that I wanted to do that, I use the mod for is, you can
remember I did this.
This, right?
And I said, I want to know whether to Output this value.
Like I wanted to know whether op out the positive value.
This again, is the zero Line running through here or if I wanted to do
the negative value.
Which one did I want to do, right?
Positive or negative tone.
And so basically what I did there is, I said, well, okay, whatever our
period is, whatever our frequency is that we want to Output.
I think we call that 256 Hertz, basically, whatever our number of
samples is here.
We basically computed using 256 Hertz.
We computed the samples basically / whole oscillation, right?
And then I said, well, let's take the half of that.
We took a half of that.
Right?
Well the half of that again, just does that same.
Relative thing.
Basically, what we're doing is we're saying where are we in terms of
half periods.
So basically an absolute sample index.
A sample Index, right, modded by the half period, is going to give us
a whole number, which corresponds, to which one of these buckets,
we're actually in, right?
So what I wanted to do of sorry about that,
/.
So the sampling is divided by the half.
Period, gives me the whole number.
I didn't want the mod yet.
I just wanted that, right.
It's the opposite of the other thing.
We did in the in the previous one, where we just wanted the remainder
here.
We actually want the whole numbers, 0 1, 2 3 4.
So as this goes up.
We basically just have a number that counts up.
That tells us which half period were in.
So what the mod then does mod to basically, just says, well, what's
the remainder when this is divided by 2.
Well the remainder when divided by 2, you know, 0 / 2, right is going
to give us 0.
1 divided by 2 is going to give us 0 2, divided by 2, right is going
to give us 1 and so on, right?
That's how that's going to work and the remainder of that.
Division is what we will get when we asked the mod.
So what's the remainder?
When we do 0, you know, when we do this, it's going to be zero.
What's the remainder when we do 1 divided by 2.
Well, it's one.
What's the remainder here?
It's 0, right?
And that keeps going, and it basically just oscillates 01, 01, 01.
Now someone on the, on the chat said, could you just look at the Loeb
it?
And the answer is yes, and not only is it?
Yes, but that is exactly.
I believe what the optimizer would do here.
I don't actually know if
It's true because there may be some odd rules forces, not do that.
If this was performance critical code, you would probably write it
directly as.
And one, basically, to look at what that lobe.
It actually is if you actually care, but this is not, this is just
test code.
So we use mod because that's, that's the logical operation, you're
doing.
And I'd rather show you the logical operation.
But yes, and 1 and mod 2 are the same for these values.
Okay, hopefully, that's relatively clear.
What's going on?
And everyone sort of roughly follows that.
Now, we will go ahead and go to the question and answers.
Please, remember to prefix your question with at senior ettore so I
can see it.
Let's take a look.
Let's see.
Looks like I answered most of these do
Sorry, I just taking a second to scan through all the questions that
have already built up.
How will the schedule look in the future?
Will this amazingly Europe?
Friendly time being at place at other times?
Yes, every Friday at least will be Europe, friendly.
That is the goal.
Why don't we use x audio to because it does not support older
platforms.
That is why I want to make sure we actually run on Windows XP.
Not because I think you need to run on Windows XP.
I think it's down to like less than 10% of all computers right now.
So I'm not not trying to push XP compatibility on anybody.
You probably can start with Windows Vista and just say Vista and up is
fine, which I don't, I don't know if x audio to even works on
business.
That might be actually a legitimate reason why you might not want to
use it2.
I'm not sure we're outside to Works necessarily, but
Basically what I want to make sure we do is on a default install of
Windows XP.
We should run.
And the reason I want to do that is to show you how to get used to
thinking about.
Installing and running properly without forcing the user, to go,
download 10 million drivers, and installing all these, all these
different things because you actually need to do most of that if you
just write your code sensibly, so it's just as an exercise room do
that.
So we're not using anything that wasn't on XP since direct Sound Works
totally fine.
Like, as you can see we got sound output.
We're pretty much done there.
Wasn't much to it.
There's really no reason to go use x audio, maybe you could get lower
latency with it.
I don't know what the, what the deal is with that stuff.
But honestly, there really isn't much reason to go.
He's like, so you're too.
It's just kind of a waste of time and makes you less.
Also, I don't actually really know that there's any reason to use it.
But if you want to use it, go right ahead.
I am using direct sun because I want to make sure we can do XP
compatibility as an exercise.
Are we going to factor sampling into a separate function?
It will actually be more than one function.
But yes.
Let's see here.
One mod 2 is 1 not 0.
That is what I wrote.
This is, this is the line.
I wrote I said 1 divided by 2 is 0 and the remainder is 1, that is
what I wrote here.
And that is correct.
This this is the mod Line.
This is the divided divided Line.
This is the result of the divides developed to the mod.
So these go up basically.
Right 3, divided by 2, is still going to be 14.
Divided by 2 is going to be 2.
So basically when you divide by
You go up every time you increment the thing you're dividing by you go
up.
Every other one.
You go up by 1.
So 0 0 1 1 2.
2 3 3 4 4, 5 5 and the mod oscillates.
0 1 0 1 0 1
Let's see.
Why don't I name the secondary buffer sound buffer, something.
I might in the future again.
It doesn't really matter that platform code is so going to be.
So tiny.
There's just not that much to it.
And it's just buried in the wind.
It'll just live in the winter to handmade file.
You don't really have to worry too much about it.
The platform, the bulk of the game, the entire D of the code, really
will never see any of those variables or know about them at all.
Is there a particular X audio to support our next week?
No, it is not.
That is not true.
You could you can install it possibly on XP but I'm talking about the
default.
Install of XP did not come with X audio to, I'm 99% sure of that.
So if you have a vanilla and salt of XP and you try to run your game
on it with X audio, it will not work.
You will have to force the user to install X audio drivers.
In order to get that to work.
I am.
Pretty positive of that if I'm wrong.
So I can correct me in email later and we'll catch up with you
tomorrow, but I'm pretty much positive that a vanilla installed of XP
know X audio too.
Is there a particular reason why we use the keyboard input events
instead of pulling?
No, there isn't a particular reason other than the fact that the
keyboard events are going to be.
We're not going to miss anything.
If we pull the keyboard, we might miss a keyboard event.
Whereas if we just use the keyboard events.
We know that the operating system already got as many as it possibly
could because it's what its are already pulling the keyboard itself
internally and getting that stuff, as far as I know.
And so I think we pretty much want to just use the events because
they're going to be more accurate than pulling.
Will we be able to remap the keys over the GUI or config file?
Maybe it depends.
I don't love remappable keys.
I don't love them.
We might we will definitely support multiple key layouts though.
At least 44, people in France.
Whose wasd keys are different.
If I understand correctly, a larger primary, buffer means a longer
latency between writing sound to the buffer and actually being heard.
No, that is not true.
So the size of the primary effort, has nothing to do with the latency.
And the reason for that is because we're writing into the buffer
wherever we want.
So basically let's go over the diagram one more time.
Just so we're clear on.
What's Happening Here If this is and primary buffers.
The wrong thing to say necessarily.
Oh, okay.
Well actually maybe that's all right.
So when you say size of the primary buffer, we aren't setting the size
of the primary buffer, so did you mean secondary buffered?
You actually mean, setting the size of the primary buffer do you who
asked that question?
It's hard for me to keep track of things on.
Okay, to n.
3053.
Which buffer were you talking about?
Can you can you tell me which buffer you were talking about?
I'll ask some other questions.
If you could go ahead and tell me 2-inch 3053 which buffer you were
talking about specifically just clarify your question a little bit.
So I make sure I answer the right.
One will be writing filters like Reverb or what have you we could.
I rarely use stuff like that when I'm actually doing stuff.
I prefer to especially a 2-D game.
Doesn't make a whole lot of sense, but we could, we could write a
Reverb filter, just to show how it's done.
And I could even ask Jeff for some advice on that since he's probably
set, the person's work with those.
The most, if he has any
Words of wisdom.
Will we refactor the code in a separate files?
Of course?
Yes.
Let's see.
What causes the slight hiccup in the sound every couple seconds?
So I think I'm not actually getting that.
Let's see.
I'm not getting the hiccup.
Are you getting a hiccup?
We were having a hiccup because of the unlock.
We weren't calling unlocks.
We were just, we were just erroneously using it.
We were getting hiccups.
Oh, I don't actually know if there is a hiccup in there currently.
Like I said, we're going to test this a little bit.
Tomorrow, but I'm not sure.
Let's see.
It takes about a second for sound to start playing.
Is that expected acceptable?
Yeah.
Well, so basically, what's happening there is again, we're not
actually.
I could actually show you this a little bit more specifically.
So what we could do if we wanted to is, we could actually fill the
buffer first and then started playing, basically we could do something
more like this, right?
I'll just go ahead and show you.
So let's say we did a thing here that said,
Sound is playing equals false or something like this, right?
Are you know what?
I don't even need to do that.
I can just do this.
I'm going to just go ahead and get this part here.
I'm going to go ahead and extract this out into a separate function.
Basically.
Well, that'll all right.
That'll take too long for Q&A.
That's what we should do.
But I'm going to go.
I'll go, I'll do the original thing first.
So let's say I do sound is playing here equals false, then I come
through here and I actually do
Do this sound play anything after the first time?
So if not sound is playing, then we play it sounds.
Playing was true.
So we start out false like that.
So we start out without the sour playing and then I'm going to go in
here and I'm going to take quick look at what we get back and what we
fill.
So let's go through here due to do.
So, let's see here.
We get back.
What is our play cursor?
Wait, cursor is 0.
We are going to look at how many bytes to write.
How many bytes to write is zero as well.
Oh, so this is because they are equal to each other.
That looks like a bit of a bug.
It should never actually happen in practice.
But in the case where they are equal, they're both 0 and 0.
Or if it happens to have in that particular sense.
That means We've Ended up in basically yet.
So, so what I think we should do here.
Just to handle the case where things have gone pear-shaped as they say
in the UK.
I believe we should probably handle the case where they're equal.
They should never be equal and or because we're always supposed to be
writing ahead of things.
But in when we first start up, they will both be zero.
So we'll say that the B to write is the whole buffer basically, but in
the case of that act, they should actually collapse down in a bad
situation in the actual game.
We probably would want to handle something like that as well.
So let's take a look at what happens here when we come through first
time through.
Are both equal.
So we fill the whole buffer.
That is what we wanted and then we start the sound playing.
Okay, so in theory,
That should be.
Not a very good sound.
I will say that.
So I suspect we still have some bugs in the thing.
Like I said, I don't want to bug it now because I want to show how to
actually go through and debug it because I think we still have some
In here in terms of how we're filling.
But as you can see, the sound, now starts basically instantaneously,
if that makes sense.
And the reason for that was just that what we were doing first is we
were starting to sound playing before we actually filled any of it.
And so basically what happens there is we would be writing into
essentially the wrong place.
Like we have to fill, we have to wait till it kind of loops around
again before.
We would actually be playing it.
It's got this kind of gap between the play cursor and the right curse.
Sir, sir, and we're we're writing that, that that problem essentially
will cause it so that we're going to have dead time when initially
starts up.
So, yeah, if we fill the buffer first, then start playing, and then
always sure that we're running ahead of it.
That is how to make the sound, start immediately.
But like I said, I think we still got a bug in here, so I wouldn't
worry too much about this yet.
Don't play with this to extensively, unless you want to start
debugging yourself because I think we still have a bug in here.
In terms of where we're filling.
One of the things that's always been true for me when writing the
circular bar codes.
I always write it wrong.
The first time.
I'm because there's so many things that play in so many different
offsets and do you use the sample indexes of the regulate?
There's, it's just very finicky.
And so you what you want to do is you actually want to go and be very
certain check everything.
And actually, if you can like, draw it out and verify, like, okay,
we're actually writing to where we think we're writing.
We're doing the right thing everywhere.
That's very important and we haven't done that yet.
So I think we probably have some bugs in here as well.
And I think if we were to use a sine wave, we probably would see that
as well?
We would hear it more distinctly.
So I think this is probably buggy.
So let's just say that.
It's buggy.
I don't want to go into it till tomorrow.
Yes, okay.
We will do a sine wave tomorrow as well.
That I didn't want to talk about floating Point yet and you do need to
do that, but wait, maybe tomorrow will be our time that we introduced
that.
So we'll just say switch to a sine wave.
Let's see.
To do.
What is acceptable latency for games?
How far in advance of the read pointer should be right?
That is a very good question.
And the answer is, it depends?
It's very difficult to actually figure out on some platforms.
Like, on Mac, you can do it exactly because they will tell you when
your video frames will actually be displayed out the HDMI port, you
know, or whatever.
So you can actually make sure that your audio is hard synced, but on
windows at least on Windows XP.
I don't know if they've actually
We finally fixed this in Windows 7 or 8.
I don't think it was fixed as of 7.
So maybe an 8 I don't really know.
Excuse me.
Wow, I'm dying here people.
All right.
Basically.
On Windows, you have this kind of slop in terms of audio sync.
That's really confusing.
And I hate it.
I really wish that they hadn't had this, that they had done it right
in direct sound originally, but they didn't.
So look, maybe maybe like with X audio to like you were saying.
I haven't looked at that myself, but maybe with, like, newer audio
apis or something you can do, but in the old days, there wasn't very
much you could do.
Basically, what happens is if you can imagine this is
Let's, let's let's clear this out here.
So you just know I'm not referring to the old buffer.
But basically this is time.
Okay?
Time is on the axis here.
The access time is running forwards, its inescapable entropy ladies
and gentlemen.
Anyway, time is going forwards and you have to imagine basically like
here's the startup of the game, right?
This we get called and then we have a bunch of startup code to do.
So, there's work here that gets done, right?
And there's nothing you can do about that.
We're looking digitalizing some stuff.
We're
Direct sound and direct input or do you know, who knows what else
we're opening?
We're getting stuff.
Set up.
At some point we start to work on the first frame, right?
So in here, this is the work for frame one, right?
We're actually doing the work for frame 1.
So this is our us doing work and that work.
Involves outputting two things.
It involves outputting the sound.
And it outputs and the picture.
That's what we need to do.
So we need to sound in the picture, right?
So we are then going to tell Windows to play the sound that we
outputted and show the picture that we outputted.
Right?
But the problem is, even if we're doing this on some regular
granularity.
Like, let's say, this right here is 1/60 of a second, right?
We can try and sometimes succeed to get Windows to display the picture
right here at the 60th of a second boundary.
And then here's another 60th of a second.
Here's another sixtieth of a second and we want to keep that locked
frame rate.
Let's say so, we might be able to buy if the vertical retrace we can
use what's called a v blank potentially to possibly have Windows show
the new frame here.
So that the person is looking at the frame here is for this duration.
So, this is picture 0, right?
And we were producing picture 0 here.
Now sound 0 is a chunk of sound that ideally would go right here.
Right, that's where we actually want it.
We want our sound that we outputted to perfectly coincide with the
picture.
And then when we generate, you know, sometime after this, we're going
to start working on sound one and picture 1 instead of 0, right?
And those we want Windows to show here, right?
Whoops.
There's the 60th of a second boundary.
So we want picture one here and we want sound one to go here, right?
But the problem is, we don't really have any way of telling Windows to
place the sound buffer, so that it perfectly coincides with when the
picture flips, right?
That is the problem.
So, we don't really know where this is.
So your question of how much latency should we have?
Well, the answer is, we actually ideally would have exactly the right
latency such that.
Whenever we wrote to the Sound by for, let's say the right occurred
right here.
Here.
The latency would be, however, long it was in between that right and
when it when the picture shows up, that's the latency we want, right?
But there's no way to get that Encore audio.
Like I said, there is a way to get that.
There's actually ways you can I think get called back with specific
things that would allow you to do that sink, but I don't think there
is on, certainly not an XP.
I don't think even on Windows 7 maybe on a I don't really know, I
could be wrong about that.
But basically the
Certainly going through direct sound is nothing.
You can do.
So you just kind of have to estimate it.
That's why I games often today.
I think ship with those weird latency estimators because you've got
that problem.
Like, if you use Guitar Hero, they got those latent estimates, you got
that problem, and then you even got another problem, which is even if
you got all of this, correct, you have yet another problem, which is
your HDTV piece of piece of well, pile of poo.
Let's say right your HDTV, which is not fabulous, is like that could.
But
Buffer frames as well.
There may be a delay in the even when they go out the wire and
furthermore.
You may have some audio receiver.
That's also introducing delay or who, knows what?
So basically this stuff goes out to here and potentially gets further
delayed differently.
Depending on if the audio is going through a separate path, then the
TV or what's going on.
It's, it's a nightmare.
So, actually the saying how much latency you
Quote unquote is really a it's bad.
I have been complaining about this for about a decade.
I have been complaining about this and I have told everyone who ever
had an ear to listen, that they need to fix this stuff.
And what should actually happen is basically the opengl driver.
What I, what I actually want, we'll just a little bit of tangent here.
The opengl driver should just take a sound sound buffers and the sound
buffer should just go out with the frames.
And then it should just be mandatory.
There should be some seal.
There should be like a little seal that comes on your TV.
There should be like this little seal.
Right like this, that comes on the TV that says, you know, not crappy.
Right or basically like maybe it's maybe it's basically a thing that
says poop sauce like this with a little line through it.
So you get a thing on your television that says no poop sauce, and
then you
That whoever made that TV had it certified that they don't delay
anything they played.
Exactly.
And that way, you would know that your buffers in your frames, always
went out exactly together and then they were actually displayed by
your HDTV it and put out through the speaker's of the HDTV at the sack
same time.
So you at least know for gamers who buy an HDTV or a monitor that has
audio out if it had the no poop.
So sauce logo on it, that you would actually get no poop sauce, and I
don't actually understand why this.
Isn't done.
I feel like someone should do it.
I feel like Gamers would want this.
I feel like the types of people who go out and spend five thousand
dollars on a gaming rig.
The last thing they want is to have this sort of like worse, you know,
they don't want these sort of bad correlations and and having their
sound not be perfectly synced to their game.
That's ridiculous.
So I would think everyone would want to get the no poop sauce logo for
a serious gaming rig.
I mean, it just seems to me like it would be a no-brainer and I feel
like that's a value-add if your
Selling products.
I feel like the no poops lost logo would be really important.
So I don't know.
I have advocated this for many years, the industry, nobody cared.
And so the answer to how much latency you want, is nobody knows, it's
completely unknown and it's so unknown even that even on an operating
system that does it correctly, like a Mac OS 10.
You still don't know because the thing that you output to has latency
that you don't that you can't predict.
So even if you get it so that your HDMI
Put is perfectly synced on the wire.
It doesn't matter.
Let's see here.
So I think we are done for the day.
That's the end of the Q&A.
Like I said, if you did have a question, I'm sorry.
If I didn't get to it, we will be debugging the sound tomorrow.
And so when we debug the sound tomorrow, you can just hold those
questions.
They'll be same time tomorrow.
11:00 a.m.
Ask the question in the Q&A tomorrow and we will go over because we're
going to be debugging sound tomorrow as well.
So, I apologize for not getting some of the questions.
We had to get to the no poop sauce logo.
That was pretty important question to answer.
So, ladies and gentlemen.
Thank you so much for
Joining me here on handmade hero.
Obviously, if you want to continue discussion, you can go to handmade
hero dot, o-- r-- g--.
If you want a copy of the source code, you can always pre-order the
game.
It comes with a nightly build updates.
You can go get the source code.
In this case.
It will be an afternoon build up that I will push the new source right
now after we're done and you can also email me a question.
This will be turning.
Hopefully today.
I'm really hoping if I don't basically fall asleep because of this
cold.
I'm hoping to have the forums up and running to this will email
Question link will turn into a link to the forums where you can ask
questions and discuss things with the community.
So watch for that, hopefully by tomorrow.
If not later today, so hopefully that should be up soon.
Thank you so much for joining us for another episode of handmade hero,
11 a.m.
Tomorrow again.
So I hope to see you all here again tomorrow, including the folks from
Europe who were able to join us.
Thank you so much.
Sorry.
We can't always be at a friendly time.
But Friday's from now on will be your friendly as well.
So, thank you so much for joining us and I will see you.
Tomorrow.