Clean one from to upload to Youtube and there we go.
All right, welcome everybody to what is day 16.
You didn't think we would make it to such a high power of 2, but we
did day 16 of handmade hero the show where we actually code an entire
professional color, quality game from scratch.
So that we can basically explore all of the intricacies of what a
computer does when it runs a game so that we, we can basically see and
Stand everything that is going on.
So we don't use any libraries and we try to kind of get down is as
detail-oriented as we can to try and basically tease out all of that
stuff.
That's kind of obscured when you when you lose higher level stuff.
And so so far we have done the win32 side of things where you just
made ourselves, basically an interface to Windows that allows us to do
the sorts of things we need to do in a game and we're almost to the
part we're going to actually start building the game.
Proper, we're going to do this week is basically transition between
those two.
And so, in order to do that, what we need to do is go through our
win32 code and clean up any of the stuff that we haven't finished yet.
Just touch things up.
Put, you know, go through any of stuff that we don't have time to do.
There's just some loose ends that were left hanging when we wrote
everything.
And so that's really what's going to be our Focus today is going
through and making sure we we kind of like get that done and we'll do
that for the next couple days until we're satisfied that everything is
in good shape and then we can move on to just game code proper.
Now, for those of you who have pre-ordered the game from
I made here at dot org.
If you are following along with the source code at home, that it comes
with you want to unzip day 15 because that is the source code that I
am starting with.
So if you want to follow along on zip day 15 from the pre-order and
that will, that will be where we are starting?
All right.
So let me go ahead and jump in here.
The first thing to me.
Yeah.
It's been a long cold.
Winter here for me, as you know, and every stream.
I'm coughing.
Just a little bit getting
But what can you do?
It's definitely going to be one of those Winters where I'm sick all
the time.
But you know what?
Sickness doesn't really have to stop me programming.
Most of the time.
Thankfully, I have not been that sick yet.
So hopefully things will continue where I can stream with just a
little bit of coughing anyway, so one of the big things that I said we
were going to do and which we hadn't done yet, but I'd like to start
doing now as we sort of move forwards.
Is one of the things that we're doing in our build script.
Here is, we are just compiling with no real warnings turned on, like,
we
We only have the barest minimum warnings turned on and warnings are
basically things that the compiler doesn't actually need you to fix.
It doesn't need you to fix warnings.
It can still generate the code just fine, but it does tend to indicate
that there might be something wrong.
So warning is the compilers way of telling you.
Hey, I'm not sure about this.
It looks like something that might be suspicious.
Could you check it out?
And that is basically what a warning is.
And so one of the things that I want to do is I want to turn on
warnings in are compiled basically.
On a higher level of warnings, warnings are typically grouped into
levels level 1 level 2, level 3, level 4 and so on such that you can
enable them in waves and they're sort of categorized.
So, if you want to enable like each individual warning, so typically
what you'll do is you enable a certain level of warning that you're
comfortable with, in this case, probably going to use worrying level
three and you're going to enable that warning level.
And then you're going to disable any warnings that you didn't want
from that warning level.
That's a lot easier than picking each individual, warning and turning
it on.
And now what will happen, you can see if we actually turn on basically
all the warnings, right?
If I do - W all, we get some pretty immediate problems, some of which
we can fix and some of which we couldn't fix.
So, for example, you can see in here.
It's going to warn us about some things that maybe we did want to know
about.
Like, for example, it's telling us that there's going to be padding
inserted here, because this is a 32-bit value, and this is a 64-bit
value.
Now, that's a warning.
I wouldn't mind seeing whirring 4820, that's, that's can be useful.
Educational for me.
In case I forgot that when I wrote the struct, right?
It's kind of just nice to know doesn't mean you have to fix it.
But it does mean that just nice.
A nice thing to know.
But as you can see, when we get down into these other warnings here,
there's just a stream of them that are all in Windows, .h there in
Windows is header files, right justjust reams of warnings and windows
header files.
So there's not a lot that we could really do about that short of
getting rid of Windows dot h, which could be something that we might
want to do.
Like I've talked about in the future.
ER I don't know that we're going to do it this week, but we might do
in the future so we could get rid of that.
But the say nothing to do potentially will just be to switch down to a
warning level that can, you know, sort of successfully.
Go ahead and compile the windows header files just to keep that out of
the out of the equation for now.
So what I did is I drop down to warning level 3, warning, level 3 has
really no problem.
I don't know if warning level for, I don't think warning level for
can.
Oh, so warning level for can compile them as well.
It's just not if you turn on all of them so we could consider turning
on water level.
Or as well.
Three and four will both work.
Just not all, which is, I guess above for, if you think about it, so,
hmm, apple is done.
Getting all those vitamins.
I don't know if Apple temp vitamins, maybe apples have vitamins hard
to say, anyway.
Couldn't leave that one piece lying.
There was too hard to do.
So, moving along basically, what we can do is we can now look at the
warnings that we do have in our code and the ones that we agree with,
we can basically fix whatever it was, that was causing the warning and
the ones that we think are just annoying.
We can turn off so we can basically decide at this point what warnings
we want and what warnings we think are busy work.
That the compiler is just telling us to do that.
We don't want to do.
Now, another thing we can do.
And I'll do that first.
Is you'll notice that if I compile this here, basically, the compiled
succeeded just fine because warnings do not stop the compile.
But what you can do, I believe it's minus WX as well.
Another command-line switch you can do.
I
You can do.
Yeah.
WX, if you pass WX, it will basically treat warnings as errors.
So it's basically the same as saying, like, Okay, warnings, just our
errors are things.
I'm going to either, I'm either going to turn the warning off.
If I think that it's an erroneous kind of warning or I'm going to fix
it, but I don't ever want you to actually let me compile this file
into an executable, if there's warnings in there, and I think I want
to do that as well, because we're going to be basically keeping our
warning set to just warnings that we consider useful and important.
We're going.
Turn off ones that we think are frivolous.
So at that point, it doesn't really make sense to ever allow them to
be in there.
We should just never have any warnings because if there were ones that
we really thought were frivolous and unimportant we would have turned
them off.
So that's the way I'm going to treat it for now.
So I'm going to leave that WX in there.
So if we look here now, what we get is basically this guy right here
that I said, I want to use the nameless, the nameless structure.
This guy.
It doesn't love that guy because that's apparently something that it
doesn't think is a standard sort of extension.
These doesn't think
Standard way to to do that but I don't think that's actually a
problem.
I don't know any compilers where that actually causes a problem.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that that warning just does not
count.
We don't want that warning.
I want to be able to use that feature.
If those of you who are standards sticklers, you may want to look that
up before you do this and verify that you think it's okay.
Bye, you know, standards and that sort of stuff, but I don't care
because as long as all the compiler supported, I'm happy with to to
use that.
So what I can do is I can
I can pass - WD - WD.
Takes a warning number, right?
So I can pass warning 4201 and that'll basically disable it.
Oops.
What did I do wrong there?
Invalid?
Numeric arguments?
I think I did that, right.
I wrote down, I do it.
Slower case.
I wrote down these command line switches beforehand.
So I wouldn't have to go hunt for them too much.
Just so you know, if you want to hunt for command-line switches.
It's not that hard.
If you go to msv.
See you can actually type in a command line switch such as the one we
just
I tried like w.
All right, and you can actually get the double, the msdn
documentation, which will tell you all of the stuff about that switch
and other switches, and over here in the compiler options.
You'll notice there's a compiler options listed alphabetically heading
and you can kind of scroll through there and just see what all the
crazy can power switches are.
So if you don't even know what kind of computers which are looking
for, it's kind of handy because you can just go read through and see
what can I do with my compiler.
Hey, it's fun, right?
So that's that's one thing.
You can do.
All right.
So this this is basically, you know, this, this is basically all I
wanted to do.
There was turn that warning off.
I had it capitalize, it should have been lower case.
So - WD-40 to a one turns out off.
We won't hear that anymore.
Now, let's take a look at what this one is.
So this one, it says it's converting from an inch to a un eight
possible loss of data.
So what it's telling me is that think, computed on this side is
basically 32 bits, but the thing on this side is, is eight and it's
feeling like the truncation should be.
Something that tells me about now, I like that warning.
I don't think that's frivolous.
I want to know and it's trivial for me to get rid upright.
I can just say, don't worry.
I understand.
I'm going to tell you with a cast that I wanted that to happen.
You don't have to do it implicitly.
And when I do that, you'll notice that gets rid of the warning, right.
So now we're down, we skipped over those, they're gone.
And so I want to keep that one.
I don't want to eliminate that.
We're that's a good warning.
I don't think there's any reason to get rid of it.
If I had made a mistake there.
It would have been nice to call that line to my attention and say,
hey.
Hey, this is actually going to going to truncate the value, you know,
and I'd be like whoops.
You know, my bad.
I got to fix that.
I shouldn't be truncating there.
Right?
Alright, so in this case, we got another one here looks like the let's
see conversion from real 32 inch possible loss of data.
So I'm not sure where exactly that is complaining about.
So the blue offsets in ENT.
This one's an ENT.
Let me take a look here.
What's going on here?
Yeah, so, okay.
So basically what's happening there is I didn't I guess we missed a
set of
You somehow when I originally wrote that.
So the cast here to integer was affecting only the 4.0 F because it
was binding, it like that.
Right?
And so, then it was it was turning this into an ENT, but then it was
doing the multiply in float, I guess.
Which then is it was not going to actually do the thing that we
wanted, which was turned it into an ENT after doing a floating-point
multiply.
So we actually want to do is make sure we do the multiply first and
then that.
So the compiler doesn't get confused about what we what we were
telling it with this cast.
We're trying to tell you, it's okay.
To turn it from the float to an end.
And I guess it was thinking that this was binding too closely to be
honest.
I'm not sure.
That's what you might want to check that.
I'm not sure about that.
It's a little odd input 0 and x.
No, that's right.
Okay, it is right.
I was gonna say, I didn't know if input end X was a float.
I couldn't remember, but it is a float.
So yeah, what was probably happening?
Was, it was turning this 4.0 F into an integer then multiplying by a
float, which up, converts it back to a float.
And then it was trying to, you know, the whole expression evaluates to
float by doing it this way.
It does the two floats times each other, which is what we want.
That's actually what we wanted, is the floats time to each other.
Once the floats multiply out.
Then we cast down to an end, the compiler thinks that's just fine and
we're done now.
Basically, this guy, I don't like this warning at all unreferenced
formal parameter.
Basically, what this tells you is that you are passing a parameter of
function and not using it.
Now I do that all the time because I'm planning for something in the
future or there's a reason why I didn't do it.
I hate that warning.
I'm maybe you'd want to do that in a compile once in a while just to
see.
But
day to day, I find it to be really annoying and not useful.
So 4100 is also going to get the virtual XO 4100 goes away.
It's gone.
Now, we're down to just a few here.
Let's take a look.
We've got initializing.
So this one is W /, a.
Okay.
So we're basically getting a VK code out of a w /.
Am now the VK code, we're asking for only 32 bits, but the W preamps,
actually 64 bits in win 64.
So we do need to tell it that it's
Okay, truncate that because VK codes, which are going to keyboard
codes that say what key was pressed.
Those are not 64-bit.
So we're fine with that truncation.
That's all good.
No, real problem there.
Now, excuse me in this G word, mass controller count is not a d where
it should have been.
So basically, what we need to do is just make that a d word because d
word is unsigned.
It was signed, it was telling us that we're doing comparison between a
signed and unsigned value, which may have been a mistake.
Not a problem.
We'll just fix that.
And then we basically get to just a bunch of
local variables that aren't actually used.
Now.
I'm fine with that as well.
The compiler will always optimize out those, if they're not used.
So usually that is just not a big savings to have it warned me about
that.
So that's the last we're going to get rid of 4189 and now we're down
to a clean compile.
No warnings.
We eliminated three warnings that we did not want and we left in all
the other ones that seem like they're probably going to be useful to
us and we would like it to keep on asking, so that's pretty good.
All right, so that's just something I want to do.
Turn on a higher warning level because War
Do catch errors for you, occasionally bugs in the code?
Basically, it's not often.
A lot of times warnings don't actually catch a bug, but the times that
they do, you'll be happy there there.
I think we already had one time on the stream when because we were at
a lower warning level, we had some, we had to catch ourselves of the
compiler.
Would it cost for us at a higher warning level?
And that's just an example of something that, you know, like I said, I
wanted to get to and turn that on, because I never code without prior,
warning level.
And so, I didn't want to mislead people into thinking that was a good
idea.
I don't think it's a good idea.
I like to keep the warning level.
Le tively.
Hi.
And like I said, if there's a particular warning level, that seems too
high because there's a couple areas that are, there's a couple of
warnings that are just really bugging.
You just turn just those ones off.
If you don't think if you think their frivolous but don't let that
discourage you from turning on the rest of them, which may be actually
been very beneficial and help you catch errors before a long,
protracted annoying debugging session to find those errors.
Alright, so I wrote down here.
I took my notebook today and I wrote down some of the other compiler
switches that I typically use.
Use and I just wanted to kind of go over some of them while we're in
here, doing sort of this kind of cleanup of our stuff that we're
passing to our build.
So typically we have some stuff in here.
One of them is minus zi and what - zi does is minus zi.
Basically tells it to produce debug information and what that is.
If you go look in the actual build directory, right?
That's these pdb files and stuff here, right?
Those those are basically read by the debugger.
Excuse me.
Those are read by the debugger to tell it essentially, where the stuff
is in the executable, that It produced.
Because when the debugger loads, the executable and starts stepping
through that executable as you go.
He doesn't know, for example, where in the executable corresponds to
where in the source code.
So what the compiler has to do is it has to spit out annotation
essentially in the form of these pdb files.
That essentially sort of illustrate.
To the debugger.
After the fact, we're in the executable corresponds to where in the
source file and stuff like, where, what names of variables were that
sort of stuff.
Lots of things have to go in there and you can see just by looking at
it.
It's a 2 megabyte file.
That pdb is, and our, executable is only 200 K.
So, it's actually, the debug info is just a lot bigger than the
executable.
In fact, it's just a lot of info.
It's sort of like browse info.
You almost might think of it, kind of like that.
Like, you know, in Visual Studio allows you to jump around and see
what things are.
It's almost like that for the debugger.
It's a thing that tells it this particular location executable
corresponds to this particular name of a thing.
And that thing is a function and whatever that sort of stuff.
So what I want to do here is I just want to point out the fact that
minus Z.
I can be problematic.
Sometimes.
I don't know if they fix this in 2013, but in previous versions, there
were a lot of problems with the way that pdb handling was done and if
I delete the pdbs here, basically.
So there
Dawn, right?
And I do this build, you know, they come back right there they are.
So when I make those pdbs they basically are kind of shared as the
program is compiling in depending on whether it's trying to do a
multiprocessor compiled and all these other sorts of things.
Or if your build script is calling a little times, you can get into
problems where you get kind of race conditions on the PD, because the
compilers trying to hit multiple times and it'll get slower at all
these sorts of things.
I don't know.
It's problematic has been problematic in the past.
I don't know how problematic it still is today, but one of
Things you can do is you can change the zi2 a - z7 and what that'll
do.
If I delete the the pdbs here, it's pretty minimal what it actually
doesn't practice.
You can see that that this guy, this this VC, 120 pdb goes away, and
it's no longer necessary.
And basically, what happens there, you can see that was gonna say.
Oh, yeah, you can see that.
Basically, it only now has this one pdb, Whatever that causes it to
do.
It's some combination of putting debug info in like
Object file or something like this, the minus Z 7 uses a quote-unquote
older format or an older method of do, using the producing the debug
info that seems to play nicer with build environments and
multiprocessor build.
So, I just wanted to point out that it's there.
It will.
I cannot imagine we will ever care about it because we're just using a
build up that file but for people who are doing other stuff and just
want to know, like the z7 is something to kind of be aware of.
So I just, I just be aware of it, read up.
About it.
If you care, we don't really care but it's wanted to point it out.
And that is something that I typically will use any time that if I was
using a more sophisticated build environment.
All, I'd probably throw that in there just because to be safe because
I've had problems in the past.
Anyway, so we've got a couple other things.
There's there's there's definitely a bunch of things we can do in
terms of training on optimizations and that sort of stuff when we want
to do an optimized bill, but we're not really at that point yet.
So mostly I just want to do a couple other things that are turning off
features.
We don't want it all.
So one of the things that we want to do all the time for example is
Intrinsics.
So for example, if the compiler knows how to is output something say
that would be, you know, like we were calling sign before, right?
You were calling sign F.
If the compiler knows how to do an intrinsic version of sign F, which
is basically to say, do the assembly code right there, that just calls
the processor and does something, you know, if the processor knows how
to do a sign, for example, just do that.
That is something that I like to keep turned on in debug as well
because I never actually want to have the compiler generating calls.
To the C runtime library to do functions that the CPU could have done.
Because I feel like that just adds complexity and changes the behavior
of the C program between debug and release.
Because in release mode, I'm always going to want it to use those
faster intrinsics.
So I tend to like to leave that on all the time.
So - oh, I just says in this build, even though this is a debug build.
I want you to always do any intrinsic stuff that you can.
So that's that.
So I leave that on all the time.
One of the other things that I try to do and I don't even know how
effectively you can do this anymore, but it's just a turn-off runtime
type information, which is a C++ feature.
Basically that is what is the thing that I wrote down the gr.
- is that that basically turns off runtime type information because we
don't need runtime type information.
We're never going to use C++ is runtime type information facility.
So we can just turn that off and save any of the extra stuff that
might be generated for its, we don't care.
The other thing is exception, exception handling, I think.
This is the way the best way to turn it off.
But those of you who maybe have more experience with visual Visual
Studio stuff, might know of an easier way to turn off.
I think that turns it off so that you can you no longer generate it,
no longer generates kind of overhead based on handling.
This kind of stuff.
I'm not going to cover what this is, but those of you who program C++
know what I'm talking about.
I think that turns it off.
I'm not actually sure.
Let's see, x equals zero, does it now?
So I don't actually know how to get that to turn off in.
There it is.
All right, that's good.
That's good enough.
Then - eh, eh appears to have turned it off again.
If you're if you're a visual C++ expert and you happen to know what
the switch is.
That definitively turns it off.
Maybe that's a good thing.
Let's see here.
That's it.
Yeah.
Okay.
So that's the one that I wanted then and and basically what that does
is it says this is a C++ feature that's basically called exception
handling.
What it allows you to do is do something.
And if
That something should do what's called throwing an exception.
Which basically allows you to type, you know, throw something here.
If you are inside a try block and somebody does one of these throw
things.
It doesn't matter how deep down you are.
You could be many functions deep.
It will unwind the stack.
The call stack all the way back up to the first and closing, try and
see if the catch Handler catches, whatever.
The thing is, that's thrown and basically what that means is if an
integer was thrown, you would have an ENT catch here.
And then it would go ahead and execute this piece of code and
continue.
That's what
Killing it.
I have no need for those at all.
Because the only exception handling we might do is called structured
exception handling, which is a win32 feature.
We don't actually need C++ has exception handling for anything.
So I'm just going to turn that off because it generates extra stuff on
the stack that we don't actually need.
But I don't actually know if it's much of an efficiency thing anymore.
These days.
I don't know if they've gotten that down to where it's not that
important.
But I usually turn those off.
Also, obviously when we compile you'll notice it still printing out.
This little Banner here.
It's like telling us about the Microsoft are C, C++ optimizing
compiler.
That I like to turn off as well.
You can do no logo and just get rid of it.
It's just cleaner to read.
I don't need to know who wrote the compiler.
I'm a pretty well aware of that at this point, so it shouldn't be a
problem.
And I think that's most of the things that I want to show now.
I did want to show one more thing.
I'm not sure.
So I it's a little bit iffy is whether whether I want to do this today
or not.
I think I'm gonna try to do it.
And we'll see how hard it is to actually get it to Output this without
having to do too much work on the tool chain.
But what I'd like to do is show how to do a 32-bit build potentially.
And so, what I'm going to do in here, I think we're still asking for
four gigabytes of memory.
I'm going to I'm going to drop that down to one.
A bite just so we can be 32 bits safe for the moment.
Basically.
What I want to do is I want to see if we can just get it compiling
under 32 bit by using Arch.
I don't remember there used to be all these kind of weird restrictions
on like you had to actually use a different version of the compiler.
If you were compiling for 32-bit versus 64-bit and then they made it
so you could or couldn't.
I don't remember it was it was all kind of wacky at first.
It wasn't like llvm where you could just always run one of them and it
worked on both or whatever, but I
Be sure that if you run at least a 64-bit one, now, we'll do 32 bit
and 64 or something like this.
So it we should be able to I think be able to actually tell it that we
want to compile in x86 but I don't actually know if that's true.
So we're just going to try and if we can then I'm going to actually
show how to do that build as well.
Otherwise, if it's if it's a little too much, I may go sort of just do
a pre-baked version one of one of those.
Get it already and then show it on the screen at some point, so we
don't waste hours going through.
You try and you know pulling our hair out, trying to make that work.
All right.
So basically let's let's take a look here.
What I want to do is I want to do M SV C, 2013, compile x86 32-bit
basically, so let's see here.
Let's see what they say.
Did you in the configuration manager?
Oh, that's actually not the compiler switches though.
I want to actually know what the compiler switches are.
I feel like this should be it, but I don't actually see it.
This, our check.
It's 86 thing is kind of looked like what I wanted this thing, but I
don't actually see ia-32.
So in size?
No.
Enhanced instruction is also specifies x87 for floating-point
calculations.
This looks more like just telling it what kind of instructions to use
not whether to use 32-bit or 64-bit in a weird kind of way.
I would have thought.
Yeah, it's a little it's just kind of strange so that doesn't look
like what I wanted.
So I don't know whether I have to actually use.
Like I said a different version of the executable to tell it which can
which, which 32-bit or 64-bit version.
I'm trying to use.
So I'm not sure about that.
What I do know.
At the very least is the, there's a couple things that I want to do
with the Linker.
And so, what I'm going to do is I'm just going to, like I said, spend
a couple seconds on this and see if I can get it to work so that we
can we can kind of go into debt, but that's okay.
32-bit compiled M SV C CL.
Let's just see.
Let's see here.
Target, Arch.
Those look like platform to finds.
I don't know.
This doesn't look useful.
Let's see here.
Yeah, I mean, the other, I guess, the thing we can do.
I mean, obviously, we have this thing.
I don't know if you remember this.
So in our shell, in our shell, dot bat that we made way back at the
beginning, you'll notice we did x64 here.
So, one thing we could do, right, is we could call this thing and
switch the mode that were in.
So if I do this, right, if I do this line exactly.
And just tell it to do instead.
Of that to do x86 like that.
Then when we build, I believe it will build 32-bit because that is
that is the thing.
I was talking about where you switch the compiler.
I was kind of hoping to not have to do it, but that's one way to do
it.
And so that should actually work.
And you can see here, when I did the build, it really did switch
because it's giving me a warning about a size conversion where where
size T is now 32 bits instead of 64 bits, so we can
Always switch it that way.
I guess that's just what I'll do.
And we'll just put it to do in here.
Will say, look.
Can we just build both without with one egg Z?
If we can't, it's not really that big of a deal because we could still
build both with a batch file without a problem.
By just instead of letting v c VAR story to a VC vars, do the work for
us.
We would basically just actually directly set the environment
variables and call the right things to make it work, but it doesn't
Like that's going to be forthcoming.
So I was going to do it this way for the sake of expediency for now.
So we'll go ahead and do that.
If we compile in here.
This is a 64-bit compile because emacs was launched from the show,
when it still had the environment setup for 64.
If we build it out here, now, we switched it.
So it'll do it this way.
We can take a look at line 634 in win32.
Handmade.
That's our only error 634 and basically, all that is is it's saying,
oh,
By the way, excuse me.
I need to convert.
I supposed total size to a size, T.
We can't actually pass it.
Things that are going to be 64 bits anymore because virtual Alec is
going to be that.
So what I'll do is I guess I'll just use size T that way on 64-bit
platforms.
Size T, is defined to be 64-bit and 32-bit.
It's defined to be 32.
So that's the compiler specific definition for that.
So we can just use that size T in this code, for that purpose and that
way on either of our builds.
It'll compile.
A properly and you sit the full 64 bits, where applicable?
All right.
So basically what that should have done.
If I do this build here are win32 handmade should now be a 32-bit
executable and I can I can actually just run it as such.
So if I come in here, right, this should be a 64-bit executable.
Now will double check to see if that's true.
If I come in here basically, we're going through everything and we
want to see does this kind of work.
What is the size of size T.
For example?
For.
So, this is a 32-bit build does everything.
Run?
Everything does run?
It's all good.
So we're happy.
We have our 32-bit filled.
Okay, so that gets me onto the main thing that I what
Is that?
What happened there?
Mmm, I got a reconnecting message.
Are people still is a stream still alive.
What's going on?
Where do we lose?
Where we leave off?
I don't know what's going on here.
What's going on?
Oh, no.
All right.
Well.
Not sure what we can do about.
That.
Looks like the internet went down.
So I guess there's not much I can do.
I guess I'll finish the lesson though.
That's really unfortunate.
Oh, well, well, the stream went down, but I guess I'll finish the
lesson and people can watch it.
After the fact that's really unfortunate.
I will have to get a better internet service provider.
All right, so, I guess moving on here.
Let's see what we can do.
Basically, we've got
32-bit build working, which is what we actually wanted.
And I don't know what I can do.
I guess, what soon as this reconnects will be able to get the
livestream back, that is unfortunate.
I'm surprised it hasn't happened earlier, to be honest with you.
That's really annoying.
But I will, I will.
Basically.
I've already kind of been a little bit mad at the internet service
prior.
So we will, we will take that up with them after the fact and then
we'll continue on.
All right.
So back to where we were before the internet service provider.
So, so gracious.
He destroyed the stream.
Basically.
I was just trying to say once we have a 32-bit build working.
There's some stuff that I wanted to show you.
So I that's why I wanted to get to a 32-bit build.
All right, so we have a 32-bit build here.
Now, inside emacs, it's 64 bit.
So I'm going to close emacs because again, emacs inherits when you
launch it, all of the settings from your shell.
So basically, I am going to go ahead and relaunch emac, so that now
we're building in 32-bit mode and we are happy.
So basically in here,
Here, I will go ahead and say in my hand made here at STP build, that
looks like a 32-bit and we're all good.
What I want to do now is the thing that I wanted to do before the that
a long time ago, but I didn't think we were quite ready for it yet.
Is I want to basically show you what happens when you try to roll.
Basically you try to run on another machine.
That's not your dead machine.
Right?
And so what I've done here is I've set up a virtual box.
A virtual box with Windows.
7, I'm sorry.
Windows XP.
Old-school Windows XP super old school, you know what I'm talking
about.
Basically, this Windows XP.
I've set it up to share our executable.
So basically, if I go in here to build, you can see that we've got
basically the win32 handmade thing here and all that.
So if I want to, I can basically open up a command prompt.
I can take a look at where we are.
I can go into where we normally run our stuff, which is an end,
handmade data, right?
We normally run it here.
And I can run our build by going win32 handmade like that.
Right?
So I can do all the stuff that I wanted to actually do but at least
I'm assuming I know what's going to happen when I hit this.
Maybe I don't, I've never tried it before, but if you notice, when you
actually try to run your stuff, this is often what happens.
This happens.
Shockingly frequently, basically, when you try to
When people try to distribute code nowadays, Windows has gotten to the
point where the development environment is.
So awful.
That the chances that you will actually be able to run an executable.
You build on someone else's machine are essentially zero, like unless
they have the exact same machine as you or, you know, all the things
I'm about to tell you.
There is no way that you will ever do it because Microsoft is
essentially written the development tools to ensure that when you
build something, it won't run.
Now.
I don't know why they did this.
I think it may just be
Not understanding that.
It's important to not have that happen.
I'm not sure.
Cause it seems like they would want things to run, but they have gone
a different route.
Basically, the route that they've gone is to make everyone build these
executables that are crazy incompatible.
And then force you to ship a ton of redistributable content.
I don't know if you've ever noticed, you try to run something on
Steam.
It's got to install the DirectX, runtime, and then it's got to install
some VC redistributable.
A 32 bit or 64 bit depending on what you want, it is, and whether it's
10 or 12, and all, this is just, it's a disaster.
It's a compatibility has gotten awful and windows lately.
It's awful.
But there are some things you can do to try and give yourself a leg
up.
One of them is the thing that I just showed you which is to have a
virtual machine that is totally free of anything installed on it.
No, DirectX!
Runtime.
No VC, redistribute.
Oh, nothing just so you can see what you are actually missing when you
go to run your
Thing.
So, the first thing that will notice is Windows XP.
Actually, if you actually want to be able to run on Windows XP, you
can't even use an executable built by a modern Visual Studio without
some work.
What you actually have to do is start passing things to the Linker by
default.
The Linker won't even create a Windows Windows, XP, compatible,
binary.
That's that's where we're at.
Right?
So what you need to do is you need to pass /, link and / link.
Will allow you to specify start.
Passing Linker options and the Linker auction that I'm going to pass
is called - subsystem which basically tells it what to build.
Normally.
This is for console or Windows.
Those are the two things that you might pass to it.
Console is if you want to make a thing that has wit, you know, Main
and it can print things out to the console printf, scanf, that sort of
thing.
And windows means it's going to open a window.
So it shouldn't be bound to a console.
That's normally what that was for.
But now they've gotten they paint themselves in this corner where
there by default they're compiler.
Doesn't
Even produce executables that when X Windows XP can even run.
And so what you have to do is you have to pass this.
Crazy syntax - subsystem: Windows 5.1.
And if you pass that then when you build, you will actually building
an executable that Windows XP can read at all.
That's not the same as saying that we're actually going to have our
thing actually work.
I'm just saying that's the first step that we need to do.
So, now, if we go back here and try it, you will notice that we
actually get what we wanted, right off the
Right, you can see, you can kind of see, I've actually surprising
that.
There's one other thing I would probably have to do but I didn't have
to we'll talk about that second.
You can see that we're now running on XP, just fine, totally Clean
Machine, nothing installed and we just ran right out of the gate.
Now that actually I said, surprise me.
I thought there was one more thing we're going to do.
I'll make it happen first and then I'll because we lucked out since
we're compiling for the command line.
If you're compiling, I think from the from the, from the
From the IDE.
This wouldn't have been true, but I can make it happen.
I can make it happen.
Anyway, hold on one second.
Let me figure out what the switch is multi-threaded, dll.
This is the one that gets most people and this is why you have to do
the VC readest stuff.
That's very, very annoying.
Let's see here.
Of course, my internet is kind of toast at this point.
So, I don't know if I'll be able to actually look up anything.
Let's find out if I can.
A deal.
Yes, we can.
So here we go.
Baseline is going to do this.
And this is what would have been done by default.
I believe if you would use if you were going to use the the IDE to
build things, which most people do.
And so they get the wrong thing selected, but I'm going to show you
basically what happens if you if you turn it off, so well, I will if
it ever can load.
I think it's / at minus MD, but we'll see here.
So basically we'll go on here - MD and that will allow us.
To sort of exhibit the bug.
Yeah, there we go.
So this is what you normally get when you build from the IDE, you get
this.
And this is basically something that tells you that you can't load
this, you know, random dll that you didn't even know you were using.
Well, the reason for that is because by default the C, runtime
Library, Microsoft, C, runtime Library, the thing that we were using
to call say sign, the thing that has our startup code in it basically
when we step in
If you look at in the debugger, right?
If we look at the call stack this stuff, the all this stuff that
Microsoft implemented.
As part of the compiler package, that starts up the program and stuff
that stuff.
That is basically the thing that it is missing because, by default
that is always done by using a multi-threaded dll by started on my
third, by using an external dll.
So instead of actually linking it into your code, it treats it just
like operating system code and assumes.
The operating system will supply the C runtime library.
Now, the
Problem with that is there are like at this point hundreds of versions
of that c runtime Library, they modify it all the time.
They ship multiple versions of it different versions with each
compiler.
And so what happens is the operating system often doesn't have the
right version of that c runtime library in the dll and so what happens
in dll form.
So it happens is your executable when it tries to load it, totally
fails, because it can't find it.
Now.
There's the thing that you can do, the, I'll show you here to kind of
understand this sort of stuff.
Little bit better.
Again, looks like my internet connections down.
So I may not be able to actually show you one way or the other.
We'll see if it actually works at all.
It doesn't look like it's going to.
So it seems like probably I won't be able to do that.
But basically, there's a thing you can use called depends.
There's a program called.
Depends.
I don't think it's installed on this machine, but maybe it is.
I'm not sure.
I'll give it a shot.
You can download it freely from the Internet.
It's called, depends dot exe.
And I think I might have it installed.
Called.
Let's take a look.
I'm not sure apps now.
I don't got it installed on here.
Unfortunately.
Yeah, it's not it's not on here.
There's basically something called depends dot exe.
And what it will do is it will show you the stuff that a particular
executable relies on and maybe I'll show that to you in a different
stream.
Well, stream, I use the term loosely now since we can't actually use
any streaming to the internet because my internet service provider is
awful.
Basically, what it boils down to is it will
Us what the executable actually relies on so you don't have to
necessarily test it first to see what dlls are expected to be loading
because we know that some of them are going to be loaded, right?
We linked to user 32.
Lib and GDI 32 .libs.
So we knew that and those are just import Library.
So we knew that those were going to link to user 32 at dll and GDI 32
dup Vol, but we didn't know about that hidden one.
That the compiler had stuck in there.
And also kernel32 is implicit here and we didn't ask for that.
So we wouldn't necessarily have known that.
That was
He's in there.
So depends on the XE is a good thing to kind of let you know that.
So basically what I want to show you is - Mt.
Instead of minus MD is the thing that's minus MD, says, use the dll -
Mt says, use the static Library, like link it in actually package, all
the C runtime Library into our executable wholesale.
Don't look for a dll that is the switch that you absolutely want to
have set so that you don't get that error.
And then when you run on another computer, you don't need to have
that, VC, vars, read.
Beauty redistributable, so that's a very good thing if you're trying
to make your game more compatible.
So basically now at least we know we are running sanely.
We can run on Windows XP.
I hear the sound.
We've got the, the image and everything.
So, I think we're in pretty good shape.
That's all I really wanted to show you.
And so, I keep a virtual machine around or an actual machine installed
with Windows XP.
For this very purpose, when I actually want it.
I'm going to actually just get rid of this.
Now.
Let's see, power off the machine.
I
Yes, because we don't need it for anything else, but that's all I
wanted to show you.
And so I'm going to put that in there, even though it's the default on
the command line.
So, I don't think you would make ever have this mistake, if you're
using the command line, because even if you don't specify it, it's
fine.
But in the IDE, I believe, when you create a new project, a default is
to use the, the, the multi-threaded dll.
And that's really bad.
Like you don't want that creates all kinds of compatibility nightmares
for you.
So, that's basically all I wanted to cover.
I think that's basically everything I had written down here.
That's not about compilation.
So I want to turn off minimal rebuild since we're building.
We rebuild everything every time.
- GM - turns off, any sort of incremental, build stuff that Microsoft
might be trying to do to quote unquote, speed things up since we're
not doing any of that kind of rebuilding.
And I think that's about everything there is.
Now, I did want to produce one more thing since this is.
Like I said, a stream about kind of learning how all of these stuff
works.
There is one more thing I wanted to do, since we've got plenty of time
here.
It's called - FM minus FM.
Allows us to basically pass something that tells the tells the Linker
a location to stick a map file basically.
So, if I do this, right, I will now get an extra file in here, where I
actually build my, my game, right?
So you can see that before.
There wasn't this thing, this map file.
There is now a map file and the map file is kind of interesting.
You can see if I actually just oops, that's tough.
All right.
Go ahead and take a listing of the executable.
If I look at the map file, what the map file actually is, is it's
basically what it exactly its name.
It is a map.
It is a thing that tells you in text form where all of the functions
are in your actual executable.
Like, you can actually see.
Every last thing that is in there is actually listed, right?
It's like here.
They all are here's where everything went right?
All the stuff that we actually wanted to know where it was.
It's in there.
Are now one of the things is you might ask.
Why do we actually care where any of this stuff is?
And why does it look so funny?
In some of the places?
You can see some of these have some really bizarre stuff on them and
that sort of stuff.
Well, basically there's a bunch of subtleties with map files.
Basically, excuse me.
What happens with a map file is?
It's going to go ahead and it's, you know, we can actually see looking
at the side.
If you look at the side here, you can see what module was responsible
for out, putting something into your map file and then what the thing
was
That the name, what the name was of the thing that got outputted and
you can also see where like this is basically the byte offset of the
actual thing where it actually was these sorts of things.
But what I wanted to point out is basically there's, there's a lot of
what's called name mangling that goes on in here.
That might be confusing to people.
So if you look at some stuff like, like this sort of thing, the names
just look absolutely crazy.
Like, that looks pretty normal.
It's got a lot of underscores, but underscores are usually,
Just saying, hey, this is a reserved keyword in C.
So a lot of things will have underscores in them.
If there's something the compiler used or introduced, right?
But these things here, right?
These, these sort of, weirdly mangled names.
Those are kind of an interesting anachronism and it's worth
understanding what they are.
So this map file, I'll talk about those in a second.
I just want to finish up.
So this map files basically just the thing.
If we kind of want to know what ended up getting put in our
executable.
And where stuff is, this is a thing that basically this is a text
file.
That tells you exactly that information and
Kind of fun to be able to look at and you can even see.
Remember I said we were using an import library to basically allow us
to bind to dll system dlls we can even see what those kind of are.
You can see this underscore underscore imp underscore underscore
right?
Console W or underscore underscore imp, like where's one that we
actually call it get file size.
There it is.
And basically what that is is that's an import function.
That was the thing that was put in place, as sort of a stub,
essentially, that's going to be replaced with the actual pointer to
the win32.
T2 to the win32 dll, when it gets loaded, so you'll see underscore
underscore imp versions of every win32 thing that either you call or
the C runtime Library calls, and therefore needs to bind to.
So, a lot of these things we don't call but the C runtime Library
called.
So they had to get Dragged In.
And that's one nice thing, too, that you can kind of see when you
start looking at the map file.
You can see all the stuff that got stuck in there.
That you ain't even necessarily want or know about, right?
There's just tons of stuff in there that you didn't necessarily want
that you
Necessarily call.
And it's just kind of interesting to kind of be aware of it that like,
oh, the C runtime Library drag that in or such and such happened,
right?
And you can get rid of some of that stuff.
Sometimes.
There's basically a thing called opt ref which you can do that.
You can pack pass to the Linker which basically says to be aggressive
about not putting anything you.
Can you do it this way, ah, pref like that.
If you pass that to Linker it basically says don't put anything into
the executable.
If you don't need to like nobody uses it, make sure you get
Get rid of it.
It's kind of like, try hard to discard things, if that makes sense.
And if we take a look at what happens when we specify that, you'll
notice it went from from a 157 k21 42 K.
So it does sorry to 134k.
And so it does get rid of some stuff.
You know, it there is some stuff that gets stuck in there that doesn't
need to because no one actually called it or used it or whatever.
But they're still, just a ton of stuff used by the C runtime library
that Justice is just stuck in there and that's unfortunate.
Right?
It's one of the reasons to get rid of the C runtime.
Library, if you can, and we talked a little bit about maybe doing
that, I've done it on projects before, but I don't know how productive
it would be to spend time the stream to do that.
So, we probably won't anyway, onto the name mangling.
So the way name mangling works is basically, C used to have saying
names for things.
Basically, when you used to call things and see, they used to look
like this.
They would look like just the name of the thing that you called, but
the problem is C++ introduced overloaded function.
Yes.
Now I've talked about what that what that was.
I showed an example of that on the stream previously.
Basically, what an overloaded function is, is an overloaded function
is having two functions with the same name like this, but that take
different parameters, right?
This kind of thing.
Right.
Basically, what this is trying to say is, all right.
I'm going to call Foo and then I want you to call whichever Foo
happens to be the one that uses the parameters that I passed.
So I might say Foo five or Foo 56 and this one will call the second
Foo and this one will come on the first few.
It's as, if they were labeled like this, right, does that make sense?
So the problem here was that C++ was originally written, sort of on
top of a
See like toolchain.
It was kind of first done as a preprocessor and then it kind of, you
know, went from there.
But the whole time they were sort of coming from C and adding features
to C++ in ways that were easy for them to implement under the hood as
it wasn't really the case that they started from scratch or C++ and
implemented each feature the way that maybe it would most optimally
be.
So what they decided to do to make this work with the c with C Style
linkers.
Was to basically allow you to write this.
And then the compiler would sort of silently go in and generate a name
for this function based on its arguments.
So,
You can imagine coming up with sort of a coding system.
Right?
Which is whatever the type is.
Like if the type is in t then maybe we append underscore in t, right
to the name of the, of the function.
Right?
And it looks like that, right.
So this is few underscore intent.
This is to underscore n t.
So now we kind of know when we generate a call, we can actually output
actual calls it in the object file that the Linker will look at, we
can actually output one.
That's an actual name that the Linker can resolve.
Lee, right?
And so that is what this name mangling was all about this name.
Mangling was about taking things that were potentially overloaded
functions in C++ and mangling them into something that would be unique
and work with a regular Linker.
So you can kind of see these sorts of things ending up happening.
I'll try to find a good example of one of them.
I'm not sure what the best example would be in C.
So, you know, this this kind of a thing, right?
These sorts of things are what I'm talking about this stuff.
After the app that sort of thing there, right?
All of that is basically code that tells that diff it disambiguates
this function from another function that may be the same thing, but
overloaded now because C++ doesn't actually know how overloaded a
function might be because you have to remember C++.
Usually, you compile and multiple files.
We're using one big translation unit.
But normally you compiled file separately.
So it doesn't know how many overloaded versions of a function, there
might be, so it can't.
Only knit mangle the names of overloaded functions.
It has to mangle the names of all functions because that same function
might be defined with a different set of parameters in a different
file that's going to compiled separately.
So it's going to be different translation unit.
And only the Linker will ever see them together.
So even stuff that isn't overloaded has to go through this name
mangling and that's why those things look like they do.
So, hopefully that makes some sense.
All right.
So basically that's all I wanted to show today was just to kind of get
our build kind of in you know in some shape there.
And then I think the the other thing maybe we've got about got a few
minutes left.
I'm going to start today on the thing.
We're going to do tomorrow, finish up tomorrow, which is we did never
did our keyboard input.
We never wired keyboard input up to the controller and that requires a
little bit of sort of finesse, and factoring here that we need to kind
of do.
Because if you remember properly, we kind of we did the work of
getting keyboard.
It right.
But we never actually went in and wired it up the way that we wear it
up the controller.
So if I go in here and Run the game, right?
I don't actually no matter what I do.
I don't actually get any actual motion.
They're out of pressing the keys, which I kind of wanted to do.
So what I think we can do in our last 10 minutes here, now that we
finish with the build stuff is just think about how we're going to do
that.
Now, I have a problem, which is that, because of the way Windows
forces me to go through, callbacks.
I have no context when I hop.
In here, so I'm either going to have to use a global variable or use
some local storage on the window, too.
You're out what we're even stuff is right because I need to stuff this
stuff into the into an input structure of some kind and I don't even
know where I'm going to be able to do that.
Right?
What I would like to be able to do is I'd like to be able to pass the
parse those messages in my in my Loop here.
And so one question that I might ask myself is could I go ahead and
process them there?
Because as we know most of the time Windows actually does send us our
messages through here, so it may be possible to just
Always do the message processing in there.
So what I could do and I'm just going to do this as a test for.
Now.
What I could do is go ahead and say these four messages that I want
the ciske up, ciske down, those sorts of things, right?
I know they're getting dispatched in here.
Well, could I do something like this?
Basically, if the message type, right, if message message, right?
In fact, I can just do this as a switch statement.
If the message is one of these things wmq down, you know, any of these
sorts of things.
I'm just going to see what happens if I feel that there and then if
there's anything else, if it's something else that comes in, I'm going
to go ahead and filled it using the standard translate dispatch out to
the window routine.
And then in here I'm gonna use that assertion that we did to say.
No just to see if we got there, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and see if that ever fires.
So what I'm doing here is I'm testing to see if the keyboard input
ever comes in through a path other than the standard.
Loop because we know that paint messages do but we don't actually seem
to say so I don't see that.
I've never hidden that.
I've never hitting that assertion which tells me that that we should
probably be safe to just move this handling down there.
So I'm going to leave this in here.
Keyboard input, came in through a non dispatch event or message.
That's bad.
What I'm going to do is I'm just going to move our handling out of
here out of the windows code, where we don't actually want to do it
down into the main Loop or a process, everything else, because that'll
be nice and convenient, and I don't have to do any kind of weird like
round tripping, right?
You know, that sort of thing.
If that makes sense, hmm, okay, let's see here.
Let's go ahead and translate these.
So we've got the wasd keys.
Those to me are going to be.
So, so basically we if you look down here, we've got this sort of
stuff that we were doing for the buttons.
We have the the process digital button.
I think that's basically what we want to do.
We want to do essentially the same exact thing for the keyboard,
right?
We can even
I'm possibly collapse those.
Basically, what I want to do is I want to do this for all of these
buttons.
So these are going to be the buttons.
I think the up-down left-right is going to be the buttons for me.
So basically, if we have a VK code of up, that's going to be Loop.
That's going to be our oh.
That's not good.
Okay.
Sorry, that's going to be our up here like this, and we're going to
get rid of that like that.
So basically pass the to, uh, parameters.
This one is going to be our left, just as you might expect are left
button.
There we go.
Again, you always important to pronounce button like this.
There we go down.
That's good.
Let's take a look.
Here we go down, and I'm
Do right?
That's good.
There we go.
Five-minute warning.
No problem.
We're just kind of wrapping this up anyway, so we can get those things
in there.
Basically, how we want to, we can process Escape as well.
If you want to.
We could we could say that that kills our game, maybe.
I don't know, we'll see will talk about.
We will think about what?
We want these things to do sometime, when we actually have the whole
game running and were like, what do we want?
Our, what do we want our stuff to do?
But anyway, yeah, so we've got a new controller up it.
Well, you know what?
Do we pass the do?
We have like start buttons or things like that?
I remember what we actually decided on passing for our first pass.
No, we didn't.
So I'll just leave it like that.
So, that's fine.
So then these will be our shoulder.
But so these will be our shoulder buttons here.
Like this.
This will be our left shoulder.
That's on the cues on that side, right?
Left shoulder left shoulder and this will be our right shoulder like
that.
That's good.
And then what we need to pass here too is we need
Past like basically which one it was.
So we need to pass gives down right.
We need to pass is down to these, so is down so that they'll know
which to do and obviously this is no longer processing, win32 button
stuff.
So this is going to be 132 win32 process keyboard events or something
like that.
T-bird message I suppose and then it will just go ahead and do the
exact same kind of processing.
That are other one did.
So that
Should be sufficient.
Okay, so I'm going to go up here and just copy this guy and do win32
process, keyboard message.
Again, that just takes the Old State and the new state and the is down
is down.
And basically, whether it ended down is just going to be, is down
here.
I guess that's, that's it.
So, it's going to set that to that.
And the half transition count for the new state.
Basically going to go up every time we get one of these.
So this is just basically plus plussing that yeah, I think that's
basically it.
I mean we guess we could do it this way.
We can say, if the now, I guess this is exactly what we want.
This is exactly what we want.
It's actually really this simple because this is coming in the
keyboard.
Messages are coming in as events.
They're coming in inside the loop.
We're going to get each key.
Keyword message each time.
So really what we want to do here is the new input old input Paradigm.
We don't, we almost really don't need old input.
Old input is, is kind of redundant at this point for us.
So, in some sense we can just use the new one, right like this.
We can just say the new controller goes like this, right?
And and we don't actually ever need to see the old one because Windows
Event processing is doing the check to see whether or not
Not the thing went up or down, or that sort of stuff.
So we don't actually need to even.
Look at that stuff.
I don't think so.
All we really have to do here is decide what we want.
Our new input controller to be.
So since we since we have the controller over here, let's see here,
new controller, this controller State.
Basically, what we want to do is we want to clear out and we, I think
we want to do this.
Anyway, we want to clear out for new controller.
Whatever its transition count was.
So at the top of the loop here.
I'm going to say that new controller whenever we get that, that first
one, we'll get that in there.
So I guess this will be our keyboard controller.
Let's say, keyboard controller.
When we get that one in there.
I want this zeroed out.
Like I want, I want all these buttons to be cleared essentially.
So I'm going to go through and I'm just going to clear the buttons out
since.
I don't actually want the well, you know what?
I could probably clear.
Just about everything.
We know that we know that the entire thing should really be cleared.
So I could basically just clear the entire thing.
I think I could do that instead, so I can do that.
I can say game, controller input, zero equals, this c0 controller and
I can just go ahead and say keyboard, Ctrl 0, equals 0 controller.
There we go.
So that will just clear that out for now.
I do want to go ahead and make a zeroing macro some point.
So we don't have to do that.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
Well, zero that guy out and then we'll go through and and use him that
way.
So that that's
Yeah, we're will have to clean this up a little bit more tomorrow, but
we should be okay.
All right, so I believe.
Now we need to actually read everything out of our of our message
thing here.
So hold on a second.
This is keyboard controller, I believe.
Yeah, roller, dude, dude.
Okay.
I just need to go ahead and make these come out of the message
because, remember, we were dispatching them before now.
We're not dispassionate.
We're just reading them out of that, message structure, this guy right
here, when we get the message back, that used to be,
Going through the win32 side of things and now it's not anymore.
So I'm going to go ahead and if the internet's working at all, I'll
check em SVC.
I'm not sure that it actually will be but I'll check for MSG.
No, not that MSG.
That's funny.
That's not the MSG we're looking for.
Basically.
I just W / a male friend, there.
They're all right there.
So basically all we all we have to do is just get those right out of
the structure.
So instead of allowing Windows to basically dispatch to our Windows
thing.
We're just going to skip that all together.
Now, no longer has to take the old State at all.
It could just take the new state and process it that way.
And we are good to go.
Now.
There's a bunch of stuff.
We haven't quite done in there yet, but I think that puts us in good
position for tomorrow.
So hopefully, we should be in a position to actually see this work, a
little bit here.
Yes, and there.
If I do push that down, there we go.
Okay, so we don't quite handle what we need to handle yet, and the
reason is and I'll put the to do in here.
So basically for tomorrow, we can't zero everything because the
up-down state will be wrong, right?
So we have to actually do some real code here that I couldn't do in
five minutes because basically, we won't be able to hold down a key,
if that makes sense.
Like, basically, we only will set it on events when we get an actual
message, and you can see that happening in here.
Right?
If I, if I push the down, I have to actually keep pushing it to scroll
down instead of holding the down button and making that work.
And the reason why that happened is basically because, well,
We're only, you know, I wanted to zero this out so that because we
want to zero out those half counts.
So I'm zeroing out everything here at the top, which means that if you
never get a keyboard message on a frame, everything's going to be set
to not be down.
So all the buttons will be set to not be down.
What we want to do is we want to persist the setting of the buttons.
So one thing I could do is change this from a ping pong thing.
Instead of you know, like that to actually just sort of propagating
forwards.
I'm not sure we need to do some thinking about how we want to actually
handle that and that's what we'll do tomorrow.
Because we want to streamline all this code anyway, and we've got some
two dudes in here.
So we should be able to go through and do that relatively quickly, but
that's really all we're gonna have to do to support keyboard input
properly in here.
It should not take too long to do, we're going to have to go through
and do the stick stuff as well.
And I thought of some things I want to talk about there as well,
anyway and are, and we'll finally get to The Dead Zone processing as
well.
So basically that's that's all we need to do tomorrow.
So tomorrow should be a nice a passing day.
We'll try to get all this code nice and clean.
We'll go through a couple different revisions of it.
Basically, just sort of pull things out, get things.
He's nicer.
We might want to pull some things out.
So this isn't so hard to read, we could make it function for them.
Those sorts of things.
That is what we will do tomorrow though.
For now.
The stream has technically ended.
I know, it'll be very difficult for anyone to ask a Q&A because of the
wonderfulness of the internet that ditched the stream in the middle.
So you probably are missing a good chunk of what actually happened and
won't have a question until you're actually able to go watch it on
YouTube in the archive.
So I apologize for that.
I will absolutely flame my internet service provider immediately after
getting off the Stream.
But beyond that, there's not a whole lot.
I can do about it.
Unfortunately, and that is definitely unfortunate to say the least.
All right, let us go to the Q&A and see what is going on here.
Let's see.
Let us see.
Please, if you can use put see me oratory in your questions, so I know
they are addressed to me and I can see them.
And also if you could keep it to code that we actually are working on,
our have worked on that helps a ton.
Okay.
Let's see, we missed a lot of the compiler options discussion when the
stream went down.
Can you go back over the stuff?
You added after no logo?
I think I'd rather not because I covered it all relatively completely.
So if you just go to the YouTube, that will be up or even the twitch,
if you will know that the twitch, you'll have to go to the YouTube.
YouTube will be uploaded tonight.
So you'll be able to watch that directly and see all the switches that
I went through because I won't be able to remember them all.
Because I even went through some stuff that I removed.
So if you could go watch the Youtube of it, I'm sorry about that.
I'll try to fix the switch thing.
I don't know what happened.
I'll have to deal with my internet service provider.
I'm very unhappy about that ive.
Actually emailed them recently about dropouts.
So I'm very angry to say the least, and they will be well, you know
what, they'll be seeing this dude, because if ever there was a time
for the owl of shame.
I think the owl of Shame is looking at Cascade link right now.
They are looking at Cascade link right in the eye for letting that
happen.
So I don't know what's going on, but I will try to get to the bottom
of it.
Towel of Shame may be involved.
All right.
Why would ever any why would anyone ever not want - oh, I well.
Okay.
So - oh I is a little complicated.
Basically.
What - oh I does is it says to always use intrinsics where they are
available in the intrinsics might have some slightly different
Behavior than the C version of the function.
I don't know.
Like, I don't know.
B - 0 I is always 100% safe.
If what you were expecting it to do, was to be exactly the same as the
C.
Runtime libraries implementation of a function and be faster because
it's not actually calling anything.
It's just using assembly directly.
I don't know if that actually is what it does.
It may use intrinsics that might not always be exactly the same and
just trust that.
You know, what, the what the CPU is doing or stuff like this.
I'm not sure I feel
Like, most of the time, it actually does emit code.
That's correct.
And in fact, you have to work around that sometimes because sometimes
like, it's doing extra fix up for like this square, root instruction
or something that you didn't want it to do.
And so you have to admit your own square root all this stuff.
So so I don't know.
So it may be the oi is just always something you should put but I
don't I'm not willing to say that because I don't definitively know
that there isn't some times when you might not want.
Oh I because the behavior program might change.
Later, something like this.
How do we add minus WX, minus W-4 to compiler for using visual studio?
I don't know, to be honest with you because I have never built a
project in the latest version, which is me.
But if you open up the like, if you open up the property stuff, so
like if you go in here into view and there's a solution Explorer
thing.
If you're building in Visual Studio, you'll have a project here.
And if you right-click on things, you'll get up a property, pains that
have stuff in them like compiler, and, and preprocessor, and all these
sorts of things.
If you hunt through there, you will find one for treat warnings as
errors or enable higher warning levels.
Be properties that you can use there in there.
You just got to find them, you know, so yeah, I'm sorry.
I don't build products that way.
So I don't know, but they're in there if you need them and they're at,
there's even a place where you can add extra switches.
So if you can't find it, I think you can even just go in and just, and
add it that way.
What turning on /od?
Be a good idea, to turn on, in the normal built?
I, you know, I think it would be so someone wrote in and said they
were they were talking about
My /od, which disables optimizations completely.
So, let me see, here, Odie, I believe that's what that does.
Let's see.
Yeah, so that suppresses basically, anything that might happen to the
code.
The compiler would want to do for performance or anything else, and I
think that is a good idea because we look at the disassembly and stuff
and we try to do educational things.
So I think a minus a minus OD would be good that basically just
No optimization be super slow, but leave everything where it should
be.
And let's, let's I think that's a good idea.
Thank you for that.
Suggestion.
Ambiguous panda.
Oh, wait.
No.
Sorry.
Sean Bryant was off by one.
Does compilers compilation message?
Always say finished in green.
Know.
That is that's kanui Max, doing that.
Yeah, if there's a bug, it still does it.
I guess I don't know.
I'm not sure that's some kind of good new emacs nonsense and I didn't
write that.
I don't know how hard it would be to change.
That to be predicated based on whether there was an error in the
Stream or in the compilation or not, or things like that.
I'm not sure.
That's a good question and emacs expert, I'm sure would be able to
tell you how to do that.
But I don't know.
I don't really look at that very often.
I think you mentioned something about not being a fan of re bindable
Keys, why?
So wouldn't it be nice to give you?
Is that option?
I just, I just don't like it.
I don't know.
It's, it's very distracting.
I don't like, it's more.
It's not really vital Keys.
It's option menus.
If we want to rebind keys by having like a text file that they could
go editor something that's totally outside of the game.
I'm like, not as upset about that or even like that weird Unity
launcher thing.
Maybe, I don't know.
I just, I just don't like having all these options because they like
clutter that the game experience.
I kind of just want the keys to be what the keys are.
And so I just don't like we bundle keys.
I really don't.
I want the designer to have.
Put the keys in good places, and if it was so weird.
That like they think they need to rebind Keys like a lot of games
today.
I've like 80 million keys and they all got to be rebound and whatever
like make a game with less Keys, you know, would be my suggestion.
So think that's basically why I don't want to read by in the keys.
I just want them to be simple and then you just use them.
How much difference in code size performance would yield?
If we were to disable the CRT?
Well, okay.
So at the moment it would be huge because at the moment most of our
executable is it is the C, runtime library, but in the future a lot of
the code will be ours and then it will be less of a win speed-wise.
It won't be anyone at all.
Because as long as long as you're not calling the C runtime Library,
there's really no speed hit.
So there's no speed but but size it would definitely be a thing.
I couldn't see what you did that made the key X messages, not being
triggered.
What happened there?
Okay.
Yeah, let's go.
I kind of went through that quickly because I was under time pressure
there.
No, thanks to the internet service provider, but I will go over that
again.
So what I wanted to do, right?
Is this is this this win32 callback function that we are obliged to
have, because Windows, sometimes calls us back directly here.
Just by cold calling, this directly like, WM paint is an example.
We will
Get WM paint message directly from Windows without ever having gone
through our dispatch Loop, but we have down here are actual dispatch
Loop, right?
This thing while Peak message is ostensibly.
The thing that's supposed to handle all the messages.
So, even though windows can sometimes cause back directly at that
wind, at that window function.
This is actually where there's where the message is supposed to come
in and I would rather process the messages here because everything is
local and logical in here.
We know what game inputs, we were look talking about.
We know where everything is.
We have our game memory.
We have all our stuff.
We don't have to, like, shuttle that stuff off into Global variables,
where the window procedure could pick it up again or store it inside
window, extra storage, which is thing you can do.
And when 32 windows we have to do that if we just process it in here.
So all I did was just say, OK, when a message comes in before what we
were doing is we always just dispatch it.
So when a keyword message would come in, it would actually just call
this which would call our window procedure.
What I did instead.
We just say, oh, well if it's a keyboard message, just don't call the
window procedure at all.
All just just handle it right here.
So it never actually gets down to this fast matches.
So it's fine.
That's it.
Nothing more to it.
Let's see.
Would it be better to just pass?
Which key was pressed to the non platform code instead of switching on
the keys in the platform layer since the keys will depend on the game
again.
I don't really want to do that at the moment.
I wouldn't necessarily advise against that.
That's a totally fine way to go, but at the moment I just kind of
wanted to just leave it so that it's all processed inside the win32
layer and then all that happens.
Is the game just sees a virtualized controller.
So the game just basically knows about a controller.
That's all it knows about.
And if the keyboard is
Like a controller.
The platform layer is responsible for turning it into that.
And the reason I want to do that is because there's some stuff we
might do, they're like we might detect whether on like a French
keyboard that has the wasd keys, laid out differently and switch them
to the to be proper keys.
That will be laid out properly look and see if there's Dvorak and use
different thing.
Like we may do stuff in the platform layer that tries to be smart
about that stuff like this.
But yeah, I mean, I should, I said it, but I'll say it again, but if
you wanted to implement the other way, that's totally fine, and I've
often implanted things that way.
So, I'm not saying that this is like the right way to do it or the
other ways bad.
It's just the way I happen to choose so far and we could even change
our mind halfway through the stream.
If it turns out to be bad we could just change.
So it's not like there's anything wrong with doing the other way.
If you build for say avx2 or something, what happens if the user has
an older processor, they will fault on invalid instruction.
Usually, sometimes I think there's ways, they work around that, but
that's mostly what happens.
So, if you want to use newer instructions like you want to use avx2,
what you have to do is you have to basically test first to see what
processor you're on and don't call the code that uses those.
If you're on a processor that doesn't support them.
So you onus is kind of on you to work around that.
Will you eventually move to a single unified build system for all your
target platforms?
No, because there's no way that it could be simpler than what we have
right here.
Right.
This is one line of a build basically.
So any build system that we were to use, would be massively more
complicated than this, for no actual benefit.
So, we will just have a one line build basically on each of our
platforms, and that'll be.
And that's the, that's way easier than trying to maintain any build
system, which will be made.
Way more complicated than that.
Let's see.
Would not - oh, I and ODB clashing or they evaluated From First to
Last.
I don't think they're clashing, but I do think they are evaluated From
First to Last.
So if this did Clash, I believe that OD will be overridden by, oh, I
which is what we
But I don't know if they even do it.
Maybe that you can turn them on totally independently anyway, because
it just this isn't about an optimization so much as it's about what
happens, whether it's a function call or inline code and the code can
still be totally an optimized right?
That does the thing.
So, I'm not sure that they Clash, but
Is there a way to make CLM it a human-readable summary of the
optimizations?
It does, when - OD isn't specified.
I do not know of one.
That would be pretty awesome.
But I don't know of one.
Just the map file spit out data about struct members as well.
Not that I know of.
No, I think that only ends up in the pdb.
So if you want to know, like what you're saying, you're talking about,
could things like that.
Be used to generate serialization code?
I think you'd have to use the pdb, to generate serialization code.
I don't think you can use the
App for that.
Unless I'm missing something.
Let's see.
Does it not allowing key rebinding mess up a different keyboard?
Layouts.
Like defaulting to wasde on an azerty or other keyboard layout.
I'd rather just handle those layouts so that the user doesn't have to
learn about remapping Keys.
That'd be my preference.
Right?
And you could even crowdsource that, right?
Like, you'd have a bunch of different keyboard files that just get
loaded.
I'd like to do it in a way that makes it.
So that it's not about you having to deal with the menu, but I'd like
to start stop discussing this because you'll have the source code,
right?
If you preorder the game.
The anyone who buys the game, has a source code and honestly, I want
to teach people to program.
So if they want to go in and add key, rebinding
That is that is their prerogative.
Everyone who has a different opinion than I do about how this game
should work.
Should take it upon themselves to build their own version that works
that way.
That's exactly how I would like it to happen so that they have their
own personal version that does exactly what they want.
So I'll be making the game design decisions.
But any time you don't agree with them.
Unlike normal games, that's not actually an impediment to you.
You can just go ahead and straight up change my design decision.
To be what you want.
Is the game currently linked to the dll version of the CRT?
No, I that's what this does, - Mt.
Prevents that from happening.
So it is, it is, it is slick to static now and that is what I what you
need to do.
You always need to do static.
Let's see.
Let us see.
I think that is all the questions.
I do not see any other questions.
There's another question.
I know you won't be using any libraries with handmade hero, but
imagine you would for example, how would you include something open
source, like Z lib with your Unity?
Old would you just include the source file like you compile your own
source files or build a separate Dynamic, static lab and linked to
that.
That's a good question.
I almost never use that sort of thing.
I tend to use Sean Barrett's libraries and libraries like that that
are just you can just pound include them and they work, but if you
were, I would say probably build a static lib and then stick it on the
end here would be how I would how I would go for a third-party
Library.
I think that's probably the best way to do that.
I can't really think of a downside to doing it that way because since
Third-party library that way, you can just compile it once and you
don't have to pay for the cost of compiling it every time because it
may be banana, cakes code in there, you know, who knows?
Right?
It may be written in such a way that it takes 12 years to compile
because it's 50,000 templates deeper.
All these are the sorts of things.
So it's bad.
Yeah.
Please tell Cascade link.
Thank you from all of us.
Yes.
I will.
I will be sure to tell them that I will send them a link to the stream
and say nobody got to watch it because of the problem that I reported
to you, that you have not fixed.
Apparently don't know what the problem is.
But yeah.
It's a it's it's unfortunate to say the least.
So hopefully it will be, hopefully be okay.
Anyway, I think that is all the questions.
I see, no more questions coming in, which makes sense because since
the stream was down for most of the time, I'm not through sure.
Anyone could really ask a question about the stream.
Is there any advantage of processing message in the main Loop other
than conceptual grouping Ronald Reagan?
S.
I don't think so.
I mean you say
Of a function dispatch, right?
You don't have to call translate message dispatch message and you
don't go through windows, but this is not really a performance
critical part of the code.
So I don't think there's any reason to be concerned about how it's
optimized.
So really, I just like the conceptual purity of being able to have it
be on the same stack and specifically what I mean by that is like,
let's say we're going to pull this out.
Right?
And I want to do it.
So I still want it in a function, right?
Which is like handle keyboard events or something, right?
So I'm still going to, I'm still going.
It out, so I'm not going to put it in line, right?
Or even you know, what I could do.
I could even do it this way.
Let's do it this way.
So this is this will this will just be like our message pump thing
here or whatever, right?
So we've got this, let's say we just do it, we want to pull it out.
So it's cleaner, right?
Like that.
Now, I'm not necessarily saying there's anything positive about
pulling it out like that, but basically, like win32 message Loop,
right?
So let's say I was going to do it this way.
So, it's
In an external function, just like the other.
The windows function was, I still prefer it this way?
And the reason for that is because when I actually go to make this
happen, right?
I can
I have control over what I pass directly to this function.
So it can stay more functional style and less about global variables
and that have to get looked up that I have less control over, right.
So basically I put this in here.
I called the message Loop.
The win32 message loop.
I probably shouldn't call it.
That I'll change that name in a second here.
But we do this, right?
And then we see.
Alright, we need this keyboard controller thing.
So we'll pass that right keyboard controller.
And I forget what?
What type
That guy is it's a game, controller input.
So pass that guy, right?
That it needs.
And there it goes, keyboard controller and we're done.
And basically, what you can see there is, it's like I can directly see
what's going on with the code.
I'm going to use the message Loop.
I'm going to put the input that comes from it into this keyboard
controller and we're all good.
If I'd wanted to do that out here, right?
And wait a minute.
You know what?
There's one thing?
It's busted about the way I just did.
That.
This is to be above that.
Sorry.
Sorry, everyone.
Just, there you go.
Basically, if I were to do that with the other one, right?
If I were to try and shoehorn that into this thing, this thing is
totally dictated by Windows Windows, is the only person who calls
this, and it's defined what, the the variables are, that get passed as
parameters, right?
So, I need that keyboard controller in here, but I can't actually,
Ali set it and that's very frustrating, right?
It basically forces me to have a notion a global variable in one way
or another, whether I store it on the window or whether I store it in
the global store here.
It's forcing me to do something that makes my code harder to read and
understand because the flow of data is not explicit.
Whereas when I did it this way, it was, of course, you know what?
I can also do here.
We can handle our selects, we can, we can collapse all sorts of things
here.
Can't wait.
There we go.
Yeah, little opportunistic there.
Why not?
Put that in there?
Never hurt.
Anyone.
Will WM quit, handling simplify things.
Anyway, but also, hopefully you can see what I mean.
By that process pending messages is what we'll call that.
It's a better name for it.
I think says a little clearer what it's going to do.
It's just a lot.
It's just a lot cleaner when you don't have callbacks based.
I don't ever really like callbacks unless you have to have them
because they just make control flow harder to read and they make side.
Difficult more difficult to understand because they're happening all
over the place.
So hopefully that makes some sense.
Let's see.
I'm super new to programming in my first semester of CSS classes at
the moment.
Are there any resources for someone like me, who is new to the basic?
Jargon and techniques.
Do you have a tutorial video on the basics?
Yes, what you can do is you can go to handmade hero dot-org.
There is a link on.
Well, that is, if the internet's working at all ever, which, you know,
hear it.
Often is not, but you can go to handmade here at the org.
There's a link to the forum's site there.
And basically, if you go on there, I wish I could.
Let me see if I can yes for himself.
Yeah.
So if you go on here for HCBS forms a hamburger, but you should be
able to go to him a hero, just dot-org, handmade hero dot-org if you
go.
Yeah.
Okay, so it's working.
Now, if you go to have me here at org, there's a news in.
Forums link along with other stuff and that.
Basically, if you go to the news and forums link, it gives you a bunch
of coding resources like you asked for there's code discussion and
there's coding resources and there's episode guide, all of which you
might want to check out.
So the the code discussion is like a forum where you can ask
questions.
And there's people who do things like asking stuff about like math
books, that are good and stuff like that.
You can look at those.
We try to gather those up into this coding resources page where we
link to things that people have done, which is kind of nice.
Rip.
Materials down here.
We'll sort of build this over time, hopefully.
And then finally, the episode guide has a stuff.
Some stuff you're asking about, I did do a brief test stream that was
intro to see on Windows that might answer some of those questions the
jargon of stuff like that for you.
So you can kind of go on there and take a look at some of that stuff
and those thanks to the to the amazing efforts of the people who are
listed up here at the top of this page.
In fact, who I highly recommend you thank if you see them on the
Twitter's and so on.
Basically inside here.
They've done a bunch of work to actually make these really easy to
use.
So basically like depending on I don't know if the intro to see ones
have it the interest to see ones, don't have it.
But on the handmade hero one's a lot of them have actual timeline
markers.
Yeah, like this sort of thing.
They're not all done yet because you know, obviously it's volunteer
effort.
So, you know, if it's basically if someone happens to have the time to
do it whether it's there, but a lot of them actually do have it now
where you can sort of go through and jump right to things as well and
there's notes.
And here there's
To get filled in as well.
You can kind of see if you go on some of these don't know which ones
have notes and which ones don't I think the audio one started to have
some notes.
Yeah.
So for example, sometimes people put notes in there.
So yeah, that's it's an effort that's underway.
And but like I said, it's just volunteers who are doing it out of the
goodness of their heart.
So, you know, it's it's not entirely complete.
If people have something want to donate for that.
I can put you in touch with the people who do that and you can help
help them fill that stuff in because I'm sure they could use the help
certainly, but that's a good place to go and we're trying to make this
site user.
Bill for people who are trying to learn.
So that's a good place to go if you if you want to
Let's see when you initialize a window.
There's that one parameter for allocating extra, bytes to associate.
Where there would it be appropriate or input State there yet.
So, that's what I was referring to.
I said window extra storage.
Basically though that doesn't help us in this case, because it's still
just a global variable is just a little video stored in the window.
If we had multiple windows and each window needed a different set of
stuff that was working with, then it would make
Our sinks going to be a little cleaner to store it with the window,
then to store it as Global's.
But if we're just talking about something that actually is global.
There's only one of them then.
Basically, what I wanted to do was I want to just leave it on the
stack where it belonged here and I didn't want to complicate it by
setting a global latch that.
Then the window picks up.
It would be no cleaner to set the global latch in the Windows store.
It's still just as janky so so you can use the window extra bytes.
You basically you could pass you pass it here.
Here and you define it in the wind class.
You can use those for that but we don't have any.
We only have one window.
So those are never going to be any different, the global variables for
us.
They're just Global variables.
There.
They give you no benefit to your control flow at that point.
Let's see.
Do you have any approximate timeline on going back to make videos
teaching?
See we and I include myself.
Are getting more beginners asking for tutorials.
Love your exhalation to teach yourself.
I don't have a timeline for it right now because well, honestly, I
don't know if my voice can handle any more streams than I already do.
It's hard to talk for an hour and a half every night or more.
And I've been sick lately.
So I'm not sure if, when I'll get to those it is something that I'd
like to do, but I don't
Timeline for it yet.
A lot of people have been asking if they can donate money to the
stream which was really nice.
A nice thing, you know above and beyond, obviously if you like the
stream you can always pre-order the game, but they were like I want to
give more than $15 which was extremely generous of them.
And so, I've been trying to think of something that I can do like a
Kickstarter or something that would allow people who want to
contribute to contribute something that I would then do.
So maybe I'll do that in the future.
I'll do like, okay, you know, if we raise x amount of dollars, I'll
just take a week off of work and
Do a set of her teaching materials or something like that.
I've been thinking about what would be good to do there.
And if I come up with some good ideas and maybe maybe doing a good set
of see tutorials would be one of those.
I don't know.
Yeah, so there already is the sort of rudimentary one, but it's not
complete enough because it go, it's only 5 days, which is not enough
time to really learn.
See if you didn't know programming before, it's just not enough, but
that's really all that exists at the moment.
Do we have a p.o.
Box?
So we send banana cakes?
I do have a p.o.
Box but you do not need to send me banana cakes.
It's really not necessary.
I don't know if I even like, banana cakes.
I'm sure it's some banana cake is good.
But I don't know if I like it.
It's hard to say.
I do like banana, sometimes will say that.
I think that's all the questions and we are just about out of time.
So that is good.
We are right on time.
Thank you so much.
Everyone for joining me for another episode of handmade hero.
I am sorry that the internet did not stay up long enough to get a full
stream out there.
But the entire thing was recorded and I will upload it to YouTube.
So if you would like to catch it, you can go to episode guide right
here.
In fact, and it will show up right down here in this day, 16 slot
where it is waiting.
You can
So from handmade here, if you follow him made here on YouTube, that's
up there.
The handmade here at our website, has a link to the video archive.
That's got everything, so that will come up on here.
And that should be up.
It'll be up in low res, right away, but low-res is hard to use because
when you're trying to read text low-res is no good.
So you gotta give you to those those hamster servers.
The hamsters are running over there at YouTube to power those servers,
but they take a while to churn through and actually compress the
high-res version of the of this stream.
So
Basically, you got to wait, typically, you know, 12 hours or something
after it.
Airs before they actually have the 1080P and 720p versions which are
the ones you're going to want to watch.
So, thank you so much for joining us.
I hope to see you again tomorrow here at 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time and hopefully the internet will stay up for the
entire time and we will go through and Street, you know, get our input
situation straightened out.
And then from there we'll be going to straightening out the frame
timing and from there will probably be at the point where we're kind
of getting off with.
So this this is going to be our last week, I think of dealing with
Windows, and it will be all game.
So it just in time for Christmas, argh.
Our Christmas present will be, we're into all our own code, which
believe me is a beautiful thing.
There's nothing I like more than being in charge of every last little
thing and not having to rely on Windows for anything.
So as soon as we get out of that it's definitely a plus in my mind.
So I'm looking forward to that and I hope you are too hope to see you
here tomorrow at 8:00 p.m.
PST on Twitch again and yet for those of you who couldn't catch the
stream because of the
Pattern it today.
Just check it out on YouTube.
Thanks so much for joining me, everyone and I will catch you tomorrow.